Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Peter Attia Drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia. The drive
is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking, along
with a few other obsessions I've gathered along the way. I've spent the last several
years working with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And
this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live
a higher quality, more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more
information on today's episode and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Welcome to the Peter Attia Drive. In this episode, which I know is long anticipated,
I spoke with Dr. Rhonda Patrick from Found My Fitness. I suspect many of you listening
to this know everything about Rhonda and have been fans of her for a really long period
of time. On the off chance there's anybody listening who doesn't know who Rhonda is,
I suspect by the end of this discussion, you will also become a huge fan of hers and her
podcast, which is exceptional. So I've known Rhonda for quite a while. And despite the
fact that we both consider San Diego home, we've just been busy enough that we just haven't
had a chance to sit down together in quite a while. So this discussion was kind of long
overdue and it was sort of funny because as soon as Rhonda walked in, we just jumped right
into a really interesting discussion. And then 10 minutes in, I thought, you know, we
should probably start recording because this is interesting stuff. And so we did. And similarly,
when the discussion finally ended, we sat around for another 20 minutes talking about
a bunch of stuff that I found myself thinking, God, I wish we were still recording this because
it's super interesting. So that's just basically to say, I suspect Rhonda and I will speak
again at some point soon. So don't worry if all of your questions weren't answered here.
The other thing about this podcast that was a ton of fun was that in the days leading
up to it, she and I had emailed each other a few times back and forth some ideas of things
we would talk about. And in the end, neither of us really had any notes sitting in front
of us. We just sort of sat there and shot from the hip and didn't follow a script or
anything like that. And didn't even get to half the things that in our emails we had
suggested we would talk about. That said, all the stuff that we talked about is stuff
that I think Rhonda brings a great deal of expertise to. So I don't recall the order,
I know that we certainly touched on IGF and the growth hormone, what I consider a little
bit of a paradox, which is on the one hand we have some evidence to suggest that elevated
levels of IGF are bad and that fasting may act in part by reducing those levels. But
at the other end of the discussion, you have some confounding and conflicting data around
that. We also got into a great discussion about the PPAR enzyme, so PPAR alpha, PPAR
gamma. One of the things that Rhonda does incredibly well on her podcast, and I would
encourage those of you who find this episode interesting, who aren't familiar with her
work to go back and actually watch some of her stuff. Rhonda doesn't put out a lot of
podcasts, but the reason for that is the amount of work she puts into them is enormous. So
when she puts out a podcast on video, there's explanations, definitions, and stuff scrolling
across the screen. So it's unlike me who's incredibly lazy and can't even stand to listen
to a podcast after I record it. Rhonda is methodical in her ability to make that easier
for the viewer. So you'll learn a lot about this stuff if you think we're going too quickly
over it by probably going back to Rhonda's site. We talk a lot about the possible genetic
explanations for why some people do and don't respond particularly well to ketogenic diets.
And of course, you can think of that in two ways. There's respond as far as the ability
to make ketones, but then there's also sort of these patients that I describe seeing where
you put them on a ketogenic diet and everything seems to go wrong. So at least biochemically
wrong. So that's a very interesting discussion. In many ways, I think my favorite part of
this discussion was the way it started, which was the first question I asked Rhonda, which
was kind of a random question, I think led to some interesting back and forth between
us, which was effectively, what do you believe today that you didn't believe before and vice
versa? And I always find that to be one of the most interesting ways to dive into a discussion
with someone who's buried knee deep into science. Because if you're really thinking
about science, you have to understand of course that virtually all facts have a half life
and our knowledge is constantly evolving. In many ways, that's what makes the field
so difficult to stay on top of, but at the same time, so interesting. And so to me, one
of the marks of a very thoughtful person is someone whose beliefs are flexible and who's
willing to acknowledge that something that they believed was once true or not true can
be flipped. And so I think Rhonda and I share that and I think it was actually really fun
to see where her beliefs have changed over time. So with that said, I think the show
notes for this particular episode are going to be very helpful and you can find those
at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. And I hope you enjoy this discussion at least
half as much as I did. I suspect it won't be the last. So without further delay, here's
my conversation with Dr. Rhonda Patrick.
Rhonda, so great to have you here. Happy to be here. It's great to see you again.
I can't believe we live in the same city and only see each other once a year. If you even.
Well thank you for taking the trip up here today to my office. My pleasure. And I'll
join the long list of people congratulating you on your 10 month old son. Thank you. Thank
you. I almost don't know where to begin because there are so many things that we share in
common as far as interests. But I want to start with a really broad question, which
is you spend so much time thinking about many of the same problems I spend time thinking
about. What do you believe today that you did not believe four or five years ago? Probably
the biggest thing that has changed in what I now believe, but I didn't four or five years
ago even more, is that one of the major modalities for increasing health span, which is the
healthy part of your life, delaying the onset of age related diseases, the major modality
for doing that, that would be the best way to do it would be caloric restriction or dietary
restriction. So eating 30% less food than you normally would eat. I used to really think
that was the way to go for doing that. And I think that my beliefs have changed for that
and that being the major modality for a few reasons. One reason is because I think that
actually, so one of the things that occurs during caloric restriction is a major drop in the growth
hormone IGF-1. And that's thought to regulate a lot of the improved health span effects, at least
in some organisms like mice and in rhesus monkeys. But I do believe now based off a variety of
research from people like Walter Longo, that periods of growth, actually specifically periods
of IGF-1 are really important. So if you're constantly doing this caloric restriction,
then you're not really going to have that period of growth because you're chronically doing that.
And really interesting, I don't know if you saw the recent nature study that came out,
I think it was in April of this year on lemurs. So the study essentially showed, and these are,
I guess they're not human primate animal model, but their lifespan is, median lifespan is around
six years or something like that. And I think their maximum is 11 or 12 years, I don't remember.
But the caloric restriction did increase the median lifespan. It also increased maximum,
so they lived a year longer than typically. And there's a lot of delayed onset of various
degenerative diseases, but there was a mass of atrophy in gray brain matter in regions of the
brain that didn't occur in control animals, which is just another sort of example of how sometimes
some of these modalities that we think are really good for increasing health span sometimes have
other effects. And I think that getting into the IGF-1, I think we'll probably, you and I will talk
about that because we both have a shared interest in that. But the periods of growth being necessary
for health, I think that's kind of turning point in my mind. And so now I actually think that
perhaps even doing periodic prolonged fasts are a better way of doing that because you can get
that IGF-1 boost and you can get the lower IGF-1 among other things that occur. But we can dive
into that if you want. But I think that's kind of- We'll be diving.
Yeah. But I think that's probably one of the major things. Yeah, there would be actually
another interest that we share would be, I think I was a lot more skeptical of ketogenic diets about
four years ago in terms of being great for long-term health and health span. And I think that some of
my thoughts on that have changed a bit based off of more recent long-term studies in animals,
specifically in mice, work from Dr. Eric Verdon and also from out of UC Davis showing that
ketogenic diets in rodents can increase health span, increase median lifespan, certainly improve
cognitive function. Now the caveat there is that typically with a ketogenic diet in rodents,
it actually can be, most of the time, is obesogenic. And the way that these guys worked around that
was they found that they had to limit the calorie. And what was interesting was that-
Or cycle them, right?
Well, so Dr. Eric Verdon, the way they did that was by cycling it. But at UC Davis, what they did was
actually put a calorie cap and turns out after talking with Dr. Sachin Panda, that they ended
up being on a time restricted feeding schedule. And so the ketogenic diet was, they were basically
eating all their food within a certain eight or eight or so or nine an hour window. And then they
were fasting for- So it's kind of one of those things where in humans, we don't really know,
I don't know exactly how people- I've never actually done a ketogenic diet myself. So I
don't know exactly what people are doing if they're eating all the time or what.
So I'm also intrigued by that. And in many ways, almost have the mirror of your experience,
which was four or five, six years ago, seven years ago, I guess, is when I really, really got into
ketogenic diets, was on a ketogenic diet for three years, save one day. And I wouldn't say I
have any less faith in them today. I just am personally less interested and find it much harder
to do. So just as far as compliance with a ketogenic diet, you know, I think my life is just more
complicated today in terms of travel and things like that and kids and stuff. But the thing that
surprised me with the recent, because those two publications came out in cell, right? The ones-
Cell metabolism, right?
I was actually kind of surprised by a couple of things. So one was what you said, which was Eric
noting that, hey, when we constitutively gave these guys this food, they just, they got obese.
That's really counterintuitive when you think about how ketogenic diets increase circulating
metabolic fuels. And that should downregulate appetite. And I think in humans, you know,
there's a huge debate about why do people lose weight on ketogenic diets? Are they losing weight
because they're eating less? Were they losing weight because they're ramping up fat oxidation
disproportionate to where they were before, which drives up energy expenditure? Of course,
I suspect the answer is both. In other words, if you do the latter, the former should happen.
So when people say, why do you eat less on a ketogenic diet? The question is really,
or the thinking would be, are you eating less because you are basically eating yourself more?
Because you're obviously oxidizing all of those fatty acids to make BHB.
Or is it some other reason that, you know, has to do with the neuro chemistry of these things
that go beyond sort of the metabolic central, pardon me, peripheral effects of it. So that's
the first thing that surprised me with that study, which was why were those mice overeating?
Was there something else in them? Because they couldn't have had that much sucrose. They usually
put sucrose in mouse child, but there couldn't have been that much sucrose. So they wouldn't have
been able to get into ketosis. And I think even previous studies, like earlier in the literature,
showed something similar where it was obesogenic. Now there was certain genetic backgrounds that
also seem to kind of little, you know, regulate that to some degree. But what I was actually
thinking, so you brought up some really interesting points, is that thinking of that in the context of
like, let's say they're constantly eating the fat or they're not having the period of rest.
I know that, for example, when you're making malonyl CoA, which is something that you do,
when you're oxidizing fat, malonyl CoA inhibits the conotene palmatilla transfer is the
basically the transporter to transport fatty acids in the mitochondria. So if you
constantly are making malonyl CoA because you're constantly eating the fat, then you're going to
start to have this inhibition. You're going to start to then store the fatty acids in adipose
tissue rather than catabolizing them. Right? So it seems to me that's-
And we don't see that, by the way, with the exogenous ketones, do we?
This is something I'm still trying to get a handle on.
I agree. I'm certain, I am extremely interested in the exogenous ketones,
particularly because I've tried them. I should have brought you some. Okay, you've tried them.
Yeah, yeah. I was going to bring you some.
So I really enjoy the effects they have on my brain. So I've used them for endurance exercise,
and I also like it for that as well. I do notice that I have a little bit of a, I seem to run
longer than I usually stop at this point on the beach and I can keep going another. But what I
really like is for me, it really helps with focus and lower anxiety levels. So I seem to be able to,
I'm always onto the next. And so this kind of helps me like, say in the now,
at least I've, and that could be completely placebo, I don't know. But anyways, that's one
thing that I like about that. But to get back to your point, I had wondered the same thing because
what's the effect of exogenous ketones on normal fatty acid metabolism. And the reason I'd wonder
that is because there was a paper that recently came out where I think it was the one that was
done in humans where humans, they were given the beta hydroxybutyrate ester for endurance
and it enhanced endurance performance, but they found it inhibited.
Yes. And also it inhibited fatty acid, something to do with the lip fatty acid transport out of
the adipose, something to do with where I was like going with somewhere, some of that had to do with
lipid metabolism, which suggested possibly there could be an inhibition.
Now, it's funny, I'm in New York next week and Dom is going to be in New York, Dom Degasino,
who obviously you know well. And we're grabbing dinner one night and we're going to talk about
this paper because I remember when it came out, Dom sent me an email.
You can pull it up. Then I'll know for sure if you want. Or I can just send it to you.
Yeah, send it to me for sure. Because there was something about that study that was a little bit
off. I need to kind of go back and look at it. But it does beg another question. So I want to
go back because I know this is going to be a theme today, which is multiple threads that are
easy for us to go off on. You and I are great at going on to it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Let's go back to the mice. Let's go back to the two studies.
Do you recall if in the Verden study, before they started cycling the ketogenic diet,
when they were just giving it to them all the time, did they have a window in which they could
eat ad libitum that they overate in or were they given 24-hour access to food?
24-hour.
So what they never tried then was, let's give you food for 10 hours and let you eat ad libitum.
Because that would be interesting if they would over eat in that setting. Maybe not that
interesting. The other experiment that I don't think has been done is, remember when they did
the, they took a variant which was high fat, but high-ish carb. And so it wasn't, there was enough
carb in the diet that it wasn't producing ketosis, but it was still a high fat diet.
I'd like to see that experiment repeated, but with an exogenous ketone. Because then you could
start to identify the effect of the carbohydrate specifically and tease out the effect of the fat
and the BHB. Right. I think I remember one of the big differences between the high fat, low carb,
and the actual ketogenic diet was the induction of PPR alpha. Yes, exactly. Which makes sense,
because that's involved in ketogenesis itself. But to what degree that regulates any of the other
important properties that were found, including the really the profound effects on the brain.
So I like to personally get my ketogenesis from my periods of fasting.
More so than carbohydrate restriction.
Well, I do refine carbohydrate restriction, but I also, I think there's a lot of benefits. And this
is part of the reason why for so long I was skeptical of a ketogenic diet is because I think
there's a lot of benefits in eating a variety of plants. I think that there's a lot of various
micronutrients that are much higher density in plants, folate, magnesium, vitamin K1, but also
there's a lot of fermentable fibers and things that are also really good for the gut microbiome,
which I also think is very important for regulating immune function. So that's kind of been my hangup.
But I think people like Dom seem to be doing a modified ketogenic diet where they're definitely
getting the greens, trying to get the leafy greens. So I think that one way to kind of get around that.
Plus, I think there's also a way to do a ketogenic diet where you're eating a lot of salmon, avocado,
nuts, olive oil, and it's not just butter and keto bombs and all this pork rinds and stuff,
where I'm just like, where's the nutrient density in some of that?
Yeah, it's funny. I mean, I guess it depends on how many calories you need, but at the time,
during that window when I was on a ketogenic diet, I was also still very active, certainly much more
so than now. And I really required a lot of calories. I mean, I couldn't maintain my weight
below 4,500 calories a day. And I still stuck to pretty strict absolutes on the protein and
carbohydrates. I really kept my carbs, and I didn't look at net carbs. Oh, by the way,
for those listening and wondering what that noise is, this is something Rhonda and I are very used
to. Those are FA-18s, which how many overhead drive-bys are we going to get today if you had
to predict? I would say three more? Yeah, I would say probably between three or four. Okay. Yeah,
it's the sound of freedom people, so just get used to it. So I was getting probably 50 grams
of carbohydrates, total carb. I should say probably about 80 grams of total carb, but you'll see what
type of carbs it was. Really had to limit protein to about 100 to 110 grams. If I went over that,
I would get kicked out. And so fat made up about 90% of my total calories. And so there's only so
many ways you can get that much fat. And the most efficient way is actually salad with olive oil. I
mean, I couldn't believe the amount of vegetables I had to consume to stay in ketosis. I basically
had to have two huge salads a day where I would make my own dressing, which was a heavy olive oil
based dressing. And I could probably only have one avocado a day, which I would always have because
other than anything over that I was getting too much carbohydrate. So it's like a lot of macadamia
nuts, a lot of olive oil, olive oil based everything. And then the hardest part for me was
clearly being stingy with the protein. What was in the salad? It's like, I mean, okay, so I'd go,
I'm a pretty boring guy. So it's romaine, tomatoes, cucumbers, celery, had to kind of
like limit the carrots a little bit. I normally love carrots. So you can eat tomatoes and
everything on the ketogenic. Yeah. Now again, part of it is I can get away with more because
I probably exercise more. And I was doing this before people were sort of putting butter in
their coffee and stuff like that. So that was not, I consumed a lot of dairy though. So it's the other
thing, tons of cheese, tons of sour cream, because you just needed those calories. And I actually
developed like a spreadsheet that was customized for my caloric needs. But I had this formula of
looking at every ingredient. Like, could you find the food that you could eat without restriction
that wouldn't destroy your ratios? And so for me at my caloric levels, like cream cheese and sour
cream were sort of the perfect thing. Whereas even high fat Greek yogurt had too much protein. So I
had to consume that in moderation. That's the other interesting thing. And I think I talked to Eric
about this was how much of the effects on health span were due to low protein intake and how much
were due to the actual being in ketosis. Yeah. I've talked about this with Vaulter a few times.
We don't see eye to eye on this because for several reasons. One, I'm not entirely convinced
of the IGF paradigm anymore. So that's one thing where the question I asked you, that would be my
answer. So five years ago, I would have said IGF is the devil, growth hormone is the devil. You
want them to be as low as possible. I'm not convinced of that today. And I can't wait to
explore that with you. But the other thing is if you really want to produce the lowest level of
insulin and IGF, I am not aware of a way to do that beyond the ketogenic diet that is incredibly low
in protein, incredibly low in carbohydrate. When I go back and look at my blood levels,
because I check my blood about every six to eight weeks, and I've been doing this for, you know,
10 years. I mean, my lowest IGF levels were during the three years I was in ketosis. I mean,
they were very low. They were, I mean, not ridiculously low, but 25th percentile for age
versus say 75th percentile today. So that makes sense to me because if you think about,
you know, some of the major dietary regulators of the IGF-1 pathway are protein, essentially
amino acids specifically, and also insulin. Insulin through IGF-PP3.
Exactly, or IPP1. So I mean, I think that, so for example, you know, if someone's eating a low protein
and low, you're getting, you may not be a vegan, but even if you had a, you're limiting your protein,
you know, even to some degree, you're certainly getting more than someone, maybe me, that's not
doing that really, although I do kind of limit my protein. But it's a misconception. You see,
I think a lot of people assume ketogenic diets are high protein diets. I think some people do
consider that, yeah. But if you're, there may be certain people out there who can produce ketones
with high protein, but in my experience, personally and more important clinically, meaning,
I don't know, over the course of my practice, my career in medicine, I mean, I've probably at
least encountered 50 or 60 patients at a very detailed level on ketogenic diets, almost with
that exception, protein is the bigger thing that fouls people up. And so that's the thing I've
always found a bit confusing in some of those discussions is, and even Eric mentioned this on
your podcast, which is, well, you got to be careful if you're on a ketogenic diet, you don't have too
much protein. And I was like, those don't go hand in hand. You're not on a ketogenic diet if you're
eating a lot of protein, because you won't make the ketones. That said, I wouldn't be surprised
if there are polymorphisms that allow people more or less. And you've obviously talked a lot about
the PPAR alpha, is it PPAR alpha or PPAR gamma, where you see the differences in a person's
ability to generate ketones? The PPAR alpha is predominantly found in the liver and it's involved
in fatty acid catabolism, the production of ketone bodies. So that would be the major one.
Now there's nothing empirically, I've seen in literature that's looked specifically at PPAR
alpha and a ketogenic diet or fasting, but most of the literature out there looking at the effects
of PPAR alpha with people that are either head or homozygous have to do with the context of high
saturated fat, low polyunsaturated fat diet, because polyunsaturated fat activates the PPAR
family of transcription factors, which are nuclear hormone receptor transcription factors. But the
PPAR gamma is predominantly found in adipose tissue. I mean, they're found in other tissues,
but I see predominantly that's like the most, they're highly expressed in that adipose tissue.
And it plays a role in basically taking up fatty acids into adipose tissue, whereas the alpha,
which is in the liver, plays a role in the transport, catabolism. So one would just sort
of imagine, I mean, it would be nice to see that someone look at that, people with these specific
SNPs and how that... Does Prometheus identify various SNPs of PPAR alpha? Yes, but they don't
really tell you anything. They sort of pull abstracts from PubMed and just kind of like dump
it there. So you kind of can start with the research there. I've been developing a genetic
tool and I just, we're actually developing it a lot more of a former NIH geneticist who's
probably phenomenal, who's been working with me on to help me sort of develop those. Basically,
look at the literature and see what some of these SNPs are doing. And then in conjunction with
looking at biomarkers, various blood biomarkers to kind of help people guide what sort of they
should do, what's a bypass around it, a potential bypass, for example. So with the PPAR alpha or
gamma, I think that the take-home, at least from the literature, is essentially you want to have a
higher ratio of poly and monounsaturated fat to saturated fat ratio in order to lower your
type 2 diabetes risk. You're saying for any, for people with the wild type or with people with
certain SNPs. With the SNPs, within PPAR alpha, yeah, and gamma as well because to some degrees,
some of the ones in PPAR gamma affect the uptake of fatty acids and adipose tissue and also muscle.
And so it kind of can affect, you know, you have a lot more free fatty acids around and that can,
you know, have an effect on insulin sensitivity and other things as well.
We should talk about this offline because I have a subset of patients for which we have such rich
data. And if I'm positive, all of them would be interested in knowing this and, you know, we'd
certainly get their permission, but it would be interesting in taking their, you know, just their
straight up 23andMe data. So here's the pattern I've seen and I'm very curious as to what the
overlap is. So there's a clearly a subset of people. I think my N is too small to quantify it,
but directionally it seems like, I don't know, 10 or 20% of people. When you put them on ketogenic
diets in the standard way, which usually ends up meaning you're getting at least 40% of your
calories from saturated fat, typically 40 to 45% from mono and the remainder from poly,
everything goes to hell in a hand basket. And the obvious things that go to hell in a hand basket
have been certainly written about on the blogosphere and Twitter sphere, which is usually
their LDL particle numbers skyrockets, despite the fact that their triglycerides go down. So
they seem to be getting more insulin sensitive, but yet inflammation is going up. And you see
that both specifically cardiac specifically, so things like oxidized LDL and LPPLA too,
but even non specifically C reactive protein, fibrinogen, but the deeper level is the why.
And what you see is they're making much more cholesterol markers of cholesterol biosynthesis,
like does master law go way up. And some of their phytosterols go up, which is very counterintuitive
phytosterols would generally go down on a ketogenic diet, but they're going way up,
suggesting that they're absorbing much more cholesterol, like biliary cholesterol.
So the first time I noticed this was 2012. And I think I wrote about this once on a blog,
but I don't remember. Maybe I'm thinking of another example. And it was this relatively
young patient who really loved being on a ketogenic diet. But when we get his blood test back,
I mean, his LDL particle number was above 3,500 nanomole per liter. And I know there are a lot of
guys out there who seem to think that as long as you're on a ketogenic diet, it doesn't matter.
None of this stuff matters. I completely don't subscribe to that. And my view is that's
irresponsible. So I said to them, I said, look, I don't think a ketogenic diet is right for you.
And he said, no, no, no, no. It's the best thing I've ever done. Like I feel better. I look better.
I'm performing better. We got to figure out a way to do this. And the only thing I could think of,
and I talked with Tom Dayspring about this. And he said, let's try an experiment and rip all the
saturated fat out of his diet. He was sort of like me. He was eating a lot. He, meaning he's a high
caloric consumer. So that gets really hard. So we created a diet form that was only about 20 to
25 grams a day of saturated fat. And he ended up getting about 65% of his fat calories from
monounsaturated fat, which was pretty gross. I mean, you're drinking olive oil at that point,
but he was interested in doing the experiment. And sure enough after, I don't know, maybe eight
to 12 weeks, same macronutrient distribution in terms of fat, protein, carbohydrate. The only
shift was the type of fat. So we just substituted mono for saturated. His LDLP was 1300 animal per
liter. All of the inflammation was gone and all of the sterile biomarkers went back to normal.
I've since seen that about six times. And now I'm wondering if we took those patients and ran them
through what you're doing. Yeah. Yeah. That would be really interesting. Would they be the ones that
have those snips? And there's a variety of them that do that. So there's the PPR alpha, PPR gamma.
There's a, there's a couple of FTO related snips also that the ratio of saturated. And basically
in the literature, these studies have all looked at the ratio of saturated to mono and polyunsaturated
fat. And for whatever reason, people with those snips, when they have a higher saturated fat to
poly or mono and or mono, they have higher inflammation, higher oxidized LDL, higher
small dense LDL, higher, you can just, you know, all these just terrible. Do you have a sense of
the frequency based on the research you've done on this? How prevalent that is? Kind of. I would
say, you know, I'd have to look back at the data probably less than 20%. So it might be in the
ballpark of what I'm seeing for this different phenotype. It might be. Yeah, it might be. So
that would be really interesting to run them through, through my tool. And, and like I said,
we're, we're even expanding that a little bit. I found, I found a few more.
Are patients sending you any of their data or are they doing it on their own and just
they're doing it on their own. Some people have shared their data with me because they've emailed
me and something interesting. And I'm like, Oh, wow, that's super interesting. Do you mind sharing
that with me? And they have. So if anybody's listening to this and they're saying, Hey,
you know, I had an advanced lipid test before and after I went on a ketogenic diet and I
looked like this situation you described, can they reach out to you through your
blog and send this data to you? They can actually just use the genetic tool and then sort of,
you know, share with you the data. If they want to share with me the data, you know, I can't
promise anything, but, but they can certainly get the why themselves by just using genetic tool
right now, which, which I have, I have free reports for, for example, the PPR genes, but then I have
a whole comprehensive report. That's a $10 recommended. So if someone doesn't want to pay
$10 to do the comprehensive, they can just get the free report and get the Y potential Y themselves.
So I hope that anyone listening to this, because I, again, if I'm seeing this at 10 to 20% of the
time and you're seeing it, then it'd be great to get a few hundred people who are that phenotype
and find out if the phenotype matches the genotype. Right. Yeah, it would absolutely be. And like I
said, I have, I have had people have that problem where they've tried to catch a genetic diet and
couldn't figure out and they did have one or even more than, than one of the SNPs that regulate
fatty acid metabolism. So, and then there's another phenotype that fortunately is more rare.
And I also wonder what's going on with PPR alpha specifically, which is people who
do everything by the book. And maybe I'm a sucker and maybe I'm gullible and maybe I believe patients
too much, but I don't think I've ever had a patient lie to me. I really think like when they're not
doing what they're supposed to be doing, they tell you I'm not doing what I'm supposed to be doing.
So it's not uncommon in this rare subset of patients that is where they're doing everything
by the book. I mean, they're working their tail off to keep their carbs here, to keep their protein
here, to keep their fat here, to keep it within this distribution. And they cannot get even close
to half a millimolar of BHB in their blood. And to me, that's a really frustrating situation. It's
frustrating for the patient because they're sort of like, what the hell I'm doing everything right.
Like I'm not making ketones. And, you know, I think Steve Finney sort of put out this notion
that the threshold was about 0.5 millimolar. I don't have anything to argue that one way or the
other. So I generally can, you know, based on my own empirical experience personally, I sort of felt
like one millimolar was about the threshold. But again, I think that's neither here nor there.
But when these people are doing what I'm describing and they're at best 0.2, maybe 0.3 millimolar,
it just made me wonder there's something in their machinery that's not doing this. Now, the question
is, is it a like policies problem? Is it an oxidation problem? Is it a conversion problem?
I mean, that I don't know, but it would also be interesting to understand where could the
weak links be in their ketosis machinery. Right. And there's probably, you know, there's a variety
of snips in these genes. And, you know, there may be certain snips that haven't even really been
tested or who knows. But it sounds like, you know, to me that there's certainly something going on
with the process of ketogenesis in some of the patients and their activity levels or they're
active. Yeah, we're pretty, I mean, we've evolved a lot in our thinking on how those patients can be
helped, but it seems that the best way to get them over that hump is fasting coupled with exercise
if they're capable. But it's got to be relatively, it has to be, it's not gardening, like it's got to
be exercise exercise, you know, they have to really deplete glycogen. So that's the other thing I sort
of wonder in some of these folks is what's happening with with gluconeogenesis? Because I
think until you start to dip down in glycogen a little bit, it's really hard to do this. And of
course we can't do liver biopsies. Wait, so fasting does get them into ketosis. And so again,
we're dealing with such a small end that I don't, I want to be thoughtful about not generalizing too
much. So there's one patient in particular who's the poster child for couldn't do the ketosis thing
straight away. But when we put him on every month, a five day FMD, so he would do the five day FMD,
but ketogenic, not long goes FMD. And then the 25 days of ad lib was time restricted eating
ketogenic. Then we've seen great results doing that in two people. So that would suggest that
something again, we're not doing this as an experiment at this point, it's like clinical,
it's like just try to get the job done sort of thing. But that would suggest that something
about the fasting and or the exercise and or the time restriction could get them over the hump.
But it's interesting because from an evolutionary perspective, you should have been selected out
really quickly if you couldn't make ketones efficiently. Well, it sounds to me that maybe
maybe there's the glycogen, you know, you're not you're not getting depleting the glycogen too,
if that's, you know, so maybe it's not to do with the production of ketone bias, but it's actually
just takes a long time to deplete that glycogen. I do think there's a huge variation. Obviously,
physical activity plays a role in that as well. I can fast I can do you know, like when I do my
time restricted eating, ideally, I like to do it within, you know, nine or 10 hours, eat all my
food within 10 hours. And then I, you know, I like to fast for like 15 hours, I can do that. And with
my physical activity levels, you know, I will be closer to one millimolar fast like you will get
to one millimolar after 15 hours of fasting. I will be closer to that when I'm really physically
active. Like during the periods a couple of years ago, when I was doing lots of like, long,
like long distance running and stuff, I can get closer. I mean, I mean, I'm going off of like a
precision extra, which probably is not very precision extras. It's I mean, that's really good.
Yeah, so I can get between like point seven millimolar to like point nine.
But are you consuming a ketogenic diet during your feeding? So my diet typically, so I like I said,
I've never really intentionally tried to do a ketogenic diet. But my my diet is I pretty much
eat a lot of the same things. And typically, it's salmon, a salad or a sauteed vegetable with
olive oil, some pasture raised butter from pasture raised animals. And my fruits will be like blue
berries, I'll have avocado. So I'll have sometimes I'll have a smoothie with some blueberries,
avocado and kale. And will you have two meals in that window? Or it depends if I have the smoothie
or not. Typically, I'll have breakfast and then an early dinner. And then I'll have like a snack,
either nuts or the smoothie, the kale with some blueberries and avocado. So I think it, you know,
I need a lot of nuts too. You know, I probably do. What kind of nuts? Walnuts, macadamia nuts, pistachios,
cashews, almonds, I think probably I put cashews in the candy category. Oh, really? No, no, I just
mean like, I can't stop eating those things. So when I when I talk about nuts, I'm like, I eat nuts
and sometimes cashews because like, I just might as well be eating M&Ms. Is there a lot? Well, yeah,
no, look, all kidding aside, when I was on the ketogenic diet, and I had to be very mindful of
this stuff. Basically, I could only consume almonds and macadamia. Everything else was just a little
too high in carbohydrate. The cashews just like my own personal demons. I don't know what it is
about cashews. Like, I love watermelon, like the summer like right now. Oh, like my son loves watermelon.
You could eat a whole one. Oh, yeah, like put a little salt on it, like my father-in-law from
the south and taught me that. So in the summertime, I like to, I like to eat some watermelon. I like
to eat peaches, you know, so I'll definitely indulge in more fruits because that's when they're
around. But you know, so I do, I think my diet tends to be... I wouldn't be surprised if before
you entered your like, so let's say you finish your feeding window just before you went to bed,
it wouldn't surprise me if you're already at 0.2 or 0.3 millimolar, right? Probably, yeah.
I never actually measured that right. So check that and that'll give me a sense because if you...
Well, I'm not doing as strict because I'm still nursing, so I'm because it's just so hard to like
time-wise get everything I'm eating probably more like within the 11 to 12 hour. Okay, well, when
you get back to the 15, I'd be curious because if you're actually able to go from 0 or 0.1 millimolar
to 0.7 to 1 millimolar in a 15 hour fast, that's impressive. So when I took the exogenous ketones
and I've done this... Did you do the ester? I did the ester by HBMN. I did their instructions,
which is eat it with a high carbohydrate diet. So I had a little bowl of some whole
oats with some blueberries in it and then I took the BHB ester. I literally went from like 0.1
millimolar ketone in one hour to 6 millimolar. Wow. Six, in one hour. That's really high.
So that's impressive. Okay.
I'm trying to think. I definitely don't get that high and that's just with one bottle?
With one bottle. And then how long did it last, do you recall?
It depends on whether or not I did exercise, like intense exercise. And so if I did the intense
exercise like an hour later, I was down to like two or three or something. And have you ever
taken it and just done work, for example, where basically the brain is doing more of the exercise
than... Yeah, that's mostly what I do it now, but I'm not measuring it because I'm usually like
doing a podcast or going traveling and doing something. But that's typical what I use it for,
is that. So I'm not really using it for exercise. Yeah, they've really come a long way and taste.
Really? They still taste awful. Yeah, it's funny. I remember Kevin Rose, who's a good mutual friend
of ours, when he tried them first, he texted me and he's like, dude, these things aren't that bad.
You made it sound like these things were horrible. And I was like, when I had it, I thought I was
drinking kerosene or jet fuel. I thought I was going to die, go blind first, then die. He goes,
no, no, no, this stuff's good. He goes, actually, I wouldn't call it a sipping key tone, but it's
actually pretty... I was talking to the guys at Human and the T Delta S folks, I think they've
done a good job kind of making them less ridiculous. They must really have tasted bad when you tried
it. Because I personally think it's closer to the kerosene side than the... It was so bad,
Rhonda, that there was a good three month period where my favorite thing to do, more than anything
in the world, was if anyone came over to my house for dinner, they had to try one finger dip worth
of stuff. And of course, the first time I drank it, I just took 50 ml and chugged it neat without
mixing it or anything like that. And I feel they just getting people to try this stuff.
The salts are obviously much more palatable. Yeah, I've tried the salts.
Less studied, but more palatable. I didn't really... I certainly didn't feel like I had the same
effects as the ester. And also, if I took a really high dose of it, I felt like I had some GI distress.
Absolutely. And I have also noticed that for some people, that is... For me, that's the case. So I
cannot take the BHB ester on an empty stomach. The only way I can tolerate that at high doses is
either to put it with powdered MCT or actually just take it with a meal, which in many ways defeats
the purpose because I like it as a way to avoid meals. Did it lower your blood glucose? Because
so significantly, it was astounding. Yeah, no, it's pretty impressive.
That needs to be studied. Yeah. Yeah. And I know that Jeff Wu, the CEO at Human,
is very interested in that. And I republished a post I wrote five years ago on exogenous ketones
a couple of weeks ago. And a lot of scientists have reached out and said, hey, we're really
interested in studying this. What can you tell us about this? And so I think people are starting to
realize that's an interesting way to lower glucose. Really significantly. More than 20%.
I dropped 30 points. Wow. Yeah, that's perfect.
Yeah. Like after a high carbohydrate, like I said, I had oatmeal with some blueberries. It was nuts.
Of course, my blood sugar because at the time too, I mean, I've just been nursing at night. And so
waking up multiple times, that is terrible for your blood glucose levels and such. But so they
were a little higher than usual. But yeah, I dropped me 30 points. Well, yeah, that's more
than we typically see. Is it? Yeah. On the topic of blood glucose, have you ever experimented with
Acrobose? No, I've experimented with it with cells and culture, but not like personally.
This stuff's pretty interesting. It works quite well. Yeah. I'll certainly, if I'm going to
indulge in some high carb action, I'm going to take a hundred milligrams of Acrobose beforehand
and just flatline my glucose. Wow. In many ways, I find it actually more potent than metformin
at glucose reduction. I mean, I think metformin has many other effects that we'll probably get
into as well. Let's go back to the IGF thing. Yeah. Because this is sort of the thing that,
here's the thing, I'll just jump right to my punchline and my question with this. There are
two issues I now have with things I used to take to be the God's honest truth. Actually, three
things. The first is I found Cynthia Kenyon's work on the DAF-16 mutants in C. elegans to be the most
convincing evidence of the role of IGF or attenuating IGF in longevity. And I now question
that, not question the work, but question the inference that that can be applied to humans
given the fact that only their germ cells divide. And therefore cancer in that organism looks
nothing like cancer in us. Cancer in that organism is only a cell getting larger. There is no
proliferation. We have to sort of, I mean, it's obvious, it's the risk of stating the obvious,
which is we're not worms, but that's a huge difference in biology. So that's the first
thing. Let me let you comment on that. Yes, because I've done those experiments.
Actually, that's probably what straight out of college. And I went to work at the Salk Institute
with Andrew Dillon, who trained with Cynthia Kenyon. I was a chemistry major in college and I
decided I kind of wanted to try some real biology. Say I only had a little bit of biology in college.
And so I went to work at the Salk and really it was like those first experiments I did
with worms where we would knock down the insulin IGF-1 signaling pathway, also known as the DEV-2.
And the worms would live literally 100% longer. They'd go from two weeks to four weeks, right?
Yeah. I mean, it was like, and not only that, the worms were so youthful. You would look at these
worms, because it's all I would do day after day under a microscope is just picking and poking and
looking at the worms and how they move. And as they get older, they start to become less mobile.
And I mean, it's just very obvious. It's the most convincing data, right?
It is very convincing. And now it's me in my mind was kind of like when I was like,
holy shit, we have a gene that's sort of homologous to this. And this is happening in those worms.
I want to understand that. And here's the thing about that data. And this is what I think,
if you get rid of another gene that's homologous to Foxo, DEV-16.
Oh, DEV-16 is right. That's homologous to Foxo.
It completely obliterates the lifespan extension, meaning it's the Foxo-3 that seems to be really
important for the life. We have how many? We have four Foxos?
You mean different Fox genes? Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. I don't know exactly how many, but the Foxo, we have three.
We have one, two, and four. Was it one, two, and three?
I thought there was like a one, two, four, five. But their analog is 16. I remember that, right?
Their DEV-16 is basically our Foxo. Yes. Foxo. Yeah. So, okay. Well, anyways,
yeah, I'm not sure I'm getting confused with the number.
You know this better than I do, but okay, yeah.
But what is interesting is that the lifespan extension was completely like ameliorated.
And did their health span curves, because the experiment you're describing,
and no one can see what I'm doing, but you know what I'm talking about, like the natural
was a two-week lifespan where for the first week, they're youthful, and then they have a declining
health span curve. So at the time of their death, they're totally decrepit. In the experiment,
you're describing, if I'm thinking of the same one, you doubled the lifespan, and their
longevity curve became a square function. It just went out and boom.
Kind of. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, that's exactly what happened. But you get rid of the DEV-16,
and they're like wild type. Oh, they're like wild type. Okay.
And that largely has to do with, you know, so that the IGF-1 insulin signaling pathway both
inhibit Foxo-3. So if you get rid of that inhibition, constitutively, Foxo-3 is constantly
active in those worms. I mean, it's just like super, you know, they're making superoxide
dismutase, they're making more stem cells, they're making just everything's active, you know,
more autophagy, more stress, like all these stress resistance pathways. I mean,
Foxo-3 is a transcription factor. It regulates a whole host of genes, many of which have to do with
DNA repair, autophagy, stem cell function, production of antioxidants, and anti-inflammatory
pathways. So it's a lot of really good stuff. You want active all the time. So there's that
component to the longevity pathway. And actually, if you look at the animal data from rodents where
they're caloric restricted, if you get rid of the Foxo-3, the median lifespan extension is gone.
So the lifespan extension depends on Foxo-3. The cancer stuff was still like, it didn't matter.
So the cancer reduction didn't depend on Foxo-3, only the lifespan extension. So I think there may
be an uncoupling between humans and IGF-1. One of the major problems with IGF-1 is actually cancer.
And if you look at, you know, animal studies, if you look at human studies like humans that have
polymorphisms that make them have more IGF-1, they have much higher cancer incidence, vice
versa. So if you look at people that have polymorphisms, I think- Is that the case? I mean,
we look at the opposites, right? We look at the ones that have low GH and by proxy low IGF and
have less cancer. So you're talking about Laron syndrome. Yeah. So Laron syndrome, yes, they do.
But I think there's also another one in IGF. There's HETs and IGF-1 receptor. So this is,
you're not talking about acromegaly or people that are making too much GH.
They also are more susceptible to cancer as well. Yes. I am talking about them as well, actually.
The people with acromegaly are more susceptible to cancer. Maybe I am. That's what I was referring
to with that have higher circulating levels of IGF-1. So you're saying you can't uncouple the
growth hormone from IGF-1? Yeah. That's been one of the things I've struggled with is it's hard to
uncouple the GH, the effect of GH on the liver. In humans. Yes. Yeah, exactly. But animal studies,
that has been uncoupled. If you do any sort of tumor transplant animals and then
make them have IGF-1 through a variety of modalities, the cancer will grow rapidly.
So how do we explain the human epidemiology? There are a few people that are more critical
of epidemiology than me. I'm not a particular fan of it. But I find it to be quite interesting in
the negative, meaning the contra positives within epidemiology can be quite interesting.
So this is the next thing that got me going, wait a minute. And that was, there's a U-shaped
mortality curve that is skewed to the right for IGF and all-cause mortality, cancer mortality,
cardiovascular mortality, and neurodegenerative mortality. But when you uncouple them by disease,
you see a very interesting pattern. So all-cause mortality, as IGF goes up, it actually starts to
go down. It naders at the 70th percentile and then it starts to rise. But it doesn't get as high
as it started. I know for people listening, this is confusing, so we'll include the figures of all
these from the papers. But the point is, it's not that as IGF goes up, mortality goes up.
It's the opposite for 70% of the ledger, only at the very end. In other words, only high levels
of IGF, very high levels of IGF seem problematic. And as I know you've talked about, I've heard you
talk about this on your podcast, you have to then desegregate that by age. The older you get,
the better IGF seems to be, presumably because of the preservation of lean tissue.
It turns out that most of the uptick in the mortality above the 70th percentile is driven
by cancer. But actually cardiovascular disease and neurodegenerative disease seem to get,
they flatline by the end. So meaning there was no benefit to being at the 100th percentile
or the 99th percentile versus the 80th versus the 70th, but you weren't getting penalized for it,
which suggested to me that low IGF might not be the ticket. Maybe it's some combination of
cycling high and low IGF, but living at around the median to slightly above that, the 60th,
the 70th percentile. And again, that's probably more a function of my misunderstanding of the
literature five years ago, but I really came away thinking IGF, we've got to keep that as low as
possible. It's funny, you and I have- We've evolved in the-
Yeah, very similar because I now also think that IGF-1 does play a very important role,
obviously in development, but also in the repair of muscle, in the growth of muscle,
preserving muscle mass. Also, it gets transported across the blood-brain barrier,
plays an important role in neurogenesis and allowing existing neurons to survive,
which brings me back to that gray matter thing with the lemurs. And the thing that was interesting to
me was the effect of exercise on IGF-1. And the fact that for one, it's been shown that the boost
in neurogenesis after exercise in the brain via brain drive requires IGF-1. Animal studies have
shown that mostly in rodents have shown that exercise causes IGF-1 across the blood-brain
barrier, get into the brain. But in human studies, I've also seen some showing that it does lower
serum levels. I think presumably it's also going into the muscle and the brain. So I think that
people that are exercising, they're putting that IGF-1 to the places where it's supposed to go,
muscle tissue, brain tissue as well. But in addition to that, and this is what's more recent
work from Dr. Walter Longo, is that we know that he does his prolonged fast and I think the prolonged
fasting is extremely interesting for a couple of main reasons. And one is, I think that it has
tremendous potential for the treatment of autoimmune disease and also cancer based on
his work. And what he has shown now in animal studies and some pilot clinical studies is that
doing a prolonged fast and or in some cases, the fasting mimicking diet causes this massive
shrinking of organs where he doesn't know how much of it's due to cell size decreasing versus
apoptosis. He does know apoptosis is occurring and he has showed that in multiple publications.
There is a massive induction of apoptosis after a prolonged fast, which makes sense because it's
a very strong stress. And then after, during the refeeding phase, their organs basically come back.
They come back, they grow, regrow. And presumably selectively repopulate. Yeah. So he's shown that
the stem cells get activated. So basically, they have to be activated by the low IGF-1,
but then to proliferate and differentiate into whatever tissue type we're talking about, let's
say we're talking about the immune system, then IGF-1 is required for that proliferation and
differentiation and repopulation of the tissue, which means you can't just keep the IGF-1 low.
The refeeding is just as important as the deprivation. And the IGF-1 is key in that.
And so, you know, what he's shown now is that you can take, for example, in the multiple sclerosis
animal model, you can actually cause stem cells to be activated through the prolonged fast and
then during the refeeding phase, the stem cells make non-disfunctional. So they're making normal,
non-auto-immune cells. And he's done like a pilot clinical study with multiple sclerosis,
people with multiple sclerosis, and it's helped with symptoms. But he's also done these cancer
studies. And this is kind of where there's been some clinical studies that he's been involved with,
like a 48-hour water fast that's been done in patients undergoing standard of care treatment.
And he's shown that it was tolerable. Not only that, there seemed to be less myelotoxicity,
less neutropenia. So basically, they're  and it sensitized cancer cells to death. So not only
were the cancer cells dying more, but less of the normal cells were dying. And then he's gone ahead
and shown this in animal models, also with the fasting mimicking diet. And it's like if you look
at the data, particularly in the animal model, because they can, you know, do all the tissue
harvesting and stuff, I mean, it's like  it's so phenomenal that I would not be surprised that in
the next 10 years, it will be required part of standard of care because it seems to be so
incredibly robust at selectively killing cancer cells, which, you know, makes sense. I mean,
oncogenes, they screw up all sorts of things. One of them is the stress response. And, you know,
cancer cells can't respond to stress. They're primed to die. I mean, it's  I spent a long
time, you know, studying cancer cell metabolism, apoptosis with Doug Green and Joseph Opperman at
St. Jude Children's Research Hospital. And that's kind of one of the primary ways that a lot of these
chemotherapeutic drugs, if they can get to the tumor site, work, is that because it's a stress,
cancer cells can't handle it, you know, they die. So I kind of went off on a tangent here.
So to get back to the IGF-1  Let me say one thing going back to what you just said that is also
interesting, but in the same thing. So I agree that I think that it would really be great if
patients had a better insight into nutrition going into chemotherapy. And the few times I go and give
talks at hospitals or go and talk at like a cancer meeting, I'm amazed at how resistant the
oncologists are. On average, obviously there were exceptions, but on average to interfering with
nutrition. Because in many ways, their primary concern tragically is preserving weight. And so
I always get a little verklempt when I walk through an oncology ward and I see patients drinking in
sure. Like, I couldn't think of a worse thing you'd want to consume when you have cancer.
And yet the goal is, hey, we got to fatten these people up. So I agree with you. And I really hope
that this research is accelerated because I do think patients would benefit greatly from this.
And the other application that I saw of this several years ago  This is quite old now,
but it blew my mind. I'm not sure if you're familiar with Jay Mitchell's work up at Harvard.
He did an experiment where he took three groups of mice. So the first group were
constitutively calorically restricted for their entire life. These were probably like one and
a half year old mice. So they're about halfway through their life. Starting the adult. Yeah,
so these animals were constantly at 70% caloric intake. The next group was your control group.
And then your third group was ad libitum diet until two days before an operation. And at which
point they were calorie restricted to a near fast. And I'd have to go back and look. I can't remember
if it was 24 or 48 hours of fasting. It might have been a 24 hour fast. 48 would be pretty extreme
for mice. So in summary, you've got control. This straight up eating, you've got 70%
or 30% CR forever. And then you've got control and then fasted for a day. All the mice were then
operated on where their femoral arteries were ligated, held for a period of time,
and then they were reperfused. For people not familiar with what that means. So that means you
open the animal up, you put clamps on the femoral arteries, which would basically stop all perfusion
of blood to the lower part of the body. And then after some period of time, just before you kill
the animal, you release that and then you reperfuse the blood. Basically the oxygen
reperfuses the organism that's considered a reperfusion injury, which is about one of the
most stressful things you can do to an organism so that you can really rapidly kill someone by
doing that. And that's something that in surgery happens quite a bit. For example,
you end up having to clamp something off to repair something downstream of that.
Okay. So what happened was all of the control animals died without exception. Of the other two
groups, the groups that were either calorie restricted for life or transiently starved
before the surgery, a significant subset did not die. And I can't remember the number. And again,
I know we're going to probably link to this study. So people are going to listen to this and go,
that idiot got all those details wrong, but this is the gist of it. A non-trivial subset of them
lived. And what's interesting is you could get the same benefit by an acute period of caloric
restriction in proximity to an insult that you could get by a lifelong of caloric restriction.
And the third piece that was interesting was the group that were just starved transiently actually
had a faster recovery, which again, they were fitter organisms. I remember the first time I came
across that thinking there's got to be something to cycling. And people used to always ask me like,
why are you on a ketogenic diet every minute of every day? Would there be any benefit in cycling?
Now I still don't know the answer to that question, but I'm more curious about it now
based on what you just described from Vaulter's work, plus this type of stuff,
plus just the general ethos of the way we evolved. We've fasted, we fed, we fasted, we fed,
we fasted a long time, we gorged. It just seems we've evolved for cycling.
Right. Yeah, I agree. It's really that with Vaulter's work, I just I'm so excited about the
prolonged fasting and the potential benefits of it. I think that actually something that you and
I discussed several years ago, and I had you interviewed you on my podcast, that you brought
up that I thought was really interesting had to do with like the failed clinical trials with binding
IGF-1 in cancer. And Vaulter brought up something interesting in a conversation I had with him. And
that is possibly that we now know IGF-1 having low and IGF-1 is important. So if you're constantly
having low IGF-1 and the IGF-1 is important for the immune system or population, you can imagine
the context of cancer when you're giving other treatments along with it, that would be important
because your immune system is key in working off cancer. And I thought that was a really interesting
point. Of course, we don't have evidence of that. But I think it's something that would be interesting
to investigate and it makes sense. Yeah, I definitely am on the same page with you. I'm not,
like I started out with saying, I don't think that chronic caloric restriction and low IGF-1 is the
essential like way for improving health span. I do think that IGF-1, you want it to go to your muscle,
you want it to go to your brain. So I think people should definitely be active, especially if they're
eating a high protein and or even high carbohydrate or something that's going to produce a lot of
insulin. They shouldn't be eating refined carbs, but people do. If they're eating them, they should
definitely be exercising. That's another change in my belief system, I think, today versus, I don't
know, five or six years ago. I think five or six years ago, I didn't think exercise was that
important to longevity, which actually sounds ridiculous for anyone who knows me because I
was probably exercising four hours a day, but not because I believed it would make me live longer.
It was just sort of soothing my addictions. But I think today I feel I am much more convinced by a
lot of the data you've described, certainly the central stuff. When we published this paper
earlier this year with Richard Isaacson that you and I were talking about before we started recording,
we wanted to get a sense of like, if you took a completely unbiased approach and look at the
literature, what was the single most compelling thing you could do to generate or preserve brain
health? And we came away thinking that it was actually exercise. And I remember when the
analysts were kind of going through this and showing me all the data, I was like, come on,
guys, there's no way exercise could be the most important thing for brain health. And again,
I'm saying this as a guy who loves exercise more than anybody, but it just struck me as there's
no way. And again, I think part of it was I was just thinking about it through the vascular lens.
And obviously, you know, I think better than I do that when you start to think about brain health,
you have to think about it through a vascular lens, a metabolic lens, growth factor lens. I mean,
there were overlapping but distinct pathways that are going to influence brain health. And so
I was kind of humbled by that. And now, I guess in many ways, I'm a little more adamant about it
with my patients. Not that I wasn't, you know, adamant before, but this is like, boy, if you're
not active every day, like, we got to change that. I actually the main reason I exercise is for my
brain is certainly just not only for, you know, preventing neurodegenerative disease and atrophy
and all that, but just because it affects my executive function and affects my anxiety levels,
it affects my ability to make decisions. I absolutely, if I have something that's bothering
me, you're giving me anxiety, or have to make a really important decision, going for a long run
really helps me. And there's been studies showing that it helps with executive function,
long term planning, like aerobic exercise, specifically, you know, and then high intensity
interval training, all that stuff, they all they all do different things.
Well, that's the thing we couldn't we couldn't tease this out of the literature, which again,
probably is just a limitation of shitty human clinical trials. But that's the second order
question, right? Which is if you're going to take the Tim Ferriss approach, which is what's the
minimum effective dose? Because there are some people like maybe you or I, who I think just
generally like exercise and also get these other benefits, these endorphin benefits. But there are
some people who are like, look, what do I need to do? Like, I'm going to treat exercise like medicine.
And I think in that setting, I'm still not clear. So if you were that person, would I say Rhonda,
as long as you are lifting weights, one hour, three times a week, like if you can only give
me three hours, would that be how I'd want you to spend it? Or would I rather you be doing anaerobic
aerobic type thing like I mean, that's, to me, those are where these biomarkers start to become
very important, because we're not going to generate hard outcome studies with that level of control.
Once you, you know, try to control that many variables and be that strict about it, you're
going to very much lose a hard outcome prospectively. But if we knew what to measure, right, and that's,
you know, would we be measuring an integral of IGF, for example, so how much it rises, how much it
falls, and then what that looks like over time. But I guess that's the funny thing, right? Like the
more we learn, the less we know. Yeah, absolutely. I think that we definitely don't know the answer to
that question. But I think there's a lot of data out there showing, for example, strength training,
you know, there's benefits on the brain that's been shown published, this benefits on preventing
muscle atrophy, there's benefits on preventing cancer incident, like, that's all been shown for
strength training for aerobic. And you know, this high intensity interval training is also, also
seems to be making its way as well. Like, like there was a study that I that I found VO2 max,
this is, you know, the ability of your your body to transport oxygen during exercise, which also is
an indicator of when you're not exercising, and obviously transporting oxygen to the brain,
for example, is extremely important. VO2 max declines with age, like 1% per year,
I forgot starting at what age, but you know, so 10% per decade.
So that's almost parallels the muscle mass decline.
It does, it does parallel. Exactly. And there was a study showing that 24 sessions of high
intensity interval training where it was like a 45 minute session, five minute warm up,
five minute cool down, and then you know, in between the max intervals, which were like,
pretty long, like a minute, there was, you know, the 70% of max water. Anyway, so
24 of those increased VO2 max by 12%. So you're literally taking an entire decade
of decline and like reversing it with the 24.
Yeah, that's, that's actually a good point. I when I was more active as a sort of competitive,
you know, in cycling, you we would get our VO2 max tested about twice a year.
Ryan Flaherty, who we were talking about before the podcast, who's one of my close friends,
and you've got to know him as well. I learned from Ryan that actually VO2 max is not the
most important indicator as a runner or cyclist. It's V VO2 max or P VO2 max that matters. In other
words, for a runner, V VO2 max is much more predictive of performance, which is the velocity
you carry at VO2 max. And for a cyclist, it's P VO2 max, which is the power output at VO2 max.
That said, every time you go to test, you want it to test well. So, you know, over time I learned
how to game the system. You know, I want to make sure my VO2 max is in the 70s, which again, to put
that in perspective, like that's not at the level of professional athlete or something like the guys
that are winning the Tour de France are in the high 80s or low 90s in terms of milligrams per
mil per kilogram. But nevertheless, just altering my training for three weeks before a VO2 max test
and dropping my weight. So if I shed two kilograms and did those types of intervals, I actually had
it down to a science where there was a workout I would do, you know, in Carmel Valley, you've got
the 56 that goes out and it's got a bike path next to it. There's a section of that bike path
that is 1.6 miles long and it goes up at about 4%. And just doing repeat intervals of that,
which takes about four minutes all out to go one direction and then about six minutes to cruise back,
four of those, that was it twice a week for like three weeks and your VO2 max exploded.
Now, of course, the question is, is that like, you know, cramming for the test, getting the result,
but not necessarily like, do you have to keep doing that to get the decade long benefit? I don't know
the answer, but I agree that like, if you can maintain muscle mass and you can maintain peak
aerobic performance, it's not, it doesn't even matter at that point. If you're living longer,
you're clearly living better, right? Like if you, if you don't budge anything on maximum lifespan,
you've dramatically improved median lifespan. Right. And that's, you know,
I think for most people, that's what matters. It is. Yeah. For me, it is. I mean,
what's the, what's the maximum lifespan that like a human's lived 120?
124 or something like that. Is it 124? 121 or 124, maybe.
Something like that. Yeah. Living beyond that. I mean, that's, I think the goal is really to,
at least for me, I think that's a lot more achievable is increasing my, my median
health span, my, my health span, you know? So, so basically preventing, staving off
cardiovascular disease, cancer, Alzheimer's disease, those sorts of things so that I'm,
so that I'm living healthier and also, you know, a little bit longer, but obviously not 125 or six.
Yeah. I don't really subscribe to the theory that we're going to meet some take off point where,
you know, there's immortality. I'm really not convinced that that's, that that's sort of
biologically possible. And I don't suspect I'll be alive at a time when it would ever come to
fruition. I don't remember the journal. It was a paper that came out of Japan and the study
looked at a variety of people of different ages. So elderly population, centenarians,
which are a hundred semi-super centenarians, which are between a hundred and 105 and then
super centenarians, which are 105 plus and looked at a variety of biomarkers for health and aging.
So telomeres, senescence, kidney function, glycated hemoglobin, lipid, the whole lipid panel,
triglycerides, kidney function, hematopoiesis, like all that stuff was looked at inflammatory
biomarkers. And what was found is that aside from age, what was predictive of being able to basically
stay alive was low inflammation, like more than hematopoiesis, more than glycated hemoglobin,
blood glucose levels, lipid, all that stuff. It was basically the ability to suppress inflammation.
Like that was predictive of cognitive function and also basically staying alive.
Do you remember what they looked at? Were they looking at C-reactive protein and things like that?
They looked at a whole panel. No, they, they, they,
they looked at the interleukins and stuff also.
Yeah, TNF. They looked at a whole panel of, and also some immune cells that are indicative,
indicative of inflammation. So there was a whole panel of biomarkers that were looked at for
inflammation. HPV, Titer or something was also looked at. So the interesting thing about that
study was that the inflammation was so key for each age group, right? Like even more than all
this other stuff, like that I've thought about like senescence and telomeres and low blood glucose
levels and all that stuff. And so I really, and if you look at some of the rodent literature,
for example, I remember the study where NF-kappa B, which is classically thought about as an
inflammatory mediator, which it is, it also has an anti-inflammatory component to it. And if you
get rid of the anti-inflammatory component, rodents will have this sort of low level of
chronic inflammation because every time it's activated, there's not that anti-inflammatory
part that's kind of keeping it in check. And so there's kind of like this, like lower
chronic inflammation that's happening. And those animals live like 30% less. So their,
so their life spans cut short by about 30%. So that's kind of interesting, right? You're that
just getting rid of that little anti-inflammatory component of just one major regulator of immune
system has a profound effect on lifespan. And then of course, if you look at SNPs and stuff,
of course, you can always find, you know, well, since inerians have a higher percentage of
10 in anti-inflammatory anyways, you know, so the inflammation, it's an interesting finding that
suppressing inflammation seems to be important for at least, you know, according to that study for
making it to every part of, you know, I don't know what you would call it every basically
progressing to the maximum level, that maximum lifespan level that humans can possibly live.
Well, there was a clinical trial published either earlier this year or last year that looked at an
IL-1 antagonist. And so this was a study that took people and made no change in their lipid
metabolism, lipid biomarker. And, you know, this was they, they didn't do anything to the patients
as far as differentiating the groups by traditional biomarkers of cardiovascular disease.
But one group was given a placebo, one group was given an IL-1 antagonist. And the question was,
could that impact cardiovascular mortality? And we've long talked about how cardiovascular
disease is sort of this trifecta of lipoproteins, inflammation and endothelial dysfunction.
But this was in many ways, the most elegant first test of that in humans using
heart outcomes. So major adverse cardiac event, stroke, MI, death. The hypothesis was found to
be correct. So the patients getting the IL-1 antagonist, despite having no difference in
lipids or any other biomarker, had an improved outcome with respect to cardiovascular health.
About a month ago, another trial that was using low dose of methotrexate, which is an immune
suppressant, was halted early. And the results will not be announced until this fall. But if you
read kind of the fine print, it does not appear it was halted for a bad reason. Meaning it might have
been halted actually for basically early efficacy, which presumably would have been in the group
getting the methotrexate. So again, we won't know that until the meeting in October, I think, when
this will be presented. But if that turns out to be the case, that's pretty interesting because now
you've taken something that we practically have great examples of, like the one you've given,
and now potentially there's ways to think about using it. So taking a step back from all of this
stuff, like, of course, I think about it at the level of like, I'm just a mechanic, right? It's
like, how can you manipulate these things in people? Like cycling, using nutrition and fasting
to cycle IGF, maybe even using an exogenous growth hormone, for all we know. I've always been quite
skeptical of growth hormones use in the field of longevity, but maybe periods of oscillating
rapamycin and growth hormone and fasting where you're cycling high periods of anabolic, high
periods of catabolic phase, maybe there's something to it, and then cycling agents like
methotrexate and all these things. So I don't know. My hope is like in 10 years, we've got
a complete personalized toolkit for how everybody could figure out exactly what drugs or hormones or
nutrients to take and cycle and how to do it. And then of course, the key is you have to be able to
measure stuff. You know, the the with the cardiovascular rate of mortality, the sauna is
something that is interesting to me for that for that reason, because of the profound effects that
it has specifically on lowering cardiovascular related mortality. And of course, there's some
clinical trials showing that, you know, there's a variety of other biomarkers and potential
mechanisms by that for which that's happening. But if you look at some of the data by Dr.
Yari Laukonen out of Finland, if you look at some of the observational studies, you know, where
there's like a couple thousand men that were doing it sauna so ubiquitous in Finland. But if
you look at, for example, men that are using it two to three times a week versus four to seven
times a week versus once a week. And you look at, for example, cardiovascular rate of mortality,
two to three times a week, it's lowered by like 27%. But when you jump to 47 times a week, it goes
up to 40. All cause mortality goes to 40. All cause mortality is also lowered. dementia and
Alzheimer's disease again, like, like 20% lowered if you're doing two to three. I'm so glad you
brought this up because I almost forgot and I wanted to talk to you about this. This is one of
those things where I think three years ago, I was completely dismissive of this stuff, which is to
say I still love going into a sauna because the one thing that I felt sauna really mattered for
was sleep and not for the growth hormone level. But because I think there's pretty good data that
a great way to sleep is to create a high gradient of temperature. So the faster, the more negative,
the derivative of temperature DT by DT, when you sleep, the faster you'll go to sleep and the
longer you'll stay asleep. So a sauna before bed, if you could jump in the sauna, then take a cold
shower, then jump into a cold bed, you're going to sleep like a baby. I've done it. It's absolutely
true. It's remarkable. Yeah. So I always accepted that, but I looked at all of that epidemiologic
stuff and I was like, the healthy user bias here is through the roof. Like I came up with a hundred
reasons why I just couldn't believe it, including saunas are painful. So if you are fit enough to
sit in a sauna seven days a week versus the guy who can only sit in it one day a week, like how
do I know that that's not driving it? Now, since that time I've become a lot more interested
because now the mechanisms are starting to become more well understood. And so I'd love to have you
talk a little bit more about this because I know you've talked about this a lot on your podcast,
but in many ways, your pursuit of this has become one of the more convincing arguments in my
thinking on the actual health benefits of this independent of the healthy user benefits of this.
Yeah, the healthy user benefits. So of course, with Yari's work, he's tried to correct for all
that physical activity that he's done everything like looking at lipid blood cholesterol numbers,
LDL number, like just like really, you know, try to try his best to kind of correct for that
healthy user bias. And of course, there's a dose dependence, which always makes it more convincing.
But he's then since published some some clinical trials where he's looked at, for example,
the arterial compliance, and of course, blood pressures. And that's one of the main things
that's affected his blood pressure, but also just like the ability of the arteries to like expand
and contract in response to pressure, like that's improved, which is really important. So I think
that, you know, obviously, the sauna, the heat itself does does affect, you know, blood flow,
plasma volume, all that stuff is change. So so I think that the cardiovascular aspects and Yari's
trying to really kind of tease apart more mechanisms, because he is a he's an MD PhD. He's a
cardiologist by training, but he's also got a PhD. So he's he's trying, you know, really hard to
to kind of understand exactly what's going on. But I do think that it's really seems convincing.
It's really convincing with the cardiovascular related mortality, specifically, it's very
robust. Personally, it's kind of interesting to think about how much of, you know, exercise
also elevates your core body temperature. I mean, there's this overlap there, you know, and when I
sit in a sauna, my heart rate starts to elevate like I'm doing cardiovascular. And that's that's
what happens. Like I'm doing cardiovascular exercise, start to sway. I mean, a lot of the same
adaptations that happen with exercise are happening when you're you're sitting in a hot sauna and even
a hot bath, like more recently, another study came out trying hot bath affected had a positive effect
on a variety of cardiovascular related markers as well, which again, but you have to sit in it long
enough, you know, to experience some of those effects with the elevation of the heart rate and
all that stuff. But there's also really profound effect on the immune system. Like,
part of the benefit of exercise is that it is an acute oxidative stress burst, an acute inflammatory
burst. You know, there's then a response to that. And the net response is a positive anti inflammatory
and antioxidant response, but the inflammatory and oxidant response is required to get that.
And something similar is happening with with the sauna as well. Recently, there was a study looking
by Dr. Charles raison, he had made this like fancy contraption where he elevated core body
temperature and he had a sham control. So actually, people the sham control also made people a little
bit hot, and they thought they were actually getting the treatment. But it had a very strong
antidepressant. How do they do that? He explains it on my podcast, so you can go to the transcript,
you can just kind of strikes me as one of the few things you can't placebo. He they did some crafty
thing, which I not going to try to explain, but I will absolutely botch it. They did it and and they
had a sham control. And in fact, about he said about 70% of the people that had the sham control
thought they had the actual treatment. So it were like there was definitely a they were trying to
control for the placebo effect. What's interesting is I even the reason I got into this sauna was
the effects that I felt on my mood when I was in graduate school, like I lived across the street
from YMCA. And so I started using this on and it was like, very black and white. Like I was like,
wow, this is amazing. Like I can handle all this wet sauna dry. So this was this is a dry sauna.
Do we have a sense of dry sauna versus IR versus all the different? Yeah, so I mean,
the infrared saunas are like, they only get to like about 140 degrees Fahrenheit. And it's not
very hot. If you look at Yari's work, like their saunas that they're using in Finland, they do they
have a lot of what they call low loo or something, which is like they throw the water on makes the
humid, which makes it really hot. I've been to Finland and try that tried the their saunas before.
But basically, the temperature gets to around 170 between 175 and 79 degrees Fahrenheit.
And most of the men in these studies are doing about 20 minutes to get the maximum benefits.
11 minutes had some benefits sitting in 11 minutes, but there was a stronger effect.
They stayed to 20 minutes. So if you're in a infrared sauna that only gets to 140 degrees
Fahrenheit, you probably would have to stay in a much longer to get the same benefit. Now, most
I see. So the IR doesn't doesn't get deeper penetration, thereby alleviating the need to
stay in at a higher temperature. It doesn't I mean, sometimes people talk about there's a lot of
marketing involved in a lot of that stuff. If you strip that out, though, if you strip that out,
the infrared saunas do affect the sweating mechanisms, like something to do with the
penetration there, you do sweat, which is great because you actually do excrete things like BPA
and phthalates and mercury and heavy metals and things like that from sweat. So that is
that's what a lot of those mark those straight up dry sauna to 170 degrees,
spend three or four nights a week in that my favorite. Yeah, that's personally, I would much
prefer sitting in a regular dry sauna or even a sauna that you can throw water on. You can throw
water just not infrared sauna. Yeah, so that so that would be, you know, the obviously they're the
the fire hazard risk is more when you're having a sauna like that versus just an infrared. And the
infrared ones are I think cheaper as well. So it's certainly more convenient to have an infrared
sauna. But personally, I prefer for the other like the barrel saunas are really nice. There's also an
effect on the immune system. I was mentioning Charles raison he met he measured aisle six,
which is also it's part of the Janus cytokine because it does like it's, it's got like multiple
pleiotropic effects. And it's it's acutely released upon exercise as well. And it has it's very
important for you know, an anti inflammatory response, releasing myokines and all these things
and muscle. So it has, it's important for insulin sensitivity. A lot of the insulin sensitivity
effects exercise has so so the sauna does the same thing that the exercise does where there's just a
rapid aisle six release, at least according to Charles raison's data. And he said that actually
correlates with you know, I've never looked at I wear a continuous glucose monitor a lot, but I've
never really paid much attention to it in the sauna. And I don't have a sauna, but I'm going to
be this weekend at a friend's place who has a barrel sauna. And so I'll make sure that I document
what my glucose levels doing, because you would think transiently would go up, right? Right. But
I know that at least there's an one animal study where the heat stress, quote unquote animal sauna,
it actually increases glucose transporters and a type two diabetic model that actually improved
insulin sensitivity and lowered blood glucose, because the glucose was now being taken up into
muscle butter. So I wonder, you know, how much of the again, it's like you're you're affecting the
aisle six is is really important for that. And aisle six is released upon heat stress without
the exercise. So uncoupling, you know, how much of the benefits from exercise, there's certainly
some overlap. And I think that there's also there are separate benefits that exercise has as well,
independent of the heat stress component of it. But I certainly think there is a lot of overlap
between those two things. And so the sauna becomes very interesting. And there's the whole heat shock
protein part where you know, heat stress is one of the major ways to increase heat shock proteins,
which do play an important role in neurodegenerative preventing neurodegenerative diseases.
And I do think it's also really hard to uncouple the effects on the vascular system,
which is important, right as well, because it's having such a profound effect on the vascular
system, the heat stress, it's hard to uncouple how much of the staving off of dementia and
Alzheimer's has to do with that versus heat shock proteins. This is to me the biggest challenge
with Alzheimer's disease just is, you know, we're talking about it in a pretty nuanced way. But I
think unfortunately, clinically, it's still considered one disease. But, you know, to the
best of my understanding, it's really several diseases that all have a very similar common
final pathway. You know, for example, like going back some of the ketone data, you know, why does
ketone enhance memory in some models? Certainly even going back, oh, God, 10 years, you see a lot of
anecdote of people in early stage dementia who when given even MCT oil would see transient
improvements in cognition. Now, Richard Veach did some of the most elegant work on this.
Richard Veach, by the way, is the guy who along with Kieran Clark created the ketone ester that
T delta S licenses to human. And, you know, they showed, I think, quite convincingly in this animal
model that the BHB was basically bypassing pyruvate dehydrogenase. And so all of a sudden,
you know, you think about the energy deficit that a neuron would experience if you have insulin
resistance at PDH. So if, you know, glucose is going to pyruvate and pyruvate can't get in because
PDH is resistant, giving BHB would just bypass it. You go straight into the Krebs cycle, you make
all the ATP you want. But that might only be a subset of people that are, you know, suffering,
right? There's also going to be the microvascular variant, and then there's going to be the sort of
more toxin variant. So the nice thing about SONA, too, just thinking about it is, as I get like,
I'm becoming more and more convinced of this, it's actually like a really pleasant thing that you can
do to potentially live longer and certainly live better because many of the things we talk about,
I mean, let's call a spade a spade. Fasting is not fun. I wish I could tell you that, you know,
not eating is fun, but like I just love eating. So anytime I'm not eating, I'm sort of like,
there's a discipline that's required to do it. But I don't know, sitting in the SONA for 20
minutes before you go to bed is pretty enjoyable. Of course, the problem is it's not, it's not,
it's not accessible to everyone. It's not accessible to a certain point.
You don't like it. Yeah, yeah, yeah. A certain point. It's enjoyable until you're like,
holy shit, it's hot. I want to get out. But it's knowing that like you get to get out
and then that jump into the pool or the whatever it is, is pretty nice.
Yeah. And the discomfort you experience from like the heat stress where you're like really
hot is actually, I think key for the positive benefits, at least for me it was on my mood,
where I was just like, felt so good. So what about the reciprocal of that cold? So I used to do a
lot of cold therapy, but all for DOMS, delayed onset muscle soreness. So that was my main interest was
back in the olden days, I would go out and buy a hundred pounds of ice or 50 pounds of ice,
I guess, throw it in the bathtub, cold water. And I would immerse myself and that was unbearable,
but that really sped up my recovery from difficult workouts. It's a pain in the ass. So I started
doing cryo and the data, I was pretty convinced that whole body cryo, three minutes of whole body
cryo at the right temperature was going to produce a roughly comparable effect in DOMS,
but had a fraction of the time and 10X the cost. But I've also had people talk to me about,
and again, I've never really looked into this, but I'm guessing you have ice cold showers for
increasing norepinephrine levels, things like that, mood altering. Have you looked into this?
I've looked into the literature. Yeah, that's something that I did notice from doing cold
showers. And sometimes I'll do them before like a big talk or something, because it does help me
focus and it helps with my anxiety, kind of very similar.
Yeah, I was going to say, how do we square the two completely different things? You sit in the
sauna to help with anxiety and then you could have the cold shower. Well, I didn't start getting
into the cold shower until probably a couple of years ago. The sauna I started doing...
In grad school. Yeah, probably about 2008,
so a long time ago. So they're completely uncoupled in my experience.
So do you think the sauna is working more through GH and other...
I think the sauna has a very profound... First, it affects the immune system and that inflammation
has a major effect on brain. And I think that that's work from Charles Raison is pretty clear.
It's definitely... There's definitely an antidepressant effect that seems to correlate
with biomarkers of the immune system. So the more potent the IL-6 response, the more potent the
antidepressant response. In addition to that, there's a very strong effect on beta-dorphins.
Beta-dorphins are dumped. And also this other system called dinoorphin, which is the opposite.
And what's interesting is that when you activate dinoorphin through the kappa opioid pathway,
instead of new opioid, you feel uncomfortable. And it's the part where I was talking about
when you're like, I'm hot. I want to get out. It's the part when you're exercising,
where you're like, oh, it's that uncomfortable feeling. Well, that's... You're making dinoorphin,
partly because it cools your body down. So it's kind of a response to elevating your...
I'm convinced by the way there are a subset of athletes that don't produce that at the same level.
I mean, seriously, there are people I think who...
There are, yeah.
Because we talk about like, why can that guy tolerate so much more pain than that guy?
And at some point, it's possible that they're actually experiencing less pain.
There definitely are variants in the kappa opioid receptor pathway and all that.
So...
I'm surprised that hasn't become a performance-enhancing drug, which is blocking that receptor,
the pain receptor in the brain, which is a very interesting thought. But now...
So then on the cold front, what do you think is mediating that? Neurotransmitters?
So basically on the cold front, the norepinephrine, that's been shown. So animal studies have shown
when norepinephrine's released in the locus corollis reason of the brain after cold exposure
and a variety of cold water exposure, cryotherapy. If you're doing a cold water,
if it's like 50 degrees Fahrenheit, you got to stay in a little longer than a couple of minutes
in a really cold cryotherapy chamber. But in humans, plasma norepinephrine has been looked at,
which does seem to sort of correlate with the release in the brain.
It's so hard though to look at the plasma to understand that stuff.
I know. I know. It is. It is. So I do think that some of the mood is affected by the
norepinephrine as well.
Have you experimented with the stacking, which is go do the sauna for 20 minutes,
then go do the ice shower for whatever 10 minutes and you get an additive effect?
I feel really good. Yeah, I feel really good. And that's when I did notice that my sleep was
really profoundly affected. What's interesting is there's some studies showing that heat stress,
at least in piglets, does affect, actually it seems to elongate the REM sleep stage,
which I don't know what all that means. So there's certainly an effect of heat on sleep.
And then of course, cold is lowering your body temperature is important for sleep onset.
But I don't know. There's something about the combination of the two. Absolutely.
I sleep amazing after doing the combination of both.
I think cold is really interesting for the effects on mitochondrial biogenesis.
I mean, exercise is probably one of the best ways to increase mitochondrial biogenesis,
but cold exposure has been shown human studies, both in adipose tissue and in muscle tissue,
to boost biomarkers of mitochondrial biogenesis.
Well, it depends on what tissue we're looking at. So like, you know, PGC1 alpha,
would probably be one of the best, I would say, for muscle tissue. In adipose tissue,
perhaps the same. I would say PGC1 alpha is probably one of the best.
It's another downstream one. I can't, for some reason, I'm drawing a blank.
Yeah. So that's interesting to me, the effect on mitochondrial biogenesis. But personally,
I like the exercise, you know, for my mitochondrial biogenesis. I'm not like doing
cold exposure all the time. It's not like something that I do often. Like I said, I'll
do it once in a while before a big event I have to talk at or something, just because it does seem
to help me with my mood and my clothes. Have you ever swam in water that's so cold that you actually
feel like you're on fire? Yeah, I have been. Yeah. Uh-huh.
That to me is an amazing, I assume it's due to the vasoconstriction. I don't know.
But it's the coldest water I ever swam in was in the Colorado River and it was 42 degrees,
which is, I mean, that's unusually cold. And the only reason I think I was able to swim in it was
it was May. And so the sun was, it was about 90 degrees Fahrenheit was the air temperature. So
you could, like I wouldn't be able to swim in 42 degree water on a cloudy day, for example,
or a cold day. But I couldn't believe the sensation of feeling like I had jumped into boiling oil.
It was incredible, which is very different from my normal exposure to cold. I used to swim a lot
in the ocean. And if you do a three hour swim at 50 degrees Fahrenheit or 52, 53, you get a little
bit of that effect, but more or less you can still, you still know you're in cold water. But this
particular time I remember, and I probably spent 15 to 20 minutes in this 42 degree temp the entire
time I felt like I was burning. Wow. And again, I had no idea why. I guess my assumption was that
such profound vasoconstriction in the periphery that. You know, the one thing that I wanted to
mention when you brought this up for recovery is because there is some evidence that for whatever
reason, strength training, when you do cold exposure, like immediately after strength training,
if you do it within, let's say before, like sometimes with it, sometime within an hour before
or after strength training, it seems to blunt some of the hypertrophy effects. Yes. Yes. And
actually, it's interesting you say that that's the exact reason I would never take like ibuprofen
or any anti-inflammatory agent. I would limit it even that day. I wouldn't take any of those
agents because you're impairing that rebuild. Yeah. Yeah. So that's also interesting that
the timing of it seems to be, you know, again, there's, it's been shown that about an hour after
exercise is when the anti-inflammatory response starts to peak. And so it's like, if you can,
you basically, if you're within that hour window when the inflammation is happening to create that
anti-inflammatory response, you don't want to dampen that. At least that's, it seems to be what
I think and literature seems to suggest. And there's of course mechanisms where it's like
specific macrophages and muscle tissue are really important for activating all these things that,
you know, eventually result in satellite cell proliferation, you know, and of course IGF-1
is in there somewhere. So again, you know, the immune system activation is important for
a lot of the benefits of exercise, including muscle hypertrophy. So there's one more topic.
I just want to get to, if we can spare a bit more time, which is, which is NAD,
the precursors, the whole shtick. You've spent a lot of time thinking about this.
What is your current thinking on, does having more NAD to NADH matter? The thing about the NAD.
I guess I should provide context for people. Why am I asking this question? Right? So there's lots
of supplements out there now that are, you know, either giving NR or NAD. And the claim is that
these things can enhance longevity. You could live longer and that also you live better. You have more
energy, all of these other things. And so in the mitochondria, you have complex one, which converts
NADH to NAD. And the idea is we do know that as you age, that ratio of NAD to NADH goes down. And so
part of the thinking is, well, and this is outside of the Sirtuin pathway, but this is upstream of
that. But if you give more of either the precursor or NAD, you're basically fixing something that is
getting worse as you age. Yeah. So that, I mean, the question is, why does it go down? And that's,
I think there's multiple reasons for that. At least that's been shown in literature. NAD is
a very important cofactor for mitochondria. I mean, obviously mitochondria are making NADH and
that hydrogen, the proton is used and electrons are used to basically generate energy through
the electron transport chain. And it's also generating the mitochondrial membrane potential
by kicking out the proton. So that's really important for mitochondrial function, respiratory
function, energy production, which is like the key of everything, right? But in addition to that,
you have, as you mentioned, Sirtuins, which are histone deacetylases, which have a whole host of
functions that they're doing regulating tons and tons of different pathways. They're also seem to
be very important for health span. And then in addition to that, there's very important DNA
repair enzyme PARP that literally syncs up NAD. I mean, it's like an NAD sync. I mean,
so we're constantly having damage. Where does it reside, that enzyme?
Where in the cell? Yeah. Is it nuclear? It must be, right? Yeah. And the reason I ask is,
how do we know that these supplements that we take orally are going to actually reach their
bioavailability in the place we want them? Right. Okay. But that said, we'll come back to that after.
Yeah. I think it's in the nucleus. I mean, as far as I remember. It would make sense to be there,
but yeah. Otherwise, it shuttles there, but I think it is. So it's very important for repairing
DNA damage. And so that's one of the major syncs in actually inflammation. All these things are
kind of upstream of PARP activation. So the more that's happening, the more PARPs being activated.
So you have NAD going there. So one argument, just to make sure I understand what you're saying
is, look, if you're getting older, you're going to have more DNA damage. That's just stochastic.
And if your little guy that repairs it requires NAD as fuel, that would explain one reason
potentially why NAD would decline as we age. Yeah. And it's certainly a sync for it. Yeah.
So the other thing is, well, if your immune system is constantly activated too,
if more inflammation you have, all that energy is required. So NAD is being consumed more for that
as well. So that's sort of another thing. Basically, NAD levels decline with age. And
it's probably because it's just getting used up more. Or the other, the alternative is,
is there something else going on in terms of this whole salvage pathway? There's another pathway
that you can do to regenerate NAD, and if that's kind of going wrong. And I think there's some
increasing evidence for that as well. Would that make Metformin a bad idea from this standpoint?
Because Metformin inhibits Complex 1. So Metformin lowers the ratio of NAD to NADH.
Does it? Has that been shown? So you're saying it should lower it?
It should lower it. Now, of course, that's counterintuitive because we know it activates
AMPK. So I probably have to sit down and think about this. But we do know Metformin inhibits
Complex 1. And we know that Complex 1 turns NADH to NAD, which makes me wonder, is it possible that
Metformin would impair DNA repair through that mechanism by reducing substrate?
I have no idea. Well, I'm going to write that down. That's something we're going to have to look
into. There we go. Because I wasn't aware of the, I didn't understand that link. Yeah, exactly.
I think that's a major one. I literally think that's a major thing for it. I think that the
part is, I think it's just like going there. Yeah. So the animal evidence, you mentioned some
of the supplements, precursors that can form NAD. I think that the animal evidence suggests
that it can, at least in rodents, improve health span, particularly in models that are heavily
dependent on mitochondria, like muscle myopathy models or something like that. I think that was
one. And also the brain. So I think those are the two organs I've seen major positive effects with
NAD supplementation. And then there's some, of course, pilot clinical studies showing that, yes,
you can take, for example, nicotinamide riboside. And it does seem to increase
NAD levels in plasma in a dose dependent manner. Now, again, you raise the question.
We have no idea if it's getting in the cell. Is it getting in the cell? Is it getting in the,
now we do know in animal studies, I think that has been shown because it's affecting the
mitochondri, like I said, those animal models of myopathy and stuff and mitochondrial function
was improved and all that stuff. So, so in animal models, it obviously is affecting mitochondrial
function. So it must be getting to the right place. I don't know why I have found myself
skeptical of this. I think it's good to start with skepticism. I mean, I think that NAD levels are,
you can increase them with fasting. So when you fast, as you mentioned, you convert NAD into
NADH in the presence of energy, because that's basically when you have a substrate like glucose
or fatty acid, that's when you produce NADH or FADH2. So in the absence of those substrates,
then you start to make your NAD starts to build up. So back to your metformin question.
You said, I know who to ask. I definitely know. I'm going to ask Nav Chandel. He will know the
answer to this question. I follow a lot of his work when I was in grad, him, Ralph DeBardini's,
I did it because I was doing a lot of cancer metabolism, mitochondrial function and stuff.
So I followed a lot of his work. Do you have Nav's book, Navigating Metabolism? No, I don't. No,
I just used to read his papers back when I was a graduate school. Yeah. So Nav and David Sabatini
were in town a couple of weeks ago and I was leaving town the day they were coming into town.
So we hung out for three hours near the airport. And I was just reminded of how much fun it is to
talk about mitochondria. Yeah, for sure. What is the most interesting question you feel you don't
yet know the answer to, but you feel is knowable that you're sort of actively putting in lots of
your clock cycles on thinking about? I would really like to know if, for example, someone who is
like myself, who I don't have a lot of body fat, I'm active, I eat a pretty healthy diet,
I don't smoke, I don't have any of those bad habits. If I were to do a prolonged fast a couple
days a year, would that truly have an effect on increasing my stem cell production, potentially
getting rid of any dysfunctional immune cells, dysfunctional liver cells, dysfunctional whatever,
muscle cells and repopulating them with healthy new cells, like basically this rejuvenation,
could I get this burst of rejuvenation a couple times a year and would that have,
in turn, have an effect on delaying the onset of age-related diseases, improving my health span,
keeping my stem cells less damaged? That would be very interesting to me because to me, that's
something that's very doable for myself. I mean, the experiment to figure that out is different
because it's in humans and so that's going to be really hard. You have to figure out if you can
even look at certain biomarkers to know that, but I feel like that would be something that's
so easy for someone to do. It's interested in longevity.
And you think it would be sort of once or twice a year doing like a five-day water only mineral?
Well, the question is how often would you need to do it?
Yeah, and how long of it. So we have a lot of the studies coming out of animal data,
which I mean, these rodents, they lose 20% of their body weight after a 48-hour water fast.
Yeah, I find it hard to infer anything from rodents when it comes to fasting
because of this exact reason. Even the Jay Mitchell stuff I talked about earlier,
I mean, I think it's an interesting proof of concept, but I don't actually know how you would
apply that to humans. Right. So the question is, it's like, okay,
so if you have a 48-hour fast in a rodent or a fast, does that mean it's 10-day fast?
Exactly. Yeah. So I guess I'll expand my sort of answer to that question, like maybe do a prolonged
water fast, like time in a kinetic study. Right. What's the frequency? What's the duration to get
the maximum benefit? Yeah. And I am specifically interested in this shrinking of the organs and
then regrowing like this potential robust activation of stem cells clearing away.
You know, we're not just talking about autophagy. We're not just talking about
clearing away damaged mitochondria, pieces of DNA, protein, which is all really great.
You are getting that, but well, in theory, in humans, in addition to that, I mean,
I'm talking about clearing away the damage to the whole cell, like just getting rid of it and
replacing it with a brand new, young healthy cell. Like that's what I'm interested in. You know,
I would love to, you know, even just the hope that that's possible, you know, based off of some of the
pilot studies that Vulture has done in humans and certainly the animal evidence, like I'm convinced
I'm going to at least try because it seems very possible. I know that he is trying to find the
best biomarkers to look at for, you know, stem cell activation. It's not quite as straightforward.
You can't just, you know, harvest a bunch of tissues and look at things. But I certainly have
gotten some anecdotes from people that have had autoimmune like diseases and things said,
like fasting is like completely reversed. Some of it like like eczema or something.
Yeah. No, no, it's, it's, you know, where it's anecdotal. But certainly when you start to have
enough people saying the same thing, it's like, wow, that's interesting that you've heard that
five or five or six times now. Yeah, I think that would, that's a good one. I guess I think of
a very similar question with rapamycin. Rapamycin. Yeah. What dose and what frequency
to produce the best longevity phenotype. Do you know the interesting thing with the
rapamycin is the effect on the senescent cells? Like, like that's so interesting to me.
I didn't know really about that until I listened to your podcast with Judas.
Yeah, she's amazing. She's really, she's really, she's really great and very knowledgeable in the
whole senescent field. Yeah. I had no, I had no idea either. The life expanding effect is,
is that males only or was that both males and females? No male and female. Is it? And it's
across, I mean, it's, it's everything from yeast to worms to flies to mammals. I mean,
it's the only drug that's uniformly extended life across a billion years of evolution.
I mean, and there's really interesting work. I mean, I think Matt Caberland. You're talking
maximum lifespan or are we talking median? Actually in the mice, it was, I have to go
back and look. Probably median. Most of the time it's median, but yeah. And what was interesting
in the mice is they started late in life. They started at 600 days, which is, you know, that's
about 60 years old. Yeah. That's, that's like starting as with a 60 year old. Wow. That was
really late in life for the mice. Yeah. It was. Wow. Which made it that much more impressive.
That is, that is very interesting. So Caberland's work, do you know Matt up at the University of
Washington? He is giving rapamycin to dogs, but these are pets, right? So these are not
laboratory animals, which is what makes it really interesting is you've got animals that
live in our environment that are, and dogs sort of have a very predictable demise, right? They're
either going to be, you know, die in an accident, be euthanized, have cardiomyopathy or die of cancer.
That's basically how dogs die. And the cardiomyopathy that they get is not an atherosclerotic
cardiomyopathy. They get a cardiomyopathy where the muscles are actually just getting weaker and
weaker and their ejection fraction is going down. And in studies as short as 12 weeks,
they're seeing a 10% increase in ejection fraction of these dogs. And so the question is how much of
that is working through senescence, just selectively knocking out senescent cells and letting myocytes
regenerate. Yeah. The study out of the Mayo Clinic where they did some drug that selectively
targeted senescent cells and it led to 20% increase in median lifespan. Sort of an interesting
proof of principle, how just, well, that was an, I think an accelerated aging model. So they had
accumulated more senescent cells. Obviously they had to do something like that. But, um,
but it all comes back to this idea of specificity and selection, you know, everything we've talked
about, if you really stop to think about it, comes down to how could you target this tissue and leave
that tissue alone or how could you target this cell and leave that cell alone? And, uh, in many
ways I think that's kind of got to be the next frontier here is, you know, even if you think
about something as crude as chemotherapy, it is not hard to kill a cancer cell with a chemical.
That's trivial. It's hard to kill a cancer cell and not a normal cell. And that's why chemotherapy
obviously targets rapidly dividing cells and it's still very crude. But the stuff we're talking
about is like taking that to the next level, which is how could you get this enzyme to work more
efficiently, but in this subset of cell, you know, just in the muscle, but not in the fat or not in
the liver. Yeah. And that's again, where the fasting is just so impressive to me. The fact that,
you know, all the normal cells is you're enhancing all these stress response pathways. So the chemo
drug becomes that most more less, almost less, you know, efficacious. Like it's like almost
like a lower dose because it's like, got these robust anti-epiprotic and anti-stress response
genes that are dealing with that sort of stress. And so it's like, it can take the toxic insole
because of that upregulation that fasting is doing and the cancer cells just can't. So I'm,
I'm so glad that that work's being done. I hope that there is more funding that goes in that area.
I think that it is a really important area of research again, like I said, for the, you know,
this is, and this is all from, from Walter's work and some of some of his colleagues. So I'm just
kind of like the fan girl, you know, but I'm certainly, I'm happy someone's doing that research
and I would love to see that be used as a standard of care someday for sure. So Rhonda, many of the
people listening to this will know everything about where to find you, but for the, let's assume
there's someone here who, this is their first time meeting you. Where can they learn more about you
and how can they interact with you? I have a podcast. It's called Found My Fitness. You can
find it on iTunes and on my website foundmyfitness.com. All the episode pages there with
links to the video, which has. And your videos are remarkable because you put so much work into
actually like a podcast like this, unfortunately we're too lazy. Like I'm not going to actually
do much except create show notes, but on yours, it's like, it's like a Khan Academy, right? It's
like everything is being explained in the video as well. Like in text. Yeah, it's amazing. Yeah,
it's explaining the figures, definitions and all that are there in the video. And also on,
I think we're having now definitions and stuff on the website. So people can, the, the goal is to
definitely showcase, you know, a lot of the, the researchers and scientists that I interview and
also to educate people as well. So Found My Fitness, I'm on iTunes and my website and social media.
And what do you like most is Twitter, the easiest place for people to get to Twitter,
Facebook, Instagram, I'm on all of them. But yeah, and what's your handle? Found My Fitness.
So you were ahead of me on this. Like you, you immediately recognize the value of exercise. I'm
a late comer to this. I mostly from, from personal experience, I realized I was like,
this is like, this is great for my brain. And from there, I just kind of dove into it. I was
convinced. Yeah, for sure. Rhonda, I can't thank you enough. This has been awesome. I don't suspect
it's the last time we'll talk about this stuff. So until next time. Awesome. You can find all of
this information and more at Peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast. There you'll find the
show notes, readings and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog and the nerd
safari at Peteratiamd.com. What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the link at the top of the
site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to the most interesting papers I've read
and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera. On social,
you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeteratiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does
not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
peteratiamd.com forward slash about.