Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Peter Attia Drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia. The drive
is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking, along
with a few other obsessions I've gathered along the way. I've spent the last several
years working with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And
this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live
a higher quality, more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more
information on today's episode and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
In this episode, I interview my good friend Dominic Dagestino. Dom, as he is known by,
is a professor at the University of South Florida. His PhD is in neuroscience and that's
where he got his background. But Dom is probably most recognizable to people listening to this
because he is certainly one of the experts on ketosis and that's in all variants of it.
So starvation ketosis, nutritional ketosis, and in particular the use of exogenous ketones.
Gosh, Dom and I go way back. We met probably a little over five years ago and instantly
formed a friendship around our obsessive N of one experiments. Although I will say he
is closer to winning a Darwin Award on the basis of his N of ones than I am. A couple
notes about this podcast. First, this is highly technical at times. And in fact, we'll timestamp
it in the show notes, but I would say roughly the first hour is even a little more technical
than I had intended to go. I think part of the issue is just once I get talking with
Dom about this stuff, I couldn't stop asking him questions. And I think there were times
when I guess we forgot we were recording a podcast and it was just us getting really
technical. I don't think it's too technical to follow if you have some background in understanding
of biochemistry, but we'll do our best in these show notes to make sure that we're given
even the recreational user necessary tools to follow this. Now that said, if you get
20 minutes into this thing and you're like, I don't understand what the hell these guys
are talking about, do not hesitate to skip ahead. There's a lot of stuff that gets later
on into the podcast and this is a long podcast. It's nearly three hours. There's a lot of
stuff we get into at the end that I think will be kind of the stuff people really want
to know, even if they don't want to get in the gory details. So in particular, we talk
very specifically about all of the ketones and I'm getting a lot of questions about Peter,
what's the difference between a ketone ester or a ketone salt? What are the mono esters?
What are the diesters? Where does MCT fit into this? What about the caprylic acid and
how many should we be using this one versus this one? And what are the advantages and
what are the benefits of this? This is going to be your dissertation level course in that
subject matter. The other thing that we get into at the very end, and we almost end on
this, but again, look to the time stamps for exactly where it is, is we get into what I
consider one of the most interesting discussions I've ever had on what I sort of loosely describe
as a metabolic oncologist playbook. So when I asked Dom about this, he had just some of
the best ideas. He was really impressed by the breadth and the organization of his thinking
around this. Now I want to point out something here and I say it in the show, but it's really
important for me to caveat this here. This cannot be construed as medical advice. Dom
is not a medical doctor. He doesn't pretend to be one on TV. He is a research scientist
who focuses on basic and translational research. He collaborates with lots of physicians. He
has trials, but ultimately Dom is not offering medical advice and frankly, nor is anybody
or nor should anybody be on a podcast. So this information I asked because I get asked
this stuff a lot and frankly, I don't know enough about this sort of outreaching and
outlying metabolic therapies out there, but I hope that if people are listening to this
and they're afflicted by cancer, which statistically speaking is obviously going to happen given
that one in six people are going to get cancer in their lifetime. I hope that if some of
this stuff does scratch someone's sort of desire to understand more that they can use
some of the resources we're going to link to, to potentially identify the right places
where either clinical trial will be taking place or they could at least pursue some of
these things under the appropriate medical guidance. I could go on and on about other
nits and nats in here, but honestly, I think the best thing to do right now is probably
pay a little bit of attention, maybe more than usual to the show notes, treat this as
a little bit like a buffet, go to the places you want to go to. Of course, I would recommend
the entire thing if you really have an interest in this subject matter. And I hope that this
podcast is going to answer many of the questions that I see people asking out there. I actually
learned quite a bit on this and I tend to know the subject matter reasonably well. So
without any further delay, welcome to the podcast with Dominic DeGostino.
Hey Dom.
Hey Pete.
How are you, man?
I'm doing well. How are you?
I'm doing really well and I'm really grateful for you making the trip all the way up here.
I know that in part you're visiting family, but it's great that you've carved out time
to come from New Jersey all the way up to the lovely city of Manhattan.
I appreciate the invite and love being here. Yeah, I love to visit.
Well, there's going to be a number of people listening to this today who are already incredibly
familiar with who you are, the work you've done. I certainly consider you probably one
of the two most authoritative persons on the subject we're going to get into today. But
for anybody who's listening to this who is not entirely familiar with you, I suspect
by the end of today they're going to want to get a lot more familiar with you. So I
actually remember the day we met and it's kind of funny. I was in Florida giving that
talk at IHMC and I knew of you by name, but I didn't know who you were or what you looked
like, so I wouldn't have recognized you. And I gave a talk that I was going to give to
you. I recognized you and I gave a talk. This would have been 2011 maybe, maybe 2012.
And at the end of the talk there was like a Q&A and it was a long Q&A and it just went
on and on and on. And then you asked a question now, I wish I could say I remember the question,
but I knew from the question that that guy knows what he's talking about. And then of
course, Ken Ford, who knew us both, had basically arranged for us to all have dinner that night.
So that was the night we met. And it was really, at least from my standpoint, not to
embarrass you. It was like a love at first sight. I was just so giddy to be able to sit
there and have dinner with you.
Same, same here. Yeah, I knew who you were and I was looking for that talk and I made
the drive up there and I felt like we were connected before we even connected. We're
definitely on the same wavelength on this stuff.
Yeah, you've got such an interesting history that we're going to get into about how you
got interested in this space. But also I think one of the things that many people might
not appreciate fully that I appreciated just because of the convenience and luxury of how
we met was just your interest in self experimentation as well. And sometimes when you're studying
something or interested in something that is not entirely mainstream yet, you have to
bootstrap it and you have to look at like limited amounts of animal data, limited amounts
of in vitro data, and then sometimes combine it with insights that you get through early
experimentation on yourself.
Absolutely. So I immerse myself in what I'm doing.
I think that's sort of why we connected.
That's how we learn. Yeah, that's really the best way to learn.
So you did your PhD in neuroscience, correct?
Yeah.
What were you-
In physiology.
In physiology. So you're finishing your PhD and you're what, planning to do a post-doc?
Yeah. I did it in the neural control of autonomic regulation. So the brainstem mechanism sort
of sense O2, oxygen and CO2 and modulate respiratory rhythm generation and also cardiovascular
sympathetic tone to the heart, like those neurons and how they sense oxygen. During
my PhD, I got interested in diving physiology and it was amazing to me that we don't really
understand how our brains and our physiology functions in extreme environments as it pertains
to elevated hyperbaric pressure, elevated oxygen, CO2, anesthetic gases, for example.
We know the anesthetic potency of a gas is proportional to its lipid solubility, but
we don't really know what that means. Like why, what's happening at the level of the
membrane of the mitochondria? So my postdoctoral fellowship was actually developing technologies
to study that, and that would be hyperbaric atomic force microscopy. And that was like,
that's what I just delved into for-
So how does that work? So I know what hyperbaric means. I know what microscopy means. Tell
me about the part about the force.
The first term for atomic force microscopy was scanning probe microscopy. And instead
of using light or electrons, it uses a very sharp tip probe that can be so sharp it's
mono-atomic. And it essentially raster scans across the sample and can detect very subtle
changes in the topography of the sample that you're scanning. So it actually spawned the
whole nanotechnology world. So this particular instrument was used to characterize materials
and really helped develop Silicon Valley in many ways. And it's a microscope that we took
basically an off-the-shelf atomic force microscope that gives you the scanning resolution of
an electron microscope, but also has the capacity to image living cells. And took this
technology and put it inside an environmental chamber, a hyperbaric chamber. And part of
my project was doing the electrical, the fluid, and the gas penetrations to make the thing
functional and also doing a series of studies and calibration tests to determine that we
could reliably make hyperbaric atomic force microscopy measurements inside this chamber.
And with this technology, it gives us insight at the nanoscopic level of what's happening
to the mitochondria, to the cell membrane. So I got a grant through the Department of
Defense, which they give these equipment grants to develop this technology and also a grant
to use it. And then later another grant to put a confocal microscope. You might have heard
of a laser scanning.
I actually used a confocal microscope in my undergrad thesis to do optical sectioning
of...
Tom?
No, because I was an engineer. So I was interested in a question of, did the direction of extrusion
that you put on a tibial plateau, so when you do joint replacements, does the direction
in which you extrude what's called ultra-high molecular weight polyethylene, does that predict
its fracture? And it turned out it did. But the tool to help us measure that was this
confocal microscope. So that was my introduction to high-end microscopy.
It's an amazing tool, yeah. So the second grant I got...
Yeah, you got it. They're the toys that we have in the lab. So that was the next phase
of sort of my experiments was installing a laser scanning confocal so we could optically
section individual cells and look at the mitochondria inside the cells under graded levels of oxygen
and hyperbaric pressure, essentially, pressure of an inert gas like helium, nitrogen. So
to simulate, for example, a Navy SEAL dive or a deep sea dive. And in the context of
developing this technology and imaging a wide variety of cells from primary neurons
to glioblastoma cells to human dermal fibroblasts, smooth muscle cells, I noticed that cancer
cells would produce proportionally more superoxide anion, which is the precursor oxygen free radical
that comes from the mitochondrial electron transport chain as a consequence of normal
metabolism. And the cancer cells look to have what appeared to be chock full of mitochondria,
and they were moving around very dynamic structures. And under normal levels of oxygen,
they kind of produced a normal level of superoxide anion or oxygen free radicals. But when we hit the
cancer cells with hyperbaric oxygen, the superoxide production went off the charts.
And it was very apparent to me that they were producing excess free radicals. And as we made
measurements over time, it was very apparent that it was accelerating membrane lipid peroxidation,
which we use a variety of tests, one is a T Mars test where we look at malandialbhyde production.
And the technology the atomic force microscopy allows us to look at very subtle changes of the
surface of the membrane. You measure the perturbations on the surface of the membrane
and nanoscopic changes. And we look at membrane roughness, and you could look at the roughness of
the membrane and calculate that and that can correlate to membrane lipid peroxidation and it
correlates the numbers correlate well. So what you're looking at is the physical correlate of
membrane lipid peroxidation when you capture that data with atomic force microscopy. Is that clear?
Let me back up and make sure I can disaggregate this into steps. So the first thing that you
notice is lots of mitochondria in cancer cells. And these are what types of cancer lines?
The main one that I was working with that I ended up publishing the paper neuroscience with
was U87 glioblastoma cells. And they're taken out of a 44 year old patient.
So a human cell line.
Human cell line. A lot of people use it.
And these are astrocytes, right? These are not neurons.
Yeah, of a glial origin. Yes.
So observation one, lots of mitochondria. Okay, good to know. Because obviously there's a
understanding that Warburg pointed out that says, hey, like, you know, these things largely are
anaerobic, not aerobic. So they shouldn't really need much mitochondria. And then what you're
saying is you put them into a hyperbaric environment. And how hyperbaric, how many times
atmospheric pressure would you need?
I saw the observation at, so normal oxygen is 0.2 ATA, we say atmosphere is absolute.
And I saw a big jump up in superoxide anion production at 0.95.
So that's almost five times atmospheric pressure.
That's almost five times. Yeah. And actually 0.95, if you're breathing produces a PO2 in the brain,
if similar to breathing 2.5 atm of oxygen. And then I actually went up to it, did the experiment
with 3.25 atm of oxygen. And then that basically was cooking the cells from the inside out the
mitochondria were producing so much oxidative stress through reactive oxygen species. So
superoxide anion can go to hydroxyl radical through the Fenton reaction through hydrogen
peroxide. And that can be driven in different ways. And I basically saw the mitochondria exploding
under hyperbaric oxygen conditions. And I had never seen that before.
Do you have a control in this of non-cancerous glial cells that are not doing the same thing?
Yeah. So most of my experiments prior to this was like smooth muscle cells I was looking at
and primary cortical neurons, primary hippocampal neurons. At the time, I was just basically looking
at I was doing these experiments to validate the tool that we had just built. So no one actually
had imaged living cells under hyperbaric conditions because no one had a hyperbaric microscope for.
So I didn't actually know what I was even looking at. I was not a cancer biologist. I knew that
cancer cells were rapidly proliferating. So they probably had amped up metabolism,
but it was just a very interesting observation to me. It was very interesting that they're also
dying. And I figured cancer cells should be hardy and that you should be able to throw everything,
but the kitchen sink at them and they should live. And then when I saw them basically the
mitochondria exploding and the membrane starting to become permeable and necrotic cell death,
I became more and more interested in that. And we ended up publishing the observation,
but I didn't actually know what it meant. Like I published it more like here, I built this cool
tool and we did this experiment. And I was actually just looking at the cell line as a model system
to study reactive oxygen species and oxygen toxicity seizures, because part of the military
was funding me to understand the cellular and molecular mechanisms of oxygen toxicity seizures.
And it's thought that high levels of oxygen creates oxidative stress and that perturbs
the brain in a way that causes these grand mal tonic, clonic seizures. And we were developing
tools. You can't understand it unless you know fundamentally what's happening at the level of
the cell and the mitochondria. So I want to come back to that because that now makes sense for why
diving could increase that risk. Because if you're using an oxygen rebreather,
you're getting a higher concentration of oxygen and then you're under multiple atmospheres of
pressure. You now basically replicated in a person what you were seeing a cell. But going back to the
cell thing for a sec, do the free radicals that get generated destroy other cells beyond the cell
that is generating the free radical? Or is the problem largely contained to the cell?
It's a dose dependent phenomenon. And we were studying cells in this particular experiment
in a Petri dish or on a cover slip. So you have sort of like an intact neural network or cellular
network. So the cells are literally connected to one another, unlike a tissue slice where you have
an intact cytol architecture, which that's a little bit different. But the oxygen free radicals and
the substances that the cells produce do actually influence other cells adjacent to it or juxtaposed
to it. That's obvious from some of the experiments we do in cell signaling. If one cell becomes
permeable and we could detect cell death with various molecules like Athenium homodimer one,
when that cell dies, it can stimulate excitotoxic events in the surrounding cells.
Same thing happens with the cancer cells. It's obvious that cancer cells use reactive oxygen
species for growth and proliferation. And I know this is something that may be contradicting
to many people. We view free radicals as something that's damaging that the cell needs to get rid of,
but they're very powerful signaling molecules, especially for cancer cells and growth and
proliferation and in normal tissues. And you mean nuclear signaling?
In nuclear signaling and activation of transcription factors. Basically, there are
many, I study as neuroscientists, I study redox sensitive ion channels. So the redox state of
an ion channel can dictate the permeability and the gating functions of that ion channel,
which is intimately linked to cellular excitability by influencing the resting membrane potential.
So as a neuroscientist, you can study a very particular and cells have hundreds of thousands
of ion channels, specific ion channels that are redox regulated. But what was obvious is that
cancer cells have elevated rates of reactive oxygen species that they use for growth and
proliferation. And it also fuels metastasis and invasiveness of cancer cells. And because they
overproduce oxygen free radicals in the context of high oxygen, you can push the cells above their
antioxidant potential and then trigger apoptosis. So it's like a double edged sword.
It's basically a U-shaped curve or inverted, depending on how you want to think about it,
where the cancer cell is not only optimized to survive, it's optimized to thrive at a certain
level of elevated reactive oxygen species. An elevated level, but if you go too far,
it becomes counter. Yeah. So they have elevated endogenous antioxidant capacity, right? But
because their mitochondria are defective in many ways, and there's that term is kind of
controversial. Some people think the Warburg effect definitely endows the cells many benefits,
but the aberrant activity of the mitochondria is creating this excess free radicals and
hyperbaric oxygen and chemotherapeutic drugs that augment oxidative stress are therapeutic modalities
that can be used. It was very apparent to me seeing that in a hyperbaric chamber,
looking at a microscope, looking at these cells, and no one had seen it before because no one had
hyperbaric microscopy. Nobody had the tool. Yeah. And that kind of, at the same time,
I was growing these cells under different conditions. I was very interested in lactate,
and I became interested in ketones too, just not for this reason. I was not yet interested in the
ketogenic diet. I was looking at it for a different reason actually, but I noticed that
the cancer cells were not growing as rapidly as they should in the context of 1, 2, and 5 millimolar
of beta-hydroxybutyrate, which I was growing them in. And I thought the lab tech may have been doing
something that was influencing, but she assured me it wasn't. So we would pull the media off and put
regular media on without the ketones and the cancer cells would start growing rapidly. Why
were you using ketones in the media? Well, I was looking at a variety of different substrates back
in 2008 and nine. I see. So you were just saying lactate glucose, BHB. Yeah, 2-deoxyglucose. Yeah,
lactate. I was using a variety of different, and ketones were like, well, let's just see what
ketones do. You know, that ketones were something that the body would produce in fasting, but I
didn't, I didn't even know the anti-seizure properties of the ketogenic diet. I just thought
of it as like, what do brains, and a couple odd papers that came out like ketones could be used
as fuel. I was very interested in alpha L poly lactate, various forms of lactate that could be
used to preserve brain energy metabolism in the face of oxidative stress. And the ketones just,
they sort of shined. So basically what they were able to do was allow the neurons to preserve their
membrane potential and normal cellular function, even in the context of extreme oxidative stress.
And it made sense, right? Because the ketogenic diet, you know, I started looking more into this
and discovered that the ketogenic diet was a very effective anti-seizure strategy, even when drugs
fail. About two thirds of patients respond favorably. You get, you know, 10 or 15% or super
responders that never have seizures again, you can get them off your meds. And it was probably
working through a mechanism independent of any anti-seizure compound because the ketogenic diet
worked when drugs failed, you know, suggesting it was working through a different mechanism or many
mechanisms kind of in synchrony. So the tools that we developed really sort of started to allow us to
understand from a cellular and molecular mechanism how ketones are working. And I was looking at other
compounds at the time, but it's just, as I kept studying, I was looking at sigma receptor agonists.
I was looking at other antioxidants, many different antioxidants and combinations of
antioxidants that were catalase, memetics, superoxide, dismutase, memetics, you know,
all these things that were in theory, they should work really well, but nothing was really working
as well as ketones. And it also motivated me because when I discovered the ketogenic diet
was a grossly underutilized anti-seizure strategy. I was like, wow, I could go back to my nutrition
roots because when I was undergrad, I majored in nutrition science, but I didn't pursue a PhD in
nutrition because nutrition was not like a real science. Like there was no jobs in nutrition and
in the 90s was a decade of the brain. So it was like, let me try to get into a cellular
neuroscience program. So I kind of just left nutrition and this was my opportunity to bring
nutrition back into my research projects into the lab. But my going back to that BHB in the media.
Did you have the same amount of glucose in as you had in the BHB free media?
Yeah. So we did everything in the context of the same amount of glucose.
In other words, the benefit was from the addition of BHB, not the reduction of glucose.
Absolutely. Yep. And as I started to get into the literature and read into this a little bit more,
we started doing glucose subtraction and adding ketones and saw that normal healthy neurons
functioned and thrived in a low glucose environment if the ketones were present,
but the cancer cells would die. And this was also replicated and published in various neuroblastoma
cell lines. And I think Skinner was one person that published and I found that he was at
University of Florida, but he was a fellow and just had left the school at the time.
And then I went up there and gave a talk, I think in 2010. And that further, that got me more and
more interested in studying cancer, even though it was not funded to do so. It was like this pet
project that was completely very intellectually stimulating to me and something that I could not
just shelf and come back to at a later time. I had to, I felt like the environment was kind of hot
for this. So I just kept reaching out to different scientists and showing them my data
and asking them to explain it like top level cancer biologists. And then I stumbled across
Tom Seiford actually. Speculating. Why do you think Tom was one of the few people that latched
onto this? Was it simply because he'd already been thinking the same things or because it's
really, it is interesting when you think about how many really interesting and impressive people in
cancer have not sort of come around to thinking about this stuff. Now in 2009, I think it was 2009,
and I'm sure you have read this paper a thousand times. It sort of, I think it was the first
obvious mainstream view of this was the Matt van der Heiden, Lou Cantley, Craig Thompson
science paper. Was that 09? That sound about right? Which reminded me of, they had a couple papers
around that time. Which one was? Well, this is the one that offered an explanation for the Warburg
effect. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It was basically an energy synthetic. That's right. It was expanding
the biomass, directing metabolites to do that. Yeah. And that was interesting because that's
a different explanation than presumably Tom would offer, right? It's accepting the Warburg effect
as a very powerful, but the question that Tom has really set out to address, no one is arguing the
Warburg effect is present, but the initiation of the Warburg effect and that damaged mitochondrial
respiration causes an energetic crisis that kicks on the oncogenes that basically turn on the genes
that are the essence of the Warburg effect. Well, let's describe the effect. I should, I'm going to
take for granted that everyone listening knows what the Warburg effect is. So for someone who doesn't
know, how would you explain the Warburg effect? The Warburg effect simply stated is insufficient
mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation or what we call respiration with compensatory fermentation
in the form of establishing the cell establishes its energy, its production of ATP, our energy
currency through the glycolysis and substrate level phosphorylation. And it's well recognized
that cancer cells, 90% of them, I would say, have a Warburg phenotype, meaning that they have highly
accelerated glycolysis and substrate level phosphorylation. So let me simplify that a little
bit more. Our cells can turn glucose into something called pyruvate and that occurs outside of the
mitochondria. And that's not a highly energy efficient process. It doesn't generate much ATP.
You then have a decision to make as a cell, which is basically how quickly does the body want ATP
and as a general rule, when it wants it quickly, it's an anaerobic environment. You think about
things that drive quick ATP requirement. And so then it will just say, look, we'll just turn this
pyruvate into lactate. That's the glycolytic pathway, which is not particularly efficient
either. It doesn't generate that much more ATP, but it has the luxury of saying, I can guarantee
to do this quickly. And I don't need to be limited by cellular oxygen. Under ideal circumstances,
you would want to generate the most ATP, you would shuttle that pyruvate into the mitochondria
as acetyl CoA, and you have this other process. So what you're saying is the Warburg effect is, hey,
even under conditions at rest, a cancer cell seems to disproportionately do this glycolytic thing.
And it generates its ATP that way, as opposed to going into the mitochondria.
Exactly. Even in the presence of normal oxygen, it utilizes glycolysis and pumps out lactate.
So under no other conditions do normal cells ferment and pump out lactate.
So that's now Warburg, did he win a Nobel Prize for this observation?
He won a Nobel Prize. Yeah. For his work in metabolism cancer cells. Yeah. And it was,
is more kind of appreciated a little bit later what the implications of this was,
but it was part of his Nobel Prize. Yeah. You know, I remember reading an article about this
once that has since escaped me, but then maybe I'm wrong. So correct me. But one of the reasons
that the hypothesis was, cause this was in the 1920s, if I recall. Yeah. Warburg was, yeah. So
one of the reasons that this sort of got discarded for lack of a better word, or at least ignored was
people tended to focus on the exceptions and there were exceptions, right? Certain lung
cancers certainly seem to pose an exception to the Warburg effect. And so the idea was, well,
look, if you have an exception, then the rule is not so much a rule anymore. And is there another
reason why the Warburg effect was largely ignored for, you know, a generation and a half to two
generations? Travis Christofferson wrote a book called Tripping Over the Truth that nicely sums
that up. I think there's a lot of reasons for that, but I think the big focus was on understanding
the gene pathways that were associated with carcinogenesis. And then if we can understand
the gene etiology of cancers and different types of cancers, then that would explain cancer in a
much more fundamental level. And that is the case. There is a dynamic interplay between metabolism
and genetics. So now we have an appreciation that metabolites, you could call them oncometabolites,
are epigenetic drivers. And metabolism is just not producing ATP. There are so many different
intermediates and redox signaling and so many different signaling molecules from metabolism
that have epigenetic regulation. And I think that has become, when I got into this, there was no
cancer metabolism conferences, you know, and now there's a dozen or more where Lou Cantley is a
keynote speaker and Craig Thompson is, and this has all sort of exploded shortly after some of
these observations that I made. And it's just, you know, it's, I don't think it's coincidence.
I think, I think, yeah, remember when we had that dinner in DC at that conference?
I still look back at that as one of the most remarkable rooms to be sitting in as a fly on
the wall. Cause there was only about 12 people there. Yeah. And you know, you had Lou Cantley,
you had Michael Bishop, Steve Rosenberg, David Sabatini. David Sabatini. Who else was there?
Michael Pollock. A Vanderheiden. Yeah. Matthew Vanderheiden. I mean, you basically had some of
the most thoughtful cancer scientists in the, in the world, certainly in the United States,
in one room. And that was an amazing evening conversation. Yeah. If I could go back in time,
exactly. That was golden. We'll talk those guys into getting in a room again. Yeah. I mean,
I think what you're basically saying is, look, part of its reason for being discarded,
or at least forgotten about was a new sexier idea emerged, which is, Hey,
we started to understand the role of the genome. And there's this weird sort of debate you hear.
And the observation that things like viruses, you know, which could, you know, encode and
change our DNA. But the viruses that cause cancer are the very same viruses that damage
the mitochondria that damage the DNA in the mitochondria and causing respiratory insufficiency,
which triggers an energetic crisis, which can trigger the activation of oncogene through
retrograde response. So that needs to be appreciated too. But there was this explosion
of technologies that allowed us to understand genetics. And that was sort of being leveraged
to really delve into cancer, I think there was, there was some politics influencing that too.
So it was the first thing you did from that point, because there's really two separate
problems that you're talking about. The first is, why are these seizures occurring? And I'm
referring very specifically to your DARPA funded work, which was, why is it that when these
Special Forces guys are doing their ultra secret dives, which require rebreathers,
why are a subset of them having these fatal seizures?
Well, it's the Office of Navy Research. Oh, it was. Okay. DARPA was doing this.
They were doing warfighter performance with ketone esters, just prior to, you know, what I was doing.
So that's one problem. Yeah. And then the other problem that's that you've also articulated is,
hey, what's going on with cancer? Yes. So oxygen toxicity seizures are a limitation for navy seal
divers. And we don't know how to predict them or prevent them. It's also a limitation of hyperbaric
oxygen therapy, right? So if you have carbon monoxide poisoning, right, and you need to live,
especially you need to get that, that carbon monoxide off your hemoglobin, you need to basically
increase the PO2 in your tissues. Oh, because carbon monoxide has a much higher affinity than
oxygen for hemoglobin. So you have to basically outcompete it. Yes. So if you were to take a ketone
ester, which we know now increase your resistance to oxygen toxicity by like 600% and take a ketone
ester and then get inside a hyperbaric chamber, you have a much greater chance of living. If you
have wounds, there's 14 different applications for hyperbaric oxygen therapy. We think that
therapeutic ketosis strategy would make it much safer and more efficacious. So in the context of
an oxygenary breather, the advantage is that there's a stealth component because you don't
produce bubbles. You can dive in a quiet lake and go all the way across and surprise your enemy.
But it just 50 feet of seawater within 10 minutes at 50 feet of seawater, you run the risk of getting
oxygen toxicity seizures. That's pretty shallow. Wait, wait, say that again. At 50 feet. At 50
feet of seawater in 10 minutes, if you're on a draeger rebreather, according to the oxygen
dive tables, that has been enough to trigger a seizure in many guys. So that produces a PO2 in
your brain of about roughly 2000 times higher than what your oxygen level in your brain would be
right now. 2000% higher. I was going to say. Yeah, percent, not time. Okay. Okay. So that needs to be
sort of appreciated. And of course, this could all be averted if you just stick to the dive tables.
Right. But if you have, you know, enemy fire with 50 caliber machine guns coming down on you,
and you want to stay down, if the water is clear, you got to go down deeper. If you have a plan of
mine and get to the bottom of a ship or a bridge, you might be underwater for three or four hours,
and the enemy is still up there. And it's, you got to get down there and do your job and dive deep
and avoid that. And then, you know, after a time, you have pulmonary oxygen toxicity too,
if you're down there long enough. But generally speaking, these rebreathers are for shallow
diving, but situations where they need to go down deeper. Do you have an estimate of how many
Navy divers just in the United States, both in training or combat, would die in a given year
from this or be injured? It's pretty rare. Fortunately, it's pretty rare. And if they do
get hit with oxygen, you know, our friend, Kurt Parsley, will tell you that Navy SEALs
are notorious about not telling what their issues are with their health, right? So if they do have
a seizure, they would be kicked out, you know, a lot of these guys, because that may make them
a weak link that they're vulnerable. So we know recreational divers that push the limit who have
been hit a couple times, you know, with this, and we're doing some studies right now, recreational
divers. So it's very underreported, but studies have shown, I always show a video in one of my
talks of a guy in a chamber where he has a mask on and the mask is breathing 100% oxygen. And the
guy inside the chamber is breathing hyperbaric air. And within at 2.7 atmospheres of oxygen,
he gets hit with a seizure and has a really violent tonic clonic seizure. And it's stopped.
As soon as you remove the oxygen mask and start breathing air, even if it's at the same barometric
pressure, the seizures stop. So one of the beneficial things of these seizures, if you
want to, if there's a beneficial component to it is that they quickly stop as soon as you remove the
hyperbaric oxygen source, or you go from breathing 100% oxygen to hyperbaric air. So what's happening
is that the high levels of oxygen are creating oxidative stress and actually impeding various
metabolic processes in the brain. And the brain is becoming hyper excitable. And the neurons are
firing so many action potentials that the cells essentially can't maintain their membrane potential.
And you get excitotoxicity that causes mass firing in the neurons and a seizure.
And this is obviously under a very super physiologic.
Super physiologic. It only happens in these extreme environments of pressures. And the
reason for it now is you have S-nitrosylation of glutamic acid decarboxylase. There's two
different isozymes. And then what we think now is that you have more glutamate to GABA ratio.
So the enzyme that converts our gamma-aminopatoric acid is actually created from glutamate.
So you have much more excitatory than inhibitory neurotransmitter.
So that ratio changes. And it's a redox dependent reaction. Actually, you have S-nitrosylation of
this enzyme that converts more glutamate to GABA. So you have increased neuronal firing and increased
release of glutamate and also less conversion of the glutamate to GABA, which has a brain
stabilizing effect. So this is going off topic for just a second, but we know that as people age,
we see greater and greater oxidative damage. So we see, you know, the susceptibility to ROS going
up. Does any of what you learned in this super physiologic environment where in a very short
period of time, you're going to generate a ton of Ross by exposing someone to high pressure and
high O2. Does anything you learned in that environment offer an insight into non-super
physiologic or normal aging and disease progression? Yeah, I think in many different ways. So it's
almost like exercise, right? If you exercise intensely, your reactive oxygen species are going
to go up inflammation, all these things kick on. So high pressure oxygen increases oxidative stress,
and that kicks on many different processes that can endow the cell with greater cellular protection.
So it can, for example, cause an increase in superoxide dismutase. It can enhance our antioxidant
defenses. So the oxidative stimulus is a trigger for adaptive processes that can allow our systems
to be more resilient against the same level of oxidative stress. This happens very robustly in
a young animal and is significantly attenuated in an older animal. And I think that needs to be
appreciated. So the adaptive response to the stimulus varies genetically, probably between
the individual. There's a lot of individual variability between people. And even if you
take the same person under different conditions, whether it be if they're sleep deprived, what they
ate that day, maybe if they're dealing with a little viral illness or something, their susceptibility
to oxygen toxicity seizures can be greatly affected by a lot of different variables. But
that adaptive response, so we know hyperbaric oxygen stimulates the production of stem cells
as much as something like GMCSF, like a neupogen or leukine. It's that powerful. It causes the
production and the release of stem cells, which kind of hone in on sites of injury and aid in
repair. So that's why its most utilized application is actually for enhancing wound production or wound
healing effects. I see. You mentioned that there were 14 approved applications. I wasn't aware that
there were that many. I certainly... I think it's 15 now. So what are some of the others? You don't
have to put you on the spot to rattle off all 15, but we can look it up. But just on the top of your
head, what other ones do you know? Yeah, radiation necrosis. So for cancer, if you are getting
radiation therapy for cancer, it is FDA approved for that. So if you have patients who have
radiation therapy, of course there's decompression sickness. So we're recreational diving. If you get
bent, another term for bent is decompression. It's the same deal. It's basically get the nitrogen
out by basically... Pump the nitrogen out. Beating it out with oxygen. Yep. Carbon monoxide poisoning.
Obviously diabetic wounds. All the hyperbaric, the UHMS, so hyperbaric medicine society,
approves the facilities. And I would say 90 plus percent of their revenue generated from that
is diabetic wounds, which is a huge problem. Like you probably, in your practice, you probably see
people with wounds that just don't heal. Well, I don't see my practice, but I certainly cut my
teeth on it during residency. Yeah. No pun intended, significant problem. Yep. So that's,
I mean, that's a few different applications and there's a lot of sort of rare things. There's
noise induced hearing loss. If you use, that's one of the newer applications that can be... So
some things that are kind of counterintuitive. So when we think of high pressure oxygen, a lot of
times you think of retinopathy or prematurity, right? If you put a newborn and give them high
levels of oxygen, you could cause them to go blind, right? A newborn. So that's an interesting...
Meaning a newborn is more susceptible. More susceptible to oxygen. It was very common,
I guess you could say, to put newborns on high levels of oxygen if they're born premature.
And why, what is it about the newborn that makes them more susceptible? The development of their
lungs. Is it the angiogenic component of this? Yes. Yes. That could be a component too. And maybe
they just don't have the robust endogenous antioxidant capacity, but probably it might
be the angiogenic component too. Do you know off the top of your head if elevated mercury or
mercury toxicity as an indication for hyperbaric? Because I've heard of a lot of people doing this,
but it strikes me as a little bit off label. Probably not. There's so much off label stuff
being done. So one of the things that I'm really interested in testing is for traumatic brain
injury. And I do think that low levels of hyperbaric oxygen therapy, if used shortly after
a traumatic brain injury, I think the faster you restore oxygenation, the more likely you are to
salvage those neurons. So ideally you want to treat with something that's going to reestablish
energy in neurons, decrease inflammation, and increase oxygenation to hypoxic pockets. And
I think from my perspective, giving something like a ketone ester with lower levels of hyperbaric
oxygen therapy would probably work. That's probably the, by far the most controversial
application because there are some remarkable responses from people who have even a regeneration
of brain cells after the hypoxic injury, for example, in kids who are very resilient anyway.
I know Dr. Paul Harch has been on pretty much all the major news networks with a girl that
sustained an incredibly severe hypoxic injury and brain death and regenerated some of her brain
brain function and brain tissue. How old was the girl? She was pretty young, I think five or six,
I believe. And I met her actually, one of the conferences and it's very clear that nothing was
working for her until she did hyperbaric oxygen therapy. So, but kids are completely, could be
another story. You know, we don't know if we could replicate that, but there are a lot of stories out
there, anecdotal reports, but it just has not been studied appropriately and those studies need to be
done. And what do you see as the resistance? I mean, when you look at what's happened in the last
five years in the NFL that has brought along with, I think, just the returning vets, TBI is, I mean,
I don't think you could walk down Madison Avenue and hit someone with a rock who hadn't at least
heard the term TBI. So everybody knows what it is. We've got, you know, these two completely
different demographics who are highly affected by it, athletes and soldiers. What's the hangup? I
mean, you and I have spent a lot of time behind the scenes trying to get organizations like the
NC2A interested in studying this. I'm struggling to understand what the hangup is. You know,
they're looking for devices to, you know, quantify TBIs and concussions. So that's a lot of funding
is going into that area, at least when we talk about the NFL hit challenge and something that,
you know, we submitted to. You know, I don't really know. I don't really know. I think the
scientific rationale for a metabolic-based therapy for the brain makes a lot of sense in restoring
oxygenation. I think the waters are very muddy though when it comes to hyperbaric oxygen with
TBI because I mean, we even did some rat studies where repeated doses of hyperbaric oxygen
in a concussion or a brain injury model, a rat caused more injury can exacerbate the effects.
Whereas a single dose of hyperbaric oxygen right after, at least in our rat model, decreased the
infarct size by maybe 30%, something like that. So this is dangerous. I mean, we don't want
someone listening to this who's suffered a TBI thinking I'm going to go to some off-label clinic
and just max, you know, repeatedly expose myself to hyperbarics. I mean, we, the point here is this
has to be studied. It has to be studied rigorously. It has to be studied empirically. And then we
haven't even got into something we will get into later, which is the potential augmentation of the
exogenous ketone. Yeah. Yeah. I would not do hyperbaric oxygen therapy if people are going to
do it with and without, you know, what I say, I would definitely do hyperbaric oxygen therapy
if you're going to do it in strong nutritional ketosis, because a consequence of hyperbaric
oxygen therapy is, could be CNS oxygen toxicity. So you do not, the last thing you want if you have
a brain injury is to have a seizure. And we know 85% of all penetrating traumatic brain injuries
lead to seizures and people who've had penetrating. What about blunt? I mean, it's less than that,
but how much less? Yeah. So I don't know. I guess you would have to quantify the blunt. The severity.
Yeah. But when it comes to penetrating, but it's, it's, it's upwards about 85% of penetrating
traumatic brain injuries have seizures. And that's because you have excess glutamate,
you know, and that's a very thing that's actually contributing to oxygen toxicity seizures. Right.
So I think the biggest thing to do is to augment your brain energy metabolism to burn energy more
efficiently. The ketones do that and lower neuro inflammation. And I think there's a variety of
ways to do that, but you don't want to throw more fuel on the fire. And I think high levels of
hyperbaric oxygen therapy could be doing that. I think maybe these soft chambers that go to like 1.4,
1.5, maybe a better means to implement that. Let's get into ketosis a little bit. I want to
come back and talk about cancer. I want to come back and talk about the exogenous ketones,
both the salts, the esters, and even different molecules. But one of the most interesting
experiments we've seen in the physiology of ketones, like, you know, as far as old school
experiments was the George Cahill starvation experiments. Right. So highly motivated by that
study. We're going to link to it here, but let's, uh, why don't you give people the reader's digest
version of what George Cahill did that could probably never be done again. Yeah. Yeah. And
I was very lucky to connect with him. Before he died. He passed away in 2012 by connect with him
a few years before that. And just to figure out, you know, did he really do this studies? And there
was a lot of studies that also didn't get published that were pretty remarkable too, that somehow they
got past ethics review at Harvard medical school, but essentially what he did a very elegant study
to look at brain energy metabolism, the AV difference in blood and metabolites in subjects
that fasted for 40 days. And most of the subjects were, uh, divinity students, I believe, or maybe
conscientious objectors to the war or something like that. But each person had like a different
story behind it. And he fasted these subjects for 40 days. And just to be clear, this is water and
mineral only water, no calories. So they took minerals, right? They had magnesium and sodium.
They did. I think they took a mineral supplement and they also were, they weren't lean subjects.
So they were subjects who from their perspective were overweight, if not obese subjects. So they
had some weight to lose. And it was very well documented and well controlled study where they
monitored free fatty acids, insulin glucose, beta hydroxybutyrate, acetoacetate and acetone.
And let's all just pause you there for a moment for the listener. We'll come back to this because I
want you to explain the difference between beta hydroxybutyrate or BHB acetoacetate or AKAC and
acetone, how they're produced, which ones are metabolically active, which ones aren't, but
hopefully by me just saying this between the two of us, we'll remember to come back to that.
Yeah. So yeah, essentially three ketone bodies, beta hydroxybutyrate being the primary ketone
that's elevated and more stable in the blood and probably more likely to be a brain fuel.
And if we just focus on that ketone body after seven days, it reached the level to where it was
at or above the level of glucose in the subject. So glucose came down from five to six millimolar
down to three and stayed at three millimolar throughout the duration of the experiment,
throughout the duration of the fast from day seven, essentially to the remainder of the 40 days.
So for the Yankees listening to this who aren't familiar with the metric system,
three millimolar is about 55 milligrams per deciliter. Yeah. Yep. Okay. So that's pretty
darn low. Yeah. But what's interesting is it gets down there. I think it was between day seven and
day 10, it hit three millimolar and then it just never went down again. Yeah. Yeah. What the heck
is going on? These people don't eat any glucose. How are they? How do they sell? And what that
tells you by definition is their liver still had glycogen because you have to be putting that
glucose out from the liver. Yep. So the maintenance of glucose is under very powerful homeostatic
mechanisms. So we have, we're hardwired from an evolutionary perspective to maintain glucose
and the glucose can be coming from gluconeogenic amino acids. So we are breaking down some muscle
and then the glycerol backbone of triglycerides too also contributes to the production of.
So triglycerides being the storage form of fatty acids, you have a three carbon backbone that's
called a glycerol backbone. It has three of these free fatty acids that are, well, they become free
once they're cleaved. They become the substrate that you're going to explain to us in a few minutes
is how you make BHB or beta hydroxybutyrate, but you don't just throw that glycerol out.
You can actually, the liver can turn that back into glycogen within itself to then slowly trickle
out into the bloodstream. Exactly. Yep. So when Cahill did this, if I recall insulin levels also
got very low by, with about by day seven, the insulin levels were at rock bottom and sort of
stayed there. Yeah. Yeah. One of the interesting things about the experiment, in addition to the
stuff I want to hear about, which is the brain metabolism and how did the brain partition those
fuels is, was it this experiment or a different one where he was able to give insulin lower glucose
levels, but not generate CNS trauma through that? Yeah. So the subjects were asymptomatic for
hypoglycemia and they felt really fine. And in another. Down to what level? Like one millimolar.
Yeah. So they infused IV infusion of 20 IUs of insulin and pushed glucose from three millimolar
or thereabouts down to roughly one millimolar, which is like 18 milligrams per deciliter. Yeah.
Which would be fatal. That would be universally fatal level of glucose. Even two, two becomes like
coma and essentially fatal if it's maintained. I hit two very briefly during an insulin suppression
test I had at Stanford and I was no longer in ketosis because I was doing this insulin
suppression test. So I started at about two and a half or three millimolar, but 90 minutes later,
my ketones had withered down to like 0.3, 0.4. Yeah. And then my glucose hit about 38 milligrams
per deciliter. And I really, that was the day I thought I was gone. That's a dangerous area. Oh,
yeah. No, I thought I was gone. I have a little self-experiment. I can mention after this,
but essentially what they did, which was a very bold and gutsy demonstration,
they injected insulin, which facilitated glucose disposal in the patients essentially and brought
blood glucose down to, you know, roughly one millimolar, which is universally fatal. And the
subjects were relatively asymptomatic for hypoglycemia, which was remarkable. Their ketones
were maintained at about above five to six millimolar. That is out freaking
rages. Yeah. Like that when you just stop to think about how you could take a normal healthy
volunteer and do something, I mean, we're all in the spirit of learning, but when you just think
about that from an ethical standpoint, like how close. I can't do that in mice. I'm not allowed to
do that in mice. The IACUC, the Institute for Animal Care and Use Committee, you know, would not
approve fasting for more than 48 hours. I think it's for 24 at our institution. Yeah. So that's
for mice and maybe rats might be 48. But yeah. And the use of insulin to further, you know, that
would, I serve on the IACUC. I mean, these things would be quickly rejected. I mean, this is, this
was the wild, wild West. Yeah. And then just the last thing on this topic that I remember,
which I'd love you to expand on is what did we learn about how the brain partitioned fuel?
How much of the brain's energy once you were in that steady state after about 10 days
came from glucose, beta hydroxybutyrate and acetoacetate? Yeah. So beta hydroxybutyrate
accounted for approximately 60% of the energy and probably 10% acetoacetate. And roughly at that
point, after about 10 days, only about a third of the energy was coming from glucose, right? And
basically what's in your blood as far as ketones and glucose is what your brain is utilizing. You
know, your brain's in a hungry state and it's effectively utilizing and clearing those, those
metabolites. You can do that. It was, it was very elegant demonstration and it kind of changed our
understanding of brain energy metabolism as glucose being exclusive predominant fuel. So in a fed
state, they were consuming 100% of their brain energy metabolism was from glucose, but only after
being fasted did that change. And he went on to write a number of reviews and went on with Dr. Veach
who actually created and developed some of the, they published together. He was a postdoc with
Cahill, wasn't he? A postdoc. Yeah. He was a student of Hans Kreb actually. And then, yeah, he was one
of the, I forgot that fact. Yeah. He was one of his best students from my understanding. Yeah. From
word of mouth. Yeah. They went and they worked together in different capacities. Yeah. I think
he might've been a fellow with him. I think most people listening to this, if they can dig back to
high school biology, that name Krebs will sort of ring a bell, right? Yeah, he should. Yeah. So you
mentioned that Cahill shared with you stuff that wasn't even published. Do you remember anything
that was, that struck you as super interesting that was unpublished? Yeah. You know, some things
maybe, uh, not worth talking about. Well, yeah, I don't know if he, I do with some stories and then
I heard some stories through other people too. Well, I don't want to make you say anything that
you're not comfortable saying publicly. But I would say some of the work that was done in animals
definitely suggested that glucose could go lower, even lower, and that, uh, you could really
transition your metabolic physiology to be fueled off fats and ketones and, and that, that was
against what we knew. These were remarkable observations that changed the whole context
of what we knew about metabolic physiology and brain energy metabolism. Do we know today if the
brain can use lactate directly as a fuel without it having to go through the Corey cycle? Yeah,
most certainly can. I think, I think lactate's a actually a great fuel. Okay. And that's one of
the first fuels I got interested in when I was studying hypoxia and then later even, uh, hyperoxia
was thinking about using lactate, uh, different forms of orally available lactate like polyl
lactate. You know, I think it's in the product CytoMax. If you remember for cycling,
I used to use CytoMax. Yeah. So, uh, so I was actually interested in that. And that actually
led me to ketones. And then once I got more into studying ketones and discovered somehow it slipped
past me all the years, I thought I knew what a ketogenic diet was, but then when I read about
the history of the ketogenic diet being used for almost a century, and I realized that it was like
the standard of care for seizures. And then understanding that these ketones can largely
replace glucose as the energy source. And then they have these signaling properties that are
even independent of metabolism that are remarkable over the last five years. A lot of these big labs
are looking at the epigenetic effects of ketones functioning as class one, class two histone,
histone laser, the functioning as a suppressor of the NLRP3 and phlammasome, producing less
inflammation in a metabolic independent way. So you obviously pretty quickly come to this idea
that these ketones are interesting molecules and they're interesting for a couple of reasons. At the
very least, what you just said, which is they have signaling properties that make them kind of unique
outside of the exogenous ketones though, you have to also undergo a pretty extreme
physiologic change, at least in a Western culture, to make enough of these to matter. And you have to
restrict carbohydrates and protein to get there. So did you first personally get interested in this
from a nutritional standpoint, and then eventually through this exogenous pathway or vice versa?
Yeah, so ketone esters to my knowledge in 2008 didn't exist. They actually did, but I didn't know
of them. I discovered them on a DARPA website as some work that was being funded in developing of
the ketone esters for warfighter performance. But at the time, when I decided to go down the route
of the ketogenic diet, I reached out to Johns Hopkins and the crew there. Which is where the
anti-seizure therapy was pioneered, right? Yeah, Mayo Clinic first, and then they worked together
with Hopkins. I would say the bulk of the work that was done to develop the protocols for the
ketogenic diet, which are in use today, was developed at Johns Hopkins. And I got Eric
Kosoff books, his book published with John Freeman, which was I just went out and did the
classical ketogenic diet, the four to one ratio. So four parts fat and one part being protein and
carbohydrates. It equates out to 87 to upwards of 90% fat, maybe 10% protein and like one or
two percent carbohydrates. So I mean, it's like basically eating super low carb and then adding
mountains of fat on top of that plate, making like a super low carb meal with protein restrict,
and then add some butter and a couple cups of heavy cream with that. And that's, I started
weighing everything out. And I wonder, what year did you start that? 2008, I think in nine, I think
it was 2008 or nine that Eric Kosoff published the modified ketogenic diet, which was more liberal
in protein and increasing protein from 10% to 25 and 30% or 25% is a huge difference. Like you can,
that's actually a diet that I mostly adhere to now. And I followed the ketogenic diet and I
bought the strips were very expensive at the time. There was a couple different kits that I got
to measure my own ketones. And you know, I immersed myself in it, I got obsessed with it,
and I wanted to know what it felt like to have a brain that ran on ketones. And how high did your
levels get measured in the blood? I kind of struggled to get up there, even with the classical
ketogenic diets, two and 2.5, I would typically with the classical ketogenic. And this is before
MCTs. So I wasn't quite using MCTs yet. In 2009, I started incorporate the same time I discovered
the modified ketogenic diet was the same time I started using MCTs. And a modified ketogenic
diet with MCTs got my ketone levels up probably higher than the classical ketogenic diet,
which was just mostly, you know, a dairy based long chain fat sort of derived diet.
So let's tell everybody how we make ketones, and then we'll tell them what an MCT is for those.
Yeah. So let's talk about starvation ketosis. And then if there's differences between that that are
worth highlighting with nutritional, that would be great. But evolutionarily, I'm going to deprive
you from eating for a few days. How do you survive? Well, you start burning up your liver glycogen.
Okay, so 24 hours later, you've got that down to about half of its half to let about a quarter of
its supply. Through the suppression of the hormone insulin, we start mobilizing fat from adipose
tissue, which are cells pretty much all cells in the body, especially muscle and heart cells,
burned fat like a superior energy source. Long chain fatty acids don't effectively cross the
blood brain barrier. So through accelerated fat oxidation, beta oxidation fats in the liver,
that stimulates the accumulation of acetyl CoA, which forms acetoacetate and ultimately beta
hydroxybutyrate. So you start spilling these ketone bodies through accelerated fat oxidation
in the liver. The liver lacks succinyl CoA transferase, so does not actually use the ketone
bodies for fuel. And they become available for your brain, the central nervous system and peripheral.
So the liver is secreting beta hydroxybutyrate. Yeah. And acetoacetate to some extent.
Okay. So is the BHB being made and then being converted into acetoacetate or is the liver
making both? Acetoacetate first and then beta hydroxybutyrate. And it's interesting that some
people have a ratio of beta hydroxybutyrate to acetoacetate of two to one and some people five
to one, generally speaking about four to one. So acetoacetate is unstable in that it can
spontaneously decarboxylate to acetone, which is volatile and we blow it off in our breath.
Does it have metabolic activity? Can we...
It was thought that it didn't, but more recent work is suggesting that the carbons of acetone
do find their way into sort of lipid biosynthesis and some other things, but it's kind of rare for
that to happen. But it's not a great ATP source. No, no, not really. It has some effect on neurons.
So it has an anti-convulsion effect through, I believe, opening a potassium channel, which
could hyperpolarize a membrane potential and actually help attenuate some hyper-excitability
in the brain. So there are people that study the effects of acetone as a sub-narcotic levels of
acetone. Acetone can be pretty narcotic and be problematic, but acetone levels that are 0.5
millimolar and even upwards of one millimolar can have a neuroprotective effect. Once you get above
one millimolar, you start to dissolve some of the membranes and you can have sort of...
That doesn't sound...
Yeah, you have problematic. Acetone is a pretty powerful solvent. It's a nail polish remover,
but small levels of acetone are neuroprotective and that's actually something that we study.
So how do acetoacetate and beta-hydroxybutyrate enter the Krebs cycle? In other words,
where do we get ATP from them?
It depends on the cells. So different cells have different... We're looking at this now,
different ketolytic enzymes. So they can feed in through a number of different pathways.
Like I said, the liver is the production site of beta-hydroxybutyrate. And when it comes to
skeletal muscle, they have a range of ketolytic enzymes that can allow them to enter the Krebs
cycle at different areas. So succinate, for example. So you can replenish TCA cycle intermediates
with succinate. Acetyl acetate can break down and provide acetyl CoA for the Krebs cycle.
So what we're finding is that the Krebs cycle is not the simple cycle that we thought it was,
especially as it relates to cancer cells. So it's almost like we can't even look at
the biochemistry book and kind of pinpoint different pathways. With substrate level
phosphorylation, there are a number of different pathways like the malate, aspartate, shuttle,
that are associated with cancer cells if we go back to those pathways.
Did you see that paper that came out in Nature two days ago about aspartate being a rate-limiting
step in cancer metabolism in the mitochondria? I didn't see that.
Bob and I were just talking about it today. It's interesting because the paper was...
Part of it was written through a lens of, hey, this might be how metformin can exert some of
its anti-cancer benefits by interfering with aspartate. I think it was interfering with
degradation of aspartate, but again, I haven't read the paper yet, just sort of the abstract,
but was yet another, like, I didn't know that. Wow. Every day I feel like I'm getting dumber
because the rate at which I'm being exposed to new information is exceeding the rate at which I'm
assimilating it. So it's just, it feels like I'm on a downward spiral to stupidity.
There are textbook pathways that I used to just rattle off and it all seems so simple.
And then, you know, I read three or four papers and I realized that I probably shouldn't talk
about it in some simplistic terms like that. I mean, we're kind of going down the rabbit hole
of glutamine lysis, right? So glutamine is the fermentable fuels. So ketones are a non-fermentable
fuel, whereas cancer cells, we use glucose and glutamine as the two primary fermentable fuels.
You know, it's funny. I mean, I know that biochemically. I'd never thought of it in
those terms though. Yeah. Yeah. It's not fermentable. That's interesting.
So that's kind of what I'm thinking about, you know, in terms of ketone metabolism with glutamate.
So, or glutamine, glutamine can make glutamate, right? And alanine and aspartate and lactate
and glutamine lysis is kind of driven by the malate-aspartate shuttle. And that has become
a major focus now of many cancer researchers are looking to target glutamine and it's not easy.
I mean, because if you have a glutaminase inhibitor, that has tremendous side effects.
Huge toxicity.
Right. Yeah. So we need to approach this in a very nuanced sort of way when it comes to targeting
glutamine. Yeah. So let's go back to the MCT. So you talked about how you started out on a
four to one ratio, which is interesting. I started out four to one. I spent three years on just four
to one. I never deviated from four to one, but then you mentioned you went to two to one, which
is obviously much easier to do, but you augmented with MCT. So MCT of course stands for medium
chain triglyceride. They're a type of saturated fat and they're of a certain length. And I don't
even remember anymore. Is it eight to 14 carbons is what we define as MCT? Yeah. Eight to 10,
I think eight to 14 from in that. But when we talk about the ketogenic ones, the, uh,
they're more close, they're closer to caprylic acid, which is the C8s. Yep. So why does,
why does taking those make this process easier? When you consume them orally, they are transported
to the liver via hepatic portal circulation and they're not packaged into kylo microns.
And you know, long chain fatty acids, when we eat them, they're packaged into kylo microns and
then they go through, essentially enter the lymphatic system and have a different route
of entry. They're metabolized totally differently. Whereas medium chain fats go directly to the
liver through a paddock portal circulation. It's like a bolus of fat going to the liver.
And it's a type of fat that's rapidly oxidized, right? The liver is chock full of
mitochondria. So if I want to study mitochondria, I'll take out a chunk of the liver and isolate
it from that. Cause that's the easiest thing to do. So the mitochondria really burn up medium
chain triglycerides very quickly. And, uh, there's very high rates of fat oxidation in the liver from
an oral bolus of medium chain triglycerides. So they're much less likely to be stored as fat.
They're a source of calories and they can be incorporated into meals and into foods to further
enhance and boost the ketone levels of the ketogenic diet. Or even if you're not on a
ketogenic diet, they can be consumed with a high carbohydrate diet and actually elevate ketones in
the blood. Yeah. I mean, I've heard that, but I've never actually measured it probably because I've
only done this with liquid MCT, which you end up getting to sort of GI tolerance becomes an issue
probably before you get a high enough level. But if you're on a high carb diet and you consume,
I don't know, two to three tablespoons of MCT, how high could you reasonably expect your BHB to get?
Depending on your absorption anywhere between 0.5 to one millimolar.
That high.
I would say. Yeah. Even on a high. Yeah. If it's pure C8, maybe, uh, so with C8, you get about a
20, maybe 30% elevation above like a mix of the C10 C8, which is generic. There's some work being
done that C10 may actually have some beneficial effects. I mean, that's kind of the idea behind
the product Exona that was on the market, you know, a while back. I don't know if it's still
in the market. I don't know. I don't know what it is. Yeah. It's a basically C8 it's powdered C8.
I used to just order pure C8. Yeah, you can order it. I ordered like from Sigma or something like
that. Yeah. Well, I Dave asked for these brain octane as is caprylic triglyceride and perillo
nutrition makes cap tree, which is a C8 oil. So if you buy pure C8, not in triglyceride form,
caprylic, if you just, uh, yeah, just straight acrylic acid. Yes. That'll kill you. I mean,
you, you consume that. I bought, I made the mistake early on and bought from Sigma caprylic acid,
but not yet. You need to buy it. How did you catch that mistake before ingesting it?
I bought it from Sigma and I think I was going to use it in experiments and we were going to mix it,
you know, with our rat chow and I wanted to go through a legitimate source and, uh, I put a
little bit on my finger and it kind of burnt my tongue off and I realized, wait a second. I think
I need to try glyceride form of caprylic acid. I need the caprylic triglyceride. Yeah. I almost
killed myself. I almost won a Darwin award. Yeah. Yeah. You know, I never looked at any
of the research. Someone probably did that before accidentally, uh, kills himself. Yeah.
Have you had any experience with the powdered MCTs? Yeah. Yeah. So powdered MCTs allow me to
increase my ketone levels higher than, uh, and I use the Quest powdered MCT formula. There's a
couple on the market now, maybe. Yeah. I have vats of this stuff at home because I feel like
anyone who's ever made a ketone product just somehow figures out my address and sends them to
me. So I have a pantry full of every type of ketone you can imagine. I do too. But I haven't,
yeah, you probably get more than me. I just haven't got around to trying any of the MCT powder,
but I'm getting ready to do a long fast in a couple of weeks. And I was thinking I really
ought to get, make sure I'm back in ketosis the week before I deprived myself of food for a week.
Yeah. So I was actually just thinking about this last week, which is I got to fire up those
powdered MCT and kickstart this thing. Cause I don't have like a couple of months to get fully
adapted. Yeah, they are great. I mean, MCTs are kind of like the poor man's ketone ester, right?
So they are, they're, they're found in nature. They're versatile. You can incorporate them in
the middle classes, man. Yeah. Given how expensive ketone esters are now.
That's right. That's right. Yeah. So I tinkered a lot with MCTs early on and increased my tolerability
from maybe 30 milliliters a day to 150 milliliters a day. Hang on a second. That's ridiculous. Yeah.
Yeah. When anytime I went to 30 in one sitting, 10 tablespoons full. Yeah. Yeah. That's hard to
fathom. You need to incorporate it with food. So I was spreading it. What I found I needed to do
was instead of doing intermittent fasting now, which I pretty much do now, I, I spread it out
over like four meals and maybe would have a little bit of MCT in the coffee too, and not including
that in a meal. So I was eating a modified ketogenic diet, but spreading that MCT out
with salad dressings, putting it on vegetables and things like that. And I was able to,
because if anybody's listening to this and is trying to, like they're just sitting there
thinking how, what could I do to do it to have a bowel prep? Like the answer is just, just, just
drink MCT. It's, you know, it's, it's better than Fleets Phosphasoda. You will, you will spend the
day in the bathroom and you'll, you'll have a great colonoscopy. But you can work your way up to it.
So there's a number of transporters obviously that are upregulated and you are enhancing the breakdown
and transport of these fat and MCTs actually do cross the blood brain barrier. So we did studies
in rats where we took out the hippocampus. But if they're getting absorbed portally,
how do we know? Oh, okay. Some of them, I forget the percentage, but I think, and some people say
it's like 50% of MCTs converted to ketones, but I think it's something like about 20% of MCTs.
And it depends on the energetic state of the liver, you know, which is the master regulator
and your, your physiology in general, but you have a fairly significant portion of the MCTs
being converted to ketones, but the MCTs do enter the blood and they can cross the blood
brain barrier unlike the long chain fats. And they, for example, if you take out the
hippocampi of rats that are eating an MCT based ketogenic diet, you'll find MCT levels are
significantly elevated. So they're crossing, they're getting into the brain and the brain is utilizing
MCTs as fuel. And do we know if that has any anti-seizure effect independent of the ketone
that might be produced alongside it? That's a big area of research right now that MCTs is functional
fats. So, and I've never heard that term before, functional fats. Yeah. Like, well, fats with drug
like properties. So I think there's a number of patents around the C10 actually that I know they
have in the UK. I think it might be a pharmaceutical now. So C10 actually has anti-seizure properties.
So there's some people argue that the effects of the ketogenic diet, at least with MCTs,
is not due to ketones, but actually due to the MCTs and not the ketones. So there's a little bit,
there's a couple of groups out there that are sort of arguing that. And I think they have a case,
but I think it's probably a common, definitely a combination of the ketones and the MCTs. So MCTs
do have interesting properties. Do you know Elizabeth Teal at Boston Children's? Yeah. So I
remember having breakfast with her about six years ago and asking her a question that at the time,
I don't think she knew the answer to, and she was gracious enough to explain that. And she was there
with someone else in her lab. So it was a very spirited, awesome discussion. But I wonder if
the answer is known today. The question was basically, do you believe that the anti-seizure
properties of a ketogenic diet are more the result of the brain having another fuel to
displace glucose or due to the reduction in glucose that invariably accompanies ketogenesis?
And at the time she shared with me very compelling data that could argue either of those points,
potentially suggesting it was the combination of them. Do you have a point of view on this or is
there more information today that steers you one way or the other? Well, I know she's done some
work with the low glycemic index diet. So carbohydrate reduction, but without the production
of ketones. Yeah. So a reduction, it's carbohydrate restriction, but only to the effect of maybe 20 or
25%, you know, and then carbohydrates that are low glycemic index. And what are the results of that
intervention? For different types of seizures, it can have a positive effect and for certain
types of seizures. That's not the first line of therapy for, you know, very powerful tonic,
clonic seizures and pediatrics. You want to go right to the classical ketogenic diet,
but it does have a number of applications for different types of seizure disorders.
And what about if you take someone on a fully-carbed diet who's having recalcitrant seizures and you
give them ketone, exogenous ketone? Does that have anti-seizure benefit? Yeah. So those studies have
not been done yet. And there's a study being recruiting right now for something called
Angelman syndrome, which is a rare genetic disorder that has seizures where the exogenous
ketones are the therapy independent of the diet. So they're just being added on top of the diet.
There are people out there because exogenous ketones are commercially available that are using
this in place of the ketogenic diet, because the families are either unwilling or for various
reasons unable to use the ketogenic diet. And they, you know, argue using exogenous ketones.
And the feedback that I'm getting could be biased, but it does seem to have an effect.
It obviously has an effect in animal models. The animal models that we work with,
we give exogenous ketones on top of a standard rat chow, which is high carbohydrate chow. And it
works very well for CNS oxygen toxicity, but also for things like phenylentetrazole seizures,
PZT seizures, even for absence seizures, we use a particular animal model with absence seizures
or absence seizures, which are works for that. So it works for a variety of different seizure
models independent. We are circumventing sort of the dietary restriction that's typically associated
with getting into therapeutic ketosis and just simply giving exogenous ketones and elevating
exogenous ketones. But a consideration is that exogenous ketones lower blood glucose.
So you have, and in some cases it lowers it really low, like the high dose ketone esters
that we do in our rat models, it pushes and rats typically maintain a glucose of around 140 to 150,
and it'll push it down to 40. So milligrams per deciliter. Yeah. And that's approaching
the maximum tolerable dose of the ketone ester. And it's interesting when we go above the maximum
tolerable dose, we actually see glucose levels spike up. And this is a phenomenon that we see.
It's almost like it's stressing out the liver or just regulating the liver in some way.
It's the data we're trying to figure out. But if you titrate in ketone salts or ketone salt MCT
combination or various ketone esters, it's inversely proportional to, as you elevate ketones,
you have a very predictable, reliable decrease in blood glucose that's above and beyond
the decrease in blood glucose that you'd observe with something like metformin.
And we use metformin for many, many studies in a lab. And we have a lot of experience with that.
So what do we think? You know, it's funny, I was up in San Francisco, like a month ago,
and I was talking with Steve Finney, who, you know, at the outset, I said, you're one of the people
who I would say knows more about ketosis than anyone alive. And certainly Steve would have to
be in that category. So I would, if I were going to just guess, I would say, between you and Steve
Finney, if the answer isn't really known on ketosis, the answer might not be known. Yeah.
So but and Steve and I were having this really fun discussion with a few other folks about
why is it that the ketones are driving down the glucose levels? And conversely, and maybe this is
a different question, of course, but why is it that when we do these experiments of you take somebody
in nutritional ketosis, and you make them do really, really aggressive exercise, you know, do a two
minute all out effort on the rowing machine, that the ketones go way down and the glucose goes way up?
Is it solely a consumption and hepatic glucose output issue? Is there something else going on?
You know, and I was like, while I kind of always assumed that we knew the answer to that, and that
it was the explanation I had, but you know, it wasn't at the end of that discussion, I was like,
actually, I pretty much now don't think I know the answer to this question.
I don't think we do. I have three potential explanations. One could be an exogenous ketone
induced release and insulin that facilitates glucose disposal. So we're that happens. You do
get I mean, it's not like consuming a protein bolus or a carbohydrate bolus, but you do get
an elevation of ketones. That's right. That's how we moderate our ketone levels, right? So as our
ketone levels, if we're on the ketogenic diet, and our ketones become elevated, there's ketone
urea, we pee out some ketones, and there's a number of products, but one is a ketone induced
release of insulin, which then feeds back on the liver to like a rheostat really, and lowering
beta oxidation, which totally makes sense, because that's the reason that someone with
type one diabetes can get ketoacidosis. They lose the checkpoint. Yep. Yep. And other researchers,
like if you asked Richard V, she'll tell you that insulin sensitivity is increased. So the insulin
that you have available and associated signaling is being enhanced in the presence of ketones.
Is that an immediate change? Or is that a change that takes place over a long period of time? That
sounds like a long standing issue. I think there's a number of regulatory things that happen. I know
in his study where rats were fed standard rodent chow, but 30 to 20% ketone ester, I think within
that chow, their baseline insulin levels went down like 50%. So that's just simply by, you know,
just the addition of the ketone, just the addition of the ketone over time, over, I think it was like
maybe a three week. I got to look to see the study, but it was, it was consuming ketone ester that was
integrated into the rat chow over a number of weeks, decreased baseline levels of insulin
significantly. I mean, it was like a huge effect and the implications of that, you know, as a rat
study, you know, you can argue rat study, but I can tell you experimentally that are just, you know,
testing on myself that the same observation happens. I can actually, if I get a significant
amount of my calories from exogenous ketones, and I do that over several weeks and I measure my
insulin, it gets below the reference range. Whereas if I get back to a regular ketogenic diet,
I'm always on the low end of the reference range, but I did find if I consume the maximum tolerable
dose of a ketone ester or ketone salt, and then I measure insulin, you know, an hour or two after
that, I do get a little bump up in insulin, but it's nowhere near the bump I would get up if I
ate an equivalent amount of calories from protein or carbohydrates, which would shoot me up to like,
you know, eight or 10 or something like that, you know, with a big dose, but it's usually somewhere
around, I bump it up from like 1.5 to like 2.5 or three or something like that. Those are still
super low. Yeah. And that's my baseline is usually between one and two.
So what has your IGF level changed in the years that you've been on ketosis? Have you tracked it
much? I have not. I've gotten it measured a few times, but not reliably. Like I do insulin
quite often, like every two months or so, like I'm doing that. And if I'm doing an experiment,
I may do multiple measurements of insulin like throughout the week, but I haven't measured IGF-1
recently. I did it a while back and I was just in the normal range, but I wasn't fasting. I didn't,
that's the one variable I wish I would have tried. Insulin was low, so I can assume IGF-1 might have
been a little bit low. Yeah. So just for listeners and stuff, how do we measure ketones? I mean,
people talk about urine strips versus blood. What are you measuring in each and breath for that
matter? You've got three ways to theoretically measure these things. Which one do we prefer and
why? For a newbie getting into this, I think the urine ketone strips will at least tell you if
you're in ketosis or not in ketosis. What is it measuring? A urine strip? It's measuring. If you're
peeing on it, what does it tell you? Urine acetoacetate is measured. And now there's a urine
beta-hydroxybutyrate kits that are available, so you could do that. So the Abbott Labs Precision
Extra and the Keto-Mojo are two devices that will measure basically a home assay kit for beta-hydroxybutyrate.
And we have used both of those things and kind of measured it against various assays in the lab and
blood that we send out for analysis. And it's pretty close. Pretty close, plus or minus,
maybe 10% or 15%. What does the urinary level, even though it's a qualitative assay, but everybody
says, hey, my urinary ketone thing lit up bright purple, can we infer anything from that about the
blood level of BHB or acetoacetate? Usually, unless you're running kind of dehydrated,
if you have a normal hydration state and your urine acetoacetate is 40 milligrams per deciliter
or above, you are probably hitting one millimolar or above. If you're anywhere between 40 and 80 to,
I think, 160 milligrams per deciliter, so you're in a state of ketosis. If you're at 15,
that's like light pink or something, you're usually probably not in a state,
what I would say, keto. That might be a normal state if you wake up in the morning in sort of
a facet state, you might be hitting that. But generally speaking, you need to be at about 80
milligrams per deciliter on the urine ketone strip. And the one thing I didn't do rather when I was
doing my sort of long foray into ketosis is I didn't use the urine meters at all. I was just,
you know, I was, I was keeping Abbott in business basically with how many of those precision extra
strips I was going through. So I don't know if my urinary excretion actually declined over time
when my body became better and better at retaining this potentially preferred fuel.
Have you done anything on that either personally or in the lab?
So what we use in the lab is the Clinitex Status device. And that device takes the Siemens 10SG kit,
so the multi-stick. So you can buy for a similar cost as the keto stick, you could buy the Siemens
10SG multi-stick and that measures 10 things, including urine acetoacetate. And you could take
that urine strip and stick that in a device that will give you more of a quantified number.
I see. So that's how you were giving me quantitative information on the urine.
Because I've only seen the qualitative stuff.
Well, it's a color change on the strip that's measured in the device.
Yeah, the device tells me.
Yeah. So over the years, I rejected urine ketone strips as something that just wasn't very accurate.
And the more I use them, making hundreds, if not thousands of measurements, the more I gain an
appreciation that it can be a pretty useful device. But I think it's, it's kind of useful for the
individual. Your hydration status definitely changes it. I mean, it's been in situations where
I'm dehydrated, where I've come out of the water after like a six hour dive, and I've
peed on those things. And it's like, it's like screaming. And I knew, I mean, I did some dives
where I purposely wasn't in ketosis for some of the research that we do. And I was deep into
into keto. It's just because I was, you know, very, very dehydrated.
I didn't know someone could dive for six hours.
I was on the NASA Nemo Extreme Environment Mission Operations trip. So I was a crew member
on that where I maintained I would lived in saturation for 10 days in a hyperbaric environment.
And that involves like an 18, 19 hour decompression to come out. So it's a NASA sort of a Mars analog
mission, where you work with astronauts underneath the sea. And I maintained a state of ketosis
throughout that whole mission and, and did lots and lots of measurements on myself down there.
And I saw really, when I one time I got out after maybe it was a six hour EVA. So essentially,
you're in a hyperbaric habitat on the bottom of the ocean. And then you go out into the water,
and then you come back inside the hyperbaric habitat. But when you're out in the water,
even though you're down in the Keys, the water water pools heat from you like 200 times faster
than air. So even though it's like, you know, upper 80s, I come out of that hypothermic and
dehydrated my blood glucose always was in like the 30s, sometimes in the 40s. When I was on the
key to I was testing some of the ketone supplements. Wow. Yeah, what were the other people experiencing
under those circumstances? Well, we'll find out with this my wife actually is was selected as a
crew member for NASA Nemo 23. I was on 22. And I did not get the IRB protocol approved to do all
the metabolic studies that I wanted to do. But I became an end of one on that and I collected a
lot of data on myself. So with this new mission, we have the Nemo NASA Nemo 23, we'll be able to make
some pretty comprehensive metabolic measurements, including things like hemoglobin h1c, we're going
to measure inflammation, hscrp, glucose ketones, all these things on all the crew members.
Interestingly, this year, it's a it's an all female crew. So you have like Samantha Christopher
ready, the famous European Tracy Caldwell Dyson, who I've known at NASA and my wife and it's all
female. So we'll have love some female data to go along with this. What surprised you the most in
your end of one? What did you see that you least expected? I saw why predicted that the habitat
would really trigger inflammation that was probably from the elevated co2 levels and the
elevated oxidative stress, I chose to stay in a state of ketosis with the idea that that was my
baseline state. We're doing studies on sleep, we're using the oral ring, you're probably familiar
with that on sleep and also the polar v800 to collect heart rate variability data, gut microbiome,
we're doing body composition measurements, we're doing stress. So we use the NIH toolbox and
juggle to look at cognitive psych parameters. So that data has not been shared to me. So I don't
know my wife collected some of that data and that's being analyzed, you know, later on for
publication. But from a metabolic perspective, from a hormone perspective, some of the things
living in that environment for 10 days decreased my testosterone. How much? I had a 25% decrease in
testosterone from the time and so we're fairly, maybe fairly sleep deprived. I average about six
hours of sleep per night, but I was getting like two and a half hours of deep sleep, which is more
deep sleep than I typically, yeah, I was like, I don't know if it's something in the environment.
It might be an artifact of how the sleep is being estimated. In other words, you know,
if you think you're assuming you're giving that off the aura ring, right? Yeah, that was the aura
ring. So the aura ring is measuring. But I usually get about 90 minutes sometimes like last last night,
I got one hour and 53 minutes of deep sleep, but I usually get about one hour, one and a half hours
of deep sleep, but I got over two hours every night. And instead of seven hours sleep at night,
I was getting consistently just, you know, five to six hours sleep at night. So where are you
getting mostly shortchanged on REM? Yeah, on REM, but my REM was even not that bad. Usually I was
getting about an hour, you know, an hour around, which is not as much as that. Yeah, that's too
low. Usually two is optimal for me, I think. So yeah, we measured sleep. The things that really
stood out were being in the water really pushes my body into and being hypothermic really turns
me into a fat burning machine. My ketones go off the chart and my glucose goes way down. It almost
looks like a six hour EVA when I came back into the habitat, it looked like I fasted for a week.
So I have all that data for that too, that I need to compile and analyze. Should we be looking at
that, we meaning people as a potential way to replicate fast under a more stressful state?
Looking at what, just underwater immersion? Yeah, do you think it was a combination of
temperature and pressure primarily that was driving that effect? So over the holidays,
we went to Thailand and we did, I did a lot of nitrox dives, something like 30 nitrox dives.
And I made these measurements too. And I did see trends for decreased glucose and nitrox dives,
we're doing like an hour, maybe hour, hour and a half dives at the most. And I saw trends,
but nothing like the trends I saw in the saturation environment when we did these long EVAs.
So do you think that the temperature was the difference or the duration?
The temperature really has to have a difference because you come out and you're kind of shaky,
even though you feel very comfy when you're down there the first two or three hours.
And then by the end, the last four, five, six hours for a longer EVA, you start shaking a little bit
uncontrollably. But it's kind of subtle, even though the water is kind of warm, like it feels
warm, but it's just your body temperature is going down. And they were on the days, maybe I wasn't
getting as much calories as I needed. I came out of that mission lighter than I've ever been before.
I came out when we got back to mainland and I stepped on the scale, I was 207, which is super
low for me. I ended up losing about maybe, I went in kind of late because I was training for it.
I'm not a very good swimmer like you. I had to really train to meet, like you, it would be like
a total day in the park for you to meet all the criteria for that. But I had to train really hard
to meet the swim requirements. So I ended up losing a little bit of weight. But when I came out,
I would definitely did the whole mission. I lost nine pounds and I came out seven. So I went in
216. So I went in pretty late. I'm like 221 now. So last year I entered the mission at 216 and I
came out like 207, which was like, I thought the scale was wrong. So even though I ate a lot of
calories during that mission, my metabolic rate was really high, you know, and that was a consequence.
That is so interesting because those are two completely contradictory concepts to me. On the
one hand, you're saying, hey, my glucose levels went down. My ketone levels went up. It looked like
I had fasted for a week. But of course, if you fasted for a week, your metabolic rate would be
going down and not up. In fact, you would expect to see autophagy skyrocket. Whereas I'm sitting
here as I'm listening to you thinking, would autophagy have increased during that period of
time or decreased? I think anything that pushes glucose that low and ketones that high, and I
think not really without knowing it, we're pretty task loaded. So you don't have all the time, you
know, that much time to eat. I mean, part of the mission is that they're training. This is part of
it's the only NASA analog where astronauts are actually part of the crew members. Like other
things like high seas mission or NASA hero mission actually uses everyday folks and they push them to
the limits and see how they can break them. But the NASA Nemo mission is actually training
sort of astronauts. So they task load you to see what you're doing. And you don't have a whole lot
of time to eat, but I was consuming what my normal calories would be, but I underestimated
my calories for this. And I think it put me in a calorie deficit, which probably decreased my
testosterone may have, my cortisol level increased, but it was still within the normal range.
And you're away from the light. So your circadian is probably a bit screwed up too,
being in the other side of the path. What depth are you at? You're only at like 60 feet. So you do see
some of the light come down in, but it's probably a little bit different than I'm a very light sort
of sun worshiper. Like I always try to get some light in the middle, you know, in the beginning of
the day. And that that's part of something that I always do. So it was a bit disruptive in that
sense. So let's talk about ketone, esters, salts, et cetera. So to your knowledge, what's the first
exogenous ketone that was ever manufactured? Is that Vitaly one or exogenous ketone manufactured?
So one three butane dial has been around a long time since the 1950s. Actually MIT did some
research as a space fuel. So that got, there was a publication in 1975 where they were trying to
identify an alternative energy fuel for long duration space flight. And the best candidate
was one three butane dial, which is sort of a synthetic compound that breaks down completely
to beta hydroxybutyrate. Meaning the liver is not required to transform it into BHB. The liver
is required through a couple simple steps. So sodium beta hydroxybutyrate would be the first
sort of ketone, exogenous ketone that was used clinically. And that there was a number of papers
that utilized that for rare metabolic disorders actually. So that would be the first one and a
lot of the IP and sort of patterns that came out were sodium beta hydroxybutyrate. And then
maybe explain for people what the difference is between a salt and an ester. So we'll leave
acetoacetate out of that for a moment. Yeah. But if you talk about beta hydroxybutyrate,
but you can have a CO acetate salt too. So I can mention that. So I didn't know that. I
thought it was only a di ester. So that's, we'll definitely want to hear about that. So on the BHB
front, people are sort of inundated with ketone salts, ketone esters, and then a whole bunch of
complete like weird stuff like raspberry ketones and stuff. But let's just leave the nonsense off
the table. Yeah. But if you just talk about comparing a ketone, a BHB ester to a BHB salt,
what's the chemical difference? Yeah. So a salt is just an ionic bond, right? Between the ketone
molecule, beta hydroxybutyrate, a monovalent or a divalent cation, or an alkaline amino acid,
like arginine, citrulline, histidine, lysine. So you can literally ionically bond beta hydroxybutyrate
to a number of different things. The easiest thing to do is to bond it with sodium, potassium,
calcium, and magnesium. Now calcium and magnesium have two positive charges. You could put two
BHBs on them. That's the advantage, sort of an advantage. A disadvantage, I guess, with magnesium
BHB, which is actually is very bioavailable magnesium. I measured my magnesium after taking
it. It went up quite high. Disadvantage is that your GI tolerability to something like magnesium
beta hydroxybutyrate may be only somewhere between one to three grams. Three grams max per dose.
Wow, which is not that much. One gram, three times a day, at least for me, has no issues. I could
probably tolerate two or three grams per day. So it's nice. I mean, it's something that's
contributing, but ideally what you want to do with a ketone salt is, because salt has a stigma,
I call them ketone electrolyte formulations, is to spread the beta hydroxybutyrate out across
monovalent and divalent cations. And they're the four that have the most utility.
And then an ester, of course, is a covalent bond, not an ionic bond, right?
Yeah. So you can take one three butane dial and you could create a mono ester with beta hydroxybutyrate
and just add it, do a trans esterification reaction and combine that beta hydroxybutyrate
to one three butane dial or acetoacetate. You can combine with one three butane, or you could
take glycerol. So with glycerol, you can come up with a triester of glycerol, which we have.
Basically, you're creating a triglyceride that is instead of three fatty acids, you put three BHBs.
It's pretty cool molecule, yeah. So we have some experience using that.
I told a story like many, many years ago, probably four or five years ago on Tim Ferriss' podcast
about how I drank this jet fuel and almost thought I was going to go blind. Of course,
what I may or may not have omitted from that story was that you gave it to me.
The ketones today taste a heck of a lot better than that earlier Gen stuff. Even when I told you
that I just took the 50 ml vial you sent and chugged it in one sitting, even you were horrified.
You're like, wait, wait, wait. You didn't read the note I wrote you explaining how to dilute it and
mix it. I thought we had talked about it. We had assuredly talked about it. I know you're very
enthusiastic about getting started. Yeah, I couldn't resist. I was too. That stuff's
unbearably bad. Whereas the ketone salts actually don't taste bad. They obviously be strong.
They could formulate it. It tastes awesome. Yeah, yeah. So why does the ester... Is there
an obvious reason from an olfactory slash taste perspective why they are so staggeringly horrible?
Or at least they were. I mean, I'm told they're better today.
Yeah, I would say the ketogenic potency is inversely proportional to taste.
So it just seems like the more potent these compounds get, even the triester beta-hydroxybutyrate
is pretty nasty stuff. Meaning that glycerol, triglyceride.
Yeah, it's a great molecule. I mean, it has lots of tremendous utility. Well,
making a ketone ester with 1,3-butane diol is really cool because the 1,3-butane diol itself...
You get some more substrate.
... gets broken down. Yeah. So that goes into another question, the whole enantiomer. So if
you use the R-beta-hydroxybutyrate with the R-1,3-butane diol, then you can really get ketone
levels up pretty high. And that would be sort of the delta G or the human ketone ester that's out
there. It's the R enantiomer? That would be the R. Yeah, the R. So you can get racemic 1,3-butane
diol, but that's the R enantiomer of 1,3-butane diol with the R-beta-hydroxybutyrate. Can we
explain to everybody what R versus L means in the enantiomer world?
So beta-hydroxybutyrate, not acetoacetate, but beta-hydroxybutyrate has a stereoisomer. So if
you put your hands together, the R-beta-hydroxybutyrate, or let's do D and L, let's do that. So the D
would be equivalent to the R-beta-hydroxybutyrate would be the mirror image of the L-beta-hydroxybutyrate.
And the predominant form of beta-hydroxybutyrate in the body is D-beta-hydroxybutyrate. We do have
a racemase enzyme in various tissues that can convert the D to the L.
So but when you're in nutritional ketosis or starvation ketosis, you are making D an
enantiomer of the BHB?
Predominantly, yeah. So we do have the capacity to make the L, but it's pretty minimal. So that
brings up the question. I think 99% of all the ketone salts being sold right now are racemic.
So they are the D and the L.
Equal.
When you give-
Yeah, yeah. They're equal amount. And there may be a concern there, but we don't know. So most of my
research has actually been with the racemic compounds and they work great therapeutically.
In pharmacology, there's a sordid history of getting the enantiomer wrong. I mean,
one of the most famous stories I know of is fenfen.
Oh, thalidomide as well. Yeah. So that's right. Thalidomide and fenfen were both examples of
using the wrong enantiomer.
Many pharmaceuticals like I think ibuprofen and I know like ephedrine is racemic and many of the
drugs out there. So and things like ringers lactate, I think lactate is-
It's usually D.
Is it D now? It used to be racemic.
Oh, really?
I think, yeah.
I think you can get both.
Okay.
So you're saying, look, physiologically exist at 90, 10 D to L and then you're buying something
racemic. You at least have to entertain the question, hey, am I ingesting something that
might have a negative side effect?
Yeah.
And so the ketone esters, they're mirroring the physiology or they're just going mostly
D presumably.
Well, the human ketone ester, from my understanding, is completely D. So it's produced the D beta
hydroxybutyrate. Interestingly, elevating just beta hydroxybutyrate in our seizure models,
even with the D, does not have an anti-seizure effect. So that's actually why we went to the
1,3-butane diol.
Sorry, say that again.
Yeah.
Did you say that if you use a pure D salt?
D salt or D ester?
Pure D salt or pure D ester, no anti-seizure benefit.
No anti-seizure effect with beta hydroxybutyrate. We need it. And the animal models even suggest
if you just look even studies beyond our study is that you need to elevate acetoacetate has the
anti-seizure effect. And we don't know exactly why that happens. The ketone ester that we work with,
which is 1,3-butane diol acetoacetate diester, elevates beta hydroxybutyrate and acetoacetate
in approximately a one-to-one ratio.
Is that what you used to give me or was I just getting?
I gave you a bunch of things.
What was the one in the capsule that tasted even worse than the BHB?
Ester.
Actually, that was the diester of acetoacetate. And that's really potent.
And it was bound to what?
It 1,3-butane diol.
That shit was from another planet of bad. I still have some because...
I've done shots of that.
I like to just give it to people.
I put many gallons of that through me and done quite a bit of blood work and know,
pretty reliably, at least in my body, that it's not toxic. And pretty much all the
biomarkers go in a remarkably positive direction.
But even though I know that, it's not enough for me to consume it.
Even though it has that. And that's no matter how great a substance can be,
if it doesn't taste good, even me, I'm not going to take it. Even in a capsule.
I just think it's an aftertaste.
Exactly. Well, I also remember you telling me, because you sent them and I was like,
oh, sweet. It'll be capsules. Because I had seen your animal data and I was like,
I want that. And then you said, okay, well, I'll send it to you in capsules because you
can't drink it. It's too bad. And I was like, perfect situation resolved. And you said,
nah, not entirely. You'll still taste it through the capsule. And I actually find it to be a great
dinner party trick. Who's the biggest tough guy here that just wants to show me how much of this
stuff they can ingest? Yeah. Yeah. I mean, we've done a lot of work with that, Esther,
and it has remarkable effects, but we think it's probably more suited for a medical food and
something that could be sort of a parenteral, you know, IV therapy.
So who first synthesized that?
So I reached out to Henri Bruningrabber at Case Western, who was the director of the
Metabolomics NIH funded, I think Metabolomics Core at Case Western. And I reached out to everybody,
but I, who, who had any experience, you know, either researching with ketone esters or
synthesizing them. And he kindly gave me the recipe on how to synthesize it that was above
and beyond the patent. It was actually a detailed recipe on how to use a Kugelro distillation
apparatus, where to get the vacuum pressure. You didn't already know how to do that?
I knew it was short past it.
Well, actually, so Patrick Arnold, as you know, kind of helped me with the art. So an organic
chemistry really is an art, you know, to be able to do this.
And Patrick is an artist.
Patrick is an artist. And he was, he thought this was like shady stuff in the beginning. And I kept
sending him papers. And, and then he realized that this could be something big, you know,
he realized that the science was there. And there was a lot of big players in this field,
who had done remarkable research, but this didn't really have what it took to like,
actually make it a product, like synthesize it in the stuff that you actually consume.
I became obsessed with Patrick after this stuff happened. And he actually introduced him to Tim.
And in the show notes to this, I'll make sure that we link to Tim's podcast with Patrick,
which I'd love to have Patrick on the show at some point to to talk about this should this
show end up persisting. But that episode with Tim and Patrick is so interesting. It's like if you
have any interest in endocrinology, in sort of like how the hormones work, how steroids work,
it's yeah, yeah, it's just what I care. I owe a lot to Patrick, I don't think I probably wouldn't
have gotten tenure without Pat, I owe so much to him. So I need to acknowledge him for that, that
there were academic icons out there who could not do what Patrick did for me. And he was pretty
persistent in doing it too. So he synthesized first the mono ester. And then it was a mixed of
mono ester and diester, but he nailed it down to, you know, ultimately getting the art of the organic
chemistry to where it's pretty much pure diester. He's such a he's such a wonderful human being.
Anytime I email Patrick a question, which invariably I do have like clinically I'll have a question
about a hormone or they'll be like, there's no textbook that knows the answer. There's no paper
that knows the answer. I'm like Patrick, I got a crazy question for you. And it's like, even if
he doesn't know the answer, I mean, he'll have a more thoughtful insight than you can get anywhere.
And it's yeah, it speaks to his capabilities. So first of all, you shared with me something I
didn't actually know today that's really interesting, which is this notion that if you are purely using
the D and antimer, you do not get any of the anti seizure benefits. Whereas if you're at 9010,
presumably you're getting them. So you don't need a lot of the L but you need some of the L.
Yeah, I don't think there's any studies that show using an exogenous ketone in the form of pure
beta hydroxybutyrate is beneficial. So what we do know is that when you deliver exogenous ketones
in a beta hydroxybutyrate to acetoacetate ratio of one to one, that that has pretty remarkable
anti seizure effects. And there was some studies that were done with acetoacetate and also some
studies that were done with acetone showing anti seizure effects. So I do think it's
acetoacetate is necessary. So what we don't know, I don't think that racemic salts or racemic
esters or esters that produce both D and L beta hydroxybutyrate are a concern. I have not seen
data to suggest that these would be a health concern. There are companies out there that are
selling 8 million sort of doses per month of salts that are racemic in nature. And there have been
sort of no consequences from that that have been reported. So how are so many companies able to do
this? Is there no IP in the salt world anymore? I don't think there is IP for the key. I think
some of the early patents may expired. So I don't think there's actually there's there's some
intellectual property with formulations of a ketone salt and a ketogenic fat and MCT. And that's
some of the stuff that my university has. And there's some composition matter patents and maybe
some use patents around the D salts, I think, and maybe the D ketone esters. So at this point in
time, do you think that the ketone salts have more physiologic benefit than the ketone esters,
just as a function of having a higher amount of the L enantiomer? So I think when it comes
to purely a metabolic fuel, I think the D beta hydroxybutyrate has some advantages, right? So
we also know that in regards to some of the signaling effects, especially the inflammation,
the NLRP3 and phlammasome is suppressed by beta hydroxybutyrate, both the D and the L form. And
we know that when we consume racemic ketone salts in the D and L form, the L form tends to stick
around longer and gets metabolized slower. So conceivably, that could be having a stronger
anti-inflammatory effect because you have a ketone body and endogenous metabolite that's functioning
as a very powerful signaling molecule that's suppressing an inflammatory pathway. So the
concentration just tends to get higher. That's my view of it. So we haven't really studied that in
detail, but the lab that did some of the work on showing the Nature Medicine paper that showed
the NLRP3 and phlammasome was suppressed by beta hydroxybutyrate. It occurred both in the D and
the L form. We do know that the L form gets metabolized slower, so the concentrations in
the tissue may actually reach higher levels. So what we have observed is that the racemic
beta hydroxybutyrate has a glucose lowering effect. So we're trying to figure out.
But we also see that in the pure D and antimer. I've seen that with the human product, which is
obviously a pure D BHB. I think they're seeing about a 20 to 30% reduction in glucose. Do you
see more in the racemic? It tends to be the case, especially with 1,3-butane diol. You see it? And
maybe it's a redox shift in the liver. That's what Henri Brueninger-Grabber thought,
but it's pretty remarkable. And when we compare, so I have some products in my bag, I'll give you,
I have been doing a lot of work with D salts. So I've been consuming D salts and pretty high
levels that bring my ketone levels up pretty close to an ester. So you can formulate sort of.
Which in you is how high?
If the elevation of my ketones gets more than 3 millimolar, I just start feeling a little bit weird.
Which is interesting because you've experienced naturally occurring ketones at much higher than
that level.
Yeah, but I don't actually, I'm a pretty good ketone burner. So you could do a glucose tolerance
test. I do a ketone tolerance test. The ketone tolerance test is consuming a known amount of
ketones and looking at that pharmacokinetic curve.
So you measure, so you'll do fasting level of BHB glucose insulin for your fatty acid,
ingest your ketone and then measure at 30, 60, 90, 120 minutes.
And athletes have, when you challenge them with a ketone tolerance test, I'm creating
like a new test here, they actually dispose of ketones and utilize it remarkably effectively.
When you take a couch potato, and this is the same as the couch potato rats,
you could push a couch potato rat into ketoacidosis if they're older. Their tissues are
not effectively utilizing the ketones for fuel. And I've seen that in some individuals and some
people, I get hundreds of emails and people show me their data. And one packet of even a
commercial ketone product on the market can shoot some people up to like five or six,
which is like that never gets clear.
And just to be clear, in that ketone tolerance test, which by the way, I freaking love this idea,
how have you not told me that until today? Holding out on your best stuff.
It's just materialized in my brain. What am I going to call it?
I don't know, but next time you get one of these ideas, just pick up the phone, you know my number,
you call me and you tell me this stuff. It's like you're holding out on me.
Just kidding. I want to make sure I understand something. Is this independent of whether or not
that athlete was in ketosis before or after? In other words, how much of that utilization
is a function of the metabolic machinery in the muscle to utilize ketone versus,
hey, athletes are just better at oxidation to begin with.
Fat adapted athletes are very good ketone utilizers and have a hard time elevating their
ketone levels with the ketogenic diet sometimes.
If you take a high carb athlete who's still fit as a fiddle and you do this test,
how do they behave?
Not as well. And I do think that high performing athletes probably are bouncing in and out of
ketosis, right? You have post-exercise ketosis just from the energy depletion that you get
during exercise. So their bodies are probably used to seeing ketones, using them as fuel.
But if you take someone who's a real keto adapted fat burning ketone machine and you hit them with
high doses of ketones, they tend to dispose of them very quickly. So they've up-regulated
ketone transport across membranes, across the blood brain barrier through the MCT transporters,
which are up-regulated.
And this of course is not the same MCT that we talked about earlier.
No. These are monocarboxylic acid transporters. It also transport things like lactate and pyruvate.
And because the MCT transporters are much higher and more dense in the membrane, you could probably
clear lactate faster. So I think that may contribute in part to why keto adapted athletes produce less
lactate.
It's funny you say that. I hadn't thought of that actually. I didn't realize that in ketosis,
you up-regulate MCT. I've always suspected that that might play a role in the genetic
differences between athletes. Why do some athletes seem virtually un-paralyzed
by anaerobic activity? And it's like, look, if you can shut a lactate out of the cell quick enough,
you can recycle it and reuse it. We actually tried to get an IRB of an N of 1,
a guy named Ryan Flaherty, who I don't know if you know Ryan.
Yeah. I know the name.
You'll know of him. Yeah. So Ryan and I and a couple of other guys tried to get an N of 1 IRB
at UCSD to do muscle biopsies on ourselves pre and post a certain type of nutrition exercise routine
we wanted to implement that Ryan has pioneered with a number of endurance athletes. And that
was one of our endpoints was could we see an up-regulation of MCT because the hypothesis was
the certain type of training stress was going to lead to that, which would obviously increase our
performance at a certain level of output. But super interesting to think about that through
the level of the ketone potentially enhancing that signaling.
Yeah, it is. A lot of things to think about there.
So I'm going to caveat my next question with a really serious caveat, but it's also a very
serious question. And I was sort of on the fence about whether I'd ask you this or not, but I
I'm going to say, screw it. I'm going to ask you anyway. I'm going to caveat this by giving the
disclaimer, which is your PhD scientist, you do basic research. You are not an MD,
you are not an oncologist and nothing you say is going to be construed as medical advice.
So with that said, I still have to ask you a question, which is if tomorrow you,
your wife, someone you cared about deeply was diagnosed with cancer and it was a cancer for
which all standard therapies had been exhausted and you are now left to the best insights you
have with respect to your knowledge of cancer metabolism. Tell me what pulling out all the stops
looks like. And again, what I'm this is in the context of you've taken and you are complying
with all chemotherapeutic radiation therapy, hormonal therapy, surgical therapy, etc.
But you're losing, right? So something else needs to be done. What is that combination of that
something look like? So I guess, I mean, when we think about the worst cancer, worst case scenario,
who'd have pancreatic is pretty bad, but probably glioblastoma would top the list of things, right?
And would your answer be different if I was asking you about pancreatic adenocarcinoma versus GBM?
I think, you know, it would be there's things like with pancreatic cancer can make it hard
for someone to follow the ketogenic diet, right? Because and liver cancer and things like that. So
they need to approach it a little bit different and you can have a lot of unexpected consequences,
metabolic consequences by someone with liver cancer if they have heavy liver Mets or
let's make it simpler. Brain cancers. Let's talk about GBM and metastatic breast cancer.
Okay. Okay. So start with GBM your loved one or you have GBM. Yeah, I would say it would be useful,
not necessarily, you know, absolutely necessary to ask for an FDG PET scan, do a PET CT. And
especially, I mean, with GBM, it's going to light up like there's no tomorrow. Right. So just for
the listener. So FDG PET means you take glucose, you label glucose with a molecule. Yeah. And then
when you do the PET scan shows by lighting up anything that absorbs that and the most rapidly
metabolizing tissues of glucose light that up, which is almost always any cancer. And then a brain
normally lights up. So a brain with cancer takes that to another level. Yeah. So you're doing that
to document that this is a high glycolytic tumor. Yeah. Okay. So even now there's a lot of experimental
things going on for GBM, but pretty much the standard of care is not offering any survival
advantage when it comes to this. So we did GBM is uniformly fatal. I believe the five, the five year
survival is almost zero. Yeah. Yep. And the mutation rate in GBM is they're very, very heterogeneous
in regards to the number of mutations. So many of the standard of care therapies that target specific
pathways just are not efficacious because you have a grossly mutated cells throughout the tumor. So
I'd probably, my answer would default back to this press pulse idea that we published in
nutrition and metabolism. Is that the one in 2017? No, actually. So the, the 2017 paper was in seminars
and cancer. And that was with oncologists at the Moffitt cancer center, where we discuss how the
ketogenic diet essentially targets the warburg effect and in doing so really targets all the
hallmarks of cancer. So any cancer biologist, you know, is writing a review on paper, like, you know,
you talk about the hallmarks of cancer. There's enhanced proliferation, evasion of immune system,
angiogenesis, all these different things, evasion of apoptosis, the ketogenic diet, nutritional
ketosis actually targets all those things and even the aberrant metabolism and the increase
in inflammation that's, you know, is now a hallmark of cancer. So from the press pulse, the simplest
way to describe it, at least its implementation, which I think is probably most important for the
listeners is to achieve a glucose ketone index. So press essentially means you were providing
metabolic stress to the cancer cells that can stop their rapid growth and proliferation. It's
like taking the, your foot off the gas pedal of cancer cell growth. And there's a number of things
that we could do to slow down cancer growth and proliferation and metabolically stress those cancer
cells. And that can be done continuously. And pulse protocols, you have a wide expanding toolbox of
modalities that can be used in an intermittent fashion that can be sort of tactically used at
different time points to kill off the cancer cells that you have applied the press stress to. So press
protocols, which are done continuously would be something like a calorie restricted ketogenic
diet, perhaps with intermittent fasting, perhaps a low dose metformin. And what was the ketone to
glucose ratio that you want to see? I would want to see anywhere between a maintenance of one to two.
Meaning that's the glucose to ketone ratio. A daily maintenance of one to two. Yeah. So glucose should
never be more than twice the ketone level when both are measured in millimolar. Yeah. Ideally,
in a perfect scenario, three millimolar ketones, three millimolar glucose. So that's kind of hard
to achieve, but not with a number of tools. So there's a number of tools that you can use to
achieve that. And that needs to, and there are things that we could talk about too. So the fastest
way to get to a glucose ketone index of, and maintain that of one to two would be what I would call
supplemented ketogenic intermittent fasting. Right. So, uh, when you eat within a restricted
time window, say of like six hours a day, you start eating at, you know, 2 PM and finish at
8 PM seems relatively easy to do. And within that fasting window, if needed, you could consume
calories in the form of perhaps exogenous ketones. And that would further lower glucose and elevate
ketone levels like within a range. And they are commercially available ketone products on the
market. Millions are being consumed and there's no kind of adverse effects. You know, when you
compare it to something like a Red Bull, which you'll find lots of adverse effects. So there's
fairly good safety data, but this needs to be studied. But the difference is Red Bull sponsors
a formula one team. So it's, it's gotta be better. Yeah. Yeah. So these things are relatively safe
and their utility are that, you know, they can help you achieve a glucose ketone index.
And when you do have a glucose ketone index of one to two, you are limiting fermentable fuels
to the cancer cells and also most likely suppressing the hormone insulin tremendously
to get there. And, and because I'm sure you'll be asked or I'll be asked, is the reason you are
applying an intermittent or time restricted feeding algorithm to this because during the
fasted time you increase ketogenesis or because there was something specific about having complete
liver and gut rest. In other words, is there a reason that an individual should or should not
consume exogenous ketones and or MCT during the fasting window? Yeah. I think if it's difficult
for them to achieve a glucose ketone index of one to two, one of the tools in the toolbox could be
to consume exogenous ketones during that fasting period. I think it can be helped. And you can also
consume them during the feeding period too. And they provide an extra source of calories. That's
a nonfermentable fuel. And I think have a benefits in and of itself. You could just talk about the
anti-inflammatory benefits. You know, I think there are a number of different benefits. So that
press protocol is pretty aggressive. Yeah. And, and it could also include things like meditation
and yoga, I mean, and exercise of course, low intensity exercise, I think. But the most important
thing from my perspective of the press. So we're just talking about the press is to get that
glucose ketone index to one to two or better or one to two or better. And then once that is
achieved or concurrently, so you could think about different modalities for the pulse protocol.
So changing your metabolic physiology with what we just described will have a huge effect on
targeting the Warburg effect. And also we'll be already targeting all the hallmarks of cancer.
So you have a different person. You have just changed that person's metabolism. You know,
I mean, the glucose ketone index of the average Joe out on the street is probably something
like 25 or 50. It's like nowhere near that. Right. So you are literally changing the metabolic
physiology of that person. So modalities that they may be resistant to or completely failed
may have an effect now. So chemo radiation, maybe immune based therapies may be working now.
But an important point, right? We view this as an as an agile. So you could do a neo-agivant,
concurrent or adjuvant approach. So and I think that what I just described can be used as a
neo-agivant concurrent and an adjuvant approach. Yeah. So people talk about cancer approaches as
look, you want to think about the legs of a stool. So you take a chemo therapeutic approach,
you take a radiation approach, you take an immune based approach and you take a surgical approach.
Those are really the four pillars of cancer treatment today. Yeah. You're basically saying,
look, there needs to be a new type of oncologist, which is the metabolic oncologist. So you have a
surgical oncologist, you have a radiation oncologist, you have a medical oncologist,
you now have an immuno oncologist. Why don't we have a metabolic oncologist? Yeah. Things will
lead that way. And just by the research that's being done now, the huge amount of research being
done, even on onco metabolites and all the genetics people are now focusing on the how
metabolism is influencing genetics. Metabolism is a driver for our biology and influencing
epigenetic expression. So, you know, the work I'd like to also point to the work of a friend of
mine and colleague, Adrian check, who was, did her work at the Barrow neurological Institute,
which demonstrated in a mouse model, GL two 61, I think model of glial blastoma that using
temozolomide and also radiation with really focusing on radiation, that being in a state
of nutritional ketosis made radiation therapy many, many times more efficacious in that mouse
model, which is kind of a gold standard model for GBM. It actually cured the GBM in that mouse model
using the ketogenic diet combined with whole brain radiation. So that was a pretty significant
finding that actually spearheaded some of the ketogenic diet clinical research.
In her research, this was done with dietary or nutritional ketosis, not exogenous supplementation.
Not does she went on to do some work with exogenous ketones and looking at how ketones
can reprogram the metabolism and ketones can actually have, they are like Cox two inhibitors.
They inhibit reactive oxygen species, which is driving growth and proliferation. So that work
spawned research just on ketones by themselves in her animal model.
So what is in your pulse protocol then?
Pulse protocol can be varied. So hyperbaric oxygen therapy.
At what frequency?
Three, generally speaking. So with the GBM you have to, so a consequence of a GBM could be seizures,
right? So getting hyperbaric oxygen therapy with a GBM is tricky.
So yes, you have to start very low, probably like somewhere around 1.5 ATA and then work
up gradually from there based on the individual person. But generally speaking, the research that
we did showed that not five days a week, which is typically used for wound healing, but I do think
there needs to be a day off for adaptive effects to happen. So three days a week, 2.5 atmospheres
for 60 minutes, three times a week. And that produces, well, reverse tumor hypoxia for one
thing. So hyperbaric oxygen increases tissue oxygenation, not by hyper oxygenating hemoglobin,
but it actually gets oxygen into the plasma. And that's a very important thing because
meaning you solubilize oxygen within the plasma.
Yes.
Because you can't really supersaturate the hemoglobin that much more here at the top of
the curve.
Yeah. You and I are sitting here. I don't know what this air here, but your hemoglobin is
essentially saturated, probably 96, 98%. But the hyper oxygenation that occurs with hyperbaric
oxygen therapy, and this is why oxygen therapy does not work independent of an increase in
pressure, right? So the increase in pressure is needed to drive the oxygen into the plasma.
And once it's in the plasma, tumors have erratic vasculature, right? And then the
red blood cells get caught inside the capillaries and the oxygen doesn't get into the tissue inside
the tumor. But if the oxygen is in the plasma, it can get past and all into the nooks and crannies
of the tumor and then reverse tumor hypoxia, which is tumor hypoxia is driving HIF1 alpha
and VEGF and causing oncogenic activation.
Oh, that's so interesting.
So ironically, you're taking something that is initially a deficit of cancer, which is
its hypoxia, but then it utilizes it as it's an advantage by saying, Hey, I'm going to work
around this. It's going to make me more resilient. It's going to allow me to increase my vasculature.
And you're saying, Hey buddy, that little advantage you had that was a disadvantage,
we're going to reverse it. We're going to hyper oxygenate you now. We're going to take away your
hypoxia. And you also increase free radicals.
Yes. So you have a dual effect, right? So you are silencing the oncogenes, you're turning off
some of the oncogenes and also by hyper oxygenating a tumor, which its baseline is to be in a,
in a state of hypoxia by super saturating the tumor with oxygen. And that tumor tissue has
damaged mitochondria because hypoxia damages the mitochondria. So basically you're hyper oxygenating
a whole bunch of damaged mitochondria. And essentially what that does is skyrockets
superoxide anion, which then through Fenton chemistry. So when you have a lot of free iron
and all that, you got a whole bunch of heme and stuff that's being broken down the tumor.
So you have a lot of free iron driving the Fenton reaction and which is producing hydroxyl
radicals. And that causes a massive oxidative stress specifically to the tumor. And you're
delivering a massive oxidative stress to the tumor while it's relatively non-toxic to healthy
cells that have normal metabolism, right? Because the tumor is thriving in a low oxygen environment
and you're reversing tumor hypoxia and hyper oxygenating it. And you have this environment,
which is just fueling redox stress, you can then trigger apoptosis and necrosis really driving
necrosis in these tumor cells. So hyperbaric oxygen delivered at the maximum tolerable dose
three times per week. And you could further enhance the oxidative stress of the tumor
by something that's a lot of people haven't heard of this, but IV vitamin C. So vitamin C,
if given intravenously at about... You could give up to about a hundred grams at that.
You could, yeah, 25 to a hundred grams is kind of pushing it, but vitamin C ascorbic acid also
functions as a glucose antagonist. So you got to make sure you have dextrose on hand if patients.
Yeah, but not if you're in a state of ketosis, right? So if you're in a state of ketosis,
so I did a pretty high dose vitamin C, but being in a state of ketosis, you can tolerate
higher amounts, right? Do you know what your glucose dropped to? So when you measure your glucose,
when you're getting vitamin C, you get a false positive on the meter.
Falsely high?
You get falsely high. Well, at least the Abbott precision extra.
When you measure that meter, that assay on the meter is also sensitive to the pH of your blood,
too, and there's a redox shift. And acorbic acid is a powerful reducing agent, and that might be
altering the assay. So it's not able to get my glucose like skyrocket. I know I went into it
hypoglycemic, but my ketones were elevated, and I took a pretty big hit of vitamin C.
And I was just doing it just for the self experimentation.
Right. So but what's the thought here? So lots of people have talked about-
Oxidative stress. So vitamin C driving the Fenton reaction to produce more oxidative stress. So
vitamin C is a pro-oxidant. When you get blood levels of vitamin C in the millimolar concentration,
then it becomes a pro-oxidant. It's not an antioxidant. So we're not using antioxidants,
or definitely you don't want to use antioxidants. Yeah, I was going to come back to that. But the
next thing is, I'm sure somebody listening to this is going to say, well, I don't have access to
IV vitamin C if I wanted to do that. You can't do it orally. You can't do it orally because of what?
It's not orally good. You can't get it out of the gut enough. Yeah, you can't. You can only get
like a very small amounts, and then, you know, your gut auto regulates it, too. So you just let's
get to the next thing you said, which is, again, highly counterintuitive to most people. We're
hardwired to think that there's nothing better for you than antioxidants. But paradoxically,
once you have cancer, that might not be the case. Yeah, so I think antioxidants may be blocking
some of the efficacy of some of the some of the therapies, too, right? Because many chemotherapeutic
drugs, their function works through enhancing oxidative stress, radiation sure does.
So radiation, maybe 20% of the cancer killing effects of radiation are due to damaging the DNA
with double, you know, double strand nicks. But 80% of the tumor killing effect of radiation is by
the generation of reactive oxygen species. Now, does that mean you can't have blueberries and
things that have low levels of antioxidants? I would say no, but you don't want to kind of
saturate your body with a cocktail of antioxidants. Like you don't want to do a glutathione push,
right after you do same with any C, so you wouldn't have any C, I personally would not I don't I don't
think that none of the cancer studies and animal models or humans are supportive of the use of
antioxidants. And that was a big focus of me. I mean, when during my PhD, I want to do a postdoc
research in antioxidant cocktails that we're going to save the world. And
none of the research on antioxidants really panned out in my mind. There's a couple things,
you know, maybe for mitochondrial antioxidants for like Friedrich's ataxia, and maybe ALS and
some research there, but it's pretty subtle benefits. But in the context of cancer, no,
I don't I don't think antioxidants should be avoided. Anything else in your pulse protocol?
Yeah, I mean, there's a lot of things that you could add. So with the press protocol,
I think a low dose of metformin could be helpful too. So that will activate amp kinase, maybe
decrease insulin a little bit, maybe increase ketones a little bit too. And it's just a readily
available cheap drug that has a very good safety profile 500 milligrams to 2000 milligrams a day
are usually well tolerated, probably starting with 500 milligrams and working up. But when it comes
to the pulse protocol, hyperbaric oxygen, IV vitamin C, and there are a number of drugs that
we're working with now, one would be 2d oxyglucose, which in and of itself from a seizure world, and
I've, I've been a reviewer in for the government for different grants and stuff. And this is in
the context of epilepsy, 2dG is sort of like the ketogenic diet in a drug. So by inhibiting
glycolysis, it has this gets back to the question, right? You have no ketones, but you inhibit
glycolytic pathways, perhaps even like reduce sort of mTOR signaling or some glycolytic
signal, and that may have anti seizure effects. So 2dG is something that we're working with now,
I think it was 2dG originally developed for pharmacologically. It's been around for a long
time for a long time. I think maybe it was just in the realm of experimental compound. But I know
there's phase two trials in cancer. The problem is it becomes cardiotoxic above say 50 milligrams
per kilogram. I know can be, I know there's some evidence that cardiotoxicity, but at 25 milligrams
per kilogram, at least on some of the grants that I reviewed, that was had a pretty good safety
profile for epilepsy. So, you know, not making any recommendations out there, but I think 25
milligrams per kilogram seems to be within the realm of therapeutic efficacy and safety.
And this is being studied in humans and you're, they're out of phase one. So this, you have phase
one data to support that.
Epilepsy world. Yeah. And I think there's some cancer trials going on too. And I do think that
synergizes really well. Once you create the environment where you put the press protocol
into action, then the cancer cells become even very selectively vulnerable to other things like
2DG will inhibit a glycolytic pathway that drives the pentophosphate pathway. And that
pentophosphate pathway is responsible for enhancing the endogenous antioxidant capacity of cells.
So it makes the cancer cells even more vulnerable to oxidative stress. The more you can inhibit the
glycolytic pathways. So 2DG, 2-dichloroacetate is something that we've worked with. 2-inhibits
PDH complex. And that can also...
Is DCA a drug that's been on the market for a long time?
It's a small molecule. Yeah. It's been on the market for a very long time.
And what's its normal use?
Its normal use is lactic acidosis, actually. So one of the side effects of metformin, right,
is once you start increasing the dose of metformin and escalating the dose, the problem that you run
into, it's still... It's a very powerful activator of amkinase. Its effects are primarily through
the liver, inhibiting gluconeogenesis, and it's a mitochondrial toxin. We published a paper that
it increases Ross production from the complex one of the mitochondria.
So it's inhibiting complex one, correct?
It's inhibiting. Yeah, mildly inhibiting complex one. And it's triggering what the cell
experiences as an energetic crisis, and that it has an activation of amkinase too.
So you are creating a scenario where that's putting a lot of persistent metabolic stress
on the tumor cells. And then you come in here with different modalities that have overlapping,
but independent mechanisms at producing oxidative stress. So hyperbaric oxygen, IV vitamin C,
and then cancer-specific glycolytic inhibitors, 2D oxyglucose, 3-bromopyrurvate, and loninamine.
Loninamine is also a hexokinase 2 inhibitor. And those three drugs that I mentioned right there,
they are very powerful, and they need to probably be used in two weeks on, two weeks off.
If somebody's listening to this and they're thinking, well, how the heck could I ever do this?
Are there physicians out there who are obviously doing this under the full and legal umbrella of
ethical medical practice? Is everything you're talking about purely theoretical, or are there
ways to actually have these things implemented? I think there are some physicians out there that
are probably not making it public, but I think they are getting success with doing 25% of what
I just talked about. They're not doing all these things, but everything that I just mentioned is
readily available. Most of the compounds in IV vitamin C, hyperbaric oxygen therapy, can be
costly if you don't have a hardshell chamber. But I like that with radiation, if you're giving
radiation to your body, it's like going in there with a flame thrower, and you have a lot of
collateral damage. Whereas hyperbaric oxygen naturally elevates the precursor for oxygen-free
radicals, and the cancer cells selectively produce more oxygen-free radicals. It's a very gentle
approach. Instead of thinking that we should just go in there and eradicate the tumor, I think it's
more appropriate to give a gentle stress to the tumor. The therapy that I'm describing, if the
patient goes into it, they're going to come out of it stronger than they were going into it.
When you fat-adapt and keto-adapt your body, so many metabolic biomarkers start to go in the right
direction. When you go in for chemotherapy and radiation, and you measure things after, your
body's a big inflammatory mess. I mean, you're metabolically deranged, you're insulin resistant,
you are pushing things, and you have chemo-brain on top of that that may not be reversible.
The suppression of your immune system with chemo is setting you up for more cancers,
potentially other cancers. The scenario that we envision is a comprehensive metabolic-based
therapy where you go into it, and it's a more gradual approach, and you start adding these
modalities as you go. Get the patient acclimated with that glucose-ketone index of one to two,
and then start utilizing some of these other therapies. You could potentially put someone
on an IV and pulse a low dose of insulin to make them hypoglycemic, even one or two millimolar,
and then deliver some of these agents where you've really restricted the fermentable fuels.
I'm a reviewer on different manuscripts that are coming in, and some of these academic
and clinical oncologists are actually suggesting this in medical hypothesis papers now.
That's counterintuitive because you'd think, well, the last thing you want to do for a tumor is give
it insulin because this is pulsatile. It's acute, and the amount of insulin, it's not like 20 I use,
it's something like one or two I use. The patient comes in fasted, and you give them just a little
bit, and that's mostly facilitating glucose uptake in the skeletal muscle, so making it less available
for the tumor. That creates a scenario where you produce severe, what would typically be fatal,
hypoglycemia, and you could deliver ketones as an insurance, and also deliver some of these agents
that would... You'd probably dramatically sensitize that tumor tissue to the other modalities.
What I didn't talk about when I did this seven-day fast years ago, I brought my glucose level
down really low, and I got to a glucose-ketone index of one, or maybe even a little bit lower
than one. You were about, what, three to four on each of them? Yeah, well, my ketones were about
four or five, and my glucose got down to three, so that was the lowest I ever captured. That was
just a seven-day fast? Yeah, after a brisk walk at the end. I never got ketones seven or eight,
I got it four after a long fast. But then I did, inspired by the Cahill study, I used various
strategies to bring my glucose level down, pharmacological strategies, and I did it slowly.
Just do me a favor, Dom. I really would be pissed off if you offed yourself doing dumb shit, because
I think the world needs you to stick around. See if you can just maybe get an IRB to do this in the
mice or something. Nothing that would break my heart more than getting a call from your wife
saying, yeah, Dom died of some freak hypoglycemic crazy accident. What's the longest fast you've
ever done? Well, that was it, actually. Seven days? Yeah, and I was pretty adapted, and the point I
was kind of getting to that, I brought my glucose down to where it was not even measurable, but with
exogenous ketones, the meter didn't even read it. So that, to me, and I did that years ago,
that motivated me more to basically focus on this area of research as sort of like my life
research, because it validated to me that this should not be happening, and ketones are an
alternative energy source that can be utilized in these metabolic-based therapies that can be
game changers for better. And we also studied glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome,
which is the inability, and people who have glut-1D don't get cancer, to my knowledge. I've talked to
the doctors, and they've never came across anyone with glucose transporter. So that's kind of
motivating too, that you can create a therapy for that that could sort of be a magic bullet.
Well, what's interesting is this is sort of, in many ways, old-school science,
where scientists would begin by sort of experimenting on themselves,
identifying unnatural or extreme physiologic conditions that are not predicted by the current
understanding. And then that sort of provokes further investigation. Remind me again, at the
end of that seven-day fast, how much did you deadlift? Yeah, I did 500 pounds for 10, and then I did
sort of a one-repper at the end was six plates or 585, but that's below my normal. But it was amazing
to me that I didn't want to push my body too hard, but it was amazing that that amount of fasting
does not really impact your strength. How much of a verdict? So what was your max at that time?
At that time, well, I was tinkering around with like, you know, ketogenic diet and fasting a lot,
but within a year of that time, I forget if it was before or after, I did 675 for 5, and maybe 5,
I did 555 for an eight to 10. So I did, you know, an extra plate for eight to 10. But I went into this,
basically, I felt like I did more, I could have done more, but I just wanted to stop. I didn't
want to hurt myself because I knew I was pushing the limits at that point. And I didn't get sore
at all. So I did that. And it wasn't like my body was broken down and sort of in a depleted state
where I was wasted the next day. I felt I didn't even have to recover from that. Like I had no lower
back soreness the next day after that. So I probably was like, I probably could have went heavier.
But it was just validation to me that if you're in a keto adapted state, your body is very resilient.
And from a military standpoint, too, which we work pretty closely with the military,
I'm trying to sort of get them to understand this idea that if you are fat and keto adapted,
and you're faced in austere conditions with limited food availability, you could maintain
your physical and cognitive resilience in those conditions, which is pretty clear to me. I was
pretty much obsessed with eating like six meals a day for many years. And it was very liberating
not to have to do that now. And I'm amazed at how little I can eat once you're keto adapted and
maintain, you know, your size and your strength. I'm not trying to be big anymore or anything,
or try to do any records in the gym. But it's amazing how easy it is to maintain
once your body is adapted. You've been so generous with your time. I want to sort of
let you get on your way. I know you've got a long drive potentially tonight. But
I want to ask you a question or the couple maybe what do you believe today to be true
that five years ago, you did not believe to be true? Let's keep it within the purview of your
ketogenic life. What today do you think things that really I would say when I got into this
field, I was really fascinated and immersed in this idea as ketones as an alternative energy
source. So is even like space food, you know, and we're still working on that front. But then over
the last five years, the observation that beta hydroxybutyrate is a powerful endogenous
metabolite that's also a signaling molecule through its HDAC activity, histone deacetylase activity,
more recently, we've been working with an organization that the name of the organization
is called all things Kabuki. So there's a there's a rare genetic disease called Kabuki syndrome,
which is a gene defect in the KMT2D, which is essentially an acetylase enzyme and a defect in
that gene or that protein creates an imbalance between gene expression and gene repression.
Right. And in the mouse model of Kabuki syndrome, two things have worked in this mouse model. One
is a histone deacetylase inhibitor, HDAC inhibitor called AR42, which restores neurons in the dentate
gyrus and kind of silences the pathological features in this mouse model. And another thing
is nutritional ketosis. So nutritional ketosis functioning as a histone deacetylase inhibitor
basically salvages or rescues the phenotype of this and circumvents this gene mutation, the KMT2D
mutation. The animals have a normal neuronal density in the dentate gyrus, and even from a
behavioral characteristic, it enhances sort of learning and memory. So this idea that an endogenous
metabolite can epigenetically sort of control gene transcription. So I believe it's probably not
unique to beta hydroxybutyrate. I think metabolites, we know that's true for acetyl-CoA and other things,
are epigenetic drivers. And I think they are really, they call the shots. So you can even
take a step back and say the mitochondria kind of call the shots too, right? Because I think
mitochondrial health and mitochondrial vitality would be the ultimate tumor suppressor. So if the
bioenergetic capacity of a cell in tissues are maintained to a high degree, that bioenergetic
efficiency is going to preserve genome stability and be far less likely to trigger oncogenes at
the level of the DNA. So when it comes to something like Kabuki syndrome, you have a persistent
molecular genetic pathology that's silenced by the elevation of beta hydroxybutyrate functioning
in an inpendant way. Yeah, it's H-stac activity. So that to me is like mind-blowing. And I think
that's the direction kind of our lab is going into now. I'm always fascinated with developing
alternative energy substrates and alternative fuels as a form of nutrition for tactical
applications, space applications maybe. But this idea that you could develop and even engineer
nutrition to have powerful effects on gene transcription and epigenetic regulation
is something I would have never predicted. That's an amazing answer actually, because,
and I know that was probably a little hard for some people to follow. So what you're basically
saying is, look, five years ago, you were completely intrigued and blown away by the
metabolic properties of these ketones, primarily as an alternative energy source. And with that
comes a lot of interesting stuff we've talked about. But at this H-dac pathway, this inhibition
of something that can result in epigenetic change or activation of in this case, you can basically
take a germline acquired mutation and silence it with an epigenetic overlay that seems to be
signaled by something as simple as ketones. And Dr. Verdin at the Buck Institute has spoken quite
a bit about this as well. I mean, this really is one of those moments where you think, holy cow,
we are really at the, just at the cusp of learning about this stuff. And if there's one reason to make
sure we don't off ourselves with self experiments, it's to make sure we can stick around long enough
to do this. Don, where can people follow you socially and then maybe more importantly,
see what you're doing from a research perspective? Sure. So the site I maintain for informational
purposes would be ketonutrition.org. It's a dot org, not.com. And on that website, I have a list of,
podcasts, there's nutrition consultants, resources like the Charlie Foundation,
which is an incredible resource that I've helped them do some educational work. And Jim Abrams of
the Charlie Foundation has really created an amazing resource there. I have a blog and we
test various ketone supplements, ketogenic foods. I'm self experimenting and I've collected a lot
of data and we'll be putting some of that data in the blog. So I think that would be sort of like
the one-stop shop website for anyone interested in hearing more about what I talked about.
I'd also like to mention that our lab in collaboration with Epigenics Foundation
is sponsoring the metabolic health summit that's occurring in January 30th to February 3rd
in Long Beach, California. And it's going to have an amazing array of basic scientists. For example,
like Lou Cantley will be there, be a keynote speaker, Thomas Safrid. There's going to be
clinicians there, influencers there, and a lot of entrepreneurial people will be there representing
companies that are really changing the shape of this industry. So I'm very interested in
technologies and foods and supplements that can make nutritional ketosis accessible for people
that want to use it, not only therapeutically for metabolic management of a disorder,
but maybe also for prevention or longevity or just as a lifestyle. So you're going to find
there's something for everybody at the metabolic health summit from basic science will be sort of
what our lab is focused on, but from clinical application to moving the science into human
application is really the theme of that. And can people register for that already?
Yes, I think you can go to the website and register if you want to be a sponsor. I think
you can sort of download the sponsorship package. There's going to be a lot of high profile
representation there that would bring sort of more awareness and more reach to your product if you
have a product there. So we're looking for sponsors. And I think we've nailed down most of our speakers,
but if you're interested in speaking to it might be good to contact us through the website.
Got it. And on Twitter, you're pretty active. What's your handle?
Yeah, before I realize how important it is to have a handle you can remember, it's Dominic
Dagosti 2. We'll link to it.
Yeah, we'll link to it. It's not the easiest to remember. And also Facebook, I'm fairly active.
Dominic Dagostino 1, I think that's my handle on Facebook too. So I kind of cross post on each and
try to use Instagram a little bit more because they tell me I got to use it more, but not too
active on that. But all right. Well, we'll make sure we link to all of those things. I want to
thank you again. I owe a lot of what I know in this space to you.
I can say the same thank you. Yeah, incredible blogs. It's been a great resource for many.
You were arguably one of the most generous people I've ever met when it comes to his insights.
Dom, I don't know that you get enough credit for not only the work you've done, but for how much
work you do behind the scenes as far as sharing your knowledge with people. I'll just share one
very quick anecdote. Personally, one of my best friends from medical school, his wife has breast
cancer and without any hesitation, you were more than happy to speak with them about some of these
things that they could do above and beyond what she was already doing, which was participating in
a clinical trial where, by the way, she is the only woman to still be alive in this clinical trial.
So the trial has closed. That agent will likely not be approved though. She will have a compassionate
exemption, but she is someone who has been on a ketogenic diet now for six years and has
and remains incredibly indebted to the work that you've done. And her oncologist in Boston are
sort of amazed that she's alive. Interestingly, next year, Lou Cantley will be explaining a very
plausible mechanism for why she is still alive. It's a paper that I'm sure you're aware of that
was just approved and will be out in nature very soon. So anyway, I could sit here and spend another
hour thanking you for everything, but I know nobody really wants to hear that. So I'll be
quick about it and just tell you again that, Dom, you're an amazing guy. You really are one of those
people that I think fits in the category of just being kind of a treasure. And so on behalf of many
people, I want to thank you. And thank you. Thank you for giving me this platform. I know your
podcast will be an amazing resource for so many people. Always great to catch up with you.
Always very stimulating in so many ways. So thank you, Peter, for having me. Appreciate it.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com. What's a nerd safari, you ask? Just click on the link at
the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my
subjectively non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance,
sleep, etc. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments. Now for the
obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk. The content of this
podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have
and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all
of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.