Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
In this podcast, I'm going to be discussing LP Little A. A little while ago, we put up
a little questionnaire on Twitter that said, if I'm going to do a solo podcast interviewed
by Bob, what topic would you want to hear? And we put up two options. The first was LP
Little A. The second was hormone replacement therapy for postmenopausal women. Survey ran
for about a day and the results were unambiguous. 80% of you wanted to hear about LP Little
A, though many of you did want to hear about HRT and we will absolutely get to that. So
on this podcast, we structured it as an interview. Originally, I thought I would just do it as
a quote unquote lecture, but I realized that would just be way too boring and it would
be more fun to play patty cakes with Bob and have him interview me. So that's what we did.
So Bob put together an interview and he just asked me a bunch of questions about LP Little
A. We're going to talk about what the heck it is, why you should care, why it's problematic,
like the protein, what some of the potential treatment options are and what's on the horizon.
Now I got to admit, this is a bit of a technical podcast, but I also know that this is kind
of a technical loving audience. So don't be discouraged. I also think this is one of the
tests where you really have to be able to look at the show notes. I find some of this
stuff really complicated myself and I find a picture is sometimes worth a thousand words.
So especially when I get into stuff like Kringle repeats and Kringle four subsection two zone
five, like that kind of stuff, you've just got to be looking at a picture to understand.
So if you can't be able to look at something while you're listening to it, that's fine,
but maybe go back after the fact and look at it or look first and then listen, something
like that. But the show notes here will be very helpful and hopefully this answers a lot of the
questions that people have been asking me over the past year about LP little a. And again,
if this format is helpful, let us know because we're really happy to kind of do one of these
every couple of months where we just put up a general topic and Bob grills me on it. So without
further delay, here's the discussion with Bob Kaplan on LP little a.
Bob, Peter, how are you? I'm doing well. I notice you have a coffee there. Of course.
What number is that today? Seven. At least. I've watched four. Well, seven doubles,
probably seven double espressos. That's true. Yeah. Yeah. That's impressive. It's a low day.
So this is the first of what I suspect and assume we might do more of where we threw a question out
to people and said, pick one, have a vote. I don't know. We gave him a day or so. And the choice was,
do you want to know about LP little a or do you want to know about hormone replacement therapy
in postmenopausal women, which by the way, has a more politically correct name now that I can't
remember endocrine modulating therapies for women in menopause or something. I don't know.
I was going to go with golden years or something to that effect. The point is HRT versus this.
And it was about 80 20 in favor of LP little a, which kind of bums me out because I actually
really wanted to talk about HRT, but next time we throw HRT in, we're going to put it up against
something like bocce ball. And hopefully HRT comes out ahead and we can talk about it.
I think you have been accumulating a bunch of questions that people have also started sending
in about LP little a and I think that's what we're going to talk about.
Absolutely. So a lot of questions are around what is LP little a and I thought in order to
explain that, maybe we might need a quick primer on lipoproteins to kick things off.
Do you know anyone who can do that? I think I'm looking at them.
Oh, okay. I was afraid you were going to say that. Starting from the basics, if you go to your doctor
and you get a cholesterol blood test, they're going to probably show you a couple of numbers,
a total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol. And if you're really lucky, they'll put bad next to it.
HDL cholesterol. And if you're extra special, they'll put good next to it. Triglycerides and
non HDL cholesterol. That is a standard lipid panel. Those numbers are largely unhelpful,
but more importantly, they're largely misunderstood. So when people look at LDL and think it's bad
cholesterol, that immediately tells you that they're missing what the L and the D and the L
stand for the LDL stands for low density lipoprotein. And admittedly, if you don't have a background in
biochemistry or something, you might not understand in looking at that, that that implies that it's a
macro structure. So cholesterol, which is the principal molecule that is carried by these lipoproteins,
is something that is made by the body. So every cell in the body makes cholesterol. And most cells
in the body make enough cholesterol to meet their own needs at the cellular level. And the single and
most important need of cholesterol we have is cellular membranes. So cell membranes must be
fluid. They must be able to move. They must be able to facilitate the attachment of one cell to
another. They must be able to hold transporters across their membranes and things like that. And
of course, cholesterol makes up the bulk of those membranes. So in addition, you turn cholesterol,
when I say you, I'm referring specifically to certain organs, like the adrenal glands,
the ovaries, the testes, turn cholesterol into hormones that are either sex hormones,
glucocorticoids, gonadotropins, these things. So if for no other reason than just being able to
have cells that work and have hormones, cholesterol is pretty important.
Because we're not going to get too far into that. The point I want to make is that you can't
traffic or move around cholesterol in the bloodstream because blood approximates water.
And so the things that move freely in the blood have to be things that are what we call hydrophilic
or things that would be soluble in water. So something like glucose can move around the
bloodstream very easily, but cholesterol cannot. And therefore it needs to be packaged in something
that is itself water soluble. And that something is a lipoprotein. And the two dominant lipoproteins
that are found in the bloodstream are the high density lipoprotein and the low density
lipoprotein. And their names are referring to their densities in a type of assay called
gel electrophoresis, which has to do with how far these things move on an ion gradient.
There are other lipoproteins that don't stick around that long. So VLDL, very low density
lipoprotein and IDL or intermediate density lipoprotein, which is almost non-existent. It
has such a short half life. And the longer residence of the LDL is probably what explains
its atherogenicity. And that's why LDL is considered the most atherogenic particle after
LpA, which we're going to talk about today. So when you're looking at your blood test,
what you're seeing is the cholesterol concentration within the various particles. So when it says total
cholesterol, it says, well, if you break apart the HDL particle and the LDL particle and the VLDL
particle, and if you can find it the IDL particle, how much total cholesterol do you have? And that's
a number, call it 200 milligrams per deciliter. Okay. And when it says LDLC is 120 milligrams
per deciliter, that means if you break apart the LDL, that's the concentration of cholesterol
contained within them, et cetera. Now, in the past, we've talked about the importance of knowing
the number of particles you have and how that is a more accurate predictor of your atherosclerotic
risk. And so the LDLP, which is similar to the APO-B in terms of its predictive power,
which is the number of particles. And the reason you can use APO-B as a surrogate for that is that
each LDL particle has an APO-B, which is an apolipaprotein that wraps around the spherical
lipoprotein. It's APO-B100 specifically. So by counting those, since each LDL has one and only
one APO-B, you can quantify the number of LDL particles. And again, we care about that because
it tracks more with risk. The LDL, the ideal and the LDL all have the APO-B100. The HDL does not.
The HDL has something called APO-A1. It's a different lipoprotein. And it probably explains
in large part why HDL is not atherogenic and LDL is atherogenic. The pathogenesis of atherosclerosis
is one that's predicated on, and we should probably attach and I'll link to this, the post
on heart disease where I go through this in great, great and gory detail, the process by which the
lipoproteins get through the endothelial space between cells, which is actually not that hard to
do. An LDL particle is somewhere between 20, 21, 22 nanometers. It's probably not an order of magnitude,
but several multiples of that is the space between the endothelial cells. So it's the size
of the LDL particle really doesn't determine the ease with which it gets through the cell or not,
or between the cells. What's much more important is because most of the LDL that gets into the
sub-endotheo space gets right back out and doesn't cause any trouble. Where the trouble comes is when
they get retained and when they get oxidized and when they kick off an inflammatory response. So
it is certainly the case theoretically that you could have a very high LDL,
but by hook or by crook, if your LDL particles don't get retained in the sub-endotheo space
and don't kick off an inflammatory cascade, you're not going to suffer the effects that you otherwise
would. But all things equal, we would love to see a lower LDL particle number because the process
by which those particles enter the space seems relatively stochastic. So in a few minutes,
that's kind of the overview of these lipoproteins. Okay, so I think one of the reasons why we've had
so much interest in LpA is a New York Times article by Anahad O'Connor. I think it was January
this year that was entitled, A Heart Risk Factor Even Doctors Know Little About. And he tells the
story of Bob Harper, who was one of the biggest loser OGs. I think it was him and Gillian were
the two trainers. And so Bob had a heart attack at a gym at age 52. And according to his annual
checkups, he always checked out very healthy. And as it turned out, according to the article, Bob
has quote, perilously high levels, end quote, of LpL in his blood, something that was I don't think
was ever measured prior to his heart attack. So I think this article was an introduction to this
particle for many people who read it. Not only that, it's reported that a small percentage of
physicians actually know about it. So kind of going back to the original question, what is
LpL? Well, in full disclosure, Anahad is a really good friend of mine. And I know he'd been working
on that story for about two years, actually, I guess I'll take a little bit of credit for getting
him interested in ApoA and LpL. And Anahad, because he's just such a curious dude, was sort
of like blown away at this. He's like, wait, wait, wait, wait a minute. Tell me about, you know,
we walked through everything that we're about to talk about today. And he just couldn't believe
that something that was so ubiquitous, probably somewhere between one and five and one and 10
people walking around with this elevation. And of course, it's a long tail to the right distribution.
So where you define the cutoff as perilously high is a function of how many people will be perilously
high. But he just couldn't believe it. And then I, you know, introduced him to many of my mentors,
and he did his own research. And the result of that was a story that I thought was excellent,
because I can't count the number of patients that sent it to me saying, Oh, my God, this is that
thing you're always talking about. Yeah. So what is this thing? So we talked about the LDL particle
number. So it's this spherical thing. Call it 20 nanometers in diameter. And it has a outer
spherical structure that is made of lipid, cholesterol, phospholipid inside. It has a core
that consists of cholesterol ester. So this is non, this is like the cholesterol without its
bulky side chain and the triglyceride. And on the outside, as I mentioned, it has this one
apolipaprotein called apo B 100. So we'll just refer to that from now on as the garden variety LDL.
Now a subset of these, and it's mostly, as we'll probably discuss genetically determined
and inherited in a codominant fashion, a subset of these have something else attached to that apo B
and it's attached covalently. So that means that it's not an ionic bond. It's an actual,
in other words, it's a much stronger bond. It's a disulfide bond, which in amino acids and in
biochemistry tends to be a pretty strong bond. So the apo B has this disulfide bond that attaches
it to a totally different lipoprotein and it's called apolittle A. And this lipoprotein is made
in the liver and it has a property that it resembles another molecule in the body called
plasminogen. Now I suspect that everything I'm about to say is going to not make that much
sense until you look at the pictures. This is one of those things where a picture says a thousand
words. So what we'll probably do is, and that defeats the purpose of a podcast, I realize,
because people want to listen to this, but they don't want to have to miss the picture. But I
think this is one of those things where it's worth looking up the picture. But this apolipoprotein A
has a repeated folding structure. These domains are referred to as cringal domains. So we're sort
of lost in a nomenclature of apolittle A and cringal potato chip folds and all this stuff. And
it's just like, it's super complicated, but these repeating structures are organized by cringal
domains and there are five of them. Plasminogen, that is, has five of them. ApoA does not have
the cringle one, the cringle two, the cringle three. It does have a cringle four that very
much resembles plasminogen and it has the exact same cringle five that comes from the plasminogen.
So to distill that again, ApoA looks like plasminogen in that it has cringle domain five
and a cringle domain four that is similar, but it's the cringle domain four that has 10
subsegments. So you have cringle four one, cringle four two, cringle four three, all the way up to
cringle four nine and cringle four ten. And if that doesn't have, you're looking at me and you're
laughing. It's like, it's hard to believe we're talking about it at this level of detail, but
the cringle four two is where you see the greatest variability and you can have a cringle
four two with just a couple of folds in it. You could have a cringle four two with 40
segments that are repeating and that determines the mass of LpA and that's going to become,
I wouldn't be telling this story if it weren't for some reason in anticipation of talking about
something else. And with the plasminogen and the cringles in the homology, in other words,
how similar are they? You're basically saying that if you were to look up, like if you were to look
at the structures of both of those, you could very easily confuse one for the other. They look very
similar. It probably depends on the similarity during the cringle four because the cringle four
tends to dominate it. So I don't want to give an answer that could be incorrect because I suspect
it depends on the individual. I think there are some individuals whose ApoA looks more like
plasminogen because everyone's plasminogen looks the same, but the ApoA is where we see the
difference. So we're really dealing with two things, which is how many of your LDLs have those
ApoAs attached to them and then what do your ApoAs look like? And what they look like is basically
what do your cringle segment four subsegment twos look like? Now it turns out that between those
two factors, the one that probably matters most is the number of your LDL particles that also have
this covalent bond to the ApoA. In other words, it's probably the number of the
ApoA particles bound to the LDL particles through the ApoB or the number of LpA's
that matters more than the mass of the LpA. So on that note, I was thinking about ApoB
and that there's one ApoB per LDL and then with ApoA, there's one ApoA per LpA, but not necessarily
not every LDL. But every ApoA is on an LDL particle. Every ApoA is on an LDL, but not every LDL has an
ApoA. And that's the difference between individuals when you look out at a population is the
how many of their LDLs are rolling around with ApoAs. Now, I don't think we'll get into it today,
but if there's ever an appetite to go ultra deep on LpA, we could probably talk about the relationship
between ApoE and ApoA. So it turns out that as people may know, you have three different
variants of ApoE. You have ApoE2, ApoE3, ApoE4. Of course, they combine in all six combinations
that I'm sure everybody's familiar with. But as you move from the two to the three to the four,
you see LpA go up. You see ApoB go up and you see triglyceride go down. And this is a pattern that
has been demonstrated over and over and over again. And what's interesting is why that's happening
with respect to the ApoA. But again, I think that's probably more the seniors course rather
than the freshmen course. Yeah. On the note of the freshman course, just looking at it and thinking,
so we're asking what is LpA? And if you're to look at how it's spelled out, it's capital L,
lowercase p, parenthetical, lowercase a, and close parentheses. And it's basically saying it's a
lipoprotein with an ApoA attached to it. Yeah. And if you were going to come up with an equivalency,
you'd do three little parallel lines as an equal line and say that's equal to LDL hyphen
little a or little ApoA. It would be the longhand way to write that. I don't know that anybody's
ever written it that way in the literature, but that's just another way to think about it.
Okay. So piggybacking on that, can you explain the difference between LpA mass,
then there's LpA cholesterol, and then there's the LpA particle content. And then as you mentioned,
there's the Kringle domains, the number of Kringles could also be called the different ApoA
isoforms. Can we quantify those? How are those measured? Yeah. I believe the first way this was
quantified. And again, this will be the type of stuff that I think would be really fun to explore
with a guy like Sam Tamikis, who's probably the world's expert on this topic. And we should
definitely make sure we get Sam on the show. I believe LpA mass was the first way that this
was quantified. And whether it was the first or not, I don't know. But what I can certainly say is
it's by far the most ubiquitous. I'm sure that 19 out of 20 times when a patient is having their LpA
checked, it is the mass that is being checked. Certainly if a patient comes to me and they've
been at least fortunate enough to have had their LpA checked, it's a mass. I almost never see the
cholesterol checked anymore. I think there used to be a company I believe called ATHROTEC that did the
test. I think they got bought, or at least that assay got bought by VAP and now VAP does it. But
I'll explain later why I don't think that's such a great test. And then of course there's the LpA
particle number, which is just the counting of it. So the LpA mass is directionally a reasonable
test, but it's not a great test. And the reason is it's measuring for particles that carry ApoA,
it's measuring the mass of everything, which is the ApoA, the ApoB, the phospholipids,
the cholesterol, the triglycerides, the dogs, the cats, whatever. It's measuring the mass of the
entire structure. Now the larger the cringal, section four, subsection two, the more that mass
is dominated by ApoA. But you can see very quickly how you could be misled. You could take two people
that have the exact same LpA mass, but if one of them has a very long segment four, sub-segment two
repeat binding domain, guess what? He's going to have a much fewer particle number, or more to the
point, the person that has the smaller segment four, sub-segment two is going to actually have
more particles. And so those people are not at equal risk. It turns out that the guy that's got
more particles is at higher risk. But when a patient shows up and their LpA mass is really,
really low, like less than five milligrams per deciliter, the likelihood that their LpA
particle number is very high is really, really low. And back in the olden days, and by the olden days,
I mean like four years ago before LpA particle number was measured, I used to actually look at
both. I'd look at LpA mass and LpA cholesterol, acknowledging that neither was perfect, but
basically coming up with a two by two, which was if both were high, I knew you had a ton of particles,
case closed. If both were low, we were off to the races and high fiving. And then when one was high,
one was low, we would just sort of follow up and test for reasons that we'll probably discuss later
around things that could actually change LpA as you march down the field. But luckily, most
patients were either double positive or double negative, and therefore you had a pretty good
sense of where their risk was. You then asked about LpA cholesterol. So that basically is
analogous to measuring the cholesterol content of an LDL particle number, except here it's measuring
the cholesterol concentration of an LpA particle number. And that, again, in isolation is not very
helpful. I am not an expert in clinical chemistry, but I've spoken with people who are, and it turns
out there are some other technical issues with that test that renders it not entirely helpful
and also misleading in its own way under certain circumstances. And it's for that reason that I
really prefer looking at the LpA particle number, which even though it's reported in an animal per
liter, to my knowledge is not actually measured via NMR, the way LDLP and HDLP were pioneered by
Lipa Science. It's a different assay, but nevertheless, it is counting the Apo little a's
that are attached to little Apo B's. And so you're getting a number of those. And for that test,
we like to see people less than 50 nanomole per liter. When people are sort of 50 to 100, I put
them in kind of a gray area when people are over 100 or certainly over 125 nanomole per liter.
That's when I start to get worried because I often get asked this question. The highest number
I've ever seen on a patient is about 650 to 700 nanomole per liter. And I've got a few patients
that walk around at 400, 500 nanomole per liter. So the Lp little a cholesterol, it sounds a lot like
when we're measuring LDLC. So if you're measuring Lp little a cholesterol, you're measuring the
amount of cholesterol that's carried within the Lp little a particles. And similarly with LDLC,
you're measuring the amount of cholesterol that's carried within the LDL particle.
Similarly, you would rather know the LDL particle. Yeah. And this is actually what makes it so
problematic is it's even worse than the discordance between LDLP and LDLC because at least when you're
dealing with LDL, you know the molecular weight. You don't know the molecular weight of Lp little a.
This is actually the point I forgot that I wanted to make a moment ago. I remember once
having a patient come to me with everything but the Lp little a P and I remember thinking, well,
I used to be a smart little organic chemistry whipper snapper. I should be able to convert this
from milligrams per deciliter into nanomole per liter. And of course, anyone listening to this who
knows more about chemistry than me will remember that all you need to know is like Avogado's number
and the molecular weight and you're ready to go. But of course you don't know the molecular weight.
That's the problem because the Apo A's don't look the same. The whole calculation goes to hell in
a hand basket. You can't actually calculate the molecular. You don't know the molecular weight
because of that Kringle sub segment, the Kringle four segment too, because it's got such variability.
It's not like you can say the molecular weight of sodium is X or the molecular weight of testosterone
is Y. So with the Apo A and how it comes in different isoforms, can you measure the Apo A?
Yes, but it would be for a given individual. That's the point. Yes, you could absolutely measure
the molecular weight of an Apo A, but it would be like yours and mine would probably be different.
So therefore, at least to my knowledge, and again, I don't want to speak out of turn because I'm sure
someone listening to this is going to go, no, no, no, you knucklehead, this is being done. But to my
knowledge, this is not something that's done clinically, whether it will be or not. Again,
that's probably a great question for someone like Tom Dayspring or Sam Tomakis or one of those guys.
I think that today the best test we have is the LP little a particle number. And there's a proxy
for it, but I'm guessing we'll talk about that later, which is you can also measure the amount
of oxidized phospholipid. If you normalize that for Apo B, you're getting almost a one-to-one
mapping of that because there's another interesting little, it's not a trivia point because trivia
tends to be irrelevant. This is actually quite relevant. Apo little a has lots of lysine.
The amino acid lysine and lysine really binds oxidized moieties. Now, Apo B does not contain
much lysine at all. And therefore, Apo B is not particularly effective oxidized moiety scavenger,
but Apo A is. And so if you think about your rolling around as an LDL, now you got a tail
thrown on you, which is called an Apo A, right? You got your little disulfide bridge attaches
to Apo B. You got your Apo A tail. Only you can see what my hands are doing right now.
This is great radio.
Yeah, this is awesome radio. We're smiling.
We'll have pictures. The pictures are definitely worth a thousand words because you can see the
cringled domains. And if you have a longer, you can see like longer tails and shorter tails.
Yeah.
This would all make sense.
And then once you've got your tail in place, now you start to fill that tail up with all
these oxidized phospholipids, you can start to measure. If you measure those phospholipids
normalized for Apo B, you're getting a pretty good proxy also of that. And by the way, this
may actually explain, and this is one of the questions like, you know, when we get Sam on
the show, this is one of the questions I want to ask him is just taking a step back from all of
this. Sometimes you clinically know when a person has an elevated LP little a before you take any
blood out of them. These are the patients who don't seem to fit the classic picture of someone
with premature heart disease in the family. Nobody's overweight. Nobody's diabetic. Nobody's
smoking or even if they are, the disease seems to come prematurely. It seems to come out of nowhere.
They also tend to, you know, if you ask enough, you might even see that somebody has aortic stenosis
and you just know the answer before you get there, especially if you have their family tree and you
can trace it and you can realize that whatever's happening here is coming through dominantly.
Is that something, it's a premature cardiovascular disease? Is that a clinical term? Is there like a
cutoff when you call it premature? Yeah, I mean, I think loosely we would say someone who's having
a major adverse cardiac event before 60 would be premature. Of course, I have a different
definition of that. I would think a major adverse cardiac event before 80 is premature, but I think
someone who's having any major adverse cardiac event, mace before the age of 60, I think anybody
would consider that premature. So what I've never been able to figure out is, you know, that patient
of mine that had like an LDL, an LP little A of 650, family history is not outrageous. You know,
when people get heart disease, they get it in their 70s. The patient of mine who has the 500,
I've tested this patient's family. I know where it came from. I know which parent it came from and
the burden of disease is modest. So there is something else going on here. And it's just
like the case with, we know that LDLP alone is not the issue. We know that it's just one factor.
And similarly, not all LPL little A's must be created equal. And so the question I'd want to
get into with an expert on this is, does it have to do with the lysine binding domains,
the affinity for these oxidized moieties? Is there some feature of one person's versus another's
that lends to a more aggressive oxidation within the sub-inethyl space or greater retention or
something like that? I think that gets into why do we have LPL little A? So what would be the
evolutionary basis? What's the function of LPL little A? Like it can't just be some
hell particle that's just trying to kill us. I mean, in theory, it could because it kills us through
basically three mechanisms that don't tend to kill you young. So if you were taking a purely
evolutionary standpoint, I think sometimes bad things track. But it turns out that even like
APOE4, which in today's environment doesn't seem particularly protective, APOE4 was quite
protective against parasitic infections in the CNS. And hell, up until a few years ago, that would
have been a pretty good thing to have. Of course, now that we can live long enough, that upside
isn't worth the downside of an increased risk of Alzheimer's disease. So LPL little A clearly does
two things that are separate. And I think we could argue, at least theoretically, that it would have
provided a benefit evolutionary. The first is if you go back to what we talked about, you have this
great homology to plasminogen. And plasminogen being a clotting factor means that people with
elevated LPL little A tend to have what's called hypercoagulability. So they have an ability to
form blood clots better than someone who doesn't. Now in today's environment, that's not an advantage
because most of us are not in an environment where bleeding to death is a major concern.
But you can imagine 50,000 years ago, bleeding to death would actually be a significant concern.
And so I think these people would have had a trauma advantage with respect to,
and I'm sure you could probably pose many benefits during childbirth.
When I think about what I saw in the OB-GYN rounds, how many times
was a woman bleeding so sufficiently that she required blood clotting products? It's not unheard
of. And so you think about the benefits this could have had all the way from birth, the
breathing of a child, right up until getting scratched by an animal or whatever. The second
benefit is more of a speculation, I think, but it's probably that going back to those lysine
binding domains that if you're in a relatively low oxidative environment and your LP little A's
know where to go when they're done, which is to the liver and where not to go, which is the coronary
arteries in the aortic valve, they're actually amazing scavengers. So I'm sure somebody out
there has got better data on this or has data period, because I'm obviously speculating,
but you could make the case that being able to have more particles that can scavenge more of
these oxidized phospholipids and oxidized moieties and take them back to the liver,
which is the ultimate place of clearance for the LP little A, which is a totally safe place to take
these things, that would pose an advantage. And it would be the case today that maybe we're in a
higher inflammatory environment and maybe we've gone too far. In other words, maybe we're
overwhelming the system's ability to clear it. And on top of that, we may have other risk factors,
hypertension, hyperinsulinemia, other drivers of inflammation that are now giving these LP little A
is another place to go, which is, yeah, you're ultimately going to end up at the liver,
but like 6% of you are going to get stuck in the sub endothelial space and wreak havoc. And
on top of that, you're doing a way worse job than the LDLP because the LDLP when it gets there is
bad enough, but the LDLP little A is now dragging all that oxidized crap in there with it.
So the next question is what is the problem with elevated LDLP little A or what are the problems
with LDLP little A elevated? So basically they fit into sort of three categories. The first being
enhanced atherosclerosis. The second, I don't know which by magnitude would pose a bigger threat,
but probably aortic stenosis given the severity. And then the third being enhanced venous thrombosis.
So what do those things mean? So basically more atherosclerosis, more aortic stenosis,
I believe about two thirds of the cases of aortic stenosis are explained by elevated
LDLP little A. So you have four valves in the heart and one of them is called the aortic valve.
That's the valve that separates the left ventricle from the systemic system. So the proximal aorta.
So that valve is under more pressure than the other three valves by a long shot,
because it's the one that's directly in front of the most powerful chamber of the heart.
That valve has three leaflets. It's a tri-leaflet valve. And it seems that LP little A has a
particular affinity for going there and inducing bone forming proteins to create calcifications.
And when that valve loses its suppleness and it becomes calcified, you get basically a blockage
of that valve called the stenosis. And so this condition of aortic stenosis is very problematic.
One of the earlier signs in the blood that somebody has aortic stenosis would be signs
of swelling or enlargement or dilation of the heart. And there are blood markers like
brain naturitic peptide, BNP or pro-NT BNP that are actually used quite frequently in
ERs to assess patients very quickly for cardiomyopathy or cardiac failure.
And so that's one of those things that we like to look at. And if I see a patient with LP little A,
I'm always screening them for aortic stenosis out of the gate. I don't care if they're 30 years old.
I mean, many of our patients are in their 30s and 40s, but if they have an elevated LP little A,
we're doing echo at a minimum and preferably cardiac MRI, which is much more accurate, to
both look at the morphology of the aortic valve and get a very accurate gradient of pressure.
And then sometimes you'll get patients. I have a patient who has a bicuspid aortic valve,
which is going to be by itself that's predisposed to aortic stenosis. And he also has a very elevated
LP little A, about 250 or 300. So even though he's only in his 30s, he gets a cardiac MRI annually,
and he's already showing a pressure gradient. So, you know, I've explained to him that he is going
to need an intervention at some point in his life, but the good news is we're going to do it
long before he experiences any strain on his heart muscle. And the good news again for patients today
is this stuff's going to be done interventionally and not via open heart surgery as it once was.
On the atherosclerosis side, I think the Mendelian randomizations, the GWAS and the epidemiology all
tell a very similar story. I suspect that it's both its ability, it's probably an all of the above
when it comes to why, meaning it's, are these particles more likely to enter the sub-enthelial
space? I don't know why that would be the case. Are they more likely to be retained? Probably,
because they have that whole big cringal oxidized moiety thing there. Are they more
likely to kick off an inflammatory response? Very likely because of what they're dragging in with
them. And then on top of that, to have the prothrombotic component, I suspect is what's
driving the increase in the risk of atherosclerosis. But in truth, we don't have definitive proof that
LPa is a more atherogenic particle. And you and I were talking about this the other day that
there is this paper that actually was looking at patients with post-MIs and even suggesting that,
well, everybody who has an Mi has a rise in LPa. And we'll probably get to that later,
why we think that might be the case. But the question posed is, well, maybe LPa is the result
of atherosclerosis and not the cause of it. I don't agree with that because many post-MI
patients don't have an elevated LPa. And I think a better explanation for that is that LPa also
acts as an acute phase reactant rising with inflammatory responses. But probably not until
the antisense oligonucleotide trials complete, will we actually know the answer to this question?
Because really without a clinical trial, you can't actually infer cause and effect the way we can with
other aspects of atherosclerosis, like the LDL particle or inflammation, where we have elegant,
prospective clinical trials that create a relationship between cause and effect.
The last thing that I guess I mentioned was the thromboembolism. So I used to have a practice of
putting everybody with an elevated LPa on a baby aspirin just to combat the effect. It turns out
that that was probably an oversimplified approach and that there's only a subset of people for whom
aspirin counteracts the effect. So unfortunately, this is still one of those things where I don't
think we have a great answer. I do take DVT prophylaxis, so deep vein thromboses, prophylaxis,
prevention. I do take it more seriously in the LPa patients and there are certain strategies you
can take around flying. There's actually a commercially available product called flight tabs,
which you can buy on Amazon. I was, remember when we did the research on this, I was blown away that
you could buy these things on Amazon because they're actually quite potent. But I do recommend
that people with elevated LPa if they're on really long flights. And again, I'm not recommending that
for people who are listening because I can't, but I certainly recommend to my patients to a
subset of them that we're particularly worried about that we look at either pharmacologic agents
or even an OTC agent like that as a way to reduce the risk of these types of events.
So do we know how much elevated LPa is associated with these increased risks? If we're looking at
the epidemiology, what are the associated risks with cardiovascular disease?
So with aortic stenosis, the hazard ratios are anywhere from two to four, depending on the
studies. And I think they probably median ends up being roughly two and a half. With VTE, with the
venous thromboembolism, I think the hazard ratio is about 3x. And again, it's important to put this
in perspective. We've talked about absolute versus relative risk. So when you talk about a 3x risk of
something that occurs like 1% of the time, that means you're going from a 1% absolute risk to a
3% absolute risk. So in other words, it doesn't mean like if you're listening to this and you have
an elevated LPa, you need to call an ambulance to drive you home because you're afraid you're going
to have a pulmonary embolism. And similarly, a hazard ratio of two and a half, three, even four
on aortic stenosis. As I said, it probably explains about two thirds of the total volume of aortic
stenosis, but it doesn't mean that every patient who's got this is going to get it. I think in the
case of that one patient of mine, his bicuspid valve is just a setup to make things worse
because he's now got a double whammy on that. And when it comes to atherosclerosis, basically
you see odds ratios of about two to four depending on the amount. So it looks like a pretty good dose
response where it's sort of below about 30 or 40 milligrams per deciliter. Because unfortunately,
all of these studies are done with LPa mass and not particle number. And I can't really convert
that, but we believe that that's probably about 50. That's probably, you're going to get comparable
in the 50 to 75 nanomole per liter is this sort of safe zone where it's relatively flat. And then
it starts to uptick pretty swiftly. So by the time you're at, call it 200 milligrams per deciliter,
you're at about a 60% increase. Now, if you stop for a moment and think about that,
what should you be more afraid of? A 3x hazard ratio for VTE or a 1.6 hazard ratio for atherosclerosis
or a 2.5x hazard ratio on aortic stenosis? This is like the advanced clinical epidemiology
question, right? I think the answer is the 1.6 on atherosclerosis is by far the most disconcerting
because atherosclerosis is infinitely more prevalent. So a 60% increase in risk on something
that is going to kill a third of people is a big effing problem. Whereas a 3% risk on something
that's going to ding 1% of people, yeah, we'll manage it. But that's not what we stay up late
thinking about. And even for that particular individual that has that risk profile,
that if they look at their absolute risks, that probably bumps up their absolute risk the most
with cardiovascular disease. Yeah. We're screening for aortic stenosis,
not because I necessarily think it's even at the population or societal level,
cost-effective, but at the individual level, we're not going to let that kind of stuff slide.
But if you were to think about this at the population level, the thing we have to be most
concerned of is somewhere between one in five and one in 10 people, and in some cultures,
it's even higher. In Southeast Asians, it's even higher, are walking around with these little
time bombs. And to the point of Anahad's story, I'm still shocked at how many doctors don't
understand this. Now look, if you're a radiologist or a dermatologist, that's okay. I don't think you
need to know this. But if you sit anywhere on the front lines of medicine, if you're a family
physician, if you're a GYN even, because for many women, their GYNs become their PCPs,
their primary care physicians. If you are anywhere in the crosshairs of taking care of a patient
where you have some input into how they lower their risk of cardiovascular disease, and you
don't understand most of what we're talking about on this podcast, I worry that you're
missing an opportunity to help patients. Okay, so another question that came in,
I think you touched upon it very quickly, is what is the prevalence of elevated LPa? Probably what
is elevated LPa? How is that determined? Well, to my knowledge, everything that's done on this that's
published is based on the LPa mass, not the particle number. But the US levels define normal
as less than 30 milligrams per deciliter. The European atherosclerotic society defines normal
as less than 50 milligrams per deciliter. And I believe both the UK and Germany consider anything
over 60 sufficient for state covered apheresis. Apheresis is a type of treatment where a patient
has a very large IV put in one arm, typically about a 14 gauge, and blood is taken out,
run through a machine that spins at a certain frequency to generate a separation of the plasma.
And you can basically fractionate the plasma and identify something that you want to remove. So,
back when I was at NIH, I used to volunteer for apheresis every four weeks to donate lymphocytes.
And then they basically put everything back that once they strip out the piece they want,
but you can actually do apheresis and remove the apo little a. The problem is the frequency with
which you have to do it is staggering, because the half-life of these particles is a matter of days.
So, these patients would undergo apheresis potentially twice a week. So, that's obviously
a very difficult way to be tethered. So, we got into it a little bit there. How is abnormal LPa
treated or dealt with? So, you just got into the apheresis. Are there other therapies currently
available? So, apheresis is something that we just really never resort to or very rarely resort to.
And certainly now that PCSK9 inhibitors are on the market, I think that apheresis is becoming
probably less and less utilized. Historically, the agent for treatment has been niacin. Now,
niacin's got kind of a checkered history because it's known to lower apo B. So, you take niacin,
your LDL goes down. And this is a super contentious topic in lipid circles. But the question is,
does niacin save lives? And depending on how you look at the trial data, the answer is maybe or no.
It's like a wonder drug, theoretically, right? It lowers LDL, HDL goes up, LP little a might go
down. So, on paper, it looks at least up to that point, it looks great. Right. That's exactly right.
It does three things that we historically know when they happen. Good things should happen. LDL,
particle and cholesterol, apo B all go down. HDL cholesterol goes up. Although I would argue that
that's not a good thing. I think we have a pretty good sense of why raising HDL cholesterol inorganically,
meaning pharmacologically is not going to be good. And it lowers LP little a by probably a third.
C-TEP inhibitors? Yeah, exactly.
Five times the charm or? I think we're waiting for number five. Yeah.
But it turns out that in the trial that basically doomed niacin, the trial probably wasn't designed
that well in that they were giving niacin to patients who were already on a max dose statin
and looking for the HDL increase to see if that was adding benefit. And so, you basically get
lipidologists in two camps and actually it's not, it's quite evenly split, at least in my narrow
sampling of smart lipidologists where you get some who say niacin should never be used. And then you
get others who say, look, it's probably not a great drug, but if you have a patient who can't take
anything else, it's still a good drug. And I know lots of lipidologists who are still putting
LP little a patients on niacin, even though there are no data to suggest that that will save their
lives. But I got to be honest with you, I'm not convinced that that's necessarily a bad thing.
I generally don't. I now move to the third thing, which is the PCSK9 inhibitor. But I guess before
I do that, I should explain statins because everybody is probably saying where do statins
fit into this? And it turns out statins don't clear LP little a, which is kind of counterintuitive
if you know how statins work. So statins work via two mechanisms, what we call sort of the direct
and indirect mechanism. So the direct mechanism is that they inhibit HMG CoA reductase, which is an
enzyme that catalyzes one of the early steps, if not the first step, I believe of cholesterol
synthesis. So if you're making less cholesterol, you would have less cholesterol, there would be
less cholesterol to carry around, you could require fewer lipoproteins. But that's not really the main
way it works. The main way it works is that the liver, in response to the statin, upregulates
something called SREBP2. And when that thing gets upregulated, it puts more LDL receptors
on the surface of the liver. So this SREBP2, which I'll just abbreviate for short, is called
the sterile regulatory element binding protein. It basically says, hey, the liver is getting less
cholesterol, and it wants more cholesterol. So I'm going to put more of these LDL receptors on my
surface to pull more in. Now, I didn't know this until recently, but one of the other things that
SREBP2 does is it actually produces more PCSK9. Now, PCSK9 is a protein that degrades LDL receptors.
So it's actually a bit of a check and a balance. So you have more LDL clearance because of more
LDL receptors, but you also speed up the rate at which those LDL receptors are degraded.
So the statin is causing these two indirect effects, but the net tends to be an enhanced
clearance of the LDL particle, the APO-B particle, and therefore a lowering of the LDL cholesterol.
But it doesn't lower LPa. And if you're listening to this and you remember what we talked about at
the outset, you're probably thinking, that doesn't make sense. LPa is just an LDL with an APO-A on
it. Why wouldn't the LDL receptor clear it? Because if the LDL receptor clears it,
it should also go down. I asked Tom Dayspring about this because a really interesting paper
came out a few weeks ago that actually tried to explain this. And like all good papers,
it ended up leaving more questions than answers. The best explanation that I understood from Tom
was that LPa will get cleared by LDL receptors eventually, but it's just the last in line.
So after the LDL is cleared and the VLDL is cleared, yeah, then you might get to the
LPa. But the problem is you never get there. So maybe in theory, if you increase LDL receptor
expression enough, or if you could knock out PCSK9 and offset the second piece of what the
statin is doing, the statin would work. And it turns out that that is largely what this paper
showed. And what we've always known, which is when you combine a PCSK inhibitor with a statin,
you actually do get a reduction of LPa. Whereas a statin by itself is anywhere from no reduction
to in some studies, an actual increase in LPa. And PCSK9 alone also lowers LPa. So to be clear,
PCSK9 inhibitors are not FDA approved for the use of lowering LPa. But those of us who prescribe
these drugs, both for patients with other indications and with LPa, generally acknowledge
that we're seeing about a 30% reduction in LPa, sometimes as high as a 50% reduction in LPa,
when patients are taking PCSK9 inhibitors with or without statins. And that also probably speaks to
the fact that we know that LPa is cleared by different receptors. So its primary receptor is
probably LRP2, but it's also probably cleared somewhat by VLDL receptors, and even something
called SRB1, although I'm not sure of that. And frankly, I don't know that anybody is. So that
what the PCSK9 inhibitor is doing is it's inhibiting PCSK9, and therefore inhibiting the
protein that degrades not just the LDL receptor, but these other receptors that clear LPa.
Interesting.
Sure.
I was just thinking about something. On statins, so oftentimes I'll read in the papers,
just to back up for a second too, I often read in the papers LPa, the words mysterious, unknown,
in some ways we're in our infancy and understanding this. But I think in one of those papers,
Samikas looked at the effect of statins, not only just statins in general, but different statins,
Atorvastatin, Pravastatin, Pitivastatin, Livolo, Arasuvastatin, and Simvastatin. I think maybe that
covers all the statins. If I'm just looking at his data, the LPa actually looks like it's trending
up on statins. Not only that, the oxidized phospholipids to ApoB are also going up.
Is there any explanation as to why the thing could actually be elevated?
Yeah, because the ApoB is probably going down. It's probably that you're lowering the denominator.
Got it.
That's my guess. What's clearly acknowledged is that when you give a patient with elevated
LPa a statin, which we do absolutely, it's not to lower the LPa, it's to lower the LDL.
Actually, I'm glad you brought this up because I missed the punch line in all the detail.
At least one of the punch lines is how do we treat patients with elevated LPa? Well,
we're probably not going to give them phoresis. If they can't afford to buy a PCSK9 inhibitor,
because it's certainly not going to be approved, you have only one other choice, which is to
actually have two other choices, but I'll get to one in a moment. It rarely works,
but it works occasionally. Your real issue is you have to give them a statin because you
now have a new LDL target. My LDL target, when I say LDL, I'm always referring to LDL-P.
My LDL-P target is the 20th percentile or lower for every patient.
How much lower you go than that is a function of other risk factors. Are we talking about
secondary prevention? What's the family history? Are they insulin resistant? All these other factors.
But a patient who's got an elevated LPa immediately falls into the category of all
things equal, they're at the 10th percentile or lower. You will often need a statin to get them
there. Now, not always. I have some patients who don't need a statin to get their LDL-P down to
the 10th percentile, but they're the exception and not the rule. I don't want people to get the
impression that if you have an elevated LPa, you shouldn't be taking a statin. Now, it's quite the
opposite. You probably should be taking a statin, but just understand that the statin is there to
control ApoB and not LpA. Okay. I don't know if we have enough ammo to cover this, but hormone
therapy, estrogen, I think has been shown to lower LpA. I didn't know that actually. This is an up-to-date,
which is a nice service that compiles a lot of this information, almost like a systematic review.
They have a section on lipoprotein A and cardiovascular disease and lipid lowering.
One of the things that they noted was estrogen replacement therapy reduces LpA levels by up to
50%. They have a couple references there. An effect that was somewhat mitigated by concomitant
progesterone therapy in some reports. I don't know if that's a women's health initiative,
so we're probably dealing with different variables, but not the PEPI trial. However,
the clinical role for hormone replacement therapy is uncertain and it is not recommended
for cardiovascular disease risk reduction. If that HRT topic wasn't compelling enough to go over,
I think this is another reason, another wrinkle to throw in there.
I'd like to understand that better. That strikes me as a bit too good to be true,
frankly, because certainly, if that's true, that's one, it suggests it might only be...
I guess the question I would want to know is, does that imply that women who go through menopause,
wouldn't they see an increase in LpA? All things equal if they did not receive HRT?
I believe so, yeah.
I'm going to go and look at the LpA levels of my patients who have gone through menopause
while under my care, but nothing jumps out at me. There was one other thing we didn't talk about,
which is what's on the front lines here in terms of really interesting stuff, which is these things
called ASOs, which is really the first treatment that is designed specifically to lower LpA.
So, ASO stands for Antisense Oligonucleotide. So, these are molecules that disrupt protein synthesis.
So, I can't remember exactly where they ask. I think they act after the messenger RNA,
between messenger RNA and translational RNA, but maybe they act between DNA and messenger RNA.
I should know this. I'm sure there's like... I'm sure that's a very well-known obvious fact
that I'm just forgetting, but the point is they disrupt the synthesis of ApoA,
which is occurring in the liver. So, this is a drug that goes right to the heart of LpA.
And I didn't say this earlier, but it's worth pointing this out.
When you go through my whole rigmarole on why do statins probably not decrease LpA,
it doesn't appear that anything that's going to lower LpA is going to do it on the catabolism side,
meaning the breakdown side. It appears to be on the synthesis side, the making side. And so,
while the monoclonal antibodies like the PCSK9s also increase degradation, they reduce the synthesis.
They're actually reducing the synthesis of ApoA on the liver as well.
So, these antisense oligonucleotides go right to the heart of that, and they directly stop the
synthesis of ApoA, and therefore, you just have your garden variety LDLs. These drugs have been
shown to have safety and efficacy. So, they have concluded phase one and phase two trials,
and they are slowly enrolling in phase three trials. I think three years ago, I said they'd
be done in five years. Three years later, I think they'll be done in five years.
consistent. The frequency distribution figure that we'll include somewhere,
it shows effective antisense oligonucleotide, and it says around 70% to up to 99%, so it could
potentially wipe out, virtually wipe out LpL. Yeah, no, even somebody who's got an LpL of 200
can be normalized. I'm a little leery of wiping out something entirely. It certainly suggests
that if you have this ASO, you can test a hypothesis in terms of LpL lowering therapy,
for sure. Well, that's what I was referring to at the outset, which was until this trial is done,
I don't think we can definitively know the answer of what is the true risk? How do you quantify the
true risk of LpL? I think we got through a lot of the major questions. This is awesome. We didn't
have to go for four hours. There's a bonus question. We're in the bonus round. There's some
other stuff we can talk about too as well. I think getting into the oxidized phospholipids,
how that works in the Lp, PlA2, we could get into. But one of the things that I was thinking about is
that with lipoproteins with LDL, with HDL, even triglycerides, you have some tools in your arsenal
just in terms of, let's call them behavioral modifications or things like that. If you
challenge somebody or somebody said, I need to lower my triglycerides in 30 days or else,
you could probably do that through diet. Absolutely. Triglycerides, by far the most
sensitive thing in the blood as far as lipoprotein lipid related molecules to dietary intervention.
In theory, it sounds like you can play around with a lot of the lipoproteins. Actually,
a lot of the biomarkers, but it seems like with LpL, it doesn't seem like it can be modified all
that much by lifestyle. Is that right? Or at least that's the current thinking.
No, that's absolutely correct. Probably the reason for that is,
as we just learned from the PCSK9 statin comparisons, directionally speaking,
there are two things that are driving LpL, how much you make and how much you clear.
But the game seems to be won and lost on the how much you make front.
How much you clear seems to be a second order thing. Now, when you look at LDLp,
just to contrast it, nevermind triglycerides, when you look at LDLp, you go back to four things
that determine the number of those particles. Three of them have to do with how much you carry.
One of them has to do with how much you clear. So three about the cargo, one about the port.
How many triglycerides do you have? How much cholesterol do you synthesize? How much
esterified cholesterol or non-esterified cholesterol rather do you reabsorb after it
passes through the biliary system in the enterocyte? And then what's your LDL receptor profile look
like? Primarily in the liver, but also in the gut. Now we just established you can clearly lower
triglycerides through nutrition. So you got somebody walking around with a triglyceride of 200
and an LDLp of 1600 and you do nothing but lower their triglycerides to 50 while I can't predict
what their reduction is going to be. It's likely going to go down. And so that's a lifestyle
intervention and that clearly does things. And it turns out that we know that diet is also going to
lower or raise. Certainly it has an impact on LDLc. That is known, but it also can have an effect on
LDLp through cholesterol synthesis and absorption. Now I think that the relationship there is much
less clearly understood. I've speculated about what I see occurring. There seems to be a subset
of people who when they consume high amounts of saturated fat see a really significant increase
in cholesterol synthesis. I think Tom Dayspring has written a really eloquent piece on this. So
if we can find it, if it's publicly available, we should link to it because I think it's a great
piece on the hypothesis around why certain people in the presence of high saturated fat just start
making much more cholesterol. And then of course the contentious topic is does it matter?
I don't think we know the answer to that question, but that's a point.
I was among them at one point. I think you get an NMR and it gives you your LDLp count. Is it in
nanomoles?
Nanomole per liter, yeah.
And it actually reminded me of Fletch and Gillette collecting rent, I believe. And he picks up one of
Gillette's letters and he says, oh, a letter from the Oakwood Potency Clinic. We're sorry to inform
you we can't process sperm counts as low as yours. So in the case of this NMR, I get the test back
and you probably know the number. Maybe it's like 2,500 or...
The upper cutoff is 3,500.
3,500 and it has one of those awesome greater than signs. It says greater than 3,500. It's like,
we're sorry, our machines can't process LDL particles as high as you. And I think during
the time I was doing an experiment where I was eating a lot of my calories were coming
from saturated fat. It was probably supposedly a well-formulated ketogenic diet, but coconut oil,
maybe some of it's coconut oil, butter, et cetera, but it was heavily loaded with saturated fat.
I would love to read that article because it's one of those things that's gone around the circles.
Is it good? Is it bad? But it is definitely something that's seen, I think.
Yeah. I mean, given how amazing we've made progress on this and how we've barely been
out for an hour and we're almost done. I mean, I'm happy to expand on this just based on my
observations because I'm sure someone's going to end up asking anyway. I've probably seen this
now a dozen times where either someone comes to me already on a ketogenic diet or we put them
on a ketogenic diet and they develop this change in their lipids. Now, there are some people who
will argue that it's transient and it's going to go away in a year or two years or whatever, maybe so.
There are others that argue that it's irrelevant, that the increase in the cholesterol synthesis
and the LDL cholesterol and the total cholesterol is actually a good thing and there's some reason
that they offer for that that I don't quite buy or understand. But my view is all things equal
until I know better, I'm going to assume that high LDL is probably problematic. More importantly,
the point is, are there ways to reverse the diet and reverse the condition and figure out what was
the component within the diet that was doing it? Was it the total fat? Was this the subset of the
fat, et cetera? And in all but one of those cases of maybe a dozen, when you just replace the saturated
fat with monounsaturated fat, even if they stay consuming a very high fat diet, the problem goes
away, which has not that that's proof of anything, but that really suggests to me that in those
patients, they're getting more saturated fat than they can process because I had one,
the first patient that I ever went through this with, my first thought was, dude, we got to take
you off this ketogenic diet, man. We can play keto camp all day long, but I'm not that comfortable
with these numbers. And he was like, but I'm not going off a ketogenic diet. And he had all his
reasons for why he felt better and performed better and all those things. So I said, okay,
well then we could keep you on a ketogenic diet, but I want to see what happens if your saturated
fat goes from 75 grams a day to 25 grams a day. And to do that, you're going to get really familiar
and friendly with olives, olive oil, and macadamia nuts. And he's like, I don't care. You know, this
kid, he was a young guy and he was, he'd do anything. He was kind of like a robot. And so sure
enough in like eight weeks of that change, his LDLP went from greater than 3,500 to, you know, 1,200.
Same thing. I had a lot of guacamole, macadamia nuts that replaced the saturated fat and the
numbers came down and everything else, give or take HDL, triglycerides, all that stuff were
sort of in the same ballpark as before, but that LDLP came down. Yeah. And I got to tell you, I mean,
I'm sure that this will kick up a storm of people with, you know, very, very strong religious like
views on, oh, there's nothing wrong with an LDLP of 3,500. And, you know, again, I don't buy it
because the other thing I don't buy is a lot of those times you'll see the oxidized LDL go up as
well. And how are we in the middle of Manhattan and some knucklehead is like drag racing on 79.
I don't get that. It's the most gratuitous. I think we should, we should get involved.
We should rev up the engines. He likes cars. We just need some jackhammers right now. So,
yeah, when I see the oxidized LDL and CRP go up as well, which I often see with that, then I think,
you know, there's something else going on here. This isn't just a cholesterol synthesis problem.
It's an inflammatory problem. Something is, and look, I wasn't that guy. I mean, I probably ate,
when I was in ketosis, I was probably eating 200 grams a day of saturated fat.
Maybe not quite that much, maybe 150, but I was eating a lot of saturated fat,
but I didn't have any of those response. You know, my CRP was really low. My trigs were
non-existent. My LDL particle number was probably around the 50th percentile, you know, 12 to 1300
nanomole per liter. Like I just didn't have any of those findings. And again, I see a lot of people
who don't have those things. So I don't know why some people have these paradoxical reactions,
but I also don't think it's safe to ignore them just because insulin levels have gone down.
And going back to oxidized LDL, if you saw oxidized LDL going up, my newbie understanding
of this is that oxidized LDL is in a sense, LP little a. So that LP little a.
Well, that's oxidized phospholipid.
Yeah. So the LP little a picks up the oxidized phospholipids from the lipoprotein from the LDL.
And then that LP little a particle itself is now carrying the oxidized phospholipids,
but that's not a oxidized LDL.
No, the ox LDL assay is different from the ox PL assay. The ox LDL assay works independent of how
many ApoAs you have. I like to see that number below 40. Again, I think the lab likes to see it
below 60, but I like to see that along with the LP PLA2, which you alluded to earlier. These are
really local markers of inflammation. And those are important because if you see a patient with
an elevated C reactive protein, should you be concerned about it? I mean, yes, probably,
but the question is, is it cardiac specific or not? You can't really tell. So that's why
looking at fibrinogen and C reactive protein and homocysteine and LP PLA2 and oxidized LDL
help you get a better picture of if there's inflammation, how much of this do we think
is going on locally at a vascular level versus someplace else. You see this all the time in
people who have food insensitivities and things like that with respect to the fibrinogen, the CRP.
Yeah. So we'll probably throw in those figures. You just mentioned that the LP PLA2 and LP little
A, and then there's another thing called it's the oxidized phospholipids over the ApoB. And in that
paper, it's a 2007 paper. And I think Samikas is the last author on it as well. He's all over the
place. They show the hazard ratios and it's a J curve. So that the very the lowest, they call it
the sex style. So they partition it into six different groups. And on the lowest, if you look
at the hazard ratio, the hazard ratio is about two. So the risk doubles. If you have very low
LP little A. Does he explain why he thinks that's happening? I'm not. I wonder if it's an
artifact of ApoB being higher. Possibly. The denominator going up would shrink the total
number. I'll have to look at that. Are there any other LP little A questions that came through the
interwebs? Not through the interwebs. Well, then I think we can bring to a close our inaugural.
Chapter one. Chapter one. Vote on what you want to hear about. Any final words, Bob? It's interesting.
I knew about LP little A a little bit prior to on a hot article in January. And after doing some
digging, there's some other thoughts about this stuff that I'm sure we'll get into down the road.
But it's that proverb, I think Naseem Taleb quotes, he says it's a Venetian proverb.
It says the further from the shore, the deeper the water. And so the more you dig into this,
the more you learn, the less you know, in a sense, you sort of expose yourself to a lot of unknowns.
So it's absolutely fascinating. And I think it also gets to how most physicians don't even know
about this stuff. And you alluded to it in one of our conversations previously, that there's this
lag in terms of the medical knowledge and what's the accepted wisdom and the guidelines and things
like that. So I think LP little A is one of those cases that's just, it's fascinating. The more you
learn, the less you know, but the more you want to learn. Yeah. And we're really, as you pointed out
earlier in our infancy of this thing. Yeah. If we were just going to put numbers to it, I think five
years ago, I had 50% understanding, like one unit of understanding to two units of perceived total
volume of content. Today, I'm at 10% understanding, 10 units of understanding to 100 units of
perceived total content. So has my knowledge gone up in five years? Yeah, it's gone up 10 fold.
The problem is my appreciation for how much information is out there on this topic has gone
up 50 fold. So my relative insight has actually gone down five fold. What is that? It sounds like
the Dunning Krueger effect a little bit. It's that when you know, like just like the surface level,
that's where you're the most confident. You think you know everything. And then as you learn more,
it's like that Dunning Krueger, it's like a you, and then your confidence and your knowledge goes
down. Hey, welcome to the 24 hour news cycle, cable TV, and Twitter, man. I don't know if that's
Dunning or Krueger, but it's that it's on the left side where it's everybody's very confident.
Well, in summary, I'd say the following. If you're listening to this as a patient,
you should demand that your LP little a be known. It's non-negotiable, especially if you have a
family history of atherosclerotic disease. If you're a physician, and this is your first exposure to
it, I hope that we've invited you to learn more. And I hope that we've provided you with enough
information that you're sufficiently curious and we'll certainly make a point to link to this some
of the what we think are more relevant things. Worth noting, I think about three days ago,
an ICD-10 code was actually just issued for elevated LP little a. That's a pretty big deal.
That's like one of the signs that it's not some little nerds only thing. Once you get your ICD-9
code issued, or ICD-10 rather. And if you are neither a patient nor a physician, I don't know
what you are. And therefore this podcast probably is not for you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com. What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the link at
the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my
subjectively non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance,
sleep, et cetera. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. But usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does
not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.