Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at PeterAttiaMD.com.
In this podcast, I'll be speaking with Matt Caberlin at the University of Washington.
I met Matt about a year and a half, maybe two years ago through David Sabatini, who some of you
may be familiar with just based on all of his remarkable work around mTOR and Rapa Mison.
Matt's recognized globally for his research in the biology of aging. He got his PhD
from MIT in the lab of Lenny Garante, who's produced a number of notable folks in this field.
He went on to his post-doc at the University of Washington. And after completing his post-doc,
he has remained there and continues to run a fantastic lab. In this episode, we're going to
talk about his experience as the director of the Dog Aging Project, which as its name suggests,
focuses on the animal model of dogs for its research. Now, of course, this is really
interesting because while fruit flies and yeast and mice are interesting, dogs are obviously much
closer to us. And of course, these dogs, because they're pets generally, have something really
unique to us that virtually no other research animal has, which is they share our environment.
And this puts them in a pretty unique spot that even the rhesus monkeys studied in the
NIA Wisconsin Project didn't have going for them. Now, if you haven't already done so,
I'd recommend listening to the podcast that I did with David Sabatini, because that will get you
some of the background on mTOR and Rapa Mison. I think we get a little technical in this podcast,
but I suspect it's something that if you've listened to that other one with Sabatini,
you'll have the background to follow. And we talk about a bunch of other things that people seem to
be interested in as well beyond Rapa Mison and aging. We also talk about NAD, probably get into
Sirtuins a little bit. The other thing I really enjoy about speaking with Matt, and I had so many
discussions with Matt over meals and stuff where I think to myself after, man, I wish that was
recorded because one, I want to be able to hear it again. And two, it's the kind of stuff that
people are always asking me. And I think Matt just has such an amazing way of thinking about this
stuff. Matt's work is really remarkable because it's actually focusing on health span. It's easier
in some ways to study health span because you can study it over a shorter period of time. And in
particular, when you look at the cardiomyopathy model, meaning it's a type of heart failure that
dogs experience, and you look at how Rapa Mison can improve ejection fraction, you can get these
answers in a really quick period of time. In fact, much quicker than I think Matt even expected. And
we talk of course about cancer, heart disease, and Alzheimer's disease. So if you're interested in
Rapa Mison, if you're interested in mTOR, if you're interested in longevity, I think you're going to
find this interview very interesting. It was actually recorded initially in December of 2017
as part of the interview series I was doing for my book. And we may at some point throw up the
video as well. You can find a lot more information in the show notes of course. And without further
delay, here's my conversation with the remarkable Matt Caperly. Matt, thank you so much for being
here. It's really fantastic to be able to talk with you in this format. I've been a huge fan of
your work for many years now. Obviously I know quite a bit about your background, but I think
it'd be great for the listeners to kind of get a sense of, you know, what did you study in college?
How did you end up doing your PhD? Where did you do it? And most of all, why did it get you where you are?
Sure. So I got undergraduate degrees in biochemistry and mathematics at Western Washington
University. And then I went to graduate school at MIT, the biology department there. And my background
up till that point had been in biophysical chemistry. So I really went to graduate school
thinking I was going to work on structural biology or x-ray crystallography or something like that.
And I heard a seminar by Lenny Granty, who I ended up doing my PhD thesis with during my first
semester at MIT, where he started talking about how his lab had begun working on the genetics of
aging and trying to understand, you know, what are the factors that influence the rate of aging? And
this was in yeast. That's what his lab worked on at that point. And it was really almost like an
aha moment where it just clicked with me that it was really fascinating that you could use
genetics and molecular biology and biochemistry to study something as complicated and fundamental as
the biology of aging. And so I got fascinated by the topic. I ended up going and talking to Lenny
and then subsequently doing my thesis research with him. So it was really that moment of hearing
him talk my first year in graduate school that got me interested in aging. And that's what I've been
fascinated by and passionate about since then. And so then I went on and did a postdoc with Stan
Fields at the University of Washington, also working on aging, and then ultimately started
my own lab. So it's been almost two decades now that I've been working on this problem.
And if my memory serves me correctly, when you were in Lenny's lab, who's obviously no stranger
to probably people who are listening to this, you worked on sirtuins, correct? Yeah. So my thesis
work was actually the work that first showed that if you activated or overexpressed a sirtuin,
in this case it was sirtu, the founding member of the sirtuins in yeast, that you could extend
lifespan and slow aging. And obviously we were very excited about that, especially when a postdoc who
was in the lab at that time, Heidi Tissenbaum, about a year later, showed that you could also
overexpressed the worm version of sirtu and extend lifespan in C. elegans. And so that was really
the first example of a conserved genetic modifier of lifespan across two widely
evolutionarily divergent organisms. Because it was a relatively similar version of sirtu. Yeah.
So more different than the DAF stuff that we saw in C. elegans versus the IGF that we would see in
some of the higher mammals. Right. So at that time we knew that DAF2 could extend lifespan in
C. elegans. I don't think we knew it was working that similar mechanism. That's right. Yeah.
Now I think one of the things that makes your work so interesting is that you work on dogs. Right.
How did you end up doing that? Yeah. So that's relatively new in my career. It was about four
years ago when Daniel Promislow moved from the University of Georgia to the University of
Washington. And Daniel had started thinking about dogs as a model to understand how genetic
and environmental factors influence the aging process. And I'm a dog person. I've always had
dogs. I have three dogs now. That qualifies. Yeah. Right. And I had never really made the
connection between dogs as companion animals and dogs as a model for understanding aging until I
talked with Daniel about this. And through those conversations it occurred to me that not only could
we understand genetic and environmental modifiers of aging but our pets could actually serve as a
transformative next step in testing some of these things that we know work in laboratory mammals
like mice but have never yet been taken outside of the laboratory. And so it was really that sort of
connection in my mind about three years ago that propelled me to really move forward with the dog
aging project. One major goal of which is to actually do this to take some of the interventions
that we know extend lifespan and slow aging in the laboratory and test whether they have that effect
in the real world in a larger mammal that's also very socially relevant. I think that that's an
important aspect of this. People love their dogs. If we can actually slow aging in people's pets
that's going to have a huge impact both on the quality of life for the pets and the owners
but also the way that people think about the biology of aging. They're going to believe it a
lot more if they see that their dog is living longer and aging more slowly than just reading
an article in the New York Times or wherever. Right. Right. And it's you know I sort of when I
talk about this I generally talk about these four classes of eukaryotes going from you know
yeast to flies worms and mammals but usually when we talk about mammals we're talking about mice.
Absolutely. They have a couple of problems at least right. One problem is they're generally
especially if they're inbred I mean they're homozygous at all low size so right you have to
question their applicability to us in terms of their susceptibility to disease. But then the
second point which you alluded to which I think the dogs might be the first quote unquote laboratory
study that gets out of this is they don't live in our environment. Right. The mice that is right.
Right. So so so the dog truly lives in the environment you and I live in which
at least in theory should be the environment we care most about preventing aging in. That's right.
I think I think that environmental variation is hugely important. The genetics is also important
and dogs are so there's there's a couple of things that are worth mentioning. Dogs have some
of that same genetic homogeneity if you look within individual purebred breeds. But we also have
many purebred breeds that are widely divergent both genetically and morphologically. All you have
to do is look at a chihuahua on a Great Dane right to see that divergence. But we also have this really
interesting and complex mixed breed population that's a combination of all these different
genetic variants that each breed has. So so we have kind of the best of both worlds in the sense
that if you want to do a study in a relatively genetically restricted background you can do it
in a specific breed or set of breeds. But if you want to capture that genetic variation all you have
to do is look in the mixed breed dogs. But the environmental part of this I think is probably
the most important from what are we going to learn from dogs that we can't learn from mice
perspective. As you said dogs really share our environment to a greater extent than any other
animal maybe with the exception of cats. And so they're drinking the same water. In fact may not
even be drinking the same water. Most people maybe drink it worse. Yeah right are not going to give
their dog bottled water right. But they're breathing the same air. If you smoke they're
experiencing that or someone in the house smokes they're experiencing that secondhand smoke. So
they really do capture most of our environment. The diet is about the only place where dogs don't
quite have the same sort of nutritional diversity that people do. But with the exception of diet
the environment is pretty close. Now we have a pretty good idea of how we die. Right I could
actuarially map out how you and I are going to die based on our age and a whole bunch of other factors.
Again it's probably an oversimplification because of this species diversification. But as a general
rule how do dogs die. Yeah so I'll make one quick comment on that. First of all that I think you're
right that we do know what diseases most often kill people. And that's important information.
I'm not sure it's the most important information because what people die from does not always
equate to what they die with. Especially today most people are dying with chronic diseases and
multiple comorbidities. Right. So just because you may die from heart disease it doesn't mean
that you didn't have kidney disease or something moving towards kidney disease or diabetes. So I
think it's important to appreciate that there are that you can have multiple diseases and only one
of them is probably going to kill you. Having said that it is useful to think about do dogs die from
and with the same age related diseases that people do. And the answer is in general the
equivalency is pretty good. So dogs get all of the same age related diseases that people do. They
don't get them at the same frequency necessarily. So one big difference is in dogs there's actually
relatively little vascular disease which is a major killer in people. So specifically
atherosclerosis whether it be peripherally or cardiovascularly doesn't seem to be as prevalent.
Does not seem to be as prevalent. But there are breeds that die from from heart disease
and certain forms of heart disease. Cancer is probably the most common cause of death in dogs
and big dogs tend to get more cancers than small dogs. But across all dogs cancer is probably the
number one cause of death. Kidney disease is a major cause of death in dogs. Is the etiology
of that kidney disease related to blood pressure? Is it related to some other nephrotic syndrome
that's otherwise unidentified? I don't know the answer to that. Yeah I don't I don't have the
veterinary background to answer that. One of the things that's interesting in dogs is that there's
seems to be a little bit of a debate whether dogs really get Alzheimer's disease. They clearly get
dementia some dogs do and they clearly show cognitive decline. It's not completely clear
whether they get what would be clinically diagnosed as Alzheimer's disease in people.
Apparently they do accumulate a beta in the brain whether they get the plaques and tangles still
seems to be a little bit up in the air and there are people studying that. But at least at the level
of cognitive dysfunction and dementia it's clear that dogs experience that with age as well. So
for the most part they do develop the same age related diseases. The increase in risk for those
diseases goes up essentially exponentially just like in people. But the relative prevalence of
specific diseases is not always the same and can also be breed dependent. So there it is certainly
the case that within purebred dogs different breeds have different predispositions to certain
diseases which is exactly what you'd expect based on the genetics. So basically they're probably
getting a little more cancer significantly more renal failure as a proximate cause of death as
opposed to dying with renal insufficiency which to your point I think a lot of humans do. They're
getting a lot of heart disease but it sounds like it's more cardiomyopathy and or valvular disease
but not atherosclerotic or ischemic disease. And they unfortunately die of accidents just as humans
do which would still probably be in the top four for humans and dogs I'm guessing. Yeah and actually
that's an interesting point you're right. What I haven't seen great data on is the age distribution
of death due to trauma. I suspect it's going to be mostly younger dogs but I don't know for sure. So
that's actually an interesting question. It is absolutely true. The other thing that is worth
noting about dogs is it's actually the case that most pet dogs don't die from an age related disease.
They die from euthanasia which is a difference between dogs and people. Yes that's a great point.
Well let's turn the discussion now to what you do about this. I've been a big fan of rapamycin and
tor and that entire pathway for several years now. It's become almost an obsession. If one can have
an obsession that's not pathologic. And I think what attracted me to your work a couple of years
ago probably David Sabatini pointed me in your direction. So maybe three years ago it was actually
after the manic paper came out in 2014. Yeah 2014. Really interesting look at the human data.
I want to come back to that paper as it relates to immune function and stuff but maybe give us a
sense of how you decided that the next logical step was to actually test the god molecule as I
like to call it. Rapamycin in this context. In dogs yeah. Yeah so again this was all happening
about three years ago when I first sort of made the leap to thinking that we could test interventions
in dogs. And actually that's not at least for me was not an immediate it wasn't immediately
obvious to me that we should. So you really have to think as soon as you start talking about
bringing trial of a drug out of the lab and into the real world whether it's the human clinic or
the veterinary clinic in the context of aging you really have to start to think about safety
and side effects right because there is a very low tolerance for side effects when you're talking
about treating a healthy person or dog. So that was the first thing that I had to really
come to grips with is could we do this safely and especially you were thinking we're not going to
take dogs that are already sick. That's right. We were going to take healthy dogs. That's right. I
mean for me as somebody who is fundamentally interested in the biology of aging the intent
is to slow aging in people before they get sick right to keep them healthy longer. So in many
ways it's it's the opposite of traditional medical approach biomedical research right where normally
historically we wait until people are sick and then we try to cure their disease. This is the
reverse of that right. So that's right. So so because we are talking about intervening in a healthy
person or a dog the tolerance for side effects from a regulatory perspective or even just
public perception is very low when you're talking about a healthy person. Now you know the way I
view that first of all I think that is we need as a society and and within the scientific community
to have a discussion about this because I think that we need to recognize that a healthy
70 year old is not the same as a healthy 30 year old right. And we know what's going to happen if
we don't do anything about aging. So my personal view is that there should be a tolerance for some
level of risk if the outcome is going to be 10 percent 20 percent 30 percent more time spent
in good health. That's that's a discussion that we haven't had either at the regulatory level or at
the society wide level. But I think we need to have. So I digress a little bit but I had to know
I think I think that's one of the most important points you could make and I sort of think a lot
about this because my colleague and I were discussing this the other day which was you know
you take this oath at the end of medical school the Hippocratic oath when you first thing you learn
to say is first do no harm. And I think the spirit of that is excellent but I also think it's highly
impractical in a world where it forces you into binary thinking which is we will only undertake
interventions that are guaranteed to have no harm and otherwise we will do nothing regardless of the
outcome which of course is not practical. We live in a probabilistic world where the probability of
harm is not zero or one but rather it's a continuum between zero and one and you really
need to take a risk adjusted approach. That's right. To outcome. So I mean I think that's a
yeah that's exactly right. So I had to kind of go through that thought process in my own head though
and especially thinking about moving into pet dogs where because of the way that that many people
feel about their pet dogs you have to be as sure as you can that you're not going to hurt anybody's
pet. They like them more than their friends. Yeah absolutely right. Yeah people love their dogs.
A lot of people feel similarly about their dogs as they do about their kids right. So you kind of
think that's kind of the way I thought about it is could we do this in somebody's child. And so with
rapamycin there is a perception out there that I don't share but there's a perception out there
that rapamycin has lots of side effects based mostly on the human clinical literature. Which to
be clear is generally in transplant patients. Transplant patients taking high doses and taking
lots of other drugs. Yeah so sick people taking a high dose of rapamycin in combination with other
medications. Right. And it does have side effects. There's no question about that but one of the
things that's come out of my own research and other research in the field is that the both the
benefits and the side effects are strongly linked to dose. So one question was is there a dose of
rapamycin that will have beneficial effects in the context of healthy aging without significant
side effects. That was an unknown. I think that we're getting to the point where we're pretty sure
that that's the case. At least you can get some of the benefits of rapamycin and we can talk more
about the data that support that. But at that point it really wasn't really wasn't clear. And
when you say the dose do you think that the peak or the trough play a bigger role in toxicity. Yeah
so that's that's still an unknown but I think the data that are out there suggest that the trough
levels are most strongly correlated with side effects. Now what is most strongly related to
health span or lifespan. There's no data as far as I know. And this is an area where I think there's
a lot of work that could be done and should be done exploring more broadly even in laboratory
animals and mice. The sort of dose response and dose timing space for where do you get the
biggest effects on lifespan or specific measures of health. Where don't you get any effects. Can
you uncouple say the improvements in heart function from the improvements in immune function
by changing the dose or the timing. There really has been very little done on that. Now maybe for
the listener who's not familiar with the pharmacokinetic discussion let's explain maybe
trough and peak. How do we think about those dose. Yeah so when you give a medication to a
rapamycin pill when a person takes a rapamycin pill there will be a rapid increase in the levels
of the drug in the blood. And if they don't take another dose then the drug will start to get
cleared and it will go down. And so if you're taking a pill every day as soon as you take the
pill the blood levels go up and then it starts to get cleared and then the next day you take the
pill it goes up and then it starts to get cleared. So if you were to take the pill every other day
it would go down further before you get that spike again. So the spike the top of the spike
is the peak level the bottom before you take the next dose is the trough. And so the little bit of
data that's available and again there's not much data for different doses of rapamycin in people
who are not also taking other drugs. So the combination here is both dose and rapamycin
as a monotherapy. And so really the only study that I know of that looked at this really at all
actually didn't even use rapamycin they used a derivative of rapamycin called RAD001 or
Everalymus that's the manic study that we talked about. So there's really no good data in people
on different doses of rapamycin as a monotherapy in healthy people. So we're kind of stuck looking
at the data that we have. So in Joan's study with Everalymus or RAD001 they gave the medication to
healthy elderly people and they tested three dose and delivery combinations. So one of them was I
believe 20 milligrams once a week one of them was five milligrams once a week and one of them was
one milligram a day. Right and this was looking in the context of immune function as measured by a
flu vaccine response. So the outcomes were that I think at all three doses they saw evidence for
improved vaccine response which was consistent with prior data in mice that immune function is
improved by rapamycin. Pause for a moment that's still a bit counterintuitive to the layperson.
When I say the layperson I mean like the layperson who still thinks about rapamycin. Or actually lots
of physicians. Sure because we think of this as an immune suppressant and yet they took this drug
in monotherapy under a different dosing schedule than a transplant patient would take it and we saw
an improvement in their T cell function. The same cells that we tend to knock out in a transplant
patient. Right yeah so let's come back to that because that I think is that's an important issue
but it's complicated. Just to come back to the the trough levels and side effects so they saw evidence
for efficacy with every delivery method although they got I think the best efficacy at the five
once a week but they also had the lowest side effects and the most side effects were the ones
every day or the 20s once a week. I think it was in the 20s once a week but I can't remember for sure.
It was pretty comparable. So the first thing to say is none of the side effects were bad by
clinical standards. None of the people dropped out of the study because they were taking the drug
which is I think a pretty good indication for how tolerable the drug is. So even though they did
detect some side effects they really were not serious. They weren't even serious enough that
they were uncomfortable and people stopped taking the drug. So I think that that's really the only
evidence that we have that I know of that it's really the trough levels that drive side effects.
So I kind of think that's probably true but I'm not confident and I really think we need more data
to know for sure. It's certainly true in other classes of drugs and when you look at
gentamicin for example and the ototoxicity or nephrotoxicity it's a trough problem not a peak
problem. Right. That's why you have to make sure the patients clear it before you redose it.
So there's there are other reasons to believe that as well. Yeah. So now coming back to this immune
function question. There was a washout. There was. So there's a couple things again there to
consider. So the data suggesting that rapamycin can act as an immunosuppressant again is almost
exclusively based on very well I shouldn't say very high doses higher doses than were tested in
the Novartis study in people who are also taking other drugs that probably are true immunosuppressants.
Typically at least two if not three other drugs. That's right. So it's really not clear to what
extent rapamycin as a monotherapy in healthy people has immunosuppressive properties and the
data in mice I would say is mixed. It really seems to be the case then for some forms of
immune challenge at high doses rapamycin can enhance susceptibility to infection for other
forms of immune challenge it enhances function. But again those studies are almost always done
at very high doses of the drug that are even much higher than you would give to a person. So it's
it's an unknown. Now what seems to be the case both in mice and people is that short term
treatment with rapamycin in an old mouse or an old person followed by a two week washout where
they stop taking the drug when you then test immune function at least as measured by a vaccine
response you get a better response. So one model would be that the treatment with rapamycin is
restoring immune function in an aged animal probably through enhanced stem cell function
although I don't I think that that hasn't really been demonstrated clearly and you might need that
washout period if there is an immunosuppressive effect you might need that washout period to be
able to see that rejuvenation in immune function. Again that's really speculative though because
nobody's done. In Jones paper did they do I'm sure they didn't actually know that I think about it
they didn't have enough people in the study would have been very interesting to have seen the immune
challenge without the washout. Yeah they didn't do that. Now I was just going to say nobody's done it in either mice or in people.
That actually would be a fairly easy experiment to do in mice. The problem is you would never get an NIH study
section to fund that experiment because we already kind of know the answer that it that rapamycin works.
They wouldn't be viewed as an even though it's really important from a translational perspective
it wouldn't be viewed as innovative or important enough for somebody to fund a grant to do it.
So it's it's an unknown and I don't know how long it'll be till we actually get the answer for that question.
Now bringing it back to the dogs one of the challenges of course in leaping from mice to dogs is
mortality becomes difficult to study. You have an animal that lives a lot longer whereas mice you know
you can get a longevity answer in you know months if you select them correctly and dogs if you want to study them for true
heart outcome of you know death. So you pick a proxy. Well you can. Yeah yeah I'm saying I'm
saying like the shortest path would be let's look at organ function or something else. Right so what we did
so we've done one study where it was a 10-week study of rapamycin in middle-aged healthy companion
dogs and we chose heart function as our short-term measure and that again was based on mouse data where
two different actually three different labs now have shown that if you take a 20 to 24-month-old
mouse that's maybe the that's like a 40-year-old no it's more like a 60 to 65-year-old person
that if you just look at the heart of a 24-month-old mouse compared to let's say a six-month-old mouse
you can see declines in heart function just like you can in people and and the parameters that have
been studied with the respect to rapamycin specifically are mostly measures of left ventricular
function so ejection fraction fractional shortening things like that and this is done by echocardiography
so it's relatively non-invasive so you can see a decline in function with age and what what has
been seen now in three independent studies is that six to ten weeks of treatment with rapamycin is
enough to cause those measures of heart function in the old mouse to go back about halfway to what
you would see in a young mouse so it doesn't bring you all the way back to a teenager but it
gets you back to you know maybe a 35-year-old heart if you're doing the sort of mouse to human
equivalency and just to be clear that was how many weeks so the studies have varied is between six
and ten weeks all of them saw improvements it's not clear whether you get bigger improvements by
longer treatments so it's kind of in that range and did these animals also require a washout to
see the benefit no no washout so these are measures of heart function taken while the mice are still
on the rapamycin and these animals were dosed daily so yes all three of those studies used the
encapsulated rapamycin in the diet so they were getting the drug daily and it was not and this is
where it gets a little bit complicated because i'd say 85 percent of the studies on aging or age
related functional measures in mice with rapamycin have been done with an encapsulated form of
rapamycin in the diet we call it e-rapa and so that's different from a pill right because mice
are going to eat throughout the night so they're probably not experiencing exactly the same
pharmacokinetics that you would experience from a pill or the other kinds of experiments that
people have done in mice have been injections where you get you know this rapid peak in the drug
and then a pretty steep drop off as the drug starts to get cleared and nobody's ever done the
like the 24-hour measures of rapamycin blood level on the mice getting e-rapa so i don't know
how different it is but it's probably different in the sense that it's probably a more stable
level of rapamycin in the blood for a longer period of time i mean i would expect that the
e-rapa animals are going to have lower peaks and higher troughs i mean that would be that would be
the expectation yes but i don't know that anybody's ever really carefully looked at that so having
said that i think all three of the studies that looked at heart function in mice used the e-rapa
and it was a pretty low dose of the the how many milligrams per kilogram it's 14 parts per million
food i don't remember off the top of my head what that works out to in milligrams per kilogram
i feel like it's in the about the two range wow but much well yeah but again you have to you have
to keep in mind that you can't translate the dosing across species very well two milligrams
per kilogram in a mouse is not going to be the same as two milligrams per kilogram in a person
or it doesn't happen because the dogs and the humans i suspect are probably a lot closer than the
you would think so although i don't know that there's actually good evidence to
to support that so certainly in terms of body size if you're talking about a bigger dog they're
they're closer in terms of metabolism of the drug though that i imagine could vary it's
hepatically clear species i don't know that's a good question i'm pretty sure it's not really
p450 yeah it's if it's going to be in the liver so how did you ultimately come up with both a
dose and a schedule of delivery for your first trial so this again goes back to this question
that i was asking myself about can we do this safely and there's very little data in dogs on
rapamycin at all and just like in people there's almost none on rapamycin as a monotherapy in
healthy animals so i started you know basically digging and talking to as many veterinarians as
i could to find out what was known and i was very fortunate to actually be able to get in touch with
a veterinary group at the university of tennessee who was studying rapamycin in dogs who had had
hemangiosarcoma of the spleen and so they had done the pharmacokinetics and had developed a dosing
strategy that they feel is extending life expectancy in dogs who have had hemangiosarcoma of the spleen
and where they weren't seeing side effects and they had had some of their dogs on rapamycin for
more than a year so so we were pretty confident or i was pretty confident after talking to them
that if we took their dosing strategy that were unlikely to see any significant side effects over
a 10-week period and so i said that cardiac function was the functional endpoint that we
were using really the goal of that 10-week study though was to confirm this is a phase one basically
that we could do this that we could get people to participate they would actually give their
dog the medication and that we didn't see any significant side effects so i was pretty confident
that based on their dosing and delivery protocol we at least wouldn't see any severe side effects
in a 10-week period. Did the nih fund that study? Well not directly so we got a little bit of nih
money because we have one of these nathan shock centers of excellence in the biology of aging and
we had a small amount it was on the order of a few tens of thousands of dollars left over from
the prior year and so i asked uh Felipe Sierra who's the head of the division of aging biology
at nih if we could use that surplus specifically for this project and he was he was kind enough to
to agree to that but it wasn't we didn't write a grant and get a grant. But you sort of bootstrap
this thing. Yeah so actually i paid for this study mostly out of funds that i had gotten because i
was recruited to get a job somewhere else and as part of my retention package the university of
washington gave me some money that i could spend on whatever i wanted to and i thought this was a
good way to spend the money. So what did that 10-week study show? Right so first of all i'll go back
to the dosing before i tell you that. Oh that's right yeah yeah. So so i talked to this group the
university of tennessee and so their strategy was 0.1 milligrams per kilogram given three times a week.
Okay. Monday, Wednesday, Friday and that made sense to me in light of the what we were just
talking about from the manic paper where it seems like if you give an extra day to let the trough
levels get down it made intuitive sense that that might also. Yeah you can reduce toxicity. Yeah so i don't
know that that's the case but but it made sense and so that was the dosing strategy that we went
with for our highest dose and then we also tested a dose that was half of that so 0.05 milligrams
per kilogram again monday wednesday friday. So we enrolled dogs into this study this was a very
small study all from at a private veterinary specialty clinic in the seattle area and so the
dogs had to be at least 40 pounds and at least six years old and they could not have any pre-existing
condition. So again this is a study of healthy aging we wanted healthy dogs coming into the
study. Six years old because at that weight range we figured that that would be you know roughly the
human equivalent of 55 years maybe big dogs age faster than small dogs so that's why we had the
weight criteria. So we wanted to have a population where we expected there would be the potential for
some age-related functional decline but that we wouldn't get a high proportion of dogs. Yeah you
don't be too close to the edge of the cliff. That's right that we're really sick. So one thing we
we found though that was unexpected was that about 20 percent of dogs in that age and weight range
actually have asymptomatic heart disease that you will see if you give them an echocardiogram
but you won't detect from a stethoscope exam and that was in hindsight it kind of makes sense right
again heart function is going to go down with age and where you decline like what is the clinical
threshold that we call disease is sort of a moving target sometimes right. If a vet with a stethoscope
takes a heart murmur and then they give the dog an echocardiogram and they see regurgitation they'll
call that heart disease. If they don't hear a heart murmur nobody's going to give their dog an
echocardiogram right it's expensive. Yeah and I'm not a cardiologist but I can't imagine the day
would ever come where using a stethoscope I could detect you know a low EF like to the tone of right
yeah I mean unless you would not get that no no it's really the regurgitation that they're hearing
as a heart murmur and and that was most of most of the dogs that we ended up having to exclude
we had to exclude because they had a pre-existing value of regurgitation that came out from the
echocardiogram but this was actually a discussion that we had to have with the cardiologist you know
the cardiologist initially went into the study with the feeling that if there's any regurgitation
that's beyond trivial that that's heart disease and so when we started to see dog after dog show
up with this level of regurgitation we had to have this discussion what's normal aging versus
disease right and right and so just because of the way that the protocol was written we ended up
having to exclude about 20 percent of dogs because they had underlying heart disease so so we had 40
dogs come into the study for their first exam that was our target number we ended up having 24 go all
the way through the study most three groups two doses plus a placebo yeah yeah and they ended up
not being evenly distributed and in part this was this was because in part is because it was my
first clinical trial that I'd ever done and I didn't didn't plan for the fact that we would
have to exclude as many dogs as we did so the way it ended up was we had eight eight placebo 11 high
dose and five medium lower dose yeah right that went all the way through we only had one dog leave
the study and that was because the owner just stopped giving their dog the medication and we
had one dog where the owner gave their dog the wrong amount of the medication which ironically
enough wrong in which direction low so the dog was randomized into the high rapamycin group and
ended up getting one quarter of the expected dose so other than that there was fantastic
compliance all of the owners did what they were supposed to came in for their exams so the main
outcomes of this study were one there was no evidence for increased side effects so the owners
filled out weekly surveys that there was a long list of the dogs didn't fill them yeah well you
never know there was a long list of did your dog experience any of these things and then there were
a couple of just open-ended questions you know do you feel like you observed any positive changes
or negative changes in health did the group in tennessee see the apthos ulcers in their dogs
because that seems to be i remember as a resident when we would give rapamycin
to the kidney transplant patients i mean the biggest complaint by far was those apthos ulcers
yeah and we didn't again in hindsight we we probably should have done a better job of looking
but we did not have any evidence that that that was happening the only thing that initially i
thought that maybe we were detecting that was because we had several owners then this was while
the study was still blinded so i didn't know which dogs were which at this point we had several owners
report that their dog was drinking a lot more water and a couple of them actually came in for
urinalysis and stuff like that and so i thought maybe that that could be like a dog's response
if they have sores on the inside of their mouth and they're uncomfortable maybe that would be the
sort of the canine equivalent of how they would respond to that as it turns out though when we
unblinded the study that reported observation of increased water consumption was equally spread
between the placebo and rapamycin group so i don't know if that's happening in dogs that's
something we'll look at in the next phase so again for all of the side effects though that we
surveyed owners on no difference between treated and untreated the blood chemistry showed no
significant changes with rapamycin which was actually a little bit surprising did you do a
glucose tolerance test we did not do any we did not do a glucose tolerance test in part because
we wanted to keep the the number of assays that we were asking the owners to subject their dogs to
as small as possible make it as non non-invasive as possible for the animals we did get blood
chemistry at at week you know before randomization at week three and at week 11 so within one week
of coming out of the study and we saw improvements in heart function now i will say it's a small
cohort they were on sort of a borderline of statistical significance so two of the three
measures that we had as our primary end points the three measures were ejection fraction fractional
shortening and e to a ratio and again that was just coming directly from the mouse studies two
of those three were statistically significant one was p value of 0.06 yeah but i mean you must
have been underpowered on absolutely anything absolutely yeah it's amazing you saw i agree i
agree yeah so i think the way i view this is it's it's about the most positive outcome that that we
could have hoped for clearly needs to be replicated but at least the changes are going in the right
direction and an interesting couple of interesting things when you actually look at the heart data
it very much looks like the dogs on rap mice and they got the biggest benefits were the ones that
started with the lowest function which is not surprising but that also is encouraging because
that's that's kind of what you'd expect right the dogs that have undergone a greater age related
decline are likely to be the ones that are going to get the biggest benefit from a treatment that's
actually affecting that so that was really encouraging and then we actually had one
doberman pincher in the study and this turned out to be interesting because doberman pinchers as a
breed are highly prone to dilated cardiomyopathy something like 60 65 percent of doberman pinchers
will develop dilated cardiomyopathy as they get older i wasn't really aware of this literature
going into the study um but it turns out that many doberman pincher owners will actually give their
dogs echocardiograms or electrocardiograms routinely as they're getting older to try to detect
dilated cardiomyopathy as early as possible and this the owner of this dog didn't tell us this
before she came into the study had actually been aware of this and was giving her dog
echocardiograms before coming into the study that dog had low cardiac function but it was not yet to
the point where it was clinically diagnosed as dilated cardiomyopathy so our cardiologist in
the study also not knowing the dog's history of of having prior echoes did not flag the dog as
needing to be excluded so the dog was randomized it just happened to be randomized into the higher
rapamycin dose and its function was that was one of the dogs where we saw the largest improvement
in function what is interesting about that is the owner then after the study was over
continued to get echocardiograms every three months and has shared that information with us
and so it's really it's an n of one but it's a really fascinating sort of case study because
you can see the dog's cardiac function declining then the dog comes into the study gets rapamycin
it shoots up it's quite a dramatic increase and then within about what was the increase in ef do
you remember i don't remember i don't want to say the exact number because i don't remember it sounds
like it was a big deal it was from the borderline of being a cult dilated cardiomyopathy up at least
10 10 percent 10 percent yeah 10 absolute percent that's right that's enormous yeah well
inked back into the normal range yeah and has that patient or that patient has that woman shared with
you what the resulting decline in ef has been since the trial so about i've got the data out
to about six months and and we're just now trying to reconnect with her to see if if she has
additional data that she'll share with us by about six months out the ejection fraction and
fractional shortening were back right at the point when the dog came into the study and at
that point her cardiologist diagnosed the dog is called dcm so so clearly going down the path to
dilated cardiomyopathy so the million dollar question in a study like that or in a case like
that is if you had to guess what would be the ideal way to take care of that dog to delay the
onset of cardiomyopathy as long as possible would it be just keep this dog on that dose three times
a week in perpetuity would it be give the dog a 10-week holiday 10 on 10 off 10 on 10 off right so
it's clearly 10 on every six months is just a seesaw if everything is working the way that
that yeah we think it is yeah my guess is that the default there would be to keep the dog on the
drug unless you start to see side effects right so so continue to monitor by echoes every three months
and unless you see side effects or unless you see something else that makes you worried that rap
my son is is having a negative effect just keep the dog on on the drug but you know it's an
unknown as to whether we would eventually see side effects at that dose because you know as I said
the only data that I know of is that university of Tennessee group yeah where they did have some
dogs that survived more than a year and continued to take the drug those dogs you know as I said had
had hemangiosarcoma of the spleen they'd had surgeries you know they were very sick coming
into that study and so I don't know even if there were mild side effects that you would really be
able to yeah to tease that apart from everything else that's going on with those dogs there are
other larger mammal studies that are going on correct with rapamycin specifically so there are
well so so there are research studies in the context of aging in marmosets they're very small
and and very early but but those are being done at the university of
san antonio yeah texas san antonio the bar shop institute and then there are a variety of cancer
studies in dogs with rapamycin so there's a large study of rapamycin for osteosarcoma in dogs and
then there are a few smaller clinical trials but I don't know of any other large animal studies in
the context of aging anti-agent yeah yeah now I want to obviously come back to the anti-aging
and the dogs but on the cancer topic there are some data that are actually suggesting
that the increase in autophagy that one might see with rapamycin which one would expect to see
at least with m torque one inhibition might be paradoxically not ideal in the active setting of
cancer right so I guess my first question is are you swayed by those data and if so
what would be the teleologic explanation yeah so I'll say I'm not swayed much I think it's I think
that those kind of data are important to be aware of I think one of the real challenges in the
autophagy field is that not everybody that we can't measure it well I was any one of them yeah
beside the fact that we can't we don't really know how to measure it I think as a as a community
we really don't know what we mean when we say that autophagy is increased or decreased different
people use different markers or measures for for autophagy so my view is that one of the things
that can happen not just for cancers but for lots of different pathologies is one of the ways that
cells try to deal with many different forms of stress in particular protein misfolding but also
other forms of stress is to turn up autophagy so I think that autophagy some markers of autophagy
going up can be a response to a pathological condition also what often happens is that
response of turning up autophagy does not lead to productive autophagy so you actually get an
accumulation of autophagosomes because they don't ever make it all the way through the process
and so depending on how you're measuring autophagy what you really might be detecting is a block
at the late stages of autophagy and what you're seeing is you're measuring a backlog that's right
so it's not necessarily the case that more autophagy is bad in that context it's the failure to
actually the through bring it through to completion and again I don't have a lot of data to support
this my intuition is that at least for some diseases one of the things that rapamycin does
and I don't really understand the molecular biology here it seems to alleviate that block
so you actually get productive autophagy working again and again I don't know exactly how that
works but that's what it seems to me is happening and so we have seen some evidence for this in
mitochondrial disease in the brain where if we look in the brain we can see these sort of massive
autophagosomes that are trying to digest mitochondria that can't do it while the disease
is progressing and somehow rapamycin fixes that so I think you have to be cautious in interpreting
an increase in autophagic markers in a disease as necessarily meaning that increased autophagy is
causing or contributing to that disease and it could be the case that depending on how you
activate autophagy it could be detrimental or it could be beneficial and so there's really two
different questions the first would be if you take a patient with cancer and you inhibit mTOR
is it not helpful because the tumor has already evolved so much to be outside of mTOR's purview
or is it it's actually harmful and that's of course separate from the option that could be helpful
right so my understanding of the clinical and the literature in humans is that for most cancers
once it's reached the point of diagnosis that rapamycin is disappointing in its effectiveness
it's not particularly effective that's not true for all cancers but for most cancers it has not
been as effective as you might expect given that we know that activation of mTOR is common
when you get high proliferation and then turning down mTOR should stop that. Turn off the proliferation.
Yeah so I think I think you're probably right that at least part of the story is that one of
the steps in the progression to cancer is evolving to ignore the break of turning down mTOR
so rapamycin may not be effective there. I think it's a complicated system though because the
effects of rapamycin on the immune system could have beneficial effects in terms of cancer or
detrimental effects so we know that immune surveillance is probably the most important
anti-cancer mechanism or certainly one of the most important anti-cancer mechanisms and we know that
immune function goes down with age that's probably one of the reasons why most cancers are age related
so if you can boost age-related immune function with rapamycin enhance immune surveillance that's
going to have a potent anti-cancer mechanism and again this is my guess my guess is that's why we
see in the studies in mice that cancers are pushed back during aging by rapamycin. On the other hand
if the dose of rapamycin is high enough that you're actually inhibiting immune function that
could be that could promote cancers and there's not a lot of data yet so we did one study in my
lab where we gave mice I think it's the highest dose that's ever been given in the context of an
aging study this was a daily injection of eight milligrams per kilogram so as we call it the party
dose yeah right right and so this was a study where we only gave the mice rapamycin for three
months so this was from 20 to 23 months and then we stopped the treatment and what was interesting
there was we got completely different effects in male mice versus female mice the male mice
lived 60% longer after the end of treatment they had better muscle function they got less cancer
the female mice had no difference in lifespan the mice that got rapamycin or didn't get rapamycin
but they died with I want to say from but it's hard to say for sure what a mouse dies from they
died with very different types of cancers so the female mice that had gotten this high dose of
rapamycin for three months all had aggressive hematopoietic cancers whereas about I think it
was about 30 or 40 percent of the vehicle treated mice so in black six that's not an uncommon cancer
to get but none of the rapamycin treated mice had non-hematopoietic cancers whereas like 60 percent
of the mice that didn't get rapamycin now the 2009 study that kicked all this off actually showed a
greater survival benefit in the female mice didn't it that's right so I think and again this is a guess
because I don't actually have the data to back it up my guess is that because we pushed the dose so
high we might have actually taken it too far in the female so one school of thought is that female
mice at least we don't know if this is true in any other organism female mice are more sensitive to
rapamycin and that could either be that they don't clear the drug as quickly or that for whatever
reason in female mice the same amount of rapamycin has a greater mTOR inhibitory effect but that's
one school of thought and I kind of think that's right so at lower doses of the drug you see a
bigger lifespan benefit in females than in males did you repeat that experiment at like four
megs per gig or something different we haven't we haven't we should so we did do we just need an
infinite pool of money I agree to do all of these like just to answer all these questions
figure out the most important questions yeah and I think the dose response is really important
we did do a lower dose for three months as well and there we saw increases in lifespan in both
males and females roughly the same magnitude so it was that dose was nine times higher than what
the ITP tested wow so one of the things that's interesting though is as you go higher in dose
so three times higher than what they originally tested the females still live a little bit longer
but the difference between males and females the gap has closed quite a bit so I think that females
for whatever reason at a given concentration of rapamycin are just more affected by that
amount of the drug and I think what we did in our high dose study is we just pushed it a little too
far we pushed it to the point where rapamycin did something probably to the immune system
that that allowed these immune cancers to to escape surveillance or become hyperproliferative and again
I'm not I'm not a cancer biologist I'm not an immunologist so I don't I don't have a good
feel for what the mechanism is I can tell you what the observation is and that's that all of
those animals had aggressive hematopoietic cancers when they got this three months of rapamycin
just out of curiosity more B cell or T cell do you recall I don't recall it's in the paper
we could look it up because there's an opportunity here to do the reverse right I mean there's an
opportunity to take right now we're seeing just an unbelievable amount of activity in adoptive cell
therapy and or even when you just talk about like checkpoint inhibitors and things like that like
it makes you wonder are there ways to make these things better maybe the checkpoint's the wrong
example because you might get more autoimmunity but but certainly when you talk about adoptive
cell therapy anything that could boost either you know cda function or inhibit the regs or something
there might be ways like it almost makes you wonder if using rapamycin in a different manner
in combination with immune-based therapy right might make more sense yeah no I think there's
a lot that could be done there for sure part of the reason why we haven't explored this
in more detail of one reason is again as I said I'm not a cancer biologist so it's not that's not
the thing I'm most interested in I think it's really interesting biology but it's not the thing
I'm most interested in but I also feel like because the dose that we gave was so high that again
thinking translationally about rapamycin as as a drug in the context of aging my feeling is that
what we've uncovered here is not going to be relevant at the doses that we would think about
giving to you yeah yeah yeah so that's why I haven't really spent a lot of my time trying to
figure out what's going on there but I think certainly in the context of cancer immune
therapies I think we do need to think a little bit more about how effective those kinds of therapies
are going to be in the elderly and maybe something like rapamycin could help could actually enhance
the ability of those I mean this question you posed when when David Sabatini Tim Farris and
Nav Chindel and I were in Easter Island a year ago over a year ago this might have been our
favorite meal time discussion which is what best explains the increase in cancer incidence with age
being in other words what would the primary driver be the reduction in immune surveillance
or the length of time to accumulate mutations or the frequency of mutations like I mean yeah it's
not an obvious answer and I don't think it has to be just one no it's almost all those things are
working together yeah yeah I certainly over the last few years have come to think that the decline
in immune function is it's certainly more important than I had initially thought that that's my I mean
I secretly want that to be the biggest driver because I think we have a better chance to control
that yeah than some of the other ones and I think it probably is that would be my guess and I and
I also think it kind of makes sense that if you have an immune system that's functioning the way
it's supposed to you can actually deal with the mutation accumulation because your immune system
is going to clear those before they become yeah problems so now let's go back to the anti-aging
thesis right which is we're going to take healthy dogs eventually healthy people we want to reduce
the rate of decline is probably the best way to think about it right so we have a deterioration
in organ function okay all right one of the things that's been surprising to me again over
the last few years is the different ways that rapamycin not only seems to delay the decline
but it seems to make things better there clearly seems to be in at least some organs a rejuvenating
function and I suspect that's mostly stem cell mediated but again the mechanisms haven't been
worked out yet so we've already talked about immune function you can take an old immune system and
make it work more like a young immune system we've talked about cardiac function you can take an old
heart you make it work more like a young heart there's some evidence from David's lab that
intestinal stem cells okay can be rejuvenated by rapamycin we've recently published that alveolar
bone levels so in the mouth the bone around the teeth can be rejuvenated back to a more youthful
level by short-term treatment with rapamycin so there are now multiple different places in the
body at least in mice where you actually see functional improvements back to a more youthful
state and so I don't think rapamycin is going to do that for everything but at least for tissues
and organs where stem cell senescence plays a big role I suspect that rapamycin can have not just
an effect on delaying declines but actually bring things partially back towards a more youthful
functional state what's the best available evidence for that centrally in the cns
that's a good question so there are studies on cognitive function in mice showing that that you
can improve cognitive function in aged animals I believe at least one of those started the
treatment late in life and saw improvements in cognitive function and then in all of the major
alzheimer's disease mouse models you can the literature is a little bit mixed there's at least
evidence that you can wait until the pathology of the disease is set in you see the a beta
accumulated you see the functional deficits in terms of cognitive function you can start
the treatment and you can improve things and on post-mortem are you seeing an actual reduction
again yeah you are so I mean we haven't done this this is the work of several other labs in the ad
area yes so again the data is a little bit mixed so there are a couple of papers out there where
they they see that you can get really robust benefits if you start rapamycin treatment early
but they didn't see benefits in the ad models when you started late and then there are studies that
that did see declines in aggregation increased autophagy and functional improvements even when
you start like staggering if you could take an animal and ultimately of course a human who's
already accumulating ab and tau yeah and even just halting that is a big deal there's one drug
right in you know the yeah you're now you're going right into my biggest pet peeve right now
which is why there hasn't been or isn't a current rapamycin trial for alzheimer's disease but I
think you're right and I and again three years ago if somebody had asked me will rapamycin is it
likely to have any benefit in somebody who's been diagnosed with ad I would have probably said no
I come around to thinking that there's at least a reasonable chance that it cannot just halt
progression but it could actually make well especially if you you know one of our colleagues
is a neurologist here named Richard Isaacson and he runs the largest alzheimer's prevention clinic
in the country at Cornell you know Richard's thesis which I think makes a ton of sense is
again I think other people share this view is you want to catch people while they just have the
first signs of mild cognitive impairment sure absolutely and your ability to actually impact
them is enormous and and so the question is why aren't those people being considered for clinical
trials when we all already know that these other agents aren't really doing anything right yeah I
agree I think that if I was going to design a clinical trial for alzheimer's disease or dementia
with rapamycin that I thought had the best chance of success that would be the target population
those trials are harder to do in some ways because they're longer right and not everybody moves from
MCI to to full-blown AD at the same rate and we don't have at least my understanding is we still
really don't have great predictive biomarkers of how fast that's going to happen in an individual
but that would be the that would be the study that would have the best chance of working
having said that I still think there's a decent chance in somebody who's you know already gotten
to the point where where they will be diagnosed as having alzheimer's disease serious functional
deficits there's a chance that rapamycin could make things better now I get the practical reasons
for why people don't want to try a risky clinical trial it's expensive if you fail you know your
then your drug gets a bad reputation all of that so I understand why people are hesitant to do that
trial I think there's actually a pretty good chance it would especially if you can combine it I mean
I think you know Richard often talks about and and others do as well that one of our failures in
Alzheimer's is we consider it a single disease I agree it's as naive as saying John has cancer oh
well gosh that's the end of his life well don't you want to know what kind of cancer first or maybe
what mutation so similarly but broadly speaking and this is a gross oversimplification if you
consider the metabolic version of Alzheimer's disease the vascular version of Alzheimer's
disease and then the sort of toxin clearance impaired version of the disease to me I'm
generally most optimistic about the metabolic one so the variant of this disease that seems to be
mostly due to a failure of energy metabolism in the brain that also strikes me as the one that's
most amenable to certain systemic therapies as well right if you improve insulin sensitivity
if you improve glucose disposal if you reduce hypercordicillemia if you you can actually through
nutrition exercise sleep a number of other things start to modulate that that strikes me as the one
where you want to at least take your first shot at adding Rapa I think you're probably right
although again with Rapa mycen because we know that it is effective at for example turning up
autophagy it might also be it might work in the harder ones yeah that's a harder but I agree I
tend to agree with you I think that's a good point I also want to add that I actually think the
biggest problem with the way that the scientific community has thought about Alzheimer's disease
aside from considering it to be one disease is not really recognizing that it's a disease of aging
I really think that one of the reasons why the preclinical research has been disappointing at
developing therapies for Alzheimer's disease is because very rarely have people approach that
from the perspective that this is a disease of aging and so something that can affect the mouse
models of Alzheimer's disease when we create this disease in young mice may not work the same way in
in an in an aged person or an aged animal and that's one of the things that also makes me
optimistic about Rapa mycen is we already know that it hits the hallmarks of aging and it also
seems to be effective in these Alzheimer's disease models so that makes me think that it's acting at
a sort of a more fundamental level to target the molecular causes of this disease well especially
look I mean if you can regenerate a cardiac myocyte from its stem cell it's not an impossible
thought that you could regenerate neurologic stem cells absolutely and this is again an area which
which I mean 20 years ago we would have said that's impossible it's metaphysically impossible
right going back to the dogs for a moment I again I'm not familiar with dog literature
what is the fasting literature look like in dogs there's not a lot that I'm aware of either and I
think that kind of makes sense so you know first of all you have to differentiate the literature
in laboratory colonies from companion companion dogs there's probably not much in companion dogs
I don't know of true fasting experiments in like beetle so we can't use like the fasted versions as
proxies for what we would hope to see on the Rapa dogs which is the way they sort of did it in mice
right they sort of said well you know we know that if you calorically restrict this mouse
this strain of mouse under this degree of caloric restriction can expect as much of a longevity
boost and oh lo and behold rapamycin is probably even better than that right although from a
metabolic perspective I think it's still unclear even in mice whether rapamycin and caloric
restriction are working through the same mechanism and this is this is this is actually another area
where there haven't been a lot of good experiments done so there's a portion of the field that argues
strongly that that caloric restriction and rapamycin are completely different which to my
mind is absurd I mean we know that one of the main things that caloric restriction does is it
inhibits mTOR right and we know that rapamycin inhibits mTOR so they're not fundamentally
different so I think they are overlapping but distinct not everything that caloric restriction
does is going to be mimicked by rapamycin and vice versa having said that when you look at the gene
expression profile or the metabolic profile they don't look all that similar at least at the low
doses of rapamycin and so I think it's it's a little bit unclear you're right lifespan they both
extend lifespan rapamycin might actually extend lifespan across a broader genetic background
than caloric restriction but when you get beyond that I think it's still an unknown whether there
are you know say are there metabolic signatures that are common to both that might therefore be
more likely to be causal I think I think we don't know the answer so another what you're really
getting at is probably the next thought I had subconsciously which is could we use calorically
restricted animals to develop a metabolic signature as the gold standard for how we would then
titrate rapamycin both in dose and frequency I don't know of any evidence to support that
would be a stretch yeah I mean it might be possible but there just isn't much good data out there at
this point I do feel like if we want to put the resources into trying to identify predictive
signatures which I absolutely think we should do I think the the metabolome is probably the place to
to go and the serum metabolome makes a lot of sense so that would be where I would look
nobody's really done it well part of the problem is the data that's out there for rapamycin is again
all at that very low dose that the ITP tested originally we know that suboptimal for lifespan
it's quite likely that the effects that the lowest dose of rapamycin are having on metabolism
are going to be relatively modest compared to higher doses so you the changes might be there
but they might be so subtle that you're not going to detect them in a sort of high throughput
screening approach so so I think there's a lot we don't know but that would be where I would
put my effort in trying to identify serum metabolomic signature yep of rapamycin that
we could then correlate with the effects on function in a variety of different tissues as
well as life yeah because I mean I think as wonderful as it would be to just wave magic
ones and have biopsies of tissue it's just not going to be I mean we're not going to take
cardiac biopsies yeah right so you if you're looking for predictive signatures you can do
those experiments initially in mice but you really have to think about is this something
that's reasonable to do in a person or a dog and have you looked at the gut biome and the
dog at all a little bit so so we did a study in mice this was that that study I referred to
previously where we treated them for three months with either the high high dose or the the high but
not as high dose yeah and we did look at the fecal microbiome and we saw quite dramatic changes
there some of which are interesting and so that's that's an area that we would love to pursue I've
tried to get a grant to do that and so far haven't been successful through NIH but it hasn't been
done in dogs yet has not been done in dogs so we have a little bit of preliminary data from our
phase one study and we're seeing changes in the microbiome there as well so far the data that
we've got in dogs is not the sort of comprehensive metagenomic approach where we sequence everything
that's there it's more of a standard veterinary approach where they they have sort of broad
classifications of different types of microbes and there are definitely changes with rapamycin
it looks it's very early but it looks as though at least in dogs that have a a bad microbiome a
dysbiosis in their microbiome which can be defined clinically from this test there were two dogs that
we've looked at that started out with a bad microbiome they were in the rapamycin group
they were better by the end of the study obviously don't know if that's meaningful or not so so there
are changes in the dogs but it's really too early for us to know whether they look like the mice
and or whether that is going to either be predictive or potentially play a role in some
of the effects of rapamycin it is definitely the case though in both dogs and mice and i'm sure
this will be true in people as well that rapamycin has a large effect on the composition of the gut
microbiome i suspect that will also be true for other compartments in the body like the oral
microbiome maybe even the skin microbiome nobody's looked yet so that there's a lot to be done there
i also don't necessarily think that's going to be unique to rapamycin i think that lots of drugs
that we take yeah food will change that and absolutely diet and it's not clear if that's the
effect or the cause of it yeah so one of the reasons why i think that there's reason to think
that at least some of the changes in the microbiome could be causal for some of the effects of
rapamycin is that one of the things we saw in our mouse study was a pretty profound increase in a
bacterium called segmented filamentous bacteria or sfb in the rapamycin treated mice it turns out
if you look in the literature there are links between sfb and diabetes and obesity and also
between sfb and t helper cell maturation so it could be the the case that changes that rapamycin
is having on this specific bacterium as well as other bacteria are then having effects both on
potentially nutrient utilization and uptake but also direct effects on say immune function i mean
the intestine is an important immune compartment the bacteria are physically right there these sfb
actually form filaments directly associated with the intestinal cells so it certainly could be the
case that there are signals being sent back and forth that rapamycin is modifying by through
modification of the composition of the microbiome and that that's affecting immune function
adiposity all sorts of different possibilities so like i said that's something we're really
interested in in testing so there's like an infinite number of things i want to know right
yeah there's this company out there that's looking at duodenal ablation to ameliorate diabetes and
the data are actually really interesting so interesting in fact that when i first saw them
i thought this has got to be nonsense what's not clear is the durability and the economics of it
just from a scientific standpoint they're doing these ablations of the duodenal mucosa and they're
seeing like immediate step function changes in insulin sensitivity arguing in fact that this
may be the mechanism by which the rue and y gastric bypass is ameliorating type 2 diabetes
it's basically taking this dysfunctional duodenum out of the loop and just saying we're going
jejunum to jejunum or you know stomach to jejunum to jejunum basically it's really
interesting so this is another area that i've gotten interested in and and we haven't really
dove into it yet much but i i think there is there's clearly uh literature growing in
all of the model organisms that with aging there is a decline in intestinal barrier function
and that at least in flies that seems to be causal for death so in other words it's strongly
correlated and there are ways every way that extends lifespan also seems to improve this
intestinal barrier dysfunction and i've been thinking and we have again a little bit of data
suggesting that rapamycin might actually have an effect on this age-related decline in intestinal
barrier function and why would a loss of intestinal barrier function be important well i mean one thing
that happens we know this happens is that you tend to see an increased level of microbial proteins
and dna in the circulatory system with age that causes a inflammatory response that may contribute
to the sort of systemic increase in inflammation that we see during aging so the loss of intestinal
barrier function may actually drive to some extent the inflammaging the increase in inflammation with
aging or at least contribute to it and so anything that you can do that is going to improve that
will potentially have an effect on systemic inflammation and that again could be another way
that rapamycin is sort of impacting the entire body in addition to the effects of rapamycin when
it gets to a cell and inhibits emitter in that cell and whether that's through changes in the
microbiome you know or changes in intestinal stem cell like zavatini has shown right there's lots of
possible ways that it could be working but i do believe that this decline in intestinal barrier
function with age probably is contributing to this sort of increase in in systemic inflammation
that we see during aging and there it's very clear that that happens in in people and in non-human
primates as well during aging now talking about people again i don't hold out much hope that
there's going to be an anti-aging trial in humans using rapamycin or a rapalog you know watching
how much difficulty it is to even try to get that study done with metformin which i mean is
about the most inert you know it's like you might as well just do it with drinking water right and
we're going to randomize you to seltzer versus flat water here so the real question is for the
people who want to be on the tip of the spear you're not going to have a gold-plated stamped rct
you're going to have to triangulate from everything else many roads point to your work and more
importantly what your follow-up work will look like right so again i realize that to try to secure
funding to do this from nih is slightly more complicated than trying to get bipartisan support
on health care but if we took the economics out of the equation if if there was a 10 to 20 million
dollar pool at the national institutes of aging said you know dr caberlin we want to we want the
definitive work on how to extend the life of dogs knowing that that's probably the best thing
we're going to get right towards humans what do those experiments look like right so so the study
that we want to do is a five-year study with rapamycin and and certainly this is scalable
right so so what we have designed is a study with rapamycin there are other interventions
coming down the pipeline that i think have the potential to be as effective as rapamycin so this
doesn't necessarily as long as you can do it safely in pet dogs yeah you can test any intervention
and one of the things that i am now convinced is owners are enthusiastic about participating in
these kinds of studies we've had more than 6 000 people sign up through our website with no
advertising at all to participate in the rapamycin trial in human clinical trials which i'm more
familiar with recruiting cost is a is an enormous cost it doesn't cost anything you get free
recruitment right right so having said that the study we would like to do is a five-year study
in dogs starting treatment at middle age so again the dogs would come in you know at least
six years old we might push that up to seven or eight years old and they there would probably be
a weight limiter like i talked about before because again big dogs age faster so let's just say 40
pounds six years old at least six years old so there will be dogs anywhere from six to 10 or 11
bring in 450 500 dogs or enough dogs to get 450 all the way through the study and look at not just
lifespan but lifespan is actually a really important metric here right lifespan is certainly
still the gold standard in the aging field if we want to convince the scientific community that
this is affecting aging it darn well better increased lifespan yep it's also important to
owners for obvious reasons and i think because as we talked about euthanasia is really what most dogs
die from because the dog gets sick enough that the owner and the veterinarian decide that it's time
to put the dog down yeah i think lifespan is actually a really good metric of health span
in dogs because most of the time that's not an easy decision right absolutely owners are not
going to put their dog down usually especially owners who want to participate in a study like
this unless that dog is really sick so i actually think lifespan is really maybe more important in
dogs as an outcome measure than it is in mice so lifespan is one of the key end points that we want
to look at and then we want to look as broadly as we can at functional measures of aging that we
know are important in dogs and so this goes way back to what we were talking about before what
do dogs get sick with as they get older so heart function we will definitely look at in part
because that's what our preliminary data yeah you showed that with a handful of dogs we have good
evidence that we can detect and expect to detect improvements in cardiac function activity so one
of the nice things about dogs is you can put a gps tracker on their collar and get very quantitative
measures of activity as the sensor technology improves it might be feasible to use a microchip
instead of a gps tracker on the collar to also get some physiological or just draw a fitbit on
their wrist you know yeah right well i mean that's really what the trackers are right of course but
it would be nice to get some physiological measures in sort of continuous real time if we
can so far the sensor technology isn't quite there at least that's my understanding but
well at least get activity and that'll give us a measure both of things like arthritis so dogs
that have arthritis are going to be less active and also muscle function and also how how well
are they feeling again a dog is more likely to be active if it feels well now obviously that's
confounded a little bit by whether the owner takes the dog for a walk but i still think total
activity is an important thing and is this a three group study in your mind so the study
that we're designing now is three groups it doesn't have to be but the three groups are a placebo
group uh short term group so six month or year long treatment and then the continuous treatment
group the reason for doing that again comes back to the mouse data in part because we as i mentioned
we've published that a short term treatment in mice is enough to give you large benefits on
lifespan and at least some measures of health and also because again as we're thinking about
ultimately bringing this to people it's easier to envision a transient or
intermittent treatment than it is a continuous for the rest of your life sort of treatment so it'd be
single dosing again that's the way we have the study designed now i can see a rationale for doing
three months on three months off or some some variation on that we felt that the simplest
thing to do first so you know it's always a balance between getting as much information as
you can from a study like this and doing things that are going to be where the complexity isn't
so great that it yeah your power analysis could give you a right so the design that we're working
with now is uh one year on and then the rest of the time off and so those so we'll get so you'll
have one group that's five years on one group that's one on four off and then placebo that's
right blinded across the board it's all going to be a randomized double blind trial right in
addition to lifespan and heart function and activity will track cancer incidence probably kidney
function get routine blood chemistry on the dogs probably every six months we'll ask the owners
owners to bring their dogs in get echocardiograms collect serum for metabolomics and feces for
microbiome so what would that study that you just described cost if you could complete so let's say
you had to screen 600 dogs to complete 450 which would actually be pretty good yeah attrition so
it would run about five million that's about the the budget for that study some of that depends on
what we can ultimately get the rapamycin for so because right now it's the street values about
the lowest we've been able to find is about seven dollars a milligram yeah now it may be possible if
we have a large study that we can identify a supplier that would cut us a deal for for less
but and the drugs are actually a pretty large amount of the budget yeah the veterinary costs
are the other large expenditure again the nice thing about companion dogs it's unlike a study in
mice in the lab is they live with their owners we don't pay cage costs and things like that
the other major costs are going to be for the analysis the analysis and also we need people
to be able to communicate with the owners retention will be important i don't think it's
going to be as hard as it is for some clinical trials just based on our experience even though
it was a short-term trial the owners that came into the short-term trial they were extremely
this will be easier than communicating with patients in a trial i think so yeah and there's
actually i mean it's kind of funny but there's actually data that dog owners are more likely to
give their dog a prescription medication than they are to take their own prescription medication so
we would not doubt that for a second so yeah so the owners that come into this study are highly
motivated and some of them are extremely disappointed after the study ends when they
find out their dog was in the placebo group so but there is a communication component to this where
we have to keep the owners engaged maintain communication we'll be sending out regular
surveys but needs to go beyond the surveys that would these all have to be dogs that live in the
northwest they'd have to be able to come in in fact they almost certainly would not be so the way that
we're planning the study now is that we will partner with five to seven veterinary schools
around the united states oh that's great and that actually there's lots of reasons why that's
that that makes sense right but veterinary cardiologists there's there's not a huge population
of veterinary cardiologists out there so if we were to try and do a study like this in the seattle
area i don't think that we have the enough veterinary cardiologists to actually do the
just the cardiology part of the study so fortunately you know veterinarians are very
enthusiastic about participating in projects like this and we have collaborators lined up at the vet
schools around the country so it will probably be five or seven sites obviously all of those sites
have to have veterinary cardiology but almost any major veterinary school is going to have that and
we prefer to work with veterinary schools that are in a suburban or urban area some veterinary
schools like like our school in the state of washington is all the way on the other side of
the state from seattle it's kind of out in the middle of nowhere so that makes it harder to get
owners to actually bring their dogs there yeah so our lead veterinarian is at texas anm veterinary
college and so she would be the head clinical person on the study and that would probably be
the site that the other veterinary sites coordinate with yeah well matt i could sit here and have this
discussion for another two hours it's fun stuff to talk about it it is and i really appreciate
your time and your insights i think the work you're doing is certainly what i would consider
to be among the bodies of work that are at that tip of the spear because i i guess i don't have
a lot of hope we're going to get the answer to this question directly i think it's going to be
an indirect triangulation of of data and and i think to be able to do this in companion dogs that
live in our environment is going to be a really important thing so let's see if we can get that
study done yeah i also want to i mean i think it's also important to at least note the impact of a
study like this would have on public perception right i mean i think in the absence of any data
and then the little bit of data we got from the phase one study the amount of media attention
that we've got yeah i've heard you on npr talking about this with tarry gross right has been huge
and so i tend to agree with you that it's going to be challenging to generate enthusiasm for a
double blind placebo controlled clinical trial of rapamycin for healthy aging in people challenging
is probably not even a strong enough word but i think we do need to or we should at least not
underestimate the potential impact if we're successful at accomplishing this in people's pets
that that will have on public perception as well as perception among the broader scientific
community i do feel like the field of aging research still has a bit of a reputation problem
among the broader scientific community part of that is historical part of that is because there
are some fringe elements that get a lot of attention but that aren't scientifically credible
i think that actually being able to show in dogs living in the human environment that we can modify
aging will have an impact not just on the public in terms of i'm sure we'll get lots of media
attention but also among scientists who might actually say okay aging research has arrived i
think that's happening already i think the tame trial has actually been mostly a positive in that
sense or the proposed tame trial i should say but i think we still have some work for the listener
the targeting aging with metformin yeah which is i mean i support that study i think that it's
probably the right first study in this area because as you've already said metformin we we
know that it's very safe at least as far as as a drug you might consider for a study like this
it's very safe there's very good human data suggesting that that diabetics taking metformin
not only have less diabetes but they have fewer other age-related diseases so i think the human
data is pretty compelling the downside to metformin and i think one of the reasons why
it has been a struggle to get that study funded is that i think there's a perception that we
already know about metformin it's not going to be completely surprising given the literature that's
out there if it does have relatively small effects on other age-related diseases and then i also think
it probably isn't going to have that large of an effect i could be wrong i hope i'm wrong but again
my view of the literature that's out there is that metformin probably has modest effects but
they're not going to be 20 increase in lifespan and rejuvenation of heart function and immune
function so yeah i agree so so i think that that's probably the downside to that study but but again
because we're also battling this perception of resistance to the potential for side effects when
you're talking about treating healthy elderly people that's probably the right way to design
this first study the other thing about the tame trial though is it's not being done in healthy
elderly people right the people that they're enrolling have to have at least one age-related
disease and it can't be diabetes so even that is really not the gold standard study that we'd all
like to see whether it's metformin or rapamycin or you know something else we've got some work to do
to get to where we can actually do that study and maybe the path forward is that you know as you
said individuals who are willing to kind of come together and do these sort of self experiments
if you can do it in a rigorous way where you're actually measuring the things that needs to be a
model system right that allows it so that if you and i and bob and rick and john do it we're you
know the downside to that kind of a model is that it's it's still going to be hard to convince just
the scientific community the way that it is no it's much harder to convince them that it's real
having said that if the effects are robust and you see it over and over and over and multiple people
we'll get there eventually so so that may be the path that we end up taking you know i'm not betting
on that path i'm betting on the path that you're describing as being the shortest distance between
these two points and i hope that as we start to do more of these studies in dogs and and also the
preclinical stuff in mice as we start to find functional measures that are improved over a
relatively short time frame that people will start to do some of these clinical trials that are
feasible in people i mean you could i mean novartis has already done it right you can do a clinical
trial where you treat healthy elderly people for six weeks eight weeks ten weeks and look at a
functional outcome and so if it's the case that rapamycin rejuvenates immune function and
rejuvenates cardiac function and and delays or restores alveolar bone levels in the mouth right
those are clinical endpoints that are impactful and could be studied in a short clinical trial so
we may get a few of those that will kind of build this body of evidence that rapamycin is having a
similar effect in people again the hard part is there's not a lot of money in rapamycin so i don't
know who's going to fund those trials that's the challenge so we we need to identify so either it's
going to be rapamycin derivatives that are under patent like novartis has developed and now rest
or bio is further developing or it's going to be alternative funding sources whether that's
foundations or wealthy individuals who recognize the potential impact of this work and are willing
to to fund a clinical trial to actually start to look at some of this. Matt thanks again this
is super interesting and best of luck with your continued work. Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast there you'll
find the show notes readings and links related to this episode you can also find my blog and the
nerd safari at peteratiamd.com what's a nerd safari you ask just click on the link at the top of the
site to learn more maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once
a week email where i'll update you on what i've been up to the most interesting papers i've read
and all things related to longevity science performance sleep etc on social you can find
me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratia md but usually twitter is the best
way to reach me to share your questions and comments now for the obligatory disclaimer this
podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine
nursing or other professional health care services including the giving of medical advice
and note no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the materials
linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk the content of this podcast is not intended to be
a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard
or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they have and should seek the
assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions lastly and perhaps most
importantly i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures the companies
i invest in and or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about