Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. Welcome back to another special episode of the Drive focusing on COVID-19. My
guest today is Dr. Michael Osterholm. You may have seen Michael on the Joe Rogan podcast a few
weeks ago. I saw him then and was immediately impressed, reached out to him and asked if he'd
like to come on our show, which he graciously agreed to. Michael is the director of the Center
for Infectious Disease Research and Policy at the University of Minnesota. He's also the author of
a book that in many ways foreshadowed this. The book is called Deadliest Enemy, Our War Against
Deadly Germs. And in that book in particular, he foreshadows a lot of what we're going through
today. Mike and I in this discussion talk about everything from our best understanding of what's
happening in the United States with respect to the spread and the slowing of the virus,
what he's optimistic about, what he's pessimistic about, what he thinks the end state looks like,
and what you'd have to believe is true if that is to be altered. We also get into the weeds a little
bit on some technical things around supply chain limitations with respect to drugs, with respect to
masks, with respect to vaccines. There are a number of things we discuss. And again, I think just for
the purpose of simplicity, rather than get into a laundry list of everything we talk about, I think
if you're, if you've got this far, you're probably interested in hearing it. So without further delay,
please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Michael Osterholm.
Mike, thank you so much for making time to sit down with us for some time today. And again,
I want to thank you because I just know that you are constantly being bombarded by requests. And
there's sort of a challenge you have to deal with, which is on the one hand, you want to be able to
do your job, but on the other hand, it's somewhat important for people like you doing your job to
be able to communicate with the rest of us what you're seeing and more importantly, what the
implications are and what can be done about it. Well, thank you very much, Peter. It's very good
to be with you. And I think that it's venues like yours that serve a very important role in getting
information out today. Far too much of what we deal with is in sound bites. It's in three minute
segments. And I think that's really hard to convey the complexities and the overall short term,
long term view of what's happening here. So I'm really pleased to be with you. Thank you.
Well, yeah, you're in the right spot. We're not fans of sound bites here. So we'll get right to
it and we'll get deep. So let's start with kind of the 30,000 foot view, which is when we sit here
today recording this on March 30th, it feels like an eternity ago that you were on Joe Rogan's
podcast doing what I thought was just an excellent job of giving Joe and Joe's audience an overview
of what we knew at the time, what we didn't know at the time, what the concerns were. What
do you feel more optimistic about relative to that time, which has probably been three weeks? What do
you feel less optimistic about? Well, first of all, I think that it's important to understand,
Lewis Carroll once said, if you don't know where you're going, any road will get you there. And I
think that one of the things that I've been very concerned about is we don't really know where we're
going. And that's not because the virus hasn't given us lots of clues. Just very briefly to take
a step back, just to remind everybody where we've been, we've been following this situation very
closely since the end of December last year. I have been very actively involved. I was involved
with the SARS investigation in 2003, very involved with MERS on the Moravian Peninsula, and have
obviously done a lot of work and influence the pandemic preparedness and planning. And so when
this first happened, and we saw these cases in Wuhan, it was really to us, oh my, here comes another
SARS or MERS-like experience, which actually, in retrospect, those were the easy ones because
patients were not becoming highly infectious till the fifth or sixth day of illness. You could
identify them quickly, get them into appropriate isolation so you didn't infect others. And we
could follow up in their context. But it became very clear to us by the second week of January,
what was happening in Wuhan was not SARS and MERS. This was acting much more like an influenza
virus in terms of transmission dynamic, lots of spread very quickly. And so on January 20th,
we actually put a document out saying that this was going to be a worldwide pandemic, almost two
months before the WHO did. We were convinced we would see spread. On February 3rd, we put out an
additional document that said it would probably take until the end of February or early March
before we would see cases around the world in any meaningful way, because it just, the transmission
of this virus was such that we had a sense, even then, probably had an incubation period of about
five days from infection until the onset of symptoms. And that if it had an R-naught or the
number of people that you transmit on an average basis to of about 2 to 2.4, you go from 1 to 2 to
4 to 8 to 16 to 32. And knowing that the cases in China were largely about 80% were not seeking
medical care. They were sick, but it wasn't sufficient. We said, you know, it'll probably be
the end of February. Well, sure enough, it was. We also put out a document in mid-February saying
that when it did start to show up, it probably hit hotspots, metropolitan areas, because of number one,
that's where most of the transportation, communication of people from China to the
rest of the world would be. Second of all, that's where the population density was high enough so
that you would actually see this amplification. Sure enough, as you know now, that's exactly what
we've seen. So having said that, it seems that we kind of know what's going on here. And I'll say
right now, we're done with that. I don't know where this virus is going to go next in terms of
how long it'll be around. You can make assumptions of what we see within influenza. I think some of
those are helpful, but I don't think that they're necessarily definitive. People talk about
seasonality. I remind people all the time that we don't see that with the other two coronaviruses.
SARS was not seasonality just because it ended in June. It was a new situation where we first
understood we had a problem in February. It took us literally several months to figure out this
infectivity period, get people isolated, stop transmission, get palm civets out of the markets
of the Guangdong province, and then it ended it. If you look at MERS, and I've been there standing
outside of a hospital in Abu Dhabi, it was 110 degrees, and transmission was going on just fine,
thank you. It was not at all being halted by the weather, and because of course,
camels are not going to be put down as such, it just continues to transmit in the Arabian
Peninsula year-round, and our primary means of dealing with it is just making sure that
people don't transfer in the hospital setting. So if you take that, but also take influenza,
because this is where people come back on the seasonality piece, and they say, well,
it's probably going to be like influenza. We forget that while influenza transmits seasonally
in the winter of each northern and southern hemispheres, it transmits year-round in the
tropics, never stops transmitting. If you look at the last 10 influenza pandemics over the last 250
years, two started in the winter, three started in the spring, two started in the summer, and three
started in the fall. And every one of them had their big peak six months after the original
cases showed up. In 2009, with H1N1, it showed up in mid to late March, and we had a big peak
mid-September to mid-October, North America was still warm. So I don't know what it's going to
do going forward, but that's where when you ask me, good news, bad news, I have every reason to
believe that it won't stop transmitting in any meaningful way until we get 50 or 60 or 70% of
the population infected, which means that the bad news is that we are going to have to deal with
those cases unless we can suppress them. And we can talk about what the implications that are.
If we suppress them, meaning that we do what Wuhan did, and the Chinese in Wuhan did, of basically
shutting down everything in the most draconian manner we've ever seen in modern quarantine
history, that means we're going to shut down our country. We'll shut down the economy in any
meaningful way, and not just about dollars and cents. Who's going to pick up the garbage?
Who's going to basically be fire and police? Who's going to do all the things that we count on?
I'm pessimistic about the fact that we don't have an easy way out. I like to say that right now we
either suppress this and have this implication we talked about in a hope that we can suppress it
long enough until we get a vaccine, which I don't think will be any sooner than 18 months, or we let
it go willy-nilly, and we will bring down healthcare systems. Many thousands to millions of people will
die, and our healthcare systems will collapse, or we try to thread the rope through the needle and
hit the middle. How do we find a way to have those people who are at lowest risk of having serious
disease, problems, who are at the highest risk of dying be in our workforce, be more public,
and handle the issues? So if we can do that, that's good news. If we can't, the rest of us
pretty bad news. Mike, the numbers you just rattled off as sort of potential projections,
is that worldwide, or was that a domestic figure? That's in the United States. I mean, if you look
at, you know, do the math, and just a little over 300 million people, if you're talking about 60%
of those infected, you're talking 170 to 175 million people. If you talk about 80% of those
having relatively milder illness, now you're talking 20% that are going to have some illness
that will likely require hospitalization. If you then take that down to even one or two percent
of those who might die, you can just do the simple math, and you realize we're talking about millions.
And that's what I don't think people understand yet, is that this virus is going to keep going. It
is very much like an influenza virus in that regard. It will go until it finds enough immune
people that shut it down, meaning they don't let transmission continue. And that's what I don't
think people are prepared to understand yet, is that they think that these waves are going to
happen over the next two to three weeks, and then we're done. Just remind people that right now in
China, here we are, the end of March, this clearly was present in China in mid to late November.
And we're still seeing transmission inside in China, even with these draconian measures to limit
transmission. There are people in the Wuhan area who've not been out of their house in 15 weeks,
and yet we still see cases occurring. So this is going to happen here, where it'll be months and
months potentially of transmission. And I hate to thought of the fact that one of the primary
ways that we limit that transmission is just enough people get infected and develop immunity.
I might add one good news piece on the immunity piece, this is an important one. I think we can
say with more certainty that there probably is durable immunity, at least for the short term.
And what I mean by that is there was a study completed and published last week using macaque
monkeys. And they infected a group of them with the virus. They all came down with kind of the
classic coronavirus-like illness. They then waited until they fully recovered. They re-challenged
them a month later, and all of them were protected against unrechallenged. None of them got infected
again. And just to make sure I know what the re-challenge implied, were they PCR-negative,
IgG-positive, IgM-negative? Yes, they were. I can't say they're IgM-negative. I'd have to go
back and look at that. But they were definitely IgG-positive and PCR-negative. Yep. And so we have
evidence clearly, and they didn't just do PCR, they did culture too. So they actually were actually
looking for the actual virus. In other words, they weren't just looking for surface protein.
No, no, exactly. And so I think this study really gave us more hope that there really is
durable immunity, at least in the short term. I can't say it's going to be years and years.
I know that if you have short term immunity, oftentimes that bodes well for a long term
immunity picture. So that's actually an important positive step that these are going to be people
who will be, as I call, kind of the human immunologic rods in the virus reaction. They
will slow it down. And today they could be the people that could be out there in the world,
not worried about getting infected, and also would not infect others.
Yeah, I was having a discussion with one of the members of my team today, and anyone who's ever
worked with me knows I play this game called the What You Have To Believe game, which is sort of a
way to probe the limits of what biology could tell us. So we got a little deep in the weeds on this,
and I said, look, imagine for a moment two extreme scenarios. Scenario one is this particular
coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 is a total nothing burger. It's just another respiratory virus.
It's getting a lot of attention right now, but the reality of it is when it all plays out and
everybody gets infected, it's going to have a mortality that's equal to or less than influenza,
et cetera, et cetera. If that is true, how would you explain the current data through that paradigm?
And we walk through it. But at the other end of the spectrum, I said, what if it's worse? What if
it's the virus that could wipe our civilization off the map? Again, I don't think either of these
extremes are correct, but it became a good illustration of what would have to be true.
What do you have to believe if SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19 will eradicate our species? Well,
you'd have to believe the following. One, there is no long-term immunity. Two, each successive
infection is worse than the previous one. And three, no effective treatments will be developed.
If those three things are true, this would be the virus that eradicates our species.
Fortunately, I don't believe any of those are true. And you're making a very compelling case
for at least the first of those not being true. And by the way, they would all have to be true
for the scenario I just described. So I take that as some good news. I do want to ask, I mean,
it literally just came out, I think, 20 minutes ago. Did you happen to see that Lancet paper that
came out going over the revised numbers in China in terms of case fatality?
I have not seen that one. I have seen a similar one, but help me. Maybe it is the same one I've
seen. Well, so this one basically took the original case fatality rate of 1.38%, but followed it up
and added a whole bunch of more people to the denominator that were previously in the
unconfirmed bucket. So you took a bunch of people that were unconfirmed, you've now gone on to
confirm them. And the case fatality rate now looks to be 0.66%. Again, largely on the basis of not
subtracting mortality, but adding denominators. Does that surprise you? And what do you think the
CFR looks like if one could truly measure all the people that are in that category of having an
infection, but not being either clinically significant enough to warrant detention or
simply falling through the cracks due to socioeconomic factors, testing, limitations, et cetera?
Yeah. Let me take two pieces of information and go at that. First one is you're absolutely
correct. It's a numerator denominator issue. Now the challenge I think in adding to the denominator
is that you can add quite a bit to that and drive the overall case fatality rate or CFR down.
But what we're also missing is the number of people in the numerator. And our contacts in Wuhan
during that time period who were pretty reliable actually concluded in their assessment that
probably six to eight people were dying every day outside a hospital that were not being counted,
meaning that they were not being tested. And if you weren't tested, you weren't counted.
And so think about this. If you have a case fatality rate of 1%, 1 over 100, and you suddenly add
100 more people to that, you now have a case fatality rate of 0.5 per 100, okay, half of what it was.
On the other hand, if you have that same 200, you added 100 more, doubled it. But you also add 10
more people who died who weren't counted, only 10. Now you're looking at 11 over 200, and you're now
at 5% plus. So the numerator is actually more sensitive in terms of impacting the rate than
is the denominator. And so one of the challenges that we've had is what is that overall numerator
and how many cases were missed? These have been well written up, these cases. So I don't know what
it is, but let me tell you what I think is important now. We've known this, I think from early on in
China, that these comorbidities we talk about, this other underlying conditions play a very important
role. We've known about that with influenza for years, that comorbidities can affect you in several
ways. One, of course, is the occurrence of acute respiratory distress syndrome, or ARDS, in the
cytokine storm picture. In some cases, there appears to be kind of a myocarditis type picture
that can occur. And of course, there's always secondary bacterial pneumonias, but I'm not even
going to count those in there because that in a sense is something we can often deal with with
antibiotics. But what happened in China was, is if you look at the overall case fatality rate by age,
we saw this exorbitant rate in those over age 65 who are male. Well, if you look closely in China,
almost 70% of men over age 65 smoke, and less than 2% of women over that same age group. So right
there, you could have an impact on that situation because smoking has always been associated with
worse outcome with these kind of viruses. And ironically, the other risk factors,
essential hypertension was also seen as a risk factor for bad outcome. But beyond that,
there wasn't much else. Obesity, which has been highly associated with bad outcomes,
is actually quite rare in the older population of China. It's primarily under age 30, where there
are starting to see a real epidemic there. Well, okay, let's fast forward to the United States.
We're now getting data out of New York. We're seeing an increased number of severe illnesses
and deaths in people between the ages of 25 and 50. And almost to a T, the risk factor appears to
be obesity. 45% of our population over age 50 is considered moderate to severely obese today.
Just that one risk factor. On top of that, renal disease has been shown in the past to be
associated with bad outcomes. 700,000 Americans are living alive today with in-stage renal disease.
And when you start adding up all these comorbidities that we uniquely have, in part because of lifestyle
or because we happen to have a healthcare system that's able to keep us alive and with the right
drugs and so forth. So we don't really know when you put this virus here, what it's going to do.
A good example of that is the difference between Korea and Italy. Korea right now has actually just
climbed over 1%. It had been below that. And part of that was a function is the big outbreak that
they initially had that they worked up extensively in the thousands of people within this religious
sector. The median age of that group was 43. So, you know, right there you had a younger population
that surely would have had a lower case fatality rate. You go to Italy and right now about 80% of
their cases are over age 80 with underlying health problems. And they have an 8% case fatality rate.
So I think that one of the things we're going to find with case fatality is going to be really
country by country dependent. It's going to matter where the virus is circulating and what age group.
And it's going to matter in a large part as to what the underlying health conditions are.
In China, there's almost nothing ever called a nursing home or long-term care facility. People
cared for in the home. In the United States right now, we're sitting in a powder keg long-term care
facility for which for years we've neglected them in terms of infection control. I can't tell you how
many long-term care facilities we have right here in Minnesota, they couldn't find one in a 95 in
their house that they needed to. Not one in 95. I think that we actually stand the risk over the
course of the next several months. I've seen it probably one of the highest case fatality rates
in the world right here. That's the first point of what I would say. The second part though,
you deal with this every day, every flu season you are constantly confronted with this increased
occurrence of illnesses, et cetera. And even during the 2009 H1N1 situation, even in a bad H3N2 year
in older people, nobody, nobody reports what's happening, what's happening now in places like
New York and Detroit and Atlanta and Seattle. And so I think that what's happening here actually
matches up with the severity that we believe it really is occurring. I've come to the point in my
old age that when something walks like a duck, looks like a duck and quacks like a duck, I think
it's probably a duck. What would you put on the floor as the estimate for the CFR in a fully
diluted sample? Do you think that there's a scenario under which the CFR is 0.1%? Again,
fully diluted, meaning you actually know all the infected people, or do you think that that's
really just a pipe dream and the best case scenario is closer to 0.4, 0.5?
That's a pipe dream to me. And I think it's going to be in the one to 2.5 range. And I think that
it's going to be heavily influenced by those who are over age 65, 70. And I think it's going to be
influenced by the frequency of obesity in the younger age group in that regard.
Mike, I've never wanted someone to be wrong more than I want you to be wrong, because if the CFR
is 1% to 2% in the United States, and you're right about the spread of this virus, the implication
of that is more Americans will die from this infection in the next 12 months than will die
of all other causes combined. And I am absolutely on your side with this one. You will get no
argument for me. I hope I'm wrong. I would welcome that opportunity to be wrong. I just look at what's
happening right now. I look at indirect indicators. A good example right now, today, the New York
Police Department reported out over 900 police officers in New York are infected right now.
13% of the workforce is out. They just had their third death today in police officers.
And when you start looking at that, and this is just getting started, when you start looking at
that and compare that to a bad flu season, which you and I have to deal with far too often,
with a vaccine on top of it, by the way, and we know what happens, look at this one. This one
has that potential, I think, to be in the one to two. I don't think this at all is going to be like
1918 because that was so unique in how it took out 18 to 30-year-olds. This one's not doing that.
This is going to clearly be associated with age and underlying health issues. But in some ways,
we are a population that is highly vulnerable because of all the other lifestyle and health
conditions that occur in our group. So I think that that's where I'm very concerned about it
and would agree with you 100% of what you just said. And I'd just say, on a given week in New
York City, in the past, 100 people die a day in New York. Right now, we're averaging close to 150
a day just dying from COVID-19. Think about that. If we're going to play that what if game a moment
ago, what if this is something that is, quote unquote, only going to result in fewer than 100,000
lives lost in the United States, which again, still seems for most people struggling to
understand what non-linearity means. We're a little over 2,000 deaths today. So even to propose that
this could be capped at 100,000 seems very extreme. But I think you would agree that if only
100,000 Americans were to die before this thing was completely contained, you would consider that
a victory. Absolutely. What has to be true for that to happen? What are the things that have
to happen scientifically, policy-wise, in terms of personal behavior responsibility? What are the
suite of things that must be true if that number is to stay below 100,000 in the next year?
I think two things. One is we have to basically suppress transmission as much as we can,
which I don't think is doable. And I say that because it would mean a Wuhan-like shutdown.
And I just don't think as a country we can sustain that. I think even, and I don't want to equate
this in dollars and cents. I had an op-ed piece in the New York Times over the weekend, which I
said this is not a choice between saving lives and costing the economy. We have to look at it's a
combination of both. And we need people to carry on every day. I mean, I look at you. I mean, I
don't want anything to happen to you for a lot of reasons, but one of them is you're a very key
healthcare provider. You got to do your job. You can't shut down. We can't shut down. I mean,
when's the last time you saw anybody do remote work to pick up garbage? If you live in New York
City, guess what? Elevator operators, maintenance people are really important because if you can't
get up to the 40th floor, you shut down a part of the city that's really important. So I could go
through a laundry list of whether it's foods, people who provide our food, et cetera. So we've
got to preserve that part of it. But at the same time, I worry that what's going to happen is an
acceleration of deaths due to the failing of the healthcare system. Right now, keeping people alive
on ventilators, having intensive care medicine does make a difference. Not for every case,
but it makes a difference. But once you go off the edge of the cliff, where it's now no longer,
do you have a ventilator available? We have to wait for someone to go off a vent and you have to
make a choice to take them off. When you start running out of the critical supplies, one of the
things that we've been working on in our center for the last year and a half has been looking at
very acute critical drug shortages, meaning these are drugs that you need right now or in the next
several hours where people die. What's on the crash cart? What's in the intensive care unit? What's in
the ER? We came up with a list of 156 drugs, which we have vetted with all the major medical groups,
the intensivists, etc. Of these 156, all of them are generic. Of those, almost 85% are made outside
the United States. And of those, many of them are made in China. We are just beginning to feel
the severe supply chain collision that's going to occur here in the next several weeks with increased
number of cases of severe disease and these drugs that we need. Because in China, the supply chains,
which were still thin, were filled just before this outbreak started and there's about two to
three months worth of supply in the chain. But there was nothing that came in the backside of it.
So we're just about done. So if you add this on, Peter, this also then means now you've got to deal
with that situation on top of it. And if our healthcare system can't take care of these people
or we have acute shortages of what we need to provide the care we have been providing,
then the case fatality rate is going to go way up. It's going to go up. And that's, I think,
a real challenge. So just to be clear, you're not saying that we're going to run out of,
pick your favorite candidate drug that I want to eventually talk about with you,
you know, remdesivir versus hydroxychloroquine, etc. You're saying epinephrine, norepinephrine,
vasopressin, paralytics, the type of medicine we all take for granted that you need to run an ICU.
But even take something as simple as antibiotics. When you're sitting in an ICU for three and a half
weeks, the chance of developing a noscumular infection as a result of being there.
It's pretty much guaranteed.
It's almost guaranteed. So if you don't have the antibiotics anymore, guess what? 85% of all of our
key antibiotics right now are made outside the United States. Ironically, you know the two areas
that have the most production capability? China in the Lombardi region of Italy. Can you imagine?
You couldn't make that up.
You couldn't make it up, but you couldn't. And so, I mean, there's something we're looking at. So I
think that, you know, the question is relative. If we had ideal intensive care availability,
we could maintain the system. We could take that kind of that spigot of cases and regulate them
enough so that they didn't overflow the healthcare system. They just appeared. I like to say if we
have 100 cases of the disease today and they all hit the healthcare system, that's one outcome.
What if you have 100 and they hit the healthcare system 10 a week for 10 weeks? That's another
outcome. If we could do that, if we could thread that needle with our rope, then we'd be okay.
But I don't think we're going to be able to do that.
Do you think we have a pretty good handle on what it's going to take to protect healthcare workers?
Do we understand what amount of PPE is necessary first and foremost? And then secondly, of course,
can we meet that need? Can we meet the demand of that? Starting with the first question,
do we actually know what it takes to protect doctors, nurses, respiratory therapists,
and everybody who works in a hospital from the cafeteria to the parking garage?
Yeah, I think we know. I don't think we talk about it very well. And we have people who are
in denial about it. I've spent my career working on both coronaviruses and influenza. I can tell
you we have absolute certainty today, no question about it, that influenza virus is in part
transmitted by aerosols. These are the smaller particles of smaller than five millimeter
particles. And people assume when we talk about airborne transmission, we're talking about
something that's many, many yards away. And they actually forget that aerosols are produced
just where droplets are right in that first six feet area. And so if you're that close,
if you have a surgical mask on, you surely can do a lot to minimize the number of droplets you
come in contact with. But that doesn't take into account the aerosol. Where there's droplets,
there's aerosols. Where there's aerosols, there may not be droplets. But people have assumed
it's droplets or then it's aerosols somewhere else. And so I think from a respiratory protection
standpoint, one of the challenges we had in China was well close to 4,000 healthcare workers infected.
Right now in Italy, there's well over 5,600 healthcare workers who have been infected. Now,
some of them obviously got infected off the job, but many of them were on job. And respiratory
protection was a key factor in each one. And so I today feel incredibly incompetent, incapable,
and frankly, sad that there are going to be many healthcare workers who are going to risk their
lives to help with this, who will not have N95 respirator, which they need to have, because we
just don't have enough. We won't. And when I keep hearing about this additional production, the White
House continues to talk about that. They never give you the numbers of what we estimate we'll need
versus what's being produced. And it's so far short, it's not laughable, because that would imply
something funny. There's nothing funny about it. But the bottom line message is that we're going
to have a lot of healthcare workers who are going to be exposed and infected with this virus because
of that. What is the number, Mike? What would we need? I don't know. I think this is where, again,
we have a PPE challenger, particularly within N95s, that was even much more severe than they
had in China. Or to that extent, in Italy, they did several unique things, which I don't know if
we'll do here. You may have heard, but in several of the really high volume wards in Milan,
they had COVID-infected healthcare workers working. If they weren't that sick, they were working.
They went in without masks, et cetera, because they didn't have them. And so I don't know what
we'll do here, but I do believe we'll have a real challenge with this. Now, some will say, well, and
this is what I find very frustrating is we have to stick with the science. And what happened with CDC
to their credit, about two weeks ago, issued new guidelines for the use of PPE respiratory
protection. But what they said was, if you don't have N95s, then use masks. But a number of
administrators and some scientists have come forward and said, CDC changed their recommendation,
saying you don't have to use respirators, or you can use masks, meaning it's just droplet.
That's not what they said. And so I think that today for a healthcare worker, they just at least
have to know what they're getting into. I think many of them will still go to work. I mean, the
camaraderie, and you know what it's like to be in that kind of setting. These are some of the most
amazing heroes in the world. We don't send our soldiers into war without some kind of protective
equipment or without bullets in their guns. We send healthcare workers into this viral battle,
and we're going to be sending them in without bullets or without protective equipment. And
that to me is really sad, but that's what's going to have to take. That's going to be a big question
as to what happens there. So really, we have a problem on multiple fronts. We have a problem on
the supportive drug front. We have a problem on the treatment drug front, which I want to come
back to in a moment. We have a problem on the people who are going to administer care. We
potentially have a problem on the number of ventilators and actual beds, et cetera. So is
it a largely irrelevant academic exercise to understand which of those things becomes the
first failure? Because it varies so much, presumably by city hospital geography,
that it ought to be an all hands on deck for all of them. I mean, is there a model here where we
pick the 10 cities that are either in the throes of hell or we know are about to be,
and we start relocating healthcare workers to those areas if that's the thing that we believe
is going to be the bottleneck first? Of course, that would only make sense if you could provide
them with the necessary PPE. Otherwise, you're losing your soldiers in battle unnecessarily
without an appropriate risk to benefit trade off. How do we think about this? I mean, I haven't
spent a lot of time truly thinking about this at the full macro level of what the White House would
hopefully be thinking about this, but I mean, what is the model? What can we learn from the
successes and failures of any other pandemic? Well, first of all, let me just say you articulated
beautifully. You hit on every major piece. Let me just give some kind of relevant information.
It'll give you a sense. Right now, the largest manufacturer in the United States of N95s is 3M.
They can produce 35 million N95s a month. They're trying to wrap that up to get maybe 5 to 7% more
out of their machines. You just don't build these machines overnight. So even when you hear other
companies talk about how they're going to double or triple whatever production it is,
be very skeptical because these are machines that are really very, very sophisticated pieces of
equipment. I mean, for example, with an N95, most people don't realize that piece of white in front
of you is not paper. It's a matrix. It was actually poured and dried, and it has a unique
electrostatic charge on it, et cetera, so you can get air through it, not virus. It's a very
sophisticated thing. Well, they've produced 35 million a month. They've been doing it since
late January, and we met with them and said this is going to be a pandemic. There's one hospital
in New York alone, just one, that used 2 million N95s last month in that month, 2 million in their
institution. Now, you start to do the math where we have basically about 35 million of these
in the strategic national stockpile. That's it. You start looking at the volume we'd need of
400 million or more of these N95s just to get through the first couple of months, and you start
looking at the shortfall. That's where I have a problem is just let's just be honest. I'm not
trying to blame anybody. We're all to blame everybody. Why are we so ill prepared? But
healthcare workers have to know. A statement I made earlier about one of the former Defense
Secretary said when you go to war, you can't go to war with what you want. You have to go to war
with what you have. To understand how do we best protect healthcare workers, I think this is a key.
Let me give you an example. If we can't protect them because we don't have N95s, what are the
other things you can do? One is we should start forming wards, large wards, where basically we
have 18 or 20 patients on one ward, and you never leave the contaminated zone. At that point, rather
than doff and donning outside every room and having to throw that away, what do you do? Second
of all, what can you do to reuse these? We're publishing an article this week on our website
with 3M support, I mean not financial, but their intellectual support, of what are the techniques
we can actually use that will maintain the integrity of these N95s, but they can be reused
so that we can decontaminate. We're working on that right now. Next is what can we do to get
infected healthcare workers back? If I had to ask right now for one gift we could give healthcare
workers is serology. I'd like to test as many healthcare workers as I could for antibody and
having the discussion we just had on the ability to know that somebody's likely protected,
then I would know also that these are the people the safest to put back into harm's way.
If we did a lot of things like that, I think we could really mitigate the risk for healthcare
workers, but what we can't do is just administratively say, well the CDC has made this
recommendation, ignoring that there are things we must do and can do. You and I both know that
this is a numerator-denominator world we live in when it gets to rates, but it's a numerator world
when that person that dies is your colleague, when that person is somebody who worked for you,
when that person is somebody who day after day was there with you, bedside, holding hands, doing
the kind of skilled work, that is so tough on these people. We also have to understand the
mental health issues. If we neglect that, I already know healthcare workers who literally go home and
cry all the way home to work after they just finished another 14-hour shift. I think that's
another area that I've not heard anybody really talking about much, is this is just like battlefield
trauma. We've got to start helping them right now. If we're going to maintain three or four or five
months worth of activity here, we can't count on these people to do this day in and day out with
more help. Protect them first, support them second, and understand them and care about them third,
and they all have to be part of the picture. Mike, I want to go back to something you said
a second ago with respect to testing. Do we have a sense where we are now? I mean,
it seems that we've done probably in the neighborhood of 800,000 tests in the United
States in total. I don't know the breakdown of how many of those are PCR versus antibody,
but does that sound about right to you? It does, absolutely. Yes, it does. Yep.
Okay. Tell me the status of PCR. Is Roche providing the majority of these tests?
Yeah. I actually commented this also in my op-ed piece in the New York Times.
Again, if there's an operative set of words in this whole entire experience, it's supply chain,
supply chain, supply chains. Just like in real estate, it's location, location, location.
We have changed our world. In 2003, when SARS occurred, China was not a big player in
manufacturing the world. Supply chains weren't that critical to what happened in China.
Well, it turns out today, supply chains are everything, including for testing.
I'll add the perfect storm here. One, the world basically is on fire. Everybody wants these
reagents for whether it's PCR, whether it's antigen detection, whether it's serology.
Number two, guess where a lot of the reagents were being made? China. Number three, now we bring
those two together and we're encouraging people to even do more testing. You know what? Within
a couple of weeks, we're going to actually see an implosion of testing. Right now in Minnesota,
we are so limited in our public health lab to test. If we don't have more reagents,
then tomorrow we're done. We can't test anymore. Commercial companies have been putting together
great packages to sell for testing, but what they haven't given you is how deep is their
inventory of resources for reagents. They're not. It used to be we filled the reagent pool
with a garden hose. Then we realized we needed a fire hose and now we need a damn water tunnel.
We're not going to have it. It's just at the time we need more testing.
I've seen these people get on talk shows and they sit there and say, oh, we'll just test
our way out of this. They don't have a clue about a supply chain issue. I think this is a
huge issue that you raise and is one that we're going to do less instead of more.
That seems counterintuitive, but it's what's going to happen.
Based on that, the idea that we should hope for the best scenario where everybody gets PCR to
detect and then antibody to follow, I mean, that's a pipe dream if we're going to be reagent limited.
Instead, it's going to be a bit of a pick your poison. And if you're lucky to get any test,
if that's the setting, which it sounds like based on the reagent shortfall, we're going to get to
that place. What other methods can be used? For example, could we rely on temperature changes?
Can we rely on any other sort of biometric as a way to take patients who are suspected positive,
but not yet confirmed and enact policy around that?
This is where we're going to get creative. And this is ironically where things like 1918 are
instructive. We're back to the future, you might say. First of all, we want to know when the virus
is in our communities and when it's doing harm. And we have a system in this country called
influenza-like illness surveillance or syndromic surveillance. We have set up in a whole series of
randomly chosen physicians offices around the country. And we survey it every week,
every several times a week during the flu season to give us an idea of, you know, if you have this
constellation of signs and symptoms, it's probably highly suggestive of flu and this is what's going
on. Well, it was very interesting. In New York City, flu had started to wind down by early February
to mid February and was actually coming down. All of a sudden in the end of February, boom,
up goes the number. And it goes and it goes and it goes. Long before anybody was test positive.
And guess what? It was COVID-19. We see the same thing here in Minneapolis. We just saw that thing
go up about two and a half weeks ago and it started going up again. So I feel confident
that we can monitor enough illness in the community this way and other means that we have
that we can tell people it's time to put the pedal to the metal. Okay. It's happening. We got
to shut it down the best we can. And so I think that's the kind of methods that public health is
going to be reverting to. But you raise a good point. What can I do for any one patient? And I
think the only thing we have going for us season wise right now is if they are sick with an
influenza-like illness, it's likely not influenza because we don't see it circulating right now.
And we can test for that and we haven't seen it. So I think you have to assume that there are COVID
infected patients and go with that. But it's going to create challenges. I mean, one of the things
we're concerned about right now is in Minnesota, our priority is testing first sick individuals
who are in the hospital. Are they really infected or not? The second thing is to test health care
workers who are sick, whether they're in the hospital or not, because we want them to work
or not. And the third thing is testing workers in long-term care. That's all we have the ability
to test for right now because we don't have any other real agents. And I said that we may run out
tomorrow. So we're all going to be finding ourselves, I think, in different scenarios. And
as much as we hear this good news about the new point of care test coming out from Abbott and
things like that, we welcome all the tests. Just make sure you have reagents to go with them.
And that's where the challenge is. Yeah. So your fear is that this Abbott test could be technically
a wonderful test, but it might only be able to do a million tests in total before the supply chain
falls apart. Exactly. You nailed it. That's exactly it. And we have been talking to the
companies at some length. And remember, when Abbott says a million, they could tell me 10 million.
It's over what time period? But it's over a whole world too. And that's the problem we have right
now. You could not buy a Roche PCR machine right now anywhere in the world. The Chinese went and
bought them all up 14 weeks ago. You can't buy one in the United States. As soon as they saw it
was happening, they bought every machine they could. And so we're in a global market for these
tests too. And it's not just the US. And that's another reason why this is such a unique event,
is because it is a global house on fire where everybody wants reagent water. And the truck can
only deliver so much. Yeah. I mean, gee, I hate saying such stupid glib things, but I really feel
like we're playing chess, not checkers. I say this all the time. I say, we got to stop playing
this. Like I play checkers with my 10 year old grandson, which I'm lucky if I beat him in one
move down the board. Yeah. Yeah. It just seems like I may have misset it, but I think you know
what I meant. Like, no, I don't. You were right. You were right. Yeah. We're playing checkers.
We're playing one move ahead. And the speed with which this is moving again to borrow from
Wayne Gretzky, right? We have to go where the puck is going, not where the puck is. And it seems like
every time, every step we take is going towards where the puck is. But in the case of a viral
pandemic, the puck moves faster than it moves in any other game. And you're really on your heels
when you're just going where the puck is, as opposed to anticipating where it's going.
And that's another really important point is, you know, we plan for catastrophes,
but we typically plan for a hurricane or an earthquake or a tsunami, one region, and then
we get into recovery right away. Not that it's not devastating, but you know, FEMA can't be in
all 50 states at once and do the magnificent job that we're seeing in New York. And frankly, many
of us fear that you don't want to be on the tail end of this outbreak where you are one of the
latter cities to break, because by that time, a lot of the resources are going to be used.
And even those that aren't going to be used up where they can be moved, like if additional
ventilators, if you can move them from place to place, it's still going to be a challenge,
because you will have used so many of the critical things like drugs and so forth.
And so where you place yourself in this outbreak right now, as bad as New York is,
they have the benefit of, at least now, like Seattle, they got more resources than most other
places will likely get. Mike, I've spoken to many people about the situation around vaccines,
including a number of people sort of off the record who work in biotech companies.
I've spoken with at least three CEOs of biotech companies off the record. Without exception,
no one has been able to give me a scenario under which a vaccine is available inside of 12 months.
Can you explain from your point of view why you think that that's likely and why you're saying,
look, we're not going to have a vaccine until 2021?
I always come back and clarify, I could make a vaccine tonight for this. I could, even with my
simplistic knowledge of this issue. But the question is, would it be safe and effective?
And that's what's key. So I think from an effectiveness standpoint, I do think we can
probably find something that will be effective even if temporarily, meaning it's not permanent
long-term protection, but something that might require boosters. We don't really know that yet.
The whole T cell, B cell combination of immunity with coronavirus is still a question.
I'm more optimistic about that. Where I think is going to hold us up a lot is safety. In the 2003
SARS vaccine work, there was some real challenges that developed with the animals with something
called antibody dependent enhancement, ADE, where if you made just a little bit of antibody,
that was bad because then when you got infected with the real thing, you had this antibody
dependent enhancement that was a shock like picture and was a real challenge. And that's exactly what
happened to the dinghy vaccine in the Philippines that got pulled two years ago, was that that
vaccine had an ADE component to it that nobody had appreciated. And because we have a history
with this vaccine with ADE, I think that no regulatory agency, at least in North America or
EU, is going to license that without substantial safety data. And if that occurs, let's just say
even one per 10 to one per hundred thousand population, think how many people you have to
study before you can actually know, is there an increased risk or not? And if this was a really
common side effect, three or four or five percent got it, that would be a much easier situation to
study. So I think that there will surely be pressure to get it evaluated and licensed and
made as soon as possible. But right now, I think the ADE thing is one that's going to hang over its
head and regulators are going to make certain that we have enough data to at least begin to address it.
What's the technical reason for that, Mike? Because that's not something that we see with
influenza, for example. No, we don't. In fact, it's more of a flavivirus type issue and the
coronaviruses we've seen it where basically this whole immune system set up. I mean, in a sense,
it's somewhat like dengue hemorrhagic fever, where you've been infected with one strain
and then you have the second strain infection that has enough cross protection but not sufficient to
fully protect you. And so it really is an immunologic phenomena. This is part of why
hep C vaccination has never really been successful as well. Isn't hep C also a flavivirus?
Yeah, I think that's also but exactly one of the reasons why it's been a problem. So I think that's
going to be a challenge. But let me just say there's one other challenge that I think people
haven't thought about yet. And that is, again, the supply chain thing where we just assume anybody
can do anything because we got something. Vaccines take manufacturing capacity. Right now, there is
no big manufacturing capacity sitting out there empty, waiting for some unknown virus to attack us
and then cause for a need for a major vaccine program. And so right now, the only players,
there's one single one player in this entire effort that even has the capacity to manufacture
these in any meaningful way. All the other ones are smaller startup companies that are bringing
some good science to the table, but they all are likely acquisition type issues where if they got
the product, they get bought by a big company and move on. And relatively speaking, the big companies
have not gotten involved. And I think that we have to also look at how do you make enough of this
vaccine for millions and millions and millions of people? And how long would that take? I remind
people that Ebola vaccine, which was heavily funded by the defense industry in both the United
States and Canada because of the concern about a bioweapon use. And so therefore, when it came into
the quote unquote Ebola battlefield in 2015, a lot of work had been done on it already. And it still
took almost four years to get that thing licensed with the data that it had and the ability to provide
the manufacturing dynamics, etc. So I think if we do everything we possibly can here and we can show
it's effective, a relative sense of safety, being able to find the manufacturing capacity. We're still
talking 18 months, I think, at the earliest. And that's not because people aren't going to be
working 26 hours a day. It's just that's what it takes. Yeah. I mean, I think another just point to
make that and drive it home is just looking at Shingrix. When we came out with a much improved
vaccine for Shingles, I don't know if you recall, but you couldn't get that vaccine for your patients
over 50. I'm one of the high risk people. I'm an old guy. I know that. Yeah. We had a really
hard time getting that vaccine for our patients. It took many of them needed to wait six months
to get it. And obviously it's a fraction of the demand. So it's just worth sort of contemplating
that. And I think the other thing that I want to go from this vaccine discussion into the sort of
the antivirals, I read a really interesting statistic the other day that I actually,
I guess I knew it was not great. I didn't know it was this bad, but it looked at sort of antiviral
drug development from about 1963 until present or thereabouts. It was a couple of years old.
A little over, oh, I don't know. I want to say in the neighborhood of 5,000 antiviral inhibitors
were proposed in the scientific literature, but only 90 of these, 9-0, were approved for final
use over about a 55 to 60 year period. And by the way, of those 90, about 40 were for HIV.
So again, I'm not minimizing. Yeah. So if you took HIV out of this, we're talking about maybe
50 drugs developed with any efficacy and safety to warrant approval in a 55, 60 year period of time.
What does that tell you? Well, I'll tell you what it tells me is I harken back to when I was in
medical school and I went to NIH to spend some time there and I was in an immunology lab. And I
just remember a lecture one day that left such an impression on me, which was, and this was
immunology through the lens of cancer. But the point was the T cell biology is so robust. T cells
are so amazing at what they do that they save us from all these viruses that otherwise we'd be
hosed from as evidenced by how few we have in terms of effective antiviral drugs. In other words,
if not for the fact that we had a competent immune system that could fight off most viruses,
we'd be doomed because our hit rate of developing drugs to stop viruses is actually
pathetic compared to our ability to stop bacteria. No, you're absolutely right. The good fortune,
I think, is we are today in a better place in part because of the research that HIV
led us into and gave us a better sense of how to do research. But I would absolutely agree with you.
Anybody thinks this is a slam dunk, it's not. And I worry about the fact that we've already made
judgments to a certain degree about what works and doesn't work. I happen to chair four different
major work groups for WHO on what they call the R&D roadmaps for epidemic diseases. We both allow
Sunnipa and Zika. Early on, Ebola vaccine was moving along fine. We were overseeing that,
but the therapeutics were still a question. And everybody had assumed ZMAP, a monoclonal
antibody, was the drug. If you didn't use ZMAP, it was almost unethical. Finally, in this most
recent outbreak in the DRC, a randomized control trial was set up, and ZMAP didn't even finish in
the top five drugs. And it was one of those ones where when you realize, wow, we've been using this
for years with the assumption thereof, I hope that we have very effective drugs in this current
regimen approach with the COVID-19 disease, but I don't know that we do. And I think, as you so well
know, we have two kinds of drugs. The Coroquine, for example, are immunologic modulators,
toll-like receptor modulators. Whereas if we have people dying from a myocarditis type picture,
well, that's a whole different situation. We may actually cause problems using Coroquine. So I think
that we just don't know yet. And I hope we have multiple fronts to deal with this, but the answers
are far from there yet. They're just far from being there. I want to come back to the antiviral
in a sec, but I want to pick up on a thread there, which is, isn't that the second time you've
mentioned it? Basically, we're so early in this and we're still back on our heels. I feel like a
boxer who's been punched in the head so hard. I'm having a hard time thinking about counterpunching.
All I'm thinking about doing is not getting hit again. We haven't really done the analysis on the
survivors yet. We don't understand how much lingering myocarditis is out there. We don't
understand how much lingering kidney disease is out there. We don't understand how much lingering
lung disease remains in terms of fibrosis or permanent destruction of a subset of the
pneumocytes. Is there anything that you've learned from SARS and MERS about the survivors that we can
take as a potential proxy for long-term view on the health of the survivors?
I can't say from a clinical standpoint, I know that. SARS was the one in and out. There surely
were over 7,000 some survivors and how much subsequent morbidity that they had with that,
I can't tell you. The one thing I can tell you, which I think is another observation, but hopefully
a positive observation, is that having done all the work in the Middle East on the Arabian Peninsula,
unlike with SARS, where once the palm service were taken out of the market, humans weren't
getting pinged anymore with the virus. They stopped it. With MERS, those camels keep transmitting and
transmitting. People who come from herds, where they're close to those animals, those are the same
animals that infected them if they go back to. It turns out that I'm not aware of anyone since 2012,
almost eight years, who have been infected going back into a relatively high infection rate in
their own animals, have ever gotten reinfected. Again, the assumption that I think we have to be
careful about, does that mean they're really protected or not, but we haven't seen that again.
That's probably the only takeaway I can come with, but it doesn't answer the very important question
you're asking, what is that residual? What's it all about? Even understanding for certain what
got us into this situation with underlying comorbidities, I'd like to understand more,
why do certain comorbidities actually predispose you to a bad outcome? What is it about that?
I was going to ask you, what do you think, for example, in type 2 diabetes makes a bit more sense,
but what about type 1 diabetes, where there still seems to be an increased risk, and that's
especially concerning for young people? Exactly, I don't know that. Of course,
that's going to be overlaid with obesity, so then you're going to have both issues operating at the
same time. How much of that is compromised lung capacity? How much of it is actually the diabetes?
That's what's really unclear. What about immune compromise? What do we know about immune-suppressed
patients? We've actually tried to get more information from the Chinese on that. We've
actually made formal requests for that information, and all we get back is saying is that they didn't
see any big increase in immune-compromised people, whether they were surviving cancer patients who
may have been predisposed to a pneumococmic compromised condition, etc. No one has reported
out of the Chinese data. I've not seen it out of the data from Italy other than to say,
what do you mean by immune-compromised? You're over 80, what does that mean? But from a clinical
standpoint, not someone who would actually, we'd classify as immune-compromised. I've seen nothing
on HIV AIDS, for example. Nothing that suggests HIV status puts you at a higher risk at all.
Yeah, again, this is yet another point on the list of things that differentiates this from influenza.
If we're looking for ways to contrast this, again, it's hyperimmunity, immune paralysis versus not
especially immunogenic to the same extent. There's just so many things that make this different that
as more and more time goes on, the more and more I feel we do ourselves a disservice trying to
compare these two. It's understandable why we do, but it could potentially mislead us if we continue
to use influenza. Yeah, and you raised a very good point about I use influenza from a transmission
model, but I don't think clinically you can. And one of the areas we ran into that was with kids.
When you look at kids today, there is pretty compelling evidence now out of studies that
were done in China that the kids do get infected at the same rate that the adults do,
but they just don't show clinical signs and symptoms, which is just the opposite with
influenza. Kids become little viral reactors in school. They transmit to everybody, including
their parents and their older sibs, and they're sick. And so there is an example of a difference
right there where what's happening with influenza in kids is not the same thing that's happening
with the COVID-19 in kids. Mike, have you given any thought to the notion that you alluded to
at the outset that you estimated R0 was somewhere between 2 and 2.4? We tend to talk about R0 as
though it's a blended number between the symptomatic and the asymptomatic spreaders.
Is there any utility in trying to think of R0 as separate and potentially assuming that the
symptomatic people might have a higher R0, although that doesn't necessarily have to be the case?
Again, you're asking a great epidemiologic question because we're having that debate right
now in a sense. I've always said R0 really didn't apply to MERS and SARS because these
super spreaders were so important. You could have five patients, six patients, 10 patients,
didn't transmit to anybody even when people let their guard down and didn't do a good infection
control. Then somebody could come in and wow. I was involved with helping the follow-up
investigation at Samsung Medical Center in Seoul in 2015 when an individual came back from the
Middle East to Seoul and they actually were infected. They went to hospital A. Another
patient was in hospital A. That person infected that other patient who then upon discharge went
over to hospital B, i.e. Samsung Medical Center, and transmitted in one afternoon an
emergency room, 60 some people. I mean, that was dynamic. Just to be clear, this is a property of
the host, not the virus because it's the same virus. Exactly. You're right. Same virus.
To say that the R0 in a situation like that is kind of like saying your head's in the freezer,
your feet are in the oven, but on average your temperature is just right. That doesn't make sense.
I've always challenged the R0 because I think that it was way, way, way out on the curve. In some
cases we saw lots of transmission. Well, I think with this disease we have a hybrid. In fact,
there's a great article in today's LA Times, I urge you to go look at it, highlighting a major
event that happened at a choir in Seattle. I saw it. If I recall, 60 people in the choir showed up
to practice. Yes. 45 have gone on to test positive. Two have died. One was 80, one was 83.
Three are in the hospital. So yes, there was something strange about that. So, you know,
we had these events like that. And I think that we've had more of those than we care to realize.
But on the other hand, we also have, I think, the regular transmission. What was really fascinating
about the Kristin Drazin and his group in Munich have followed up on individuals there who were
part of this early outbreak associated with somebody who had flown from Wuhan, China to a car
manufacturing location in Germany, was supposedly mildly ill, asymptomatic, transmitted. Okay.
Well, they followed up on a group of these contacts and they said, okay, as soon as you
get the first symptom call us, which they did, and they have a series of patients that they literally
have blood, urine, feces, throat swabs, nasal swabs, etc. in the earliest hours. And these people
were just getting sick and they were getting progressively sick over time. But what they found
with the virus in the throat was fascinating. This is on culture now, not just PCR. The virus
level in the throats of these people were about a thousand times what they see with SARS at its
highest level. And this was right at the very first moments that they were just showing clinical
symptoms. And if you follow those cases, the virus level drops precipitously over each day,
day four or five, it's really much lower. Now, clearly before that, and their hypothesis is that
these virus levels may have been higher on day minus one, day minus two, but they weren't coughing
or they weren't sneezing. So you can say, well, they may not have been as infectious, but to see
that kind of virus level, just breathing, creating the aerosols. And people want to understand an
aerosol. I tell them there's two things to understand it by. Next time in your house and
sunlight is peering through a window and you see all that dust floating in there and you think, oh,
my house is dusty. Those are aerosols. That's just from us talking. That's from us breathing. That's
what goes on in your house. The second thing is next time you're at a shopping center, hopefully
they open up and you are in a department store, you're three aisles, four aisles away from the
perfume section, you can still smell it. It's an aerosol. So I think that breathing and just the
talking would put that out there. So I think that whether they call it asymptomatic, we kind of call
this pre-symptomatic, meaning that they're going to get sick, but they may be infectious beforehand.
And this is not a surprise. We see this with influenza all the time. Whether somebody is truly
asymptomatic, never showing discernible signs or symptoms, I think is a question that is the data
really come down harder and harder. In fact, I just reviewed a paper for a major journal from the
group in China that found a sizable number of people who are asymptomatic never had reported
symptoms where they had more than just PCR data. They actually had culture data and they were
pretty loaded too. So I think there is a role for these people. How much they're driving the
outbreak, I don't know, but I think we can't ignore that they have to be there. And I do
believe we have SARS-like super spreader events, just like one we just talked about with the
chorus. But there's a lot of us, it's just efficient transmission. Did we learn anything
about what characteristics those super spreaders had that made them super spreaders such that we
might be able to identify these people a priori and isolate them better? No, that is again a
million dollar question we have. And even with all the years of looking at what happens with MERS,
and part of the reason is with MERS, for example, it's not that the virus got less effective in
spreading, we just got more effective in early detection and getting these people isolated.
The first outbreaks, for example, in the Arabian Peninsula with MERS were largely in dialysis units
where people who were in sick, they were in there for a while, and then classic hospital
associated infections occurred where they transmitted to others. Once they figured that
out, and as you alluded to a moment ago, R0 is a relative term. It refers to in the natural state
unaltered, this is who you transmit to. But if you have somebody that's just hotter than the devil,
but you put them in an isolation room, they should transmit to nobody. Technically, there R0 should
drop to zero, even though if you had them out in the waiting room, there R0 might be dead.
I think that's one of the issues with MERS, we can't even tell you for sure, because we've just
gotten a lot better at making sure they don't transmit. And had these occurred otherwise,
like the one happened in Samsung Medical Center, I think we'd see more of these. I don't think we
know yet, but it's a very important point that we do need to understand much better than we do now.
How is anyone to be able to model this out, given all of these unknowns? On the one hand,
I think we would all agree forecasting could be helpful, because it would be great to know
some order of susceptible areas in the country, if not globally. We've talked about it now on a
couple of occasions here, we're going to have to allocate resources intelligently. We can't take
an approach that says it's going to be all hands on deck simultaneously everywhere, because one,
we don't have the resources to do it, and two, it doesn't mirror what's going to happen. So
it would really be helpful to know that while New York is right now the epicenter of this in the
United States, these five cities are next in line, and therefore we should at a national level be
ramping them up, such that at a local level, they're ready. But how do we do this? I mean,
I think my fear is, and we've internally been working on models, we continue to work on models,
we're collaborating with people, putting together models, and they're beautiful and they're elegant,
but ultimately they're wrong. I mean, they just have to be wrong, because we don't know the
simplest things that the models are very sensitive to, such as R0. And I mean, that's by far the most
important metric, which of course the problem is, it's a single number or a couple of numbers
in a model that as you point out is anything but a single number. The average, the example that is
often used, the average, you can drown in an average of three inches of water. So just as you
can have your feet in a freezer in your head in an oven and still be on average at the right
temperature, it's very complicated. And it's not just to say, we don't know what the distribution
looks like. We don't know what the probability distribution looks like of these things. So
as someone who has studied these things for such a long period of time, are you more or less
optimistic that this exercise of projection and modeling is a fool's errand? Or what do you think
we should be doing here? Well, first of all, let me just say I'm not a modeler. I've had a lot of
graduate hours, statistics classes, and I ascribe very much to the fact that all models are wrong.
Some just provide helpful information. And I've always said that. I've always been, I mean, I had
to live through the 2014, 15 Ebola situation where WHO came out and modeled it and said, we're going
to have 20,000 cases. And CDC said it could be as high as a million. And it scared the hell out of
everybody. And we had to explain the next year why we didn't have a million cases. It was close to
20,000. And just that error by itself created a lot of controversy because it made it look like
we're trying to really hype this. I think here, the points you're raising are exactly the ones
that we've been looking at carefully to say the variability around this feature is from zero to
one. I mean, it's from infinity. And so that one factor is kind of like A plus B plus C plus miracle
and you get an answer. And the miracle part just can't be there. Okay. And so I think that that is
a challenge. On the other hand, I would say you can theoretically say without knowing if it works
like this, this is what will happen. If you were able to suppress it in 85 or 90% of the transmission
events, you can have this happen. Or if you do this, you can have that happen. But it can't tell
you that's what it's going to be. It can just tell you within the framework of what might it look
like. I think you're exactly right. I have gone, my predictions, which I talked about earlier,
and I surely don't need to sit here and sound, well, look at me. But we were right on with this
thing all along, right to this point, even to pick in hotspots. And now we can't. I can't tell
you for certain what it's going to do because it's beyond the scope of our experience. And we were
just modeling the lot intellectually, not statistically on the flu transmission model,
because it looked like that a lot. I think you're asking exactly the right question. What
intelligence would give us the information so that we could plan this is the next front. Two weeks
from now, this is what we're going to need to be, this is how much we're going to need to have.
And we just don't have it, which is one of the other real shortcomings of our ability to respond.
Today, weather forecasters can tell you, you got 80% chance in this region right here of having
tornadoes today. I can tell you, I can paint the whole United States. We have 100% chance of
having a COVID-19 problem, but I can't tell you exactly much more than that right now.
Is there any evidence that this is a globally coordinated effort on intelligence now,
or is everybody still kind of acting like the guy who just got punched in the nose, who's
still stinging from the pain and trying to not get hit again to worry about the person
sitting in the front row and whether they're drinking a Diet Coke or a Diet Pepsi?
Many of us were incredibly disappointed, for lack of a better word, on the WHO in its response.
There was a sense that China's going to contain it, the whole world can contain it. And I give
great credit to China for what they did, but they didn't contain it. They slowed it down.
I surely give them that. But why did they close down all their movie theaters last week again?
Why did they remove all the outside reporters to China two weeks ago? I think many of us think
that they are in part experienced in some resurgence as they're opening up their economy
again, and they don't want anybody to know it. And I know that's a strong statement,
but I've talked to a number of people from Asia who would say they tell you the same thing.
So when you look at what WHO did, I think they set us back a great deal because they made
countries believe if just the few countries that were going to get this would just do the
containment work, we could stop it. And we couldn't. Trying to stop this kind of transmission,
like trying to stop the wind. And so we held back on a preparedness and gave people excuses not to
do it. Now, again, we don't have global leadership in terms of how do we coordinate this? How do the
low and middle income countries do with this versus the high income countries? Every country
is fighting for the same tools, the same tests, the same N95s. And we don't have a way to globally
allocate those in any kind of meaningful way. So the have and have nots are going to fight it out,
and the haves are going to get more, and the have nots are not. The only thing that ironically,
we have going for us, which is in a sense a sad commentary, there are a lot less at risk people
living in low income countries, because they already died. And they're not able to be around
80 with long term renal disease. They died a long time ago. And that's a sad commentary,
but in a sense may do better on case fatality rates overall than we do, because they're not
going to have that high risk. Yeah, when you, again, this is not a statement of low income
countries. So, but looking in Europe again, when you consider Italy, Spain looking very similar,
and then Germany looking different, do you think that the majority of that difference is explained
by the underlying health of the population? Do you think more of it is just stochastic bad luck,
where in Italy and Spain, the regions that got hit first happened to have a greater center of
older, more susceptible individuals? Do you think it is an artifact of testing? I mean,
how do you explain, what are your explanations for potentially those differences?
Yeah, I think it's totally artificial. And I think as demographics, if you look at what happened in
Italy, it started in the ski areas, but it quickly got into older populations. If you look at Germany,
a lot of that was introduced back in Germany from the Italian ski areas. And it was in a younger
crowd. If you look at where the illness is, I can tell you right now that it's starting to change.
And it's starting to see more transmission in Germany in older populations. And when that
happens, case fatality rates go up. It's just like in Korea, when Korea had this predominant
case mix of these younger individuals in this religious sect, case fatality rates were one
thing. Now look at what's happening in the older populations more involved, case fatality rates are
going up substantially in Korea. I hate to say this, but every week is like a snapshot. It's not
the whole movie. And if we could play the whole movie out for the next two to three years, I think
there'll be a lot more similar kinds of pictures that will over time bear that out. That where the
risk factors were for comorbidity, associated severe disease, we're going to see higher case
fatality rates. When you age adjust and when you adjust on risk factors, I don't think there's a
lot of difference here that we're going to see around the world. Mike, I want to be sensitive
to your time. And of course, I want to make sure that you'll agree to come back and talk with us
in a week, two weeks, something like that. Because as you said, the rate at which this is changing,
I mean, to talk again in two weeks would be like talking over two years outside of the time frame
of an epidemic. But the last question I want to ask you is, is there any of the sort of repurposed
drugs that are currently being thrown around in non RCT manners that you have any optimism around?
I mean, as you probably saw the study that was published out of France on Saturday,
looking at hydrochloro, I mean, again, I thought the study was impossible to interpret because
without randomization, it looked promising, but you could argue that all those patients would
have done just fine without the drug. I mean, without a control group, it's very difficult.
At the same time, I don't want to be critical of that, that we have to do something in terms of
studying this and using case control cohort. If that's the best we can do, so be it. But you gave
a great example with Ebola, which said, look, you can be really deceived by these non-randomized
trials. And when you put them to the gold standard, they can fail miserably. If you're lucky, they just
fail in futility, not harm. Based on that, how much of your energy are you spending looking at
the different types of repurposed antivirals, everything from remdesivir to camastat to
hydroxychloroquine? Are you looking at these closely enough to comment on your optimism or
pessimism? I'm not because I'm not in that part of it. I'm doing much more in the epidemiology
prevention side, but I think it's a critical question. I actually feel confident though,
that the systems are being set up to actually collect the data in a meaningful way so that we
can have answers. And I think you nailed it. I mean, I actually read that same study you're
talking about, and I had the exact same conclusions you did. So I think we just have to,
it's Godspeed, do these as fast as possible, but we have to keep an open mind and let the data
take us wherever it's going to and do them. So on that regard, hopefully I can come back in a couple
weeks and we can have more information. I do believe we're going to have much more information
on therapies much sooner than vaccines. And that could be a really important response.
So I know I said that was my last question. I guess I want to give you one last thing to say.
There's people that are going to be listening to this less than 24 hours after we've recorded it.
So consider it as current as possible. What's the message you want to deliver to people listening
to this who are afraid, who are not afraid? Just assume you're talking to a heterogeneous mix of
people. What do you want to communicate to them as far as what steps they should be taking to
protect themselves and the people they care about? Well, number one, we throw around a lot
of numbers and we have to never forget these are all people. They're our loved ones. This is real
and more people are going to know somebody in the next couple of weeks that are going to be seriously
or die. The second thing is I would just say that we're going to get through this. We are going to
get through it. The question is how do we do it? And that's where I think some of us are trying to
get the kinds of approaches in place that have a better chance of getting us through than not.
I appreciate it. You are wonderful. I would be happy to do this with you again. You're great at
it. You're really good at it. I appreciate that, Mike, and we'll get back to you soon. Thank you so
much. Bye for now. Bye. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're
interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that
allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our
goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end,
membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast
show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the
street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear
everything without having to listen to spiel like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast,
typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the
best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures in the
companies I invest in or advise. Please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.