Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. Welcome to a special episode of The Drive. To celebrate our 100th anniversary,
we have decided to try something a little different. The title of this episode is Strong
Convictions Loosely Held. And what that basically comes down to is Bob asking me questions about
things that I've kind of changed my mind on over the past year and a half. So we definitely go
into a lot of areas where I had a strong point of view or a reasonable point of view on something,
and then after either preparing for a podcast or going through a discussion, I sort of came away
with a different point of view. And it's usually changed my behavior for the better. So we thought
this would be kind of an interesting and maybe even clever way to go about doing a retrospective
on the first 99 episodes. And of course, we also do take a moment to sort of talk about some of the
things, highlights, things that I've maybe enjoyed the most or that Bob's enjoyed the most. If you
like the style of this episode, by the way, please let us know because I'd be open to doing it again.
I actually found it quite fun to reminisce. So again, if you find this interesting, please let us
know. I'd be happy to repeat this every 50 episodes or so. And I guess without any further delay,
I hope you enjoy episode 100 of The Drive. So for episode 100, as I alluded to in the introduction,
we're going to do something a little bit different. And I can't take any credit for this idea. So if
you like it, Bob gets all the credit. If you dislike it, well, hopefully you won't dislike it.
But many of you know Bob Kaplan, the guy behind the guy behind the guy. And one of the things
that Bob has had the luxury of doing, if you can think of it as a luxury, is sort of helping me
get ready for many of the past 99 episodes of podcasts. And there's a lot that goes into
making this sausage known as the podcast. Once in a while, I just get up there and wing it. But I
think more often than not, a lot of thought has to go into who do we want to interview? What do we
want to talk about? What do I need to know in order to have this discussion in sort of a thoughtful
way? And throughout that process, my opinion on things can change. And sometimes not necessarily
through the podcast per se, but just through the evolution of learning and what it means to sort of
scour information and test a hypothesis and see data that conflict with your pre-existing way
of thinking about things. I mean, all of these things have led to an enormous evolution over
a period of time in the way I think about things and do a lot of things. And I think,
I know that on some levels that might sound like a real cop-out to think that one can change their
mind on how things work. But I think that when I've written this before, I think in politics,
that may be a cop-out, but I don't think in science or in medicine that should be viewed as a cop-out.
I think one should always be malleable and willing to sort of lean into new information. And in fact,
the title of this podcast, Strong Convictions Loosely Held, is a phrase that exists in various
different forms. So sometimes it's Strong Opinions Loosely Held, Strong Opinions Weekly Held, Strong
Convictions Weekly Held. I've seen many different versions of it, but in particular, this version
of it, Strong Convictions Loosely Held, is something that I remember one of my patients telling me a
couple of years ago in reference to one of his mentors in the investment space. So this patient
of mine is himself an investor, and he came out of a very successful hedge fund, and he spoke very
affectionately about how he was mentored there. And he said that that was sort of one of the things
that allowed them to be so successful was they had very strong convictions and they would make
bold investments based on those things, but they were very loosely held convictions and they were
always looking for ways to change their information. So in that spirit, I am joined today by
Bob Kaplan, and I think Bob has, along with maybe two or three other people around me clinically,
as good an insight into some of the various things I've changed my mind on. And so, Bob, how do you
want to do this? Do you want to just ask me about things I've changed my mind on or point them out
to me or call me out on what you want to do? Yeah, I think that works. Call you out on things you've
changed your mind. But again, I think it's really important. That's a feature, not a bug. One of the
quotes that I heard or somebody talking about this idea of the strong opinions, strong opinions
weekly held is it was on a blog actually, and it's Richard Feynman, just to confuse everyone,
Richard Feynman the other, the SUNY biochemist who said that a colleague at NIH said,
And by the way, that's SUNY S-U-N-Y. Just to confuse people. Just to really confuse people now.
It's not the Shia Richard Feynman. It's, yeah, forget it.
Yes. So he had a colleague, at least he wrote this in his blog, and he said,
what you do in science is you make a hypothesis, and then you try to shoot yourself down. And I
think that that's really succinct. And the podcast for over the 100 episodes, Peter has a lot of
hypotheses, which is great for me, because I think I share a lot of those and I get to dig into them
as an analyst. And so I think from a selfish perspective, what I see in podcasts and the
episodes and why Peter is so successful, other than his rugged good looks, is that he has a lot of
hypotheses. He has a lot of ideas, and he's not afraid to just say whatever he thinks and try to
find the people who are the absolute experts or even just somebody who disagrees with him and his
take on something, try to dig into it further to see basically to see if he can shoot it down,
because I think the more hypotheses you can shoot down, actually, things get a little bit simpler,
even as much as we're waiting in a lot of this uncertainty.
But a lot of that actually occurs behind the scenes. I hear what you're saying, but I think
most of the shooting down is not actually done in the podcast. It's actually done in the preparation
for it and some of the analyses that come after the fact. So I also could imagine somebody listening
to this saying, well, your podcasts aren't really that contentious. It's not like you're getting
into rip roaring fights. It's not like our podcast is sort of an environment where we're always just
trying to come up with a contrarian point of view or an antagonistic point of view. I think
a lot of the places where my minds have been changed has been in getting ready to do it.
And sometimes, frankly, it just doesn't have to do with the podcast, but I do think this is a great
excuse as any to be 100 episodes into this thing and say, hey, two years ago, what did I do or what
did I think or how did I behave in a way that was different from today? So yeah, hopefully we've got
some interesting ones to talk about. I've seen that you and Nick have been comparing notes.
We have. I've got a good mixture here of hard topics and maybe a little softer. So we'll see
if we can sprinkle them in. This might be on the harder side. Metformin. So maybe think about,
I guess in the context of the episodes, it was probably it was summer of 2018 or so you started
the podcast since then. How have your strong convictions, if you had them, changed at all
since then? Well, in the summer of 2018, I was taking Metformin. I had been taking it for about
seven years. I think I started in 2011, and that was based on a lot of research that I had seen
and read in a white paper we had written internally that looked at the benefits of
Metformin in people with type 2 diabetes and in people without type 2 diabetes, but with obesity,
which was probably just a proxy for hyperinsulinemia, but it's not entirely clear. But the benefits were
not subtle. In particular, the benefits were around a reduction in cancer mortality and
survival with cancer as well. So both a reduction in the incidence of cancer and an increase in the
survival of cancer. And we certainly weren't the only people to figure this out in 2011. There are
people who figured this out long before us, but we were sort of, I think a little bit early on the
cusp of viewing Metformin as a drug that might have a benefit for people who were not type 2
diabetic, but looking for sort of a boost in longevity. And truthfully, not a lot of our
patients in the practice were taking Metformin. One, because my convictions, I guess, weren't that
strong. They were strong enough that I was willing to take it because I could also kind of monitor a
bunch of things in the background, but not strong enough that I felt like it should be dispensed like
you would dispense chiclets or tic-tacs to people. I don't know why I said chiclets or...
Because you dispense them like candy anywhere you go. We know you're the chiclets and tic-tacs guy.
Whenever I don't know the last time I had a chiclet or a tic-tac, do they even make
chiclets anymore? I think they do. I don't even remember seeing these things in a grocery store.
I know they made tic-tacs. I've seen tic-tacs, but I don't think I've seen a chiclet in a long
time. I miss chiclets. So that said, a lot of patients over time would say, hey, I've heard
about this drug called Metformin, kind of interested in it. What's your take on it? And sort of share
our white paper with them. And in the end, we ended up prescribing it for a number of patients.
I would say off label, meaning these aren't patients that were hyperinsulinemic or diabetic.
So fast forward. Well, actually we had an interview with Nir Barzilai, who is certainly
one of the world's experts on this topic. That was a very interesting podcast. I
learned a few things there that I didn't even know before, which again, given that I'd been
spending so much time thinking about Metformin, I think that really speaks to Nir's depth of
knowledge on that front. But somewhere along the way, something changed. And the first clue
was December of 2018. So in December of 2018, which was when I first became interested in
zone two training, it was the first time I'd ever been checking my lactate levels
under low levels of exertion. And it was the first time I'd been just checking lactate levels
in a while since I hadn't been doing much lactate testing since I stopped competing in
sports where that mattered. And I was kind of surprised at how high my lactate levels were,
especially my fasting lactate, just baseline, like not exercising lactate levels.
And that got me poking and poking and poking and coming to the obvious conclusion that Metformin
is a weak mitochondrial toxin. And as such, it probably shouldn't be surprising that you'd have
a higher level of lactate. In medical school, every student learns that one of the potential
rare complications of Metformin is lactic acidosis. I'm sure somebody in an ER somewhere has even seen
it. So again, it's not a huge stretch that you would see elevated levels of lactate. But it did
get me thinking, which is, wait a minute, what if the benefits of Metformin are only going to be
most pronounced in people who have otherwise quite defective mitochondria to begin with and or people
who can tolerate a slight hit in the sort of mitochondrial performance because of all the other
benefits they're getting? And what if that doesn't hold true for someone who's otherwise quite healthy
and looking to really maximize mitochondrial health and throughput? And basically, since that
time, I would say that more and more literature have probably emerged suggesting that we might
want to think about Metformin different in people who are quote unquote sick versus healthy. I hate
using a stupid division like that sick versus healthy, but I mean, I could sort of explain
what I mean in a bit more detail, but I think people get the gist of it. What if this is a drug
that still offers a sizable benefit to people who are metabolically ill, but that benefit sort of
evaporates in people who are not. And so I would say that my position today, so I've stopped taking
Metformin after making this observation in December of 2018, I then spent the next six months,
maybe not that long, maybe the next four months experimenting a lot with it. So only dosing it in
the evening, but not in the morning, reducing the dose, like making a whole bunch of changes to see
if I noticed any difference before ultimately stopping it and then stopping it altogether.
And then realizing a couple of things. One, yeah, my lactate levels went down and my zone two
efficiency as measured by lactate went up, but also my glucose levels are a bit higher. There's
no question it was suppressing glucose levels and that was probably a good thing. So I have no way
of knowing if the net benefit of stopping Metformin has been positive or negative, but I now would say
I reserve Metformin prescriptions for patients who obviously are in need of it from the standpoint
of glucose and insulin regulation, but I don't view it really as a pro-longevity agent yet. Again,
very likely we'll be having a discussion in two years, Bob, and I'll have changed my view again.
There will be some new data that will have emerged that will have told me that yes, despite the
elevated levels of lactate, it's still a net positive even in someone who's metabolically
healthy. And we've obviously looked at a bunch of other papers that look at the impact of Metformin
on muscle mass and training effects. Though a lot of those studies seem suboptimal because they
don't include some of the more functional analyses of the muscle that you'd want to see. So I don't
think this is not an open and shut case. We have a lot to continue to learn, but as of today, I have
a really different point of view than for the previous decade. And I don't think the jury's
necessarily out that in the next 900 episodes that you do going forward, you'll probably have a few
that are on Metformin and you may change your thinking on it down the road, I imagine. Yeah.
I mean, I think one big thing that's going to be interesting is to see if TAME, which is the study
that Nier Barzil I spoke about on our podcast, does TAME actually get funded? Because again,
if TAME is done correctly, it's really not going to be weighted towards people with diabetes. It's
going to be looking at people without diabetes and asking the question, can this extend life
indirectly via mitigating the onset of chronic disease? So in the end, nothing matters more than
that is health span and lifespan. All of these other things that we're looking at, such as
lactate levels and zone 2 efficiency or muscle mass, those are proxies for that. So in a large
enough study, if we could actually go after the thing that matters, that would hold great weight.
Okay. So I'm going to bring in a little social media into this on Instagram. I think it's pretty
clear that anybody who follows you that you recently got a dog. You're snuggling up with that pup.
And along the same lines, have you changed your mind on having a dog? Because I believe in some
of the podcasts, maybe we've talked about in the AMAs and other times about the reluctance to get a
dog and maybe you caving at some point down the road. Yes. We do have a puppy. Four weeks ago,
we got her little Molly and you are absolutely correct that remember that scene in planes,
trains and automobiles when I think it was John Candy's character says something to the effect of
if I'd woken up with my head sewn in the carpet, I would have been less surprised. Remember that line?
I think I thought the day that we were going to get a dog was never, I just thought it'll never happen
because I don't have the bandwidth to absorb any additional work. My wife is already functioning
at the level of three wives. And it's just like, why would we do that to ourselves? And even though
our daughter was the one begging, it's not like she can take care of a dog when she's at school
or whatever. So I was just like, no, this is never going to happen. And then I don't know what, I mean,
I just don't know what happened. For lack of a better way of describing it somewhere in there,
the resistance just weakened. And I was in Australia and I must admit prior to that Australia trip,
we had gone and looked at a couple of puppies in a dog shelter nearby. And I must admit there were
some cute little puppies in there, but I still kind of came away from that experience thinking,
we just need a couple more years. We just need the two guys to be a little bit older and a little
less dependent on us. And then somehow they just went to the dog shelter when I was in Australia.
They FaceTimed me from there and said, there's this little girl, little puppy, Molly,
she's perfect. And they gave me all the reasons why she was perfect. And I actually went out to
social media to seek an opinion. This was like one of the few times social media was actually helpful,
because this puppy was the runt of her litter and she was visually impaired. And I really wanted to
know if we were biting off more than we could chew. And so I asked that question broadly and
the feedback was overwhelming actually, both on Twitter and Instagram. And people said,
she's going to make an awesome puppy. And I will say this a month in, it's way more work than I
expected. And not so much for me, but certainly for my wife and for my daughter and for me too,
but I'm taking on 10% of the additional work. But I think people were right that a dog that
doesn't see perfectly, perhaps coupled with some other characteristics of just being a rescued dog,
she's amazingly gentle and sweet and kind. And I don't know. So I don't regret it, even though
it's harder than I thought it would be. And there have been a number of accidents that have required
significant cleaning. But I think I'm getting the point that people had been trying to make for
years when I had been saying, why would anybody get a dog? Which is, I think there are these
intangible benefits that come from a dog that you don't appreciate. If you try to just think
about it with your logical brain, you guys have a dog, right? We do. The dog has passed. We're
going to get another one. But yeah, I mean, I definitely share your feelings about it. It's
funny. It sounds a lot like having a kid where you think you get older. I think if you don't pop one
out when you're younger and you're older, you're trying to think like, when's the right time? We
need to line up all these things. It's just like, there's never the right time. Although probably
any time is probably the right time if you don't have a kid and then you raise that child. And
there are probably accidents along the way as well. Whether it's a dog or a person, this is
completely inappropriate, but I thought of it when you were talking about loving a dog. This is a
joke. This is not my joke. It says, want to know who loves you more. Put your spouse and your dog
in the trunk of a car and drive around for an hour. When you open the trunk, who's happy to see you?
I honestly, I think that joke, I don't know, I've heard it recently, but I would always be amazed
that you just think of dogs and you come home every single day and it's like you went to Afghanistan,
toured duty for three years and you came back and you get that kind of reaction every single day.
And it's pretty amazing. I'm a big fan. So I have a...
So I'm in the club now.
Yeah, I'm in the club. It was interesting too. I caught one thing which is great is that
when people ask you, where does Peter Uttia get his second opinions, you can say Twitter and
Instagram, which is nice.
When it really counts.
We're going to go back to the pharmaceuticals. We've got Rapamycin.
However your feelings changed on this one.
Well, this has sort of been another area of real interest of mine for many years,
not quite as far back as the sort of metformin interest, which started I think around 2010,
2011 for me, but probably by about 2012 and certainly by about 2014 when the first
that sort of really interesting ever all in this paper was published by Joan Manick,
Lloyd Klikstein and others in December of 2014. That was a real, real peak to my curiosity.
That was a paper that showed that the strength of vaccination in healthy subjects who were,
I believe about age 65 could be augmented by basically a Rapamycin analog, which again
is counterintuitive, right? That's the adaptive immune system getting better with Rapamycin.
Very counterintuitive because of course Rapamycin's on label use is specifically to suppress the
adaptive immune system. And that's what makes it such a efficacious tool for mitigating organ
rejection. But of course, what that study would show was a couple of things, which is there are
different ways that you can dose it. Two of the three treatment arms in that study were only being
given Rapamycin once a week, one at five milligrams, one at 20 milligrams, by the way,
I said Rapamycin. I almost use Everolamis and Rapamycin interchangeably, but it was not Rapamycin.
And that study was sort of the turning point for me. And what it really led to was the next
four years, just a deeper and deeper look into all of the literature. We've had, I think, two
podcasts that have been dedicated to Rapamycin and mTOR, one with David Sabatini, one with Matt
Cabraline. I feel like we're overdue for another one, by the way, because I know that was very early.
Yeah, a little inside baseball, but those interviews were, I think, like in 2017.
That's right.
Was that Sabatini and it was this summer we went over there, you gave a talk?
That's right. Yeah.
Talked to some geology geeks.
Yep, August of 17. So we're way overdue to go back and revisit that. But basically just more
and more data, both in animals and in humans, really got me to a point where I felt really
comfortable that, one, I was taking enough because you've probably heard me talk about this before,
that you always think of two risks when you're taking a medication that you don't have an
immediate biomarker for. So if you're talking about taking a statin or taking a PCSK9 inhibitor,
well, you have a very clear biomarker that at least tells you if the drug is working.
And similarly, you have either clinical signs or biomarkers that tell you if things are going awry.
Clinical signs might be muscle aches and you might see outside of complete breakdown of muscle,
you might still see significant elevations of CK or significant elevations of labor function tests
or things like that. You have some sort of bearing on either symptoms that would cause
you to revisit your decision to use the medication or lack of efficacy or other signs that tell you,
hey, this isn't a good idea. But with rapamycin, you don't have any of that. I mean, on the symptom
side, obviously, if you take too much, you're going to start to see some of the symptoms like
mouth sores and things like that. But you don't really know if you're taking enough and you don't
know if you're taking too much beyond some of those symptoms. And so you really have to be able
to triangulate on what the right dose is. And so that's what basically took me about four years.
Once I sort of felt like I think this makes sense, there was still, I couldn't quite get to the point
where I could understand what to do, how to do it. And I think that was sort of the big switch that
flipped in, well, probably about 18 months ago, kind of in the fall of 2018. And I would still say
that here I am a year and a half later, I'm still really eager to figure out ways that we can
have biomarkers that can lend some insight into this. Probably more so on the efficacy side,
there's still a lot of questions I have on the use of rapamycin, even though I'm using it. I sort
of cycle it a little bit. I think there's lots to be asked there. Is it the right cycling? Is it the
right period? Is the right on versus off? All of those things are, we don't have enough answers yet,
but my convictions are now high enough on the side of something that looks like what I'm doing
right now is probably beneficial. One thing interesting too, just about the metformin and
rapamycin is, I think you might've talked about this with Nier, that was January of last year,
so about a year ago, is him and a few other colleagues, I think Steve Ostad was one of them,
they were talking about what is the trial that we want to do. I think there was a lot of debate
and healthy conversation around whether they should use metformin or rapamycin. I wish that
there was enough resources in the world to try both, but it sounded like they had to do one,
then it was metformin. Yeah. I remember actually having that discussion with Steve Ostad over
dinner about four years ago at the time before Tame had been fully formulated and saying,
if you're only going to get one bite at this apple, rapamycin might be the more interesting agent to
study. I think their concern was the monitoring was going to be more complicated, just the
economics of trying to understand how the immune system was potentially changing, was going to
make that sort of cost prohibitive study, unfortunately. On the subject of apples,
I don't know why this is apples, I think of archery and shooting an apple on someone's head,
but are you still practicing archery? I am. I practice a lot. I think archery and driving are
the two things that I really sort of just try to carve out time for every single day that I'm not
traveling. Luckily, I travel a lot less than I used to, so that means more practice. How do you think
that goes? I was just thinking that in terms of getting better, the more you practice it, is it
just do the gains become more and more incremental or do you always feel like you're learning something
each session, so to speak? In terms of archery, I think it's more objective where maybe you can
take your score and say on average, I'm improving over time with those things.
Yeah, I think they're both so different and yet so similar. I think that with archery,
it's so hard to explain how addictive it is if you've never done it, but I think anybody who's
fired a compound bow, I think most people are like, oh wow, I can see why this is really something
else. First of all, there's no ceiling to how much one can improve. That's the beauty of something
like this is you have so much ability to measure how you're doing that you can never say, I've kind
of plateaued, I've kind of hit my limit, there's just always a place to go up. Really, it's many
different sports in one. There's the indoor target, you're shooting at 20 yards, and at 20 yards,
you're expected to be able to hit something the size of a quarter. So if you think about that,
something 60 feet away, you have to be able to hit a quarter 60 feet away, and in a perfect round,
you would take 60 shots and do that 60 times. How many times do you think I've done that so far, Bob?
A hundred.
Zero.
See what I did there?
Very nice, very nice. Yes, the hundredth episode. So I have yet to score a perfect
300 round, like a perfect 360 round, which is what that would be. So anyway, this is meaning
all 60 were in the tiny little X. And to be clear, there are days when I find that fact infuriating.
There's times when I get so close and then I blow it at the end, and then there's times I just blow
it in the first shot and I'm frustrated and I don't even want to finish. But you also realize
that archery is kind of a great metaphor for life and you can't focus just too much on your
target. You really have to focus on the process or you're not going to get better. So one of the
things we do a lot in archery is called blank baling, which is taking a shot at a huge target,
like they're these big bales, without actually looking at a target, like literally not having
a target there. So there's nothing for you to fixate onto so that you can just go through the
sequence. And when I'm traveling, I take this thing called a shot trainer with me, which is like a
little string attached to something that sits in your hand that sort of mimics the feeling of the
riser. And I'll take maybe 20 to 40 shots a day in my room, hotel room or whatever, that are obviously
not aimed at a target or not doing anything, but just going through the muscle memory of where are
my feet? Where is the pressure on my hands? How am I feeling the contraction of my rhomboid? All
those sorts of things. Again, if you're listening to this and you're thinking, oh my god, how did
that guy just manage to waste the last three minutes of my life telling me that? Again, I
don't think you have to like archery to appreciate the notion of mastery. And I do think that as
people, we crave getting better at something and that can be lots of things. It doesn't just have
to be a physical domain. It can be an intellectual domain. It can be an emotional domain or a
relational domain. But anyway, for me, this habit with archery, this curiosity started three years
ago and now it's something I can't imagine. If a day goes by that I don't do it, I feel like I'm
missing something. I think there's something to that process. I think about my childhood,
the intellectual pursuit. I had these things uncoupled that I just wasn't very good. I was
not a very good student. 1.44 grade point average in high school. What? Don't fire me. That's
actually really hard to graduate with that kind of GPA. It's not just hard to graduate. How do you
even get a grade point average of 1.44? The secret is not showing up. That's how you do that.
What were you doing? Having fun. At least what I thought was having fun at the time. But I was
also, I guess to the larger point here, not get into my childhood too much.
You can't throw out the 1.44 without explaining it, but okay.
I was also playing hockey and that's a totally different sport, but I excelled at it. I went
through that. You don't automatically excel at a sport like that. I probably, particularly in
Massachusetts, you got to really work at it and it instilled a lot of stuff in me. I never made the
connection until later in my life that intellectual pursuits and educating yourself and things like
that, it's not very much different. It's like in order to be good at blank, you are going to suck
at blank. If you have a few of these victories, Peter, you have so many of these things. I think
you're in a way obsessed with mastery and you have so many different things that you've pursued
excellence in that you realize even if you have no idea what this thing is, if you put the time
and the effort in that you can get better at it. I would put a plug in for anybody at a younger age.
Maybe it's like, I never thought about musical instruments that way, but maybe it is. I know
Olivia plays the drums and that's something you first start and you're just like, you can't keep
a beat. Then check in a few months later and you can see that progress. You just know that work
and effort and time, this sounds like grit, those kinds of things, but they apply to so many
different things. With this podcast, I think there's a parallel there with all the episodes and
all the information that goes into the prep with the guests. I think that you have a
predilection to guests who have a healthy obsession, let's call it healthy, a healthy
obsession with these topics as well. They know a lot about these things probably through
similar practice with those things. It's funny you bring that up, by the way. I actually had
this discussion with Olivia two days ago. I know how it came up. We were sitting there at dinner
and I was just complimenting her on how impressed I was with how hard she's been studying this year,
which was a real switch that flipped in her. It's like, you don't have to ask her to do her homework.
She just wants to do it and she makes cue cards and is always just going out of her way to really
try to learn stuff in a way that I just didn't see her doing before. I was just saying, hey,
that's so great, blah, blah, blah. Then she asked me, she's like, well, when you were my age,
how much did you study? I was like, Olivia, you have no idea. You couldn't have done less than I
did. I was categorically a moron in school. Again, there's a fine line there. Really, what it was
was I wasn't interested in what was happening and so my interests were elsewhere. The point I made
to her is exactly the point that you made, which was the reason that I was ultimately able to do
well in school was fortunately I had spent all of that time still trying to master something.
It was that pursuit of that that became transferable. I agree. I just think I do pity the
person who's never found it interesting to try to get better at something. To be clear,
you can take it too far. I don't consider archery for me to be the greatest form of recreation
because I am very internally competitive and I'm sometimes too focused on the result and not the
process. There are days when archery is like meditation to me. Just being out there just
feels so amazing and the sun is shining and the wind is blowing and I can disregard the outcome,
but that's not often the case. When you think about the podcast with Ryan Holiday, where we
talk about stillness, I would say that archery for me does not constitute stillness because
stillness can't really have an objective. I think for me, archery carries with it too much of an
objective. I still think that one has to have those other things in there. This is funny. I
didn't even think of it this way, but I think this is one thing I've noticed about having a puppy.
A puppy is as kinetic as she is. It is a form of stillness for me. Taking her out and walking her
and picking up her poop, there's nothing else to be doing and there's no outcome associated with
it. There's no objective. It's literally just a forced reason to be outside and to be observing
the completely comical nature of a puppy. It's funny, even though we didn't pose it this way,
if you want to ask me about another really big change in the way I think about things over the
past couple of years, it's a huge appreciation for how essential it is to have something that is not
object-oriented, outcome-based. Not everything in your life can be outcome-based.
I've recently gone back to swimming, actually. This might be a good segue to another topic,
but it's funny when you were talking about stillness and how some of these little things
that you don't even realize are stillness or stillness. I was going to use the example of
washing dishes and then I realized you've got the forks and spoons and knives game,
so you turned that into a competition. Even a lot of people just wash the dishes and it's
therapeutic for them because it's stillness for them. You turned it into a competition.
Things that were once like, you know, saying a second ago, even swimming for me now is something
that is really a form of stillness. I just started swimming again a couple months ago and I go like
once a week and I don't keep track of how far I'm swimming. I know I'm not swimming too far.
I'm in the water maybe 45 minutes to an hour and all I'm doing is swimming. I'm not doing workouts.
I'm not looking at the pace clock. I'm not doing intervals. I literally just get in the water with
no agenda other than to get wet and hear the sound of water going by my ears. Probably I'm not even
swimming hard enough to get into zone two truthfully. I doubt my heart rates above 120.
That's the next topic. That's where I think this is a good segue. I think this is out of the
row. If you think about it, you can talk about it, but I think that's one of the things is like a
governor putting a rate limiter on your performance when you do zone two. That it's almost like for a
lot of people it is for me doing this reminds me kind of of stillness. Although I might read on
the bike or things like that, but can you talk about zone two importance and how you're thinking
has changed on that? Yeah, when I stopped riding a bike with a purpose, which was for me a time
trial. That would have been late 2014, early 2015. I kind of really just stopped doing any low
intensity aerobic training. Anyone who does ride a bike or swims a lot has plenty of that activity
in them. Even if you're training for the 200 meter individual medley, which is a race that's
very short, very quick and very painful, you still put in hours and hours a week of aerobic
based training. Similarly, if you're training for a one hour all out time trial, you still put in
hours a week of low end aerobic based training. When I stopped doing that, I was like, well,
I don't need to do this anymore. I went from cycling to rowing and running. I was sort of
obsessed with just being as efficient as possible. So everything was all out. I mean,
if I was running, it was going to be a six minute mile. It wasn't going to be a nine minute mile.
I think, especially through the interactions that I had with Inigo, who I met about a year before
I had him on the podcast, which was just recently, it was sort of meeting him and kind of going back
through the literature on that type of training and the benefits that it could have both from
the standpoint of metabolic benefits such as glucose, insulin dependent and insulin
dependent glucose, mediated disposal, looking at just sort of mitochondrial function, mitochondrial
health density, and then looking at sort of the sort of neurotropic factors, the BDNF secretion
that can come from this type of activity. I mean, all of these things were just pointing towards,
this was a glaring hole in my training that I needed to get back. And so that has been great.
And like you said, I mean, one of the things about zone two that I really enjoy is it's just
not that hard. You know, like, frankly, sometimes it's just nice to get on the bike and I probably
spend three or four hours a week doing it. And that is my time to listen to podcasts and audio
books. And I really enjoy it. I can't wait to get on that bike as sort of boring as it seems to be
sitting on a stationary bike for that long. There's never been a day when I've been like,
I don't feel like doing this. I just, I always look forward to it. And I think in large part,
it's because I also get to combine it with learning, which you wouldn't be doing if you're
out there crushing intervals. And not that there's something wrong with that. I think each of these
things has this time and a place, but I think that we can do zone two our entire lives, we can do it
safely. And it just yields enormous dividends. What's nice about that too, for I think a lot
of your training is you've got the smart ERG so you can tie yourself to the mast that the output,
whether you pedal faster, it's going to give you the output that you pre-desired. So you can't
start cheating, which is what I find myself doing when I don't have it on smart. Just the ERG that I
find myself peddling faster, just unconsciously, just wanting to push myself harder. But do you
use a Wahoo kicker? What's your device? Are you on a Wahoo? Yeah, Wahoo kicker. So you can set it to
either smart or set it at a certain level. Yeah. Yeah. I love my Wahoo kicker. Yeah, me too.
Did you ever have a CompuTrainer back in the day? I did. Yeah. I had it on an old Windows
computer. I remember that I had the little CompuTrainer and then it's connected to the
to the bike trainer. Yeah. Tried simulating the Tour de France one year, just in terms of the time.
Yeah. So talk about the time over summer. I had a bucket. My wife now, I can't believe she's my
wife now. I was living in Las Vegas and it was the middle of our, I would sit in our apartment
with a bike trainer and had a bucket with ice of water bottles and things like that. And eggs. I
think I was doing a ketogenic diet. So I was eating eggs at the time, but I don't know if that
was stillness. I wasn't going anywhere. It was stationary biking. So on this topic, moving along,
the importance of deadlifts as an adult, how has your thinking changed on this? I like your history
on this one. So maybe even take it back to in school when you were, you were doing powerlifting
before it might've been in vogue. Yeah. Yeah. Long before it was in vogue, one of my best friends in
high school who was also involved in boxing and martial arts, we would go to the Scarborough
campus of the university of Toronto every day and lift weights. And it was, it's still one of the
fondest memories I have of what a gym could be like. It would certainly be the, it was certainly
not the sunny, warm golds in Venice, but it had some of those features, which was old school,
lots of iron, nothing fancy. Of course, unlike a nice gym, this was like two stories below
ground. So there were no windows poorly ventilated. So in the summer it was staggeringly hot. In the
winter it was so cold, you felt like you were getting frost bitten by touching the iron.
And aside from me and my friend, there were no kids there. We were 14, 15, 16 years old.
And it was this group of men who to this day I think back and like can't believe how strong they
were. And most of them competed in powerlifting. And so that sort of got us interested in power
lifting. And that's how we sort of started putzing around with it. And as most people know who are
listening, or I guess people who might know who are listening, powerlifting is different from
Olympic lifting. Powerlifting is three lifts, the deadlift, the squat and the bench press.
And so yeah, make along for a short grew up doing a lot of deadlifting, a lot of squatting,
a lot of bench pressing was always very horrible at bench press, much better at squatting and
deadlifting. Fast forward to, I don't know, a few years ago, maybe three years ago,
I had an injury where I kind of tore or partially tore one of my obliques. I don't even remember
how I did it. I remember it was very stupid, whatever I did. And everything, tearing a phone book.
That would be great possible. But everything went kind of sideways after that. And I really
was never able to fully deadlift again without some discomfort. And so again, this is now take
it back to maybe 2016, I sort of decided, you know what, maybe the deadlift has
reached its point of futility. And maybe I've extracted all I'm going to out of that. And
there's no denying what a wonderful movement it is, in terms of being a total hip hinge compound
movement. But I was like, look, I could probably get most of the benefits of a deadlift doing
things that place me under less load. And also, again, in the spirit of thinking about longevity,
I thought, why does one need to subject themselves to twice their body weight or more in an axial
load? So I sort of got away from it. And then I think all that kind of changed when I started
DNS, dynamic neuromuscular stabilization, which I started about 18 months ago. And we're going
to have a podcast on this topic, because it's just, there's so much I want to talk about here.
And so actually, I think today we got an email about how we're trying to make some time for this
podcast. So we'll definitely, if you're listening to this, and you don't know what DNS is, dynamic
neuromuscular stabilization, by all means, you should go read about it. But we're going to have
at least one solid podcast on this. But it was through that process that I realized, actually,
the deadlift, for me, was going to be beneficial, not because of the metabolic benefits, I was not
going to be doing Tabata deadlifts, like I used to, or even by trying to set records for how much I
could lift or anything like that, but rather, because it becomes a beautiful audit for everything
working perfectly. So I deadlifted this morning. So today's a Monday, I deadlifted on Saturday,
I deadlifted a few days before that, like I deadlift at least twice a week, often three times a
week, both straight bar and trap bar. And Bob, I don't go that heavy. I don't know the last time,
maybe I've had 400 pounds on one of those on the trap bar in the past year, but I usually
sort of stop at about 350 to 375 on the straight bar, I'm even lighter, maybe 185.
I do a lot of slow eccentrics. I film every single rep of every single set. And I study it,
and I send it to Beth Lewis, who is my coach. And we do so much around making this deadlift perfect.
And I'd rather take a lightweight and deadlift it perfectly several times a week. And I'm not doing
killing crusher sets. Today was four sets of 10, five sets of 10 maybe. And at no point was I past
my limit. So again, I can push myself harder doing other things, but what I could get out of doing
that deadlift perfectly is, do I have just the right amount of thoracic extension? Do I have
just the right curvature in the lumbar spine? Am I activating my glutes? Am I activating my
hamstrings? Am I pulling back instead of pulling up? Am I wedging correctly? All of this little
stuff translates biomechanically to the activities of daily living that matter to me, like getting up
off the floor, picking up one of my kids, lifting a piece of luggage or something like that. And so
if I can do the deadlift and it feels right, then I know I'm ready to do everything correctly. And
when I'm deadlifting and I feel like, hey, this isn't correct, this doesn't feel right. Well,
first of all, now I've really learned what that feeling is. And secondly, I've now learned the
steps that I can go back and reconstruct what needs to be done. And so one of the things I
definitely want to do at some point in the next year is actually put together kind of a video on
deadlift and deadlift preparation. Because I think that there are probably 10 exercises
that I do as a way to get ready to deadlift. And they don't take long. My deadlift checklist
is like 10 to 15 minutes. So it's not so onerous. It's almost like ketosis, the way we were talking
about it in the past, which is it's not even clear if it's the ketones themselves that can sometimes
be the benefit versus the metabolic conditions that allow you to make them. In other words,
I'm not even sure how much of the benefit is the actual deadlift versus all the things you have to
do to do the deadlift correctly. And one of the most exciting things, just on this last thing I
say on this, is it never occurred to me up until a year and a half ago that you could actually
deadlift in a way that puts your spine under traction. That's very counterintuitive. You would
think that anytime you're lifting under an axial load, your spine is under compression. But it
turns out when you learn the right positioning and you understand how to create intra-abdominal
pressure and you know how to elongate your spine, you can actually deadlift and create
traction in the spine actively. And that's why deadlifting is the most important thing I do
before I get on an airplane. Because when you're on an airplane and you're sitting there for five
or six hours, what you really want to do is not let your spine be compressed. And the deadlift
primes me to then go and sort of maintain that activated form of traction. Yeah. It's a
significant investment, but I would say it's worth it that you'll bring your hex bar to the gate
before your flight and pump yourself up and bang out a few sets. I mean, I don't know what it is
about the TSA guys. They get so wigged out when you have your hex bar there at the gate. Put that
overhead. Yeah. If you're TSA pre, they don't mind as much. But if you're not TSA pre, they just lose
it. Sticklers. They're sticklers. Yeah. Separate topic, a little lighter, maybe. Have you read any
good books lately? I am about a third of the way through Andrew Solomon's Far From the Tree. Have
you read that? No, I have not. It's super interesting. It's a long book, so yeah, it's going to take a
while. But I've actually thought it would be probably really interesting to have Andrew on
the podcast. He's obviously just one of those guys that when you're in the process of writing a book,
you probably shouldn't be reading their books because they just make you not want to write
yours anymore because you're so bad. You're like, oh, how does he do it? It's like Sid Mukherjee.
It's just one of these people who are just so, so exceptional in their ability to write. Not a word
is wasted. Everything is just perfect. Prior to that, I reread Stillness is the Key for the third
time. I know we interviewed Ryan a few months ago. That is a book that has just spoken to me probably
more than anything else Ryan has written. He's written some really great books in that series.
Just overall, the other two books in that series, Ego is the Enemy, which I'm also a huge fan of,
and The Obstacle is the Way. Stillness is really the one that captivates me. That's why I've just
finished it for a third time. I've also gifted that book probably half a dozen times. I suspect
there'll be at least a fourth reading of that book in my future. What about you?
Good question. I was thinking in the context of the podcast, and there are so many books,
I guess it's not recently, but for the guests, just reading a lot of the books is great. It's a
pleasure. Actually, think of Gary Taubes and how you read Why We Get Fat, and you had a list of
questions, and you asked him all those questions. There's a version of that where I get to read
these books, and I have a list of questions, and I'll ask you to ask the questions or ping them
off of you. Actually, what I'm reading right now, it's not out yet, but it's really interesting,
which is Vinay Prasad, who will probably be right around the time of this episode, I guess,
or now he recorded around that time. He has a book called Malignant, which is really interesting.
It gets into public health policy and cancer. It's funny about the books that you reread.
There's a Taleb quote. It's funny. He's now like the, I would say, Einstein or Lincoln,
but you attribute all these quotes to him. He has a lot of aphorisms. Is it better to read five books
or to read one book five times? I think it depends on the quality of the book.
Azra Raza is another guest on the podcast. Hasn't come up yet, but the first cell.
That's right. Yeah. We'll be talking with her very soon. That looks like a great book.
I'm waiting. When you had Sid Mukherjee on too, he talked about a PBS that they're going to do
another follow-up, which is not a book, but for that podcast, I went back and I read The Gene
and The Emperor of All Maladies and The Three Laws, which is like a, I guess it's a Ted book.
It's almost like a Ted talk in a book. And that is really, really interesting. And you went into
each law in depth there. My thing is I usually go in the sauna about an hour a day and I either
print out a stack of papers that I want to read for research or just read a book in there. So I
should probably just write all the, put these down in a spreadsheet and see what I'm accumulating as
far as reading. But a bunch of it has been on the podcast prep. I also read that stillness is the
key, which I found that's definitely worth reading again. I've got a bunch of others, but we'll move
on. Baby aspirin and the use for prevention of blood clots or thrombosis during a flight.
Yeah. So I used to be of the mindset that anybody who was on a flight, on a long enough flight,
should be taking a baby aspirin for prevention of deep vein thrombosis. And I just assumed that
that was the case. I mean, it's widely understood that baby aspirin or aspirin in general inhibits
platelets and platelets of course are one of the cellular matters in blood that's responsible for
clotting. So it just struck me as sort of reasonable. And then I don't know, again, maybe about a year,
year and a half ago, kind of did a little digging into this and found that there really wasn't much
evidence that aspirin or baby aspirin had any efficacy in mitigation of deep vein thrombosis,
especially on an airplane. And in digging around, we sort of found that, well, the gold standard
would of course be heparin, which could either be fractionated or ultra low molecular weight heparin,
but these are not very practical. I mean, intravenous heparin is obviously not something
you're going to do before a flight. And even the low molecular weight heparins have to be injected.
So we found a couple of supplements online. One was called FlightTab, I think. I think it was FLITE
Tab. At the time you could buy it on Amazon. I haven't looked in a while to see if it's still
there. But it was a pretty potent agent that actually had pretty remarkable evidence that
it prevented DVT. And then the other is something that is also pretty easy to get over the counter
called Natokynase. And I think that the Natto is a plant. It's plant derived. I think it actually
kind of, it's like sort of a stinky odor is sort of the types of foods that it occurs in naturally
or certain types of mushrooms or cheeses or things like that. But these are things that
actually turned out to have far more evidence. And they were both things I'd never heard of until
we sort of really dug into this question. So that was a bit of a humbling experience
because you think, well, look, on first principles, aspirin has got to be thinning
the blood. It's got to be good for this. And then you realize, well, wait a minute. Even something
as simple as that, when you actually really antagonize the literature, it turned out not
to be the case. And the things that did seem to have some efficacy are things I'd never even heard
of. So it's a little scary because it makes you wonder how many times is that happening throughout
the course of my life. Yeah. This sounds apropos in terms of strong convictions held loosely.
Your feeling on generic drugs, obviously, Catherine Eban was a guest there. What do you
think prior to that and some of the stuff that you were seeing in, I guess, the clinic, or at least
at the some of your patients and taking generics? Yeah. I mean, Catherine's podcast is, I mean,
it would be hard to say that that hasn't been one of the 10 most important podcasts that we've done
in this first hundred. If you haven't listened to that, I suggest you just hit pause on this now
and go back and listen to it. What number was it? Do you know? You can search E-ban, E-B-A-N,
and your podcast player and it'll show up. But I think prior to that, my view had always been
generics are great. They're the exact same as branded except they're a fraction of the cost
and branded drugs are a scam. That was sort of my default thinking all through medical school.
I'd say in the last couple of years, I began to wonder if maybe there were a couple generics that
weren't great because in the case of certain drugs where you do have a very clear biomarker
for use, such as a statin, you put a patient on Crestor, but of course they don't get Crestor,
they get Resuva statin, and you look at their blood level two months later and there's no
change in anything that you would expect to see a change in. And when you query them, they tell you
they've taken it every day and you believe them because there's nothing they need to lie. They
can easily say, I forgot if they did. You see a couple of those things and you start to wonder
if maybe not all generics are created equal. But then of course in the discussion with Catherine,
I came away thinking, oh boy, this is a totally different way of doing things. And frankly,
it's completely changed the way we do things in the practice now. So we work primarily with one
pharmacy that will either at our insistence or the patient's insistence only issue branded drugs,
sometimes even when it is a little bit costly. And when we do generics, we do it through the lens of
looking at the companies specifically that make them and at least taking a first order pass at
cross-referencing that with an FDA list of potential bad actors. So I don't think that has
completely mitigated the problem, but I think it's probably taken care of three quarters of it.
Another one, this one is a omega-3 fatty acids. Your thoughts on that, and obviously Bill Harris
is somebody who came on the podcast recently. So Catherine Eban was number 71, that was in
September of last year. And Bill Harris was in December of last year. And he came on and talked
about omega-3 fatty acids. So what's your take on omega-3 and how has it changed?
This is funny. I think I'm still sort of in my evolution on this. I mean, I think I've
longly held the, for a long time held the view, longly, is that even a word? Do I just make that
up? Longly, I've longly held the view. I have for a long time held the view that EPA and DHA
are beneficial. Obviously had some questions as to, again, how much of it was the other things that
you got when you ate things that were high in EPA and DHA versus just the supplemental thing.
I would say that my thinking has evolved to the point where EPA and DHA by themselves are quite
potent drugs. And we really ought to think of them in that way. So in fact, you look at a drug
like Visepa, which is just pharmaceutical grade EPA at the tune of four grams. I mean,
that is as potent as any anti-cardiovascular disease drug that we have. So clearly EPA
has a benefit to it, especially in patients that are at risk for cardiovascular disease.
I think with DHA, the clinical trials data are still not clear. And there's a pretty interesting
setback on a clinical trial in the fall that was looking at a combination of EPA, DHA, and it was
a trial that was stopped for futility. So there was no harm from it, but there wasn't the big bang
benefit that we frankly expected to see based on the earlier trial with Visepa, which was just EPA.
I think the discussion with Bill Harris certainly increased my level of confidence
in the necessity of EPA and DHA. And also probably drove me to a point of thinking about it being a
higher level that we should strive for. We used to generally look at an RBC or red blood cell
membrane level of about 8% to 10%. But I think I came away from the discussion with Bill Harris
thinking we could really push that up to 12%, 14% without undesirable side effects, and also
getting more value or more benefit from it. I think one area that Bill had a very strong
conviction on that I've also, I've kind of had the opposite conviction to. So I think I'm still in
the space of wanting to learn this. So I think my strong conviction had generally been that excessive
amounts of omega-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids or PUFAs were generally not a good thing. And the
associative data there is not hard to understand. But again, the problem with the associative data
is things that are full of omega-6 PUFAs are often crap. So it's easy to see an association
with high omega-6 polyunsaturated fat and disease, chronic disease. But Bill's point was that the
omega-6 polyunsaturated fats aren't harmful. It's just that diets that are rich in them tend to be
void in EPA and DHA. So his real takeaway was don't think about omega-6 polyunsaturated fats,
you just need to add more EPA and DHA in. That's the issue. And so I think you and I have been
talking about this actually over the past couple of weeks, but I think I'd really like to go back
and do a podcast that looks specifically at the omega-6 polyunsaturated fatty acid discussion
and really kind of dive into the whole PUFAs literature from an omega-6 standpoint. Because
again, this is a very polarizing topic. People just on both sides of this. Both sides I think
have people that I think are quite bright. So I'm a bit confused on that. And for me, it's not really
a huge issue personally, because I just don't gravitate towards those oils. I find them to be
kind of gross. And I don't know why you'd want to consume. It wouldn't occur to me to put canola oil
on a salad when I could put olive oil on or something like that. So on a personal level,
I think the point is somewhat moot because N6 PUFA don't make up much of my diet. But I do think it
has huge implications for public health. And I think it has implications for our patients when
we think about people who are potentially eating a lot of PUFA. Okay. One question here. One theme
in recent episodes, not overly related to medicine, has been the idea of saying no. I think of a
Jason Fried, Rick Elias, actually probably Jason Fried twice have talked about this thing and how
you viewed this sort of in the past and now today, this idea of saying no. How good you are at it,
when do you think it's applicable? And if you've improved on this. I've definitely improved on it
in the sense that there was a day when I couldn't say no or wouldn't say no to anything or anyone.
The pendulum was pretty far off on one side where I was basically on a treadmill of sort of saying
yes to anything and everything that was asked of me. Began to realize that I just couldn't do that
anymore. And I'm getting a lot better at saying no. And I don't think I'm doing it at a level that's
unhealthy either. I mean, you can obviously take these things to far extremes on both sides and
you could sort of say no to everything and become sort of dysfunctional in that way. It's hard to do.
It is hard to do. And I remember there was a podcast that there was someone that Tim Ferriss
had on his podcast. God, I want to say like a year and a half ago. I forget the name of the person,
but hopefully we'll find it for the show notes. It was a really good episode on saying no. And I
remember that was actually the first time I started really contemplating it. And I remember shortly
after listening to it, I had someone who I really liked respected called me and said, Hey, I really
like you to be on the board of such and such. And I mean, deep down, I knew it was going to be a pain
in the ass. I knew it was just going to be so much work. And even just the travel of getting to the
board meetings was like, wasn't in a place where there was easy access and all those other things.
And I remember like thinking, I just, I just got to do this. I just got to do this.
And I remembered one of the lessons in that podcast was don't answer, just say, can I get back to you?
So I pulled the, can I get back to you on this? And then with the benefit of a little bit of distance,
I realized, Peter, you're crazy. Like you can't possibly do this thing. You already lament the
time you don't get to spend at home. So then the next day I just called him back and said, Hey, I
can't do this. I'm sorry, but here's why. And just like this person in the podcast with Tim said,
the guy understood. It wasn't like I'd committed some grievous heinous crime and declining this. So
I think that's just an important thing to remember. And yeah, I continue to look forward to refining
my no saying skills. It's interesting. I think it's always hard for ourselves to do it. But then
when you think in the context of how you work and operate with other people or decision making,
you'll very easily say no, if it's whether it's like having more patience in the practice,
if it's not going to benefit what you have going on, then you're usually very matter of fact. But
I think it's almost like a, it might be like the ego getting in the way or something where you just,
you want to tackle everything. I mean, I think it's, this is probably a little cathartic,
but it's getting into some of this research where you'll have to tell me no, as far as the
the deep dives and the rabbit holes that I want to go down or say like, we're just, we're on a
mission. I don't want to give the milk analogy, but for a lot of these episodes and a lot of the
guests, a little bit of the deep diving can help. But oftentimes it's really about the stuff that
you say no to help shape the things that you actually are focusing on day to day that matter.
Yeah, that's the insight that I think Jason Fried brought to his episode really well, which was
when you're saying yes to something, you're actually saying no to something else. You just
don't know what that something else is yet. That's a very important insight. Then again,
I would, anybody who struggles with saying no, I think would, would benefit greatly from actually
both episodes with Jason, because I think we touch on them in both. Yeah. Yeah. It's funny. I think
Tim Ferriss just himself talking about saying no and his evolution, he's probably done his own
podcast talking about that. And I always think of, I do a lot of reading on Charlie Munger and
Warren Buffett, but if you look at their schedules, they're like practically empty. I think Munger
refers to himself as like a book with legs that all he does is he just reads and that's how he
gets smarter. And so he jealously guards his time. You would look at the schedule and you'd say, oh,
it's wide open. It looks like, you know, if you're the secretary and say, yeah, it looks like a
schedule's wide open. Nope. It's more about saying no and what that schedule can be open to. If you
have all those vacancies there. Yeah. I have great envy for that. And I hope to one day get
to that point where my calendar doesn't look like it does now. And it's much more last minute things
that are being scheduled where you can actually say like, Hey, do I want to have this meeting
tomorrow as opposed to do I want to have this meeting in three months? So I think maybe one
more question, if you want to take it, I know this one is difficult because it's like, what is the
thing? It's like asking you like which of your children is your favorite. But as far as the
episodes go to any of them stand out in your mind, maybe even just like the style or the way
it's happened or separate question, as far as just doing a podcast, hosting a podcast and interviewing
people and having conversations, are there things like going into this that you thought, I mean,
part of it was like, you never wanted to do a podcast. And now I think that you might have a
different opinion about that. So how about that strong opinion, maybe a little more loosely held
today as far as doing a podcast? Yeah, you're absolutely right. I mean, I think the first time
the idea of a podcast was floated to me was about 2014. And I mean, it was the worst idea I ever
heard. And it was mostly due to a fear of the amount of work that would go into it. Because at
the time I knew a few people who were doing podcasts. And it was sort of the only thing they
did was like, well, that's a nonstarter, I just don't have the time to do something where it's
the only thing I'm doing. So it's just not going to happen. And I sort of kind of kept that point
of view, frankly, until about two years ago, when we, or maybe a little less than two years ago,
actually, when we decided to give it a try. So yeah, that was a very strongly held or strong
conviction, fortunately, loosely enough held that I was able to sort of get out of my own way on that.
And yeah, I really can say that I have enjoyed it a lot. It is hard, it is a little more work than I
thought. But also, we have such a big team that works on it, that I have it easier than probably
a lot of people who do a podcast, in that I have a great research team. We have two people that work
exclusively on the podcast and Travis and Nick. So all the heavy lifting of making show notes and
things like that, none of that falls on my shoulders. So all I really have to think about is
having discussions with people and trying to think of topics that I want to meet people who can speak
to those topics. So I've loved it. And it's hard to believe we're at 100 because you sort of realize
there's not that many podcasts that sort of get into the territory of multiple hundreds of episodes.
And I mean, barring some unforeseen thing, we're going to one day be that podcast that's on our
300th episode or something crazy. Now to your first question, honestly, I just I've thought
about this a lot. And I do, I get asked this question a lot, Bob, which is what is my favorite
episode? And I just, it's so hard because they are so different. There are some that I've really
enjoyed from a technical standpoint. I think the Rick Johnson podcast and the Keith Flaherty podcast
really stand out to me as podcasts that I have gone back and listened to several times because
of the technical content in them. So they're probably half a dozen that are like that for
me, where they're just just so much interesting information that I can't wait to go back and
listen to them again, which I don't listen to most of the podcasts. I think on the other side of the
coin, there are experiences for me like interviewing Damon Hill was just unbelievable. And just to
have him be so open and so just available to talk through his own difficulties and obviously
everything that went into his career and beforehand, that was a really special episode for me
as just a fan of his and it was such a fan of F1 and obviously a fan of Senna,
who was his teammate when he died. I thought the Rick Elias podcast really, even though I knew Rick
really well, and there was nothing we talked about that I didn't know, but I just, as it was unfolding
and we were having the discussion, I remember thinking, you know what? I think a lot of people
are going to really benefit from this episode. I know I was. And then we've already touched on
some, but you look at the Catherine E. Ben podcast, which is just an unbelievable opportunity to,
I think, help people with information, which is also kind of part of the itch that we're trying
to scratch here. So the irony of it is if I sat here long enough, Bob, I could tell you something
special about all 99 that came before this with the exception of the AMAs. I could probably rattle
off something special about 80 of these podcasts through the lens of one or more filter.
Yeah. I'm going to bring Tom Brady into the podcast. I mean, it's probably a record as far
as how long I've waited. I think he's often asked the question, what's his favorite Super Bowl ring?
And he says the next one. So I think maybe you think about that with the episodes. What's your
favorite episode? Might be the next one for me. I mean, that's how it is for me. I like reflecting
on these episodes, but the research that goes into these guests. And I think we just have a lot of
similarities as far as our interests. So for me, for me, for you to be creating the podcasts that
you would want to listen to having Z dog, who's your buddy Stanford from Z dog to Marty. I don't
is it Macquarie Macquarie. I usually say Macquarie to Mark Messier to say like, why hasn't
somebody sat down for a multiple hour podcast with Mark Messier and just talk about the Oilers,
one of the greatest teams, if not, I'm sure you would say maybe the greatest team
ever in any sport. I mean, that stuff to me is so cool. Yeah, I think about it that way that it's
similar. I could talk about each one of them and how great they are, but I'm hopefully looking
forward to the ones that come too. Well, I mean, I am as well. I think we're, I just, I know we're
getting better at this. And I remember having, I think I may have even mentioned this once before
on a podcast, whether it was ours or someone else's that I had this little tiny fear when we started
that we were going to run out of things to talk about and run out of people to interview. And
I was sort of reluctant to start this thing and then realize, well, after 50 episodes,
there's nothing left to do. And I think you can attest to the fact that our list of people we want
to have on is growing at the same rate as our AMA list of questions. Like we can't interview
people quick enough at the rate that we want to learn stuff. So I have a feeling we're going to
be able to do this for a very long time. And I do look forward to getting better at it. It is a craft
and it's hard. I do try to listen to some of the podcasts to learn from them. And I've certainly
picked up a number of things I could be doing better. And as I think I talked about on Tim's
podcast, I enjoy listening to other really good podcasts for some insight into how to do this
thing better. But anyway, I'm excited about it. And it's hard to imagine what the next hundred
have to hold actually. Yeah. Well, I'm looking forward to it. I think maybe we cheers, have some
champagne or you can wrestle a centenarian to commemorate the moment. I'm sure that's what you
probably have that on your schedule anyway. Yeah, I've got a little bit of centenarian
boxing this afternoon. Yeah. Well, Bob, this was a good idea. I don't know if it was your idea or
Nick's idea, but maybe both of you guys deserve credit for this. But I think this was a fun way
to commemorate a hundred kind of looking back and looking forward. Absolutely. Thank you for
listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any
topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth
exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much
more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch
of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less
than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions,
topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on
previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts
on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch
of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and
access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe.
You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can
also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast player you listen on. This
podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of medicine,
nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked
to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a
substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not
disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they
should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.