Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. Hey everyone. Welcome to a special edition of the COVID series. This is going to be
COVID for kids. So my guest today is my daughter, Olivia. And this was mostly her interviewing me,
but also a little bit of a discussion in me asking her some questions as well, all pertaining to the
coronavirus, but really through the lens of questions that Olivia had. So if you're a listener
of the podcast and you have kids, this might be the one episode that you want to sort of bring
your kids into. It has, hopefully it answers a lot of the questions that they've probably been asking
you. And maybe these are some of the questions you don't have answers to. So anyway, I hope you
enjoy this special episode of the coronavirus series, Corona for kids. Hey dad. So I know you've done
podcasts about questions people had on the coronavirus for adults, but I thought we could do one for kids.
So the first thing I'm going to ask you is what even is a virus? Well, a virus is a sort of living
kind of living thing that has genetic material in it, which all of your cells have genetic material
in them, but these viruses, they can't replicate on their own. So you know how like you get big,
your hair gets longer, your nails get longer, you get taller. All of these things are cells in your
body that are dividing. Yeah. Well, viruses can't divide without using another body. They don't have
the machinery, so to speak, to divide on their own. So they have to infect a host. That's the term we
use to do that. Now it's important to understand how small a virus is. Do you have a sense of how
small they are? Kind of. Do you think you can see them? No way. That's right. No way. So a virus is
like about a hundred nanometers wide. Do you know what a nanometer is? Something very small.
Yeah. It's like a billionth of a meter. So if we were to cut one of your hairs, and you can barely
see the end of your hair when it's cut, right? How many coronaviruses do you think you could line up
across the tip of your hair if it were cut? Probably hundreds. Yeah, about a thousand actually.
So think about how small that is. That's very small. So we can't see these things,
but these virtually invisible things without special types of microscopes, they get into our
bodies and the bodies of other animals, and they use our body to make more copies of themselves.
And a lot of times when viruses do that, they don't really hurt us or hurt the person or animal
that they're infecting. But sometimes they do. So when you think about bad colds that you've had,
or nasty GI bugs that you've had, that's just a virus that is causing that pain and suffering to
you as part of its replicating process. Okay. So I'm sure a lot of people are wondering this.
So how do you know so much about this virus? Well, I don't think I know that much about it.
To be clear, I didn't know anything about it until a couple of months ago. So there are people who
spend as much time as I spend thinking about longevity or Formula One or all the other things
that I love to think about. There are people who spend their whole lives thinking about these
viruses. And so I just have talked to a lot of those people. And that's how I've learned the
little bit that I think I've learned in the last couple of months. But the reality of it is I pretty
much a noob. Okay. So how did the coronavirus start? Well, I think we have a pretty good sense
that this virus, this particular coronavirus, and to be clear, there are many coronaviruses,
but this particular one, which now has a formal name, that name is SARS-CoV-2. So just like your
name is Olivia, that guy's name is SARS-CoV-2, it causes a disease called COVID-19. That virus
probably originated in bats. But the most recent evidence we have suggests that it went from a bat
to something called a pangolin. You know what a pangolin is? Yeah. It's like a mini ant eater,
like a picture, a little tiny scaly armadillo looking thing that eats ants and little insects.
And these are little tiny mammals that are actually quite protected in China because they're
endangered. But there is some illegal poaching of these things and people do, I believe they use
their scales for medicinal purposes and things like that. So I think the current genetic analysis
suggests it went from a bat to a pangolin to a human. The first person was infected with that
in this part of China called Wuhan probably in about November of last year, so relatively recent.
So like you said, this isn't the first time corona has showed up, but it's definitely the
worst time I'm assuming, right? Yes and no. I think it depends how you define the worst. It's
definitely infecting a lot of people, but there have been other coronaviruses that have shown up,
two in particular in the past 15 or 20 years that have been more lethal, meaning a higher
number of the people who got the infection died. So one of those was called SARS and one of those
was called MERS and those would kill somewhere between 10 and 30 percent. SARS about 10 percent,
MERS about 30 percent of the people who got it. That's a huge number, right? That means in the
case of SARS, one out of every 10 people that got the infection died. In the case of MERS,
one out of every three people died. Think about that. But the good news is those viruses didn't
spread very far, so very few people got them. So in some ways those were worse viruses. Of
course this one is spreading a lot. At this point in time we've got over a million confirmed
cases, but of course we probably have tens of millions of unconfirmed cases. But there are
other coronaviruses that come and go every summer that have infected many more people than that,
but they just don't cause anything more than a miserable cold. Alright, so like you were saying,
this has been a problem before, but do you think it will show up again after this, assuming it's
all resolved at some point? You mean this one in particular or another one? This one. I think
it's a bit too soon to say, but probably. Could another one show up? Yeah. Alright,
so this next question I'm going to ask you is probably the one all kids are wondering. When
do you think we're going to be able to go back to school? I don't really know. If I really had to
guess, I don't think you're going back to school this year. Alright, and I've heard some people
say that not even until maybe next year, is that true? Oh, I think it's really too soon to say. I
know that sounds like a cop out answer, but there are so many things we don't yet know. Like we
don't actually know how many people have this infection. And it could be that a lot of people
already have the infection and they're doing really well and it's not causing that much harm. And in
that case, people who aren't at very high risk for getting very sick could mosey on back to school
and move back into work and things like that. But it's also possible that we have to be much more
careful and much more concerned. And if that's the case, then this quarantine might be something
that lasts a little bit longer. Yeah. So I've just recently heard that the US has hit more cases in
China. Why do you think that is? Well, that's a long story. And it's one that gets my blood a
little bit boiling. So I don't want to talk about it too much. I mean, basically, we didn't do a good
job of preparing for it of a couple of things. So we didn't heed our warnings. So we had very
clear warning signs that this virus was out there and that this virus was very infectious. Furthermore,
we had lots of evidence that it could easily spread outside of China, but we didn't take a bunch of
steps we should have taken. Now, part of this is not just what we did or didn't do in the last
couple of months, but really, this is a much bigger problem that goes back a number of years.
We don't really have the infrastructure in place to prepare for something like this,
because, for example, we don't have a national stockpile of the type of equipment that doctors
and nurses would need to be protected from this if they're taking care of a bunch of people that
got sick. At the beginning of January, when the Chinese government and Chinese scientists
were able to figure out exactly what this virus looked like, that's called sequencing. That's
when you can actually look at the, basically, the fingerprint of what this virus looks like.
So you have a very unique fingerprint. If I took one of your hairs and took it to a lab,
they could tell me exactly what your DNA sequence looks like. And you're the only person in the
world that has that. So we would know exactly what Olivia looks like. And similarly, at the
first week, second week of January, the scientists in China had already done that for this virus.
And that would have been a great time to have doubled down on developing tests in the United
States or taking tests that others had developed and making sure we had enough of them, because
testing is a really important part of this. That's a big way that you can help understand
how people have it and don't have it and how you need to isolate the people that have it from those
who don't. So without having all those systems in place, we were also a little bit late to the party
in terms of understanding what to do when people showed up and were infected. So we had our first
case basically at about the same time that a country like South Korea had their first case.
But we have now had more than five times the number of deaths for an adjusted population,
meaning for every million people in the United States versus every million people in South
Korea, we've already had five times the number of deaths, even though we both started at the same
time effectively. And that speaks to sort of not being able to put these measures in place.
All right. So you were saying that you weren't very prepared and listening to the warning. So
how could we have been better prepared and more aware of this? Well, I mean, I think it's sort of
what I just said. Part of it is non-specific type of preparedness. So it's having the infrastructure
in place to deal with pandemics. So it's having like a pandemic preparedness program that is well
funded, that has all of these things that don't seem that interesting when you don't need them
laying around ready. And then part of it is very specific to this case, which is this is a really
tough virus because it spreads pretty aggressively, more aggressively than say the flu virus. And
look, I just don't think our leaders were doing a great job. Do you think it would have helped if
people started to quarantine sooner than they actually did? Yes, I think it would have, especially
in places like New York, New Orleans, probably Florida. So there were places where a lot of
things just went kind of sideways. Like New York has a high density of people. You've been there a
bunch. You know what New York is like compared to San Diego. You can imagine that a virus that can
spread basically by you breathing on somebody is much more likely in New York. Imagine you're
sitting on the subway. You have these people that have to commute in and out of Manhattan every day
from these different boroughs. So you just have a high population that's close together that has
these commuting challenges where they're in close proximity to others. And so all of those things
would lead to kind of an amplification. And I think that in some ways New York has done the
best job it could, but it probably started a little later than would have been ideal compared to what
we now know from other countries. Yeah, so some people are saying they just want to get the virus
and be over it, meaning they won't have to quarantine anymore and they've already been exposed to the
virus. So it would be a lot easier. Do you think that's a good idea? So the technical term for
that idea is called herd immunity. You know what a herd is? Probably when you get it so that your
body is used to it. Well yeah, but like the herd means everybody, you know what I mean? So the idea
would be once you have chicken pox, do you remember when you had chicken pox when you were a kid?
You're lucky you didn't have to get it that bad because you already got a vaccine for it. But when
I was a kid we didn't have a vaccine for chicken pox, so when we got it it was really bad. But
once you get the chicken pox or once you get the vaccine for it, you're not really going to get it
again. I mean technically you can get a cousin of chicken pox called shingles when you get a lot
older. So that's what people want. They think they won't be able to get it again. That's right, but
there are a couple things. One, we don't really know exactly what the immunity looks like. In
other words, we don't know that once you get this coronavirus, if you recover from it, and let's say
you're one of the majority of people who recover from it, and to be clear most people who get this
virus recover from it. At a minimum 80 percent do, but it could be significantly higher. It could be
95 percent. We don't know if that immunity is going to last them for another six months, another year,
another five years, for the rest of their lives. We don't know. The second thing is
there are certain people who are at high enough risk to get sick from the virus that you might
not want to take the chance of letting them just get infected. So you and your friends are at
virtually no risk from this virus. In fact, in the United States, as of this time, there is not a
single person your age who has died from this virus. That's good. Yeah, it's good for you, but
you have to understand that you could still transmit it to somebody. So if you lived with
your grandparents and you were back at school and you and all your friends had it, and obviously
it would be great that none of you would get very sick. But what if you came home and gave it to one
of your grandparents or gave it to somebody who was at a higher risk and then they transmitted it?
So it's a bit complicated to think of that, but it's definitely something that might end up
happening, and we just don't know it yet. In other words, we don't really know how many people have
already been infected. So you're saying different age groups can have a better or lower chance of
getting it? I don't know if it's a better or lower chance of getting it, but it's definitely a
better or worse chance of dying from it or being hospitalized for sure. So the younger you are,
the better you are, your risk is, and the fewer diseases you have, like high blood pressure
or diabetes or things like that, the better your chances of surviving it.
All right. So what should a proper quarantine look like? Because I know that while we're
quarantined, we sometimes order things from Amazon, and when they order the packages, we have
a specific way of taking them out. We don't bring them inside. We have to wash our hands and take
it apart outside. So explain that kind of. Well, do you know why we're doing that, by the way? What
are we afraid of? We don't want to bring the germs in. Right. There's a chance that there could be
some virus on the cardboard box. So let's assume that the person delivering the bag or someone
or the box or the person who touched it a few hours earlier has the virus. Maybe they don't
even realize they have the virus and the virus is sitting there on the cardboard and then that
cardboard box gets dropped off at your door. So there was a study that was published about
three weeks ago that actually looked at putting the virus on different surfaces, cardboard, plastic,
steel, copper, those sorts of different things. And it started to measure how long the virus
could survive on those surfaces. And what came of that study was that this virus can live for a day,
maybe two days on cardboard. So what you want to do is sort of assume that anything you come in
contact with potentially has some amount of virus on it. Now, that study doesn't really tell us you
can get infected from that because maybe there's not enough virus that's really surviving that
you're going to get it all over you. And if you don't take appropriate precautions, it's going to
infect you. But it seems to me at least that the safest thing to do is to assume that anything
that shows up has some amount of the virus on it and that virus could potentially infect you. So
what we're doing is we're opening Amazon packages outside. We're cleaning off the contents of them
and then just washing our hands really thoroughly. And you remember how long we have to wash our
hands for? 20 seconds. You got it. And that is a lot longer than it feels like, isn't it? It is.
Reese is the best at that, by the way. Is he? Yeah, that kid can wash his hands.
Well, Airy just throws soap everywhere. Yeah, he's not so good at washing his hands.
So is there anything else we haven't covered that you think kids should know about this virus?
I don't know, but there is something I do want to use as an example for kids to think about,
because I've been thinking about this a lot with you as we're going through this. So you can
probably tell, I mean, do I seem like I've been more irritable in the last month than normal?
Yes, kind of. Yeah, I apologize for that. But I think part of the irritability I feel is
just a frustration in what I consider to be kind of incompetence. And I think it's worth
using this as a teaching point because you asked a question, how did we get here? And the underlying
theme to how we got here is we didn't really do the things we needed to do before it was too late.
And so why does that happen? I mean, is it because we don't want to? I mean, I think the point here is
it's sometimes really hard to do things for which the payoff is far in the future.
But that's kind of what you're explaining this morning, right?
Yeah. So we're talking about the thought experiment of imagine mom and I never once
harped on what you ate, what time you went to bed, how much you looked at your iPad,
how much TV you watched, when you exercised, what sports you played, what activities you did,
when you did your homework. Like imagine you could do anything you wanted. You could watch as much
flash as you wanted. Okay, that sounds kind of fun. You can eat as much ice cream as you wanted.
Think through how much fun you could have if you were allowed to do anything you wanted.
I think it would be fun for a little bit, but then I would obviously in the long run,
it would be really rough. But how do you make that trade off?
You have to have discipline now so that it can benefit you later.
But that's hard. It is really hard. You know it because you and me and we all struggle with this.
We make these decisions today that don't always feel good. You make these sacrifices. Remember
what Jaco's, what do my Jaco shirts say on them? That before the enemy or that one. Discipline
equals freedom. What does that mean? It means the more you have discipline, the more free you'll be.
Eventually. Not in the moment, but eventually you will be. Right. And so when you think about
why it is that you can't just eat all the ice cream in the world, even though in the moment,
it feels so good, it is undoubtedly more pleasurable to eat ice cream than not to eat ice cream.
It is undoubtedly more pleasurable in the moment to watch as much flash as you want and do as much
TikTok as you want and screw around on your computer as much as you want. Those things
feel awesome. I can't deny that. But the problem is you will pay the fiddler tomorrow.
And life in some ways is a balancing act between enjoying things for the sake of enjoying them in
the moment and indulging, but also being responsible enough to make sure that when
something goes wrong, you're prepared. I think if you're a kid and you're listening to this,
it's important to understand that the adults screwed this up. This is a great example of
the adults not doing their homework, not saving their allowance, not eating their vegetables,
not exercising, just completely dropping the ball. And now we're paying the fiddler.
That's a problem. I think it's a huge problem. And that's probably the thing
that on a deep level has me most upset right now. It's that a whole bunch of innocent people
are suffering badly because the people who are supposed to be in charge, the grownups,
so to speak, couldn't make the long-term trade off. They couldn't sacrifice in the moment.
They couldn't invest the time, the money, the infrastructure in science that was necessary
to make sure that when this happened, we were prepared. And so I have to hope that this is
a wake-up call. And I have to hope that when this is over, maybe you guys will be the ones
to tell the adults, quit screwing around. So we were talking about this this morning.
And an example you used was that Reese was watching a show called Biggest Little Farm.
And the people in that show, they had to grow their own food. They had to produce everything
by themselves. And if they didn't wake up one morning, even if it was raining, and they didn't
go outside and garden or help their animals, then they wouldn't have food in the long run,
and they would starve. So they kind of had to do what they needed to do for the future.
Yeah, I'm glad you remember that example. I think that's another great one is farming. Think about
if you have to go out there and plant your crops and go and tend to them and tend to your animals.
And if you just for a month decide, eh, I don't feel like doing it. I mean, I'd rather just screw
around. Well, you're going to starve when winter comes. Another question I had was, I was wondering,
is this China's fault? It has become incredibly convenient to blame China for all of this.
Consider the following scenario. You don't drive yet, but you know what it's like to be in a car
with me or your mom, right? I know it's like to be in a race car. Yep. So imagine you're driving
down the freeway and somebody changes lanes in front of you and cuts you off and they don't signal.
Is that their fault or your fault? That's their fault. That's right.
Now, how you respond to that is up to you. I could honk my horn or I could just.
Well, okay. Yeah, that's true. But I'm saying like how you respond from a safety perspective
is up to you. If you're paying attention and they cut you off, I mean, that happens like 10 times
a day. So if you're doing everything right, you're probably not going to die when somebody
cuts you off on a freeway. So like if you're texting and they cut you off, that could be a
worse situation. Exactly. Now imagine for a moment that you're speeding. You've had a couple of drinks.
You don't have your seatbelt on. You're texting and somebody cuts you off. That's not going to
work out too well for you. Now whose fault is it? That's my fault. Well, it's both of your faults
at this point. True, because that person did cut me off, but I was kind of not doing the right thing.
You were not doing your best to be ready for the situation. Okay. And that's kind of how I think
about this. To sit here and blame China for all of this, even though that's clearly where the virus
originated. And it's probably in part due to practices of food handling that we would never
do in this country. And all of those things are true. But again, we have to take responsibility
for all this. So China may have cut us off in the freeway, so to speak, but we were driving too fast.
We didn't have our seat belts on. We had a couple of drinks in us. We were texting and we were
looking back to check on our kids in the car seat and tell them to stop arguing with you. I mean,
we bungled every aspect of this. And I just think that in the moment when you're spinning out of
control, it's easy to say that guy cut me off. But at some point you got to be like,
I was doing something wrong too. Yeah, you were doing a bunch of things wrong.
I want to ask you a bunch of questions now. Okay. So Olivia, we went into quarantine a week before
your school closed. Right. That was about as upset as I've seen you in a long time when you went to
school on a day and I said, Hey, Olivia, this is going to be your last day at school for a while.
So can you please bring all your books home? What did you think when I said that?
I thought you were absolutely out of your mind because I've learned a lot about the virus since
then. And at that point when you said that I didn't even realize how bad the coronavirus was.
And I did start learning about it until a couple of weeks ago and none of my friends were leaving
school like I was. So I thought it would be really weird. I thought I would fall behind in
schoolwork and I thought I would be the only one. And I thought it was very odd and I couldn't leave
the house. So I couldn't do basketball. I couldn't go to drums. I couldn't do anything. I couldn't do
singing. And yeah, I was really upset at first, but then the next day a few of my friends dropped
out and then the next day school closed. I don't think school closed till the following Monday,
but I think they told you in that they said a few days later, Monday would be the last day.
Yeah. So a lot of my friends started dropping out and I was like, oh, oh, okay. Because I thought
me and my brother would be the only ones that weren't going to school. And the first few days,
all my friends were texting me, where are you? Why aren't you at school? And then kids started
dropping out super fast and then schools closed. So what's been the hardest part of this for you?
No friends because I'm a really social person. I usually have a million play dates.
And so not seeing my friends has been really hard for me probably. And also no sports because
basketball season just started and I couldn't play any games until next fall now.
What's been the hardest part about working, doing online classes and stuff?
Definitely having questions because usually at school, if you have questions, you can ask the
teacher after class. But now that teachers have things to do after each class, you can't really
stay online because you have another class right there. It's kind of hard to explain, but online,
it's hard to ask questions because everyone's talking over each other. It's total madness.
Like I have a headache after each class. And yeah, I do not like online school. I wish we could have
schooled back. That's interesting. So when you go back to school, assuming you go back to school in
the fall, back into actual school, what will you appreciate now that you probably didn't appreciate
in the past? Just school in general. Like me and my friends are saying how we took school for granted
and we didn't realize how amazing it was to have school because now we wish we had school.
That's interesting. What has been the best and worst part of your dad not traveling for the
longest time ever? Well, I have to work out a lot. So that's not fun. But I do like you being
home more because you made crepes this morning and you're just here to help more. And I think
it's really fun that we have a puppy during quarantine. So that's like really lucky that
we got her a few weeks before quarantine started. And so yeah, I mean, quarantine is good and bad
in some ways. Yeah. What's the deal with this puppy? She pees every three seconds of her life.
Yeah. Is that ever going to stop? I hope so because yeah, you could always walk around
the house and if you step in a puddle, you know what it is. So you don't regret that we got her?
No, I don't. I really like her. You don't think she's too much work? No.
How many watts are you up to on your zone two workouts now? 65 to 70, but I think I can start
coming higher because I'm doing longer rides now too. Yeah. What was your last lactate level at 70
watts? It was like 2.1 or something like that, 2.3. Pretty good. Do your friends think you're a freak
that your dad has lactate testing on you? They don't really know that part, but they do know
that I work out. They just don't know what lactate is, which I didn't until a couple months ago.
Well, Olivia, thank you very much for making the time. I know you've got a lot of things going on
today. I hope we answered questions that your friends would find interesting. Yeah, me too.
Is there anything else that you want to know about the coronavirus or that you think your
friends might want to know? I think we've covered it all, but yeah, I think that's it.
All right. Do you think there's any chance we'll get Reese on the podcast?
Oh, that would definitely be crazy. I mean, I'm sure he'd love it and you guys talk about
gardening and trash cans and what else does he do? Trains, Legos, probably talk about that.
We'll see if maybe he'll hear this one and he'll decide he wants to do one too.
Yeah. Speaking of which, I have online drums to go to now.
That's right.
Yep.
All right. Thanks, Olivia.
Thank you.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less
than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions,
topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.