Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. Welcome back to another COVID-19 episode of the Drive podcast. My guest this week
is Dr. Paul Conti. Some of you may recognize that name as Paul was a previous guest on the
show about a year and a half ago when we spoke about mental health, depression, trauma, and a
number of other things. On this episode, we kind of pick up a little bit of that thread, but obviously
talk much more specifically through the lens of the anxiety, trauma, uncertainty that many people
are experiencing in the midst of the pandemic, the quarantine itself, the isolation, the uncertainty
that comes from it both economically, socially, politically, etc. Paul and I go off on a number
of tangents here that I think, on some level, speak to societal problems, on other levels,
speak to challenges that we all have at the individual level. So I hope you'll enjoy this
as a bit of a deviation from the normal flow of information as it pertains to some of the more
technical aspects of this, which we'll obviously continue to return to. But I found this to be a
very helpful discussion and frankly the type of discussion that Paul and I will often find ourselves
having in the midst of situations like this, but hopefully by being able to have this discussion
and share it with you, some of you may find value in this. So without further delay, please enjoy
my discussion today with Dr. Paul Conti. Hey Paul, thank you so much for making time to talk this
afternoon. I know you're even busier than you normally are, but I know you appreciate that
some good can probably come of us setting some time aside to talk. Thank you very much and I so
appreciate you having me back on. It's such an important time and there's so much to think about
and talk about and thank you for taking the time to have me on. So Paul, before we jump into some
of the stuff I really wanted to talk about, it's probably worth you sharing with people your own
experience with what has to be believed as a presumptive diagnosis of COVID-19. You got
sicker than hell about a month ago, as did one of your children. And as you've described those
symptoms to me, they are very classic for the diagnosis. And you're no stranger to getting
the flu and things like that, but tell folks a little bit about what you experienced.
My wife and my two-year-old both just had malaise, mild symptoms, but my six-year-old,
who were kind of like carbon copies of one another, she had pretty significant symptoms
by pediatric standards. So I kind of knew it was coming and I had the malaise and just generally
not feeling good. And that was there for a couple of days. And then I very rapidly got very, very
sick in a way that felt different than flus or food poisonings or other illnesses felt extremely
hot, alternating with really terrible chills that kind of took over along with an awful headache.
And it's just deep nausea, not like I've experienced before. And interestingly, I wasn't
congested. It was strange to start to have a feeling of shortness of breath, really having
to catch my breath and start taking deep breaths and to be that sick, but to not have any congestion.
And it was scary. I mean, I remember at one point I was in the shower and I had the water turned up
high enough to scald me, like it should have been really painful. And I was just shivering and I
had goosebumps and just things that haven't happened before. And I could really see the lethality
in someone who has some of the medical comorbidities, I'm fortunate not to have, or is
older. And it was scary. It was scary. Well, I think it also kind of gives you an interesting
perspective to be able to talk about the stuff I want to talk about with you today. As you know,
I've been spending the past month trying to figure out how to be useful and that's required more
starts and stops and fits and starts than normal, because there is this feeling of helplessness.
You and I were talking about this earlier, which is like you have this desire to do something,
but at the same time, you feel like you can't really do anything. And there are days when I
just wake up and all I want to do is watch Netflix and play in my simulator and literally have nothing
to just forget that this is all happening. And then there's days when I wake up and I feel really
motivated and I think, how can I help? And I haven't figured the answer to that. I suspect
doing these podcasts is helpful. The feedback has been great. And I also think that people are
probably at least as interested, if not more interested in the kind of stuff we're going
to talk about today, as they are on the nuances of this type of RNA virus versus that type of virus
versus this drug and that drug. And while those things matter, I get a very vague sense. There's
a coming fatigue around the uncertainty of when are the cases going to peak and what all these
things. And there's a little bit more of a sense of, okay, well, what does this mean for me as a
person? And how have you been sort of struggling with the role that you play as an individual to
your family and then the role that you're trying to play with your patients and then maybe even
thinking more broadly? As I know that you know, and you and I have talked about on your podcast,
I see the world through the lens of trauma. And I think part of what just frustrates me at times to
just utter exasperation is I think the predictability of so much that has gone on around us.
And I think we've had an explosion of so much technology, so much increase in capability. And
I think we've made errors as a society in how we're utilizing that technology. And we've really
paved the way, I think, for deeply traumatizing ourselves as a society, as a country, and also
as species. And I think I'm a psychiatrist and one of the principles that's at times used in
psychotherapy is this idea that everything is as it should be, which does not mean morally right.
It means that the vast majority of things that ail us, I mean, some of them befall us,
but so often there's a predictability that we've gone 19 steps down a 20 step path
and then are surprised when we get to the 20th step. And I think that we have been paving the way
for terrible trauma to happen both medically and also socioeconomically. And what so disturbs me is
that as the virus itself recedes in whatever way that ends up happening, we're going to have to
make decisions. And I think that those decisions have tremendous gravity to them. I mean, I try
not to be inclined to hyperbole, but I think that they are as serious as you and I have discussed
in other venues. I mean, is it America passing the torch as really no longer being the world leader
that we have been since the second world war? Are we setting the planet on a reckless course
that we can't recover from? And I think we have to learn from this. And I think where I wring my
hands and gnash my teeth is the idea that maybe we won't learn from this. And I'm worried that we
could then sort of traumatize ourselves out of existence. What do we know about how humans
internalize this type of stress versus other types of stress that are more potentially uniting?
So I know that there's a body of literature that would say, look, pandemics do different things to
the human psyche than most other things like war, terrorist attack, even natural disaster, because
by their very nature, they are isolating. Sebastian Younger has written very eloquently in his book
Tribe about how post 9-11 suicide rates actually went down. People united. There was a common enemy
and then there was something we could all do to stand together. But the literature on pandemics
actually doesn't suggest that to be the case. What is your take on these sort of differences in the
psychology and psyche of us when confronted with these different external stresses?
I think on the one hand, it creates tremendous feelings of loss of control and tremendous
vulnerability. And it also creates suspicion. We know that viruses are real, but there's still
that part of human beings that we can't see it. We can't just stop it no matter what we're doing.
It can be lurking around invisibly. And those are things really that terrify us, the idea of an
invisible enemy. And we internalize this in a way that is more and more isolating. And I think
historically just makes people very suspicious of one another. I don't know the idea that, hey,
if I meet you on the street, I don't know if you're going to accidentally kill me. And I can't read.
I can't use what I would do to read safety, to read control in order to keep myself safe.
And I think in addition to that, we have a very big added problem, which is that that feeling of
vulnerability, that feeling of loss of control is looking for an enemy. I mean, after 9-11,
whether we ultimately were targeting the right enemy or not, is there was an attack. There was
an enemy. And here I am very, very worried that the social structure we have allowed to arise
is a social structure that searches for an enemy. And I see the xenophobia, the racism,
that then makes us feel that there's an enemy that actually isn't our enemy. Instead of seeing,
look, this is a human ailment and people who are suffering are suffering in the same way.
I mean, as you and I know as physicians, when you see someone who's really suffering, nothing else
matters. And we're not thinking about like, what's the color of that person's skin? And how much
education or money do they have? Like it makes us all the same. But we lose that perception of
people who are suffering in China, suffering in Iran, suffering in America, suffering in Europe,
suffering in Africa and South America. We lose that. And we start to, I fear, further the processes
that are separating us already to such a dangerous degree. Paul, if you could wind back
the clock to January 12th, so the virus has been now identified, the scientists in China have
sequenced it. If you had mind control over world leaders at that moment in time, and you could have
programmed everyone in such a way that there would have been complete cooperation
and borders would have effectively dissolved, not from the standpoint of interstate travel and
things like that, but in terms of nationalism, everyone said, Hey, you know what? We're all in
this together. This thing's going to be a potential disaster. Let's completely share every piece of
information we have. And we're all part of the same country. So whether you're our enemy in Iran
from a political standpoint or not, no, no, no, we're all going to share resources of testing,
of data, of medication, et cetera. Is there any precedent for the world being cooperative and
productive in a manner like that? Because I got to be honest with you. The only thing that comes to
my mind is these goofy sci-fi movies where the aliens come to invade and all of a sudden the
Russians and the Americans are friends because they have to sort of fight the alien. Like,
so outside of goofy sci-fi, is there any reason to believe we even possess the ability
for that degree of cooperation? I don't think we do right now. I think we can, but I don't think
we do. And this is because it is much, much easier to ally around a common enemy. How long
has the expression, you know, my enemy's enemy is my friend. I mean, that's probably been around
since people develop language in some form or another. It's very easy to identify that is my
enemy. So now you are my friend. Hence the alien invasion. Even you look during the second world
war, nations that had a lot of adversity, there were examples of unification around fighting the
common enemy. The problem is what becomes much, much, much harder and requires different elements
of the human being's ability to call upon the deeper parts of our brain, the parts that don't
just react with what I think of as traumatic aggression in order to ally around something
that really isn't an enemy. The virus isn't plotting against us. This isn't of intelligence.
It's invisible. In order to unite, we have to recognize our shared humanity. And our ability
to, for people to cross borders, our ability to destroy one another with weapons has so far
exceeded our ability to do that. I mean, if you look at the reactions in various countries,
it's been the same reaction. I mean, I think to me, core principles here are the everything is,
is, it should be. If we make decisions one through 19, we're going to end up at decision point 20.
And the other point is how much the middle school playground plays into all of this. Even it was
three, four weeks ago, around maybe three weeks ago, my father, who's in his 80s, his girlfriend,
who's in her 80s, we're going to go out to an event with like 500 people. My response is,
oh my God, stay home. And then he responds, why would I stay home? There are no cases of the
virus in New Jersey where my father lives. Right? Sure. If you don't test people, then you don't
know that there are cases. And I think this is so part of the problem that we've reacted in this,
hey, not, I don't have the cooties. It's not mine. It's a middle school playground reaction.
And when you combine that with how easy it is to just blame somebody, it's someone else's fault.
And that we've, I think socialized ourselves through how media in general, let alone the
subcomponent of media, that social media has grown up around us to self-indulge to that appeal.
It's not me, it's somebody else's fault. Somebody's my enemy. Can't land here. And then it's a
combination of misguided aggression and sticking our heads in the sand. And then
look where this leads us. I mean, the scenario that you cited shouldn't have to be science fiction.
We should be able to collaborate in ways that recognize common threats to us, but we don't
do that. We so quickly devolve into the first part of what we were talking about, which is,
I feel insecure, I feel vulnerable, are you my enemy? And I certainly don't want you to think
that there's something wrong with me. Maybe you'll think I'm your enemy. And then we all put our
heads in the sand and look what happens down the road. It's so clear how preventable this was,
and also how inevitable it was given that we did not set the groundwork in place to prevent
something like this. So you've been very busy, obviously, in the last month. You're as busy as
I am, if not more busy generally. But my guess is that the people you help have found themselves
relying on you perhaps even more than normal. Is that a fair assumption?
In some ways, I mean, it's been interesting. That has been the case for some people.
For other people, there is some sense of safety in sort of hunkering down at home,
and that idea of circling the wagons. So it's interesting how much it has really dichotomized
in that way. And also, what I'm not seeing nearly as much of are the people who were so at risk
socioeconomically before this. A lot of what I do, I'm the medical director at a place that
provides drug and alcohol treatment for mostly an indigent population. That's part of the work I do,
and the other part tends to be with people with more resources. What I'm not seeing is the gigantic,
and I mean gigantic swath of most of the country that were on a socio-economic precipice before
this. So then not only do they have the medical risk, the fears that I do think are pervasive and
are perhaps temporarily soothed by holding up at home, but they're not soothed by holding up at
home if you don't know what you're coming out to. We've known for a long time that the specific
numbers vary by study, but the idea that like half the population in this country couldn't survive
and move forward from $500 unexpected cost or a $500 shortfall. So on the one hand, we've talked
about, oh, look how great the economy is doing because employment rates are high. But so many
people are living either in desperation or one step away from desperation. And I think what we
are doing is yes, a lot of people are traumatized, absolutely, but that gigantic swath of the
population that is most of us are traumatized disproportionately because they don't know what
they're emerging to because we've set up a system that has essentially made that inevitable. I mean,
how long was it going to be if half or more of the population can't survive through a $500 need or
$500 shortfall? Something is going to trigger that, and it's not a surprise that something triggers it
en masse. And I think that's where this is a gigantic medical problem. It is a social problem.
It is an economic problem. When you add those things together, those things synergize and it
becomes a societally threatening medical socioeconomic problem. And we haven't had that before.
So let's take both extremes of the types of patients that you're most working with,
most commonly working with. In the first group you said is the indigent population who
you're helping with substance abuse, presumably many other medical and psychiatric problems that
accompany those. How is that population doing in the presence of what's happened in the past
four to six weeks? I think it's added desperation on top of desperation, which is obviously not a
good thing. It's an element of the population that I think in large part we've left behind.
Because I see the world through the lens of trauma, I see part of my reason for existing
in fighting the shame that's created by trauma. But there are ways in which shame is called for.
And I think as a society, there are things that we really should feel ashamed of. The ways we don't
give people chances to get back on their feet. And then we have a populace that's... There's
so much desperation in that part of the population that yes, this makes things worse, but it's not a
change in how a lot of people in that situation are living day-to-day life. And I think that's
lamentable. Which is a sad statement. Yeah, it's a terrible thing to say, but that's even in the 20
years or so that I've been doing this, which is it's not a gigantic amount of time, it's not a
small amount of time. But the change has been dramatic where there is a part of the population
that we just leave behind. They need more resources than we're willing to put towards them. So we
check a few boxes and we say we're doing things that we're not really doing as a society. And
we've written people off en masse. Now that is not true of everyone. And there are people who,
of course, work so hard and so selflessly to help other people. But as a society, we've decided
that it's okay if you can't navigate complex systems or if a couple of bad things happen,
either things happen to you or you make bad choices, that as a society, I don't think it's
subtle that we've written people off that way. And then what about the patient population you
take care of for whom the economic stress of this is not nearly as it is for perhaps the majority
of people, but who still have their own demons, their own neuroses, their own stresses. What are
you seeing that is unique to this environment that is maybe either similar to or even distinct from
other things that you have been in the capacity of being a therapist, for example, during the
economic catastrophe of 2008, 2009, again, post 9-11, any other sort of external stressor,
how does this stack up and what is it that you see that's maybe unique about it?
I think I've never seen something that just supercharges this idea that if I fear enough,
then I'll be safe, which I believe is an impact of the insecurity that many, many people, if not
certainly most people I encounter, I believe feel about the world. This idea that our biological
drive to recognize threats so that we can stay alive and pass on our genes has in so many people
mutated to where we're essentially living in a state of constant hypervigilant discomfort.
There's always something else to do. It's never enough for us to be safe and secure. I think
the society is always telling us that. The news has mutated from providing news to grasping
people's attention, grabbing people's attention in a way that says, look at that news again,
because you're going to see something else bad. All the anecdotes of he got up at nine and felt
healthy and by noon was in the intensive care unit. We know this. We don't need to be assailed
every moment by every threat to us. We have become prisoners of the insecurity that we have
generated. I think that comes through these biological drives that have led us to a place
that is no longer keeping us safe. If you think of the biological drives and psychological drives
to increase our safety by participating in social systems and economic systems,
a lot of that has mutated into strivings that make no individual sense within systems that make no
group sense. People that are working and working and putting money away for retirement, but the
vehicles that they're in aren't safe vehicles anymore. We've created so much insecurity
that it affects people even who say have enough economic means, but still have this pervasive
feeling that there's always, always, always something to fear. Then this idea that if I fear
enough, I'll be safe, then starts to spiral out of control and people get obsessive and people get
ruminative. The negative thoughts go over and over and over. What if something happened to my
kids and like, okay, what if we all get sick or what if we don't get sick, but there's a terrorist
attack or what if, what if, what if, what if, and become so pervasive that what's fascinating to me
is that I don't see peace in any demographic. Does it matter if people have tremendous amounts
of money or have no money? I just don't see peace anywhere. I think I am trying to scientifically
ascertain for it. I mean, I'm trying to listen to people, talk to people, learn what's going on
inside of them. What is uniting us is this pervasive insecurity and then these parts of
our brain that want to keep us safe go into overdrive and inadvertently make us feel so much more vulnerable.
What do you think is actually happening from a neurobiology standpoint? I mean,
we're now over a month into our quarantine here and spoken about this on the podcast before. I'm
pretty fortunate there are people who are quarantining inside tiny apartments and they
don't have the luxury of being able to go outside in their yard and things like that. So I want to be
clear that I'm not for a second lamenting the quarantine I'm in because I feel really, really
lucky. But I can't for the life of me understand the degree of irritability that I've experienced
over the past month. And I've done a little bit of a better job in the past few weeks, at least not
lashing out. But there's no denying internally a feeling that I have that is, well, frankly,
I don't know how to explain it. I'll tell you because I mean, it's so frequent, I can tell you
how I felt this morning. So this morning I was, I was exercising. So I'm lucky to have a gym at
home so I can exercise. And again, intellectually, it's not lost on me. What a privilege. Like, I
think of all the people who can't go to the gym now and their best thing they can do is pushups
and sit ups in their apartments. So intellectually I get that, right? But I'm sitting there thinking,
I don't really feel like doing this. And frankly, if this quarantine ended tomorrow,
I don't feel like going anywhere. There's this weird feeling of, I don't know what I want,
but I don't want this. I have a lack of interest in anything. But of course, I'm as busy as I've
ever been. So there's this very difficult feeling of every minute I'm moving, I'm hustling. I mean,
even my exercise is scheduled and between calls and this thing, the other thing. But if you told
me, Hey, I could wave a magic wand and make the coronavirus go away tomorrow and everything would
be back to normal. I didn't even have a sense of joy over that. I was just like, Oh, well, what
would I do? I don't know how to describe this Paul. I'm sure there's a word for this sort of
overall just lack of interest in life. Maybe that's too broad a way to explain it, but
it's this really weird oscillating feeling of sadness and irritability and almost wishing I
could just escape something, but not sure what I want to escape. Does any of that make sense?
Absolutely. And then I am finding there are more people who are escaping drugs and alcohol and
other really unhealthy things through that sense of desperation. And I think what you are describing
is demoralization. And you could tell me if this resonates with you. You and I haven't talked about
this before. So you tell me if this resonates that, that I think somewhere in there is a sense of
futility that says, if you look on two different levels, one on a personal level, you've worked
very, very hard to better yourself, better your situation in the world, take care of your family.
And there's something that speaks to, okay, there's a roof over our heads and we're sheltered here,
but have I succeeded in doing that? Or have those efforts been futile because I can't
protect the people around me. I can't make things okay. That my personal efforts to make life okay,
have come to naught. I mean, obviously not saying these things are true, but this is what goes on
inside of us because you feel that, okay, you can shelter everybody for now, but what does it say
about the world around us? And what does it say about the next threat that maybe you won't be able
to shelter from? That's one aspect of how we become demoralized. The idea that, hey, no matter what you
do and how hard you work, you can't make a difference because you can be vulnerable anyway.
And I think it brings that home to a lot of us because I think, I'm not saying that we should
be demoralized, but I'm saying I believe there's truth to that because I think the world around us,
the world around us leads to that. Everything as it should be says the world is such that we're not
safe. On the other hand, there are things that you've done on a broader level that are about
trying to contribute to the world in a bigger way around you.
I think what you said is incredibly spot on. And of course, that's part of what makes you who you
are is your ability to sort of see things I would never see. I've never thought of this as being
demoralized, but I think you're absolutely right. And I think you're right that I'm not alone.
I suspect people in 2008, 2009 were demoralized for a different reason, which is if you're that
person who did everything right and found themselves on the wrong side of a mortgage
because the value of their home came crashing down and they were not sophisticated enough to
know that, hey, these types of loans have these hard, nasty resets on interest rates, etc, etc.
You could very easily say, hey, I did everything right. And look what happened, right? And now,
I think you're seeing that same thing all over again, but with far less economic stratification.
The economic stratification plays probably a broader role in your resilience to this,
but it probably doesn't play as much of a role in what you just described, which is whether you're
the wealthiest person in the world or the least wealthy person in the world, there's still sort
of a view that you should live in a world where you have some ability to control your health
if you do the right thing. If you take care of yourself, if you eat, sleep correctly, exercise
correctly, you shouldn't be afraid for your life. And I'm not saying that that fear is rational,
by the way, because as we've discussed, the majority of healthy people who get this virus
are going to be totally fine, but there is a degree of fear that says that that might not be true.
I think that's right. And that's where I'm sort of fond of saying it's the soup that we're all
swimming in. And I think that's the commonality, wealth status, social standing, those things
don't matter when we're swimming around in the same soup. And neither you nor I, we're not
political animals and we don't have political discussions in that way. And this isn't about
politics. I mean, I'm a believer that many things in the world are driven by strong individual
people, good, bad, or otherwise. But I do believe that that's not always the case. There are cases
when social forces evolve and then they produce something that's going to be a certain way,
regardless of the specifics about it. So this isn't Republican, Democrat, like it's so far from that.
But the idea that the importance of expertise actually has become less and less and less and
less important because everybody can have an opinion and can just yell that opinion louder.
And then what we get is an erosion of expertise, which isn't so much mattering. What does somebody
know or not know? Because well, everybody's got an opinion. And I think we've seen that evolve.
And my thesis is that the inevitable outcome where the basics that we think of about the state
around us, the government, keeping us safe, it just isn't true. And we do expect that. We live
in this society. We participate in it. We vote, we pay taxes. I expect that if I'm driving down
the highway, there's not going to be like 20 foot long hole that's 20 foot deep that my car falls in.
Like I expect that's not going to happen, but that's not the only expectations we have. We
expect that there's something going on that's providing us with some sense of protection,
that there's some force to the world around us, that everything isn't just based upon opinions
and opinions that then justify whatever the person expressing them wants to justify.
And I think what we're seeing here is like truly that the emperor has no clothes. And again,
I'm not speaking. This is not me trying to be political about the president. I mean like the
emperor of the society we live in, it's not adorned with the splendor that we think will protect us.
There's a truth here that there can be hurricanes that devastate individual places and people don't
come to help. I mean, some people go to help, but not in a way that says, look, let's make sure that
this doesn't devolve into complete lawlessness. Like we've been able to pull that off in focal
settings. How are we going to pull that off on a national setting where there has to be acumen and
resolve to decide what tests should we deploy to have the willpower to deploy? I mean, it's not that
long ago where people were still saying, oh, some person somewhere in this place had the coronavirus.
Oh my gosh. Oh my gosh. And we look at that person had it. We now know this by half a million people
who have it. There's a seduction of like, let's look at that person and look at that bad thing.
And then we can posit that we're other than that. And the truth is that that never made any sense.
That never made any sense. That example you gave where everybody's cooperating,
we would identify who's been exposed, know who those people are, test those people,
protect their contacts. We could have done so much better containment, but instead,
there really hasn't been that much going on to protect us. And I think this lays that bear
in the way that the hurricane showed us in a focal way, but it's not just about health. I think it's
about socioeconomic risk. Paul, I want to shift gears for a minute and talk a little bit about
healthcare workers. I don't know how much time you've spent thinking about that in this setting
but do you have any thoughts about sort of the lingering effects of this on that population,
which has a couple of things working against it. One, they're on the front line. So while
people like you and I have the luxury of working remotely with people we care about during a time
like this, they don't. The doctors and nurses that take care of these patients don't get to do so
remotely. So now they're at this increased physical risk and there's still some evidence
to suggest that the risk that they face is even greater just based on potentially the viral loads
they're encountering and things like that. So this is real risk. Secondly, you have the sort of
the morale insult that comes with seeing their own colleagues also become patients. So when they
start to have to care for each other, do you have any thoughts about sort of the PTSD that
comes to this population in the months that follow this or in potentially even longer?
I think it's going to be so pervasive. I think the trauma is going to be pervasive
and even generational. I think that family members, children of people in that situation
will be affected by it and potentially deeply affected by it going forward. I think we are
facing the, what I think of as the appalling consequences of compounded ignorance. I mean,
look at what we have done in our health system. Like you and I have both been in it in a whole
bunch of different ways. And I think people in it can see how little it makes sense that we're
trying to run our healthcare system in a way that is sort of pushing people to the limits and
extracting profit and reducing costs wherever possible. And then ultimately everything is
running in a way that stretches people to the limit, stretches people to the limit. And how
much have we seen of that in anyone, doctors, nurses, social workers, respiratory therapists?
I mean, everybody is pushed to the limit in systems that have in a sense abdicated their intelligence.
They're not being run with intelligence. They're being run by rules that no one is looking at,
whether they make sense or whether they keep people safe or whether they make the people who
are doing the work in that system feel so disempowered and so devalued. How many times have
we heard, I mean, you must, I guess you can hear this the way I do of healthcare workers, just
talk about the feeling of their own expendability. They're working in a system that doesn't
know them, care about them, value them. And again, I'm not trying to criticize individual people.
There's so many people trying to do their best, but we've allowed the systems evolve into this
compounded ignorance where we can't take care of the people who are supposed to take care of us.
And they know that. And they've known that for a long time. And they're seeing it come
to the forefront. So what's a path forward, either in the scenario where this just lingers on longer
than any of us would like to imagine, or where it becomes sort of a vacillating, ebbing,
flowing pandemic, or even under the scenario where, look, six months from now, everything is
back to normal. This virus is squarely in the rear view mirror. We have effective treatments and
the healthcare system is back on its feet. In either situation, how would you think about
managing the long-term toxicity of this? Because especially if it's sort of smoldering, but not
resolved. I mean that from a psychological trauma perspective. I think the first thing we have to
do, which is by no means a given, is acknowledge the trauma. When a person has been through trauma,
there is a strong and reflexive impulse to keep that inside. We don't understand it. We feel ashamed
of it. It's so threatening and we push it down and we need it to be validated. I think we need
to validate as a society that we set ourselves up for this. That we set the healthcare systems up
to be overwhelmed, to not have the protection mechanisms, the testing that they needed. Now
we need to essentially acknowledge and atone. I don't mean in some way that's atonement in
some abstract way, but we actually need to make things different. I think you would agree, and
again you're the master of what data tells us. I think we can look at data and see how we can
and should be doing things better. There's not a tremendous mystery to that. I mean there are
places that are doing it better. There are paradigms that we could utilize more that don't
reduce people to cogs in a system. I think we need to, number one, acknowledge that to the people who
have felt like just things in the system. You can throw away a mask. You can throw away a gown.
Just like you can throw away a person. We have to get out of the interchangeability of employment
in the modern world in healthcare as well. We have to look at what are we doing with our resources.
We have to make it different so people feel like you understand me and what has happened to me.
You are trying to make it better. You being all of us as a society. If we don't do that,
just like with any other trauma, if no one acknowledges it and there's nothing being done
to try and make it better, then it will stay with that person and fester. It will lead to all sorts
of bad outcomes that we'll see years down the road. We'll look in retrospect and we'll see rises in
rates of alcoholism. We'll see rises in rates of domestic violence. We'll see rises in rates of
suicide. We'll see rises in rates of people just giving up and walking away from important things
to them. We'll see all of this. We will see all of this because if we demoralize the population
and we don't rectify that, it's not going to be okay. If somehow it seems to be in six months,
that will be a deceit. It will be tempting to just believe that and go on. But we have to have
the courage of our convictions to know that that's not okay. Is it true that everything is
as it should be? Meaning we let ourselves here. If it's not, let's argue about that and prove
that it's not. If it is, let's look at it and change it. I think it involves people standing up
and saying, look, this needs to change. How do we make the systems better? How do we fine tune this
or that or give this to this population that really suffered? No, it's how do we acknowledge
the need for change? That's the hardest thing to do is not that we're going to make systems better.
We're going to look at systems and we're going to bring change to them.
What does that look like? I mean, I understand what you're saying in the abstract. I don't think
I understand what it means. I don't think I know what that looks like five years from now. When
this is long forgotten, how does a society from a mental health perspective look if they are going
to be resilient to the next pandemic? So if there's a SARS-CoV-3 that's coming in 2030,
what does a national psyche, what does the mental health of a population need to look like
the year before that hits to do a better job than we might be doing today and to do maybe the best
job that can be done given the circumstances? What has to be true of that population?
I think what we need is what I would call an alliance of common sense. I was talking about
this earlier this morning with our friend and colleague, Jim Kochalka, about the ideas of how
would we work towards an alliance of common sense where people would say, I can't pretend that
something is okay just because it suits my interests, even if I know it is false. I have to
first prioritize looking at truth and can we, the people who would do this, which ideally could be
a growing movement led by people with influence and with the ability to say we have to put aside
whatever our wishes might be, whatever our animosities might be, that we actually do have
to treat this like post-9-11 or like the Second World War and say what we need to look at now is
truth. What are the failings in our public health system as a planet and also as a nation? They
stretch people to the limit. They stretch resources to the limit. When do we pretend
that lies are truth and how can we say that that's okay? Republican, Democrat, or other, who cares?
And again, this gets contentious because as soon as you get political and you can't talk about
change without treading into the political, then there's such bitter and brutal animosity
that it tells all of us. Part of me, I want to have this conversation because I care about the
world. Even if I didn't have children, I would care about the world, I hope. But the fact that
I have children is I want to have this conversation. But there's a part of me that says, hey, put your
head down and go back home. Because ultimately, whatever you say is going to make some people
really, really angry and people get angry and bitter and vindictive. What we need is something
that fights against that, that says we are going to ally around truth in our medical system, in our
social systems, in our economic systems. We have to look at this. And if people start
allying in that way, then we have all the expertise that we need, social systems, public health,
economically, whether it's economic on a local or on an international commerce system. We
absolutely have every single bit of expertise we need. What we do not have is an alliance of
common sense of people who say, I will stand by that, come hell or high water, I will not give
into lies. I will stand by that, then we can start making the world better. If half the population
can't survive a $500 shortfall, I am not going to pretend that the economy is okay, or that our
social systems are okay. Or if the healthcare choices that people are facing are too complicated
for them to understand, and then people ultimately don't get the care that they need. They show up at
emergency rooms for their primary care, demoralizing the emergency room staff that wants to take care
of people who have emergencies. There's so many thousands and thousands of examples, and we just
need people to say it's enough. Do you think that this event is potentially a catalyst for changing
the way people think about science and truth? And again, I use those two in the same sentence,
because when you take a step back and think about what the truth means, I think we have to
differentiate between personal truths and absolute truths. I think it's true that Formula One is
amazing, but I also recognize that that's a personal truth. It's shared by you, but it's not
necessarily shared by everybody else, and that's okay. You and I believe it, that doesn't make it
true. I believe I are at the incentive is the greatest Formula One driver of all time. Again,
I think that verges on being an absolute truth, but I'll leave it in the category of a personal
truth. Yes. But when you start to get into things that are absolute truths, that's really where
science comes in. Science is a toolkit that allows us to test hypotheses. It's a methodology that
allows us to examine absolute truths. And do you think there's a chance that what we're seeing here
could ever be a catalyst for allowing that distinction to be made in broader society?
Because it's not clear to me that it does. I think that for the majority of society,
there's a blurred line between absolute truth and personal truth or relative truth.
Peter, I think you're striking to the heart of the matter because absolute truth operates
through logic systems in our brain. I mean, ultimately, this does relate to brain biology.
Absolute truth resonates with logical systems in our brain. Relative truth, personal truth,
resonates with emotional and what's called affective or limbic systems in our brain.
When we engage effectively in the world around us, and again, I have a thesis that says we as a
society are not engaging effectively because we have lost the distinction between those two
that lets us make the personal truth secondary to the absolute truth. So the idea is there's a
strong resonance if I feel something to be true. I mean, there are social issues I feel very
strongly about. That resonates with me emotionally because I'm a human being and says,
because I believe that, that makes it true. That's my belief. So that's how I want it to be. So that's
true. But then the other systems in my brain say there are absolutes that I want to hold up and
against that. And I want to have those absolutes govern my own personal feelings. So I may feel
just as rabidly that Formula One is the greatest sport ever. I want everybody to believe that. And
if I let my emotion run away with me, where do I end up? I end up thinking everybody who doesn't
believe that is an idiot, as opposed to saying, look, I feel that way. But hey, look at all these
other sports. And there are people who really love those other sports. And they see the excitement and
the personal strivings that I see in Formula One. So the reflex in us is to elevate the personal
truth, the emotional, to supremacy. And we need to overcome that so that logic wins the day because
logic is not charged the way that emotion is. And I think media, social media, I mean, this is the
heart of the matter, have made it very easy to elevate personal truths. You believe A, I believe
B. Instead of having a conversation about it, isn't it just easier? And in some ways, doesn't it feel
better for us each to say the other one's an idiot? And that's that. We're indulging that in a way
that then starts making logic subservient. It makes the absolute truth subservient to the
emotions, to the personal truths. And if you look at how change happens, the concept of a dialectic,
where you have something and you have something different from it, right? You have two different
things, and they become something that's different from both of them, I think is where we're at.
This is going to be a catalyst to something. And something on the other side of it, I strongly
believe, is going to look differently than what it looks like now. If it's not after this and things
seem to be back to normal, this will just be one of steps that lead us to things being different.
And one way things could be different is that absolute truths really do go out the window.
We very much come back to superstitions, and we're really not that far away from it now.
And we could very, very easily get there. Or this will be a catalyst for us writing ourselves
and saying, look, we must prioritize logic, whether I like what it says or not. And there,
I think, how do we make the catalyst, the resolution of that dialectic, go one way and not the other?
We need people to make this, I'm just calling this no magic to the words, but an alliance of
common sense that says, hey, if you think A or you feel A and I feel B, that's the word, if you feel A
and I feel B, that instead of immediately being at each other's throats, let's stop and look at the
facts. Let's stop and look at logic. Otherwise, I mean, how far, I'm not trying to be overly
dramatic, but look, when the Khmer Rouge took control in Cambodia, one thing they did away with
was doctors. This is very easy to put one person's blood into another. We can teach people to do
that. Okay, what about blood types? You didn't have any doctors or science or hospitals, and then they
just started randomly transfusing people and either making hemorrhages or putting one type of blood
into another. I mean, that was an utter human catastrophe there, but there are whiffs of that
going on now. Who cares what the science says about hydroxychloroquine? Try it. I mean, this is
emblematic of us leading ourselves away from logic. I don't see how we're not heading towards
destruction. The everything is as it should be tells me, we can't let that happen because it
ends with destruction. There's nowhere else it ends. So we need this alliance of common sense,
of people who will stand up and say, if I disagree with you because I feel differently, I'm going to
look at the logic. And if the logic tells me that what you're saying is right, what I'm saying is
wrong, then damn it, I'm going to go forward with your way of seeing it no matter how I feel.
We need more of that. I mean, do you worry, Paul, that we have spent such a scant period of our
evolutionary history with any formal language around logic and science? I mean, for all intents
and purposes, it's about one-tenth of one percent of our evolutionary history has operated with even
the nomenclature of science, the skill set and the tools for logical thought, the reason that
I think religions exist and the reason that mythology exists and superstitions exist is
they became ways to explain things prior to a nomenclature that could describe things. The sun
went up on this side and the sun went down on that side. And before you understand that the
earth is spinning around the sun, you have to concoct another explanation. And so we're not
hardwired to think critically. Our limbic system has literally billions of years of repetition
and maybe not our limbic system exclusively, but say from amygdala up, right? In other words,
the most primitive part of our brains have billions of reps in them. And as you point out,
the brainstem, the amygdala, the limbic system are generally driving us now when in reality this
would be the time to have higher cortical functioning take over. But that is such a recent,
recent development, not just evolutionarily where maybe for the past 50,000 years we've had those
structures of our brain and I could be off by some magnitude there, but directionally,
but really only about 500 years in terms of formal structure of scientific methodology.
Is this just not even a fair fight? I mean, we're sitting here having this philosophical
discussion about logic, but I mean, in times like this, when we recede to our lowest common
denominator, how in the world can we expect those systems of logic and science to prevail?
So on the one hand, you're speaking to a very powerful truth, which is we are driven to be
driven by the limbic system, by emotion. It has always held the upper hand. So it's not a fair
fight, but it's a fight we can win. You know what I mean? The odds may be stacked against us,
but we can win that fight as evidenced by the fact that we have evolved in a way that the
scientific method became understood. And then we learned, oh, wait a second, the earth does
revolve around the sun. We can fight that just because the odds are against us. This is because
we're swimming against a strong current. Does it mean that we can't with the right preparation
and cooperation successfully swim against that current? What has happened, and I think my
amateur read of the sociological data is that what has happened is our ability to unleash emotion
has way outpaced our ability for our logical processes to keep up with that. The explosion
of social media, of people being able to communicate with one another so rapidly about what they feel
our control mechanisms haven't kept up with that. I mean, the fact that the lead physician in charge
of fighting this virus has to have bodyguards, right? I mean, whether he does or whether it's
been talked about, I don't know. It's part of this anger that that person said something I don't like.
So stone him, right? I mean, these emotional responses are in us. And what we need to do is
be adults and not be children. We're being children. And we need to be adults. And we need
to say, look, we need to hone our control mechanisms. But what we're not doing is saying,
we can't have systems around us that propagate just how someone feels about something and then
stokes the emotion of everyone else who feels the same way. I don't like this. That person is bad.
Like this political opinion, I don't like whatever it is I don't like. That spreads like wildfire.
I think in a way, I don't know if it's happenstance or not, but I think the wildfires that are
plaguing us in California and Australia, right? These are far flung events that I think mirror
the wildfires of emotion that go on. And it doesn't matter what's true. People's emotion runs wild.
And what we need to do is to step up to the plate and develop greater control mechanisms
and look at how do we stop misinformation? How do we establish sources that are arbiters of truth
outside of politics? What's actually true? And we don't have that. We need more of the things
that aren't sexy and aren't glamorous. Otherwise, this emotion you're talking about is running
wildly ahead of us. And it's going to metaphorically make wildfire that consumes us.
And I don't think that's catastrophizing. Do you think part of it is we're also not very well
equipped genetically to understand uncertainty? So in what we're talking about of absolute truth
versus personal truth, there's another layer of complexity. So if the personal truth is that
formula one is the most exciting thing on the face of the earth, I think most people, if they're
being intellectually honest, can come to an understanding that that's a personal truth, no
matter how strongly one feels about it. But let's use the example you've brought up, the example of
hydroxychloroquine as a potential treatment for this. To say that hydroxychloroquine is an effective
treatment for COVID-19 doesn't really fit in either of those categories. It depends on how it's
expressed. It could be expressed as, hey, it's my opinion that looking at the scant data to date,
the risk of this is lower than a certain threshold which deems it an effective treatment in someone
whose risk is high enough. That level of nuance to something kind of straddles both personal and
absolute truth. Another example is climate change. Part of the struggle with climate change is nobody
can really talk about it in terms of probabilities and with error bars. And so you basically get
polarized arguments that both sort of have their own flaws. So on the one hand you have people that
just completely deny it, or if they don't deny climate change, they're sort of adamant that man
can play no role in it. And on the other end of the spectrum you have these extreme hyperbolic
estimates that might represent a scenario, but not necessarily the most likely scenario, or not
necessarily a complete picture of the plausible scenarios. In other words, again, it comes down
to uncertainty and probabilities. And I think that something like this, this experience that we're
dealing with, makes it very complicated for our little plebeian brains, our little reptile brains,
to deal with. And I'm struggling with it. And I'm someone who understands probability, and I
understand logic, and I understand science, but I have to be honest with you. I am tired of saying
I don't know. And yet it is the only answer I have to give. A hundred times a day I get asked a
question, and it can be my daughter saying, dad, when do we get to go out and have dinner? And it
can be one of my patients, and he was asking me, let me ask you your opinion, Peter, what do you
think is going to be happening in six months? And again, all I can say is I don't know. I can give
you five different scenarios of maybe this, maybe this, maybe this, maybe this, but there is no
absolute truth that I can offer that person. So I could give a personal truth, which is this is my
opinion, but science rarely proves anything. It's not like mathematics, right? In mathematics,
we have proofs, but in science, we just have high degrees of certainty. And again, I just, I worry
that this introduces a new layer of complexity to a discussion that already makes it impossible
to sort of cope with a lot of signal, a reasonable amount of signal, an extraordinary amount of noise
and then a supercharged emotional swamp that dilutes and amplifies the wrong things,
if that makes sense. I'm rambling a little bit. I think my point is I'm generally pessimistic,
Paul, I guess is my point. Yes, Peter, of course, I don't know, right? For sure. But I see it
maybe in a more simplistic way. I don't think there's another level on top of it, because I
think that I don't know is actually a beautiful answer. If you don't know, what do we really know?
Right? So we know so little that admitting that we don't know engenders humility. It engenders
the humility that makes us careful. I don't know if a pandemic is coming. Let's look,
let's have some preparedness to it. I don't know if this is helpful or not. Let's learn more about
it. There's a caution that then leads to alliance. I mean, we started early on talking about how can
people, countries, nations, ally. It's through a sense of humility that you know what? I don't
know. And I'm not ashamed of not knowing. I mean, think about in medical school, I think part of
the myths of medical education, right? It's like you never say you don't know. I think it's the
worst thing ever. I think why would you ever say you know when you don't know, and we're talking
about somebody's health. There's a humility in I don't know that leads to collaboration,
that pushes against aggression. It pushes against that middle school playground of,
oh, I don't know. And now I'm ashamed. And it leads towards progress. The other side of that
coin is what I see as the hubris that leads people to just declare that they know. And there's a
recklessness to that. I mean, I think we're a society of angry, frustrated people and we're
getting angrier. We're not going to come out of this with more of that. I mean, people already
were feeling insecure, traumatized by the systems that we live in, the insecurity about it, where my
healthcare is coming from, where people's fear of that $500 that's going to sink them. We're not
going to come out of this angrier and the anger is what fuels the emotion. And then it's the emotion
that then falls into the political spectrum. So if that's the case, then whether you agree with
something or not, it becomes a mechanism of your allegiance. We start to look more like systems
that say, it doesn't matter what's right or wrong, do you agree with me? Because if not, you're bad.
And we're doing that all the time. Why is the efficacy of hydroxychloroquine a politically
charged question? That's insurmountable then. We need to make it not a politically charged question.
There are political issues, taxation rates, social equality, value systems we're deploying. There are
lots and lots of political questions, but because we are so angry and I think so traumatized and
desperate as a population, we make everything a political question. And then that adds to that
emotion side of things. I think it is just the real truth versus personal truth, logic versus
emotion. It is that, but it's become so convoluted because the emotion is so high and it gets attached
to things as vehicles for that emotion. And that's what we have to work against. That's where the
alliance of common sense would say, look, we have to not be children. We have to be adults and we
have to look at what is it that I don't know. And if there are 20 questions and I don't know the
answer to any of them, well, at a minimum, I hope that that engenders humility in me and the ability
to work together with other people and listen to their opinions. Even if I have a say, if I have a
strong personal opinion about 15 of those questions, but actually there's no logic to know any of the
20 of them, can I find it in myself to have the humility to admit that and to say that and to say
that to you and know that you're okay with that. You're not going to humiliate me for it and embarrass
me for it. That's what people are afraid of. You have to know because you have to fight with what
you're going to say you know. We need to stop that. And we don't have to be, look, I'm pessimistic too,
but that doesn't mean that I feel hopeless. I am pessimistic, but not nihilistic because I think
the wake up call, what this can catalyze is people who are trying to do good things,
but may be hesitant to step into what seems like a political arena. I don't mean to run for office.
I'm just saying that truth, personal truth versus real truth just has to stand aside from politics.
And our economic system, our social system, these are systems tied in politics. And we have to look
at the truth of those systems because they are not serving us well. We have to separate ourselves,
our trauma and our anger and our shame and our frustration from what is logical truth or not.
And I think again, I think you and I between us is what I was talking to Jim about this morning.
There are enough people who could step up to this plate, but boy, it's a thing people are
least inclined to do because it's a thing that draws the most flack and the most personal animosity.
Paul, I want to shift back from the macro to the micro now. You and I have spent a lot of time
over the years talking about something that I think you're better at than I am, but I think
we both struggle with what has been your recipe in the past month for self-care? I don't know how you
do what you do. I mean, I think, and I don't just mean you, I mean people like you, right? People
whose job it is to take on sort of the burden of other people's pain and suffering and then to be
able to do it in a manner that's not detached, but rather to be fully involved and invested in
whatever crisis, whatever struggle, whatever turmoil that person exists and how you then
manage to buffer yourself from that without being detached, take care of yourself so that you can
continue to take care of people, take care of your family. Again, you and I have had endless
discussions on the types of things that one can do here. I just wonder if there's something that
you can teach listeners about how you've done that and what can somebody take away from this
when they're feeling going back to where we were a while ago, back to that feeling of sort of
low and morale. I forget how you described it. The way you very aptly described how I was sort
of feeling demoralized, right? Yeah, demoralized. I think is the word you use. Yeah. So let's assume
that this quarantine is going to continue in the weeks and even months that follow and people are
going to be in their routines that are full of stresses and stressors that they might normally
be able to escape from. And they don't have the luxury of picking up the phone and speaking with
you or Jim or some of the other amazing people out there who are really just sort of a godsend
to folks who have access to you. Is there something that they can do to ease the suffering? And I mean
the suffering in their mind, which is of course the worst kind, I think. I think the answer to that
is finding one's way to the lowest common denominator of what matters. And I think if people
are experiencing the truth now that they're say with their family, the realization that
that is what matters the most now. And it's also what's going to matter the most tomorrow.
And I'd rather be with my family in a lean to out in the middle of nowhere than any luxurious
living situation alone. And part of that realization that I think I can sustain that if
everything else went away, like it probably, I don't know, put some sticks together, give us
some shelter, right? Like it gives me a feeling that what matters is care and concern between
people being with the people we care about. And look, I'm hearing that from people too. I'm hearing
a lot about the silver lining of this, which is more time with family. I talked to almost nobody
who's a purchased anything in the last month other than necessities. I don't care so much that I think
matter matters. Doesn't matter. And look, I'm not advocating like I'm not a Luddite or anything.
Let's go back to just living like we did a thousand years ago, or a hundred years ago,
or whatever. But it is meaningful to realize that the things I care about most are actually more
immediately accessible to me in the moment. And I think that's still going to be the case tomorrow.
Hopefully everyone's staying safe and we're trying to ensure that that's what most matters. And it's
a good place to start from. I think it engenders practicality. It engenders humility. It engenders
a sense that everything is okay. I've sat at home with my family for a period of time I wouldn't
have before. And I have a very strong sense that everything is okay. I sit around with my family
because I have a six year old and a two year old and we blew up six balloons. And we're just throwing
these balloons between the two of us. I mean, and we're happy. And I think we need more of that
because it works against the trauma. There's a realness and a connectedness to that that works
against the trauma. Now look, I think we need to change the social systems or we are not going to
change the trauma and things are not going to be okay. If I'm understood your question, you're not
saying how do we fix this on an individual level of people in their homes? I think the answer is we
don't. But how do we feel better? How do we let ourselves find some peace? I think that is the
answer. My daughter who's turning six this coming weekend said to me, she said, Daddy, with you at
home more, it's like spring has come but inside of me. And my thought was, oh, I'm not sure what
else really matters. And that doesn't mean I don't want to go to work and do my job. But when I'm
talking with people on the phone, I'm looking more through that lens of what else really matters to
that person that I'm talking to than the people that they love. And I think we need more of that.
We need to fix our social systems, but we need more of that. And that's something that each of
us can do at home. Because it's really our interpretation of things. Are things not okay,
because I don't know what's going to be like when it boots back up? That's true too. But I don't have
to live in that every moment. And I can live in more time with my kids. That's real. And that's
tangible. And that's going to mean something to me this evening and tomorrow. And that can be real
for everybody and people who don't get to be with people that they love and that love them. So
thinking of how do we make more of that in our life? The idea that we all need love, and we need
things that are generative, that make where there wasn't before, does not just have to apply to
human relationships. It can apply to nurturing a pet or nurturing a garden to making a poem where
there wasn't before. It's kind of strange, but our needs are not that complicated. But I'll be damned
if they aren't hard to meet in the system that we've set up around us. We need to change it. We
need to change the systems. But part of how we change the systems is to change how we're looking
at them as individual people. What am I valuing? So if I'm hearing what you're saying, it sounds
like you think that this sort of attachment to others or connection to others is sort of an
antidote to this trauma? Put more broadly, I think the attachment to things that are meaningful.
Yeah, yeah, sorry. Not to, yeah. Meaning to other people in relationships that matter to our kids,
to our friends, to our spouses. Right, right. Because not for all the money, success, prestige,
world mastery. I mean, if you could have all of it, I mean, you wouldn't sacrifice the ability to
be with one of your children. That stuff matters the most to us. And it's also where we generate
our own meaning. That's where I don't feel demoralized. That's where I don't feel demoralized.
Because I know that I have meaning to people and people have meaning to me. And then I can find
within myself the strength to put one foot in front of the other, keep doing what needs to be
done, even though I sure do feel demoralized often. I mean, the reason why I think I can project and
guess how you were feeling is because you and I know each other very, very well. And I'm feeling
the same way that you are. Has whatever I contributed to the world made a difference? Or
whatever I've done for myself and my family made a difference? I mean, the answers to those
questions are yes, but we feel that they're no when we're confronted with the state of the world
around us. And again, it just brings me back to that something more is called from us. I mean,
there's a little bit of, again, I'm not trying to be political, but when John F. Kennedy said,
like, ask not what your country can do for you, but what you can do for your country. And yes,
he was speaking about difficult things. He wasn't just saying, do more of what you're good at doing
or what's easier for you to do or even think that you're hard for you to do. But you may need to do
some things that are very, very difficult. Do you see people having a difficulty reintegrating back
into the world when the quarantines lift? Do you see lingering fears? I mean, fears literally of
infection, recurrence of pandemic, other forms of phobias that might not even seem
logical or rational. I mean, do we have any insight into what people do after quarantines
and what their psyches are left with? This idea that if I am more afraid, I will be safer is going
to precedents. We're going to see more anxiety, more obsessiveness, more panic, more agoraphobia,
right? Fear of being outside of the home. We're going to see more and more of that. And we're
going to see more of the unhealthy coping mechanisms to that, more drugs and alcohol.
We're going to see more of the unintended results of that, like depression and accidents. We're
going to see more of all of those things because there's nothing to prove to you that you're not
safe, like a period of time in which you were very clearly not safe. And I think if we reintegrate
into the previous lies, then underneath that is the knowledge that this is not okay. It wasn't
okay before. So if we're now back to it, it's not okay now either, which is why we need to make
change. That ultimately, yes, this is about trauma and how this pandemic is traumatizing us
and how we paved the way for the trauma of it to be so bad. And we need to change that,
just like we need to change what traumatizes people individually. If someone has been traumatized
individually, someone has been attacked and hurt, and that person knows that there are people around
them that care about that, that care about them, that care about what happened to them,
and that are working for change in the systems that allowed the trauma to happen in the first
place, then we help move that person towards healing. And yes, we need to do that for individual
people in their trauma treatment. And we need to do that as a society. Otherwise, we will be no
more successful as a society than we'll be the individual sufferer from trauma who is trying to
deal with that trauma by pretending everything is okay, which is a natural response because we're
afraid of it and we're ashamed of it and we don't know how to deal with it. And there aren't the
systems around us to say, you can come and talk about that and you don't have to be ashamed of it.
And you know what? I have that too. Maybe I have a different flavor from you, but I have what you
have. And you and I know this. Part of the reason I think we've survived our own traumas is because
we have not gone through them alone and we've had them validated and we ourselves have been validated.
And then we look to ways to make the world better. And that's part of our demoralization, that it
kind of hasn't had as much of an effect as we might have wanted. So let's start doing something new
about it. Because it does not have to be this way. Say rape cultures on college campuses, you know
what? Doesn't have to be that way. And we start making changes. My good is not that we've made
the changes we need to, but we start looking at that, looking at what it really is and looking
at the lies that said, oh, it's all okay. And people are consenting and everybody who's drinking
is de facto giving consent. We look at those lies and we start making change and we start making
less trauma and we start better being able to help the people who have suffered trauma.
That is a very real and tangible example that we are going to need to do on an individual basis,
whether it's healthcare workers who are afraid to go back in the hospital or it's people who are
afraid to try and go find the next job or it's our society as a whole. We have to change those
things. There's nothing else that makes it better. I think it's worth pointing out for listeners,
you and I have known each other for 25 years. We're pretty much inseparable. In fact, this is
probably the longest we haven't seen each other in person because the last time we were together in
person was January. So that's for us, that's an eternity. I think it's worth the listener knowing
you and I have never once talked about politics except in the context of history. In other words,
you and I together, we are not the type of people that sit here and wax on about current political
affairs. We over a meal, we'll sit here and discuss the Cuban missile crisis ad nauseum.
Talk about Nixon and all these things we love to talk about the history of politics. We're not
political people and I think it's important that people who are listening to this don't take this
to be a political rant. Everything we've talked about today seems to come down to a common theme,
which is those of us who sit here in the peanut gallery who are not in a position of leadership
are going to have to sort of become the movement of change. In other words, it's not enough to just
sit around and pontificate about this stuff. We are going to at some point have to do something
about it. We're going to have to take some sort of action. It's not going to be enough to just
think about this, lament this, talk about this with our friends. That won't change the system.
Everything you've talked about from this most recent example, which I think is a great one
of sort of date rape culture on college campuses to social support network. I mean,
all of these things in the end come down to not just being open about what we think is right and
not right, but it's also taking some sort of action. It is going to come down to that.
I don't know. It's funny. I didn't come into this discussion with any sense of what we were really
going to talk about. I just knew it was going to be something sort of interesting and not sort of
how does this drug work versus that drug work. But I don't know that I really thought about it as
broadly as you've been thinking about it. It sounds to me like this experience, you've made
good use of your time, you're forced exile from the busy travel schedule, and you've thought even
more broadly and deeply about some of these problems that we've thought about and talked
about in the past together. But I don't think, I think you've coalesced a broader mission urgency
around this. I think so Peter, because I've just felt it. These are not foreign concepts to me,
and these are things I have been afraid of, but really seeing it play out, it becomes so compelling.
And you talk that we're all going to have to do things, those of us in the peanut gallery,
we're going to have to do things. And it's not just that, we're going to have to do things that
are unpalatable. And that's what I've really come to realize. It's like a couple of weeks ago,
garbage disposal, it gets kind of clogged. And there's a whole bunch of strategies I have to
try and fix that. I mean, I put a bunch of water down and I've got a butter knife and I'm trying
to do things with it. And I'm doing things, but ultimately, what I had to do to make it better
was the thing that was unpalatable. I had to stick my hand down there into a bunch of gross stuff
and unclog something. And now everything is okay. I have a willingness to do things and you do too,
and lots and lots of people do. But what we shy away from is doing the thing that's unpalatable.
And the way society has developed, I don't think we can get around the political flavor of this.
Because if you want the setup, like if I had my way, there would be committees of people with
expertise that would look into these different areas. But what they have to do is really
unpalatable things. Stand against the status quo. Enter into areas, arenas that are politically
charged. Enter into minefields, knowing that something unpleasant is going to happen, right?
I'm going to try not to get myself killed doing it, but something unpleasant is going to come of it.
And I think those are the things we shy away from. And I have the privilege of knowing and interacting
with lots and lots of people who are helping. And God bless that people are helping. But there's
a difficult message for all of us here that says, yes, help in the ways that you're built to help
uncomfortable helping, but you got to help in the, I'm sick of my hand in the garbage disposal way
too. Which is why when Chiaokook calls and talks about this and he starts talking about leadership
in ways that come through humility, that come through marshaling people to do unpleasant or
unpalatable things to really look at this, it resonates with me in part because like you and I,
I mean, he and I have an ongoing dialogue about life, but because I just, I can't not believe
that's what's necessary. I try and do thought experiments where I come at a position that's
diametrically opposed to mine. It's different from mine. I feel differently, have a different personal
truth. And I can't but come to this conclusion, which obviously doesn't mean that it's right,
but I'm using all the due diligence I can inside of myself. And I can't but come to any other
conclusion. Well, Paul, on that note, I want to thank you for this discussion today. I look
forward to continuing our discussions over the coming weeks. I rely on them heavily.
Thank you so much. As always, Peter, I appreciate your trust in me and my opinions to have me on.
And as always, I deeply appreciate your friendship. Thank you, Peter.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper,
person thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rivalties.
Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less than five
minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to peteratiamd.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise. Please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.