Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. Welcome back to another special episode of the COVID-19 series of The Drive.
Joining me today is Dr. Emesh Adalja. Emesh is a senior scholar at the Johns Hopkins Center
for Health Security. He has long been focused on pandemic preparedness and emerging work on
infectious disease, biosecurity, et cetera, for many years long before this coronavirus
entered our consciousness. I wanted to talk with Emesh for a couple of reasons. One, I'd heard him
on other interviews, particularly the one with Sam Harris. Also, I'd seen him in interviews,
read some of his work and just found him to be a very thoughtful guy who could put the
coronavirus pandemic in the context of all the previous pandemics and not just the ones that are
immediately in our recollective memories, such as SARS, MERS, H1N1, but even going back a little
bit further than that. This is a very brief discussion. He was incredibly busy. We were
very fortunate to get 40 minutes of his time between other interviews, but we do cover quite
a bit of ground and certainly everything I was hoping to speak with, which is a bit of a more
clear history of when this virus likely emerged, how it came here and what we know about it relative
to other coronaviruses. We talk a lot about what the plan forward should be and we end with really
what he is most optimistic about. So though this interview is relatively short for the standards
of interviews that I do, like I said, it's about 40 minutes, I think we cover a lot and there's no
question I would like to have a mesh back. I do think it is really just an inevitability that we
will once again face a pandemic and whether it's a coronavirus or another virus is probably less
the point here, but unquestionably there are things that we could do better the next time we're
faced with this. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Emesh Adalja.
Thank you so much for making time to speak this afternoon. I know you're incredibly busy and we
were lucky to sort of catch you in between interviews and television appearances. So thanks
very much. I'll just sort of jump right to it. I reached out to you because I was
very interested in your perspective on the historical similarities and differences between
this pandemic and previous ones. Maybe just briefly tell us a little bit about your background
and why it is that you're not just someone who came to be interested in this in the past three
months. So I'm an infectious disease emergency medicine and critical care physician whose focus
his entire career basically on the issue of pandemic preparedness, pandemic prediction,
infectious disease and national security, emerging infectious disease. Even from the time when I was
a trainee, that's basically all I focused. And I work at a think tank that's devoted to this issue.
And I've been there basically full time since 2010 or so, but had been there since 2008 working on
this. I published on pandemic prediction on what the characteristics of certain pathogens that
cause pandemics would be on H1N1, on Ebola, on agents of bioterrorism. So I really focused and
tried to niche myself into this aspect of infectious disease in medicine. So this is
an outbreak that had been on my radar before it hit headlines. And I've been following it almost
the way people follow sports teams that they like. Tell me a little bit about what you thought in
call it December when we at least in the West saw the first report of the case in China. What was
your intuition at the time? At that time, I was trying to take what the Chinese were saying at
face value, meaning that they had learned from the lessons of SARS about transparency. And we're
going to do this in a different manner. And they did produce the virus sequence very quickly that
allowed diagnostic tests and vaccine development to start. And we were able to identify novel
coronavirus. But initially, a lot of the reports were saying, this is something that was animal to
human, really tied to wet markets in Wuhan, that there wasn't evidence of human to human spread,
there were no deaths yet. But I did think that 41 patients getting something from one animal
at one market really seemed very odd to me, that that seemed to be too much. So I was a little bit
skeptical that this was just an animal to human event, unless there was something different going
on, or there are multiple animals that were infected and infected multiple people. But as
soon as I saw the first paper, and that was the Lancet paper where they showed the first case got
ill on December 1. And he had no contact with the market. That told me that we were dealing with the
transmissible human to human respiratory virus. And that this was going to be a pathogen that was
going to spread and not be containable and that we were going to have to get ready. I had a lot of
questions about the case fatality ratio, the hospitalization rate, which I still have. But I
knew at that point, when you had a virus that spreads efficiently between human to humans
through the respiratory route, you really have to prepare for this being everywhere, especially when
you know that this had a head start at least spreading since mid November in China. And nobody
knew about it until late December. So that gave a virus a very big head start and could have been
anywhere by the time we actually knew it was as soon as we discovered that it actually existed.
Based on that, do you think it's possible that this virus was in the United States potentially
even within an individual prior to December 31? This is a little bit of controversy. I do know
that with past novel coronaviruses that have been discovered like HKU1, which isn't one that people
think about, but it is one that was discovered post SARS, it was everywhere as soon as they found it.
This one, it doesn't appear that at least that there wasn't widespread presence of it before
maybe January. However, I don't rule out the possibility that it could have been mixed in our
flu and cold season, maybe a sporadic case here or there that was mild, that didn't get diagnosed.
But it doesn't appear at least from the phylogenetics, the genetics of the virus that we're
seeing from both New York and in Washington, that this was around before that. But I do think it's
going to be important to go back and look at bank samples and look at people to see if there were
cases. I don't think there were a lot of them. I think we would have noticed if there were a lot of
them, but I think there may have been sporadic cases that were mixed into flu and cold season,
but it's an open question. And I think it's a good hypothesis. And I think it's something
that deserves a lot more attention. At what point, Amesh, were you becoming convinced that this was
going to enter the US in a manner that was going to pose real difficulty for the country?
So I knew it was going to enter the United States almost from the onset, as soon as we knew that
this was transmitting between human to human, that this wasn't going to be containable, just
like when H1N1 appeared in 2009 and was found in Mexico, that we knew that this wasn't going to be
something that would spare the United States. What I wasn't quite attuned to was how difficult
it would be to contain in the United States. Because I, like many of us, believe that our
diagnostic testing and our case finding and our contact tracing would have been really much better
than it was. But the fact was, we didn't know who had this, who didn't have it. Our testing
made it much harder to actually do that. And we weren't even testing mild cases. And those mild
cases are arguably more contagious than the severe cases. So that let this slip from something that
was potentially controllable and wouldn't have been a problem, or a major problem, not putting
cities like New York City under the stress that they're under, to one that became completely
unmanageable because we basically were allowing this virus to have about two months of unabated
spread in the United States. And that's something that most of us did not think would happen,
because we thought that we were much more resilient to these types of infections than we
really were. And I think that's, it didn't have to be that way, but that's basically how it turned out.
When you go back and look at the history of not just the other coronaviruses, which have gotten a
lot of airtime lately, of course, most people, even if they don't remember the ins and outs of SARS
and MERS, they're certainly familiar enough. But when you go back even further and look at some of
the flus that occurred in Asia, Hong Kong in the 1950s, 60s, and of course, going back even further
to the Spanish flu of 1918 to 1920, what are some of the similarities that you see with this novel
coronavirus? Then of course, I'll contrast that in a moment with what the differences are. And the
point of this exercise is less about just abstract history, but more to understand what we can learn.
Sure. So if you go back to 1957 and 1968, these were pandemics that were marked by the emergence
of a novel flu virus that spread around the world very rapidly. And if you look at the United States
experience, about 1957 and 1968, about 100,000 people died from that, which is a substantial
number because on record right now, the worst flu season we've had outside of 57 and 68 has really
been 2017, 2018, where about 80,000 people or so may have died. So these were severe outbreaks. And
flu has a lot of similarities with coronavirus, but there are some differences. So one thing is,
I mean, they both are transmitted through the respiratory route. They both have symptoms that
are included coughing and sneezing and sore throat and muscle aches and pains and fevers. So they
have a lot of overlap clinically. And I think that because of the way they spread and their symptoms,
you can look at their spread. And there's a lot of analogies that you can draw. But what I would
say is with flu is sometimes it's difficult because people have already taken flu and put it into
their own risk of daily life that they know that there's going to be maybe 30,000 to 50,000, 60,000
people who die every year. So even during a pandemic like 1957 and 1968, most people still
carried on because this was still a flu virus. And the same thing happened to an extent with 2009 H1N1,
especially when we realized that its case fatality ratio was actually less than seasonal
flu, even though it infected 61 million Americans led to a lot of hospitalizations and put hospitals
into distress. It wasn't that deadly. So people kind of took it in stride. This is something
that's a little bit different because it's on top of flu, it's additive to flu. I think that's one
of my pet peeves of the media coverage is sometimes they try to compare it to flu. But
remember that we're already going to have 40 to 50,000 deaths from flu. And this is on top of that.
I do think that influenza gets a short shrift by people because it's something that they take for
granted and don't realize the burden of infection that it has. And that influenza still even today
remains the biggest pandemic threat that we face. If you think about some of the influenza viruses
like avian influenza, they have case fatality ratios about 65%. That's too much for the world
to bear. So if one of those like H7N9 became able to efficiently transmit from humans, that's a
totally different type of pandemic that we're talking about than what we're dealing with today.
And I think that's important. And maybe that's why I seem a little bit more optimistic than most
people are a little bit more measured when I'm talking about this, because in my mind, I'm
thinking about avian influenza and what that kind of a pandemic would represent. And I used to say
that this is kind of a trial run because it's less than 1% case fatality rate, maybe as low as 0.3
case fatality rate. But we didn't do that great of a job with it in terms of diagnostic testing
and hospital capacity and personal protective equipment. So that's magnified this. And that's
the human factor that's magnified what the virus could do. And I think that's an important point
to make. And that's how I would kind of leave it is that you have certain ways to think about this
using flu as an analogy. But I do think that I'm a little more worried about our pandemic
resiliency based on how badly we've handled a 1% case fatality rate pandemic virus where you've
got cascading decisions by governors in states and countries all around the world that really have
magnified the damage that the virus has done. One other question I want to ask before we leave
the historical, which is the sort of ebbing and flowing recurrences that occurred back in some of
these other pandemics where it's easy to sort of think of them as this was the impact on the United
States, but not realizing, well, actually, it had a different impact on this city versus that city.
And they were not just different in terms of the strain they put on the healthcare system or even
the mortality rate, but even temporally, they could be separated by quite a period of time.
Is that something that also applies here in your opinion?
I do think so. We have this tendency to think of a pandemic as a homogenous
wave over the whole world or even a country. But it's actually many small outbreaks together. And
everybody's on a different timescale based upon when the virus is introduced into that area,
what their population density is, what their hospital capacity is, what demographic got
infected. So you aren't going to see synchronous outbreaks. They're going to be a little bit
staggered. And there's going to be differences on, for example, when did somebody do social
distancing? When did someone not do social distancing? How do they vary between this state
and that state? That's also going to impact the trajectory of the outbreak. You might see places
like I'm sitting here in Pittsburgh right now, which hasn't had a bad experience with this virus
yet. But we've had the opportunity to learn from New York and Seattle and San Francisco.
And that's gauged the way that we've dealt with testing and hospital capacity. So our outbreak is
going to be different because we've learned from them. And we don't have the population density
issue. So I do think there is going to be ebbing and flowing, especially with social distancing,
varying, and maybe lifting in certain places of the country and not lifting in other places.
And you may find that this virus is going to have some degree of seasonality. I don't think it will
have complete full seasonality because there's so many people that are susceptible to it. But you
may see this come back in successive waves. And remember, there are four other coronaviruses that
circulate every year and cause about 25% of our colds. This is something that I suspect will be
the fifth one that does that. And it looks like it has an intermediate severity. It's not as severe
as SARS, for example, which has a case fatality ratio of about 10%. But it doesn't seem to be as
mild as the other four coronaviruses. So I do think you're going to see ebbing and flowing,
especially as social distancing changes across the country until we have a vaccine.
And is it your view that this will now be a fifth coronavirus that will fit into the mix,
and it's never really going to go away in the way that at least SARS and MERS, because of their
severity, they don't really factor into that recurrent cycle we see every year?
I do think this is going to be the fifth season of coronavirus. And I would say with SARS and MERS,
it's not just that they were more severe, which they are, it's that they're poorly transmissible
from human to human. They are mostly zoonotic, or meaning animal to human transmission. So
Palm civet cats, Middle East respiratory syndrome, MERS from camels. So that's something that's
really limited to their spread. It's only those individuals who are in contact with those animals
that are really at risk. And when you look at their outbreaks, they're very specialized,
they're happening in healthcare facilities with poor infection control, and it doesn't really
sustain itself in the human population. Whereas if you look at the other four coronaviruses,
the ones that cause common colds, they are ubiquitous, they transmit very easy,
they have a mild spectrum of illness, which allows people to go about their daily life
and spread. And this new novel coronavirus does appear to be more like them in terms of their
transmissibility. So that's why I think that this will be the fifth seasonal coronavirus until
there's a vaccine. Do you think a vaccine is going to be specific to this coronavirus, or do you think
that it will be more geared towards all coronaviruses to cover not just this one, but perhaps others
that will potentially emerge, you know, a SARS-CoV-3 that's five years away? Right now, vaccine
development is premised on making something specific to this specific immunogenic protein
that the immune system recognizes for this virus. So it will be specific to that. But I do suspect
you might see some cross reactivity between the vaccine for this SARS-CoV-2 and other related
coronaviruses, maybe the SARS-CoV-2 clusters in something called the beta coronaviruses,
maybe the vaccine will work against all beta coronaviruses, but it would be great if it worked
against all coronaviruses and we had a pan-coronavirus vaccine. We might get something
like that because coronaviruses are different than, for example, influenza, which has been very
hard to make a universal flu vaccine. The coronaviruses in general tend to be much more
stable, even though there's some diversity among them, and we might have cross protection, which
would be useful to take other threats like Middle East respiratory syndrome and the original SARS
off the table as well. When H1N1 hit, you sort of alluded to this briefly, the case fatality rate
was initially deemed to be much higher. It was only once we appreciated how prevalent it was
that the case fatality rate came so far down. I believe in the end it's less than 0.1% correct?
Yes, yeah, definitely.
What is your real assessment now? And again, you can only be speculating at this point,
I understand, but what do you think is the true case fatality rate of SARS-CoV-2 specifically?
And if you want to answer that, by the way, in terms of I think that the CFR is going to be this
for people over 60 and this for people under 60, and it blends out to this, I mean, answer it any
way you see fit. So the CFR has been really hard to calculate because we have a severity bias
because testing has been so heterogeneous around countries. So what I do is try to look at a place
that's tested extensively and use that as kind of a barometer. And right now, it used to be South
Korea that tested, and now it seems to be Germany is doing the best testing. And you're also looking
at modeling studies. So some of the modeling studies from Imperial College put the case fatality
ratio at 0.66%. Germany looks like it's at a 0.3 something percent.
Yeah, I think 0.37 this morning, yeah.
Yeah, doing antibody testing to try and understand. So I do think it's probably in that range,
probably in the 0.3 to 0.66. I say that with some confidence, but it may drift lower or higher,
depending upon how much severity bias is in the samples. And it's very hard. We probably won't
truly know until we do retrospective studies looking at antibodies to understand how prevalent
it is. And there's differences amongst that because that's an average number. If you're above
80, your case fatality ratio may be as high as 15%. If you're eight years old, your case fatality
ratio may be 0%. So I think it's important to remember that these are average numbers, and it's
not every person carries that risk. Some people will have much, much higher risks, and some people
will have lower risks. And I think that's sometimes lost in nuance when you try to come up with one
number.
Absolutely, yeah. Blending that is, there's lots of glib examples of how you can drown in an average
of three inches of water, of course, if you're walking across a river that has vacillating depth.
Because you're, again, kind of a veteran of this, what do you think was sort of the
overslash, underdoing of some of the predictions that came out in the sort of Gen 1 models that
showed up in sort of February where they were saying, look, this is something that is going to
infect 200 million Americans. It's going to kill two to four million Americans. Do you think that
that type of modeling historically has ever shown to be accurate? Or do you think that, yes,
that was accurate, and it's the measures that are in place that are going to hopefully prevent that
from happening? Because it seems less likely now that we're heading in the direction of those types
of doomsday scenarios. But again, it's hard to know how much of that is in response to the
measures that have been enacted versus predictions that were predicated on poorly understood things,
including what the R0 was. I think that models you have to realize have assumptions built into
them. And you have to look at those assumptions, because just a small difference in the assumption
can lead to a big change on the end of it. And what I would think, at least from my
understanding of many of the models, is that the hospitalization rate was probably overstated.
Because we know, for example, that the diagnosis that we're talking about in any given city or town
are likely understated by a factor of at least maybe 10. And I can say that from my own practice
when I order the test and don't order the test. There's many patients, I think, have the disease
and I don't order the test. So there clearly is a severity bias in who gets tested. And then I
think you see this idea of 15% to 20% getting admitted to the hospital. I think that that
doesn't necessarily mean everybody of the people that get infected, maybe that's 40% of the
population over time, that 15% to 20% of those individuals get admitted. It's more like, of the
40% of the population that get infected, the ones who go to an emergency department,
15 to 20% get admitted. And maybe the real hospitalization rate is 5%. If you look at,
for example, Westchester County's data, which I haven't looked at lately, but the last time I
looked, they did a lot of heavy testing in that part of New York State, because they had that
outbreak in New Rochelle. And their hospitalization rate was around 5%, a little bit less than 5% the
last time I calculated it. And that changes, that gives you a major change from going down from 20%
to 5% in terms of what your ventilator needs are, what your ICU bed capacity needs are,
and what the case fatality ratio is going to be if you look at what the hospitalization rate is.
And I think that that's at least one of my criticisms of some of the models, the hospitalization
rate was set too high. And if they were taking too big of a fraction using the wrong denominator,
I think, to come up with what their case fatality ratios are, what their ICU bed needs would be,
and what their mechanical ventilation needs would be. And that happens because models have lots of
assumption in them. And they should be used as tools. They're not ironclad. And I think that
sometimes that gets lost in the press reporting of them, they get looked at as if they are the truth,
and they need to be revised. And when you have real data from real hospitals and real people,
it should supplant what you're using with a model. So if your model is not matching reality,
then I think you need to either change the assumptions on the model or actually look at
reality. These are tools and all models are going to be wrong. Some of them are going to be useful,
and some of them are not going to be useful. I agree. I think it's unfortunately the press
sometimes views corrections of models as a sign of weakness as opposed to a necessary part of the
evolution of utilizing the tool as you described it. We've talked a little bit about this being a
dress rehearsal for what is coming unquestionably at some point, very likely in our lifetimes,
which is another pandemic, another virus, and potentially one that could be much more devastating.
You used an example of viruses that are typically transmitted only from animals to humans that can
potentially be much more catastrophic. But if those viruses ever figure out how to go human to human,
they spread much more. What is your view on the role of local versus central government in
dealing with that? Can't imagine there isn't a role for both, but I feel personally very confused
when I try to sometimes play the game. If I was czar for a day, what would I do different? But the
reality of it is it's easy to play armchair quarterback. I'm not really sure I know
what the federal government should be doing in this situation versus the state governments and
local governments. This is something that's pretty unique to the United States because we have a system
of a federal government with states and locals having most of the power, especially true in
public health because most of the public health powers are vested at the local and state level.
The federal government is more of a coordinator. Even the CDC can't actually get involved in
something unless they're asked by a state. You will often see differences and heterogeneity
between recommendations from maybe one county to the next and definitely from one state to the next.
Sometimes that can be confusing. I do think that I'm generally supportive of local health departments
being the ones running it because they actually know their community, they know their capacities,
they know where their gaps are, and they're able to really be on the ground with the people and
able to do great things when it comes to stopping an outbreak. But often what we find is local health
departments aren't appropriately resourced. You've got one person doing four different roles in a
small town's health department, and that can be very constraining. What you need to really do is
have those local health departments actually operating the way that they should be and thought
of as part of the whole pandemic response apparatus, whereas many people think of just the CDC, the NIH,
and parts of the Health and Human Services Department as the main pandemic apparatus.
It's actually the local health departments that do all that case finding and isolation and talk to
the public and deal with hospital capacity levels. It's the local health department, so I can't
overstate how important local health departments are. I do think that that system works well,
but you do need to have federal leadership to guide the nation as a whole on what to expect
and what's going on. I think that's sort of been missing a lot during this outbreak compared to
other outbreaks. Because of that, you've seen governors at state health departments take on
roles that they usually haven't taken, where they've deferred much more to federal experts,
not the powers, but the guidance and looking to them to set the tone. I think now we're finding
governors basically stepping into that role for the most part, and even mayors in some places.
I think that can be confusing to a member of the general public because they don't know who to
believe, especially if there's conflicting information. You have a press that's constantly
trying to pit one governor against another governor or against the federal government,
and that makes it much harder. I do think that when the process works well with local,
state, and federal government all in step, all doing the appropriate roles, I do think it works
pretty well. You have a locally managed, federally coordinated response, which I think is the best
way to think about how it would be ideally done. Is it safe to say that testing is really something
that like if you go back in time and maybe change one thing, if we're sitting here and it's January
12th and we now have the sequence of this virus, would that have potentially been one of the more
important things for the federal government, for that centralized piece of government to have put
in place? The CDC could have said, look, we're going to make this the highest priority because
it strikes me as that's something very difficult to be done in a decentralized manner.
What happened was the CDC put out guidance on who should be tested, which basically was taken as
gospel by the state health departments. That included only people that had traveled to China
in the last 14 days, as well as someone who had to have lower respiratory tract symptoms. You
couldn't have just had a sore throat. You had to have evidence that maybe you had pneumonia to be
tested. So we weren't testing mild cases and we weren't testing people that hadn't come to China.
That was a federal decision. And I think that could have been done better and allowed much more
latitude. Because you can remember that first case in California that didn't have traveled to China,
they, the hospital had to actually fight to get that test run. And there were many cases like that
all over the country. And if you look at New York's epidemiology, their introduction of the virus
was not from China, it was from Europe. And that slips through the type of testing algorithm. So
I do think that there could have been at the beginning, an idea that somebody could have said,
this is a respiratory virus, it has many overlapping symptoms with common colds and
flus. You should think about this in your patients. And we are going to allow testing to be done,
if you have certain risk factors for this, and they shouldn't just be restricted to you having
severe disease or having traveled to China. That would have changed the way that the general public
and clinicians would have thought about this. The other thing is, is that there were bureaucratic
wrangles that paradoxically, once a public health emergency was declared, they were unable to make
diagnostic tests as freely available as would have been if there wasn't a public health emergency
made. So for example, you had university labs and big commercial labs not being able to make a test,
even the CDC test had to go through FDA emergency use authorization before it could be distributed
to the states. So there were a lot of bureaucratic hiccups that created a problem that compounded
the testing protocol with the scarcity of tests and a delay in getting testing kits everywhere.
And then we still have shortages of reagents and nasal swabs, and we're still not to where we need
to be with testing. And not to get too far ahead of ourselves, but do you get the impression that
the response to this is serious enough that it will now be taken more seriously to have kind of
that type of emergency response ready five years from now when people have long forgotten about
this? I hope so. I think this is something that's going to leave a mark on society. This
hasn't happened in modern times, not during the 68 or 57 pandemics. And it did happen in 1918,
but that's not in anybody's living memory anymore. So I do think that this is something that people
will remember. And they will remember the costs that they personally had to incur filing for
unemployment for the first time. All of that type of stuff is going to hopefully push the public to
demand that pandemic preparedness be taken seriously. So this doesn't happen again,
and that this should be a priority. This should be something that's in a candidate's campaign
literature. This is what I think about pandemic preparedness, and it always should have been.
But we've gone through this cycle for a long, long time. You can think about anthrax in 2001,
bird flu scares in 2005, the H1N1 pandemic in 2009, Ebola in 2013, 2014, Zika, right after that.
We've had multiple types of episodes, and you get this cycle where everybody runs to fund this
reactively, and then it disappears from the headlines, and no one remembers it. And then
the same cycle happens. They cut positions at the National Security Council when there's nothing
going on. And they do lots of things that make us less resilient to pandemics, not realizing that
this is a perpetual threat, just like any other national security concern, that you have to be
prepared for this at all times. And you have to actually think about it that way and fund it that
way and have the proper personnel, even between pandemics and between outbreaks.
But you are optimistic that this time, I mean, just based on the economic consequences of this,
even if not one more person were to die in the United States, which means frankly, let's be clear,
if not one more person died in the United States as of today, this would not be a major source of
mortality. This would still be a rounding error compared to influenza. But you're just saying the
economic consequences of this have been so severe that you're optimistic that we're not going to
walk away from this one in 18 months and sort of forget about it and do all the wrong stuff all
over again. Yeah, I do suspect we're going to have many more deaths, probably closer to that 60,000.
I do think that the fact that this outbreak touched people personally in a way that Ebola did not,
the way that Zika did not, the way even that H1N1 did not, H1N1 actually engendered complacency
because only about 12,000 Americans died. And then people said we all overreacted to H1N1. So I
think this is actually something that every American is feeling right now because of the
economic shutdown, the stay at home orders, all of that, the fact that they had to adjust their
entire life. This is something that's been extremely disruptive. And I think that hopefully
the public remembers that when they vote. And when they ask their policymakers about what their
plans are for the future, that pandemic preparedness becomes something that is a platform issue now.
Based on where we are, what do you think is the right strategy in, for example,
a place like New York versus a place like you could pick any city you like, whether it be
Pittsburgh, Houston, cities where it's been nowhere near that. I mean, how would you start to think
about changing any of the policy or is the answer until we have more testing, we can't make any more
decisions? I do think based on modeling, if these symptoms are valid and what's going on in the
ground and hospitals, you can start to see this heterogeneity across the country. And not every
place is going to be New York City, not every place has that population density or hospitals
that are at the brink all the time. So I do think that there are places where you can start to think
about relaxing some of the social distancing recommendations as well as the economic shutdowns,
especially things like elective surgeries at hospitals and opening clinics at hospitals.
I think that already needs to happen, especially so in places where they're not
undated because you're going to get other health consequences that are not captured by the models,
which are really measurable and will pay for down the road. I do think you can look right now at
the governor's lists of what is an essential or a life sustaining business and what is not,
and look at who they're granting exemptions to and try to be a little bit broader about that.
Think about looking to see what your school system is like and can you open schools in a safe manner
right now based on what the conditions are in your area, because even the whole closure of schools
was very controversial and not supported by everybody in my field. So there are things
that you can do. And I do think it's not going to be one size fits all, it's going to be dependent on
what's going on locally, how much transmission do you have? What is the antibody status of your
population? What's your hospital capacity? And what is your ability to do diagnostic testing?
Do you have the new rapid test available in many different places? All of that can help condition
how we get back to normal or a new normal, because I do think that things like mass gatherings are
going to be very hard to have for some time until we have a vaccine, because I think a mass gathering
is kind of can put a town over the edge if they get multiple episodes of transmission at a mass
gathering. But I do think that we can start taking steps and I hope that we start doing it,
because this cost is something that is measurable and it increases every day. And I do think that
there are going to be consequences that are not captured by our models, which are really only
focused on coronavirus. Yeah, it's an interesting point you raised there with respect to mass
gatherings. I mean, I think the German data, which just came out basically last night, would suggest
that it's really the mass gatherings that are disproportionately driving the spread versus
two people having dinner at a restaurant. Is it your view that there's really something quite
devastating about concerts and live sporting events that is not necessarily captured in
going to the grocery store? Yeah, a mass gathering brings people from
wide geographic areas. If you think about, I live in Pittsburgh and there are Steeler fans that
come from everywhere in the country to watch a Steeler game and then they go back to their
hometowns. That's a way you can disperse things. And sporting games are not people sitting
quietly with just one person. They are social gatherings where people are yelling and screaming
and eating and drinking and all types of things that a virus would look at is an easy way to get
from one person to another. We know that when people shout and scream, they make particles
come out of their mouth. That can transmit. We've seen this at choir practice, for example,
with this coronavirus. Just think of that. It's at a football stadium and you can imagine how these
types of things can transmit. I do think that mass gatherings, because of the density, because of the
fact that people come from different geographic regions and then disperse, are a particular
problem when it comes to communicable infectious diseases. And we see this every year with,
for example, religious pilgrimages to Saudi Arabia, where they make sure that you have this
type of vaccination. They have a whole division of the World Health Organization devoted to mass
gatherings because we know what their role is in spreading infectious diseases. And I think that's
going to be something that's going to be a challenge to have until there is a vaccine.
And I want to go back to something you said about HKU1. Tell folks a little bit more about that
coronavirus and the concern it gives you. It's less of a concern that it gives me now,
but it's more of understanding what happens with coronaviruses. So go back to 2003 and SARS is the
first coronavirus that really hits the map as a pandemic threat before they're thought of as
common cold viruses. Now everyone's on the lookout for any new coronavirus. And what they do is,
in Hong Kong, HKU stands for Hong Kong University, they find a novel coronavirus in some individuals
that had pneumonia. And they start looking, they find more, they actually look at bank samples
that were negative for SARS, positive for HKU. They look at other countries, they find HKU1.
They actually find it in Cleveland. In the proportion of patients that were hospitalized
for coronavirus, HKU is disproportionately found, even in patients who died or on ventilators.
And it was basically everywhere you looked. That's interesting because it kind of flew under the
radar because no one knew it was there because we do such a poor job at testing for respiratory
viruses. Many times people go to the doctor and they say, Oh, you've got some virus. We don't know
which one, but you're going to get better. And that's even the case for pneumonias, because most
people don't get a specific microbiologic diagnosis of their pneumonia. So we really have this biological
dark matter everywhere. And I initially thought maybe this coronavirus was around hidden in our
cold and flu season. It clearly was hidden in China's cold and flu season since at least November.
But it doesn't appear, at least from what I've seen now, that there was much burden of that
in the United States prior to 2020, that this might have been something that really only began
in earnest in January. But I would not be surprised if you find a bank sample that there were cases
in December that were mixed in just like with HKU1. But I do think we would have noticed if there
was a lot of these people getting really ill and ending up on ventilators and were flu negative and
not negative and negative for everything else. At least enough of them would have raised some alarm
bells, I would hope. But I do think that's an important lesson to think about with a virus
that can spread surreptitiously. And you don't know about it because our diagnostic
curiosity is so bad for many infectious disease syndromes.
Yeah, that's a nice way of putting it, poor diagnostic curiosity. Have you been following
the sort of natural experiment that's going on in Sweden? Natural experiment meaning there's no
randomization, but rather Sweden has sort of elected to not shut down to the extent that other
European and Scandinavian countries have. Have you paid attention to the transmissibility in Sweden?
Do you have any comments on it?
I've looked a little bit at what Sweden is doing where they're trying to pursue a herd immunity
strategy. And I do think that you're going to see more cases there, which is what they're aiming
for. I'm just worried because their per capita ICU bed numbers are not very high. And that's what
we're really worried about is, do you put an ICU into crisis? Do you have problems with ventilators?
And I think it will be really instructive to see if they can get through this because I know they
have a steep curve of infections. But it's all going to depend upon who's getting sick and how
well they can sequester their high risk groups, which I think is very daunting and challenging.
I'm all for cocooning the elderly and those with other medical conditions. But I know it's very
challenging because they have to interact with other people to get their food, to do other things.
And that can be really challenging. So I do think that everybody's eyes are on Sweden to see if this
type of thing can work. But I'm worried about how challenging it might be for them because there is
that group of people that are going to get hospitalized and could put a hospital into crisis.
Last thing I want to ask you is what role do you think masks are going to play as we start to
slowly ease restrictions in the coming months? Do you think that we kind of got off to a bad
start on understanding the potential benefit of an N95 mask for people in public who are otherwise
at relatively low risk? So this is controversial in my field. And I tend to be someone who's not
someone supportive of masks by the public, especially not N95 masks, which I think are
in short supply, unclear whether the public can actually bear wearing them for a long period of
time because they're not comfortable to wear. And really what we saw in the beginning was a
recommendation to not wear masks for the general public because it wasn't going to protect you
from getting infected to one that's transitioned to wear a mask so that you don't infect other
people. So I would say if someone is sick, if they have a cough, if they have a fever, if they're
sneezing or a sore throat, they should be wearing a mask when they're out in public. Question is,
are people who are asymptomatic having no symptoms, how transmissible are they if they don't wear a
mask? And this is an open question, but CDC made a recommendation for people to use homemade masks
in that event. And I'm not sure how well those homemade masks prevent you from spreading it if
you are one of those asymptomatic persons, because they don't even stop the coughs and sneezes very
well based on some studies that have been published. So I'm someone who doesn't necessarily think
that these masks are going to be very beneficial. And they could be paradoxically negative because
people may then refrain from washing their hands as much. They may not social distance as much.
They may contaminate other people with their mask if they don't store it properly or wash it.
So I have a lot of concerns about masks. But I think that this is a decision that's going to be
made on a political basis. And there is enough scientific controversy that I think politicians
may use it as a way to move forward in a way that allows us to open schools, open businesses up if
they have people wearing masks. But I'm not sure if we'll get much benefit from them. But it is
something that's going to be an object of controversy for some time in the field.
What are you most optimistic about today?
I would say that I'm most optimistic about the fact that we have seen plateauing in New York,
Seattle, California, we've heard about for example, California actually taking ventilators
and giving them to other states. We've heard about Washington State dismantling their field
hospital that they made that did not see any patients. We've heard about Washington returning
ventilators, Chijic National Stockpile, all of that makes me very optimistic that we will be
able to meet the challenge of this virus without putting any of our hospitals into crisis,
that this is going to be a severe challenge for this country, but it's not something that
that is going to break the country. And it's not going to be cataclysmic. So all of those types of
things, which are not well reported, the fact that ventilators are going back to the stockpile,
or that field hospitals are closing, I think that makes me optimistic because there is a narrative
that's rightly focused on areas like New York and New Orleans and Chicago and Detroit. But you also
have to tell the good stories that there are places that were preparing for a surge. And now
they're downsizing their nursing staff because less people came. So I think that that's an
important part to know that it's not going to be doom and gloom in every place and that we need to
help New York and New Orleans and Detroit and Chicago get through this, but not every city is
going to have that experience. So we're going to learn from those experiences. And I think,
hopefully, we'll get to a better pandemic resiliency position after this. So I am
generally more optimistic than most people in my field, I think.
Mesh, thank you very much for all of your insight today. I'd like to reserve the right to invite you
back when the dust has settled and we have much more time to talk about what a true preparedness
strategy would look like. Because again, I do have a significant fear that as visceral and palpable
and disturbing as all of this is today, both in terms of the physical suffering, but the fear,
the economic devastation, that we're a species that is relatively hardwired to have remarkable
amnesia. I don't know. I think it would be an unmitigated disaster if two years from now we're
sitting here and this is not at all a topic of discussion and someone like you is not able to
command the type of audience of policymakers to do what's necessary. So I hope that we can have
that longer discussion when there are fewer fires burning, but when I think the stakes are equally
high. Thank you.
Absolutely. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in
diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiels like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less than
five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions,
topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on
previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts
on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch
of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and
access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe.
You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can
also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for
general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing,
or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No
doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this
podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in
obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the
assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of
interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please
visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.