Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive Podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in health
and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make this happen.
If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you far more
in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of the space to the next level. At
the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Lou Cantley. Lou is the Meyer Director and Professor
of Cancer Biology at the Sandra and Edward Meyer Cancer Center at Weill Cornell Medical College
in New York City. Lou's research has made significant advances in cancer research stemming
primarily from his discovery of the signaling pathway for PI3 kinase or PI3K in the mid 80s.
And his results here have really touched multiple fields, including cancer first and foremost,
but also diabetes and autoimmune disease. Lou is a very decorated scientist, to put it mildly.
It would take me too long to rattle off all of the awards that he's won, but I'll leave it to the
four most prestigious, the Gairdner Award, the Breakthrough Prize in Science, the Wolf Prize,
and most recently the Horowitz Prize. Arguably, the only two prizes that are not on that list
would be the Lasker Prize and the Nobel Prize. And I think that many people suspect that Lou
will ultimately be awarded at least the Nobel Prize, if not both. This is a podcast that at
times gets very technical, but most of the technical stuff falls at the end of the podcast.
It's actually what we started with, but much like we did in a previous podcast, we're going to move
that to the back end of the podcast so that we can jump right into the more concrete stuff that I
think people want to hear about with respect to science. And we'll treat what was the first 45
minutes of this interview as a technical tour de force of the discovery of PI 3K, and we'll move
that as basically an appendix. So if you're listening to this and you really want to understand
science and you really want to understand how discovery is done, stuff that I really like to
hear about, by all means, you'll just listen to this as it's laid out. And if you really just
want to hear about the implications of Lou's work as it pertains to cancer, then you will probably
just listen to the first hour and 45 minutes or so of this and not the remaining 45 minutes.
Before we jump into this, there are just two things I want to say. The first is I want to note
Lou's disclosures. Lou is the co-founder of two pharmaceutical companies, Agios and Petra. And he
is also the co-founder of a company that is just getting off the ground called Feith. That's F-A-E-T-H.
Feith is a company that hopes to pair nutrition with pharmaceuticals, and that will all make sense
during the podcast. These are all really interesting companies, but I think it's important, obviously,
to list those disclosures at the outset. Secondly, I want to be sure that everyone understands that
we have a discussion here that is very detailed at times and very tactical at times with respect to
cancer treatment. And certainly every time I talk with Lou, I come away with a new way of thinking
about the care of patients with cancer. Please do not mistake what we are talking about here as
medical advice. It is impossible to provide medical advice to someone with whom you do not have a
doctor-patient relationship. And so unfortunately, I hate saying that, but it is an obligatory
disclaimer that I must provide. And whatever we talk about here, the combinations of therapies
with respect to drugs for diabetes, drugs for cancer, and of course nutritional therapies
really needs to be had in discussion with your physician. Actually, I lied and I said two things.
There's one other thing I want to talk about, which is there is a cancer trial that is about
to take off that is a really interesting and exciting prospect through one of Lou's companies.
The enrollment for that trial is just kicking off now, and we will list to that should anybody
listening to this podcast either have the type of cancer that's being studied or know somebody who
does. And it would be great to know that people are able to more readily get enrolled in that
clinical trial. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Lou Cannery.
Lou, thank you so much for coming over. It's great to be here, Peter.
You live like 10 feet from me here, and yet this is the first time you've been here, I think, right?
Yeah, it took me five minutes to walk in. It is great to see you always. You're definitely one
of the most generous people with his insights and with the work you've done, and I consider you an
absolute mentor in how I think about these problems in biology. So we've been trying to get on this
podcast together for a year, but it's a testament. I was going to say to how busy I am, but it's no,
it's to how busy you are. I'm busy, but you are even busier than me. I do keep pretty busy.
Well, there are a lot of things I want to talk about today. I think to set my own expectations,
we probably won't be able to get through them all, which speaks in some ways to the breadth of your
work. We're going to talk so much about cancer and metabolism and things here, but there's what we
know today about PI 3K, which I think would be a nice thing to spend a moment on. But I also love
this idea. Like I have this idea, Lou, which is we should be teaching kids science, not the way you
were taught biology as a 16 year old, which was rote memorization. We should simply teach science
through the lens of discovery. So in other words, every biology class, even at the high school level
and even younger should be less about memorizing what it is that you see looking at this microscope
and memorize all the organelles or something like that. It's more of let's tell the stories of
science because one, if our goal is to train scientists, well, they're going to go and become
experts in whatever they're going to become expert in. We don't have to worry that in high school,
they're not going to learn enough content. But if we're trying to screen for people who are
interested in science, what you have to be screening for is the process is the discovery,
is the game, is the thinking that went into the experiment. It's the blind luck. It's the bad luck.
And that comes out in the story of everything. I've yet to hear a single world-class scientist,
and I have the privilege of sitting down with so many of them, tell their story without some element
of good luck and bad luck combined. Serendipity. Yes. Serendipity in science is absolutely critical
that when you get a result that's unexpected, you should be laser focused on understanding
at the biochemistry, at the chemical level, why you got a different result than you expected to get.
And following these journeys is to me a better way to weave the narrative arc of science. I mean,
I think frankly, it's not that there's no value in knowing that DNA is a helical structure and it
has these base pairs and it has this backbone, but that shouldn't be the focus. To me, actually
walking through the fumbling of how those guys got there, that's a very interesting story.
And that probably will serve a non-scientist better when they're done with science class,
because they'll have an appreciation for the process. And now I'm getting on my soapbox
about it would be better if policymakers understood that that's how science worked,
as opposed to trying to remember what they learned in a biochemistry class 30 years earlier.
And of course, for the people who are going to go into science, I still think they're going to
go back and learn the basics anyway, so we don't have to through rote memory get that stuff into
them. But it's this process of thinking and collaborating and walking down the hall,
and seeing the result, as you said, that doesn't quite make sense and saying, well, wait a minute,
there's something in there. There's a story. I mean, science is basically just one big mystery.
It's really about curiosity. That's what I'm hearing in your story is it's less about your
innate brilliance and more about your obsessiveness, your ability to make an observation and not let
it go. Yeah, if I get a result that suddenly doesn't make sense, to me, that's more exciting.
It means there's something more complicated going on than the simplest explanation for what I'm
seeing. If the simple explanation works, then fine, you publish it in some second rate journal.
But if you've broken up a whole new field, because your simple explanation doesn't work
and you figured out why it didn't work and what was wrong, then that's where most breakthroughs
come from. When did cancer become such a high focus? We met in 2011, two years after you,
Matthew Vanderheiden and Craig Thompson wrote what I thought was sort of the one of the most
interesting papers I'd read on cancer in the journal Science. It's hard to believe we're
10 years away from that paper. What was the lead up to your collaboration in that paper and less
about the paper, but more about thinking about cancer metabolism? Because today when I think of
Lou Cantley, I think of cancer metabolism. When did that transition occur? It was a postdoc
joined my laboratory, Matt Vanderheiden, who had trained with Craig Thompson. Matt's an MD, PhD,
now on the faculty at MIT. But he had been obsessed about glucose metabolism as a graduate
student with Craig. In fact, I'd gotten one of his papers to review, which I was very impressed by.
He suddenly showed up at my office one day saying that he was interested in doing his postdoctoral
work as he finished his clinical training. At that time, a graduate student, Heather Christoff,
had been working in my laboratory, and she'd made the observation that if she used tyrosine
phosphorylated peptides to pull down a degenerate sequence context, it wasn't a single peptide,
it was a whole mixture of billions of peptides all the same length, biotinylated so you could pull
down anything they bound to, and then use mass spec to identify all the things that came down.
First of all, she rediscovered all the proteins that were known to bind to,
that have SH2 domains. This is a domain that many proteins, including PI3 kinase,
have that allow them to bind to tyrosine phosphorylated proteins. In that one experiment,
she rediscovered everything that had been published of all the things that bind to tyrosine
phosphorylated proteins. But she discovered the thing that bound better than anything else in the cell,
or that was most massively pulled down, was an enzyme in metabolism, pyruvate kinase.
That was shocking. I remember her first response to that was, well, the only novel thing I found
here that wasn't already known was this affinity for pyruvate kinase. She said, well, that's a
metabolic enzyme, and they're all boring, so I don't think I really want to work on that. I said,
no, no, that's whenever you get to resolve. You pulled the lube. The totally unexpected result.
That's the thing you should focus on. And so she did, and at the time that Matt was interviewing
with me, I told him about her results, and he got very excited about that, and the two of them worked
together to show how that was working. So this is early 2000s, right? This was 2000 and...
Mid-2005? 2005, maybe. Matthew Vanderheiden was a classmate, I believe. I've obviously met Matt
since, but I believe he was a medical school classmate at one of my close friends, Ted Schafer,
who actually I had on the podcast. And Ted also was an MD PhD, did his PhD in Harold Varmus's lab.
So it all kind of comes full circle. A lot of smart folks came out of the University of Chicago.
So anyway, so he, Matt and Heather ended up publishing two back-to-back papers in Nature
that both explained structurally how phosphatyrosine peptides or proteins binding to
pyruvate kinase could turn off its activity. And then also explained why turning off the activity
of pyruvate kinase was important to increase anabolic growth. And that is kind of the basis for
why we decided to start AUGIUS, that Craig was interested in how metabolism was regulated in
cancer cells. And we had made this observation that pyruvate kinase regulation was important in
oncogenic regulation, anabolic processes in cells. And so we proposed pyruvate kinase activators
rather than inhibitors as a way to reduce tumor growth as one of the targets to go after at AUGIUS
as we were starting the company. So that review, which I should say that Matt played a much bigger
role in writing that review than Craig or I did. He was the first author. So yeah, that was pretty
clear. When did the Warburg effect, when did you start paying attention to it? I mean, obviously
it was around before you were born. Yeah. So actually I mentioned F. Racker earlier. F. Racker
was, knew Warburg quite well and they overlapped in Germany. He was obsessed by understanding the
Warburg effect. The Warburg effect being a result published by Warburg back in the 19,
21 or so, almost a hundred years ago, that if you chemically induce cancer in rats,
the tumor that evolves takes up glucose and metabolizes it in an anabolic way much, much
faster than the tissue of origin prior to transformation. This was chemically induced
cancer formations. And this also, this observation was that even when there was sufficient
cellular oxygen to generate ATP much more efficiently through the mitochondria,
it was as though the cancer cell elected to go this faster, less efficient route.
That's right. The surprising result was, well, there's plenty of oxygen. We've taken a tumor
out. We are in an oxygen environment. Why doesn't it make ATP through mitochondrial
oxidative phosphorylation instead of through glycolysis? Why do you think the Warburg effect
was largely forgotten in the forties and fifties and sixties? I mean, it wasn't, it felt a lot of
favor, really not until late sixties, early seventies. And what was taking over at that time
was evidence for virally induced cancers, V-SARQ, Harold Varmus and Mike Bishop. So once it was
shown that viruses could turn on cancers, the idea that it was just an altered metabolism fell out
of favor. Of course, the discovery of oncogenes of which V-SARQ was the first clear oncogene,
because it told us that we've met the enemy and it is us. It is our own genes that are getting
altered in cancer. And so proto-oncogenes were being picked up by retroviruses.
Did anyone at the time think these two mechanisms aren't mutually exclusive?
The expression of or the amplification of, or the mechanism by which this viral injury to the genome
can perpetrate and can perpetuate could be through this defective metabolism?
I think people who thought about it deeply and who were trained as biochemists who were doing
metabolism, which F. Racker was one of the prime examples, continue to realize you have to alter
metabolism to do cancer. You need to switch a cell from a quiescent, not only from a quiescent state
to a dividing state, but in order to divide and make a bigger cluster of cells, you have to drive
glucose and amino acid uptake and anabolic processes, converting those to proteins and
lipids and DNA and RNA. So there was no doubt you had to turn up metabolism. The question was at what
level did metabolism play the role? Was it just a consequence of the viral transformation or the
ocogenic transformation or did they work cooperatively in some more complicated way?
So the R. P. R. on pyruvate kinase suggested yes, there is some clear cooperation where the active
tyrosine phosphorylating proteins was directly regulating the activity of metabolic enzyme,
rather than just turning up the expression, for example, through a transcriptional cascade.
So that's why it shifted the emphasis back to there may be targets in metabolism
that could give you an efficacy toxicity ratio for treating cancer. The truth is chemotherapy,
as you know better than I, is really targeting metabolism. You're blocking DNA synthesis or
other steps in metabolism as a way of killing cancer cells. So that's in a way targeting
metabolism is our first approach to curing cancer and now we're back to doing it in a more serious
way today. What was the point that you guys made that was so novel in that 2009 paper? Because
it's a subtle point that I think you can easily miss. You could easily look at that paper and say,
oh, this is just another paper discussing the Warburg effect. But you came up with a very clear
explanation for why the Warburg effect might exist that was different from the explanation
that I think I had looked at before, which was the mitochondria are defective. So I think
the easy explanation for the Warburg effect is the mitochondria don't work.
Therefore, the cancer cell has no choice but to undergo anaerobic glycolysis. You guys proposed
something different. Yeah, we proposed that you could even with totally functional mitochondria,
you could divert intermediates and glycolysis into anabolic processes by regulating steps in
glycolysis. And so the biggest question we know that if you have high ATP in the cell,
it will shut off glycolysis. And that's a feedback that there's high citrate and high ATP, either one
of those directly bind to phosphofructokinase, shut off its activity, and the remaining glucose
that comes in, it gets phosphorylated, either goes to the pentose phosphate shunt, or it goes to
glycogen storage, or it just goes back out of the cell again. So there's a break right there.
And so, if Racker was obsessed by how you relieve that break, because how do you get a 10 to 50
fold increase in glycolysis, if you're making so much ATP, it should shut it off again. So the
idea that was defective mitochondria was a simple explanation. There's no other way to make ATP. So
you have to make it through glycolysis. But the idea that there was something more complicated
than that was really what we were discussing in that review, that there was a way to regulate
steps in glycolysis that would divert intermediates in glycolysis from making ATP
to the carbon atoms of glycolysis and go into lipid synthesis, serine synthesis, glycine synthesis.
So it was sort of like a mass balance argument. It was an energetics for construction argument.
It was basically saying, look, the way to really think about this is, cancer is growing like crazy.
It's easy to talk about the energy requirement, but just think about the carbon requirement of growth.
Right. So one analogy I like to make is, imagine you have a river flowing through a valley,
and you want to flood some fields in order to get enough water to grow plants. So if you put a dam
here, then those other little canals that you've generated, the water level will go up to flood
into those other canals and allow you to grow plants. That's sort of what happens if you turn
off pyruvate kinase, then you slow down ATP production. That means there's less ATP made.
That means glycolysis, upper part of glycolysis continue. But instead of going to make more ATP,
it goes off to make serine and glycine and ribose and lipids. And that gives you all the molecules
you need to grow without shutting the system off because you don't let it go all the way to ATP.
Right. And that allows the mitochondria to make whatever ATP you need. And glycolysis is now used
to do anabolic processes instead of make ATP. That still makes some ATP, but you can now rebalance
that whole equation so that you can grow better rather than just make ATP.
Now, this had a profound impact on the way you thought about your life. You're one of the,
I don't want to say the few, but there are a lot of people who, a lot of great scientists,
frankly, who their professional work and their personal, the way they go about conducting
themselves and their own choices around food or whatever, there seems to be a disconnect there.
Not the case with you. I remember the first time we had a meal in probably 2012, you were quite
particular about what you ate and what you didn't eat. And the thing that you were most careful
about was fructose. So what is it about the work that you were doing in the 2000s, the early 2000s
into this decade we're in today, the beginning of the decade we're in today, that had you start to
think about nutrition in that way? So I have to say that I made my decision about what to eat and
not to eat before I knew anything about metabolism. And it came from a simple empirical observation.
So I grew up, I mentioned earlier, I grew up West Virginia, Blackwoods, West Virginia. In retrospect,
I realized that as I was growing up in the 50s, we were eating incredibly healthy meals.
In those days, the most expensive thing to buy at the grocery store was sugar.
And my grandparents, who I spent a lot of time with working on their farm,
raised everything they ate. They were sustenance farmers. They had essentially no income. They
sold some strawberries in the spring. My grandfather would plow fields for people to make additional
money, but they had very minor income. But they lived off of everything they grew. The one thing
they couldn't grow, for a while they grew some sugar beets, but it was hard to get enough sugar.
And so when my grandmother went shopping, essentially the only thing she would buy
was flour and sugar. And one five pound bag of sugar had to last several years. And so when she
would make what she called a cake, we would call it a biscuit today. It had essentially no sugar in
it because it had to be sprinkled in very small amounts. And so that, as a consequence, we were
all very healthy, nobody in my family. In fact, I didn't know anyone who was overweight in my
spring because most people lived like my grandparents. And that was in the fifties.
What happened in the sixties was really what was tragic. It was all triggered by Castro,
as you know the story. And Castro's taking over Cuba and us boycotting sugar from Cuba
and the anticipation the cost of sugar would go up even higher. A German scientist had worked out
a way to convert cornstarch into high fructose corn syrup, which could be made much, much more
cheaply than raising cane. It's funny. I always thought it was a Japanese scientist. I didn't
realize it was a German scientist. I could be wrong on that. I would take your word over mine.
Well, blame somebody from World War II. The irony of it is it's always someone that got
hurt in World War II. And the joke is this was their payback. Exactly. And then Castro's payback.
So Castro did this to us. We did it to ourselves is the truth. And we saw doing it. And as long as
I was where the primaries are held, first primaries, and where nobody's going to cut off
taxpayer support for cornstarch and growing corn. But you had this profound belief. I mean,
I guess you got to experience something very few people do, which is a natural experiment.
Yeah. So I watched West Virginia go from what I would argue in this fifties was the
skinniest state in America. I never saw anyone overweight. None of the kids in my school,
none of my relatives, none of them were overweight in the fifties. Most of them were very thin. And
then along came high fructose corn syrup. And suddenly the cheapest thing you could buy were
sodas that normally at a six ounce Coke would be my total allowance for a week to buy one six ounce
Coke. And now suddenly you've got 10 times as much for that cost. And so people advent of very
sugary drinks. People would start consuming 10, 20, 50 times as much sugar as they were consuming
before. And over from the mid sixties to mid seventies, I watched when I went back, I was at
that time at Cornell getting my graduate degree. And then didn't go back to Western into that
often. But when I did go back, I every time noticed a dramatic change in that all my friends
and relatives were suddenly becoming obese. And I just watched what they ate. And I realized they
were consuming massive amounts of sugar. Many of them were consuming diet drinks. But then at the
end of the day, because of their addiction, the sweets would eat like a gallon of ice cream per
person. When I asked them, how can you eat a gallon of ice cream? And they would tell me if I don't
eat a gallon of ice cream, I'll wake up two hours later and go to the refrigerator. So I can't sleep
through the night without eating a massive amount of sweets. So at that point, I realized this is a
real addiction. And I cut out drinking anything that was sweet. And I cut out eating dessert. So
that was 1975. Didn't know anything about the metabolism of fructose or glucose. Just empirically,
I saw the change in diet and the consequent massive change in obesity. So you basically
have these two sort of separate stories, which is this is this observational journey of your life.
And then you have the work of your career that is bringing you closer and closer to cancer
metabolism. When did you finally realize in the laboratory that this observation of yours had
mechanisms to it that could go far beyond obesity, but also play a role in metabolic diseases
inclusive of cancer? What really brought it all together, and this is why I keep emphasizing
insulin as a postdoc and ultimately starting my own lab, I kept coming back to how does insulin
work. And whenever we managed to see this PI kinase activity coprecipitating with SARC and insulin
receptor, I realized that the same enzyme was mediating the effects of the oncogenes and also
effective normal insulin signaling. And so that by 1990, it was very clear in my mind that insulin
was triggering cell growth in exactly the same way that oncogenes were. They were both activating PI3
kinase. And that suggested then a correlation between the two. And particularly as we began to
notice that the mutations, so many years later mutations in PI3 kinase were identified, it was
more than 15 years after we discovered the enzyme, the mutations were picked up from Burt Vogelstein's
laboratory. And as we began to explore what those mutations did, we realized they increased the
ability of insulin to activate the enzyme. So this whole connection between everything that
insulin does goes through PI3 kinase and most oncogenes managed to activate PI3 kinase by either
directly binding or indirectly activating it. Not necessarily through insulin, but they were
bypassing the need for insulin. We're going to come back to that very important observation in a
moment, right? Yes. You know exactly where I'm going with the next line like questioning. Okay.
But it also raised the possibility that being insulin resistant, which results in elevated
serum insulin because the pancreas has to generate more insulin. If your liver and muscle and fat
cells are failing to respond to insulin, then more insulin has to be made in order to bring glucose
back down. So insulin resistance is pretty much a silent disease because you don't really know it
if you go for an overnight fasting glucose measurement in the urine, your glucose is okay.
But if you do a glucose tolerance test, which very few people do, you realize that the glucose has
goes up much higher, takes longer to come back down. And the insulin level is much, much higher
than normal during that process of adapting. So that's how insulin resistance is defined.
But I realized that high level of insulin, if we add it to our cells and culture, cancer cells
and culture, it makes them grow better. And we've known that since the 1960s and 70s. We use fetal
calf serum to make our cancer cells grow in culture. And if fetal calf serum doesn't work,
we either order another batch, you know, another lot from the company, or we just add insulin.
And adding insulin always makes it work again. And so we've known for a long time that if you
have high levels of insulin, you can make almost any cancer cell grow better than just pure fetal
calf serum, which already has some insulin and it's variable from batch to batch. So in a way,
it's been staring us in the face for years, that insulin will drive the growth of cancer cells.
And cancer cells tend to have more insulin receptor than the tissue from which they emerged.
So in the process of tumors growing out evolving, they turn up the expression of the insulin
receptor, and that allows them to respond insulin better. So as I kept seeing more and more data on
this, over the last 15 years or so, I became convinced that the active being insulin resistant
or the state of being insulin resistant in humans sets them up to accelerate tumor growth.
When I interviewed Sid, I don't know how long it's been, probably six, eight, nine months ago,
he shared something with the listeners that I think for many people is still hard to believe,
which is smoking is the leading environmental cause of cancer, obesity is second. In fact,
I think he even mentioned that in the documentary that was made after his book, you were in that
documentary as well, great documentary. It was not named after the book, was it? Was the documentary
also called the Emperor of All Maladies? Yes, it was. Okay, okay. Phenomenal, we'll link to it in
the show notes because it's a real gem. I mean, it's worth every penny you got to pay to download
on Apple and watch that PBS special. Ken Burns, of course, is a master, but Sid made the point
there as well. And hearing you say what you're saying makes you think it's really less the obesity
and more the hyperinsulinemia that accompanies obesity in 80% of cases, which is high enough that
you could easily, just from an epidemiologic standpoint, identify obesity per se as the
trigger, meaning excess adiposity. But my belief, and I think yours, is that no, it's probably the
hyperinsulinemia, which means if you're lean and hyperinsulinemic, you're worse off. And I think
those data are becoming abundantly clear. There was a paper published a few years ago out of
Montessori Albert Einstein showing that in fact, if you take breast cancer patients and separate
them into overweight slash obese insulin sensitive, because a lot of people can, if you put on
peripheral fat, but don't have don't have visceral fat, you don't necessarily become insulin resistant
with overweight. So body mass index is not, yeah, it's not enough. It's a first order term,
that subset of overweight women who were insulin sensitive did not have an increased risk of breast
cancer, but the ones that were insulin resistant did. So that says a lot. And that paper also had
data on lean women who got breast cancer. And that correlated with insulin resistant lean women.
And in many nationalities, particularly Asians, they may look very lean, but still have a lot of
visceral fat. And so that I think we, our current mechanism of using body mass index is our
correlation is not a good one. Yeah, it's just not good enough. And Mitch Lazar in 2013, I believe,
published a paper showing basically the two by two of lean and not lean, metabolically healthy and not
as a proxy for hyperinsulinemic. And it turned out that it wasn't the body mass that was the thing
that tracked with health. Now, a moment ago, you gave this very eloquent explanation of the role
of insulin in cancer. Now, four months ago in science, you published a really interesting paper.
What did that paper show? So this is a paper in which was inspired by Mayor Bloomberg's attempt
to ban the 40 ounce Coke. So GA Young, a postdoc in my laboratory who migrated with me from Harvard
to Wal Cornell 2012-13, decided that she was inspired by Mayor Bloomberg and she would try
to test the possibility that high sugar consumption would increase colorectal cancer. She had worked
with Bert Fogelstein as a graduate student. So she knew a lot about colorectal cancer and
was working on mouse models of colorectal cancer as she migrated into my lab. And so we decided
we would design an experiment to test whether there was higher risk for colorectal cancer
with high sugar consumption. And so it was really two questions there. And my hypothesis going into
this was the insulin level, that if you go on a high sugar diet, that you'll eventually become
insulin resistant and that will drive high levels of insulin, which may accelerate the growth of
colorectal cancer. And in fact, we had data that said that what I just said was true, that in fact,
yes, if we allowed the mice to have sugar in their drinking water so they could ad lib feed as much
sugar as they wanted on top of their normal chow diet. How much sugar was in the chow?
So the normal chow diet, I don't remember exactly. Normal chow might be 10%, but you can buy these
really high sugar standard American chows that are. Yeah. So we just gave them the normal. Okay.
Child diet. And so because they were consuming massive amounts, they could drink as much of
the sugary water as they want. They drank five, three to four times as much water, sugary water,
as if they just had the controls without the sugar. And a consequence, they became massively
obese and they had accelerated polyp formation in the context of having knockout of the APC gene.
So APC is the first gene in human cancer that gets lost to initiate the process of
colorectal cancer development as birth focal steam. So the controls drinking normal water
versus the sugar drinking water is both had the APC knockout. They both had the APC knockout.
And what was the difference in polyp formation? So in that three or more fold size of polyps,
they were much more aggressive. And what about the cancerous transformation? Well, these mice,
the polyps became so big that we had to sacrifice the mice because they literally could not digest
food anymore. They didn't go into metastatic disease. So we couldn't call it a progressive
other than the fact that they were massive and it was beginning to include polyps. Now in this
experiment, you also tried to figure out what was playing the role in this and you looked at
glucose. So you could do this experiment with glucose water and fructose water, correct?
That's right. But let me get to the next step first. So that was nice and fine. It was consistent
with my idea, but GA wanted to challenge me on the idea that maybe the sugar was directly feeding the
growth rather than just making the mouse insulin resistant obese. Oh, I'm sorry, because at this
point your hypothesis was all still through the insulin. This was all being mediated through
insulin. Yeah, that was my hypothesis. So in order to try to always challenge people in my lab to
prove me wrong rather than prove me right. And because it's always learned more if my
simplest idea is wrong. Another great tenant of science. So she challenged me on this and Marcus
Goncalves is the other postdoc in my lab that worked with her and the two of them worked together.
And they designed a diet that would not allow the mice to become obese. In other words, they were
taking the total amount of sugar they ever consumed. It was the equivalent of a 12 ounce
cola sugary drink. And so on that diet, at least over the six months or so that they were on the
diet, they really didn't gain weight, maybe 5% increase in total calories consumed. So they did
not gain weight. They did not become insulin resistant. We didn't see elevation and C peptide,
clicosylate hemoglobin. So by all characteristics, those mice were normal, they were not insulin
resistant. And yet they still had increased polyps by two to three fold size. So at that point,
that raised the possibility that the sugar might be directly feeding the growth of the polyp. And
so we characterize that by using either radioactive glucose or radioactive fructose, or carbon 13
labeled and non radioactive, but traceable form of carbon atoms in fructose or in glucose. And we
also tried feeding them only glucose, the same number of calories of glucose, or the same number
of calories of fructose versus the mixture of glucose plus fructose. And they had to have both
sugars, fructose and glucose before the polyps would grow faster. So that was really surprising.
And do you think that that could be because the glucose provides the insulin and the fructose is
what do you think the fructose is doing in there? Because based on everything you said earlier,
a glucose water alone, just a pure dextrose solution should have been sufficient, right?
That's right. So that turned out not to be the case. And the way to figure it out is again using
carbon Tracy, either by radioactivity or heavy atom. So we did both. And first of all, does the
fructose or glucose get all the way to the colon? Question number one, it would seem highly
improbable. But it turns out if you add, if you have glucose plus fructose, the glucose competes
for the fructose for entry into the small intestine. And as a consequence of glucose is not as
efficiently taken up. And it makes its way all the way to the colon if you give it in a sugary drink.
I was just about to say, Lou, does this have something to do with it being in a liquid so
the transit speed is quicker? That's right. So if you gave the same amount in a solid food,
it would never make it to the colon. But because it was in a watery mixture, it would transit the
intestines fast enough that there was still fructose left. Your experiment was elegant
because you didn't have to do what my next experiment would have been, which is why I'm
not a postdoc in your lab is I would have done colonic lavage. I would have gone retrograde
and seen if I could bathe the polyps and not even deal with the absorption. But I would have
missed this detail. We wanted to replicate what you what's physiologic, of course, yeah, the condition
which humans do it. And other labs had already shown that again, give me a fructose glucose
mixture as a liquid at a certain volume, the fructose would make it all the way to the colon.
So what we found if the fructose made a colon, the glucose got absorbed in the small intestine,
but there was some local increase in glucose level in the bloodstream that's that is this is
the first time I've ever seen this elegant a demonstration of how you could miss in blood
sugar a problem, because by definition, the faster it's going through you, the faster the glucose and
fructose are getting through and bypassing the small intestine, the more likely you'll get actual
colonic content of them. And the less likely you'll see glucose in the blood sugar, which is why the
group that in the second experiment who were not being given ad libitum access to it didn't get
obese and didn't develop hyperinsulinemia, but still developed the polyp phenotype. Yeah, as a
side issue along the lines you're saying, we actually found in the case where we had the water
fed rather than a fixed amount to 12 ounce soda equivalent that the subset of mice that had the
APC mutation actually had more protected from insulin resistance. There was the polyps reading
so much of the sugar that it was protecting the mouse. That is unbelievable. And at some point,
you'll blow through that and they'll become quite insulin resistant and get hypertrophic polyps.
Yeah, yeah. But in this case, we weren't allowing that to happen. It was a very small amount of sugar
equivalent of a single drink a day, 12 ounce sweetened drink. The real surprise was when we
got to the molecular mechanism. And that was that you had to have fructose and glucose because the
actual carbon atoms that were being used to grow the tumor were coming from the glucose and not from
the fructose. And what the fructose was doing is when it went into the polyp, it was converted to
fructose one phosphate by an enzyme called ketohexokinase, also called fructokinase. That
enzyme is only found in three tissues in any significant concentration, the liver, the kidney,
and the gut. And so these polyps like the normal gut cells have that enzyme. That has been something
of a mystery of why that enzyme exists in it at that location. But in any event, it does.
What happens is the fructose goes in and it gets phosphorylated by that enzyme. And it happens very
rapidly. It's a very active enzyme. And that drops the ATP level in the cell because you're
consuming ATP to phosphorylate that fructose is coming in. Now, I mentioned earlier that the thing
with the Warburg hypothesis is that in order to get glucose to flux at a high rate into a cell,
you have to drop the ATP level. Well, this is a way to drop the ATP level. Instead of consuming
it in some other way, you're consuming it by phosphorylating the fructose. There's an additional
complication or not complication, but intervention that is also important, which is once you start
doing glycolysis at a higher rate, process of doing glycolysis incorporates an inorganic phosphate
to make the doubly phosphorylated glycerol and 1,6-bisphosphate. And so that additional
consumption of inorganic phosphate drops a negative regulator of inosine deaminase.
And that drops the ability to keep ATP synthesis going on in the cell. So the combination too
drops the ATP level dramatically. And now the glucose that's coming in is flooding through
glycolysis, but it's going into all these anabolic processes. It's being used to make lipids. We see
all the label from glucose going into fatty acid synthesis and serine synthesis and
nucleotide synthesis going up five or 10-volt. It's really quite dramatic what happens. But if you
leave the fructose out, even though the glucose gets in the cell, it can't go through glycolysis
at a high rate. And so you don't get growth. You have to have both molecules. The carbon
atoms are coming from the glucose. The fructose is basically driving the kinetics. Exactly.
When you describe it this way, you sound crazy. I mean, you're the guy that nobody wants to talk
to at the party. Your wife must be annoyed senseless by her crazy husband who's got this
hypothesis that now has so much emerging data behind it that says if you wanted to create a
molecule to kill people, it's not just glucose. It's not even just fructose. It's put the two
together. And guess what? Nature did that. Nature came up with a 50-50 mixture of this thing.
And if that weren't enough, she made it taste so good. Right. How do we reconcile this? Yeah,
so that's the part I like best. Because I think about everything in regard to evolution.
Why did things evolve? Why do we evolve to be addicted? Because you're ruining the party right
now. Exactly. So I think this allows if you think about humans 100,000 years ago, our metabolism
hasn't changed in the last 100,000 years. So 100,000 years ago, how often during a typical year in a
temperate climate would you have available high amounts of fructose and glucose? I mean, maybe in
the fall. A month, a month or so. So you would get berries ripe and apples ripe. And keep in mind,
these are very small berries, very small apples for domestication of plants. And so as a consequence,
what that means is at the end of the growing season is when most of the sugary producing
fruits are being produced. If you could eat enough of those, and you could keep your appetite up
enough to just keep consuming anything in place, anything available, you could put on weight. As
you go into the cold season. As you go into the cold season. And if you put on enough weight,
then you might actually survive to the next spring period when there's actually some roots
to dig up to eat and keep going. And anyone who probably almost anyone 50,000 years ago,
who didn't put on 50 pounds or so in the fall would not be alive for the next spring. So very
strong requirement to gain weight in order to survive a period of time when no food is available.
Yeah, Rick Johnson has written so eloquently about this. And I'm blanking on the name of his
collaborator, who's an anthropologist. And they even trace it back to which primates probably
developed this first. And they were primates that had left Africa, gone to Northern Europe.
And most of them die off. It was only the primates that could develop this mutation. And I believe
it was a mutation in both uricase and frictekinase. I could be wrong on that. And I've interviewed
Rick. And so we can go back and listen to that. But you had to develop this mutation or else you
wouldn't survive the winter. And then what happened was tens of thousands, if not longer of years,
of strengthening that is what allowed those primates to then come back to Africa to basically
become our descendants. So we as humans, as a species, have these mutations that would have
served as well when glucose and fricteaus combined were provided just at the right level.
Yeah. So if you didn't anticipate that you needed to gain weight, your body would tell you to do it,
basically how it came about. And so makes perfect sense. The extreme example is the hibernating bear.
We call it the honey bear often, right? Because in the fall, not only do they eat every berry they
can find in the woods, but they also climb up the trees and get to the honey bees. And they put on
150, maybe even 200 pounds within a period of two or three months. And then they go into extreme
insulin resistance and they hibernate, they fall asleep. But because of being insulin resistant,
having metabolic syndrome, their ability to break down fats is impaired. And that keeps them from
quickly burning up. The metabolism slows greatly. They preserved a little bit of glucose they have
for their brain and they feed their body off ketones and fats, I assume. Very long period of
time and then they survive. So we don't hibernate, but we probably became insulin resistant every
fall, a hundred thousand years ago in order to survive these periods of starvation. I mean,
you've touched on this briefly from a public health perspective. I know you're not a
policymaker, you're a scientist. Many would say it's impossible. Like we're just never going to
see the day when sugary beverages go away, but the data are becoming harder and harder to ignore
that there is something uniquely toxic, chronically toxic. People don't like the word toxic because
they think it only has an acute implication. Like ethanol can be acutely toxic, but I'm talking about
the chronic toxicity, but the chronic toxicity associated with sugar sweetened beverages,
inclusive of juices and things like that, right? It's not just a Coke. These data are becoming almost
impossible to ignore, yet they still proliferate. I believe their consumption is down. I don't believe
people consume nearly the amount of sugar sweetened beverages that they consumed 20 years ago. I believe
we peaked at around the turn of the century, but we're nowhere near what you consumed growing up
in West Virginia. Is it possible to get back to that? Is there a solution or is it simply something
that each person must be accountable for? Do you have a view on that even? How you reverse the
policy? I think changing cigarette smoking, there's a lesson to be learned there. What was the
incentive? How did the government make this happen? Reducing advertisement is one way to do it. I mean,
if you look at TV commercials, almost every commercial about food is about sugary food,
and there are many of them tailored to young children to get them to buy the sugary cereals,
to get them addicted to young children. You've got them for life. Just like cigarette smokers,
you get them addicted at 15, 14. They're addicted for life and there's a market for you. So I think
that's the appeal we have to make. And the question is, how do you do this? One way
taxing also helps. If sugar suddenly becomes like it was in the 50s, the most expensive thing that
you bought at the grocery store, then maybe you would quit buying it. But of course,
most people don't buy sugar anymore. They buy processed foods that have sugar already added
to them. By the way, looking at your experiments, was there any distinction between if you used
sugar as the substrate versus high fructose corn syrup? No. Succrose by sugar, we typically mean
sucrose from cane sugar, which can be crystallized because it's a pure molecule.
While high fructose corn syrup is a mixture of fructose and glucose, that's 60, 40 rather than
50, 50. But in our experiments, the difference between those two doesn't make a whole lot.
The fact that you need to, if it's sucrose, you have to hydrolyze the bond is irrelevant to the
kinetics you should describe. Yeah, that happens very quickly. So you don't buy the argument that
some, I don't buy it either by the way, but that you should eat your sugar in natural form, which
is it should say cane sugar or beet sugar or something on the ingredient. And there's this
whole group of folks who believe that high fructose corn syrup is horrible, but quote unquote,
naturally occurring sugar is not. There's so much confusion around this, but I just want to know if
experimentally you see any difference. No, I think whether sucrose, what shows the difference is
whether the sugar is embedded in a fibrous fruit as opposed to being pure in a water. There's
something about that liquid that is devastating. There are two things. One for colorectal cancer,
it is, as I said before, the fact that having it in a sugary water drink gets it all the way to the
colon. If you had the exact same amount of sugar, but it was embedded in a fibrous fruit, like an
apple, then none of that fructose would make it to the colon. The transits to the intestine would be
so slow that the sugar would have get absorbed. But does that increase the risk of cancer
in other organs? No, I think this is absolutely unique to colorectal cancer. But I would argue
on the other hand, the difference between eating an apple and eating apple juice, not only is
whether the fructose makes it all the way to the colon, but whether or not your glucose levels
spike after consuming an apple, a whole apple eating it as opposed to apple juice. And the
answer is with apple juice, you're going to get a glucose spike for sure. Eating an apple, you may
get hardly any change in your glucose because it takes so long to break it down that the absorbance
is slow. And you might, you know, what I've observed, I don't drink apple juice. I don't drink
beverages that have sugar in them. But what I notice is nothing has ever spiked my blood sugar
more than a raisin on a per mass basis. You took a fixed mass of raisins and you contrast it with
a fixed mass of anything else. It's pretty stark because it doesn't have the water, doesn't have the
fiber, doesn't have anything else. And even if you ate, say call it, compare apple to apple juice,
if you did equal grams of glucose, you might even get a similar area under the curve. But where
it's going to look different is the apple juice, which will have, you'll get a big spike and the
apple, you'll get a gradual, you're going to have different insulins in response to this. So the
glucose AUC could be the same, but the insulin response could be quite different. That's the
point. And it's, in my opinion, it's all about insulin. Most endocrinologists worry about the
glucose. I worry about the insulin. So really there's three things you're worried about. You're
worried about glucose, fructose, and insulin, but in how they coexist. Right. So colorectal cancer
is unique and you can feed directly off the fructose if you get it all the way to the colon
through a liquid form. But it has to be in liquid form. But the difference between liquid form
and apple juice is, as you say, the area in the curve is the same, but the fact that the glucose
isn't going up as high means you don't get as much insulin release. And of course, if digested very
slowly, the rate at which you're ambitly burning glucose in your brain and muscle may be almost
equal to the rate at which it gets absorbed in the bloodstream, in which case you hardly see any
increase at all. And that means no spike in insulin whatsoever. So that's the ideal situation,
is to never allow that insulin to get high. Now, before we go into the why, I want to go back to
some experiments, some drugs, and something you said earlier. Let's go back to PI3 kinase.
Everything you said about PI3 kinase would make someone listening to this think,
if you could block it with a drug, could you block cancer? Well, obviously you thought of that.
So tell us about drugs that block PI3K inhibitors when given to cancer patients.
Okay, so by 1990, I was quite sure that everything insulin did went through PI3 kinase. And it was
also quite clear to me that many cancers have emerged because of activation of PI3 kinase.
Some pharmaceutical companies came to me and said, should we develop the PI3 kinase inhibitor?
And I said, well, I can't imagine how you would be able to thread that needle of being able to
inhibit PI3 kinase without causing diabetes, without causing severe diabetes. And unless
insulin went up high enough to offset the inhibition of PI3 kinase, you would have to go
off the drug because of the hyperglycemia. If you raise the insulin level, it could override the
PI3 kinase, it's also going to activate the tumor to grow more. So it could be worse.
Yeah, so I was skeptical and never, in spite of all of our data saying that PI3 kinase
was driving a lot of cancers, I never pulled the trigger in starting a company or even encouraging
anyone else to start a company to make inhibitors of PI3 kinase. The fact that mutations in PI3
kinase were picked up in Bert Vogelstein's laboratory in colorectal cancer and ultimately
shown to be in many types of cancers led the charge to actually develop an inhibitor because
by then it was clear that other mutant-hirusin kinases, when they were hypermutated or
hyperproduced in cells, could be drugged and those would be effective ways to block cancer growth.
So with those observations, numerous companies, probably 15 companies, went after projects
developing PI3 kinase inhibitors. I was still skeptical that you would be able to manage the
insulin problem, but agreed, in fact, applied for and got funding from Stand Up to Cancer,
American Association of Cancer Research, to put a team together to try to figure out how to most
effectively use those inhibitors as they went into the clinic. And I remember after we received that
money, several pharmaceutical companies contacted me and said, will you work with us? We have a PI3
kinase inhibitor in human phase one trials. And they said, what's more, it doesn't cause
hyperglycemia, so it's going to be a safe drug. And I said, well, if it doesn't work,
if it doesn't cause hyperglycemia, it's not hitting PI3 kinase. So no, I'm not interested
working with a drug that doesn't cause hyperglycemia. Ultimately, we decided to work
primarily with Novartis that had a drug that we, several drugs actually, that clearly called
hyperglycemia. So I was convinced that they were hitting PI3 kinase and that that was in one target
effect. And the question then is, can you thread that needle? Can you manage the glucose level
without getting insulin levels so high that they would reactivate PI3 kinase in the tumor?
And that had been the challenge. So we suspected, I should say that in working with Novartis,
we got them to agree that if when the patients got hyperglycemia, that the endocrinologist would
judge was not tolerable, that they would ensure that if the patient could not be managed on
metformin, that they would have to go off the trial. In other words, I didn't want them to be
given insulin. I didn't want them to be given insulin or an insulin secretagogue, which also
raises serum insulin. And I should say that the endocrinologists who were called in and consulted
for these patients who were hyperglycemic on the trial disagreed with me. They said insulin is
totally safe. They should be able to get insulin. And we should do it that way. But I was quite
adamant. I said, well, I won't work with you on these trials unless you exclude patients who have
to be managed on insulin or insulin secretagogues. So Novartis kind of reluctantly agreed to do that
and went all the way through their approval trial with that as their requirement. Anyone who couldn't
be managed who would need an insulin or insulin secretagogue would be off the trial. And their
drug got approved just in May this year. It took a long time because roughly half the patients who
tried to enroll could not be managed on metformin. Could you also use SGLT2 inhibitors? So at that
time, the SGL2 inhibitors had not yet been approved. So we're talking about 10 years ago,
when the phase 1B trials that were the lead into the approval trial were being where we worked with
Novartis on that. But Novartis stuck with the initial requirement through their approval trial
that everything had to be managed on metformin. Otherwise, they had to go off the trial. And
that's why it took them a long time to enroll enough patients to complete the trial.
Now the SGL2 inhibitors are approved sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitors that reabsorb
glucose from the ultrafiltrate in the kidney. If you block that, then the glucose ends up in the
urine. And so that's a good way to lower glucose and thereby lower insulin. So that tool wasn't
available at that time. It's now available today. So we did a study over the last four years. It took
a long time to do this. Lots and lots of mice and lots of experiments to test whether in a mouse
model for cancers, a variety of cancers, 12 different types of cancers, if you give a PI3
kinase inhibitor and use either a sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor or put the patients on
a ketogenic diet, which means that they only have about 8% of their total diet as carbohydrate. And
even that is slow release carbohydrate. The rest, 80% is fat and 12% is protein. And we ask now
comparing metformin versus insulin versus sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor versus a
ketogenic diet, what works best in getting the PI3 kinase inhibitors to shrink the tumor.
And I want to just pause for a moment. This is something you alluded to in passing 30 minutes
ago, which is very important, which was insulin can go around the PI3K inhibitor when you block it.
And that's why just blocking PI3K alone wasn't going to be enough. Is that correct?
More accurately, we know that if you take a tumor that has PI3 kinase mutations, for example,
ex vivo. So we did a lot of this work in organoids from our human patients at Weill Cornell,
and we would take an organoid in a mutual tumor, for example, and give it a PI3 kinase
inhibitor at the therapeutic dose, and we could kill every cell in that organoid. But if we now
added back the level of insulin that would be in the bloodstream, at the level of glucose that they
would have experienced, and the level of insulin that we actually measure in the blood of the
patient 30 minutes after giving them the inhibitor, how high is an insulin level typically in that
patient? So 10 nanograms per mil is roughly what we see within 15 to 30 minutes. And by 90 minutes,
it's up to twice that 10 to 20 to 30 nanograms per mil of insulin. And by two hours, the insulin
level was high enough that the glucose now in the bloodstream starts to drop. So that tells us
that that massive amount of insulin is enough to reactivate PI3 kinase in the liver and muscle.
And so it's not going around PI3 kinase, it's just reactivating in spite of the presence of the drug.
Because you can't develop a complete inhibitor for physiologic reasons.
That's right. At the dose that you can tolerate. Fighting this battle.
I see. I see.
If you completely turn off PI3 kinase.
So insulin still has to go through PI3K no matter what. You're putting up a porous dam
because a complete dam would kill the patient. Exactly.
And insulin is tougher, and in the end, it's going to win.
So let's suppose you're giving an estrogen receptor antagonist,
and you start getting toxic effects of losing estrogen. Would you decide that you would now
get estrogen? Yeah.
To correct that problem. And so that's what the endocrinologists are saying. We want to
give them insulin to bring their glucose down. You're like, that's the whole thing we're trying
to stop here. That's what we're trying to stop is insulin because insulin is what's driving
the activation. Those mutations in PI3 kinase will not activate PI3 kinase unless insulin is
added to the tumor. And I recall, I think I even told this story. I may have told this story when
I was talking with Sid on the podcast, but we were having dinner one night and I talked about
a friend of mine with breast cancer who was in a trial and she was in an arm in one of the Boston
hospitals and she was on a PI3K inhibitor. And I think it was a phase two. She was the only woman
who survived. She's still alive today. The only woman with metastatic breast cancer that survived
who on her own went on a ketogenic diet. And I remember telling you this out of curiosity,
like, Lou, what do you think of this? Do you think this is just an odd coincidence?
And that was the time that you and Sid were starting these experiments. As Sid described it,
that was sort of maybe the final clinical, the little pearl that sort of made you guys go off
and do this. And that paper was published a year ago, right? That was published last summer,
last July. So what was the efficacy of a ketogenic diet versus an SGLT2 inhibitor in
Metformin? Were they equal? So if you did a run-in to the ketogenic diet, so they have an entire week
on the diet, and then they're given the inhibitor, it's incredibly effective because by then you've
depleted all the glycogen, all the relevant tissues. If you just start on the ketogenic diet
a day before you give the first PI3-kinase inhibitor, it's still pretty effective,
but not as effective as the whole week run-in to deplete glycogen. Is there any reason not to
combine these? Ketogenic diet, Metformin, SGLT2 inhibitor, PI3K inhibitor as a
FU to cancer? Four cancers dependent on this pathway of course. Yes. Well, let me address
the sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor first, because that is almost as effective as
a ketogenic diet in our mouse models. It keeps the glucose level not quite as low as a ketogenic
diet, but pretty damn low. And the importance of course is in both cases, it brings the insulin,
imid insulin in the serum drops dramatically. But the important thing is that every single 12
different types of cancers, some of them had PI3-kinase mutations, others didn't, some were rasp
mutant tumors, didn't matter, some were, one was AML and SIDS study. That's right, we're talking
about that then. And I was skeptical that AML would have, because you never see a PI3-kinase mutation
at AML. But the bottom line was, there was a benefit in every single cancer we looked at.
The reason we did 12 different types, we were trying to find one example of a cancer. That
would violate this principle. That would violate the principle. The bottom line is, I think all
cancers require some amount of PI3-kinase to survive. And so if we can keep the insulin level
low, and insulin of course is the best way to activate PI3-kinase, if you can keep the insulin
level low, and now turn off PI3-kinase, you don't get that rebound of insulin, and the tumors just
go away. So ketogenic diet, if you can stay on it, would be my recommendation if you have cancer
and you're going on a PI3-K inhibitor. Sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor, however, is
easier for most people to take. It's a pill. And that's, I would say, the second best.
And of course, again, it's hard because we're sitting here, we can't give medical advice to
people. I get asked this question all the time. It's a very difficult question to answer because
I'm not managing the given patient. But cancer patients are among the most motivated patients
you'll ever meet. I mean, you know this, you've been involved in these trials. They will do
anything they believe has some modicum of science behind it that can increase their odds of survival.
Tragically, we're still kind of living in a world where the mainstream approach to this is a little
bit convoluted. Obviously, one of the most significant concerns that many oncologists have,
well-meaning, is that patients are going to lose weight. I don't know how bad it is today, but
certainly back when I was on the wards, we would force feed cancer patients with Insure.
I don't know if you've ever had Insure, Lou, but let me ensure you, it is full of sugar.
So now we're back to force feeding patients liquid sugar when they have cancer because we're
afraid of them losing weight. Exactly. So one caveat or one concern which came out of the SIDS
part of our trial is that, at least in the mouse models of AML, ketogenic diet alone...
It was actually negative, wasn't it? Ketergenic diet alone in most of the tumors doesn't have
too much. So just switching to a ketogenic diet, I think it's rare that that alone is going to work.
Maybe in some cases, but in the case of the AML, there was some evidence of some toxicity that came
in the context, not normal-miced ketogenic diet, they're perfectly healthy. They live a normal
lifespan. In fact, probably live a little longer, but in the context of this AML model that SIDS lab
was using, there could be some adverse effects. So we're cautioning people don't automatically go on
a ketogenic diet if you have cancer, unless you can have somebody paying attention to
potential side effects. Well, I had the luxury of sending... I mean, you've been so generous and
I've sent many tissue specimens to you from patients or friends, relatives of patients,
and you've got your own CLIA developed assay to look for insulin receptors. And we've even made
clinical decisions based on that, which is this is a patient who has lots of insulin receptor on
their tumor. This is a favorable approach to cancer. This is a patient who doesn't,
might not make that sense. How far is that type of an assay away from being a mainstream
assay that any physician can use as part of their toolkit to start to customize cancer therapy?
To reveal my conflicts here, I do have a company I've started, Petro Pharmaceuticals, that is
beginning a PI3 kinase inhibitor trial. It will be combined with sodium glucose co-transporter
inhibitor. Oh, I didn't even realize I'm bringing up all this stuff. I'm teeing it up for you here,
right? Yeah. That trial will be starting any day now. What type of cancers,
Lou? Are you looking for enrollment? So in phase one here, it's going to be a combination
with sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor plus PI3 kinase alpha inhibitor. Initially,
we'll be looking at solid tumors, breast endometrial, where you see high rates of mutations,
but we won't... So breast endometrial in what stage of disease? Is this stage four? Yes,
in stage four disease. So have you fully enrolled or? No, no, we're just, you know,
trials just hasn't enrolled. So in other words, someone's listening to this that either has or
knows someone with breast or endometrial cancer, who is stage four, how can they best find out
information on this trial? So Petro Pharmaceuticals, so of course, this will be registered at
clinicaltrials.gov, where you can find every single trial. So if you just go to clinicaltrials.gov
and type in Petra, P-E-T-R-A, that will... We'll link to that for sure. How many patients will you
take in the phase one? I've forgotten the exact number, but there depends on how many responses
we see and so forth. But the dose escalation... The dose escalation is going to be pretty quick
because we already have, we know what the dose is without a... Each of these drugs, you sort of know
what they do. We know, we don't anticipate any... So the hope is to get to phase two quickly. Yeah,
we should get to phase two very quickly. And the person, patients on the phase one could transition
into the phase two. This is really exciting, Lou. So in that case, we will recommend that they have
for breakfast because all these drugs, most of these drugs require that you eat breakfast before
you take the pill because that limits some of the toxicity you should get from and increases
the absorbance. But I think it makes a hell of a lot of difference what you have for breakfast.
So you'll recommend scrambled eggs and avocado and... Whole milk yogurt and not yogurt with sugar.
Yeah, yeah. Or high fat yogurt and... High fat yogurt.
With some crunched almonds in it or something like that, yeah.
Right. Now, Lou, is there any way to pair? Absolutely no juice, no inshore.
Yeah. In that time in the morning now, by the evening, the drug will have already
be below effective dose. So one might have some elasticity for what you had for your evening meal.
Although I will tell you something, Lou, you probably see this thing on my arm, right?
That's a glucose meter. I know what a nighttime high glucose meal, I know what a dessert at dinner
can do to my glucose in the morning and my insulin and it's still high. So for people listening to
this who want to enroll in this trial or even for you, Lou, I would just say the more stringent
people can be based on what you're saying. If the hypothesis that's being tested is more insulin is
worse, I think you're almost better off just biting the bullet and saying we're going to do
ketogenic diets. In fact, is there any probability in this trial of actually providing the meals to
the subjects to make it easier? So I have another conflict here. I've also started a company that
says making meals for dietary intervention in cancers in general. And this company, also,
Sid Mukherjee is a co-founder of this company as well called Feas Pharmaceuticals. How do you spell
that? Feas, F-A-E-T-H, which is a Welsh name for health, F-A-E-T-H. So my co-founders are Karen
Valston and Oliver Maddox from her laboratory, Ben Hopkins and Marcus Concalves from my laboratory.
These are a lot of the folks that were on that paper last summer. Ben was the first author,
right? Right. Sid Mukherjee, also founder of this, also Scott Lowe and Greg Hannon. I think I got
every question. And the idea here is for patients who have cancers, which the KD will be potentially
a viable adjunct to what they're doing, the idea is let's pharmaceuticalize it, basically. So is
Feas already selling product? No, it's just now getting started. We've gotten it funded and we're
looking now for where we're going to be making the meals and how and whether we contract some
of the meals out or we do them internally. This isn't going to be purely ketogenic, although we
will focus on preparing the meals, make sure they have exactly the composition that we expect,
rather than just giving advice and hoping people find the right foods. But it's not purely
ketogenic. In some cases, there's evidence coming out of Karen's lab and also my lab that reducing
serine levels can make some drugs more effective. Producing methionine levels can make other drugs
more effective in different mutational backgrounds. Say more about those two. I mean, those
methionine and leucine might be two of the more potent activators of the target of rapamycin,
TOR. Tell me about serine. That one's a bit, we don't hear about that as much. So serine,
some tumors rely on synthesizing, can either use serine in the serum or they can synthesize their
own serine. So the enzyme phosphoglycerate dehydrogenase, PHGDH, is the first step in
converting intermediates of glycolysis into serine and glycine synthesis. You need serine
and glycine in order to make nucleotides as well as glutathione. So for redox potential
and for combating ross rather, and also for building nucleotides, you need serine and glycine.
So you're trying to selectively deprive a cancer cell from nucleotide precursor.
That's right. How difficult is it to restrict methionine and serine in food?
So this has been done both in humans and in mice. Diets have been tried too. And you can get the
serine level down about tenfold and still have quite viable human. What about methionine?
Similar. You can also. Without just restricting protein. Right. We've been using diets for
metabolic disease intervention for years. Children lacking enzyme in particular. Sure.
Ketogenic diets for epilepsy and things like that. But even ketoneuria. PKU. Yeah. PKU.
You need to reduce the phenylalanine in the diet. So this idea that you could get better clinical
outcomes by changing amino acids, for example, in their diet, it's been proven clinically and
in bone areas and metabolism. So the idea that the same kinds of interventions and in fact,
ketogenic diets, as you say, were developed for not for cancer, but for epileptic seizure syndromes.
Yeah. Have you seen the data that have suggested this is a little changing gears. I don't want to
let you leave without at least some discussion of this, that in certain cancers, when you restrict
glucose, which would then imply potentially a ketogenic diet, you actually make the cancers
more robust and in particular in pancreatic cancer. Have you seen some of these data?
Actually, I've seen the opposite in pancreatic cancer. If you use a ketogenic diet in combination
with the drug. So in our hands, putting the mouse that has a K-RAS, P53 mutant pancreatic cancer,
which is majority of human cancers have those mutational events. So in that context,
ketogenic diet doesn't really do anything. It doesn't accelerate. It doesn't slow it down.
But if we combine that with the PI3, and PI3-Kineson never doesn't do anything to those tumors either.
But we give the two together, the tumors completely disappear. So you have to combine
the diet with the right drug or it doesn't really work. And it's really this diet drug pairing that
is really on the cusp of innovation right now. We're scratching the surface of that, right? And
will these two companies, Feith and what was the other one? Petra. Petra. Is the goal that
these companies collaborate and start to pair diet with drug? Yes, we could certainly do that
at this point. As I say, for Petra, we focused on the sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor
because we think compliance will be easier to monitor. And at this stage, we aren't yet revved
up to produce the diets that would allow those trials to continue. But yes, we could move on to
a ketogenic diet and even possibly on top of a sodium glucose co-transporter inhibitor.
But we'd have to do a phase one study. Yeah, you still have to go back to phase one.
Phase one B. How many PI3-K inhibitors are currently approved by the FDA?
So there's the alpolisib, the varnish drug just approved in May that hits specifically only the
alpha isoform. Now that's the isoform that insulin activates and mediates everything insulin does.
And that's the one that's caused all the problems with hyperglycemia. But there is also a delta isoform
of PI3-K that's seldom mutated, but it's actually required for B cell growth. And we discovered that
back when we started knocking out PI3-K in a metapoietic lineage cells in mice back in the
late 1990s. At David Fruman, a postdoc in my laboratory, was doing those mouse knockouts.
And found that B cell lineage cells failed to thrive if you knocked out PI3-K. T cells on the
other hand were fine if you knocked out PI3-K. And ultimately it turned out to be the delta isoform
that was critical for the growth of B cells. So when delta inhibitors were developed, they went
into B cell lymphomas as the first possible place to work since that enzyme was already known to be
critical in B cells. And they turned out to be effective. Adele and Lissab was approved
about five years ago. It's a delta specific PI3-K inhibitor.
Who made that?
That was made by Gilead.
Oh, Gilead, okay, yeah.
And then more recently a drug called Capan-Lissab was approved about three years ago by Bayer.
This is a drug developed by Bayer.
And which isoform is that?
Again, it also hits delta, but it also hits alpha.
So the alpha one is the only one that causes the hyperglycemia. Yeah, that's the one that my
friend was on by the way.
Right.
But that was approved in May. And that seems to have the most ubiquitous application, doesn't it?
It's certainly where you see the most mutations. And of course,
breast cancer is far more numerous than lymphoma.
Yeah, but that's the one that's going to need the most management of the hyperglycemia and
the hyperinsulinemia. Is that message reaching the oncologists?
Slowly, I think they're beginning to understand what we're saying,
why it's important to keep the insulin down.
The problem, as you know better than I, that we are so specialized today in medicine,
that people commit to go into either oncology or endocrinology. And from there on, their studies
are completely, they're studying completely different things. And if you have an endocrine
problem as an oncologist, you don't try to solve it yourself. You call in an endocrine consult.
So your brain isn't really even focusing on how to solve a problem because you have an expert
who can do it for you. And the problem is the endocrinologists are not really that alert about
what's going on with cancer. Their job is to make sure the glucose is in line.
Yeah, sort of, I think it's time that we either, I mean, there's really two ways around this.
I see one is you sort of create a new specialty, which is metabolic oncology.
So just today, if someone wants to study oncology, they choose between surgical oncology,
medical oncology, radiation oncology. Of course, the challenge is you have to differentiate very
early. You don't do oncology first, then surgery, then medicine, then radiology. It's you do radiology
or medicine or surgery and then subspecialize. So therein lies a problem. How would you become
a metabolic oncologist? So the other option is basically oncologists learning more about the
metabolism of cancer so that when it comes to managing understood and predictable complications
of these medications, which are actually desired features, as you point out, if you're using this
drug correctly, you should see hyperinsulinemia and hyperglycemia and you should treat it
accordingly. Which reminds me, by the way, how often with the alpha isiform does that drug need
to be administered or in your trial? Decision of how frequently the dose is based on PKPD,
fast the drug level goes into the bloodstream and how long it stays high
and following how quickly it declines. And so most of these drugs that make it in the clinic
can stay at their therapeutic dose for three or four hours. So a lot of the companies want to do
buy two drugs a day, one in the morning, one in the evening. And what's the total cycle? How long
are you being given drug? How long are you given a rest from the drug? And so, for example, the
Novartis drug is daily. It's once a day daily after breakfast on a full meal. And why does it
need a full stomach? Because otherwise absorption problems, you don't get as good a PKPD if you eat
your own empty stomach and you get more side effects, diarrhea or nausea or whatever, if you
try to do it on an empty stomach. But there's no recommendation in the approval trial as to what
you're supposed to eat for breakfast before you take the drug or whether you take it with insure
or apple juice or water. Hence the importance of a company like Feith that could start to standardize
that because look, everybody wants to do the right thing here. And wouldn't it be great if as a doctor
you could write a prescription that's not just covering the drug but covering the food? Yeah.
So we have, that's what we're anticipating at Feith at some point. If you can prove in a clinical
trial setting that you need this particular food for the drug to be effective. To maximize absorption,
minimize symptom side effects, and most importantly, maximize efficacy. You should be able to get that
food paid for, the delivery of the exact food that matches what your need is. And think about
it, what a trivial cost it is compared to the drug. I mean, you could send people caviar spread
all day long at 1 1 hundredth the cost of a drug. Exactly. But you have to prove it. You've got to
prove it in a phase three clinical trial. Well, don't get me started on that. I mean, think of how
many drugs have been approved that haven't proved Jack. I mean, it's Ambien should have been
approved. Anyway, don't get me started on the drug approval process here, but I'm completely
with you on that. Lou, I want to be kind of mindful of your time. There's kind of one last theme I want
to explore. So you're going to be 70 this year, right? Which is kind of hard to believe because
I already passed. You already passed it. So you don't look a day over, I don't know, 56. You've
got this ageless phenotype to you. So I don't want to for a moment suggest your career is anything
other than continuing to go up in terms of the work you have to do. So as you think about the
next chapter of your career, what is the question that you are most obsessed with? What is the
question you want to spend as much time as you can trying to answer that currently really don't have
an answer to? That's hard for me because I'm the most unfocused. In some ways, I'm compulsive
about getting the answer of every question that I get curious about. And as you can tell from this
interview, I have an opinion on how everything works. And having never taken any biology course,
I have no prejudice about how it should work. I just so for me, everything that I run into biology
is here's a mystery. I don't bother reading the textbooks because I know they will prejudice me
to the wrong answer. And so I'd like to get to the bottom of what's really going on. But the bottom
line is that I get absolutely brilliant postdocs and graduate students come to my laboratory.
I allow them to do anything they want to do. And if it obviously gives them advice and help
interpret the experiments. But this has kept me in so many different fields for 40 some years as I've
run my own laboratory. It keeps my mind continually alert about every possible thing. So yes, epileptic
seizures. It turns out probably most of the people have epileptic seizure fits have PIC3CA mutations
as a mosaicism in neurons in the brain. Ketogenic diet was developed to minimize that. It makes
perfect sense to keep insulin down. If a PIC3CA mutant neuron was solved, you're going to get less
firing of that neuron that's going to solve the problem. But that wasn't how the ketogenic diet
was developed. So my curiosity, if just studying everything that's which PI3-kinase is involved
at some level could keep me busy for several years. But that's not the only thing I'm interested
in. I'm interested in whatever curious observation that comes up from experiments in my lab.
It can't be easily explained by current knowledge. To me, that means there's an opportunity to break
open some new explanation for some disease. So I'm willing to work in almost any disease that's not
yet solved. And there's an opportunity to figure it out. I'm a chemist. So to me, unless I understand
something at the molecular level, I don't really understand it. But I think with PI3-kinase,
I really understand it at the molecular level. I think that's an understatement.
There's still some mysteries there. I should say that we're about to publish a couple of papers,
hopefully over the next six to nine months, that are going to completely change how everybody
thinks about PI3-kinase regulation. So there's still some major things to learn about this enzyme.
Well, there's so many other things I'd love to speak with you about, Lou. But I know that some
of them are still work that you're doing. And therefore, I know you would prefer to wait until
things are a little further along to talk about them. But we'll have to come back in a year or so
and do this again, because there's so much other stuff that I know we've talked about informally
about cancer that is I want to believe it's where the field is going to start to go. I want to
believe that because I get so many emails from people who say, you know, my mother has cancer,
my husband has cancer, and they're being offered this therapy. And it's a very standard therapy.
The patient is progressing through it. What metabolic options are there? And people like
you are people like Sid, people like all your colleagues and Matt and Ben and all these guys.
I mean, you guys are the guys that are kind of driving that forward. And you've made a lot of
progress in a decade. It doesn't feel like it sometimes. Like sometimes I feel like it's not
going fast enough. But I think having a discussion like we did today makes me realize how much has
happened in a decade. And it's actually quite a bit. I have no doubt that you're going to be here
a decade from now working just as hard. Well, my real motivation, of course, is to convert
every observation we make in a laboratory to actually change in practice for whether it's
diabetes or cancer or what other disease that we begin to understand in molecular mechanism.
If we don't convert those observations into actual change in behavior or change in practice
or change in drug metabolism and diet, then in the end we failed. And so that's my goal.
And as being a cancer center director, people sometimes listen to me now when I suggest this
is the way, this is the trial we should do, and this is the way it should be designed to test the idea.
For me, it's spectacular being here in New York City at Wild Cornell, New York Presbyterian,
where we really can translate these breakthroughs into new therapies.
That's what my goal will be over the next 10 years.
I hope you enjoyed that discussion with Luke Antley, and I hope you found it half as interesting
as you can probably tell I did. As you may recall, at the outset of this podcast, I said that the
first 45 minutes, which was a much more detailed technical description of Lou's initial work in the
70s and 80s that led to the discovery of PI3 kinase, that content would be bumped as almost
an appendix to the end of the podcast. And that's what you're about to hear now. So I hope you enjoy
what was originally the first part of my discussion, but ultimately the appendix to this
fun discussion with Luke Antley.
There are a lot of things I want to talk about today, but I do want to start with
the discovery that you led that probably most people would associate with you if they go to
your Wikipedia page. That's probably the first thing they're going to see, although I haven't
been to your Wikipedia page in a while, so I don't recall. But let's talk about PI3 kinase. How do we
define it, by the way? Tell people what it was. So PI3 kinase stands for phospho-inositide 3 kinase.
And the 3 means that it phosphorylates the 3 position on the inositol ring, which is the
head group of this lipid. And so in the mid, early mid-1980s, phosphatidylinositol phosphorylation,
which was known to occur from 1949, the purpose of it was totally ambiguous. Why did this lipid
get phosphorylated? And in early 1982, 1983, there was a breakthrough with the discovery that the
phosphorylated form, phosphatidylinositol was phosphate at the 4 and the 5 positions of the
inositol ring. By the way, inositol was hexa-hydroxycyclohexane. So there's six hydroxys,
one of them connects to the glycerol backbone, and then the others are potentially available
to be phosphorylated. Anyway, the 4 position and the 4 plus 5 position were both identified the
year I was born, 1949. And the purpose of that was not known. It was called the futile cycle,
maybe a way of just getting rid of phosphates or something. We're getting rid of ATP. Yeah.
Just phosphorylated, indeed phosphorylated. And sort of like an ATP sync. And then the idea,
the observation that this phosphorylation could be stimulated by various GPCR pathways and growth
factor pathways, got people thinking about what it might be doing. And it tended to correlate with
calcium elevation. And so the breakthrough paper showed that in fact, when cells are stimulated
with certain growth factors like EGF or certain subset of GPCR activators. No stand for. G protein
coupled receptors. And EGF just for folks. Epidormal growth factor. Okay. So all growth.
And so these signaling pathways would activate the hydrolysis of that lipid that the inositol
1,4,5-trisphosphate that comes off when you hydrolyze it away from the lipid,
turned out to regulate calcium release from cells. And that was a huge breakthrough
because no one knew how calcium got elevated and that explained it. So I, in the meantime,
it was not working on that particular pathway. And let's pause for a moment and remind everybody
you trained, you were interested in science from a young age, but you were sort of deciding,
I think a little bit, if I recall between chemistry and biology, you were very interested
in both. Correct. I was a pure chemist. The last biology course I took was in 1964 when I was a
sophomore in high school. So you very quickly declared chemistry your obsession. I hated
biology because at that time, at least in the backwoods of West Virginia, where I was growing up,
biology was just a bunch of descriptive memorization. And so I was bored with that
and decided I would never take another biology course. And I stuck to that. I was pure chemistry,
mainly organic chemistry. And then I switched into physical chemistry, but was totally
uninterested in biology at all until I took one semester of biochemistry and realized maybe
there's something interesting going on in biology. So I went to Cornell and Ithaca to get my PhD.
And there I focused on biophysical chemistry. It was the chance to apply chemistry to
questions like how do you get molecules across membranes? And that's what I worked on. How do
you synthesize ATP in the mitochondria or chloroplasts? So that kind of slippery slope
of going into biological questions that could be addressed by simple chemical questions or
physics questions. Now, what got you interested in the mitochondria so early? I read a paper
when I was an undergraduate that was an idea that Peter Mitchell had proposed, that the way you
make ATP in the mitochondria and or chloroplasts was using a proton gradient. And his idea was
that that gradient would allow you to pull the protons in one direction, the hydroxy ions in
the other direction, and remove water from phosphate plus ADP and condense that into ATP.
That was just very simple physical property that if you could move those two ions in different
directions, it would produce ATP. In effect, the idea was not correct. It was correct that ATP
was made from the proton gradient, but the actual mechanism was turned out to be different.
There are actually three Nobel prizes given for how ATP is synthesized in the mitochondria.
I wasn't aware that there were three separate Nobel prizes. Do you recall who won all of them?
So Mitchell. Mitchell obviously. Then there was a second one by Boyer
on the figuring out the actual mechanism by which this occurs. And then a third one from Peter
Walker, who figured out structural basis for how this all worked. Oh, I didn't know the Walker one.
He was a crystal structure, did crystal structures. And I met all of them when I was a young man
before becoming a professor. And so it's, I was very invested in that. That's what I worked on.
For the person who's listening to this, whose world is not necessarily wrapped up in this,
which is most people, it's worth pausing for a moment on how much is involved for the Nobel
committee to recognize one body of work that says something that three times they would recognize
a different angle of the same body of work probably speaks to why there is so much to this day,
complete interest and fascination with the mitochondria beyond just the obvious,
the energetics, which is what was initially how we would think about it.
Well, it was a fascinating question in the 1960s. This was the biggest mystery
because we knew how you made ATP from glycolysis, but how you made it into mitochondria. And how
could the mitochondria do it so much more efficiently than glycolysis? That was the
big question when I was a graduate student. I think this podcast may represent the
point at which mitochondrial topics exceed all others. It also speaks to that nature.
So Mitchell the great, tell me about how you interacted with Mitchell. How did you come
across him? So he came to give a talk at Cornell. And I should say, Efraakr, Efram Raker, who was
chaired the biochemistry department at Cornell, and who I got to know as first year graduate
student, because I was getting mitochondria from his laboratory in order to purify the enzyme that's
synthesized ATP. Every time I would be waiting for the centrifuges to stop running, if he saw me,
he would grab me and pull me into his office and start throwing out ideas of how he thought ATP
was synthesized. And the truth was, at that time, he did not believe Kimme Osmotic hypothesis,
Peter Mitchell was proposing. And so as a consequence, I got all of these ideas that
he was throwing at me. I personally believed that Kimme Osmotic hypothesis was correct.
Between those discussions, as I continued to, I was working in physical chemistry,
I was in the chemistry department, not the biochemistry department. But the fact that he
would spend so much time with me, even though I wasn't even in his department, to me was quite
flattering and really exciting that this world quality person had done it, was willing to talk
to me. So he went on because he was trying to prove Peter Mitchell wrong. He completely purified
every component, generated a synthetic membrane, reconstituted the proton pump into that membrane,
generated a proton gradient and was able to quantitatively synthesize ATP. And it was the
year after he published that paper saying that Kimme Osmotic theory is actually correct.
But he did the definitive experiment that the prize went to Peter Mitchell. Today, I'm almost
guaranteed they would have shared the prize. Mitchell had the idea Racker proved that it was
correct, even when he was trying to prove that it was incorrect. So that was an interesting story
that Mitchell was invited to come and give a talk at Cornell just at that time my last year as a
graduate student. And so he met with me and my advisor Gordon Hammes. And I went through my
entire PhD thesis with him and F Racker, showing them the various experiments I did about the
mechanism by which this enzyme worked. It was really quite interesting because this was before
Racker had actually published the definitive proof paper. So he had still some questions.
And every slide I would show, Mitchell would say that's consistent with the Kimme Osmotic theory.
And Racker would say, no, but this is why it's not right. And so I hardly get to say a word
because the two of them argued every piece of data I showed. But you provided the substrate
for the argument. Yeah, it's the data from my PhD thesis. That was a fun experience.
So this is early 70s. It was 1974 when I met Peter Mitchell. At any event, the next year I decided
finishing my PhD that I would look for a place that was asking questions that were a little more
biological. But I didn't want to dive too deeply into biology. So I was looking for someone who was
working on like red cells or something. It was pretty simple study and ended up going to Guido
Guidotti's laboratory, who had focused on membrane biochemistry. He was an MD PhD, but he understood
medicine quite well. But his real focus was in biochemistry was not a practicing clinician.
And he was in the department of biochemistry molecular biology at Harvard, recruited there
by Jim Watson. He was absolutely is still a brilliant biochemist. I learned a lot from him.
And he was working on sodium potassium ATPase. It had first been purified in his laboratory,
the enzyme that pumps sodium out of cells and potassium into cells. And since I'd already
worked on how you pump protons into cells with an ATP molecule, I thought this would be
easy for me to understand. I knew how to do those kinds of assays. So that's why I started working
on it. But it turns out that Guido was also very interested in how insulin worked, because
whenever you add insulin to cells, within seconds to minutes, they take up a massive amount of
glucose, but they also turn up the sodium potassium ATPase, the sodium pump, use that sodium gradient
to move amino acids into cells. And so there was a lot of membrane transport being regulated by
insulin. Was it understood at that time how anabolic insulin was? What you've described are
anabolic attributes, but was it understood clinically how anabolic the hormone was?
Yes, it was because just by observation that type 1 diabetics failed to thrive. They were very small.
They did not put on weight. They didn't, their cells didn't grow. And so during development,
insulin is an anabolic molecule. In a mature adult, it no longer, except under certain
situations, drives growth. It will continue to drive growth of fat cells. It can also facilitate
growth of muscle, but most tissues do not grow further than those two major tissues.
So yes, it was well known it was an anabolic process. But now you were seeing the steps by
which it could carry out that anabolic property. Yeah, and it was generally known. What I just said
was generally known that amino acids uptake accelerate immediately within a minute or so.
Sodium export of the cell went up and glucose flux of course went in, particularly in muscle
and fat cells and glycogen was stored. And then of course there was a whole lot of change in
transcriptional regulation of all kinds of things. So we knew all of that, but the actual
mechanism was totally unknown. In the mid-1970s, no one had even purified the insulin receptor,
had no idea what the receptor was. People could quantify it because if you added radioactive
insulin to fat cells, it would stick to the surface and with very high affinity. And that
correlated with the responses that you see. So we knew it existed. We knew roughly how many copies
there were per cell. We could quantify by radioactivity, but no one had quite purified
the enzyme to homogeneity. And so the numerous labs were trying to purify it. So eventually the
insulin receptor was purified and it was about the same time that SARC, the SARC tyrosine kinase,
the SARC oncogene for Ralcisarcoma virus was shown by Harold Varmus' lab to be protein that had
amology to pKa, a protein kinase. And that also was an endogenous protein that had been picked up
by the virus and altered. So that really was a major breakthrough. It got Nobel prize for
Harold Varmus. He shared that one with Michael, right? Michael. Yeah, Michael Bishop. Michael
Bishop and. 89, they shared it. 79, I think. Oh, but they won the prize in 89 maybe? Maybe I'm...
Oh yeah, the prize was... The prize awarded. Yeah, the discovery was 78, 78. Yeah. So that was about
the time the insulin receptor was being purified as well. And then Ray Erickson's labs showed that
SARC had a kinase activity. They thought it was a threonine kinase. They looked for that possibility.
Joan Grogy was his lab at that time given the sequence homology to protein kinase A,
that it's probably also a protein kinase. And then Tony Hunter showed that actually by thin layer,
the molecule that was thought to be phosphotanthine was actually phosphotyrosine.
And phosphotyrosine had never been seen as a product of a protein kinase before. It had been
picked up as an intermediate in DNA unwinding. And so he could get a marker for that from Jim
Wyng's lab that showed that he could use on the thin layer and showed that what SARC was actually
producing was actually phosphotyrosine. So that opened up a whole field. And then comparing the
sequence of the insulin receptor to pKa versus SARC is clearly most highly related to SARC.
And so multiple labs at that point showed that yes, the insulin receptor was like SARC,
a tyrosine kinase. But in this case, a transmembrane protein had an extracellular insulin binding
component, and then the intracellular kinase activity. So putting that in English for folks,
insulin hits this transmembrane tyrosine kinase. And when the molecule of insulin hits it,
inside the cell, this kinase pathway kicks up, it moves the GLUT4 transporter. Well,
there's another step in there, but oversimplifying a little bit, that chemical reaction is necessary
to translocate this transporter across the cell to bring glucose in. And that's, so the leap there,
the new insight was exactly how insulin got glucose in the cell chemically and mechanically, right?
So the initial observation was then insulin binds and about the same time EGF receptor was purified
and FGF receptor and PDGF receptor. And they all sort of were like insulin receptor.
They had an extracellular. And this was back, I mean, today, a young student who's in a lab
doing this now is scratching their head going, what do you mean? Why didn't you just use PCR or
something like that? But I mean, you guys were literally what, crystallizing a protein or how
were they actually figuring out what the structure was? So these proteins were all being purified to
homogeneity by just plain fractionation. There was no way to knock out genes and knock them down.
So you just had to purify the protein based on its ability to bind insulin. You just run it over
column after column after column. And eventually you've got to a single band on a gel and you said,
that's your protein. And that only gives you the primary structure of the protein. It doesn't tell
you how it's folded, does it? No, that only tells you. It tells you the molecular weight, basically.
All the thing you get is the molecular weight. Yeah. You see, it's.
Here it is on the band. Yeah. Insulin receptor is, it gets cleaved.
But it's a heterodimer, isn't it? It's a single polypeptide that gets clipped during processing
into two proteins, but are held together by disulfide bonds. So it's, and then a dimer of
that composition. So that we knew late 1970s and EGF receptor and all these other receptors are all
look a lot like the insulin receptor. And they all had tyrosine kinase activity
that was triggered by binding the growth factor insulin. IGF-1 receptor also very similar to
insulin receptor. One by one by one, different labs purified them. They all found the same thing.
You had the growth factor of the cell and you get the tyrosine kinase activity activated on
the inside of the cell. You know, that was a huge breakthrough. But still, if you ask when you
triggered the cell with insulin or EGF or PDGF, and you ask what was the major thing phosphorylated,
it was the receptor itself. So you just ask, where's the radioactivity going? Phosphate,
radioactive phosphate, it goes mainly to the receptor, cytosolic domain. It's auto phosphorylated.
So now we were left with this several years of, we have a tyrosine kinase that explains how all
these growth factors work, including insulin and how SARC works, but we can't find anything other
than auto phosphorylation. How does that help? So the breakthrough ultimately then came with
the observation that these auto phosphorylations or phosphorylation of adapter proteins were
recruiting a host of other proteins to the membrane that we're actually doing the work that was
required to drive the cell growth. And so that was again, early 1980s, these were all being figured
out. So I got interested as soon as I saw that there was a different kinase activity, this tyrosine
kinase, I got very excited about it and realized there was an opportunity now if I can figure out
what that tyrosine kinase does to figure out what might be the downstream signal. So we got one step
into the cell. We didn't know how many steps we needed to explain glucose uptake or amino acid
uptake, etc, etc, or glycogen synthesis. So I saw a paper by Ray Erickson's laboratory
in which he found an activity associated with SARC that would phosphorylate glycerol.
And he published it in JVC. It co purified with the protein through numerous steps of purification.
And so in addition to having the ability to phosphorylate tyrosine antibodies that got
phosphorylated on tyrosine on the purified protein, there was also an activity there that
phosphorylated glycerol. And I looked at that and thought, no, glycerol looks like half of an
anositol. So anositol is six carbons, glycerol is three in both cases. But in the pure glycerol
case, it has OH on each of the carbons. Yeah, three carbons with an OH on it. Yeah. Anositol has six
carbons with an OH on all. So if you took two. Yeah, if you took the two rings and shoved them
together, yeah, glued them together, you would get anositol. And then what the paper showed was
the KM, you know, it's a 50% concentration of glycerol, you need it for it to be phosphorylated
was something like a hundred millimolar enormous concentration, huge, like a hundred to thousand
fold higher unit ever finding a cell. Yeah. So they weren't claiming this was a physiologically
relevant. I see. They were just saying, here's a chemical reaction that can take place. And they
just noticed it because they saw this molecule running on their thin layer that ran faster than
proteins. When they isolate, it turned out to be phosphorylated glycerol. It was sort of out there.
Here's, we saw this other activity. What might it be? And so I went to Ray Erickson and said, well,
that looks a lot like anositol. So why don't we was Ray at Harvard at the time? Yeah, one floor
below me at Harvard. So my graduate student, Malcolm Whitman, who knew how to do kinase
assays on small molecules collaborated with Ray Erickson's postdoc to see whether phosphatidyl
anositol might be a better substrate than glycerol. And he tried it and sure enough,
he got this KM now of like five micromolar. Wait, wait, wait, how is this even possible?
Let me make sure I understand what you just said. You take glycerol and you need a KM of
a hundred millimolar to get it phosphorylated. You simply take the same structure, but now it's
basically two of them stuck together in a ring and you get down to five micromolar. And it's also on
a membrane component. So the anositol is in a membrane bilayer. So you sonicate the lipid and
instead of free molecule floating around. Oh, so it's not a free anositol. It's the
anositol in the phospholipid or in the lipid. Yeah. Tell me from a chemistry standpoint,
and I apologize. I know that for some of you listening right now, you're thinking, wow,
you guys are really in the weeds. I promise we're going to get out of the weeds in a minute. But
I also think this is just an interesting example of the specificity of biology too. What is it
about that lipid holding that? Is it the position with which it holds the ring in place that enables
that phosphorylation? Well, now that we know the structure of PI3 kinase and how it works in its
mechanism, it's easy to explain in retrospect. But at that time we didn't know that there was
anything there other than SARC. So it was hard to explain why the SARC, tyrosine kinase itself,
was carrying out this reaction. What did the editors even say of that? I mean, that's one
of those things where people are like, is there a mistake here? Because that's like a five log
difference. Physicists who had no problem understanding what I just said. If you can find
things to two dimensions, they can come together much more readily than if you do it in three
dimensions. And that would account for the difference? Yeah, easily. Try closing your eyes,
bringing your two fingers together in space, in three dimensional space, and then do it again on
the table. When they're on the table, yeah. You'll find each other. Yeah. So combining things to two
dimensions is the way nature continually uses membranes. And the lipids basically keeping it
in a two dimensional plane. Yeah. So in any event, we're really getting in the weeds here now.
But just personally, I mean, all of that is intuitive to me. What's not intuitive to me is
five log difference. I would take a one log difference for what you said. That's what's
amazing to me. I didn't- Well, there are other reasons that will come clear. Let me move on.
So the bottom line was that that SARC preparation, which we assumed was completely pure,
wasn't completely pure. It was a certain amount of the SARC harvested out of the cell
brought along this second enzyme, which ultimately turned out to be PI3K,
phosphonosatide 3 kinase. But we didn't know that at that time. And so we suggested in the paper
that the SARC very same enzymatic pocket could both accommodate tyrosine as a substrate and also
accommodate the head group of phosphatide and onositol. That in the end turned out to be incorrect
in that even though by all criteria that we could characterize at that point, we couldn't
prove that there was a separate function. If you used a kinase dead SARC or a mutant of SARC that
no longer had activity, then the phosphonotidol and onositol kinase also went away. That's why
we thought it was the same pocket that was doing both. Retrospect, it turns out that the enzyme
has to be active in order to bind to PI3 kinase. And that's why that activity was coming along.
So we published that. We're very clear to say that we used sonicated membranes to do the assay,
which was necessary to get this mini log preference for that substrate. In the meantime,
after publishing that, multiple other labs tried to reproduce it. But they didn't have
the machine that would sonify the lipids to make the membrane bilayers. So they just added detergent.
So even though we showed in our paper that if you added detergent, the enzyme activity
completely disappeared. Wouldn't the detergent break the glycerol off the lipid?
The phosphotidol and onositol would now get embedded into the detergent rather than being
a bilayer. Yeah, it wouldn't stick to it at all, right? Right. So you're going to lose that
advantage of having a membrane. And that wasn't known at the time, I guess. Well, we knew it
because I'd worked on membranes for the previous 10 years. But the other labs didn't, I guess at
the time they didn't know that. They were not membrane biochemists. They were all molecular
biologists. So they tried to reproduce the result, but they didn't have a sonifier to make
membrane lipids. And they assumed it phosphorylates the head group. Phosphotidol and onositol shouldn't
make any difference how you present it. And so they presented it to detergent micelle and they
could not reproduce the results. So there were three prominent papers coming out a year or so
later saying, Nope, this is incorrect. This is incorrect. This is incorrect from major laboratories.
So at that point, it already started collaboration with Tom Roberts. But at that point, Lou,
did you have confidence that you had done this correctly? Or were you questioning yourself?
I had no doubt. So you knew this was a methodologic error on the part of these other three labs.
And despite the fact that at this point, the scientific community would look at you and say,
Lou, you're probably wrong. You were confident in your methodology. Yeah, there was no doubt. All
my research had been on membrane enzymes and membrane reconstitution, etc. So I knew what I
was doing made sense. And I knew our results are reproducible. Because not only can multiple
people in my laboratory do it, but multiple people in Tom Roberts laboratory who we started
a collaboration with could do it. And Brian Schaffhausen's lab, which was a third collaborator,
could also reproduce it. So multiple people in multiple independent labs all got the same
result. If you sonified the lipid, and if you added MP40 detergent to solubilize a lipid,
then the activity went away. So there was no doubt about that. And so I had no lack of confidence
that we were right. But the problem was how to convince these other laboratories that they needed
to do the essay right. They didn't want to buy a sonifier. They were like, I'm done with that
when there doesn't work. So we actually sent David Kaplan, the graduate student Tom Roberts lab,
and Malcolm Hootman, the graduate student of my laboratory, to these other laboratories with the
sonifier. They went there, they sonified the lipid form, gave them to their graduate students
who then did the essay again. And now they got the same result we got. Are you pushing this hard
to get the other labs to see it because you know how important this is going to be? Or you have
sort of premonition about the role that PI3K is going to play in growth? I mean, you couldn't
have possibly seen in the early 80s what you know today. So how much of this was just scratching an
intellectual itch versus a biologic intuition about the importance of this to overall growth,
which is obviously where we're going. I'm amazed we are this far in and we haven't used the c-word
yet. So the reason I was completely convinced by 1976, 1977, that this was driving growth of cancer
cells is the collaboration we started with Tom Roberts lab. And Tom Roberts had been working on
polyoma middle T. So polyoma virus is a DNA virus while SARC is an RNA virus. So it causes,
as the name implies, the formation of multiple tumors in mice. So you infect a mouse with this
virus and all kinds of tumors show up everywhere. And so Tom had begun mutating various regions of
polyoma middle T. And reason we looked at polyoma middle T is because his lab and Sarah Courtney's
lab and others in Schaffhausen had shown that SARC copurifies with polyoma middle T. We already
knew by the mid 70s that SARC was somehow implicated in how polyoma middle T transforms
cells and forms all these tumors. That's why I went to collaborate with Tom because he had
additional tools that we could collaborate with to understand. And so he had made all kinds of
mutations. He'd also found that SARC phosphorylated his site in polyoma middle T, a tyrosine site was
highly phosphorylated. And even more importantly, that if you mutated that tyrosine residue to
phenylalanine, polyoma middle T completely lost its ability to transform cells. It's a single point
mutation. Even though the SARC protein was still bound, there was no longer tyrosine phosphorylation
315 and that eliminated the ability to transform cells. So we said, well, if PI3 kinase is not
SARC itself, maybe it binds to middle T independently. But we found that if you prevented
SARC from binding the middle T, then you didn't get that tyrosine phosphorylation. And now there
was no PI3 kinase activity bound to middle T. So you needed SARC for middle T to bind to PI3 kinase.
At this time, we didn't know it was phosphorylated in the three position, which we'll come back to.
However, the shocking result was that if you eliminated that tyrosine residue,
now PI3 kinase would no longer bind and middle T would no longer transform cells,
even though SARC was still there and was still activated. So that said that activating SARC
is not sufficient to transform a cell unless you also activate PI3 kinase. And we published that in
Nature in 76, I think, 76, 77 in Nature. Were you collaborating with Bishop and Varmus at this point
in time? 86, 86, and then 86, 87. So 84 was when we published the paper with Ray Erickson.
And then a couple of years later with Tom Roberts and a couple of papers we had, and we showed that
PDGF receptor also when activated brought down COPRIS of the PI3 kinase activity, etc, etc.
So that's where we were in 1986, 87 or so. And at least some of the people who had gotten sonicators
also believed us that this was really uniquely associated with tyrosine kinases after they were
activated by growth factors. We saw the insulin receptor would also bring down PI3 kinase only
if you stimulate insulin first. Then you could also bring down this PI kinase activity.
But at that time, the only monophosphorylated form of phosphatidylinositol known was phosphatidylinositol
4-phosphate. That was discovered in 1949. I mentioned earlier there's a 4-phosphorylation
and there's a 4 plus 5 phosphorylation. And those are the only two species of phosphorylated
phosphatidylinositol. So we assumed that this was phosphorylation at the 4 position.
But as we began to characterize the ability of proteins from cells to phosphorylate phosphatidylinositol,
we found that there were two activities. There was one that required that you sonic
by the membranes for it to bind and get for it to have activity. And another that would work
perfectly well, in fact even better, if the lipid was dissolved in a detergent. So we called those
two enzymes type 1 and type 2 PI kinase. And it was only the type 1, the one that required sonified
lipids that coprecipitated with all these tyrosine kinases. The type 2 had completely different
enzymatic characters. So it was inhibited by adenosine, the type 1 wasn't. And so we had a whole
lot of profiles that said these were two different enzymes. So Malcolm Whitman, registered in my lab,
decided to separate them. So he ran column fractionations and mid-S activities with or without
detergent, with or without adenosine. And he characterized the two enzymes, separated them
completely. And he had a lab, we had a lab meeting which every other spot on the thin layer,
which is how we characterized the lipid phosphorylation, we ran it out
to separate the molecules based on migration in a solvent on a silica plate. And we noticed in the
lab meeting that every other spot migrated about one millimeter different from the previous spot.
And the way that Malcolm had spotted them on the thin layer was it was type 1, then type 2, then type 1,
then type 2, type 1, type 2, all the way across. If you looked at where the radioactivity ran,
it went up, down, up, down, up, down, up, down, up, down. And the bottom line was, to me as a chemist,
the fact that they migrate differently means they have to be chemically different.
That meant that one of those molecules was being phosphorylated at a different position on the
inositol ring from the other. And so we began the process then of chemically characterizing
the product of the type 1 and the type 2 enzyme. And how subtle was this, by the way?
Was this obvious in looking at it? Or was it something that could have easily been dismissed?
I guarantee almost everybody would have dismissed this. One millimeter.
Yeah, I was about to say that just doesn't sound like...
The spot was at least 10 millimeters diameter, and the center of the spots were one millimeter
different.
Do you naturally have an eye that gravitates towards symmetry?
I have an eye that gravitates towards unexpected results.
And to me, there's no way to explain it. If you had only two spots beside each other,
you could say, well, that side of the thin layer migrated a little faster because of
the solvent front was not completely horizontal. But you couldn't explain the up, down, up,
down, up, down, all the way across.
Do you still have a photo of that?
It's in figure one in the Nature paper that we published.
From 88?
88.
We'll link to that figure.
But the observation was made in 1987. I bumped into Peter Downs, who's one of the best lipid
chemists in the world, and at a meeting at Cold Spring Harbor, and I told him this result. And
I said, I know you must have standards for anositol degradation. So can we work together? And
so we knew it had to be some site other than the four position, but it could have been the five,
it could have been the three.
Yeah. Was there a chance it could have been you were looking at four
versus four plus five? Four versus four plus five?
No, because we knew at four plus five, it would migrate to about three inches different.
So that would look totally different. So the null hypothesis is you're just looking at four
and your assays a little dirty, but you're thinking, no, it's something else.
Yeah. Of course, we repeated it multiple times. And we also did HPLC separation, reverse phase,
every way you could look at it. And in every way we did it, they were chemically different.
They migrated differently in numerous. The nature paper, we only put that one slide,
that one figure of the slightly different migration. Because from there on, we did the
chemistry to prove that it was a three position.
Why do you think the three position had such a similar look to the four versus the five?
Well, keep in mind, there were only two species known to exist. At the time we made this discovery,
phosphotidylinositol, four phosphate.
Oh, and four, five.
And four, five.
It was not a five by itself.
Got it.
So this told us there's a three by itself. And then we went on to show there's also three, four,
and also three, four, five. PI three counties could phosphorylate the three position,
whether or not the four or five were already phosphorylated.
So we now, that generated three new species, PI three P, PI three, four, and PI three, four, five.
But I have to say the three, four, five, this is sort of another
sidebar that we could drop out of this, but it's so cool. Never published it because it
was embarrassing. But to say it, you may as well get embarrassed.
So we knew that there were species that had been claimed to be four, five that were probably three,
four for the same reason that the three P was thought to be four P because separating the three,
four from the four, five was also hard. So we looked for that carefully and found that in fact,
there was a three, four being made and proved that the same enzyme was making three P.
And if you gave it PR four P to the substrate, it would make three, four P two.
Leslie Serunian in a postdoc in the laboratory was doing the experiments to really verify that
those two species really were being made from the same enzyme. And in the course of that work,
she came into my office one day and said, I no longer get the same results that I've been getting
for the last six months. Something has changed. And so we went over all of her thin layers.
Again, this is how we separated all the species. And sure enough, after getting numerous results
in which she could give PI four P and get PI three, four P two, suddenly over the past week,
she no longer got that doubly phosphorylated lipid when she added purified PI three kinase
to that lipid. So the question was what had changed? And she said, well, the only thing
that changed is we ran out of the PI four P and I had to buy a new jar of PI four P from
Baron Germanheim. That's interesting. As I looked at the thin layer more carefully, I noticed that
just when the experiments were no longer working, there was a new spot on the thin layer that was
just off the origin where we assumed it would probably just be ATP. There was always a little
bit of contaminating ATP that got left over when you separate the lipid out. And we assumed that
that was ATP, but I noticed it ran just a little bit faster than ATP. And that it only appeared in
experiments where she could not find the three, four P two. And I said, okay, stained is what I
had and it'll tell you where the lipid that you used from Baron Germanheim runs. And I'll bet
that it's actually four or five P two. And that turned out to be the case that they'd mislabeled
the bottle. What was commercially sold as phosphatidylinositol four phosphate was actually
phosphatidylinositol four or five bisphosphate. And so by accident, I almost think that God looked
down on us and said, look, they're missing the most important lipid PI three, four, five P three.
It never occurred to us to look for it because we were, no one had ever claimed of something like
that to ran on a thin layer. That was because it runs so close to the ATP that was always missed
because it's got three phosphates. Yeah. It's very highly charged and therefore runs.
I never once thought of that until you just said that Lou, I never, I never would have had that
thought actually. And then of course, when you say it now, I mean, that's, think about how dominant
those three phosphates are, right? In fact, a year after we made this observation, the paper came out.
In fact, I got called by nature saying there's this paper claiming they found something that
looks like triply phosphorylated phosphatidylinositol. And they asked, do you think that's
possible? And I said, yeah, in fact, I know it's possible. We already have results showing that
that can happen with purified enzyme. Lou, thank you so much for the generosity with your time and
your insights and most importantly for the work you're doing. You and your colleagues are helping
a lot of people. Thank you, Peter. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If
you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that
allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our
goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end,
membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes
that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing
these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast,
typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday,
highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive.
This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily
listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting
paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time
goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over
to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only. It does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.