Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Ned David. Ned is the president of Unity Biotechnology,
a company that he co-founded in 2011. In this episode, we're going to talk a little bit about
Unity, but more importantly, we talk about the science upon which Unity is developed,
and that is the science of senescence or cellular senescence. We begin this episode by putting that
into context. I think if you're interested in the space of longevity, you're listening to this
podcast, you've undoubtedly heard the term senescence, but it might not mean much to you.
I think what Ned does a great job of here is explaining not just senescence, but where it
fits in the overall lattice, if you will, of all of the different cellular processes that occur
during aging. Where does it fit in with the role of mTOR inhibition, caloric restriction,
mitochondrial dysfunction, stem cell exhaustion, methylation of DNA and epigenetic change, all of
these sorts of things. We also talk quite a bit about Ned's background as a serial entrepreneur in
biotechnology. Ned is at least partly responsible for the development of a number of FDA approved
compounds, and he talks openly about what he learned good, bad, and indifferent along the way,
and how that helped him at the beginning of this process of creating this company,
Unity, define sort of the jugular questions that needed to be addressed as sort of a proof of
principle. In fact, I found that part of the discussion most interesting, and I think you'll
know what I'm talking about when we get to that part of the episode, because I found that exercise
that he and his co-founders went through between about 2011, 2015, to be some of the most
interesting thinking around this idea of company creation. Ned is a prolific innovator. I think
when he was about 30, he was named to the top 100 innovators in the world by MIT Technology Reviews.
He holds a PhD from Cal Berkeley, and he got his undergrad degree in molecular biology at Harvard.
So without getting into too much more of the details of this, please enjoy my discussion with Ned David.
Ned, awesome to see you today. Thank you for coming by. Oh, thank you for having me. I feel
like I haven't seen you in person in way too long. Is this true? We tried to get you to come to dinner.
Oh, God, I feel horrible about that. Yes, sorry. Yeah, you were distracted. It's all good. No,
you know what I was doing? You were doing a podcast. I was doing a podcast that I thought
would take two and a half hours. It ended up taking six hours. That must have been an intense
experience. It was a very intense experience, and I felt horrible after. I'm sorry. So I owe you an
apology for that. It's okay. We love you. There's so much I want to talk with about you. In fact,
I've been bugging you for about a year to come on the podcast, because what I was hoping we could do,
and we can never do it when there's a microphone in front of us, but was sort of reproduce at
dinner conversation that we would have ordinarily, which would be pick some topic and we go way off
on a tangent about it. It could be energy. It could be biotech. It could be whatever.
But some of the most interesting discussions we've had over the past five years have been around
longevity, something that we both share an interest in. God, it's been probably nine years since you
talked to me about what became that which you're doing today. Is that about right?
Yeah, that's about right. It was 2011 towards the end. Yeah, actually, we're in December now,
so it's actually been somewhat more than eight years. So I want to talk a lot about your work.
You're always a guy who's got a lot of hats on. Right now, you're mostly wearing one hat,
and that's a hat that puts you squarely at the center of a pretty big circle with a bunch of
folks working at a company called Unity Biotech, which we'll certainly get to. But I think for
listeners to really understand what you do today, what your company does, they need to sort of
understand the journey you've gone through over the past several years and how that's sort of
shaped your thinking about an interesting problem. You're a serial entrepreneur, and we will likely
discuss some of that in your background. But let's just start with how you think about this problem
that I think about, which is how do we help people live longer? How do we help people live
better? How do you define that, by the way? I don't want to impose my definitions on you.
What is longevity to you? Well, longevity for me would be being able to live without the indignities
that I've witnessed, we all witness in our lives, all of these features of aging that seem to be
inescapable. So my father, for example, he has profound degenerative disc disease, which makes
him functionally immobile. It defines his life. My stepfather died of Alzheimer's at 87.
That defined the final chapter of his life. So I've been up close to these things in other people.
In addition, we all, and you and I are now, I'm a little older than you, I'm in my 50s now,
we are witnessing these changes in ourselves. And for me, longevity would be the ability to use
what I know how to do, which is science and biology, and be able to change how we get to live our lives,
to be free of these indignities. And I think it's something that we can do and we are doing it.
And so for me, it sort of began as a dream, but now we're generating human data that says
this, we can actually do this. So I remember when this started, Ned, circa 2011, how you read
steeped yourself in this field, which at the time was kind of new. You had already done a number of
interesting things in biology that had led to the development of drugs, but none quite in this space.
I mean, I literally remember many nights I'd be driving home and we'd be talking on the phone and
you would be telling me about things that you had just read about. And I saw this paper and it's 10
years old, but it was almost like you were going through a second postdoc or something, getting up
to speed in this. I've always liked the way you sort of explained your evolution of thought there.
Do you want to maybe for the listeners, give them a sense of how you developed a framework around this?
About sort of aging biology.
Yeah, why do we age and what can you do about it ultimately?
So maybe it's helpful for me to just create some context. And so the way I think about this and the
way I explain it to people that are new to this or people that aren't scientists is I always talk
about there are these sort of three principles that if you remember nothing else from listening,
if you're awakened two weeks from now in the middle of the night, it's these three principles
that I think are a good way to think about this. And the first principle is that aging is not a
rigid thing. So it's this flexible, malleable thing. And nature has throughout evolutionary
history sort of bent and twisted aging for its own purposes to create creatures that have very
different lifespans. And this kind of takes us to the second principle, which is that nature has
done this with these control knobs. These are sort of biochemical systems that nature twists.
And these systems are now something we're learning. And this takes us to the third principle
to turn as people that do drug hunting like us. And so it's these three principles that
nature is flexible or that aging is a flexible thing. And nature has then bent and twisted
control knobs to make it flexible, and that these are turnable stuff. So if you take those three
principles as the context, you may ask, well, why do we as scientists, why do I believe these things
are true? So if you just look outside at nature and creatures across phylogenetic history,
you see very similar creatures with very different lifespans. So if you take the hard clam,
so this is this thing you can eat at a clam bake. If you don't eat it, it will live about 40 years.
And it has a deep ocean dwelling relative called a quahog that lives at least 500 years. And
these are very similar creatures. They look very much the same. And no one really knows how long
this quahog lives. This 500 year thing was just because that was what the age of the wreck off
of which it was pulled was. So these are very similar creatures on the order of 12 fold
different lifespan. Similar story, if you flip over to, let's say the order of rodents. Actually,
let's not even go to rodents. Let's just talk about mammals, because that's us. Of course,
rodents are mammals too, but we are mammals as humans. So if you look at the shortest living
mammal, which is this thing called the tiny shrew lives less than a year. And then you look at the
longest living mammal. So it's called the bowhead whale. And again, no one knows how long a bowhead
whale actually lives. So the estimate is at least 200 years. So again, you've got this 200 fold
difference at least in creatures that kind of have the same biochemistry or both mammals. Now,
if you flip over to rodents, it's the same phenomenon. Okay, you can take a field mouse,
which can live somewhere between two and three years. And then you find this naked mole rat,
which is this very unusual looking subterranean creature that's blind and hairless. This creature
lives 10 times longer lives on the order of even more than 10 times longer lives on the order of
30 years if it doesn't die of some trauma. And again, these are these are in the same order.
And so these are closely related creatures, very, very different lifespans. So nature has clearly
gone to town on this and created these marvelous examples of disparate lifespan, but sort of the
same creature, the same biochemistry. So this kind of takes us to this idea of that nature has done
this. How has it done this? It's done it with these control knobs. And I'll walk through why
we thought they were control knobs and how we turn them. So the first control knob that got discovered
molecularly was the work of Cynthia Kenyon. And this was a paper that blew me away. I was a first
year in graduate school, maybe second year. And Cynthia published a paper that was pretty
heretical at the time. And the paper showed that you could knock down the function of a single gene
in a worm C. elegans. So it's about a millimeter size little worm. And when you knock down the
function of this thing, it doubled the animal's lifespan. And this was a wild result. Because at
the time, aging was thought of as this kind of decay process. But the notion that you could
essentially break the function of something or at least make it function a lot less well,
and double the lifespan of a creature was just a total mind warp for me and other people. Just like,
oh my gosh, you can dent something and it gets better. Now what's happened in the intervening
decades, this has been repeated in flies, it's even repeated in mice, you can knock down the
function of a single gene and calorie restrict an animal. And you can double its lifespan. That's
like you or me living to 160. Okay, because this is a creature with really similar biochemistry to
ourselves. So this just said that you could take single genes, turn them and do radical things to
lifespan. Now in fairness, with Cynthia's work in C elegans, I always felt that it wasn't the best
model to extrapolate from because of the division stopping at the germ cell. And therefore,
if you take DAF2 and DAF16 and project them forward to mammals, I don't think we've seen
the same magnitude of reduction with attenuation of those, have we? No. And maybe it's worth,
rather you explaining it than me, do you want to tell folks what DAF2 and DAF16 do just to bring
them along for the ride? So these were genes that were discovered in Cynthia's screen as
receptors and transcription factors associated with what we now talk about as the IGF-1 receptor
signaling pathway. And if you go in, so this is something that now has been explored in great
detail in mice, for example. And the analogous knockdowns in mice of the receptors don't produce
the same degree of longevity that you can produce in a worm. Now interestingly, a paper published
somewhat recently, this was near Barzilay and actually Pedro Beltran who I work with now,
with an antibody that antagonizes the IGF-1 receptor. Yeah. It extends life, but there's
a sex difference. So it only benefits the females. And it's not something that translates perfectly,
but I think that's not the interesting piece in terms of the whole story of what we're learning
about aging. It was to us and to me, it was, oh my gosh, you can damage the function of a single gene.
The fact that it still works in mammals is remarkable. The fact that it works less,
it's not as cool, it's a little bit of a bummer. But to me, it was really the DAF2, DAF16
observation that opened up the field and said that there were these knobs that you could turn
and you could get these radical impacts on longevity. And the additive value of DAF16 plus
caloric restriction was also very interesting in Cynthia's worms. And I actually thought that that
was perhaps the most extrapolable insight to mammals. But to your point, it was a proof of
concept, right? It was, this thing is malleable. Yeah. And to me, at the time, it was just like,
as though the mask tipped a little bit and you could see the face underneath like, oh my gosh,
there's something almost programmatic going along here as opposed to just this idea that you just
decay. And that was exciting. And that paper stuck with me for several decades. It was not something
that I chose to work on. Although I became friends with Cynthia at some point in the early 2000s and
we continue to be friends and talk all the time. But that particular biology is not,
it's more of a marker people use now, as opposed to something that people are actively trying to
perturb. So going back to this question about of knobs, this goes to our, this third principle,
which is that we can turn some of these knobs. The first knob actually that got turned in a
super aggressive way goes way back to the 1930s. And it was this guy at Cornell named Clive McKay.
And he had a colony of rodents. And this is shortly after the great depression. And his lab
didn't have a ton of money. And in an effort to keep portions of his colony alive, he fed some
of the animals all the time. And then other animals he fed infrequently. And what happened
was not what he expected. The animals that were restricted with food lived longer. And it was the
first times ever got experimentally demonstrated, albeit by accident. And for me, that was the first
time that scientists had sort of set out all for a very funny reason and turned a knob that extended
life. And it brought forward this idea that as we live, aging or your biology is making a decision
about the rate at which you are aging. Now flash forward several decades, a molecule is discovered
on Easter Island made by soil bacteria. It's one of your favorite molecules, rapamycin. Now the aging
effects of rapamycin were not figured out until about 2003. And then the awesome work of David
Sabatini eventually linked this caloristriction observation from decades and decades earlier
to rapamycin. And it turns out that rapamycin and caloristriction are both turning the same
control knob. And this is pretty wild because biology typically only invents a few ways to do
things. And what was really neat was the way in which these two totally different approaches
were both touching the same biology. So it's my belief that this biology, so there's this complex
called mTOR, which is this megadalton complex. It's this master decision maker of whether or not
we are choosing to divide and make more biomass because there's enough resources, or are we
choosing to fight another day. And this biology that rapamycin and caloristriction and restriction
of various other things like methionine is the single best validated biology across labs, across
species. And one of my co-workers, who's a sort of incredibly brilliant, but cynical guy, always
says, if you want to know what the real biology is, it's the stuff that works in every lab no
matter who's doing it. Okay. Rapamycin and caloristriction definitely have that feature.
It works in all these labs. Did you know that I tried to get a personalized license plate
for rapamycin and they got rejected by the DMV in California because rapamycin is a drug
and you can't have a license plate that's a drug. So then I tried again in vain to get rapalogue
as a license plate. And I got thwarted again because apparently someone at the DMV was smart
enough to Google rapalogue and figure out that it's an analog of rapamycin, which is also a drug.
And I got the same rejection letter from the DMV. I would just assume knowing you would have done
rapaman, which sounds vaguely like a supervillain. Okay. But now we didn't go stop there. I'll tell
you over dinner what I eventually went with. Okay. Gotcha. So anyway, there's this mTOR thing,
which is the best validated control knob. The next knob that got turned is this thing with
young blood. So this is something that's sort of popularized if you watch things like Silicon
Valley, but this goes back a ways. But the first time that the lifespan effects of this were
demonstrated was in the 1970s. And so what you do is you take two animals, one's young and one's
old, and you literally suture them together. And their circulatory systems join. And it's not a
giant mental leap to imagine that crap in old people is bad for you. So the old blood would be
bad for the young. The awesome result was that stuff in the young was good for the old and it
could extend life by as much as 15%. These are with animals that are sutured together, which is
not exactly an optimal way to live. So that tells you that's another knob. There's stuff in young
blood that is able to exert biology and do good things. And I think that's going to be an area
that will be fruitful. The next sort of control knobs we've learned about, so mitochondria age.
So mitochondria are the descendants of ancient bacteria. So they have their own DNA, they have
their own genomes and mitochondria live really hard life. And so their mutation rate of their
own DNA is somewhere between a hundred and a thousand fold faster than our nuclear mutation
rate. So their DNA just gets all chewed up. And as a consequence, by the time you are in your 70s,
you can go into a human being and look in their colonic crypts. And on the order of half of the
cells in their colonic crypts don't have functional mitochondria. They can't utilize oxygen to make
energy or do all the other things that mitochondria do that are important. And so that's something
that we've learned that is clearly a part of this aging story. Another thing that could be a knob,
and this is an area of some intense debate these days, is this thing called the methylation clock.
So this is this ever ticking clock in which these methyl groups, this is a little carbon atom with
three hydrogens around it, are attached or detached over time to the various Cs in your GATC
code. And when you're young, there's essentially these five methyl Cs, these methyl groups on your
DNA. It's like a crisp pegboard where everything's lined up perfectly and you've got areas where
they are and crisp areas where they are not. And gene expression is not noisy. And as we get old,
it's like someone drops the pegboard and suddenly you've got methylations where you're not supposed
to have them and you're missing them in other places. And it looks as though that might, and
I stress the word might, give rise to sort of noisy gene expression. And the metaphor I often
think of for this is imagine you have a vinyl LP if you're old enough to know what that is,
or hip enough to know what that is, it's going to be hip to your thing now, and you play an LP a lot.
The actual act of playing that LP takes the little knobs and grooves and wears them down so
the LP doesn't sound as good. And it's possible that the act of being alive and that aging actually
is modifying these little methyl groups in such a fashion as to cause aging. No one knows if these
changes in this epigenetic clock are the cause of features of aging or the result of features of
aging or even a little bit of both. And that's going to be a super interesting area of biology.
Yeah, I've spoken with David Sinclair quite a bit about this. He uses an analogy that's
similar but has a couple differences, which is the methylation could be thought of as the
scratches one gets in a CD surface. And the question of course being, can you restore the
CD back to its original form if you have that master template? And that's not exactly the same
as the analogy you've used, but it certainly speaks to the music and the disc.
Yeah, it's interesting. So I always think of CDs getting scratched because you're negligent.
Right, as opposed to just putting them in the CD player and using them.
And so there's a nuance. I mean, it's funny, those two metaphors may even, as you know,
may speak to different intuitions between me and David about what's going on here.
But I don't really have an intuition. I'm sort of reporting out what's sort of known and what it's
going to be just very exciting to see when we can actually do experiments that can tease this apart
and ask questions like, if you take these methylation groups away, do you in fact start
making cells that are younger functionally? And that's going to be an awesome experiment.
David did an experiment recently and I think you have to be a little cautious with interpretation.
So twice in our lives, we press a factory reset, you are methylome. So you do it once
at conception. And so a bunch of gene products get made, which erase and reset your methylome
back to day zero because you're now an embryo and the program is beginning again. Now, a few weeks
into your life, it happens a second time, but only in a little bit of your cells.
Yeah. So let's explain that. So when you start at conception, you have one cell.
It goes through about 50 divisions.
So I don't know exactly. So are you talking about when we do the second reset? First of all,
it's different in humans and mice. And I apologize. I don't know.
But it's some relatively small number.
It's a small number and it happens within, I believe it's weeks in the human. I think it's
a little over a week in a mouse, but anyone out there that works on this, and I have friends I
could call, but not right the second. What happens is there's a second wave of these gene products
that are made and for a second time in your life and the only second time in your life,
you will reset because now you are making germ cells for your children and they are
kept in a special spot in your sex organs until you make babies.
So those are the only two times that this factory reset gets pressed.
And then going back to where I was saying you have to be a little cautious with interpretation.
We now know how to do this artificially. So we can express four factors called the Yamanaka
factors. And these four factors by themselves, if you express them in cells, it's super inefficient,
but one in every few thousand cells you can cause to become a reset cell with a prime.
When did Yamanaka do this? This is in our lifetime. I mean, this is quite recent.
Yeah. He got the Nobel prize. I, at last, I don't have the date. I know a lot about
actually how he isolated them. I just don't know the precise dates, but basically he did this.
It was a beautiful experiment with Yamanaka did. He initially identified genes that candidate list
of genes that were turned on in this sort of embryological state. And then he started using,
he was delivering the genes in various combinations. He ultimately wound up paired down to about two
dozen. And then he then would take various pairwise combinations and figured out how few he could do
and still managed to turn on one of these embryonic genes. And he managed to weed it down
to four and he got the Nobel prize for them. And so what's happened in the intervening years is
there's been some efforts to see, could you actually impose features of youth? Because it's
sort of a simple minded leap to say, Oh, if you look embryonic, that's young in fact, and I think
that's the little dangerous leap. Right. Just because you don't have the methyl groups on your
DNA doesn't mean they translate into the phenotype that is youth. That's correct. What I think you do
when you do Yamanaka four factor reprogramming is it's a self fate decision. You've entered a very
unique cellular state. Now it just so happens to have things that are in common with youth. And so
I think that when you do a reprogramming event and you were able to exert something that looks like
youthful biology, you may have actually just created new young stem cells that are able to
somehow pick up the music developmentally and participate. That's sort of different than youth.
It's a bit of a sort of cell transplant, sort of thing, although done by the delivery of genes.
So anyway, this whole question about this methyl clock is something that it's an intense area of
interest in the biological community. It's evolving a lot. There's a bunch of labs that
are working on this and it's going to be a very interesting next five years to see where this
drops out. We sort of covered a bunch of things. We've talked about. Yeah, you've got mTOR reduction
slash caloric restriction, loss of the circulating youth factors, mitochondrial dysfunction,
methylation clock, which sort of ties into sort of stem cell exhaustion. And then we've got another
big one. What I wanted to do was I've spent the last now just a little over eight years working on
one of these last knobs that we know how to turn, which is cellular senescence. But I wanted to
place that particular knob in the context of the others because I don't want to sort of overhype
this idea. But I do want to explain why I've dedicated a large chunk of my life on planet
Earth to this. Because if you look at all of these aging mechanisms and these knobs that I've
described, they all play a role in this. We don't yet know what the sort of underlying primordial
clock that ticks that makes us age. What we do know is that you have a series of these component
mechanisms that work collectively and they create this phenomenon that we call aging. And I want to
talk about cellular senescence now because I work on it because of all of the mechanisms,
it strikes me and struck me as the simplest mechanism to perturb and make medicines
that you can use to treat human beings. And I'll get into why that is in a sec, but I'll just tell
you about the knob. So we all begin life as a single cell at conception. And then over the arc
of our lives, we, the single cell, will divide as many as 50 times. And on the road to 50 divisions,
the cells that make us up will encounter some form of stress they cannot resolve. They will
pull an emergency brake and they will stop dividing forever. And we call this state,
when you do this, we call cells that do this a senescent cell. And this is something that we've,
we find these cells in all of the tissues we've examined. And these cells, they're a very small
number most of the time. Typically it's on the order of hovering around 1% or less. Now in some
disease states we have looked at that number is dramatically higher. And I'll talk about that a
little bit later. Children don't have these cells. Now they can make them, but they don't accumulate
and we don't know why, but as we age, these cells accumulate. Now, before the work of my
collaborators and my co-founders at the company I work at, no one knew if these
accumulating senescent cells were good for you, bad for you, or neither. And so my two co-founders,
and now almost a decade of collaborators, Judy Campisi at the Buck Institute and Jan
Vandersen at the Mayo Clinic, both of their laboratories genetically engineered mice,
where we could eliminate senescent cells from these animals whenever we want it.
And for the first time we got to ask what happens. And what happens is pretty eye popping. So normally
I carry this picture around on my iPhone, so I always show people this is what I work on, but
essentially by a podcast you have to use a little bit of imagination. So imagine two animals,
siblings, born within seconds of each other from the same mom. These are animals that are 24 months
old, so it's kind of equivalent to a 70 year old person. And one of these littermates is blind,
it's osteoporotic, it's frail, it has kidney dysfunction, it has cardiac dysfunction, it looks
visibly old. It's littermate from whom we eliminated senescent cells from midlife until it
dies. This animal lives on average about 30% longer, which is cool. But what's more awesome
than that is that when this animal dies and when it's similarly treated animals die, they die with
many of the features of aging either absent or reduced. And that is awesome. So we're trying
to do it unity, the company I work at. Now before you say something interesting you said, which is
they have this knockout of senescence that only occurs in midlife. No, what we do is we insert
into every cell of that animal's body, we genetically engineer the animals, so that we can administer a
drug weekly which kills senescent cells within that animal. But do you begin that administration
at midlife? And what happens if you begin that administration at birth? We have not done that
experiment in large part because we don't see senescent cells at birth. I see, is there a chance
that those animals would prematurely get cancer if we eradicated their ability to create stem cells
at the beginning of life? Didn't Judith have some data that suggested the importance of senescence
early on as a sort of break against cancer as well? So you bring up a really important
point that I should clarify. So whenever I tell people about this result, people often ask,
this is an important system. Why are you messing with it? So it turns out the ability to make
senescent cells is vitally important to our survival. So if you genetically engineer a mouse
that cannot make senescent cells, this animal is born normally. It's got 10 fingers and 10 toes,
but it statistically winds up full of tumors before it's in reproductive age. So it tells you
that this emergency break, the cellular senescent system, is an anti-cancer system. And you do not
want to mess with the emergency break. You have to leave it alone. And so in the experiment I
described where we eliminate these cells, we don't touch the break. We allow the break to pull
completely. And for the cell cycle to stop, we only show up after. Now, I think it's still a
reasonable question. You'd say, dude, it's like this is an anti-cancer system and you're kind
of screwing around with it. Are you sure this is okay? Let's take a step way back. So in medical
school, we spent all this time learning about different cellular insults. And perhaps the most
obvious one, and the one we could use as an example, is DNA damage. So when a cell's DNA is damaged,
presumably its first choice is, can I fix this? But if a cell's fate is such that it can't repair
its DNA, that's sort of when it has this bifurcated pathway of going down the pathway of apoptosis,
which means for the listener that it has a programmed form of cell death. So it basically
kills itself in a programmatic structured way. Or it goes down this pathway that you've described,
which is senescence, effectively saying, I will no longer do anything. I'm still alive,
but I don't grow anymore. I don't replicate. I don't reproduce anymore. My DNA is dysfunctional.
As we'll talk about, I suspect it still does things. It still secretes factors that wreak havoc.
But is that a fair assessment that I've just made of using an example of a cell with DNA
damage? Has that sort of choice? It does. And we don't understand how cells make the choice
between the two. I was going to ask you that. Do we have any sense of what sways that decision?
Well, I'll tell you some anecdotes. So what we do is we in the lab will irradiate cells or treat
them with a DNA damaging agent. These are both things that... Yeah, known things that destroy DNA.
So we have a setting on our irradiator, which does both. So it both causes cells to die.
And then 99% of the cells that remain will enter senescence. So you know that all those cells in
the dish got the same radiation. They're all the same clone of the cell. Yet some of them chose
death and some of them chose senescence. I think it's a really interesting question for us to try
to understand about why did some die and why did some live? Presumably it's driven by some
explicit cell state at the time. Is there a way post hoc to examine the DNA damage of the cells
that died and compared to the DNA damage of the cells that underwent senescence? Because presumably
the actual DNA damage is going to be stochastically distributed across those cells. And even though
they are the same cells receiving the same radiation, they probably undergo different
degrees of DNA damage. And could it be something as simple as if you damage this portion of the DNA,
you lose the ability to undergo apoptosis, but you still retain the ability to undergo
senescence or vice versa? Yeah, I mean, you have to be a little tricky because if you're... So
the challenge with asking cells that died, what happened is that it requires a bit of a cellular
seance. Okay. I have a cellular Ouija board. No, I'm just kidding. Yeah. Since we've been talking
about this, as I've been thinking creatively, there are these... There's moments on the order
of minutes to hours after the insult happens in which the cell is going through its pre-death
throws. And you still don't know which direction it's going to go? This is not something I've ever
seen studied. So this could be something that just outside of my personal experience, but I just
think about what we do every day in which we insult cells in an effort to make cells become
senescent, but a portion of them choose death. There's got to be a dozen postdocs thinking about
this problem, right? Yeah. You'd have to be in a hardcore apoptosis. The thing is, you'd want to be
in a apoptosis lab. I don't know who is actually working on this problem. It's a pretty interesting
problem though. I think the way you'd want to get at it would be, you might want to be looking
quantitatively. For example, if you had some sort of die that could tell you how much DNA damage a
cell got, you had some sort of high content imaging, and you could look down at a plate and say,
oh, these guys that accumulated in the minutes of radiation three times more of the... They
incorporated three times more of the die. These are the guys that chose death. You could do something
like that. And so then you don't need a seance. You just need somebody. It's kind of a, I guess,
it's more of like a cellular death watch. There's ways that you could start to get at that. It's
kind of cool. Sorry to take us off that track, but now let's focus on the guys that didn't
undergo apoptosis. So you've got all these cells that have undergone some insult and they've now
committed to sort of a celibate life. They're not going to reproduce anymore. And if they just left
it at that, it wouldn't be such a problem. It's this other thing they do that's problematic,
which is they sort of poison the well for cells around them that are otherwise not damaged. Is
that a fair assessment of senescence? That is. So in fact, early on in the history of this field,
which we can get into in a little bit, it was a real theoretical problem. How could something
that's 1% of your cells damage the function of 99% of your cells? Well, as it turns out,
these cells have a very active secreter that my co-founder Judy Campisi discovered in 2008. And
it's, this is the means by which these cells exert bad biology. They secrete into the micro environment
around them all this crap that distorts tissue function. And that is how these cells contribute
both to features of natural aging as well as very particular diseases of aging is via the
secreter called the SASP, which stands for senescence associated secretory phenotype. And I know it's a
mouthful, but well, SASP is pretty cool. Yeah. And so it's really a paracrine feature. So in medicine,
we learn about endocrine versus paracrine versus exocrine features. But paracrine is when a gland
can actually secrete its hormone. And it goes directly to the tissue that it's operating on
without having to even pass through the circulation and go around like the way, for example,
insulin, when it's secreted by the pancreas becomes systemic, but this paracrine effect is to secrete
it and poison your neighbor right next to you. And I guess your point now explains why if you
don't have the ability to undergo senescence, that would be bad because you take all those cells that
are damaged that for whatever reason, don't choose the apoptotic pathway are now, they should be
celibate, but they're not and they keep reproducing. And that's why you might be born looking normal,
but as you accumulate injury and insult, boom, you're going to develop into tumors. But that's
very different from saying, we're going to let you undergo senescence, but we might potentially
block your ability to cause toxicity after the fact or other means of targeting those cells.
I mean, there's many ways to do this, but yeah. Well, let me just go back to this whole thing,
which is that cancer thing. So we know that if you can't make cells become senescent, you
dramatically increase tumors in mice. And that's a powerful lesson about what not to do,
which is don't mess with the underlying biology here. Showing up after, however, is a pretty cool
idea. And the fact that this paper, and I'll come back to how I got involved in all this, but
the fact that eliminating these cells can produce a series of youth effects while not increasing
cancer risk was very awesome. And it was actually kind of a theoretical validation of the picture
in our minds about how this was all working. So it might be useful to actually sort of at this
moment, sort of talk a little bit about the history of where this actually all came from.
And then we'll come back to what we're doing with this now and how we're making medicines based on
it. But I think it's always helpful to place what you're doing in historical context. So this whole
idea of cellular senescence traces itself back to the early 1960s. There was a very clever guy
named Leonard Hayflick, who I've actually had the pleasure of meeting very randomly on an airplane.
But at the time in the early 1960s, it was widely believed that cells from us, from mammals,
could have infinite capacity to divide. And this was made famous by Alexis Carell, who goes back
decades before that. The leaders in the field all believed this. And it turns out this was the
result of the fact that the food that was being fed to these cells, which was derived from chickens,
was contaminated with chicken cells. So every time cells were fed food, they were also fed
other cells. And it gave this impression that these cells were dividing forever. And this Leonard
Hayflick showed up and... And for someone listening who's listening to this thinking,
how can years, decades of dogma come from such sloppiness? It is important to understand that
they're basically relying on light microscopes. Today, you wouldn't make that mistake because
you'd be able to look at the DNA of the different cells and realize that, hey, these are chicken
cells, those are mouse cells, et cetera. But it's a beautiful example of both how far biology has
come, but also how the simplest mistakes can lead to catastrophic misinterpretation. I write about
this in my book, this story. And I remember the first time I came across it like you, I was sort
of like... My first thought was, how the hell is that possible? But then upon further reflection,
you're imposing too much of your current worldview on the problem.
Yeah, I think it's important to show a little bit of compassion as you have by pointing out
the limitations of their technology at the time and the context that they were living in. What's
funny is I will report an interesting mistake that turns out we ordered from ATCC what we thought
were mouse cells and they were rat. And as a consequence, they weren't behaving properly.
This is about a year ago. So these types of things are still happening.
So Hayflick turns over this 60 year belief basically.
And so he published this paper in 1961 and it's pretty heretical. And he coins this term,
he said, he calls them senescent cells, meaning cells that lose the ability to divide in culture.
And he says something very prophetic. He says, this may contribute to features of aging.
Isn't that sort of like Watson and Crick's DNA?
Yeah, the thing about it does suggest a means for replication.
The most understated.
Yeah, exactly. Which I love these things. Here's the great story is that when I ran into Leonard
Hayflick at the Portland airport, having gotten off the plane, I pull out my phone and I show him,
he's very old now, and I show him a picture of the mice with and without senescent cells,
the term he functionally coined. And I said, this is what happened when we delete these cells
that you said may cause aging. And it was just a mind warp for him. He hadn't heard of the paper
at the time. The paper had been out for six years. He was very old. Then his daughter walks up who
lives in Portland. And she thinks you're accosting him or something. No, it was immediately clear
that we were your fans. Exactly. We were fanboys. And I show her the picture and I said, this is
where your dad's work went. She was like, oh my God. And then she turns to her dad and said,
dad, you realize what this is, right? And so there was this moment. It was one of these great
moments where you get to see this person who really architected this major insight in biology,
confronted with the historical result right to his face and watching him trying to process it all.
It was pretty neat. Anyway, so that's the kind of the backstory of where this all came from.
Now flash forward decades. Now, Judy Campisi was the first individual to find a marker that we
could look at in vivo. This was about 1995. So you could actually figure out because senescence
was something that you did in plates, like plastic plates in an incubator. But it was
Judy who figured out the first biomarker where you go into a living creature into a tissue and say,
aha, there are senescent cells. It was the first time we got to know how many there are, right?
It's not a lot. And her work really asked, it raised this larger question, which I mentioned
earlier, which is how can so few cells do so much bad for so many cells? And it wasn't until 2008
when Judy described for the first time this thing that I mentioned earlier called the SASP, the so
called senescence associated secretory phenotype that are how these cells exert bad stuff. And it's
over a hundred factors that have been characterized that these cells make now that drive their negative
biology. Now, it turns out that a lot of what we know about the SASP was all figured out in cell
culture and plastic. And what we've been working on the last eight years is doing a lot of this
more in vivo. And it turns out the SASP is very different in different tissues. It turns out to
be very different from different cells within those tissues and different disease states.
Give folks some of the, I mean, I know there are so many of the SASPs, but what's a handful of
things that they have in their playbook? How do they sort of wreak this havoc on their peers?
So if you look at the sort of the totality of the SASP, everything that's been labeled a SASP
factor, what you will see are kind of usual suspects of badness. Okay. So things like TNF alpha,
which is the target of the most successful drug in the world today, you know, Humira,
it's an anti TNF drug. You see a factor like veg F alpha, the target of things like Lucentis
and ILEA multi multi billion dollar drugs for the treatment of diseases of the eye and also
using cancer, but that's a sort of a separate thing. So those are both SASP factors that are
the targets of existing massive drugs. There's also some SASP factors that have been clinically
validated. So there's one called CTGF, which if you make an antibody against that, you have
efficacy in a rare lung disease. That's pro-fibrotic that we now know is driven by senescence.
And that's not a marketed drug yet, but it makes the same point, which is antibody.
But we're taking a step back from this. I mean, let's put some broader strokes on this.
Inflammation would result from SASP, right? So there's lots of things that go out there that
basically tell immune cells, Hey, let's recruit you to this area. You mentioned fibrosis. What
other types of broad destructive categories of things go on out there? And I'm fascinated by
this work because it's just a little counterintuitive. I totally get the, and again, this is
just my need to teleologicalize everything if that's even a word, but it totally makes sense
why senescence exists. It's a little harder for me to accept the breadth of its destructive capacity
to its peers. My general thinking about teleological discussions. I know you and I could debate this
all night long, which is get over it. Yeah. Because these things are not testable,
any teleological explanation should be evaluated solely on its entertainment value. Okay. Right.
But that's not why we're here. I will say that there's an idea that is also teleological, but
which I use and is a framework that I think is helpful. So many things that we see in aging
biology in particular, they're kind of head scratchers. Like, why is the system doing this?
This seems bad for the individual. Didn't evolution get a vote? Isn't that the whole
point of evolution? Well, it turns out that features of aging are manifest post reproductively.
Oh yeah. No, no. I don't think there's going to be an evolutionary explanation for this for
exactly that reason. So is your argument that this occurred, call it stochastically,
and evolution was never there to fix it or catch it. So it's just a random muck?
No, it's actually something it's a cooler idea. So it turns out these decisions, if you want to
call them that these seemingly irrational decisions made by evolution, of course, evolution doesn't
make decisions. It's a votes with the survival of a species to reproduce or an organism to reproduce.
Many of these so-called decisions are things which benefit the young.
Yeah. So it's basically, let's get the post reproductive folks out of the way to
conserve resources for the young. I don't think anything so active or sort of sinister. I think
mostly it's, let's take cellular senescence, for example, it's an awesome mechanism to block tumor
formation in young, reproductively competent organisms. So if you can make more of those
organisms to make more babies, I guess I'm not arguing the senescence, it's the SASP that I'm
struggling with. Right. Well, so it turns out this is interesting. So it turns out the SASP does some
other things that are useful. So a paper published by Judy Campisi again, and Marco DiMaria,
who is a professor in the Netherlands now, they got interested in wound healing. And what they
demonstrated was that if you make a wound in an animal, a week or two after you make a laceration
wound at the wound site, you will see an accumulation of senescent cells. And they are dumping SAS
factors into the wound. And the question Judy and Marco asked was, is this important? And so in this
experiment, they went in and they eliminated senescent cells in the course of wound healing. And
what they saw was that the wound closed less well, and more slowly. And it suggested that the SASP
had another role wasn't just well, the SASP, this is a role for the SASP here. Its role was to
facilitate wound closure, which if you think about it for most organisms in a naturally evolving
ecosystem is super fricking important. And so essentially senescence got co-opted into
suppressing tumors in one case, and in a very different case was co-opted into helping heal
wound. And so I think that what you see in these diseases of aging is often the sort of
unintended consequences of a system that was absolutely awesome for the young at the expense
of the old. One metaphor for this that I sort of like is that, let's say you innocently write a
computer program to fill your bathtub. It also unintentionally becomes a computer program designed
to overflow your apartment. It wasn't why you wrote it, but it is the net effect.
Yeah, no, that's an interesting point. Certainly, things that favor wound healing could be quite
beneficial. Some have even argued that LpA, lipoprotein, apolipoproteinA, which is attached
to an LDL, so it makes this thing called LpA, has very potent prothrombotic properties. And even
though it's wildly atherosclerotic, you could argue, well, frankly, that's a very favorable
phenotype to carry for most of our evolution. It's only recently that we need to concern
ourselves with atherosclerosis, but there was certainly an era where having a prothrombotic
factor to help you in periods of trauma would far outweigh the tail effect of knocking off a few
elders who managed to survive and die of aortic stenosis or atherosclerosis. So that's an
interesting tidbit with respect to the wound stuff. I wasn't aware of that.
By the way, the other example of this LpA is a perfect comparator to the whether or not either
of these teleological explanations matters not. The point is that those are the same logic.
So let's go back to something you said at the outset, which you've now given us enough to put
in context. You said, look, you went on this journey of thinking through final common pathways
of aging. You arrived at this mTOR-CR thing probably matters a whole heck of a lot. In fact,
it seems to be the only one that works across organisms, across labs, no ifs, ands, or buts.
You've got this loss of circulating youth factors. Clearly, something is happening to mitochondria
as we age that is very problematic. We clearly see this observation of methylation, whether it's
causal or not, is unclear. We get a sense of what's happening to stem cells, exhausting, and
senescent cells. Your view, which you very briefly touched on, is the first four things I mentioned
are probably harder to drug than the last one. Is that a fair summation of how you arrived at this?
Yeah, that's how I wound up focusing the last eight years of what myself and my colleagues have
been working on was that. It was how do we make medicines that target a fundamental mechanism of
aging? I was not clever enough or knowledgeable enough, or both, to figure out how to do mTOR
and CR. I mean, there are a lot of people who are trying that by trying to get more and more
selective molecules, but it was not an area where I had anything creative to add. But the
backstory of how I kind of got involved in this was I was sitting around actually in the Calgary
Airport. A lot of these important things are happening in airports, okay, for some reason.
And I was eating french fries. And in this 20-minute interval of french fry consumption,
five different people sent me the same PDF, and they were subject lines like,
holy shit, you have to read this. This has to be your next company. And I opened up the paper,
and right on the front page was a figure showing these two animals, siblings, one of which had
senescence cells, the other one. These are the mice you talked about earlier. Yes. This was
Jan or this was Judy. Were they collaborating at the time? They were collaborating, though. Judy
was not on this particular paper. And this paper was not exactly the same mice I described. So it
had a very similar or the same means of senescence cell elimination, but there was a difference.
This is 2011. These animals also contained a mutation where they made less, far less,
of a protein called BubR1, which is an anaphase checkpoint protein. So this is a protein that
makes sure that your chromosomes line up on the spindle and it sort of is like a bit of a school
master. It sort of says, you're not dividing until everything's lined up. And so if you don't have
BubR1, you just blow right through the checkpoint and you become polyploid. And Jan van der Senn,
my other co-founder and long-term collaborator, he created this animal thinking this animal was going
to get tons of cancer because he was a cancer researcher. So let's just make sure we understand
why that's the case. If BubR1 is there to make sure your spindles line up, it means that you
should not be able to divide until all your chromatin is perfectly aligned. Everything is
in perfect tip top order and you're ready to undergo mitosis. That's right. So if you take away
your master, a lot of faulty division should follow. That's correct. So Jan's hypothesis is
we either attenuate or knock out BubR1, we should get a lot of cancer. That's right. Okay. What
happened? That wasn't what happened. The animals were super polyploid, meaning that they wound up
with super weird numbers of chromosomes, too many, too few, all that good stuff. The animals aged
quickly. So the animals wound up full of senescent cells. Okay. So there was something about having
very wrong numbers of chromosomes and all of the effects of that that caused the animals to be full
of senescent cells and to age very rapidly, have features of aging that were on set very rapidly
and die. So it accelerated the speed with which the record played, but it didn't change the music.
In other words, they didn't die sooner because they got cancer. They just died sooner because
they sped up their aging. We don't know the answer to that. So these animals are extremely sick
animals. So trying to make a larger statement, I think it's too much to say with an animal like that
of the whole record metaphor. What I can say with, I think conviction is that clearly a whole bunch
of things that go along with being old happened very quickly in these animals. And these animals
die very quickly. They look visibly old. For me, it was an experiment that suggested that
it was consistent with the notion that the senescent cells were actually driving these
features of aging. And what's so cool about this paper and why it caught so many people's attention,
even though there was a somewhat earlier paper that Jan Alsud did that for many allowed one to
draw the same inference, but it just didn't smell like a drug. I won't get into that paper today,
but what was so compelling was that you added senescent cells through this mutation that gave
rise to the production of less bub R1 protein. And then you eliminated those cells or a subset of
those cells with this insert into the DNA of every cell of that animal. And you could ameliorate
a subset of the effects of senescent cells. Now you didn't get rid of all the senescent cells.
By the way, interestingly, the animals don't live longer in that particular mutant because it's so
sick when you eliminate the cells, but a whole bunch of the features of aging, for example,
their bent spines, their organ atrophy, their cataracts in their eyes. These were all severely
blunted when the senescent cells were eliminated. And when I saw this paper, I thought this feels
like a drug. You just eliminate cells that are driving bad things. And so I contacted Jan and
Mayo Clinic and 72 hours later we had agreed to meet and a little time after that I set up the
company. But this was a observation in a mutant animal. And I remember the sort of early blogosphere
talking about how this paper didn't mean anything. And this was exaggerating the role of senescence
in humans and it's a mouse and all this stuff. But to me it really felt important. Now it was a
long way between that paper and when you could ever credibly claim there could be a drug discovery
program based on it. And we spent the next four years in stealth mode asking for biological
questions. And I had some very patient investors who gave us sort of a spoon fed or dropper fed
money into the company. We did not have lots of excess resources, but I will confess that some of
the best times in my life have been under resource constraint because your decision making is very
high quality because every single resource decision matters. So we had four questions we
were trying to ask an answer. And the first question and none of this stuff got answered in
the first 2011 paper was do senescent cells contribute to natural aging as opposed to some
genetically contrived mouse. Second question, could we find a disease, any human disease that we could
model in an animal where we could eliminate senescent cells and take that disease and either
stop it or even better send it backwards. Third question, could we find a molecule that could
trigger the elimination of senescent cells from a living creature safely? And last question,
which is, was getting rid of these cells safe? We know that kids don't have them, but that doesn't
mean that getting rid of them from an adult, like what if adults need them for some reason when kids
don't. So that was a formal question that really was on our minds. Now today I look at question four
and realize that it's not an equivalence between children and adults because of the following
reason. We know that if you prevent kids from being able to make them horrible things happen,
we don't know that if kids make them and you nuke them, horrible things happen, which is what
you're trying to do with adults, correct? We don't know that. Those could be two different things.
Yeah. So kids naturally nuke them. So we know kids can make them because you can do experiments
in young animals and they make senescent cells and then senescent cells are gone. So in effect,
that is your living breathing experiment right there. That's right. The superpower of kids is
the ability to make them, which prevents the replication of a cell that shouldn't replicate.
And then it has the good sense to get rid of it before it harms anyone. The adult retains the
ability to make it, but keeps it around. I want to go back to your second question. It seems obvious
now. Your second question, just for the listener, if I recall was, could we find the right disease
in which to study this? Could we find any disease? Because if you think about it, that first mouse,
oh, the first and second mouse experiments that John did both 2008 and then 2011 publications in
nature, those weren't diseases the way. Right. They were sort of poly death conditions. Well,
they were sort of like this animal has these features of being old. They weren't things that
the FDA would label a disease like a bent spine, like who's going to develop a drug for that?
But your intuition was, of course, you can't study lifespan here. It has to be health span related
because if you have an interest in taking this to humans, mortality is a very difficult endpoint.
Yeah. That's not the way we develop drugs. I mean, unless you're tackling conditions that
kill people quickly, mortality is a reasonable endpoint for cancer and heart disease drugs.
Sure. So in fact, I would even make us even ruthlessly more practical. We wanted to find
very diseases of being old diseases, things that the FDA has regulatory paths for and
endpoints that you can get drugs approved on. And so we wanted to do that. And that's what we did.
So tell me about number one. Number one, again, we take that for granted today,
but it was a very reasonable question eight years ago, right?
Yeah. So again, Jan van der Zent to the rescue here.
So Ned, at this point, it's just you and Jan and Judy.
So it was myself, Jan van der Zent, Judy Campisi, and a guy named Da Hong Jo, who helped us discover
one of the early synthetic molecules. Also, Darren Baker, who's a professor at tomato clinic,
was also instrumental. He was first author on the 2011 paper. And he also was the first author on
the paper I'm about to describe as it relates to question one, which is how did we figure out that
senescence was driving features of natural aging? And so that was what Darren Baker and Jan van
der Zent spent the next few years after 2011 doing. And that paper took five years before
published in 2016. And what they did in this paper was they took natural mice, mostly natural,
they contain one difference was we mated into natural mice, that same construct, that piece of
DNA that was wound up in every cell of their body. So we could eliminate senescence cells whenever we
want it. And so now we got to do that in a very slow multi year experiment. But these were naturally
aging creatures. And that paper took as a half decade to happen. And when we got that result,
which was in 2016, we managed to also ask the other three questions by then. But that was really the
trigger for us de-stealthing the effort and speaking openly about what we were doing. Because
if it didn't contribute to natural aging, and it didn't cause a particular disease of aging,
and we couldn't find molecules, there was no company. So you basically were processing question
one, and 234 in parallel. That's correct. We had a small team was a relatively virtual for a few
years, we were just living at arch the venture fund. And then we moved and we got too big,
we moved up to the Buck Institute. So we were camped out right over Judy's lab, or a floor up
and a few doors over. No pun intended. Yeah. And we essentially went to town with a small group,
it was just a few people supported very intimately by Jan's group, with Darren's support and with
Judy's group. And so we had this sort of virtual research group where every week we'd get together
and review all the data for each of the four questions. And we had work streams for each of
questions one through four. And it was a great time. So I want to kind of pause on this journey
and take a parallel or orthogonal journey for a moment, because I suspect that at least one
person listening and likely more also have some sort of entrepreneurial bent in them. And as it
pertains to biology or biotechnology, I think I'd love to figure out a way to extract from you
some of the lessons that you've learned along the way. You've done this over and over and over again
in many companies. And I'm just sort of wondering what, well, let's start with a broad question.
You've already alluded to the fact that you enjoyed that period of time, right? It was really
less of a company and more of a lab at that point. It was sort of a virtual postdoc that you guys were
doing. Yeah. It was a coalition of the willing doing an incredibly hard project. And it was far
more likely that we were going to fail than succeed. Well, that's actually the question
I wanted to pose to you. So we don't talk enough about sort of what the graveyard looks like of
these ideas gone wrong. It's quite possible that 2011 to 2016, you spent all of that time working
on something and it didn't work. In fact, that would be the expected outcome of this type of
endeavor. But that said, no one goes into something with a belief that it's going to fail. Without
getting too much into the rose colored glasses that inevitably bias our ability to look back,
what proof points did you look to to say there's a biological plausibility here that if it wasn't
there would have had you less likely to consider it. And if you can, Ned, try to answer it in a broad
enough way that it would be applicable to other endeavors that maybe don't deal with senescent
cells. In other words, I'm asking this through the lens of somebody who's considering finishing their
lab or finishing their time in their lab or even graduating from undergrad and wanting to join a
company, how can they think through handicapping the odds of success, which you've done a number
of times. So the approach I take to a bold idea like this idea of making drugs that eliminates
senescent cells is I try to picture, it's a simple, beautiful idea. I try to picture the end state.
Like what does this look like at the end? And then I say, okay, I can see this in my mind. And then
I say, well, what are the existential risks to that beautiful, simple dream? And I try to write
them down in the most primitive way I can. And so those four questions, they were the four risks,
which is that senescent cells don't contribute to natural aging. I'll use this particular example,
and I'll back out in a sec. That was a risk. They don't contribute to natural aging. They don't
cause a particular disease of aging. You can never find a molecule to eliminate or eliminating the
ones that are not safe. And those were the four risks we came up with. And you can apply this
risk to a beautiful, simple idea in any technological endeavor that I've been involved in.
What's nice about that is one of those is a very clear market risk. Three of those are biologic or
technology risks. Your second question is actually a market risk question. In other words, if number
one worked, so if number one is this absolutely explains natural aging, if number three was true,
you could come up with a molecule that could block it. And number four was true, you could do so
safely, but there was no way there was a regulatory pathway that was going to allow you to go from A
to B because hook spine disease was never going to show up on the FDA's list of druggable things
to think about. It's not to say that it couldn't work, but now you've taken on an enormous regulatory
risk that would be almost crushing to any one company. So what I'm hearing you say is embedded
in your questions was actually a very thoughtful risk analysis that reverse engineered success.
I think so. It turned out to be a good way for us to focus ourselves. How long did it take you guys
to come up with those four questions? Because it was just five of you if I did my math right.
There was a few orbiting. So my long-term business partner, Keith Leonard, he was at the time
we'd founded a previous company together and he was still being the CEO of that company where I'd
previously been the chief science officer, but he was involved in this and a few other just very
smart people that I will pull into these things. I need very simple thinkers for this sort of thing
because you must in a very disciplined way distill out to these primitive risks that can animate
behavior over many years. They have to be durable. If you can summon the discipline and
the simplicity to distill the next say four to five years of your life down to call it two to
four risks, because any more than that and your life gets too complicated. And then you can build
work plans that systematically remove each of those risks or do not remove them. But at least
identify them. Yeah, identify them and then build plans. Everything we did at the company
for four years, everything was those four risks. That was it. And the money we raised was pretty
paltry at the time. It was all budgeted around those four risks. And whenever I go after a new
thing, I always try to just go back to that simple, beautiful idea and then say, can I write down the
risks to this beautiful idea? Then you build plans from them and then you build budgets and then you
politely ask people for money, which by the way, almost no one would provide because this idea
seems relatively preposterous at the time. The people that stepped forward were people like Bob
Nelson from Arch, who has been a visionary across decades of biotech. And it was he who when I
explained this to him very rapidly said, yeah, let's do this. There are some other people at
Arch like Christina Burrow who was very supportive early on. So that really was the prime anchor
early on in the life of the company and animated all of our behavior. And that was four years of
my life. How long did it take you guys to define those questions now? Because the way you rattled
them off, they're so logical, they're so obvious. But my guess is those were not immediately
apparent to you in 2011, that those were the four things that had to be wrestled to the ground.
No, we kind of did know them. Really? Yeah. So it's funny, I recently went through the early,
I was looking through some old files and I found an old PowerPoint where there was six risks.
And it was clear that we'd done some kind of pruning down to the most primitive because I'm
kind of a tyrant when it comes down to like, we must have the simplest plan sort of thing.
So there had been some pruning, but I know that we initially generated the list of a half dozen or
so. And then over a period of weeks, I think we managed to just in a disciplined way,
shear them down to this relatively streamlined plan. Now, did you learn this the hard way? Was
there a time when you went down the path of trying to do something, lacked this discipline,
and found yourself sort of looking back sometime later thinking we wasted time,
we wasted money. We didn't pursue this as linearly as we could have.
Absolutely. No one really taught me this. This is something I sort of learned a bit on the fly,
kind of in the eras in which I was building companies like Okeijin and Kaitheira. So those
were all early 2000s. So Okeijin was 2003, Kaitheira was around 2005. My first company,
which I founded my last year of graduate school, we were strategy free. This was a high throughput
structural biology company called Sieriks. And we never had any of these intellectual tools.
And so these were tools that were really developed through feeling as though we wasted time,
which is your most valuable resource. And you wasted people's money, which was also valuable
resource. And the net effect of this has been now this disciplined streamlining of idea and risk.
Yeah, so it's something that just picked up over time. And now it's reflexive. And
everybody in my group, everyone thinks this way. And so whenever a new thing comes up, immediately
everyone goes to the board and starts writing out risks, and then starts writing out, well,
this is the de-risking plan for this, this, and this. And okay, that means it's 18 months,
and this is kind of the budget. Do you think that that type of thinking is productive or
counterproductive in academia? It's clearly productive in industry. If you tomorrow decided,
I want to go back and start a lab and go back to Berkeley and apply for a grant. Would you
encourage your graduate students and postdocs to think that way? Or would you modify the thinking
slightly? I would be modified. But I think there is kind of value to this. I think in any setting
where you have a problem or a technological thing you're trying to solve, which is being explicit
about the failure modes, even if you're in an academic setting. And I'm speaking specifically
of biology or something akin to it. Like I can't talk to you about math or something,
because I think it drives a certain degree of honesty when things are failing. So you know what
to see. And so if you're looking out for this isn't working, this isn't working, and only this
is working, and all three have to work for this project to go, you can make a go no go decision
in an academic setting and pivot to another project because there's no end of creative
ideas that you could be working on. They're limitless. And so the important thing is to
conserve your most valuable resource, which is your time. And so I encourage my academic friends,
some of whom listen and some of whom do not, to think similarly and to take a sort of portfolio
approach to academic projects, which is it's okay to prosecute this question for 18 months, but
there are certain things we want to have in 18 months. And if you do not have them,
we make a formal go no go decision. Meanwhile, you had two other projects going. And so what
you need is only one to raise its hand and say, I'm working.
Yeah, that was super helpful. Let's go back to kind of, you now have the answer to these four
questions. Is it safe to say there are still a number of ways to do this? In other words,
if you know that senescence is a natural part of aging, if you know that there are specific
diseases for which it plays a role, if you know that there are molecules that can be developed
that can target it, and you know that it can be done safely, that third question really has many
heads. You can have molecules that kill senescent cells, you could have molecules that target the
factors they secrete, presumably there are other ways you could machinate around this. Had you
fixated early on, you alluded to it that killing cells is something we really know how to do pretty
well in biology. Was that the path you guys run from the beginning? Or was that a pivot?
Early on, we honored the possibility that we could either eliminate the cells, because that's what
was achieved genetically, and was our proof of concept. But we could also come up with ways to
reduce the pathological sass that these cells were creating. It wasn't so much as a pivot,
but a decision to go one way rather than the other. Because in the beginning, we thought you
could do either. And the decision was driven by a simple idea, which is that were you to make
molecules that would simply suppress the secretions of the cells, but not remove the source of all of
these factors, you'd have a drug you had to take all the time. And the cool thing about eliminating
senescence- And it also assumes you know all the factors. Your approach strikes me as the more
logical approach, but there are companies doing the other approach, correct? Yeah, well, you could
take the position that any antibody therapeutic against one of these pro-inflammatories in the
SASP is just such an approach. But actually, I was saying something a little bit more-
I understand your point though.
Primordial. I was suggesting, if you understood, for example, the regulatory mechanism that makes
the cell decide to secrete all of these factors, and you targeted that, then hey, what you've done
is you've shut down the secretion, the cells sit in there not dividing, how bad can it be?
But what motivated us was this would be a drug you would have to take all the time. And what we
thought was so neat about the idea of making a molecule that could eliminate senescent cells,
which we then named, we called them senolytic molecules, if you could make a senolytic molecule,
you could dose it once. And once you eliminate senescent cells, the cells are not there anymore.
So these are not drugs you take every day, every week, or every month, these might be dosed once a
year until your body makes more senescent cells. And in fact, which maybe we can talk about later,
in our human clinical data, what we show is that when we eliminate senescent cells
from the painful knee joint of a human being with osteoarthritis, a single administration
of a senolytic medicine, eliminates pain dramatically in these humans for as long as
we've looked. And so the cells, we don't know if the cells have come back, but we don't think
they've come back by that time. This sort of validates the notion that you can now have a
drug that's far safer because what kills most drugs actually is the fact that they're unsafe.
That generally is a result of treatment again and again and again. If you don't have to do that,
if you can go in once, surgically eliminate the cells, I mean, surgically, metaphorically here,
it's not surgical. You can make a safer drug, at least theoretically. And that's why we went
that direction. So there's another big challenge here, which is how do you identify which cells
are the senescent cells in vivo when you don't have the luxury you've had in the animal lab,
which is you get to label those cells, you get to put big targets on them. What was the proof of
concept that you could go into an organism and without the luxury of having the senescent cells
raise their hand and say, here we are metaphorically, actually send out snipers to get them.
Deep profiling of human tissues for senescence exists, but it's few and far between. And so
we undertook a study and this is after we demonstrated in animals that osteoarthritis,
which is the second most prevalent disease of aging and the primary reason it hurts to be old.
What's the first, by the way? Type 2 diabetes. Interesting. So what we did is we knew from
animals that if we could induce surgical trauma to an animal's knee, a mouse, and we eliminated
senescent cells, that we could eliminate pain and actually repair cartilage in a mouse.
Wait a second. That's counterintuitive. I know. That's what's so cool. Well,
it's counterintuitive because of the experiment you shared with me earlier that Judith's group did.
I think it was Judith's group that did this looking at wound healing. You would think if senescent
cells were necessary for wound healing, they would be necessary for the non-pathologic healing of
cartilage following surgical trauma. And they may be. So our theory about what's going on in
osteoarthritis, and this is just one of the ideas we entertain here. And I can explain what data we
have that supports this notion is that senescent cells accumulate at sites of osteoarthritis.
In fact, they may be trying to heal. Got it. But unlike in the skin, they literally fall off
in the context of healing, the cells remain and essentially continue to sound the alarm
over and over and over again. And we think it could be giving a sort of flawed attempt at wound
healing that could be driving the pathophysiology of disease. And the margin for error, sorry to
interrupt, is much smaller in a joint. In other words, you don't have to heal a wound perfectly
to achieve a functional outcome that is perfect. You might not have a cosmetically perfect outcome,
but functionally, you could have a hypertrophic scar, you could have a keloid, you could have
this, you could have that, but you've closed the barrier to the outside world. But inside of a
joint, it's a very delicate balance of one cell layer too many. And all of a sudden you have a
different outcome than you had prior to the insult. Coupled with everything you said,
I mean, that's all of these things factor together, I suppose.
So what we were able to show in animals was that when we induced trauma by cutting the ACL,
which is known to be risk factor for human osteoarthritis of the knee, we got something
that looked like osteoarthritis and we eliminated senescent cells either genetically
or with our drug, which we've now taken into human beings, we could, in this trauma induced
setting. And sorry, that genetic mouse, just to be sure, that's a mouse that has a genetic
tag for senescent cells that's easy to turn off. That's correct. Okay. One aside question,
is there a mouse model of osteoarthritis that comes from overweight or obesity?
No. Is that the most common cause of osteoarthritis in humans? It's a comorbidity. I'm not aware that
anyone's established causality, but it would make some sense that it could be causal because of
weight-bearing this. Interesting. So the animal model for osteoarthritis is an ACL injury, which
is still true in humans, but it's- There are a few different models for osteoarthritis. And so
really, one of the things we've learned is that when you attempt to model disease, there are lots
of off the shelf models that people have built for things like osteoarthritis because they're
making a painkiller. So they do things like hurt the animal's knee and then give it a painkiller.
How relevant is that to osteoarthritis in a human? It's not. You inject iodoacetate into the joint.
It hurts like hell, and then you give them painkillers. So we had to search around for
models that happened fast because that's the way we do experiments in which senescence played a
role in the ACLT model. So this was work we did collaboratively with Jennifer Elisif, who's a
professor at Johns Hopkins of bioengineering. And she was someone, an old friend, and she'd been
thinking about osteoarthritis and had the model in her lab. And I called her up one day and I said,
we have this crazy idea. We think that senescent cells could be driving this disease. Do you want
to try to figure this out with us? And she was an awesome collaborator. Some of the first
senolytic molecules we found, we shared with her and she had her model in operation. And very
quickly in her laboratory, we were able to demonstrate the senolytic molecules that we
had identified at the Buck Institute in Judy's group. One of them was active in Jennifer's model
of osteoarthritis. And so for the first time, we actually had a disease, a human disease,
the second most prevalent disease of aging. The primary reason it hurts to be old, I can't
overstate that enough. It's like being in pain sucks and this is the reason old people are in
pain mostly. And we could drive that disease backwards in a mouse. So we were just overjoyed
by this because we could achieve it genetically, which says it's really senescent cells. And the
second thing is we could also achieve the same result with a drug-like molecule. It was the
confluence of those two results that convinced us, this is really cool. It seems that we got the idea
right. How does the drug actually target the senescent cell when you don't have the luxury
of a genetic tag? We spent the first, remember that was question three of the big four questions.
We spent the first two and a half years of this whole effort searching fruitlessly and not finding
a senolytic molecule. And the first molecule we identified followed swiftly by the second,
and then a series of others that were very related to the second one. The first molecule
we identified was a MDM2 P53 interaction inhibitor. And so normally MDM2 is this
ubiquitin ligase. So it walks around and it's like a meter maid who goes around marking cars
with chalk for getting a parking ticket. But what MDM2 does is it walks around and it marks proteins
with a little molecule called ubiquitin and it marks them for destruction. And P53 is one of its
client proteins. And so if you break up the interaction between MDM2 and P53, P53 doesn't
get marked for destruction. So it's concentration in the cell goes up. And discovered in Judy's lab
by a few people, including Remy Marten-LaBerge, who was a postdoc in Judy's lab at the time,
he discovered that when you did this to senescent cells, senescent cells died preferentially.
By the way, is there anything on the outside of a senescent cell that identifies it?
There are some things on the inside and we've been searching.
But it's not like you have an antibody or anything that would render it externally identified.
We are searching now and we don't have any universal external marker of senescent cells.
We do have some that we just haven't talked about openly yet in various disease states where the
senescent cells in a disease state have a marker that's on the outside. We've not found and people
like Ned Sharpless have been searching for over a decade for such a marker.
Wow. So just to add to the complexity of the biology, if you were on a little mini nano
spaceship and you were inside the joint of a person with osteoarthritis, you wouldn't be
able to look out and see which of the cells are actually senescent and which ones are
normal, which ones are simply injured. You wouldn't be able to make that distinction.
So even if you had a special gun to shoot senescent cells, you wouldn't know which cells
to shoot based on just the observation of the cell.
Optically, no. Now, if you had a little bit of a sniffer, eyes would not be useful if you were
very small. A nose, however, would be useful. So if you could just sort of swim up the gradient
of pro-inflammatory and pro-fibrotic markers, you would find yourself.
You'd find your source.
Yeah. Right. So I do think that the little mini spaceship things often very
illuminating to think about biology. I use that a lot.
Your drug then targets P53.
Oh, that's right. Yeah. So, so P53 goes up in these cells. So it doesn't target P53. It actually
binds on the MDM2 side, thereby kicking,
Relieving.
Yeah. Yeah. So, okay.
And then, so P53 goes up in concentration. The senescent cells die selectively. And then,
and this turned out to work very well in our trauma osteoarthritis models. And another very
cool result, and this is something else that Jennifer did wound up in our Nature paper,
our Nature Medicine paper in 2017, was Jennifer got knees from patients undergoing total knee
arthroplasty. So these are people that don't need their knees anymore because they're getting a
metal one. And she would take the cartilage at the site of the osteoarthritic lesion,
and she would digest out the exocerular matrix. And she'd take the cells, the cells that actually
make your cartilage, and she would grow them in 3D culture. And she would either expose those
little blobs of baby cartilage to either vehicle or our drug that's now in phase two clinical
trials in humans. And she observed something awesome, which is that exposure to the drug
eliminated senescent cells that were very prevalent from this site of damage.
You talked earlier about how you might see one to two percent senescent cells in an organism,
but when you talk about a very local spot of damage like that, how highly concentrated were they?
So it's a little hard because I'll tell you a slightly different number because
the cartilage stuff, so basically it's very, there are a lot of them at the site where you
have the osteoarthritic injury and you go millimeters away and then it drops way down.
So it's more puncta of it in that setting. If you look at the synovial membrane, which is,
I'll talk to you about another study we did in humans where we actually counted
senescent cells in patients with osteoarthritis, the number hovers around one to two percent,
even in patients with osteoarthritis, but it scales with you have more senescent cells when
you have more disease. And when you say, do you mean synovial fluid? Like if you did a joint
aspiration on somebody with osteoarthritis, you're saying one to two percent of the cells
in the synovial fluid is senescent? So we actually did tell you, I'll come back to this a little bit
later. Let me just finish up and then we'll immediately flip to that. Sorry. Okay. Is that
we did this experiment where we soaked the cartilage from the patients that had osteoarthritis
in our drug and eliminated senescent cells. But another really cool thing is they started
growing cartilage in the plastic dish. So these are cells that came from that sick person's knee.
They had the capacity to make cartilage, but they just didn't. But once you eliminated the cells,
all of a sudden they were producing cartilage again. And so that was super cool. We have yet
to prove in a human being that this drug can grow cartilage when it's still in your knee.
But that experiment is kind of cool because it suggests that you have this innate capacity
if you were unburdened by these cells and their bad stuff they're making. So this next question
about how many senescent cells do you have in the disease? I'll tell you why I'm asking the question,
which is not just general curiosity. It's really to get a question of how difficult is it to target
these things in vivo. Are they ubiquitous enough that you can whack these things with an injection?
Because obviously when you're doing this in a person, you're not going to have the luxury of
taking their knee out to do it. That's sort of the etiology of my question. So I'll tell you a
little bit of what we've done in the clinic. So in human beings, we have eliminated senescent cells
from patients' knees with a single injection of this drug. And we can not only eliminate or
dramatically reduce pain, but we can also eliminate factors that senescent cells are making.
So the quick answer to your question is that this molecule is safe enough, selective enough,
and potent enough that we can do it. So it doesn't just work in a plastic dish,
but it works actually within the knee of a patient suffering from osteoarthritis.
So this was your phase one trial with your first agent. This is the 101?
Yeah, that's right.
I've seen the phase one data maybe explain a little bit of what was done. Phase one for
people who aren't familiar with drug studies is mostly to ensure safety, but sometimes you'll see
efficacy. Sometimes you'll see that the drug actually does something beneficial, and that's
a bonus if you can see both efficacy and safety. But you're typically escalating the dose, and
again, you want to see if more drug leads to more toxicity. But if there's efficacy and the
efficacy improves with dose, that makes you a bit more confident that it's not the placebo effect
or not the effect of the vehicle that you use to deliver the drug.
That's correct. So the experiment we did, and this was all the result of what we saw in animals,
that was a result of what we saw in a phase zero study in which we went into patients with
osteoarthritis, no drugs, but we biopsy little bits of their synovial membrane and counted
senescent cells. And we saw that the more senescent cells they had, the worse osteoarthritis they had,
the more bone deformation they had in the knee, the more pain they had.
So emboldened by these results, we then took the drug to humans. And as you noted,
phase one studies are typically for safety. We realized though, that we couldn't really do the
right safety study in patients that didn't have a senescent cell burden. Because if you're asking
the question, is it safe to eliminate senescent cells from an osteoarthritic knee, you need to
have the cells to eliminate. And so that was our kind of logic in the design. And so the way we did
the study was 48 patients where we did a three to one randomization, meaning three people would get
drug versus one person getting placebo. And as you noted, we stepped up in dose and it was a single
dose of the drug at day zero injected into the knees of patients with painful osteoarthritis.
And we then followed these patients for three months. And we checked in with them every week,
and they checked in with themselves every day on a little iPhone device. And we monitored their
pain. And the investigators were blinded as well. Oh, yes. It's called a double blind study, which
means nobody knows who's got drug, who's got placebo or what dose of drug you were on. So there's 12
placebos, 36 treatments, treated patients, and those 36 treated patients were about six per dose.
They were six per dose. Yeah. So we had six dose levels. And so they were marched up from
essentially a group of a series of doses, three of them, which we based on some modeling we did
in cell culture, we thought would be sub pharmacologically active doses. So we thought
they'd be semi inactive or inactive entirely. And then we moved into the dose range where we thought
we'd be doing biology in the knee. And we saw what happened. And we asked the patients, they had
once a week meetings with their physician where they answered questionnaires about their pain,
about their functional state. Then every day they would go and they'd enter on a little iPhone
device, they answer one question, which is how much pain am I in on a scale of one to 10. And
what we saw when we unblinded the data was that there was a dose dependent meaning as you go up
in dose, you get more and more pain reduction and durable impact in pain. For as long as we
looked, when you got to three months, the pain is not returning. It's completely flat. Do you
remember what the placebo group experienced? How much of a reduction in pain did they achieve
relative to their baseline? It depends on which of the end points we're using. But I'll just
summarize by saying that injections into the knee placebo effect is a big deal. In fact,
if you did not see a placebo effect that looked like other clinical trials, you would scratch
your head and wonder what's wrong. We saw a very similar placebo effect to what is seen with the
injection of steroids into the knee. And that was actually good. Meaning if you do a trial with
steroids and with saline, for example, you saw the same placebo effect. You didn't see the same
effect as you saw with steroids. Correct. You see the placebo groups in a steroid trial.
Had comparable benefits.
Looked like the placebo effect in our trial. And that is something that one must, the placebo
effects in pain studies is absolutely important. But what we saw was that we vastly exceeded
anything looking like the placebo effect. So in fact, at our highest dose of drug, again,
because it's a phase one study, the N number of patients was small at the highest dose.
We saw patients who were entering, so this is this scale of one to 10 thing. Okay. It's actually
zero to 10 patients were entering on average at about a 6.2 and at the highest dose, they were
dropping to just over one. Is that comparable to what patients experience with steroids? I know
it's not apples to apples. And by the way, it's a reason it's not apples to apples that I actually
learned on this clinical study. The reason you don't compare across studies is that different
studies in rural different patients, different inclusion, exclusion criteria, even if you use
the very same clinical instrument, it's really not an apples to apples comparison. That said,
okay, the effect looks very large in terms of what we are doing in terms of approaching
our highest dose, getting some patients close to pain-free. Now, I know that the phase one trial
was a three month study. What's the average duration that patients have now been since their
injections? I don't have the answer to that question. We are not monitoring the patients
in that study going forward because we didn't consent them for that. What we are doing now is
we're actively dosing patients in our phase two study. So presumably the duration will be extended
in phase two. That's right. So because we only went three months in the phase one study and we
didn't consent patients to keep watching them, we really wanted to answer this question, which is
if you eliminate senescent cells from somebody's knee, how long does the pain stay away?
And so the phase two study goes out to six months, so it's 24 weeks, and we're trying to replicate
the phase one study as much as we can. So we're using the same clinical instruments to measure
pain and function. We're similar dose levels. So we're doing placebo, a half-meg, two-migs,
four-migs, which was the highest dose that we explored in the phase one study. And it's 45
patients per dose level as opposed to six. So we should have sufficient statistical power to
really see this really clearly. And in terms of the criteria of the patients that are coming in,
they have to have painful osteoarthritis of the knee. And so there is a score, this thing called
the NRS, which is this numerical rating scale. This is this zero to 10, so it's an 11-point scale.
And you have to be between a four and a nine. And are these patients that typically have
already tried corticosteroids and only achieved limited or short-term response? Like I'm trying
to understand clinically, somebody listening to this, who should and shouldn't be excited about
this type of work on the horizon? So I think all of us should be excited about this work,
because not only is this a solution, so if our phase two replicates the phase one,
and which we all hope and believe it ought to, not only is this a means to treat the primary
reason it hurts to be old, but it's a read-through to this whole idea of medicine, which is could you
treat diseases of aging by eliminating these cells at sites of disease? This is just the beginning of
something. Well, let me go back and make sure I understand a few things, because I'm already
doing what you're doing, I think, which is sort of extrapolating to the what it means.
Is radiographic evidence a way, because you can certainly look at a person's knee on an x-ray and
examine the loss of cartilage and appreciate an osteoarthritic knee. You could do the same thing
on an MRI. Do you know if the reverse is true? Do you know if the level of cartilage that's making
its way back into the knee as a result of the loss of senescent cells is radiographically evident as
well? Or is it possible that some of the amelioration of pain is due to the reduction of the
circulating factors there, but not so much an increase in the structural integrity of the knee?
So what we saw in terms of the speed of pain resolution in the phase one was that within
two weeks of the injection, you achieved most of your pain reduction. So it seems pretty
implausible to me that that is the result of a structural change to your joint. It seems far
more likely that this is the result of getting rid of factors that are driving pain acutely.
And it's possible, like my questions are probably so ignorant, and I'm sure there's some orthopedic
surgeon listening to this cringing. We would assume that some of the pain that people experience in
osteoarthritis is due to the structural part of this, but your evidence would suggest that at least
part of the pain is not. It's consistent with that idea, but who's to say? So we're going to
know because we're also doing MRI and x-ray in the phase two study. And so we're going to be able to
not only follow pain, but we will follow structure as well. But we have no idea if you will see
improvements in the structure of the joint over what time scale you would see changes and
improvements to the structure of the joint. This is the cool thing about doing cutting edge biology
in clinical science. I mean, I would love to take a group of patients if resources were no object,
and we could continue to be absolutely sure of the safety of this. You know, you imagine
take a bunch of people our age and you do a bunch of T2 weighted images, MRIs of their spine, and you
look at these signal loss L4, L5, L5, S1 discs. Many people our age, myself certainly, have these
blown out blackened discs that just aren't taking up water. Yeah, I have them. Yeah. It would be very
interesting to note if you did directed injections of synolytic agents like this, if you could restore
this signal, could you, by eradicating enough senescent cell, create an environment where the
existing cell could proliferate into a healthy enough place where it takes up water? Something
as simple as that, that again, it's a slippery slope in the spine to go after indications because
it's not as clean as the knee, I don't think. But again, just a great proof of concept.
Yeah, I will say that I suffer from degenerative disc disease. It's, well, everyone does at some
point, but it's particularly prevalent in my family. There was a result I did not mention earlier
from mice, that when we eliminate senescent cells from mice, from midlife until death, and we
do x-ray on their spines, we see a 41% improvement in the maintenance of the intervertebral disc
volume. Now, do you see a restoration or a reduction in decline? We only measured reduction
in decline, so we do not know if you could see restoration. So that's still an unknown question
in the senescent space. Absolutely. So it's possible you, me, and all the other folks that are
in the senior category here won't necessarily reap the benefits nearly as much as the people like
your kid, my kid right now, where you figure this out and when you're 20, you start to prophylactically
take these things to reduce the glide rate of decline. That might be true structurally,
but I would say that what we saw in our phase one study was you can take people with Frank,
painful osteoarthritis of the knee, dose them, and two weeks later they have profound pain reduction
at the highest dose. So that tells you that you are taking a big feature of that disease,
the one that you get to feel on a minute to minute basis, and you are sending it backwards.
Now, whether or not that becomes a structural change is something we hope to understand in
the phase two study. And the other thing we, I guess, don't understand, and it might take even
more than a phase two study to understand, is with corticosteroids we have problems, which is
excessive use of corticosteroids is not a viable option. No. They themselves become destructive
and or potentially lose efficacy over time, and so they're a great once in a while tool,
but not a great maintenance tool. It will be interesting to know if this, if you become
tachyphylactic to this, or if the efficacy increases with use as you start to increase
the amount of cartilage laying tissue that exists, and you tip the battle in favor of the chondrocyte
over the senescent cell. Yeah, that would be the kind of prediction one would make from the simple,
sort of zero order prediction would be that, I think. Is there an example in biopharmacology
where the good guy ends up winning with progressive dosing? Oh, I would say oncology.
If you think about cancer as a gain of function. Only in the cancers that don't spread though,
but that's sort of, that almost seems binary, doesn't it? I guess you're right. I guess you
could say that. So because if you think of cancer as a sort of pitted battle between you, the organism,
and cancer, which is sort of a gain of function, separate organism based on you living in you,
but not you, when you successfully treat cancer through the elimination of those cells,
the good guy won. Yeah, I guess that's true some of the time, but most of the time that's not true.
It's sort of a tautology, right? It's true when it's true, but when it's not, it's not, but most
of the time it's not true is the problem. But it could certainly be the case here. There's certainly
a case, but even if the worst case scenario is you need a drug injected every six months or every 12
months, it's certainly interesting. Let's go one step further because this is obviously a critical
piece of health span. In fact, you could argue that along with cognition, there's no more important
piece of health span than the structural integrity of your body as you age. Have you, in your leisure
time, had the ability to think about how this might impact lifespan vis-a-vis atherosclerosis,
cancer, or other diseases that actually shorten life? Well, we know that atherosclerosis is another
disease in which senescence plays a role. Now, we're not currently working on that. One of the
things you may have noticed is that osteoarthritis, the way we approach the disease, even though it
affects many of the 360 joints in your body, we treat the local version of the disease with local
therapy. Atherosclerosis is about as systemic as it gets. And Jan van der Zinn at Mayo Clinic
published a paper. Actually, it was Jan van der Zinn, the guy named a very excellent young scientist
named Bennett Childs. And this is a paper in Science in which he showed in Rodents that
senescent cells accumulate in the atherosclerotic plaques that form in a high-fat diet mouse,
which is a model that can predict, say, statin efficacy to some extent, although it exaggerates
it somewhat compared to the human case. And what Bennett showed, these plaques are full of senescent
cells. And if you eliminate those cells, what are the cells that have become senescent? What's their
origin? So they appear to be macrophage in origin. I see. So it's not the endothelial cell. Well,
no, there's three cell types. It's basically there's a senescent endothelium. There is a
myofibroblastic type of cell that's in there. And then there are macrophages. So it's all three.
It's basically the barrier, the immune cell that came to the rescue and the fibroblasts that
attempted to repair the damage. Yeah, all of them. And when you eliminate these senescent cells,
either genetically or with a drug, first of all, you can reduce plaque volume, which is cool. But
what might even be cooler is that, and again, it's in a mouse. And so you just gotta wonder,
what is that really saying about the pathophysiology of the human disease? But there is this
fibrotic cap that forms on the surface of an atherosclerotic plaque. And one of the ideas in
the literature is that the thinning of that plaque gives rise to a unstable plaque that is
clinically dangerous and that interventions that can thicken that plaque might be a therapy,
because you could take a plaque that you have and now convert it into something clinically
more innocuous. And what Jan showed was that genetically and with drug that he can thicken
the plaques of atherosclerotic plaques in a mouse. That would seem to counter the idea that you could
lessen plaque volume. Do you have to pick between one of those two strategies? Because typically,
if you thicken the plaque, wouldn't you likely increase the volume? No. So if you look at the
relative partitioning of how much of the plaque volume is the cap, and then how much is this
lipid deposit with macrophages in it, eyeballing it, 90% is this kind of lipid-y macrophage blob.
And then there's this thin little veneer on top that is the cap. And so the thickening of that
cap doesn't dramatically contribute to the overall volume of the atherosclerotic plaque,
at least in a mouse. But both are happening. You're thickening the cap and reducing the
subendithelial portion of the reducing the femme salins. So the ATHRO is a very tough
place to do drug development. I mean, we've seen the PCSK9 story has been a multi-billion dollar
battle that has given rise to relatively moderate uptake of those drugs.
I could argue that's just due to the cost of the drug.
It's also the fact that it's a relative cost issue going up against statins. So switching
people and all this sort of thing, but it's not been, it's caused a sort of downward pressure
on people's enthusiasm for doing cardiovascular drug discovery. Because now we have to, you're not
using surrogate markers anymore, you're using outcome studies, you're actually following people
until they die or have a serious cardiac event. Do you see an application here in oncology? I mean,
it seems like there should be. Well, it's an area of interest of ours. So one of the things we saw
in Jan van der Zent's 2016 paper was that these mice from whom we eliminated senescent cells from
midlife until death, they had the same cancer prevalence. So 85% of them die of lymphoma with
and without senescent cells. The difference is that when you eliminate the cells, the animals
from whom these cells were eliminated get cancer 30% later in their lives. So you have to kind of
head scratch for a moment. Like what does that mean? And if I recall, you said they got a 30%
lifespan extension. Yeah. So you basically created centenarians, you just phase shifted chronic
disease by a third. And some of the diseases were just dramatically reduced. So the effects
on kidney function, the age effects of kidney function were reduced dramatically, cataracts were
reduced dramatically. So there's a whole bunch of behavior stuff that we don't know what that means.
But these animals seem to preserve features of youthful behavior. Their spinal lord lord doses
looks youthful. So there's a whole set of things. But one of the things that people often ask about
the experiment is, do they die of different things when you live 30% longer? And the answer is no,
they die of the same thing mostly. Now that could have to do with the fact that it's mice and these
lab strains of mice. Yeah, they just get cancer like crazy. And it's less interesting to me that
it's how much lymphoma they get. It's more interesting to me that you could phase shift it.
So we don't know why that is. But an explanation that makes some sense to me is that there is
something perverse that senescent cells do to the tissue microenvironment. So this system, which is
an anti cancer system in the young, could become a pro cancer system in the old by doing something
to the tumor microenvironment that makes it more amenable to tumor genesis. And that would be
consistent what you see where the rate of tumor formation across the animal's life is unchanged,
but its ability to take root is delayed. So you could imagine applications in oncology,
but you would require something in which you had some sort of highly sort of tumor prone
situation where you could intervene in it. There's also an idea where if you could make cells
senescent, which is what chemotherapy does in many cases, and then do a sort of a two hit strategy
where you drive the cells into senescence, and then you exploit a senescence associated, you know,
Achilles heel. So it could be a strategy in which you deliberately are trying to drive tumor cells
into senescence and then killing them. And then there are a series of cancers that we think that
are age associated that may be essentially the product of a highly senescent environment.
So cancers of the skin, what if you could or cancers of the say the bladder or something
like this, these things that older people get, could you go in and eliminate senescent cells
and change trajectory of disease? That's an idea. That's very cool that you could think about. But I
would say that the most powerful read through from our results so far in humans are these other
diseases of aging for which we have no treatments. So let us take something like the dry version of
macular degeneration. This is a disease for which there is no treatment. And it's eight fold more
prevalent than the wet disease that you can treat with anti-veg S. This is a disease that appears to
have senescence associated with it. What's the distribution of those two? So people that have age
associated macular degeneration, one in eight has the wet disease. And only that one out of eight
people is treatable with the anti-veg F antibodies. Seven out of eight of those people are untreatable.
Now that disease, the dry disease moves more slowly, but it makes you just as blind. And so that is an
area in which senescence and senolytic medicines may play a role, but we'll have to find out in
the clinic. And next year we are going with our first molecules into the eye. Do you have an animal
model for that? No. So you have animal models of the wet disease and our molecules work in that
model. And so you could say that that's pretty neat. This is a giant opportunity, but I'm
personally attracted. First of all, I just want to say that when we talked about the four risks,
defined your work stream for four years, we live in a different risk set. So if you think about it,
the chapter one of this entire effort really was demonstrated in a human being that eliminating
senescent cells could take a feature of aging that otherwise was untreatable and sent it backwards.
Our phase one study, certainly if the phase two replicates, that was the end of chapter one. And
we're sort of living in this chapter two moment where we're seeing how broad can we make this
work. And if you think about what risks live in chapter two, for me, and I think anybody, it would
be that the risk is you have your biological disease hypothesis wrong. And animal models,
they only ask an answer the questions they're built to ask an answer. And the only way you get
to really ask an answer the question you want to ask is in the clinical setting in human beings.
So the way I think about diseases of the eyes, you have a series of these untreatable diseases
that make you blind, where we think senescence could play a role. And we're going to explore
each of these in the clinic. So essentially being able to ask in the relevant setting,
that can we intervene in these diseases of aging, using the very same approach that we took
to osteoarthritis, albeit with different drugs. Now you won't be doing a real phase one here,
you're going to go directly into a phase two, right? So this is something that we haven't
really talked about yet. But notionally, we're going to be going into patients, because obviously
your eye is something that's super, super important and you can't mess with it. We're
going to be going into a very select population first, demonstrating safety and then branching
outwards into multiple diseases of the eye. How do you deliver the vehicle? Is it an injection?
Yeah, so it's very similar to clinical practice for anti-veg.
Anti-veg after delivery.
So it goes right into the vitreous fluid of the eye. And our drug then takes up,
we actually know exactly where the drug goes into the various sub compartments within the eye.
And we know where senescent cells are in these different diseases and our drug gets there. And
the clinical hypothesis is that one or more of these essentially progressive diseases of the
aging eye, when we eliminate the cells will stop.
And can you speak about the drug? What is it targeting? It's not targeting p53?
No. So we have two molecules that we're advancing toward the clinic. Both of them are inhibitors of
the BCL2 protein family. So these are molecules that inhibit inhibitors of apoptosis. So they
cause cells to enter programmed cell death. But interestingly, we've shown in animals that they
don't cause that to happen in normal healthy eyes. They only target cells that have been damaged by
the disease process and the stress associated with disease process. And so-
Why is that?
There's something about, so senescent cells when they enter the state, do a variety of things. They
turn up proteins that are pro apoptosis and they also turn up proteins in terms of their expression
that are anti apoptosis. So what we do is we go in with a drug and just give a little shove in one
direction.
I see. But you're saying if you give that same shove to someone who has not up regulated or
down regulated either of those factors, it doesn't seem to matter too much.
Yeah. And so we have a beautiful experiment in mouse where we have a disease condition,
and we have a normal condition. Mice are identical, but for this. And we put the drug in and we can
see the drug molecularly going in and engaging its target. So because it actually breaks up to
proteins that are stuck together. And you can see in these animals, both of them are equally
engaging target, but the apoptosis program only turns on in the disease state. And it was a pretty
awesome result because you can see the selectivity of the molecules in a living creature's eye.
Does that same molecule work in the osteoarthritic scenario?
No. So we couldn't get it to work either in the trauma models in mice. We couldn't get it to work
when we took the cartilage out of human needs. It didn't work there either. And so it never raised
its hand.
What do you think that says about the biology?
There's something about cells and their fate that determines which apoptosis vulnerability
you have. They have different Achilles heels. And we don't understand mechanistically why that is.
We've sort of figured this out empirically and picked molecules based on their behavior
against the cells that we find to be senescent in these human diseases.
So 15 years from now or 20 years from now, we will likely look back and companies like Unity,
and presumably there will be many like Unity, you will have an entire suite of targets. You will say,
well, here's the playbook in this type of cell or this scenario going after the anti-anti-apoptotic
pathway is the way to go. In this case, we're going to go after P53. And you might have a dozen
of these different targets. Well, we're not sure yet. I think it's too early to say how this is
going to play out. Oh, so you don't think it's a fait accompli. I mean, you think it might be that
there's a very small number of ways to go about doing this? I doubt that. I doubt it will be
dozens though. I think it's going to be a small number. I think it'll be context specific. I think
there'll be super creative ways that we and others come up with to exploit these different
vulnerabilities. I don't think biology is going to have made 24 different keys to this lock.
They think it's going to make a half dozen. And we actively search for these. It's just interesting
to me that you can turn one key and get a benefit. I mean, think about how often that doesn't work.
Think of the futility of that in chemotherapy, where you target this one piece of cell cycle
replication and very quickly the cell mutates away around that drug. So cancer is incredibly hard,
okay? Because cancer exploits the single best tool biology has, which is variation. Cancer cells can
divide and mutate and become anything to avoid death. They live under selective pressure,
particularly in the context of drug. Senescent cells can't divide by definition. So their ability
to access variation is dramatically reduced. Now that's not to say that there couldn't still be
selection without division, but boy, it's way harder when you can't make a million progenate
with tiny variants and test them all in parallel, which is what cancer does.
Yeah. It's sort of funny, isn't it? Cancer is the ultimate A-B tester.
We like to think of senescent cells as cancer cells that can't divide. I've heard that said
semi-humorously, but that's actually really neat.
Right. Which is sort of funny because it's like,
tape the top 100 most valuable traits of cancer and take away 99 of them.
By the way, I was saying that in some joking.
No, I understand. Yeah.
In the sense that senescent cells become senescent. Well, first of all, in vivo,
we don't often know why they became senescent, but one of the mechanisms by which cells can
become senescent is activation of a cancer causing gene. But that could be very rare event
compared to mitochondrial failure or high concentration glucose or telomere shortening.
I mean, I was going to actually ask you exactly about that example, which is,
do we have any reason to believe that the increase in age associated type two diabetes
could be resulting from some sort of pancreatic senescence where beta cells
become less and less robust due to senescent beta cells in the proximity?
There is some data in support of senescence in that cellular niche, but it's very complicated
biology. And there's even some talk about compensatory mechanism where senescent cells
actually may improve the function of some of those cells within the niche. It's an area of
intense literature debate. The other challenge we have there is we don't have good models in animals
of studying this. And so it's been hard for us to get our heads around. What I will say about type
two diabetes in humans is that there was a large meta analysis of a genome-wide association studies
looking for the genetic correlation between grievous illness of aging and loci. Where did
these mutations map? And what you saw is that one of the very big peaks for diseases of aging maps
into the control system for the establishment of cellular senescence. This P14 Arf locus.
And you look at this is where this very important gene that people use for senescence all the time
called P16, which is this part of the emergency break. Its gene lives in this locus. And what you
see is diseases like type two diabetes, mutations that give rise to that live there. Mutations that
give rise to late onset Alzheimer's live there. Frailty lives there. Atherosclerosis lives there.
So a whole bunch of these diseases where we saw phenotypes in mice, you see a natural genetic
variation of humans also shows a kind of tie-in to senescence. And so type two diabetes caught my
eye there because you see that in the GWAS studies. And lastly, what about Alzheimer's disease? We have
to believe that astrocytes are losing some functionality to protect neurons, right? So
this is what my group works on. And it's something that animates a lot of us at the company. We know
that astrocytes or glia, just call them glial cells. So if you guys don't know what glia is,
that's actually derived from the word glue. So this is the cells that are not your neurons
in your brain that seem to hold the rest of it together. Which outnumber neurons tremendously.
Vastly. I think the number is on the order of 10 to 1. 8 to 10 to 1 or something like that.
Guys got to look that number up, but it's on that order of magnitude. And what was known before we
got involved was that as human beings aged, there's a dramatic increase in senescent glial
cells, specifically astrocytes and microglia, which are the sort of macrophages of the brain.
And stuff we've been working on, if we've been looking at that trend in rodents, and we see a
very similar trend. Now, we have not talked about doing on this yet, because it's still early days,
but it's hard to imagine that the pro-inflammatory environment created by this vast number of
senescent glial cells is good for you. One needs to ask the question, what would happen if you could
eliminate senescent glial cells? Would that enhance cognition? Would it harm cognition?
And this is something that we are actively looking into. But all of the work we've done over the last
eight years, everything going from the mutant animals to the wild type animals to human data
in osteoarthritis, and now moving into human data soon within the eye, it would just be very hard to
imagine that senescence is not playing a role in aspects of cognition loss as we age. And this is
something when I think about why we do what we do, that is something that there could be very few
greater contributions that myself and my colleagues could make than making a contribution
there, because it has been an unsolved problem and a scourge to humanity. I mean, do you get the sense
that doing what you've done now, it would be very difficult for you to go back in time and do
something like Kythera over again? And I'm not saying that to be critical or in any way, shape,
or form. I'm just saying like, I mean, maybe tell people what Kythera did. That was a very successful
company for you, but there's no comparing the nature of the two problems you're trying to solve.
Actually, thank you for actually pulling me out of what would otherwise be a kind of like
overly sort of sappy discussion about contribution. Okay, so Kythera is actually a total kind of
opposite sort of thing. And Kythera was a company myself and two co-founders founded
now almost 15 years ago. It's about as opposite as you can get from doing unity. And so it was
basically this idea that all this biology that's been explored for oncology and inflammatory
disease, taking molecules from that and applying it to the biology of aesthetics. And we did this,
and I had these great business partners that continue to be partners with me today.
One of them is Keith Leonard, who's CEO at Unity and very close friend. And he's been my big brother
for 15 years and continues as of this morning, calling me and giving me feedback on things. And
the reason I did Kythera was it was sort of a cute idea, but it was mostly because of people,
was these guys said, hey, let's do something together. And it was a great decision, because
I learned so much in a sense because, so the drug we ultimately got approved, we took four things
into the clinic, and one out of the four things worked. And it was a molecule that causes fat
cells to explode. So we went from an in vitro observation all the way to a launched commercial
product called Kybella, you can go get it, you're dermatologist. And Allergan acquired the company.
And it was a great learning experience of just how to develop pharmaceuticals in something that
didn't have historical resonance at all. And so it was a great moment where the stakes weren't as high
whether you succeeded or failed. And as a consequence, it allowed you to hone your skills
of kind of making really high quality decisions on risk and making drug development decisions in a
way that's actually frankly, a little more dispassionate. And it was a great growth experience for me.
I mean, is it safe to say that if you had not had the experience at Kythera,
because then you would have been coming from a cajun, right? Basically, yeah. Would you have had a
more difficult time doing what you and the early co-founders did at Unity?
It would have been impossible. I would have none of the intellectual or emotional toolkit to do
what we did. I mean, that whole risk thing, that was stuff we built. I mean, it was a little bit
when we put together a cajun, but it had become a kind of ritualized practice by the time we were
doing Kythera projects, this dimensionalization of risk and creating work plans based on it.
And so, yeah, I would say that there would be no Unity without there being Kythera.
Last question, Ned. I actually have two questions for you. I'm sorry that I think about it.
First question is, what advice do you give for a person who's studying science and trying to
decide between the entrepreneurial pathway that you've been on versus a more academic pathway?
What would you offer them as an insight or a set of questions that they could pose to themselves
to further delineate that? Well, I would say two things. First, don't create a false choice.
I have friends that are academics that have founded as many companies as I have.
I do from time to time have career jealousy over some of the freedoms and some of the
responsibilities, frankly, that they have as people who have academic appointments.
There are wonderful things that you can do from the seat of academia in company creation if you
are so lucky and so positioned to do so. So first, don't fall into this idea of a false choice. And
I see people do that, I think, out of some emotional discomfort, this desire to just move
and confuse action with progress. And I'd say just slow down, take a deep breath, don't rush,
you have your life. That'd be the first thing. The second thing is animate what you do with a single
beautiful idea. So something that moves you, that literally gives you goosebumps, that weird
tingling sensation when you think about it, when you think how cool it is, and oh my god, if we
could actually make this work. I mean, few things in life rival that feeling when a hard fought
battle for data that was 18 to 24 months and the experiment finally works, and you're looking at
the data and you feel like the future taking root in the present. The only thing I can compare it to
is love from your kids. That is the only thing that has the same emotional gravitas. Finally,
third thing, learn from people that are better than you, that are more experienced than you,
that will have patience with you. I mean, the Kythera experience was that. I mean,
good heavens, I was, I may still be sort of unemployable in normal corporate settings.
Yet the people there saw that I knew how to do certain things and I learned from them and I
learned how to do the things that allowed us to build unity because people were patient and took
time to teach. I learned from real experts and I don't claim to be an expert at much of anything,
but I do claim to have a deep appreciation for learning from people who are better and more
skilled than myself. So three things. Well, I'm going to leave it at that. I was going to ask you
another question, but I think this was the more interesting question and so we'll leave it at that
and grateful, Ned, for the time that you've set aside today to talk about this stuff. I think this
is a super interesting topic. When I think about the pillars of longevity, going back to your
initial framework, which is things that inhibit tor, things that target mitochondrial function,
things that may set back the methylation clock, slow down time in that regard in this problem.
It's not a zero sum game and it's very likely we need to be pursuing all of these strategies
in parallel, but the data so far with respect to a very tangible problem like osteoarthritis is
pretty exciting. So I suspect there's going to be a lot of people listening to this who are going to
be very eager to follow the results of the technology that you guys are trying to bring
to market along with presumably some others down the line. Thank you, Peter. It's been really a
treat and an honor to share this with you and I've always and shall always, I love your questions.
They're awesome. Thank you. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're
interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that
allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our
goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of this subscription. Now to that end,
membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast
show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the
street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing
these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this. The QALYs, which are a super short podcast,
typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday,
highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive.
This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily
listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting
paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time
goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over
to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only. It does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.