Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Stanley Perlman. Stanley is a professor of microbiology
and immunology, along with being a professor of pediatrics and the chair of virology at the
University of Iowa. Stanley has researched coronaviruses for nearly four decades, and his
lab is currently using mouse models for SARS-CoV-1 and SARS-CoV-2 to better understand the more
severe diseases that affect humans. I've wanted to talk with Stanley for a few months now.
Understandably, he has been incredibly busy. We have been part of a collaboration that is
working on a longer study trying to understand the durability of immune response and the impacts of
that, which we discussed very briefly at the end of this podcast. So most of our contact has actually
been through that, but as we got a little bit of breathing room in and around our other projects,
inclusive of the one we're working on together, we decided it made sense to finally sit down and
have this discussion, especially as a beautiful extension of the discussion that I already had
with David Watkins. So I do recommend that you would listen to these podcasts in that order. The
one with David Watkins, of course, goes over the immunology a little bit. Here we talk specifically
about coronaviruses, including the sort of common cold coronaviruses, and of course, more importantly,
the three versions that really have caused incredible damage to humans, none more so than
the one we're in today. In this episode, we talk about a whole bunch of things that, again, just,
you can probably imagine interest me to no end. When we were talking specifically about SARS 1 and
MERS, what did they teach us about this coronavirus? What does our knowledge of this coronavirus today
versus what we knew, say, five months ago tell us about how this story ends? And what do I mean by
ending? All of these are topics that we get into, along with a very interesting discussion around
the therapeutic side of things, the vaccination side of things, and ultimately, what could happen
again? So without further delay, I hope you enjoy my conversation with Dr. Stanley Crum.
Hey, Stanley, thank you so much for making time to talk today. I've wanted to speak with you for a
couple of months now, and I know when we first connected, it was just nuts, and you said,
hey, Peter, thanks for reaching out. Can we talk when things calm down a little bit? And I was
so gracious that, first of all, that you even took the time to respond. And then, of course, now we've
been able to work together on a separate project that maybe we'll talk about down the line.
But I'll tell you, the reason I reached out in the first place was really the result of something
that my research team came to me and said, which was, look, Peter, if you want to understand
coronaviruses, you've got to speak to Stanley Perlman. Everybody is an armchair coronavirus
expert now, but you actually want to talk to the guy who is studying coronaviruses before they
were sexy, and that's Stanley. So before we get maybe into how you became obsessed with coronaviruses,
how did you get involved in medicine and immunology, per se?
Well, I actually started, I obtained a PhD many, many years ago in the areas, actually, of cell
biology and developmental biology and virology. So I did a whole potpourri of training as a PhD
student and then again during post-op. And then I went to medical school. So there was a period
there where I learned, I didn't do coronavirus research, but I learned how to do research.
And so then when I went to medical school, I became interested in pediatrics, men and infectious
diseases. And I don't know what my plans were exactly when I started medical school, but
became really interested in how baby brains interacted with viruses, which was not good.
So when babies are getting infected with viruses, especially in utero, it often has devastating
consequences. And I worked with somebody who was really good at thinking about those babies. And I
became just interested in research issues around how viruses interact with the brain. So at that
time point, I became interested, it turned out that coronaviruses and mice provided a model that
could lead to potentially important information. So I went from all the other things that I did,
and from being a pediatric infectious disease person, part of my training, I also started
working with coronaviruses. Now, what was the decision point that had you leave sort of a pure
academic track, which you would have been on from your PhD and your postdoc to sort of take that,
I don't like to use the term backwards, but I think you sort of get what I mean. Take that
backwards step and go back to something remedial like medical school. In other words, what really
drove you to want to have a clinically active research focus? Well, I think there are two
things. One, I was interested in, I felt I was getting compartmentalized in a small area of
research. I don't think I wanted to be in something that was quite so confined and didn't have too
many relevance for general health issues. And the second thing is ironic. I started my PhD at an
early age, and it was almost like I was looking for a chance to take a little bit of a break.
A medical school in residency is more than a little bit of a break, but it was pretty fast.
There was a total of starting medical school to finishing fellowship was only six years,
which is a long time, but not compared to what most people do to this kind of training.
There's a combination of both those things of being wanting to really step back a bit and also
wanting to find more relevance for human disease. You're kind of a doogie howser because how is it
you could do med school and because today, med school is four years, pediatric residency is three,
and then pediatric infectious disease would add at least two to that, right?
Or three. It's actually three now, yeah.
You'd be talking about a 10-year training program that you did in six.
So I was lucky because when I went to medical school, there was a shortage of doctors,
and there was one or two programs that allowed people to truncate their medical school training.
I went to one in Miami that if you had a PhD, you could basically do the whole thing in 22 months.
What you did is you cut the first year down to six months, the second year down to about three
months, did the entire third year, and then you did the fourth year in eight weeks. So at the end
of it all, we did everything. We could do it to people who had PhDs, though I have to say they
took PhDs in whether it be physics or physics to psychology to biology to chemistry. So people had
different amounts of training. This training was good. The classes were really full of people who
were really creative and thinking about things. So it was a generally intense but very good
experience, and you were well trained at the end.
You did your residency at Boston Children's or fellowship or both?
Both, yeah, both.
At the time and probably still to this day, Boston Children's Hospital remains easily in the top three
in the world, perhaps along with CHOP and Sick Kids and maybe a few others. So you're at the
premier pediatric hospital in the world. You're training with, I guess you're referring to
Brazelton as your mentor there?
Yeah, yeah, so right there.
So tell me more about childhood development. I mean, I don't know much about it, obviously,
and it certainly rings a bell when you say that viruses can really wreak havoc. One of the few
things I remember from OBGYN is the lengths you would go to to ensure that a mother wasn't
infected actively during childbirth.
Yeah, so we don't understand everything about this, but certain viruses that invade the brain
during the first trimester really cause devastating loss of neurological function.
And the later you go in the pregnancy, the more likely it is to cause less disease. But even when
you're infected during delivery, babies infected with certain viruses always have hearing problems,
visual problems, and even cognitive problems. So the babies, just because they're developing,
they're incredibly sensitive to anything that disrupts their development. And when I think
about it, the direct relationship to what I later did with research was really not so strong,
but it was just the whole notion of could you do anything to prevent these viruses from
spreading in the human brain? And then also, the way they do spread within the human brain,
could this be something that would be useful for understanding other functions if you did
this in an experimentally infected animal. So that's kind of the way. And then coronavirus
has turned out to have this interesting ability to cause demyelination, which was similar to what
we see in multiple sclerosis. So it sort of ended up in a long roundabout way for my studying this
multiple sclerosis-like disease for 20 years before SARS came about.
Maybe this is probably just as good a time as any, Stanley, to really give people a bit of the
lay of the land on what a coronavirus is, because anybody listening to this, when they hear
coronavirus, they're thinking of SARS-CoV-2. It might be helpful to put that in a much broader
context, which is what does a family of viruses actually mean? When we say the Joneses and the
Smiths, we're talking about a family, not Billy Smith necessarily. So what does that look like?
So the coronaviruses are like any other set of viruses. Their viruses are put into that
category because of what they look like under the microscope, what they look like under the
electron microscope, or how they make new viruses, the kind of replication strategy we call it that
they use to make new viruses. In the old days, you might have some serological testing that would
tell you about relatedness. I say in the old days, we still use that, of course, but we have genetic
ways now to really see how close viruses are. So you put all those things together, and particularly
looking under the microscope, we can say coronaviruses have a certain pattern under the microscope.
All viruses that are coronaviruses have those patterns. It doesn't mean that they all can
infect people, or they all can infect this animal or that animal. They're really very, very different.
The ones that were known before SARS came about really were the experimental ones, like the ones
we use, which infected mice, and then also these other coronaviruses that infect swine and cows and
cats and dogs. And even now, they're finding viruses that are not quite coronaviruses, but are
very closely related that affect insects and snakes. So these viruses infect across lots of species.
And bats, of course, we know, because that's been made very clear in the COVID-19 outbreak,
because that's where this virus undoubtedly started, at least distantly.
So is it safe to say that coronaviruses as a family, probably when compared to any other
family of viruses, flaviviruses that produce hep C that otherwise would have nothing in common,
about the only thing that's true of viruses is they need a host to replicate. Is that about
where the similarities end across the broadest discrimination of viruses, or are there other
things that are uniquely... I mean, I guess they all have either DNA or RNA, but typically not both,
right? Yeah, except maybe HIV seems to have both. But generally, they have one or the other.
Depending on the amount of genetic information they have, they can do more or less functions
than other viruses. This is gigantic viruses, or these giant viruses, which they've called, that
seem to have almost all the material. You need to almost be a cell, but not a cell.
But they have a lot of their own material for making proteins and RNA. Most RNA viruses just
have the genetic material for programming the functions needed to reproduce the virus and also
make the proteins that cause the structure of the virus, that form the structure of the virus.
So those are simpler viruses. Coronaviruses have the unusual characteristic of being huge.
So the genetic information of a coronavirus is about four times that of the polio virus,
and yet the virus doesn't seem to do that much more than polio virus. So a little uncertain
exactly why it needs all that genetic information. And when you say huge, Stanley, do you just mean
the amount of RNA in it, or do you mean the actual diameter under an electron microscope as well?
The amount of RNA in it. Certainly the coronavirus is bigger than the polio virus,
but that's because it has all this genetic material stuffed into the middle of it.
Can you put it in context for us? If you take the genetic material contained within a typical
coronavirus, how does it stack up against a human gene? I mean, the listener might not understand
what base pairs look like or how many kilodaltons we're talking about, but just
contextualize it in some way. Well, let me see how I can do that. Because it's big for a virus,
a gene. If you took genes and laid them side by side, it could be equivalent to 15 human genes
laid side by side in terms of length, but human genes have variable length. So if it was a longer
human gene, it could be fewer of those for the viral genome. This particular virus codes around
probably about 25 or so different proteins varying size. A lot of them are pretty small.
So it's a lot of information, but it's not compared to the human genome, which has 20,000
genes. It's a very tiny amount when you think about 25. And does it like human DNA contain
coding and non-coding segments alike that are just as important? No. Human DNA contains both
non-coding sequences within genes and non-coding sequences outside. The vast majority of the human
genome is not for coding. With a virus, the vast majority is for coding. There may be stretches
here and there that are spacers, as there were, between genes, but they're a real and a minority.
The strict answer to your question is yes, there's parts that are non-coding, but it's a tiny fraction
compared to the amount that actually codes for genes. Just to go down the path of some speculation,
do we have a sense of what the evolutionary pressure was for coronavirus? I've never really
stopped to think about it, but it always struck me as viruses, unlike bacteria, don't really serve
a useful purpose. I mean, it's true that maybe most of them don't directly harm us, but if you
eradicated this planet of bacteria, we would all die pretty quickly. We live in a very healthy
symbiotic relationship, despite a pathologic relationship with a small few of them. But
if I could conduct a thought experiment and remove every virus from this universe, wouldn't
the world just keep ticking along fine, or is there something I'm missing about their function?
Well, I don't think you're right. We have lots of great examples. For example, in the ocean,
there's zillions of viruses that interact with bacteria. I would bet if you took that interaction
away that there would be a problem. And in the people talk about, even in the human gut, there's
all these viruses that people find. Some of them, I think, interact with those commensal bacteria
and are useful. Whether they're absolutely necessary, I don't think we know as much as we
do about commensal bacteria, which are really important for human life and animal life.
But I would bet if you took away all the viruses in the world, sure, you'd eliminate some of the
ones that cause human disease or non-human animal disease. But I think you might get away from
others that are actually beneficial. Yeah, so there might be some knockoff effect where they're
helping something that's second order to us. They're helping the bacteria that are helping us,
or helping some other distant organism that's way down the plankton sub-chain that I haven't
considered fully. I think that that's a possibility. And then bacteriophage on bacteria are going to
be even different than the ones directly on human cells. But there may even be animal viruses
that have roles that we don't understand very well that are important. I know there's some
animal viruses that interact. The insects have a relationship with each other, and the animal
viruses have an important part in maintaining some of the developmental patterns in those insects.
I know that some of them are lost, but I can't tell you more, remember. But there's definitely
viruses that, without which, there would be problems. So I'm sure you're tired of telling
this, but I think everyone should know this by now. But if not, why does it derive the name
corona virus? What is the corona referring to? If you look under the electron microscope, it has
these projections from the surface of the virus that look like either the corona of the sun or
the corona of a crown. So I think the first people who saw it under the electron microscope decided
to name it based on that. You have to have a little imagination, but it's not so far off.
And of course, this is relevant when we start to talk about the immune response to it, because the
immune response is particularly strong when it comes to certain parts of the viral coat. And
we'll probably come back and talk about spike proteins and things like that. So when did these
corona viruses show up in terms of our understanding of common colds?
I think we identified the first one in the 1930s and 40s from chicken. That's what I remember,
that the infectious bronchitis virus was found in chickens. And then in the 1960s,
people identified viruses that caused the common cold that had the same kind of appearance as the
infectious bronchitis virus. And I think by then we knew something about some of the pig viruses
as well. So the human, it was isolated from people with colds and had the same structure
as corona viruses and chickens and pigs. So that's how the new was in the coronavirus family.
Is it the exception or the rule, Stanley, that a virus that infects humans also has an animal host?
I think I would say it can go either way so much that it's hard to make a strong conclusion.
Viruses like measles virus infects only people, smallpox only infects people. That's why we can
eliminate them from human populations, in theory. Viruses or the corona viruses mostly seem to be
able to infect other animals as well. But the virus that I worked with for years in the lab,
mouse hepatitis virus was a mouse virus. And I don't think it affected anything but mice.
The human viruses, even now, so we're seeing that SARS-CoV-2, the cause of COVID-19, can infect
animals. So humans can infect these other animals by spreading the virus. SARS-CoV certainly
infected other animals. MERS-CoV is really a camel virus, so by definition, it affects other animals.
The human common cold coronaviruses, at least one of them can infect other animals. And I don't know,
one of them probably came from bats, but I don't know if they can infect bats. So I think
coronaviruses usually can go across species, but I don't think always. And other viruses often can
go across species, but not always. And it's really going to play, as I was saying, into the ability to
eliminate a virus from the human population. So if you're keeping track of all the things that make
a virus difficult for us as a species, so if you're trying to build a super virus, having the ability
to go into an animal host is an important feature of that, because you can basically
quote-unquote hide outside of the humans for a while, even while a large population of the
humans are either vaccinated or acquiring natural immunity or even approaching herd immunity,
and you can effectively lay dormant outside of the humans for a while.
Maybe. When you think about different viruses, certainly that's true for West Nile virus. We
have the best vaccine in the world. We still have West Nile virus floating around in birds and other
animals. Of course, West Nile virus really isn't a human virus. It's a virus that ended up in humans
at the end, but it wasn't really the intent as a word of the virus to infect humans. Others,
like measles, did just fine with having infecting everybody and having huge amounts of herd immunity,
and still every three years are less coming out and infecting human populations again.
Is that because the R-naught of measles was just so high that it was like you just had one little
crack in the dam and it was a disaster, whereas for most things like influenza or even coronaviruses,
the R-naught is an order of magnitude lower? Yeah, I think that that certainly contributes
to measles. You had five people out of 100 not vaccinated or not resistant to the virus. Those
people would get infected if you put them in a room with somebody who was positive for the
measles virus. Same thing is true for smallpox too, where it spread out an animal host. Others,
I don't know, polio, I don't think of polio as having much of another animal host. I think that
continues to be in human populations mostly because of poor vaccination and because we
use live attenuated vaccine that ended up in water and either mutates or doesn't mutate,
it's not gone. Where did those viruses come from? If they never had an animal host,
where did they evolve? I think they did initially have an animal host. Measles is thought to evolve
from rinderpestin, which affects animals in Africa. You see, that's the other thing about
the animal host is if you evolve from an animal host, the virus evolved from animal host,
but then change so much to infect humans, it may not be able to then cause an infection in the
animal host. So these like the SARS-CoV-2 that causes COVID-19, we don't really know what it
would do if you put it back in bats. No one's going to try it, but I don't know if a bat would
be infected by it because it may have changed enough even in the little bit of time it's been
out of the bat. So it can't infect the bat very well anymore. Wow, that's really interesting. So
ping pongs back and forth until it finds a more favorable host. I mean, this would suggest from
an evolutionary fitness standpoint that if it starts in an animal, comes to a human, stays in
a human, it must find the human on some level a more desirable host. I don't know, but that's
making the virus a little more anthropomorphic than it might be needed. If it's in humans,
it may never see a bat again. So it's not that it's more desirable host. That's a fair point.
Yeah, humans and bats don't interact that much even though they interact more than
maybe desirable given these viruses, but it's not like the virus can look around and say,
oh, there's a bat I think. Yeah, let me go try that out again and see how it compares to this.
Last question on this topic, tell me a little bit about HIV. I'm just not a student of my
immunology. Is HIV a virus that is now believed to have evolved? I mean, I know back, I remember
a million years ago, people said, oh, it came from this monkey or that monkey. Do we have a
very clear sense of the lineage of HIV? I think it's beyond what I know well. I think that we
have a very strong sense that it came from non-human primates. I think we may know more exactly, but
what I read periodically is some studies, it seems like the virus was in human populations
or identified way before its first obvious entry into people who became HIV infected. So I think
it's clearly from non-human primates, but the exact details, I don't know. But I think some
people do and some of these sources, like some of the non-human primates have an HIV
like virus that's pretty close. Let's go into the, let's say it's the late 90s. So it's pre-SARS.
You're working hard on coronaviruses. At that point in time, am I doing the math right that
there are basically sort of four endemic coronaviruses that are not especially severe,
but just circulate through humans causing annoying respiratory infections year after year.
Is that directionally the lay of the land? It's actually only two in the mid-90s because two of
them discovered after SARS in 2004. Wow. Which were the two that came along and that were there in
the 90s? 229E and OC43. Okay. And what did we know about people's immune response to them? I mean,
did anybody ever say, hey, we should vaccinate against these? Or was it they're not that
interesting? They don't make people that sick. Who cares? Yeah, it was more of the latter.
Appropriately so. If you're going to spend a huge amount of money and we know that huge amounts of
money involved in making a vaccine, why would you spend it on a cold virus? People get colds. It's
annoying. The other thing is that really that may be relevant to, I think, about COVID-19 is that
people got these cold viruses. They could be reinfected. So they could be reinfected a year
later. And that's what the papers we were talking about earlier really talk about is that the immune
response may be, if you have a mild infection, you may have a more transient immune response.
Yeah. There are three or four papers that I can't wait to dive into and we're going to do it. I just
want to make sure the listener doesn't get too lost in what we're talking about. But actually,
if you're listening to this now and you have not listened to the interview with David Watkins,
this would be a great time to hit pause, go back and do that. Because in that discussion, we really
do the immunology tour de force and we explain the difference between the innate immune system,
the adaptive immune system, and the two branches of the adaptive immune system,
the humoral system, which relies on B cells and their antibodies, and the cellular system,
which relies on T cells. And I have a very strong suspicion that very soon Stanley and I are going
to get into some of the weeds around the B cells versus the T cells. And again, I don't think you
can educate yourself enough on this topic if you want to truly understand what's going on with
these viruses. Bringing it back to the late 90s, tell me what your interest was at that time. So
obviously, you're a scholar, you're doing incredible work. Did you think at that point in time, gosh,
these coronaviruses aren't that interesting. They're not really a threat to humans. They're not really
a threat to my patients in the way other viruses are. Even RSV would be more of a threat to children.
Wupenkopf would be more of a threat to children. What is it that kept you in this at the time
relatively benign virus? Help me understand, was it kept you in a field that ultimately turned out
to be a very productive decision? At the time, we were interested mostly in this mouse virus and
the human disease multiple sclerosis. So thinking about how does a virus go into the brain end up
in the cells that make myelin, which are the sheets in the brain that cover the axons. And how does
the virus end up there? And then once the host realizes that the virus is there, how does it
manage to destroy tissue while it's eliminating the virus? How come the immune response can't
figure out how to rid the cells of virus without also destroying the cells themselves and destroying
the function of their cells? So that's what I was really studying. How does this occur?
What kind of immune responses were elicited by the virus? What mattered the most? What caused
demyelination? And what caused remyelination, which is the process of getting myelin back,
and which is in people with multiple sclerosis is the period when they have
immune emissions after relapsing and permissing or after relapsing have disease and they get better
again for a bit of time? For people who have some form where they get better to a large extent,
how does that occurring as well? So we were using the virus to try to study that.
But to be clear, was your personal interest at that time more in this is a virus that helps
us understand a disease like MS where we can understand the demyelination, remyelination process?
Or was it more, I think from a pediatric and a neurobiological development standpoint,
I want to make sure I understand what's happening in trimester one that is potentially injuring a
child's brain. Those two aren't necessarily mutually exclusive, but were you bent more
towards one than the other? I think that by the mid 90s, I was thinking much more about the first.
How does the virus infecting the brain? How is it cleared? Why does clearance always involve
tissue destruction? Why is that happening like that? So you're basically now becoming a
neurobiologist with a background in immunology, virology, and pediatrics. Well, at that point,
I became a neurobiologist with a background in virology and cell biology. I didn't really start
doing immunology till the early 90s, 1990s. So then we were doing some of it. Yes. The virus
preceded my doing immunology. So tell me what's going on when SARS hits. What is it? I can't even
remember exactly. Was this 02, 03? The end of 02 became a big deal in 2003 and then was eliminated
in July 2003 for all intents and purposes. So tell us this story in some detail. I think
for many people, I remember it because there was a component that was in Toronto. I grew up in
Toronto. I wasn't living there at the time, but just that sort of perked my ears. But at the same
time I was in residency, so I was so sleep deprived. If I could drive home without crashing,
that was an accomplishment. So it's not like I was really paying attention either, but can you
give us sort of a really detailed account of where this virus came from, how it emerged,
and what impact it had on you and how it may have shifted your thinking.
Yeah. So the way it emerged, we heard about this virus that was causing a respiratory disease in
southern China. And initially we all thought this was going to be a kind of flu virus because flu
viruses we know initiate often start in southern China, particularly in the city of Guangzhou,
which is across the bay from Hong Kong. So we heard about these viruses and then it became
clear that they were a coronavirus. This was isolated by several laboratories. But we learned
in retrospect is that they actually came from a live animal market in Guangzhou. And this was
a place where animals were all put together for sale for food and other purposes. And so there
were bats along with other exotic live animals. And we learned that the coronavirus, the SARS
coronavirus, was almost certainly a bat virus that spread to these other animals. And the
virus rapidly adapted to these other animals and sometimes infected human handlers of that market.
So people were actually handling the animals to sell them. And many of those became sick. Many
developed subclinical disease. And we know that up to a third of the handlers actually had antibodies
to SARS-CoV. So we know that this was going back and forth a lot. Then we know that some of the
time it spread to mainland China. How many times that occurred, we don't know whether it was exactly
the same virus that we study in the lab. I don't think we really know that well. The reason that this
became really was brought to the world's attention is that a single animal handler became ill enough
to see a physician. The physician actually became quite ill, didn't go home, rather went to a Hong
Kong hotel. And at that point, it was really sick and spread the virus to the other people on the
floor. And they all went through their homes. And that's how the virus ended up spreading around the
world because of this one physician who ended up going to Hong Kong. Whether this would have
occurred anyways is an open question, of course. The main set of events was single event. And that's
why the virus seemed to start from a single point source. Now, help me understand something. I think
most people listening to this are now familiar with R0, but we'll explain it again. What was the
R0 of that SARS virus? In retrospect, I guess, what do we believe it was? How transmissible was it?
Yeah, so this is a good question because the official numbers has an R0 of about two to three,
which means that a single person will infect two to three people. So clearly, as you can see,
without even thinking about it very hard, if a virus starts with one person, then infects two,
and then each of those infects two more people, you now have four infections, they infect two,
you get eight. So you can quickly get up to high numbers by this exponential growth.
And we'll hit pause there for one sec, just to put that in the context. Earlier, for example,
you talked a lot about measles. Measles has an R0 probably north of 10, correct?
Yeah, around 15.
I mean, that's about as high as they come. I mean, that's an explosive exponential multiplier.
At the other end of the spectrum, today, HIVs R0 would be less than one.
Yeah, and I think that HIV is a little different because it's not a respiratory spread.
Yeah, so let's use another respiratory example. What would be a low R0? Well,
let's use the other coronaviruses. If you take those other coronaviruses, they're one to two
at most, right?
Exactly. So one person infects someone else on the average. This is on the average, of course.
So going back to now SARS, sorry to interrupt you there, but now you've got a two to three R0. So
this is quite a spreading virus. This physician goes to the hotel, he gets a bunch of people
potentially sick. And obviously now that can take the virus around the world because presumably
people at hotels are going to go back someplace, right?
Yeah, so I think that the R0 of two to three though may be misleading because there's no
question that the R0 on the average was two to three, but it consisted of spread within the
hospital. Spread occurred much more readily. SARS was a virus that really caused pneumonia
and not much more. So the virus didn't readily spread from one person to another until that
first person was pretty ill. And then if that person went in the hospital and you now started
as a word mucking up their lung fluids so that virus was now released into the air by procedures,
either intubation or suctioning or whatever else needed to be done, then the R0 factor would be
much more than two or three. And the community, because this is a deep pneumonia, it really isn't
that contagious. So I think that if we split it up, those 8,000 cases would be an average of two
to three with quite a range depending on where the virus was acquired.
And I think the other lesson we have to take away from SARS is it gets widely quoted as having a
10% mortality rate. But again, how could we possibly say that when we don't know the total
number of cases that might be the case fatality rate? I mean, case fatality rate is not that
interesting. It's the infection fatality rate that really matters. And it's certainly possible,
isn't it, that many more people had it. Even let's say there was five times the number of people who
actually had the illness but didn't come down with a severe enough version that they warranted
hospitalization or testing. You would all of a sudden say technically the mortality of this is
2%, which is still absolutely devastating virus. But it's not the devastation of when you hear 10%
mortality. I mean, that's literally like playing Russian roulette.
That's a way to think about it. But it was very hard at the time finding patients who are
asymptomatic and were infected. So the thinking was that anybody who became infected actually
became symptomatic. What you say makes perfect sense. But I'll tell you another story. So the
next coronavirus that came upon us was the MERS coronavirus, the Middle East respiratory
coronavirus. And this is a disease that's exactly the same, not exactly, but very similar to SARS
and being a deep lung disease. This disease, the mortality is billed as 35%. So really terrible.
And it's different though. So what you just talked about, the 2002 to 2003 virus that started in a
market in Southern China who has the same name as the current virus we're talking about, but we
refer to them as SARS-1 and SARS-2, they're in the same beta family, which we didn't really get into.
Do you want to take a minute to explain that? Because MERS is a slightly different subdivision
of the family. Can you help people understand that nuance? Yeah. So it's all very similar.
They're all in the same general group of coronaviruses and within the same subgroup of
coronaviruses, but they're slightly different in their genome organization and in some of their
coding. So they're put into a separate category. So it's a coronavirus. Before we knew so much
about from sequence, they would have been considered the same type of coronavirus,
but it's different enough. So we classify it a little differently. What that means is it's a
little more distant from the SARS coronavirus. So there's less thinking that one could actually
provide immune protection from the other. Though in fact, there's some cross reactivity. MERS
coronavirus is recognized in part by SARS coronavirus sera from people who survive. They're close.
It's like your third cousin instead of your first cousin. It's pretty close, but not as close.
And this will obviously be interesting when we come back to this discussion of cross immunity.
And basically that's probably the biggest difference as opposed to a functional
difference about the virulence or the potential for virulence, correct?
Right. Right.
Okay. So again, let's not pick it back up. It's what is it? 2009 when MERS came along?
Well, MERS and camels probably came along at least in 1983, but in people it was found in 2012.
And that's the earliest cases. There's a few mysteries about MERS coronavirus. Why is it only
in the Arabian Peninsula? So tell me about that. Did people, and when I say people, I really mean
scientists. I'm sure the population wasn't wondering around thinking about this, but
did scientists appreciate that there was a coronavirus in camels in the 80s from the early
80s? Was that something appreciated? Nope. This was absolutely not appreciated because in camels,
these coronaviruses caused the common cold. Well, they could.
So that's why nobody would care. Camel gets a cold. You don't even know. He goes to camel
Walgreen and you never hear about him again. So what do we think accounts for the virus
jumping quite literally from a camel to a human and call it 2012-ish?
We don't know. The virus has been a camel since the 80s and probably earlier,
don't look earlier. And we know it doesn't jump in Africa or other parts of Asia. So this is real
mystery in this virus. Why is it only in the Arabian Peninsula? When you look at the MERS virus
in the camels, it's still the same in the Arabian Peninsula versus other camels?
Hard to know. It may be subtly different in parts of Africa where there's no MERS,
but we have a lot of trouble saying that those differences account for the fact that there's
basically no cases in Africa and you have these cases in Saudi Arabia rising all the time now.
And when you say Africa, do you include North Africa? Were there any cases that arose in Egypt
or Algeria, Libya, Morocco? Yes. They did not occur in those places? Yeah, yeah. The camels
are infected there, but people are not. Oh, wow. Because a lot of people would sort of say, look,
I mean, if something happens in Saudi Arabia, it would be just as likely to happen in Iran or
Egypt. I mean, even though they're technically belonging to different continents, they're very
similar geographically, but you're saying, no, there was a really hard line distinguishing that.
And we don't to this day have a sense of what allowed that jump. Yeah, we don't know. The fact
is not only occurred in 2012, it's occurring once or twice a week now because people are coming in
who actually have no contact with camels and are coming into the hospital with MERS. They often
have comorbidities that are older or they might have diabetes, but otherwise they don't even have
contact with camel. They have to get it from a camel, but not clear how. So wait a minute.
That was my next question. Do we know that it can or cannot spread human to human once a person gets
it from its most likely source of transmission, which is a camel? Can one person infect another?
Yeah. So this is where the R naught factor becomes important again, because the official number for
MERS is somewhere between zero and four. I think outside of hospitals is probably near to 0.35, 0.5,
somewhere in that low range. So it means it's not impossible, but all you need is somebody to be
infected and happen to infect someone else who's highly susceptible and that highly susceptible
person will then appear at the hospital not having had any contact with a camel. And that zero to four,
which is such a broad range. I've read that as the official range. It's so broad as to be unhelpful.
That's really the camel R naught. That's the spread from camel to human. And then as you said,
human to human transmission is probably going to occur in the hospital. And so MERS becomes the
scariest of them all just on mortality because the official numbers are basically it killed a third of
the people that were infected. It's about almost 900 deaths out of call it 2500 confirmed cases.
That's about as scary as any virus, maybe outside of Ebola. But again, the absolute numbers are so
low. The transmissibility human to human doesn't seem as high, especially when you
consider that the scariest viruses are ones that are transmitted from asymptomatic people, right?
Yeah. So this one, like SARS, is mostly transmitted from people who have lung disease already,
who have severe lung disease. I don't think the R naught is actually camel to camel. I don't think
it takes that into consideration. Rather than what it takes to the consideration is a hospital
spread. It's like SARS and some hospitals spread. And that's been basically not stopped completely,
because it's my friends in Saudi Arabia say somebody comes in with this disease. We think
about it quickly, but we may not think about it in every case quickly enough. So there may be still
some spread within the hospital. So nosocomial spread, which you're referring to in hospital
spread, is a big problem because you just don't have it on the front of your mind that every
person who shows up in respiratory distress could have this. And therefore, A, potentially the
healthcare workers themselves can be infected because it's not just the proximity, but it's
the type of procedures that are being done. When you put a breathing tube in somebody, you're
really creating an effective portal for the virus to get to you. And then obviously we know how
infections like that can spread through intensive care units and such.
Yeah, that's exactly right. That's exactly why it's a problem.
So why did this not turn into even an epidemic within the Arabian Peninsula? I mean,
you did mention that we still see a few cases each year, but 2500 confirmed cases directionally
makes it not even a sort of an epidemic, really, let alone a pandemic. Why do you think this just
wasn't something that spread despite its potential for devastation at the mortality level?
Because I think that that R naught of 0.3 really makes it not possible or not likely.
There's plenty of cases with murders where people went back to relatively poor country
after having been a worker in Saudi Arabia, were found to be infected and infected nobody.
So that nobody became ill from that patient, even though they weren't really looked at.
That's as opposed to Korea where there's that one patient who infected 186 people.
So there was really a confluence of lots of bad luck for that to have occurred.
And then going back to SARS-CoV-1, what basically accounts for the eradication of that,
call it in 2003, 2004?
The combination of there being no reservoir. So it's not like camels, which could continue
introducing to human populations. And the fact that because you weren't contagious till you were
sick, it was easy to look at somebody and say, oh, that person has SARS. We're going to stick them
in a room by himself, take care of him and make sure he infects nobody else.
Then you would stop the disease. It's a classic kind of quarantining,
identification quarantining that we talk about all the time with COVID-19.
But it's really feasible with SARS when you're talking about a total of 8,000 cases around the
world. I mean, Stanley, to hear you tell the story this way, it's just it's like a bad movie,
because you could be lulled into a false sense of confidence by the time MERS blows over.
You can say, hey, OK, I got it. We've got a few of these coronaviruses. They cause a bunch of
colds. You get a runny nose in the summer, but it's really nothing. And yeah, it's true. Two
really bad actors showed up that on a virus to virus level can really hurt their host.
But they're nothing to really be afraid of. In the case of SARS 1, it has two things that make it
really friendly to humans. One, it can't bounce back and forth between humans and animals.
And two, you don't really spread it. You're very unlikely to spread it if you're not symptomatic.
You don't have to shut the world down. But not only that, you get to isolate people when they're
sick and treat them before they treat others. So the virus really gave up two big potential
superpowers. In the case of MERS, sure, it lives in animals and it's never going to leave those
animals. But it has such a poor ability to spread between humans almost under any circumstance,
unless you're probably sticking a breathing tube in them, that it was just so easy to contain.
If the stories stop there, you'd say coronaviruses are just not a threat to us.
Yeah, so I think some people in the field more than me said, well, let's go look at
coronaviruses and bats. And so what they did is they found other coronaviruses. And it was
actually for scientific reason or a different one than just searching for the viruses. We were
trying to figure out where did the SARS coronavirus really begin. So people went and looked at bat
colonies throughout a train accident. That's where SARS began and asked, can we find other bats,
other bat viruses that are more similar to SARS-CoV than the ones we know about right this minute?
Because we could isolate the virus in the wet markets in Wurundjel, but we didn't know where
they came from exactly, which kind of bats. And it was just a trick finding it in bats. And so,
but while doing that, people found other viruses that could, in theory, enter a human cell by using
the same kind of mechanism that SARS-CoV used to enter human cells. So there was some people who
were saying, there were a lot of people, some people in the field who were saying, well, we
potentially have more of a problem because there may be other ways to infect people. There may be
other viruses that can infect people. And so I think there was a concern that this could happen
again. And MERS is the same thing. We haven't identified the exact precursor to MERS in bats,
but it's clearly viruses that look like the MERS, coronavirus in bats. And so if they were able to
use the human receptor and didn't take too much adaptation to infect humans, then you can imagine
the same thing occurring with MERS sometimes in the future occurring again with SARS-CoV-like
viruses. So you're right, in 2015, we were thinking these viruses really caused bad pneumonia,
but it's going to be like influenza H5N1. It's going to have very, very little human to human
spread and mostly animal to human spread. Is there a necessary relationship that says
the viruses like MERS that are incredibly deadly if you get them, just luck is on our side and
they don't have much transmissibility? Or is that simply luck so far? And there's no reason to
suggest teleologically that that has to be the case. In other words, you could imagine a scenario
where you take something that has the transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2, which we'll get to
and explain why it is much more of a headache than SARS-CoV-1 or MERS. If you take the
transmissibility of that, which is both and primarily is a factor of the fact that it can
spread before you're symptomatic, coupled with the actual pathology of MERS, which I want to contrast
with these viruses. I mean, that's a double whammy. You can really get into a dangerous
situation. Not that this hasn't been a disaster, but it could be a 5x disaster. Is there anything
that tells us that's unlikely because of this feature of the biology of the virus?
I don't think there's anything that's unlikely. I don't think there's anything about the feature of
the virus. I think about this as SARS-CoV-2 being a mixture of the common cold coronavirus
and then a mixture of either SARS or MERS coronavirus in the lungs. That's why you have
the transmissibility and the severe disease because it does both. When you think about other
bad diseases, like even the epidemic flu in 1918, that really did about the same thing. It was very,
very, very transmissible and it killed about a few percent of the people infected. But if you infect
everybody and you kill 3% or 4%, you're killing a lot of people. That's what this virus is doing
also because it's transmissible so readily because it behaves like a common cold coronavirus. That
rate of lethality is not super high, but the denominator is so huge that you have a lot of
people dying from it. Is there something about the pathology of this virus? How does it differ?
I mean, when you think about SARS-1 and MERS, that let's just say directionally those numbers
are right in terms of the denominator wasn't bigger than we think and you're killing basically
1 in 10 or 1 in 3 people infected. What did the virus actually do in the lungs that would render
people so helpless? Yeah, I think it's the same thing that SARS-CoV-2 does in the lungs. In those
people who get severe disease, I think we don't really understand what's going on. We think that
there's lots of virus in the lungs and we think there's a very strong and probably inappropriate
immune response that's causing much of the damage that we see in lungs. It's a combination of those
two features. That's why people are, from the beginning with SARS, people are trying to figure
out a way to both limit virus replication and also decrease the host immune response so that you
don't have this extra result of an exuberant immune response. Do the other two viruses,
SARS-1 and MERS, do they also gain entry through the ACE2 receptor or did they use a different
receptor to enter the pneumocyte? Well, SARS uses the same receptor. MERS uses a different
receptor. One thing that's really curious is SARS doesn't affect the upper airway to an appreciable
extent even though it uses the same receptor. There's also one of the common cold coronaviruses,
NO63, uses ACE2 only affects the upper airway and doesn't affect the lungs to any appreciable extent.
And that could also account for the change in transmissibility because if you are only
infecting the lower airway, you're probably less transmissible than SARS-CoV-2, which can infect
both. Exactly, exactly. That's why SARS was not so contagious because it only stayed in the deep
lungs until you went to the hospital and had that tube put down for breathing or some other procedure done.
So do you think that SARS-1 and MERS were so much more lethal than SARS-2 because they elicited a
greater immune response once they infected the lung or because they caused greater pneumocyte
damage when they infected the lung? I think that it's actually because they all cause the same
amount of damage or pretty similar, but you have this huge denominator in SARS-CoV-2 if people have
mild disease. So I think that it's one way to look at these numbers and this is not a perfect
calculation, but if you have with SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, there were 100 people infected, they all get
some variation in pneumonia, and you have a certain mortality rate ranging from 10% to 30%.
SARS-CoV-2, of those 100 people, maybe 20 of them are going to get the lung disease, the other 18
are going to be asymptomatic, subclinical, have a cold, have something in the upper respiratory tract.
If you now take that 20% as your denominator and divide the 6% mortality that we're seeing,
the 5% mortality, I don't know what the number is exactly, but let's say 5% by 20%, you have a 25%
mortality, which is near the SARS and MERS. So just let me make sure I understand that.
Are you saying it's more the law of large numbers and we have such a big denominator with SARS-CoV-2
that you're going to normalize more or are you comparing case fatality to case fatality,
whereas I'm thinking of it as the IFR as opposed to the CFR for SARS? Because I think the IFR
of SARS-CoV-2 is very population dependent, but I think it's much closer to 1% to 2%
than the initial numbers that people feared of 5% to 10%, which would put it more in the
ballpark of SARS-2. That's the way I used to think about it when this first started.
In January and February, the mortality rate was 2.8%. And now if you look at anything official,
it's near to 5% to 6%. So what you say makes perfect sense, it should be near to 1% to 2%,
but it's been hard to prove that by all the official numbers. So what I was saying more is
that if the mortality rate in SARS and MERS out of everybody who was sick all had pneumonia,
and of those people some number died, and SARS-CoV-2, if only one out of five people or less
actually get pneumonia, then the fraction that died, if you use that same fraction who died
over that 20%, you basically are multiplying your number by five. So if your number is 5%,
then it goes up to 25%, if it's 3%, it goes up to 15%. So where we are exactly, I don't know, but
it may be that the upper transmission is the readily transmissibility of the virus is what's
really making the numbers so huge, and that everything else is doing is consistent with
what SARS and MERS did if you confine yourself to just looking at the lower respiratory tract disease.
Now this is something that might be a little bit outside of what you've studied, but I'll ask
anyway. One of the lingering questions, there are so many that I have, comes down to the survivors.
I mean, obviously we think a lot about the mortality of this, but if you take a person
who gets infected, and they're not asymptomatic, so we know that a lot of people kind of don't even
know they've got SARS-CoV-2, and the only reason you figure it out is after the fact serologic
analysis tells us that they did. But there's a non-trivial amount of people who get sick as hell,
and they get what they would describe as the worst cold of their life. I have at least two friends I
can think of in this situation who three months later can barely run a nine minute mile again,
and they're slowly getting back in shape. When I did a quick check on this, looking at the SARS,
MERS patient follow-up data, I didn't find a heck of a lot that told me about long-term lung function.
Do you know much about this? And I would imagine that there's now more of an interest to go back
and assess that than there was three months ago when I tried to look this up.
Yeah, even before this all occurred, I asked my friends in Saudi Arabia about follow-up on the
MERS patients, and I could never get information as to what exactly was going on. I suspect that
they had problems, whether they be forever or a few months is unclear, especially since your
friends were younger and fitter. In MERS, particularly MERS, if it's mostly older people,
people with diabetes, people who have comorbidities, they may take them longer to get back to base
or fine. It's probably not going to be running miles. I suspect it'll take a while to get back.
I don't know how much fibrosis was at the end of it all, how much permanent damage there was.
I suspect that there was a fair bit, but you always have, you know, at Kinsaurus, people
always talk about neurological disease without actually ever finding the virus in the brain.
And then it was attributed to being on ventilators and corticosteroids for long periods of time,
contributing to cognitive dysfunction. And occasionally, the virus was in the brain.
So it's all a mix that's hard to really sort out what the major components are,
because there's several things that contribute to the outcomes.
Well, based on your knowledge of coronaviruses and your knowledge, in particular, their impact on the
brain, do you think that there are plausible mechanisms by which, even for those who recover
from SARS, there could be lasting neurologic impact that is not the byproduct of hypoxia
or vent head, pump head, any of the other more mechanical or other physiologic accounts? In
other words, do you believe that there is a plausible scenario by which the virus
could have residual neurologic value? We can't find any evidence in the virus
in the brain that it seems less likely that it's direct virus infection.
What about an immune response?
Yeah, that's what I was going to say. If you take a disease like Kawasaki's in children,
we know that that's a disease that is mediated by some sort of immune response. We don't know
who it seems here, like COVID-19 is somehow provoking this response in this very, very small
subset of children. That certainly leads to consequences in the heart, long term consequences
or it can. You can certainly imagine scenarios like that. How often this occurs and what's going
on exactly, I don't think we know. Between the resolution, so to speak, of MERS and where we were,
call it a year ago today, Stanley, where was your head at with respect to the big one? Were you in
the camp that said, yeah, I've carved out a pretty nice niche here. I'm going to be studying
coronaviruses forever. Or was there a part of you that said, this is a threat to national security,
to the world. There's a pandemic brewing here. How did you think this could unfold?
I certainly wasn't smart enough to predict that there was going to be a pandemic. As I said,
some of my friends were worried about additional infections in humans. I don't know that anyone
would have predicted a pandemic like this one. I want to pause you there for a second. Why?
Not that I did, but I want to push on that for a moment. All the ingredients were there.
I was going to say is that Department of Defense in 2010 or 11 put out a report about possible
emerging viruses as being really the major threat. Coronaviruses were on that list.
Bill Gates talked about this. It's become a very well-known TED talk that is painful to watch now
because of how accurate it was. You have these two examples of viruses that have enormous potential
to cause harm, but fortunately for us at the time, they just don't spread well. A few tweaks, i.e.,
infection of the upper respiratory tract and a slower onset to symptoms would easily double
your R naught. Fair enough. I'm joking, of course. I'm joking on you guys for not thinking this could
happen. Let's fast forward now to when did you first hear about the outbreak in China? I'm
assuming it was early December, late November? No, I don't think it started quite that early.
I would say late December. The first official cases were in December. We think there may have
been some in November, but I think that the people in China, scientists and doctors in China,
knew something was going on in December. Then it was eventually reported very early January.
I think we knew a few weeks early, but even then we didn't really know how much human-to-human
transmission there was. Now, I have to say that at the time, given the number of cases, we should
have guessed that something unusual was going on. But to the SARS epidemic, we had these cases and
lots of people were infected. We didn't really know how the spread was occurring. At the time,
by early January or mid-January, we had 800 cases in the world. It didn't seem to be extraordinarily
different from these other viruses. Maybe if we had had more information about what was going on
in Wuhan, we would have realized, aha, this is doing something that's different than what SARS
and MERS did, but we didn't have that information. When did it become clear to you personally that
this was going to be a much bigger problem than SARS and MERS ever were?
Funny you ask that because I remember in December when we really didn't know anything about human-to-
human transmission. I spoke to my friends in China and I got off the phone and told my wife,
this is a big deal. So I'm not sure what I was basing that on because it wasn't so much evidence
of human-to-human transmission. It was pretty clear to me then that this was going to be a
major problem. At that time, could you have predicted it would have been this big an issue?
I don't think so. Mostly because all the previous diseases had remained geographically confined.
So SARS was really a disease in China with a little spread around the world. MERS was really
a disease in the Arabian Peninsula with that one case in spreading, infecting several people in
Korea. But this one, maybe the dynamics of everything are so different. People spread
travel from Wuhan much more frequently because people have more money. So they fly more, they
take the train more. So that helped to spread a lot. Then of course this is transmissible.
The other thing is that we had gone through some of this with H5N1. So in the late 1990s,
people were saying, all we need to do is have this be transmittable and it'd be a disaster
because we don't really have good immune responses to it. And it never happened.
So yeah, what happened in 2009 with H5N1? Because the skeptics would say, hey, we don't need to
worry about this SARS-CoV-2. The last time we cried that the sky was falling, it didn't fall.
Right. So that was H1N1 in 2009. And that started off as a lethal disease. It was identified in
Mexico. It seemed to have a high lethality, but it's more cases became clear, identified. It's
clear that it didn't. It just was lots of cases and very little mortality.
It was basically influenza.
It was influenza. It was just a variant of influenza. There wasn't H5N1, which causes
a severe pneumonia.
H5N1 is the 1919?
No, H5N1 is the one that's never made it to a human population to an appreciable extent.
Pure swine.
Yeah, it's mostly pigs and birds, but it kills birds and most food doesn't kill birds.
So the concern was that it would change to infect, to be transmissible human to human,
but it never did. So the same thing with thinking about coronaviruses. They hadn't done this so far.
We certainly thought they could do it. But this is an interesting question that's, how do you
prepare for a pandemic that you don't have? Because it's something I've been asked about and
thought about. So you're sitting there in 2005 and SARS goes away. How do you decide what kind
of resources you're going to put developing antivirals, developing vaccines against SARS,
a disease that doesn't exist anymore?
The way the American system is set up for this, if you have a good idea and you propose to the NIH,
you have a good chance of getting funding. But on the other hand, if you're competing against
other grants that make more compelling arguments for funding and deal with diseases that are
actually present, they're going to look better to a study section. So you have to figure out a way
to identify a disease that could be a problem without going overboard and using lots of
resources for diseases that never will be a problem.
I mean, it seems that you'd want to structure it in a way that says, look, there are some
no regret moves here for any viral infection. And then there are some things that are going
to be very specific. So for example, not that this is an NIH question, but what would a national
stockpile of PPE need to look like? What would an electronic infrastructure for contact tracing
need to look like? What would a national stash of reagents to develop serologic and PCR testing need
to look like? So we don't know what the gene sequence is, but the moment we know the gene sequence,
wouldn't it be great if we could hit go and actually deliver a million tests a day and not
talk about it for three months and not do it? Those strike me as just a no regret moves. You
don't need to know a single thing about what's coming other than it is infectious. It's the
little stuff. It's the nasal swabs. It's the reagents. It's all the stuff I just said and about
20 other things I've been thinking about that kind of I really hope that when this is said and done,
this doesn't get forgotten because it's not a staggering investment. When you consider what
we spend on health care and defense, which are disproportionate to any other country by a log
order and oftentimes by two log orders per capita, you put a few billion dollars into this type of
resource and you consider it more vital than you would consider our national surplus of oil or
other things. For example, most people I would assume know this, but if not, we keep an enormous
supply of oil on hand. If the world shut down and we couldn't get a drop of oil from anyone in the
world, we would at least have, I don't know, I don't remember these stats, but probably a 60 to 90
day supply of complete independence on oil, maybe more than that. And that's just a national defense
imperative. So this should easily be in that front. The other thing on the therapeutic side, I would
say is don't we already have enough evidence to suggest that at least one avenue to treatment
is immune modulating therapy. So maybe not antiviral because that can be quite specific,
but all of these diseases have an enormous component of an overactive immune response,
which we'll discuss. And therefore having a huge stockpile of immune modulating drugs to be
appropriately dosed also strikes me as a no brainer, right? Yeah, yeah. No, you could argue that. I'm
not sure that these diseases are all the same in terms of the cytokine storm type activity, but
they may be close enough so that your point is well taken. They are similar enough so that
that would be a reasonable thing to do to have those on hand. I think that's what Bill Gates was
probably talking about more than specific drugs against specific viruses, because you don't really
know those so well. Think about it. So the whole stuff with ventilators and all that, that was
really poorly done. Testing, I think once we know, you're right about nasopharyngeal swaps and
mechanics of being able to do the testing. The actual identification of targets for like R2P4
are not that hard. I mean, that probably took four days to figure out. But it took longer to scale
up. I mean, I think that's the point, right? It's not no, I mean, the virus was sequenced
in January 11th or 12th, wasn't it? Yeah, yeah. Early in that, actually. It's just scaling up
the ability to do testing. So anybody who says, well, come on, it would be crazy to have $3
billion invested in that on the off chance that the virus doesn't even make it out of China.
To which the answer would be, did you look at what happened to the US economy? It's called a hedge.
This is what sophisticated companies do. Sophisticated companies hedge their bets. And if the answer is,
every time a really scary virus emerges in China, we have to spend $3 billion to be ready for it to
land here. But guess what? We don't have to shut our economy down as a result. We can instead
mitigate 90% of that damage. I mean, it's the wisest investment that could ever be made.
But I'll get off the soapbox now because nobody wants to hear me rant about that stuff. I want
to get back to kind of the interesting biology on this stuff. So let's now go back and talk about
these four viruses that cause us nothing more than nuisance when we get colds. Do they have any
seasonal variability to them, by the way? Are they winter viruses, summer viruses, or does it matter?
They tend to not be summer viruses, and they tend to be more winter, early spring viruses.
What determines that, by the way? Is that simply a function of being close to each other in the
winter and spreading it, or is it actually a property of the virus?
Yeah, we used to think it was that, but as we know more, I don't know the answer to that. I know
that some of these respiratory viruses are more active in the late fall, winter, and others in
the winter, early spring. And I don't know why there's a difference. I don't think anyone else
really knows either. We know these viruses are usually happier when it's a little cooler and a
little drier. But that wouldn't explain why one virus did well in November, and another one did
better in March. Interesting. And then from an immune response, why is it that these viruses
haven't basically become irrelevant in the sense that we all eventually get them and we all develop
immunity and we're sort of done? That's really the question about all common cold viruses, whether
they be Corona or otherwise. So why do you actually get reinfected? I don't think we understand it very
well. We know that there's an antibody response to these viruses. It seems to wane. It goes away.
We know that you need a specific kind of antibody, the IgA response, that seems to help. We don't
have that much information about IgA responses. They seem to wane as well. The T-cell response is
the other part of the immune system that you mentioned earlier. We don't know that much about
the T-cell response in common cold coronaviruses. Before all this began, we didn't think that was a
big deal because common colds usually go away in a few days before you actually have a T-cell response.
So we don't know why things will, why virus immunity wanes. We know there's such huge differences.
Smallpox you can detect and people had smallpox in 1918, 1995, they still had antibody responses
that were measurable. Here we have these common cold coronaviruses a year later. They've waned
and a couple of years later, they're probably almost gone. So we don't really understand that.
That's really a key question. And it both impacts the ability to people to be reinfected by SARS-CoV-2.
It impacts the vaccine responses and impacts general herd immunity as we try to get rid of
this virus. So really important for not knowing. There probably hasn't been a case of a coronavirus
before where we've cared enough about herd immunity to talk about it. But do you mind
explaining to folks what you're talking about with herd immunity, specifically with respect
to SARS-CoV-2 and what it means? Well, herd immunity is really the other side of what you
were talking about, the R-naught factor. So if the herd immunity means if you have a virus that's
extremely contagious for people who are susceptible to be protected from the infection, you have to
have most of the people around them be resistant to the virus. So to put this in a different context,
if somebody who's infected with whether it be SARS-CoV-2 or measles or anything else comes into
a room and they're spreading virus, the virus is going to land in various places. Some of it will
land on the floor. Some of it might land on somebody's hands and could in theory infect that
person. But if that person is immune to the virus, then it doesn't matter. The virus can land in that
person's hands and then that person can touch his face, but he won't get infected or he won't get
disease anyway. But if the person is susceptible, then he will. So then if that person is susceptible,
he could then spread it to other people in this proverbial large room if they all stayed together
for several days. Now, if you take a situation where you have an extremely contagious virus,
so in that room of 100 people, I was saying before with measles, if five of them are susceptible,
the virus might spread to 25, 30 people from that one susceptible person. And then if that 5%,
maybe one or more of those people will become infected. If you have a virus like SARS-CoV-2,
which has a lower R0 factor than at that same 100 people, if their five are susceptible,
the odds are it will not get to the point of infecting one of those five people. So herd
immunity is that ratio, the fraction of people who are immune to a disease. For measles, the number
is said to be 95%. If you don't have that 95%, then measles can infect people who are susceptible.
For most common viruses, it's around 60 or 70%. So that's the number that people are really
looking at in terms of immunization or infection with SARS-CoV-2 to protect the general population.
It's not the same as being immunized or having the previous infection. You're still susceptible,
but it just means that it's much more likely the virus won't spread. And if you get sick,
it's unlikely you'll spread it to that 30% of the population that has never seen the virus.
So that's why it matters. Yeah. And there's a very non-linear but monotonic inverse relationship
between R0 and herd immunity, which I can't believe I actually just said all that. It's
basically math speak for the higher the R0, the higher the need for herd immunity,
but the relationship gets there non-linearly. I don't have a non-math way to say that,
but the example you gave is a good one, which is, and I said inverse, it's actually not inverse,
it's direct. The R0 for measles is very high and the herd immunity threshold is very high, 95%.
Going down to an R0 of two to three, you have a herd immunity threshold of 60 to 70%. Now,
do you believe that based on everything we know today, and that includes potentially there being
many more asymptomatic people who are infected and who have gotten over the infection than we
previously believed, do you believe that the threshold for herd immunity is still as high
as 60 to 70% for SARS-CoV-2? Or do you think that it could be as low as 20 to 30%?
Well, I think it's still going to be 60 to 70%. It's just that there's a higher percentage of
people who have immunity already. So in other words, you're saying, yeah, it becomes a bit of
an academic or a moot point because it might be that of those 60 to 70% who have to be infected
for herd immunity, two thirds of them don't even know they were infected, but they actually were
from an immune, okay, fair point. So is there much genetic drift in these viruses? Like influenza,
I think most people know, hey, I got to get a flu shot every year. But what they might not
understand is the reason they're getting the flu shot is probably less because their immune system
forgets what influenza looked like and more because influenza looks different every year.
How much do these coronaviruses genetically drift to use the lingo?
So far, we haven't had evidence that this one drifts. I think when you look at the other viruses,
one of them seems to vary quite a bit. OC43 seems to have different variants. A lot of the others
don't seem to change that much. SARS was adapting to human populations, so it changed. But if it had
stayed around, I don't know that it would have changed much. MERS is completely a camel virus,
so any drift you see is what happens in camels, not in people. Again, both for MERS and the human,
the other coronaviruses is not really well, except for OC43. I don't think there's huge
effects on immunity. This virus is really, there's certainly a lot of talk about changes in the virus
and becoming more brutal and more weaker and more attenuated, but there's really no evidence so far
that says this virus has changed in a way that makes it unlikely a vaccine will work, unlikely
that a previous infection won't protect you from a second infection. There may be reasons why it
won't, but it won't be because the virus is changing so far. That's an important point. I
think we want to reiterate that, right? Which is the doomsday scenario would be a virus that retains
its virulence, but constantly drifts enough genetically that your immune system never
recognizes it again, but it retains all of its bad properties. I mean, that's a disaster. If you
had a new version of a deadly virus show up every year, it could hurt you just as badly, but somehow
its genetic drifting created a different coat on it, a different set of antigens, and every year
your immune system was caught off guard. That would be very painful. And what you're saying is,
hey, we don't have evidence of either of those things happening, that it's genetically becoming
more or frankly less harmful of equal, if not more importance, that it's not becoming a different
immune animal as time goes on, at least in the very short window we've studied it. But again,
it's helpful to go back and look at these other coronaviruses that you've studied because they've
given us a lot of insight, right? Yeah, exactly. The immunity when you have a mild infection just
do not develop great immunity. So let's double click on that. You've said already part of that.
I want to make sure I understood it. So part of it is the innate system, just for whatever reason,
doesn't seem to do much. You've already talked about how a lot of times with at least the common
coronaviruses, they might not even stick around long enough to develop a T cell response. Can you
say a bit more about the adaptive humoral system? What do we know about the IgM and IgG, which again,
if you haven't listened to the interview and the discussion with David Watkins, I think this would
be a great time to go back and make sure you familiarize yourself with that so that we don't
have to go into the details of what those things mean. But six months after a person has a common
coronavirus, do you still see evidence of at least the IgG? Yes. And do you know how often it is
basically binding, non-binding? Do you have a sense of what the functionality of that IgG is?
Is it neutralizing fully necessarily? Not necessarily. I think the human volunteer
studies are best answers for that for the common cold coronaviruses. And they show that immunity is
there, it's measured by neutralizing anybody, and then it wanes with time. And that a year later,
it's there and may not prevent shedding. It's still, I think it sounds remarkably like what
I think we're going to hear about with COVID-19 and immunity when people have mild infections or
asymptomatic. Now, we've talked about this paper that came out, God, I think it's been maybe three
weeks ago. Alex Seddi was the senior author on it, 2020 cell paper that looked at 20 patients who
recovered from COVID-19. And I believe about two thirds of them actually had a CD8 T cell response
and a CD4 response that kind of correlated with that. The point being, they looked to have been
at least partially aided in their response to SARS-CoV-2 from T cells that looked like they had
been sensitized by other coronaviruses. Now, this was a small study and this was based on in vitro
assays. Can you explain that study a little bit or at least the idea behind it? Because it's an
incredibly interesting idea and it has clinical relevance if this turns out to be true.
Yeah. So I think this is one of actually several studies. This is the only published one, I think,
that shows that people who have never seen the virus have some sort of T cell response to
SARS-CoV-2. Now, there are some caveats when I read this paper that make me pause and drawing too
strong a conclusion. One is that in most of these papers, the way T cell responses are measured is
not by functionality, but rather by being activated in a certain way. And these activations, to my mind,
are surrogate for actual functionality. And the functionality was not well demonstrated in any of
these studies. You may see a little functionality, but it's not the major point. Second thing is the
targets for these virus, for the T cell response is not the usual response that you get in terms
of targets. And you see after the wild type infection, the SARS-CoV-2 infection. And because
of this difference, it makes it also a little unclear to me where this response is coming from.
So you can say, okay, that doesn't matter. It's still from a common cold coronavirus. But then
when people go back and look at the sequence of the common cold coronaviruses for the same targets,
there's actually very little homology with T cell responses that are recognized in these patients
who have never seen SARS-CoV-2. So altogether, on one hand, you could say, well, maybe this is
something that's important. Maybe it contributes to protection, pathogenicity. On the other hand,
it's a little odd because it's mostly measured by activation, not necessarily by function. And
that may matter. And it's also targets are not totally clear how that's working. So maybe it's
something that's not completely clear yet. So I'm a bit confused by that, Stanley, because if we were
doing this on the B cell side, which is where we normally would, you would do an in vitro assay
and demonstrate the presence of neutralizing antibodies, not just binding, but neutralizing.
And that would give us great confidence that the B cell response would translate from the
in vitro finding to the in vivo finding. Is that correct? I agree with you completely. Yes.
So we can do comparable T cell assays where we actually look at killing function and not just
signaling functions and things like that, right? Yeah. And this isn't really signaling. This is
protein, what was measured with proteins that come up if a cell has been activated at all.
So this is not killing assays, not even making cytokines, which are the my preferred way of
doing this could be easier. Yeah. So that's what I was going to say. Usually when you look at
typical studies that are looking at, say, response to flu vaccination, they look at cytokine response
on the T cell. So do you know if studies are looking to do that? Because that just seems to
be a very obvious thing to want to ask at this point. Well, for the people who are naive, who've
never seen the virus and who have these assays done, T cell responses are done, but they're
they're very, very low levels of activity. So the amount of cytokine produced are extremely low
or non-existent. So you just wonder, part of the issues, we do some of these assays and you can do
it very well. But the level of the background, as it were, is approaching what we're seeing in some
of these patients. So I think Jerry's just out on how important it is and what it means. To me,
it's really interesting. It kind of doesn't go with what we used to see, what we've seen in
MERS patients, where we don't really see much of a background, much evidence of cross-reactivity,
but we didn't actually do these surrogate assays, these assays for activation.
And there may be a temporal component. In other words, it could be that, let's assume that on
average, a person gets one year of quasi-protection from a given coronavirus until it can infect them
again. You now have a hundred people who are in various stages along a continuum of that recovery
from, pick your favorite endemic coronavirus. And then they all, at one day, get infected with
SARS-CoV-2. Well, presumably there's also a strength and a decline of immune response.
So even though they would all have some immune response lingering, some memory of immune response
to the benign coronavirus, they could technically mount very different responses to the much more
feared SARS-CoV-2, simply as a function of how far they are out from their initial infection, correct?
I think that's a different layer because it assumes that there's something there.
That's correct. If there's something there, yes, absolutely. This is a totally second layer.
Do you think there were other viruses or other vaccines that could provide cross-reactivity?
I don't think provide cross-reactivity is, of course, these ideas that you should immunize
everybody with attenuated polio virus because that'll activate the immune system and that'll
give you some protection. You should do something like that BCG, which we use for immunization
against tuberculosis, whether they have any effect. People are suggesting this, and I think
they're in trials even. But in terms of specificity of getting at the coronaviruses, I don't think so.
The BCG one's worth probably explaining a little bit to people because it got so much attention.
I think the other one that got quite a bit of attention was MMR. There's a very famous graph
that a friend of mine sent me that said, hey, the entire pandemic and the mortality profile,
which basically hockey sticks above 50, can be explained by exposure to MMR. People below 50
uniformly had MMR vaccination. People above 50, it's much more spotty. The further you get from
50, the less likely you were to have an MMR vaccine, and that explains it. Now, I can go on
why I don't believe that's the case, but I'd rather hear your views on whether that is or is not likely.
I think it's actually contrary to what one might think because those of us who are over 50 had.
You actually got the real virus.
You're really on all three of those infections. I don't consider myself resistant. In fact,
almost everybody my age had all three of those viruses. Everybody certainly had measles and mumps.
Our German measles may have been less frequent.
But from an immunologic perspective, Stanley, is there any reason to believe
that your memory T cells and B cells to measles, mumps, and or rubella would offer you some
protection against this particular coronavirus? Is there any evidence that they offer protection
against other coronaviruses? No, I can say that. No one's looked very, very hard, but there's no
reason to think that it would. If there was anything like that, we would all have some
preexisting immunity to the virus that's way higher than what we're talking about.
I'll just tell you why I'm also quite skeptical of the BCG claim, which is not to say that in
certain cases, maybe there's an anecdote that it works. I mean, obviously, one of the first
examples of cancer immunotherapy came out of an understanding of the Cooley's toxins that sort of
came out of this idea of BCG. But the reality of it is BCG has never shown enough specificity to be
a viable immunotherapy against cancer. And it's for that reason, I guess, even if that's overly
simplistic, that I really doubt that BCG could have a meaningful impact on a virus because it
requires just as much immune specificity as it does for the immune system to attack cancer.
Yeah, and you know, there's other agents, so we've worked with agents that turn on interferon.
And I think if you give interferon at the wrong time, these infections, you may make people worse.
So if you were exposed to COVID-19, you had a very good exposure right now. And I gave you one of
these agents that turn on interferon, that may well help you. Because before you really get an
infection, if we jazz up your immune system, that may help you do better with the virus. Once it
gets going, that probably isn't true. There's all these issues that one could imagine that if you
jazzed up the immune system of BCG, that it can help you if you got it right the right day, and
then you were exposed to COVID-19. But I wouldn't want to be inoculated with BCG just for fun with
the possibility that in the next two days, I get exposed to the virus. You provided a much more
elegant description of how you might possibly benefit from it in a Hail Mary, pure luck standpoint,
but how mechanistically it just doesn't even make sense. And you're right, by the way, I think the
broader point I would take away from your comment is, there's a really interesting way to think about
this from a targeted therapeutic standpoint. When you think about the sophistication with which we
try to treat other diseases with multiple lines of defense, this is a great example of one, going
back to everything I said before about when I was on my rant about how would you begin to prepare
for the next time a pandemic comes back, it's all that stuff. On the therapeutic side, I think it's
being more thoughtful about what the strategies are. The moment we identify those early cases and
say, boy, this is a disease that typically, like influenza, is a little bit more of an immune
paralysis disease, at least at one point here, you're seeing this hyperactivated immune sense. So
early treatment is antiviral with immune amplifier, late treatment is immune modulator,
antivirals long since gone, and respiratory support starts to matter. You can start to really
be more sophisticated in how you think of these things. I think that's probably something that
people are starting to think about now, and I suspect that a lot of the clinical trials now
will focus on more partitioning. So we don't just think of it as drug X, good or bad, drug Y,
good or bad. We don't have this sort of nonsense binary thinking. I agree with you completely,
because that's exactly the way I think about this disease, is that you need antiviral therapy early
on, and then maybe an immune modulator later. And in terms of immune activator, if you just catch it
just at the right time, maybe that would help. I think it's actually going to be the same for severe
flu, like the H5N1. I think the same scenario applies. The other thing you point out is that
with different patients in different disease courses, one has to be ready to modulate therapy.
And this is one of the things that I'd love to have that we don't have, which are biomarkers for
different stages of disease. Well, I think for so many diseases, we know that something works well,
and then we do large studies and we find out, you know, it didn't work as well as we think.
But if you go back, you say within this population, if we could have identified it first,
that would be the people who would have responded to this particular therapy. That's one of the
reasons that some therapies work that don't work that you might think would work, because if 20%
of people own a category of benefiting from it, would you treat 100%?
You dilute all the benefit. Exactly.
That's such an interesting idea. What do you think some of those biomarkers could look like?
There's some obvious ones. When a patient's in cytokines storm, you can measure the cytokines.
But if you could go deeper than that, and you could look at the proteome, and you could look
at metabolomics, or look at the gut, or something like that, where do you think the answer could lie?
Okay. So there's two parts of the question. First one is what would you sample? Because
the ideal person to be sampled is that person who comes in like your friend who had trouble running,
who didn't feel well. And I don't think he progressed to having disease enough to get
him in the hospital. No. Yeah. Young, healthy guy in his maybe early 40s, and yeah. Never
hospitalized, but sick as a dog for two weeks. Right. So that's a person you'd like to do a
test on and say, okay, is he going to progress or not? Clearly, in his case, we'd want something
to say he's sick, but he's not going to progress because he didn't progress. So that's a person
who you might not want to do anything for. On the other hand, he may look exactly like someone who
has diabetes and is sick in terms of how poorly he felt. And so what you'd want, you'd need a mark
in not only for severity, but you wanted something that would distinguish between the two of them,
and that you could sample easily in the blood because your friend would not have wanted to
undergo some sort of lung measurement because it would have been way more invasive than the
sickness he felt. So that's why you come back. I think you can come back to things like cytokines
and metabolic products. The problem up till now has been that you can see an increase in
cytokine X in people who are going to be sick and not increased in people who are going to do better.
But when you put them all together, it's not like you have populations that are very high versus
very low. You have ones that have a range of X to Y, and the other one would have a range of 0.75X
to 1.5X. So you can see that. It seems to be a problem that is set up perfectly for some type
of machine learning because everything you said is correct. And then as you also alluded to,
there's another layer here, which is we know quite a bit about the epidemiology. All things equal,
a 40-year-old without a single pre-existing condition, you're going to weigh that input
differently than a 60-year-old with no pre-existing conditions or a 40-year-old with type 2
diabetes versus a 60-year-old. They all have a very different physiologic age, even if their
chronologic ages are similar. And so when you start to factor in that plus some of these signatures
plus the temporal nature of the signature, when am I getting this? I think there is an amazing
opportunity for information and data scientists to help prepare us for how we will think about
this when it happens the next time. Yeah. And so what you need out of this is you need,
as we've talked about for some of the projects we've talked about, what you'd ideally like to
do is you'd like to take people, sample them every couple of days, see what their numbers look like,
put them in the machine learning model that you're talking about. And then if you had enough money,
so you can measure all these different cytokines, you might say, okay, this person has this block
of markers that say he's going to get single. Whether it'd be the 40-year-old, because, you know,
the 40-year-old can get sick, or whether it'd be an older person. And you put the other point you
make about the epidemiology on top of that, and maybe you would not even bother testing the 40-year-old
because the odds of his getting sicker and meriting all the costs and use of research is not worth it.
We're not there yet in terms of thinking about which markers are best, and also how do you
actually do this? How do you actually do a study where you can help a person by getting serial
testing and seeing which way he or she is going in terms of disease? But that would be the ideal
way, because that person, if you saw signs that things weren't bad, maybe that's the person you
use, either remdesivir or hopefully an oral form of remdesivir, stop the virus in its tracks,
maybe give him a immune activator. Again, unclear, I think if you give him immune activator,
some people will be deleterious, so it has to be done so carefully.
There are two last topics I want to get to, one being how we would study the durability of immune
response, which is effectively the most jugular question out there today. I mean, if we're going
to think about this through the lens of vaccination, and we're going to think about this through the
lens of herd immunity, natural or otherwise, we better figure out exactly what's going to happen
to these people who get infected and what superpowers they do or don't have in the future.
Before I do that, though, I want to go back to one thing we kind of alluded to very briefly
and then skipped ahead, which was that paper that came out kind of recently. Matt Ridley is the
journalist who wrote about it, I think in the Wall Street Journal, but he refers to the paper by Zahn
that came out, I think in April, that argued basically the virus may not have come from
the wet market the way we think it does. I know we've been sending each other so many papers back
and forth over the last few weeks. Did you have a chance to look at that paper? I think so. It's the
one that says there's a bunch of these, so I'm not sure I have the Ridley one in mind, the one that
says it was released accidentally from the Wuhan lab or the one that says it was- No, the one that
said it was basically so genetically stable, it's mostly a person-to-person transmission. So I
think it basically said, look, this is mostly a person-to-person transmission. And I think it
said if it came out of animals, it was so long ago that we don't know about it. It basically
argues that the narrative that this came from an animal source to a human source in somewhere
between October, November, December of last year is not correct. Had you seen this paper? No,
I don't know that paper then. Okay, all right. We won't dive into that too much. The point is
well taken that it is remarkably fit for humans. I don't know about the first part of the conclusion
that it came out earlier, but it is remarkably fit. Yeah, I mean, I think they basically looked
at the amount of genetic drift that occurred and said, I read it I think four weeks ago, so I'm a
little rusty on it other than a few notes I took that were somewhat cryptic. But I think the
argument was, look, this has probably been in humans longer than we think. I'll re-forward it to
after just for the purpose of pure interest. So how do we figure out how long people are going to,
because it might not be that interesting how much immunity people have to regular common cold
coronavirus, but it's going to be pretty darn interesting to know how long people are going
to have immunity to this virus. I mean, we've already at a minimum seen close to 10 million
people infected worldwide with this virus. Personally, I think that's a gross underestimate
of how many people have been affected. I think it's probably closer to 100 million people have
been infected. But regardless, the durability of their immune response has to be one of the most
important questions we understand. How would we do that? Yeah, so just doing the things we're doing,
people who are infected, measuring their antibody responses, if we can, measuring the T cell responses,
the odds are that we're going to see waning immunity for people with mild disease. That's
what we're hearing over and over again. And that's what's been true for other coronavirus infections.
And what will the implication of that be? Will the implication then be that no matter how
successful a vaccine is, it's going to need to be an annual vaccine? There's two goals. One is to
protect the individual who's vaccinated from getting severe pneumonia, and that may actually
occur already. That may be whether immunity wanes or not. That person may never get a severe pneumonia.
The other issue, which is equally important, is how much immunity do you need to prevent shedding,
to prevent transmissibility to other people? And that's the one that I think is really unknown,
and to me is more important. Not important to the individual, but to society.
To me, that's the jugular question that decides what do economies look like when we have subsequent
waves of this. Because there is something on Instagram a few weeks ago where I did a kind of
Q&A with my son who's five, and he asked a very honest question, which is, when is this virus
going to be gone? And it was an interesting discussion to explain to him, actually, it's
never going to be gone. This virus is never going away. There is nothing about this virus that
suggests it's ever going away. And so now the question is, how do we coexist with this virus?
So even putting aside future pandemics, which could be much worse, for example, an increase
in the lethality while preserving the transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 would be devastating.
But just coping with this, if another one never shows up, we have to understand this question,
especially if the vaccines are somewhat risky. One thing that doesn't get a lot of discussion is,
how much risk is going to be posed by vaccines? There's a reason they never come up with RSV
vaccines. It's a lot harder from a safe perspective to make an RSV vaccine, unlike an
influenza vaccine. So if everything is going to be a risk trade-off, right, and we're going to decide,
you might not want to vaccinate everybody with a SARS-CoV-2 vaccine if the risk is slightly higher
than we deem acceptable. So then you have to do a cost benefit analysis. And then to your point,
which I think is even more important is, okay, what does the secondary shedding look like? What
do these other factors look like? It's hard for me to imagine a world that's fully functioning
without these questions resolved. Right. That's really the key question. The other hand, though,
if you get to a point where there's enough herd immunity or that 100 million turns into a 6
billion, people have seen the infection, so nobody gets pneumonia anymore and turns into a common
cold, then there may be enough of a balance between the virus mutating a little to become
a better common cold and no longer causing the pneumonia. But that's the point. It requires a
mutation, doesn't it, Stanley? Yeah, yeah, yeah. We don't have the memory like we do with measles
and polio and smallpox to truly generate herd immunity. In fact, we've never generated herd
immunity to influenza commonly. In that case, of course, it's because of the genetic drift. And so
isn't it a bit of a misnomer to suggest that we could ever have herd immunity to SARS-CoV-2?
Let's just say if we knew that the immune response was gone after a year.
The question is, what is immune response being gone?
Yeah, a sufficient immune response. I mean, it becomes a sliding scale of efficacy, correct?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's right. But if you have enough immune response to protect you from
pneumonia, then the question is, how much shedding do you have? So that would be actually a
significant ... When we talk about studies, I was thinking about this a little while ago.
The simplest study would be to take some human volunteers, give them a common cold coronavirus,
and then a year later come back and do the exact experiment that was done in the 80s,
measure do they get a cold? If you reinfect them a year later, do they get a cold? And how much
shedding do they have? We know they shed, but if you are a naive person with a cold, you shed
10 to the 8th, and now you shed 10 to the 3rd, and it doesn't matter.
Yeah, then it doesn't matter. Yeah. Well, and of course, here ... So again, I completely agree
with you. That's the single most important question. But the other thing is, I don't have
my fingers crossed that this is perfect because of that upper respiratory part of this. So you said,
well, what if you don't get the severe pneumonia before? Well, it turns out the severe pneumonia
that came with SARS-1 and MERS isn't really what was the problem. I mean, that was the problem for
the individual, but that was not the problem for society. The problem for society was the
upper respiratory part. That's what we're seeing in SARS, or the lack thereof. And that might be
what's making SARS-CoV-2 such a problem. Yeah, yeah, that's right.
Anyway, Stanley, as you can tell, we can talk about this for days, but I want to honor our
commitment to get you out of here in a certain time. So I look forward to talking with you again
very soon as we continue to work on the project we're working on with David and a group of other
really amazing people. But thank you for your time and your generosity of insight. Anything else,
any last thoughts you have on either this particular pandemic or just coronaviruses in general?
No, I think the key thing we talked about is how do you prevent this in the future? We're going to
muddle our way through this one. We're going to do, we'll get to points I think where we'll have
antivirals, I hope, vaccines, even with the caveats that we talked about that should work,
how long they'll work, I don't know. Whether people actually agree to be vaccinated is another
issue we didn't really talk about. And then for safety, I mean, all these things we're going to
know very quickly because we have to do it quickly. Well, that means we're going to have to talk
again. Okay. Thanks, Stanley. Okay. Thanks, Peter. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of
The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a
membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying
on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription.
Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive
podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word
on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear
everything without having to listen to spiels like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast,
typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best
questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.