Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Lloyd Klikstein. Lloyd's the chief scientific officer
at Restore Bio. So that's little R-E-S, big T-O-R, little B-I-O. Get it? Tor, T-O-R. Restore Bio is a
clinical stage bio farm company that develops meds that are primarily aimed at targeting Tor,
targeted rapamycin. We'll talk a lot about that throughout this episode. So prior to joining
Restore Bio, Lloyd was the global head of translational medicine for the new indication
discovery unit at Novartis. Prior to that, he was an academic physician at the Brigham and
Women's Hospital, which is one of the flagship programs at Harvard. Lloyd received his bachelor's
from Tufts and an MD, PhD from Harvard. He's got more accolades than you could shake a stick at.
So accolades aside, the reason I wanted to speak with Lloyd was because he is really one of the
few people on this planet that has a really nuanced understanding of the clinical application
of rapamycin and rapologs. And we talk a lot about one of them in particular called
Evrolimus. Lloyd was the senior author on a paper that I have spoken about many times on this
podcast, which we'll go into in great detail here. December 2014 paper, Joan Manik was the
lead author on that paper. And that was the study that was basically the turning point in my personal
evolution or thinking when it came to the use of rapamycin for the purpose of longevity. Prior to
that, there had been a lot of studies that had certainly suggested in animal models that rapamycin
could be a true longevity agent, but it was the Manik-Klickstein paper of December 2014 that was
the real turning point in my thinking. And that's really where we're going in this discussion along
with talking about all that's been done since then. It is important before we start this interview
that I mentioned, of course, that Lloyd is an employee of RestoreBio. RestoreBio is a for-profit
company that is working on mTOR inhibition. So please caveat everything that we discuss
through that lens. Before this podcast begins, I want to note that we recorded this interview in
September 2019. Now in the interview, we discussed an upcoming phase three trial from RestoreBio.
Since that time, the results have been published and the study did not meet its primary endpoint.
Now I frankly left the option to Lloyd as to whether or not he wanted to still have the
podcast air and he felt that that would be fine to do. And so we're going to go ahead with it. And
eventually I'm going to be interviewing his colleague, Joan Manik, along with Nir Barzal.
I'm going to have the two of them back on an episode where we're going to discuss a whole
bunch of things that'll be quite interesting. And this gets more complicated because I think
I have a pretty clear understanding of why that study failed and what it does and doesn't say
about selective inhibition of agents like it. Nevertheless, I think the most logical thing
to do is to go ahead and proceed with this interview, which is one of my favorite interviews
on this subject matter, and just know that there are going to be a number of things that are left
as open-ended questions from this discussion. We're going to pick back up with Joan Manik when
we do that interview, which I'm scheduled to do a few weeks from now. And hopefully we'll try to
get that one out at a much quicker turnaround. There are a number of issues that delayed the
release of this, not the least of which being some of the COVID stuff, but I can promise you
that there will be a shorter gap between when you are hearing this and you will hear the follow-up
to this than there was between the recording of this and when you're hearing it. And without
further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Lloyd Klikstein.
Lloyd, thank you so much for making the trip up to San Francisco today. I know you didn't
come here specifically to see me, but I appreciate you carving out a little extra time to meet today.
I'm happy to be here and looking forward to our talk.
I hope the view is enticing enough here.
It's lovely.
When the weather is nice in San Francisco, there are a few things that compare to it. And when it's
not, it's like Mark Twain said, right? The worst winter he ever had was a summer in San Francisco
or something of that effect. And hear from Boston, so you laugh at that.
Right now, this is the weather we all wish we had in Boston.
Yeah. So Tim Wright, one of your colleagues, offered to make this introduction over dinner
one night. And there's probably never been in the history of an introduction from the moment the
intro was offered until I was sitting down talking to someone on a podcast that was quicker than this
one. In other words, I'm sorry to hear that actually.
Well, it was just a meaning I was so excited when we sat there and it was so I was with Tim and with
DA Wallach, who some folks listening will know because I've interviewed DA on the podcast as
well. And we were having this dinner. And as is always the case when I'm talking with dorky
science friends, Rapa Mice comes up and one thing led to another. And then I'm embarrassed to say
this, but the 2014 paper that I talk about constantly, I always refer to it as the manic
paper because she's, of course, the first author. But you're sort of the lead author. You're the
final author. You're the senior author on that paper. And so I was embarrassed to say this. I
didn't even when they mentioned your name, I didn't put two and two together. And I didn't know you
were at Restore Bio at the time either. So anyway, they connected us. We communicated over email. The
rest is history. We're sitting here today and I am beyond excited. And then this is a topic that I
just know listeners are dying to hear about because it's been over a year since I've had a
podcast on this topic. So very early in this podcast, which is about a year and a half ago,
we had discussions with David Sabatini and with Matt Kaberlin, who are both amazing folks and
legends in this area as well. So I'm going to discipline myself for a moment before getting
right into the Rapa stuff to give a little bit of background. You've got a pretty interesting
background. I want to hear a little bit about it. When did you realize this is what you wanted to
do, which was be basically physician, scientist, and then ultimately now move into industry?
Well, I guess I can begin by stating that science and medicine is the family business. So it wasn't
much of a stretch for me to be here doing what I'm doing now doing what I've done before on both
sides of my family, both sides of my kids family. All of my kids are scientists, doctors are both.
So did you do a combined MD PhD or did you do them separately?
I did the combined one. My wife did them separately, actually, the long and expensive way.
Yeah, exactly. At least when you do them together, they pay for each other.
Yeah.
When did you decide you want to focus on immunology, rheumatology? I mean, there's no shortage of
things one can specialize in.
One of at least my challenges and I know the challenge of many physicians and many scientists
is that so many things are interesting. How do you focus? And like many things in life, it was about
the people, not the science that led me into immunology, rheumatology and where I am. When I
had left college, and wasn't sure where I was going to go next, I spent a couple of years working in a
laboratory at Brigham and Women's Hospital. I had such an incredible time and met such wonderful
people that ultimately my decision was to stay there and work with them, learn from them. What
years were you at the Brigham? I worked in a technical capacity from 79 to 81, started medical
school in 81 and finished both degrees by 1989 and then stayed there through all of my training and
then left in 2006 to join actually Tim Wright's department at Novartis Institutes.
What prompted that decision? And is that a one way street for most people?
There are people who go back and forth, but I think we have to be realistic that it's more
challenging to go back to academia if you don't have extant grants and external funding. It has to
come from somewhere in most places. In terms of what drove the decision, I'm a physician-scientist.
For me, it's important to do both, science and medicine. And it's harder and harder and harder to
do that now in an academic environment. At least I'll get in trouble for saying this, but at least
a primitive academic environment like Harvard, where you eat what you kill and you have to, at the
same time, see patients be at the top of not just your game, but the world's game in seeing patients
and administrative and teaching responsibilities and so forth.
Well, I mean, let Harvard get upset at you for saying that, but I mean, there's no denying what
you're saying is the case. I interview so many people who are straddling that and I'm constantly
amazed. In fact, I was interviewing someone recently, a very remarkable scientist and academic,
and I couldn't believe how much clinical obligation he had and yet how prolific he was. It's sort of
amazing to me that some folks can actually straddle that. It's certainly not optimal, I guess,
is the point. No, and it was much more challenging than I had seen it in the late 70s and early 80s.
What changed? Is the reduction in grant? The competitiveness of the grant environment or?
No, it wasn't so much the grant environment. It was more the regulation and the paperwork
that was imposed mostly on the clinical side. I need to be fair and say I was both running from
something and running to something. As a physician scientist, the goal is to have each of them
contribute to the other and translational medicine, which was a new concept around the turn of the
millennium, was growing and was perfect for somebody like me. The Vardis Institutes was
created by Mark Fishman in the early 2000s as a new concept and a new approach to drug development,
thinking about pathway biology. They were building translational medicine departments and Tim
recruited me to lead the musculoskeletal one. Maybe explain to folks the difference between
basic science, clinical science or clinical research and translational research, which,
as you said, the latter there being a relatively recent phenomenon.
Lots of examples of basic science. One that's pretty exciting and has led to Nobel Prizes
is the study of restriction enzymes. Who thought that studying obscure bacteria and how they limit
their infection by viruses might have led to the concept of restriction enzymes, which was required
for the development of modern molecular biology. Another one of basic science. You've probably
talked about CRISPR technology here. We have a dedicated podcast to it and I'd love to get
Jennifer on to do so, but please continue. Yeah, that's a great example. I'll give you a one-minute
summary. It is another critical element of the bacterial immune system. It's simple, it's elegant,
it's powerful and there were scientists in Europe studying fermentation for yogurt and cheese.
And they discovered CRISPR, Jennifer Doudna and colleagues here, MIT and the Broad Institute. And
they were studying basic science. They were studying bacterial biology and it became so exciting
when somebody translated the biochemistry, if you will, in the bacteria to see what it
worked in humans. Who would have thought that would work? Bacterial chromatin, the DNA is so
different, it's supercoiled in a bacterial cell whereas human DNA is organized into chromatin
and methylated, but it did. So the point here is basic science isn't necessarily in pursuit of
anything beyond knowledge, but it doesn't come with the caveat of this needs to have a clinical
application with respect to the species of interest. Exactly right. Clinical medicine,
I think everybody knows, it's getting your flu shot in the fall, it's being told the diet and
exercise and take your antihypertenses if they've been prescribed. Right, does taking this medication
lower your risk of a stroke? Does taking this vaccine lower your risk of getting the flu?
Exactly. And translational medicine... There's a big gap between those two, isn't there? Yes,
and that's what translational medicine does. People had been doing this for a long time,
but never in an organized and conceptually holistic way, if I could say that. It's,
how do you take a basic science observation and make something useful for human health out of it
and prove it, which is surprisingly challenging. So you're saying that basically up until roughly
20 years ago, this hasn't been particularly well organized, and now pharma companies, among others,
are saying we'd like to own some of this risk. I think everybody has bought into the concept of
translational medicine now. Probably all big pharma companies and many small ones do it.
Many academic institutions have organizations to do translational medicine. It's in part our
responsibility, it's in part a way to do it more efficiently by providing appropriate training and
experience to younger scientists. We always have to think back to who's funding our basic science,
especially in academia. Ultimately, it's the people. Most heavily taxpayer funded. Yes,
it's most heavily taxpayer funded, and the reason they're doing it is to make their lives better,
or the lives of their family and friends better, and we need to be better at that, and I think
this is taking a step in that direction. So what was the first translational problem then you
began to work on when you joined Novartis in the, what would have been I guess the 90s, right?
It was in the early 2000s, so I joined a musculoskeletal program at the time Novartis was working on,
it was a regenerative medicine concept in musculoskeletal biology to increase bone density and
increase muscle strength, and so we had to put together some programs that would translate some
basic biology observations from human genetics. Remember translation can go both ways, and in fact
to skip ahead a little bit, we actually did that from that 2014 paper. We took what we learned there
and went back into the mouse, and there were a few projects. The one that has been successful
is a drug called zolidronic acid to increase bone density. And what was the state of assets that you
came into? Did Novartis already have a basic program that had shown some new insight with
respect to biology that could then be extrapolated into a compound? Did they already have the compound?
What was the actual program you were creating? At that time Novartis worked very much like most
other pharmaceutical companies did. There was a basic science department led by PhD scientists,
there was a clinical development organization led by clinical developers including MDs,
and there was a throw it over the wall mentality. The scientists make something that they like,
then they throw it over to the clinical scientists and they have to figure out what to do with it.
This is pre-IND? Yes. Okay, we should explain what an IND is I suppose. Yeah, do you want to tell
folks about that? Sure. So an IND stands for investigational new drug, and this is the
application that sponsors make to the FDA to get permission to begin clinical trials.
And there are a whole raft of requirements that are necessary in terms of quality manufacturing,
clinical plans, risks and benefits, experiments and so forth, so that we can make it as safe as
possible to test something new in people. But in any event that's the way Novartis worked is they
separated research from clinical development. Other companies did it a little differently. They
had the initial testing in healthy volunteers or the initial testing in patients depending on the
risk-benefit argument as part of the research organization. But in principle it's the same
thing. You had scientists making medicines and then clinicians testing them. The goal of
translational medicine is to provide clinical input right at the very beginning of the process,
even when you're thinking about what to do. And it really helps to focus the drug development
process on the patients and the clinical need right from the beginning so that ultimately the
drug that's made is the drug that's needed. Not let's make something and figure out what we can
do with it. Let's figure out what we need and then make it. Is there evidence by the way this is a bit
of a tangent but that that transition has rendered pharma more efficient at yielding capital?
This is studied in an anonymized fashion by an industry organization. It varies by company.
I see. So let's fast forward a little bit to the first time you became involved in
a molecule that would be involved in a nutrient sensing pathway. What was your foray into that?
There's a step before that and that is how did I get from musculoskeletal disease
to something new. We have to credit again Mark Fishman who was the founder of the Novartis
Institutes for this because he challenged me and a few others to put together an organization within
the company and answer the question what aren't we doing that we should be doing and then start
some projects. And again it's all about medical need and of course scientific tractability.
So we started that project. We called it the new indication discovery unit. What year is this
roughly? Mid-2000? This would have been about 2008 or 2009. We basically applied those principles,
a real medical need, a problem that's scientifically tractable and that Novartis wasn't working on an
ideally that nobody was working on. And we ended up with a few very interesting areas.
Joan Manick who was the first author on that 2014 paper brought the idea forward. Well maybe
the biology of aging is tractable but how do we actually make a medicine and develop it?
That was Joan at Novartis at this time? Yeah she joined our group in part to do this.
Her real innovation beyond just the ideas that she figured out a way to
test a medicine that could alter the biology of aging in humans and find an endpoint that's
measurable and modifiable in a reasonable time frame. Which really is the Achilles heel of aging
research which is the ultimate outcome is virtually unmeasurable in the species of interest.
Yes so our approach is not necessarily what you might read in the popular press about making
medicines for aging. Our approach is to address serious aging associated diseases and if we're
successful the side effect will be longevity. Yeah so keep going then. Now Joan floats this idea
which is here's a really good proxy for aging that can be measured out in a time course that's
clinically tractable and also frankly amenable to the type of research that we can do in humans.
And so what was your aha moment? This is interesting. This is interesting to Lloyd.
I needed and beyond interesting to Lloyd we then as a team had to persuade the rest of the
organization hey let's try this idea and again we always come back to the medical need,
scientific tractability and in proposing a project what's the evidence that it's going to be successful
and you know as well as anybody there's substantial scientific data that mTOR inhibition will
extend health span in many preclinical species certainly all the ones that have been tested.
Now that was not obvious in 2008. I mean 2009 people had been speculating and of course there
was a major publication that came out in 2009. I have to correct the time frame. We started our
new indication discovery unit in 2008 or 9. I think Joan started the project in 2010. Got it.
So you already had a very important study behind you as a catalyst for that. Let's take a step
back now and explain because it's been a while and there's going to be people listening who
don't recall all the details of our discussion with David Sabatini and with Matt Kaberlin.
Let's talk about what is mTOR. Sure well I can't add anything to David Sabatini about what mTOR is.
Nobody can but let's assume people have not heard what David has to say. Sure. In a nutshell,
mTOR is the master integrator of external availability of nutrients and growth factors
and then is the master regulator of the outputs of that integration deciding whether
cells are going to make proteins, make lipids, make nucleic acids grow or are we going to circle the
wagons, conserve resources, recycle and wait during times of little for hopefully future times of
plenty. So that's the role of mTOR. So it takes a bunch of signals which are external to the cell
ultimately become internal to the cell because mTOR is in the cell not out of the cell. It
assimilates and integrates across that signal and makes decisions that lead to, as you said,
at the risk of oversimplifying grow or don't grow. Yes I think that's exactly right. The signals it
takes are amino acids, glucose, cellular energy, growth factors from other parts of the organism
as probably the major ones and then decides are there sufficient resources that the cell
should grow or not. And between, this is just a little history lesson for the listener, sort of
between 1991 when Hall first identified what was not called at the time TOR but what would go on
to become TOR in yeast and 94 when Sabatini identifies it in mammals, you basically had
some of the just the heaviest hitters in biology all sort of converging on this idea which is
this is a really ubiquitous thing that has been preserved across about a billion years of
evolution with very little change. You don't see that every day in biology. Why is that relevant?
The simplest argument is that things that have been conserved from single-cell organisms to
us are probably important. There's some interesting comparative zoology that's relevant to mTOR here.
If you think about where in the cell mTOR lives, it's active on something called a lysosome
and that is a structure in the cells that's responsible for breaking down either cellular
material or material that's been acquired from outside the cell into its component elements
that then could be recycled like amino acids and sugars and so forth. Very early in development,
well in evolutionary biology when there were single-celled organisms and then the early
multiple cellular organisms, the way that the organism ate was by creating a vacuole
from whatever was on the outside and then creating a lysosome. So we can sort of picture this
endocytotic process as the cell membrane or wall depending on what if it's eukaryotic or
prokaryotic, sort of sucks in a little bit which creates basically a space and then the outer parts
of that wall reach up, reach around it and can actually seal and now you've created like a vacuole
that you pull into the cell. Yes and in the early multicellular organisms there were specialized
cells for doing this and they were called phagocytes for eating cells. Later on it was
learned that phagocytes could also serve an immunologic role, in other words that they could
eat pathogens as well as nutrients. This happened in the late 1800s when higher quality microscopes
were available. A Russian scientist named Ilya Mechnikov did a lot of the pioneering work on this.
He was working in Paris and he described, he was an embryologist and comparative zoologist,
and he described by looking at small animals that were completely transparent so he could see all
the cells inside and what they were doing. He actually imaged them while they were alive and
he could watch them eat and he could watch them fight bacterial infections and he was the major
champion of something called cellular immunity. At the same time some German scientists, notably
Paul Ehrlich, were working on what we now understand as antibodies and they said no it's
humoral immunity or soluble immunity in your blood and they had the cellular immunologists
in Paris and we had the humoral immunologists in Germany. Eventually they figured out they were
both right and they both got the Nobel Prize in 1908. But this is why mTOR is probably on
a lysosomal vacuole because in the context of evolutionary development it was on these vacuoles
that very simplest organisms use to ingest food and nutrients. And so you want to have it close to,
because it's there to sense those things, you want to have it very close to where they enter the cell.
Yes, exactly. So if we take a given eukaryotic cell today, take one of our cells, how many mTOR
complexes would exist in a cell? What order of magnitude? I'd turf that question to David
Sabatini. I don't think I've ever asked David that question. I don't know. I would guess it
would be on the order of thousands, not millions, not tens. So one of the other things that David's
done is not just recognizing this in mammals but also recognizing that mTOR, which again,
it's one of those things that's funny when you start to explain it to people,
because you can't explain what mTOR is without somewhere explaining what rapamycin is,
given the name. mTOR stands for mechanistic target of rapamycin. But David also played the
fundamental role in elucidating that mTOR can be organized in a couple of different ways and
sort of two main different ways it can be organized known as complex one and complex two.
Explain a little bit about what those two mean. How do they organize differently? And
perhaps more importantly, is there a functional difference between those?
Sure. So in yeast, there are two separate TOR proteins, one and two. And in, I think,
all other species, there's just one mTOR protein and it can be assembled into two different
complexes. One of them, or called TORC1, for target of rapamycin complex one,
regulates many of the things we've been talking about. So protein synthesis, lipid biosynthesis,
protein translation, and so forth. The other complex, TORC2, regulates cytoskeletal,
so in other words, the skeleton of the cells organization, and growth decisions. So different.
Now this is sort of interesting. So let's talk about rapamycin now. How does rapamycin interact
with TOR, its target? That's an excellent question because you think about TOR being
the target of rapamycin. It's not exactly. The target of rapamycin is an immunofilin
called FK binding proteins or FKBP. And there's several of these. There's three different classes
of immunofilins. The complex of rapamycin bound to FKBP then binds to the TORC1 complex
and inhibits it. And it inhibits it in different ways for different downstream targets. The one
that's most commonly measured is something called phospho-S6 kinase, which name's not important,
it's just this is the protein translation pathway. And it's very efficient in inhibiting that.
A little less so for another target called 4-EBP1, and even less so for a target called ULK1,
which is involved in activating the cell's recycling machinery called autophagy.
In other words, let's go through that again. So rapamycin binds, and how tightly does it bind,
pretty tightly? So it binds pretty tightly to this binding protein. This binding protein then
moves towards TOR. And in the case of, did we explain Raptor and Richter yet? We haven't
explained those cases. Do you want to spend maybe just a minute so that they can see the difference
between complex 1 and complex 2? So mTOR is present in both TORC1 and TORC2 complex,
but there are proteins that are unique to each complex. So as you were saying, the yeast have
two different TOR. Everything else has the same TOR, but it's another binding protein. It's another
protein bound to it that creates the distinction between complex 1 and 2, correct? Exactly. And we
should qualify every organism we looked at as only one mTOR. I'm sure we haven't looked at all of them.
So Raptor and Richter, again discovered in David Sabatini's group, Raptor is unique to TORC1 complex,
and Richter is unique to the TORC2 complex. And they're covalently bound to TOR? I don't think
it's covalent. Okay. So it's some sort of conformational configuration, but not necessarily?
Well, it's a multi-subunit complex, but I think they bind on the basis of having a fairly large
surface of interaction, not covalent. And then the complex, to get back to the FKBP of FKBP plus
Rapamycin, then binds to the TORC1 complex and inhibits it. But again, it inhibits it very well
for some of the downstream pathways and not so well for some of the others. And let's review,
again, those three. So the first one that binds really well, the serine phosphate, is which one?
There's the binding interaction of the Rapamycin FKBP to TORC1. Yes. And then that alters the TORC1
downstream activity. It inhibits quite effectively phosphorylation of S6 kinase.
S6 is a critical protein in the ribosome required for protein translation. It works a little less
well for a protein called 4-EBP1, which is an inhibitor of protein translation. So you inhibit
the inhibitor and you activate protein translation. And it's less effective at phosphorylating ULK
1, which is an early step in the activation of the cell recycling machinery called autophagy.
The interpretation of that is as following. Rapamycin is a strong inhibitor of making new
protein and a modest activator of autophagy. Exactly. Is that a fair statement? Yeah,
I think that's a fair statement. We're talking about these pathways as specific examples.
Remember, TORC1 does other things too, particularly in terms of regulation of lipid synthesis,
pyrimidine synthesis. Pyrimidines are part of DNA. What about mTORC2? So how does RAPA and FKBP
bind to mTORC2? I don't think it does directly because there's no immediate effect of the
complex on TORC2 activity. If you look at the downstream targets, they're not affected in the
short term. There's a longer term feedback inhibition of TORC2. And is that more due to
the failure to resynthesize enough TOR? Is there a shortfall of TOR because so much of the TOR is
bound to the RAPA FKBP complex that you now run out of enough TOR to make mTOR complex too?
You could imagine that is one possibility, but I don't think that's the case. I think it's more
there's a feedback signaling pathway that down regulates TORC2. What you said is very important,
and we're going to come back to it in great detail, but there's something temporal about this,
isn't there? Yes. Do we know how much exposure to rapamycin or a rapalog is necessary,
constitutive exposure, before you start to see this dual prong of inhibition? Are we talking about
a day, two days, three days, a month? I know you had David Sinclair on recently. Yeah. And I listened
to your talk with him. He talks about mouse experiments. My bias is to talk about people
experiments, given my role. In humans, after a week to a month, you can start to see consequences
of TORC2 inhibition with a rapalog alone, and it's reflected in hyperglycemia and hyperdruglyceridemia.
So biomarkers in the peripheral blood, you can measure. Why is it that inhibition of mTORC2
leads to that phenotype you just described? I don't think we know exactly. Is it confirmed
that that phenotype exists in healthy volunteers? In other words, we see this for sure in patients
who take rapamycin or its analogs in the context of organ transplantation, but if we took
non-diabetic, non-immunocompromised, quote unquote, as normal as possible subjects,
do we have evidence that those things happen? We do. MTOR inhibitors, well, rapalog specifically,
have been tested in non-transplant, non-malignant disease patients. Some specific examples include
the rapalog RAD001 was tested in patients with polycystic kidney disease. These people are
basically well, except for that renal disease. And even in those patients, there were a substantial
fraction who saw these biochemical changes in their blood. Now, not everybody gets it. We don't
understand that either. Do we know what the dose equivalence was of RAD001 versus rapamycin? In
other words, they were getting it daily. Do you recall at what dose did you start to see this
consequence? That was a phase three study. It's published so you could look it up. If I recall,
the dose was 10 milligrams a day and I think they had an opportunity to decrease the dose to 5
milligrams if it wasn't tolerated. Is RAD001 identical to rapamycin in dosing? What's the
dose equivalence? Again, it's hard to do an exact dose equivalence because the biochemistry of how
exactly the complex works with the mTORC complex is a little different. But if your rapamycin dose
is somewhere between 2 and 8 milligrams a day, roughly, at the immunosuppression level of dosing,
which is what we're talking about, that's comparable to 5 to 10 milligrams of RAD001.
Got it. So they're pretty similar, but not identical. Yes. So let's put a bow on this
particular question and then take a step backwards. Is it safe to say that most of the
inhibition of mTORC complex 2 seems to produce things that are not really desirable at all,
whereas the output of an mTORC complex 1 inhibition pathway seems quite desirable at least some time?
Yes. And in fact, most genetic experiments have supported that conclusion.
Let's talk a little bit about those experiments. So if you genetically knock out
raptor so that you no longer have complex 1, but you still have mTORC and rictor, so therefore
you have complex 2, what does that animal look like? Depends on how you do it. If you imagine
making a mouse that doesn't have raptor 1, which means it doesn't have
torque complex 1 from conception. I assume it has muscular dystrophy or something like that?
They're embryonic lethal. Yeah. Okay. You need torque 1 for development. So if you just turn it
down by some amount, 50% reduction. Not much of a phenotype of that, but the way the experiments
have been done is you can conditionally knock out a target in a mouse experiment. So you can
create an experiment where the mouse is normal and is born and develops normally. And then when the
mouse is a young adult, you can knock out raptor or knock out torque 1. So once they're out of the
development window, then they've reached adult size, then it's better tolerated. Yeah. And again,
David Sabatini has done a lot of these experiments. His group published a nice paper not that long
ago where they knocked out several components of the torque 1 complex. Inhibition of torque 1
extends lifespan and health span and rodents. If you do that to torque 2, it accelerates death.
Such an interesting concept. I mean, because what it basically suggests is at least with the tool
that we currently have to block tor, which is like rapamycin or rapilogue, giving intermittent dosing
may be beneficial. Giving constant dosing may cancel out the benefit. It's hard to know because
when you give it constantly, you're getting the quote unquote good inhibition and the bad inhibition.
You don't know what the net effect is, right? If you're using a rapilogue with continuous
administration, yes, you'll eventually down regulate torque 2 as well. And as far as we know,
that's not favorable. There are some other ways to do this. And Joan Mannock's second paper from 2018
was the first time we've explored that in humans. I want to come back to the 2018 paper, but I want
to build up to the 2014 paper. In 2009, this mouse study comes out. It was the first of what
would become a series of very interesting, highly reproduced ITPs funded by NIH that sort of did
something we didn't typically see, which is consistently across multiple labs and across
different strains show the same result. A lot of times in biology, you just don't get that. You get
the one hit wonder and it doesn't work in any other model or in any other lab. And that's not
because people were nefarious. It's just there's some very, very particular niche sort of circumstances
that are being exploited that we don't even understand. That didn't seem to be the case in
rapamycin. On a personal level, by 2009, I am now very interested in this compound, but I don't know
what to make of it because I remember being a resident at the hospital giving lots of serolimus,
a rapamune, to transplant patients along with their prednisone and their other immunosuppressive
drugs. And there didn't seem to be anything about that that seemed to be longevity producing. It
didn't make sense that you could suppress the immune system and somehow reduce death. It seemed
counterintuitive. I mean, in the transplant patient, it made sense because of course their
greatest risk is by far organ rejection, but these animal studies were not replicating that.
So I remember being incredibly confused for about the next five years. How did you guys
start thinking about that problem inside Novartis?
Joan proposed the idea, and again, the real innovation was being able to recognize
that I'm doing air quotes for the listeners age of the immune system is something that's
measurable and potentially modifiable in a reasonable timeframe. And we had that
paper from Chen in Science Cell Signaling that showed a short course of a rapologue
could alter the biology of lymphocytes.
And you're saying that in a favorable way, not a disfavorable way.
Yes.
Because the earliest observations of Serensegal were that lymphocytes being highly proliferative
were heavily targeted by rapamycin.
It's all about the dose.
Yeah. So let's talk about those doses. As you alluded to earlier, a transplant patient
might be taking five milligrams a day of rapamycin, day in and day out.
What types of doses were you seeing that were producing this counterintuitive phenotype?
Well, if we get back to the mouse paper.
Yeah, yeah, exactly. Like lower or higher, I guess is what I'm saying relative to that.
It's hard to compare is you have to look at exposures. So the doses on a weight basis
or a body surface are much higher in a rodent experiment, but the exposures can be comparable.
They were actually fairly high in his paper. They were at least equal to what we use in
transplant. Obviously, we couldn't do that in healthy volunteers, especially healthy
elderly volunteers. There was some additional information that gave us some confidence we
could use much lower doses than what was used in transplant patients, yielding much lower exposures.
And for the listeners, exposures means how much of the drug is actually in your body over time.
So let's use Cialis as an example of this. I don't know why, but it's just I was talking to
a patient about this the other day. Cialis is typically given as either five milligrams or 20
milligrams. And patients typically have a choice if they want to take 20 milligrams, quote unquote,
on demand. So you're heading into the weekend, you're going away with your wife. It's Friday,
you take the 20 milligrams of Cialis and erectile dysfunction is ameliorated Friday through Sunday.
Conversely, another way to take Cialis is to take five milligrams every single day, whether or not
you're going to be sexually active or not. But now all of a sudden, any time you want to be sexually
active, you're functionally like that person who just took 20. Use the lingo of exposure to explain
how those two things are comparable. I don't know why this is somehow the first example that
came to my mind, but probably just because it was a discussion I had two days ago.
It's actually a good example because when you take the medicine, doesn't always reflect if the
medicine is in your body or not. And medicines that work have to be in your body to work.
So the five milligram dose of Cialis taken once might be in your body for a day. A 20 milligram
dose of Cialis taken once is in your body for two to three days. So it's why the higher dose
taken once can last over the even long weekend perhaps, because it's still there. This we call
in drug development a half-life of the drug. So the half-life of Cialis is long enough that it can
do that. But there's not the case for Viagra, for example. That's right. Now there's another
interesting thing here, which will also be another, will have a parallel to the Rapa story, which is
generally patients will tolerate five milligrams daily of Cialis more than 20 milligrams on demand
because of the side effects. You have fewer side effects because you don't have the same peak levels.
So five milligrams daily will produce a very consistent and narrow gap between peak and trough,
which is therapeutic, whereas 20 will overshoot. You'll get a very high peak level, which may
increase the side effects, lightheadedness, changes in vision, things like that. And then you have a
long enough way down before you hit trough. And it's during that entire window that you have
the availability of the effect of the drug. Now that's true for the class of drugs. The
phosphodiesterase inhibitors. Yeah, B5 inhibitors. It's not true for other drugs. Two specific
examples, Rapamycin, where if you remember when you were treating your transplant patients,
you measured trough levels. We measured, yeah, daily. I mean, we were constantly doing this.
But you measured the trough levels, not the peak levels. That's right. Because the side effects are
driven by the trough levels as well as the efficacy. And I think that's also true with
gentamycin and a lot of the antibiotics that have the same toxicities on the trough, right?
Yes. So gentamycin, years ago, we used to dose three times a day. And modern times we dose it
once a day and we get better efficacy and far fewer side effects. So why is that the case? That
a drug like gentamycin or Rapamycin is producing toxicity by its nadir, not its peak.
Every drug is different and it depends on the specific mechanism for gentamycin
and immunoglycosides in general. Remember these work on the bacterial ribosome and there's some
congruency between mitochondrial ribosomes and bacterial ribosomes. And with sustained inhibition
that can cause toxicity, particularly in the kidney and the tubular epithelial cells, also in
interior hair cells and some other places. So having some drug-free time seems to allow the
organelles to recover. At least that's the hypothesis I heard in medical school. We all
know that half of what we learned in medical school is wrong and they just weren't sure which half.
You had a better medical school than me. I think 90% of what I learned in medical school is wrong.
But you went to Harvard. I only went to Stanford. So I think that's the West Coast, East Coast
difference. No, I think that's, I mean, to me, that is the most logical argument, which is
drugs that have trough toxicity are drugs where you must have a break from the drug.
And the higher the trough, the lower the probability of a break. Peak drugs aren't
about time away. It's literally too much of this thing eventually hits a trigger.
That's probably an oversimplification, but it's a useful conceptual framework.
So let's now taking that model back, the first glimmer of hope that this drug had
wasn't uniformly immune suppressing was, yeah, what if we dose this lower, basically? And not
from the standpoint of side effects, because that's a common reason you'd go lower, but actually
change the profile of inhibition. Was it known at the time that that's what they were trying to do?
Like, did they have enough insight into how rapamycin bound to the two different complexes to
test this hypothesis proactively? Or was this more empirical an observation that after the fact,
the mechanism became elucidated? We had some information up front. One bit of information
that the mechanism could be favorable for immune function, not solely immunosuppressive,
was looking again in your transplant patients at those who were on a calcium ion inhibitor versus
those who were on a rapilogue. And there was a significant trend that those on rapilogues had
fewer cytomegalovirus infections than those on calcium ion inhibitors, all of the things being
equal. An observational study, not as well controlled as ideally we would like, but
it was intriguing. Do you remember the order of magnitude on that difference? So you're
basically talking about FK 506 versus? Cyclosporine. Yeah. Well, it was rapamycin versus
cyclosporine or FK. Maybe I don't remember. We'd have to go back and look. So that was item one.
Item two is we had done exposure response experiments in cellular systems, looking at
how much drug is required to inhibit the downstream targets of torque one. And it was
much, much lower than the exposures that are observed in the usual dosing framework of
rapamycin, at least for transplant and immunosuppression. If we were going to be treating
healthy people with a rapilogue and test whether their immune function was better, we couldn't be
giving them a typical rapilogue side effect. And this is again, a critical element of the
translational medicine that Joan did in order to make this proposal is what doses and what schedule
would be required to keep the trough levels actually less than assay, which would be as
safe as we could get it, plus nonetheless achieve adequate exposures to at least partially or
temporarily fully inhibit torque one. That would let us ask the question.
Let's now pause for a moment to explain we've switched back and forth between the term
rapamycin and rapilogue. So again, a little bit of a history lesson, but rapamycin
is the name given by Seren Segal to the compound identified on Easter Island. That
went through two companies before being eventually absorbed by Pfizer through Wyeth.
And that was a drug named rapamune or cerolamis. And that was FDA approved in 1999
for transplantation. What was the first rapilogue to come along?
Arguably, it's rapamycin. The next drug...
Yeah, sorry, semantics aside. After rapamune, rapamycin, cerolamis, we're talking about the
experiment that we're about to discuss in detail is using a different molecule.
It's using a different molecule. We called it RAD001 in the paper. The generic name is
everolamis. It was the second one. Temcerolamis is another one.
How does it differ from rapamune or cerolamis?
There's small structural changes.
And it was synthesized to be different versus discovered in nature or was it deliberately
modified, presumably?
Yes. Again, to improve the properties of the compound.
Has that borne out? I mean, obviously there's an IP reason one would do that, obviously. But
in terms of clinical efficacy, are there differences?
I'm not aware of any comparative studies. In vitro, potency seems to be a little greater.
I can tell you from firsthand experience looking at the cost of these drugs,
there certainly is a difference. Good Lord!
Yes, it's generic versus brand, I think, at this point still.
But even rapamune branded compared to...
But anyway.
I am not somebody who can talk about drug costs.
Yeah, yeah. No, well, it's one of the most comical things I've ever seen, actually.
So let's now talk about this experiment. I'll tell you from my vantage point the day I'll
never forget, which is I remember getting an embargoed copy on the day before Christmas.
So it's Wednesday, December 24th. It's probably noon.
It's funny, I was in my office, which is dumb. Why was I in my office at noon on Wednesday,
the day before Christmas? I certainly shouldn't have been, but I remember being in my office
and I remember how sunny it was. I remember what a beautiful day it was and I remember
someone from the New York Times emailing me the embargoed copy and it's embargoed.
Yeah, it was embargoed for another couple of hours.
The person at the time she sent it to me knew how interested I was in the subject matter.
And I'm reading this thing and I'm like, this is unbelievable. I just couldn't believe what I was
reading. And I have a background in immunology, so of course I can understand what these figures
are showing. Give people a sense of how long it takes to get there. So if the public is first
seeing this in December of 2014, when did the experiment start? And I didn't mean that
conceptually. I don't just mean you're enrolling patients. This is about a four or five-year journey,
right? That's right. About 2010 we started.
So what was the hypothesis that you wanted to test and that you, Joan, and the team wanted to test?
There was some pre-work before we could ask the question. The pre-work was one, we reviewed
the existing literature, especially that paper from Chen. And we then looked at some other work
that had looked at drug levels in cellular systems necessary to partially or fully inhibit
the target. And we had to look at a lot of different cells because Torq1's biology,
while in the big picture is the same in different cells, the sensitivity of the complex to the drug
is different in different cells. And we have some hypotheses now for why that is. And we then did
some modeling to understand whether the low doses, and we looked at internal data that
the company had to see, could we come up with a low dose and a schedule that would
yield exposures in people that would partially or fully inhibit Torq1, yet give
less than assay trough levels to help ensure safety in the healthy volunteers.
Now, Lloyd, was this mostly because at the time you wanted to see if it even made sense to pursue
a new molecule entirely that would inhibit complex one or so-called selective inhibition,
but the idea is why go down that path of doing that without a proof of concept that says it works?
Or did you think at that point in time, if we can get this to work, you would never need a
selective mTORQ1 inhibitor? You're asking really for Novartis thinking that's probably still
confidential, but the big picture is we want to know if something works. We want to figure out if
we can make it better. Again, ultimately, Novartis, we at RestoreBio, and hopefully everybody at a
pharmaceutical company is thinking about how can we make patients' lives better, and then everything
else is important but secondary to that. And then what do we measure? What dose do we use?
How frequently do we give it? How long do we treat people? How do we answer the question clearly? What
do we measure? All of those questions had to be answered, and they had to be answered before
Joan brought the program to the decision board of the company to say,
give us a lot of money to do this experiment. Each of these clinical experiments costs millions of
dollars. And at the time, RAD001 was FDA approved for another indication or no? Yes. It was already
approved in cancer or in? I think it was in renal cell. RCC? Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So that only raises
the stakes of what you're asking because you're taking a drug that's already gone through phase
three, and you're going to spend a lot of money on it that you technically don't need to spend.
Is that a common thing to do inside of a company as large as Novartis to take a
drug that basically you're trying to make the case for a totally different use?
Yes. I suspect most companies do things like this, where when a drug is registered in one indication,
if you can find others, it's a good thing. So, I mean, for the sake of time, I will just,
I mean, basically say that you guys did something kind of amazing, which is with so little human
data, you did a great job of identifying the right patient population, identifying the right primary
outcome, identifying a correct power analysis so you wouldn't miss the signal. So in other words,
you didn't know how to power the study, which means you had to have a sense of how much the
benefit was going to be, knowing how long to pulse, how to dose. I mean, this could have gone sideways
six other ways. It could have. We had some additional help too. At the time, Novartis had
a vaccines group and they had commercialized a flu vaccine. So we knew a lot about flu vaccination
and responses required for making a clinical difference and so forth.
So let's walk people through the study design. You've got what, about 300 people
aged 60 plus more or less? I think it was 218 in that 214 paper. Everybody was over 65,
no unstable medical conditions. Were these subjects all in Australia? Was there something
about this that was in Australia? Well, because this was a flu vaccination, so let's just skip
ahead. The endpoint to the study, the primary endpoint by which we were going to decide, did
the study work or not work, was the response to a flu vaccination, the seasonal flu. Now,
because it's a seasonal vaccine, we had to do the study when we were ready, wherever in the world
people were about to get their flu vaccines. In that paper, we were ready for the Southern
Hemisphere because our summer is there winter. Right. And since the CVS and the Antarctica
ran out of vaccine that year, Australia made the most sense. Australia and New Zealand. Yeah.
So there are four arms in this study. There's a placebo arm that gets just obviously a placebo.
There's three treatment arms, one that gets 0.5 milligrams of RAD001 daily. So ever all of us.
There's a group that's getting five milligrams once a week, and there's a group that's getting
20 milligrams once a week. So it's a clever design because the five and the 20 that are
both getting it once a week gives you a great, you get to answer both efficacy and toxicity questions
as they pertain to that dose. The 0.5 daily versus the five weekly is your closest aggregate dose
where you get to see is there a difference in trough. So overall, a lot of interesting stuff.
What was your personal null hypothesis? Not necessarily the same, but do you recall what
your null hypothesis was going into that experiment? I mean, obviously the null hypothesis is that
there's no drug effect. Yeah, sorry. What was your first alternative hypothesis? I guess it's
a better way to say it. This was a little bit less hypothesis testing the way that academic
investigators work than it was asking questions. And the question was, and there were several,
but at a high level, it's can we see an improved vaccine response at an acceptable level of
toxicity that would have this drug make sense? And that's the high level question. And you went
through the doses and schedules we used and we tested three different ones because each of those
doses did a different thing to torque one inhibition. The 0.5 milligram dose partially
inhibited in a sustained fashion. The five milligram once a week fully inhibited torque one
for a couple days out of the week. And the 20 milligrams we modeled would fully inhibit torque
one over the dosing interval. I didn't realize that actually. 20 is so high that it gave you
functionally nonstop inhibition of mTORC1 until your next dose. Did any of these have mTORC2
inhibition? I would have expected the 20 milligram would have. I don't remember that anyone had to
discontinue the drug for that reason, but it's been a couple of years since I read that paper.
Well, let's look at the toxicity table. So table one of this paper, which is again such an
interesting paper, I was surprised. Obviously it was the first thing I looked at. Usually table
one is inclusion criteria or something like that, but you guys just skipped the foreplay and went
right to it. Table one, incidence of treatment related adverse effects. I wish I could honestly
say I remember how I read this the very first time because I've looked at it a number of times
since. But what's interesting is I certainly remember seeing that the placebo group had
21 adverse events. So that's important to always keep in mind when you look at clinical studies
is there's just a baseline level of adverse effects that have no bearing on the drug whatsoever.
So it's almost like you could subtract 21 out of all of the others to get a sense of what the noise
is. So the group that got 0.5 daily had 35 adverse effects and each of the treatment groups had about
the same number. So I mean there were 53 groups in each of the three arms, 59 in the placebo. So
the 21 you might discount that slightly, but it basically went from 35 to 46 to 109. So
at this point, obviously this means each patient is having more than one adverse effect likely.
But here's what I found interesting. The next line in the table tells you how many people actually
had adverse effects and not just the total adverse effects. And this was surprisingly
constant. So in the placebo group it's 12. In arm one it's 22. In arm two it's 20. In arm three it's
27. So looks like 0.5 daily versus five weekly. No real difference in adverse effects. And by the
way, I'm not going to, don't worry, I won't read you guys the whole table here. We're going to link
to this paper in the show notes. The other thing that really stood out to me though in terms of
side effects was mouth ulceration. Now that's the side effect I remembered the most from residency
was the patients getting apathos ulcers with their daily dose of rapamycin. And most of them were
getting more than 0.5 daily. So most of the patients that I wrote, my recollection was that
two to four milligrams was a very common daily dose for rapamune. And again, this is rad001. So
it's a different vehicle, but it's comparable. And so 0.5 daily would definitely be lower than
what I was used to seeing people get. And yet 11.5% of these folks had mouth ulcerations,
whereas the people getting 0.5 daily were at 0.5 once a week was about 4%. And 20 once a week
was about 17%. So that's really interesting. I mean that tells a very interesting story about
the kinetics of this drug. Was there any other toxicity that surprised you in the study?
Well, as you pointed out, mouth ulcers are one of the more common and fairly specific side effects
for rapilogues. Should we spend one moment explaining why? I think we could certainly
speculate why. I don't think anybody knows why there are some hypotheses, but, and it isn't just
rapilog associated mouth ulcers. We don't know what causes the ordinary spontaneous
apthas ulcerations that people get. There've been a fair amount of work on it, but nobody knows.
There are a lot of mysteries in medicine and that's just another one of them.
Anecdotally, through five years of residency, I don't think I went more than two weeks without
an apthas ulcer. They can be stress related. I'm sure they are. And it was to the point where they
would drive me so bananas, I couldn't even get relief from those sort of topical lidocaine gels.
The only thing that could give me real relief was if I could inject bupivacaine directly into it,
because it was such a long acting agent. Lidocaine only lasts an hour or two. That was not going to
do me justice on a call night. And it got to the point where I would sit there and inject bupivacaine
into my tongue or into my mouth. And I remember once somebody walking in the call room while I'm
sitting there holding my gums out, jamming bupivacaine in and I'm kidding them. They must
have thought I had some drug problem. But two weeks after leaving residency, I never had an
apthas ulcer again. I hope you never have another one. They're very painful. They're unbelievable.
But then of course I did get them once I started rapamycin. So we'll come back to that. But I
certainly went many, many years without them again. My hypothesis was some combination of
stress and sleep deprivation might have played a role. It doesn't help mechanistically though.
We just don't understand them. So overall, I thought the side effects were less than I
would have expected. Let's now talk about the results. I'll actually hand you the table here,
because not that I would ever expect you to remember table 2a, but walk a little bit through
kind of what you guys saw and how you tested it. So you're using a couple of different
flu vaccines, et cetera, a couple of different strains. Yeah. So the standard flu vaccine had
in those days, three different antigens for three different kinds of viruses, two
influenza A strains, one influenza B strain. And I think as we all know, the flu vaccine is designed
every single year based on the circulating flu strains in Asia to try to match the vaccine
to the strains of flu that we expect to get in this case in the Southern hemisphere
or for us in the Northern hemisphere. So patients were treated with one of those doses of RAD001
or a placebo. And the study was randomized, double blind and placebo controlled. So neither
the doctors nor the patients knew who was getting what. And I guess there's one detail I omitted,
which if my memory is correct, the patients were treated for eight weeks. Six weeks. Six weeks. And
then there was a washout. So then they had a period of nothing for, was that six to eight weeks?
It was two weeks after the six weeks of treatment. Oh, that's where the eight came in. So it was six
of treatment, two of washout, then vaccination. Right. And the rationale for that was we wanted
the drug to be completely gone at the time we vaccinated. So we were asking the question,
is this a residual effect of the drug on the immune system? Not a lingering effect on the
immune system per se. Yeah. Not a direct effect of the drug, but an indirect. Yes. Okay. So with
that said, what was the first finding? So we were looking for whether the response to the flu
vaccine was 1.2 fold better in a drug treated group than the placebo. And that 1.2 fold came from
a previous study that had been published that showed that was the minimum requirement
to see a clinically meaningful decrease in symptomatic flu in vaccinated patients.
We saw, and we required, and this was pre-specified two out of the three strains to have that
improvement. And we saw that improvement or better in the two low doses of RAD 001,
but not in the high dose. And the high dose we just saw one string better. One of the three
strains was better. And the other two were actually a little below one, so a little below
the placebo. What do you make of that? Is it noise? Do you think there's something
mechanistically happening there? I do. I think we certainly know that high doses of
a Rapalog or immunosuppressive, the dose of 20 milligrams once a week is sufficiently high to
fully suppress torque one. I expect that we probably interfered with lymphocyte proliferation.
And do you think it's just a tweak that you didn't see? What's confusing to me is that you
still saw a much greater immunity in one strain. And if I recall, it was even higher than the two
low doses, thinking about the first figure in the top figure in the second figure of the paper. So
that would be, my first guess would be, oh, clearly you just hit the daily dose of an
immunosuppressed patient if they were all below baseline. But if you did a 25
weekly in there, do you think you would have just seen them all eventually start to go down?
Certainly, if we got to some high enough dose, I think they all would have been low.
I got it. Yeah. So it's almost like there's a J curve here, or an upside down J curve,
really, or an upside down U, I suppose, of some combination of dose and frequency producing a
sweet spot where we're seeing, and by the way, I can't recall, it's been so long since I looked
at the paper, was there any lympho proliferation? I mean, these were functional assays. Any changes
in the counts of lymphocytes or any other? This specific assay that was the primary
endpoint was an antibody titer assay. Right. We didn't do mixed lymphocyte reactions or some
proliferation assays part of this paper. Did anyone ever look at fractions of lymphocytes,
for example, did anyone look at CD25, CD3 to see if anything had happened to suppressor T cells?
We didn't do it in this study. Well, we didn't do functional lymphocyte assays. Part of this study
was a very comprehensive multidimensional flow cytometric assay to get lymphocyte subsets. And
we reported one of the results in figure three, which is where we saw improvement in
checkpoint protein levels on both CD8 and CD4 lymphocytes, which mean in checkpoint proteins,
they're very popular in oncology now. And some of your listeners may have heard about those things
like PD1, for example, the drug target of Keytruda or Optivo. We had Keith Flaherty on recently,
and we had a beautiful discussion about checkpoint inhibition. But that said, let's assume people
don't know what that is. It's always worth rediscussing it. Yeah, these proteins inhibit
lymphocyte function, and they go up as the lymphocytes get exhausted. And what we saw in
this study is that the level of PD1 went down on the lymphocytes in the drug treatment group
compared to the placebo. By what percent? It was a relatively small effect, a 10 to 20% change.
But comparable to the effect that you saw in the increase in antibody recognition. I mean,
it was like the mirror of that. I guess, yeah. And presumably the teleologic rationale for that is
the more tired a lymphocyte gets, the more it wants to weaken its breaks. I'll go along with that.
Everything in me, in my world, Lloyd, comes down to just anthropomorphizing the immune system.
That's how I do things. So has anyone looked at this, by the way, to see what rapamycin does
or rapalog does in this type of intermittent dosing to inhibitory T cells?
There have been a lot of studies of T cell subset functions with rapalogs,
both in mice and in humans, looking at effector memory transition, looking at Tregs with high
exposures or substantial inhibitory effect on B cell function. There's a lot out there.
Do you think that rapalogs could be used to suppress Tregs? Selectively, of course.
There are a couple of papers that show that.
Because it would sure be interesting to start layering in rapalogs with immunotherapy,
oncology-specific.
Yes. Yeah. There's a small literature on that.
What else did you see in this paper? I think we've touched on the high points.
Yeah. The other experiment we did, which I think we mentioned in the text,
but didn't go into great details, is the flu vaccine is a T-dependent antibody response.
We also vaccinated patients with a 23-valent pneumococcal vaccine, which is B cell,
which is a pure polysaccharide vaccine. So it's a T-independent response.
We were thinking, could we improve antigen presentation? Perhaps if the dose of
the rapalog we used augmented autophagy, and could that contribute to antigen presentation?
We saw and we measured seven of the 23 antigens.
Wait. Tell me why that would be... That's not an obvious purview into autophagy to me. So let's
back that up a little bit. So you're giving them a pneumococcal vaccine, which is what type of
vaccine? That's a...
Polysaccharide antigen.
Polysaccharide antigen. You're not giving back the whole bacteria.
And how does it get presented to the immune system?
There are specific elements of innate immunity that recognize bacterial polysaccharide antigens,
and that brings it to professional antigen presenting cells, likely dendritic cells.
And then it has to be internalized and then presented.
So that's MHC class one?
This isn't a peptide presentation. This is presented in the context of an innate
element that recognizes polysaccharide antigens.
Okay. All right. So we're outside of class one, class two.
Yes.
And you're saying the ability to internalize, or basically the ability to phagocytose
that like the polysaccharide, and then...
And directly stimulate B cells.
It was an exploratory element of the study. We saw in the seven specific antigen responses we
measured, if I recall, six of them increased, but by a small amount.
It was an encouraging trend, but we didn't further follow it up.
Okay. Any other markers you could have here for autophagy?
I mean, did you look at light chain transition or anything like that?
No. Autophagy is a really difficult clinical investigation paradigm.
And I know you recently saw Mitch Weiss's paper on unpaired hemoglobin.
In thalassemia patients. I was super excited when I read that paper,
because here is now a clinical paradigm where we can test drugs that augment autophagy and see
something easily measurable in a not that rare patient population.
Yeah. Let me think. In those patients, did you collect serum that allow you to look at amino
acid levels in the plasma or anything else?
No, we didn't do any of that.
Do you still have any of that banked serum?
I don't think so.
Easy enough experiment to repeat, but of course, the other thing I'm curious about is,
is there anything about RAD001 administration that mimics fasting, for example? I mean,
how much of the benefit here is through direct inhibition of mTOR? And are there any
pleotrophic benefits that aren't quantified through this? Obviously, some of them, I mean,
the fact that you waited until the drug was out of the system to check the immune response is
actually a great insight, because obviously you eliminate some of those things. But in the way
that many people have argued statins have a direct effect, they inhibit cholesterol synthesis,
an indirect effect, the liver upregulates LDL-R, a really indirect effect, which is immune suppression
or other sort of benefits around endothelial health and things like that. Do you think there's
a possible third leg to this stool that we haven't thought about?
The fasting story is kind of complex. So do I think there's some other persistent benefit of
a rapologue? I think the mouse experiments tells us there is, and it's because relatively short
course of a rapologue is nonetheless sufficient to extend a mouse's lifespan. And we do not
understand that. Although it's so hard to extrapolate what short versus long means in a mouse, isn't it?
Yes. Look at the mouse that fasts for 24 hours. Look at Jay Mitchell's stuff where they do a one
day fast prior to ephemeral artery ligation and a reperfusion where the mouse that was just fed
normally through the insult, they all die. The mice that had 24 hours of fasting prior to a lethal
reperfusion injury either all or mostly live. I don't know how to extrapolate that into a higher
order animal because it's not even the duration of the fast, it's the metabolic consequence of
the fast. There's some long-term consequence of that that we don't understand. And there's
several things you could hypothesize. Is there a change in the DNA structure based on histone
methylation or DNA methylation? Or is it something else? Those are just the things that come to mind.
Yeah, that's a great point, right? You could literally be resetting methylation on that.
You could turn back a methylation clock to its template, potentially.
But people have looked at that with raphologs and it doesn't seem to happen.
In other words, you take a Horvath clock pre and post and you're not seeing unwinding of methylation.
Yeah.
That's been done in mice as well or just in humans.
I suspect it's been done in a bunch of species. It's one of these sort of negative studies that
may never get published. That's a pet peeve of mine, by the way. Negative studies not getting
published. I think it's a pet peeve of a lot of people. It's hard enough to publish
positive studies. And I'm sympathetic and agree.
So we're high-fiving on New Year's Eve, 2014. How do you go from, what is Novartis,
and again, if this is confidential, by all means, just gloss, we'll skip it, but what are the brass
that Novartis think of the results of this experiment, which is effectively taking a drug
that we already have on the market for a very clear indication and now potentially
expanding an indication? Can the FDA take a study? This is a very well done study here.
This is double-blinded. This is placebo-controlled. And this found a significant outcome. Is that
enough to change the indication for a medication like this?
I can speak in general in that for an indication that could be relevant to many, many people,
you need a corresponding, a lot of safety data. This study was way too small for
studies that would be required for marketing authorization.
I got it. So because something like renal cell carcinoma is relatively infrequent relative to
influenza vaccination, you had enough safety data to justify treating people with RCC. This would
not constitute sufficient safety data to basically give every person over the age of 65
who's getting vaccinated this type of a medication.
That's exactly right. If we fast forward a little bit in the conversation,
we've advanced this program in Restore Bio. Novartis licensed it to Restore Bio. And our phase
three program is two very similarly designed clinical studies. One has a thousand patients.
The other one will have about 1600 patients.
You able to speak about how the decision was made for Restore Bio to basically acquire a piece of
an asset from Novartis and what else was brought in to create that company and how did you, Joan,
and I assume many others decide to leave. I mean, that's obviously a loss to Novartis,
presumably, which implies that they probably still have a vested interest in the success of Restore
Bio. Yeah. Let's take one step backwards and answer an earlier question you asked,
which is, what did Novartis think when we got these results?
Oh, yes. Yes, thank you.
I think everybody was very excited for reasons that you're excited.
That was my Christmas present of the year.
And the guidance was, this is so important, let's go back and do it again.
Try to do it in a more torque one selective way.
Are you able to say how much that study cost just to give a sense of?
I don't think we talk externally, but any clinical study like this, a phase two study with
two to 300 patients costs millions. And a lot of the cost is driven by
often exploratory assessments you do in the context of the study beyond the per patient
cost and investigator cost, but millions. I mean, it's a lot of money for anybody,
and it's done with a lot of deliberation and thought.
So the guidance was to go back and do it again, make sure it's real,
come up with a way to be more torque one selective.
But using the same vehicle, which means putting a finer point on the dosing, not necessarily,
I mean, you're still not at the point where people are saying,
we need to make a new molecule to replicate this.
Well, we had one.
The research team at Novartis had come up with a very cool finding that a combination of an
allosteric and catalytic torque inhibitor could be more torque one selective and more potent.
There was actually synergy. And this is published by Beyot Niefeller and Lohn Murphy.
They showed synergy. So a wrap along.
Can you explain to folks what the difference is between allosteric versus catalytic inhibition?
Sure. So catalytic inhibition means an inhibitor that's binding at the catalytic site of torque one
and blocking phosphorylation of targets. An allosteric inhibitor is a fancy way of saying
an inhibitor that binds someplace else on the molecule and nonetheless inhibits it.
Rapamycin complex.
I always think of allosteric as sort of shape blocking.
Could be.
Let's say shape blocking. So in this case, the allosteric inhibitor is the
combination of FKBP12 plus rapamycin binding to torque one. So the combination of those two
synergistically inhibits torque one and it's a little more torque one selective.
Everol almost does the same thing. It also binds to FKBP.
Yes, it binds to FKBP also. Maybe later on we can get to that lambing paper, which is...
Which I'd love to get to that paper.
Yeah.
So with that understanding, we could then explore, put a finer point on the dosing as well as explore
the biology of that catalytic inhibitor with and without RAD001. And that's what the next study did.
Overall, a very similar study design. We treated for six weeks,
two week washout, interrogated the immune system function with flu vaccination and got
fundamentally similar results. There's one other point I'd like to bring in because it leads to
where we are now. In the very first study we did in analyzing, we saw immune function improvement,
which in our marker for that was flu vaccine response. In the adverse event listings,
we saw fewer infections in the drug treated people compared to the placebo patients.
Over what time horizon?
We followed people for a year.
And by the way, did that increase in vaccination translate to a reduction in influenza?
Or was that the infection you're speaking about? Are you speaking about all infections?
All infections.
Okay. What about influenza specifically?
Too few events to be able to make a conclusion.
It's underpowered to look at the flu.
Exactly. If you think about all infections you get or patients get, most of them are respiratory
tract infections, colds and flus in the winter season.
An interesting thought experiment, you wouldn't do this experiment, but an interesting thought
experiment would be a two by two vaccine, no vaccine, RAPA, no RAPA, powered to see difference
in infection.
Big experiment.
Huge experiment, but great gedanken, right?
Yes, I agreed. So in this very first study we found, again, we weren't thinking about it and we
weren't looking for it, but we observed it in the adverse event listings.
So what were some of those infections, Lloyd, that you saw? Like UTIs or cellulitis, that kind of
stuff?
Two most common ones. By far the most common was upper respiratory tract infection or respiratory
tract infection.
That was not influenza, yeah.
Maybe some of them were. We didn't measure. We don't know what the pathogens were.
We do know from surveillance experiments that the CDC has done that most of them are
rhinovirus and then there's metanumavirus. There's various other.
Echo, God only knows what.
Yes. And we saw a decrease in UTIs also.
And that persisted for a year?
The biggest effect was when the patients were shortly over the course of drug treatment and
sometime thereafter. But even if we analyze it over the course of a year, we saw it,
although the effect waned. In this very first study in 2014, we brought patients back a year
later and revaccinated them to see if the improvement in immunologic function persisted.
And?
It did not.
Okay. So by a year, they'd clearly lost it.
Yes.
And of course, we didn't do the experiment, but do you know if six weeks was necessary or could
you have done four plus two or three plus two or two plus two? Would the benefit have been better
if you went eight plus two or 10 plus two or 12 plus two? Like how did you agree on six weeks of
treatment? I understand the two week washout, but what about the six weeks of treatment?
It came from two places. One is that that's what they did in the mice.
My same caveat implies.
Totally agree. And then secondly, we know the timing of lymphocyte production from committed
precursors in human bone marrow. And we were thinking that the drug could be acting at that
level. And six weeks of treatment is sufficient to, by the time you vaccinated eight weeks,
have some new lymphocytes from those committed precursors.
So your hypothesis would be six was the minimum time required to get a full turnover and going
eight versus 10 would not necessarily bring benefit and might only expose you to longer side effects.
We actually never tested this. We came up with our dosing period for the rationale that I gave
you. And we've not, at least with a Rapalogue, tested other intervals. We did see in the second
study, which also worked on the vaccine endpoint, we promoted respiratory tract infections and
infections in general to secondary endpoints. So we're looking at them prospectively. We're
collecting them more carefully. That was in the second study.
In the second study. And again, the drugs decreased the incidence of respiratory tract
infections. The biggest effect was observed with just the catalytic inhibitor alone.
The second biggest effect.
Wait, the catalytic inhibitor was a new molecule?
Yes, it's a new compound. In that paper, it was called BEZ235. And this is the molecule licensed
by RestoreBio.
So BEZ235 is not RAD001 combined with something else?
No, we tested the combination and it also decreased respiratory tract infections. And the
combination was the best at improving the flu response. But the single catalytic inhibitor
was the best at preventing respiratory tract infections. This study had an extra arm. It was
a somewhat bigger study, 264 patients.
Was this the one published two years ago?
Yes, 2018.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, a year ago. Okay. So let's now talk about the creation of RestoreBio.
So essentially the story is that we did the second study for prevention of respiratory
tract infections and enhancing immune function with mTOR inhibition. Worked again. Everybody's
excited. And Novartis, as in most big companies, big pharma companies, the research teams produce
more than global development can handle. And it's done deliberately. It gives early in drug
development, you never know exactly what's going to work best. You want to create enough
opportunities so something will be exciting. And the program transitioned to global development,
and they had a lot of exciting things to do. And this fell below the funding line. It reflects in
part the excellent productivity of Novartis research. It reflects in part the great opportunities
the global development has. Of course, as the champions of the program, we were kind of
disappointed. But Novartis felt, and again, I'm speaking for myself now, I'm not a Novartis
spokesperson, but Novartis felt this drug looks like it could work and it could help people. We
have to find a way to make it available to people if it could work. So other pharma companies do this
too. The decision was to out license it. And Joan is the sort of originator of the idea and the
biggest champion, wanted to go outside of Novartis and start a company. I introduced her to an
absolutely awesome CEO I know who was ready for his next role. And they raised money and they
created the Restore Bio. And that was a pretty quick path to going public. Restore Bio went public
late in 18, didn't they? It reflected in part the need for funds to run a phase three program.
Yeah. What did Restore Bio raise in the IPO? You're asking me a hard question. I was at Novartis,
but probably around 90 million, I think. Wow. Yeah. So yeah, as you said, that's, you're
basically going right to phase three at this point because, so you licensed one or two molecules from
Novartis. Restore Bio licensed BEZ235, which is now named RTB101. And they then did a phase two
B study. These two studies we had done were phase two A. Phase two A. Yeah. Right. So in the first
study published in 2014 that we've been discussing, respiratory tract infections and infections in
general were observed to be decreased in the drug treated group compared to the placebo
by reviewing the adverse event listings. This was not something we had considered a priori,
but we recognize decreased infections could be a consequence of improved immune function,
which is why we looked in the first place in the listings. And then in the second study,
where we explored a catalytic inhibitor, which is now RTB101, RAD001, as well as the combination,
we promoted respiratory tract infections and infections in general to a secondary
endpoint. And we specifically included collecting those data, both by patient reporting, as well as
investigator querying the patients at home regularly. And again, we saw decreased respiratory
tract infections. The best drug was BEZ235, which we now call RTB101 in terms of decreasing
respiratory tract infections. The combination also worked. Interestingly, the combination,
as well as RAD001, improved the flu vaccine response, but the BEZ235 or RTB101 did not.
Remind me, it's catalytically inhibiting. So it's binding directly to TOR?
Yes.
And is it binding equally to TOR when bound to raptor, meaning complex one, as it is binding to
TOR bound to Richter, known as complex two?
So the way this is usually done is in a cellular assay context. So we don't look specifically for
the binding, but we look for inhibition of phosphorylation of sites.
Of serine 6 or which one?
S6 kinase for TORC1 and phospho-AKT there. And we look specifically at the phosphorylation site
that TORC2 does, not the one that any other enzyme does. So we're able to see that a catalytic
inhibitor at high concentrations will inhibit both. RTB101 has some preference for TORC1,
and it's a little different depending upon which cell you look in.
I wanted to come back to that because, and I got to remember where we are in this story,
because I don't want to lose this thread. So maybe we can agree to just park this again,
but I definitely don't want to leave the discussion of tissue selectivity.
We've focused so much on C1, C2 selectivity, but we haven't talked about muscle versus liver
versus adipose tissue, for example, which you could argue you might want very different behaviors
there. In terms of drug design, drug pharmacokinetics, is it easier to target tissues or is it easier to
target enzymes, proteins, et cetera, when designing a drug or waving magic wands?
No magic wands involved. It's far easier to design a drug to hit a target. To hit the target in a
particular tissue is harder, but doable. Sometimes you can do it in a deliberate,
designed fashion. For example, making a prodrug that's cleaved to an active form only by an
enzyme present in your desired tissue. You also have to be mindful that within every tissue,
there are multiple cell types and you want the drug in the cell type that will make the difference.
And again, all of this is possible and it's just how much time and effort you're going to put into
it. So when you go back to even the first experiment in 2014 and all of the animal data that came from
it, did you have a sense of where this was acting tissue wise? Did you feel like you were acting on
bone marrow? Did you feel like you were possibly acting in the thymus? Did you feel like you were
acting in some other cell line that directly or indirectly was playing a role? I mean,
or did you have a sense that you were seeing this everywhere, but it didn't seem to matter except in
the bone marrow? We thought it would be bone marrow and perhaps secondary lymphoid tissue,
which are lymph nodes or glands, but we didn't explore it exactly. In general, small molecules
that aren't specifically tissue targeted will often go to many tissues. We knew from toxicology
studies with the compound that it distributed to our target tissues. We felt we had enough
information to move ahead. Yeah. So when RTB101 was basically the basis upon which RestoreBio
was formed, correct? That's right. Now, I was very confused during your road show, which was
about a year ago, maybe more than a year ago. It might've been early 2018. I've sort of lost track.
You were at Novartis at the time, so it wasn't really your road show at the time, but I naively,
I guess, thought that RTB101 was actually RAD001, the Evrolimus, combined with a PI3K inhibitor.
So that's actually what I thought was happening. And I remember even having discussions with other
people looking at the data and saying, is this what this company is? So I assumed that this
company outlicensed Evrolimus combined with a PI3K inhibitor. So how were we confused by that?
When RestoreBio was formed, it licensed RTB101 from Novartis for all uses. And there was also
a limited license to use RAD001 only in combination with RTB101 for our indication.
Now, the phase 2B study that RestoreBio ran showed that the most effective drug or drug combination
for preventing respiratory tract infections was just RTB101 alone at 10 milligrams. And remember the
previous study that Novartis had run had shown that although the combination was best at augmenting
a vaccine response, it was just RTB101 alone, which at the time was called BEZ235, was the best
at preventing respiratory tract infections. We believe this is because the mechanism by which
it prevents respiratory tract infections is upregulation of an interferon-stimulated antiviral
gene response. Interferon, remember, is a substance in the blood that upregulates many
different proteins, most of which are involved in preventing viral infections. And you need protein
synthesis to make all of these proteins. And I worry that if we inhibit mTOR for a long time,
we can upregulate the genes, but they won't be expressed adequately. And there are some
literature data that you need mTOR in order to express the proteins induced by interferon.
So these experiments taken together suggest to you that I guess it just reinforces this idea
of intermittent dosing, not just intermittent within the week, which I think was clearly
established by the phase 2A study, but even applying a secondary cycle over the course of a
year, for example. I mean, you know that doing a six plus two once a year is probably not adequate.
So there's some frequency upon which you want to meta cycle that. But the reason you don't just
want to go all the time taking it presumably is you might actually start to impair protein
synthesis that's necessary to, for lack of a better word, basically empower your new superpowers of
immunity through enhanced protein synthesis. Yes. Protein synthesis, there's several different
kinds of protein synthesis and some are more or less sensitive to inhibition by Rapalog.
Mitch Weiss's very recent paper, one of the interesting things I found in it was that
there wasn't much of an inhibition of hemoglobin synthesis, despite the fact that they were using
fairly high exposures of a Rapalog. So I think there are some proteins that are sensitive to
translational inhibition by Rapalog and perhaps some that are less sensitive.
Before we go down this path of getting a little bit more into RTB101, let's take a step back here
and say, do you think that all of the benefits that we saw in the ITPs across all these other
species, if you think of the benefits that Matt Cabraland is seeing in dogs, if you think of
sort of the global excitement that exists around Rapamycin and Rapalog's, how much of it do you
think is mediated through what you guys are testing, which is you're clearly enhancing
immunity in a positive way, which could have at least two very distinct benefits. One is the
reduction of infection. The other could be frankly reduction of cancer through increased surveillance.
They're very similar. Viruses and cancer obviously behave or susceptible to the similar
branch of the immune system. Do you think there are other things that we haven't talked about yet,
such as increased autophagy, targeting of endor, destruction endor, desilencing of
senescent cells, reduction of inflammation, enhanced mitophagy. What other mechanisms do
you think could have been involved here and what evidence exists to support or refute that?
Well, I think we know from academic experiments that every single one of those mechanisms
can extend health span in preclinical models. We do not know in people. And I think similarly to
follow up our earlier discussion about what tissues you have to inhibit endor in in order to get a
clinical benefit, we don't really know the answer to that either. It's been studied in some of the
preclinical models. I can recall an experiment in the Drosophila fat body where inhibition of
endor right there was sufficient to extend a fly lifespan. There's still a lot we need to learn.
What does your intuition tell you? How much of an overlap or parallel do you see between the
benefits of fasting and caloric restriction and the benefits of rapamycin globally?
Yeah. So one of the interesting things that we did and was done previously in a Nature publication,
I think the author was Sengupta, was looking at the consequences of fasting on endor activity.
In young people, as you would expect, fasting leads to suppression of endor activity, activation
of the cellular recycling machinery, autophagy, suppression of protein synthesis and DNA lipid
synthesis and so forth, basically preparing for lean times. In old mice, that's impaired. We've
only done the liver tests in mice. So we back translated this experiment and gave,
actually I think it was rats, it was old rats, doses of endor inhibition that corresponded to
the doses we were using in people that were well tolerated. And then we looked at their ability to
suppress endor. So in the old rats, even with fasting, their endor was still active in the liver.
In a young rat, it's suppressed. So the young versus old had the same degree of inhibition
to the same dose of rapamycin. Well, you couldn't test in the young rats because their endor was
already low. Oh, but if you did it outside of the fast, I mean. Well, certainly the exposures were
the same. There was no age dependent difference in exposure of the liver or the blood. That's
interesting. Does that suggest that the older animal lost the ability to respond to the
environmental reduction in nutrient? Exactly. Exactly. Hmm. That's upsetting. Although it
does explain a very interesting finding, which is everything comes back to the 2009 paper.
What really was interesting scientifically was that those mice were 600 days old. Those were mice
that if you fasted them, wouldn't have lived longer. It already passed that stage where
caloric restriction would extend their life. And yet their lives were extended 15 and 25%
by rapamycin. That was a big freaking deal. Yeah. We published our experiments in that 2008 paper.
It was sort of an interesting back translation experiment where we treated the old rats based
on what we do about the old people. And of course we could do in rats. What we can't do in people
is take their livers out and study their endor inhibition. But we weren't the first ones to do
that. There was a very good nature paper that showed the same thing. Do you think this applies
to humans? I mean, do you think that intermittent periods of caloric restriction are not beneficial
to people in their sixties or seventies, which would be the equivalent of those quote unquote
old rats? The only thing that our group has been able to try is we looked at whether we could detect
mTOR activity as assessed by things like fossil S6 kinase in the peripheral blood leukocytes of old
people and we couldn't detect activity. We can't answer the question. I think we would need liver
samples under fasting conditions. I mean, are you volunteering? Yeah, I'm absolutely volunteering.
No, I tell you, there's a lot of things I subject myself to. I'm never excited about the liver
biopsy. I just, I think that's the problem of doing a residency in general surgery is you've
had one too many calls down to the interventional radiology suite with the patient that you have
the recency bias of you only remember all the cases of liver biopsy has gone bad. The,
all those hepatologists that have never had an issue, you don't hear about those cases,
but you hear about everyone that. Yeah. There's sort of a referral bias. You never see the
thousand that go well. Yeah. You only see the one that didn't. Yeah. I don't know. I think
at some point I'll probably have to sign up for a liver biopsy. I think there's a lot going on
there. There's so many questions I have about the liver, especially my own. No liver biopsies. You
can get samples other ways, at least for this reason, but it is an interesting open question.
And yet another one of these things we don't know is, is mTOR suppressed in elderly people
with fasting and in which tissues. And by the way, do we know if autophagy is impaired in older
folks with fasting? Because autophagy and mTOR inhibition are not synonymous. That's right.
They overlap, but they're not synonymous. Yeah. Well, there's a lot of biology there and you,
it's not only mTOR that can trigger autophagy. There's other mechanisms. There's
Becklin one mechanisms and so forth, but it's an interesting set of experiments to do
with a young group of patients and an old group of patients. And there's a priming effect to this
that I just don't, I mean, it's so multifaceted to study all of these things. You think of the
infinite combinations you can have, which is what's the effective wrap-up plus fasting when
staggered, for example, does one prime the other? It's hard. You can't really go on fishing
expeditions with these questions. You have to be more thoughtful in your hypothesis generation.
There's just too many variables. That's right. There's too many ways to be fooled. That's right.
So what can you tell us now about RTB 101? What has been published on this? In other words,
I don't think we can speak about obviously anything that's not published at this point,
or at least hasn't been publicly signaled. What's next for this compound?
So the excitement is in the phase two A study that Novartis ran, we saw decreased respiratory
tract infections in elderly people treated with it. In the phase two B study that Restore Bio ran,
again, the same dose, 10 milligrams once a day saw the same thing, a decrease in respiratory tract
infections. Now that study was a complicated study. And did it also have an RTB 101 plus RAD 001 arm?
It did. And there was not a decrease in respiratory tract infections there.
But there was an increase in immunity? Or was that, that was a secondary outcome?
That was assessed, but it hasn't been talked about yet. The cool thing about the 2018 paper
that was published from the Novartis study is that because we saw a decrease in respiratory
tract infections, but we did not see an increase in vaccine response, it told us that the mechanism
for the decrease in respiratory tract infections had to be something different. And we had collected
some samples for exploratory profiling. We learned that there was an upregulation of antiviral
gene expression in peripheral blood leukocytes. So a set of interferon stimulated genes responsible
for antiviral activities was upregulated. So we identified a candidate mechanism and it
makes a lot of sense. So to put that in English, it's not that the response was mediated by better
recognition of viruses. It was mediated by more efficient targeting of and or disposing of viruses.
Perhaps another way to say it is that the vaccine response we were measuring as the primary
endpoint was a lymphocyte acquired immunity measurement. So in other words, you're immune,
the flu, because you've been vaccinated. If you've been vaccinated for rabies, you're immune to that.
I've never been vaccinated for rabies. I'm not immune to rabies. In contrast, there's something
called innate immunity, which is the immunity of our species. This is an immunity that was
developed because we have all co-evolved with our pathogens. And those of us who are here.
Yeah, this is what the LPS on strep is. You don't need to be vaccinated to recognize it.
Exactly. So there are many, many, many, many other things that we can recognize,
elements of pathogens. So we can mount an effective immune response. And we're born with this. We don't
have to be immunized for it. And this part of the immune system is what mTOR inhibition
can also activate. Yeah, which is to go back to historical, that's not what we care about in
transplant. No. Because in transplant, we didn't evolve to reject kidneys. We evolved to accept
our kidneys. Therefore, we reject someone else's kidney. That's MHC-based. Right. Although blood
type matching of your organ transplants is for... Well, that's true. And now they're doing so many
ABO incompatibles that it's... I mean, the immunology involved in organ transplantation today is
remarkable. A subject for another time. I know. And all started that you're alma mater. That was
the Nobel prize right there, right? That's right. Dr. Murray. So is there anything else you can tell
us? Because this is obviously something like, have you guys spoken about what the phase three is going
to look like? Yeah. Well, we're almost halfway through. Halfway through enrollment. We enrolled
the first phase three study fully and getting ready to start the second. So tell us about the
first one. Yeah. So, well, let's do a little more on the phase two B because that study answered
several questions in one study. We enrolled patients with pre-specified comorbidities
and pre-specified an analysis of them independently. We did doses. We did five milligrams and 10
milligrams. We did a different schedule. We did 10 twice a day. And we did a combination with
a raphalog, our RAD001, with the primary endpoint of decreased respiratory tract infections. We also
extended the dosing period to cover winter cold and flu season. So now we're dosing 16 weeks.
Uninterrupted? Uninterrupted. Okay. Although with the once a day dosing, which is where we saw efficacy,
we're only inhibiting mTOR partially for part of the day. By the way, if you had to speculate,
going back to the very, very first, the 2a with RAD0001, if you had taken all four of those groups
and measured them at the end of six weeks and then after the two week washout, what's your
prediction as to how they would have differed? I'm sorry, because we didn't vaccinate until
if we vaccinated at six weeks versus vaccinated at eight weeks. Correct. And you did comparison.
In other words, I'm asking on drug versus off drug, how much, I know why you had the washout,
but is it also possible that on drug you would have the same immune response?
Yes. On the low doses, on the high doses, I bet we wouldn't have.
And do you define high as five and 20?
High as 20, yeah.
Okay. Got it. So you think the five and the 0.5 still would have had benefit on drug,
20 probably got a benefit. In fact, that might explain the question I asked, which is why did
they still at least have one good strain response? It could have been that the two weeks off gave them
recovery.
It could be.
Yeah. So back to restore bio, we figured it. And then the other element to the study is we ran it
in two different cold and flu seasons, one in the Southern hemisphere, one in the Northern hemisphere,
652 patients in the study, because we answered a lot of questions.
We found that some patient populations responded well, over 85 patients and patients with asthma,
patients with diabetes also responded. Patients who were smokers or had COPD did not.
There are some preclinical data that provides a mechanism for why this is the case,
in the sense that it's a different mechanism for airway inflammation and smoking and COPD,
and it's exacerbated by mTOR inhibition.
Oh, so I thought it was going to be a different way of antigen presentation or something.
I don't think so.
Okay.
The coolest thing about the study is that we saw the same degree of efficacy if we looked at the
patients in the Southern hemisphere as in the Northern hemisphere. It's almost as if there was
two sub-studies in this study. Now, each of the patient groups by themselves were insufficiently
powered to get any statistical significance, although overall, the patient population did.
That's a bold study design move. That could have backfired badly, right? Because if you had
discordance between the Northern and Southern hemisphere, you would have been underpowered.
Well, the goal of the study was to look at the overall patient population, which we did,
which included responders and non-responders. We saw a 30% decrease in respiratory tract infections.
Yes, but you had two different strains of the flu, didn't you?
Flu was not involved here. There was no vaccination in this study.
Oh, sorry. What I mean is you had two different environments of viruses.
Yes, absolutely. Absolutely.
So you diluted, I'm just saying you loaded the deck against yourself. If you did everything
identical, but they were all in the same country, presumably you'd have a higher concentration of
pathogen. You'd have a better chance of seeing a signal. That's sort of all I was saying.
Yeah, I think you'd have a higher chance of seeing consistency.
That's right. And you had the lowest chance imaginable because you spread out across two
hemispheres.
Yet we saw consistency.
Yes, so I think we're saying the same thing, which is it's more a credit to the finding.
Yes.
And I'm just saying, thank God.
Well, if the drug works, this is what we should have seen.
Yeah, it's just a big bet for a startup to take.
Yeah. And so now we've seen 10 milligrams of RTB101 decrease respiratory tract infections
in the phase 2a and in each of the parts of the phase 2b. And we use the phase 2b to power
the phase 3 program. So the phase 3 program is-
And the primary indication is respiratory infection or all infection?
Respiratory tract infections.
And patient population is 65 and up?
65 and up. So the first study that we're calling the program, the protector program, the first one is
fully enrolled, 1,024 patients. They're getting 16 weeks of drug treatment and we're following them
for respiratory tract infections with sort of an electronic record that the patients fill out.
If we were just targeting this at Northern Hemisphere patients, is it your view that the
optimal 16 week window would be sort of May, June, July, August? How are you deciding when?
Winter cold and flu season.
Is when they actually want to receive the drug?
Yes.
Okay. So basically, so you're so confident that 10 milligrams is not too high that you're willing
to give them the drug during flu season or during winter cold season?
Yes.
All right. So let's turn over to something else you brought up earlier, which was the
the Laming paper that came out about two months ago. That's a prolific lab.
Laming was a postdoc in David's lab. So no stranger to this science. There are lots of folks out there
that are working on selective mTORC1 inhibition, notwithstanding the potential ways around it
through intermittent dosing or looking at catalytic binding or things that might be off
you a little bit more insight. What is your take on the biochemistry of selective binding
and selective inhibition more specifically? The binding is quite selective.
Yeah. I thought basically to summarize that paper for the listeners,
the Laming group looked at, I think it was 90 different rapologs, presumably related to
rapamycin and looked for their ability to be selective for Tork1 even with more sustained
exposure. Then they identified a couple that were and most of the paper was on one that they liked
the best. The really cool thing, and this is going to get us into an immunofilin discussion,
is that they found possibly the reason the compound was selective was that it bound to
one of the immunofilins, but not another. So specifically it bound to FKBP12, or at least
FKBP12 was required for the compound to have activity, but another FKBP, FKBP51 was not.
But I still don't understand this. If you bind to FKBP12 and then the rapologue plus FKBP12 binds to
mTOR, don't you still get into the same problem where after a long enough period of time,
you don't have enough TOR to make complex 2? I don't think that's why complex 2 is inhibited.
What do you think rapamycin specifically is doing to inhibit complex 2 then?
I think it's a downstream and indirect counter regulatory signaling mechanism.
I see. So it has to do more with the serine kinase or the 4EBP1 or something like that.
Like something downstream of a direct phosphorylation is counter regulating or...
Yes.
Yeah, I see. And you're saying presumably if you only bind a rapologue to FKBP12,
you somehow don't hit that target?
Well, I think what their data say is because the compound that they show has no TOR2 activity at all
does not bind to FKBP51 or at least that's the implication because down regulating FKBP51,
which I think they did with an siRNA, had no effect on its inhibitory activity,
suggests that there's a complexity to the complexes formed, sorry for that,
that we don't yet understand and it's an exciting area to explore.
So remember every cell has many immunophilins in it. It has several cyclophilins.
It's got several FKBP's. So FKBP12, 51, and 52 are probably the big three,
but there are a few others.
By the way, I thought rapa only bound to 12. Rapa binds to what?
They showed that it binds to at least 12 and 51.
Okay. I mean, that's amazing. I had always thought that rapa binds only to FKBP12.
Which then binds to TOR. I didn't even realize it was binding to 51.
So we know it binds to 51 in their paper and there have been some other papers
studying the ryanidine receptor that show that it binds to 12.6 also, which is in cardiac myocytes.
We've talked all about inhibition. Are there any times when you want to be activating this?
There's a lot of talk that ketamine may be activating mTOR and obviously ketamine has
some really interesting properties as it pertains to recalcitrant depression.
Yeah. So two points here. For patients with major depression, intravenous ketamine
is almost a miracle drug. We're accustomed to typical antidepressant drugs requiring weeks
and weeks to work and having modest effects at best.
Or even days, but this is minutes.
Ketamine works in minutes to hours and a huge effect size. It's really amazing.
I don't think we know what the specific cellular mechanism is of that. I'm giving you lots of
things we don't know in our discussion. Wasn't there a study that showed
rapamycin blocked the effect of ketamine? Yes. And there's a biotech company called Navator.
I know them well. And they're using an mTOR activator to treat depression.
Their Lloyd equivalent is also a very smart guy. So, yeah. George is fantastic.
So Lloyd, is this a relatively recent understanding then about how RAPA is binding to the FKs
and how it's the complexity around first of all, how many of these things there are
and how you can change their properties by which ones you're binding to?
Yeah. So it's something that's not discussed a lot in the literature, but there are several
FKBP's or FK506 binding proteins. We almost always talk about FKBP12, and it's sort of a shorthand.
But the understanding has been that rapamycin binds to all of them.
In a few specific cases, that's been shown to be true. There's also a bunch of other activities
and roles for FKBP's that aren't at all part of Torq1 biology. For example, they all have
enzymatic activity. They're peptidylprolilisomerisis. But what the biology of that is
remains pretty much unclear. It's a very interesting enzymatic activity. It's involved in
protein folding. But there have been some studies where maybe a dozen different of these
immunophilins are completely eliminated at the same time from cells. There was no clear cellular
phenotype. So whether that means the others can all substitute because it's such a critical function
or they have no function that's important. Are there disease states where people are lacking
any of these? There may be, but I don't know them. And how conserved are they across species? Highly
conserved. These immunophilins are present in almost all species, although they can vary a
little bit. Is there any cell in the body that does not contain mTOR? I would bet some of the
terminally differentiated a-nucleate cells may not. Red blood cells, for example, do? Certainly
red blood cell precursors do. I was thinking about platelets, for example. I don't know if
they have mTOR. Yeah. Interesting. And I bet that's known. It's just, I don't know the answer.
I feel better that you don't. So now we need to make a list of David Sapatini questions.
Well, I'll make sure David listens to this. And you know what? Maybe we'll do an AMA with David
specifically on tOR. So last thing I want to chat about, because the paper came out kind of
recently, was this sort of interesting paper. It's interesting not in the sense of the intervention,
because it was an N of 9 and it was a very poorly controlled study in the sense that there was no
placebo group and every patient actually was on their own sort of tailored cocktail of three
different drugs or two hormones in a drug. But the paper did get a lot of press because it used an
epigenetic clock. Are you familiar with these clocks? Yes. Yeah. This is Horvath's work, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Horvath's probably the best of these clocks. Maybe it's just as a little bonus episode.
Tell folks how these things work, what they're measuring. We've already talked a little bit
about methylation. So maybe we put a bow on this by discussing that. So I forget how many years ago
it was now, but it wasn't that many that we learned from Horvath and others that by looking
at the methylation pattern on peripheral blood leukocyte DNA, we can tell how old you are within
about six months to a year. And this has been replicated by several groups. So we're all familiar
with DNA and... And that's even true among centenarians and people that are just genetically
blessed to live longer. Excellent question. The studies that I've seen and actually the one that
we participated in, I don't think we had people over 80. Okay. I don't know the answer to that,
but for people between about 20 and 80, there's a stereotypical change in methylation patterns on DNA.
And this is just a chemical change to DNA that happens over time that's quite characteristic of
your chronologic age. This is what David Sinclair talks about as sort of the scratching of the CD.
The CD being the master copy of your genomic. Yeah, I guess we have to say something like that
because we can't use wearing out of the vinyl anymore. But I think about it a little differently.
I think about aging fundamentally as a biologic process controlled by pathways. And presumably,
it's a consequence of changes in gene expression. And this methylation changes gene expression.
So it's a pretty cool story. And certainly we know that if you take a differentiated cell
and treat it with a set of transcription factors called the aminaka factors,
you can reset the cell back to a pluripotent stem cell and the methylation goes away too.
So I'm thinking that DNA methylation likely could be causally related to the expression,
gene expression changes that not only are associated with aging, but may cause aging.
So has anybody looked at the effect on the Horvath clock or DNA methylation in response to the
rappalogs we've been discussing today? I'm thinking of one experiment,
but I don't know that it's published yet. And I think the answer was negative.
So it's interesting because the paper that I was talking about, again, there are 10 ways to Sunday,
this could just be an outlier, especially without a control group. I mean, it's really difficult to
make any conclusion. But if any of this benefit was real, which was growth hormone, DHEA and metformin,
set the Horvath clock back, I think it was a year and a half or two and a half years,
the initial hypothesis of the experiment was that this was going to improve thymic function,
which was going to improve immune function. Doesn't seem like a stretch that you could
potentially see that benefit from a rappalog if it's also acting on immunity, which is why I think
I was sort of probably why I asked about the thymus in the past. Yeah. So I have a few comments
about this. One is first DHEA we know goes down substantially with age, but there have been
several to many studies of replacing it and there's no clinical benefit. And I think the author
used it for the effect of reducing the hyperinsulinemia that follows the administration
of growth hormone. And in his, I think, personal experience, taking growth hormone noted that he
could blunt the hyperinsulinemia by taking something like 50 milligrams of DHEA by itself.
But again, I've, that's not something that's well documented in the literature. And your point,
of course, is documented, which is DHEA by itself. You can fix the number, but that doesn't
seem to have any clinical bearing. Exactly. My second point is the growth hormone,
the biologic activity of it is mostly driven, not exclusively by IGF-1, which used to be called,
I think, somatomedin when we were in medical school. We know that lymphoid tissue is probably
the most sensitive target organ for IGF-1 and it causes hypertrophy. So if he's looking for
enlarged thymus in patients he's treating with growth hormone, I would be surprised if you did
not see that. And he did. And so the question is, wouldn't you have expected that to have sped up
growth? I would have expected, if he treated long enough, I would have expected to increase
the size of the thymus if he could find it in people. I believe the study looked at MRI and
showed an increase in thymic size. They were treated for a year, I believe. Not surprised at
all. I bet the spleen increased too. Is there any reason to believe that that would enhance immune
function? I'm thinking if I've read a paper about that and I don't know. And then what about the
metformin wrench in the works? Metformin is a really interesting compound. I think we have
excellent data that in diabetics it is a wonderful drug. And there's some retrospective data of
longevity in diabetics treated for a long time with metformin. And of course, this is the question
near Barzilay wants to answer with the TAME study. Right. And Nier and I have spoken about this many
times and I agree that it's hard to make the case for a more beneficial agent in someone with
diabetes or hyperinsulinemia metabolic syndrome or anything on that continuum and on that spectrum.
Of course, the question is, what is the benefit of metformin in a perfectly healthy person or even
a fully optimized person with respect to other variables? I'm not aware that there is a benefit
of it. Remember, it has some adverse effects on mitochondrial function too, potentially.
It's so funny you bring that up. That's exactly the question that I think most plagues me, which is
if it is a weak mitochondrial toxin, is any benefit that you might see in a non-diabetic
more than dwarfed by that downside? Whereas even the simplest benefit of it, like a reduction
in hepatic glucose output in diabetics might more than make up for the sort of inhibition of
metformin. Yeah, I don't think we know the answer to that question.
It's one I'm super interested in and working on and actually going to volunteer for a study that
will take some muscle biopsies and look at peak mitochondrial function, which you can induce
through certain types of exercise with and without metformin. Interesting. Yeah. Well, Lloyd, this has
been just a fantastic discussion. I am so grateful for the introduction that Tim made and it's been
an honor to sit and speak with you. I had tried to reach out to Joan about a year ago. I never
heard back. So I'm gathering it was just too busy a time, but in many ways it was better to get to
talk now because so much more has happened in the last year and maybe that might've been just after
the IPO. So it was a very busy time. I'm guessing my email went to spam, but this has worked out
really well and I'm incredibly grateful for this. I wish you all the continued success with this
program. Well, thanks. We remain optimistic and we will have top line data from the first phase three
by the beginning of 2020. So the data will speak for themselves. Well, we'll count down the day
till we see it. It's been a great discussion. I've enjoyed being here. I feel like I've said,
I don't know an awful lot. I'm feeling a little bit like I'm back in school, but it's been fun.
And I have some homework to do. Thanks. Well, I think that's one of the beautiful things about
folks that come on this podcast is great scientists say, I don't know probably more than they know the
answer. So that's, I think a testament to your honesty, but thank you, like, appreciate it.
Thank you. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in
diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of this description. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast, typically less than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting
the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to peteratiamd.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to
this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a
substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not
disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they
should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.
Thank you.