Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is John Arnold. John is probably the guy that'll go down in history
as the most successful natural gas trader of all time. And we spend the first part of this episode
explaining that story. And you might think, well, what does that have to do with anything? Well,
it's only by understanding how John came to amass a fortune of billions of dollars trading natural
gas. Can you understand the second part of this discussion, which is how at the age of about 37
or 38, he shut it all down and turned all of his attention to the full-time craft slash business
slash art of philanthropy. John's philanthropy is as serious as his natural gas trading. And his
foundation, Arnold Ventures, which he is the co-chair of along with his wife, Laura, focuses on really
the hardest social problems imaginable. And in this episode, John discusses at great length where
philanthropy fits into the broader picture of the nonprofit sector, differentiating it from charity
and how that fits into even the broader umbrella of public or government spending and even private
spending. And it's only by understanding that lens that you can really understand how someone like
John thinks about deploying the types of resources they do, which are legion to be clear. The foundation
currently spends about $400 million a year in grants. And John's goal is to basically spend
their entire fortune in their lifetime solving very hard problems, problems like criminal justice
reform, health policy reform, K through 12 reform, public finance, things like that. We obviously
don't go nearly as deep as I would love to go into all of these topics. And yet somehow this podcast
managed to be probably two and a half hours, if not slightly more, which certainly leaves ample
room for a part two of this at some point in time. I guess one thing I would say about this is I'm
obviously fascinated by this topic and could sit here and talk about natural gas trading forever.
If that subject matter isn't that interesting to you, what I would suggest is paying close
attention to the timestamps in your podcast player. You'll probably want to listen to the
first part of this because it's, I think John's background and growing up and his card trading
business, his baseball card trading business. I think that stuff is really important to kind
of understand John's mentality. You may actually want to skip his career where he goes from college
to work at Enron and don't worry, he's one of the good guys at Enron. And then you may want to
sort of skip to the part where he decides to shut his own hedge fund down and instead focus on
philanthropy. Again, I'll leave it up to you, but I guess the point I want to make is I wouldn't be
put off by the fact that if you're not interested in natural gas, you won't find this episode
interesting. I think this episode is interesting start to finish, but there may be some people who
only find one part in a string or another. So just pay attention to where that is. So without
further delay, please enjoy my conversation with John Arnold. Hey John, awesome to sit down with
you. I'm bummed we are not able to do this in person because anytime we sit down in person,
it is a long and fruitful discussion where I just feel like I'm learning at a geometric rate. But
nevertheless, I'm excited that we're finally getting to sit down and talk because there's so
many things on my mind. Now, a lot of people listening to this podcast will not really know
who you are. And I've struggled to think about the best way to introduce you. So I thought one of the
funniest ways to introduce you is to do so through the tweet that you have pinned at the top of your
page. So remind me your handle on Twitter is, is it John Arnold Foundation? John Arnold Foundation.
Okay. And what is it that you have pinned at the very top of that?
So it's essentially that I've been called the next Koch brother by the far left. And I've been
labeled the next George Soros for by the far right. And I think I write that I'm an equal
opportunity special interest pot stirrer. And I think it does label me a couple of ways versus
our actions at the foundation, which has been in his current form for about 10 years, have led to
getting into a lot of squabbles with both the left and the right. And at times it's been
frustrating at times it's been liberating. But it has brought a lot of conflict, which one doesn't
normally think about when you think about philanthropy and a philanthropist about having
conflict and fights and battles with a lot of these issues. And that's generally been a component
of our work, not by design, but by necessity. And then I think the second part of it that I like is
that we don't approach all problems with the same ideology. I think problems are different,
problems are complex. And the type of solution for each problem is different. So we don't say
that the free market is the right answer for everything. Don't say government is the right
answer for everything. But it depends on the makeup of the problem, the actors, the market
failures, et cetera, as to what the right solution is. And therefore, over the years, I've managed to
make mad both the left and the right, and sometimes simultaneously.
And by extension, I think there are many times that the right and the left also think you are
doing the greatest work on earth. I mean, I think that's the corollary of that, which is there are
times when you were in lockstep agreement with both sides as well, correct?
Yes, although whenever... Not simultaneously.
They tend to be louder whenever you're in conflict with them than when they're showing appreciation.
Yeah. I think part of how we've chosen issues to work on is we're looking for
these system problems that have a lot of impact in people's lives, where the two sides, the left
and the right, have historically been divided for some reason, and that they're starting to come
together. There's a reason why there can be a solution that's viable today that wasn't viable
five years ago or 10 years ago. And that ends up being a component of almost every issue we work on,
is that the left and the right are coming together. And so we need to be able to work with both sides.
And so we've tried to tamp down the politics, both personally and professionally, over the years,
and try to see in the Venn diagram of things the left will support and the things the right will
support, even if it's for different reasons or different motivations. Let's explore those
territories and see what can be done. And I think we're going to explore one of those in greater
detail perhaps than others, which will be criminal justice. But currently, the foundation, I know,
focuses very heavily on health policy, public finance platforms, and criminal justice. And I
think at least one of those, and I don't know why I just personally find criminal justice to be such
an important one, maybe we'll come back to it, because it is one where I think
maybe the left and right have a different ultimate motivation for establishing it. But
the solutions can certainly benefit society on both sides. Let's take a step back, because to
put the magnitude of your philanthropy in scale, the foundation is deploying what type of assets
per year. Can you put some numbers to this for people? We give about 400 million a year. The
assets in the foundation are a little over 2 billion. And then we have a couple other giving
vehicles, specifically a DAF. We contribute money every year as well. So we have a high
spend rate, but our philanthropic intent is to give away the vast majority of our money
during our lifetimes. Yeah. And you're very young, John. You're in your mid-40s. You and your wife,
Laura, have been at this, as you said, since you were in your 30s. And yeah, you're sort of on a
mission to spend this enormous sum of money during your lifetime. That's something I want to come
back to, because it's also not a typical path to philanthropy. Many people are thinking about
serious philanthropy at a slightly later stage of their life. Let's start with the first half of the
story, which is where did this money come from? You didn't have a trust fund to my recollection,
right? I did not. I did not. So where did you grow up? I grew up in Dallas and a very boring,
great upper middle class lifestyle in Dallas, went to Dallas public schools, ended up going to
Vanderbilt. Let's go before Vanderbilt. What was your first business? First business. So probably
mowing lawns. I was sitting around one summer and said, I want to make some money. So what can a
12-year-old do to try to make a dollar? Not much. And so went knocking on every neighbor's door and
tried to find a lawn to mow and realized that everybody either cut it themselves or had a lawn
service already set up. And so that wasn't going to be my path to riches. And then kind of around
age 14, I ended up getting into the baseball card business pretty actively. So this was right around
1988, 89, 90, when the sports card business was taking off. And I had a small collection at the
time, but I always thought of it more as an asset rather than a collectible that I wanted to put
on my desk and look at every day. And so the first experience was just renting a table at a
local trade show for $30 and putting a lot of the collection on the table and trying to sell it. And
again, the sports card business was booming. And so came home with maybe $100 from the $30
investment. Now, of course, the cost of goods sold didn't really factor that in. Maybe that was a sunk
cost at the time. But it started getting me interested in this as a potential business. And
I kind of quickly figured out I didn't want to be spending my weekends sitting at the local trade
fair and couldn't I played highly competitive soccer. So I had things to do on the weekend.
But there was a wholesale market that didn't require as much time. And so this is really kind
of the, again, during the start of the bulletin boards of ways where people would transact. And
there was a small bulletin board of baseball card dealers where they would do the wholesale trading.
And the market was so volatile at the time. If a particular player went on a good streak for two
weeks, that card would get hot, especially in the region he played. And you'd start seeing
number one volatility in prices and second and a geographic differentiation in prices. So the
market for hockey cards was very strong in the Northeast and in Canada, a little in Michigan.
They would sell them across the nation. Now, the guys that bought them in Texas, there wasn't much
of a local market. So I could go buy the hockey cards there, ship them up to a dealer in New York,
and make a few dollars. And that few dollars, I would then reinvest and do it more.
Then the sports card business was going parabolic at the time. And so kind of one thing led to
another, and I ended up spending a couple summers just finding full time on this baseball card,
really geographic arbitrage and information arbitrage, that I would have a sense of who the
best buyer was for every product, wherever they were in the United States, or even into Canada,
and would go around and try to find any bargains I could in the Texas, Oklahoma, Louisiana,
Tri-State area, kind of do day trips down to Houston and go to the big fairs down here. It
would go canvas all the dealers. And that was really my first business.
And how were you able to drive around so young? This was pretty unusual for a kid your age to be
able to track that circle of geography, right? It was. I got my driver's license at a young age.
I think it was at 14. My father at the time was going through an illness. He had Crohn's disease.
Through his life and kind of a chronic condition that especially in my teen years became a bit
debilitating for him. And so I was able to get, I forget what the name of that particular license
was, but because there was a kind of family hurdle, family handicap that I was able to
start driving when I was 14. Did you know what the word arbitrage actually meant when you were
conducting it? Great question. And I don't remember. Can you explain to people, I mean,
you've effectively explained it in concept because it's such a big part of your ultimate business.
Can you explain it more formally and technically to people? I would describe arbitrage as taking
advantage of price differences with little to no risk. I think true arbitrage is no risk where you
bought it for one and you've sold it at two and you've taken no risk in doing so. In reality,
there's always a little bit of risk. And so by knowing that the market in New York
valued something at $20 and it was trading in Texas at $15, I could take advantage of what I
call geographic arbitrage there, that the market in Texas was different from the market in New York.
Now, of course, today with the internet, a lot of those arbitrages and inefficiencies,
pricing inefficiencies have gone away or have been, we call them the trade, arbed out. And so
now you see the high frequency traders trying to make a hundredth of a penny on a share of stock
and have huge incentive to do so and do so at massive volume. But it's like buying and selling
same item with little to no risk. Which is a theme we'll obviously come back to at length. So
you go to Vanderbilt, you studied, if I recall, economics, yes?
Econ and math. Did you have a sense of what you wanted to do when you were finished college?
I remember reading Liars Poker and I think Barbarians at the Gate, both
classic books about Wall Street. And although growing up in Dallas with my mom as a accountant,
my dad as a corporate lawyer, I didn't have a sense as to what Wall Street was except through
these books, except by reading Wall Street Journal every day. And it seemed like that was the biggest
game around. I got drawn to that game or the desire to enter that game. And so my goal
throughout college was to get the job and the classic post college analyst job at a big Wall
Street bank. So then how did that pan out? And I also recall from our discussions that you
blazed through college. I think you got your degree in three years by taking summer classes
and just being kind of maniacally focused on your degree. Is that right? Yeah, take 18 hours
every semester, did summer school one summer, came in with some credits. And I was the guy that
was trying to get out of there and into the game as quickly as possible. Every day I was at college
was one less day that I had to be in the game. And I think my grades probably reflected that.
I was not academically focused, either in high school or in college. I think academics came
relatively easy to me. So it didn't instill a great work ethic at school, but I just wanted
to move on. It was a task to complete to get me to the next stage. So do you start interviewing
for a bunch of Wall Street firms when you're in your senior year or junior year, I guess?
I did. So at the time Vanderbilt was probably a tier lower than it's considered today as a school.
And the investment banks didn't do much recruiting there. So there was maybe one or two and some of
the regional banks. And then I was able to talk my way into a couple of interviews,
but I didn't get those jobs. So I was a bit crushed. Here's what I want to do. And I got
things that were close to that working at the regional investment bank. And then one of the
jobs I got, which I thought was closest to what I wanted to do to being in that game,
was at the company Enron. And Enron at the time was in this transformation, trying to become
essentially an investment bank to the energy industry and specifically the natural gas and
electricity industry. What year was that? So I started at that job in 1995. So at 95,
nobody knows Enron. They're a pretty unsexy company, right? Correct. They're basically doing
disintermediation, like their market making on energy. And that's about it. They're not this
darling of Wall Street that they would become before their fall. Is that, do I have my era right?
Right. It was historically a pipeline company. And over the decades, natural gas, which went
from a highly regulated business and all the troubles associated with trying to regulate a
commodity, right? That you end up having these huge booms and busts, way too much supply or way too
little supply was deregulated. And that deregulation ended in 1992. And that was really the emergence
of Enron as it became the late stage company, was that previous to then you had the pipeline was
responsible for providing the merchant services to the buyer and seller. So the producer of gas
would sell to the pipeline and then the pipeline would transport the gas and sell it to the customer.
It was viewed that this was negative because pipelines are natural monopolies frequently.
And so the services and the costs of those services were too high. And so
1992, they deregulate and here's Enron as the gas merchant.
Only because they become relevant later in this story. So was Ken Lay the CEO at that time of
deregulation? And when you came on board, or was Jeff Skilling there at that point in time? Not that
you would have had any interaction with those guys as a lowly first year guy.
So Ken Lay was chairman CEO shortly after I joined. I joined, I think May of 95. There had been
two aspects of the company. It had the historical pipeline business. And then it had these new,
it's called investment bank side. And there was what I later came to realize was the great
decision point for the company was who was going to be the number two at Enron? Was it going to be
the head of the pipeline business? Or was it going to be Jeff Skilling, who was the head of the energy
bank? And so shortly after I joined, Jeff was promoted up and Rich Kinder ended up leaving
and starting Kinder Morgan. And obviously that promotion was based just as much on perhaps who
they were as the direction that the company was going to go in. Right. I think this was a trend
in corporate America then was go asset light. So get rid of your big assets. Coca-Cola spins off
its bottling business. They just become the seller of the syrup because that's lighter on assets,
but your return on equity is higher if you have fewer assets. And so that was the direction
of corporate America generally and the one that Enron took. So I love that you show up in May of
95, not even taking a month off like any other kid would. And what is your first job at Enron?
Where do they stick you? It's very rare for someone at Enron and even someone at an investment bank
to be put on the trading floor. There's just mistakes are expensive on the trading floor.
And so they don't want the kid that's a few days out of college. That would be the equivalent of
we're going to take kids out of medical school and you're going to get to start operating even
simple operations without supervision. That would be catastrophic. Organ transplant is your first
thing. Right. But I had expressed interest on the trading side when I went through the interview
process and they called me in April and said a couple of people recently left our oil trading
group. If you can start immediately, you can start in trading. And I said, well, I graduate
in 10 days. How about 12 days from now I'll be there. And so I literally graduated, drove
from Nashville to Houston that weekend. And that Monday show up at work in the oil trading group
at Enron. So what did that mean? What did an oil trader do without as much supervision
or experience as maybe you would ideally want of a trader? Right. So I certainly was not trading.
I was kind of an assistant on the desk, which meant doing a lot of spreadsheets of running
analytical studies and correlation studies, building models, getting lunch,
doing all the things that first years do, trying to learn the business.
And at what point did your bosses there start to realize that this kid that just came out of
Vanderbilt, a year younger than everybody else has a knack for this game? Or maybe asked another
way, when did you first realize you had a knack for it? Quickly. I look back at all the good timings
and kind of good decisions that went into my career. And one of them was, I found the perfect
job from my skillset as my first job. And I think that's pretty rare. And it happened by accident,
could have very easily ended up a mergers and acquisition investment banker at Merrill Lynch.
But I ended up trading commodities at a relative upstart of a company. That was just the perfect
spot for my skillset. So tell me a little bit more about that. So oil is a very complicated
thing. Gas, perhaps less so, at least at the time, were those two viewed as the same trading desk at
Enron? Or did you shuttle back and forth between them and find yourself eventually at gas?
Enron by its nature was always a gas company. It was gas focused. The oil group was small. It was
kind of the redheaded stepchild. It didn't make much money. It was necessary because some customers
wanted to transact on oil with the same company that they were doing their gas transactions with.
But it was always a small group. So then how did you work up the ranks in natural gas trading? And
when did you actually start to go from modeling to actually making some trades and by extension,
then earning Enron some money? So early 1996, I was supposed to be on a
formal rotation, six months on one desk, six months on a different business within Enron,
and kind of rotate four rotations over the two years and then go back to business school.
And after six months, I think the team there liked me and I liked being there and kind of got made to
be an exception. So I didn't have to rotate. But kind of shortly thereafter, one of the traders,
I was speaking earlier about mistakes are costly in the trading side. And there was an older gentleman
who kind of made a mistake, kind of did a trade that ended up going bad. And they reorganized the
whole group. And the new boss came up and I worked for him for a couple months. And one day he pulls
me aside and says, I have to blow up this group. I like you. It's not going to be good for your
career to be here. You need to find a different group. And he gave me two options. One was,
go to London and work in the oil group there, or go downstairs and work in the natural gas trading
group. And as a 21 year old getting offered an expat package to go to UK, it was extraordinarily
tempting, because I'm thinking of going back to business school anyway. It was a hard decision,
but I realized the core of this company is natural gas. That's where I need to be that I need to learn
that. And so I went downstairs and started natural gas. And that was on its own, just very
fortuitous timing. I spoke about in 1992 was when the full deregulation happened. The winter
of 1996 was the first time that natural gas prices really blew out. It was extremely cold winter.
And all the historical relationships that gas had just completely changed. And so going down there,
I knew nothing about gas, but people who had spent their career in gas, wasn't sure if they
knew anything about gas either. They knew I had the fundamentals about the physical molecules.
But what the historical pricing relationships were, it was a whole new game. So I went down there
knowing nothing, but it felt like the whole industry was trying to figure out what does
the world of natural gas look like today going forward, given everything's changed.
How did you rise through those ranks there? Because that's a pretty interesting situation where
it's not necessarily the person with the most historical knowledge that's going to bring the
most value. It's probably the person who can learn the quickest spot patterns, the quickest,
and basically morph to a new environment. Right. So my first job in the Nat Gas Division was
they put me as an assistant trader with a gentleman who had expertise on the physical
side of the business. Didn't know anything about trading, but he knew natural gas. And I knew
nothing about natural gas, but knew something about trading and was good with numbers. And
they essentially put the two of us together and said, you guys go figure this out, work together,
and run this book. And so that was my first real trading job where, although I was an assistant
trader on the book, but where I was involved in the trading at this time, Enron started to become
a darling. And it was certainly within the energy side and within the pipeline business had become
this darling. Its stock was higher than all other stocks. So every other company was trying to figure
out how do I be more like Enron? So what's the easy way to be more like Enron is go higher,
Enron people, go hire someone kind of mid-level, give them a promotion and a raise and have them
come over to your company. And so that was happening all the time, which was great for the young guy
at Enron because the guy above you was leaving to go get a better job. And so it was an environment
where if you could prove that you were responsible and that you were smart, you could rise much faster
than you could at a mature company or in a mature industry. And so that next four years for me was
really the roller coaster where every nine months or so I would get a promotion again, like much
faster than I would have gotten had I been at a more mature company and ended up by the time I was
25, I was the head natural gas trader at the largest natural gas trading company in the industry.
It's almost hard to believe that that's possible, especially now when I looked
what I was doing when I was 25. Right, right. It is almost hard to believe. It was a company that
was very merit focused, I think, by giving out that responsibility. It was fantastic to work
at a place like that. I think it ended up being the downfall of the company as well as there just
wasn't the controls on people who were given too much responsibility, too much of the company's
balance sheet to use without their adequate controls on it. What was the stress like that
you felt just in a self-imposed manner? I mean, were you, if you're 25 years old and just give
me a sense of as a head trader at Enron with the largest gas trading company, we're talking in the
billions of dollars worth of potential profits and losses here, correct? In a given day, I was
trading billions of dollars of notional value of gas. A lot of it was trying to buy it, $2,
trying to sell it at $2.50 for enormous volumes. Enron was the largest market maker, was the largest
speculative trader of gas. It had the most customer business coming through it. Being at the center
of that, being the head trader there, it was just from the moment you sat down in the morning until
about three, four o'clock, it was just nonstop trading. Someone would bring food and put it in
front of me, run to the bathroom and run back. Internet trading was starting to take off then,
so there was still the trading in the pit on the trading floor, like trading places style. So there
was that, there was trading that was happening on the internet, there was trading that was happening
with other people within the company that they had customers or somebody needed to put a hedge on
because of another deal that they did. And so it was just nonstop action. And the stress level
was intense. I think I'm very good at handling stress. The stress level was intense to a point
of not being healthy. And I think this is true of many trading floors, especially back in those
days. I think it's why traders generally have short lives, trading lives, trading careers.
It's hard for the body to handle that level of stress for decades and decades.
Were you seeing this creep out into other areas of your life? Did you have difficulty sleeping?
Were you able to exercise in the periods of time, presumably in the evenings would be your only
window to exercise? Were you eating like crap? I mean, you're a very fit, healthy guy today.
Is this what John Arnold looked like when he was the head of trading?
No, I didn't realize it. Looking back, probably after I eventually lost the weight that I gained
during those years and cut down on some of the drinking, started exercising a lot more.
Looking back at the health of my life, it was a bit telling, even going and putting on some of the
clothes that I used to wear, seeing how so differently built today than I was back then,
you had to find some method to relieve stress.
And unfortunately for a lot of traders, that's pretty negative behaviors, right? It's more
drinking, more partying, more gambling or whatever.
Exactly, exactly. It is not a healthy lifestyle. As I grew up, I learned how to handle the stress
better. I got tired of the drinking and partying and gambling, especially as I got into my 30s,
as I got married, as I had kids, that all starts changing. But it also can be a reason why
people start to get repulsed by that career, is the lifestyle that doesn't necessarily go
along with it, but oftentimes does. I want to go back to just something before we leave this topic,
which is, did you get a sense of an addiction to trading? Because I've spoken with many friends of
mine who have at some point in their life been in that field. And for some of them, the addiction,
the high, the physiologic response that they get to a good trade is easily on par with what the
most indebted gambler feels when they're sitting at a blackjack table or with the drive that
someone has to drink who is so disproportionately dysregulated by alcohol. I mean, did you personally
get that or was it more of an intellectual exercise for you? How much of this was just purely
limbic system, dopamine surging versus more of a calculus?
So I've definitely seen traders where they had that dopamine aspect to their trading personality.
I've gotten the question many times, why were you a good trader? Why were you considered one of the
best traders in the market? And it's always been hard for me to answer. I think part of it is,
I had this emotional detachment from the business. So if I was having one of my best days or having
one of my worst days, if you walked by me, you couldn't tell. It was just 100% focus on executing
the process. So my views would change, but the process of how you look at the market can easily
get swayed by emotions whenever, and there's the phrase, fear and greed, that drives a lot of
price trends in financial assets. You're either greedy or you're fearful and that's driving your
behavior. And to the extent, I think that you can eliminate those two emotions from the trading and
from the process, you get better. And you know me well enough, you wouldn't describe me as an
emotional guy. So does that mean it was natural for you, John, that this superpower, because that is
probably a trading superpower. Is that something you had to cultivate or spend any energy training
in yourself? Was it the product or byproduct of something in your childhood or was it simply as
innate to you as your hair color and height? I think it was just innate. I think this is how I was
born, that detachment from the emotions that doesn't affect my decision making process. And so I think
that's one of the two superpowers, superpowers that I had. I think I also fell perfectly on
the confidence spectrum. And I say that it takes a certain amount of arrogance to be a trader,
because the market's usually right. And to be a trader, you have to say, I think I'm smarter than
the market here. I think the market is wrong. I think I am right. So it takes that arrogance in
order to be willing to put on a trade. And I've seen people just get paralyzed where they just say,
they're so concerned about the downside and of being wrong that they can't do anything.
So you have to be arrogant, but you can be too arrogant. And that's been the destroyer of many
trading careers is if you stick with it, I am right, the market is wrong, then you're going to
blow up. And so it's how do you have the right level where it's like, I'm confident in my view on
this, but I know I might be wrong. That's amazing. When we get to talking about the second half of
your career professionally, which is now your full time work in philanthropy, especially the type of
bets that you make and the scope and magnitude of problems that you go after, I think those two
traits that made you, I think most people would argue the greatest natural gas trader of all time,
probably serve you just as well in your philanthropy. Would you agree?
I think you said that well, the notion of going in saying, I think we're right about this,
but it might not work. Or we might be wrong. It's kind of write down our theory and test it along
the way and see if it's playing out the way it should and not get wedded to this theory that
everything we're doing in the foundation is evidence based, but the evidence is never perfect.
So we're taking the best available information and saying, how much risk
should society be willing to take to test a different idea?
So bringing the Enron chapter of your career to a close, help me understand how you and your
colleagues under your direction are making so much money and yet by 2001, Enron is going bankrupt.
How are those things happening simultaneously? I don't have the right answer for that. I knew
things in the company and other divisions. I had friends that worked in other divisions. We would
go to have a beer after work. I would hear their stories about some crazy deal that their division
was doing that they thought was stupid. I would hear stories about this, but our day-to-day in the
trading group was just so focused on the one activity that we didn't have firsthand knowledge
of any of that. It was always kind of hearsay, but the trading group was making so much money
that there was a thought, I think, that we could actually see this whenever earnings were getting
released that the trading group could support the other divisions until they stopped making the
dumb mistakes and became profitable on their own. I can't speak exactly about why the trading group
was making so much money. There were some really dumb ideas in retrospect when you look at the
documentaries. I remember reading the book, The Smartest Guys in the Room in 2006 or whenever it
came out and being completely fixated on this thing, but the whole broadband water idea, the
Indian power plant that didn't seem to make any sense. There were a lot of ideas that, and again,
I'm not saying this like I would have known at the time these were dumb ideas. I'm sure I wouldn't
have. So hindsight, of course, offers that luxury, but I mean, these were really, really half-baked
at best, right? It's always easy in retrospect. I think the disintermediation, which not only
Enron was doing but was a broad theme in the business world at the time, was real and the
investment community was valuing companies who were disintermediating in the same way that they do
today in the tech sector. There's a lot of value to be created if you can disintermediate a business
chain. I think Enron, trying to approach it from the commodity side and trying to do it with water,
trying to do it with electricity, doing it globally in places where the quality of law
and of intellectual protections isn't what it was in America, and then having the culture of never
being able to admit failure that existed not only in Enron, but again, in many other companies at the
time as well, meant that whenever mistakes were made, there wasn't the admittance to Wall Street
that this was a mistake and we're going to change. It was swept under the rug and Enron,
the process of bankruptcy happened so quickly because all these financial businesses, which
at the time, Enron had morphed into a financial business, is completely contingent upon having
the faith of your creditors, having the faith of Wall Street. Once Wall Street loses faith in you
and refuses to fund you on a day, the business is toast and that's what happened.
It happened, as you said, precipitously. I could certainly sit here for another four hours and
talk to you about mark to market and all of that, but I think we'll let the listeners who are really
interested in that go back and either read the books, watch the documentaries, or go deeper on
that. Let's bring it back to you, which is at what point do you realize your career at Enron is going
to be cut short? Despite the fact that you've had your head down, I think you could make the
case the single most profitable human at that company. If the company goes under, you're out
of a job. When was that apparent to you and then what were your next moves and how did you consider
the decisions you had to make? It happened so quickly that there was a damage control that I
could see from my perspective in the company. Again, my perspective was sitting at a desk with
two phones in my ear for most of the day. I didn't get much of a sense of what was going on
outside of what natural gas prices were ticking up. It happened so quickly that there wasn't much
to be done from the trading side perspective. All those decisions end up in the finance side,
the CFO's office of how do we raise money? When it finally, November of 2001
was shortly after 9-11 and that caused some havoc in the financial markets. Then that's when
Wall Street was not going to give you a second chance in that environment. Enron arguably didn't
deserve one. It all happened so fast that whenever Enron lost credit worthiness in the business,
then it was over. There was some time spent trying to find a credit worthy JV partner
to come in and would contribute the intellectual assets and someone would contribute new money
and keep the trading operation going because it had been so profitable. If it was just swept away
in bankruptcy, it was a loss of a lot of potential value to what was then the estate of Enron,
the creditors of Enron. There was a lot of focus on trying to cut that deal. A deal was eventually
cut with the New York bank. I looked around and I looked at the deal and for the first time stepped
back and started thinking, what do I want to do with my life? That's where the decision was,
I don't want to go with this entity. I have different views on how this business should
proceed in the future and I want to go try it somewhere else. You take your bonus check,
you take some money from a few other folks and you set up your own hedge fund in early 2002, right?
Yeah, mid-2002. Again, you're the perfect guy to do it because you're not too stressed about it.
You've got a proven track record. I guess you're somewhat toxic because even though
you come from the part of Enron that is fully legitimate, you still have that name on your
back. Did that hurt you? Were you trying to raise capital? How did that factor into your hedge fund?
It was an interesting time to say the least. Right after Enron declared the first quarter of 2002,
I was getting calls by a lot of people, people I didn't know, saying,
if you are going to do your own thing, I have interest in investing with you.
My intent was to try to raise $50 million of day one capital and just start there and let it grow
organically and increase over time. I thought I'd be cutting people back. I thought fundraising
would be very easy. There was going to be $200 million of interest and I was going to cut
everybody. You can invest 25% of what you want to. Second quarter of 2002, dramatic change. This is
when a lot of the investigations into Enron start to bear fruit, if you will, and the headlines come
out. Every week, there's a new scandal that's coming out. Now, the people who had called me,
one, they don't know if the profits that were posted in the New York Times, whether those are
real or not, whether I was going to jail or not, all these questions. Everybody who was banging on
my door to invest pulls back. Meanwhile, I've rented office space. I've hired employees. I've
bought computers and telecom systems. I've got to move forward. I have almost no money to do this
now. I ended up starting in August of 2002 with $8 million of capital, some of which was mine,
and I had two outside investors. Talk about pressure. $8 million of assets under management
is not exactly what you had in mind. As far as you know, basically, the only way you're going to grow
your fund at this point is by organic returns. You're going to have to return your way into more
money. You're not going to be out there fundraising. One of the things after N11 Bankrupt is Wall Street
started looking at all the copycat Enrons, all the other pipeline companies and electric utilities
who had started out these merchant businesses or trading businesses. Wall Street essentially says,
we're not funding those businesses anymore. There's too much risk. What happened was that
there is great need for risk intermediation and for risk warehousing in the business.
Half of the largest players are out of that business over the first six months of 2002.
And so the market became incredibly inefficient and was willing to pay for the task of
intermediation at a very high rate. And so just by setting up the computer, there was,
going back to the arbitrage, it was very low risk or arbitrage type trades that shouldn't exist in
a normal functioning market that existed for that next year just because the market players had been
so decimated. So the first month, it was up 36%. On a percentage basis is high, on an actual dollar
basis, it made $3 million. But also to put a point on what you just said a second ago, you're up 36%
in a month at a very low risk. So it's not just the value, it's the value at risk here that matters.
Exactly. Value at risk, I like the term. Well, I was a McKinsey guy, I remember. I was in the risk
practice, right? So we think a lot about VAR as well. So then second month, I'm up 33%, third
month, I'm up 38%. And I'm sending the notes out, the investor notes out to everybody that was in
my Rolodex that expressed interest. And now all of a sudden, three months in, I'm up, what's the
compound rate? Probably 150% in three months. And so some of the people will start calling me back
and saying, hey, maybe I'll send you some money. And so those first few years, it was doing a lot
of the low risk trading to create the base and this upward trend in profitability, and then layering
on some speculative trading on top of that. And I was able to play bigger than my asset size,
because I had this upward trend in profitability. If I was wrong, on my market call, I wouldn't be
decimated because I was still making money on the market making arbitrage side of the business.
Your spec market initially was actually quite small. You switched those 10 years later,
you were basically doing the opposite. But at the beginning, it was an amazing, you described it to
me in the past as I think the perfect time to be a natural gas. Yes. Based on that inefficiency.
Yeah, there was just risk reward. It was don't even bother about taking risk. Yeah, there's so
much free money in the market by providing that service, just do that. You can think about the
business as a bundled product. One was the market making, providing liquidity and getting paid for
that service, warehousing some risk. And the second was trying to make a call on where natural
gas prices were going next. There's some synergy of having those together. There's a lot of synergy
in having those together, but that's the two strands of the business. And most people, myself
included, when they think about gas trading, are only thinking about the speculative business,
which is my former countryman, Brian Hunter, very, very famously blew up in the fall of 2006,
a hedge fund called Amorith at the time was probably one of the biggest blowups in all of
energy. We'll come to that because you were on the other side of that trade, if I recall. But it's
those stories that get most people thinking about that's how you make or lose money in natural gas
trading. But you were doing something, I always talk about risk to people. I sort of explain it
as a two by two. Are you picking up Bitcoins or are you picking up pennies? And are you doing it
in front of a bulldozer or are you doing it in front of a tricycle? You want to think through
that two by two very clearly. It might be worth picking up a Bitcoin in front of a bulldozer,
but it is not worth picking up a penny in front of a bulldozer or a bullet train or something like
that. And so you sort of have to understand that's this idea of risk and return. So at what point,
I mean, I just want to kind of go back to John the guy who's on this ride that seems hard to believe,
but anybody who's made the type of money you've made in life goes from being, I mean, I guess
I'm asking this question in a weird way. Is there a moment at which you realize you're not going to
have to worry about money anymore? I don't know what that dollar amount is. And I'm guessing for
different people, it's a different amount. I've had people tell me that this is going to sound
ridiculous too. But I've had people explain to me that until you have $600 million in your bank,
you will never feel totally secure, which I find that ridiculous. And I disagree with that idea,
though I will never have $600 million in my bank. But there must be some number at which you realize,
oh, my life and the life of my family is going to be very different. Do you remember that occurring
for you? Yeah. So that first year was remarkable for many reasons. But one of the things that
happened was that the gas market ended up being very tight, that demand was high and supply wasn't
keeping up. And so the outright level of inventories was okay. But the trend was that
we were drawing inventories or not putting gas in the ground, like we should have been doing.
And again, had the market been more efficient than I think other traders, other traders did notice
this and others put it on. But there were some trades that were I thought were very
misvalued from a risk-reward perspective. And that was that if we were to have a cold winter,
that first one, 2002, 2003, if that winter was cold, the gas market could experience some
significant shortages and the price spikes that would correspond to those shortages.
Now, the weather event was maybe a one out of five probability. But I think the
bets were pricing them that it was one out of 50. And so as I'm making money on market making and
providing liquidity, I was putting on some of these trades, just putting a little bit of money
into this trade at various points. And that winter ended up being the one in five weather event.
And there was the two day stretch in late February. February, oh, three, right? That's like one of
the three. Yeah, one of the three highest gas prices we've had in the last 20 years, right?
I think so. Yeah, it all starts to blur together now. But you had this massive spike in price of
gas, I think, approximately doubled in two days. And that was the day the fund also had more than
doubled in those two days in terms of assets. And that was the day when I was like, I feel rich for
the first time. I am set for life today. Did you call anybody? I remember calling my mom, pretty
much saying those words that we're set, we have financial security now forever, regardless of what
happens. So doing the math, you're in your late 20s at this point. Did you have any sense at that
moment that you were going to be out of the game in 10 years and full time working as a philanthropist?
Or was that not a clear part of your vision yet? I always recognized the limited social value
of trading. I think there is a need for someone to provide risk warehousing and liquidity to markets.
But trying to tell the story about how I was adding value or contributing to society was hard.
And that always bothered me. So when I first started getting my first $100,000 bonus back
when I was at Enron, I shortly thereafter was at a supermarket. And I see a magazine that says,
top 50 nonprofits in America. And I pick it up and throw it into my grocery basket and take it home
and immediately turn to the education section. I think a lot of younger philanthropists, a lot of
people from the finance industry get drawn to K-12 education. One of the organizations was based in
Houston. It was KIPP, KIPP charter schools. And so I called them up and got scheduled to go do a tour,
went did a tour. They had no idea who I was at the time. I wasn't a rich guy back then,
but I came home and wrote them a five-figure check. And I get a call from the founder who I had
not met on that original tour a couple of days later. And this was back when five figures was
really significant to the organization. And he said, thank you. And who are you? And I need to
cultivate this relationship. And that was the start of my very long journey thinking about K-12
education in the country. And so in this time, 2002, 2003, I was getting more interested in it.
My check size was going up, but it was something I thought about 1% of the time.
So as your hedge fund is growing and growing and growing, at what point are you now
getting the attention of basically everybody who wants to come in and you're doing the opposite?
You're probably starting to force distributions at some point.
There was a trading magazine that came up with a list of highest paid traders. And that was
from specifically from the hedge fund world where most of the highest paid traders existed.
And it was not only what was the return on your investment in the fund, but what was your
incentive fees and kind of trying to estimate that. And they would create these lists of top 100
for the year. And I don't remember what year it was, but somehow they got a hold of my returns
and started doing the math on it and figured out that I was not only on the top 100, but I think
top five that year. And that was the first time in a broadcast to the world that I was making
big money, but also was a broadcast to the rest of the industry that something's going on in natural
gas and all the other hedge funds should... It was a signal to them, go figure out what's going on
over there. How is he making this much money and see if there's something for us to do?
So during that time, as will happen in any market, whenever there's kind of above market returns
going on in a field, new entrants come in. And that's certainly what happened during that time.
It made a very deliberate decision that I was going to keep the focus of the business narrow,
which I wanted to be the best in the world at North American natural gas and power trading.
That was the business. Didn't want to trade oil, didn't want to trade natural gas stocks
or natural gas bonds. Didn't want to trade agriculture. Stick to our expertise.
Don't try to build an empire here. Just do this one thing. And I think by doing so, I think it...
By keeping focus, it allowed us to achieve that mission of being the best in the field.
I think it also started... It put a natural limit as to the amount of assets that we could manage.
So we just couldn't be too big relative to the market. And the amount of money that we were
making was significant. And so we started sending back money to investors.
What was the greatest you allowed your AUM to swell to, to allow yourself to stay so
narrowly focused? At the peak, it got to about $6 billion.
That's a staggering sum of money. There are lots of hedge funds that have ballooned to $20 and $30
billion in assets under management. And your point is, yeah, that sounds great. And you're
going to collect a lot of fees on that if you're the fund manager, but you may be spreading
yourself too thin into areas that you don't have the deepest, deepest domain expertise.
Right. Very shortly after I started, I was the largest investor in the fund. And I was in it for
the return on my money. That's how I managed the fund. And that's how we would pitch it to
central investors was, I think this is a great investment opportunity. This is where I want my
money. This is the risk, where I am on the risk spectrum for my money. And if you want to join
on that journey, I'd be happy to have you. But I'm going to run a risky business. And you have
to be prepared for that going on because I wasn't in it to make the management fees. That's not how
I wanted to. That wasn't my business. Right. If you're more than 50% of the AUM,
you can't make money on yourself. You can't make fees on your own money.
Right. Right. So it was always driven by, how do I want my money managed? What do I think is a good
investment for me? And then if other people want to put money alongside, that's great.
So by the way, I want to go back to one thing. Talk to me about the 06 Amaranth trade. Explain
for people that given the historical significance of that was pretty significant and the fallout of
that has reverberated for many years as far as the amount of money that was lost in things.
Who was Brian Hunter? What did he do so well in 2005? How did that speculation sort of go the
other way in 06? 2005, I hope I get all these facts right. My memory gets a little bit cloudy
from those days, but 2005 was Hurricane Katrina. It came in and caused significant damage on
the offshore natural gas production as well as the natural gas processing facilities that were
onshore Louisiana. And because of that, the price of gas spiked significantly. People were
short supplies. I looked this up yesterday, John, that is both unadjusted and adjusted for inflation,
the greatest peak in natural gas pricing of the last, I think, 30 years. That's September 05,
right after Katrina. Yeah. And after that time, I think two things happened. First was as ocean
temperatures were rising, there started to be a belief that number of hurricanes and the intensity
of hurricanes, and thus the damage from hurricanes to the energy sector and natural gas sector
was structurally increasing. And second, that there would be a great fear amongst any trader to
be short during that time period, the hurricane season, and of August and September, peak hurricane
season. So he had done very well in 2005. This is Brian Hunter. Brian Hunter in 2005. He was long
during that time and made a lot of money for his fund. And at the time he worked for a fund
Amaranth Advisors, which was a macro hedge fund, meaning they do everything. They trade stocks,
they trade bonds. Brian Hunter was the natural gas trader for them. Now in 2005, as I understand it,
he was by far the most profitable trading desk and trader at a large hedge fund. And so he was
given a lot more position size or capital to trade with. And I think he had the belief that
something similar would happen or at least a big scare would happen next year and would cause the
same type of move. The difference was partially in reaction to the spike in prices that we saw in 2005,
it sent the signal to every producer to increase supplies. So every producer gets that price
signal, every producer puts more money into drilling for gas. You start to see that in 2006
that supplies are ramping up. And talked about earlier that the supply demand was tight in 2002,
supply demand got very loose in 2006. And so the market was just oversupplied. It was a very
bearish market, but Brian Hunter kept this trade on, this very bullish trade on, and kept the prices
supported even though the fundamental picture was deteriorating by continuing to buy more and more
and more of this one product. And I'll put it a long story short, he distorted the relative values
in that market so much. It gets told now that the trade was me versus him. And that's very not much
the case. It was the whole market versus him because he was such a large position in this as
started to get into the first, the very early part of hurricane season and there was no hurricane
and then prices were starting to collapse and he couldn't hold it anymore. So he kind of single
handled that position, bankrupted this macro hedge fund. And I did well during that trade. I think I
may have had on 25% of the opposing position. I was very cognizant that it is possible that a
hurricane comes and has a short term price spike and I don't want to blow up if and when that
happens. So I need to size this appropriately. I don't think he had sized it appropriately given
the alternative scenario. And that's an interesting thing because it wasn't just that you guys were
betting against each other in terms of climate or weather for which I would say three months out,
that becomes an unwinnable bet. Nobody can have more or better information on that.
It's the second order bet that's interesting to me, which is, okay, he's taking a position on
climate or weather, but it's really you're taking a position on the more important question, which
is supply. And you're saying even if we are hit with a demand shock, I believe the market is better
able to bear this now than it was in 2005. And ultimately that's really what the bet comes down
to. It's true, a hurricane didn't hit that year and the price collapsed. But it's also possible
that if a more mild hurricane than Katrina had come, we probably wouldn't have seen the price
shock we saw in 2005. Right, right. The market was so scared. And so people were hesitant. People
were only going to put on that short trade if they thought the market had already priced that in.
And I used to think about it as you have this unknown weather event. How cold is the winter
going to be? What's the hurricane situation going to be? And you can think about it, you
had this probability distribution function of the possible outcomes. And then think about, okay,
under each outcome, how would I think about what fair value is of the commodity at that time? And
then did you do your simple math and come to expected value? And that really simplifies
the process down much too simplistically. But that was the type of thought process that would
go in is, okay, if it's 80th percentile hurricane damage, what is that? If it's 90th percentile,
it's 99th percentile. What if it's 10th percentile? And think about all these and then how's the
market price today? Certainly at that time, there were people who weren't allowed to be short. There
were people who were only going to be short if it was way mispriced relative to expected value.
And I think that's what got him was that it was already so mispriced to expected value
that even had you had this supply shock happen, what's the upside now? We're already priced for
that. Yep. When you explain it that way, it's a much sadder story than just two guys betting
against weather and one guy's got to be right and one guy's got to be wrong. You realize that it was
probably a bit more of an error and hubris as well, which goes back to your point about maybe
being a little too confident in your ability to predict what's going to happen. You spent a lot
of your time doing research. I mean, again, we've already talked about you having two superpowers,
but having known you for a while, I would add to that list maybe a third superpower, which I
believe also has come to serve you very well in your philanthropy, which is you have an insatiable
bordering on pathological obsession for knowing everything. And I say that in the kindest way as
someone who shares part of that affliction. And I remember once you explaining to me some of the
details you would study about natural gas pipelines, it's like, look, if I'm going to be
the best trader in this commodity, I have to know everything. I have to know exactly what this
pipeline looks like. How does it cross this type of part of the country? What type of bolt are they
using in it here? And what happens to it during this type of weather? I mean, how much of your
time went into understanding every piece of the minutia of how this system worked that you were
basically going to dominate in terms of arbitrage and speculation.
So by being a hedge fund structure and not being in the physical business, not dealing with customers
and dealing with pipelines, we were at an information disadvantage going in. When we were
thinking, think about whenever I trade against a counterparty and they're putting on the opposite
trade I am, what are they thinking? What do they know? Can I replicate as best I can the knowledge
that they have so that I can make an educated and confident decision, do I want to be on the other
side of this bet? And to do so, we were at an information handicap just in terms of BP had
more information that would come through their shop than we did. So we had to make it up by
having better analysis and knowing where to get third party information and how to analyze that
information, how to craft better models that described what the past was and thus what the
future is going to be, and then try to overlay some good smart trading and structuring of trades
on top of that to get the above average returns. But I think we were always fundamentally focused.
And this came from the days at Enron, which was the largest physical mover shipper of gas,
was count the molecules. Try to count as many molecules as you can. Where did it come from?
Where did it travel? How was it consumed? And so you can build a molecule about, if you know how
every molecule behaved yesterday, you can model how those molecules are going to behave tomorrow
and how those molecules are going to behave in six months. Now, your confidence level is not as
good in the six month model, but you can start doing that and then you can start doing the
speculative trading on top of it. And so I think we probably had the biggest fundamental research
department of any competitor in the space at Centaurus. And that was really what I thought
our advantage was, was that we're going to invest in the fundamentals more than anybody else is,
and then overlay that with some good trading. You just alluded to something which I guess I
hadn't picked up on before, which, or at least it just occurred to me now when you said that.
Earlier, you said natural gas was easier than oil. When you just gave that explanation,
you talked about being able to count every molecule of gas. I suspect that that's what
allows an island like North America to be easier to trade gas than oil, because we have more insight
into where gas is coming from. LNG was not a big part of gas. So gas was being locally produced
and consumed. It's not like with oil where, my God, it's coming from everywhere and it's
going everywhere, right? Is that a fundamental difference between natural gas and oil trading,
at least at that time? I mean, I know natural gas is more complicated now with shale, with
liquefied natural gas that can go offshore, but is that part of why you made that statement earlier?
Yeah, I think there's three main differences that made natural gas a great product to trade. One was,
it was this closed system that you described that the molecules for the most part were just
stayed in North America. There was a little bit of LNG business. It was mostly baseload, so it was
easy to predict what those flows were going to be in the future. That wasn't a big variable that
was going to cause price moves in the future. And because it was this closed system, you can model
it with much better accuracy. Second was that the deregulation that got the pipelines out of
the business and the pipelines had to be third parties that couldn't take ownership of the gas.
The only service that they could provide was transportation. And by doing so, they didn't have
the pipelines which had the most fundamental information about where the gas came from and
where it was going. They had to publish all this information in a way that was publicly accessible,
and they couldn't trade on it. So there had to be the Chinese wall between the trading group.
And when you compare that versus oil, Exxon can own the oil platform in the Gulf of Mexico to get
in on an Exxon ship, take it to an Exxon-owned refinery and put it in Exxon gas stations.
And so as an outsider trying to figure out and track those molecules, it's impossible. And that's
why the best and most profitable oil traders have to be in the physical business, have to be moving
molecules. And the third is that natural gas, because it was a seasonal product, you store it
during the summer, getting ready for the peak winter demand, that there was a window of storage
that the industry almost required when you go into the winter. And there was a window of what it
should be when you exit the winter. And so twice a year, there was a mechanism to get you back
close to fair value. And if you compare that to a tech stock today, I have always debates about
some stock, there's nothing that necessarily has to get that tech stock back to one's belief of fair
value. There's not that forcing mechanism. And if you're talking about gold, there's no forcing
mechanism in gold. If you have a surplus of gold, you can stick it in a safe someplace. But with
limited storage in natural gas, and the need to have a certain amount of storage when you enter
the winter, it caused that forcing mechanism, which got you back to fair value. So while price
could deviate from fundamental value for parts of the time of the year, twice a year, it kind of had
to go back to that, which was great as a fundamental trader. There's a lot of commodities where they
don't necessarily have to go back to that fair value. So the country is entering a recession,
2008, 2009. You are still staggeringly profitable. Where at this point in time is your head with
respect to philanthropy? So we've established the fact that when you were making $100,000 bonus
as an early trader at Enron, even before you became head trader, you're already spending 1%
of your energy thinking about how you want to utilize your wealth down the line. But now let's
talk 2009, 2010. You're almost a decade into running your own fund, which will probably go
down in time as one of the most profitable hedge funds of all time, certainly in this space.
Are you, what are you 10% now thinking about philanthropy? I mean, how are you now thinking
about chapter two of your career? Yeah, so I met my wife in early 2006. And she had moved to Houston,
she was a mergers and acquisitions lawyer and had moved to Houston to help start an energy company.
And I've spent, I forget exactly how long, but call it 18 months on that job. She and I had
started in the meantime, we'd gotten married. And we're starting to think about what should we do
with our lives now? This momentous event of marriage, what does she want to be doing? What
do I want to be doing? We have the financial resources to do what we want with our time.
And so she answered that question by saying, I don't want to work at the energy company anymore.
I want to focus on our philanthropic activities, which we had both been doing a little bit on the
side. At this point, call it 2006, I was spending maybe 3% of my energy on philanthropy. And she the
same. And by 2008, she had gone full time with our nascent foundation. And we started hiring a few
people. And I was starting to spend more of my energy, call it 10%, 15% of my energy on the
foundation, which became troubling a little bit because it's obviously markets are efficient in
the long term, the markets are smart, the competitors are smart, competitors entered,
you had to keep finding new ways to stay above the competition. And one of those was, you have to be
100% focused on this job. It's too competitive to not be 100% focused. And when I went 90%, then it
got harder. As the preceding years happened, and I started thinking more about giving the money away
than making more of it, that was really the signal to me that I want to be spending my time on the
other side of the table. And I'm physically and mentally emotionally exhausted with trading
natural gas is the only thing I had done as a professional again from a few days after graduating
college. And here I am 17 years later, still doing pretty much the same thing. And I want to do
something else with my life. And so that was 2012. And that's when I decided it's time to shut this
down. I'm guessing that I mean, I've spoken with some of the greatest scientists in the world. And
not everybody says this, but there are some that do that they say, they can't stop thinking about
what it is they're working on. Anytime they get to a stoplight, that's where their mind wanders.
When they're in the shower, that's where their mind wanders is to the problem, is to the questions
that they're trying to ask, is the problem they're trying to solve. Is it safe to say that you
probably felt the same way until you hit that inflection point? Absolutely. It was spent more
than a decade living, breathing, after work, go out with other people in the industry and talk about
natural gas, dream about natural gas. I would wake up in the morning, first thing you do is
check the prices, get in the shower, think about it, what could go wrong? What do I want to do today?
What's the plan? And it was just all encompassing in life. I think to be successful in these
competitive fields, whether it's in health research or in trading, you have to give it that 100% focus.
And if you don't, you're going to see it in the results. It's just too competitive.
So was it a hard decision for you then to shut your fund down, return the capital to people,
and become a full-time philanthropist? Or was it actually quite easy once you accepted,
I'm no longer giving 100% of my brain power to this other thing?
It was hard. That's who I was as certainly a professional and who I was largely defined
as a person as well was as a natural gas trader. Had been the place where I'd had the most success
of anything I had tried to do in my life. And so starting in about 2010, I knew this was the
decision I needed to make. It was hard. It was a hard decision to make. It got easier because
things had changed in the market. So if you look at the graph of natural gas prices, you see them
peaking about July of 2008, maybe late June 2008, and just being on a steady decline and the
volatility starts to change as well. The Shell revolution took the market from one that was
ever increasing demand and harder and harder to get the next molecule of gas out of the ground.
So having to try to balance that through price, which becomes very volatile and leads to booms
and busts, to one that was in perpetual oversupply and kind of bouncing around marginal cost to
produce. And so the opportunity had changed. And so I'd given back $3 billion back to investors.
And it was at the point where by 2012, I was at, I need to give back another 50% down to a billion
and a half, just the market opportunity is not there. And it's hard when you've been playing
in Vegas with the $25 table to go back down to the $5 table. It's just not as emotionally
interesting. And so that happened. I got married, we had kids, the regulation in the business
partially, in fact, maybe largely due to the Brian Hunter episodes that had when the price
distortions that wasn't good for the market had just become harder. And I had just lost the focus
in my interest in the foundation side. And so all these things came together. And it still took me
two years to really figure out, to make that call, that it's time. It's time to close us up and go
find happiness somewhere else. And I think part of that struggle was I had seen many other people
in the industry who had similar thoughts along the years, that they want to go do something else.
And a lot of times those people left and couldn't find what to do or couldn't find satisfaction
with their lives doing something else. And so even though that they were unhappy in the trading
business, they ended up back in the trading business because they were even more unhappy
the other thing that they had tried to go do. And so that was my fear, was that a year from
when I close up, I'm going to miss it and I'm not going to find satisfaction in this other thing.
And then what? What do I do then? Am I really going to go start it up again? It took me those
24 months to really get the confidence to say, I can find happiness here. I can find other things
to do and to close it down. So talk me through some of those early days then. Laura has obviously
been well up and running. She's been on this full time for several years now. You both have
a great number of interests at the time. How do you begin to make that transformation? We've
already talked a little bit about what the skills are that you brought to bear. And again,
I'd reiterate them as kind of an emotional temperament for it to not let your feelings
get in the way of what you're doing. The second one being kind of the right amount of confidence
to say, yeah, this is a huge and hard problem, but we should go after it. But maybe not too
much confidence to say, we're going to solve this problem no matter what. And then I think the third
one being probably one that gets overlooked a bit, but basically an ability to become an expert in
something in a relatively short period of time. I mean, I think people who are familiar with Bill
Gates just watched a documentary about him and not read much about him. You'll realize he's not just
a guy that revolutionized the computer industry. But when you look at the voracious appetite with
which he has explored other topics, I mean, I've only met Bill in person once. And I'll share that
the subject matter that we were speaking on, which was something in my wheelhouse and not his,
it only took me about 10 minutes to realize I was talking to someone who knew as much about this
topic as almost anyone I had spoken with. And that's saying something because this is not
something you would assume that a person would know a lot about. I mean, this was at the beginning
of the discussion, I'm using terms that I would use with a lay person. And he's like, yep, yep,
yep, yep. He's like, no, no, no, you just go straight to shorthand for me. And I was like,
but he wasn't doing it from a place that was anything other than totally genuine. You knew
that this is a guy who really knew the subject matter. Again, you share that trait, which is,
I don't know, that's, that allows people, I think, to have a bigger impact in their philanthropy.
I appreciate the comparison, but it's not close. I agree with, I've gotten to know
Bill over the years and agree with your assessment of him that his breadth and depth of knowledge
is something that I have never seen in somebody else. And it incredibly impressive in that he
knows the background and knows the issues of almost anything you can think of in a way that is scary.
And I am certainly not that way. Well, I will agree to disagree on that, John. So talk to me
about the first problem that you decided to turn your attention to once you became a full-time
philanthropist. As I said, I'd gotten my start in giving with K-12 education and kind of over the
years, I've just gotten deeper and deeper into those questions of why does one school have
different results from a school down the street serving the very similar population of kids?
What's the theory of change in K-12? It is such a massive system that's broken down at the school
level. And how can we as a country try to get results that we're happier with knowing all the
hurdles that go into that and all the factors that go into education and behavior? So how does that
scale? How does those small gems that you see, how can you scale that? And this is a question I think
the educational reform movement has been struggling with for decades and I watched that
journey and was on the journey along with many other philanthropists of is it small schools? Is
it better principals? Is it better teachers? Is it the curriculum? Is it technology? All these things
kind of bouncing from one idea to the next trying to find what's the idea that scales and creates
structural change. And so we're still involved in K-12. I think it's just the most fundamental
issue facing long-term health and viability of this country. And when you talk to almost any
social service provider, they always refer back to education. And so I think it's one that we've
spent a lot of time thinking about and happy to get into that if you want. But it was the first
and it continues to be a major effort of the foundation. And I know that you've worked with,
as you said, others. I think Citi Fund has sort of largely, a lot of your efforts have morphed
into that, correct? Right. So I guess I'll give you the theory of change that drives our work of
late in K-12. And that's that strong and robust systems of any kind have the attributes of
biological evolution, right? And so in living organisms, that's the phenotypic variation.
You have variance amongst the organisms. The differential fitness, is there a different
rate of survival and reproduction? And then the heritability of fitness. And I think this is true
of any organization. It's true of businesses. It's true of any system. And it's true of the
healthcare system, the criminal justice system. And it's true of the school system. So you need
to have a strong, robust system that's getting better over time. You need those three traits.
And the traditional public school system does not have them. So if you think of a school district
that is a monopoly in its area, it doesn't have much variance. It might have a school that's
Spanish emerging. It might have a school that's for the talent and gifted. It might have another
school that's a magnet or something. But generally, it's same curriculum, the same process,
the same way of hiring, of training, of trying to develop teachers, how your principal development
is, right? You don't have that variation. The differential fitness of do things that are working,
do they grow, or do they go away? Yeah, there's no pressure. The good stuff in public education,
there's no natural mechanism for them to grow, for that to grow. And there's no mechanism that
really works in the public school system for it to go away, for the things that aren't working
to stop. And then the readability of traits, you need the learning organization aspect of it,
which I will tell you, a school system is not good at, and any government monopoly is not good at
quality control. It's not good at innovation to provide that variance. And so the theory with
Citi Fund and the theory of our K-12 work is that the school system needs to become a system
of schools, that the natural role for government is not to be the service provider. The natural role
should be the regulator. And right now, those two functions are bundled together into one,
and no system can regulate itself. And too often today, I think those systems are structured to
regulate themselves. And so you don't get that innovation, you don't get the quality control.
And so the vision is, and what we saw in New Orleans after Katrina, was this change of
going from the school system to the system of third-party nonprofit operators that are given
the chance to have the resources and responsibility to educate kids,
K-12 kids. And the theory, again, if it works well, that the parents, the kids have real choice,
get to choose what type of model they want, whether it is a immersion program, whether they
want high discipline or regular discipline, whether they want an art school, et cetera.
That demand, if you're given real choice to the kids, to the parents, that that's the best quality
control that can happen. And then the government as the regulator needs to make sure that all kids
are served, because we need to make sure that ideal, that every kid is properly served,
but is largely out of the business of providing the service of education.
So let's put some numbers to this, John, more broadly. So maybe think of it in terms of GDP,
how much is private, how much is public slash government, how much is nonprofit? What's the
approximate breakdown of the dollars that get allocated in the world or in the country, I'm
sorry, along those three divisions? Of the total economy, the private sector is approximately 60%.
Government's approximately 40%. The philanthropic sector is about 2%. Now, when you take out giving
to museums, to religious organizations, to the arts in general and religious organizations,
you get down to about 1% of the economy is philanthropy for social services or social
goods. Okay. So you're stripping out basically what I used to call maybe erroneously brick
and mortar philanthropy. And you're saying 50% of it, the 50% that remains is this type of
philanthropy that people like you work on, people like Bill Gates works on. No, it's not just the
brick and mortar. No, no. So I'm including gifts to food banks, gifts to the hospital system to
build a building. Oh, okay. Okay. This is about 1% of the economy. So one of the things we've
thought about is what's the role of philanthropy? Because the government is giving a benefit to
people who give money to nonprofits. There's a tax deduction. And so there is a stake, there is
some type of tie that I think exists between the donor and what that money should be going for.
And so we've thought about how should that 1% of philanthropic funds, what's the best use of that?
And you can think about, or we think about, it can either supplement government services. So by
providing more money to the homeless shelter, a service that the government already provides,
but you can supplement that with more resources. And that's typically described as charity, trying
to solve today's problems. And then there's the, what some would describe as strategic philanthropy
of trying to get at the core roots of issues to prevent those problems from developing tomorrow.
Both are really important. There's not a priority or hierarchy between those two. We give some
charitable dollars. You give money to the food bank. We give money to the homeless shelter in
town. You do have to meet those needs. But there is a role for how does the philanthropic money
complement government services to make them better? What is the market failure as to why government
is not working as well as many people believe it should? How can the school system be better?
Well, the school system now is so focused on, is already budget constrained. It's so focused on
just providing the day-to-day activities. And the same of all these nonprofit social providers is
that they're so focused on the day-to-day job that they don't get to experiment like they should.
And so there is this role for strategic philanthropy to come in and say, how can these
actors and these systems perform better? And I think that's where we've largely focused on
our giving is looking at systems change. It's structural and it's scalable to a way that just
providing another dollar for a program largely is not. There's different roles for different types
of givers. Anybody can write the check to the food bank. And again, we write the check to the food
bank, but the smallest giver can also write the check to the food bank. Looking at the strategic
side, which requires a lot of manpower and expertise and hiring experts and getting access
to experts and thinking about here are the ideas that have been tried in the past, what's worked,
what hasn't. Here are the current ideas, what's the theoretical framework for those ideas and why
they could work. What are the potential second order effects of those and making those decisions.
It's really, it's hard for the small donor to do that. It's really geared towards the large
national foundations. And so that's really where we see our role.
Were you humbled by how difficult that is, how difficult it is to someone could easily
listen to this and say, how hard is it to give away $400 million a year? You're just,
you're writing big checks, but the way you just described that actually, it sounds very difficult
to give away a lot of money if it's trying to mostly be philanthropic and not charity driven.
Because as you said, the philanthropic one is the one that's strategic. It's the one that you're
trying to scale and be maximally leveraged in the silo of another agent, for example, in the case of
what the government's already doing or what the private sector is already doing. I mean, it just
strikes me as very difficult. How long did it take? A, do you agree with that? And then B,
how long did it take you to come to that realization that your second career is
probably harder than your first? We have about 120 employees of the foundation today. We had
no desire or interest to have 120 employees 10 years ago. That was not by design. We thought
giving would be easy. I remember very specifically thinking, or giving was going to be find the
highest social return projects for organizations. And just write those five big checks every year,
make it easy, make it fairly passive. We started down this route and I started pulling the research.
I had a conometrics background and college, like smart enough to read the papers. I could figure
out what they were saying. And so start with a topic like preschool. You see three papers that say
preschool is amazing. It generates all these outcomes later in life. And then you see one
evaluation of the Head Start program that shows it doesn't really have an effect. And then as you
dig deeper in, start seeing there's huge battles within this research sector about what the evidence
really shows, what it demonstrates, and the quality of the evidence that's going into all these claims
about success. And I think in every area that we thought of, look at work training programs.
The first scan through, everything works. It's all great. Writing checks there is a great way
to invest money. And then you dig deeper and start getting into, okay, the problems with
those research that organizations are holding up saying, here's our evidence that we're successful.
And it got very frustrating because the more we would study, the less we knew
about what worked, what didn't. One of the learnings was very few programs worked,
or new programs. So the things that work are generally already part of the fabric of society,
like K-12 education. We know that works, what works. These programs that have clear evidence
of successor are generally already funded by government, already part of fabric of society.
So what's our role? Are we just going to supplement with a few extra dollars on the side?
And I didn't want to do that. So where could our dollars go the best? And that really led us down
this issue of how do you change and improve the system and the incentives and the rules of a
system rather than what's the next program we can fund? Because the frustration of trying to find
that program just became immense. So speaking of a system that I think almost anybody who spent
any length of time thinking about it will pretty quickly come to the conclusion is broken, is the
criminal justice system. When did that system come to your and Laura's radar? Laura really drove
us entering this field. She was a lawyer by training, although on the corporate side, I think
she was just from having the legal background, you see the world in a different way. And one of the
first organizations that we started sending some checks to was the Innocence Project. And we had
met the head of the Innocence Project, Barry Schecht, at some event and start hearing the stories
that will just tear at your heart someone who's been wrongfully convicted and was going to die
except for the actions of the Innocence Project. And we started funding that just because it was
the right thing to do. It was a way to help save a life that was going to be terminated without that.
I have great respect for the Innocence Project because as they started building up
dozens and into hundreds of examples of people that they got off death row or out of prison for
wrongful convictions, they started looking at the policy angle as well. So it wasn't just about the
one person or the 100 people that they were saving, although massively important. They started
thinking more strategically about how do we change the system so that the wrongful convictions don't
happen in the first place. Right, because you have to believe that for the amount of effort it takes
to take one person off death row, one wrongly convicted person off death row, having followed
a few of these cases, it can take decades. And I mean, it can consume the effort of tens of people,
tens of thousands of hours. And you would say, well, it's wonderful that we've saved that life.
What if we put an equal amount of resources on the other side of the equation, which is getting
few of these people into the system? In other words, you start to think about where's the
asymmetry on this one. And it seems a lot of it's on the front end, right? I mean, you could have
a hundred Innocence Projects, you will still never fully be able to rectify the situation,
notwithstanding the fact that you can't undo retroactively all the harm that is done by the time
the person is set free. Exactly. A couple of examples like that really led us again to,
okay, the systems change, the policy focus is where we want to spend the time that there's
higher potential reward, it is harder work, the chance of success is lower. But the impact,
if successful, is so much higher, if you can improve how the system works. And so we started
looking at kind of a number of areas of the criminal justice system, where I guess first,
we spent a year, hired someone to lead that work, we spent a year just thinking about all the ways
the inefficiencies in the system that lead to bad outcomes that don't promote public safety,
that destroy neighborhoods that aren't fair and equitable for those that are charged or convicted
of a crime, et cetera. And where could we as a foundation, where could we be effective?
Let's pause on that for a moment. Because again, I think that's just a very interesting
approach that is a bit counterintuitive. You decide this is something you're passionate about,
but you don't go right into it, both guns blazing, there's a humility that says,
why don't we bring an internal team in that we'll hire, that'll spend a year helping us get up to
speed on this and identify the specific targets that we can focus on. Do you find that to be a
period of impatience for you? Or do you find that to be a period of great enjoyment as you are on the
upswing of another learning curve? It's certainly impatience. We have all this money sitting in the
account. The goal is to do good with it. And we'd rather figure out how to do the most good today,
rather than waiting until tomorrow. So there was this natural impatience, but I think we've been
smart enough to realize that it's smarter to invest wisely tomorrow than do something that's
unlikely to have impact today. And so that's just kind of a necessary function of it is
bringing in some experts, but really study where is the leverage that a foundation can have on
the problem. It's very different from the other actors that are already in the system. It's
different from what politicians can do or government policy makers or judges or police,
everybody has a role. And the question is, how can a philanthropy or foundation that is not a
natural actor in the system, but has a checkbook, how can that create some leverage to try to steer
the system and improve it? Now, in your first version of the foundation, there were two versions,
right? There was a C3 and a C4. And I believe currently the entire foundation is a C3. Is that
correct? We've always realized that the goal is not to just do research or just do idea generation.
The goal is to have real positive policy change. And policy change requires some advocacy,
political action, it just does. And so we used to have those, the C4, which is the advocacy arm,
is a separate tax vehicle. And there had to be a Chinese wall between the C3 and C4.
With the C3 being the traditional philanthropic vehicle. And we realized was that having that
Chinese wall really was harming our ability to have positive impact. And so we combined the two
entities into an LLC, so that the same employee who was the expert in fines and fees and the options
on how to change fines and fees to make them more equitable and just could also go sit there and
talk to a legislator about why the problem existed and what the optimal solutions were.
So what were some of the things that you and the team learned when it came to understanding how
the criminal justice system could be so broken? And I say that again, not knowing much about it,
but knowing a little bit about it, right? Which is there seems to be an enormous racial disparity
that exists. There also certainly by state, certainly seems to be great difficulties in
appealing even in the presence of evidence that the first trial may not have been a great trial.
The amount of coercion that goes into convictions that turn out to be, I mean, there's so you could
just rattle off. You don't have to know anything as clearly I don't to still rattle off five or
six structural problems. How did you decide which ones were the most important and or which were
the ones that you could have the greatest impact in? I think it was important to figure out how we
got to the current system. And in this world of real partisanship was a bipartisan response to
the growing violent crime that was happening starting post World War II. And then really
peaked late 80s, early 90s that got everybody, all politicians concerned and scared and they felt
they were being elected based upon crime rates, based upon the amount of violent crime and trying
to get a handle on that. So the violent crime was also destroying communities. And so you had
Democrats, Republicans, whites, Blacks, Hispanics, all come together and start this tough on crime
mantra, which was we're going to jack up our number of police, we're going to jack up the
penalties for any criminal act, have it severely intensify the war on drugs, and then all the
second and third order effects that came with it happened. Now, crime ended up peaking in the early
90s. And some of it was because of some of the policies passed, but a lot of it wasn't. So you
can see different areas that adopted policies at different times. And it seems like the drop in
crime was relatively independent of when communities both across America as well as globally, adopted
some of these policies. So why did crime go down over the past 30 years is still a mystery to some,
they have some great researchers have looked at this and tried to figure it out. And it's a lot
of like, okay, a small piece of it's this small piece of it's this, etc. But the times have
changed. So we still had on the books, the reaction from an environment that was very different. And
the question is, we've seen what those policies did to neighborhoods. And we've seen the financial
costs of those policies, and the trade offs associated with some of those policies. And I
think you saw both Republicans and Democrats come together trying to rethink what's the right way
to structure the criminal justice system, all aspects from policing and courts and prisons and
reentry. What's the right way that we should do given the environment that we're in right now?
Now, thinking back to those late 80s, early 90s, when everybody came together and said,
we just can't handle this amount of violent crime, we're going to get tough on crime,
we're going to create more prison beds, we're going to put more police officers on the street,
etc, etc. Was it sort of a combination of things that led to where we are now? Was it basically
more police, more arrests, stiffer sentences, less leniency around parole, lower tolerance on
parole violations? Like, was there any one thing or even three things that stood out as the most
damning factors that led to mass incarceration? What is your assessment of that? And I would be
curious to hear your thoughts, because I think your thoughts would be more informed than mine or just
the average person on what other factors could have accounted for the reduction in crime, if not
the increase in incarceration. Yeah, I'll take the latter question first. The best report I've
seen on this is from the Brennan Center that really looked at, spent significant amount of time trying
to piece together what were different responses and how much of it was just kind of demographic
trends, how much of it was economic growth and drop in better education, better skilled police
tactics, all these different avenues. And I'm doing a short shift on all the things that they've
assigned some causation to. I think the summary is, it's hard to see any one of them being really
causal in the shift in crime. It was, most tellingly, you saw this same trends happening globally.
Different countries had different reactions to this. And they all had that move up in crime
over time into the 90s and then this downward trend. And so people were scratching their head
trying to say, well, what caused it? And part of it, I'm not sure we'll ever know. And then to the
first question about, which I'll reiterate just in case you forgot, is basically of all the
mechanisms or tactics that would lead to an increase in incarceration, do you have a sense
of which of those were perhaps most responsible? I don't want to get too far of my ski tips on this
and misrepresent the research. I think part of it has been longer sentences. A part of it has been
the conviction rate. So once you're arrested, you can get convicted, what percent of the people are
done so? And it leads into the system is built to demand a plea bargain. We just don't have
the court resources, the defense attorneys, the prosecutors, the judges, the court systems
to hear a vast majority of cases. And so it ends up being less than 5% of cases actually go in
front of a judge. Most of them just get pled out. And for a long time, because those resources
don't exist, there's been incentives that have been built into the system that almost coerce
people to plead guilty to crimes that they may not have committed. Because just from a risk reward,
it is, I didn't commit this crime, but there's a 20% chance to get found guilty. I get a 20 year
sentence, or I can serve I can plead down to a lesser charge and get six months of which I've
already been here for three months. So three more months and I'm out or my life's over.
Going back to your days of trading, that's a no brainer calculation.
Yeah, and it's really hard to see how you solve that problem without a massive infusion,
resources into the courts and into prosecutors and defense attorneys, which is not where we
want to be spending money. We'd rather spend money on preventing crime on social services,
to not have that problem to begin with. And so how do you get rid of this culture where
the system can't handle everybody going to trial? One of the biggest challenges that nobody has a
great answer for. Now, I don't know if this has been a focus at all of your foundation within
criminal justice work, but obviously in the last few months, it's quite topical with respect to
the relationship between the police and race and the role of systemic racism within law enforcement.
How much does that factor into the economics of it beyond the obvious, which is disproportionately
arresting, presumably disproportionately convicting just based on what you just said,
the stats you just laid out. I mean, I would have never guessed that 95% of cases would be
pled. And if that's the case, then yeah, I just answered my own question, which is if you're going
to arrest disproportionately minorities, then you're going to convict or at least put in prison
disproportionately minorities. And certainly the few times I have visited prison, it's disproportionately
minorities. Take all of that and try to package it into a question. What is the role for philanthropy
if there is one to try to address the questions of racism within law enforcement? Does that factor
into a tool for criminal justice reform? There's obviously been a lot of debate or discussion
this year on that very topic. And there's no doubt the disproportionate nature of the criminal
justice system on minorities, and particularly on the black community. For so long, the political
incentive and so much of the focus has been just on crime rates with no regard for the secondary
effects that the criminal justice system causes on these communities and on families. And I think
that's one of the things that we as a society are trying to grapple with now, not for the first time,
but for the first time, this has gone into a mainstream discussion.
Sorry, just to make sure you're saying we all acknowledge and have acknowledged historically
that it's disproportionately black men that go to prison. But we're now taking a more broad look
at the implication on, for example, children that are now left without a father. Is that what you
mean as an example of the impact on the family? Right. And the psychological effects of being a
black man in America, especially in a low income neighborhood that has, and especially if it's an
aggressive police force there. I think one of the dilemmas has been that minority communities have
felt both over policed and under policed at the same time. They feel over policed with the
techniques that the police are using in their neighborhoods. So the random stops, certainly
back in the era, stop and frisk, and a presumption of guilt and that people, especially young black
men, are likely to be up to something bad. However, there is still a crime problem. Most
crime is committed in one's own community. We're in the very near geographic area around the
community. And there is a huge cost to society of violent crime. So nobody wants the police to leave
entirely. There still has to be that function of deterrence and trying to clear cases that have
been committed. So how do you create a policing system that tries to address both of those,
that treats people more equitably, more justly, recognizes their constitutional rights while
protecting those communities because the cost of policing on communities is high, the cost of violent
crime on communities is high as well. And that's the struggle with the policing reforms. And there's
things that we absolutely should do. A lot of those are getting enacted now, or at least being
discussed now, but it's not just, the problem doesn't get solved just by passing one new policy.
These problems got created over decades, over centuries, over decades of policing techniques,
over centuries of disinvestment in these communities. And the question is, how do you
both provide the public safety while not causing the damage that some policing techniques cause today?
So then shifting gears a little bit within the criminal justice system,
how much of your effort has focused on the other side, which is recidivism. I mean, one of the
things that I was most struck with when I visited prison was the lack of what appeared to be
logic around why somebody was in prison. So again, maybe I'm being overly simplistic, but the way I
would view it is there are sort of not that many reasons to put someone in prison. One reason to
put somebody in prison is to protect the public from them. Another reason to put someone in
prison is to punish them for something they have done. And yet a final reason to put somebody into
prison that would factor into the first two, should they be released again, is to provide them with
a set of skills to reintegrate into society in a better way. So you've got these, call it two
pillars and then a foundation. And I was very surprised. Admittedly, I was in a maximum security
prison, but nevertheless, at least half the men that were there were going to be out of jail in
their lifetime. I was very surprised at how there was virtually no effort into the rehabilitative
part. So even if you took a long view on protection and punishment, the lack of rehabilitation,
almost guaranteed recidivism. Again, going to your point, if 95% of people are
pleading out of something, many of which are things they didn't do, what they don't realize
in that VAR calculation is, yeah, I'm going to be out of jail in three months, but I'm going to have
a very difficult path to getting a job. I've now moved off the track of non-felon to I am a felon,
and that's a very different path. So is there an opportunity for strategic philanthropy to play a
role in the rehabilitative side of incarceration? Yes. I agree with everything you said. It's
very hard to design effective recidivism programs after someone's come out. We've tried this as a
society in many different forms and shapes for a long time, and the evidence is very poor that
they have. You study it in a diligent way that these programs work. It's a very tough problem.
And so there's a theory, which I believe, and kind of going on what you said, that the nature of
prisons has to change. That if you wait until the day someone's released, that's way too late. It's
like if you wait until someone drops out of school to step in with some more social services,
it's too late. And so we have a couple of projects trying to reimagine prisons, think about exactly
what you said about what's the role of prisons. What do we want society to do? The struggle is
that states and cities, states and counties that fund this are often constrained financially. And
so they're trying to figure out how do I meet today's problem, which is I got a lot of people
in prison, versus how can I make investments to improve outcomes over the long term? And how much
of the budget can go to improving outcomes over the long term while we have to meet today's needs?
And anytime that there's a financial shock, you stop investing in the investments, because you
try to meet today's needs. And so I think so much of the public money has gone to the day to day
work of it, that not enough is trying to step back and think, how could a system be redesigned?
What should people who are stuck behind the bars, what should they be doing with their day?
How can we try to maximize the percent chance that they don't come back here when they're
released? Because the recidivism rate is incredibly high. And we just haven't found
ways to lower that through programs that reach people when they are released.
So part of the problem with that, I think, is you could certainly make an ROI case that if you
invest more now, you'll save much more tomorrow. But so in other words, if you have 100 people in
prison that are going to get out every year, and ordinarily 80 of them are going to be back within
five years, and you can make it 20 of them are going to be back within five years. Oh my god,
the cost savings, you could almost invest anything you wanted to make that happen, and it would pay
itself off. The problem is it won't pay itself off for five years. Is that a fair statement?
Right. So in the private sector, they would make that investment every day. But in the public
sector, it's on a cash accounting, you have to balance the books this year, and you have a fixed
amount of money, we can raise taxes and raise revenues, but it's hard. Nobody likes to raise
taxes. And so you have a fixed amount of money. So how much money goes to the investment, even if it
has a strong ROI. And I think that's where the philanthropic sector can be an active player or
actor in this system is by providing the funds to experiment with different ideas, different
programs in prison, and then funding the high quality evaluation to see what is the ROI. Can
we get good data so that we can go to the state and say, look, this program has a very positive ROI,
I know it's hard in the short term to deviate money away from just the way we're doing it now,
and it's gonna be hard to find the funds today to make that investment. But there's great evidence,
if you can find those funds that five years from now, everybody's gonna be better off.
The state's gonna be better off, society's gonna be better off, the person entering society is gonna
be better off. And so you got to make that argument, but you have to be able to provide that
high quality evidence of effectiveness because everybody shows up saying, my program works,
my program works. Is that exactly the type of work you guys are doing in this space,
which is basically trying to design the best, quote unquote, trials or experiments that could
at least allow for an evidence based decision with respect to how to handle these things?
That's certainly a line of the work. Some of it is more about values. And it's, should we keep
someone detained in jail before they've gone to their court date because they don't have the
money to pay bail? I think that's just a value. So the criminal justice has this mix of things that
you can talk to ROIs on some things. Other things, it's just, is this how our society should be
functioning? Is that a right thing? Is that balance the interests of the system? I think a lot of times
when you sit down with people and you're like, is this an American value? Is this an American
ideal that the system works this way? They will say no. Okay. Then how do we fix it more closely
represents American values without while minimizing any potential second order effects, negative second
order effects. So let's pivot to another area that is enormous for the foundation, which is health
policy. This might be, I don't know, this is easily one of the most complicated systems in
this country. How are you thinking about it and where are you trying to apply yourself? Because
it's just too big. This strikes me as sort of the hedge fund problem you alluded to earlier.
You could potentially try to spread yourself too thin, try to play in every area of it and get
nothing done. So knowing you, though I don't know where you've chosen to invest your time lately,
I'm guessing you have some clarity about the precision with which you want to think about that.
Yeah. And you're right. It's just such a big issue complex, the number of things that one could work
on and health policy is immense. And so I did the same thing. We're thinking about where in health
policy should we be focused? We started working in this area about eight years ago. And after
doing that same type of canvassing that we did in criminal justice work, we realized that our first
area should be on drug prices. Kind of identified that as an area where kind of very obvious flaws
in the existing system, that there were ideas that one could conceive of being enacted on how to fix
it. And that the political window might open in the future, such that there was demand by the public
and thus by politicians to actually adopt some of this stuff. And so using those three criteria,
we ended up with how do we create a more rational system to price pharmaceuticals that balances
interest, balances incentives that are necessary for the private sector to do the innovation that
they're doing. It balances the financial interests of the state and the federal government that's
largely paying for a lot of this stuff and that maximizes access for the patient.
So if I understood you correctly, you're basically saying, look, let's look at what solutions could
look like, even though if today the political will to make changes is in there, this is going
to take us a while to figure out what to do. And maybe in 10 years, the water has gotten hot enough
that the frog is willing to jump out. We'll at least have something in place. Is that kind of how
you went about thinking about it, was taking a long-term view? Yes, it was that the political
window wasn't open eight years ago when we started the work. We could see cracks in it. We could see
cracks in that window. And I think that's one thing that we've been good at at a foundation is
trying to identify where's the political window going to open up in the future, whether it's in
changing the bill system, whether that's in doing pension reform or in pharmaceutical prices. We've
gone to these areas and we were early. And so when the window opened, we had evidence-based
ideas that we could present to policymakers and could properly document the problem.
There was a whole effort on communications to both individuals, to society about what the abuses
in the system are in any of these areas, including in drug pricing. But then also had ideas that you
could go to him and say, here are the three things you need to do. Now, the pharmaceutical
industry is perhaps the most complex industry of any. And so there aren't the three things that
should be done. There's the 20 things that should be done because it is just such a broad and complex
system with so many loopholes and bad incentives that's driving bad behavior that to get at it is
not, okay, here's the one thing, it's here's the 20 things. The downside is you start to lose
policymakers when you hit number four, because they only want to speak in lists of three.
So how optimistic are you? Because this is an area where I know a little bit. I've had Marty
Macri on the podcast before. I know you know Marty and we've spoken about this. We have an
entire episode on this topic. I've had Catherine Eben on before to talk about a different angle
here, which is basically just the difference between the basically the corruption within the
generic drug industry, which is a totally different problem from the one you're addressing.
For as much as I know about this, I feel like I still don't understand it, which I think speaks
to exactly what you just said. If a problem has 21 bullet points to fix it, it's a complicated
problem. What is your level of optimism? I mean, to be blunt, do you feel like you are spinning
your wheels for eight years? And this is a problem that will only get fixed when we are on the verge
of bankruptcy in this country. Because as you said, this is largely a government spend problem.
This is my view, by the way, this is my little rant on the United States. So we basically carry
two enormous burdens for the world. There are two things we disproportionately pay,
that our taxes disproportionately go to on some level subsidize things in the world. And one is
military spend and the other is healthcare spend. And you might say, well, gosh, why would healthcare
spend in the United States be a subsidy for the world? But it's effectively that we pay so much
more for drugs here than our neighbors do, that we in effect subsidize the cost of R&D to the point
where the incentives are to make the drugs here, to distribute them here and elsewhere,
but we disproportionately pay. Do you agree with that assessment or is it overly simplistic?
Right. We're 3% of the world's population. United States, 3% of the world's population,
we pay 50% of the pharmaceutical revenues of the world. So there's no doubt that the prices that
we're paying is helping and creating incentive for more medicines that others then get the benefit
from. But one of the talking points I have in this is the NIH spends so much money on the basic
science that's required to get these drugs started. And in return, the pharmaceutical companies
charge us 2x, 3x the prices of other countries. We shouldn't be getting a discount because the
United States taxpayers funding some of the basic science, much of the basic science, but some of
the total cost of developing these drugs. But rather than we don't get the discount, we don't even
get the same price as we get the highest prices in the world by a large measure.
So it comes back to this notion of you'll hear people say things all the time like this is not
sustainable. Our cost of healthcare is not sustainable, blah, blah, blah. And I remember
hearing somebody say something once and I don't remember who it was, but I really agreed with the
point he made, which was nonsense. It's totally sustainable because we're still doing it. I mean,
it's going to be sustainable until it's no longer sustainable until we default on our debt as the
largest sovereign default. This ridiculous system is totally sustainable. So then my question is,
what will it take to change this given the complexity of it, given all of the bad incentives,
given everything that you and I just said, what would it take for us to not be spending 15, 16,
17% of our GDP on healthcare at a clip that's probably increasing at 5% per year in relative
growth? Right. We spoke earlier about the downsides of the state having to balance the budget,
and that's that it can't make the high ROI investments that it should. The upside is that
it forces the states to consider trade-offs. They can spend a dollar on healthcare or a dollar on
roads or a dollar on education or a dollar on social services, and they have to decide
where's the highest value, and they look to save money. The federal government, without that
constraint, at least in today's environment, doesn't have to make that trade-off. So any
proposed legislation where somebody gets harmed unless it's concentrated mostly in the other
party's constituency, that will not pass because no hard decisions want to get made.
And so the ramification of that is enormous budget deficits today and an enormous debt
that has had a lot of people sounding alarms for decades. Now, those alarms and those concerns
about the debt and what it's going to lead to have not come true today. It doesn't mean they're
not going to come true in the future. And I think that's the greatest concern is that
the United States is not going to default on the debt. We can just print the money,
but what can happen is high inflation. And again, people have been talking about this for years,
and I don't know if it ever comes true or not, but we in this country now have a fiscal or monetary
response to every problem, and the one problem you can't solve from fiscal and monetary tools
is inflation. And in fact, you have to go the other way. And that's when things get really
bad is when you have to be cutting fiscal spending, when you have to be increasing interest rates
to try to combat inflation. And so I don't know if the inflation comes. I don't know if it ever comes
as someone who thought a lot about risk in their career and very concerned about the downside
should it come. We just don't have a political environment now where tough decisions can get
made. And so what happens if we start seeing high inflation then forces up interest rates
that causes all the repercussions, negative repercussions of that, because we have the
system now so levered with debt at the household level, at the business level, at cities and states,
at the federal level. So what would we do, John? Help me understand that. So right now,
we can get away with printing money because the interest rate that the government pays is very
low. If inflation hits and the interest rate goes up, I mean, as it stands now, the United States
government's debt service is a staggering number. You probably know it. I certainly don't. I try to
block numbers I really, really hate out of my mind, by the way. So I think at one point, I knew
how much the United States paid per day in debt, and I quickly buried it somewhere in, I don't know,
somewhere in my spinal cord. It's not even in my brain anymore. But at some point, as you said,
if inflation hits and interest rates rise, that debt service could overwhelm our GDP, yes?
Yeah, it could. People argue we should do more deficit spending today because interest rates are
low. We can borrow for 10 years at very low rates. The reality is we borrow generally short term,
but even if we put all the borrowing at 10 years or 30 years, we never actually pay off the debt.
It's just accumulating. So as long as GDP is growing faster than real inflation, it's okay,
because in a real basis, it declines. But that's not what happens. Debt's increasing much faster
than real GDP. And so the real debt is increasing, and we never pay it off. And we're not sure whether
the low interest rates are going to be around forever or not. It was 2007 when interest rates
were close to 5%. Just imagine that now if interest rates went back to 5%, what it would do
to stock prices, to businesses who are so levered, to cities and states, to everybody,
to households. If you raise the cost of borrowing. Historically, 5% is not astronomical either.
No, we've certainly seen double digits. And they've got to go back 40 years now. But we've seen
double digit interest rates before in this country. And the decimation that would take place
if that happened again is immense. And so I always think about, I want to help the world. I want
to solve problems. But if the answer is just shovel more money at it, that's not a sustainable
answer in my mind. So everything becomes, how do we improve the system without spending more money?
Or how do we prove the allocation of resources today? And that gets us back to pharma, is that
a dollar spent on pharma, which some portion of that goes to innovation and creates incentive
for innovation. Well, innovation is great. In a world of no trade offs, there's no problem with
that. And if you believe that there are no trade offs with how we spend our resources,
then pharma prices are fine. In fact, double them, triple them, there'll be more incentive
for innovation in that world. But that's not the world that I believe we live in. I believe there
is a trade off and that a dollar put into pharma innovation is a dollar less for everything else.
It could be other healthcare innovation or healthcare services that aren't getting provided
today. Or it could be an education, it could be in making our prisons better, so that there's less
recidivism in all these ways. And somehow the pharma industry has been able to create this
island. Every other industry has to fight for the dollars and try to convince the state and federal
government, give me an extra dollar. Here's why. And the pharma system has just been able to create
this island where they don't have to compete with anybody. They got their own rules. And it's a
messed up set of rules that incentivizes the wrong thing. So even within that, we're not getting
the drugs that we should be getting. We get a lot of marginal oncology drugs that probably
don't provide any real benefit versus the current drugs. And we're not investing in the antibiotics.
We're not investing in vaccines because the financial incentive isn't there for lows.
So we're spending tons of money as a society and not even getting good returns for it. Sorry,
that's my rant. It's very disheartening to see just how low that ROI is. I mean, I think,
again, it comes back to this question of where does the crack finally have to occur?
I love this expression. I don't know who it's attributed to and I'm probably paraphrasing it,
but it's like change happens very slowly and then it happens very quickly. It's like the
stone mason that is banging, banging, banging away on the stone for hours and hours and hours. And
to the outside world, nothing is happening. And then with one more strike, it splits. And I feel
like a lot of your philanthropy is like that. It is years of banging away at something that seems
unchangeable. And there's a belief, there has to be a belief that at some point that
nth strike is going to split that rock. Is this a skill that you, because that seems like the
opposite of trading in some ways. Trading was in a relatively short period of time, you're going to
find out if you were right or wrong. Again, you always had the advantage of being able to adjust
your positions in the presence of new information, but at least you had a feedback loop that was
relatively short. Here, your feedback loop is much longer. Does that pose a challenge for you
emotionally? Absolutely. And you're right that the trading world has that instantaneous feedback
about whether you're right or not. And you used to have the P&L marker up in the corner of the
computer screen that would tell you at every moment in time what the market was telling you
about your position. And a lot of these efforts that were involved in on policy change,
number one, it'd take a long time. And second, as you described, you don't know if you're making
progress often because it feels like you just have the hammer against the wall, have the hammer
against the wall, and driving yourself crazy and wasting money. And then all of a sudden, it happens.
There's a great book I read. It was written by an advocate who was trying to get rid of the don't
ask, don't tell policy in the military and allow gays to openly serve. And this turned out to be
close to a 20-year campaign for him. In the first decade, his wins were so small. His advances in it
was like he was trying to get invited to give a talk at a class at the military academy was a step
forward. And you could see at any given time, he could have spent five years with very little
visible progress and just stopped and said, pushing this rock, I've been hitting the wall,
I'm not making any progress. This is a waste of my time. I should be doing something else
and gone and done something else and not achieve success. But he stuck with it. And the second
decade, he ended up getting the policy reversed and it led the effort. And I think about that story a
lot of it's hard to know, but during that time, like five years in, are we wasting our time and
this is never going to pass, or is the wall going to crack tomorrow? And you just don't have that
feedback mechanism in this work that you had in the market and the complete opposites into the
spectrum. And I guess that's why the research that you do, the time that you take, the amount of
deliberation that goes into your philanthropy at least gives you a greater foundation of confidence.
Interviewed someone by the name of Rick Doblin, who's been singularly focused on the legalization
of MDMA since about 1986. Again, it's staggering to me to think 34 years he has worked on the
exact same problem. And I just had a call with Rick yesterday and I guess I don't know if I'm
going to be careful what I am allowed to say or not say, but I think I can say with some confidence
that he is probably closer than ever to achieving that goal through his organization maps, the
multidisciplinary association for psychedelic studies. And again, I just think that people who
can do what you can do, who can do what Rick Doblin can do, who can do what a lot of great
philanthropists can do. It's not just writing the check. That's amazing. That is unbelievable
to be able to write the check. It's equally amazing to be able to stick on a problem.
Speaking of problems, there's one problem you and I have never discussed, but it seems so up your
alley. I wonder if you have evaluated it and decided it's not worth, you don't have the assets,
you don't have sort of the problem solving asset to go after it, or you think enough people are on
it. But I'm very curious as to what thought you guys have given to climate change. Again,
given your understanding of energy, which is at least a third of the problem, tell me how that's
come across your radar. Yeah, we do a little bit on climate change. I think as a trader and again,
someone who thinks about risk, it's a problem where the downside possibilities are so enormous
that it makes sense as a society for us to make the investments today to try to decrease the
probability of those downside scenarios. I don't know what probability it is of those downside
scenarios that are truly catastrophic from an economic standpoint, from a life standpoint,
that change how humans really live, but it's greater than zero. It's less than 100%. It's
somewhere in there, but the downside is so great that society needs to make that investment.
We typically get drawn to the areas where I'd call them orphan areas, where there's not much
focus, especially philanthropic focus. Things like public pension reform, or changing how
elections are conducted, or the pharmaceutical pricing, or surprise billing. Things where the
day we enter it, we probably have committed the most money of any other philanthropic actor in
the system already. What strikes me about the climate field is that there are remarkable people,
these brilliant people who are working on this today, who are very thoughtful philanthropists
who are working on this today, who oftentimes either make their single issue or one of two
or three issues that they'll be working on. I always think about what's our additionality
into the problem. One of them is that I think because we work with both the left and the right,
and we're not a political organization, and many of those who are both the researchers, the advocates,
the funders in the climate space, do come from the left. I think we can try to support those
efforts, those organizations and politicians that are on the right who want to start taking
the steps, because this has to be a bipartisan effort to solve. It's hard to imagine today
how that happens, but the Republican Party is moving slowly, very slowly, but you start to see
some people with real credibility within the Republican Party, and there are thought highly of,
start to think about there's an acknowledgement that there's a problem. There is dispute about
what level of investment is merited to deal with it, and I think that Democrats don't help
Republicans get there. When you put the whole Democratic platform into a climate change bill,
I don't think it helps Republicans talk about the issue and be a productive partner, and I think
it's going to have to be, again, it has to be bipartisan for it to be sustainable. Perhaps
Democrats win the White House, to perhaps Democrats win the Senate for 2021, they might
take down the filibuster, but what happens when that changes, and do those rules and laws
stay enacted, or do they get repealed? That's why I think all these things that we work on
need to be done in a bipartisan way, including the pharma. We got a bill passed through Senate
Finance Committee, Republicans, Democrats come together, get this close, and we just can't get
it onto the floor. That's where we are. John, your kids are, I'm guessing, they probably don't,
even your oldest probably doesn't remember you being a traitor. Your kids are going to grow up,
and they're going to think of mom and dad's job as philanthropy. What's the impact that that has
on them? I suspect it's pretty profound. They see how seriously their parents think about this stuff.
Do they come to you with questions about the work that you have? Do they have their own interests?
They're obviously not that young anymore, and they're obviously very smart kids. They must be
thinking about, hey, mom and dad, why aren't you guys working on this problem? Or what do you think
about this problem? How does your curiosity for the world trickle down to them, and how deliberate
a part of raising your kids is that? They certainly understand high principles about
what we do. We're philanthropists. They know what that means. They know that we give money,
trying to make the world a better place. But we do have those conversations when we walk past
a homeless individual who's asking for a dollar. My daughter says, we need to give them a dollar.
Having those conversations about, do we give this dollar here, or do we give it to someone trying,
in a more philanthropic or more strategic way to try to get to the root of the problem?
Do we give the dollar here, or do we give it to the food bank down the street that hopefully he
can go to and get the same meal that we would want him to get, or something like that?
Right. It ends up being both. I think you need to teach kids about humanity, about
the love of the individual. We can't say no every time, but also have to teach them about,
you're not going to give all the money away, dollar by dollar, to somebody on the street.
You've thought a lot about, what's the kid's role in this going forward? Laura and I are very much
on the same page here. We don't want their lives to be defined by their parents. We don't want them
working at the foundation. We don't want them, at least when they're in their 20s,
and probably in their 30s, to be working at the foundation if it's still open. We want them
to go have their own life experiences, create their own life. Then after they've done that,
if they want to come join the work here, that's great. It's really important that they're not
part of the foundation at a young age, because there's a downside. Whenever you have that
checkbook, people look at you differently and treat you differently. Your jokes are funnier,
and people have a sense of their own best behavior around you, because there's always
something that they want funded, or that they're involved in, and are going to come with an ask at
some point. We minimize this largely because of the types of things we fund, and we've made it
very clear about what we do fund. But if somebody's growing up in their teens and their 20s, and is
looked at by the rest of the world as a checkbook first, I think that's a very damaging way to grow
up. It's not reality. The 20s is the time when you need to be kissing somebody else's butt.
You need to be going to get the lunches for everybody else, not vice versa. You need to be
trying to climb up to the organization, not be gifted the checkbook on day one.
So what advice would you give to people who were where you were 25 years ago, which is,
they're going to be writing three-figure checks, or maybe a four-figure or a five-figure check,
to an organization. They're not going to be able to set up their own foundation.
They have the same tug that you have, which is, hey, whatever stage of my life I'm at,
whatever my means are at, I know that giving away some of my money makes the world a better place.
I just want to make sure I do it as intelligently as possible.
Yeah. In many ways, what we're doing is not remarkable. So many people in this world,
especially in the United States, are very generous with time, with resources relative to what they
have, relative to the time that they have, relative to the money that they have. So it can just be done
at a different scale, but I think there are some people who are much more altruistic than we are.
There's people who give away 10% of their money when they're making $100,000 or $50,000
that changes their quality of life. There's a sacrifice, a trade-off by doing that, and they
still do it. And there's a small movement called Further Pledge where you pledge to give everything
above a relatively small salary, like $30,000 or maybe up to $50,000 to charity, and knowing that
that dollar you're giving is creating more total good than you spending it. And that's huge. And I
think we as a society benefit when our community around us is stronger. And that's why people do
it. Whenever we have the needs of our family, whenever our family is secure, then I think it's
natural, it's human nature to start thinking about your community and however you define your
community, whether it's your group of friends, your city, your country, might be shared experiences,
but everybody kind of goes through that process of defining his or her own community and then
uses the resources of time and money to try to help that community to the best extent they have.
There's no right answer in how you define your community. There's no right answer as to
how you improve your community. But it is remarkable just this culture of giving and
philanthropy that exists in this nation. I think largely because we are a wealthy nation, right?
Where more people are more secure here, people have more likely to have the needs of their family
set aside or in line of sight. And so they're able to do these things. And that's one of the
reasons that make this country so great. I don't know if I answered your question.
No, you really did actually. I mean, certainly what I took away from that was you pointed out
something that I think doesn't get enough appreciation, which is you're absolutely right.
For you to give away $400 million a year is less, I mean, I'm not minimizing that at all,
but you're right. It's less of a sacrifice than someone who makes $50,000 a year giving away
$5,000. The incremental $5,000 is when making $50,000 is staggering if you're trying to raise
a family or do anything else. And the other thing I took away was this idea of giving locally. I
think the way you define locally is very important. It doesn't mean necessarily if I live in this city,
I only give to this city, I can broaden my definition of local. Local could mean I'm a
veteran and therefore my giving back to veterans affairs or other vets is what I define my community
as. I think that's an elegant way to think about it. I think the other thing that comes with that
is frankly, giving to your community means you can probably make a more informed gift. You have a
better sense of potentially what the needs are of your own community. Absolutely. John, I'm going to
be honest with you, man, we've been talking here for like over two and a half hours. I took a bunch
of notes before we spoke. We haven't got through half what I want to talk about, but I also can't
keep one of the world's busiest philanthropists wasting any more of his time talking with me. So
I'm going to honor my commitment to you to keep this relatively short, not make it a seven hour
discussion. I'm going to let you go. We might have to do a part two at some point, but I want to thank
you very much for first and foremost, just set aside the time today, but more importantly, just for
the work that you do. I know personally how seriously you take this work and the world is
definitely a better place for having the best natural gas trader of all time, no longer trading
natural gas. Thank you. It's been a fun experience. Looking forward to part two. All right. Thanks, John.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of this subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast, typically less
than five minutes that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions,
topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to
this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be
a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not
disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they
should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.