Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of the space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Dr. Tom Despray. His name is probably familiar to some
of you because back in October of 2018, we released a five-part series with Tom and that
set of episodes, despite being quite technical, are some of the most popular episodes we've
released, especially amongst people who really like to get serious about their understanding
of cardiovascular disease. So we wanted to have Tom back basically to pick it up where we left
off. And in this episode, we try to focus on things that have changed in the last couple of years. And
that kind of loosely fell into three categories that we probe. The first is digging really deeper
into the recognition of the importance of atherogenic lipoproteins. So kind of revisiting
the idea of what ApoB is, why it matters. And both Tom and I discuss a little bit about how our views
have changed with respect to the use of ApoB as a laboratory surrogate over LDL-P. And we get into
all of the nuance around that with respect to VLDLs, triglycerides, LpA, et cetera. We also get into
why HDL cholesterol is a far less relevant metric, at least why we believe that to be the case. We
then pivot a little bit and talk about risk assessment. Basically, how do you understand
these metrics? How do you use these metrics? This is a lot of the clinician type stuff here around
ApoB and triglyceride-rich lipoproteins. We again revisit the idea of LpA. And then finally,
we bring it home with some discussion around therapies. And in particular, we talk about
the continued evolution of the PCSK9s, the evolving data around omega-3 fatty acids,
in particular, some of the controversy between EPA alone versus EPA and DHA. And obviously,
we talk about the most recent addition to the lipid drug story, which is a drug called Bembandoic
acid, which has not been around very long. And probably many people are not going to be familiar
with that, but Tom does a great job explaining that. Tom's a diplomat of both the American
Board of Internal Medicine and the American Board of Clinical Lipidology. He practiced internal
medicine in New Jersey for 37 years, the last 17 of which was devoted to consulting patients
with lipid and cardiometabolic disorders. Between 2012 and 2019, he served as the chief scientific
officer at two major cardiovascular biomarker laboratories. Since that time, he has been
working with us in our practice, primarily on the research side of things, but also as a consultant
advising on most of our cardiovascular cases. He's both a fellow of the American College of
Physicians and the National Lipid Association, the NLA. And he's an associate editor at the
Journal of Clinical Lipidology. He was also the recipient of the National Lipid Association 2011
President's Service Award. He's authored and illustrated more manuscripts and book chapters
related to lipids than I can count. And so without further delay, please enjoy my conversation
with my mentor and friend, Tom Dayspring. Hey, Tom, thanks so much for making time to sit down
again and talk about lipids. It's been almost two years since we sat down for what still remains
the longest podcast I've ever done, nearly eight hours, which I believe was divided into a five
part series that is still a very popular podcast series. And don't take this the wrong way, but
I'm kind of surprised at the popularity of that episode, given that I thought it was really
geared only towards people that were really, really diehard lipid fanatics. But it's had
broad enough appeal that I think we've agreed mutually that it makes sense to sit down again.
That was amazing. First of all, it's always great to sit down with you, Peter, and chat about my
little lipid world. But yeah, I'm shocked every time somebody tells me we've listened to the whole
series and I've done it three times and I just can't imagine that. But I'm glad it came across
pretty good. You know, one of the things I wanted to do today, Tom, and I can promise you and all the
listeners, we are not going to do this for another eight hours today. But what I want to do today is
I think kind of pick up the mantle from where we were a couple of years ago and talk about what's
different since then. I think the last two years has seen a number of things that are actually
pretty exciting in the field of lipidology, in the field of cardiovascular disease. Some of it's been
at the really nuanced level scientifically. Others have been, frankly, at the broader level in terms
of recognition of certain things that you've been talking about and many others. People like Alan
Snyderman have been talking about. A lot of this stuff is very clinically relevant. The way I pose
this to you and I think this, unless you're opposed to it, the way I'd love to kind of go through this
is maybe use our time today to talk about things that are different today than perhaps they were a
few years ago and dive into those things in enough depth that everybody from the lay person to the
aficionado will have something to chew on. Yeah, that's a perfect strategy for today. Now,
there's no doubt we'll reiterate some concepts that we went over in great depth back then,
but we won't have that opportunity today. And you know me, Peter, I've always lived on the
cutting edge of lipidology science leading the charge, trying to understand new concepts that
come down. But one of the great satisfactions of my career is much of what I've promulgated for the
longest time has come to fruition. And that's what's really happened in the last two years.
There are certainly some new concepts and some abandonment of some other issues, but it's just
the, you know, my whole mantra for a long time, you know, we've known each other a decade probably,
is that atherogenic lipoproteins are really the issue behind clinical atherosclerotic vascular
disease. And although many of us have known it for a while, the data has just become so overwhelming
that virtually all of the guidelines have signed on to that premise now that atherogenesis is
certainly a sterile mediated disease, but sterols are trafficked within apob containing lipoproteins,
which provides the vehicle that transports them into the artery wall where they can in some start
a pathological process. So it's the recognition of atherogenic lipoproteins that is now in the
guidelines. And you know, atherogenic lipoproteins are still diagnosed using various
cholesterol metrics, but there are things beyond LDL cholesterol matter in the guideline. And even
ApoB is certainly within every of the contemporary guidelines in the last two years. And that's of
course, the Allen Snyderman thing that he's been harping about for a long, long time. So it's
atherogenic lipoproteins within that category, though, the things that are also emerging is
what contributes to the atherogenicity of an ApoB particle triglycerides has really taken
center stage, how they affect lipoprotein concentration and quality or functionality,
whatever adjective you want to ascribe to. It's the loss of the ability of at least the HDL
cholesterol metric to be terribly informative to us. And it's the emerging significance for a lot
of reasons of lipoprotein little a. So those are the big areas where changes really become important
and is really useful at the bedside. Of course, pharmacology and intensity of pharmacology
has also advanced and we'll touch a little bit on that today, I'm sure.
To sort of summarize that, we're going to talk about kind of double clicking on ApoB
slash LDL particle, basically the atherogenic lipoproteins front and center in the pathogenesis
of cardiovascular disease. We're going to talk about the modification of our risk assessment.
And I like that you brought up HDL because I want to have a pretty interesting discussion about that.
And obviously, we're going to talk about what's happened in therapies. There have been actually
quite a number of things, including the continuation, more data around zetimibe and
PCSK9 inhibitors, much more data since we last spoke around omega-3 fatty acids. I spoke with
Bill Harris about that, but I think we can go a little bit further. And there are a couple of
other therapies. So let's start with maybe a little bit of a reminder for people as to what
ApoB is. People like you and I sometimes use ApoB and LDLP interchangeably as shorthand.
That's not entirely correct. And when we last spoke, we probably disproportionately spoke about
the number of LDL particles. And now we're going to focus on ApoB. So do you mind explaining
what the difference is both from a biology standpoint, but also from a laboratory standpoint?
And those are critical points, Peter, because it's one thing to talk about ApoB,
but almost what you're saying about it depends how did you analyze it? What laboratory metric
did you order that you think is telling you something about ApoB, whatever that encompasses?
So to make a story very simple and short, lipids go nowhere in aqueous plasma because they're
hydrophobic. So for a lipid to be trafficked throughout plasma, it has to attach to a protein.
Now, a few molecules of any lipid can attach to albumin, but that's not the primary way lipids
get anywhere. Serious collections of lipids, hydrophobic substances, attach to fairly significant
proteins which solubilize them. And these Apo proteins, as they're called, proteins that wrap
collections of lipids, provide structure and stability to this macromolecule that we're going
to call a lipoprotein. So the main structural protein that enwraps lipids in our body is
ApoLipoprotein B. It's a 500 kilo Dalton molecular weight protein, so it's pretty big,
and it has a great ability to attract a lot of lipids to bind to it. But once the lipids are
bound to it, this is a water soluble lipid transportation vehicle. There's basically one
other class of lipoproteins, and that is the HDL particles that you mentioned, and they have
no ApoB on them. Their structural protein is ApoLipoprotein A1, capital A dash either Arabic
or Roman number one. So right away we have a double classification of lipoproteins, the ApoB
containing, they're often called beta lipoproteins, or the ApoA1 are called the alpha lipoproteins.
So now within that ApoB family, it always gets a little more complex in lipidology. The two tissues
in your body that can make ApoB are the liver, hepatocytes, and of course the small intestine,
which is absorbing a lot of lipids, so it has to put them in something if those lipids are going
to get into your plasma. So the ApoB that's made in the liver is a big 500 kilo Dalton protein that
I mentioned, and it's called ApoB100. Now why do they add the 100 on it? Because the intestine
also produces ApoB, but it produces a truncated version that has 48% of the molecular weight of
the hepatic-produced ApoB. So that's called ApoB48. So if the liver makes an ApoB particle full of
lipids, it's got one molecule of ApoB100 on it, if the intestine makes a big lipoprotein, and it
does, they're called chylomicrons, that has one molecule of ApoB48. The intestine can put it in
your lymphatics, it enters the systemic circulation, the liver just secretes it directly. So those are
the two types of ApoB. We're not going to talk a lot about chylomicrons. They're in most people
without a pathological, genetic pathological issue. It's not your chylomicrons that are the major
problem here. They're a postprandial lipoprotein. So the liver makes these ApoB100 particles,
and they can go out, the liver can secrete them, but some of the particles that the liver secretes
can be catabolized into smaller and smaller versions, even though they're still ApoB proteins.
So if we're going to talk about the ApoB100 family, and I'm probably not going to use the term 100
anymore, we're talking about very low density lipoproteins, intermediate density lipoproteins,
and low density lipoproteins. And of course, part of the LDL family is lipoprotein little a,
if you happen to produce that, not everybody does, to significant amounts. The names of those
particles, as you know, they were originally discovered via ultracentafagation. So the ones
that floated on top of the tube with a very low density, the ones that sank to the bottom,
were the high density, and the in between were the IDLs and LDLs. Now, so the ApoB family is VLDLs
plus IDLs plus LDLs plus LP little a, if you have it. Well, that's true. But here's the reality.
We have to look at plasma residence times. How long do these things float around? How long are
they in your system? Because that's important, because these are the particles that have the
potential to crash your artery wall and traffic stirrulls and whatever else into the artery wall.
The chylomarkrons I mentioned are half-life is in minutes. They're plasma residence time a few
hours. The VLDL particles, their half-life is two to four to six hours, depending on how rapidly
they're catabolized. The IDL particles are a transient in between particle between a VLDL
and an LDL. They're around for an hour or two. They're not, other than an unusual genetic
condition, a player in this ApoB game we're talking about. And finally, we have the LDL family.
Now, LDLs have a plasma residence time of two to five days. And there are other attributes to the
LDL that determines, is it going to just hang around for two days or five days? Clearly,
the longer it hangs around, you're going to have a lot more LDL particles than if you could rapidly
clear them. So when we talk about whatever ApoB metric you're doing, technically you are measuring
VLDLs, their remnants, their smaller VLDLs, IDLs plus LDLs plus LP little a, but because of the
half-life, 90 to 95% of your ApoB particles are LDL particles. So that's why many people say,
hey, ApoB is just another way of getting an LDL particle count. And that's true. Even in people
who might have a lot of remnants, the remnant particle number is quite small. It is still way
more LDL particles floating around in these people who might have these random VLDLs that cause issue.
Not to say a VLDL remnant might not be a very injurious ApoB containing particle. It certainly
is in some people, but if we're looking at the number, which is the primary driving force as to
how an ApoB particle enters the artery wall, LDL is king. And that's why our metrics of ApoB or LDL
particle count are what are at the top of all the guidelines. And of course the metric most people
use are LDL cholesterol and non-HDL cholesterol. I mean, Tom, on a personal level, the reason I
have switched to ApoB in our practice, which is obviously heavily influenced by the work that
you've discussed, the work that people like Alan Snyderman have been doing for many years, frankly,
comes down to a consistency factor. So we had historically relied on LDL-P, LDL particle number,
as a concentration count. But frankly, in the span of eight years, went through three
technologies to do that, right? Two generations of NMR coupled with electrophoresis. And while in
the end we felt the electrophoresis provided the most accurate measurement, you always have a
problem when you don't know what you're comparing it to. So if we have Gen 1 NMR, which is probably
still being used by LabCorp and Quest today, that is probably quite inaccurate compared to Gen 2 NMR,
but the percentiles, meaning the populations of people that were measured, are still what we use
to understand where someone lies. It puts you in a bit of a dilemma. As a clinician or as a patient,
you want to continually upgrade your technology. In other words, if you're talking about getting a
new iPhone, you don't really care that your phone is so much better than two generations ago's phone,
because all your metrics are better and there's nothing to be gained by comparing yourself to
how much better you are. But when you're talking about diagnostics, it does matter where your
reference range is and if you're moving it. So do you agree with my logic for switching to APO-B
a year ago as now being a much more homogeneous way to assess patients even across labs? So
especially now in light of COVID, we can't always use the same lab to measure APO-B. So I might be
sending a patient to one lab versus another lab and I just feel like we're getting better results
this way. Does that jive with you? No, that makes total sense. And a real important take-home point
for listeners is pick your favorite metric. Peter's right now is APO-B, mine right now is APO-B,
and stick with it. Don't do APO-B this time in an LDL particle count via NMR. Peter didn't even
mention Quest has a particle number technique called ion mobility transfer that people are,
they're not comparable. All biomarkers you should consistently try and use, of course the same lab,
not always possible, but the same assay. And the APO-B immunoassay is pretty standard throughout
the industry. It's not like everybody's got their own APO-B assay. The NMR can vary widely. The
other big reason to do that, consistency of results over time, is sooner or later yourself,
you're going to read the guideline or maybe your patients are going to go, all the guidelines talk
about APO-B. There is no guideline telling you to do a NMR LDL-P or an ion mobility LDL-P. So it's
another reason to just stick with the APO-B. And I think there are less false positives with the
APO-B. It's just been my personal experience. I've been an NMR guy all my life and as we got better
and better, we just so often saw totally unexplainable discordance between LDL-P and APO-B.
That that is overwhelming for APO-B. So I think that's where you should be in today's world,
as your marker of atherogenic lipoproteins. Yeah, I think we saw that, especially with the
second generation NMR. It was almost like it had become too sensitive. We were seeing discordance
that far exceeded what the Framingham or Mesa data predicted the discordance should have been.
And that's really actually what took us to the ion mobility assay. But again, I'm actually very,
from a diagnostic and management standpoint, I'm actually quite comfortable with where we are.
I think the final point I'd add to that, Tom, is just the economic one. Frankly, I think the cost
of an APO-B is, at least in Canada. And the only reason I know that is because Alan Snyderman is at
McGill and he's been pounding this for a while. I mean, we're talking about a three or four dollar
test. So there is no excuse for any physician to say, we're not going to order your fancy APO-B
because it costs too much. I'm going to order the LDL cholesterol. I think that excuse has lost
all of its water. It's so true. And Alan just published a beautiful paper where he's researched
the cost of APO-B assays, because, you know, even some of the people in the guidelines always,
oh, we can't say APO-B, it's so expensive. That's an old excuse that is no longer applicable to 2020.
So of all the technologies to quantitate atherogenic lipoproteins, APO-B is the most
affordable. And even, you know, look, labs sometimes change crazy. But if you tell a lab
you want to pay a cash price, it's really pretty cheap. Yeah. Let's go back to kind of the macro
point here around APO-B, which is a greater coalescing around the idea that APO-B concentration
matters. So I think it's very well understood that two of the biggest risk factors for cardiovascular
disease are smoking and hypertension. I don't think there is any ambiguity that cigarette
smoking and high blood pressure increase the risk of cardiovascular disease. And they both appear to
do so through a mechanism that weakens the endothelium or creates an injury to the endothelium.
The question now becomes, as you put it, Tom, how ironclad is the story that it's the APO-B bearing
particle in the presence of injured endothelium that is the Trojan horse that begins this
destructive trajectory of taking that cholesterol into the subendithelial space, becoming retained,
undergoing this chemical oxidation process, which then kicks off an inflammatory response
that paradoxically, as an attempt to repair the damage, results in what can be a fatal injury.
There are other hypotheses, for example, there are people who note, and we have, I mean, look,
I have a patient in our practice, Tom, you've weighed in on her case, walks around with a
total cholesterol of 300 and something, an LDL cholesterol of 220 milligrams per deciliter,
an APO-B of 170 milligrams per deciliter. She's in her late 60s and her coronary artery calcium
score is zero. We have elected to not treat her with any lipid lowering therapy. In other words,
there are exceptions to this. How do we reconcile that? Well, it's the human body in medicine. As you
know, not all smokers are going to come down with lung cancer or chronic obstructive lung disease.
Why not? If that's such a horrible risk factor. I try to explain this, and I've certainly seen
cases like you say where, oh my God, if I was just going to say, give me your APO-B or whatever
cholesterol metric, you're going on three drugs right now, you got no choice. And maybe the old
days we approach people that way, but no more. I think you have to individualize your whatever
risk factors you discover that might wind up causing atherogenesis and then figure it out.
So particle number is certainly a major factor that might force it in, but not always. Endothelial
function, although you can certainly, if you review the history of this and how do you really
determine endothelial function, not everybody has serious endothelial dysfunction who winds up with
atherosclerosis. So particle number itself, and some people can just make the particles go in.
I think if we take most adults who's not going to have a little bit of endothelial dysfunction, so
I agree with you, it's a combination of something about atherogenic particles, be it their number,
endothelial dysfunction. But I'm talking more and more now when I discuss any type of lipoprotein,
I don't care which subgroup you want to talk about. I think we certainly have to know it's
particle concentration, but I like to talk about particle quality. So what are the other attributes
of any lipoprotein that might contribute to its atherogenicity or in some perhaps not understood
make it relatively, it's not going to generate atherosclerosis. And there certainly have to be
things like that going on. So as we're getting smarter, we're looking at other components of
the lipoproteins that could be other proteins that are on them that could be their complex
lipidome. And trying to see, aha, can that help us discern whether in you, a given particle
concentration is more worrisome than it is in the next person. So there's a lot going on. And also,
from the gist of this conversation, listeners will know atherosclerosis, atherogenesis is a
multi complex, multi factorial disease. And that's why even when Peter and I, if we consult on a case
and we realize in this person, we have to beat up Apo B and get their particle numbers to a more
physiologic range, we don't stop once we do that. We examine in great detail for other things that
might be injuring the endothelium or the arterial wall and see are any of those treatable or so.
So we're getting a little bit smarter on lipoproteins, but there certainly is more to it than just
particle number. Do we think that there's a limit to where the benefit of reduction
becomes diminishing or even J curves in the other direction? So we discussed it in the first episode
significantly. We did so again with Ron Krauss. It wouldn't be the worst idea in the world a couple
of years from now to sit down and do it again and reexamine the data. But again, I think the causal
relationship between Apo B and atherosclerosis is as strong as virtually anything we see in medicine
for which you can't do the perfect experiment where you have to rely on natural experiments.
Nevertheless, maybe it's not entirely clear what the dose response looks like. So if you have
somebody whose Apo B is 160 milligrams per deciliter, there's a risk reduction that comes
to lowering it from 160 to 100 and lowering it from 100 to 80 and lowering it from 80 to 60.
What do we know about the risk reduction in lowering it, say from 60 to 40 to 20? And I ask
both what we could infer pharmacologically and non-pharmacologically. In other words,
from the Mendelian randomization versus the pharmacologic. Well, even using pharmacologic
trials and Mendelian randomization, the concept you're going to come across with is lower is
better. And with the pharmacologic thing, we're modulating things that either have clinical trial
proof that if you lower them, it's good or the Mendelian randomization, looking at genes where
that drug might be doing something, it works. Now you do need a few Apo B containing lipoproteins.
They do traffic other lipids. They traffic fat-soluble lipoproteins. But we must never
confuse A-beta lipoproteinemia where nobody, or that person can't make them, or hypo-beta
lipoproteinemia where they make a few enough to traffic those other things that a lipoprotein
might have to traffic. But even the guidelines where they examine people looking at their baseline
Apo B or LDL cholesterol, the first thing they suggest, at least in the higher risk people,
is try and get a 50% reduction. And that's where most of the bang for the buck is going to be.
Now, if you still have options that you can lower it further, yeah, the trials show, yeah,
there is incremental reduction events, but it's a much smaller absolute risk reduction and dropping
it the 50% or so. So I don't know if that answers your question. So most people don't have the type
of levels where with modern therapeutics, with modern lifestyle, we can more often than not attain
physiologic concentrations. And if I want to talk about Apo B, that's probably under 50 milligrams
per deciliter, if we can get there. That's what the newborns have. That's when you go in clinical
trials, if you take it down that low, you see your most risk reduction. And so far, at least with
pharmacologic lowering of Apo B with the currently FDA approved drugs, there is no signal of harm.
Yeah, again, it's funny because I was just about to say with the current crop of drugs,
specifically the PCSK9 inhibitors, we are routinely seeing patients who easily can get an Apo B into
the 20 to 40 milligram per deciliter range. You and I actually sat down a couple of months ago
and did a calculation to estimate how much cholesterol is actually contained in the
circulating lipoproteins versus that which is in cell membranes. Do you remember doing this with me?
Not per se, but and where we're developing equations, you're the master of that.
Well, it was one of these things, right? It was sort of like, look, when you look at a person's
plasma glucose level, you realize pretty quickly it represents a tiny fraction of total body glucose.
And similarly, there's such a concern about plasma cholesterol level, but, you know,
given how essential cholesterol is, it's understandable why people would be concerned
that low cholesterol could be problematic. But once you do the calculation and realize
virtually all of the cholesterol in the body is contained within the cell membrane or within the
steroidal producing tissue, the circulating amount is a very narrow window into the total
amount of cholesterol and therefore a reduction of say 60 milligrams per deciliter to 50 milligrams
per deciliter of ApoB or even something more extreme like a full 50% reduction of total
cholesterol, 200 milligrams per deciliter to 100 milligrams per deciliter does not represent
a significant reduction in total body cholesterol. This is a very important point,
right? Let me repeat it. You have a total body cholesterol that you measure in the plasma that
says, oh, it's 200 milligrams per deciliter. That goes down to 100 milligrams per deciliter. Let's
say the LDL fraction reduced from, you know, 150 to 75 or something. Someone might say, God,
you just cut cholesterol in half. That can't be good for you given the importance of cholesterol.
But my point is no, you simply cut the amount of cholesterol being carried by the lipoproteins in
the plasma in half. That doesn't capture the majority of the cholesterol. Yes. Thanks for
refreshing my memory. What you're talking about now, it's really pools of cholesterol throughout
the body. And I think I'm so glad you brought this up because this is just not even understood,
even in the lipidology community. We have a total body cholesterol. There are basically three pools.
There's your brain and nothing we're talking about today has anything to do with brain
cholesterol. It's a separate system. It doesn't interact with the other cells in your body or
certainly with the cholesterol in your plasma. So if it's not in your brain, where is cholesterol
in your body? Well, it's either in all your peripheral cells, perhaps some more than others,
or it's circulating in your plasma. And if it's in the plasma, where is it? There's an
easy weensie amount bound to albumin. There's more bound within all of the lipoproteins that
are trafficking in your body, meaning your ApoB and your ApoA1 particles. But believe it or not,
if I wanted to search down blood cholesterol for you, I would suck out your red blood cells and
extract cholesterol from them. Red blood cells carry far, far more cholesterol than do all of
your lipoproteins put together. And the other crucial point you made subtly, and I hope everybody
understood you, the amount of cholesterol within your lipoproteins has no correlation with your
cellular cholesterol or even your red blood cell cholesterol. So whatever, however you're
modulating some LDL, total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol metric, that tells you nothing about
what might you be doing to the cholesterol content of your cells. So don't have a panic attack if
you're making LDL cholesterol 30, because I can assure you virtually every cell in your body,
even if that's your plasma LDL cholesterol, has more than enough cholesterol because it can
de novo synthesize it, it can put it in its cell membranes or other organelles that require
cholesterol. If it's a storogenic tissue, it can produce a little more or perhaps dilipidate some
life. So there's no cell that's being deprived of cholesterol in the periphery when you are
modulating lipids through lifestyle or drugs. Tom, what's the best explanation for why it's
not the red blood cell that is the primary driver of atherosclerosis given the fact you just stated,
which is red blood cells contain within them a lot of cholesterol within their membranes and
red blood cells clearly traffic to and from past the endothelium. I certainly have my own answer
for this question. I think the histology makes it abundantly clear. But is there any thought you
would add to that? No, I think histologically, we know it's foam cells. And where do foam cells get
their sterile content from ingesting oxidized lipoproteins carrying cholesterol is the vasovisorum,
which supplies the arterial intimate with blood cells dumping red blood cells in there that are
contributing cholesterol, maybe a few molecules, but I don't think we have any evidence. It's that's
a driver of cholesterol that's resulting in arterial wall pathology. Yeah, this is one of
those moments where sometimes a picture just serves a thousand words. And maybe this will be
one of the best. I mean, we're going to obviously accompany this podcast with a
a lot of figures and diagrams of yours. But what we're basically talking about is you have to
differentiate from the vasovisorum side, which is the non-luminal side of the vessel, where of course
you have to have blood vessels to keep the artery itself alive versus the luminal side, where the
endothelial lining is damaged by everything, including just daily life, but certainly high
blood pressure, smoking, uric acid, high glucose, high insulin, shear forces, you name it. And that's
what's allowing these lipoproteins in. But you're right, it's really this histologic examination that
makes a very clear, unmistakable case that it's not the cholesterol in the membrane that's doing
this. It's this trafficked cholesterol that ultimately becomes a foam cell through the
macrophages ingestion of the lipoprotein that is the insult. That's a pretty good tour de force
on this topic. One more little caveat, Peter, with that vasovisorum, as you know, as you have
an evolving plaque, it gets bigger and bigger and it becomes prone to erosion or rupture
and the coagulation system. So there's nothing to say that even in a minuscule histologic rupture
of a plaque that the vasovisorum can't be contributing some clotting factors or something
else to that pathological process. It almost assuredly does. At some point, once you have
damage, I would fully expect coagulation factors to be coming from both sides, the luminal side
and the vasovisorum side. It's an all hands on deck war. And the uric acid too, probably,
you know, which can crystallize just like cholesterol. You touched on it in the
outset, which is what have the guidelines stated with respect to other lipoproteins? So if we take
a step back and we went back to the early 1980s, right, in the early 1980s, when we were just
beginning to talk about the subfractionation of cholesterol. So little history lesson for people.
It's 1959-ish, early 1960s. Ansel Keys is clearly on to something and he is identifying a relationship
between serum cholesterol and coronary artery disease. He's correctly identifying a relationship.
And at the time, they're doing very rudimentary assessments saying, hey,
if you take the people who are in the top 10% of serum cholesterol and you compare them to the
people in the bottom 10% of serum total cholesterol, there's a profound difference in atherosclerosis.
Most people are not familiar with how that history went and, you know, where it got
taken off the rails a little bit by what might be the root cause of those things. But nevertheless,
it was pretty clear into the 1960s and 70s that something about serum cholesterol mattered.
Eventually, people began to, as you pointed out, Tom, begin to fractionate those things. So it
wasn't just about total cholesterol. It became about different densities of those
cholesterol. And these lipoproteins, some of them were lighter, some of them were heavier and really
light and heavier, the wrong words. They had different densities. But one that emerged pretty
quickly as a contrast to the low density lipoprotein was the high density lipoprotein.
And through all of the epidemiologic work that emerged in the late 70s and into the early 80s,
and that also, by the way, continued into the 90s through the work of Jerry Reven,
as he was in the early stages of identifying what would be called metabolic syndrome at the time
called syndrome X, it became clear that higher levels of cholesterol in the HDL particle,
which unfortunately is erroneously often referred to as high good cholesterol, had a positive
association, the opposite of what we have just been describing, which is high levels of cholesterol
in the LDL particle. There's a lot less talk of that today, at least amongst the people who know
what they're talking about. Unfortunately, there's still a lot of people who talk about that in
social media. But why is it that we aren't sitting here in the guidelines talking about HDL
cholesterol, the so-called quote unquote, I hate to use this word, good cholesterol.
And you know, I'm in your corner. I'm that one. Folks, there's one cholesterol molecule. I don't
care whether it's in your cell, whether it's in any lipoprotein in your brain. If I drew you the
structure of cholesterol, it's identical. So how dare we put an adjective on it like that's good.
And that's bad. How do you know? So you don't. So they're silly terms, but they,
they sort of evolved for a good reason. And this is a wonderful historical journey that you really
have to do to figure out why did HDL have like such importance? And now it's an afterthought.
Although it's an afterthought, I must say virtually all of the current risk algorithms that are used
to classify you as are you at high, very high, moderate or low risk still use the metric HDL
cholesterol to determine that because the data is just 40, 50 years old. The problem with HDL
cholesterol as a metric is all those studies that seems to suggest a higher is better or lower is
worse, we're never adjusted for anything else. So, you know, observational type data. Aha. I found
the answer. Here it is. You got blue eyes and everybody with blue eyes gets this, that, or whatever.
And of course you never adjusted for, oh, wait a minute. Everybody with the blue eyes has this
lethal thing going on also. So in retrospect, it turns out that the overwhelming majority of people
who might have low HDL cholesterol have a high APL B level. And that's what drives their atherosclerosis.
So all guidelines, even though they might do your baseline risk using an APL B metric like total or
LDL cholesterol, they'll use HDL cholesterol as trying to figure out the lipid component to your
wrist. They use smoking and blood pressure and other things Peter talked about also. When they
get to goals of therapy, though, only because we have multiple trials now where for decades people
have been trying this, that and everything to raise HDL cholesterol, because if high is better
than low raising, it has to be fantastic. And not a single trial has ever panned out that what you
do to HDL cholesterol results in cardiovascular benefit. Let's pause there for one sec, Tom,
and just make sure people understand that there have been multiple trials using at least two,
maybe more technical approaches to raise that number that is unambiguously associated with
better outcomes. Is that correct? No, there are no clinical trials that would support raising. No,
no, no, no, no. I'm sorry. There have been multiple clinical trials that have attempted to
raise HDL cholesterol. That's true. Yes. And it's more than two drugs. There are other drugs that.
Yeah, I think more than two mechanisms of action. Correct. At least two that I can think of. There
might be, there's probably three mechanisms of action that have been, that would all raise HDL
cholesterol. But the point that you made that is, should not be lost on anyone is at best those
trials have been neutral. As have the Mendelian randomization trials looking at genetics,
surrogates of HDL and cardiovascular outcomes. Yes. And at worst, those trials have been harmful.
Yeah, there are plenty of people and you know them. You've seen them in your practice. Certainly
I have when I was practicing with high HDL cholesterol who are full of plaque. And we
do see people with low HDL cholesterol who just like you said, you see some people with high LDL
or total cholesterol don't have plaque. There are plenty of people with low HDL cholesterol who,
my God, you don't seem to have much cardiovascular risk. So there has to be,
if HDLs are important to the cardiovascular system and I maintain they are, the metric HDL
cholesterol is useless. Yeah. And this is really where I think I want to go with this. And just,
I mean, there's so much we could say on this, but I think it's worth maybe even just explaining
this very important point, right? Which is HDL cholesterol, the number that everybody sees when
they look at their lipid panel, that if it's below 40 milligrams per deciliter is probably flagged as
being too low. If it's above 70, your doctor gives you a high five that is measuring the
concentration of cholesterol within an HDL particle. Now it doesn't tell you anything
about the functionality of that particle. And this is where I think, I don't remember if it
was Ron Kraus that said this, but someone said this to me and I've never forgotten it. It might
have been Alan actually. They said, this LDL biology stuff is trivial. All you got to do is lower it.
It's the HDL biology that is really complicated. That's what the 21st century is going to be about.
We don't have a clue what we're talking about with HDL. We've been using this idiotic crude
metric of how much cholesterol it contains. It is now completely clear that that was the wrong
metric. Then any attempts to increase it were futile. We've count the number of particles.
We can even measure the size of them. That also appears to be almost as crude as what the
cholesterol concentration is. But to come up with an assay that truly measures functionality may be
beyond the scope of laboratories. Whereas with the APOBL side of the equation, it really appears
to be a stochastic problem. The more of these things you have to the first order, the more
problems you have, you've already alluded to other attachments to them that can add second and third
order terms. But I mean, do you agree with my assessment, Tom, that this HDL problem is way
harder and we don't have a clue what we're talking about? It's just so perfect what you've just said
in the last few minutes. We all use laboratory metrics to try and figure out what a given
biomarker tells us and what we can do about it. The only metric that's really available to the
world world now is HDL cholesterol, which Peter says that's the collective cholesterol mass within
all the HDLs that exist in a deciliter of your plasma. If you are doing ion mobility or NMRs,
you can get an HDL particle count. But that although it might be a tad better than HDL
cholesterol telling you something, there's so many exceptions to that rule that it's not a useful
bedside metric either. But presuming again, HDLs must perform some function in the human body.
And part of that function might be either preventing or putting out arterial wall
plaque fires that have many etiologies. How can we measure what Peter referred to as the
functionality of the HDL particle? Being a fireman's son, if you listened to that last podcast, I look
at HDLs as fire engines. But I know any fire department has about 10 different types of
different fire trucks. And they all supply something different that fire flutters can use
to extinguish a fire. Some might carry chemicals, some might carry ladders, axes, water, some carry
more firemen than others. So what type of fire truck do you need at a given scene? Well, it depends
what the heck the scene is all about. So what do HDLs do? They certainly traffic some degree of
cholesterol, which it turns out is probably just there for stoichiometric reasons, making a spherical
particle to which other things can attach. The other things that are in that HDL, remember, HDLs
are tiny, so they don't carry a lot of cholesterol. Here's a stat that will astound a lot of people.
If I took the average HDL particle, the average size HDL particle out of your plasma, how many
molecules of cholesterol would be inside of it? About 45. How many molecules are in the average
size LDL particle? About 1,500, 2,000. So the volume of a spear is the third power of the radius.
What might influence even the cholesterol content of 45 cholesterol molecules within an HDL? Well,
it's a spear. There's only so much can go in there. What if that HDL was carrying extra triglycerides
for whatever reason? Well, it couldn't carry very many cholesterol molecules. So that would be a
cholesterol depleted HDL. What if that HDL, if I had five groups of HDL particles, same size, same
cholesterol content, but they all had different phospholipids on their surface lipidome, or they
all were trafficking different proteins. They all have APOA1, but what else are they carrying? And
those proteins have a multitude of functions. Dan Rader years ago always told me, Tom, HDLs are part
of the innate immune system. They're little fire engines. They're carrying, God knows what, that
could go into wherever there's inflammation in your body, a swollen knee, any in-tissue injury,
or your arterial wall. And they could maybe help what's going on there because they're trafficking
immunomodulatory functionality molecules, or they could go in because, oh my God,
these are corrupt HDLs. They're carrying bad junk, which is further inflaming it. We have no way
of measuring those now. I mean, researchers can do lipidome analysis of the phospholipids,
the sphingolipids, the ceramides that are in HDLs. We can, you know, they've identified over 150
different proteins that might be on an HDL. Now, they're not all on one given HDL, but some HDLs
may have two of this protein, none of that. And you have different groups of HDLs. In my analysis,
there are different types of fire engines carrying different things. Peter, in our lifetime, there
will never be an affordable, reproducible, high throughput way of evaluating anything.
People are hanging their hats now on the ability of HDLs to efflux cholesterol from a cell. And,
hey, if an HDL can suck some sterols out of your foam cells, yeah, I'm kind of thinking that's
pretty good, but it's probably a minuscule function of the hundred other functions that HDLs
can do. So what if the HDL is pulling out some cholesterol, but it's dumping other crap in the
process? So if we ever had an HDL function panel, it's going to be a dozen or more type tests,
which we're not going to see because nobody's going to pay for them. The research to be done
to prove that these have relevance in a large clinical trial is just not going to be done.
So that's the dilemma. There are such panels, right? I mean, I think, I feel like I've seen
a couple of commercial panels that attempt to subdivide the HDL particles even further. I've
never personally been able to know what to do with such panels. And I, you know, these days,
I don't even look at APO A1 anymore. I'm really focusing most of my efforts on
VLDL cholesterol as a poor man's proxy for remnant triglyceride, basically as a strategy
for how to lower APO B, APO B, LP little a, and then focusing just frankly much more on the
metabolic stuff that we've talked about, the obviously glucose, insulin, homocysteine,
uric acid, much more aggressive stance on blood pressure. But in some ways, my lipid world has
become a little bit easier in light of this discussion we're having. It is because you've
got the ability based on analysis and understanding of things to not order the silly hocus pocus HDL
panels that are being offered by people as a way to generate revenue. Now look, I've been associated
with labs all my life. I'm not at the present time. I don't work for any lab that does or doesn't do
any of these tests you're talking about. But mostly those panels that you look at,
they're looking, they're reporting HDL size, they're reporting APO A1. Peter knows there can be from
one to five molecules on APO A1 on your various HDL species. So you have just a few HDLs carrying
a lot of APO A1 or do you have a ton of HDLs that carrying little APO A1 and that could be a
misleading metric. People are looking at some of these phospholipids now. Some labs are offering
ceramide levels or shingosine levels. But again, you can find something that might support that,
but then you have to weigh it against the APO B and the things that are almost beyond discussion.
And you would realize this is contributing nothing to me. Why am I even ordering this? Am I trying
to impress some patient that I can use big words and this means anything? So they're silly. I'm in
awe for doing research on HDL functionality and looking into it so we all get a better comprehension
of it. I'd love to have a test that tells us what I talk about the flux of HDL particles,
how do little e-C-Ween-C HDLs mature, fill up, then what do they do with that cholesterol,
and are they catabolized? Are they not catabolized? Are your HDLs pulling cholesterol out of an artery
wall and then sharing it with an LDL that might take it right back into the artery wall? So there's
just so many phenomenal issues to get into with HDL, but right now don't waste your money. You're
going to get an HDL cholesterol. Everybody's going to be doing a lipid panel. Do not waste your money,
time, or your brain energy on trying to figure out these HDL metrics.
So let's at that junction pivot now to more of the risk assessment stuff.
We have talked probably on at least two podcasts about LPa. You and I spoke about it during our
marathon podcast. I think we had an AMA segment where Bob Kaplan asked me a lot of questions
about LPa. It's still on my list of things to do. I'd love to have Sam Tomikas on the podcast.
For people who don't know, Sam is certainly among close to the world's experts on LPa.
And I think, frankly, a dedicated podcast on this topic is warranted, given that directionally one
in 10 people listening to this podcast has an elevated LPa. And it represents, unless you
correct me, Tom, I believe it would represent the single greatest genetic driver of atherosclerosis.
So here we have this thing called LPa that tragically most people don't know they have.
I'll tell you a funny story. Have you ever heard of this reality TV show called Alone?
No.
I don't think I've watched TV in 12 years, but it now shows up on Netflix. And I do watch Netflix
from time to time. So a friend of mine mentioned to me the other day, he goes, you got to check out
this show called Alone. It's right up your alley. They take these people who have remarkable
survival skills and they throw them out in the world's worst environment, 10 of them,
separately, of course. And basically the person who last calls uncle wins half a million bucks.
So I'm into season six right now, which is, it's the first one I've watched, but it's clearly into
a really nasty part of the Arctic. So I'm watching this and I'm just humbled by the fact that these
people can survive any length of time. Anyway, one of the guys in the show, you know, you learn
their backstory and he's, this guy looks as impressive as anybody I've ever seen, but somehow
it comes up that part of his motivation for doing this is he had a heart attack like the year before.
And I think he's 39 on the show implying that he had his heart attack at the age of 38 or thereabouts.
Now, if you looked at this guy, Tom, you wouldn't think this is the kind of guy that could have a
heart attack. I mean, he looks, he is a specimen. And of course, what's the first thing that comes
to my mind? Well, I've seen this story play out 50,000 times, right? I mean, my wife's grandfather
died at 40. He was a firefighter, fit as if it'll drop dead of a heart attack at 47 in my mom's dad's
arms when he was 16. So I know the story very well. And it's, to me, it's LP little a until proven
otherwise on a hot O'Connor wrote a great story about this in the New York time several years ago,
disclosing that he himself found he's a carrier of LP little a. So always want to make sure
everybody stops, reevaluates, make sure that they aren't a high LP little a carrier. What else is on
our list of real risk assessment here? And by the way, feel free to just pile on to more LP little
a stuff because this to me is, I mean, this, this is interesting stuff. And I do think unlike my
pessimism around HDL, where I don't think we're going to learn a whole heck of a lot about it,
I think we're just scratching the surface of differentiating between really aggressive LP
little a's versus not as aggressive LP little a's. And I'm optimistic there. Well, you're right. And
of course, on the favor of LP little a be in dangerous is the a bunch of Mendelian randomization
trials, which don't exist for any HDL metric or so. So right away, it's a, a marker that requires
more serious evaluation or so you want to remind people again what it is. I guess I glossed over
that. Yeah, sure. For those new to this low density lipoprotein is a collection of cholesterol,
triglycerides, fossil lipids wrapped by a single molecule of a polipro protein B, because of the
size and density, it falls within a certain fraction of their centrifuge tube and it's called
low density. But all lipoprotein subclasses are heterogeneous. They consist of big particles,
small particles, or maybe a particle carrying something else that doesn't really change its
density that much. So it separates with the LDLs and LP little a is basically you have your LDL
part of this macromolecule. But co attached to the Apo B structural protein is another protein
that shouldn't be there. And it's called apoprotein little a and by little a we mean small case, not a
capital A. And that molecule that attaches Apo A, you know, can vary in molecular weight, size,
length, etc. But that's beyond this discussion. So it's an LDL, it's carrying an extraneous
passenger. And here's the problem. We know people with high LP little a that don't seem to be
bothered. They're not coming down. There's no premature family history in them. And other
people's the example Peter just gave my God, they're atherosclerotic Rex at young ages.
So I also just as I've sort of iterated about other lipoproteins, I think when we're talking
about LP little a in the year 2020, we are talking about all right, let's what's its mass,
what's its LP little a particle number. But I also think we have to be smarter on understanding the
quality or other attributes of this LP little a particle. What makes this Apo little a attachment
may be terrible for that guy who had his heart attack at age 30. But here are other people who
are coming in at age 80 and they got high LP little a and they're not full of plaque or so.
And one of the things we're beginning to understand is look, Apo a has potentially some
thrombogenic properties, which perhaps get expressed in some people more than others.
But more and more, one of the functions perhaps even of Apo a wide even evolved is a little
scavenger protein that attaches to oxidized lipid moieties, specifically oxidized fossil
lipids, oxidized sterols, they bind to it with great affinity. And maybe that little garbage
truck full of oxidized particles, if it could bring it back to the liver or some other tissue
that could catabolize it, those oxidized lipid moieties, which tend to be destructive to cells,
are not getting to cells. So we are beginning to have metrics that are starting to appear and
available in the real world that we can measure the oxidation, the oxidized lipid moieties that
are on Apo little a. They're actually it's called oxidized PL fossil lipids on Apo b.
And if you say, well, these oxidized fossil lipids are on all the Apo b particles to a minuscule
degree for because of the affinity of oxidized lipid moieties, Apo a, you overwhelm if you have
a positive oxidized fossil lipid Apo b, the overwhelming majority of Apo b particles trafficking
those oxidized lipids are LP little a particles. So two people came to consult me tomorrow, they
both have an elevated LP little a metric. One has a normal oxidized fossil lipids on Apo b,
but the other one is elevated. Based on Sam Sinekis and others were work, I'm going to be a little
more worried about that person who's my God, not only do they have this undesirable particle, but
this particle is loaded downward, injurious other lipids that are potentially very harmful. So that's
one aspect of it. We're nowhere near being able to test for the thrombo genicity, if that's a big
factor of Apo little a and everything. So there are other ways of doing this. I mean, I all the
time when I get my weekly email from Peter T here's the podcast this week. I'm waiting for Sam
Sinekis. So but for those of you still waiting for Peter to nab him, he's pretty active on Twitter.
And he really tweets a lot of good information on the cutting edge of what's coming down with LP.
I think it's LP little a dash underscore doc something like but we'll go on Twitter and Sam
Sinekis, T S I M I K S and you'll be happy you followed him. So there's just a lot to understand
Peter. So it's who has it. And by the way, the new guidelines are the European guidelines suggest
that everybody ought to have it once in their life as they approach adulthood. And you never need
repeat it unless somehow you're trying to modulate it or maybe you go through medical is where it can
go up a little bit. But it's a genetically determined marker you have it or you don't have
it if you don't have it at age 18, you're not going to have it at age 68. So it's a one time test.
And it helps us before we talk, let's do thorough cardiovascular risk assessments, no matter what
your APOB is. And this would be one of the tests that at least the Europeans have signed on to now,
the National Lipid Association, other people have issued guidelines to it and they're still telling
you, well, do it for unexplained heart attacks or strong family history of heart disease. To me,
again, it's not a very expensive test. Get it once and for all. But there's so much to talk about this,
Peter. And in the future, I mean, there are ways, what would you do for somebody with high
LP, little a, we have strategies, which is mostly attacking APOB right now and any of the other
cardiovascular risk factor. But there are drugs in the pipeline that may give us better alternatives
to perhaps stop your liver from making APO, little a. Let's talk about that a little bit. So up until
I would say a few years ago, the only strategy for patients, let's assume that we've confirmed
that a patient's LP, little a is elevated. And furthermore, let's confirm that we have reason
to believe that in that patient, the LP, little a is also problematic. And again, this usually shows
up in family history. It's not a subtle thing. A lot of times I'm taking the family history from
a patient before I've got the blood test. Those could be offset by weeks. And it's because we give
our patients the template to work on this, they come in with a very thorough family history. They
really know what happened to the mother's older sister and the grandfather and all of these other
things. And you usually just see this history of lots of heart attacks before the age of 60.
Obviously it can be confounded by people who are heavy smokers and things like that.
Yeah. Let me just interrupt you for one second. It'll be a minute because published yesterday
in the Journal of the American College of Cardiology is a study and a fantastic editorial.
And they looked at people with terrible family histories of heart disease and people who had
LP, little a issues or they didn't. And the conclusion was simple. Don't have high LP,
little a if somehow you can avoid that, which you can't. Don't have a terrible family history of
coronary artery disease. And I don't know how you avoid it, but if you want the worst scenario,
don't have both LP, little a and fis so Peter, what Peter is just saying is now backed up by a
nice study. Yeah. I love the best advice is choose healthier parents. So let's assume we're in that
situation, which is we have high LP, little a and we have the family history that is not favorable
or something else that's even more germane to the patient, which is a positive calcium score,
something to that effect. Well, again, historically, our best bet would be remove all other risk to the
extent that it is possible. So we lower all other ApoB maximally pharmacologically. We optimize
completely all of the metabolic parameters that we've discussed briefly here, but touched on in
greater detail elsewhere. And that includes everything from modulating blood pressure as
aggressively as it needs to be to controlling all of these other factors that don't get enough
attention in my book, the uric acids, the homocysteines, things like that. But then as you
point out, there's a strategy now that says, wait a minute, what if we knock out the liver's ability
to make Apo, little a and all of a sudden you wouldn't have an LP, little a. So what does that
strategy look like and where is that strategy in the pharmacologic pipeline? In pretty early trials
and of course, any cell we're talking about the liver here, if the liver is the primary site of
production of Apo, little a and it is, if we could mess with the genes to ASO therapy, we could
probably stop a cell from making a given protein. If we can stop the liver from making Apo protein,
little a, if you don't have that, you certainly the liver can't secrete it so it can attach to
LDL particles, transforming them into LP, little a particles. So that's almost like a no-brainer.
The Mendelian randomization trials says don't have high Apo way or LP, little a. So let's just
inhibit its synthesis as we've done with other things that contribute to coronary artery disease.
And that has to work. Yes, provided that protein doesn't screw or that ASO treatment doesn't screw
up something else or cause a downside to it. And that's why you ultimately have to do large
clinical trials looking at not only event reduction, but safety. But those drugs are in early,
you know, and like anything else, the first generation of those antisense oligosaccharide
drugs that came around, they've perfected them. So there's a second generation of them now that
they've made even more hepatoselective so they can dose less of it. And it goes right into the liver.
But they're phase one, phase one, two trials. And Novartis, I believe, has now acquired the
product that they're going to put it in a major which has just started enrollment of phase three
trial on let's not. But here's the problem. Peter knows the billions that probably have to be
invested when you're developing a drug of that type of magnitude to reduce something. You're not
going to do it on every time Dick and Harry who has a trivial LP little a you want that first
trial to work because if it doesn't, that's it. The drug the drug is dead. It'll never be tested
and lesser risk people. So the only way you can get into this current apo little a synthesis
modulator drug is you have to have had an atherosclerotic clinical event of myocardial infarction,
stroke, blah, blah, blah, stents. And you have to have an astronomical like upper quintile
concentration of LP little a. Because Bendelian trials suggest if you're going to get benefit
by lowering apo little a or LP little a, it has to be a pretty significant drop in it. So you're
not going to take somebody with a trivial LP little a elevation and, you know, if you tested 50,000
maybe it would work. But so if they go through this first trial and it'll probably take three,
four or five years to show efficacy and safety, then they're going to have to maybe do some
sub trial analysis. And then is anybody even going to fund the primary prevention trial with this
drug with the cost that that takes? I don't know. So even if you're somebody who's had a heart attack
because of LP little a and you're waiting for this drug, you got five, 10 years to wait. And
for primary prevention, go on to other ways that clinicians are attacking this problem right now,
because you're not going to have anything. Why is it that statins, which are probably the most potent
drug until five years ago to lower LDL and by definition, then lower APO concentration,
have virtually no effect on LP little a. But this new class of drug that's been around for five
years called PCSK9 inhibitors, well, even more potent in lowering LDL seem to also be able to
lower LP little a. I think there's two reasons there. And one, we've gotten enough trials now
that seem to show depending on your APO a makeup, do you produce the large high molecular weight APO
a or the smaller low molecular weight APO a, which in epidemiologic trials seems to be way more
associated with atherosclerosis, that if you're one who does produce the low molecular weight,
short APO a, which means because it's such a small protein to make the liver can make a ton of it,
so they actually, even though their molecular weight of APO little a is lower, they have much
higher LP little a particle counts. If you have that isiformity LP little a statins can induce
the synthesis of that statins do not affect the synthesis of the larger APO a moiety. So in some
people, Peter says statins do not much to LP little a concentrations, but there is a small
component where statins will actually raise it a little bit. And people get scared. They go, well,
I'm lowering LDL cholesterol, LDL particle counts a tad, but I'm raising LP little a, even Sam
Samikas will tell you, don't worry about it. LP little a, if you learn nothing else about our LP
little a discussion is a minority LDL particle. So even though if you have the small isoform of
statin may be raising LP little a a tad, it's so blowing away the LDLs that don't have APO a attached
to it that at the end of the day, you have less cardiovascular risk. And that little excursion in
LP little a concentration is probably meaningless. Now to go on to the second part of the questions,
the piece SK9 inhibitors don't have an effect on the synthesis of APO a in the body. So at least
they're not aggravating it in some people. But we're still in our infancy trying to understand
how LP little a particles are, you know, catabolized or cleared, and it's probably due to multiple
receptors, the LDL receptors part of it and a PCSK nine can give you more LDL receptors than a statin
probably can putting aside the synthetic interference with it. But PCSK nine, their finding has effects
now on APO we receptors in three or four other lipoprotein clearing receptors that are expressed
in liver and other cells or so. So I mean, that's, there's got to be better clearance of the particles
with PCSK nine inhibitors, then there is with LDL receptor expression with statins or statins plus
whatever other apo b lowering drug you're going to add to it or so. So I think that's where we're at
right now. Most of the time, these people are going to wind up on statins plus PCSK nine unless
they can't tolerate a statin or there's another reason not to use a statin. So that's my explanation
right now, Peter, that I think we touched on that a little bit in the last podcast, and we still
don't have a lot of info and clearance of LP little a particles. And as you said, it's quite variable.
I mean, we've seen patients where they're on a PCSK nine inhibitor for other reasons. And every
time I put somebody on when I recheck their LP little a just different or the reason than to
gather our own data on how much of an effect the drug either prior went to Rapata is having on
LP little a and there's the range is zero to 60 70% reduction. I mean, that's literally how broad
it is with probably a median reduction of a third. Yeah, so two important points here. One,
LP little a is not an acceptable goal of therapy because there wouldn't be trial data. So even
though we all think that's probably going to be good. But I think most people like Peter when he
prescribes it, sort of likes to at least see what happens to get his own information or so. But
realize that's not what you're making a therapeutic decision on per se is the LP little a concentration.
So just keep that in mind when you when you're following up on these people.
One last thing I want to circle in on you with that you and I spoke about a couple of years ago.
It was an experimental metric that was being bandied about. In fact, I remember you guys ran it
at THD on some of my serum. But I don't know that it ever saw the commercial light of day,
which was I think it was like LDL triglyceride concentration. Have those tests ever seen the
light of day? I think if you look around enough, you might find a lab. It's a very easy
assay. Denka makes it where you could get an LDL triglyceride level. And by the way, just
another thought jumped into my brain on that LP little a, as I told you, there are other things
that attach to even LDLs and HDLs that make them less clearable or more atherogenic. And a very
recent study show, believe it or not, there are LP little a particles that carry Apo C3.
You're not going to clear that particle if you make it so. The double whammy. Yeah. Oh my god.
But anyway, back to LDL triglycerides. People, I often tease them if you said, you know what,
we're really cost effective. We're only going to allow you to have one lipid concentration on this
person. Nothing else. I would tell him, give me an LDL triglyceride level, certainly not an LDL
cholesterol level. And remember, Apo B is a lipoprotein metric, not a lipid metric. So that's
what I would really take. But the triglyceride part of the core of any lipoprotein has a lot to do
with plasma residence time of that particle. What else might be attached to that particle?
Even I alluded to it a little bit in my brief HDL discussion before Dan Rader calls them fat HDLs.
What if your HDL particle is not carrying very many cholesterol molecules, it's carrying triglycerides.
Well, he's shown, God knows a decade ago to those fat HDLs, meaning triglyceride and rich,
are dysfunctional. They're carrying some of the bad stuff that HDLs carry that don't allow them
to do their cardioprotective functions. So if triglycerides gets into an LDL, number one,
what happens to an LDL that's floating around and it might still be a big LDL because it's full of
triglycerides, not cholesterol, but it has a very great affinity for lipase enzymes that line our
arteries or the surface of the liver. So hepatic lipase is a very potent triglyceridase phospholipase
that is just like a fly trap looking for flies. It's looking for triglyceride enriched HDLs.
And if it binds to it, it will extract hydrolyzed the triglycerides. So if I had a LDL full of
triglycerides and I pulled the trigs out, what am I left with? Well, that's an LDL particle that's
lost a lot of surface phospholipids as well as a lot of core triglycerides. I have the so-called
small LDL or dense LDL. I try not to use both adjectives together because they're redundant.
And we have plenty of evidence that, yeah, it's no good to have an increased total LDL particle count,
but try not to have too many small LDL particles because the evidence has certainly emerged that
particle for particle, they're probably more atherogenic than the more buoyant larger LDL
particles for a variety of reasons. And the bigger non-triglyceride rich LDL, it might be a
better fit for an LDL receptor. It's going to clear it. So LDL triglycerides, basically, if you told
me it was high, I know you probably got a high LDL particle count, APOB. I know you have the
small LDL particles. I know where those triglycerides probably came from, your VLDL triglyceride rich
particles, your chiral micron particles. And when they transfer their triglycerides to LDLs,
they become remnant lipoproteins, which Peter has alluded to. And you can bet those same
triglycerides are invading the HDL particles contributing to HDL functionality. And last but
not least, in the studies where they've looked at LDL triglyceride, many of the inflammatory markers
are high because those particles set off the inflammasome in various endothelial cells and
elsewhere. So it's a really simple, easy to do metric that could tell us so much. And I think,
if I saw it was up, the first thing I'm saying up, I'm dealing with an insulin resistant person,
because that would be the most common cause, not some genetic triglyceride problem.
Right. And again, I think perhaps the reason why people aren't leaping up and down to
bring this to market is, frankly, if you're looking at VLDL cholesterol,
and you're looking at all of the markers of insulin resistance, along with the lipoprotein
markers we've discussed, I think you get the story. And look, I mean, taking a step back,
let's play devil's advocate for a moment. I think that it's worth doing ApoB over non-HDL
cholesterol. There are some people who are so opposed to advanced lipid testing that they will
argue, as long as you have non-HDL cholesterol, you don't even need to measure ApoB, because of
course the non-HDL cholesterol is measuring the LDL cholesterol, but somewhat correcting
for the additional VLDL by adding the VLDL cholesterol. What is your take on the idea of
non-HDL cholesterol versus ApoB as they are somewhat proxies for the same problem?
Well, I'm in the Snyderman School, and he's published on this extensively. I find it,
all right, it probably gives you a little bit more information for the reasons you just described.
Versus LDL cholesterol, yeah.
Beyond LDL cholesterol. But as Snyderman has clearly shown in several studies,
even though non-HDL cholesterol correlates with ApoB a little bit better than does LDL cholesterol,
there's still 20, 30% of the population in our diabetics and psoriasis where they're discordant.
And where there is discordance, even with non-HDL cholesterol and ApoB, risk follows ApoB.
So why am I wasting my time with it? Look, it's all useful. It might help you pick what therapy
you want to use, but at the end of the day, I see no need to follow your non-HDL cholesterol.
I'm following ApoB because I'd be a fool if I told you I normalized your non-HDL cholesterol,
and I've eliminated your lipoprotein mediated risk. Until you measure, you quantitate
these particles, and if we ever get a quality test, that's a silly thing to say to a patient.
Yeah, exactly. We saved $3.
Yeah. And we might spend a little time, or you're very good at explaining it. How do you determine
VLDL cholesterol in your patients, Peter? You're not dividing triglycerides by five,
the old Friedelwald formula. No. So we use a lab that is actually giving a VLDL cholesterol,
and even if they didn't do that, we would still take total cholesterol and subtract from it
LDL cholesterol and HDL cholesterol. Not perfect either, because in that situation,
sometimes the LDL is calculated. But I always do a back of the envelope trig divided by five.
It's not close enough. No, that's true. And listen, you made a key point here,
which maybe went over people's heads. You cannot do that calculation if you have a
calculated LDL cholesterol. You must have a directly measured LDL cholesterol,
because total cholesterol is LDL cholesterol, VLDL cholesterol, and HDL cholesterol. So if
you subtract a directly measured HDL cholesterol, a directly measured HDL cholesterol, in effect,
you have a directly measured VLDL cholesterol, which in our current world is about as close as
you're going to get to an evaluation of remnants. I think in our last podcast, we talked why there
are exceptions to that rule, and that's a more complex discussion. But please, you can't get VLDL
cholesterol using the Frito-Waltz calculated LDL cholesterol. All right. Let's talk a little bit
about therapies. Statins have been around forever. They still take up most of the air in the room.
They are the workhorse of lipid-lowering therapy. Is there anything new and exciting to talk about?
I would say that there's no new statin on the market today that wasn't there two years ago.
Is the most recently introduced statin live-alow? Yeah, and that's probably 10 years ago introduced.
What do you make of that, Tom? Why are we not seeing more statin innovation? Two things. I think
third-party payers would never pay for a new branded statin. They're going to always insist
you use the cheapest generic that's appropriate to the degree of LDL lowering that you need.
There are seven of them on the market now, so I don't think a bean counter at some farm is looking
for, let's get a new statin. We're well aware of potential downsides to statin things. We have to
look for who tolerates them, who doesn't. I don't know that they're somehow going to invent a new
statin that brings none of the potential downside of a statin to the equation. They're looking at
other therapies that will, now that we understand it's atherogenic lipoproteins, that will reduce
that. If your investment pays off, you'll have a branded product for X number of years, and you
might get a little return on your investment. I don't think we're going to see another
statin right now. The biggest thing that's happened with statins and in a guideline,
you know, in the old days when we had nothing else to do and we didn't know a lot about all
this lipoprotein stuff is, hey, you got this most trivial elevation of some LDL metric,
mostly LDL, you're going on a statin. I want them in the drinking water. In the old days,
oh, Tom, I just took a statin because they just reduced heart attacks. You and I know there is
an event reduction, but there's plenty of residual risk, even if you're aggressively using a statin.
So there always is more to the story. But I think the newer guidelines give you a lot more ability
to ascertain in a given individual after you do your thorough cardiovascular risk assessment,
you and I do our own risk assessment, which is a little different than what the guidelines might
offer. But then once a person crosses a certain threshold of atherosclerotic risk, then it becomes
plausible to consider a statin. And there's more to it than per se the LDL cholesterol level.
There's all those other factors that go into risk assessment. And there are other
adjunctive diagnostics. Now you earlier, we briefly alluded to coronary calcium scoring,
LP, little a, they would be things that current guidelines says use of your
Hammond or horn. Should I give a statin? Should I not? Or the patient? I don't want to take it
at least to a CAC, at least to an LP, little a look at the family history, as you mentioned,
look at the blood pressure, other concomitant risk factors. In fact, that add into,
do I want to use a statin or other Apo B lowering therapy? So that's the biggest change with statins.
Nobody's saying, hey, they belong in the drinking water. You should carefully choose who you're
advocating statin therapy to. Any sort of rules of thumb, just in terms of the alchemy of this,
you mentioned that there are seven out there, you know, in our practice, we really only pick from
four of them, Livolo, Crestor, Lipitor, and Prevostatin. I mean, most of these are generic now.
And if you listen to the podcast with Catherine Eban, which I know you did, we are actually still
pushing for branded whenever we can get it. And if we're not getting a branded version of those,
we cross check with who the generic supplier is. And we've seen differences, right? We've seen that
two versions of Resuvostatin can produce different outcomes. So our default position is that all
generics are crap until proven otherwise. And that's why we use a tightly controlled list of meds.
But I don't think I've ever prescribed Simvastatin, for example. What's your take on some of the older
statins versus the four? I mean, the reason I think we look at Prevostatin and Livolo is mostly for
the sensitive patient, and then Crestor and Lipitor, Resuvostatin and Torvostatin being kind
of the workhorse. Yeah. Well, you're just too young, Peter, and old fogies like myself,
Lova statin or Mevacor was the first statin that came around, Simvastatin was an accident,
Prevostatin and Prevocol came. So we have a lot of experience with those drugs. But as time went on,
in pretty early on, there was a pretty rational thing that whatever the reason Prevostatin is
a safer statin to use than Simvastatin or Lova statin. And it turns out that was mostly related
to drug-drug interactions where Prevostatin is pretty clean. Subsequent to that, the only statin
that is even cleaner than Prevostatin on drug-drug interactions is the Livolo. So Ptoavastatin would
be its generic name. So that's in today's polypharmacy world where, and we're not only even
talking about prescription products, but the multitude of supplements or God knows what people
wind up taking, we have no way to check on drug-drug interactions. So you're probably going to get into
less trouble with Ptoavastatin or Prevostatin. Of course, along came Resuvostatin many years later
after Prevostatin. And it shared some, at least pharmacokinetic attributes with the Prevostatin
in that it was a hydrophilic statin, kind of hepatoselective, but it was way more potent on a
milligram basis than Prevostatin. So it became an over that evolution of all those early statins,
every three years we had lower and lower and lower LDL metric goals, which weren't there when we first
started. So what used to be acceptable is no longer acceptable. So it was very easy to transform from
the hydrophilic Prevostatin to the way more potent hydrophilic Resuvostatin. And that pretty much was
my statin of choice thereafter, unless you had a putz around because of statin intolerance,
where you would try some of those other things. Personally, once all this was known and once
Resuvostatin hit the market, I don't think I ever prescribed another Lipitor dose again, unless,
you know, third party payers are influences here. They sometimes tell people you either take this
one or here's what you're going to have to pay if you don't go on our formulae. So that can factor
into its use. Now Lipitor is a potent statin milligram per milligram. It's not as potent as
Resuvostatin, but you can get whatever LDL reduction if you use a higher dose of Lipitor,
as you can with a somewhat lesser dose of Resuvostatin. So unless the third party payer is
telling me to use it, I'm probably not going to advocate Lipitor. Just there are more drug drug
interactions and it is Lipophilic. There's perhaps other issues at play. You and I have talked about
statins ability to get into the brain and everything where Lipophilic statins might be have a little
more bit propensity to do that than hydrophilic statins. So there are other issues at play that
would influence where you're going. The other thing that, and I'm going to disagree in, I think
it's the way you practice too, all of the guidelines right now say, okay, you've made a
decision to use a statin. Pick the two most statin, the most potent statins. That means you're on
Lipitor or Crestor and prescribe it at the maximum dose. Because the way these trials were designed,
lowers better, they all start, you know, they very few trials where they took people with
minuscule LDL cholesterol levels and drew statins at them. So they want you to get,
hey, the clinical trial shows this statin at that dose works. Maybe there's pleiotropic effects at
that statin is doing too. So how do you know you have to be evidence-based? I don't buy it. I think
virtually all of the statins contribution to atherosclerosis reduction is ApoB reduction.
And I think you've known me long enough that rather than maximizing a statin using the Gorilla
dose day one, I would prefer to start with a smaller dose, again, dependent on your risk and
your metrics. I mean, if you're coming off an acute coronary syndrome and your LDL metric is
off the chart, okay, I'll start with a big one. But I'd rather take that baby statin, meaning a
lower dose of a statin and perhaps optimizing it with a second ApoB lowering drug. And for the
longest time we had a Zetimibe, which has since been proven in clinical trials to further reduce
benefit and also in Mendelian randomization trials, looking at the Neiman pick protein.
And now we have the new guy on the street, this Bempedoic acid, which is a weaker cholesterol
synthesis inhibitor affecting an early on cholesterol synthesis step. Also that has
Mendelian randomization support. And if you can't use a statin or if you can use a statin, if you
add dastudastatin or even the triple therapy statin, is that a Bempedoic acid? Maybe you can avoid the
expensive PCSK9 inhibitor. So we have a lot more therapeutic options now a day, Peter.
And then talk about the differences in the synthetic pathways between these two drugs,
or where are they targeting the synthetic pathways and what makes them different? Is one
more hepatic selective or is it really a question of potency with respect to where they're blocking
the chain? Yes. The cholesterol synthesis pathway is something like 37 steps. Each step has its own
different enzyme catalyzing the transformation of these precursor products into the next down the
stage. Statins happen to inhibit what's called the rate limiting enzyme. It's the third step
in the cholesterol synthesis pathway. And of course that's modulated by the enzyme HMG-CoA reductase.
Statins pretty significantly in a dose dependent fashion inhibit that enzyme. So you can seriously
slow down cholesterol synthesis in various cells. The one cell we really want to do it in is the
liver because that's a cell that has the greatest propensity to upregulate LDL receptors that can
clear our APOB containing particles. So statins do that. Now if you can deplete cholesterol pools
beyond what a statin can do in the liver, you will express more LDL receptors. So when we use
hisetimide, we block intestinal absorption of cholesterol or back flux of biocolestral into
the liver, further depleting hepatic cholesterol pools, you will get more expression of LDL
receptors. So now we have this new Bempedoic acid. It's called an ATP citrate lyase inhibitor.
Well, the first step in cholesterol synthesis is citrate, Natomitochondria coming out of the Krebs
cycle is transformed to acetyl-CoA, which boom, then goes down and becomes after it becomes HMG
and then the subsequent things. So this Bempedoic acid is called an ACL, ATP citrate lyase inhibitor,
but it's a prodrug. You swallow it. It's only up taken by the liver and it inhibits an enzyme
in the liver that you can't make acetyl-CoA. So hey, the less acetyl-CoA you make, you're going
to make less HMG and then therefore that's going to, you'll have less substrate for the statin to
add on to. So collectively you get additional APOB lowering. The cool thing is, because one of our
biggest downsides to statin is people get these myopathic symptoms, be they weakness muscle aches
or whatever, you know that. It's a big problem with statin therapy, probably more prevalent than
what clinical trials would show us, but this Bempedoic acid does not have any uptake in the muscle cells.
There's a specific receptor that pulls it into the liver. So it is hepato selective. Look,
razovastatin is somewhat hepato selective because there is a special cellular receptor that pulls
in razovastatin, but other cells can pull it, razovastatin, razovastatin can give you muscle
aches. So it's not quite as hepato selective as Bempedoic acid. Do you know what they saw, Tom, in the
trial versus placebo for muscle soreness? Because even PCSK9 inhibitors still had some
noise with respect to muscle soreness, even though mechanistically it's not entirely clear why,
whereas at least the statin, there's some explanation as to why someone could experience
muscle soreness. I'm just kind of curious as to what the head-to-head... Yeah, no, they did look
at that and it's not zero. So there are still people who... But they've also shown studies that
you can give... You give up placebo on your head. ...a placebo and people get muscle aches too.
But it's... And they did comparative trials versus a statin versus a placebo, and there is definitely
less with it or so, but it's not going to be zero. So it's worth a trial if you're really hung up.
So I think right now it's used and the FDA approved it. The FDA says, look, you got to go do a big
outcome trial, which the company is doing, but Mendelian randomization suggests it would work.
Before we ever had outcome trial with Zetimide, Mendelian randomization data suggests that
reducing cholesterol intestinal absorption would reduce cardiovascular events, and that turned out
to be so. So, and they only had to do with a certain amount of phase three safety trial, and
the FDA let it come on the market. And its use was you can add it to a statin and people with
familial hypercholesterolemia, who the statin probably is not going to get you to go by itself,
and you can combine it to that, or even very high risk people where you didn't blow your
LDL-C down to 70 or 50, whatever you're trying to do it. You need a junk of LDL cholesterol,
APOB lowering. You can co-prescribe the bempedoic acid. And they also allow you to co-prescribe
Zetimide with it. In fact, the company that manufactures this, and the brand name is called
Nexitol, they also have been given FDA approval because there are a lot of statin intolerant
people out there, or people who need triple LDL lowering therapy, that we're going to give you a
combo product, which is bempedoic acid plus Zetimide. I guess it's priced a little cheaper. So rather
than swallowing two pills, you could just take that combo pill. You could add it to a statin or not.
And look, I think for the nightmare of Zetimide, you could ultimately, if you had to add PCSK9
inhibitor, the end of the day, if you're good at individualizing your therapy, I think we have
four APOB options now a day. And you're going to get down a fairly standard path because not
everybody can afford a PCSK9 inhibitor. Not everybody might be at the type of high level
risk that the FDA wants you to be at to, or the third party payer wants you to be at.
But it's a fun time to be in the APOB world. We have a lot of therapies, and we're not even
talking about addressing triglycerides, which there are therapies that do that that might
contribute to APOB lowering also. The statin works a lot by the hepatic upregulation of the LDL receptor.
Do we think that's the case here as well? Or do we think that this is
more about the actual reduction of cholesterol synthesis?
But remember, if you inhibit cholesterol synthesis, you're going to do hepaticals of
cholesterol, which will through the sterile regulatory element binding protein upregulate
LDL receptor expression, perhaps some VLDL receptors or other things like that, APOE receptor.
So at the end of the day, probably depleting hepatic cholesterol pools is what you have to do.
It's still its primary driver. So really, at least on some level,
bempedoc acid is attractive because it's more hepatic selective, even if it's less potent.
And remind me again, what do we think is the relative potency compared to a statin?
If you look at its monotherapy trials, it's like a zetimide. You're going to get anywhere
from a 10 to 18 percent lowering of LDL cholesterol by itself, a tad less APOB 10 to 12 percent,
if you use it as a monotherapy. As you know, with a zetimide with statins, there's a wide range of
responses. I think with all these drugs, there are hyper responders, middle-of-the-road responders,
and hypo responders. And I think that probably has a lot to do with how much synthesis of
cholesterol, how much absorption of cholesterol, what type of LDL receptors do you make or express.
There's a lot of factors at play, but if you want a generalization, that's what it is.
And now you alluded to it, but what do we think about in terms of what's changed in the last
couple of years in terms of our thinking about EPA and DHA specifically?
Well, two things, and it's been a long time and nobody has respected triglycerides more than I
have been lecturing about triglyceride rich lipoproteins forever. And I knew despite all the
nonsense that it doesn't matter what you do to trays, you don't reduce events like you do with LDL
cholesterol because of improperly designed trials and enrollment of people who basically didn't have
triglyceride issues and giving them triglyceride-lowering drugs. But anyway, we're far enough down
the road that not only does the Mendelian randomization trials certainly suggest, look,
there are certain genes that are involved with triglycerides that are seriously involved with
atherosclerosis. So it's very plausible if at least through those mechanisms we improve
triglycerides, you're going to reduce disease. So for the longest time, what was our other than
lifestyle? What was our way to lower triglycerides? We had niacin around forever. We had the emerging
fibric acid story, which progress, progress, progress until the terribly improvised trials
that were done to, let's see if fibrates worked. They didn't give them to anybody who had
triglycerides. So of course the fibrate didn't work, but there's always been this, hey, Omega-3s
really are a potentially triglyceride-lowering drug, and maybe we should use them. Anybody who's
known Bill Harris for the longest time, as I have, you have, no, yes, Omega-3s, if you really want to
get triglyceride-lowering from an Omega-3, you better be using serious, serious doses of the,
you don't give a gram, you don't give two grams if you want to get rid of triglycerides, or better
yet, triglyceride-rich lipoproteins. If there are other attributes to Omega-3s, we have no way
of measuring that. Now, and there almost certainly are, because, you know, Omega-3s are a crucial
part of cell membranes and cell signaling. But if we're just going to deal in our lipid world,
and you want to have an Omega-3 on board to help you combat triglyceride-rich lipoproteins,
you want to have a maximum dose, which looks to be 4,000 milligrams a day. So this was the
belief, Bill used to always, listen, don't tell me that you gave somebody a thousand
milligrams of Omega-3 and you didn't reduce heart attacks. The odds are strong, you could never
reduce heart attacks with that drug, you know? So now we got confused, because as we started to
realize this, they started to do trials with, okay, let's give four grams of Omega-3s,
and let's really not make the fibrate mistake, put them in the drinking water, let's enroll
people into these trials who have high triglycerides. Many of those people also have concomitant low
HDL cholesterol, but that necessarily doesn't have to be an entry criteria. But you better have a
triglyceride level above a certain degree, or we're not going to waste our money giving Omega-3s
to people with triglycerides of 42. And lo and behold, the first trial that started to come down
the pike was done in Japan, so God, probably almost a decade ago, the Japan EPA trial.
You know, Japanese people eat a lot of Omega-3s, so they have higher baseline levels anyway,
so they just gave them, for whatever reason, EPA only, on top of a statin. And they didn't
necessarily have to have high triglycerides, but many of the people did. And lo and behold,
although it was not a blinded trial, the evidence was pretty good that, wow, this is really plausible,
that EPA at high dose, four grams a day, reduces the macrovascular outcomes when given with a statin,
that of course is working on the LDL metric you're looking at. So, you know, of course,
people said, aha, that's proving Omega-3s work. Nobody was given a lot of credence, perhaps other
than the people who produce it, that, oh, this is unique to EPA. Most people are taking Omega-3s,
are taking some combination of EPA and DHA, but as long as you're going to take four grams of that,
why wouldn't it do exactly? So here's what happened. So after that EPA trial, the company
that makes the branded EPA medication, which is VSEPA, Amarin is the company, did a major clinical
trial called REDUCEIT, where they enrolled people with, who were taking whatever statin they had
to take to get their LDL cholesterol below 70. And in general, these were high risk people. They had
some degree of carny disease or they were full blown diabetics or had a lot of cardiovascular.
So it wasn't a low risk primary prevention type of study. You had to have a triglyceride above 137
to get into that trial. Most people, it was 150, but you know, the triglyceride assay always
varies plus or minus 15 points. So they would let you come in if you had a 137, because they thought
in a week you're going to have 150. So they enrolled people. That was the cutoff. You had to
have that. And lo and behold, and you were maximized on whatever statin it took to get your LDL-C,
under 100 at the time, pretty good. And lo and behold, and we haven't come up with much in the
world so far, at least it has a big trial saying we lower residual risk with a statin.
Azetomide did it in acute carny syndrome survivors to a certain degree, but this high dose EPA,
two grams twice a day with food, because it is an FLSter, theoretically it needs to be de-esterified
before it's absorbed. There was almost a 30% residual risk reduction. That's mind boggling
to be honest after taking a statin. But they would still say, oh, that's fantastic. We all have to
start using omega-3s at the appropriate dose way more than we ever did. But a lot of believers,
and I think probably Bill Harris and myself said, yeah, but we could also just give four grams of
EPA plus DHA, because deep down many of us believe DHA is a pretty important omega-3 fatty
acid too, if for no other reason than your brain needs it. But I believe all cell membranes need
to a certain extent. And not everybody can convert EPA to DHA, although most people probably can.
So, AstraZeneca had acquired a free omega-3 fatty acid, meaning it's not an ethyl ester,
which means it has a better absorption, better pharmacokinetics, more bioavailability. And it
was called epanova, but it was EPA and DHA, but free EPA and free DHA. And they enrolled basically
the same type of people, high triglycerides, maybe the HCL cholesterol is low, at-risk people.
And two years into the study, the company just stopped the study. It's never been published,
so we don't know. But the reason was its futility. We're not seeing a signal at two
years that it's going to work. So we're not wasting any more money on this.
Yeah, this was last November, right, Tom?
Yeah.
I got to tell you, this caught everybody off guard, didn't it?
Because-
Surely caught me.
It was certainly announced that the study was being stopped. And I would say most observers,
myself included, felt, oh, wow, they're stopping it because the signal is so big.
And then they announced at the cardiology meeting, actually, it stopped because there's no signal.
I'm a little surprised it hasn't been published yet, are you?
And annoyed, to be honest with you, is there something there hiding that didn't come out in
that press release or the early discussion about it or so? So are there subgroups in there where
maybe, yeah, I understand these trials are super expensive and where they say, hey,
we're cutting our losses. We'll have to take this out to five or six years before we ever see a
signal. And I wish they had done that, but it's not-
But then they wouldn't have made the announcement. I mean, I guess to me the thing I'm trying to
understand-
Well, they would have announced it if they're stopping it.
Yes, yes, yes. Yeah, that's what I'm saying. But if they were going to keep running it,
they probably wouldn't have made that announcement.
Oh, no.
And so the thing that I'm trying to wrestle with, which I shouldn't spend any time on it,
I'll just wait till it comes out, is how much of this is the vehicle versus the EPA-DHA split?
You got to bring Bill Harris back on. Look, technically that should,
if what we want to do is achieve a certain level of omega-3s in our blood, be it in a red blood cell
or a cell membrane where we would measure the omega-3 index, which they did not measure in the
reducing trial, or whether you just want to reduce plasma free fatty acid levels.
And by the way, that they did do in the reducing trial, and though it's not been published yet,
it has been presented that the efficacy of the EPA-only product highly depends on the level you
did achieve with a serum. So again, to me, that supports going with four grams a day. Don't think
you can get away with two grams a day, perhaps unless you're really checking the levels,
but even that would be guesswork. So to take home points right now, people ask me, Tom, EPA or EPA-DHA,
if I want to be evidence-based and you're in that type of risk category, I think you got to go with
EPA four grams a day. What if Trigless rides are below 150? What about the person with Triggs 100
who still has residual APOB risk? Yeah, it's an unanswerable question right now. I'm not afraid to
keep using EPA-DHA. Whatever the magical mystery effects of the EPA are, which is, you know,
are all theoretical at the given moment, and they're checking a lot of biomarkers to try and explain
and it's all winding up in this massive inflammatory world that's maybe to do something or self
signaling world. Yes, but your brain needs some self-signaling from DHA too. So if I'm going to
throw four grams of EPA at you, I, as you know, I'm a big advocate of doing the Omega-3 index.
So if I'm giving you four grams of EPA only, but your Omega-3 index shows me you have adequate DHA
in your system. I know some of that EPA is being converted, so I'm kind of happy. And I don't
perhaps necessarily have to co-prescribe some degree of DHA with you. My worry would be what
about somebody who's taken the four grams of EPA and the Omega-3 index shows you you're still
deficient in DHA. Then I think you got to scratch your brain and do what you want to do. And I might
be, hey, let's start giving a little DHA. But I can't buy into the concept that a little bit of
DHA is negating EPA. Maybe that's true. And that's what the EPA purists will tell you.
Well, hopefully we have some published data in the next six months that can at least give us a
hint. I don't think this study had enough in common with reduce it to answer that question,
but I think it could potentially give us a clue. Yeah, and we're getting more and more data.
They're doing additional trials with EPA and they're doing more subtrial analysis. They've even shown
some angiographic data with despite that great reduction residual risk, if you actually look at
plaque, it looks a lot better when you're taking four grams of EPA. So that's pretty encouraging
of that type of study. Anyway, you know about predicting what a plaque image shows an event
reduction, but good nonetheless. Anything else on the pharmacology side, Tom, that's really
interesting to you, especially in the last couple of years, because I like the way we've sort of
at least tried to bring people up to speed on what the big changes have been.
Listen, I still think fibrates are widely underused drug. I think for the right person where you've,
through whatever method you use, have identified triglyceride rich lipoproteins,
perhaps those where you clearly see insulin resistance, their diabetics, or their insulin
levels are high. That's where the fibrate subtrial analysis shows miraculous things,
not only with macrovascular endpoints, but with microvascular endpoints, retina, peripheral
nervous system, renal function. So even though you might screw up creatinine a little bit,
you're actually improving EGFR because of overproduction of creatinine, which in that
case is not reflective of EGFR. So I think there still is a group of patients right now
where fibric acids, the purest fibric acid, which is an approach drug, is that phenofibric acid
still so is trilypics. So I think if you have to use a fibric acid, if at all possible,
that's the one to use. And the good news is there is a new fibrate, permafibrate,
pammafibrate that's being invested in clinical trials. It's called a SPARM, a Selective P-PAR
Alpha Receptor Modulator, that they're really high on. And there's big outcome trials going
on with that yet. But nobody's going to be using that or thinking about it until those trials are
stopped for good reasons, bad reasons, or published, of course, and get FDA approval.
So I think there's still hope with the fibrates. Niacin is a dead drug. I know there's going to
be a lot of people listening to this who, oh no, it's not. It's out of every guideline. There's
not a single guideline in the world that recommends you can use anything you want if
you're stuck between a rock and a hard place. And I certainly know there are LP little A advocates.
If you bring Sam on, he will still selectively use niacin in certain cases, but few in the
lipidology world still agree with that. Yeah. And back to your point on trilypics,
we probably have three or four patients on it. And man, it's a world beater. I had one patient who was
probably, I mean, he looked like he had FH and he looked like he also had, of course,
a familial hypertriglyceridemia. I mean, you couldn't distinguish them. And even though you
knew he was going to end up on both a statin and a fibrate at some point, I just out of curiosity
wanted to see what ApoB reduction we'd get starting with just the trilypics. So his trigs were about
400 to begin with. ApoB was over 200. The trilypics took him from a triglyceride of 400
milligrams per deciliter to about a hundred. My memory serves me correctly. And that took the
ApoB from wherever it was, high 100s, 200 down to somewhere between 80 and 100. So that's monotherapy
of trilypics, which was not the intention, but just in a stepwise progression showed you the potency.
And unless you're dealing with a super humongous high risk and acute carnitis, I don't think it's
irrational to go down that route. There are plenty of people who you have to bat them over the head
with whatever to convince them to use a statin. And maybe they'll say, well, I believe in
triglycerides. You're giving me a triglyceride. I'll work with you. Well, let's see what the
parameter. Clearly you picked the right person there where it's triglycerides were generating
the ApoB particles and the multi mechanisms on how fibrates reduced triglyceride had a beneficial
effect. I've actually with Peter Jones published data using NMRs on resubastatin and phenofibric
acid. And you, in some people, there were pretty nice reductions in LDL particle counts using
phenofibrate, always more. But when you looked at the particle analysis, when you were even
combining phenofibric acid with the fibrate or excuse me, with the statin, you got way more
dramatic remnant reductions with the fibrate than you ever did with the statin. So another reason,
and almost certainly that person would trigger 400, there was some contribution from remnants in that
person you would think. So just don't forget fibrates. A tragedy to me or young lipidologists
are not being taught about it. Few of them can give you a dissertation on fibrates and how they
work and what is their trial history. God, there's 40 years of trial history that you can
always garner a little bit from any trial. So I find that sad that it's not even being taught
anymore. And people bad mouthfully condemn it without knowing what they're talking about.
I always feel lucky to have been trained by dinosaurs.
Well, some of us have been around the block for a few times or so. But you know,
us old dinosaurs, when we meet you young, brilliant guys, you keep us, if I want to still
talk to this guy, I got to keep up with this stuff. Because I know things I said 10,
15 years ago are silly now, because you got to keep learning. You know that.
Guys like you are really good for me that I just can't rest on my laurels.
Tom, this has been a lot of fun. We were supposed to do this last week and we had some technical
difficulties. So we postponed till this week and I'm glad we did. Because it was worth being able
to do it and actually be able to look at each other through a screen as opposed to just have
to do it by phone. And so I want to thank you obviously for your continued insight. You make a
great difference in our practice. I guess I should fully disclose to people you are now
basically full time inside Attia Medical as a practice. You're on the backside of things,
doing mostly research, but we drag you into at least a third of our patient calls and we
always consult with you on all of our cardiovascular cases. So I hope you're also enjoying being
back to clinical medicine somewhat, even though it's at a much lower volume. We certainly enjoy
having you. It's been such a wonderful part of if this is the finish of my career, still being
able to do this. And you know, although I know a lot of this lipid stuff, the basic science,
I've always been what I, I, Mike Davis, was a clinical epidemiologist. None of this lipid
stuff is meaningful if you can't use it at the bedside and make individualized things.
So I'm just thrilled to be able to contribute to you. And I think one day, as you know, I'm trying
to write and generate and put more and more of this into writing, and that will become available to
your followers and subscribers. And so folks, stay tuned for that. And I will say, maybe it's
another podcast and are probably better people than me to talk to. But the one thing we didn't
get into today is the emerging genetic world, genetic analysis of lipoproteins, and specifically
the genetic lipidosis, FH, who needs that type of testing, who doesn't, whatever you discover,
what can you do for it? It's another whole serious podcast. So other than that, thank you for
everything, Peter. Meeting you a long time ago in Reno, Nevada was a big day in my life.
Oh, mine too, Tom. Thanks so much. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership
program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription.
Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive
podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word
on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to peteratiamd.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
peteratiamd. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to
this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay
in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the
assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of
interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please
visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.