Hey, everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia Drive. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The Drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way. I've spent the last several years working
with some of the most successful top performing individuals in the world. And this podcast
is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you live a higher quality,
more fulfilling life. If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode
and other topics at peteratea.md.com.
This podcast episode, I'm speaking with my friend, Dr. Brett Cotless. Brett is a New
York City based, high and facial plastic surgeon who specializes in cosmetic and reconstructive
surgery of the face, but particularly specializing around things to do with everything with the
eyes, including the skin around the eyes. He's trained both in general oculoplastic surgery
and general cosmetic surgery. I met Brett about three years ago. And I still remember our first
meeting we met for the first time when he just came by my office at some point. And we sat around
having coffee. And as he walked me through not just his training, which is actually quite unique,
but also his particular approach, I realized we were kind of kindred spirits in our appreciation
for nuance. As you'll learn in this episode, I know pretty much nothing about looking good and
skin and eyes and all that stuff. And in many ways, to spend time with Brett is to spend time with
someone who thinks a lot about how to make small and subtle changes over time that lead to long
lasting effects. And I think the reason that resonated so much with me is my belief in longevity,
of course, is that it's a compounding issue and therefore making small but consistent changes
that lead to seemingly small improvements over the short run is actually what leads to amazing
results over the long run with respect to the reduction of risk of disease, etc. Brett's approach
to Cosmesis is the same way. And I suspect that my bias is probably what has me thinking that
that's really the right way to do it. And once I got to know Brett better, and we started to
collaborate and work together, and I've sent a number of patients to Brett, I was always amazed
by the responses because to me, the right way to, for example, do Botox is to be able to look at a
patient after the procedure and say, I didn't know you had Botox. And so things that we talk
about here are a bunch of things that you can do to make a huge impact on the health and vitality
of your skin. And he does get into a number of these things specifically around Botox. He also
gets into a growing list of sort of all the facial treatments and cosmetic procedures that are out
there, lasers, peels, all of these sorts of things. And most importantly, I think he also helps you
as the listener think about how to pick someone because again, you know, many of you listening
to this might find this stuff interesting. And sure, if you happen to be in New York and you
want to meet Brett, that's great. But most likely you're not. And so the more important question
is how do you sort of separate the good from the great or even the great from the not so great
in this space. So again, like I said, I don't think a lot about this personally, I realize I
should probably think about it more when I look at pictures of myself today versus pictures of
myself. When I was 30, I am sort of surprised at how much I feel like I look like I've aged.
And I guess part of this was a bit of a wake up call for me that I might need to pay a little
more attention to that. If for no other reason than just to have the optionality to look a little
better when I'm 80, then I'm probably on the course to looking. Brett does a great job here
explaining why our faces change over time, what he considers the three most important tools for
skincare and rejuvenation. He gets into all the procedures, as I mentioned, the lasers, the peels,
the needles, the devices. I really enjoyed his discussion of the right way to do Botox because
I'd heard this before because of course Brett and I had discussed this a lot, but I'm glad we were
able to sort of revisit that for people here. And he also talks a little bit about the current
trends and future trends of cosmetic and plastic surgery. You can follow Brett on Instagram. He's
Dr. Kotlis, D-R-K-O-T-L-U-S, where he puts up lots of before and after photos, especially around
the eyes, which I find particularly interesting. That's something about myself that I've always been
curious about making better. And his website has the same URL. Lastly, you can see some stuff in
the show notes here. I asked for Brett to give us kind of his recommendations on products that he
suggests that his patients get that if anyone is interested in, they'll at least be able to sort
of get that. And you can see that at peteratea.md.com forward slash podcast. So without further delay,
here's my conversation with Dr. Brett Kotlis.
Well, I'd like to welcome to the show today, Dr. Brett Kotlis, who is an oculoplastic guru
and also a close friend of mine. Brett, we met what, about three years ago?
I would say maybe it's two. Okay. Yeah, it just seems like we've known each other a long time.
The first time we met, I remember being really impressed by kind of the nuance of your training.
I tend to think and talk a lot about longevity, but I don't tend to think
and talk a lot about or know anything about looking younger. And you have learned an awful
lot about that. So remind me, how did you train? What was your medical training?
When I was in medical school, I was drawn to this specialized field that was sort of a cross
between ophthalmology and plastic surgery. And it's called oculoplastic surgery. I was
watching this doctor do an orbital tumor resection. And so I decided this is what I want to do.
And I learned that I needed to do a residency in ophthalmology before I can do a fellowship
in oculoplastic surgery, which the field basically revolves around the eyes and the face
and plastic procedures related to that. So I found out that I had to do an ophthalmology
residency first. So I did that. And then I matched in this training program,
the match process is sort of like the medical matchmakers and you are assigned to a program
based on a ranking system, which you've been through that as well. And I matched with this
doctor in Tucson who happened to have transitioned his practice into cosmetic surgery. And so when
I arrived, I thought I was going to be doing mostly orbital tumors and tear duct surgery and
eyelid reconstruction. And that was part of what we did. But we were also doing a lot of facelifts
and fat grafting and liposuction and lasers. And so my fellowship training qualified for two
different organizations, the American Society of Ophthalmic Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery,
and then also the American Academy of Cosmetic Surgery. So when I finished my fellowship,
I ended up working in this practice in Michigan. That was the largest medical spa in the Midwest.
And it was an exposure to even more lasers and more technology that was on the cutting edge of
what doctors are doing for our appearance. I remember one of the things that really surprised
me when we spoke was just understanding that basically anybody with an MD can hang a shingle
and do kind of whatever the heck they want with respect to facial plastic stuff. I mean,
anybody can be injecting Botox and fillers and all of these things. And of course, not everybody's
doing this stuff well. And not everybody's doing this stuff with the eye towards how will this
look down the road. And I think your approach seemed very nuanced and sophisticated. So I hope
to certainly touch on that today. But I kind of want to start with some just fundamentals. So
I saw a picture of myself 20 years ago, meaning I recently saw a picture of myself from 20 years
ago. And I was like, God, you were like a better looking dude back then. Why is it that at 25,
I looked better than 45? And part of it I think is just my skin looked so much better. So
even though by most people standards, I'm not an old guy today. Clearly, my skin doesn't look
like it used to. What has changed? It's interesting because there does happen to be a double standard
for men and women. And we have the benefit of looking more distinguished as we age. So it's,
I don't think all men feel that way that we're looking worse as we age, but we certainly were
faces are changing. And there are some aging changes that are intrinsic and some that are
extrinsic, right? So your genetics, your programmed to have certain changes over your lifespan,
right? You're, we lose bone as we age, which happens in our faces. We are losing facial fat
as we age. And in some ways, we're losing it in maybe the wrong places. And the sun that we're
exposed to over many, many years causes something called solar elastosis. So we are losing collagen
elastin. The thickness of our skin is decreasing in many areas. And we're also gaining small blood
vessels, the telenjectages, and we are gaining brown spots and the combination of these things on
every layer, your skin, your fat, your muscle, your bone, the ligaments that connect the interplay
between these layers are all losing support. And they're getting thinner and they're degrading.
So from the time that you're born until now, you started off with really chubby round cheeks.
So you look at your one year old son and it's all downhill from there.
Now, there seems to be something about the face in particular. So I used to swim a lot and I used
to swim outdoors, obviously. So I'd spend sometimes six or eight hours just swimming in the out in the
ocean. And I didn't even bother putting sunscreen on because, you know, I have dark skin, I have olive
skin, I never get sunburned. So I'm pretty used to being the guy that's getting a ton of sun. And
while I accept that that's probably caused some damage to my face, why does it not seem to have
caused that same damage to, say, my back, which was even more exposed to the sun when, you know,
I'm swimming in a prone position? Well, if you think about the tension at play based on your face
and your back, I mean, they're different. So your face has more movement, but there's also
because you need to move in certain ways, there's also more areas of laxity. Whereas your back,
the skin is stretched and it's taut. Even though you can certainly get brown spots and wrinkles on
your back, think about scars on the back tend to spread. They look wide and stretched and
they don't heal well because it's under constant tension. But I think that tension makes the back
skin look different than the facial skin. But you also have different oil glands in different
parts of your body. So you have a higher density of sebaceous glands in your face.
And the muscular expression, I think it affects the way that you age more than it does in other
areas. Now, I read once that by about the age of 35, you'll lose about 10% of the fat in your face,
which is kind of amazing to me, given that by the age of 35, I probably gained 10% of the fat
in my body. What is it about the face that doesn't do what the rest of the body does,
which is accumulate fat? Yeah, well, I think there's probably local hormone effects that are
making you accumulate in other areas. And in the face, we have the fat cells come from different
embryologic origins. And for some reason, that's what's happening there. And we're talking about
very small amounts of fat. So you'll see those small differences. But think about your facial fat
as insulation. And as you lose that insulation, you start to see the structures that are underlying
the surface. And so you can see where the ligaments are tethered. And you can see the
places where they're not tethered, which would be an outpouching. And so all of those tight areas
opposed and just directly next to the areas that are not tightly attached, you see these contours.
And so as you age and you deflate, and you have gravity pulling down, I mean, the effect of gravity
is real. Have you ever seen a like a slow motion video of a runner? And you see their face and the
way that the face bounces up and down. And there's so much force on those facial ligaments. And so
you can imagine what happens as you're just walking and running up and down the stairs and over and
you're smiling and you're doing all these things with your face. So there's wear and tear, just like
it happens on our joints, it happens on our facial ligaments. Have you ever lied down on your back
and take a picture and then stand up and take a photo? That lying down image, that eliminates the
effect of gravity on your face. And that shows you what is gravity doing in combination with
the deflation. So that's how you take a selfie is when you're lying down. Take a lying down selfie.
There's tip number one guys. It's called the anti-gravity selfie. In longevity, I used to,
used to, I still do and I certainly don't, don't deserve credit for the smarter people than me
have said this first. But the joke is the most important thing you can do to live longer is
choose the right parents. So there are lots of things that you can do to live longer, but genes
really play a role. Now in the longevity space, we have a pretty good sense of what those genes
are. There are somewhere between about eight and 12 genes that offer pretty remarkable protection
in delaying the onset of chronic disease. And therefore, centenarians, people who live to be
a hundred or longer tend to be bestowed with a greater proportion of those genes. But you mentioned
a second ago that genetic factors can also influence these sort of intrinsic changes that
occur. Do we have a sense of what those genetic factors are? Clearly, there are people who just
have remarkable skin and they age with remarkable skin. And you know, you'll see a woman who's 40
who looks like she's 20 and her mom is 65 and she looks like she's 45. Well, we know that there are
some correlations between certain genetic types and certain traits and the way we age. I mean,
if I see a lot of people for under eye bags, and it's almost everybody says, Hey, this is,
this is genetic. Well, yes, I know it's genetic. I mean, your parents have it. You came in with
your mom and she has it too. So the structure of your face obviously comes from your parents.
But when we talk about skin types and the skin color, darker skin types tend to have
more connective tissue or denser connective tissue and tend to look better as they age.
So maybe it's a generalization, but a lot of the Asians in my practice tend to look better,
longer, darker skin individuals, the same thing. And so the darker pigment in skin does give you
some UV protection. Doesn't mean that you don't have to wear sunscreen, but it offers photo
protection. And I theorize that UV exposure from sunlight causes fat atrophy over many,
many years. Wow. What do you base that hypothesis on? We use heat and we use laser procedures
in a very highly focused way. And we know that it destroys fat cells. So these externally applied
devices that are available now, they effectively remove subcutaneous fat. And I believe that UV
radiation does the same thing over a long period of time. And if you've seen people that have always
protected themselves from the sun, they look like they have white porcelain skin. They have less
wrinkles and they have younger looking faces. I know we're moving away from the genetic question
you're asking me, but I think you can often overcome many of the genetic things just like
with chronic diseases or with your lifestyle modifications. But I think that there is also
an internal drive that we have to perpetuate our gene pool. We each have our own internal
motivation to do that. That's just our evolutionary goals. And I think some of the more favorable
genes become selected over time. And so I think there's a genetic motivation for people to want
to look good because they want to present themselves in their best possible way to a possible mate.
Kind of like a peacock. No, we don't have feathers. So one of the things that I'm sure
anybody listening to this and certainly I've always found a little bit, I don't know, worrisome is
God, if I had a dollar for every time I saw someone walking down the street and who'd looked
like they'd had a million procedures done and you just feel bad for them, you feel like,
God, something went wrong there. You don't look natural or normal. And I think for many people
it becomes off-putting and they think, well, gosh, I don't want to do anything.
So it begs the question, are there strategies that one should take to consider gracefully aging
in as much as one cares? I mean, look, I think in the end, some people are going to say,
I don't care about any of this stuff. But presumably if someone is still listening to
us talking now a few minutes into this, they probably care. How do you think about this? And
maybe how does that differ from what other docs think or what would be a traditional point of view?
Think about all the people that are walking by you on the street that have had
worked on and you don't notice it because it's done well. So I think you're seeing that every day,
but you just don't know it. Yeah, I only see the numerator. I don't see the denominator.
And what are the reasons for the unnatural appearance? Why do people get to that point?
I think in some cases, maybe it's unlimited access or unlimited resources. I think there are
forces that push people in that direction. Your appearance is a very emotional subject.
And I think we tie ourselves to that maybe an age that we feel like that was our best age.
Think about the actress that everyone knows for the role that they played when they were 20 years
old. And in our minds, we think of them as that person. And it's almost hard for us to imagine
them aging and you see them and you're like, oh, look how old they look. And I think it's
a natural tendency to think that because you're remembering that favorite movie that you saw
them in. But think about the pressure they feel in that situation. My career is based on my image.
And so if you try to hold on to that 20-year-old version of yourself,
at some point, you're going to cross the line into a natural distorted look. So
there's probably a rough guideline. Your goal should, you know, if you want to look your best,
maybe I'd like to be, look a little like seven years younger than where I am now,
or 10 years. But if you go beyond that, it's a little too much. That's one part of it. I think
the images that we see around us, if you look at some of the, this is part of what I call the
Instagram effect where you're scrolling through and you see these photos of celebrities that have
blown up their lips and their cheeks are over the top or whatever it is. And some of it is
Photoshop, but some of it is from medical augmentation. You start to think that that's the
new normal, but it's overdone. And that exaggerated appearance, people around you in your circles
might be doing some of these procedures. And so you all see each other like that. And then you
want to get a little bigger and just push it a little more. And then before you know it,
you've gone too far and it can be a slippery slope. So I think people start to lose sight of
where they started and what their goals were. Your goals maybe change. And maybe you've found a
provider. There's a doctor or a nurse injector that said, okay, you know, let's take this a little
further, a little further. And then they say, you know, I think you're good here. Let's stop it.
But you want to go further. So you'll find somebody. And so you'll, you'll get to another
provider and they'll do it. I personally feel this way. If someone comes into my office
and they've had something done, I think I can fix them. But maybe you can't or maybe it's time to
say, okay, let's put the brakes on. So I think there's different reasons why people get to that
point. But the technical reason that someone looks unnatural is when you either try to enlarge
something beyond its natural dimensions, there's only a certain point is how far the skin will
stretch before you start to lose the contours. And we say like, you can't have light without dark.
So the goal of your face, the goal of a natural looking face is not to be totally smooth and to
have no curves and no shadows and no lines. When you smile, you're supposed to, you see my brow
elevate and you see some lines in my forehead, you know, I'm, I'm conveying expression, I'm conveying
a message to you that I'm surprised or that I'm angry. And so if you lose those expressions,
if you lose the shape of your lip, you have a cupid's bow where it looks like it dips down in
the middle, or you have two pillows in the lower lip. And if you distort that by just blowing past
all of that and filling it up. And so you have a sausage now for your lower lip. I mean, your eye
will pick up on that very quickly, that that's not natural. You might not know how to describe
what is natural, but you know what isn't. And so you distort the natural dimensions and pulling
will achieve the same type of distortion if you go too far. Facelifts when they're pulled back too
tight, because someone is being too aggressive on the surface of the skin, you see the windswept
look, those type of things where, you know, you see it in older actresses or even actors,
maybe they feel like, okay, I can spend this much money to look like this person of myself. Well,
there's no amount of money that will make you look naturally 30 years younger than where you are.
You know, if you compare, I think people's bodies today to people's bodies 30 years ago,
based on augmentation, there are some inevitable trends. Now, I don't have any data to back this
up, but I can only imagine that breast size is larger today. I think breast augmentation must
be more common than it was 30 years ago. When it comes to facial augmentation, what are the trends?
And I'm not talking about the just the extremes where people have like gone too far, but it would
seem to me that people tend to have fuller lips these days. Is that, would that be true?
I would say yes. And for good and bad reasons, I think we recognize now more and more that global
volume loss is something that's happening to our faces as we age. And that includes the lips. So
lips can be reinflated because they've lost volume in a natural looking way that you wouldn't know
about. I think that there is a tendency now to focus on these areas. So look when you come to
my office and you say, Hey, look at my face. What should I do? I'm probably not going to just say,
like, okay, you should do this, this and this. I'm going to focus on what you're seeing. But I might
point out certain things like, you know, you've lost a lot of volume in this part of your face.
And I know you're focusing on your, your brows for some of me, let's say, but, but I see, you know,
I want to maintain a balance. So it's been, you know, popular to fill these nasolabial lines
next to the lips, you know, the lines that go from the corner of your nose to the outer corner of your
mouth or to inflate the cheeks. But we have to look at the neighboring areas like you're a car guy,
and you get a scratch on your car. Well, you have to paint the panels next to it in order to make
it look good. And so a good provider, a good physician will look at you and say, okay, your
concern is your, your nasolabial lines. But I think we should also just at least consider your lips,
because let's look back at your photo from 10 years ago and look what your volume status was
then. And let's look at it now. So I think in a good way, people are focusing on lips,
but also I think the negative is that there's always going to be some people that are over the
top. And I see it a lot when, you know, when you have a lip injection, you know, typically we're
using hyaluronic acid fillers, which is something that's a constituent of our skin to begin with.
So these are very safe in terms of that they're not, they're biocompatible. There's no allergic
reactions to them in general. And they're reversible. So we have an enzyme that can take them back
if there's something that doesn't look right, or there's an issue. But with these gel fillers,
they tend to be hydrophilic, meaning that they absorb water. And for the first two or three
days after you do it, your lips look like that person that you're trying to not look like,
they get pretty big. So most people for about two days, they're sort of like
homebound or they're freaking out. They're wondering if they overdid it. Yes. But
it's almost a hundred percent of the time, the first time someone does lip filler and they come
back. And I said, okay, you were pretty swollen, I bet for the first two days. And they say, yeah,
but I sort of miss some of that swelling. And so the next time around, we do a little bit more.
And that's sort of like where you have to determine. And that's a personality thing.
It's a personal decision in terms of what is good. And it's a discussion between myself and my
patient. And we don't always agree. My patient might say, I hear what you're saying. You're
telling me this is natural. I want to go a little further. And I'm open to that.
Now, that's something that doesn't like a facelift. Once you get a facelift,
you're kind of stuck with it, right? I mean, a redo procedure there is going to be cumbersome.
It depends on what the reason is for redoing. There's a big, I think, role for revision facelift
surgery. But you're right, when you take something out, right, or you overreduce a nose or you
overstretch someone, that can be very difficult to repair. But obviously, the hyaluronic acid
doesn't last forever, right? Right. So if someone is doing, whether it's an extreme or incremental
strategy of filling, how often do they have to do that?
It depends on the area. So, you know, lips tend to not last as long as other parts of the face.
I do a lot of under eye filler. Under your eyes, you don't have a lot of movement there. Even
though you're blinking, under eye filler lasts a year or two years. I've seen it last four or five
years in some people. Whereas the lips, you're always talking and piercing your lips and eating
maybe six to eight months. Now, you have a very interesting technique of doing the under eye
filler, which I've sent a number of patients to you because I've been so impressed by just
how amazing it looks and how minimally invasive it is. What do you do different there?
So this has sort of become my niche in my practice. And I probably do that one procedure more than
anything else. And it wasn't by design. I didn't plan for this to happen. But it was definitely
an interest of mine. And, you know, when you look at someone's face, the first thing
that starts to age would be the eyes because that's where we have so much movement. We're
blinking all the time and we have the thinnest skin in our body. And combine that with the fat
pads under your eyes, which can enlarge with time because they have a different embryologic origin.
And we're losing fat in our cheeks and the upper part of our cheek,
which that groove where you get that shadow is called the tear trough,
which I don't really like that term. It makes me think of like pigs eating at a trough. But
that trough would be, if you were to cry, would sort of spill down that kind of slide in the
inner corner of your eye. This is what makes people look like they have almost a black eye.
So right from the shadow. Right. And people think, you know, that everyone says I'm tired,
but I'm not. And so when you combine the puffy under eyes with the tear trough area,
you look tired and you might not be, or maybe you are, but you just don't want people to know it.
So what I do with fillers, I use a hyaluronic gel filler and I inject it there, but with a
cannula. So a cannula. So what's a cannula for people who don't know? It's like a needle,
but the tip is dull. It's a blunt tips needle. So what I do is I approach that area from the cheek.
We make a little needle hole in the cheek and then I introduce this cannula through that little
needle hole. So you have no needles under your eye and I can use that cannula in a very accurate way.
And at this point, I know exactly where my tip is all the time. Even though I don't always see
the tip, I know where it is. And when I'm doing this, I'm imagining the surgical procedures that
I do very frequently, which is blepharoplasty. And so because I know the eye, so that's,
blepharoplasty just means that modification of the eyelids through surgery. And so cosmetic
blepharoplasty is often either removing the fat pads, the bags, removing skin from the upper lids
or shifting the fat, whatever I have to do to make your eyes look younger or the way that they
used to look. So I do a lot of blepharoplasty and because of that, I know what it looks like inside.
And so I imagine that in my mind when I'm placing the filler, and I'm placing this gel that takes
up space, and it's replacing the fat that you've lost, or it's also disguising the fat pad that
might be bulging. And so by putting it in the right place and using the right filler, because
there's certainly, there are hyaluronic gel fillers that are incorrect for that area because they
just have the wrong properties, the wrong stiffness, the wrong amount of water attraction,
but placing it in the right area and the right amount.
Is Restylane a hyaluronic acid paste filler?
That's one of the fillers that I use. And it's also amount of, it's having restraint. So
I understand at which point that this will become puffy or look unnatural. And that's where we stop.
And sometimes we stage it, but this procedure will brighten up people's faces who look like
they have bags and look like they're tired. And it's really gratifying to see, you know,
people's reactions to this when they look in the mirror, especially when you do one side,
and you look in the mirror and then you see the difference. It's pretty remarkable.
And so it's one of the things I really enjoy doing. And I think that there's a lot of doctors that
sort of stray away from it either because they're not comfortable with the idea of injecting under
the eyes. There's risks with everything we do. To me, that's not a high risk procedure,
but I think it's perceived as one. I think part of it too is this gets back to your unique
training. I mean, you trained first as an ophthalmologist, which, you know, if I think about
it, like I trained in general surgery, like my scope of what I needed to know was so broad.
But when you look at someone who's training in ophthalmology, like you get to focus five years
on like two inches of a person's body, so your knowledge of that anatomy is unparalleled.
Right. I was narrow to begin with, and then I became even more.
And then you become even more narrower. So it seems to me that the advantage that you have,
and this is certainly why I've always felt very comfortable sending people to you,
is I know that people who understand the anatomy because they've operated,
they've actually been beneath the surface, can do exactly what you describe, which is they're
sort of, they know what the art is. Put it this way, when I was in residency, there was never
any confusion that I would go into plastic surgery when I was in medical school. Like,
I just don't have that artistic capacity. But I would say, you know, at the same time,
you know, I like to talk about my skills, but I don't, I think there's like a political part
of this conversation where the question is like, who do you go to and who's the right kind of
provider? If you want to do something like this, I don't think it has to be a certain person or
a certain kind of person. I think that there are good injectors and bad injectors. I think
there's good doctors. How can people distinguish? So if you're, if someone's listening to this
podcast and they're saying, well, you know what, these bags under my eyes are driving me crazy,
let's say they don't live in New York, so that you're coming to see you wouldn't even be an option.
Well, people come from other places or countries to see me, but I think when you're looking for a
provider for anything, obviously everyone, everyone says, oh, I did my research. Put it this way,
if your wife needed a procedure and you decided, you know what, I don't want to be the one to do it
because there's an emotional connection to this person. And how would you pick the person that
would do this to your wife or your mom? I think you have to find out first, what are the organizations
that certify people? From my field in, let's say, talking about blepharoplasty, I think there's a
handful of specialists that would be competent. You could be a plastic surgeon, a facial plastic
surgeon, an oculoplastic surgeon. I am biased towards oculoplastic surgeons because that's
a big part of what we do. I would look at that first. References like referrals from other
people, obviously, you know, look, if you wanted to find out the best surgeon in the hospital,
you'd probably ask the nurses or the scrub techs and say, tell me, or the anesthesiologists,
because they have firsthand knowledge. So I think referrals go a very long way. And if you know
somebody that had a great result or you know someone who's done something, but you have to
meet with a few people because you might have the best surgeon or the best under eye injector or
lip filler person. And that person could also be a physician assistant. It could be a nurse. I mean,
I've seen some amazing physician assistant injectors that I would have inject myself, you know,
without hesitation. But it's like, do you have a good rapport with that person? Do you think
you're on the same page? Do you have the same goals and style? So it's almost like an interview
when you go for a consultation, sometimes you have to pay for a consultation fee.
But I think it's worth doing that, at least for two or three or four doctors to meet with someone
and say, I get the wrong feeling here, or this office seems frantic, or the doctor just didn't
even really look at me or listen to me. I mean, those things I think are all really important.
So I know doctors that are family practice doctors that are exquisite Botox injectors.
And so I think it's wrong to fall into the political trap of you have to have this label
next to your name, or you have to be this kind of like training. I think that a lot of the training
that I've done was post post your formal training. And some of the training is there are things that
I developed on my own. But for blepharoplasty or eye procedures, I recommend looking at the
oculoplastic organization. But for things in general, I think you should look you look at photos of
people who have their galleries online, they're going to show you their best work. So you look at
those pictures and you say, Oh, those look good. Or some I look at some well known doctors and
surgeons and I look at their photos. And I think this does not look good to me at all. I don't
think this is natural. And they're promoting it as their best work. There are a lot of things that
I see around the eyes where, you know, I preserve fat. And sometimes I'm often adding fat, which
a lot of people don't like to do, because they don't maybe have the same philosophy that I do.
But I see hollowed out eyes and people are pushing that putting that forward is that
this is my best blepharoplasty. Maybe for someone that is, maybe that's the look they're going for.
You should want to ask how many procedures the person has done. Is there a certain
number above which you sort of hit that threshold of, okay, now I've really
You should ask all of these questions, like how many procedures? I mean, look,
I've done well over 1000, 2000 of under eye fillers, blepharoplasty is like, it's 1000. So,
but in early in my career, I did lots of procedures and was probably hundreds. So
you should ask and your doctor shouldn't be defensive about those questions. You can say,
hey, can I talk to somebody who's had this with you? And we do that all the time. We connect
patients with previous patients who are who are open about it and say, Hey, what was your
experience? Or can you say, well, tell me about the complications you've had. And if I get one of
those, what are you going to do for me? How do you, how do I manage that? Do I have to pay
to fix the complication? Those are questions you should be asking.
That's such an important thing in medicine in general. It's amazing how easy it is
to gloss over consent forms. And you just sort of list a whole bunch of generic
complications, but you don't actually talk about what probabilistically or expected
complications could look like. And to your point, what are the next steps? So for example,
you know, with breast augmentation, I know a woman who had these really horrible contractures
develop. And I was like, God, I'd never even heard of that. You know, I didn't even realize
that was a complication. Obviously, I'm not in the loop in that space.
It's actually a common complication. Yeah, it's about 3% I've learned.
I think it could be even higher depending on the type of implant and the placement. So
those are things that surgeons should be saying to every patient that 3% is a,
you know, relatively high rate. Yeah. And you're right. It could be, I mean,
it depends on the implant. So if you're using the different textured implants, it could be as high
as 5%. I mean, 5% complication is really high, right? One in 20 people who do this is going to
have this. And a lot of times on redoes, it still happens, which is not to say one shouldn't
have an augmentation, but boy, I'd be very upset if someone I cared about had that procedure,
wasn't told about that complication and then developed it, especially if they required redo
redo. Of course. And so that going into it, you know, let's say this busy surgeon's doing 20
breast augs a week. And so one, one patient every week is going to have potential re-operation.
So going in, you should know, hey, I might have to do something else. And that's with,
I think any procedure, the risk is relatively low with many of these things. Sometimes we're
talking about one, certain complications might be one in a million. And so you don't have to put
that as like, this is likely for you to have, but yes, that's part of the discussion.
So let's go back to Botox for a second. I think about like six years ago,
one of my good buddies from residency, who's a plastic surgeon, I was just hanging out with them.
We were just sort of playing patty cakes one day. And he was like, Hey, dude, why don't I throw some
Botox on your wrinkly forehead? And I was like, All right, fine. So I like sat down in his little
chair and he whipped out some Botox and put like what felt like 3000 injections into my forehead.
And you know, put an ice pack on it, went home. Classic mistake, though, I think is what you're
starting to describe is treating your forehead directly. Well, let me tell you, oh my God,
I don't remember how long it took to wear off. I think it was about two to three months.
The most miserable two to three months of my life, because this was at a time when I was
a very active cyclist. And I didn't realize it until of course, I lost the ability to do so,
but not being able to lift my brow meant I had absolutely no way to keep the sweat out of my
eyes, even when I was wearing my kind of do rag under my helmet. So I couldn't believe how miserable
I was not being able to lift my eyebrows. So it's uncomfortable. And then it's also a dead
giveaway. So when you look around, let's say you're watching the Oscars on TV or something,
and you want to know which people have had poorly done Botox and it's a lot. It's when the
frontalis muscle, right, which is the only. So where is that for the people who are listening?
That's the forehead muscle, right? Okay. Between the eyebrows and your hairline.
Okay. Okay. So for some of us further back than others. But the frontalis muscle is the only
muscle that raises your eyebrows. So you get those transverse, those horizontal lines across
your forehead and your instinct is like, Oh, I should do Botox to get rid of these. Well,
if you inject the frontalis to the degree where you smooth those lines, because, you know, those
lines are formed by the muscle contraction. So your muscles don't contract anymore. And I said,
they're the only muscles that raise the brows. So now you can't raise your brows. In fact,
they drop, but your forehead will be shiny, smooth. So if you see somebody and they can't
raise their brows at all, you just see smoothness. They were over Botox and their forehead. And we
say Botox as a generic term. It's actually, that's a trade name. And there is the AMGEN product,
right? That one is Allergan. Both Allergan. Okay. Currently FDA approved his Botox,
Xiamin and Disport. So those are all types of botulinum toxin type A. There's slight differences
in the molecules, but they all have the same effect. So the mistake that was made for you
was going after the horizontal forehead lines. And in fact, what,
which seems like a common mistake given on the frequency with which we see this.
Yeah, I think people know a little bit more about it now, but still, I think they use too
many units up there. So the unit is the strength of how much is being injected. But what would
have been better would be to inject the corrugator and proseris muscles, which are the ones that
are just at the top of your nose, but the ones that furrow your brow, you treat that and then
just a light sprinkling in the forehead. So you can still elevate your brows,
but you weaken that muscle contraction. Then over time, if you do it a couple,
it'll last you by four months. And then over time, as you repeat it,
then those lines will soften because you're not making as much of that contraction.
So if somebody comes to you and says, Brett, when should I start doing this stuff? Let's say
someone takes the long view, right? Someone says, look, I'm, you know, whatever, I'm 40,
I'm 30, I don't know what the age is, but I want to know that when I'm 70, I look more like I would,
otherwise when I'm 50, they want to take that view, which is, I'm not trying to look like I did
when I was 16, but I want to really take a long view of plenty of iterative interactions.
Are you looking at a magnitude of wrinkling or are you saying, you know, we start with very,
very small, for example, just looking at that area that furrows the brows, but not touching
anything on the frontalis muscle above it? I mean, how do you think about this from that
I think we have to think from the beginning that you don't have to do anything, right?
Nobody has to do Botox. Nobody has to even spend this much time thinking about their appearance,
right? People do it because it's important to them. And what's important to you might not be
important to someone else. So with that aside, let's say your goal is to look your best as long
as you can. You should probably first start focusing on the preventive things, which can
include neurotoxins like Botox, but it should start with sun avoidance at a young age.
You should do Botox or something like that before you start to get etched lines.
Is an etched line one that means when your forehead is relaxed, the line still shows?
Right. And I think it's okay. You know, I have some etched lines and horizontal
etched lines in my forehead and I think it's acceptable for me and I'm okay with it. I mean,
look, there's a range of what's acceptable. I used to look at Bill Clinton on TV all the time and
I'd see his big eye bags. And when I was in my training, I'm thinking, I would just die to be
able to take out those nice juicy fat pads, but he doesn't care about them at all. Right. And so
it's meaningless to him or maybe he thought about it, but you know, he obviously didn't pursue it.
So it doesn't really matter if it doesn't matter to you. And I think, you know,
it's interesting at the root of all of this is, you know, why do we do cosmetic procedures and
why do some people think it's so important? Why do people think it's nonsense? It's about your
confidence. It's about how you feel about yourself, your self image. And I think that there are some
people that will chase after confidence and may never be able to achieve it. And it's because of
what happened to us in our childhood, our upbringing, the, I guess, the stability that we
had when we were growing up, and it's being able to experience love in your family, experience
acceptance, people that were proud of you. People can say that they love you, but if you didn't
experience that, it's much harder to be self confident and to have a good self image. And so I
think it all goes back to that. I think there's a healthy way to do it. And I think it's not
something that we should frown upon. I think it's becoming more accepted in our society to
have a focus on how we look and how we project ourselves. And I think the best way to do that
is to have a healthy attitude about it in terms of, look, I'm doing this for me.
I'm not trying to impress somebody. I'm not trying to fit in with somebody. And what's amazing
is sometimes a little tiny thing that you wouldn't even know you wouldn't notice it,
but I see people walk out of the office with a different gate or they're smiling when they
weren't before. And we barely even did anything, but it's a little shift in the way that they
were thinking about themselves. And so it's not so much exactly what you do, but how you
help somebody to feel better. So in terms of doing like a neurotoxin, like doing your first
Botox injection, if you're looking at your parents and you see these lines and you think,
I don't really want those lines. So you do it before they start to become fixed lines,
those etched creases, you do it before you get that. So there's not really an age. I mean,
I've injected people in their twenties. I've injected people in their eighties. I think it's
never too late, but there's certainly times where it can be too early. Now, have you ever found
yourself in a situation where you felt it was unethical to participate in the care of a patient
because you felt that they were just being too neurotic or they were asking for something that
you felt was too much? I mean, did you find yourself in that situation? All the time,
all the time. I think that's the nature of what I do. It goes along with it. And so
the way that you look is tied in very closely to your emotions. And when you, especially when
it's your eyes, and I see people all the time that have had poorly done procedures and they're
tearful when they're talking to me. And I see people, I think they're unrealistic. And I try to
guide them. My goal is to be on their side all the time. So in order to sort of focus on overall
wellness, not just appearance, but, but there is, I think there's a connection between appearance
and wellness. And if you seem to me like, you know, there's something else going on here,
why are you chasing after this, this one line when you look, anyone who would look at you
objectively would say, oh, yes, you look younger, you look more relaxed, you look refreshed, like,
what are we really talking about here? Well, maybe there's something else to talk about.
So you're almost having to try to be a psychologist, psychiatrist at the same time.
In a way, I mean, maybe it's also my, my wife is a therapist. And so some of that probably
has brushed off on me in terms of how important it is, having somebody to talk to that's outside of
judgment. And so I think sometimes people need to, maybe it's not just one thing, it's both, it's
having someone to talk to, maybe there's some other issues going on. And, you know, what is your
goal in doing this? Let's go back a little bit further. Let's say someone's listening to this,
and maybe this is a lot of people and they think, look, it's really good to know that there are
people out there like you who can do the most nuanced, complicated grafting, injecting techniques
above, below the eye, the forehead, etc. But what if they say, look, I don't want to do anything that
I can't do as the patient myself, meaning lotions, potions, behavioral changes.
Let's start, you alluded to sun, let's start there. I get asked all the time, and I'm kind of
embarrassed because I just don't know the answer. And I have to say, I have no clue. I get asked
all the time, Peter, what sunscreen should I be wearing? Like, I feel like it's easier for me to
answer like, how would you solve the Iran nuclear missile crisis? Or, you know, before like, I don't
have a clue what sunscreen to wear. It's a complex marketplace, let's say, because the way that
sunscreens are marketed, the way that the labeling is done, can be a little bit confusing. And there
are technologies that are being employed now that are newer that we don't fully understand.
So let's start with the first question, which is, there are some people out there who say sunscreen
is horrible, you should never wear it. I'm assuming you don't think that that's the right approach?
It's absolutely untrue. I mean, I can't feel strongly enough about, look, I see a lot of skin
cancer, and I treat skin cancer, and it's, it's obvious, and it's been well scientifically proven
that there's a correlation between UV radiation and skin cancer, right? So I have to reconstruct
people's eyelids, their faces, their noses, because they've had basal cells, which basal cell
carcinoma, which is related to sun exposure. My wife has had several Mohs procedures where,
which means a dermatologist with special surgical training has to remove pieces of skin,
and then that has to be reconstructed. And you know, I don't think anybody wants to go through that.
Look, the recommendations, the American Academy of Dermatology is to protect children from sun,
and there's recommendations about levels of sunscreen. So you can get your vitamin D,
even if you're using sunscreen. So when we talk about UV, they talk about UVA and UVB,
and you'll see these things on sunscreen. Can you explain what UVA and BR? Traditionally, UV,
you can think about it as UVA, the A might stand for aging, and the UVB is for burning.
UVB is what's responsible for your skin turning red. Okay, they're just different wavelengths
of ultraviolet light. And when you're looking at SPF, they're talking about UVB. The way that
they determine SPF is they will take a subject, they'll do it probably, I think you'd have 10
subjects, this is just done on a person is not like a laboratory test that works well for this,
they still use it on people. So they would put you under a light in a laboratory with UVB,
and they would wait and see how long it takes for you to turn red. And then an SPF, so that's
UVB radiation. SPF 15 means what do we need to put on you that will make you turn red 15 times
longer. It'll take 15 times longer to turn red. And 30. And this is messy, silly question, but
is there an objective metric for what redness is? Like there's a color, you know, how like you can
define colors by the percent red. You can measure the color. Got it. So it's a purely objective
measurement. So it's interesting, SP 15, which seems like very mild sunscreen, still gives you
15 more times. So if it takes you 10 minutes, this is going to take you to, you know, what 150
minutes is like two, two and a half hours, basically. If you look at the difference between SPF 30
and SPF 50, you're getting a difference of, I think it's like a 96 or 96% protection against
UV during that time versus 98% protection. So it's, it actually becomes less of a difference
in protection from those rays as you go up higher. So over 30, you don't get that much more benefit.
So, but you should be using at least a 30, but that's talking about UVB. If you want to protect
yourself from UVA and UVB, which you should, you should be using a sunscreen that says broad
spectrum. Okay. And it's still the same SPF system? Well, no, SPF does not apply to UVA. It
doesn't measure UVA. In fact, there's no measurement of UVA. So if you buy a broad spectrum sunscreen,
it will not have an SPF number on it. Or if it has an SPF, but it relates to UVB. Okay, got it.
Because UVA doesn't cause redness. So you can use that test. Which of the two is more responsible
for vitamin D synthesis? That's a good question. I don't have the answer for you.
All right, we will, we will find out the answer to that question at some point. That should be
known. My, my intuition is it's UVA, but I, I, I don't know. But both are responsible for skin
cancer. Got it. So UVA is can, can lead to melanoma. Now, I remember reading that, you know, I mean,
I've read so many things like you should always have zinc in your sunscreen. You should never have
zinc in your sunscreen. So there's other divisions of sunscreen types. And so there's something called
organic and inorganic, which we also more commonly is termed chemical versus physical. So the inorganic
sunscreens are physical. And those typically use zinc or titanium, which are metals,
as a reflective agent, and it just reflects the rays of sun. So those are the ones that you think
of like Baywatch and you have like the white under your eyes, but they don't look like that anymore,
because now they have micronized versions of those inks and they have nanoparticle.
All right, so smaller particles mean that it looks clearer. You still get a little bit of that
lightish. I gave you one of my sunscreens before. You get a little bit of a whitish hue, but it's
not like a pasty white. Those are the ones I recommend because it reflects the light. Now,
there are some newer chemical sunscreens that are thought to be safe, but there are some issues
so the way the chemical sunscreens work, which are considered the organic sunscreens,
they absorb the UV light and they convert them into heat, which disperses locally in your skin.
So if you have melasma, those type of sunscreens could potentially worsen your melasma.
Tell us what melasma is. Oh, sorry. So it's also termed like the mask of pregnancy. You see darkness
or hyperpigmentation on the cheeks, the upper lip, the forehead. Any dyschromia or brown spots can be
made worse by heat, which is why I recommend against some of the chemical sunscreens. I wouldn't
say it's a blanket statement. Some of the chemical sunscreens also have hormonal disruptive effects,
which is why they're not recommended for children, but I wouldn't recommend it for myself either.
So what are some, maybe what we'll do in the show notes, we'll link to like brands that you really,
really like versus brands that people should really avoid. If you're sitting there at the
CVS and you're trying to get some sunscreen before you go to the beach, are there any ingredients
that are red flags that you should avoid? So I don't like octanoxate, which is a hormonal
disruptor. I think it's debated and how much dose do you need in order to really disrupt hormones,
but I don't really need that at all. If I just would look for physical sunscreen that has broad
spectrum and at least an SPF 30, that's pretty simple. Some of them say they're waterproof versus
not waterproof. Is that a gimmick or is that the real deal? It's hard to measure the waterproof
effect, but they do that the same test, but they're spraying it down with water
in the lab and then they're waiting to see how long you turn red. I think the key is that you
have to apply enough. Most people don't put enough sunscreen on. I'm guilty of that as well. I mean,
I was in Florida a month ago and I'm still sort of tan and I was wearing a wide brim hat and I'm
applying sunscreen, but it obviously wasn't enough. So and you apply every couple hours. I mean,
every two hours you should probably reapply. Interesting. I know people, we don't do it.
I don't do that either. But if you care about how your face looks,
then at least focus on that and maybe your hands too and maybe your chat, what we call the declotage
like your chest. Those are the areas that are going to be exposed. And if you want to look
your best, don't forget about your hands because when you're 70, you'll have brown spots and you'll
have wrinkly skin on your hands. If you don't protect yourself, your face, you don't want to get
wrinkles. So put on sunscreen, wear a hat that has a wide brim. And then particularly for women,
or if you wear a low-cut shirt or you're wearing a v-neck t-shirt, then put it on your chest.
Are there certain moisturizing creams that people can apply that have sunscreen in them,
but they're primarily like, they're not necessarily sunscreen per se. Like
CeraVee is a product that I have used from time to time. It's not a very high SPF. It might be a
15, but I really like it because it's odorless. I think part of the thing I hate about sunscreen
is I can't stand the smell of it and the greasiness of it. But the CeraVee, I'm like, yeah, I can
actually wear this. Yeah, I think 15 is probably low. Look, if we're here in New York City and you're
walking from your home to your office and you're probably getting a blast of sun on your face,
I put on a 30 in the morning. You can do a trial and you go to your cosmetic store,
you go to your dermatologist's office, and you ask to try a couple of them and you feel in your
skin. I mean, the technology is getting better and the scents are, I think, have a wide range
to appeal to a wide range of people. You'll find something that will suit you if you look for it.
What brands do you like? I don't necessarily want to promote a specific brand because I think that
there are so many good products out there. If you look at the medical grade brands,
which are sold in doctor's offices, but you can find them also online. You can find them on some
of the online vendors. Elta is known to be a good brand, MD Solar Science. I like Replenix,
Skinceuticals. You'll find a long list of potential products. I don't mean to leave any
out or focus on those. Yeah. Okay, so then the next thing I want to talk about as far as just
sort of nuts and bolts maintenance stuff is something I've heard quite a bit about and also
have tried from time to time is retinoic acid. So first of all, what is it and why does one use
it or how does it work? Well, so we're talking about a form of vitamin A and it acts like a
hormone in the fact that it works in the intracellular and the DNA level. So it's affecting
transcription of particular genes. It's promoting collagen synthesis. It's increasing the turnover
of skin cells. It's one of the few things that's proven for anti-aging, but also for acne. So there
are a wide range of forms of vitamin A, but it's one of the top three things I would recommend for
everyone to be using if they are interested in having a skincare regimen that's effective.
Now, retin A cannot be bought over the counter or can it?
You can get over the counter retinols. Okay. So the retinol is a less potent
version of what you're referring to, which is retinoin. And do those over the counter versions,
which are obviously less potent, do they have the same efficacy or do you have to reply them
more frequently? They're not as potent, but they have less side effects. So if you have not used
one of these products before and you're looking primarily for anti-aging or for anti-wrinkles,
you want your skin to look younger. So it helps that you have less wrinkles. It helps reduce
pigment in your skin. Someone who's been using retinol from their twenties on, they always look
better. How often should one use it? This stuff can dry your skin out, right? Yeah. So it's less
drying when you're using the over the counter retinol type products. I would start with something
like that if you haven't done it before. And often those have moisturizers or hyaluronic acid or
other things in there that avoid some of that drying. If you do get dry from that, then you can
just use it every second or third day, or you can do sort of a pulse treatment where you put it on
and then 10 minutes later, you wash it off. So you've sort of gotten a short exposure
if you can tolerate that. And that's primarily recommended for nighttime. There's a myth that
retinol is making you sun sensitive. I mean, it's possible because your skin has less pigment in it
and your skin looks younger, but it's more that the retinol breaks down from sun exposure,
right? So it becomes ineffective. I always assumed it was for what you said in the first place,
which is you'll get more burned if you use it. And that's okay. It's not necessarily true,
but it is recommended. We use it at nighttime. I use it every night. Now, if you can tolerate that,
then you can talk to your doctor about getting a prescription for a higher strength. And that's
usually like 0.025% or 0.05% or 0.1. So I'm up to 0.1 now and I do it every night and I have no
side effects, but I use just the generic 0.1% tretinoin. Yeah, that stuff ain't cheap. Yeah,
no, I know. And there's newer generations that also have less side effects, but the traditional
tretinoin works nicely, but a little bit goes a really long way. I mean, you can use one of those
45-gram tubes, can last you several months. And you put it all over your face. Yes. The other
myth. So for guys, someone like me who's got kind of a beard, am I also supposed to apply it over
the bearded area? I think that's tough to do. The nice thing as someone who shaves every day,
that area, when you're shaving it, you're basically giving yourself like a microdermabrasion. So you're
mechanically abrading the outer surface, the surface layer of your skin, which also promotes
skin turnover. So you're probably a little bit protected there, but I would apply it to your
whole face and include your eyelids. A lot of people say, don't put it on your eyes. There's
a myth, I think, that you have skin on your eyes, right, on your eyelids. So that skin, if anything,
it's more effective because that skin is thinner. So you might not use it as often there, but I
close my eyes, I apply it to my upper lids, I apply it all the way up to the eyelash line.
So if we're going to do, we've got two things in our toolkit so far. We're going to put sunscreen
on in the morning. We're going to put retinoic acid on at night. Is there anything else that you
recommend as part of a kind of overall maintenance plan? So like vitamin C would be the third part
of the trifecta. Vitamin C is also- Vitamin C, which most people think of as like a vitamin you
take to avoid getting colds, though that seems to be kind of bogus. So topical vitamin C. And
this one might be a little bit more controversial. I mean, it's not thought to be controversial because
every skincare line promotes their vitamin C. And the question is what type of vitamin C is
effective, but think about vitamin C deficiency, right? What happens to your skin? Yeah, well,
you'd get scurvy, you'd get collagen deficiency, right? So we know that lack of vitamin C is a
problem for the way you look in your skin. If you're healthy, does vitamin C help your skin?
Well, we know it's a very powerful antioxidant. So it's scavenging free radicals. So it's protecting
you from UV damage in that way. It also is a cofactor for collagen synthesis. It turns out
it does work better if you have it with vitamin E. But here's the thing. A lot of the products that
are out there, they oxidize. Vitamin C oxidizes very easily. And the L-ascorbic acid, which is
meant to be- it's thought to be the form that penetrates the best and is the most effective
once it's penetrated. It needs to be stabilized. And so there's different patents that are developed
by these companies. And they sort of have these patent wars, like whose patent is better for vitamin
C. And they try to protect their technology so other companies can use it. You'll find a lot
of stuff out there. And if your vitamin C can oxidize over time in the bottle.
That's why they always tend to- these things come in very dark bottles, right?
Right. And you keep it in your cabinet. Sun damage skin tends to have lower vitamin C levels. And I
think vitamin C is effective in those cases. Why can't they just add vitamin C to sunscreen,
for example? I don't know if it interacts well.
Isn't there something about iron that they put in this as well?
I think the one that you're thinking of that product, which is the C-E frulic. So the C in
the E we know are synergistic. The frulic acid is just another antioxidant. So it's just another
form of antioxidant that's added into the mix. But the issue is- and what I've seen in the literature
is that if your serum levels of vitamin C are high, then your skin doesn't absorb topical vitamin C
very well. So we don't know if applying vitamin C topically is preventing you from developing
sun damage. We know that if you already have sun damage that it helps to reverse it.
And you put this on in the morning or in the evening?
I typically do it in the morning, but you could do two times a day. But I use vitamin C in the
morning and I do retinol at night. And then the sunscreen goes on top of the vitamin C?
Yes. But I don't want too many steps. If I tell you you need to do 10 things,
you're going to stop doing all of them. So but if you can do these three things,
which I think that's pretty easy. You just have to think about your
C in your sunscreen in the morning and your vitamin A in the evening.
Do you have to separate the time between the sunscreen and the vitamin C so they don't
interact negative? I like the serums, the C serums. So I usually wait a couple of minutes
and when it's dry, then I apply my sunscreen. And look, this isn't a universal plan for
everybody. We all have different skin needs. But in general, this is a pretty good plan for most
people. Yeah. If one does this kind of stuff, right, they say, look, I'm going to put the effort
into what I do with respect to sunscreen with topical vitamin C, retinol. As you alluded to
earlier, I'm going to take greater care to care for my skin by wearing a hat, that kind of thing.
What percentage of the benefit is someone getting in terms of an anti-aging regimen?
Is that like half the battle right there? It will go a really long way. I've had patients
where we didn't touch them with a needle. It's been no surgery. It's just been recommendations
and a directed skincare regimen. And look, I'm not a dermatologist, but a lot of what I do is
skincare. Using these powerful basics, I've seen amazing changes. And so when you combine that
sometimes with some other concerns, some directed treatments, then it's synergistic. It's even better.
It sounds simple, right? But it's powerful. I mean, I think that makes sense. I guess anybody
can do those things. You do need prescriptions for at least the retinol, but I think everything else
you... But only for the prescription grade. Only for the high grade, yeah. So kind of going back
to something we talked about earlier, what are some of the trends that we're seeing now? I mean,
we alluded to at least one of them, which is lips getting a little fuller. Botox has certainly been
around for quite a while now. Are we seeing people using Botox in ways today that they weren't doing
it 10 years ago? Well, yeah. I mean, there's many more indications for Botox. We have
non-cosmetic indications, bladder spasms, vocal cord spasms, torticolis, migraines,
axillary hyperhidrosis. Botox is being used for so many different things. And I think we've
developed a more nuanced approach to how we treat people with Botox. I hope so. I still see people...
I even know Botox injectors that have these spock brows. If you've seen that where you get the
overarched, Nicole Kidman sort of had that appearance for a little while, not to say that
she doesn't look good or I don't know anything about how she was injected or treated or not.
But that look is often not desired, especially if you didn't have that look before.
So I still see a lot of those, what I would consider like amateur mistakes or maybe just not...
The field has progressed and most of us have gone along with it. But there's sort of a pressure,
I think, for a lot of physicians to move into the cosmetic realm because the world of insurance
doesn't reimburse as well as it used to. And so we're seeing a lot of new providers in the marketplace
and some of them have more experience than others. But we do have better ways of using
Botox, using it in smaller amounts, spread out over a larger area, using different facial muscles.
We can turn up the outer corners of the mouth so you don't look like you're frowning as much.
We can reduce a gummy smile by injecting above the lip. I can treat the lower eyelids so that you
can look like your eyes are slightly more open or we can reduce some of the squinching wrinkles
that happen under the eyes. There's a lot of ways that we can use this, that we didn't use them 15
years ago or 10 years ago. We've talked about some of this stuff in the past and one of the things
that I think I've taken away from those discussions is that if you're going to have this kind of stuff
done, you really want the person who's doing it to understand the anatomy. That's true. Because
you can see the wrinkle on the surface, but you have to understand that the wrinkle is the product
of changes in musculature and connective tissue and fat. I'm sure when you look at a face,
you actually are almost doing so with X-ray vision. You're seeing beyond the skin. You're
seeing everything that's underneath it and knowing that, well, look, if I actually want to reduce
that wrinkle, I don't necessarily inject into the wrinkle. I'm injecting obviously where the
muscle is. It's not just looking or understanding. It's also asking the patient to move. I say,
okay, I want you to frown for me and I can touch them. I can see where the muscle is pulling.
There's a variation in the way that we're built. Your muscle might come up at an angle and might
be different on the two different sides. It's important to look at those little differences
and to see what's happening. People say, look, I like to avoid a cookie cutter approach. Everything
is personalized. It's easy to say that. Everyone markets themselves as like, oh, we offer personalized
care. Every doctor says that that's what they do, but do they? Are they really giving personalized?
I know in your practice, you're giving personalized care because you're diving deep.
You're looking at things. You're not just ordering. You don't just call the lab and say,
hey, give me a CBC and a Chem 7 and then I'll tell a patient what he needs to do.
You're diving deep. That's truly personalized care. When you're looking at a patient and
if I have a fellow following me, I have to answer to what someone is training.
I have to answer to him too in terms of what I'm doing. If he sees me or she sees me doing the
same procedure in the same place in every patient, they're going to ask me, why did you do that same
thing? I don't because I feel that scrutiny for myself as well that your treatment is going to
be different from the other persons because you look different in your bodies, different in your
muscles or in different places and you have different concerns. That's what personalized
treatment is. It's not just saying it on your website. One of the things I get asked about a
lot by patients and this is why I'm really glad I know people like you because I obviously don't
know the answer to any of these questions is my friend got such and such a laser treatment on his
or her skin and I want to do that and all these different types of lasers and these things together.
Can you give us the 101 on laser treatment for skin?
I think lasers are effective in many ways and lasers are getting better. The technology is
getting better. There's fractional technology. There's different types of energy and it's
confusing though to consumers because you don't know, are you selecting a doctor? Are you selecting
a device? Anyone can buy a laser if you have a certain amount of money and you have a certain
amount of patience and how much of the work is being done by the laser by itself? You just turn
it on and it just happens or is it the provider selecting the right patients and changing the
settings? There's a lot of variables. There are some devices that doesn't matter who does it,
for the most part, like the cryolipolysis, cool sculpting. It's a device that suctions your fat
and it freezes it at a certain temperature and it uses an algorithm to figure out what
temperature needs to stay at for how long to adequately cause apoptosis of those fat cells.
Basically, someone just has to say, okay, this is the area we're going to do it and they stick
the machine on you. There's a little bit of understanding and training that goes into it,
but once you turn it on, it's done. You sit there and it happens and then you-
And is this cool sculpt procedure effective?
It's effective. There are other ones too. There's other types of the sculpture. There's other
devices that also effectively, non-surgically, can reduce fat, but they don't require a lot of,
it's not an operator dependent for the most part. So you turn them on and they're good and so
you can probably go to most places and they'll do a good job for that.
There's a procedure where they use heat and then there's a procedure where they use
cold. What is more effective?
They're both effective. There's a lot of devices, but the two main leaders in the market are both
effective and they're probably equally effective. They work in different amounts of time,
but usually you get about 20% of subcutaneous fat reduction with that course of treatment.
So if a person wants to take a little bit of fat off, presumably you do this on your belly
or you can do it like- You can do your flanks. Anywhere you can pinch fat, you can do it.
So it's subcutaneous fat. It's not visceral fat that's under the muscle, but it's the subcutaneous
fat and it works well. As long as you can apply the applicator, there are some limitations,
but they both, the main devices have FDA approval for NEX as well.
So those devices, doesn't really matter so much about who's doing it. You want to go to a reputable
place. You want to make sure it's the real device. There are Chinese knockoffs that are not FDA
approved. So you want to get the real one. There's cool sculpting as an FDA approved cryolipolysis
device, but I've seen fat freeze or something. And then you look into it and you say, this wasn't
even approved by the FDA for marketing. Got it. So at least make sure you're going with an FDA
approved procedure or device. There are lasers that work on skin. There are lasers-
What are the skin laser? People talk about getting their face
lasered for skin. I've had a chemical peel once a little while ago. I was really,
I mean, this has got to be about five or six years ago, I was amazed at two things. First of all,
how quick and easy it was for this dermatologist to apply this stuff to my face. That's the first
thing. The second thing that amazed me was how red I was for five days and how I had to lather
myself up in aqua for. And then third, I was just amazed at how many sunspots vanished.
Yeah. Well, I mean, that procedure can be very effective. There's lots of different types of
peels. There's phenol peels, which can have more risk, but more benefit. In fact, for a phenol
peel, you have to be connected to an EKG. So you're monitoring for arrhythmias. There are TCA peels,
which can be also equally strong. There's a lot of experience that goes into selecting the type
of peel, how it's being applied, how many layers, what you're seeing. That is a very
operator-dependent procedure. So is there a chemical peel that you would say is,
if you were going to have one tomorrow, that you would preference?
I wouldn't say that. I think that's more of a depends on your skin type. There are certain
things that are not safe for darker skin types. So that's a very specific treatment plan for each.
Questions could people ask the provider to know that that, because really what you're
saying is you have to rely on the provider's judgment to know that.
Very heavily. Very heavily. And you can get a burn and you can get a scar.
So how do you screen out for who the right person is?
Well, it's asking, how many of you have you done? Can you show me examples? And is this
safe for my skin type and what are the risks? So chemical peels are essentially using an acid
or a chemical to burn away the outer layer of your skin. That's why you look so red.
And they go at different depths depending on how many layers of chemical are being applied
and what type of chemical and the strength. So I can use a 10% TCA peel on you and you'll
look slightly red and you'll look a little better. I can use a 35% and your skin will
peel off like a snake. So there's a wide range and it might not be safe for all skin types.
So let's look at me right now. I'm kind of an olive skin dude. I've probably got,
I don't know where I would rank on the sun damage scale, but I would say for you,
either you're looking at a, let's say you want to just do a skin rejuvenation,
you want to look smoother, less wrinkles, improved texture and brown spots. So we would
either talk about a chemical peel, like it may be a TCA peel of 20% and I might recommend three
treatments or we would talk about a laser. So the laser does the same thing that the chemicals do
except it's using energy to burn the surface. Most lasers today are fractional, meaning that
they're not taking away everything like a peel would, right? The liquid from the chemical peel
is going to take off all of your skin, at least the outer layer in a continuous fashion,
whereas the fractional laser is creating dots and leaving some normal skin in between.
So the most common lasers for resurfacing would be Herbium and CO2, carbon dioxide.
And again, within those, there's different levels and different energy settings
and certain patients are not candidates for those and some are. So that relies heavily also
on the experience of the provider. Now there's some very safe lasers that are very low grade,
like a laser like clear and brilliant, very low risk at causing a problem for most people
and doesn't always have to be a doctor performing the procedure. It can,
and depending on your state laws can be an esthetician or a nurse.
And are these painful procedures? Do people need some sedation for them?
Usually no, it means it depends on your pain tolerance. The heavier duty lasers, the more
powerful are going to require some type of anesthetic, whether it's an injection,
topical anesthesia, sometimes sedation. And often we do them in combination with surgery. So my
patients asleep while I'm lasering them, we're doing one thing and then we're lasering another.
That is something where you need a consultation and someone to evaluate your skin type and say,
okay, this is my recommendation for you based on my experience and my knowledge, my training.
But there are also, I think when you would also lump into that category would be the energy
devices that are now becoming more rampant and these are designed for facial adjuvenation in
terms of tightening, not the skin surface. So the first generation were things like
thermage that used radio frequency or today you see all therapy, which is a focused ultrasound.
You're seeing more plasma devices. The idea is heat is stimulating collagen synthesis and
contraction and tightening. And for the most part, I'm underwhelmed with these technologies.
In a way, it's almost like, you know, I kind of referred to like the emperor wears no clothes,
right? Where the doctor has invested a lot of money in this device. And so they have some stake in
it working, whether it does or not. And the patient is investing a substantial amount of money,
potentially for them. And so you don't want to feel like you're a sucker and you've spent a lot
of money on something that doesn't work. But you have to look at the before and after photos.
And if you have a hard time telling which is which, then you're not going to see a lot.
Is anybody doing anything with PRP in terms of facial rejuvenation? PRP, plate-labelaged plasma
has obviously achieved, you know, some success, although I think it is still somewhat questionable,
but at least anecdotally, there are people who are certainly reporting success in the periphery,
for example, treating orthopedic injuries with it.
And it started out, I think, in the dental realm for dry sockets. I mean, I think they sort of
pioneered PRP in a lot of ways. Oh, I didn't know that.
And I think, you know, here in New York, I feel like you can get PRP on every corner now.
It's become so widespread in medical spas and cosmetic practices, because it's so
accessible for providers to perform. And it's always autologous.
Yes, yeah, of course. So what that means for people is it's your own. They take yours out,
they spin it, they return it versus aloe, which would mean you could use it from a donor. So
what do people do in skin with this? I think you probably feel the same way
as me. Whenever there's something is like touted as a cure-all, you have to be a little bit
skeptical. Can PRP help your joint pain? And can it make your skin look smoother?
And can it replace your hair? And is it going to heal all your wounds?
Enhance your erections. I know. So I think it's a nice thought to think that the magic
that we were looking for all these years was inside of us. It's like the end of a Disney movie.
But is it true? I mean, I'm skeptical. I've had PRP injected in my head, my scalp,
for prevention of hair loss. And I'm underwhelmed. So let's talk about hair loss.
The mechanisms that are causing hair loss in men, the antrogenic alopecia,
are still happening, whether I do an injection or not. So how often are you going to have to
do it? Let's say it does work. You're creating, what does PRP do? You're talking about
the platelets in your blood, which are, what is their purpose? They're there to help with injuries.
They clot. They send out signals saying we have an injury here. So send more growth factors. Let's
heal this injury. There's angiogenesis, neocollagenesis. So let's explain those terms. So angiogenesis
means recruiting more blood vessels, neocollagen, more collagen. We're trying to create a scaffolding
and a framework to heal a wound. So when you have a cut on your arm and your platelets go to that
area and they create a clot. They send out chemical signals to also do those other things.
So we do heal ourselves. And if you're an animal in the woods and you get a gash in your leg,
then you'll get a clot there and it'll contract and hopefully if you don't get infected,
then you'll just have a scar. So for hair growth, if you inject it in your scalp, then I think
there's probably a role for the idea is that you're creating an environment
that will help to stimulate the existing stem cells that lie within your hair follicles,
maybe creating more blood flow to allow for more hair or prolong the cycle of hair growth.
Right. So the hairs grow longer. So you have more of them and they become potentially thicker.
But we still have the hormones of 5HT is still in that area and it's still fighting in the opposite
direction. So if you do have a benefit and let's say you do three treatments a month apart
and you look a little bit thicker, then how often do you have to repeat it like every four
months or every three months? Wow, that's a lot of work. And for me, it was uncomfortable. I mean,
look, you can do a ring blot. You can numb the area by injecting all the way around your head.
I drew my own blood, but then I had my dermatologist friend inject it for me. But by the time I did
that, the anesthetic that we injected did already worn off and it was uncomfortable.
But I tolerated it and I don't think it was, I didn't get a great result. I think it's known
to work better for females. But the literature is not very, it doesn't support it very strongly.
I think maybe it will eventually. We just don't have good studies on it.
And do you stratify by, you know, patients that are taking 5-alpha reductase inhibitors,
so a drug like Propecia or Avadart that block the conversion of testosterone to DHT,
the hormone that's responsible for hair loss. And then you can also apply these topical things
like Minoxidil. I mean, you can go all in and that probably is better. Or if you're having
hair grafting, right, like transplants, then it's often done at the same time and do PRP.
So I think I haven't seen any negative to it other than sometimes I think it's ineffective.
And I think it's one of those things also like these skin tightening lasers, the
facelift lasers that I think it's oversold. And the same thing with facial rejuvenation.
You know, it's very popular to do this thing called vampire facial.
What's that?
So that's taking the PRP, which is your, you know, from your own blood. That's where
the term came from. This was like a, I think it's probably like a Kardashian.
How much, how much blood do they need to do a PRP treatment?
Typically, if I'm so, and I offer this treatment, I don't oversell it, but I offer it in my practice.
I'll draw, let's say 10 vials, 8cc vials. So a total of let's say 80 milliliters.
And we spin it down. I do a double spin method. And then we extract the platelets from,
we separate it from the platelet, poor plasma and the red blood cells.
And then we, I activate those platelets. That's also controversial.
There's a lot of different methods of creating PRP and there's a lot of variety.
And so that's one of the problems with the studies that are out there,
that there's inconsistent methods and not everybody is also quantifying how much PRP
are they collecting. Some doctors have counters in their offices and they can say,
okay, this is the concentration I'm delivering, but there are different methods.
And so you don't know what you're getting. Some people are injecting platelet, poor plasma and
platelet rich plasma together and calling it PRP, but it's not necessarily.
So if you're going to get PRP done, you should confirm that the person doing this
has a way of counting the platelets. Not necessarily. I think you just have to
have a proven method of concentrating the platelets. They have to know exactly what
they're doing. I used to have a lot of experience with aphoresis when I was
back in the lab and this was super complicated. I mean, at the time we were identifying,
we were trying to extrapolate or rather identify lymphocytes. So you would put a huge 14 gauge
needle in one arm, draw a bunch of blood out, run through the aphoresis machine and basically return
everything except the lymphocyte. That's serious business. Like you've got to know exactly what
you're doing. It seems that PRP would be similar, wouldn't it? Especially because the platelet and
the red blood cells are the same color. So you can easily be confused by color contamination.
But you can see what the difference is when you spin this down. Yeah, the density should
separate them. The red blood cells are all that bottom section is all red and I don't want any
of that. But when I first started doing it, I did send the samples into the lab and we got an
emergency call in the middle of the night. Your patient has super high platelets and
oh, it's okay. We were just checking it. But I did quantify it initially. I don't quantify it
every time because I'm still using the same method. But then the question is, do you activate the
platelets or do you just put them there and hope that they're going to activate? And what do you
activate them with? You can usually use some form of calcium, like calcium gluconate or calcium chloride.
And so you just... And you dilute the platelets obviously before you inject them
or do you inject them in that concentrated... So I go from that ADCC of initial blood draw
and I end up with about 8cc total of PRP. And that's fully concentrated platelets.
There's a little bit of platelet-poor plasma in there, but I've gotten rid of most of that
platelet-poor plasma. So it's platelets suspended in plasma, but it's highly concentrated and many
fold more than what you'd have in your serum. So the vampire facial, what we're doing is taking
micro-needling pen, which is a pen that has 12 needles at the tip that are surgical small needles.
And these are not reusable. They're per-patient. So it's a sterile setting. This pen has a motor
and it's going up and down, driving the needles in and out of your skin at a selected depth.
It actually doesn't hurt like you would think it does. Come in and I'll do it. I might pass.
But I can do it at a depth of a millimeter. I can do 1.5 millimeters, 2 millimeters.
The deeper we go, the more you bleed. It doesn't hurt like you think. We numb you first with a
topical anesthetic. But as you bleed from those channels, the face looks sort of bloody. And I
think that's where the term vampire facial came, but then we're using the PRP on the surface,
but also applying it as we're doing the needling to drive the PRP into those channels.
So this is a hollow bore or solid bore needle? Solid bore needle.
So solid bore needle creates the trauma. And then how do you get the PRP into it?
So this is variable among doctors and providers, but you can apply it to the surface and then
needle over it. The idea is that you're driving it into the channel. You can apply it to the channel
and assume that it's going to absorb because you have now like more porosity. And you can also
inject it directly under the skin like a filler. I'm not a major proponent of this procedure.
I mean, besides infection, what are the other big risks of this?
It's actually a pretty low risk procedure. I think the biggest risk is financial loss.
How much does this procedure cost? I would say on average, it's about, you know,
let's say 800 to $1,200 a treatment for the PRP with the micro needling.
You can spend a lot of money trying to look good, huh?
Yeah. And you know, it's recommended to do it every couple months or do it every six months.
I mean, so I wouldn't say, I'm not saying I'm against this procedure,
but I don't think it's well proven because look, it's marketed for wrinkles,
for acne scarring, for hyperpigmentation, for anti-aging, most of the time. So again,
look at the before and afters because everyone's going to put their best work out.
So if you look at the before and afters that I've seen, like type in Instagram,
PRP facial or micro needling facial or PRP injections, and look at the acne scarring
pictures. And it's very hard to find good results that are not the result of differences in lighting.
Right? You have a shadowy picture before, and then you have a front-facing light in the after.
And I would say the majority of the time, any benefit that you're seeing is from that.
There's some evidence. There's some evidence that it does help. And on a histologic level,
yes, we're building collagen, but it has to be significant enough to be observable to the people
around you. Otherwise, are we just like making ourselves feel better? Or are we just jumping
on to the bandwagon? Or is it a money grab for a doctor's office? I mean, I'm not criticizing
anyone for doing this, but I don't think it's been fully vetted. And so I think because it's a
relatively safe procedure, I think it's overall, I don't think it's detrimental, but the results
speak for themselves. Is it safe to say then that these are three broad categories of facial
rejuvenation? You've got the chemical peels where you're like physically applying a chemical to the
skin and burning it. You've got the laser peels where you're fractionating and selectively burning.
And then you've got this whole PRP vampire trick. And micro needling, there's radio frequency needles.
I mean, there's a huge realm of devices. And there's a lot of money in this industry. So
there's definitely a drive that's motivated financially for companies to come out with the
next thing. And they have to sell the next thing to the doctor's office.
What is the typical FDA approval process? I mean, a drug typically takes more than 10 years
to get approved. It's not that lengthy. And it depends if there's a predicate device.
So if there's something that's a similar energy, it's much easier. And you can usually get it
based on the previous device. A new device can take longer. It depends. But it could be,
it depends what it is. If there's an IRB study that's been already done, it could be six months,
it could be a year, it could be two years. But you also have to have an understanding that
such because something's FDA approved doesn't mean that it's effective. It just means that it's safe.
Safe, yeah. So there's lots of devices that I think are bogus. And I see them all the time.
And you have to look at what's really going on here. Is it that this industry needs to make
more devices? And I hate to say that I'm not trying to criticize my friends and my colleagues
that are in the industry. But I think we do have to step back sometimes and look at this and say,
who are we serving? Are we serving ourselves? Are we serving our patients? If I do a treatment
on you, and it's not that effective, are you going to come back to me? I mean, you might.
But if I do it again and again and patients are walking, that's not the foundation of my practice.
And hopefully it's not like that for everyone, but everyone has different motivations. And
I would say I wouldn't do something on you that I wouldn't do on a family member.
And hopefully that's how most people are. And it probably is. I think most physicians,
most providers have good motivations, but it's not universal. And so I think you have to be
careful. If you look for a device or a treatment, it's probably better to look for a provider that
you trust than to look for the device. I mean, devices, you can find the same devices in most
cosmetic offices. But how are they being used? And who are they being offered to? And are they
being selective? I mean, there's a treatment that I do now that's called thread lifting, right?
It's a dissolving thread that has barbs in it. And we sort of lift the skin non-surgically.
And more than half the people that come in asking for it, I turn them away because I think they're
not candidates. And I think it's effective in a very select group of people. And everyone
else, I have to say I'm sorry, but I don't want you to walk around saying that it didn't, it didn't
work. So it's interesting that I was in residency. I remember one of the attendings saying something
that I never forgot, which was, he said, you know, your reputation as a surgeon is going to be much
more about the patients you choose not to operate on the patients you choose to operate on. Yeah,
I didn't really understand that at the time, but it certainly has made sense later on down the line,
which is effectively what you're saying, you know, if you, you only need a couple of times where
you've done something on someone who shouldn't have had it done, and it can out outweigh the
benefits of the, you know, the hundreds of people who responded well. Yeah. And those are the ones
you stay awake thinking about, right? We stay awake thinking about the mistakes. Yeah, it's true.
And hopefully you learn from them. I mean, the other phrase that you hear a lot is like,
to the hammer the world's a nail, right? And so how that applies to this field is when you go into
someone's office, are they, are they willing to refer you to somebody for something that they
don't do or that they don't think that they're the best person to do? If someone comes to me and
they want tattoo removal, you know, I might have a laser that can do tattoo removal, but it's not
the best one. If I'm not going to do it on my wife, then, and I'd rather, you know, I'm going to send
her to my dermatologist friend that has the Pico second laser, then I'm not going to push you
into that box. So you, I think you have to be wary too. If you're looking for a solution,
you have a problem and you want a solution and you go to somebody, are they giving you the solution
they have? Are they giving the solution that you need? So that could be another good filtering
question for patients, which is when you meet with a doctor say, Hey, Dr. So-and-so, what are the
types of procedures you typically don't do and you refer out? And depending on their honesty with
that, you may get, you know, better insight into, you know, who they are. Yeah. Or if there's a
procedure, let's say there's a problem that you have and you say, what is your solution and say,
are there other solutions that are out there that you can discuss? So in my area of interest, which
is longevity, I spend a little bit of time, not a tremendous amount of time, but maybe 10% of my
energy goes into thinking about the future. What are the step function changes? What are the things
that are out there that are not a part of what I do today because they're not ready for prime time,
or they're still very theoretical, but they're the things I want to keep enough tabs on because
I hope that within the next decade or maybe beyond, they become relevant.
What fits that description in your field? What are the things that maybe aren't ready for use
yet but show promise? It sort of makes me shudder to think about the future because I imagine myself
20 years from now, hopefully I'm still practicing and I'm going to look back and think like, wow,
you know, we were in Plato's cave at that time, like we were seeing the shadows on the wall
and not seeing the true objects, right? And I think we are in a sense, right? I mean, what is
our, how limited is our understanding and the things that we, we don't know that we don't
know them yet. And so I think there are things, the things that we're doing today that I don't
fully understand, like things like fat grafting, I use it and I think there's some predictability to
it, but we don't fully understand why it works and how it works. And I think some of that relates to
the stem cells, the stem cell effect. And you hear a lot about stem cells being used for all
types of medicine. And it's the same with cosmetic procedures. And I do some procedures.
I think of stem cells, like I think of Chevy Chase describing ball bearings and Fletch,
you know, that scene when he's like, you know, that's all ball. And the guys like ball bearings,
he says, that's all ball bearings nowadays. And it's like, that's like stem cells and ball bearings.
It's just the same thing to me. It's the cure. It's the PRP of the future.
Which remains to be seen how viable it is, right? It's the PRP of today. I think,
look, there's something there. We know there's something there. We just can't exactly
understand. We can't put our finger quite on it. And there's some good science there now.
But I think there's definitely going to be something. And I have colleagues, I have friends
that are doing a lot of stem cell treatments, whether it's intravenous, direct injections.
I'm in a sense using nanofat as a stem cell, you know, that our fat is a rich source of stem cells.
Yeah, this is counterintuitive, isn't it? People have always considered fat to be a
totally inert tissue, but it's actually an endocrine tissue.
That's true, right? And then why are we going to bone marrow first stem cells when it's
closer to the surface? It's right there. And it's abundant in a lot of people.
When I do procedures with fat grafting, and I'm thinking, hey, I'm injecting fat,
and these fat cells are making them look younger. But it might be that the fat cells are not,
none of them are surviving. It might be none of the fat cells at all. It might be the adipokines
or the cytokines. Maybe it's a combination or when I do what I call nanofat, which is the
stromal vascular fraction or the soup that's in between the fat cells. And now I inject that
with the fat. Am I supporting my fat grafts with these factors? Maybe. I mean, I'm seeing
results and we sort of look at the literature, which is limited. And we look at large scale
studies, which are also limited. We're looking for answers in doing these things and we try to
stay safe. But there's definitely a lot to learn when it comes to that particular area,
right? We know that. We look at other types of growth factors. I've seen some promise with
fibroblast growth factor, which is also an injectable. I consider that a biologic therapy.
And in FGF world, which is the abbreviation for fibroblast growth factor, there are so many
numbers to them. Are you talking FGF 21 or? Well, this is something that's not even,
it's not approved in the US. We don't have it here. There's been studies in Asia.
Actually, I don't even know which version. I probably have it in my notes here because I haven't
been able to do it. But basically, are they harvesting autologous FGF from an individual?
No, these are laboratory derived. Got it. So they're basically making FGF as a growth factor
and then just injecting it. Correct. And is this done in Europe? It's done in Asia.
And what's the indication? Volumization, facial volumization. And it seems to have
long lasting results. So is the FDA evaluating this stuff now? I'm not clear about that. I don't
haven't heard of any studies. I don't know if anyone who's part of an IRB, but it seems to hold
some promise. I think customization, like what you do in your practice, and you're going to get
down to the specific gene level eventually. And hopefully we'll be able to have a full map of
everything. And each person will know exactly what drug is going to work well for them. And we'll
be like that, I think, with cosmetic procedures. How is your skin going to respond to this laser?
And what energy setting is appropriate for you versus this other person based on
what your genetic screening told us? I think that's definitely in the future.
I think customization in terms of 3D printing, bioprinting. So let's say there's something
you don't like, you want to change your ear, we'll probably be able to print ears. We'll
be able to print organs. I mean, there's no question that bioprinting is in the future
and we'll be able to replace blood vessels, organs, skin. That just seems so far out. I mean,
as an interesting aside, I remember once being in your office and you showed me a bunch of surgical
instruments that you designed yourself and had 3D printed and they were just perfect. It was like
you knew exactly what you wanted and you were like, well, this doesn't exist, I'll just make it.
Right. I mean, in the past, you would have to go to a manufacturer and you'd have to convince
this industry person of what you want to make. Right, make a fab.
And then they're going to say, well, how many people are going to buy this and how useful?
Well, I don't know, it's for me. It's useful for me, but then they're not going to make an
injection mold for me based on, you know, let's say the 300 eyelid surgeon specialists in the
country, that's a limited market. So with a 3D printer, I just draw what I want and I have it
translated into a digital file and then I print it in a, there's a place in Long Island City,
Queens, and they make it in stainless steel and then it comes to my office and I'm using them
every day. And I've sent them out to my friends and that kind of thing, but we're in the future,
we'll be able to make what we want. Imagine a box that is connected to your computer and
whatever you can imagine will be in that box. And it doesn't have to be just like in silly,
like it doesn't have to be a Hello Kitty made in plastic. It can be made out of multiple materials
and so you can have, imagine your phone. I mean, I'm not trying to promote 3D printing and it's
not my, my practice isn't 3D printing, but let's say just you pay on Amazon and then you press the
button and then it prints the phone in your box and then you have the new iPhone. I mean, I think
that's conceivable in the future. I mean, it's easily conceivable. And so the same thing with
organs, I think there's a big- See, I didn't realize we could go beyond, I mean, I've certainly seen
amazing things in 3D printing where you're dealing with something that's homogeneous,
but a phone is like a completely heterogeneous thing. Well, you can print circuits,
you can print in different materials right now. You can print in different thicknesses and
rubbers. So you can have a soft rubber inside of a hard rubber. So you can print a, let's say you
can print a silicone breast implant, right? And you can make it exactly your shape. So I would
scan your body. Well, I don't know if you want a breast implant. Yeah, I'll probably pass, but
maybe you want a peck implant though, and I would scan your body. Are you saying my peck's
inferior? You can use a little bit of bulk. I know you did the Joe Rogan podcast, so maybe
you're thinking you need to be a little beefier. Yeah, I take a lot of heat for looking too scrawny
on that. But I could scan your body with a 3D camera. I would probably get some CT scans of you
as well to look at your bone structure. We would design an implant that was, and you'd have, maybe
your left peck needs to be a little bit higher, and your right one needs to be a little more
projection. And it would fit your body exactly. And it would be, let's say soft on the inside,
a little firmer on the outside, so it feels like muscle. But when you press on it, it's kind of
squishy like muscle. But why stop there? Why not just make it out of muscle cells? Right? We'll
create a scaffolding. And that scaffolding will populate with cells that we cultured from your
muscle in a lab. And then we populated it onto the scaffolding, and we grow it over a week or two.
And then we just use a small incision and we implant it in you. Yeah, it's interesting. When I
was in medical school, my very first summer, the first lab I worked in was the lab of an ENT surgeon,
and he was interested in growing septal chondrocytes. So taking these chondrocytes,
these cartilage producing progenitor cells, and growing ears. And at the time, a very,
very popular paper by God, I'm trying to remember the name, it was Langer and Vakanti,
two very famous guys in this space from MIT and Harvard. And they grew the ear in the
mouse. And we had that picture up in our lab. And we were trying to replicate it. And of course,
the challenge at the time was coming up with biodegradable scaffolds. And of course,
I haven't paid attention to this problem in 20 years. Well, there are scaffolds now,
there's people that are printing blood vessels, but I think it's a big regulatory obstacle.
I think for me, what I was always interested in was printing in materials that are already approved,
right, like silicone. And I think the living cell printing will be there. But think about
the regulation of if you're in the operating room and you want your tissue printing device,
you have to approve it for every indication. So we have to approve it for making this thing for
this procedure. And you have to, it's, it's, it's like an endless permutation. So the FDA now is
looking at 3d printing, and they do have new guidelines and regard to that. And they're
recognizing that this is the future and that medical 3d printing is growing. But it's definitely
going to happen. There's been use of 3d printed implants in University of Michigan for infants
with trachea, Malaysia. It's actually considered to be 4d printing because these implants change
over time. So the implant can grow with the patient and eventually can reabsorb. But someone with a
baby with a narrow trachea, they were building 3d printed cages and suturing the trachea to the
cage to hold it open externally. And then as the patient grows, the cage and larges and then
eventually can absorb. So the application here goes far beyond cosmetic surgery and it will be
unbelievable. And I mean, it is believable to me, but I can talk about it for another two hours.
It's just, it's mind blowing and it's exciting. And it's frustrating because I want the next step
it takes money, it takes time, and it takes people that are interested. But if somebody's
listening and wants to talk to me about developing 3d printed materials for surgical procedures,
I mean, I have something specific in mind. I've been trying to do that for a while. I have
non-disclosures with a lot of large companies, but it's hard to get someone to invest money
in something that doesn't give you a return in the next two years. Right? That's one of the,
I think the struggles. Well, speaking of people contacting you, I follow you on Instagram because
I just love looking at your before after photos and how can people follow you? What's the best
way to follow you? So on Instagram, it's at Dr. Kotlis, D-R-K-O-T-L-U-S. You can look me up on my
website. I have some videos and procedures in my website. And what's your URL? It's DrKotlis.com,
D-R-K-O-T-L-U-S. But yeah, I share a lot of my stuff on Instagram. I think that's kind of fun
because people can give me feedback and I've seen my audience grow and I'm following you on
Instagram too with your race cars and your family. My nonsense, yeah. It's fun. I think
Instagram has connected me with a lot of people that I probably wouldn't have met otherwise.
The internet and social media has made the world a smaller place in a way. Look, there's a lot of
garbage to wade through, but it's not all bad. I don't think there's anything I do clinically
that is really relevant to Instagram. It's not visual, but it is, right? I mean, I think
people are interested in seeing what you're doing in your day. I'm interested in your routines.
I'm interested in like, oh, what is he eating? What is that indwelling device that you have that's
measuring your blood glucose or what's going on your lap? You posted that picture on your white
board of your, like it looked like your Einstein theories of longevity. I mean, it's actually
very poignant breakdown of your longevity approach. And I've seen you working on the white board,
so I'm imagining you writing that and sort of like constructing your book that everyone's waiting
for. But I think people are looking for insight into your life and into your philosophy and it
doesn't have to be, I mean, for me, it's a little bit easier maybe because I can show a before and
after, but that's not, I think the before and after is not the important thing. The important
thing is like the story behind the before and after. Like this is a teacher and she came to me
because she was recently divorced and she's thinking about finding a new partner maybe or
maybe just feeling better about herself because she's surrounded by younger teachers. Like those
kind of stories to me are the powerful things. And what's important, like what I love about
what I do is that people bring me into their lives in many ways, not just for an injection,
but to tell me about why they want to do it. Yeah. You have a video on your website that
you produced, right? Right. Yeah. So that was just, I think trying to convey my philosophy
in a way that I thought was more powerful about the stories of people who are seeking my help or
my advice. And so I'm always thinking about the next one. I think I could do it better,
but that was a fun project. Well, Brett, I can't thank you enough for this. I've learned a lot
from you over the last couple of years. Oh, and I feel the same way. But I appreciate you taking
the time to sit down today. I hope that people get something out of this. And again, it could be
as extreme as they know that they want to do some of these procedures and now they feel armed to
scrutinize the providers out there and make sure they're getting the best care possible. And
alternatively, it may be, I don't want to do any of that stuff, but boy, if I can just do these
three things, you know, put my sunscreen on, use some rhinoic acid and maybe a little topical
vitamin C, that's going to make a 10-year delta. Well, thank you for inviting me to do this and
for leading the way for many of us in terms of searching for the answers and also sharing those
answers. It's great to see you and I will continue this discussion, I'm sure. All right, see you.
You can find all of this information and more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode. You can also find
my blog and the Nerd Safari at peteratiamd.com. What's a Nerd Safari, you ask? Just click on the
link at the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my
subjectively non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most
interesting papers I've read and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook, all with the ID peteratiamd,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any
medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for
any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest
very seriously for all of my disclosures. To companies I invest in and or advise,
please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about.