Hey Beth, do you have any idea how exciting it is for me to do an in-person
podcast for like the first time since probably February? Yeah I'm sure it's kind
of weird right? It's been kind of interesting just to be around you for
the past like four weeks, five weeks. Yeah you were really stuck in the thick of it
you've been back here obviously in SoCal for as you said four or five
weeks but I think you were you were going crazy in New York for four months.
Yeah it was it was a bit of an adventure you know with COVID and you know I'm
stuck in a very small one-bedroom SoHo walk-up which is beautiful when you're
just like sleeping there but when you're quarantined there it's a little more
interesting so yeah it was it was nice to get a little fresh air with my dogs
and you know just be. Yeah and you weren't just sort of quarantined there in
the normal way you had to basically lead 10 to 11 hours a day of workouts
remotely with your clients you were teaching a rowing class on your rowing
machine in your apartment I mean it was you got more out of 500 square feet than
anybody. More like 350 square feet if we're gonna be real but yeah I had to
completely revamp my work situation and I went from being on my feet 10 to 12
hours a day to being essentially a desk worker which was an interesting shift
but I learned a lot from it. You know Beth I've described you to people as
probably one of the most remarkable physical specimens I've ever met and you
just have a unique ability to you know kind of do what Bruce Lee did in
martial arts right not to put too much pressure on you. Great thing to say at
the beginning. Yeah which is basically be agnostic to form or to discipline but
in you know what Bruce Lee talked about when he created Jyukundo was to extract
what was useful discard what was useless from all disciplines into this agnostic
bucket that really served only one purpose was fight execution and
similarly your breadth of knowledge and at the same time your total lack of
being wed to one system in movement in training has led you to come up with
something that has no name and again Bruce Lee referred to Jyukundo as you
know the way of no way and without form and all these other different things in
many ways that's just sort of what you do and that makes it hard sometimes for
people like me who like to label things and say well wait does this fit in the
DNS bucket is this FRC is this PRI and you're like no no no it's just it's
what's gonna work right now. So how did we meet so Michael Strombsness
introduced us I don't know two almost two years ago. I think January of last year. Yeah yeah and the rest is history but
and I know your background but give people a sense of like where does this
where does this Southern Bell wind up in New York? It's interesting I never
wanted to live in New York but that's another story. I was an athlete as a kid
I was a gymnast I was a martial artist I played soccer I swam competitively and I
danced from the time I was six until I still think I danced but definitely
retired. I was also a musician I was a drum major of my high school band and I
wanted to dance. I actually was in school initially to be a secondary education
Spanish teacher believe it or not and I decided my junior year this was not a
good thing for me and all I wanted to do is dance and I had a guidance counselor
I was like you need to just dance so I transferred and changed my major my
junior year I have a BFA in dance performance from the University of
Georgia. I moved to Atlanta I started in fitness I worked at a gold's gym in like
rural Atlanta this little place called Carter'sville and I got hired with a
dance company that was based in Connecticut but basically New York and I
started touring internationally with this company and I did so for about four
years and then I decided it was time to get off the road I was actually in my
early 30s by then and just decided to make New York my home and it has been
for a while now. So for people like me frankly who don't know a lot about dance
when you say dance do you mean ballet? I don't mean that I am trained in ballet
but this is more it's all it's more physical theater the company's called
Pilobolus it was founded in the 70s basically these scientists from Dartmouth
made this dance technique up called weight sharing and it's it's very athletic
it's mostly a men's company actually traditionally six I'm sorry four men to
women in my particular company we created shadow work so it's it's physical
theater but it's very physical so a lot of acrobatics a lot of rolling around a
lot of partnering and it's actually quite similar to the way I teach to lift
weights it's about sharing the load and working with the weight it's a pretty
cool company definitely worth checking out so more contemporary more physical
theater and during this period of your life how much of your ability to do the
things you were doing were just based on natural ability obviously you're
naturally pretty gifted versus being quite astute and dialed in to the science
of what was going on because you know I remember certainly in my late 20s and
early 30s was when my immortality started to vanish you know I trained so
hard growing up and it just like I couldn't hurt myself like you just
couldn't be hurt in your teens and 20s no matter how dumb you were but by the
time in your late 20s and early 30s like if you're not doing things
correctly it catches up and I can only imagine with the stress of what you were
doing even all of your gifts couldn't protect you so what was the balance of
just raw athletic talent versus very specific you know well thought-out steps
it's interesting because with dance it's very in the moment and that company in
particular is an improv based company wait wait you mean you guys are
improving when you're doing your shows no not when we're doing shows but when
you're making work it's all based on improvisation so it's a lot of intuition
it's a lot of I mean there's definitely like a training time where you're
learning how to work with each other and basically not fight with each other to
make the movement happen but a lot of the the coolest stuff we came up with was
all based on improv Wow yeah so you're dancing how many hours a day at this
period of your life so when we were making so we created a work from the
ground up that's actually still touring so we were in the studio initially for
eight months eight hours a day five days a week yeah and then once we started
touring I actually found touring much harder because you were you know on an
international flight once a week and living in hotels and living on red wine
and chocolate and you know doing a show every night eight shows a week so it was
just you know it's a different stress it's a different challenge to your
system so I actually found touring much harder because I would wake up and I
would be like where am I I had no idea and that's kind of what got me out of it
I was like yeah tired of waking up not knowing where I am so explain to me what
your body looked like when you left that and started in New York were you totally
lean emaciated and wasted because you could barely keep weight on given how
much you were moving around or was that an environment where you actually had to
work to keep your weight down because of the you know strength to mass ratio that
was needed to do the acrobatics definitely had to keep my weight down
but I wasn't actually wasn't so fixated on it because you know number one I was
younger and just traveling all the time and dancing all the time you really
didn't have to worry about it too much I was definitely I had less mass I was
pretty skinny by the time I finished you know touring no butt no legs I mean
definitely stronger than most like aesthetically than most answers would
look like but pretty skinny compared to what I am now yeah yeah so you get to
New York do you have a sense of what you want to do other than not travel no clue
I was basically like oh maybe I'll try the Broadway thing I did a couple of
auditions like this is definitely not for me and I actually did like pretty
intensive yoga teacher training it was like a month long eight hours a day five
days a week very similar to what I can't come from and started looking for
training jobs because before I started touring I actually had a quite
successful business in Atlanta training and teaching group fitness and it just
kind of seemed like the natural fit to go back to that but it just I wasn't
content with the regular gym setting so I was definitely looking for something
so I started teaching once I finished the teacher training I was teaching 25
classes a week I was you know training a gajillion people a day working seven
days a week you know just trying to make it in New York yeah you're like the James
Brown of trainers you're like the hardest working woman in show business
it's crazy I love it number one you know and the hustle is real in New York you
have to you have to live that for a while and it's kind of hard to get out
of that a bit I get to have it we're working on it though yes I know this week
has been working I think I've had more downtime this week than I've ever had
it's good it's good so you you were basically are you sort of freelancing
for lack of a better word at that point or you sort of wed to one gym that
you're working out of I was wed to one gym and then I was working I was
teaching group fitness there and then I was teaching group fitness at a couple
of other studios that's kind of the group group acts way in New York like you
work all over the place that kind of came to a halt I got involved with the
rowing studio that was just openings called City Row so it's funny because
the only reason I really I knew nothing about rowing but it was right across the
street from my gym and all I could think was yes I can stop like running around
like a crazy person and just like walk across the street to teach class so that
was pretty much the end of my running around so it was that gym and then City
Row and that was it for a long time all right so at that point in time what is
your philosophy and and and how were you dividing your gym time you've got
obviously these group fitness classes and I assume that's like what people now
see in an Orange Theory fitness or a Barry's Boot Camp type thing right and
then how much of your gym time is that versus one-on-one with a person
strength training powerlifting etc I was probably doing eight nine sessions
a day privately and then teaching one to two classes a day okay yeah so what was
your when you're in as far as the private stuff what was your philosophy
at that point in time where were you you know what was your North Star how did
you guide people basically do no harm just try to keep people as safe as
possible and make it as pretty as possible you know try not to load people
too much and just keep them safe and how did what was your what was your
knowledge base at that point just general strength and conditioning you
know I I went to Exos which is it's a center they usually train a lot of
professional athletes they do a lot of combine training I did a lot of them I
did all of their mentorships actually so you know it basically it turned into
like basic movement prep a lift and then some sort of energy systems development
work pretty basic and just trying to keep people as safe as possible I mean
when I think back on my sort of strength training career is not the word I'm
looking for I think just trajectory is probably the right word I'm just I don't
know I'm surprised maybe at how unsophisticated it was I'm not I mean I
guess surprise is also the wrong word I'm amazed we don't get more hurt with
how unstructured it is in the way we teach people how to do things where you
can cause a lot of damage yeah right a back squat a deadlift an overhead press
you know these are things that frankly speak to the resilience of our species
that we just pretty much always do these things biometrically incorrect and then
we load ourselves repetitively repetitively repetitively for the most
part people kind of limp through it so where would you put yourself on the
scale of the average sort of trainer back at that stage of your or maybe maybe
a better way to think is what percentage of the person you've become
today were you at that point in time oh like 30% okay wow so which is probably
still pretty good right yeah yeah you know everyone got strong enough and and
they won't really get hurt yeah so what was sort of the first thing that began
you know or at least put you on the path to where you are now which again is you
know I've sort of built you up maybe in a way that you're uncomfortable with but
but you know having this sort of completely integrated systems approach
to wow there are all of these different philosophies that we've got to you know
start to integrate into how we get people to move and then how we load them
and right I think when I first started training I remember thinking I didn't
understand why people couldn't do what I could do like I didn't understand why
certain things were hard or impossible and that was something that kind of can
you give me an example like why can't someone squat like what is limiting them
from being able to squat because you've never not been able to squat perfectly
right not that I've never been able to squat perfectly but I've always been
very movable and good balance and relatively strong and I just didn't
understand and I wanted to understand what was limiting someone so I
you know would see all these accommodations and and compensations happening and
things that were just impossible and learning issues like why can't that
person learn what I'm telling them to do and my kind of frustration not with them
with me not being able to help them led me just to really diving into a lot of
continuing education so I actually left the gym that I was at and I went to
another gym which was more more of like a like a true strength and conditioning
setup the gym I was at prior was more of like a spa setup and I really I wanted
to learn more about lifting I wanted to learn more about Olympic lifting power
lifting had you done any Olympic or power lifting yourself until that point I
had a mentor that I worked with at my first gym who was really into power
lifting and he taught me a lot of the basic lifts and I was just kind of
naturally good at some of them but I wanted to know more so I started working
a gym called Soho strength lab downtown anything that has lab in it is gonna be
awesome right I agree there's this place here called swim labs in San Diego I'm
just gonna make a plug for them yeah freaking amazing yeah yeah best swim
school that's awesome I mean this was a it was a really good place for me at the
time I learned a lot from those guys they were you know very smart very you
know attuned to strength and conditioning some pretty talented
Olympic lifters coming out of there some just strong dudes and women actually so
it was good for me to be there but I also wanted to be kind of on the
physical therapy side of things so I started working one day a week in a
clinic and that's how I was introduced to functional range conditioning so went
to the cert was just like wow it opened up so many doors for me of like why some
things could be challenging you know how if we don't have a lot of
proprioception and awareness of where our body can go in space motor control
that it won't go there actually so that was kind of my first situation with
really diving into continuing education past just a regular strength and
conditioning cert well I definitely want to come back to FRC you know your
comment about squatting is an interesting one I started squatting when
I was about 13 you know I think I've told you the story you know I just kind
of got in with a bunch of older men like they seem like older men they're in
their 30s you know which when you're 13 they seem like they might as well be a hundred
who took me another wing and just you know got me power lifting and I think
when you start somebody that young and you're around these monsters who are
squatting six seven hundred pounds you just you grow and you do that thing but
I remember always being amazed like and feeling these I something you did which
is I would try to teach somebody to squat and I actually had no idea how to
do it in other words I could teach somebody who had the natural ability
which means I did they didn't need me in the first place but anybody who didn't
have either the ankle flexibility the hip flexibility the balance this stability
all these things I couldn't do anything I could never understand why and it's
funniest thing about two years ago when I met Michael maybe it was a little over
two years ago Michael Strom'sness he did something that it was like the biggest
aha moment I've ever had which is he said have you ever met a person who on
their back can't do a perfect squat yeah and I was like I that's so much easier
right like if you lay anybody on their back you can put them into a perfect
squatted position so why is it that everybody laying on their back can be in
a perfect squat right and I'm talking perfect where like you know hip
extension knee extension hip flexion knee flexion you know below like
everything is perfect but under the load of their own body weight very few people
can do that and you start to realize that's the stability piece if you can't
even stabilize the weight of your own body there's no way you're gonna be able
to load yourself and so for me that was like this moment of holy cow there's
there's a whole world here I've never considered understanding so what was the
first thing you saw in FRC which maybe we should take a step back and explain
what FRC is after you maybe explain the first thing you saw but I want to spend
some time understanding this because it's one of the many systems you now
bring into what you do and how you coach right I think the biggest thing
was like you can't go where you don't know right so if you're working on in
range joint control explain what that is so we like to live life in our mid-range
so it's very comfortable there we're very used to being there but if you
think of like overhead flexion like your in range would be way back here but you
probably have more than that depending on a lot of situations but if you're so
used to going just here over and over and over again and you're really able to
go here this is the area you don't know or the area you can't control and their
whole thing is like control yourself so it was interesting to me you don't think
about you don't if you don't use it you lose it so you know our assist our brain
our central nervous system is quite a lazy one and if you don't kind of remind
yourself where your end ranges are you'll stop going there digress for a
moment to tell a story about the first time you exposed me to this do you know
which story I'm gonna tell I have no idea it was doing a tricep kickback and
range and well you went you went to the dumbbell rack and you got a five pound
dumbbell and I remember you walking back to me and I was thinking I wonder
what she's gonna do with that other than like I yeah yeah like I it wouldn't even
hold the door open like what could you possibly be doing with a five pound
dumbbell and then you had me get down on my hands and knees and maybe we'll even
demonstrate this exercise afterwards because we're gonna this podcast will be
accompanied by a great video but you had me do basically what amounted to a
tricep kickback but at end range so full shoulder extension you know
accompanied with scapular retraction yeah and I think I got to seven reps
before my triceps seized and I couldn't do anything right right and I just I
just couldn't imagine that that muscle which you know ostensibly is strong in
its mid-range oh yeah could be so weak and deconditioned at its end range right
I mean you have to think you're like you're in maximum stretch on the
opposite side and you're having to control that length with the regressive
side the opposite side and it's your weakest at your in range yeah just show
people the position I'm in from a explain all the terms you just said so
we talked about the scapular position yeah retraction yeah and then depression
extension or yes shoulder extension and then you're adding load onto that with
elbow extension yeah and again with five pounds with five pounds most people I do
that body weight first and they're like I should feel pretty good about myself
yes totally thousand percent I was so annoyed by that and then the next day I
just went to the eight pounds and you were like you're such an idiot like now
you're doing it incorrectly you're caught you know right because when
you're working in range you have to actually hold in range if it drops out
of it then you've lost it and to really get in touch with the mechanoreceptors
like you have to be on in range it's a stimulus that your brain wants but it
won't it won't fire to it it won't pay attention to it unless you're actually
on in range so you know one of the things that you started talking about
the first day we ever met was you were very attuned to scapular mobility which
resonated with me because I have very as you like to put it gooey I just had the
gooeyest scapula if that's the plural word for it yeah when did you start to
recognize the importance of that scapular girdle because again I don't
think a lot of people walk around thinking about this and thinking about
the pathology that results when a person can't control it well the cool
thing about your scaps is they're super movable right and they sit right on the
back of your rib cage and they kind of guide where your shoulders should go and
they guide where your rib cage should go so when you are in scapular protraction
to show people what protraction would be a reach which we're all made to do so
we have these beautiful rounded ribs at the back you have these triangular bones
exactly sit over them and as you said they glide up and down but when you get that
good reach you get a nice retraction of the rib cage which allows air to go into
the back of your rib cage which I could talk about that relationship for hours
but it it gives you more of a three it helps with breathing it gives you more
of a three-dimensional or it can assist with the position in particular
breathing exercises I should say but it assists that three-dimensional breath
which is so incredibly important for for stability but also kind of guides where
your shoulders should go extension flexion all of it because your scaps
move accordingly so what muscles play a role in that and why do most people have
the inability to control it because one of the first things that you start
having people like me and others do are cars which we're gonna spend some time
talking about just as a way to start having people understand what that
mobility cycle is cars to kind of teach you where your scaps are like I the
step one is to know where they are and then you can kind of figure out what you
can do with them but a lot of people don't even realize because they can get
stuck for a lack of better words on the back of your rib cage and you can if
you don't use it you lose it so you can kind of lose a sense of awareness of how
they can move or even if they can move I don't think I ever thought about it I
mean and this is I'm someone who had I think above-average kinesthetic awareness
always played a sport that involved my upper body so it was either boxing or
swimming or you know something where you'd think I'd be attuned to that no
chance never gave it a thought right well it's as it can be a couple of things
it can be a stress response to hold them in retraction so they're kind of loaded
retraction elevation if you're if you don't have great load tolerance in your
hands and wrist these guys will always try to help you out and that kind of
becomes your new normal and it can it can impact breath it can impact gait it
can impact shoulder mobility all of it so there's I mean there's a couple things
that I always try to see cars number one I want them to know where their in
ranges are and what their scats can actually do with minimal accommodation
from head rib spine and then I want to show people a scapular car and tell
people what it stands for sure so cars stands for controlled articular rotations
that is a movement that you learn in functional range conditioning so
basically you're trying to make the biggest circle you can with minimal
accommodation so head trying to stay as still as possible ribs not going along
for the ride spine not going along for the ride and also for me it's
maintaining breath like if you're having to hold your breath or like
hyperventilate to do a scap car like we got some things to work on yeah and when
we started them we were doing them in squares because that the coordination
for me was so hard circles are hard you know and creating us because you'll see
sometimes when people don't have the ability to control it they'll go circle
jump circle jump they'll kind of skip over this I call it like a neurological
hiccup skip over a range that they're not used to being in because the brains
like uh-uh uh-uh yeah so I like to start in squares first because they're easy to
visualize and they're very easy to control so it's like step one step two
step three step four and then you're trying to get that circle to move
consistent and so it's elevation protraction depression and you will not
change one thing at a time nice and smooth coordinated and when that gets
easy we then do it under load which is really hard yeah so then you make it more
closed chain and closed chain meaning your hands aren't free anymore they're
more like the open chain is the hands with the feet are on air closed chain is
they're on the ground or on the wall or something I try to get people to close
chain as quickly as possible so I'll put them on the wall to be less load because
I want their fingers and their hands to be experiencing load because they should
all the time but it's tricky when you start adding load or adding speed your
bad habits your your I shouldn't say bad habits that's wrong your strategies show
up you know yeah so elbows start bending spine start moving head start moving
so now you're getting pretty deep into the FRC world and what are the what are
some of the other things you're bringing back into the gym from FRC and actually
before we do that give folks a bit of a background on FRC and its use application
I think that's the one that was formed by the Canadian chiropractor right Dr.
Andrea Spina yeah yeah he's a chiropractor was created they have a whole
system functional range system so they have a soft like a manual therapy part
of it and then kind of more of the the strength and the strength application of
it so the biggest thing was like using isometric input to remind your brain of
where you are or what you can control so they do they also do pales and rails
progressive angular isometric loading which basically means you're putting
isometric input into stretched stuff and then the regressive side is actually
owning what you've just kind of stretched essentially give a little bit more of an
explanation of those things so the way they set it up or the way the system
would set it up is you would hold a stretch let's say hip external rotation
you would find your in range of hip external rotation hold it for two
minutes get the system to kind of accept that you're holding the stretch
because you know when you're on an in range of a stretch initially you're like
no you have to kind of give yourself time to calm down and accept the stretch
from there you would do an isometric input at various intensities and then
you would do a isometric meaning force without movement exactly force without
movement so you would push into that stretch trying to and you actually feel
more sensation to the stretch so it's really great when you're working in that
capsule full of mechanoreceptors it's great for communicating to your brain
like okay I can actually be here and work here and own it right so be there
work there and then the rail regressive angular isometric loading would be
moving in the opposite direction to pull you into more stretch and if you're
truly on your in range it ain't moving at all so it can be quite frustrating
and it's it's hard to pull into your in range but it basically gives you the
opposite side tissue to own your stretch so let's also put each of each of these
down as things will demonstrate when we get into the gym I think I can certainly
remember a few times that you had me do these and they're they're hard you just
don't feel like you have strength and coordination when you're at that end
rage to them it's stressful it's super stressful absolutely and it's you do get
a temporary mobility gain after that but it has to be practiced for seems like
forever to make it happen just like with anything so I mean FRC is one of its
stated goals is is sort of developing greater movement obviously in mobility
yes is it more of a PT slash rehab school of thinking or is it more of a
performance based school of thinking performance based I would say it's I
mean the functional range release the the manual therapy part of it is more of
obviously a PT I've actually taken a couple of those courses just audited to
check it out and it's basically the same kind of deal like you're holding the
input because all input is stress and you have people push into it and then
relax push it so you're you're basically teaching them where tissues are by
having them isometrically push which is it's pretty interesting it's it can be
insanely helpful for increasing proprioception so what did you see when
you started bringing FRC back to the weight room I mean clearly better like
controlled movements more coordination absolutely did you did you meet
resistance I mean from from people saying come on I just want to like do my
deadlifts and do my bench press oh yeah oh yeah a lot of tall-talking this whole
life talking convincing you don't do that with me I'm pretty accepting it for
sure you know at that point I'd been training my clients for so long that
they're like Beth did another thing and she's just trying stuff which was great
mostly mostly in this in the like weight room setting I was using cars and then
isometrics to you know get people to experience feels if you will before we
would lift doing some pails and rails at the end because it's not good to do
pails and rails before you lift because I tried to do that I tried to max out
once after doing pails and rails and I nearly died I was like goo essentially
just kind of neurologically fried because it's a lot it's a it's stressful
on the system but I didn't meet you know I'm really big into educating you know
why we're doing this trying to make it accessible so people were people were
doing it you know I had some people that were like man I'd be like well I'm not really
on train anymore you know but it went well it went really well actually so
another one of these sort of schools that you've integrated is something
called the postural restoration Institute PRI how did you come in contact
with PRI um you know same same idea working in the clinic and just kind of
doing a ton of research and I wanted to just went to a course and wanted to
check it out the first course I went to was actually a pelvic course which was
crazy because I had no no idea what they were talking about at all because it's
more designed for PTs and chiropractors a lot you know some strength and
condition coaches use it but it's mostly for in the clinic type things but I just
kept taking courses I've taken I think almost I've definitely taken all the
primary courses I've been to their advanced integration and a ton of
secondary courses actually yeah what's the overall philosophy of PRI so they
it's um how do I explain this they put people in patterns so they say you know
basically your liver is on your right side so you're gonna naturally have more
diaphragmatic compression on the right side so we're going to tend to kind of
spin towards that in times of stress and it creates different deviations in
movement so makes you quite asymmetrical and it can create pain and discomfort
yeah so basically that would be a left AIC pattern if you're really kicked to
the right so in a left AIC they would say that your left side of your pelvis
your left rib cage is kind of stuck in external rotation and your left side of
your pelvis would be in it would be an interior tilt right so if this is if I'm
looking at you and this is my right side the left side is tilted a little bit
more forward yeah which makes more makes your right leg more of a standing leg
and your left leg more of a swinging leg right and again part of that is that
we I so I always knew most people preferred to load the right leg if
they're standing anybody can try this at home just notice anytime you're standing
there you're gonna prefer and she'll want to stand on the right side I assumed
it was a dominance thing but when I met you I remember you saying it's probably
more to do with we get more compression from the liver on that side and I do see
it in most people I kind of assess I do see that they prefer their eyes I do and
I'm a left-handed that's right you're a lefty and one of my kids is a lefty so
I'm looking forward to seeing how that turns out but yeah it'll be interesting
all the lefties out there I'm curious as to whether when you catch yourself
you're your right side loading right so the whole the whole idea is because
you're on that right side a lot especially in times of stress that
you're gonna get more repetitive injury on the right and you know the left side
just becomes kind of weak and almost useless remember the day we met so
that's January of 2019 some miserly cold New York Day do you remember what my
only complaint was right SI right SI just and elbows right elbow yeah a little
but really it was that right SI that on some days didn't bother me and I could
deadlift like a beast and then on some days I just I couldn't deadlift as heavy
as I wanted to and that was sort of it and I really I thought other than that
everything was fine right and then we did your squat assessment yeah yeah should
we include the pre and post photos and the show notes please I think I have it
on my phone okay what did you see in your squat assessment I saw you standing
on your right side I saw actually a dent right above your elite crest like
from the compression on the right side I saw a left scapular hike and you were
spinning out slightly to the left which is remarkable to me given how quote-unquote
well I thought I could squat like I guess I could squat deep I had total
balance and control like I could mm-hmm but it's when you showed me the picture
from behind that I was shocked right I mean it was so clear how much I favored
my right side in that spot and you had later you talked about some right knee
pain but yeah it's pretty interesting to watch that spin out it was very clear on
you yeah yeah so tell me about the ribs cuz boy if there's another thing that
you just hammer into people it's the ribs yeah it's your center of mass you
know it's it it's respiration is one of our constant stresses because you do it
20,000 plus times a day and if you have the same strategy for dealing with
respiration whether it's a big vertical inhale or a big vertical inhale that's
asymmetrical or you know holding your breath it's it has an impact on you so
putting you in making sure that your breath can be wide and three-dimensional
and easy is is vital for creating good efficient coordinated movement now for
some people their first exposure to even the awareness of the breath is yoga or
maybe even Pilates if you meditate you know for example if you do Vipassana
meditation you know that we use the breath as a object of focus but it's not
taught I mean in other words it's not a forced breath it's just you're breathing
naturally but you know for me I think Pilates which I did a couple of classes
with my wife back in the day and actually found it quite interesting I
could just never make the time for it was sort of my problem but I distinctly
remember the the woman that was teaching me sort of putting her hands on
my back and just sort of having me breathe into her hands and you know
that sort of resonated years later when we started doing some of this stuff and
I was like oh okay that's that's interesting of course by that point I'd
already been really exposed to DNS which you know in and of itself was just you
know an incredible experience to be able to then learn how to breathe into my
pelvis but these things are not mutually exclusive you can breathe wide
and deep and create the right structure within the rib cage correct yes yes
because when you take a full inhale your diaphragm descends which you have two
diaphragms right and it they both descend so the more to reverse engineer
it the more productive your exhale is the more productive your inhale is going
to be because if you're if when you exhale your ribs should go into internal
rotation so inhale exhale but if you exhale and they stay put and you go to
inhale again that you just you only have one way to go and that's up and what does
that person look like how does that person show up to you pretty significant
not pretty significant it could be very subtle but usually an interior tilt a
bilateral rib flare retracted scapula sometimes the forward head and what type
of symptoms do they have what's their problem what are they where they struggle
plantar fasciitis knee pain hip flexor discomfort anxiety lower back pain
shoulder pain neck pain all the pains yeah I mean not all of them but one of
those or two of those or more it's it's kind of amazing how numb we can become
to certain chronic tensions right like the you know that that sort of
consistent nagging trap tightness that you almost forget is there until it's
finally under control right you can finally put your shoulders back down
yeah well they can unload yeah so another constant stress is gravity right
and how how are you working with or against gravity so if you know if you're
not breathing well for a lack of better words and if you're not dealing with
gravity well that has a high cost you're having to hold this and you're gonna have
that loading all of the time so what do you think is the root of that problem
like is there I don't know if we could I mean there's probably some anthropologist
who could speak to this but presumably our ancestors never did more than they
needed to right they would have conserved energy they didn't want to
fight gravity more than they needed to so presumably we evolved in an
environment that didn't promote the movement patterns we have today would
you buy that I think that external like stress has a big thing to do with it
like not sleeping well not sleeping I'll just say well staring at a screen
because your your eyes are always fixed on the screen so you're missing out a
lot of the peripheral parts of vision which is stressful because you don't
know what's going on around you you know a lot of people think that this just the
sitting part which the sitting part is rough it's never good to be in the same
position all the time but I think it's more of you know your eyes are always
fixed you're worried about meeting a deadline you're worried about money and
so that's interesting so you you know because I would have said oh look the
root cause of this is sitting you're saying it's probably that's just
probably one of the components of it it's sitting plus a lot of chronic
stress as opposed to acute stress because I suspect our ancestors had tons
of acute stress like tiger is there you know this guy's gonna kill me you know
to whatever but but probably not a lot of worry about as you said mortgage
payments and divorce and and footwear I'm guessing too has played a pretty
harsh role in this is I got I got to think that going from a minimalist
pattern to a heavily supported pattern has altered our attachment to the ground
well yeah it goes back to that whole thing if you don't use it you lose it
right so if we're never experiencing load through the toes and the forefoot
and you're never it you know feeling your feet so to speak you're gonna lose
that and you're gonna you know with those squishy heels you're gonna kick
back and stop I mean I've literally seen people just standing there and
their toes are just popped up because they don't even know their toes exist
yeah we're what what gave you the evil idea to start doing that toe yoga
actually I got that from FRC actually oh it's a part of their morning routine and
it's funny cuz I it is so hard and I assist a lot of FRC certifications and
to watch these people try it for the first time their brains are about to
explode and they're like holding their breath and squeezing their fingers and I
mean it's a it's basically how well is your brain able to communicate with what
your feet can do so was I like in the top 10 worst initial I wasn't great like
was I how bad was I most people trying it for the first time that have never
really tried it aren't great yeah maybe just using your hand as though your hand
is your foot and assuming your thumb is the great toe yes go through the
assessment the whole idea is you want to keep all four bases of support if this
would be my heel and then lifting all five of them up and can they can they
abduct that's huge because a lot of people are like so can they abduct number
one and can you without changing that these guys so no curling can the great
toe go down and then also can the lateral fore go down in the big guy up
without with minimal ankle movement just to see if they can dissociate and and
something as simple as that you could make the case that if you're not doing
that your feet aren't fully connected to the ground I mean it shows like how well
your mapping is like if they don't if they can't move if they can't dissociate
you probably aren't using them when you walk and that is they're just like
fingers they they dampen stress they dampen force and you know you've got
people that are you know when you're walking your that force is one time your
body weight but as you start running that increases and as you run faster
that increases more so it's just a bunch of just pounding yeah I think I'll never
look back I mean I don't own a single pair of non minimalist shoes now for
exercise if not for anything and I just can't imagine not exercising barefoot or
with a minimalist shoe right and making that transition a couple of years ago
what a difference it's made to be able to really start to experience my feet I
mean I took it to a whole level for a while I was using toe spacers 24 7 I had
the toe spacers you could wear during exercise I had the ones that you would
use to stretch out your toes when you were just sitting around and I mean it
was really a it was a big transition for me I mean I don't know why I don't know
again if that's just a normal pattern for someone who's now crammed their feet
into shoes for so long tight shoes or a big I see that Morton's neuroma just a
tight squeeze and you just you're not using them anymore so your brains like
cool I don't need to think about them anymore yeah and you sort of I don't
know I'm thinking you may have made the example it's like imagine you had a
glove on your whole life and then you took it off but you really had no
ability to move your thumb in a different way from your fingers right how
limited you'd be and your ability to like transmit force to the outside world
and and resist force right and you know people don't think about their toes and
their feet until there's a problem but I mean you have to there are above your
waist is two-thirds of your mass they're basically supporting that mass all the
time and pushing you through space so and then actually the way we met was
through Michael which I alluded to and Michael met you through DNS yeah I was
at I think exercise to I met him January right before like a couple weeks
before I met you actually so talk to me about then your foray into dynamic
neuro muscular stabilization you know I didn't I never super like did a deep
dive into DNS I thought it the positions were great I love you know how you use
your developmental patterns from three months to walking I love kind of reverse
engineering that and putting people in some of those positions I think it's
great I love the the talk about developmental you know just skills and
how we lose them as we start moving around this um you know I have three kids
and my youngest is three and I'm sure my other two did the same thing but I
didn't have an eye for it but now that I've been into DNS for two years
watching my three-year-old move is like being at a DNS seminar with the world's
best teacher right he is like a little prodigy he's little like it's like a
little Prague school prodigy and I just can't believe it I just can't believe how
innately these kids load perfectly and move perfectly and do so efficiently
right like you watch him get up from a from a position without using his hands
just rolling his load from the greater trochanter down the femur over to the
knee and boom he's up and it's like he didn't even miss a beat yeah and you just
think that the fact that we are born with that neuromuscular control is so
humbling is so remarkable is such a testament to evolution right and to
think we flush it down the toilet by the time a kid is six years old right yeah
because they're not they're missing out on the chance to roll around on the floor
anymore after they go to school yeah yeah it's I mean that's what we're
designed to do move around efficiently and then once you stop it's it stops
it's amazing when you look at people as adults and think how did we possibly
come from kids like that and and I guess for people who don't know much about DNS
and you know at some point I will absolutely be doing a dedicated podcast
to that as well but basically it you know it came from a school in Prague
that initially I believe was interested in understanding how kids with cerebral
palsy cerebral palsy could be trained right or retrained to move by going back
and teaching them developmental steps that they missed based on what kids
without CP learned so it started out as really a PT school that said hey kids
with CP missed this step from it from it from a neurologic standpoint and
that's what's completely impaired their movement pattern as adults what if we
can as kids train them to do the the non-seat you know to do the kids without
CP do and from there of course it then morphed into wait we could this is a
school of thinking that can help people without CP and so through that lens I've
you know I found it to be just you know remarkable but again going back to the
way I sort of introduced you most people I interact with are practitioners of one
discipline right they are very steeped in X very steeped in Y or very steeped in
Z you don't claim to be the world's expert in any of these things but you
like to borrow from all of them including many we won't get to so now
let's talk you know fast forward to where we are now which is you know
you're the interloper who's taken from these systems you know and you and I
have had many discussions and maybe you're you'd like to share there are
aspects of each of these systems you actually don't find particularly helpful
is there any that stand out that you're like you know for the work I do I don't
think this aspect of PRI or FRC or DNS is helpful I don't think you're gonna
offend anyone I know you're worried about I think that I like to look at the
human that I'm working with and you know sometimes doing cards is not what they
need you know what I mean so they might need more distal control more distal
load tolerance they might need just to control their rib cage so then and
they're hyper stress and I call them hot with anxiety they might need to just lay
down and breathe to kind of tap into that parasympathetic side that PRI
would give you sometimes people need to be up regulated so doing a higher
intensity pale and rail would be great but nothing's a one-size-fits-all
because we're all so different yeah I remember you once talking about I
remember what the example was but it was a great one I wish I wrote it down about
oh I remember most people are of the mindset that a knee
valgus is a no-no and we want to do everything we can to avoid it maybe
explain to folks what a knee valgus is so when you're doing a lunge for example
the knee would cave in towards your midline right and I think for most part
people would agree we'd like to minimize that yeah but you don't take a purist
view of that your view is not that you know knee valgus is evil no I say train
you because it happens sometimes and if you have someone with a chronic knee
problem or discomfort or pain let's put them in that position and teach them how
to own it because that might be part of it you know what I mean your brain's
number one job is to keep you safe to protect you if every time you go into
valgus it doesn't feel comfortable that could be a part of the problem so train
knee valgus because it's going to happen in life you're going to bend down to
pick something off the floor and your knee is not going to be perfectly in
line with your hip and your second toe it's going to happen so if every time
that happens there's pain or discomfort let's figure out why and see if we train
it if it's less discomfort now does that mean you would let somebody deadlift
heavy with a valgus not necessarily well it depends I'm not having a lot of
people max out let's be real and things get ugly when you max out but if you're
lifting at 65 70 75% I think they should be pretty yeah I really do it that is a
deadlifting is a sport and I think that unless you're a power lifter and most of
the people I'm working with or not like when I maxed out my debt my heaviest
deadlift it was not like it was ugly and I trained for things to be pretty but if
you're just training someone in the gym and they want a deadlift like keep it
keep it to a dull roar keep it conscious pay attention and keep the
tech as technically sound as you can so how much of movement do you think is
kind of or should be conscious versus should be subconscious like how do you
and I guess let's start with two types of movement let's start with basic
movement walking you know grabbing something out of the cupboard etc and
then let's talk about something very advanced like a deadlift or you know
pick your favorite sport right I think that movement everyday life should be as
subconscious as possible I think you know a lot of people that are in pain or
discomfort or worried about hurting themselves have this really big but
bracing strategy in their trunk and that doesn't leave a lot of space for things
to go wrong things going wrong meaning like your dog running in front of you or
lights turning out that could be very broad but to create a person who is
reactive and adaptive and resilient so to speak they have to be able to respond
to different changes in their environment so if you're so fixated on
making things so conscious that space is out the window so opening a cabinet and
grabbing a cup should be pretty subconscious you should have enough trust
in your limbs for your midline to reflexively load so your nervous
system doesn't have to think about that so much now most people when they do
that are doing it subconsciously but what if as you evaluate them doing these
things you realize their movement pattern is unsafe and is going to be you
know leave them susceptible to injury how do you take them from
subconsciously doing something incorrectly to subconsciously doing it
correctly being very cautious about it so if if there are muscles around their
spine are quite loaded like meaning they're an extension I would have them
work in a way to unload them to give them a little more space because this
has a high cost things are working yeah my posture isn't the best I've always
noticed this what is it about posture and what does it tell us there's no bad
posture that's my biggest pet peeve actually and every person that I do an
assessment on the first thing is like what's wrong with your posture there's
nothing wrong with your posture I know I love how you love this thing all right
let's talk about posture okay the only time it's bad posture is when you don't
have another option like if this is your only option that ain't great if
this is your only option that ain't great you should be able to move all
sorts of ways and have options because that's when things go wrong when life
presents you something and you don't have that tool so training people in
different postures is very important exposing them to different postures
allowing their you know midline stability to be reflexive and not brace
and not brace on one side being able to load and unload accordingly so how does
one translate that to something like okay I'm sitting at a desk and I'm gonna
be typing for a while is the idea that one should vary their position from you
know I'm here I'm here you know move it around like what's the what's the sin is
the sin staying in one position for as long as possible I think yes I think get
up and move because I even find I do more computer work now than I ever have
especially since Covid and I'll find myself because you your no
perception just kind of turns off like you forget that you're supposed to
actually move so it goes back to that whole thing if you don't use it you but
what about certain things like you know for example we don't we know that too
much looking down is going to create unbelievable cervical you know strain I
don't know if I can answer that I don't I honestly don't know if I can answer
that because you know there has been studies where no you know there's it's
just like saying if you're deadlifting with a flex fine all the time there has
been studies that it doesn't create any problems but you know I would have to
you would have to do an assessment to see the full picture of the human to see
so what's going on what do you think makes that difference because I agree
with you that there are two people that can have the exact same movement
patterns and yet one gets injured and one doesn't and what do you attribute
that to or what what could explain those differences how they tolerate load and
is that genetic or is it a function of these other stressors in their lives I
guess it could I guess it could be genetic but I would probably say more
environmental I don't know if I can answer that a hundred percent but I
would definitely if I had to like make a guess I would say more environmental
stress how how are they tolerating load you know someone might be able to really
tolerate load well like this for whatever reason so how do you then
incorporate that into what you do so when you see somebody and you assess them
how do you know if what you're seeing is a problem versus an adaptation there's
no way to answer that like it's kind of one of those things which came first the
chicken or the egg all I can do is address what I see so if I see them
standing there and their response to gravity is to be here then I would want
to give them a different option for that this is not bad but it could be
causing them discomfort so let's see if we give them a different option if that
gets them out of discomfort and makes them more adaptable you know I also do a
lot of like visual and vestibular testing just to see I obviously too much
of that is out of my scope of practice but if they have a glaring vestibular
issue I'm gonna train head movements to make them more responsive and I guess
part of it could also be what they're presenting with symptomatically I mean it
so it so I when I showed up and met you I was complaining of right SI joint pain
and then my movement pattern matched why I would have that pain right if I had
shown up with the exact same movement pattern but no pain whatsoever would you
have taken me down the same path of correction probably to some degree
because you had less stretch ability or mobility on the right side of your rib
cage so I would want to give you that option yeah what do you remember sort of
the general path you took me down how did how did we sort of address that
issue plus the scapular gooeyness probably my two biggest issues right we
did a lot of breathing work with you in the beginning a lot of still do a lot
of compressive work because you were presenting with a pretty significant
bilateral rib flare like that was your strategy for deadlifting for life for
walking down the street and I like how you say it that way I like how you
describe it as a strategy to me that's it's funny too it's making light of it
like because you know how much I love talking about objective and strategy and
tactics so it's like I have a strategy everyone I'm going to flare the hell out
of my ribs not just on one side on both sides make it real hard that is how I'm
gonna get through the day mm-hmm and what so when I flare those ribs I'm gonna go
into much more lumbar extension right you're pretty and you have a history of
you know with your surgery and and that could be you know maybe part of the
reason yeah you know an apprehension thing you're afraid maybe to let those
unload so so my QL's which are these they are big muscles in the lower part of
your back loaded they're locked and loaded 24 7 ready for anything and
that's not uncommon there's a lot of people that go through life locked and
loaded in the QL's ribs flared mm-hmm interior tilt of the pelvis yeah high
cost limits variability yeah it makes it's so interesting to me because to go
back to my favorite the scaps it it impacts your gate you can't swing your
arms anymore when you're like that so then you can't move the rib cage to load
the leg and it it has it changes a lot of things how long does it take to
typically unwind that type of a pattern in somebody long time and it's it can
make it a hard sell because people will feel better once they start to learn how
to either load things that need to be loaded or unload things that need to be
unloaded they'll feel better but it takes a while to kind of stick so to
speak and it can be it can be frustrating for sure because it's a
process so how do you motivate someone to do this I mean you've worked with many
of my patients I want to have you working with many more of them and
you're right it's a hard sell there are a lot of people who are like that's not
for me I got my trainer we we do we do really fun stuff with you know boxing
mitts and yeah body weight stuff and TRX and we do our thing three times a week
I don't need to meet Beth and do her silly exercises yeah it feels good to
crush it I mean it feels good when I crush it like I I love it the jumping
around heart rate going through the roof like that feels good but if that's all
you do you're limiting your options and you're not efficient while you're doing
it and when things have a high cost they either break or it just makes it much
harder so what is your strategy then for communicating to people the importance
of this or do you not do that and just say look you're not in the in the you're
not in the position of trying to explain to people the value of this it's either
they're gonna see it or they're not and the ones who see it you're gonna guide
them and the ones who don't they have to wait until they get to that point in
time I mean I educate the best I can I try to I'm very real when why is it
happening I mean I don't want to use anybody's names including those people
who have spoken publicly about you but but what do you think it is that's there
are some people who the moment I introduce you to them it's like love at
first sight there's an immediate connection and they immediately respond
to what seems like a reduction of pace what seems like 25 steps backwards what
what do you think are the traits common to people and I would put myself in that
category I mean I basically stopped doing any bilateral hip hinging for six
months I didn't do a deadlift I didn't do a squat you had me doing only very
light split leg movement for six months yeah I mean it was kind of infuriating
I remember so pissed but I believed you that there's something I don't know what
it is I think I just believed it's I think there's just little you can see
little improvements like oh my feet don't hurt quite as bad as they used to
or I could you know I'm always I'm always reassessing like I want people
and taking photos of everyone I want people to see and even if it's this much
I'm like but we're going in the right direction and it's going if it's done
right it's gonna be this much at a time if you see vast improvements it's just
it's not gonna stick that's just not the way we work so I'm always taking pictures
of people I'm always you know it's very subjective like my feet feel better and
I ran another an extra half a mile and I had no you know pain that's a win like
you have to point out the wins yeah I'm trying to think back I mean I think at
some point clearly my right SI joint stop hurting in fact it's been so long
I it's hard to even remember what it felt like that's a that's a huge win but
I'm trying to think what it what it took to get there I remember for me one of
the wins and this will be hard to explain but it's the first time you had
me lay on my back so knees are up feet are flat okay so we had this was you
trying to get me to contract my left hamstring do you remember this yeah I
think so so it's basically so knees up right and it's contract push and pull
push and pull with a pelvic tilt without losing the tilt without losing
the pelvic tilt and I couldn't do that you would want to fire abs to make it
happen yes and then my pelvis would flip the wrong way and it's like why can't I
control this left hamstring mm-hmm and that was really weird and I was like oh
I'll never be able to do this like this is you might as well ask me to grow an
extra foot and then one day it just happened like I don't it might have not
been that long it might have been like a month later it was like oh my god this
is so easy now because I think when we first started doing it there was an aid
I forget what the aid you put me on a block right and now it's like oh my god
like I can do that totally I can do that blindfolded on the flat ground it's
it's so easy to find as you like to put it to find my hamstrings to me those
were kind of some of those those were some of the things that said oh my god
these really little things they start to work I mean the people that are
successful like you pay attention when they practice and that's it's hard to
pay attention especially to the same thing all the time when for the longest
time it it will turn on and turn off and turn on and turn off and it can be
so frustrating for sure but having that control over your body you have to pay
attention to control it well I definitely am looking forward to to
working on you know kind of creating a cool curriculum around how to teach some
of this stuff with you because as you know this centenarian Olympics is sort
of my obsession and I think honestly unless you're you know training for the
Olympics or your professional athlete whose livelihood depends on what you do
here and now everybody should be training for the centenarian Olympics
what other sport matters that's why you should exercise yeah then being the best
person who's in their 90s who can crush everything and everything should be an
extrapolation backwards from that and it kind of begins with all of these
things around strength stability movement control all of these systems I
think one of the things that you've discovered through COVID is you can do a
lot of this remotely I can and it's so funny because I have so many requests on
social media for online training I was like no way uh-uh and then COVID hit and
I basically I was like sorry guys I'm shut it's shut down and I started doing
you know 10 12 virtual sessions a day and it was such a learning curve and it
was so challenging so what did you learn like what what is it that has enabled
you to become about as good as anybody out there virtually training you gotta
you have to be very clear with your words and it's you know it was for me it
was practice paying attention and practicing you just you have to be very
clear where you want them to be and what you want them to do and you know
demonstrate and now do you find it so I remember the very first time we did a
virtual session which was probably in March actually it might have been April
because I remember thinking I don't want to do it it's gonna suck it's gonna be
a waste of time and I was but I was just also like in Beth withdrawal and I was
like okay fine I'll do it and I was like so pleasantly surprised at like how
efficient it was it felt like 90% of what we had done in person do you think
that's only because we had already worked in person and you knew me enough
actually no I have so many patients now that I've never met in real life it's
it's interesting like so many probably now more than I've never met in real
life that I actually have worked with and put my hands on and that might be
increasing so and and and do you find that it's just a vocabulary issue that
the patients need to understand like I'm trying to imagine how hard it would be to
explain to somebody for the first time what protraction with depression of the
scapula is like at least I had the luxury of always knowing what those words
meant just from medicine but that's that's hard stuff for normal people
don't who don't have the lingo training what I found because we have a pretty
extensive exercise library now is they'll get the first kind of introduction
with me as I'm doing our assessment and then they can see the video and I think
it actually makes for better learning because they've been exposed to it they
can kind of review the video and then feel it out for themselves and then
we'll check in in a couple weeks and it's like wow that's really cleaned up I
think it makes for better learning because you have to have more
responsibility to do it on your own you know yeah now the other part of this is
you know someone listening to this might think well I mean do you actually do any
real training with these patients like yeah and and then that's it my favorite
story is the guy who what did he decide he was gonna pay you a thousand dollars
for every inch you put on his butt he did and he did pay you he did pay me
three thousand dollars today actually too I'm working on another too yeah
you're gonna get it you're gonna get a couple thousand more dollars I love that
I love that bet that was the best one ever totally no we I like to lift I
totally like to lift I'm a meat-headed heart so what are some lifts that you
just think everybody male female thick thin should be doing like what is I mean
you're a huge deadlift fanatic like oh yeah we trap bar and straight bar every
single week is there anybody who you don't like putting through deadlifts a
lot of people yeah is it because they can't do it yet or I just for me I love
split leg work I mean I personally hate split leg work and I make myself do it
but it's so applicable to real life so tell people like what is when you say
split leg work tell people what you mean split squats walking lunges single leg
guardiels you know I you just get so much bang for your buck as far as like
hip stability and you know just kind of owning your movements as opposed to
bilateral work which you could kind of wriggle yourself around I think part of
the single leg tragedy I use tragedy kind of lightly is it exposed it's like
the it's like the tide going out and seeing who's doesn't have their bathing
suit on you really understand what's wrong right right absolutely because
you're you know you're only as good on two legs as you are on one I think yeah
so so is it your goal to get everybody to be able to do a deadlift at some
point if they want to yes I think but I to be a successful you're saying you can
get somebody you with a bunch of split leg work you can you can functionally
get them to do the same stuff yes okay yes and you know the whole thing is is
like how well can they do their work without you know holding their breath
and how well do they actually own that work how much of their legs actually
working because you can wriggle yourself around and use you know anti-gravity
stuff and just like you do walking through life so I want to see how with
how much integrity can you do that are things coordinating well together is it
efficient can you actually breathe because that's important so what are
some of the things I mean you've seen my list I think of 20 activities I want
to do be able to do in my 90s and maybe not talking about what your specific
events are in your centenarian Olympics what are some of the principles of your
centenarian Olympics in other words what is a 95 year old Beth either want to be
able to do specifically or conceptually I want to be able to be independent okay
yeah like I want to be able to walk to the grocery store and carry it all back
just like I do now you know I want to be able to walk upstairs you know I
personally want to still be able to do a pull-up and a push-up just one at least
and you know dance is such a big part of my life I want to be able to keep up
like it's not gonna be as pretty as it was when I'm now but let's talk about
dance because that's I mean there's so much going on there like and we have
patients that you take care of for whom dances their life they're in their 60s
there you know and they couldn't be in better hands because to be working with
someone who knows the discipline and then knows what challenges lie ahead
what does it mean to be able to dance into your 90s because that's a whole new
level of coordination balance from just walking right it totally it's just
there's more variables but I think just being able to recall what you've just
learned cognitively it's so good for you to be able to put your body in
different positions and have those options I think is wonderful I think
every you know I have a couple actually have an 80 year old and I make him
recall choreography very simple like it's nothing fancy or flary but it's
like a jazz box step touch and I'll do it in different orders and make him
recall it because I want him to think I want him to pay attention do you make
him do that thing I do with the little colored little things I have to hit I
brought the blaze pods no but I do play other like the switched on game that I
played with you just you know I want to know that he can respond and if he trips
great he's learning how to not fall and then he has to recover from the trip
actually it's you know I'll have him do step like tap-ups on a short box and
then I'll call out a different number he's got to change movements and like
not miss a beat making him be reactive and pay attention and multitask can can
balance be trained yes so you can take a person whose balance is oh so so and
make it better yes and preserve it presumably yes it's a top-down and a
bottom-up approach but yes so say more about how you would do that after an
assessment I you know they might have a vestibular discrepancy and they need to
be exposed to loading their vestibular system because a lot of time balance is
basically how are you dealing with gravity how well are you dealing with
gravity so or as you would like to say what's your strategy for dealing with
gravity a great strategy you know I would do I would do basic vestibular
training with them you know just is that some of the stuff you have me do where
my eyes are closed yeah well I would have them do yeah eyes closed to work
proprioception of the lower leg because you need for your lower legs to be
adaptive and reflexive because I've always felt I don't have good balance
right and I feel like I feel like it's improved yeah and I just feel like ever
since I mean when I was young when I was in my teens I badly sprained both of my
ankles like probably it's a miracle I didn't tear all the ligaments but I feel
like they got stretched to the point where like my ability to everton invert
my foot now is comical the laxity of those and I feel like from that point
forward my balance just yeah I mean never was the same with injury chronic
pain surgeries that can disrupt mapping yeah so it can really impact your
proprioception but part of my centenarian olympics goals like one of my centenarian
goals is a balance goal right because I realize things that we can all do now
you you just take for granted now boy when you're 90 like no way I mean
everything naturally declines anyway so I mean that's and that's what I tell my
40 and 50 something I'm like yeah you're great now but that's not gonna stay
great and the more you ignore it the worse it's gonna get I'm not saying we
should all like you know be standing there with our eyes closed for a whole
session but it's okay to check in oh yeah I mean I'm as you know I'm pretty
hard-nosed about this stuff because my view is the decline is nonlinear and I
don't think the average person especially if they don't have a great
facility with numbers and mathematics you know most people don't comprehend
nonlinearity we're pretty good at understanding linearity mm-hmm well
between the ages of 20 and 30 this thing went up by you know this amount yeah it's
gonna go up the same amount from 30 to 40 we can we can comprehend that but when
you think about the physical decline a person experiences from 20 to 30 and
then 30 to 40 and then 40 to 50 most people are like yeah I kind of got a
handle on that and what they don't realize is that the rate of decline is
going much it's just it's accelerating so dramatically and what you do from 50
to 60 to 70 is amazing now again people who have you know been able to watch
their parents age or have spent enough time around people who are elderly will
realize that if you don't put an astronomical amount of work into it the
decline that occurs between 60 and 70 and 80 is from another world yeah it's
interesting because I have a client named Barry I'm just I'm in love with
very 80 year old Barry oh my god I post them on my social media all the time he
can do six trick push-ups now like he's he's a badass but when I met Barry I
guess three years ago now he couldn't get up and down off the floor without
assistance he was in so much discomfort walking around because he spent 50 years
just working like you know very successful making money doing his thing
but trading health for wealth but Barry is an animal like I have to tell Barry
to stop going to the gym twice a day so much attention into it and he does all
my little like weird coordination things and balances with his eyes closed but
Barry is incredible and he I mean he's 80 doing like I call it the Barry get up
like his get up variation and he can get off the floor from his back only
using one hand touching the floor that is so important right and let's talk
about that for a second because if you're a 40 year old and you can't do
that there's a problem so every 40 year old can do that but that becomes so hard
when you're 80 yeah I mean it's yeah and and and it's important to also
understand what the implication of not being able to do that is right there's a
safety part of this right if you can't get up all and if you fall and you can't
get up without someone assisting you there's an enormous safety problem if
you live alone or something like that let's put that aside for a moment and
just talk quality of life a big part of the centenarian Olympics as we do this
with our patients is getting them to you know literally do the exercise right so
you 47 years old now your kids are 12 6 and 3 and now map forward add you know
45 years to where you are add it to the kids extrapolate how old the grandkids
are going to be and maybe the great grandkids and it all kind of works back
to this thing that says when you're that age what's going to matter well I know
that when I'm that age it's not going to be podcasting it's not going to be
working it's not going to be you know it's it's basically going to be yeah it's
gonna be enjoying what's left of time with friends family and doing activities
that I like and nothing else and a big part of that because I still have the
luxury of having young kids is kids play low like kids play down they're on the
ground and you can basically be stuck in a rocking chair sitting back in the room
and not being a participant with them or you can get with the get the doll
play in the dollhouse get the Lego get the trucks and get on the floor and if
you could get up off that floor using your own you support that's a huge
difference from because you're more likely to do it than if you can't get on
the ground and get up because if you can't get up on your own I just think
you're gonna be less likely to do it and I think if you're less likely to do it
you're gonna start to pull back and distance yourself from those activities
it's a whole like spirit thing too right yeah so what do you think about these
guys these muscles here your abs my abs your six pack yours in particular no no no just in general
I mean they're a thing if you're a bodybuilder they're a thing it's not a
big deal yeah I noticed like there's no abs like I'm not doing crunches and I'm
not doing a lot of you know hanging knee raises and stuff like that and I'm
not paying we're not paying any attention to my six-pack yeah I mean do
you need quick flexion or your gymnast no no yeah and you know that rigidity can
impact your ability to be adaptable and reflexive I've actually been doing a lot
of study with I can integrated kinetic neurology which they do they have a big
like top-down bottom-up approach and their whole thing is is like you know
to make a resilient robust human how reflexive can you be that's the whole
thing because inevitably you know something's gonna go wrong and you have
to be able to respond and if you have a bracing strategy you can't you lose
variability things can't go wrong because you can't handle it and then
that lessens your options this is something that I think probably only in
the last three months have I really started to be more aware of and maybe
it's just that you're doing more pointing it out to me which is how often
I do revert to bracing my rectus abdominis muscles for pretty much
everything we've made some huge strides in your deadlift the past like four or
five weeks because of that just teaching you like you don't need to
brace like you're picking up a car it's only 275 only you know yeah yeah when
we're doing relatively light stuff yeah I'm hindering myself by overdoing it
totally totally and you know when you have that much attention on your bracing
you can't think about your legs but even this the simpler stuff we should probably
do a demonstration when we get into the gym later today of the the breathing
exercises where my heels are up on the block you know the difference of being
able to do that posterior tilt with your hamstrings yeah to use the hamstring
versus the rectus abdominis to tilt the pelvis is everything yeah and not saying
that that's the only way that you would do that but that's a different option
most people don't have that you know so I want them to have that every time you
take a step and have to use your hamstring you should not have to tip
into an anterior tilt or you shouldn't have to brace you know I mean you are so
obsessed with the posterior chain it's really it's just such a beautiful thing
one of my favorite exercises that I've never done until I met you is kneeling
curls so why do we do our curls kneeling as opposed to standing because I
want to get a lot of bang for your buck at that bicep curl I want you to have to
use your hamstrings to keep you from falling forward because you're loaded in
the front and if you're playing with scapular protraction as well you're
getting a lot of like reflexive ab tone you should feel abs and hamstrings
they're like I love it yeah in fact I kind of do it as a hamstring exercise
that makes me feel so good I actually taught you something no it really does
like I I do it as part of my hamstring loop right it's great because I don't
find doing biceps all that exciting it's like one of those things it's kind of a
chore for me you laugh at my little skinny arms but I it's such a great
hamstring exercise yeah I mean like I'm not and I love a bicep curl I have
people do it you know it can really assist with loading tolerance to help
with shoulder pain and all of it but if you're gonna do it you might as well be
in a good position good position yeah to get more out of it any other sort of
general principle so again I'm trying to think of all my Beth isms there's so
many but but your your obsession with hamstrings is is is sort of comical well
they help hold your pelvis in place is that I'm just trying to figure out how
much of that was just specific to my pathology or is that something that is
generally a theme for most people because it took me a while to
understand the why right which is and again if it took me a while I think it's
gonna take the average person a while because the anatomy I mean I could at
least picture the anatomy of the pelvis here the Istio tuberosities the
attachments of the hamstrings and if you have no control over those guys pelvis
is all the way over here you've got and so how do you do this well again this is
a great way to explain it Peter strategy is flex the muscle in front
shorten the muscle in front and you lift up from the symphysis pubis right so
you've got the pelvis wraps around here you've got the symphysis pubis is the
attachment of the rectus abdominis so one strategy to pick this thing up is
shorten this muscle that's flexing your abs that's always been my strategy oh
yeah but that makes it impossible to get a good exhale exactly because where's
the other attachment it's to my xiphoid which is in the middle of this rib cage
so that strategy sucks and then people are like you have great posture though
yeah and you have nice abs right fabulous but how do you feel right and
so and I always thought well my hamstrings are totally strong but I had
no control over them that's the and that that was a fundamental difference I
don't think I had weak hamstrings I could never I couldn't on-demand get
them right and therefore I was never accessing them when I needed to and it's
funny like when we met my deadlifts were basically quad dominant movements
right you would kind of slip your knees forward and scoot under it yeah which is
it's a good strategy if you're trying to use your quads and you don't care that
much about your back right totally yeah hamstrings hamstrings hamstrings hamstrings
toes it's a thing yeah how many people that you work with are in sort of
chronic real pain because I don't think that my you know right SI joint was
constituted chronic pain but but do you have people that come to you that are
really suffering from something significant I have in the past and a lot
of it is just kind of down regulating to kind of if you don't you have to make
space for them to make change and if you're really hot like I like to call
it you have to let them down regulate a bit so just totally like neurologically
yeah like those are the people I'll have you know put your feet on the wall it's
just our breathing hmm yeah you mentioned rowing at the outset so you
started teaching at City Row I guess it's been them now three months you've
had me rowing that's funny I rode for you know a year in college and I used to
do a lot of work on an erg I think every human should row but the funny thing is
I was clearly never my technique was obviously not very good I was getting by
on a lot of brute force and now that you've got me doing it correctly it's
it's much more difficult I mean it's difficult maybe the wrong word it's much
more involved is the right word it's much more involved what what stemmed your
obsession with rowing aside from the fact that you know City Row was across
the street from you when you started well you know I had to do a lot of
research for them to kind of help develop a program so I tried to make like
an Apple version of rowing like very you know easy to follow but the more I would
practice I was like wow this is really getting me to move backwards and you
know a lot of people don't move backwards so they lose a sense of back
space and that puts you in a great position to breathe in your back space
to reach with your shoulder blades to actually use your legs to push and it's
like I've a lot of people that were in a pretty high amount of back pain I put
them on a rower and a lot of things cleaned up which again is very
counterintuitive yeah you would normally say someone with lower back pain should
never be rowing just like they should never be deadlifting right yeah and maybe
we should even do a little bit of that when we're in the gym later today which
is what is it about teaching somebody the correct sequence of events on a
rowing machine you want to walk us through what a perfect stroke looks like
in recovery so a lot of it's about finesse like when do you grip when do you
relax you have to let yourself relax and most of the stroke is actually relaxed
so coming from catch position the in it's like you're at the very front it's
like a wedge on a deadlift explain the wedge I love the wedge not just a good
salad so it's basically the position that you've that you get in before you
stand up with the weight so you want to wedge into the floor so you so the wedge
has tension it's the preload is what the way I think of it yes yes you starting
catch position you have the wedge you drive back through your legs you have a
nice tight grip because you have to connect yourself to the machine that's
what makes rowing so different from the like deadlifting is it's kind of a loose
situation so you have to really grab then so rowing would be easier if there
was more resistance at the front exactly because you'd feel it'd be easier
to connect to the thing that you're tensing up against exactly that's what a
lot of people have a hard time with and the catch is feeling that tension and a
lot of times because they're losing segmentation of the mid spine and there
you know it's it's hard to create tension when you don't have anything to
push against it's challenging yes from there you drive back once your hands get
right so who's doing the work right now which muscles legs legs legs so it's 60
percent legs okay once you get about to your knees you have to start when you
say to your knees you mean once your hands pass your knees you have to start
to relax the grip the drive is the most finesse part once you start to get a
little further back behind your knees you start to open up the hips and the
hips is another 30 percent so it's like when you stand up from a deadlift at
that point you actually have to really relax because a lot of people want to go
here and they're missing the hip extension because you go into actual hip
flexion there so you have to relax bring the bar in the bar is the biggest
mistake because people want to rip the chain it's literally 10% it's nothing it
should feel like nothing and then the hardest part is letting it relax and you
following it in for me the hardest part is actually keeping the abs relaxed and
keeping the ribs down it goes back to that over bracing thing it's my strategy
I know all about the rectus baby I know hang on tight yeah for dear life but
that's what causes back pain yeah and it's funny I remember when you had me
start rowing my qls would seize up after like 10 minutes dying yeah like my qls
are fried and again it wasn't back pain and a sort of this is like pathologic but
I was like this doesn't feel good I don't I feel like it doesn't feel like I
feel like I'm on my bike I feel great but on the rowing machine I just felt
like crap and I think the barefoot rowing strapless rowing yeah oh yeah yeah
sorry strapless rowing and learning to relax my hands when I crossed my knees
right that was the that was the game change with respect to that at that point
the ql pain vanished right so when you actually can relax the grip this stuff
can relax easier because your arms and rib cage have a direct correlation so if
you're hanging on for dear life this stuff is like just so tight so you can't
relax if you're hanging on for dear life and that's what makes it counterintuitive
because people just want to hang on so tight especially when it's new and I see
so many people they just pop on the machine and go 35 strokes per minute as
crazy as possible and they're like my back hurts I'm like well yeah I bet you
know I mean I remember when I used to row I feel like I was always trying to
like you know fatigue my upper body at the end of each stroke like trying to
basically gas my lower body and upper body as much as was humanly possible on
each stroke which almost undoubtedly meant because really you should be
gassing your lower your lower body should be fried when you row our body and abs
actually like when you're doing heavy heavy like almost power poles I feel my
abs more than anything it's because they are bracing your torso yeah because all
that it has to fire more because it's more force so these are your breaks yeah
so your breaks have to work harder because there's more force back from the
catch so do you use rowing as like short like you know do you use it as a form of
high-intensity training with people do you like to do it as more I'll substitute
it for deadlifting a lot huh yeah and what would be a typical workout so I
would ten strokes at a time like once once I have people so like I'm working
with Jill right now teaching her how to row and it's you know we're working on
just speeds like nothing faster than 24 let's see if you can stay coordinated
from there like that would be step one like you have to be able to keep that
coordination because as soon as you add speed and power things are gonna start
getting yeah I can't go anything faster than about 25 26 yeah it's really
frustrating but right right after that I'll start adding a little bit of weight
to the stroke so we'll start looking more at like watts or split time see if
you can keep your speed kind of low but see if you can you know have a higher
wattage but I don't usually start working higher speeds for a while
because coordination kind of goes out the window and I want them to stay
coordinated again because we're not doing like 2k time trials and we have
like one client that's doing that you know I know and then you told you told
me his time and then I was like I kind of want to do a 2k test as well oh he
sent me his 5k today what did he go I can't remember his total time but he
kept a 149 the whole time it's pretty impressive because his 2k he was about
141 140 654 was his total time yeah yeah but like I'll have I have people do a
lot of single leg rowing too mm-hmm I love that yeah it's great I mean you can
use it for so many that's what I love about it so much cuz like I'll do my
zone to I'll stay on a rower for 60 plus minutes but you can also work on
like strength and power development which is so great I mean if you can zone
to on a rowing machine you're very efficient yeah but I've been rowing every
day of my life for the past seven years I have a rower here I have a rower in New
York in my apartment you know I was teaching multiple rowing classes a week
I'm just always on it yeah you're you're you've got me you've got me doing it now
it'll never be as fun as a bike for me I don't think but that's cool it's just a
different situation yeah yeah I think it's it for runners though because it
takes a you know it why yeah why do you think it's a good augment for a runner
less load less impact on the lower leg just give them a little bit of a break
but also really you know work the hips yeah let's talk a little bit about
concentric versus eccentric strength within a muscle I want to do a little I
want to demonstrate a little of this when we get into the gym because it's
also another fixation of mine you know obviously you know archery and hunting
or something I'm really interested in and one of the things I've paid a lot of
attention to in the field because I'm always sort of thinking about I'm out
there and I'm doing something what do I need to bring back into my training to
make this a better experience and the two most obvious things are scapular
protraction is everything so so when you're on your on your on the arm
that's holding the bow out the difference between the good archer and
the great archer is the great archer is always able to maintain protraction so
when this hand is back here they can keep a relaxed arm with a protracted
scapula now why is that important because when you're pulling back to
release you have to have no slide back of the bow in other words you want the
only thing that's being pulled is the release on the D loop now if the arrow
is sliding back in the bow by definition it means the entire bow is slacking
right so what that means is your scapula are coming back your shoulder is
going up and so it was realizing oh my god once you start to break down in your
shot sequence once you start to get tired you've lost the ability to keep
that scapula all the way forward and that's a whole other issue the second
thing that I brought back is and this is not just true of hunting frankly this is
true of any sport I think especially if you like hiking and being outdoors or if
you like being in an environment where it's not perfectly predictable is
eccentric strength matters exactly if you can't stop yourself you're hosed and
we focus so much on accelerating and on the explosion which is the concentric
right the you know the strength as the muscle gets shorter right but very little
about what happened what type of strength is necessary as the muscle
elongate right I always kind of equate it to like a sports car with no brakes
goes super fast but that's not great if you can't stop yourself so like I'll see
it a lot with like big strong dudes they'll do a bodyweight split squat and
just crash to the ground because they have no eccentric control that's a body
control thing to just being able to control that descent is it okay so I was
gonna ask you that if you have if you are strong concentrically is it really
just a neurologic issue that prevents you from being eccentrically strong or
is that a different I mean because I now very deliberately train eccentric
strength well so you have to think about what eccentric says it's a loaded
stretch right so if you don't have that stretch ability I mean that's gonna be a
big part of the issue too this is one of your tests you typically will have
somebody do bodyweight bodyweight split squats where they take five seconds to
go down pause at the bottom and then they come up at normal speed yeah so how
many normal like 50 year olds can pass that test mmm not many that's a stark
stark statement let's read let's repeat what that is usually okay yeah explain
again exactly what you're asking them to do starting in a split stance a lot of people can't
even stand in a split stance without falling over or over bracing like it's your bodyweight
you're not picking up a car you should be able to stand there yeah and then the the stretch
required to lower you'll see a lot of people tip into a tilt because they they want to avoid that
stretch or they don't have it and then to load it with your body weight it's a lot so they usually
just end up crashing down to the floor and that's I want to see how much midline you know
adaptability they have how much stretch they can get can you get your pelvis in a position
you know or are you locked and loaded do you have to hike your arms up to make the movement happen
or using momentum or can you push down with your legs and actually own it and stand up and lower
down with control and I have some people that I've worked with that couldn't even be in a half
kneeling position without falling over but the good news is everybody can fix them this is all
fixable stuff yeah it takes time but it's definitely you know for most people fixable it just takes a
lot of attention and a lot of time um any other thoughts on sort of longevity when you think
through like essential movements again my you know I think about eccentric strength being so important
balance being important um where does flexibility fit into this for you like you take somebody like
me who's really quote unquote inflexible right like I you know it's not like I can do the splits or
right do anything outstanding but but I've seen a lot of people that can do the splits that can't
control it yeah so how does flexibility fit into your world view around the centenarian olympics
I think if they can control what they're doing I think flexibility is relative
so you view control as a much higher premium control and load tolerance absolutely
so you're not disappointed with my lack of hamstring flexibility no what I get more like
if you're doing a toe touch assessment I'm more looking at higher spine segments which we're going
to do that today I think because that's a great example I think that people should be able to touch
their toes and and really I mean this is one thing I both you and Michael have independently
showed me and it blew my mind you can touch your toes without barely requiring anything
of your hamstrings if you know how to get correct if you know how to access your spine you should
actually feel your hamstrings kind of working when you touch your toes and you know for years
when I was dancing like you know I would just kind of kick back into my hips and you know hang out
in my heels that's the only time I've ever had like back discomfort in my whole life like even
deadlifting over 300 pounds my back never hurt like hurt or was achy but it was more you know
from just kind of hanging back on myself and never felt a hamstring stretch I never felt work
until I figured you know I got a little more control of my spine and a little more control
and once and once you really learn what what how to get good lumbar and lower thoracic flexion
you don't actually need very flexible loosey-goosey hamstrings to be able to touch your toes.
I actually prefer you don't. Yeah you know.
How big a how big a role does hit play in your in your world?
Hit. I think that it should be done but like 20% of the time. That much. I just don't I think that
zone two as far as like you know aerobic work we definitely need more zone two we don't do enough
of that and a lot of it's an attention thing it's sometimes even for me and I can sit and do stuff
forever but some days are so much harder than others and like I don't want to do this for an
hour or more or whatever and it's hard to sit with yourself for an hour doing the same thing
and it you don't experience those feels and whenever you do hit work it's like exciting and
new and you know you feel like you're gonna die low level and that's exciting but I think that it
can kind of enable that stress cycle that we have to crush it all the time and I don't think that we
necessarily need to crush it. I tell a lot of my clients and patients that you should rarely feel
like death like it's just not what it's about you know if you're if you're a power lifter like when
I was training for that I would feel like death a lot. And you're you when you power lifted you were
you were a good squatter. No I'm a terrible squatter. It's in my brain. So your deadlift is
your lift? How was your bench? Not superb. So you were your your deadlift was best then bench? Yeah
and like my deadlift was so just beyond everything. I think I just felt more comfortable because if
it wasn't gonna work you just drop it you know it's like gonna squish you. Why do you think your
squat was because you certainly have the biomechanics to squat? I do. I think it's a mental thing. I
would get over a certain amount of weight and just like it wouldn't happen. I would just give up.
Yeah. What's your take on sort of the difference between
what we do which is mostly training versus going out and playing sports?
I think sports are fun but I think they don't replace training. I think you know it's a lot of
people be like oh I went and played tennis today. I worked out. I'm like no you played a sport which
is fine but you're not you have to be so reactive and so stressful when you're playing a sport that
you're not learning anything. For me training is about learning. Paying attention and learning
and that learning will actually help you in your sport but your sport is not you know it's also
usually your heart rate is so high you're not getting that good aerobic foundation from it.
It's stress which is great and we need stress in our lives but that's not training.
I think about this a lot. I don't know why because I'll never be able to do it but I'd love to
fantasize about it which is like if you could revamp kind of the physical curriculum for kids
you know you could go into schools when kids enter pre-k and what would you do different? Like how
would you change the way we teach kids how to move? Have them play more. You think it's simply
and it's just as it's just get them away from desks. Have them play more. That's how we learn.
You make a decision it either works or it doesn't and then you learn from that and you either
try a different way and or it's successful and you learn something and then you repeat it. I think
it's the same thing with play and working on movement options. Like I played all the time as
a kid outside. Now let's get back to this genetic issue. You're obviously just sort of genetically
predisposed to being athletic, having this great sense of kinesthetic awareness.
Do you have a sense of how much you could take somebody who's less
genetically capable and just leave them in a natural environment by presumably keeping them
away from some of the things that you know limit that like screens and sitting and such
and have that be sufficient? I think once they're past a certain age they would need training
I would think. Because you were kind of a hyper kid right? Oh yeah my parents would be like
go run around the house five times and then come back in because I would just bounce and it was
just constant. And you know I grew up in the country middle of nowhere so I was always on a
bike or swimming or climbing a tree and I was lucky to have that. You know my parents kind of
limited how much TV we could have. I think we got like one hour a day or something. So I had the
opportunity to play. And then I also played sports. I wanted to be involved in everything.
And my parents would be like okay but you have to finish the season and if you don't you know even
if you don't like it you have to finish the season. The problem was I liked everything so I ended up
just playing that's what I did a lot. So which was great. But a lot of people don't have the
that background or options. That's actually one of the questions I ask in history like
when I'm taking someone's history I'm like did you play sports as a kid?
Because that can tell you a lot about you know what kind of learner they're going to be.
Interesting so you're saying someone who's got a really strong athletic pedigree
might actually pick some of the things up quicker that you're talking about simply because they have
the reps on learning new skills. I find that people that played multiple sports and just played as a
kid usually people that are specialized it can be almost harder because their patterns are so
wired. They live like they're playing their sport. Like I worked with a golfer and he looks like he's
swinging a golf club. Like that's how that's his strategy actually. That was something actually
Michael also I remember explaining when we started working together was my scapular
issues were going to be harder to unwind because of how many thousands of repetitions they had
in the various movements that I'd done. So how many times I'd taken a stroke and swimming just
slightly incorrectly without the perfect scapular control. And so he's like look it's almost easier
to take in somebody who's been a bump on a log their whole life. Yeah because yeah they've got
a bunch of problems but they don't have a whole bunch of ingrained movement patterns. Right they
would have more like coordination issues and you know obviously midline stability issues just
because they've never used it. But someone who's like especially repetitive sports I see it in
runners a lot. Yeah running, cycling, swimming. Yeah just anytime you're doing the same thing
over and over you're going to develop that strategy for lack of better words. And that's how you live
life but that decreases options. Well Beth it's been pretty awesome having you in SoCal this summer.
It's been great. I guess you're heading back to New York soon and we'll get back to the hard work
of getting everybody ready for the Centenary Olympics. Yeah for sure. Thank you. All right well
let's go ahead into the gym and try to do some of the things we've talked about here so that people
can get a better sense of what we're talking about. Cool.