Hey everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Vinay Prasad. Vinay is a practicing hematologist and
associate professor of medicine at UC San Francisco, where he focuses on not just the
treatment of patients, but also health policy, clinical trials, and decision-making. He's what
some might call a meta researcher. He studies the quality of medical evidence and lately his focus
most of his energy on oncology, of course. He's the author of over 250 academic articles,
along with two books, Ending Medical Reversal, which was published about five years ago and
published this year, the book Malignant, which we spend a lot of time discussing. He also hosts
the oncology podcast, which is called Plenary Session. I recommend you check it up. He runs a
YouTube channel along with his various activities on social media. He's primarily active on Twitter
at VPrasad, that's P-R-A-S-A-D-M-D-M-P-H, where he writes some really great tutorials related to
clinical trials, critical thinking, decision-making, et cetera. In this episode, we talk a little bit
about his beginnings, how he got into medicine, and really how things that he saw during his
medical training kind of woke him up to some of the issues in clinical medicine. Probably the first
thing that he observed with some of the limitations in cardiology and how there was a disconnect
between clinical practice and research, but really that kind of took off once he chose the
profession of oncology, which is a field that is really rife with some of these inconsistencies.
Now, this is a podcast that sort of builds on a lot of the stuff that we discussed in a previous
podcast with Azra Raza, but we go a little bit deeper into some of the structural failures.
This one goes by quick, and yet somehow at the end of it, I looked and realized we'd been talking
for two hours. I could have spoken with Vinay for another two hours. We close this by doing
kind of a deep dive on what he describes as his six hallmarks of cancer policy. And I think this
is a really great discussion. I was just constantly impressed by the way that Vinay was able to kind
of articulate things in ways that I even made the comment at one point, if you gave me two hours to
explain what you just explained in five minutes, I wouldn't have been able to. So I hope you enjoy
this. And without further delay, please enjoy my discussion with Vinay. Hey Vinay, thank you so
much for joining me. Where are you physically today? I'm physically located in the Bay Area,
in one of the distant suburbs, just a temporary place I'm staying here, but hope to be settled
in soon. I started at UC San Francisco pretty recently. Yeah. I noticed that and I was going
to ask you about that. That's a soon to be your new permanent gig, huh? Yeah. I mean, I started
the job, but I do not yet have a permanent place to stay. So I'm just kind of hanging out for now,
but I'm going to work on that. And right now, you know, we're in the midst of forest fires and COVID.
And so it wasn't a terrific time to move in retrospect. UCSF has a dear place in my heart.
When I was in medical school, which was at Stanford, we still spent a lot of time at UCSF.
We had the option to spend time electively and Stanford was not a great place to get a lot of
trauma experience for a budding wannabe surgeon. But of course San Francisco general was. And then
many years later when I returned, my wife was an ICU nurse at UCSF before later moving over to run
the Coumadin clinic, which was run by just a solo NP and one hematologist. So up on Parnassus,
they're at some of the most beautiful views of the entire city. So one thing I remember her saying
was there was this gym up on the Parnassus campus where she would go and work out at like 5 30 before
clinic starts. And you sort of get to kind of just watch the city as the sun was coming up.
Oh, it's gorgeous. That sounds terrific. I'm actually based in San Francisco general hospital
for my clinic. So that's where I do my clinical time. Fantastic. So you and I were scheduled to
speak, I think initially, God probably around the time of the COVID outbreak. And then obviously,
everything kind of got derailed a little bit. So I appreciate your patience. There's a lot to talk
about here. And I almost don't know where to begin. But I do think it probably helps the listener to
understand your background a little bit. Because it's a lot of times people who come to medicine
through the not so obvious routes that maybe bring in a little bit of a different perspective. So
I know you weren't a pre med student. It's not like you grew up thinking I can't wait to be a
doctor. If I recall from reading something, you were actually like a philosophy major in college.
Is that right? Yeah, I guess I kind of might have done a little bit of both. I genuinely felt
undecided at the time. I graduated high school and I thought I'm good in science. I like science,
maybe I'll major in science. And so when I started college at Michigan State University,
I think my original major was in the sciences. Early on in my second year, I took a philosophy
class and it really kind of struck a chord. The professor was very kind and reached out to me.
And very quickly, I added that on as a major. And so I ended up doing a little bit of both.
I can't say when exactly I started thinking about medical school, but I remember feeling
really sort of uncertain if that was the right path for me. I certainly wasn't somebody who
in high school always knew they wanted to be a doctor or something, anything like that.
It came to me sort of on the back end of college, really.
You went to University of Chicago, is that correct?
That's right for medical school. Yeah.
What was that like? I mean, I know that different medical schools had different environments.
Stanford, for what it's worth, was a very relaxed medical school.
My guess is University of Chicago being one of the top 10 schools in the country was not relaxed.
It didn't strike me as relaxed.
It's so funny you say that when I was a medical student at University of Chicago,
I once visited a friend who was doing his doctorate work at Stanford and I toured the hospital and the
windows were open and the smell of Jasmine kind of wafted in. And I was like, wow, this is a place of
healing. And it was really markedly different than University of Chicago, which is a really gritty
city hospital feel. A lot of the faculty had trained on the East Coast and I think it really
had that East Coast mentality. It was an intense place. I remember yelling in the operating room
was common, throwing things was common, people getting chewed out was common. So it had all that
sort of East Coast feel, which these days might be a bygone era, but I kind of caught the tail of it,
at least maybe second generation. But I caught the tail of, I think, that sort of tough East
Coast mentality, which was President Chicago. Yeah.
There's a book that I've spoken about before on the podcast called Forgive and Remember. I don't
know if you ever read it. It was written by a sociologist from Pennsylvania University,
Charles Bosque. And in the book, he spends 18 months with a group of surgical residents to
understand the culture of surgical training. In the book, he never mentions to my knowledge,
I don't think he ever mentions where it was, but for some reason, either I spoke with Bosque and
asked him or somehow inferred, but I believe it actually was the University of Chicago where it
was. And you have to imagine you take the environment you saw and go back a couple of
decades. This was sort of late 70s, early 80s, and you want to talk about toxicity, but you're
absolutely right. There's a real East Coast, West Coast divide in medical education. And I think,
put it this way, when I applied to my residency on the East Coast at Hopkins, there was a real view
that no one from Stanford could go there and do general surgery. Because the last guy, I think,
who had gone and done general surgery, who had come from Stanford had committed suicide.
I see. They thought you were too soft.
Yeah. The view was, it was just a little too soft to come from there. And of course,
that's such a silly thing to say that this person's suicide had anything to do with that. I mean,
the distinction between one versus the other, but it was really viewed as no, no, no, no. Like,
if you went to Chicago, you could go to Hopkins if you went to Penn or Michigan or something you
couldn't. But anyway, that was my view, having friends that went to medical school in Chicago
was I was academically just a tough school in a tough environment. So how did you like medical
school? Well, I guess I probably would be honest with you. I mean, I think I was in the fraction
of people that didn't really care for it a lot of the time. To be more specific, when you start in
medical school, especially in the years in which I trained, you had two just full years of classroom,
almost 40 hours a week of just memorize this kid, memorize this, memorize this, memorize this,
you didn't really get into sort of the decision making of medicine. You didn't get much exposure
to patients. You didn't get that side of medicine. What is actually medicine? Those first two years
are, I found it really demoralizing. I mean, I wasn't somebody who was used to memorizing lots
of things in sort of a disconnected way. I was somebody who liked to think about things and think
about them rigorously. And so I really felt, I would say, very frustrated in the first two years.
Step one, studying was a very anxious time in my life and I didn't quite care for it. And it was
only when third year started and I was there on the wards and I was on internal medicine first as
my clerkship. And I had some really great and influential practitioners of medicine who would
kind of teach me how they think about cases. That was when I started to feel like, okay, that's the
first moment that this felt like the right choice for me. So it wasn't until my third year. So I was
pretty frustrated in the beginning. And then from third year to fourth year, fourth year is really
sort of an expensive vacation, but there were ups and downs in that process too. Remind me where you
did your residency. Northwestern University, I stayed in the city. You stayed in Chicago.
My folks at that time were living in Northwest Indiana, not too far. And so my undergrad,
medical school, residency, it was all pretty close to where my family was. Okay. So when is it like,
if we look at the work that you are now basically defining your career by, right? I mean, and we're
going to get into this in some detail. Where do you think those seeds were sown?
I guess I'd say I was somebody who probably said what I needed to say to get into medical school
and get into residency. But the truth is in my heart, I was probably somebody who was thinking
about medical school as a route to private practice and that I saw myself as a practitioner.
I didn't know exactly what field or what specialty, but I thought I would primarily be taking care of
patients in a private practice setting. I think that was true even when I graduated medical school
and even sort of the beginning of the first year, my internship, but only kind of changed for me in
the middle of residency. And what made a change for me was I had consistently been put in clinical
situations where what I saw we were doing and then what I would read about in the evening,
they was a disconnect. They were things we were doing that were not supported by strong evidence.
There were some things that appeared to run counter to the best evidence, but it didn't make
a lot of sense to me. And so I started just on the margins of that problem, doing a few studies to
kind of make sense of what were these things that had become a part of medical culture that
ultimately proved not to work. We ended up calling that medical reversal. We wrote a few papers about
it, but that was really kind of how I got into it. I got into it from the point of view of a clinician
who was struggling to make sense of what was going on around me. And that was really how I fell into
research. And I didn't know that research would become my career, but the funny thing about life
is you do something long enough and it starts to define you. And so after maybe 15 or 20 papers in
this space, people started to say, this is a guy who's doing health policy research in that space.
And eventually it kind of just keeps yourself so busy. You're just doing the next thing,
doing the next thing. And eventually it kind of starts to turn into a career.
So I think in your book, you write a story about a woman who had a stent placed and had a bad
outcome and maybe tell folks a little bit about a, what a stent is, b, what her situation was
specifically, and perhaps C, and we can probably both elaborate on part C, which is what in the
hell was going on with stents? So I guess I would say, I appreciate you looking through my book and
reading it. I guess I would say that we tried to use composite patience. We try not to base it on
any one particular person, but the situation you're talking about, somebody who gets a stent placed for
an indication that is kind of questionable, who suffers a complication. Oh, there are many people
that come to my mind about that. I have very clear images in my mind of people in that situation.
And I guess I would say, I guess there's two parts to this. So the first part is like,
what is a stent? So a stent is a little flexible metallic tube that expands. And it's often placed
in a coronary artery when there is a blockage. And for people who come in with an heart attack,
an ST elevation, myocardial infarction, a total blockage of the artery, a stent is a
transformative, life-saving intervention. It's one of those amazing medical miracles that we
proudly celebrate in medicine. But it's also something like so many medical technologies that
can be used more broadly. It works really well in a critical situation. Maybe it works well for
somebody who just has a little bit of narrowing of the arteries and maybe just a touch of angina.
That's that kind of reproducible chest pain that comes on when you shovel your driveway in the
winter or go for a long walk. So people would extrapolate from the critical situation to less
severe situations in medicine. And of course, there's a lot more less severe situations than
there are severe situations. So it becomes a big driver of market share. So it turns out stents
became very popular for chronic stable angina. And I knew in the years in which I was a resident
that we had just had a large mega randomized control trial called courage that asked whether
or not stents lower the rate of heart attack or improve longevity. And the answer was for people
with chronic stable angina, not that acute heart attack, but this sort of chest pain that comes on
when you shovel your driveway, there was no improvement in survival and no reduction in
subsequent myocardial infarction or heart attack. Yet survey after survey of patients showed that
when they were consented to the procedure, when they had it done, they believed it was being done
with that purpose in mind. So there was a disconnect between what patients felt it was for and what
doctors knew it could do. This disconnect always played a role in the lives of residents. We're
not the people who place the stent. We're the people who manage the patient in the days afterwards.
And every so often you place a stent, something bad happens. There can be a cardiac arrest on
the table. There can be an occlusion of the stent, a thrombus that forms within this foreign body
that's being placed in the artery. And we witnessed several of these sort of complications. These are
known complications. All things in medicine have some complications. But the question that kind of
plagued me was, it's okay to accept the risk of a complication if the procedure has a net benefit.
But if the procedure is questionable as it's being done and the benefit is questionable,
you're just taking risk without any upside. So cases like that, that we talk about in the book,
were a powerful, I think, motivator for me personally, to kind of look deeper into this
issue, to really understand why we do what we do. And that led to a lot of work in this space.
And I think part of it is, this gets to how we deal with policy, especially on the procedural
side, which I think we'll get to is, because I remember seeing this very tangentially as a
resident as well, you couldn't ignore the conflict of interest that existed there, which was when
interventional cardiologists were being compensated for the number of stents being placed. And I say
that, to be clear, not being critical of them, but acknowledging that if I were in their situation,
I'm not sure how I would self-police. That's the real issue. It's not that they're necessarily
bad people, but they're people. They're just good people. They're just normal people. Yeah,
they're good people. And we all suffer from our own cognitive biases. So what was the next step on
that rabbit hole? I just want to kind of build on what you're saying, which I think is really astute,
which is that these are just people, interventional cardiologists are just people like we're all
people, and they suffer from the same sort of psychological trappings that we all suffer from.
And in this case, I think there's two parts to the equation that make stents so seductive.
So part one is, you place this stent and the patient comes back in your office nine times out
of 10, and they're happy that you did it. They believe you have saved their life or extended
their life. They may even believe they feel better. And in fact, we could talk about orbita
and whether or not that's a real effect or a placebo effect, we can come to that. But they
believe they feel better. They believe you saved their life. So you do this procedure, the patient
comes to your office and say, thank you so much, doctor. You saved my life. And you know what? It
doesn't hurt so much when I shovel the driveway anymore. Thank you. So you pair that incredibly
powerful feeling of gratitude. You pair that with one other thing, which is you get a little bit of
money and you get more money the more you do. So when you combine that powerful psychological
stimulus of gratitude with a little bit of financial remuneration, I think that's the
methamphetamine of being a doctor. That's a highly addictive substance that whatever we do in medicine,
particularly procedures, because that's what pays, we become addicted to that. And then a couple
years later, some investigators say, you know what? The patient didn't feel better actually when we
randomized them to stenting or we made them wear headphones and we told them we put a stent,
but we didn't put the stent. We kind of deceived them into thinking they had a stent. They actually
both had the same exercise tolerance improvement on a treadmill test. So that's the orbit of study.
So when somebody comes at you and they tell you that, you know, actually it's just a placebo effect.
It doesn't actually improve symptoms. It's psychologically unacceptable. How can that be?
It doesn't fit with my experience and it doesn't fit with the way I've been rewarded. And I think
that's in part why many of these medical practices that have evidence, I think that goes
the other way, are very difficult to dispel. We have become addicted to doing them.
So you're chugging along through your residency, which means you're basically getting to rotate
through all the different subspecialties within medicine. Obviously, you're taking care of the
critical cardiac patients. Presumably at some point you're taking care of GI patients,
oncology patients. What is this journey like for you now that you've got bit by this bug of,
hey, wait a minute. If the stent thing is a little bit off the rails, is there anything else in
medicine that's similarly off the rails? No, it's like being a kid in a Kanzi store, Peter.
You're onto something. I mean, it's kind of a privilege really, now that I look back on it,
as a student, I got to spend a month with neurosurgeons watching what they do. Then the next
month I got to spend it with a breast surgeon. The next month I spend it with a radonk
specialist. As a resident, it's a GI doctor for two weeks. Then it's a hematologist,
and then it's an allergist. I mean, it's really a privilege. I get to be a fly on the wall of so
many different situations and see so much of medical practice. And the moment you start to
recognize some of the classic, I think, research pitfalls, the evidence pitfalls, you do as you
exactly say, you start to see it everywhere. You start to see it in how decisions are made in
one clinic, decisions are made in another clinic. There's a theme that emerges. So one theme might
be for mechanical interventions done to alleviate a subjective symptom, whether it's angina or pain
or dyspnea, which is how you catch your breath or back pain or any sort of discomfort. If you do a
mechanical intervention for that, a number of studies show that it is no better than a sham
intervention. And that's different than if you compare it to a medical pill where the person
doesn't get that sort of psychological benefit that you're doing something for them. So you start
to see this theme emerge when you go shadow many places. Explain to folks what a sham intervention
is because I think we don't do them much anymore. But there was a day when actual sham surgical
procedures were done. Yeah, well, you might know a little bit more about that surgical history than
I do. But I guess I would say, when I think about a sham intervention, I say, let's just start with
arthroscopic knee surgery. So you know, a lot of people have pain and discomfort and degenerative
osteoarthritis of the knee, and they get a orthopedist to go in with a scope and actually
debreed some of the cartilage, clean up the joint, make it look a little nicer. So hopefully they
have less pain and discomfort. And lo and behold, if you have that done, people feel better
afterwards than they did before. And if you compare that to physical therapy or maybe taking
ibuprofen, it might even work better. But when you compare it against a sham intervention,
that's where the orthopod goes in with the scope, they fiddle with it a little bit, but they don't
actually do anything inside. And they take out the scope and they tell you they did something,
there is no difference in outcomes, they both feel better. And what that shows you, it's not
the debreedment, per se, it's the psychological stimulus of having that done. And this is true for
injecting polyacrylamide cement into osteoporotic fractures of the vertebra. It's true for a couple
of shoulder procedures. It's true for, I believe, stenting chronic stable angina. That's what the
orbiter trial shows. That's they did it or they made the person believe they did it. And this is
called a sham intervention. And it's a really useful, I think, method to separate what is the
benefit from doing that final step that you think matters versus from all the other things we do in
medicine, which is reassuring the patient, telling them I'm going to fix it, telling them that I fixed
it and telling them that they should feel better. What's the added benefit of actually doing the
thing? In orbita, did they actually cannulate the femoral artery? Yeah, they did. Yeah, they
cannulated the artery. And I believe they performed a diagnostic angiogram. They have all
the pictures of it. And they made the patient wear headphones. And they didn't inform them whether or
not they had the stent placed. And then the primary outcome that they're looking at is the modified
Bruce protocol exercise treadmill. So they put people on treadmills and see how long they can go.
And we knew from prior stenting trials that when you stent someone and you tell them you stent them,
they're going for another minute, two minutes. And in orbita study, they're going for a difference of
16 seconds. And it's not statistically significant. And it's not clinically meaningful. So they really
do call into question that the benefit of that procedure on this sort of standardized endpoint
of subjective symptoms is really sort of what the patient believes it to be. And so that's what a
sham study is. And so to your point, which is you see the theme emerge across many spaces in medicine
when you have the privilege of getting to shadow in many spaces. And now, five years into my faculty
career, I don't have that privilege too often in my own bubble. I'm in my own clinic. I'm in
oncology and hematology. But in the last year, befriended an orthopedic surgeon who I really
like, I have a great deal of respect for her. She's terrific. And she let me shadow on a couple of
surgeries that I hadn't seen. So I get to feel like a medical student again, maybe someday to
lead to a project that we're working on. But to answer your question, I mean, I think you're right,
which is that you do get a sense of sort of the broad lay of the land in medicine when you are a
trainee and you can see things with fresh eyes and in many places. So how did you choose oncology
as your fellowship? I guess the first jump in becoming an oncologist is you decide to go into
internal medicine. I went into internal medicine because I'd had so many positive experiences in
internal medicine. I guess the other options for listeners who may not know are you could do general
surgery residency, a few subspecialties of surgery you can go into right off the bat like urology or
your nose and throat or neurosurgery. You could also be a radiation oncologist. You can be an OB
guy. You can be a pediatrician. For me, general internal medicine was sort of a very broad
category. You have sent the most kids each year into internal medicine. We had really good mentors
in internal medicine. So I knew I wanted to be an internist of some sort. I wanted to kind of
have a broad look at the body and think of things very broadly. I thought for a while I might be a
cardiologist, not just because that's a stereotype, but because I actually was a little bit interested
in cardiology. I thought I might be an intensivist, a critical care doctor along the way. And finally,
I had some really positive experiences with a couple of oncologists at Northwestern,
one of which is Dr. Munshi, who's still there on faculty, but really terrific experiences with
sort of consummate doctors, people who balanced. They knew a little bit about the basic science.
They really knew about clinical trials. They knew about evidence and they were really good
with patients in great bedside manner. And they made decisions I felt were substantive and
important. And so because of that, it's so funny how so much of life is shaped by just the people
you meet. I decided to go into oncology. And so I made that decision early on in my internal
medicine training. Talk to me about your first days as a medical oncology fellow. Now you're
basically also going through comparable stuff. Presumably you're doing rotations on GI oncology,
going through the liquid cancers. I mean, you're running the gamut again, correct?
Yeah, you have a great sense of it. Yeah. The first time I left the Midwest, I went to Washington,
DC and the National Cancer Institute. They have a very unique and fascinating program and you get
to see a lot of stuff. And it's just as you say, one month, you're with a couple of GI oncologists,
you spend a few days at the NCI, a couple days at Georgetown, and maybe you go to Washington
Hospital Center, one of the other flagship hospitals in the city. One month, you may go
to Hopkins and do leukemia. Another month, you may be at the NCI on their clinics, which are really
highly specialized, often rare disease, every patient on a clinical trial or protocol, just a
different experience. And so you get a huge, I think, exposure in oncology. You get exposure
to so many different diseases, many of which before that time, you know very little of. I think the
sad reality of internal medicine training is it trains you a lot in things like cardiology and
pulmonary disease. But oncology is one of the things that you don't get into that much until
you commit to being an oncologist. And so the learning curve is steep. You got to learn a lot
of drugs. There are more new drugs every day, which I think we're going to talk about. And you got to
learn a lot of new diseases and a lot of genetics and a lot of things you didn't know before. And so
the learning curve is steep. But to be honest, I probably think that's one of my favorite years of
training. My first year as an oncology fellow, I had a really great cohort of people training with.
We always went for the drink on Friday evenings to have some camaraderie. And we had a great
exposure to faculty and we were learning 20 new things every day. I mean, I thought it was really
sort of a terrific and transformational year for me. It's also a special place. I was at NCI in
medical school and then for two years after and lived just outside of Bethesda in Silver Spring.
And I still think of it as some of the fondest memories, which is a very special place. I know
we're going to come back and talk about NIH. And I think the NIH in particular, how it funds
research is I certainly have some issues with it and maybe we can get into that. But there's really,
it's not hyperbolic to say there's no place like it on Earth. And I still remember that first day
I stepped foot on that campus as a third year medical student, just thinking, how can this place
exist? It is so marvelous. Yeah, it's a marvelous set of buildings there in Bethesda, this huge
campus, a lot of greenery, so many different buildings. And the building that predominantly
where clinical operations have is Building 10, the sort of centerpiece building, this massive
federal building that's just been constantly expanded over the years. So much of history
occurred in that building. People pioneered the cure for Hodgkin's Lymphoma, at least the chemotherapeutic
cure for Hodgkin's Lymphoma. People did some fundamental work on chemotherapy and breast cancer.
So many great laboratory scientists come from that place. And it's a place that certainly gives you a
feeling of awe and reverence when you're actually physically there. And I think many of us really
are appreciative of the time we spent training there. I think it's a great experience for anyone
who listens who's a trainee, or they're thinking about going into medicine. If you can spend a
year there, spend a summer there or do a fellowship there, you'll be richer for it. Now coming back to
oncology, I mean, I think, again, maybe I'm biased because I know enough about cancer relative to other
disciplines of medicine. But one of the things that strikes me as challenging about doing a fellowship
in medical oncology as you did is that there's not a lot that's consistent or similar between
acute lymphocytic leukemia or lymphoblastic leukemia and breast cancer. And even though
they're both quote unquote cancer, for all intents and purposes, they're totally different diseases.
And now multiply that by all the cancers you just rattled off, right? You've got these patients with
lymphomas, and some of them are Hodgkins, and some of them are not Hodgkins. And then you've got the
leukemias, and then you've got the pancreatic cancer, and you've got the colon cancer, and the
breast cancer, and the head and neck cancers. That is a lot of different diseases. How did you
sort of navigate your way through that as a trainee? And then how do you decide as you're going
through that, what does this mean for me in my career? I mean, I agree with your observation
that cancer is a category term. It's not a single monolith. It's so many things. And even within
cancers, I mean, even within something as small as non small cell lung cancer, which itself is
a category of lung cancer. Now we have EGFR, mutation driven non small cell lung cancer,
we have Alkary range, non small cell lung, RET, and then ROS1. We have all these molecular
categories, we have RAS, this undrugable target, we have superimposed with that sort of the role
of immunotherapy. I mean, it's a lot. And I guess the only way to kind of do it is just to do it
piecemeal a little bit at a time, just reading as you go. Every night you read an article or two,
you read up to date, you start there, eventually start to dig into the references. I don't pretend
to know everything about every cancer even to this date. I don't think, and I once heard somebody say,
1963 was the last time a scientist died who knew everything. I mean, it's just impossible to know
it all. You can't know all the basic science, you can't know all the clinical medicine. I pick a
certain spot. And I think that spot is the spot of a clinician. I mean, my primary sort of interest
and still to this day, what I do with about half my time, hour wise is see patients and think about
patient care. So I start with that vantage. And then I go outward from there. And so what trials
do I need to know? What clinical evidence do I need to know? What heuristics do I need to know
to guide patient care? How can I work on my bedside manner? And then beyond that, what policy
determines these things and what basic science is relevant to that. But yeah, I don't know everything
about cancer basic science. I don't pretend to. That's beyond what I can know. That's what most
people do in oncology. They start with the patient, they work their way outward and they try to learn
as much as possible. And you're always going to be learning new things even four or five, six years
into practice as I am now. You've brought up bedside manner indirectly twice. So I want to touch on
that. It obviously means a lot to you. You mentioned it in the first setting with respect to
a mentor you had. And again, you referenced it now in a way that I think is quite interesting,
which is it's an area of something you would think about improving upon being better. And
do you get the sense a lot of doctors feel that way? And how do you specifically think about
improving that? Because anybody who's done what you do understands two things that are simultaneously
true, yet cut at odds. The first is the practice of medicine can be exhausting. And at times it can
sort of suck the life out of the practitioner, be it the doctor, the nurse, the therapist, etc.
But the flip side of that is, again, you referenced this earlier, it's an unmistakable privilege.
And that anybody gets to be that intimate with another human being at their most vulnerable time.
That's something that can't really be forgotten. And therein lies this tension, at least for me,
around what bedside manner means. Yeah, I mean, I guess I can't profess to be the expert in bedside
manner, but it is something that I take seriously. And I'm constantly trying to do better. I'll start
by saying one thing, I think there is a misconception, I think, among many people outside of
oncology that oncology is often doom and gloom and tough situations. And I guess I want to say
that that is true. There is a fair bit of end of life in oncology. We do have to have those hard
conversations. But it's not exclusively true. That's not all we do. We also have a lot of people
who are concerned about things that frankly, are not going to be the thing that shortens their life,
it's not going to be the end of the world. We also have many patients in whom we cure and we have to
follow for long term side effects. So it's really a range of medical experiences, some of which I
think is that stuff stuff that people focus on. I'll just tell you one anecdote, sort of what put
it all in perspective for me. When I was at the NCI, I worked with a really senior oncologist who
had been practicing for 30 years. And we had seen a patient on several visits, and I followed this
patient for many months with this senior oncologist. And the senior oncologist had followed this patient
for I think over a decade. We finally reached an impasse, we reached a situation where there were
really no further therapeutic options, the tumors were growing uncontrolled, it was clearly going
to take this man's life. And we had sort of radiographic and laboratory evidence that that was
the case. We were going to go into that room, and this senior oncologist was going to have to tell
this gentleman, somebody he had known for over maybe nearly a decade at that point, that there
was nothing more he could do for him and that he was going to pass away. To me as a trainee, I
thought that I have no idea how this guy's going to do this because this is a heartbreaking
conversation. My heart is broken. And I've only known this guy for a few weeks. And I'm not in
his shoes. And so I go into the room and he does what would be the stuff of legend. I mean, he's
compassionate, he's caring, he's hearing the patient, he's seeing the patient, he's keeping
a little bit of distance, he's giving the information he needs to give, but he's also giving
sort of the emotional support he needs to give as well. It's very hard for me to even describe how
he did it. It felt like magic to me as a trainee. And afterwards, this patient thanks him for the
news, and is clearly upset about it, but then hugs him and says, I just want to thank you for taking
care of me for the last 10 years. I couldn't have done this without you. We come out of that room,
and we're just all sort of in that shocked feeling of what we had born witness to, which is
really sort of that rare privilege moment of being a doctor. And I remember telling this attending
physician, I've seen a bunch of people do that. I don't think I've ever seen anyone do it as
gracefully as you have done. That was really well done. How do you think about that? What's going
through your mind? How do you approach these situations? And he looked at me and he said,
I can't say that I'm good at it after doing it for 30 years, but I can say I try to be better
at it each year. And I realized that that was his secret, of course, is that he had never let
himself become complacent. He never let himself feel like he did a good job. He always aspired
to be a little bit better at delivering that news a little bit more in the moment than the year
before. And that was why he was so good at it is that he didn't take it for granted. He knew how
important it was, and he worked on it. And I guess that's how the moment he told me that, obviously,
it was sort of the moment that that was how I was going to think about it forever, because he was
right. And it's so easy to think as an oncologist that your decision is just prescribing the right
chemotherapy drug. But so much of oncology is being the person you need to be for this person
who needs you to be there for them in that moment. And I think that's in part what makes the feel so
rich and so interesting. First of all, that's a absolutely beautiful story. Secondly, I find it
interesting that it's hard to actually articulate the nuances of what he said while you're still
able to capture the gestalt of it. And that actually echoes an experience I had also at the
NCI with my mentor, who I remember a very similar situation. This was a very young patient, about
27 years old, metastatic melanoma. He had progressed through at the time the best available
immunotherapy. So a couple of things that stood out to me. One is when we were rounding on patients,
we were never permitted to say this patient failed such and such. As you know, in oncology,
that's a very common parlance. Mr. So-and-so is a 27 year old male. He has failed interleukin-2.
He failed GP100 vaccine. Now, it was never that. It was the therapy failed the patient. The patient
didn't fail the therapy. So we were very clear in our words. There was no ambiguity about how we
spoke about it. But when it became clear, just as you describe radiographically, that there was now
no option remaining for this patient and the tumors in his lungs and liver were exploding.
Steve Rosenberg was my mentor. He said something to me that was, it's really easy at this point
to think that because we have failed, we should be ashamed and we should run away from this patient.
But he said patients who are dying need us more than patients who are living. Which again,
sounds kind of vague, but it's that ethos that gets carried into the discussion. And if you think
of it that way, I think that's what actually contributed to the interaction. So your story
is really a beautiful example of that. We're going to end up talking quite a bit about cancer here,
not only because it's your career, but it's also potentially maybe outside of cardiology,
one of the places where we see the best of intentions gone awry with respect to how to
help people. God, there's a part of me that almost wants to jump right into your hallmarks,
because you close your book with, and by the way, I'm in the process of sort of trying to write a
book so I can appreciate the comedic relief in how the appendix or slash end of your book is,
oh, by the way, as I finish this book, I think I finally figured out a succinct way to explain this
now, which I loved. Yeah, yeah, so true. But maybe we'll save that for a moment. And because I think
that's a nice way to synthesize it, unless you just want to start with that. But do you want to kind
of get into a little bit of the how you came to appreciate what was not working and how that sort
of led you to formulate your journey through this? Yeah, I guess I'd say I'll talk a little bit about
what are the sort of structural problems in oncology, but I guess I'd say one of the sort of
moments in my life that it all came into crystal clear focus was there was a year at the National
Oncology Conference that there was one super transformational drug. And it was the drug that
made the big stage and it was the drug everyone was celebrating. And it was a drug that prior to
having this drug, the median survival with this condition was something on the order of six months.
And now that we have this drug, unfortunately, nobody was cured with this drug, but the median
survival was extended to 11 months. And so it's something like five month improvement in average
median survival that a patient would experience. And it was getting standing ovations and people
were incredibly enthusiastic about it. And I just remember I think at the time the conference was
going on in Chicago and one of my high school friends was visiting, and he asked me he's like,
you know, what's the big talk at that conference? And I told him about this drug, survival six
months, and now it's gone to 11 months. And he said six months, 11 months. And he said, Oh,
he said, what are you talking about? He said, do better than that. That's not good. I mean, 11
months, not good enough, man. He just said it. And it was just his gut reaction. He didn't go to
medical school. And he didn't even complete college. But he's a terrific person. And but
he was just giving his sort of just raw feeling about that that wasn't good enough. You all need
to aspire for more. And led to a lot of investigations where we and others have looked at what's the
average benefit of a new cancer drug come into market. If you look at 71 consecutively approved
drugs for the solid cancers, as Foho and colleagues did in a famous paper a few years ago,
the average improvement was 2.1 months. So that's the average of 71 drugs. Two months can mean a
lot to somebody. I mean, those are those could be two months where you do a lot of important things.
But two months also feels like, boy, can't we do better than that. And two months should also come
with another asterisk, which is what is the cost of these medications, they now routinely run 100,000
to $200,000 per year of treatment. And you got to take it for maybe eight, nine, 10 months to get
the two month benefits. So you're spending nearly $100,000 of money, just on the drug itself,
potentially all these other costs that come. And so many of us, myself included, started to feel
like, why are we spending so much money on these drugs that appear to offer less than what we would
want and hope for, for our patients? Why are there so many of them coming? Why aren't there fewer,
but better drugs coming? What are the sort of structural problems in this space that create a
glut of often me too drugs? And by that, I mean, there's a Coca-Cola, and there's a Pepsi-Cola,
and we're getting lots of Pepsi-colas. We're getting a lot of me too drugs. We're not getting
as many drugs that are as novel, that really are transformative. And so that was kind of one of the
core questions that started me on this path. And Malignant is sort of a book that summarizes
sort of all the work we've done in cancer and cancer drug space and drug policy space. But it
wasn't, of course, the goal when we started doing this work, we just kind of wanted to understand a
bunch of things. And after a while, we understood a few things in a way. And we realized that I
realized that there's a story that could be told across all these different domains, and that it
makes more sense when you tell the whole story. And so that's why I decided to write that book.
So let's start with the idea of reversal. You alluded to it earlier, let's go back and revisit
that. So that was sort of inspired by work I did as a resident, I had seen those situations that we
talked about situations where people were getting things done that appear to run counter to the best
available evidence. And with a colleague of mine, Adam Sifu, who's a professor at the University of
Chicago, he was a former teacher of mine, later became a mentor of mine and later became a friend,
which is sort of how the progression of those events often is in life. We started to ask a bunch
of questions about how many medical practices are adopted based on low levels of evidence,
what drive their adoption, and what happens when years later, people come along and do really
carefully done rigorous studies and find that some of them do not work as intended. And we call
those practices, practices that weren't just replaced by something better, but practices that
truly were reversed. We found that not doing it was better or whatever you did before was better.
We called those medical reversals and we started to kind of make lists of them, keep track of them,
and try to understand how often they occur, why they occur, what the downsides of having so many
reversals are. That led to the sort of the first book that I wrote with Adam Sifu, which is called
Ending Medical Reversal, which is really about all the flip-flops that happen in the doctor's office.
What are some of the examples that people might bring to mind when you think about that?
I mean, I guess a lot of them are actually from our talk and shop or sort of things that doctors
do, but I'll give you a few examples. So one is hormone therapy. So there was this very provocative
idea that was put out in the 1990s and supported by a couple of observational studies from the
Harvard investigators. And that was the idea that women who typically have low rates of
cardiovascular events, when they go through menopause, they have a higher rate of cardiovascular
events. Maybe estrogen was protecting them, lowering the rate of cardiovascular events,
and maybe if we supplement them with estrogen after menopause, they'll have lower rates of
cardiovascular events. A retrospective observational study from Harvard found that nurses who happened
to take hormone therapy, replacement therapy, did in fact have lower rates of cardiovascular disease.
And this led to sort of widespread promotion. There's a company called Wyeth that was really,
I think, instrumental in driving prescriptions of hormone replacement therapy. There was a lot of
basic science evidence that corroborated that estrogen has sort of favorable effects on vascular
endothelium, etc., etc. It quickly became sort of a widely used common medication accruing dollar
amounts in the billions of dollars. And then lo and behold, in 2001, 2002, a randomized controlled
trial called Women's Health Initiative came out, but randomly assigned postmenopausal women to
estrogen supplementation or not. And it found, in fact, it was halted for an increase in
thromboembolic and cardiovascular events. It actually did the opposite of what investigators
had thought. That was sort of a seminal moment, I think, for many people, that maybe things that
are widely done don't work as intended. I'll give you just another example. After somebody has a
heart attack, if you put them on an EKG machine and watch it, you'll see there are a bunch of
aberrant beats, premature ventricular contractions, PVCs. A number of really well done studies have
shown that the more PVCs a patient had, the more likely they are to have sudden cardiac death.
And there was a reason why that might happen, that these aberrant electrical activity of the heart
could actually precipitate a reentrant circuit and precipitate actually cardiac arrest.
A number of drugs were made that could suppress PVCs. They suppressed PVCs rather potently,
so you could have somebody take the drug and you can watch those PVCs just drop out of the EKG
tracing. And finally, somebody came along and said, look, we know PVCs are bad. We know the
drug suppresses PVCs, but we don't know for sure the drug lowers the risk of dying. Let's test that.
Let's do a randomized trial. And they did that randomized trial. It was called CAST. And
cardiologists were really reluctant to randomize patients because they thought it was unethical
not to give the drug. And finally, through persistence, they did do the randomized study
and actually found that it increased the risk of dying. And so those studies have led to the
abandonment, primarily the class 1C agents, flec and the like. And I think what the takeaway
message there is that, wow, a lot of smart, well-intentioned people who really have plausible
pathophysiology, who have a compelling retrospective observational story, they can be wrong
and has this happened elsewhere. And so we started investigating it. Now we have lists of
hundreds of items. They span everything from ways in which we screen patients, ways in which we test
patients, drugs we give patients, procedures we do on patients, surgeries we do on patients.
It really spans the gamut. There have been these medical reversals across broad domains of medicine.
They are quite common. I'd like to come back to one of those because I do think the
WHI is arguably the worst study that's ever been done, which then brings up a broader question,
which is how do we know if the patient in front of us is represented by the patient in this study?
But I don't want to take us off the oncology path, although the WHI's biggest headline,
of course, was the increase in the risk of breast cancer, which of course has since been
abandoned, which actually brings up another point, which is the difference between relative
risk and absolute risk. So I think there's a lot of interesting stuff to talk about.
So let's get back to oncology and go back to what you were just outlining as I think the broad
problem statement here, which is we've got a disease that I think it's safe to say we haven't
really had much success against, despite a lot of propaganda. I sort of explain it to my patients
this way. I don't know if you'd agree, but I say, look, there are three broad pillars of disease,
chronic disease that are going to kill us. So you've got sort of this foundation of metabolic
disease. So that's everything from hyperinsulinemia to insulin resistance to fatty liver disease to
type 2 diabetes. That creates the foundation upon which three other disease processes get a lot
worse, cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease, cancer and neurodegenerative disease.
There's really only one of those three pillars we've had some success against, and that's
cardiovascular disease. Your probability of surviving a heart attack in 2020 is infinitely
better than 1960. I mean, between advanced cardiac life support, better drugs to lower
cholesterol, lower blood pressure, as you pointed out earlier, stents that actually do their job
in patients who are having an MI or immediately post. And also, I think we have a greater path
ophysiologic understanding of it. But if you have metastatic breast cancer in 2020 versus 1970 or
1960, if you have Alzheimer's disease in 2020 versus 1970 or 1960, you're not a hell of a lot better
off. And I think that's a hard thing for people to understand, especially when you consider
the resources that have been put at it. Have you got a ballpark of how much has been invested in
cancer research in the last 50 years, directionally since the war on cancer was declared?
The total will easily be in the hundreds of billions of dollars. So I guess I would say,
I mean, I think your assessment, although people may not like it, I think it is not inaccurate.
It is accurate assessment is that we've poured in hundreds of billions of dollars. That's probably
combined with public purses and private purses. And the returns on that, it's easy to sort of fixate
on the few sort of examples where we've made massive progress. But we can't forget the denominator,
which is the average person walking in clinic who might not have chronic myeloid leukemia or one of
the rare conditions that we've made sort of transformative leaps in the average person,
I think is still facing a very grave prognosis and that the progress is, as my friend said,
that's not good enough, you got to do better. It's a great story about your friend,
because sometimes you just need an outsider to sort of call your BS, which is we celebrate this
drug. I remember when I was in residence, I don't remember what drug it was, but I literally remember
going to ASCO or something and someone presented a drug that increased median survival by 0.7
months, 0.7 months, right? 20 days. And I remember doing the math. It was at a cost of $38,000 for
the extra 20 days. And I mean, I think people listening to this might be understandable to
question, well, who are we to say what $38,000 is worth? How do you think about that question,
which is the societal cost versus the individual cost? So all things equal, let's assume there was
no toxicity of the drug or let's assume that the pain and discomfort of the drug wasn't a deciding
factor. Who is to decide the cost of a life? I guess before I dive into that answer, let me
give a little bit more background that I think will even make it more sort of relevant for the
listener to really get a sense of why I'm going to answer the way I answer, which is that 0.7
months, that's not in everybody. And what do I mean by that? So the trials that we use to identify
these numerical amounts that the drugs improve survival are not average Americans off the street
with the cancer. They're really carefully curated populations. They're often 10 years younger than
average cancer patients. They don't have the same range of comorbidities. They don't have as much
diabetes. They're not as overweight. They don't have cardiovascular disease. They don't have renal
dysfunction. They're younger, healthier. One of my colleagues describes clinical trial patients as
somebody who could run a marathon who also happens to have cancer. They're really fit individuals.
And in that person, you give them a drug that may make some of them have diarrhea eight times a
day or make their hands and feet ache or make them lose their hair or have bone marrow suppression
or all of these things. But because they're so fit, they can tolerate that drug and they can take that
dose and they can handle those side effects. And in that person, even though they push the dose in
that person to handle all that side effects, the benefit is still 0.7 months. So now imagine what
happens when you give it to an older person who's frail, who can't handle the full dose because they
need a dose reduction because that side effect is massively more severe in that person. What's the
benefit in that person? And I think a number of empirical studies have looked at these cancer
drugs and find that the benefits in the average American are maybe even absent. I mean, I'll give
you one example. There's a drug seraphanib in the trial that led to its approval. This is for patients
with liver cancer that can't be treated by surgery. This is liver cancer where the horse has left out
of the barn and it cannot be cured with surgical resection or transplant. If you randomize them to
seraphanib or placebo, sugar pale, 11 months median survival with seraphanib and about eight months
with placebo, a difference of about three months. And this got a standing ovation at the national
meeting. People really celebrated this drug. A couple of researchers looked at Medicare data
sets, your Medicare, which is Americans over the age of 65. And they found people who took seraphanib
for this disease. And they found the median survival of somebody who took seraphanib in
Medicare was around four months. So in other words, in the real world, somebody taking the drug
that improves survival lives 50% as long as the person taking sugar pill in the trial,
which just shows you that the Grand Canyon of difference between real world patients and
clinical trial patients. And in the real world, they compared those people taking seraphanib
who live four months to similar people who didn't take seraphanib. And they also live four months.
So I think that some of the benefits of these drugs do evaporate when you give them in broad
populations. First of all, I'm really glad you brought that up. I interviewed Azra Raza a little
while ago and she made the same point. I just don't think that can be overstated. So I want to
make sure that people really understand what you're getting at. When we look at name plate clinical
trials, they aren't just best case scenario by a little bit. They are best case scenario by a log
order based on patient selection. And let's be clear, if you're in the business of trying to get
your drug approved, it is in your best interest to spoon feed and handpick the absolute healthiest
people on the planet in whom to test your drug. So again, the system is set up to make this happen.
This isn't some grand conspiracy. It's common sense. You've spent a billion dollars generating
this drug. The final hurdle for you to get this drug to market is a very large phase three trial.
You're not about to blow it by screwing up the patient's selection. It's no different
than being a trial lawyer who spends a year preparing for a case only to pick the wrong
jury. You've got to do your job and pick the right patients. Your point is, hey, and Azra made the
same point. Look, the likelihood that the person sitting in your clinic in front of you is half as
healthy as the patient that clinical trial is very low. And therefore, they're not going to be as
resilient, which means A, they probably can't tolerate the drug as well. And B, they don't
have the physiologic reserve such that the delta between them and the untreated patient is likely
to be far compressed. That's right. And I think you make another terrific point, which is that
we can't blame the tiger for being the tiger. The pharmaceutical company is doing what's rational.
They're tasked with running a trial to test their own product. If you win, you're going to earn,
on average, $12 billion in the next 14 years. If you get a P of 0.049, you get 12 billion.
If you get a P of 0.051, you get minus a few hundred million dollars, your outlay on the drug.
And if you have an incentive system like that, I mean, you should not blame the industry for,
I think, all of the things we see in clinical trial design, which are sort of okay, acceptable
ways to put a thumb on the scale. One of which is you carefully curate your patient population.
Another is you test your new drug against, well, maybe not the drug doctors are actually using,
maybe you test it against the oldest, weakest drug in the space. Maybe for patients who take the old
drug, when they have progressive disease, they don't get access to the best new drugs. They get
substandard care, which often happens in these registration studies. There are a number of ways
that I think are within the realm of what people accept that allow for gaming of the trial. And it
would be irrational not to take advantage of that because the amount of money at stake is vast. And
the incentive to put a thumb on the scale when you can is great. But I think it's worth restating,
as you say, that these are drugs that we're really talking about the best case scenario and the best
case scenario is often less than desired. Should we go to the next part, which is the cost? How do
you decide who pays? Yeah. So I'll think back to probably the first time I remember thinking about
this was when Gleevac was approved. Now Gleevac was, God, I'm trying to think I was probably in
residency when Gleevac was approved. Yeah, 2001. Yeah. This was a big deal because I remember in
medical school, I had read Judah Folkman's book. Judah Folkman has since passed, but he was sort
of a luminary oncologist and he was basically one of the first people to propose this idea that if
you cut off the blood supply to a tumor, you could stop a tumor. And again, to put this in the broader
context, this was a pretty remarkable idea because up until that point in time, you had this idea
that you could cut a tumor out if it was localized. You could give a bunch of chemicals that targeted
its ability to replicate. That was sort of the gist of chemotherapy, or you could radiate the
crap out of it, which also basically destroyed its ability to replicate. And some people like
Steve Rosenberg and Jim Allison were working on these immunotherapy ideas, but Judah comes along
and says, look, there's another really obvious idea here, which is any cancer cell that leaves its
site of origin and goes to take up residence somewhere else, better figure out a way to get
blood. And so we have these growth factors for blood, VEGF being one of them. And so this whole
new thing of anti-VEGF compounds comes along. And so Gleevac becomes the first drug approved for this.
And if my memory serves me correctly, it was for colon cancer was the first indication.
You probably think of a Bevacizumab and Avastin. Oh, that's right. I'm sorry. Sorry. Sorry. Sorry.
You're absolutely right. I'm thinking of Avastin. Of course, Gleevac is for
GIS, Dremel tumors. And then, yeah, I'm actually thinking of Avastin. Yes. Okay. Same time period
though. Avastin was about 2000, 2001, maybe 2002. And was it colon cancer for Avastin?
Yeah, it was the first one. Yeah.
And I sort of remember directionally it being about a hundred thousand bucks for a year.
And do you remember what the improvement in survival was with all the noted caveats that
we just gave? Was it like eight versus 12 months or something to that effect?
I think it was less than that. I think the original paper that led to approval was the
Hurwitz paper. And I think it was on the order of a couple of months. But I guess I would say that
if you look at Avastin across all the different cancers, I mean, you're, you look at where it
works and where it doesn't work, where it works, we're talking about a month and a half, two months.
I mean, that's about the average. The point of my very unfortunate long-winded story was
certain countries, and I think the UK was on the list, just said, no, we're not paying for this
drug because it doesn't reach our threshold, which I think at the time was about 100,000
pounds per quality adjusted life year per quality. And the United States, of course,
took a different position, which was private insurance companies will pay for this, which
basically means the government and or employer will pay for this. And I remember that being the
very first time that I thought about this and thought, huh, what is the implication of this?
How does this work? So how do you think about that? And again, this is almost asking you to
put on a policy hat on half of your head with a physician hat on the other half of your head,
right? I think you're right about one thing, which is that there are different hats. And when you're
in the room, what you do might not be the same thing as what you advise a government to do.
And maybe that's okay. That's the right way these things should happen. When you're in the room,
you do everything you can that adds anything that the patient really wants and that the
toxicity worth it to the patient. When you were in the policy hat, you ask what's best for everybody.
And I guess what I would say here is one thing that fits in this discussion is that every dollar
spent on Avastin is a dollar not spent on a lot of healthcare interventions that may have better
bang for your buck. May I take all that money that we're spending on Avastin for 100 people,
and we might get 100,000 people to take their lisinopril or their hydrochlorothiazide, their
blood pressure pills more religiously, we might get them to do something else. And the cumulative
number of life years added to the world from those people doing whatever that other thing is,
that may exceed the Avastin benefit by an order of magnitude. When societies pay for something,
it is different than when you and I pay for something. If I take my own money and buy
anything, it's really nobody else's business. And if you do whatever you want with your money.
But if we all make a commitment to healthcare, what we're saying is, we're all going to pool all this
money. And we're going to pull this money so that we pay for this thing that we think is a different
commodity. It's something that's a human right, something that we all deserve to have. The only
rational way I think a society to spend that money is to do what benefits the most people,
what brings the most good in the world. That might mean sometimes societies make, as the UK does,
tough decisions. They decide instead of 20 people getting access to some new cancer drug that
doesn't cure the disease but may extend survival by a couple months, let's take all that money and
let's give pregnant women access to X, Y, or Z that might improve the longevity of their children
and another generation of kids in the UK. And so I think that all nations struggle with this
question, which is how do we ration limited resources? In other countries, they are upfront
and open about the discussion. They use things like cost effectiveness to ration products.
In the US, we do ration. We just ration in a way you don't see because some people don't get
anything. They don't get beneficial medicines and they don't get really marginal medicines either.
They just don't have access at all. They're cut out of the system. And so we ration by
discriminating against people. That's a different type of rationing. It's cruel and irrational,
but it is a rationing nonetheless. I think that this is a thorny problem and no one person has the
answer. And I guess I also think that people should be free to spend their own money as they so choose.
I think the reality is if you had to spend your own money versus deciding whether or not to leave
that money for your children or for a loved one, I think a lot of people wouldn't buy these drugs.
There might be some ultra wealthy people, but I think some of us might make different choices
with our own money. If you have to spend society's money, I think the obligation to really know that
they work, that they actually are delivering benefit to people, I think that obligation is
a bit stronger. When you go back and think about your undergrad as a philosophy major,
this is probably one of those places where you probably have an insight that someone like me
doesn't have. How do you think about this through the lens of what philosophers would have said?
Yeah, I mean, I guess I would say, I don't know if that's true, that I have an insight that you
don't have. I think you have a lot of good insights. I guess I would say, obviously, what
I'm speaking about is a type of ethic, which is probably called utilitarian ethics, which is this
idea that ethical principles, when they are in conflict, they prioritize the greatest good for
the greatest number over a lesser good for a lesser number. And when it comes to deciding
whether or not to cover really costly cancer drugs that have small benefits and idealized settings
and have question mark benefits in real world settings, versus paying for other things that
have more convincing evidence that they improve outcomes for a lot more people, I think a
utilitarian ethic would tend to side with the latter that you got to pay for what benefits more
people. I mean, one of the constant criticisms of the UK system is that cancer outcomes aren't as
good in the UK as they are in the US. I think that fact alone has been overstated to some degree.
But that's not really the question because the question is their life expectancy is better.
They're spending less on healthcare, they got better life expectancy, their medical care may
be better. I think if you're looking at somebody, if you're looking at the person just getting the
Avastin, I think the decision is different than if you're looking at everybody. There are different
conceptions of ethics. And I think some people might put a value on caring for people at the
end of life, irrespective of I think societal implications for others. And I guess I don't,
sort of a deontologic perspective, and I guess I don't discount that at all. I mean, I think
when people are question mark on Avastin for colon cancer, we're not saying don't treat a person,
there's still lots of treatments you would give. You give the same treatment except leave out the
Avastin and the difference is probably very slight. Maybe there's no difference at all,
is what somebody like me might think if I haven't reviewed all the evidence.
One of the things that I just think, I'll tell you a funny story and I'll come back to the thing.
And I may have even mentioned this during the podcast before, but I've got a friend who used
to live in Saudi Arabia. He's an American, lived in DC. So during the summer, he would always come
back to DC. So he would sort of spend June to September in DC before going back to Saudi
Arabia. And I was there visiting him once and I asked him, I said, dude, what's it like when you
come back to your apartment in September? Just tell me how hot it is. Is it like, does it hit 130
degrees after you've left the apartment sitting there all summer? He goes, no, man, it's like 70
degrees. I leave the AC on the whole summer. And I'm like, what do you mean you leave the AC on
the whole summer? You have a timer set to come on an hour before you get there. He goes, no, no,
no, no. When I leave, the AC is on. When I come back, the AC is on. I can't wrap my head around
this. I'm like, how criminal is that? How much money are you spending? He goes, it costs me $4
a month. I'm like, how is that possible? He goes, oh, our energy is totally subsidized by the
government here. We pay 19 cents a gallon for gasoline. So it's about $4 a month for me to,
at the time, this was more than 10 years ago, it's about $4 a month for me to keep my apartment
in Saudi Arabia and Riyadh at 70 degrees when it's 120 degrees outside. Now you have to understand
something. This is a totally rational human being. This is a reasonable guy who would never do this
in his apartment in Washington, DC. It just gave me a great example of how when we don't have skin
in the game, we are incapable of making rational cost decisions. It's like, if I said to you,
you can have any car you want, but you only have to pay 5% of the cost of the car, I think you're
going to make a very different decision than if I say you can have any car you want, but you
actually have to pay for the whole car. Now we can lend you the money and you can do X, Y, and Z.
I guess the thing I've always struggled with, I don't know how to solve the problem of healthcare
cost of which oncology is a huge driver, and we're going to get to that shortly, because I don't
know how to reconcile these two points, which is on the one hand, you cannot make rational decisions
if you don't have skin in the game. And if the physician and the patient don't have skin in the
game, how is a rational decision being made? But on the other hand, with the costs of these things
being so prohibitive, how can people have meaningful skin in the game? So how do we
reconcile these two forces? Probably not going to have the perfect answer for that. I like what
you're saying and I like your analogy and I want to kind of expand on it a little bit.
So in your analogy, I think you're right that your friend is making the rational choice, which is
it doesn't cost me much more, it's like a 50 cents, let us keep it cool all day. Who cares?
Somebody else is paying for that. In your car analogy, yeah, if you only pay 5% of the price
of car, yeah, I'm going to drive McLaren. I like your choice by the way. Good choice. McLaren,
thank you for that. Big fan of Top Gear and Grand Tour. But I guess I would say, but to make it
really more analogous to what we're thinking about, you pay 5% for the price of the car,
but you never actually get the car and you don't get to drive the car. You just get told how good
the car is. I'm telling you how good the car is. This is a great car. Don't you worry about how
good the car is. You are not in a position to judge how good the car is. Having the car may change
what you do. What do I mean by that? When it comes to cancer drugs, in a theoretical situation,
I do think people will say, if it adds anything, if there's any upside and somebody else is paying
most of the cost, I'm willing to accept that. I want to try it. Let's just try. That's the mantra
of oncology. But many of these drugs, that idea that it only has an upside, that is sort of a
construct that's been created through a system that is not giving you the accurate information.
And in fact, some of these drugs, they may actually have a net downside. How might that be? One,
they don't actually improve survival. That's one. They have no survival benefit. Two,
they may have an opportunity cost that instead of being somebody who in their last few months of
life is going to Tahiti or going to visit a friend, I'm somebody who is tethered to the infusion
suite. And I got to keep coming back twice weekly for four weeks. I got to keep seeing this doctor.
I got to spend 15% of my extra life you gave me, maybe 40% of that I'm spending in your lobby.
You're taking it back from me. And so it makes people make choices about what they prioritize
and how they view the end of life that may actually, I think, dissolve whatever ideal
benefits that the drugs provide. I mean, your point is well taken that there is this sort of
tension between who pays for something and choices people make. And I guess the way I try to get
around that is, if we could just start an oncology with the choices that probably are not in your
best interest, we probably would save a lot of money and people will be better off for it. And
then we can go to the next level of choices where there really is that trade off that you
articulate so well. What do you think are the no regret moves in oncology today?
I guess I could do a tumor by tumor. I guess I mean, if you have localized cancer for the most
part, no regret move is to cut it out surgery, you guys win a lot, no regret moves. Very little
advanced in the last 50 years, right? I mean, where have we gotten better? Well, I think 50
years ago, Whipple procedure carried a much higher mortality than today. I think 50 years ago,
women were decimated by radical mastectomies that are, I didn't do one radical mastectomy in
my residency. So basically for 20 years, that's a procedure that's never been done. And today,
there's been a push to more and more and more localized surgeries with just as good an outcome.
So that's been a huge advent. But yeah, for the most part, we figured that one out a long time ago.
Exactly, right.
Let's keep doing it. Okay, next.
So next category. So let's get into I mean, I'm gonna make a nod to radiotherapy, which I think
is really useful in many situations. Maybe the Michael Douglas situation had a cancer localized
probably anything for a or better, you know, you get a great shot of a long lasting cure with
chemo radiotherapy. Okay, so I think surgery radiotherapy are on the table. Now let's talk
about drugs. You got Hodgkin's lymphoma. Well, good news. We've got a four drug combination
that's curative. You've got testicle cancer and it's spread to your lung. Good news, we can cure
95% plus of you, including those that are non-seminomatous. Now, obviously, it depends on
the exact subtype. And sometimes you require a combination of both chemotherapy and surgical
therapy. So for instance, like teratoma or something like that. CML chronic myeloid leukemia,
this is the Gleevec story that I think is transformative. Some will argue is not cancer
right away, the skeptic would say, is this a cancer, right? I mean, it's a very fair point,
which is that what is CML? It is a blood based cancer. One of the things about blood based
cancers is you tend to see that a lot sooner than you see other cancers because it's easy to find
because it's in your blood, you can just draw the blood and there it is. And if you had that
access to every organ in the same way, maybe you would be finding similar malignant lesions and
other organs. That's a possibility. We also know it's genomically dumb. It's driven by BCR-able
fusion, a genomic event, and not a whole heck of a lot else if that's the sole driver. And if you
give a drug that inhibits that fusion event, you can turn median life expectancy from three to four
years to nearly normal life expectancy in a Swedish dataset. They're living almost a full life,
maybe a year shy of normal life expectancy that is a tremendous advance in medicine.
So those are just a few no brainers, but there are a lot of no brainers I think that have to do with
there's a benefit and the toxicity is low, or there's a benefit, a smaller benefit, but the
toxicity is reversible. So you could try it and if it doesn't go well, you can stop it and you don't
have them lost too much. I think those are kind of no brainers, but some things are much more dubious,
which they are caustic, toxic treatments, long-term toxicity, toxicities that don't get better,
don't go away, that at the best don't add that much. I mean, I think there are a lot of dubious
choices that people find themselves in. And I think the other thing that's hard to express is that
the person in the chair, the patient, is in a very difficult position. I mean, they didn't spend their
lives studying cancer and studying all the data or maybe even studying how to think about cancer
data and they're in a vulnerable position. Their life is on the line and that's not always a great
position to make choices. And people often tend to make choices that may not be compatible with
their best interest. Some people make choices that are driven by family members who believe those
choices are in their best interest, but they might not be. There's a lot of social complexity here
that makes it a thorny problem. But yeah, there are few no-brainer decisions. There are some real
advances in the last 20 years and then there's a lot of fool's gold. A lot of things people say
are game changers, miracles, revolutions that are no such thing, but really don't have those
substantive benefits when you look at it critically. Give me an example of something you put in that
latter category of something that's getting a ton of attention that you're not a big believer in. I
mean, where do the cell-based therapies for immunotherapy fit in or something like checkpoint
inhibitors like Ktruda, which I mean, boy, when those things work, they're game changers. And when
they don't work, they don't work. Yeah. I mean, I guess I would say, I have a good example that
comes to mind, which I will come to, but let me just first comment about those things. I mean,
I guess I would say the cell-based therapies or things like CAR T or Tisagen, like Lusol or these
sort of novel cell products, they still have a lot of promise and they have definitely shown sort of
great responses in some people. But the real question will be, are they so beneficial in
every condition? We're trying some of those cell-based therapies in multiple myeloma and a lot
of people are having remissions, but those remissions are fleeting and it looks like everyone
is having relapse. That's different than what we found with lymphoma and what we found with
pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia, or ALL, which you talked about earlier. With Ktruda,
we have a number of randomized control trials that show clear survival benefits in Ktruda in
specific settings. We also have a bunch of settings that have been disappointing and we've
had confirmatory randomized trials that don't show benefits. So Ktruda might be almost a case-by-case
basis. What cancer, what patient? But let me give you a good example of a drug that I think is just
a classic example of really a questionable decision. I'll talk about it in one cancer,
pancreas cancer. So some people with pancreas cancer have a germline mutation in BRCA gene,
or BRACA, which is a gene that confers susceptibility to cancers, one of which is
pancreas, but often breast cancers where you most think about it. And if you have a BRACA germline
mutation in pancreas cancer, they did a randomized trial where they gave people four months of the
standard of care for fulfirinox therapy and they stopped it after a minimum of four months. You
could have had a little bit more, but they stopped it after four months and randomized you to
elaprib or sugar pill. And if you take elaprib, you have a progression-free survival benefit,
which I can explain what it is in a second, versus sugar pill, but you don't have an overall
survival benefit. You're not living any longer. And maybe it wasn't a good idea to stop fulfirinox.
I think a lot of doctors would have continued that. So the control arm shouldn't have been
sugar pill. It should have been continuing the drugs that were working. This is a trial called
polo. This is a drug that has a cost of about $12,000 a month. And the reason the rhetoric
and the reality are so separated is that the drugs we were using in pancreas cancer were old
cytotoxic chemotherapy drugs. They were drugs that were not sexy, didn't sound so great.
And this is a new targeted drug, quote unquote targeted drug. And it's based on your genomic
signature, which is unique to just your tumor. I mean, it sounds like that should be terrific.
The reality is the data suggests it might not be as good as if you continued that old fashioned
therapy. So that's an example where I think that hype can easily outpace benefit. And then I guess
I just wanted to just explain real quick for the listener, progression-free survival, which comes
up just so often in cancer. It's a unique endpoint. It's really often interpreted in the lay press as
the time it takes for cancer to get worse. That's not quite right. So progression-free survival is
the time from when a patient enrolls on a study to one of four things really happening to them.
One, they could die. The first thing they could be going along and then one day they could just
die. So that's part of the endpoint. So if you die first, that's it. You have a PFS event.
Fortunately for most trials, that's not the most common thing that counts as a PFS event. The second
thing that could happen is you have a new lesion on your CAT scan. We're scanning you along and
your lungs, we didn't find anything, but now there's a little ditzel there and I stick a
needle in it and it's pancreas cancer. So you have progressed, you got a new lesion. That's
progression. The third thing that could happen is your tumor that we measured at one centimeter,
it got to 1.2 centimeters. It got 20% bigger. The moment it gets 20% bigger, 21% bigger,
it's progression. When it's 19% bigger, oh, it's stable disease. That's what we call that. That's
stable, but then 20%, 21%, that's progression. So it's an arbitrary cut point, very arbitrary.
And that's why it doesn't always track with how people feel. The fourth thing that could happen
is your tumor got smaller before it got bigger. And if your tumor got smaller before it gets
bigger, it's 20% from the smallest it ever was. So those are the four things that count as
progression. Often trials are driven by the latter two events. The tumors look 120% bigger.
I like to also tell people that when you measure a tumor on a CAT scan, if you haven't done a lot
of that, I'm sure you've done that, but if you haven't done a lot of that, people think it's
like measuring your height. It's a lot more like measuring the width of a cloud between your fingers
looking up at the sky. People have dispute about where the tumor ends and where the normal tissue
begins. And that's been shown in many studies. The reason I say all this is let's go back to that
example, that drug. This is a drug when tested against sugar pill in a setting where probably
shouldn't have been tested against sugar pill, should have been tested against a real therapy we do.
The only thing it could improve was the progression free survival, which is an arbitrary line in the
sand for tumor growth that really doesn't measure people living longer or feeling better. That's why
I think it's really a problematic drug. Yeah, I remember. God, how many years ago? Is that five
years ago or four years ago when that came out? This trial actually is more recent than that. It
was just in the last year, but they probably started it five years ago. The enthusiasm for
it was there and they started down the path. I think I'd followed that drug maybe back at its
phase two. And I don't know why. For some reason, I felt like that was a fool's errand, but it seems
like that just concludes it. So there are a couple things I want to come back to. But before we do
that, I want to go back and talk through your hallmarks because this strikes me as the culmination
of all the work you put into this book and you do what everybody's doing when they're writing a book.
You're probably putting the finishing touches on it and you have this epiphany and you realize,
well, I could go and weave it into the narrative of the book or I could very concisely lay it out
here. And I think you chose the latter, which is actually quite elegant. So walk us through
the notion of these hallmarks, these six hallmarks and explain what they mean because they're not
entirely obvious just from the brief description. Sure. Thanks for that. I guess I think one year
I really write about how it happened, which was you write a book and people think you write the
book, but of course there's so much back and forth and it goes on for years. And where you are
emotionally and mentally when you finish the book and where you started are very different places.
And often you grow a lot in the process of writing it. It changes the way you think about things. And
so I start by in this chapter by saying, here's a way I should have said things all along. I could
have said things better, but at least for my case, it's better late than never. I could still
toss it in the book. And I think the other thing the listener should know is there is something
called the hallmarks of cancer. These are six things proposed by Hannahann and Weinberg. There's
six hallmarks of cancer like invasion, invasion, basement membrane, poor immune surveillance,
angiogenesis, one of the ones you mentioned. These are sort of six biological hallmarks of cancer.
And that is a highly influential paper and it's been really extremely well cited and has
shaped a lot of people thinking. It might be one of the most cited papers in oncology,
isn't it? I think it might be. I think you're right. It might be in fact the most cited
paper in oncology. So anyway, so like all great things I try to steal from them. No, I try to
imitate. When I finished this book, I realized that, well, you know, I'm not talking about
biology. And in fact, I say many times, it's not a cancer biology book. This is a book about policy,
our rules, our laws, our guidelines, and how policy can make things better. And I realized
that maybe policy can be distilled like biology to six essential hallmarks, six ways in which
we might make things better. And so I guess I'll take you through the six. I guess the first of
the six was independence. What do I mean by this? So I guess one of the things in the book that I
spend a lot of time talking about are conflicts of interest, ways in which the industry gets people
who should be sort of competitors with the industry or should be stakeholders that push
back on the industry, it gets them to buy into the industry's narrative in part because they fund
those stakeholders. So talk about patient advocacy groups are often heavily funded by the industry,
how FDA employees who you think should be sort of separated from the industry, their most common
place of employment after the FDA is the industry. And so they kind of have a unique role as regulator,
but also future employee. So I call independence is we need sort of some rules in the space to,
I think, minimize conflict of interest and to allow entities to be free to advocate for their
constituents. Probably the biggest offender is expert oncologists like me. In my case,
unfortunately, I don't receive money from the pharmaceutical industry. However, I think that's
not the case for the majority of expert oncologists, they do. And their views are often very supportive
of these questionable drugs. They're almost at times as if they're cheerleaders. And I believe
that some of that is driven by those sort of financial ties. So I guess the first one is
independence. How does one do anything about that? Maybe we'll probe each one a little bit.
Okay, let's probably.
As opposed to just going through them. So completely get your point there. Look, I mean,
when I was in residency, drug reps brought us lunches.
Oh, yeah.
Right. And gave us pens. Like, you know, something as silly as that, but that's a hook.
Yeah, it's a little bit of a hook.
It's a little bit of a hook. It's who has the coolest pen? Because these weren't just generic
pens. These were like really cool pens. Like you wanted to be there at that lunch and get that
really cool pen. It was like, I remember some of them to this day, like a pen that looked like a
needle syringe. And when you clicked it, that color changed and all these other cool things. And
look, all they wanted was five minutes of your time. And I remember by the end, residency,
some of those, they were starting to take us, the senior residents out for dinners.
And I got to be honest with you. I don't recall giving it any thought. Like I don't recall
actually feeling like I was doing something wrong. I remember being kind of annoyed that I had to
listen to them talk. Because at that point in my life, I feel like the only thing that mattered
was getting a meal. And I was sort of like, hey, why don't you just shut up and let me eat?
Let us enjoy. Yeah.
But I honestly don't think it crossed my mind, Vinay, that this is the beginning of a very slippery
slope. They're not buying me lunch, giving me pens and eventually buying me dinner because
they think I'm a nice guy. I find that a little bit disturbing that I was too stupid to see
through that. I guess I'll give myself some grace and say the sleep deprivation may have played a
role in it. But have things changed in the last 20 years? I assume that pharma is not allowed in a
hospital anymore. Well, in many, but not every place. But I guess I'd say a couple of things
about that. One, I guess I don't blame you so much. You're a resident at the time. And to be honest,
I actually don't know what you described, although it is problematic. Those pens are collector's
items. So if you have any good ones, send them my way. No, just kidding. They really were
spectacular. They really were. Many people did collect them. And the next thing I would say is
that there is evidence that shows even so much as a meal that is paid for by the industry is
associated with a statistically significant but very small increase in prescribing patterns. So
it is a strategy that pays dividends. I guess I would say that I see the problems with that. And
I think that they are problematic and they have largely been curtailed through a number of sort
of well-intentioned efforts. But one of the things I talk a little bit about in the book
is that we haven't yet curtailed things on the high end. So here we spend a lot of time trying
to reform on the low end, the people getting the pens and the meals. There are many senior
oncologists who receive over $100,000 a year in consulting payments from companies, even more.
They receive millions of dollars in research funding. We have shown in some publications that
even controlling for research funding, controlling for prior publications, controlling for seniority,
personal payments from the industry are associated with greater publication in the future.
It's likely it's a positive feedback loop. Working with the industry helps your career,
which helps you work with the industry, which helps your career. The people in those roles,
the most conflicted people, people who are earning as much from the industry in their side hustle as
the average household income in America, those people, they write the guidelines. And the guidelines
by law in the US make Medicare pay for drugs for off-label purposes. So the people who write the
guideline that mandates Medicare must pay for this drug, no price negotiation, that person is
being paid by the industry, even for the exact same drug. And so those relationships, I think,
are an order of magnitude more concerning than the resident, hungry resident taking a meal.
In fact, I try not to talk too much about those sort of little things, but I think you're right
that it's a slippery slope and part of it is to get you accustomed to the fact that this is no
big deal. So I think you're absolutely right. I guess I would say the way I would sort of structure
the solution is the way I sort of structure lots of solutions, which is I don't want to be the
person setting rules and hard rules with punishments because I don't think that that's
really what gets people to change behavior. I want to create a different set of incentives that get
people to maybe do something differently. And so some incentives, I think, are we still need
guidelines to help decide what to cover off-label. Why don't we incentivize people who don't have
conflict to join those guidelines? And what if we had rules and policies that favored faculty members
who didn't take money from the industry to be on the guidelines? Suddenly, career incentives look
very different. I mean, right now, if I'm a junior faculty member and Eli Lilly offers me sort of an
ad board consulting opportunity, I might jump at it and I can still have open the opportunity of
sitting on a guidelines committee. But maybe in exchange for one opportunity, I should lose the
other opportunity. And if I want to keep the other opportunity, it's my choice. And the more you kind
of build in those kind of structural incentives, I think people will do things that preserve different
opportunities. So I think that's sort of one way you tackle the problem of conflict of interest,
which is that you just sort of tinker with incentives. You create opportunities for academics
to not take money and still have robust and rich careers. I think in the current system,
all the opportunities are tied to taking money from the industry. And so I guess how can I blame
anybody, just like I don't blame the industry for putting a thumb on the scale, I guess I don't
really blame the faculty members for doing it. Is there evidence that physicians are, for the
most part, honestly disclosing these things? I mean, I know there was a very famous case at
Memorial Sloan Kettering where there was a huge blow up over this. So if a system like the one you
described were in place, do we believe that we could believe people? Yeah, it's a great point.
I mean, I guess I would say that most of the available evidence suggests that disclosure is
incomplete and often inaccurate. Some of the available evidence suggests that people don't
even believe that they have the conflict. And so some of it is an honest error that they don't even
see that they're being conflicted. They may have forgotten. You cite a really sort of high profile
example of Jose Baselga, who had found to omit conflicts in dozens and dozens of articles and
conflicts that were really pertinent to what he was talking about. And he ultimately was pushed
out of his role at Memorial Sloan Kettering, which is a form of punishment. But very shortly,
he became vice president of AstraZeneca, a job that probably pays him several times as much
money as he was making earlier. So I hope someday somebody punishes me in the same way and pushes
me out of my job, but then pays me a whole lot more money to do something in the same space. I want to
be punished like that. But I mean, I think that speaks to the fact that we don't really take
disclosure seriously. I guess the other thing I would say about disclosure is disclosure has been
one of the methods that we have confronted conflict of interest with, but I'm not exactly
sure it makes the world better. There's some psychology evidence, some business evidence that
suggests that once people disclose, there may be actually greater trust placed in the disclosure.
And it doesn't actually correct, I think, the bias. It just leads the patient to have more trust in
their doctor, having seen the doctor disclosed. So I think maybe divestment is a better way,
maybe sort of different rules and incentives for people is a better way to kind of separate these
things. I think that these conflicts are problematic in one respect that I'll kind of flesh out a
little bit. So in cancer medicine, so often you've got a drug that costs $100,000 a year and it
changes something like how big the tumor is on a cat skin with all the problems of measurement.
We don't know if you live longer, we don't know if you live better, and you got to take the drug.
Who decides whether or not we should recommend that routinely or not? That guideline decision is
of huge importance. It will shape how many, many people practice. And I want people to make that
decision who are oncologists, who have experience, who may know a lot about how to read studies and
interpret data, but who don't have any financial relationships with the company that makes that
product. I think that leads to sort of a cleaner decision-making process. And it's the same kind of
way we set up a courtroom. Can you imagine a courtroom where the prosecutor and the defendant
are both being paid by the defendant? I mean, I think many of us would say that's not really a
balanced courtroom. And yet in medicine, we do have many imbalanced courtrooms where almost
everybody in the courtroom is getting money from the company. And so I guess I'm just suggesting
that we don't take away the industry's incentive. We keep the profit. Of course, I think it does
drive innovation, but we remove it from the people that's supposed to provide opposition force and
try to preserve a healthy sort of dynamic there. What is the opposition to your idea, which is so
obvious, it's painful to listen to you articulate it? The opposition is probably principally that
the people who are best in the position to fix the situation are the ones who are personally getting
the most money. I mean, I guess I'd say that our professional societies are driven by the industry
payments, the professional societies, senior leadership at universities and academic medical
centers are often on the boards of directors of companies. They're the ones getting the biggest
payments. The most senior and famous oncologists are the ones getting the most money. And so I
think it's hard in any system where the people you need on your side to change the system, the
people with the power are the ones benefiting most from the system. Doctors are smart people. We can
all come up with reasons why what we're doing is not bad. And in fact, probably, I believe this
might be true for everybody. We all believe we're all ethical actors. I mean, I don't think anyone
thinks that they are an unethical person. They just feel that they're a product of their circumstances.
And so I think the real way to fix this problem is somebody external to the medical profession has
to come in and do it. I don't think it's ever going to happen from self policing because the
people who are in power are the ones who are getting the most payments. And very likely the
case that there's a reason why they're the ones getting the most payments is because
the industry knows that that's what it takes to keep the system going.
All right. So the second hallmark, second hallmark evidence. Yeah. What does that mean?
Evidence is I describe it as measure what matters and do it fairly. There are a lot of technical
things that I won't get into for this podcast that I talk about in the book. But I guess basically,
evidence is the following that when we give cancer drugs, we care about two things, people living
longer or living better, increased survival or health related quality of life. We have a system
where two thirds of cancer drugs that are being approved. One third, I know they shrink tumors
more than 30% in a fraction of people. The other third, I know they delay tumor growth by 20%. And
then the other third, I know you live longer, live better. That to me is a strange reorientation of
you're spending so much money on costly drugs. Only one third do you measure what actually matters to
people. The other two thirds, you're measuring tumor size on CAT scans. And I'll say one more
thing that I think is interesting here, which is we use this cutoff of tumor shrinkage of 30%.
In writing this book, I spent a lot of time trying to get the bottom of why it is this 30%.
And I found out it goes back to a 1976 paper where this Mayo Clinic doctor got a bunch of marbles and
he put them on a dining table and he rolled out foam rubber. And he got 16 oncologists to come
to his house with calipers and measure the marbles. And he asked, at what size difference
can two doctors reliably tell the marble has gotten bigger or gotten smaller? And the answer
was certain cut point. And that cut point is the same cut point we use today. We use a cut point
to measure tumor shrinkage as a response or not response, because a bunch of men in 1976 measuring
marbles through foam rubber, which was how we measured tumors in the day before imaging,
that's what they could tell apart. So these cutoffs that we have sort of confused as measures
of efficacy, we're really just sort of operational measures to sort of get some interrater reliability
get us to agree. And so the moment you start to know that you realize like, why am I putting so
much stock in drugs with a 10% 20% response rate, I really don't know if the patient lives longer,
lives better. And this cutoff is really arbitrary. So that's what I mean by evidence. Let's measure
more, not always, but more what matters living longer, living better. And what would be the
implications of that? I mean, it basically would imply that two thirds of the treatments out there
go in the waste bin. At least they won't be approved at the same moment in time. So what
might happen is that if you really created a policy where generally the industry is obliged to show
survival or quality of life benefit, a lot of things are going to change in the industry. So one
thing is, they're going to run more trials in patients who have relapsed cancer than trials in
patients with low risk early stage cancers. They're going to go into the last line setting,
because that's where the event rate is highest. They're going to be more selective. I think about
drugs that they deploy, they're not going to deploy drugs that may change tumor scans, they're really
going to try to think about drugs that improve survival or quality of life. So they might be more
picky in which drugs they advance in the process. I think it changes a number of things in the drug
development pipeline. And I guess I kind of talk about that in the book. But to your point, which
is, does it actually change the number of drugs that come to market? I guess I would say that of
those two thirds that just change tumors on scans, maybe some of them actually do help you live
longer and live better. Those are still going to come to the market. But the ones that don't are
going to fall short, they're not going to come to the market. So we'll have probably fewer drugs
come to market. But the drugs we have will probably be better drugs. My friend who posed that
dilemma to me many years ago, he'll probably be more satisfied. All right, what's the third hallmark?
Yeah, the third hallmark is something that we talked a lot about on this podcast is called
relevance. And it basically means that we should do more studies and people that look like average
Americans. And I think we kind of talked about how we're studying populations that don't reflect
what average people have and experience. Why don't we just study average people and let's find out if
the drugs work as we prescribe them. And again, that'll have the same effect, which is it's
effectively going to reduce the success rates, probably due to both decreased tolerability and
actual poor response. Yes, I think that that's the case. Yeah. Okay, the next one is near and dear
to my heart. Affordability. Tell us about that. How did we fix that issue? That's a thorny problem.
We've written a number of review articles that have looked at so many different solutions. I mean,
I can't even get into all the solutions just to put them in a few buckets. They're solutions that
rely on existing legal structures to make progress here. They're solutions that require novel legal
structures. One solution, I think maybe one of the clearest solutions here is that in the US, we have
a system that any time a cancer drug is approved, Medicare, which is perhaps the single largest
payer in this country, Medicare has to pay for the drug and they can't negotiate the price. Not only
that, they have to pay for any drug recommended at a level 2A or higher by a number of guidelines,
like this National Comprehensive Cancer Network, which has got a lot of people writing the guidelines
who are funded by the industry. So I think one way we could kind of make some headway in the
affordability is to give Medicare the ability to decline to pay for drugs. Many years ago,
a couple of states went to SEMA Verma and colleagues at HHS and they said,
let us at least experiment. States are the laboratory of experiment. Let us say Massachusetts
doesn't have to cover all these drugs for Medicaid, but they were denied the ability to experiment
at a state level. I think we should encourage state level experimentation and how to bring
down drug prices. And there are a number of other things that are really sort of technical solutions.
But I guess what I think is important here is just the recognition that a drug that you cannot
actually get in the hands of somebody is no better than no drug at all. And we have
affordability crisis in this country, but globally, we have a huge affordability crisis. These drugs,
for the most part, are out of reach of billions and billions of people in this world.
And so it's one thing to live in 2020 when you have access to the greatest medicines.
It's really sad, I think, when there are some drugs that are transformative and the best centers
globally just really do not have access. And in the book, I give an example of Trasetuzumab,
a drug developed in the late 1990s for a certain type of breast cancer that is really
a terrific drug. But in a study that came out of India just five years ago, only one in a hundred
people who could have gotten that drug got that drug. And this is at a referral center in sort of
one of the biggest cities in the country, at a really sort of premier center. And it's still
so difficult out of reach of so many people globally. I think that's a real tragedy.
Do we have a sense of, on average, how much more a drug cost in the United States than,
say, in Europe or Asia? Yeah, I mean, I guess, I mean, a couple of figures are, of course,
of the pharmaceutical space, about 50% of spending in the US comes from the US, even though we account
for maybe 4% of the world's population. And how much of that do we know if it's volume versus price?
Like, obviously, there's an accessibility issue, which says in the United States, you're going to,
on a per capita basis, more people are going to receive the drug as well. It just seems like,
as a casual observer of oncology, that basically the United States kind of has a sort of tacit
quid pro quo with pharma, which is here's the deal. Do the lion's share of the R&D inside the United
States? Let us have first access to the drugs. We're going to subsidize the cost for the rest
of the world. Directionally, that seems to me what's happening. Is that about accurate?
That is a fair summary of the lay of the land. I guess I say a couple things. I mean, one of the
points you made earlier was what about the price versus volume? I mean, I think one helpful
comparison would be like two nations with comparable GDP, US and Norway, and we pay roughly
double what Norway pays for cancer drugs. The other thing I would say about subsidization is,
I think people like me who are reformers, I guess the real question I have in my mind is,
why do we subsidize marginal drugs the same way we subsidize transformative drugs? I think that's
the kind of crux of the space. You named a couple of drugs Avastin. This is a drug that has multiple
approvals in many different tumor types. It doesn't cure a single person. Immediate survival about one
to two months, a tremendous price. Global lifetime earnings of that drug are close to $100 billion.
I mean, that is a massive global lifetime earnings drug. You get another drug, Gleevec, it doesn't
cure everybody, but for the cancers, it works and it works rather dramatically. Massive transformational
benefit. And I don't know off the top of my head, lifetime earnings, but it's still in the several
billions and billions of dollars. And then you get drugs that are really marginal toxic drugs that
don't do that much and still can accrue billions of dollars. I guess what I want to say is that
one of the ways in which I think we can correct the market here is if we just incentivize the
drugs we want, which are drugs that have bigger benefits, more substantive benefits. And if we
didn't pay so much for those drugs that really don't add a lot, don't cure people and just prolong
survival very modestly in very select cohorts. So I guess I'm not opposed to paying for things
that really do work. I guess I'm opposed to paying for things that we don't know work,
that have a lot of uncertainty or that we know don't work. I think that's more what my criticism
is. Yeah. And it's funny, I find myself struggling with this one a lot because on the one hand,
I really do agree that pharma needs to be incentivized to innovate and the cost of
innovation is staggering. Now that said, I also think pharma grossly overstates the risk they're
taking. I mean, they've basically outsourced research to biotech. So if you really want to
think about it, drug discovery is now a venture capital problem, which means it's a private
citizen funded risk. So private citizens and pensions basically fund VCs that take the risk
to take biotech from IND to phase one to phase two. Pharma then says, okay, this is de-risked
enough. I'll come in and on my balance sheet, I can do phase three. So their success rate has gone
way up. That seems to be a pretty efficient model, I guess. I think pharma has basically decided we
don't want to own all of those risks. We don't want to own technical and market risk all the way
through. But the flip side of that is do we really want CMS and you'll have to forgive my
skepticism, but I don't know that I trust CMS to be the one negotiating price because what's the
knockoff effect of that going to be in terms of incentivizing pharma? Even though I agree,
CMS shouldn't have to pay sticker price. Like I guess this is why I'm so glad I don't do what you
do because these are some of the hardest decisions one has to think through. If you're trying to do
this through the lens of what is a policy, what is a logical and reasonable and fair policy around
the incentives, it seems obscene that CMS doesn't have the ability to negotiate. But at the same
time, I don't know that I want anybody in the US government making a decision when it comes to
healthcare because I've stopped trusting these entities. Just using Congress as an example,
right? I mean, we've got what, 550, 600 people make up the US Congress. Like two of these people
have a degree in science. Oh, yes, it's tragic. They're just not a group of people I want ever
making scientific decisions. Same for the Supreme Court. Yeah. Yeah, yeah, exactly. So how do we
think about balancing that? Is your solution of let the states do it better where there's less
collateral damage? But I can also think of ways that that goes sideways also. Yeah, I mean, I
guess I would say that, I mean, one thing to acknowledge is that no one has solved the problem.
So the problem remains unsolved. I guess the next thing I would say along these lines is that
having a CMS the way we have a CMS, it is a certain type of incentive. It's a very interesting
incentive. The incentive is basically we will pay for any drug that gets FDA approval, whatever you
charge. So companies will always keep cranking it up as much as they can. And some of the things
about how they crank it up, they'll crank it up in lockstep. So they'll all move together upward,
they won't go too much, nobody will be an outlier because then you're going to be on 60 minutes,
and that's no good for your brand. So you want to go up together slowly, but you can keep cranking
it up. You can do a 9% year over year over year over year and when the frog doesn't jump out of
the pot when the water is boiled slowly. So that's one, two, then the next thing they build into CMS
is once the drug is approved for one use, we're going to let CMS pay for the drug for any other
use if these expert doctors believe it should be used in that way. And we're going to detail those
expert doctors and give them a lot of money and make them come on our side and they're going to
see things from our point of view. So we're going to get all that market share that way too. And
sometimes that market share can be even more lucrative than the initial approval market share.
So I guess what I think this creates in the system is an incentive, a powerful incentive that
the hurdle for a drug is drug approval. You can charge whatever you want. You really don't have to
look too deep into like what it costs you to make the drug or what the benefit of the drug is. You
can charge what you want as long as you're not too much of an outlier, you're not going to stick out
too much. We had that drug, the CAR T cells, they cost $300,000, $400,000, but then they'll rationalize
and say, well, it's a one-time dose. It's not every month after month and those other drugs,
they cost $200,000 a year anyway. Well, of course, that's how you got us to where we are.
So I guess what I would say about CMS negotiating is I guess I think I want to say that not
negotiating is a decision of sorts. It's a decision to just really put a lot of incentive here
without any sort of care as to what you're incentivizing. You're incentivizing an approval.
The next piece of that puzzle is, well, how are they approving drugs? And I think many of us who
look at the FDA approval process will see that the bar for approval is getting lower and lower.
Used to be able to trip on it. Now I think you can probably go over right over it,
but it's getting lower and lower. I mean, the number of patients for approval not having a
control arm. There's a drug which I always forget the name. It's a drug that lowers the rate of a
blood protein, but almost everybody who takes the drug suffers ocular impairment and some people
suffer severe ocular impairment. So there's a lot of blindness going on or pre-blindness like
conditions, but I don't know if people live longer. I don't know if they live better. I know they have
to see the ophthalmologist a lot that adds more healthcare costs. Costs a ton. Why is this approved?
I mean, why can't we wait for a little bit better data? So I think that's part of the puzzle. I think
that among the many ideas out there, one idea is sort of the value-based pricing model, which a
number of sort of commenters have kind of developed, which is this idea that we should pay more for
drugs that provide us more value, that have more incremental survival benefits than drugs that are
more modest or mediocre. And I think if there's some way in the system to build in greater
incentive for the drugs we want, well then that would be good. It would have a lot of good
secondary effects. But I agree with you that all policy, it's so hard because there's always
unintended consequences and people will always sort of find paths of least resistance you couldn't
foresee. The reason I do like state-level expansions, state-level initiatives, is that to some degree,
good policy is experimentation. You experiment, you see what happens, you course correct. You run
experiments in parallel, you see what works, you adopt that broadly. I think you do need
experimentation in the policy space. And in medicine, we've suffered because we have not
done enough of it in the long run. Now, if CMS makes up, I don't know, I have no idea what it
is today, but let's just say it's 25 to 35% of the payer in the world in the United States, right? So
25 to 35% of all insurance is CMS. What about the private payers? Why have they not banded together
and say, well, there's no law that's preventing us from negotiating with these clowns. We're going
to do it. Now, I know that part of it, of course, is that the majority of their business is probably
ASO. So they're not on the hook for risk. They don't care. I mean, they're basically administering
a service and it's the employer that's doing so. Is that why? Is it just, is there's no one big
enough to negotiate? Clearly, CMS is bigger than any one entity. Yeah, I think there's probably
a couple of reasons why we haven't seen more activity from private payers. One is that if
they don't cover what CMS covers, I think they will look bad and they can easily be on the nightly
news where you'll find a cancer patient who's angry that they didn't get some drug or the other,
and that's not good for your brand. That's not good for your reputation. And there have been some
high profile situations in the last 30 years where people went on the news and I think insurers,
they may not want to take that risk. And the next thing is some of these drugs may cost a lot,
but the budgetary impact might be a little bit lower to the insurer because it's a small
population. So in those cases, it might be cheaper for them just to pay for the drug than it is to
deal with the pushback from not paying for it. I think the worst thing is that the insurers
may have a different incentive altogether. What do I mean? One of the provisions of the Affordable
Care Act was to cap the amount of profit that could come off revenue through an insurance
company, 20% profit on revenue, the medical loss ratio, the MLR. The moment that that is inserted
into a system, it's a really unique incentive. The insurance industry, now they're being told that
no matter what, you can never earn more than 20% profit on revenue. That's the most profit you can
earn. That's a law. So if I tell you you're really hungry and you can only eat 20% of the pizza,
what size pizza should I order? The answer is going to be extra large. So what I think has
happened in the insurance industry is that although we hear a lot about insurers who
have preauthorization requests and all these things that are a pain in the ass for doctors
and doctors hate, although we hear a lot about insurers pushing back on this or that,
I think they do that for a couple of reasons. One, that the insurer's incentive is to make sure
year-to-year variability of costs is predictable and that they can model that out and make sure
their premiums go where they need them to go to ensure their profit revenues. They're really
nervous about year-to-year variability and that's why hep C drugs come along and they can blow the
whole model because the population is massive. But I think the insurers in the long run keeping
costs down, I think that they may not have enough skin in the game. They don't have enough skin in
the game to keep costs down. So they really don't care. And so I think the narrative is of course
that insurers are the downward force, but I don't think they're the downward force that we think
they are. I agree with you and I think it's the employer that has the most skin in the game,
but the problem is they're so disaggregated and so spread out that they can't speak in a unified
way and they can't fight in a unified way. But if you were to look at the sort of my, this is a loose
way to think about it, but let's just call it a handful of buckets of insured, Medicare, Medicaid,
private insurance that is administered only through the insurance company. So the ASO employer-based
versus the insurer-based insurer, private insurer, I think the biggest one has to be the employer.
And even if it's not, it's the one that would have the most sway. But yeah, it's like how does this
company of 300 people band together with this company of a thousand people and that company,
which again, I think speaks to the pain of all of this. One last thought on this space is there's
also a tragedy to the commons problem. Many years ago when autologous stem cell transplant for breast
cancer gained popularity, there were a couple of insurers that did pay for some of the clinical
trials that ultimately debunked that procedure. But now one of the risks is, let's say there's
some new drug out there and a lot of people say like, this is not, doesn't work so well,
this trial is really contrived and insurer could come along and they could do the right study.
They could really test how it works in a different population. They could fund such a study. The
moment they fund that study, that information is generated while all their competitors will get
access to that information. So there's a bit of that challenge as well. But yeah, I mean,
I think you're asking terrific questions about this space. So let's get back to Hallmarks. Number
five is possibility. What does that mean? I guess I call it the preclinical pipeline must be expanded
possibility. So I guess I would say we spent a lot of time talking about drug development from the
point of view of the fledgling biotech to the pharmaceutical industry. One of the things that
a part of drug development that gets forgotten about a little bit is the role of the NIH,
of course, in funding basic science. And the NIH, to some degree, does shoulder some risk in this
space. They fund a lot of sort of science for science sake, identifying novel targets that are
ultimately some of which are clinically exploited. I guess I would say that although it feels like
we spend a lot of money on the NIH, $30 billion or so per year, I think it's not nearly enough
that science is like the greatest thing that people have ever done. And if I were in charge
of anything, I would crank up the funding for science because I think science is possibility.
And that's what I mean by this possibility. We need to increase the funding for science.
We should increase it slowly and steadily. I think there are problems that happen when you
give a lot more money to people who are not used to getting that. I think there's a lot more waste.
But if you slowly grow something, we need to kind of separate science funding from political
cycles. It shouldn't be that just because the red team or the blue team is in power that science
funding is on the chopping block or getting more. We need some sort of stability for science funding.
Science needs slow, steady growth. And then the last thing I kind of talk a lot about in this is,
how do you give out the money? It's fascinating to me. We've been giving out billions of dollars in
research funding. We've never really studied how you give out the money. If you look at the way the
money is given, it's really kind of lopsided. There are a few people who get a lot of funding.
Their labs are flush with money. Some of their labs are so big. One wonders if the boss ever
meets all the people who work in the lab. There are hundreds of people who work in the lab.
They're really like financial operations run by a financial manager who's the boss and then some
scientists underneath it. And there are a lot of people on the other end of the spectrum whose labs
struggle to get money, even basic funding. And so I guess in this kind of section of the book,
I kind of explore, are there ways we can kind of bring some experiments to giving out money,
do some small, simple randomized control trial studies, follow people and look to see measures
of equity, of who gets the money, measures of research satisfaction, burnout, measures of
how translation occurs, some kind of controlled studies in grant giving. And then the last thing
I just say is blue sky science. So there's this branch of science typically called blue sky
science, where it's just science for science sake. You don't come to me and say, I want to do this
experiment because I'm going to cure melanoma. You come to me and you say, I just want to know
how the cell does this. I just want to know why does this happen? And that type of science,
that type of inquiry that we all have as I think kids and high school kids, that inquiry is really,
really difficult when you are an academic doctor because there's not a lot of money unless you
make promises, I'm going to cure this disease, I'm going to cure that. If you want to say,
I just want to understand how this works, it's really hard to get funding. And I think it should
be the other way around. Some of the greatest advances in science were people who pursued things
purely because that interested them and the finding and the translation was serendipitous.
And so I think that's what I mean by possibility. I couldn't agree with you more on this. I have
many friends who sit on study sections in NIH, which means they're basically the people that
watch how NIH gives money. And their biggest complaint is, look, we are really not permitted
to take big risks here. I mean, we are very incremental in how we fund because we are on
a funding cycle. They cannot fund pie in the sky, blue sky, really, really fundamental basic
questions. Because when I go back to Congress in two years and say, I need this much money,
the answer better be because I did X, Y, and Z with this. And I've seen some of this firsthand.
And again, I understand it. I mean, we don't want resources to be wasted. So it almost suggests
you want to have two arms. That would be my take. You want to have two funding arms. You want to
have the translational funding arm that is meant to be incremental, that is meant to look at basic
science and ask, is this ready to go to the next step? Is this ready to be taken to a clinical
pathway? If so, are you leaping too much? Are you not leaping enough? And then I think you have to
have a totally separate group that is responsible for funding a totally different type of science,
which is all about basic inquiry and the advancement of natural knowledge, regardless of where it takes
us. Because as you pointed out in the book, actually, there are lots of examples of some of
the most exciting discoveries in the history of the last 400 years, which is effectively the era
of modern science that came from nothing other than pure inquiry. I think that's well said. It's
a very thoughtful way to look at the problem. One of the people that you cited, Jim Allison, whose
work ultimately led to a blockbuster class of drugs, an immunotherapy doctor, it wasn't that long
ago when people, I remember people made jokes that that line of inquiry was foolish and misguided,
and that was never going to succeed. Lo and behold, it turned out to be sort of a Nobel prize-winning
discovery. So I think you're right. Yeah, that's the right way to think about it. So the final
hallmark is agenda. What do you mean by that? Agenda is something that there have been a number
of researchers, including people who work with me and myself, who have gotten interested in the last
couple of years, which is what happens when you take a 30,000 foot view of cancer and look at the
clinical trials agenda. And it's very interesting that some spaces in cancer medicine, you got the
same drug or similar drugs, 20 such drugs, Coke, Pepsi, and 18 other Cokes and Pepsis. And people
are running redundant and duplicative trials. They're all testing them in the same tumors,
in the same setting, with the same old controls. Sometimes they're running many different clinical
trials with drugs that have low promise. And one of the observations that we make is, well, boy,
by chance alone, aren't some of these trials going to be positive? I mean, we're not using a very
stringent nominal cutoff for significance, we're using a P of 0.05 usually, some are going to be
positive by chance alone. How do you account for that? How do you account for this duplication?
Who's keeping track? It's like you need a Bonferroni correction factor for the number of trials as
opposed to the number of looks, right? Absolutely. In fact, we did a paper where we corrected one with
a Bonferroni. We got a lot of pushback from those peer reviewers. It's a totally novel
application of how you would use a Bonferroni correction factor. But you instantly see what
I'm getting at, which is that within a study, if you do a lot of comparisons, you take into account
the number of comparisons to some degree. We can debate what statistical procedure to use, but we
do take into account that we're looking at this data many times so we could fool ourselves. But
when you're running many, many studies, shouldn't you also do the same? It's a philosophical question,
it's not really a statistical question. And the answer, I believe, is yes. So that's what we talk
about in this section in agenda. We talk about what does it mean to take that into account. And also,
we forget sometimes that the most critical resource in cancer medicine are the patients
themselves, their scarce resource. In some tumor types, there are now more trials ongoing than
there are even people with that condition, which may sound ridiculous, but it's because everybody
chases the ball. Somebody recently told me this great story about it's like three-year-olds and
five-year-olds playing soccer. They all run after the ball, nobody plays positions. And that's what
happens sometimes with the pharmaceutical industry. They're all running after the ball, they're all
running duplicative trials. They're not enough patients with this condition anymore. We're
depleting that resource. And what do we have to show for it? And how do we interpret those studies?
So I think that's what we talk about, which is that somebody has to think about the big picture,
or at least we have to look at it and be recognized what the agenda look like across the entire field.
So coming back to oncology, is there a role anywhere for tumor genome sequencing? There
are many companies that do this commercially. If there's one email or call I hate getting,
and unfortunately, I get it every two weeks, it's the friend of the friend or the friend of the
family, the patient's cousin, whatever, that has just been diagnosed with essentially an
uncurable cancer. They're basically saying, Peter, what advice do you have? And it's always
heartbreaking because I don't have any. It's by definition, if I'm getting that call, it's because
their oncologist has already said there is nothing to do here. These calls go in many different ways.
I just had one a week ago, they were asking about some supplement. And generally, when I get asked,
when I go down the path of, well, this person has this hyperbaric oxygen protocol with this supplement
protocol with this, this thing and the other, the first thing I like to inquire about is the cost.
My view on this, which may differ from yours is, first, we don't want to increase the harm of this
person. I don't think there's anything wrong with hope. I think there's a lot of things we don't
know if they work or don't work. But I'm certainly pretty squirrely when someone's offering a panacea
treatment for $20,000 of vitamin C, rubbing garlic on your testicles or whatever the concoction is.
So we go down that whole path, which is, is there anything out there that's in the quote unquote
holistic world that's going to work? Another thing that tends to come up is, is there a role for tumor
genome sequencing? And I've certainly had within my own family and that of friends, sent people to
foundation medicine. Truthfully, I haven't really had anything come out of it that's been a game
changer. Probably the only time in my life with this experience that I've gotten kind of lucky was
a friend that had pancreatic cancer. I mean, this was several years ago, but he had Lynch. And I had
just remembered reading a paper about how patients with Lynch were more likely to have
checkpoint mutations. This was prior to the approval of chitruta, but it was in trials. And so
we're able to get him into a trial of chitruta. And he turned out to be a remarkable responder.
And to this day, he went from unresectable to cancer free, which he remains about a decade
later or nearly a decade later. Long-winded preamble, talk to me about your view on tumor
sequencing, off-label drug use, targeting therapies, that sort of thing. Just to allude to
the other part of what you were saying that I thought was really right, which is, I think we
probably share the same philosophy, which is that often people come to me and they talk about some
alternative or complementary approach that they want to bring into their care. And my view is
probably maybe not dissimilar from yours, which is as long as it's not too costly, as long as it
doesn't have an opportunity cost to interfere with what we're wanting to do. It's not a hill I want to
die on because I think people should be allowed to pursue those things. And I do think that one of
the problems I get a little irritated by is there are people who want to die on that hill and really
draw a line in the sand. And I think you can poison a relationship with somebody and it's not worth
it. I mean, at the end of the day, if it doesn't cost too much, it's not really too harmful. And
somebody really is motivated to do it. And it's not going to interfere with what you want to do.
Have at it. And just the humility of like, what do we know? We have to be clear here. Like we don't
know a lot of stuff. Right. And by the way, it's not like we have a track record that says we're
winners. Right. I mean, I think that all goes into it. And that's also why I think that's all a part
of it. Yeah, right. And then to come to your NGS question, I guess I would say next generation
sequencing tumor genomics, I guess right off the bat, there are definitely some people who definitely
need to be tested for some mutations. So let's just talk about the ones that definitely need to
happen. You mentioned lung cancer. It's a no brainer. Right. Lung cancer, there are at least
six or seven mutations that we now have FDA approved therapies for. Definitely. There are
different ways you could test for the same mutations, but that's another thing to keep in
mind. But you need to know about EGFR. You need to know about elk, particularly if the person is
a younger person, non-smoker melanoma, you need to know about BRAF colon cancer, you need to know
about MSI high status. So there's a number of things we have approved drugs and we published
some papers, there's maybe 20 or 30 things and a good oncologist usually knows the mutations for
the tumor. The next thing is now we do have an approval for microsatellite instability high,
which is probably like your patient with the Lynch syndrome pancreas cancer, no matter what
tumor type, you know, that's something that we have an approved drug, very reasonable to test for.
Then I think the next way that NGS can be used is exactly as you used it. I'm a huge supporter of,
which is that you're using NGS to pair your patient with a clinical trial. I think that's a
perfectly acceptable way to use NGS to run a broad NGS panel. And if you find a trial that fits,
have edit. The next part about it, I think is tricky, which is that the part that I think that
I kind of have the most friction with some of my colleagues is after having done all these things,
you've looked at mutations, we have approved drugs, you've tried to find somebody trial.
Sometimes you do NGS on a patient and there is a mutation that is seductive. It looks like you have
a drug for it. There's no trial available. And you also have a standard drug that we normally give.
And in these situations, it is so seductive to believe that because we found the mutation and
the target, it's better to use the targeted drug than that older drug that may have a longer track
record. And I think that's where people get into a bit of trouble that sometimes you actually end up
eroding outcomes, not enhancing outcomes. You actually make worse choices in those cases,
because the truth is that some genomic mutations are mutations that are fueling the tumor. And that
if you fix those mutations, you would improve the outcomes. But some mutations are the product of a
genome that is undergoing massive instability and damage. Some of these tumors, when you look at the
sequence, it's like a dinner plate that's been dropped on the floor. It's in shards, it's broken
all over the place. You may find that for one of those two shards, you can put a little piece of
tape on it, but are you really going to help the whole person? And there are some studies that show
sometimes if you take biopsies from a bunch of different sites and you sequence them, you don't
even have the same mutations in different sites. And one study shows that if you sequence this part
of the body, different parts of the tumor, the tumor has spread to, let's say, the lung and the
liver. If you looked at the liver, you might give drug A. If you looked at the lung, you might give
drug B. That's not a very precise therapy. And then the other thing that's a complexity is some
researchers have sent the exact same tumor to a couple of different companies and they haven't
always gotten the same result. That also makes one a little concerned. So I guess I would say
approved drugs, this sort of very common mutations, all good doctors are going to test for,
to pair somebody with a trial as you did your friend, that's really terrific. I think particularly
people who suffer from rarer tumor types at younger ages, they should also keep an eye out
for fusion events. Those are really important to know about. They're often, there are a lot of
researchers who are interested in studying that there's some trials that's lone-kettering.
The place I think maybe you don't always have to do it is for somebody who is not doing well and
they have progressed through many lines of therapy and they have a tumor that we just don't have a
lot of mutations that we know a lot about. I mean, I don't think it's obligatory. And if you do find
something, I think sometimes you got to be careful that you don't just gravitate to what is a key in
a lock, what sounds like a key in a lock, but it may be sort of taking you away from something that
has a better track record. That has to be literally one of the most elegant and brief descriptions of
the pros and cons of that type of approach. So I'm glad I asked that question because I could have
spent two hours and said less. Are you bullish or bearish on liquid biopsies? You indirectly
alluded to it, which is, look, with leukemia, we're basically doing a liquid biopsy. Correct.
So now the question is when we, a year from now, presumably have at least phase two data on
liquid biopsies for solid organ tumors and lymphomas, are you optimistic and how do you
see that changing the way we practice potentially? I guess I'd say the interesting thing about
leukemia is it was very likely one of the first things we studied in part because we can access
it so frequently and so readily and we can actually track its volume in an era where
the doctors had to measure marbles through foam rubber with their calipers. And so that's why
leukemia has always sort of been a couple of steps ahead of everything else.
About liquid biopsies, I guess I would say that, you know, we do have a number of approved liquid
biopsy tests and they're certainly going to have a role. Anytime we've already conceded that there
are some mutations that are very important in certain tumors and we have drugs for those
mutations, if you can find out that mutational information without having to stick a needle in
someone, everyone is going to be grateful for that. I guess the questions that are always going to be
kind of, and they vary probably test by test, mutation by mutation is, is the test sensitive
enough in this case? If you find you don't have the mutation on the liquid test, are you still
going to want to go get tumor tissue or do you need to get tumor tissue for another reason to
figure out the subtype? And in that case, you might as well, you already have the information
you need. The real role for liquid biopsy might be the serial nature of it. You can track something
over time, see how it's doing over time. And that might be the real boon. But I guess I would say,
am I bullish about it? I'd say yes. I mean, I'm not known for being a bullish person, but I guess
I would say that's something that I would definitely study more and do sort of really
good clinical trials at the end of the day to see what the role can be. But yeah, they're already
in our clinics. We use them. Yeah. You've talked about this indirectly that, I mean, look, you're
naturally a skeptic, you're naturally critical. Those are very valuable tools. They've served you
well. And more importantly, they've served many people well, meaning your skepticism and your
critical thought has sort of made medicine better. How do we, or maybe I'll ask it more directly,
how do you navigate that balance? There are some people that are skeptical for the sake of being
skeptical. They're always the contrarian. No matter what the answer is, they're always going to take
the opposite side of that. How do you sort of, police is the wrong word, but how do you navigate
that internally? I guess I would say, I mean, there is an example of something where I was not
on the side, I'm usually odd and people gave me a hard time about, which was the dexamethasone in
COVID, the recovery study very recently. So I mean, let me just put it in a context. One of the
things that happens a lot in medicine these days is medicine by press release, which is one day,
Eli Lilly announces top line results are positive for this trial and this drug,
improved outcomes in these people. And this is the hazard ratio 0.7. But how long did they live?
Did it have side effects? None of that's in the press release. You know, it's just sort of a
fragment of information. And I think they put that out primarily for the shareholders and for
their information. And some doctors may act upon that. I mean, that might be something
that people find enough to act upon. And I'm always a big critic of that and say, let's wait
for the paper. Let's wait for more information. Recently, there was a recovery trial out of the
UK. And they say that dexamethasone for people who are hospitalized requiring O2 with SATH less
than 94 people who are mechanically ventilated, that they benefit from dexamethasone, all cause
mortality benefit. Whereas people who are hospitalized did not require supplemental O2.
They actually maybe they didn't benefit. They were harmed. And there's a significant interaction
coefficient. They put out that press release. And I went online and I looked and I'm like,
oh boy, you can read their protocol. Their protocol was published a month ago. It's available.
It's 35 pages. You can read it and you can read the statistical analysis plan that's also out
there. It tells you exactly what they were going to do, what the pre-specified endpoints are.
And we're in the midst of a pandemic where people have been trying things left, right,
and center, throwing the kitchen sink at people with COVID. And so I said, the evidence is good
enough. We got to do this right now. We got the press release. We got, you know, I like to say a
press release and a protocol. That's like a driver's license and a social security card and a paper.
That's like a passport. Do I have to show you my passport? I can show you the other two. It's
another form of identification. Okay. So anyway, so I say this and I got a lot of heat from the
usual critical club because they said, well, we got to wait for the paper. And I say there's such
a thing as too much skepticism. And that's what I think is a good example. I guess I would say that
probably the greatest way in which I can't even claim that I'm on the set point on the thermostat,
but I can say the only way to kind of keep this in balance between skepticism that's so bad that
it's paralyzing, you can't do anything, and blind acceptance that's so bad that you are cheerleader
for everything. The way to keep that in balance is I find going into the clinic because no matter
how skeptical you are about drugs, you have to have those conversations with real people. And
there's some people who are going to be taking drugs that you're skeptical of. And maybe I should
just make a point about what I think my clinical philosophy is. Some people sometimes ask me.
It's not the doctor's role to determine what treatment is right for someone. It's really the
doctor's role in my mind to empower the patient with what I know about the drug, what's been shown,
what hasn't been shown, what the benefit might be, what are the uncertainties, what are the known
toxicities and risks, and then to walk them through how they would decide. Is it worth it
to them to take those risks? And different people will choose differently. Some people will choose
differently than what I would choose for myself. Some people will choose differently than the next
person with the same information. I think those are all okay. The more you practice medicine,
the more you realize that this is an art. You're never going to have perfect information. You're
going to have to make decisions today with less than perfect information. And I think that's a way
that one keeps skepticism in check. I actually think this is one of the biggest challenges in this
art slash science of medicine. This is very different from experimental physics, where we
could all hang around a particle collider and debate the experimental results all day long
and red team, blue team. I mean, it is really different. And I struggle with this
so much. And I think you said it exactly correctly with respect to that thermostat is if you're too
much of a skeptic, you're not doing anything. You're going to sit on your hands forever. And
there's a cost of doing nothing. And that should never be forgotten. And if you blindly accept
everything, you are almost unquestionably subjecting patients to unnecessary treatments.
I feel lucky, right? Because I have two full time colleagues in my practice,
and then two part time colleagues. So there's a group of five of us basically can argue with
each other all day. But we never lose sight of the fact that it's not an intellectual pursuit.
At the end, a decision needs to be made, even if a decision is to do nothing. That's still a
decision. And I love that I actually find that to be some of the most enjoyable stuff we do is just
the debate. That's another nice thing that you brought out, which is that's another way to keep
skepticism in check is you go to a tumor board or you go to a multidisciplinary meeting, or you
sit around the table with a few of your colleagues and you present some cases. And you hear what
other people have to say at the end of the day that something's got to be done. They're either
going to do it or they're not going to do it. And sometimes it is important to know that people do
things differently than we might do it. And I think it keeps us in sort of a balance.
This was a fascinating discussion. Yeah, there's a lot of other things that we could talk about
here. But I also am wary of the fact that in the COVID environment, people have less and less
time for podcasts. So the longer this podcast goes on, the lower the probability people are
going to listen to it. And I want to make sure people hear this one. So I wish you the best
as you continue with your move into San Francisco. I'm sure we will speak again.
Thanks so much, Peter. Thanks for having me. It's a terrific discussion and great to chat with you
on these topics. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple
Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining
medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of
their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest
very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.