Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Dr. James O'Keefe. James is a cardiologist and medical
director of the Charles and Barbara Duboque Cardio Health and Wellness Center at St. Luke's
Mid-American Heart Institute, an enormous practice of more than 60 cardiologists in the middle of
this lovely country. He is also a professor of medicine at the University of Missouri,
Kansas City. James has authored best selling cardiovascular books for health professionals,
including The Complete Guide to EKGs, Dyslipidemia Essentials, and Diabetes Essentials. James
has also co-authored with his wife, Joan, the best selling consumer health book, The Forever
Young Diet and Lifestyle. He is actively involved in patient care and research and has published
numerous peer reviewed articles, which honestly, I feel like I'm reading at least one every couple
of weeks. I came across James for the first time about nine or 10 years ago when I heard him speak
at a conference and frankly, what he had to talk about just threw me back on my heels. And since
that time, of course, we've become friends and James is in many ways a mentor to me with all
things that pertain to preventative cardiology. In this episode, we talk about a lot of things,
starting with his background and how he made the pivot from going into interventional cardiology
to now this much broader area of preventative cardiology. We get into some really detailed,
but very accessible physiology of what the heart does, how it works, and therefore how it's
susceptible to disease. And then we kind of launch into some of the things I wanted to get to. I
wanted to talk about the impact of exercise on the heart, both positive and negative. We go into
that in exceptional detail. We get into the role of nutrition and specific nutrients such as sodium,
magnesium, et cetera. And then we round the discussion out with a sort of tour de force
discussion of many of the pharmacologic agents that some of you have probably heard of. And
frankly, even this discussion taught me quite a bit and actually invigorated my knowledge for
this space. So I always enjoy talking with James and I suspect you will all enjoy this episode very
much. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Dr. James O'Keefe.
James, thanks so much for sitting down with me today, albeit not in the same physical location,
which is always a shame. The last time we were in the same location, you swung by my office in
New York, I remember. It was probably about three years ago and you were kind enough to bring a
recent manuscript you just published about the impact of exercise on heart disease. And we had
a lovely discussion. I don't think we had the time for a meal that day because it was an impromptu
visit, but I never imagined it would be almost three years before we'd be doing our podcast,
which is something that from the moment I started a podcast, I knew I wanted to sit down and talk
with you. You're also just an incredibly gracious guy who's always sending me stuff. And so I consider
you one of those people in as my sort of constant educators. So this is going to be an exciting
episode because I'm going to be learning a lot. And I know that anybody who cares about heart
disease is going to be learning a lot. And I don't know how you cannot care about heart disease if
you care about longevity. Yeah, it's the heart of the matter for sure. And yeah, I think we
all instinctively understand how important the heart is to our health. And I might say in the
spirit of educating each other, I love your podcast. I think it is easily my favorite podcast. I love
the way you dig down into the science and really get to the heart of the matter without overhyping
things. And I just think you're doing a wonderful public service for improving the health of the
population. And the other thing I'm really impressed at because a lot of my fellows and
residents and kids will talk to me about what they heard on Peter Attia. So your audience is
a particularly, if I might say, tuned in intelligentsia, interested in health and
well-being. And I think you have a really curated, remarkable audience.
Thank you for that. You and I first met probably 11 years ago, I think. I heard you speaking at a
conference and it kind of blew my mind. You won't remember this because it's obviously a topic you've
been speaking about a lot. But as the listener, when it's the first time I heard about it, it was
kind of a gut punch. So it was probably 2011. And at that time I was still a wannabe professional
athlete. So even though I was into my late 30s, I still pretended that I was a professional
something or other swimmer, cyclist, incredibly high volumes of training, incredible intensity
of training. I actually did the math for somebody yesterday. And I think I was probably on my bike
at least, I don't know, 20 to 23 hours a week with a third of that being at or above threshold.
And you presented data basically suggesting that that was harmful potentially. And then I may have
actually gone too far and I may have actually set myself up for cardiac injury later in life.
So with that as a teaser, I now want to take a step way back and talk about your journey to
that among many other topics that interest you. You trained as a cardiologist and just for people
who don't understand what that means, that means after medical school you went and did internal
medicine and after internal medicine, you then train in cardiology. And then you went one step
further and said, look, I want to do interventional cardiology. Can you tell people what
interventional cardiology is? Yeah. So that's using procedures to fix the heart, whether it's
putting stents in the corner arteries or putting in pacemakers. These days it's expanded to fixing
the valves. The technology is just absolutely spectacular these days. We can put in valves.
It's become our default way of replacing a valve now is through the artery. So it's a really cool
field. At the time I went, I trained at the Mayo Clinic for internal medicine and cardiology,
and then went down to Kansas City at the Mid-American Heart Institute in 1988 to work
with Jeffrey Hartzler, who was the world's expert in interventional cardiology. He invented
infarct angioplasty, that is somebody who's having a heart attack. He had the sort of huts to go in,
do an angiogram, figure out which vessel was blocked, open it up with a balloon,
and suddenly the pain goes away. At the time it was radical. This is 1980, and he took a lot of
heat for that nationally at the meetings. But it turned out to be a game-changing therapy,
announced it's the standard across the world for treating angioplasty. So I went there and worked
with him and started off my career. And maybe I'll back up saying, I'm like you. I love exercise.
It's how I calm myself down, turn myself up, whatever. I mean, it's just always, my kids say
it's how I've been self-medicating my hyperactivity all my life. And there's probably some truth to
that. And it turns out that exercise, it's good for ADHD. Never had trouble focusing. But certainly
exercise, since I was a little kid, is just my mother used to, her mantra to us was up in the
prairie up in Northern North Dakota near Canada. She said, you kids, go outside and play. Go to
school. Play with your friends outside. And so that was kind of what I did growing up. And I got
into basketball and running cross-country in high school when I was just fascinated by heart. So I
figured out I wanted to be a cardiologist when I was 13 or 14, just because I was fascinated
with the heart. So back to, you know, through my cardiology training and then doing interventional
cardiology. And I did it for about a year or two. And then I realized, this is back in the night,
then we're only doing balloon angioposties. So we balloon these dialed, you know, dilate these
vessels up in elective people who are having angina. And then they'd be back in six months or
a year with more blockages. And just don't, I mean, this is not the ideal way to treat coronary
disease. This is a systemic disease. It's highly modifiable. We just need to, you know, focus
double down on prevention. And this was just when, you know, prevention was blossoming, you know,
statins came along in 86. And, you know, we're, you know, the beta blockers and now, I mean,
it's discontinued to blossom. So that coronary disease these days, even though it's the leading
killer in America, should be an entirely preventable, medically managed disease. Unless you have an MI,
you don't need to be going in having procedures. Stands in electively, you know, we have the tools.
And so it's also just the more enlightened approach. I mean, it doesn't pay well, you know,
you don't get paid for prevention, but it is the logical way to approach disease, whether you're
a physician, or just a person out there who's trying to live a happy, long, fully functional
life. I mean, you want to be thinking proactively. And it is so effective. We know what works now.
But you know, we just have to kind of get people's attention and get them to change their habits
lots of times. There's a lot in there, James. So let's kind of go back and hash some of it out. So
the first thing you noted was that in its earliest renditions as a specialty, interventional
cardiology basically had one tool, which was balloon angioplasty. And so as you explained,
you're putting a very small catheter. Can you tell somebody how large a coronary artery is just
to give them some scale? So let's take the left main artery coming right off the aorta.
Right before it bifurcates into the LED in the CERC, right at that widow maker location,
which is named appropriately, how many millimeters is that in a normal, healthy 40 or 50 year old?
So that's typically about four millimeters, four or five millimeters in the left main coronary,
you know, so not quite half a centimeter, which is a third of an inch.
Yeah. So we're talking tiny, tiny little, little, little things.
Yeah. It's even smaller than that. It's, it's, it's probably even
because an inch is 25.4 millimeters for context. So it's a four is obviously less than a quarter
of that. You put a little catheter that's obviously smaller than that into said vessel,
and that catheter is complicated enough in that it has a built in balloon that the operator
outside the body can control with a syringe by inflating it or deflating it as needed with saline.
So it's a really brute force method, isn't it? To sort of force open something that's narrowing.
And of course at the time you weren't leaving anything behind. So the best you could do was
get in there, inject saline back and forth, basically use the hydraulic pressure of that
to try to force open what was going on. And then you, you left. Now years later,
obviously interventional cardiologists could leave behind something called stents.
So little flexible metallic things that would spring open and stay open. And then there's been
an entire evolution of that. So folks who are interested, I had a great discussion on this
topic with Ethan Weiss. If you're interested, check that podcast out. I don't recall which
episode number it was, but if you just search Ethan Weiss's name, it'll, it'll come up.
And we go through the history of this a little bit, but more importantly, something you alluded to,
which is kind of what the literature tells us about it, which is outside of a few settings,
one of them being someone who is actively having a heart attack. Even today, it's not clear there's
an overwhelming benefit to putting these stents in people. There's certainly a lot of economic
benefit to certain parties, but there is not an enormous clinical benefit outside of, you know,
acute MI and we can bifurcate into which types of MI, et cetera. But, you know, for someone who
shows up asymptomatically with a blockage, I don't think there's a single shred of benefit unless
something has changed in the literature in the last few months that I was unaware of. Is that still
true? That's absolutely true. We think of this and it's very logical, which is why it's been
one of the many reasons why this has been so difficult to extinguish this flawed paradigm,
that this is a plumbing issue. You have blockages in your arteries. Well, duh, you get rid of the
clock. That's simple. So we've been working on that flawed paradigm for 40 years now. And you're
right, as logical as that is, it doesn't really turn out to be true. If you have an acute coronary
syndrome, but the way to think about atherosclerosis is kind of like the zits we get when we're
teenagers, and we get these pustules filled with oxidized triglycerides and LDL cholesterol,
then then attract the monocytes and the macrophages that elute these inflammatory markers and they
thin out the collagen overlying the zit and it ruptures and, you know, and it drains and heals.
If it's a particularly bad zit, you end up with an acne scar for the rest of your life. That same
thing happens in your arteries underneath the skin of the artery, the inside skin, which is the
endothelium. You form these zits, these pustules filled with nasty gallowish and flame, and these
get hot, they rupture. And instead of just draining, they attract thrombi because they think
there's a rent hole in the vessel. So a thrombus forms, platelets and fibrinogen. And over time,
you know, it heals if you're lucky enough. And mostly, most of the time you are, this happens
time and time again through decades before it gets to the point where one ruptures and then
completely closes it off. But in the meanwhile, every time you get one of those inflamed zits,
the ruptures, you get the growth factor, stimulate the growth of the smooth muscle and the collagen.
And if it's a really bad zit, you know, eventually you'll calcify. And those are
fossil evidence of previous badly inflamed zits, if you will. So this is like really
everyday common stuff, but we know how to prevent it. But going in with a balloon and
addressing one little area, and by the way, tearing it up even worse, it works if you're
having a heart attack. But most of the times we can regress those plaques. We can melt the
inflammation out of there with a lot of things we could talk about diet, lifestyle and exercise,
keeping the lipids down, the triglycerides down. And we can't make the acne scars go away. They're
there forever once you have those calcium deposits. But we can pretty much make the risk
go away. And that's why prevention is just so effective and so instrumental.
Well, again, I think you said a lot there. And I want to go back because first of all,
I love that analogy. I've never thought of using acne as an analogy. And I think that's actually
a more accessible analogy than the ones that I use. So I think with everybody listening to this,
I'm going to declare that I'm going to start plagiarizing that. I hope you don't mind.
What I find interesting, and I think it's important for patients to understand this,
is the complicated biology of both the oxidative piece, the inflammatory piece,
and how they feed off each other. And it is a bit of an irony, isn't it? That the body is actually
trying to repair something. The immune cells, when those monocytes get recruited to the site
of endothelial injury, and obviously when they translocate through the endothelium and become
macrophages and start doing everything that you just described, which leads to this creation of
thrombus, we would normally welcome that response elsewhere in our body. If you were out in the
field and you got cut, that's exactly what you would want to happen. You would want the immune
cells to show up there to make sure there are no bacteria. And then you would want those thromboph
cells to come and prevent you from bleeding. And so the problem is all of that stuff is happening
in an area where you don't have a lot of real estate. You've got a few millimeters, and that's
why it can obviously lead to this enormous problem. The other thing you said that I think is,
it just can't be overstated, is the understanding of what calcification means in that context.
I had a patient I saw this week who, after some hesitation, finally agreed to have a calcium scan.
He had very elevated lipids for a number of years, but they seemed to elevate more in the
previous few years. He had been quite resistant to any medical management of that, and frankly,
his other factors are really good. So this is a guy who eats very well, who exercises very well,
is metabolically very healthy. So when he got the calcium score, you know, it was about 100 and
change, placing him between about the 75th and 90th percentile for age, located in three vessels.
He was visibly alarmed, right? He said, this is really bad. And, you know, the stenoses in each
of these by calcification were, you know, in the ballpark of 30 to 50%. And what I tried, and I
don't know if I explained it successfully enough to him, was, look, the 30 to 50% stenosis you have
in that vessel is not the issue. That's a huge warning sign of what has been going on over the
past decade. It's telling us that now is the time to act and add other agents to our toolkit for how
we're going to prevent myocardial death. The analogy I use is it's like having bars on the window of a
home. You know, it doesn't tell you that there's a break-in that's about to happen. It tells you
that you live in a very bad neighborhood and there's probably a break-in that took place at
some point. Yeah, it's a great way to put it. And also I'm glad that, and I know from our previous
conversations that you're a fan of the calcium score, we call it cardio scan. We charge $50
for it. We use modern CT, high speed CT scans that give these really great pictures of the
coronaries with a minimal dose of radiation. So men over age 40, women over age 60, I call it like
the mammogram for the heart. I mean, everybody should have one really because you can have a lot
of risk factors for like, say lung cancer. You might be a smoker in a family history and this,
that, the next thing. But if we do a scan and see that you're growing a tumor, that's a whole
different deal. And that's the way this is, as you point out, there's a lot of people who have high
cholesterol and high blood pressure, bad family history, just a frightening array of risk factors.
You do a calcium score on them and it's zero. And you say, well, we've gotten through 53 years of
life without making any hard plaque. So we're not going to like, we maybe don't need to use a statin
on you. Maybe we don't, maybe we can tolerate and it seems like you're doing fine. On the other hand,
there's a lot of people who have relatively minor risk factors that are growing plaque. And,
and let's be clear, your coronaries should be soft and supple and smooth like they were,
like when you're a baby, when you're a teenager, there's no calcium in the coronaries normally.
And you see people, I think the record I've seen is 13,500 per calcium score. I mean,
I often show the residents like we put the Houndsfield area of interest over the left main
of the LAD and it'll be 800, 900, then you go to their spine and it's 600, 700, their arteries
are more bony than their bones. That's not a good thing. What is the youngest person,
James, that you've seen a legitimate spec of calcium in? So something that's not an
artifact of a score of one or something, but where there's actual calcification.
Yeah, late teens, but that's really unusual. In the twenties, you start seeing it. And I might say
that family history, when people come in, like the patient you described, they come in and say,
well, why do I have this? I'm doing everything right. They said, well, you probably have a bad
family history, right? Yeah. Yeah. I just said, well, if you weren't doing everything right,
if you were a smoker, you'd probably already have had a heart attack. So some of this is
non-modifiable, but more and more, I mean, this is a highly modifiable process.
Gosh, I almost don't know where to start, but I now feel like I want to start talking about some
of the exercise stuff. So I want to come back to cardiovascular disease prevention because there's
so much I want to talk with you about with respect to glycemic control, hyperinsulinemia,
other agents that we should be thinking about beyond just lipid lowering agents. And we can
dip into that, but I want to talk specifically about one of my favorite classes of drugs,
SGLT2 inhibitors. But before we do that, let's go back to circa 2011. James O'Keefe is up on stage
and he puts this graph up of a J-shaped mortality curve of exercise. And by the way, at this point,
Peter Attia sitting in the audience has probably just finished a four hour bike ride and he's
proud of the fact that he kept his heart rate above 172 for half of that time. Can you walk people
through basically, not that you remember that exact talk, but basically the thesis?
It's a reverse J curve actually, because if exercise were a drug, it would be the best drug
we have for preventing heart disease. I mean, for that matter, for preventing dementia, preventing
osteoporosis, depression, diabetes, obesity, I mean, it is a wonder drug if it were a drug.
But like with any drug, you got to get the dose right. Say you're using Carvedilol, one of my
favorite drugs, and you give somebody who has a fib or recent infarct or high blood pressure,
give them Carvedilol, but it's one milligram. You don't get any benefit. On the other hand,
you give them 120 milligrams twice a day. So if you give them 100 milligrams twice a day of Carvedilol,
it's a disaster. I mean, their blubbers are going to be low. They'll feel terrible.
Right. They'd have a hard time getting up off the couch.
Exactly. Right. So it's kind of the same thing with exercise. And amazingly, the dose of exercise
to get benefit is really small. I mean, most 50% of Americans do no exercise. If they just got off
the couch and went for a walk, a brisk walk, 15 minutes a day, they would get like a 30% reduction
in serious cardiovascular disease, 15 minutes a day. Now, ideally, we say 150 minutes a week
is sort of a lower limit benefit. But the point is that early steep limb of the survival
perversive exercise dose falls steeply. Your benefit goes down 30, 40, 50%. But then for the
last uptick, the people doing the most extreme doses of exercise, you start to lose some benefit.
And it's probably upwards of a third of the benefit. So people argue, well, I mean, no sense
scaring people off of exercise. I mean, it's just sort of an encouragement to not exercise,
knowing that if you overdo it, you could make yourself worse. And, and, and to be clear,
it's only like 2.5% of Americans are probably overdoing exercise versus at least 50% who are
underdoing exercise. But still, it's a bit like just because 50 to well, 70% of Americans are
overweight or obese. And it's like saying, well, we don't really want to talk about the dangers of
anorexia, because then, you know, we're kind of, we're sort of discouraged people from not eating
as much minutes, the mirror image of this. But the point is, you can overdo exercise. And, you know,
it might be interesting, as just an example, I know that you swam the Catalina channel,
like 15 years ago, right? Yeah. And I mean, that's pretty amazing feat. So when you're sitting here
talking to me, and your heart is beating probably about 45 beats a minute, and pumping out about
five leaves a minute of blood, when you're doing high intensity intervals, or when you're swimming
across the Catalina channel, you know, I mean, fast rate, I mean, you did that 20 miles in like
12 and a half, I mean, 10, 10 and a half hours. So actually, I think cycling is a is an even more
amazing place to show that because actually, for the channel, I would probably a there's something
about swimming where you're horizontal, I think your heart rate, for very short distances can
obviously climb like crazy, but I find on the bike, you would get the highest heart rate. So for me,
the maximum area under the curve heart rate was a one hour time trial. So so like a 40 kilometer
time trial would be absolutely maximum heart rate. How fast would it be going? I have a slow heart
rate all around. So my max might my my heart rate would be about 172 for for that type of a race.
An hour. Well, take less than an hour, probably. Yes, exactly. It would take about 50,
56 minutes, 55 minutes, maybe. No, that's a perfect example, because it's not only
high heart rate, but it's exercising under a load. It's like rowing. You know, this is your
your your using big muscles, you know, your blood pressure is also probably 200.
Your system pressure, your pulmonary pressure is probably 80, 60, 70, 80. Let's give people
symmetrics of normal. So for obviously, doctors listening to this will know what we're talking
about. But let's take a step back. So let's say my blood pressure is I have pretty normal blood
pressure. I'm probably about a 115 over 75 is my normal blood pressure. Can you tell people what
that means, by the way? What do those numbers mean when you have blood pressure checked?
You know, this is just the pressure that is exerted to pump the five liters of blood around
your around your circuit every minute. It takes that pressure to, you know, that's the normal
pressure to just kind of get that blood squirting around there. And then it comes back at only like
two or three or four more meters of mercury up from the legs. And that's that's a more
difficult physics problem, right? Because you're overcoming gravity at low pressures, which is why
it's good not to be obese. It's good to be exercising because those muscles milk the
blood back through the veins, through the through the valves up to the heart.
And those two numbers, of course, referred to as systolic and diastolic. The systolic is when the
heart is squeezing. So during the squeeze of the left ventricle, the pressure at the tip of the,
basically in the aorta is 115 millimeters of mercury. Now, anybody who's ever mucked around
with a pressure transducer will actually be surprised at how much pressure that is. That's
a non-trivial amount of pressure. If you've had the luxury of operating on people, you know what
115, even a normal 115 millimeters of mercury is, that'll squirt across the room. Across the room.
But the 75 refers to the relaxation phase of the heart. It says even when the heart is relaxed
and in the, what we call diastolic phase, receiving its blood supply, there's still quite a bit of
pressure in there. 75 millimeters of mercury in my case. Because your vessels are nice and elastic.
So, you know, as it receives the bolus of blood, everything expands. And then when the aorta valve
shuts, then those vessels, they rebound a little bit and they keep the, take the sort of pulsatile
bolus flow and turn it to more of a laminar, less bolus flow. So that elasticity of the vessels are
super important. Now you talked about my pulmonary pressures. What are my pulmonary pressures sitting
here right now? And I'll, I'll confess to you, I have no pulmonary disease, though I've never had
a swan GANS catheter placed in me. So what would you assume my pulmonary pressures are?
Oh, they'd be low, you know, like 20, 25 over 15, something like that. Nice and low. Okay. So
basically that's the same exercise, but now you're in my pulmonary arteries instead of my systemic
arteries. Let's just assert to me that my heart rate's 45 beats per minute. And you said my
cardiac output is five liters per minute. So that means every minute my heart sends five liters of
blood around my body. So I love that you brought up cardiac output because I think that's the
variable most people are sort of failing to appreciate how much that has to improve. So
when a weekend warrior like me would try to do his best one hour time trial, or when the best
cyclist in the world or the best runner in the world is, you know, doing their most exerted thing,
what's the variability or the range in cardiac output that we can see from best in the world
to sort of weekend warrior to average conditioned person? Just by way of context, if you look down
at your hand and make a fist, that's about how big your heart is. This is an amazing pump.
So five quarts a minute, I think if you were squeezing a bowl, five quarts a minute, five
liters per minute, five liters per minute, it never stops. And you're a good heart should have
about three or four billion beats in it without ever stopping. Okay, it's about a billion beats
every 30 years, which is for a math geek like you, it's kind of fun to think about, you know,
think about designing a lifestyle and exercise program to sort of minimize the number of heart
beats per year. Okay, and it does involve exercise, but it doesn't involve, you know,
it doesn't involve perculean efforts of protracted exercise. All right, but a good athlete like you,
an exceptional athlete like you, you go out and do that time trial, that one hour time trial at 175
beats a minute under load for an hour, you're pumping like 30 or 35 liters a minute.
Think about that, you know, 10 gallons a minute, you know, like Lance Armstrong and those, you know,
the professional cyclists or cross country skiers will get up to 40, 40 liters per minute.
You mistakenly referred to me as an exceptional athlete, which even at the time I wasn't.
But yeah, when you do talk about the exceptional, when you talk about Lance Armstrong riding up
Alpe d'Huez in 38 minutes, and it doesn't matter that he was on EPO, it really doesn't change the
metrics of this 40 liters per minute of cardiac output. You know, to put this in perspective,
James, I just love this so much, because the only times I've ever measured cardiac output
are in patients in an ICU. I mean, I can't count the number of times I've put a catheter into
somebody's lungs to measure and their heart to measure their cardiac output. But it's always
been in the setting of a patient under critical care. And in that setting, it would be routine
to see two and three liters of cardiac output per minute. And that's with every drug under the sun
used to squeeze their heart. And to think that you and I have the luxury of sitting here without a
single drug to increase the contractility of our heart, and we're at five liters per minute.
And even a couple of old guys like us could probably go out and exercise and still hit
25 liters per minute, but that the best in the world can hit 40 liters per minute. Now,
let's do some math. To get to that volume, flow rate, really, their heart rate isn't making up
the whole gap, because cardiac output is a product of two variables, the heart rate and the stroke
volume. Can you sort of explain how those play together? Well, rather, stroke volume is, you
know, your heart's a pump. And so, you know, in between beats, it fills. So how big it can
accommodate, how much volume it can accommodate with each beat is an important factor. And I
remember Miguel in the rain had some studies done years ago, and his heart was basically twice
normal size. So you get the heart rate up, the volume goes up, your arterioles and venules dilate
up so that the resistance goes down. And the heart is actually not just a pump, but it like it rings
out the blood, it shortens and twists. And when it's going fast and you're exercising, it's basically
sucking blood out of the lungs and the venous system into this and pumping out as fast as
it can. I mean, it's just an elegant, astoundingly well-designed system when it's used right. And
of course, that's one of the beauties of exercise. You know, you can feel that from, as you get into
shape, you can just feel yourself being more capable of this. And it's just intoxicating,
and it's one of the beauties why people get addicted to exercise. But the point is,
to get back to the underlying concept is that you can imagine when you're going that hard
and your blood pressure's up and your pulmonary pressure's up and you're doing 25 liters a minute,
the soft, pliable chambers in the heart, that's the atria, the right and left atria, and the right
ventricle, they get distended, they stretch out. Let's pause on that so people see why, James,
because if my cardiac output, which is the dot product of heart rate and stroke volume,
meaning if one goes up by two-fold, the other can go down by half and they'd stay the same,
but if the whole thing has to go up by 6x and my heart rate's only going up by 3x,
because 45 to 170 is about 3x, you have to bring the other one up by 2x. So how do you take up
stroke volume that much? Well, part of it is what you just said. You can squeeze harder, you can
twist, you can get every last dropout, but there's no getting around what you're just
about to explain to people, which is you have to make that chamber a heck of a lot bigger.
Right. And we're designed for this through nature. We're designed to be very active creatures, but
most of the time, if you look at tribes in the wild, they're doing like 16 or 18,000 steps a day,
but most of that is out of sort of a comfortable walking pace. Lots of times they're carrying
things or they might be lifting, chopping, swimming, whatever, building, and occasionally,
critical times in the hunt or whatever, they might be sprinting, although the younger members
in the tribe would be assigned that task because they're faster runners, but we're not really
designed to do what you did when you were doing these, like you still do, do these really long
bike rides. The chambers are marathons, ultramarathons, the chambers dilate up, and we have
enough circulating buffers in our bloodstream because this is like an engine, like an exercising
muscle used as fuel, glucose, fatty acids, ketones, to create energy, but it throws off exhaust.
And when you're exercising that hard, it throws off a lot of exhaust in the form of free radicals.
We have a lot of circulating buffers in there to basically neutralize those free radicals,
but we deplete that after 45 to 50 minutes of high intensity exercise. And there's good animal
studies showing and human studies showing that diastolic function improves for the first 30
minutes of exercise, and by 50 minutes or 60 minutes, it starts to worsen, and the endothelial
function will start to worsen too. After you've depleted those antioxidants after 45 or 50 minutes,
you start searing inside of your vessels, those endothelial, those sensitive endothelial
linings with high free radical levels. And you also start overtaxing the heart muscle.
And I'm not saying it's not a big deal, especially when you're young. Youth is, when we're young,
we're so resilient that you can get away with doing this stuff when you're 15 or 20 or 25 or 30
or 35, and maybe even 40 or 45. But after 45, it starts more likely taking a toll. You start seeing
troponins will rise, and NT Pro-MP will rise after really, really strong efforts like Amerifond.
Tell folks what those markers mean, because anybody who's been to an ER with chest pain
will know what a troponin is or has taken their grandmother into the ER with heart failure. But
for most people, they might not know what those are and why
seeing an elevation in those post-exercise should cause us to pause.
Yeah, so troponin is one of the proteins that is unique to the heart. And it leaks out of the heart
and gets into the bloodstream when there's been some heart damage. We usually associate it with,
like you say, heart attacks, where the artery closes off and the muscle is stored for oxygen,
and it dies downstream in that unless there's good collateral. So that really raises our eyebrows
and gets us into action when we see an elevated troponin. But a lot of people, I mean, upwards
of half or more people after a marathon will have an elevated troponin. It's just the best at that
high level, 25, 30 liters a minute for two and a half, three, four hours. It starts overstretching
the muscles in the atria and the right ventricle particularly, and it leaks into the bloodstream.
And again, tell people if you want to run a marathon, fine, run one or two, but don't make
it. It's like climbing Mount Everest. If you want to do that, do it once, but don't do it
three times a year. You could do it, brag about it and all that. But you got to move on to healthier
forms of exercise because these really, especially after age 40 or 45, really protracted exercise
will cause this small little micro damage, like overstretching and tearing because the high
levels of catacolamines and high levels of free radicals that are now unbuffered. And so if you're
designing, like I like to talk about, training for longevity is very different than training
for peak exercise and a car buff like you can understand that. It's like if you're going to
build a Formula One car to go fast, powerful, the most impressive performance machine ever,
it's going to look and perform a certain way. And it's good at that, but it's not going to go 500,000
miles. So it's built for power and speed and performance now. Like a car that's going to go
500,000 miles, I don't know, it might be a Honda Accord that you're driving never more than 70 miles
an hour and maintaining it really well. And so the point is that you have to really focus on what
your goals are. And our goals as an athlete is different than our goals for longevity and health
and wellbeing. You know, I love that analogy and I appreciate you using it for me because you know
how much I do love cars. In fact, I actually think I made that comment to a patient this week
using a Formula One car as the reference, because as you pointed out, James, these are cars that are
built for each race effectively. They'll go through three engines in a season. So everything about that
is meant to extract the absolute maximum performance. Again, I want to reiterate what you said.
If your goal is to win the Ironman triathlon, nothing we're saying here should pertain to you.
We're not going to tell you how to train for that. That is a remarkable feat. I mean, when I
think about what it would take to go seven hours in that heat to do what's involved in an Ironman,
I can't fathom that. There's never a time in my life when I've even approached the level of
raw performance that the winner of Ironman is going to take, or frankly, even somebody who
comes in under 10 hours. But swimming the Catalina Channel in the Dohrk, in 10 and a half hours,
that is also a pretty remarkable feat that's way beyond what a normal person is anywhere capable
of doing. Yeah, perhaps. I've never had to do all three at once. So when I was growing up, I was a
good runner. Good is maybe a stretch. I was a decent long, long, long distance runner. When I
was swimming channels, I could swim for long distances. And then when I could time trial,
like a time trial, but there's something about the Ironman or triathletes that can do all of
those things simultaneously. That's always impressed me. But my point is you're bringing
up the important distinction here, which is at some point an individual has to decide which master
they're serving. Are they serving the performance master or are they serving the longevity master?
And I think everybody goes through a difficult transition here. And I see this struggle with
many of my patients, especially the former, you know, exceptional athletes, or frankly,
not even people who were themselves exceptional athletes, but people who have also become,
I don't know how to describe it, but they found a new sense of purpose through some of their
athletic endeavors. And they've done their first marathon and they've thought, Oh my God,
this is really a great thing to do because there was a purpose. There was a goal. There was a
training plan. There was a camaraderie that came through that I got to do the thing. And now I
want to do it again and again and again and again. And they've made a lot of friends doing it too.
And it's a bonding experience and there's a lot good about that. But I'll just interject my
transitions because I've played basketball, you know, competitively in varsity and high school
and college and then for the first two years of college anyway. And then because I felt that
exercise was so important to me, I made this mental note when I stopped playing varsity
basketball that I would exercise pretty much every day because I knew it made me happy and healthy.
So then I kind of got into running then triathlons and I did short, you know,
like short distance sprint triathlons, but I hammered it. I mean, it trained really hard
and especially during my thirties up until my mid forties. And I was pretty good, you know,
winning like sprint distances, you know, and local races and stuff like that. But it was just
the fun of the competition and the friends and all that. But then I started noticing when I'd go out
and also in the back of my mind, being a cardiologist, you know, sort of thinking,
being proud and happy that, you know, that I'm capable of doing this, you know, in my in middle
age. But then I started noticing like when I go on really hard rides and do those hard intervals,
after I have this sort of vague sense of like aching in my chest. And sometimes I feel some
like I'm one of those people, maybe you are to a lot of people who are athletic, you can feel like
if I stop right now and be quiet, I could count my pulse just just feeling every heartbeat. And I
could feel some at the B some PVCs and some PCs or two or three runs in a row of PCs or as
superventricular tech cardio. And I thought, you know, my heart is not happy about this, you know,
and it disturbed me a little bit. And I kind of checked the cardio scan had a little bit of
calcium 21. But then I started thought about it, I thought, you know, this is makes no sense. I mean,
I'm thinking that if some exercise is good, and moderate exercise is better, that extreme exercise
is the best. There's nothing in biology like that, where the far extreme, it's usually moderation,
and especially moderation in the context of what we are evolutionarily designed to do. And what I
was doing for a 45 year old was out of bounds with respect to what, you know, my body was expecting.
And so I started looking into this and talking to some of my friends and colleagues from around
well, my practice and around the world, really, Peter Schnoor and Copenhagen putting together
some databases, and showing that in fact, and this is there in plain sight all the time, by the way,
path and Margaret, one of the godfathers of the exercise movement in his study in the New Moon
Journal of Medicine, pointing out in these Harvard alums that exercise improved longevity, like eight
to 10 years. But in the in the extreme deciles, it's just a small group of people who were doing
the most exercise per week actually lost like 38% of the benefit conferred by the less extreme
effort. And, and then Ken Cooper, another one of the sort of founding fathers of the modern aerobics
movement down in Dallas used to say, if you're running more than 15 miles a week, you're doing
for some other reason besides health. So they recognized and even Hippocrates 2500 years ago
said, if we could prescribe the right dose of exercise and nutrition, not too little, not too
much is the safest way to health. I mean, so this has been there right along that, you know, even
back 2500 years ago, they, they recognize that it's not going to be centered, but you can overdo it,
you can kill yourself with too much exercise. Let's go back to what you were talking about
with respect to PVCs. Explain to folks what's actually happening with a PVC, because I think
this for me became the area when I, where I started to pay attention. Just to be clear,
James, it took me three years to fully embrace this message. It was not until 2014 that I finally
realized I needed to get into one camp and I couldn't serve two masters and my higher priority
was going to be my longevity. And that meant I was not going to do these crushing workouts anymore.
My workouts were going to be geared towards what makes me live longer.
And the data that I found most convincing were the electrophysiologic data. So it was looking at
athletes, the incidents of atrial fibrillation in cyclists and runners who were at or above a
certain volume versus normal age matched controls. And yes, that's full of all the same problems and
pitfalls that epidemiology was full of. But when the magnitude was so big, it was difficult to
ignore. And if I recall the magnitude was in the ballpark of about seven X. In other words,
if you took, you know, retired professional cyclists and you compared them to aged matched
controls and match them in any way possible, these professional cyclists were seven times
more likely to have atrial fibrillation. Does that, is my memory serving me correctly or am
I out to lunch on that? No, that's, that's almost spot on. But also I point out that,
you know, the heart is very capable of healing itself almost always. And so it's really these
high volume athletes, high volume, high intensity athletes who continue to do it. All right. Past,
you know, like in the middle age and beyond are the ones I see these people all the time,
because I've written about this a lot. I see patients all the time come in with a fib and it's
like 700% increased incidence of a fifth, which is a really common part of the rhythm, where the
atrial, where the rhythm arises, becomes disorganized and chaotic. And so it, it just
scoots through the AV node to into the conduction system down to the bottom, working part of the
heart rapidly and irregularly. And it's becoming more common all the time in America, because
it's common among older people, obesity, diabetes, sleep apnea, tall people, too much alcohol can
cause it. But one of the causes that we see is in people who are overdoing high intensity exercise.
So yeah, you're right on there.
I cut you off or rambled too long in my question, but tell people what a PVC is and why,
and is that an early warning sign?
The high catecholamine levels from protracted exercise and the high oxidative stress and the
stretched chamber causes some tearing of the myocardial fibers with protracted exercise. And
over time, that can cause little micro islands of fibrosis in the myocardial scar tissue.
And so if you keep doing this like year after year, a decade after decade, you start ending up with
this stiff dilated chambers, which then is the electrical milieu that is favorable for
creating these rhythm problems at first things like PVCs, but eventually can can lead to VT.
But again, and a fib is much more common still, but these are signs that your heart's irritable.
Your heart's been irritated by something. And in this case, it's too much exercise.
So let's talk about perhaps one of the more sad, publicly known examples of that, which you've
spoken about publicly, which is the sudden death of Micah True. Tell folks a little bit about who
he is and what a remarkable specimen he was and what conclusions you drew from his death.
Yeah, so he's sort of the poster boy for the thing, you know, that you really kind of
an extreme example. So Micah True was a remarkable endurance runner. The book,
Born to Run, was written about him. And he was kind of a hippie who sort of dropped out of society
and decided to just become a runner. We went down to northern Mexico and ran with this tribe that
has its runners in it, the Tarahumara Indians. And he would run just remarkable distances and
became sort of like an example of any of this. He was in his 40s or 50s when this happened, but
he was out for a run and he died suddenly. And they did an autopsy on him and he found
this, you know, dilated scarred up heart, just what we're describing, you know, the scarring
and the atria and the ventricles, especially the right ventricle, interventricular septum.
But the point is that he was really fit. He accomplished a lot of really impressive things,
but it did take a toll on his heart. And now granted, he was doing just superhuman volumes.
I mean, he would typically run 12 miles a day, as I recall, and lots of times would do these
50 or 100 mile races through the desert heat and things like that. But yeah, I'm not a big fan of
these extreme, and there's more, I have a friend who did the seven marathons in seven days on seven
continents race, Megan. You know, she's a really, she's a good friend, known her for a long time.
She was one of the best triathletes in America when she was doing that 10 years ago. And now
she still exercises a lot, although she's kind of cut back on it. But if you measured what's going
on with her heart during those times, it's, I mean, it's not pretty. It's like the heart suffers when
we really, really overdo it. Of course, all of these data that we look at the inverted J curve,
a lot of the Harvard prospective study, even though they're prospective, they're still epidemiologic.
A critic of this would say, look, we don't have any randomized data, experimental human randomized
data to tell us that the dose curve to exercise is nonlinear. Again, what that means is linear means
the more you do, the better you get. You're proposing the more you do, the better you get
to a point. And then it actually goes down. Hence the inverted or upside down J. What about
animal models? Are there appropriate animal models that can be studied here? If so, what have they
shown? Yeah, the animal models, most have done with mice, but a few with dogs have been pretty
much consistent with this, that you do see these elevations of a troponin acutely. And if you keep,
keep them going for months or a year or two, you can see these dilated chambers, the, with the
substrate for arrhythmias. And if you look at the epidemiological data in our last paper that we
just published, it's called training for longevity, we put all the major 10 big epidemiologic studies
and all but two of them showed this very distinct reverse J curve so that you get this deep
reduction in mortality that plateaus off in the middle. And at the very end, the fish hooks up.
It's like diet in that. So you're not going to be able to prove it because these are lifelong
kind of patterns that, that emerge and it's impossible to randomize people to it. But,
you know, there's a lot to be said for the end of one. You know, you're paying close attention
to your body. I can tell you for me as a cardiologist and also just as an athlete and a
person, it was very apparent to me that if I didn't change this, it was not good for my heart.
And let's just talk for a moment about the best kind of exercise. If you just stop talking about
volume and intensity, but just talk about like the best kinds of exercise because this, this friend
of mine, Peter Schnorr and Jacob Marat, he's a, he's a brilliant PhD from Denmark, from Copenhagen.
Peter Schnorr founded the Copenhagen city heart study. This is 10,000 Danes that they enrolled
25 to 40 years ago and focus kind of like the Framingham study was in America for diet and
lifestyle. This was like the Framingham study for exercise. They, they sort of collected a lot of
data about what people were doing for exercise and then followed them through the decades. And,
you know, the people in Copenhagen, I think it's the city in the world that has the largest number
of people who bike to work. I mean, it's just, it's a flat city. They have these, these, these kind
of really generous bike lanes and it's just really fun to watch how people bike to work, but they do
a lot of other things. And so they collected data on eight or nine specific sports, including running,
swimming, cycling, health club activities, which included treadmill and all those station
exercise machines with weight that put all that together. And then there was tennis, badminton,
soccer, golf, I think were the ones. And so we sat down, we'd done some other analysis,
this data showing that it was the moderate dose runners that did the best for longevity
during the four decades long follow-up of that. But this was a more, this was a different look
and so we said, what sport is best for conferring longevity? And so, you know,
they did all the multivariable analysis for, because, you know, tennis players are different than,
than maybe cyclists or whatever, but quantitative how much exercise per week. And maybe, you know,
this data, but, but what do you think? I know it just shocked me. I went over there to, to
finally look at the data and we were sitting on a coffee table one Sunday afternoon, having a glass
one and talking it over and he sort of reveals this data to me and I look at it, you know,
it's multivariable, just data. And I was really like speechless. I was just, it just, I just thought,
oh, what a waste we spent all this time and this is nonsense. So, so what do you think came out
as the least effective way for improving longevity compared to say sedentary population?
I've read this, so I'll let you disclose both the best and the worst to people.
Okay. So the worst was health club activities and the best was tennis followed closely by
badminton, soccer, golf, and the middle three were like cycling, swimming, running. And that was like
three to four years out of life expectancy. Health club activities is only one and a half year
life expectancy added and, and those social sports, badminton, tennis, golf. I mean,
it's easy to imagine soccer, but we're like six to 10 years added life expectancy multivariable.
And I just thought, well, it's not even a sense of publishing this, but then I started looking at
and thinking, wait, what if, what if it's not so much about what hammers your body into peak
fitness as well as what sort of reduces stress, makes you happy, something you can do lifelong
and sort of fosters personal relationships? Because there's a lot of studies in recent
decades, one by Juliana Holt, Lonested that said that single best predictor better than smoking
or diabetes or exercise or blood pressure, lipids for conferring longevity with strong social support.
You know, relationships are the key and you could instinctively would understand that,
but then I started thinking, well, you know, particularly for us sort of like emotionally
challenged gender, you know, males, it's like we make friends at work and we have our family, but
lots of times we bond by playing. And when you think about these, the sports that were done
playing were the ones that conferred best longevity and they're also the ones that sort of promote
more social activity. So I think we need to change our mind around about what best exercise is not
about if you're training for longevity, yeah, take it down a couple of notches, but also make sure
that you have some play in your life. We played as kids. We need to be playing as adults even more
because it's so important not only for social bonding, for stress relief or at the press,
I mean, I just think it's so important. Yeah, I think my reading of that was basically,
look, there are a lot of variables that can't be teased out of any multivariate analysis or
correction, but a couple of things stuck out to me. One was, I think you're right. I think
what tennis and golf, badminton, soccer offered that running, cycling, and swimming didn't to the
same extent on average, not globally, but on average, is you got to combine two medicines instead of one.
And you know better than me that two drugs are often much better than one to control blood
pressure. So when you got to combine exercise with social interaction, it does better than
just exercise. That's sort of the first thing I take away from that. The second thing I take away
from it frankly is the challenge of doing any sort of large-scale study where you don't have
a close ability to understand the intervention. And I'm very fortunate that I have a gym at home,
so I don't work out in gyms anymore. But from the days when I used to work out in gyms,
I realized that if we were going to treat everybody in that gym as one cohort of everybody who goes
to the quote health club, we would glean very little because the difference between what people
did in that gym is so enormous that the average of that borders on meaningless, just as the average
of what any group of individuals does is effectively meaningless because there is no ability to control
for it. So those are the two things that I took from that. Now I do want to go back to kind of
something you said because I look, I think there were going to be a lot of people who listened to
this who are going to be exercising more than what you put forth. I think you said earlier something
to the effect of, look, 15 miles a week of running is probably adequate if you're, if running is
something you enjoy doing. You probably don't need to be running more than 15 miles a week.
I'll tell you this right now, my wife runs a hell of a lot more than 15 miles per week.
So here's my argument to her to run less. It's, and I use economic terms called opportunity cost.
It's like, look, Jill, I know you want to run 50 miles a week, and I know if you had all the time
in the world, you'd run 50 miles a week, but it comes at the cost of you doing not a single other
form of exercise. No strength training, no rowing, no this, no that. So really the argument is,
and this was the argument for me in cycling as well, which was, look, one, you just, you're tired
of spending all this time training when you, you have kids that are getting older and older and you
have more kids and it's, there's just a cost to being away from that. But, but it really comes
down to how can you be a more balanced athlete for life? So maybe not a better athlete in a very
specific sport because cycling's a very specific sport. Running's a very specific sport. If you
want to be very good at those things, by definition, you're not going to be very good at much else.
But life is a pretty complicated sport and it requires strength, stability, aerobic fitness,
and anaerobic fitness. Yeah, flexibility, I mean all of these things. So you have to be able to
train all of those things and unless you're retired, I'm not sure how you'd want to run more
than 15 miles a week if you have to be able to put effort into those other things. So for me,
that is the prescriptive takeaway here is how do you have a portfolio approach to exercise?
What is your prescriptive approach to patients that I just sort of laid out in mind?
Well, yeah, you're right on as usual. If you're spending a lot of times running,
I know a lot of patients who run or cycle like a lot, I mean 30, 40, 50 miles a week of running
like an hour or two a day of cycling, it's like you're, yeah, you're getting your aerobic fitness
really high, but it's not great for your skeleton or your balance. I mean, I tell people
just after 30 or 45 minutes of aerobic exercise, if you want to do more, circle back home and
do some yoga, do some weights, these things that kind of don't necessarily tax your heart the same
way that the other high intensity sports do or sexual activity, if nothing else, is exercise that
again is a totally different realm that is worth investing time and energy into and also,
it's for relationship building. And so yeah, I think that it's a matter of being more balanced.
And also if you try to figure out the area under the curve for maximizing your heartbeats,
you want to do stuff that keeps your resting pulse low, but some high intensity intervals to keep
your maximal rate, your maximal capabilities high, that'll develop fitness quicker than anything,
some high intensity interval training in a relatively short period of time. But it's the
sort of thing that high volumes of really high intensity exercise is just not, I just don't think
it's the ideal approach to fitness. Either as a podcast I did with Inigo San Milan where we talk
very specifically and in great detail about zone two, zone two being defined as this area where
you have the maximum efficiency of the mitochondria. So you're able to keep lactate systemically below
two millimole and just barely keep it there, right? So you're sort of maximum utilization of glucose
and fatty acid that is mitochondrial without undergoing non-oxphos. For most people, that's
a lower level of activity than they're used to. If you do popular classes, if you hop on a Peloton
class or something, you're spending very little amount of time in that zone. But you're also
spending very little amount of time at peak capacity sort of north of kind of zone five.
You're spending a lot of time in the middle. And I actually think it's that in the middle time
that unless you're an athlete who competes in the middle is actually some of the least important
areas to be training. A lot of the data looking at even world-class athletes says it's 80 percent
low intensity, 20 percent high intensity. Of course their total volume is enormous, but I think they
even have the ratio right. And yet I think most people don't have that ratio correct and they
don't appreciate how important it is to do that low end aerobic, which depending on your fitness
might just be brisk walking. If you're a little fitter, it might be again zone two level of
fitness. One of the things as a cardiologist people are always asking me, so what should my
heart rate be? What's my training zone and a lot kind of stuff? And for most people I tell them,
do you know, I wouldn't pay much attention to your heart rate. I mean, except for the fact that I love
activity trackers and that they could track the pulse and stuff, but I think the most important
parameters about pulse are what you're resting pulses. We want to get that nice and low. We want
heart rate variability. We want that to be more variable when you take slow deep breaths, which
is why meditation or yoga is a really good thing to add to somebody's fitness regimen. But with
respect to trying to, you know, get your heart rate maxed out, it's like there was a recent study
showing in middle-aged adults looking at life expectancy as a function of number of steps taken.
And people compared to people who are less than 4,000 steps a day, people who are getting 8,000
steps a day had a 50% reduction in mortality during a 12-year follow-up. And people were getting up to
12,000 steps a day. That was the peak. I mean, it plateaued there. Above that, it didn't go
down further, but there was a 67% reduction in mortality. So like you can get pretty much the
full benefit of exercise with just a lot of steps and most of those being walking. I would agree
that you want to add some higher intensity interval, but it doesn't take a lot. I mean,
like if you look at running, five miles of running a week will give you the longevity boost
from running. That's almost as good as it gets. One of the questions patients ask me, and I don't
really know the answer, I'm hoping you might, is how much resting heart rate is a function of
fitness versus genetics. So sometimes, because now a lot of our patients do use tracking devices,
and they often report your lowest resting heart rate overnight, which would really be your true
nadir. And I have some patients who say, gosh, mine is 57, why is it not 47? And I really don't
know how much of that is their exercise versus, look, some people just have different size engines
that rev at different levels. For example, I've always had a very low heart rate. So nowadays,
my resting heart rate, my overnight resting heart rate might be in the low 40s, but when I was
athletic, when I was very fit, I would wake up with a resting heart rate in the mid 30s. So actually,
I have a pretty high heart rate relative to my baseline now, but I've also never had a very high
peak heart rate. So I've just always thought of myself as having more of a diesel engine.
I have to believe that's somewhat genetic. So what is your view around resting heart rate,
given that it is a metric people are becoming more and more aware of?
So for one thing, females tend to have higher heart rates than males, even at equivalent fitness
levels. And that being said, a resting pulse is a much stronger prediction, predictor of mortality.
Lower is better in that regard, lower pulse, better longevity in males than in females.
Males with a resting heart rate above 85 is not a good place to be. Some of it's genetic. And as
people get, you know, into advanced years, some of it's disease, six-simon syndrome, you know,
where your pulse just slows down, because, you know, the engine's wearing out, and they need a
pacemaker. But most of the time, it's, you know, it's a function of, well, for instance, like
alcohol, the more alcohol you drink, the higher your pulse will be, your resting pulse, stress,
sleep problems. There's a lot of things, but it's generally a pretty good marker of fitness. And so
like a lot of things, rather than worrying about how you compare to, you know, your buddy you're
working out with, is how you just compare yourself to you and keep track of your pulse. And you'll
notice that when you get into a rhythm, like for instance, one of the reasons I love watching my
my resting heart rate, and I'm kind of like you, it runs, you know, 42-44 most nights. And if I get
overtrained or under slapped, I've been on call, been under more stress, been traveling too much,
it'll start raising up to, you know, 47-48-49. And if you pay close attention to it and use that as
feedback, it's a really great way to tune your lifestyle to get into a, like a cardio protective
zone. And it involves the right amount of exercise and the right amount of sleep and not too much
alcohol and, and some, you know, plenty of downtime and play and, and those sorts of things.
How much do you see patients' resting heart rates improve with appropriate exercise-based
interventions? So when you take patients who are underdoing it, which as you said at the outset,
we shouldn't lose sight of the fact, most people are underdoing this drug called exercise,
but patient shows up with the resting heart rate of 75, who's otherwise quite healthy, has a cack,
their score is, places them at the 50th percentile. They're in no grave or acute danger at all,
but they say, Dr. O'Keefe, I'm here to get serious about this. I want to, you know, I want to bend the
arc of my life. I'm 45 and this is the time to really pay attention, even though there's no
heart attack in the next decade of my life at all. And you say, look, I want you to do X, Y, and Z.
Is there an expectation that their resting heart rate is going to be 55 one day?
55 only if they get really serious about, you know, losing 30 pounds and getting fit from unfit.
But more typically, you know, five or 10 beats per minute is not uncommon.
And you, you're happy with that. That's a positive sign to you.
Oh, absolutely. You know, and, and of course it goes along with their waistline coming down and
their blood pressure coming down and their triglycerides lower and their A1C lower. So,
you know, these things tend to move in tandem when you kind of dial in your lifestyle and diet
and exercise program to that sort of ideal zone. Well, let's pivot then and talk a little bit about
nutrition. Gosh, there are so many places to go on this, but something you've written extensively on
is the relationship between diabetes and cardiovascular disease. And what can be
gleaned from that as a model for studying a disease. So tell folks a little bit about that work.
Well, this is another thing that I sort of like paid attention to in my diet. And, you know,
back when I was in medical school in the eighties and my training in the eighties and, and, you know,
that was the time when, you know, the Pritikin diet and like a low fat diet was all the rage.
And unfortunately, you know, that took a long time to extinguish that, but I started following that
pretty closely. And it was a disaster. You know, it's like my triglycerides went from 80 to 300.
My HDL went down from 50 to 33. And I just thought, you know, when I was getting skinnier and, you know,
my athletic times weren't better. And in fact, they were worse and I wasn't feeling that good.
I thought this is not the right diet. How restricted were you? Well, like, for instance,
when I, you know, I was at 20 something, you know, so I'd go out to eat with friends and
we'd be eating pizza or, and I'd take off the toppings and just eat the crust, you know,
and then, and then for a while, then I kind of got into the sort of keto phase and I would eat
the toppings and throw away the crust. And then I figured, yeah, pizza probably just not worth
eating at all. So, you know, and I'd eat lots and lots of white rice and, you know, and try to
minimize fat. And then I realized, you know, you can't generalize. For one thing, that's a disaster
for, and it's played out on a, on a population wide level in America, that kind of diet, you know,
makes us fat, belly fat, triglycerides, rub, diabetes rates are up. It makes you hungry all
the time. It is not the right diet. Just two days ago, we published an article in our, our
flagship cardiology journal in the world called the Journal of American Culture Cardiology,
called the PESCO Mediterranean Diet Intermittent Fasting as like the omnivore solution to the
omnivore's dilemma of what to eat. And we think if you put together like all the data and the
guidelines and, you know, the observational data and a little bit of randomized data that we have
that a diet that's moderately high in fat, very low in refined carbohydrates, like almost no added
sugar and minimal white refined grains, but, but high in nuts and extra virgin olive oil and high
in fish and seafood and high in vegetables and low in processed food and drinking mostly water or tea,
coffee fasting for at least 12 hours each 24 hour period of time and preferably moving more like to
like a 14 or 16 hour fast per day. We think this is like arguably the healthiest cardiovascular
diet, both for preventing diabetes, but also preventing heart disease and dementia, obesity,
and a lot of the other scourges that are so common in our society. The PredaMed study,
which I'm sure I've discussed in great detail on a previous podcast, though unfortunately I can't
recall, hopefully in the show notes, if it's been done, we'll make sure to link to it. Probably one
of the most impressive diet studies with respect to cardiovascular disease prevention. And, you know,
I think the findings of that though they needed a revision based on an error in randomization the
first time around were difficult to ignore when you consider the challenges of studying primary
prevention, even with drugs, let alone with a diet. And yet to see the success of a Mediterranean
diet in that study, that was a wake up call for me. Peter, that is in my opinion the most important
diet study that's been done. Emilio Ross was the primary investigator on that. He was a co-author
on this recent paper that we wrote and Emilio and I have been working together on a lot of projects
recently, but it was the Mediterranean diet versus the American Heart Association diet, which is that
diet that we were just, you know, dissing. That's, you know, the low fat, so trending towards vegetarian
diet that's high in carbs. But that showed in this group of 7,500 people followed for
four and a half years that the primary endpoint, which was MI, heart attack,
stroke or cardiovascular death was reduced 30%. But also follow-up studies showed that the dementia,
cognitive impairment, diabetes, obesity were also, each of those were significantly reduced in the
people that got the Mediterranean diet. But it's important to point out that they were specific
Mediterranean diets that half of the people in the Mediterranean diet got a free liter of extra
virgin olive oil per week that they were supposed to use up in a week. And the other half got mixed
nuts, tree nuts, there were almonds, walnuts and filverts or hazelnuts. So they were adding fat
in the case of the nuts, you know, vegetable protein. And when you do the multivariable analysis
on what correlated best, it was the added fat. It didn't increase saturated fat, but it increased
these healthy fats from these healthy foods. And as Emilio likes to point out with the olive oil,
you know, it has to be not only extra virgin, but more importantly, it needs to be high in polyphenols,
which is perceptible as this black pepper stinging at the back of your palate. You need to, every
time you open a bottle of olive oil, because it's not on the maple, generally, the polyphenol content,
you taste it and it should have this, this, this burn 10 or 20 seconds after you swallow it in the
back of your palate. Those are super important antioxidants that because they're dissolved in
oil, they seep into your blood vessels, they seep into your brain and your eyes and your skin.
And they really correlate with good long term health. Whereas there's been studies,
decades, Dr. Vogel and his colleagues did a study showing that olive oil was bad for your endothelium.
And that never made sense to me. And then I realized, oh, they were using a like an,
you know, antioxidant depleted, not not one of these high polyphenol,
antioxidant olive oil. So it's really important to look for those high antioxidant olive oils and
then use them generously. So two comments. One is most people that think of the grocery store,
myself included historically aren't really paying close attention to what olive oil is. And boy,
you only need to get fooled once, which is to say catch what the label says to really get upset. But
a lot of things that are marketed as pure extra virgin olive oil or anything, but,
and I don't know how they get away with it. Truthfully, it's really an embarrassment to
how this stuff is regulated, but it's basically a bunch of canola oil that has some olive oil in it.
And they they've somehow managed to lie their way into saying it's pure olive oil. So you have to
be careful what you buy. But because of those, because of that, that's the pre-demand study,
though, had the intervention of extra virgin olive oil or nuts. And we have a rare thing,
by the way, as you're always pointing out, we have first level randomized data showing that adding
this to the diet will reduce heart attack, stroke and cardiovascular death. And, and so I mean,
it's also, you know, these are delicious foods when you get used to eating them. And, and, you
know, if you want to follow a high fat ketogenic diet, it should be high unsaturated fat. It
shouldn't be cream and cheese and butter and red meat. It should be, it should be nuts and seeds,
extra virgin olive oil, avocados and oily fish like salmon. It's only those five things. I mean,
you need to get a lot of your calories from those five things, which by the way, is kind of the
traditional peasant Mediterranean diet. These were these were Mediterranean's who are living high on
the hog. These are the peasants who were growing their own vegetables and tending their own olive
garden and their own grapes and the red wine and that sort of thing. So. So how convincing do you
think are the data demonizing saturated fat? Given that so much of it is in the context of
refined carbohydrates and other things. I mean, again, when you look at the epidemiologic data,
unfortunately we just don't have big enough cohorts of people who consume saturated fat,
absent carbohydrates or refined carbohydrates, it saturated fat in epidemiology becomes a proxy for
people who are probably eating a lot of other bad things. So mechanistically maybe or otherwise,
how do you feel about it? I'm actually like what people ask me about, you know,
what's the most important thing of the diet? I don't mention getting rid of red meat or getting
rid of saturated fat. I mean, a moderate amount of that is, you know, again, our evolutionary
history. You know, we ate a lot of red meat and we ate saturated fat. The evil white crystal in
the American diet is not salt. The worst is sugar and sugar and refined carbohydrates are by far
the absolute worst dietary villain. Saturated fat, you know, a little bit of butter is not going to
kill you. You know, like, like if you're a vegan, there's nothing you can eat that'll be healthier
for you than like a juicy steak. It's not, it's not overdone, you know, because, because you're
probably low in, in the things like B12 and zinc and iron and high quality protein. So yeah,
it's, it's a natural food and in moderation. I mean, I think saturated fat, excessive saturated
fat is not a good idea, but we don't focus successfully on it. My wife Joan is a really
smart dietician. And like you, you know, we went to school till we're 32 or 33 to promote health
and wellness and we got zero, nothing. I mean, hardly an hour of training in nutrition. It's
just so embarrassing that it's still like that. But, but so, you know, she kind of taught me a
lot of the fundamentals and still continues to teach me a lot of fundamentals of nutrition because
this is an important thing. And, and any good dietician will tell you that, you know, red meat
and saturated fat are essential nutrients that they're not toxic in and of themselves.
So you touched briefly on salt. I know you've written about not just salt, but also magnesium.
And that's something that's also really near and dear to my heart. Our patients consume a lot of
magnesium, both in the form of oxide, which we basically titrate as high as they can tolerate
from a bowel function perspective. And then we use, you know, slow mag typically just to make sure
that nobody's getting any sort of cramping or anything like that. But my thesis is there's a
global shortage of magnesium in the human. Somehow we're just not getting enough magnesium.
Now I don't know why that's the case, but my proof for that, if that's too strong a word,
is that when you give people back on the order of two grams of magnesium a day,
they always feel better. Why is that? Well, it's the same story with potassium, Peter, by the way,
our evolutionary ancestors living out there in the wild, eating wild game, nuts, all the
vegetables and fruits we're getting like, and fiber is the same way, you know, like five times
more. They were getting a lot more magnesium, a lot more potassium, a lot more fiber than we're
getting today. So when you add those things back to the diet, and the best way to do it is with
lots of nuts or high magnesium. But I agree. The other thing, so basically I think it's like
getting us back into sort of like an ideal range of consumption of a really important
mineral. I mean, it's an important cofactor for a lot of the most essential, you know,
sort of chemical reactions going on in our body of magnesium. So it's really important, but
it also makes me think that, you know, a concept that I've come to recently that I think you'll
like, and you probably think this way as well, but again, if you look at our ancestors, when they
would get a bird or a mammal or a fish or a squirrel or whatever, and they would cook it,
or buffalo for that matter, and they'd cook it, they would eat nose to tail, right? They'd eat
the whole thing. These days when we eat meat, we usually muscle meat, which is a very narrow sort
of range of animal-based nutrients. One of the things when you eat nose to tail, say when you're
cooking the bones, for example, you cook them long enough to eat them, you get a bunch, and the skin
for that matter too, a bunch of collagen. You get calcium hydroxyapatite, which is a form of calcium
that we're meant to eat. We weren't meant to eat rocks, which is the standard calcium supplement.
It's calcium carbonate, calcium glucanate. Those are rocks. We didn't eat rocks. We ate bones,
and for the last 5,000 years, we ate dairy, but a lot of people have trouble, you know,
tolerating the lactose. We think that, and Mediterranean diet really focuses on fermented
dairy, but getting back to, I think the other supplements that are really important is like an
organic bone meal that you have to add magnesium to it, because that's calcium hydroxyapatite.
If you get that up to the gram a day of calcium from there, and your magnesium, I would agree,
two grams per day. Then the collagen, because you're not going to eat enough skin to get the
collagen that we're meant to get, the collagen supplement, like whether it's pills or powder,
is really, really good for hair, skin, and nails, not to mention bones. It's also good for putting
on healthy muscle and maintaining healthy muscle. I mean, this is like ideal protein,
glycine, and other amino acids that, by the way, were really meant to have in our diet. So I think
those are really important supplements to that sort of healthy Mediterranean, PESCO Mediterranean
diet, but the fasting, I think that it's good to add because it's hard to get those kinds of
minerals at those levels. Do you restrict sodium in any subset of your patients, including maybe
even those that are both hypertensive with compromised kidney function?
We see a lot of really sick people with, you know, with class four heart failure and
bad kidney disease or whatnot. There you have to do, be somewhat careful, but I virtually never
tell people to do that less than 1500 milligrams of sodium. And you're better off having sodium
kind of in the medium range, you know, from two to three grams per day. And actually,
a good rule of thumb for the listeners here, and generally healthy people, is like eat mostly whole
natural foods, which are very depleted, sodium core, right? And then salt to taste, because a
lot of the healthiest foods you'll eat, like vegetables, nuts, fish, you'll eat a lot more
if you can salt it to taste and make it taste good. And when you add salt to those natural,
you know, or lightly salted nuts, I mean, you don't need to worry about that. That's good for
you having some salt in your diet when you're eating an otherwise naturally healthy whole foods
diet. All right. Let's go back and talk about that drug that I'm so enamored with or class of
drug, there are at least two out there. Tell folks what an SGLT2 inhibitor is, besides a mouthful.
Yeah, an SGLT2 inhibitor, you know, is a diabetic drug that blocks this sodium glucose co-transporter
in the tubule in the nephron. When we filter our blood through the nephron to the kidneys,
we pull out a lot of things, your water, sodium, toxins, urea, including glucose. And then because
the body is saying we're interested reason to waste this glucose, you know, we need we need
these calories. So it reabsorbs the filtered glucose before the urine goes out. So we figured
the engineered a drug to block the reabsorption of that glucose that's filtered. And when this drug,
when these classic drugs first came out seven or eight years ago, I have to tell you, Peter, I
thought this is a dumb idea. I mean, everybody knows that glycosuria is terrible for the kidneys.
And this is like, it may be lower sugar, but in the long run, it's going to be, but that's the
beauty of science. That's why you do these big randomized placebo controlled trials. And when
the first one came out, the MPA reg study five years ago, like my phone and text messages,
emails just lit up with people from around the country, around the world, friends who were
saying, did you see this? This can't be true. Keeping in mind, we've been trying to prove for
40, 50 years, 100 years since the first diabetes drug, insulin came out, that controlling sugar
prevented cardiovascular death. And we couldn't prove it. Shockingly, until this trial came out,
and it reduced cardiovascular death 38%. It reduced heart failure, renal failure. I mean,
it was just an amazing thing. And subsequently, there's been, oh, a good seven mega trials now,
between three and 17,000 patients in each study randomized to SGLT2 inhibitor or placebo,
that shows that in fact, these are the most potent drugs for, I mean, not for lowering sugar,
they do that modestly, but for improving cardiovascular prognosis, reducing heart failure
and renal failure. And it's just fascinating to speculate about the mechanisms of action,
but may have something to do with ketones. But the most shocking thing about this that's really
blown the lid off is, is that these drugs reduce things like heart failure, deaths, heart failure
occurrence, and renal failure in people without diabetes, as well as with diabetes. So that really
makes us wonder. Well, that's why I take one. And they're currently being studied, frankly,
as just straight up longevity agents for exactly that reason. And I'm actually, my interest in this
even goes a bit beyond that of metformin, which has historically garnered much of the longevity
attention in the diabetes medication repurposed camp, because I like the mechanism of action more.
I like what it doesn't do. Again, I think metformin is an amazing drug. I think it's,
it's efficacy in people with diabetes is remarkable. I do have my concerns about its efficacy
in very healthy people who exercise at the upper limit of what we've discussed. And I think it
might, it might impair there. I think it's too soon to say. I've had lots of interesting discussions
with people and we're actually in the process of designing a study now to test that. But to me,
this is a drug that doesn't really show any evidence of impairing the benefits of exercise
and yet offers through totally different mechanisms, some of those cardio protective benefits. So
the good news, as you pointed out about science is it just, over time, it keeps accumulating
information and we'll get better and better answers. Churning away. And you know, but so,
it's so fascinating to think about how this works. And I don't prescribe metformin for
people without diabetes. I mean, it upsets your stomach. It kind of makes you feel a little queasy.
I use it on all my type two diabetics, but I always understand that the SGLT2 inhibitor is
more important. It burns off belly fat. When you, even a non-diabetic person takes, takes an SGLT2
inhibitor, you urinate out about a hundred grams of sugar a day. So we were talking about the evil
crystal compound, you know, white, the sugar. This basically is like pulling the plug and draining
a substantial amount of sugar from your body every day. It's like following a ketogenic diet
without having to follow that. I mean, it raises ketones in the low, in your system because of
the fact, and it does tap into belly fat. It taps into belly fat to get the fatty acids that then
turns in, the liver turns into ketones. So, and we still don't fully understand how it works,
but it's an important drug class that is going to only get bigger with respect to its impact on
health and longevity. Why do you think it hasn't shown an increase in UTIs or bladder cancers or
things like that? I mean, cause so seven years ago, that was my thinking, right? Which was,
Oh, interesting idea, but you're going to have a UTI every week. No, thanks. Like I don't,
I don't see how that's a good trade-off and it just hasn't panned out. Why do you think that is?
It's sort of interesting because well, when you think about it, the UTIs, you are getting rid of
some glucose in the urine. It actually, the only predictable side effect that you see,
and it goes up, especially in females is topical yeast infections, you know, fungal infections
down in the growing regions on the genitalia. And you know, when you think about it, you are
putting sugar in the water in warm, moist places. So I tell people on, on the SGLT2 inhibitor,
they need to, you know, pay special attention to use a wet wipe after urination, especially
females, because there's just more surface area there to get a yeast infection on. But,
but it is sort of interesting that it doesn't really increase things like UTI or pylo-naphritis
or uro-sepsis. So it may be just that it's making the system otherwise healthier, you know, your
immune system, your, your kidney function, your cardiovascular system. Maybe it's just, you know,
you're better able to deal with that. I don't know. This really brings it back to this point,
which is, you said something earlier that I think is worth coming back to. When you take
a patient with type two diabetes, you take two patients with type two diabetes,
and you give one of them a lot of insulin and you give the other one not as much insulin.
One of them is going to have lower blood sugar than the other.
In the one with lower blood sugar, we see less microvascular disease. We see that they
have fewer amputations, less kidney disease, lower rates of impotence. Basically any tiny,
tiny blood vessel in their body does better when their glucose goes down. But if it came down
on the heels of insulin going up, we don't see a reduction in cardiovascular disease.
So why is it, in your opinion, that lowering glucose with more insulin does not reduce
cardiovascular mortality, which is so clearly tied to type two diabetes and post-prandial glucose?
This is the key issue. You know the answer to this is that insulin is the problem. Insulin is a
really super important hormone that Jason Fung and you had a really wonderful discussion about
this. But insulin ushers nutrients, fats, and glucose into cells to be burned. Or if you're not
in a burning mode right now, you're not exercising, you're sitting around sleeping,
it stores on its belly fat. So insulin is super important if you have type one diabetes. In type
two diabetes, I consider it the court of last resort. I mean, this is an obesity hormone.
Insulin and cortisol are the two obesity hormones. You want to get somebody fat, put them on insulin,
put them on prednisone. They will get belly fat like crazy. And I always felt sorry for these
diabetics. You know, the endos would be putting them on all this insulin. That'd be telling you
got to get your weight down. That's impossible. You cannot get your weight down when you're getting
a lot of exogenous insulin. You're hungry all the time. It causes weight gain. It causes fluid
retention. If anything, it accelerates atherosclerosis, you know, high insulin levels.
The key is low. You want to drive your insulin levels as low as, like your pulse. You want a nice
low insulin levels. They go up when you eat and then they go right back down. And the way you do
that is you exercise, you minimize belly fat, you eat a diet like we were just talking about.
You get no sugar. None of that easily digestible refined carbohydrates. You eat a lot of fiber,
a lot of low glycemic fruit, but more, more, more sort of non starchy vegetables. You eat modest
amounts of lean protein and a little bit of saturated fat. It don't hurt you. You eat a lot,
like 50% of your calories from unsaturated fats from those, you know, nuts and all the well and
avocados, guacamole and salmon and sardines and trout. And you will have, you know this from
wearing a glucose monitor. I've worn a glucose monitor for a while too, being non diabetic. I
find it a really great behavior modification thing. But when you eat that way, you don't see
your glucose go up at all. So when your glucose goes up, your insulin doesn't go up. And when
your insulin stays low, your vessels are happy. You're not putting on belly fat. We wrote an
article called, you know, insulin is a cardiotoxic medication. I mean, we want to minimize the
amount of insulin. Unfortunately, it's new, these new drug class, SGLT2 and impers,
GLP1 agonist. That's semaglutide and dulaglutide. There's a couple others. These two together,
along with metformin for diabetics, amazing drugs. They all lower insulin. They all reduce fat,
belly fat, and they all improve cardiovascular prognosis. And by the way, you know, a lot of
it has to do with the effect on insulin. Tell folks how the GLP1 agonist work.
We might as well round out that trifecta. Yeah. So GLP1 agonist work by supplying a
hormone that tends to wane and people as they develop type 2 diabetes. This is a hormone
that tells after you eat, it tells the pancreas to give a shot of insulin. And when you eat
a shot of insulin and when you're not eating, it also tells it shuts down glucagon production
in the liver. So you're making less glucose, gluconeogenesis when you don't need to be. And
that's one of the problem when you're eating this junky diet, you get these incretin levels,
get low, you get this gluconeogenesis. So you wake up in the morning, even after not eating for
eight or 10 hours and your glucose is high because you're making glucose when you don't need to be.
So this basically restores a hormone that is low and it sort of balances out, kind of
lowers fasting insulin and raises postprandial insulin and in-frit
and I'll combine it with SGLT2 inhibitors and non-diabetics. It works, reduces cardiovascular
risk. People on GLP1 agonists tend to complain of some when you first start it and when you
dose titrate it every week, some constipation and or nausea, but those go away with time.
And it is FDA approved for weight loss, isn't it? At least one of them is, right?
It is. One of them, liraglitide is sextenda, but it's a once a day drug. The semiglutide will be
approved in the next year as a once a week drug, the way we use it for diabetes and at a higher
dose, 2.4 milligrams rather than one milligram for the top dose. And it's shown it's just best
ever weight reduction and it's sort of an alternative to bariatric surgery for these
really overweight patients. Wow. I didn't realize that. So you're telling me that you can now take
a GLP1 agonist once a week with a sub-q injection and achieve comparable levels to the normal daily
injected routine? Because that's historically been one of the barriers. Better cardiovascular
reduction. It reduces heart attack, stroke, cardiovascular death better than the daily one,
the liraglitide. These are also revolutionary drugs, but the cool thing, they're very safe
otherwise. Whereas the SGLT2 inhibitors, you kind of reduce heart failure and renal failure
and overall cardiovascular mortality and all cause mortality in sicker people. This reduces more the
atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease. It has a stronger effect on MI stroke and those ruptured
plaques we were talking about at the beginning. They cause weight reduction from two different
mechanisms of action. They improve cardiovascular prognosis from two different mechanisms of action
and they really work well together. It's a phenomenal combination. Well, we can't have
a discussion about medications and cardiovascular disease without talking about statins, which
you've written about a lot. Certainly would have to be in the top three most prescribed
classes of medications out there. I'm kind of a five statin guy. There's a lot out there,
but there's probably only five that I'll use in patients. Every physician, I think who prescribes
these has their own little secret alchemy around it. When they're using Livolov versus
Prevostatin versus Crestor versus Lipitor, et cetera. Let's talk broadly about them as a class.
Obviously, a type of drug that inhibits the synthesis of cholesterol, which is its direct
action, but the money may come more from its indirect action, which increases the LDL receptor
on the liver. You're pulling that ApoB bearing particle out of circulation and you're having
this pretty pronounced effect in terms of LDL, C, and ApoB reduction. Second really now only to
PCSK9 inhibitors. Rather than talk about that, although I'm happy to hear your thoughts on that,
I want to talk a little bit more about the potential other benefits of statins because
I think this is where most people do believe there are pleiotrophic benefits of statins, but
they're harder to quantify. I'm curious as to what your thinking is on when you want to bring a
statin in. Is it also something you use in patients whose ApoB might not be that high,
but for whom you're looking for this other benefit?
The latest pleiotrophic effect, if you will, on statins is there was a study just this week
came out that people who are on statins seem to have some better resistance to severe COVID
infection. It may be that the people that get a lot of inflammation are the ones who are more
likely to have a bad outcome with a COVID infection, but in any event, they do have
anti-inflammatory effects. We use them a lot. I'm always arguing with my patients about statins.
They'll say, have you read about these things on the internet? I'll point out to them, in the
history of science, in the history of medicine and randomized trials, there's never been a class
of medications that have been so thoroughly tested in gold standard randomized placebo
controlled trials. Last thing you have to use, there's like 500,000, half a million people
in various randomized trials showing that if you have heart disease, or especially if you've had
cardiovascular event, they will help improve your prognosis. They reduce MLIs, stroke,
cardiovascular death, probably all cause mortality of high risk people.
Pause for one second, James. I agree with you completely. There is no drug, no class of drug,
I spend more time defending than statins. Why is that? Why is it that the internet is absolutely
crazy with this obsession that the statin is a drug planted here by foreign operatives
designed specifically to kill us? Yeah, it's crazy. It's a combination of things. Number one,
and I was kind of skeptical about this, but then I started taking the statin back about
when I was 45 and I had that calcium score. When I was working out hard, I wouldn't read,
like my muscles would hurt harder. They would ache worse after a hard workout.
Then I started taking constant Q10 and switched over to a more of a less potent one. Sure enough,
they got better. They frequently are associated with these nuisance side effects like muscle aches.
Some people swear that causes some brain fog, some sort of mild cognitive impairment.
But a lot of it too is sort of the no SIBO effect, the VUDU effect. They read about this and there's
all sorts of people trying to capitalize on selling people alternatives to statins.
That being said, I argue with people about statins who really need that. The 55-year-old just had
MI who tells me, I'll do anything but take a statin. Fortunately now, we do have other good options.
Zetimide lowers cholesterol by reducing absorption by blocking the neem and PIC receptor. PCSK9
inhibitors which just prolong the life of LDL receptors, both really elegant ways to lower
cholesterol by removing it from the circulation without poisoning the cells ability to make
cholesterol. That's really, really important. I know you were talking about the day spring about
that and I completely agree. We have an option for those people who are statin intolerant because
zetimide and PCSK9 inhibitor, they work synergistically like statins and PCSK9 inhibitors or
zetimide with statins. But for people who have a zero calcium score, who are at relatively low risk,
we do the mesa risk calculator or the ASCVD 10-year risk and they're under seven. Lots of times they're
one or two or three. It's hard to improve somebody who's got such a low risk. Then I say,
let's not get overly shook up about your LDL. You don't need to statin. We can stop your statin.
We don't need to start it, whatever. We'll focus on diet and extravital lifestyle. But
in middle-aged people, I need to see that zero calcium score or low calcium score to do that.
But yeah, statins are a wonderful tool. They're cheap and we use a lot of them, but we also
stop a lot of them. I'd be fascinated to hear this. I've thought about writing a paper on this
topic because there's nothing out there in literature, but you kind of touched on it on
one of your sessions. I think it was with Tom Dayspring that to the extent the statins do
sort of impair a cell's ability to make cholesterol, it does that not only in the liver that makes
mostly cholesterol, but it does that in the brain. People say it doesn't matter about getting
cholesterol too low because cells can, if your brain makes its own cholesterol, if it does,
if it needs it, if it's not poisoned, the HMG isn't poisoned by the statin. But if it is,
that gets into the brain and it can't make its own cholesterol. And when you look at
demented people, they have lipid depleted brains. There's shrunken brain. I mean,
there's a good study showing that omega-3 helps to keep your brain plucked, a high omega-3 diet.
And for that same reason, I have some sense that we might be better off using non-statin
approaches to lowering cholesterol, like PCSK9 inhibitors, omega-3, a Zeta-Mob, a good diet,
and other people that if we want to maximize sort of cognition and reduce Alzheimer's disease down.
Tom, of course, works very closely with us in our practice. And that's absolutely been our approach,
which of course puts us at odds with many of the people that are in the very strong
pro-heart camp, very organ-specific camp. We look at two markers of cholesterol synthesis,
desmosterol and lithosterol. We monitor them very closely. And there is a small body of literature
that says, at least in high-risk people, maybe people who carry one or two copies of an APOE4 gene,
that very low levels of desmosterol and or lithosterol in the presence of statins may be
a predictor of increased risk. And we just, in that situation, based on all the reasons you've
laid out, play to the precautionary principle. And frankly, our application of that is,
there's probably only two patients in my entire practice that are going to walk around with a
desmosterol below 0.5, because there are so many other options if we need them that we don't need
to overly suppress cholesterol synthesis. So only in the most high-risk cases of cardiovascular
disease when we have no real other options, then we do this. But otherwise, you're right. I mean,
we're incredibly liberal with the use of Zetia, and I think physicians are becoming more liberal
with that, which I think is great, coupled with, frankly, Prevostatin is my favorite statin,
if I can get the results there. You know, it's so mild. Also, anecdotally, it seems to produce less
symptoms. It also doesn't raise glucose the way, say, Atorvastatin or Prevostatin will,
and it doesn't increase risk of type 2 diabetes. And when you use it with a Zetimod, which, again,
we have a great study, the Utopia study, in primary prevention, Zetimod reduced cardiovascular
events by 30%. And then we also have the improvement study that showed that if you combine it with a
statin, it reduced cardiovascular events. So we have really good first-level evidence about a Zetimod.
The only thing I would disagree with you on, and disagree might be too strong a word, is tell you
how I think about things a little bit differently is I don't look at a 10-year risk calculator.
That's one area where in my practice, we just have to do things a bit different,
which means we have to deviate from guidelines, because I agree with you. Look, if a person's
10-year risk is 2%, and their calcium score is zero, but their APO B is at the 80th percentile,
the textbook answer is do nothing once you've exhausted all the lifestyle modifications.
My view on that is if you're 40 years old and your 10-year risk is zero, congratulations,
but I'm playing a different game, right? I'm really in this camp of Alan Snyderman that says,
we have to be taking a 30- and 40-year view of cardiovascular mortality. And that means I can't
look at a 10-year risk calculator. I have to take a longer arc. And sometimes that means primary
prevention is adding drug to treatment of all other variables, even if the calcium score is zero.
But again, that's a patient's decision based on their appetite for risk and their appetite
for longevity. So I completely agree. And we don't, at least I don't know of 30-year risk
calculator. So that calculator you're using is in your head. And I'm sure that's a very good
calculator. But one point I would make is that in those kind of people, and I would say myself
included, I don't take a statin. I haven't for years. I don't have a lot of risk factors, but
I did have a little bit of calcium when I checked it years ago. So I'm sure I have more now. Statins
will accelerate coronary calcification, by the way. So I use Zetimibe with a PCSK90 neighbor in
myself because it doesn't have any side effects. Neither of those have side effects. I mean,
rarely, rarely. And they work through very elegant mechanisms that don't distort your sort
of milieu of cholesterol homeostasis, whether it be in the brain or wherever. I mean, this is
just sort of making you as if you were genetically one of those gifted people that tends to run a
nice low cholesterol. Well, that's interesting. That's sort of where I've migrated almost. I'm
a low dose Prevostatin plus PCSK9 inhibitor. And I was thinking about doing the experiment of
switching from Prevostatin over to Zetia to see. And the reason for me is I had a calcium score of
six when I was 36. And that's in the presence of all the exercise and stuff. Now, I would
argue at the time my nutrition was horrible because it was a quote unquote traditional athletes diet
of a gallon of Gatorade a day or Powerade. That's the old athletes added, if you run the engine hot
enough, you can burn any fuel. But Peter, I would say, you said, calcium score of six when you were
36, despite your exercise, I would say maybe because when you're swimming 20 miles over,
you were hammering, hammering and really intense exercise will accelerate coronary calcification.
Yes, I have actually thought about that. And I repeated the calcium score in 2017. So that
would have made me 44 or whatever. It was zero. Wow. Now it's very interesting because as you know,
That was super rare by the way. Yeah, well, and I talked about this at length with Bob Peters,
who is, I think Bob Peters and Steve Wolf are hands down the best cardiac radiologists in New
York City. And so I had a CAC and CTA done with them, incredibly low radiation by the way,
2.2 milli sieverts for a CTA and CAC. And the question was, hey, is it an artifact when you
have a calcium score, go from six to zero, we just sort of missing it because there was still a little
blip in the endothelium of the LAD in that 2017 study, it just didn't register as a full calcium.
So, so I'll probably go back in a year and just repeat the CAC because I am curious.
The point is, like, even if there's a little calcium there, it's really, really unusual for
the calcium score to go anywhere up and usually goes up like 25, 30% a year or more with calcification.
So it's kind of like, we wish our investments, you know, like the compound interest, you know,
it really, it really can accumulate. But, and I'll have to say, I've probably read 150,000 calcium
scores in the last 20 years, because we've probably done 600,000 in our practice and we
do 50 or 60 of them a day. So, like, you virtually never see that. And now, granted, at that low
level, you know, you kind of nipped it in the bud with your better diet and, you know, probably,
you know, tapered your exercise, I don't know. But in any event, I saw a distinctly unusual
pattern of regression in a calcium score in a good friend of mine, who's an executive, we've been on
a statin for, you know, decades at a calcium score of like 1200, it had been going up, no diabetes,
but you know, it's obese. And we switched them over because have some eggs to a PCS canine in
Hebrew and a seven mile. And a calcium score a couple of three years, three years later,
had gone down from like 1200, I mean, from, no, it's like 1400, but it was like two or 300 lower,
you know, more than the margin of error of the test that made me think, you know, well,
number one statins do tend to increase corner of calcification, but I bet PCS canine inhibitors
don't. And certainly that anecdotal experience and I bet, I'll bet you Zetimov doesn't either.
So I saw an abstract, but I don't know if it ever made it to publication that actually
suggested PCS canine inhibitors decreased calcification.
That was my anecdotal experience.
Yeah. Now, of course, I don't know what that means because in the end,
I don't typically rescan patients. I'm a 50 year old who shows up with a calcium score of a hundred.
I have all the answer I need to know, which is we need to be way more aggressive. And there's
nothing I'm going to glean by rescanning you next year to find out your 120 versus 80. It will not
change our management.
And it just discourages, you know, somebody who's doing their best.
Yeah.
Very discouraging to think, and then you have to explain, well, you're on a medication that
does accelerate it, but it reduces your risk despite that because it's making the plaques
less prone to rupture. And I'm the same way. I rarely, the only time I increase it is people
who aren't doing the same right thing. They're not taking their medications or they're still
smoking or they're not exercising. Then I'll check and say, you know, it's gone up from a
thousand or 1300 or a hundred to 200. You know, you need to get on this, but the dirty little
secret is that it goes up in most people, but nonetheless, we can prevent cardiovascular events
with all these strategies we're talking about despite the coronary calcium.
I'm so happy to hear about what you're doing. A $50 CAC really at that point, when you can get
that level of a diagnostic test for less than the cost of a nice dinner, there's really no
barrier to entry.
And then those people that have a positive score, we get them over in our cardiometabolic clinic,
our cardiore wellness clinic. We have two different clinics, one focusing on the glucose
side of things and, you know, the SGLT2 inhibitors and the GLP1 agonist and metformin and weight loss,
and the other one on is just standard risk factors of lipids and whatnot. But we get them
plugged in and we see them two, three times a year. We make sure there's nothing like feedback,
right? You're a big fan on getting lipids tested and test these various markers, HSCRP, A1C,
you know, a lot of things we follow because when you know better, you do better and people need
feedback.
To round out our discussion on the pharmacologic tools, where are you on the high doses of EPA
versus EPA, DHA combined? Obviously these are becoming very popular tools in the toolkit.
Again, just at the pharmaco level, also at the supplement level, if you pick your supplements
right, how do you think about these in terms of heart health and brain health?
So again, you know, super enlightened question. And this is like one at the crux of some of the
most exciting stuff going on right now. So Omega 3, like we're talking about some other nutrients,
we're eating like maybe an order of magnitude less of that than what we did in our evolutionary
experience. Some people argue when we get access to shellfish and seafood is when our brain expanded,
you know, 300,000 or 400,000 years ago. So the Omega 3, you know, like 20% of the dry weight of
the brain is polyunsaturated fats and its favorite polyunsaturated fat to plug into those membranes
in the neurons is DHA. EPA is also, you know, another super important Omega 3. And a lot of
my patients come in and they stop their fish on the stop their Omega 3 because their doctor told
them, Oh, no, these don't work. And as you pointed out many times in your writings and whatnot is
even randomized controlled trials can be wrong, can be large and wrong if you're testing the wrong
people, if you're using the wrong dose. And a lot of those trials were done with small doses. And
these big meta-analyses, not to mention the reduced study, which recently tested the foregrounds of
EPA and people who had heart disease or diabetes with other risk factors, you test
in triglycerides above 150. So you test the right people, give them a nice robust dose,
and you see these spectacular results from a nutrient. And a lot of the reasons doctors
dismiss it is because again, we don't get taught anything about nutrition, we have an inherent
distrust that anything doing diet or supplements is worthless. And that is so untrue. And Omega 3
is exhibit A. So the latest meta-analysis, there was one just out in Mayo Clinic proceedings coming
out this coming week. I wasn't on this, but one of my best friends was Chippewa B from down in
Oschner. This is done with some Italian collaborators, but it's a really good meta-analysis
of all the randomized data with Omega 3. And they show for every gram per day of EPA, DHA
taken, you reduce risk of MR, cardiovascular death, and even trends towards all cause mortality.
But the point is, like a lot of the studies just use one gram, but if you use two, three, four grams,
you see these really remarkable, like in the reduced study, 25 to 30% reduction in cardiovascular
events and all cause mortality, even in people, especially if they have triglycerides above 150.
The question about whether it's EPA versus DHA, the evidence in that trial was EPA. But if you
look at the meta-analysis, as long as you're getting that dose of EPA and DHA, I think it's
important to have some DHA in the supplement too, just because again, it's important for the
membranes. And our evolutionary experience would suggest we weren't just using EPA,
using the combination. I'll tell you, I agree with you completely on that. And this is,
I put this in the category of things I can't wait to learn. I mean, sometimes I just get excited
about the state of natural knowledge and how it continues to evolve. And I can't wait to see five
years from now what we know on this question, because I was a bit surprised by the combined
EPA, DHA trial. I really expected that to be a favorable response, especially in light of what
we saw in the four gram EPA visepa trial. So again, we just have to see where this thing goes,
but I agree with you. That was the strength trial you were talking about.
That's right. That was halted early. Yeah. So it might be that four grams of EPA in that
concentrated form is the way to go in a super high risk person for cardiovascular disease,
but a combination of EPA and DHA through food, oily fish, as you said, might be what's conferring
the real benefit. That's how we got it in nature. I think the broader question always comes to,
is there a harm of higher doses of EPA and DHA? And I feel very confident now that the answer to
that question is no, provided you're getting your product through a clean source. I think the answer
is no. And so we have zero affiliation with any companies that produce any of these products.
And we had a third party do a validation of Carlson's, which is the one that we have preferred
for our patients. And we found it to be pure without contaminant and it contained what it
said it contained. So I'm always happy to pay that little bit of a premium for that product
to at least get an over the counter version. That's, that's good. So, so I don't have to sort
of fork over for a prescription version. Yeah. I'm the chief medical officer for a company called
Cardiotabs. We, you know, I don't get paid anything from them, but that's kind of my goal
with them too. And we also source it from Norway. They know more about purifying, concentrating,
detoxifying Omega-3 than anybody in the world, as far as I'm concerned, and usually go over to
Scandinavia there and visit with the leaders in that just to see what their latest and greatest
stuff is. But yeah, this is a food and I think it's, it's super important, not only for cardiovascular
health, but Peter, the latest data on mental health is, is really important. Again, this is
a fundamental component of cell membranes that most Americans, upwards of like 90%
of Americans aren't getting enough Omega-3 in their diet. And it correlates with depression,
ADHD, suicide, cognition, dementia, all those things. I mean, this is like an super easy way
to markedly improve mental health. My wife, Joanne is constantly harping on this,
that, you know, there's all this violence and suicide and depression. And like, the basic
thing to do is take a nice high dose of Omega-3 every day. It's harmless, it's cheap, and it has
profound benefits. And lots of times you can keep people off of, off of antidepressant medications
that in a, like a well-absorbed curcumin with high dose Omega-3 is as good as any or better than any
antidepressant out there. And they also have to improve brain function. And again, your doctor
won't prescribe these, but these are very, very effective ways to improve mood, cognition, and
probably reduce dementia in the long run. We have a paper coming out, I sent you a copy of it,
the journal Alzheimer's disease showing that, that a highly absorbable curcumin,
a theory curamen in a randomized trial. The study was a TNF-alpha inhibition for preventing dementia
and TNF-alpha, as you know, is this master hormone of inflammation. And there's some really
fascinating, which we outlined in this sort of systematic review, that the biologics that reduce
TNF-alpha, like a Tanner-cept is the best one. It's a decoy receptor for TNF-alpha. And so it reduces
inflammation. And there's multiple big studies of millions of people in databases that's all
observational data, but that it reduces risk of Alzheimer's disease 60 to 70%. Now those are
expansive biologics that sometimes can cause serious side effects, but curcumin is the activity
of turmeric. And if you use a highly absorbed one, you get some pretty impressive reductions in TNF-alpha
that have been correlated in small randomized trials with reduction. And there's good animal
models on this too. I mean, it's one of the most exciting things to me right now is I really think
this is easily the most exciting thing ever for maintaining cognition, preventing Alzheimer's
disease. And it still needs to be flushed out, but there's some very good biological plausibility
behind it and some fascinating animal data, human data, and even some small randomized trials.
You know, working with Richard Isaacson, who I've interviewed for this podcast, and I'll be
interviewing again shortly, we've sort of put together our in-house kind of playlist for
basically once we identify patients that we deem high risk for Alzheimer's disease, which
we define as age over 60, a relative that has a history of Alzheimer's disease, or at least one
copy of an APOE4 gene, or some other gene such as an anti-TNF gene or Tom40, or one of these other
genes that tends to be associated with Alzheimer's disease plus or minus APOE4. We just have sort of
a full court press approach. And one of the things on that list is indeed thermocumen for exactly the
reasons you've stated. I became pretty impressed with those data about two years ago. And so I was
excited when you sent over that manuscript last week. So you noticed that Richard Isaacson was a
co-author on that paper as was Gary Small from UCLA, who's in my opinion, those guys are two top
brain scientists in the country for things like preserving cognition. So yeah, I mean, I think
that the people who are best informed on that would agree with you on that approach.
You know, I guess closing thought, James, is I'm just impressed by the breadth of your
curiosity and obsession. You know, again, interventional cardiology is a niche sport,
right? It's a, you know, you're a cath jockey at that point. And you sort of left that behind,
and the world has become your oyster, so to speak. And you're now interested in the role that
Theracuman can play in inhibiting tumor necrosis factor in the development of dementia. I mean,
do you ever kind of look back and reflect on the journey of your career? I'll pause there
before asking another question. I just followed my heart and what I was most interested in and
I like to joke that, I mean, I'd be doing the same thing right now if I wasn't getting paid. I mean,
I love what I do. And I think of life as, you know, like this gift of we have our time here
on earth and it's about like helping others and making a positive difference. And I'm just so
grateful that we live now where we have all these tools. And like you say, it's just so exciting.
There's all this emerging data for people who are trying to pay attention. It kind of like that line
from Dickens was it was the best of times, it was the worst of times. You know, there's a lot of
people out there that, you know, suffering from all sorts of terrible things. A lot of it's
lifestyle related and it's not their fault. I mean, it's like this whole world is set up to
minimize activity and maximize calorie consumption. But there's also people who are paying close
attention and we have all these powerful tools and use this information to help each other
and to live not only longer, but more sort of active and fulfilling and enjoyable lives. So
to me, it's just a blast. My last question then, James, would be,
if there's somebody listening to this who wants to go into medicine and feels or is in medicine
for that matter and kind of feels the same conviction you do, which is the real answer
is in preventing disease and whether that's their passion is in cancer or cardiovascular disease or
neurodegenerative disease, diabetes, whatever the case might be, you know, you said it at the outset,
nobody's reimbursing really for prevention. You've got to kind of create your own path.
What would your advice be to somebody who wants to become a preventative oncologist,
a preventative cardiologist, a preventative neurologist? How would you advise them to craft
their way? Well, that's a difficult question, but I can just tell you that it doesn't have to be all
or nothing, you know, even like the calf jockeys, like they say, you know, some of my partners are
calf jockeys, they're very enlightened about lipids. And you don't necessarily have to do it
all the time, but you need to be able to be well versed enough to strongly endorse it. And I mean,
I'm in a big group of 65 cardiologists with another 50 nurse practitioners or physicians
assistants. And so I can kind of carve out that niche and live there most of the time, although
I still ride in the hospital and that sort of thing. But in the future, this is going to be an
increasingly important part of medicine. People are going to understand, you know, they'll pay a
lot to have their life optimized, not only for longevity, but also for enjoying life and being
fully functional. And I think it's never been a better time to get interested in prevention.
It's just, it's a lot of blue sky out there and a lot of promising therapies and lifestyles and
strategies that we can deploy now. I've enjoyed this discussion immensely, as is the case with
virtually every podcast. I learn at least one thing. And in this one, I've learned many things
that I can't wait to take back to my patients and frankly to myself. So thank you for your
generosity and thank you for continuing to mentor me. I've considered you both a friend and teacher
for many years now. And I look forward to that continuing. Thanks for the opportunity,
Peter. It's really my honor to be on your show. Thank you for listening to this week's episode
of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created
a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying
on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription.
Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive
podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode.
The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me
anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast
feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The
Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting
the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to peteratiamd.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise. Please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.