Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Dr. BJ Miller. BJ is a hospice and palliative care
specialist. We talk a lot about what that means. The reason I wanted to speak with BJ is I've been
really thinking a lot about better understanding what end of life means and how understanding the
end of life could help us better understand, frankly, what we want out of life. And by an
amazing coincidence, BJ and I met very, very briefly many years ago in medical school,
although I don't think he remembers it. But when I saw him again giving a TED talk several years
ago, I immediately realized, hey, that's the guy I met at a party 20 some odd years ago and became
really interested in his work and then reached back out to him and said, hey, would you be
interested to sit down and talk about this? And so in this discussion, we talk a lot about his
personal story because you can't really avoid it. And frankly, his personal story is a big part of
why he ultimately chose the life path he did, which is doing something that many of us,
including people who go into medicine would find just too difficult to do, which is basically help
patients die as a means to reach this culmination of their life. We get into all sorts of things,
the difference between death and dying, the difference between palliative care and hospice,
the differences between loss and regret, what the medical system that we're a part of is good at and
what it's not so great at. We talk about what really happens at the end of life, how enlightened
or transcendent is it? And he tells a number of stories that are quite moving about patients and
also from his own life. And finally, we conclude with a discussion on both the hastening of death
and also what he's most optimistic about, including the use of psychedelics. This is another one of
those episodes that I think people at the surface might think, gosh, I don't really have an interest
in that. I would encourage you to push through that. I think it's natural to find this topic
unpalatable. And I think that's exactly why people need to listen to this.
So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with BJ Miller.
Hey BJ, it's a real honor to be sitting down with you, even though we're not in person together.
Thank you, Peter. I appreciate you having me, but I'm looking forward to this.
Now, I don't know if you remember this. In fact, you can't have remembered this because
I'm not memorable in the way that you are, but we've met a few times at parties in medical school.
You went to UCSF and I went to Stanford. And I don't know if we were the same class,
but we were pretty close. What year did you matriculate at UCSF?
Ninety-seven.
So we were the same class. And I don't recall you guys ever coming down to Palo Alto,
but we sure as hell went up to San Francisco a lot.
For social reasons or for school?
No, just for social reasons.
Oh yeah.
We just had friends in common and stuff like that. And so it's almost 25 years ago. And I remember,
one of the things that stood out was you had a dog, right?
What was your dog's name? I don't remember.
His name was Vermont, like the state.
I got it.
Yeah. Wow. I'm so psyched you remember him, Peter. He was a huge part of my life. I can
tell you that's beautiful.
So I will admit something, BJ, which is that I never had the nerve to come up to you and say,
hey, what happened?
Because it wasn't subtle, right?
Yeah, no, it's pretty, it's pretty pleadingly obvious. Yeah.
So as I would learn later, your life changed shortly after Thanksgiving in 1990, right?
That's right. You got it, bud. Yep.
And that change, which I think on the surface would sound like a change for the worst,
maybe wasn't for the worst after all. Can you tell folks what happened that night?
Yeah. I mean, it was a big moment in my life as you're pointing to Peter. Yeah. I mean,
and there's a lot to talk about it. So I'll try to just kind of parlay the basic facts and then
we can talk about any of it. So just back from Thanksgiving holiday, and I was very happy to see
my friends. We were all kind of that early college. We were basically in love. We couldn't wait to see
each other. Being away for Thanksgiving break was a bummer, really. So anyway, we got running back
and we immediately decided to go, a handful of us would go out and have a drink and just run
around. I was actually on my way to the computer lab to print a paper when it kind of got intercepted
and off we ran to go have some fun. Nothing crazy. It was, we didn't go nuts though, but we were
heading to the Wawa Market, which on the East coast is sort of like a 7-11. Late, open all night,
place to get a sandwich, kind of joint chips or whatever. Anyway, so we're walking to the Wawa
Market and this is at Princeton University where there's a commuter train that runs right up along
campus because Princeton is sort of a bedroom community for New York and Philly. So this
commuter train was called the Dinky of all things. It was just sitting there, not operating hours.
So I was just sitting there and we stumbled across it and just decided to climb on top of it, just
relatively innocently for things we had done, but felt much stupider. But anyway, we decided to jump
on top of it, climb the ladder, just stand up on it like you would a jungle gym or a tree or
something. And when I got up on top of the train, I had a metal watch on and the electricity art to
the watch when I stood up because I got close enough to the line. And that was that. Electricity
entered the arm, my left arm, and then ground down. And eventually there's a big explosion
and whatever else. And that was that. I survived that, but ended up losing both legs below the knee
and that one arm below the elbow, very touch and go in the burn unit and living through New Jersey,
St. Barnabas Hospital for, I don't know, maybe a month or so. Then I was in there another month
in the burn unit and then eventually out of there and into rehab. And then a long process of
reentering the world. But anyway, that was my big, the thing I call the cosmic spanking, that big,
big moment that just came along and completely reoriented me, changed things around.
Do you remember the actual shock or is that sort of so traumatic? A lot of times trauma patients,
for example, when they're hit by cars or sustain a significant gunshot wound, especially if it's
followed by a prolonged period in the ICU, they suffer some antigrade amnesia. So they forget
things in front of them, not so much behind them. But a lot of times that includes the actual event.
So what is the last thing you remember? Do you remember actually climbing up on the train?
I don't know. I remember the night is all very fuzzy. I remember sort of snippets from the hours
proceeding, but I don't have any recollection of approaching the train or getting on top of it.
This is just pieced together through stories from my friends who are with me. But the first memory I
have around the accident itself that night, I can picture a lot of it again because my friends have
told me, but my own memory really began in the hospital that night. I was taken to the local ER
where they just did basic things that are called fasciotomies, which as you know, with electrical
burns, you burn from the inside out. So you've got all this heat running around in your system
and it'll keep burning you. So they've got to vent that heat. Basically the local ER, they cut
these fasciotomies to vent me and then stuck me in a helicopter to go to the New Jersey's one burn
unit at St. Barnabas. I can remember being loaded into the helicopter vaguely. I was very
tall. I was almost six five and I just remember the pilots. There's this awkwardly trying to get
me into the cockpit because I was too long. So all the amputations I had were surgical. So at that
night my legs were burned. I still had them. So then you get to a burn unit and you're with
now a team of doctors and nurses who have seen the worst of things for what it's worth, just as
a bizarre coincidence in general surgery, which is what I went to do after medical school. You
rotate through all the different disciplines of surgery. It's quite random. You'll spend a month
on this, a month on that, a month on all of these different things. And my very first month of
internship was in the burn unit. I had never done any of that during medical school. So to show up
on day one at sort of the premier burn unit of Maryland, which basically meant it was the referral
center. So if you got burned in Pennsylvania, you were still coming down to Hopkins. I mean,
it was another world. You got it. I mean, it was very difficult to get used to doing
dressing changes on patients and just seeing the amount of pain people were in when they suffered
these burns. And the other thing that was remarkable, at least to me, was how otherwise
alive people could look when they came into a burn unit, but yet how poor their prognosis could be
based on the amount of surface area that was burned. We basically had actuarial tables that
would say, well, he has this much of third degree and this much of second degree. And even though
he's sitting here actually able to even communicate with us, this person has a very high likelihood
of not surviving this injury. Yep. It's interesting that you say that because one of the early
memories would piece together for me by a nurse with whom I became very close was when I landed
in the bay at the burn unit, this was not uncommon, but apparently the techs and the team were sitting
around basically taking wages on whether I was going to make it. It's probably based on very
much the same kind of what you were just describing. That sounds kind of harsh, but I'm sure it wasn't.
I think that was just, as you know, these things can depersonalize the net setting almost by
necessity. It's a brutal setting. But anyway, we can talk more about that. But I'm in a way
glad to know that you know what a burn unit is like. It is an other world that I've always
struggled to impart to people what it's actually like in there. It is a wholly unnatural place.
I mean, nature is completely kept at bay. Yes. And there's a reason that it's very separate.
I mean, in small hospitals, they do what they can. And I'm sure they don't have dedicated burn
units. But at tertiary care centers, they have dedicated ICUs that are exclusively for burn
patients that don't take other medical or surgical or neuro or pediatric cases. And it's also a very
special type of nurse that works there and a special type of doctor because everything from the,
frankly, just at times the grotesque nature of the disfiguration of the skin, these dressing
changes that we talk about doing several times per day on a patient, they require incredible
sterility at the bedside. Frankly, in the early days, early days of the patient's admission,
even the smell of burn tissue is a very foreign odor to people. So everything about it, it places,
by the way, everything I've said says nothing to what the patient and their family must be
experiencing as they're coming to grips with this. So when did your parents arrive? I'm sure you
don't remember it, but based on the stories, they came almost my poor parents, man, that they got
the classic in the middle of the night, they were in Chicago where I grew up at the time. So they
get a call from New Jersey at 4am or something ridiculous. And basically, not a lot of information,
just everything was emergent and scary. And basically, your son's here with us. He's very
badly injured, might not make it through the night, get here as soon as possible. Basically,
one of those calls. So my parents were there as quickly as could be the next morning, to your
point about this place. So what they've learned, burn treatment science is that infection is very
often the thing that kills people, hence all the sterility. So someone might look just fine, but
they're so exposed, their body is so exposed, that you're so susceptible. So that means whoever's in
your room, they're in spacesuits and whatever else. And for a while, I was not allowed many
visitors. There were friends who had come, but they couldn't come in to burn in it. Eventually,
they allowed my parents at the bedside, one at a time. That was it. But it was really powerful,
very potent visits. I remember them very well, as did my parents. As you describe your experience
as a student, as a trainee, it's not much different because it's such a foreign exotic environment
that works against intuition a lot of ways. The things that touch, for example, something you have
to avoid at all costs, smells, everything is foreign. There's just no place to rest into it
familiar. You can imagine if that was that way for you as a student, trainee. It was certainly
that way for myself and my parents. But in a way, too, that foreignness and by virtue of me being so
undeniably vulnerable, I was not moving. I was completely at their mercy. In a way, it allowed
me to very quickly submit to the place and to the people working there because I clearly had
nothing approaching an option. Very quickly, I was aware of my vulnerability and immediately
trusted the people working on me in a way because I had to, but also as a comment of how skillful
they were at their work. Do you remember the actual discussion you had with the doctors about
the need for amputation? Because obviously, when the fasciotomies are performed initially,
it's with the hope of salvaging the limbs. Presumably, at some point, they came to the
realization that trying to salvage the limbs was actually going to threaten your life due to
infection. They had to go. I've been around those discussions. Do you remember that?
I do. I do. I do. My first memory, real vivid memory besides that helicopter moment was the
night before my initial amputations. The part I remember about it, which was maybe five or six
days in, Peter, that's when I was hemodynamically stable enough. More to the point, the demarcation
of viable tissue versus unviable tissue was a little bit more obvious. Surgeons had a fighting
chance to remove the right amount. Dr. Mansour was the main surgeon, an amazing, amazing person.
I remember he came in the night before and said something. All I remember is an A conversation.
Then I remember falling asleep. I fell asleep in my little room. Somehow, you know that feeling,
Peter, where you wake up from a dream and there's a moment of reorienting yourself and maybe it
wasn't a very pleasant dream. You take a little second and you get your bearings and you go,
oh, it's just a dream. Thank God. The classic thing is people show up taking an exam naked or
something. They're late for their wedding or some moment and you wake up and oh, thank God,
that was a dream. I remember I woke up in the burning and having that sensation. Strangely,
I remember I looked around and I had this weird feeling like, oh, this whole amputation thing
that I was just hearing about was a dream. Oh, I'm fine. Got to go to the bathroom. I, in my haze,
just managed to extubate myself. Not an easy thing to do. Extubate myself, pull my central
lines out of my neck, unstrap my arm from the bed. All the while, I can remember this so clearly.
I'm looking around my room with all these cues that obviously I'm not in my bedroom. For some
reason, I'm just thinking, oh, yeah, this is my room. I'm just going to go to the bathroom now.
I got up and out of bed eventually and started walking to the door with all these alarms going
off in the middle of the night. Somehow, I don't know where the nurses were, but there was a gap
there. I started walking to the door just to take a leak on my crispy little feet. The Foley catheter
line ran out. As you know, they're usually attached to the bed. When that line ran out,
it yanked on that Foley. That's a pain that I won't soon forget. That catheter ball was not
deflated. We can explain this for your listeners. Anyway.
I was just about to say, we're going to hit pause and explain everything you just said.
But let's start with the extubation. You have a tube that is in your airway and a machine that
is breathing for you. The act of pulling that out means you now have to breathe on your own,
something you have not been doing for the previous week. That alone could have killed you.
Yeah, right.
You then pulled out a bunch of central lines, which if not compressed, so central lines are
very, very long intravenous lines that go into the main veins inside your body, veins that most
people don't even realize they have called the vena cava subclavian vein, et cetera. To pull those
out without the appropriate protocol of compression could also lead to internal hemorrhage and all
sorts of crazy things. You're dodging death. You're three for three on this.
Yeah. Yes. In retrospect, I smile almost with pride because it feels sounds so daring. I mean,
obviously, the time I had no freaking idea what I was doing. But now it sounds-
You're unkillable.
Yeah.
Right. But then the thing that finally gets you is a catheter about the size of an HB pencil
that is in your urethra up to your bladder, which stays in place with a balloon that's dilated to
the size of a very large gumball. And said gumball prevents the catheter from ever coming out. And
before we take these catheters out of the urethra, which is by itself unbearable, I myself have had
one, we have to deflate the ball because trying to pull a gumball sized device out of the urethra
would be tantamount to torture. But of course, you just went ahead and through the force of walking
towards the door, basically removed your own Foley catheter minus the balloon removal.
You're still alive, but all of a sudden that dream-
But not happy.
Yeah. It is amazing that you're right, that you must have done this all very quickly
to make it happen. So now you're sort of having that moment of maybe that wasn't a dream.
Mm-hmm. I will never forget this. It was a clarity, that world, all the haze cleared up
instantly when I felt that Foley dislodged from the bladder. But incidentally, it didn't come all
the way out. So it's somewhere halfway-
Which is even worse.
Yeah. It was just terrifying. So I immediately fall to the floor and I'm screaming and now a nurse
comes in. I don't know what the delay was. Incidentally, that poor nurse, we never saw her.
She was never assigned to my room again. Poor thing. Part of her explanation, she was avoiding
my room. She admitted in some ways because she had a son my age and looked just like me. And it was
really hard for her. Anyway, so eventually, so I'm on the floor now screaming, trying to break the
catheter line, which is impossible. But it's the only way I could, I thought I could break the
tension. But anyways, they came in, got me back in bed and all that stuff. And away it went. But
to your question, Peter, it was instantaneous that I realized this wasn't a dream. And all the
relief that had just I had experienced moments ago in the other direction just immediately went away.
And I was very, very clear on where I was and what was happening to me. Instantaneously, it was a
wild, wild moment. I won't soon forget.
So what kind of a mourning process did you go through post-operatively when you come out with
both of your legs amputated and your left arm?
Short answer is my mourning process took me a while. And my conscious mourning process was
delayed because I at that time embodied the sort of absorb the American notion that no,
what you do is you pick yourself up, you get back on the horse immediately. The less you acknowledge
what's gone on, the better. The tougher you are, the faster you'll be functional again, et cetera.
So early on, I didn't do any mourning, not consciously. I was kind of going the other
direction, joking around, making light of it. And both the moment of somewhat of denial and also
probably something pretty poignant too. I remember when I came out of that first surgery,
so I didn't know that there were people, I knew my parents were there. And oddly, Peter, I don't
know how this was possible. But my parents moved into the hospital. Somehow they got a room in the
hospital from Chicago. They lived there all the time I was there. I don't know how the hell that
never heard of that, but they did. Maybe they had huge wings of St. Barnum's that weren't being
used. I'm not sure. But I knew my parents were there. So I come out of the OR, come out and I'm
heading, they're wheeling me back. The leg amputations were what they did first. And I knew
whatever the cases I had absorbed, what Dr. Mansoor told me the night before eventually,
I woke up from that surgery with no surprises. But I'm wheeling back to my room. And there's a
brief moment where you're going from the OR suites back into the burn units, and you go
to this little hallway. And I come out, it was packed with people. My friends and some friends
had flown in from Chicago. I was so moved. I had no idea that they were there. And it was just a
brief second. There was no time to talk, but there was just a lot of love. I just remember
their facial expressions. I was very, very moved. And then I went back into the room and I remember
my mom came in and we were sitting and she was crying. And my mom had polio. She'd been disabled
my whole life, most of her life. And I just remember, this is going to sound, I don't know,
it was part denial driving it. But I just remember my thought when my mom came in was,
my response to her was, oh, mom, well, now we have so much more in common. Now we're both disabled,
almost like a cheeriness. I love my mom very much. We're very close. And I honestly felt
like I was joining this ranks of folks that I always knew existed and felt very much a kinship
with the disabled community by virtue of being close with my mother. My first response was weird
kind of immediate acceptance, but I had to go back and it wasn't a thorough acceptance. It was
where I wanted to be, but it wasn't really where I was. But anyway, that was my first statement.
It took really weeks. It took actually my nurse kind of trying to work on their member time,
maybe a week or two later where one of the nurses with whom I was very, very close,
Joy Varkada-Pone. And Joy came in one day and she was just really moody with me. She was just
like throwing, she was just strangely moody. And I was just sort of joking around. And anyway,
she's like throwing bedpanes around. It's like, Joy, what the hell? What is, what's wrong? What
are you okay? And she's just basically lit in me. She's like, I'm just sick and tired of you not
taking this seriously. You're just joking around. You haven't even cried. This is a big, big deal.
You're not being real. And she just let into me. She let into me until I finally cried. It was the
first time I cried. I was weeks in. It was the most magical thing, Peter. I will never forget
that one either. In part because there was like a dam had broke and so much came pouring out.
And it felt so good. It felt like such a relief. I hadn't realized. I hadn't consciously fought
back tears or tried to be tough. I just thought that's what I was supposed to be doing. And I
was otherwise on autopilot too. But what was also weird about those tears was for the moments,
the tears were falling. I had really no physical pain. I've never looked into this, but I wonder
what the connection is between the act of crying, not just feeling sad, but actually crying and
anesthesia. It was a fascinating moment, but it really moved me. And it began my relationship
with a began letting in that this was a bigger deal than I had managed to let it be. I offer that to
say the morning, the grieving was very gradual. Took me a while to wake up to my own feelings
about it all. That took months and years really. Do you think that that was mostly a sadness and a
loss that came through expectation of these are things I wanted to do that I will no longer do.
And I am sad as a result of that. Or do you think it was tears from a different sadness, a sadness
that's more born of anger? Like how could this have happened? It's such a random event. I've done
far stupider things in my life. Like why was I wearing that watch? You can sort of go through
all those things. Like do you have a sense of where you were in terms of that damn, the floodgates
opening? Yeah, yeah. My sense is Peter, it's a sense driven by most of where, how grief materialized
for me over the months and years. But my sense is for a number of reasons, I did not have
a lot of why me moments. And there's a lot to say about that. But to answer your question,
no, I think it was more like, first of all, the physical pain. I hadn't really let myself,
I had just been literally gritting my teeth. And for as vulnerable as I felt, as so exposed as I
felt, I was looking for anywhere where I could look or feel or act or present as strong. And
this is the only way I could think of I think was to kind of keep this stuff in. And so I think
part of it was a release around just a physical pain. And I think the rest of it, it didn't have
a lot of clarity around the object of my sorrow. But the sorrow I really think was had to do with
embarrassment for doing this for ending up here, putting my parents through so much pain, I could
see it in their faces, slowly began to see what it did to friends too and others around me.
It's the feeling I think a lot of the pain or a lot of the tears had to do with here I was taking
so much from so many people. I was embarrassed about that and ashamed about that. I think that
was a big part of it. And I think there was also an image I had just kind of come into my body as
a 19 year old. And I think there was a sadness. I didn't know if I would ever have sex again,
what women were going to think of me, what my friends would think of me, I'd been around
disability my whole life. And I've watched how cruel people could be and the projections they
make. And I think part of it was the more tears that I knew what I was going to be walking into
with that. I think yeah, all of those things, but low, low, low on the list Peter were the why me
questions. I know a lot of that to the prep work that my mother, my family life had said it,
it was always much more the question of why not me? If anything, I felt guilty for having too
perfect a life before that. Separate from all of this BJ, there's another kind of really
transformative event in your life that has to do with your sister. When did that take place?
So that was 10 years later. So that was. So you're in medical school. Yeah, exactly. And I want to
come back to how you got to medical school, but can you tell me a little bit about your sister
and the relationship you had with her in the 10 years that followed this and then ultimately
her demise? It's a good segue. It's a lick of the way I grew up was I was no stranger to pain.
I was around it. And there are all sorts of reasons to feel like that life was inherently hard. And
that was something about I felt almost a perversion that I could feel happy ever. That felt that
almost felt wrong. I don't know how to explain it, but part of my growing up was growing up with
a sister. I have one sibling, Lisa. Lisa was four years older than I am. Wild, brilliant,
fascinating, just intense person. And our whole family life so much centered around her and her
moods and her thoughts. So I was enamored with Lisa. She was my older sister. She seemed so smart
to me. She had emotions around things that I hadn't even thought of. And she had these developed
psychological, emotional responses. I just felt like she must have insights in the world that I
just couldn't see. And she had such conviction. And she was harsh, harsh, harsh, harsh. That
conviction, older sister I wanted, I aspired to her. So I chased her moods around. Anything she
told me I took at face value. I mean, she owned me in so many ways as her younger brother. And she
was very troubled. And part of my adulthood was coming in to realize that Lisa wasn't just full
of conviction. Lisa was also full of some other things. And so in my twenties, here I am going to
med school, I'm finally learning to have some separation from chasing my sister's moods around.
And then in December, December 1st of 2000, roughly almost exactly 10 years after my injuries,
Lisa decided to kill herself. Lisa decided to leave the planet. So yes, that was another,
one of the major, major life events for me. And that was deep into medical school. And one of
the things that precipitated my deciding to leave medicine, I was going to get out of medicine at
that point. No, I didn't know that actually. Yeah. I want to come back to this. Can we talk
for a moment though, just to make the connection of how you ended up deciding to go into medicine,
because when you were in your freshman year at Princeton, I get the impression that medicine
wasn't even on your radar, correct? Yeah, that's right. You got it. Yeah. No interest. That even
crossed my mind. Yeah. So after returning to Chicago, going through a very lengthy process
of rehabilitation, you re-enrolled at Princeton a full year later, correct? Almost. Yeah. The
following fall. So I went back in September of 1991. And you changed your major to art history.
Is that also correct? You got it. Yep. Why did you do that? I had been there to for, that's a word.
I had been studying Chinese language and was heading for a major in East Asian studies.
But when I was away, when I was in that, the burn unit, it's like a torture chamber interspersed
with incredible boredom. You're just so, and this was so wild. When I look back on these, I'm sorry,
I'm just a quick digression. So this was the first Gulf War was happening. It was so strange. I was
watching a war, remember it was like a televised war. Such a wild thing, bored stiff, in horrible
pain to and from that tank room for daily deep readment. So horrible pain interspersed with
slight relief and boredom. No touch with it. There's not even a window. It's such a weird
thing. And I would toggle between on the television between watching the war and some cooking show.
It was just the strangest, I don't know why I bring that up. It was just how I spent my days.
But now I forgot your question, brother. What were you asking me about?
The decision to change to art history. Oh, golly. How did I get to that? But anyway,
well, I know because I'm sitting in this bed, bored stiff. And of course, even with my little
structures that were still in place that kept me from crying or acknowledging a lot of things,
of course, there was no getting around some stuff. And I was beginning to let into my consciousness
and my daily thinking, like, you know, sort of preparing, imagining my life down the road.
When am I going back to school? Will anyone want to be friends with me?
But I'm basically bottom line is I'm sitting there very much pondering the value of my life.
What am I now? Am I less of a person? Do I have less to offer the world? What will people see in
me wanting me? I know. So basically questions of meaning and questions of identity. Who am I?
What do I do with myself now? What can I do? I found myself in that mix, just sitting there
pondering questions like the meaning of life, not in a recreational or intellectually kind of Ivy
Leaguey write a term paper way, but in a way that was very obviously relevant and therapeutic and
practical. These existential issues became very practical. And I that's where they belong, by the
way, I think. So sitting there, one of my friends and closest friend Justin would come visit me at
the burn unit eventually. And we find ourselves talking about art is this thing that humans do.
So I was looking for meaning making what humans how humans work with pain, how do humans work
with things they can't control. And that led me to thinking about art, why do human beings make art?
Why do we take the material of our life and create with it and fashion something from it
that wasn't there before but now exists thanks to us? It's kind of a stunning impulse that human
beings have, whether you're making art that's going to hang in a museum or you're just futzing
around your house. We are a very creative species. That was lighting up for me as a very important
and telling and that maybe, maybe the art world had something to teach me. So when I went back
to college that fall, I rejoined my class, I just had to finish the exam somewhere in the summer,
and I had a free semester. I was supposed to be in China the second semester of sophomore year
anyway. I didn't have to do much to jump back in with my class. And that was very important to me.
I wanted to be back with my buddies. That was a real driver. So anyway, I head back to Princeton,
join my class and change my major to art history to studying art. And that was a really consequential
decision when I'm actually very proud of. I've talked about it before on this show. I think
it's even come up during a discussion where someone asked, what's the best major that I
would recommend for someone who wants to go into medicine? And I don't have great insight on this,
but the one thing I generally suggest is anything other than pre-med. Because I think whether you
study art history or engineering or a foreign language and a foreign culture, you're probably
going to get something out of it that you would never get if you studied pre-med, yet most of
everything you study in pre-med, you're going to pick up in medical school. Which is not to say
that studying pre-med is not a good idea, but that's my two cents is that the people who came
in with totally different backgrounds often were people who didn't actually plan on going into
medicine as is the case in yours. The stories are usually pretty interesting. So when in the journey
of art history, do you then realize you want to make what I think is even probably a greater
stretch or leap, which is to actually go to medicine?
Yeah. So let me first see your two cents and raise a mind. Unless we want medicine to simply be
the stuff of technicians, of technical pursuit, which of course it is in many, many ways.
I teach in med school. I haven't as much lately, but I've spent a lot of time teaching in schools
of medicine and nursing and love it, love it, love it, love it. And if we view medicine
as a technical pursuit simply then okay, pre-med, focus, great. But the trick is of course in
medicine is our job is not just to, it's one thing to know details about molecules, how they work,
but it's a very different thing to know why it's amazing to have molecules in the first place. And
if you have not thought one way or another, it doesn't have to be art. It doesn't even have to
be through school per se, but you better find a way that if you're going to go into the healing
professions, the clinical professions, you better find a way to delve into why life is amazing and
horrifying. Why is it so hard to let go of? Why is it so hard to love life when you know it's going
away? What is this all about? In other words, questions around meeting an identity. One way
or another, weak physicians. And you can see what happens in a healthcare system that is somehow,
has crowded those thoughts out as somehow being irrelevant. You're left with a lot of zombies,
you're left with a lot of people with pulses, but have no idea why it's amazing to have a pulse in
the first place. So anyway, I can go on and on and on, but boy, I really, really, really love
the notion of people who study humanities then going into the healing professions. I think it's,
some people see that as like a left turn, like, oh, but I couldn't make a bigger case for art
history was some of the best preparation for medical school I could imagine. I think you're
bringing up really great points, BJ. I think medicine needs all of the above. You need people
who have probably gone incredibly deep on a very narrow subset of science. You need people who come
in with engineering backgrounds. You need people who come in with humanities backgrounds. And I
haven't, to be honest with you, paid much attention to how medical schools are doing these days in
terms of recruiting talent, but the war for talent looks like in medical school versus business
school versus law school versus other graduate schools. But I would hope that they've figured
out what you're saying and are making adjustments in that direction. I think they are. I know UCSF,
my alma mater has, they've really invited folks like myself. I didn't tell any of the pre meds
at Princeton. I did all the pre-med work after college. And UCSF has purposely attracted a lot
of folks who are starting med school a little later in life, have some other life experience,
et cetera. Something of a trend there. I'm with you, right? It takes all of the above. Medicine
is also a technical pursuit. I guess even if someone wants to be a pre-med major, take that
more conventional route, my advice to them was just make sure you actually love it. Just make
sure you love the nuts and bolts. You're not just doing chemistry just as a means to the end of
medical school. You find something to study that actually cultivates you loving something.
I think that's a major distinction. That could be engineering, that could be art,
that could be chemistry. Yeah. I've always felt that the history of science is also equally
beautiful. And so when you're studying physics and you're studying chemistry, to be able to
study it through the lens of how the people who discovered it went along their journey probably
creates or at least fosters some of that intellectual curiosity and passion that I think
can be found across multiple disciplines. But still, I want to get a better sense of
what made you decide to take a very bold step, which is I think to leave a comfort zone of you've
now spent four years doing very well. And you've got this degree in art history from one of the
best schools in the country. And you now decide to presumably go back and do a post-bac year to do a
bunch of pre-med courses to go and do something that seems about as orthogonal from that as
anything. I'm sure it had a lot to do with your experience, but can you speak specifically to what
it was and how it, for the lack of a better word, marinated over the previous four or five years?
Yeah, no, absolutely. I can track this out. So one of the things the injuries did for me,
cut to a spoiler, one of the therapeutic endeavors here, one of the ways to get through
something is in some real ways to let yourself be changed by it. I knew enough that thanks to
my mother and the disability rights movement, that the goal for me was to not get back to where I
was before the injuries. First of all, practically speaking, it wasn't possible. I wasn't going to
get my old body back. Also, why cut myself off from all those lessons and all the experiences
that happened during that period? It's not something I could forget, but nor is it something
I would want to forget. It's too dang rich. So the idea was really always, I knew, versus the
sort of normal language and thoughts around disability, and it's something you would want
to overcome, put behind you. I think a lot of lay people or able-bodied people think the highest
compliment they can offer a disabled person is, oh, I look at you and I don't see disability at all.
I know what they're trying to say, and we can talk, we can open that up too, if you want it on
the road here. But you're trying to say, but in a way, it's not really a compliment. I don't want
people to ignore major parts of me just to look at me. I'm not getting over these injuries every
day. I'm reminded this is not something of the past, it's something I live every day. So when I
hear comments like that and you just feel that you're still aware that someone isn't really
seeing all of you, that's problematic in a number of ways. So I knew that I wanted to work with these
experiences. So that was a major, major theme. And medicine lit up just theoretically as a way
to put these experiences to use. And the linkage between studying art and studying human endeavor
and the study of medicine was not such a big leap. The interest, the throughline, the basocontinuo
for me was just being very interested in human beings, human pursuits, human endeavors,
and human creativity. Art was one application of those interests and medical science was another.
As I pondered what I wanted to do, I thought, well, gosh, medicine would be interesting. If a
doctor walked in to see me in the shoes that I'm wearing now, that would affect me. In a positive,
this was some way I was actively looking for an outlet where my injuries weren't something that
someone would look past or forgive, but were actually in some way something of an advantage.
And in this way, for me in medicine, I can tell you having this silhouette, having this body has
really been an advantage in a lot of ways. If the goal is empathizing with your patients and their
families, if your goal is seeing yourself as a fellow human being next to them, if you know
and believe that's where healing happens, then this kind of stuff is the best prop I've got going.
I really feel for my able-bodied clinicians who don't have some obvious source of pain and
suffering that imparts to your onlookers, imparts to your patients that you've been through some
stuff, you've scraped a barrel. So anyway, I'm going on and on about that. But to get back to
your question, that through line, I knew I had a hunch that that would serve me in medicine just
as it did in art and that I could apply these lessons into a therapeutic application of studying
perspective and meaning making. So medicine lit up as a potential thing that I could do that would be
fascinating, I could make a living, and I could exercise these lessons in an awful way.
So it makes unbelievable sense actually. And I suspect it changed many things for you. I mean,
look, if you just described yourself as a six foot four handsome guy who goes to Princeton,
you probably are a pretty ambitious guy. You're going to go off and study foreign relations and
do all sorts of cool things. And then everything kind of gets taken away in an instant. How does
that change your relationship with your own ambition or what it means to try and fail?
Had you ever failed at anything, by the way, athletically and sort of academically? Even
in the 90s, I imagine getting into Princeton was almost impossible. Yeah, I exceeded in ways,
but also so true. And I just had some green lights right in front of me. I had this amazing
education, I had some basic abilities. I can make a case for us that I had suffered and struggled
in various ways up until that point. And some things hadn't always gone right for me. But there
are such a such a different scale. There's such a different scale. But even as a kid, so in some
ways, no, I really hadn't experienced loss in some big way. But what I had experienced was lost
through people and others that I cared about watching Post-Folio syndrome take my mother's
physical function down, watching my sister struggle. So in some ways, part of my charge
as a young person was I hated that I didn't have more wrong with me. I felt there was a mismatch.
I felt at odds with the world, I felt this pain around me, but I didn't really feel like I had
my own access to it. My problem was I didn't really have anything to complain about. I knew
that life was really, really hard for many, many people. And internally, my life was hard
just imagining that. And in some ways, getting this new body. And in some ways, I have to say,
I made it such I could have cultivated this idea. But in a way, I got the body that much more mirrored
how I felt inside, fragmented, broken, confused, unintegrated, different. In some weird ways,
this body really the physiognomy of my body actually suited me in some real ways. I chose that.
I ran with that. It was true, but it also was a way for me to get into this body eventually and
quit wishing it were something else. By building on what this body was showing me, I knew the clever
thing was I knew what I was doing was building a case that this was the right body, that this was
a good body. This is the one for me. And then you can imagine that really cuts down on the regret
and the second guessing. And if only I had four limbs, then blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. That's
the kind of mindset I was heading for and trying to cultivate. Now here again, brother, what did you
ask me that I went down on that? No, actually, I was talking about this idea of this could have
actually liberated you a little bit. Yes. Yes. And I think you've articulated that very neatly.
I want to come back to your sister. We all do this when we get to medical school is we start to
learn things that explain things we've seen in our past. For example, it's the first time you would
have learned, I suspect on some detail what the polio virus looks like and what a virus does,
how it is that your mom actually came to contract this virus and how a vaccine ultimately would go
on to make sure people wouldn't get that virus. And I would learn about the cardiovascular disease
that ran so deeply in my family and really understand the pathology of this. At some point,
did you start to suspect that your sister had whatever you want to call it, formal mental
illness, or did you not think that that was the case at all? Or how did you think about
your sister once you were in medical school and you began to learn about
mental health in a somewhat formal way? Quick answer here is no, I didn't. The only time I
actually let myself do that sort of the pathological overlay was after the fact, after she had died.
Leading up, it's telling, I mean, leading up to that, even through medical school,
studying manic depression, something that she was posthumously diagnosed with.
Oddly, it never registered as me reading about someone like my sister. Somehow,
and I referenced this a little bit earlier, was somehow the way she was or the our dynamic,
and it wasn't just me, it was my parents too, and her psychiatrist too. She was a master manipulator.
She could have anyone thinking exactly what she wanted them to think, and particularly me as her
little doting brother who just looked up to her. If I absorb anything from Lisa, it was that Lisa
was right. Lisa had it right, including her angst and her pain, that the world is a painful place,
and Lisa was reflecting that. But anything I saw, Lisa was the standard. She was right. Everyone
else was wrong. But she kind of rolled with what she was selling. I did roll with what she was
selling, and deeply, to the point where any idea of pathologizing her just completely bounced off
my head. It didn't register as relevant to her. She was the right one until she ended her life.
Then that prompted all sorts of revisiting that thinking. Also, then eventually, my parents,
what they did to try to make sense of all this, they went through her diaries with the psychiatrist.
It was in that act. I didn't join them in that, but I received the news, and I believe it, which
is just textbook bipolar. I mean, just outrageously textbook. Sometimes, I'd get my quitting, wanting
to quit medicine, did have something. This was right after Lisa died. On the list of why I want
to get out of medicine, I was like, Jesus, I didn't even see right under my nose. I'm trying
to become a healer person. I can't even acknowledge that my sister's sick. I just was demoralizing on
some level. But I also comforted myself. She had a shrink for better than a dozen years who didn't
notice this, who was somehow shocked that Lisa killed herself. Weirdly, I remember,
on the one hand here, I didn't see any of these signals coming. At the same time, I remember
where I was when I got the news of her death. I was with my dad in a car and my buddy Justin.
My mom called, and my dad picked up in his usual sing song, Yue, and there was a pause. Then he
immediately starts bawling. I knew instantaneously that Lisa was gone. When I heard it was suicide,
there was not a single cell of surprise in my body. That's just an observation. Also,
I'm telling you two things. On the one hand, I didn't see it coming. On the other hand,
I completely saw it coming. I don't know how to reconcile those two, but that's just the case.
You're in your last year of medical school when this happens. You've now alluded to this twice.
Were you not planning to do a residency at this point, or was this the event that tipped you
to not pursue your residency that following summer?
All through med school, I just assumed, because I wasn't so enamored with medical science,
per se. That was just a bag of tricks. I was interested in gaining a career in work that
allowed me to continue to think about these things and work with others and serve others around these
ideas of identity, of loss, and trauma. I just figured the best place for me to exercise that
would be in the rehab setting. I was beelining for physical medicine and rehabilitation.
Deep in medical school, UCSF didn't have a program. I went and did an externship,
rotation elsewhere at East. During that, I'd already begun to apply for residencies in rehab
medicine at that point. Then I heard a rotation. I had already committed to this field. I hated
it. The rotation was, I just really did not enjoy it for all sorts of reasons. One, it was all
mechanical. This idea of rehabilitation. First of all, the phrase is problematic. Rehab, the
goal would be to get back to where you were before the injury, which I've been saying, I just don't
believe is true. It's importantly untrue. This idea that it was so mechanical had nothing to do
with the personal transformations that happened. That's where I realized I was so interested.
That plus, I realized as I was walking out of patient's room, I kept hearing nurses say,
look, Timmy, you can be just like BJ. He's a doctor now. I could hear myself being served up
as a poster child. I didn't like the mechanics of the job. I didn't want to be a poster child.
Ipso facto. I was like, I got to get out of this. One of my promises to myself going into medical
school, having learned what I had learned was, hey, life's short, life's important, life's hard,
life's beautiful. I'm not going to just get stuck somewhere and have a sacrificial life.
I know a lot of our colleagues in medicine who went into it because their parents were doctors
and they hated it, but what else am I going to do now? I've gone this far or one way or another,
they just sign up, willfully sign up for a life of misery. I knew I wasn't going to do that.
I promised myself. At this point, another thing I learned from the injuries, which was so critical,
was the ability to, I was much less afraid now, I was much less afraid of failure. I was much less
afraid of falling. You asked me earlier if I had anything really go wrong before in my life. In
some ways, the answer is no. I was a very frightful, melancholy child, sensitive, but to which I end
up manifesting as fearful at times. Now, I was going the other direction, man. Fear, I had a
totally different relationship with fear. I saw falling as a skill. Anyway, the bottom line there
was I was willing to try medicine and willing to dump it. In fact, it felt empowering to do so.
It was a reminder that my life was bigger than just a job choice. Anyone's life is.
There I am deep in med school already applying for residency. I said,
screw this. As I promised myself, I called and dropped out of the match, talked to my dean,
said, hey, I'm finished. I'll graduate, but I'm going to do other things. She talked me into,
she said, okay, okay, right? I had begun to be disillusioned with medicine before my sister's
death, but that was the straw that broke the camel's back. As you've referenced, I think
we bring in idealism one way or another into the healing professions. Then you have to go through
this process of disillusionment where the practice of medicine isn't necessarily jiving with the
ideals that you bring into it. That can be very stressful. But I do think it's important for any
trainee at one point or another to go through some disillusionment. My response to that disillusionment
was to get the hell out of it, especially as I realized I did like rehab medicine. Again,
Lisa's death was just proof that I'm just not, I don't want to do this and I'm not cut out for it.
Then I got talked into doing my internship, that first postdoc year. My family was in
Milwaukee at the time. I had gone away, I had left home when I was 15. Given Lisa had just died,
given I didn't know what I was doing in some ways, I said, okay, while moving with mom and dad, we'll
recongeal as a family, spend that year together and I'll bang out my internship and just get that
done and be done and move on. But it was during that internship that I stumbled into palliative
care and that's where everything changed again. So, PJ, what is it that you saw during your
internship that both made you change your decision leaving medicine and also concentrated or focused
you on an area of medicine called palliative care? So a couple of things happened. One of the things
I just stumbled into this elective during my internship. We have basically one month of an
elective time if I remember correctly, maybe more, but I had spent a little time with a
hospice doc at one point. Actually, my best friend's mother was involved in hospice and she turned me
on to the idea. But again, I was so hell bent on rehab medicine figuring that was the place for me
and wasn't sure that I had anything special to offer beyond that sort of rehab setting.
But I had absorbed that hospice was simply just where people go for the final days of life.
That was, I thought I understood what that meant. But anyway, I stumbled into this palliative care
elective at the Medical College of Wisconsin, which just happens to have been one of the early
adopters of palliative care. David Weissman, an oncologist there, had built one of the early
great palliative care programs, just happened to be there. And on that first day, we went and saw a
patient. I watched David talk to her about code status. This was in the hospital. He was a woman
with heart disease, advanced heart disease. And David was trying to talk to her about her wishes,
what kind of care she wanted for and trying to impart how serious her heart condition had become.
Tricky conversations, very emotionally, psychologically loaded content, really tricky.
The zone that medicine traditionally does not handle very well. And so I'd seen all these
counterpoints. But I hear I'm watching this guy sit with this woman, sits on the edge of her bed
with her, just immediately this very different rapport. He's talking to her like a human being,
not hovering over her like a superior, someone who's there to fix her. He was there as a fellow
human being. And it just showed it in his body language and his tone and his word choice. And
it was beautiful. And he said to her, and I just watched how she responded to him. And it was
remarkable. And he said something to her. He tried to get to the code status question, said something
essentially like, when you die, do you want us to help that process along and make sure you're
comfortable through that process? Or do you want us to really fight that? You want us to go to war
with that notion and do our best to pull you back? Something along those lines. But the magic moment
was him looking at her in the eye and saying, when you die, of course, as human beings, that's
a very reasonable thing to say, because we all die. It's not if, it's when. In the medical setting,
that is not the way these conversations generally work. I was so moved by watching this,
and he dared to acknowledge this woman's death. And what I saw on her face was not shock or anger,
but relief that this man was talking to her plainly about her life. And it was so gorgeous,
so poignant. That moment really, really stuck with me. And as I got to one home that night,
I remember thinking about it, it's like, well, this is what I've been looking for. This is,
in this world, we take, in the pout of care world, illness, disability, death are normal.
They're not anomalous. This field treats these life events as normal life events, which of course
they are. The starting point for pout of care is something's happening that you can't fix,
that you can't change. And that was, for me, all along, in rehab, you could see what would be
similar. Like rehab, the events already happened. Something's gone wrong. Now what you do. I knew I
was interested in the now what. But here, this field was digging into all the, it's not just
the angle of the joint it was concerned with, but the angle of the thoughts and the way that we see
ourselves and the words we choose to describe our place in the world and how we either suffer for
those words or how we really can find ourselves doing something more therapeutic. And it was such
a craft. It was such a, a stuff of words, not of an instrument. So anyway, I really was really,
really moved. But the first axis that opened up was, I'm not here to fix people. I'm here to be
with people as they find their way, as they deal with things that they can't control. And that was
a hope for me in so many ways. How would you explain to someone the difference between palliative
care and hospice, which I think many people use interchangeably, but I don't think they really are
interchangeable, are they? They are not. Thank you, thank you, thank you. A quick public service
announcement because it's a really big problem for a number of reasons. But palliative care is simply
the interdisciplinary pursuit of the quality of life. Within the context of serious illness,
palliative care is that mode of care which helps you feel as well as possible, emotionally,
physically, spiritually, you name it. My job is to help you deal with the facts of your life and to
feel as well as you can. There is nothing in a definition of palliative care that makes it that
you need to be dying anytime soon. Time is not mentioned. There is, death is included in this,
but it's not the focus. It's simply the pursuit of quality of life. And if you need to pose it,
like we do in medicine, if you need to have objects of your efforts, an enemy, as it were,
the thing we're after, palliative care, the thing that we treat is suffering versus disease.
There's a lot to that. We can unpack that. So that's palliative care. Hospice is a subset of
palliative care, which is that mode, that type of care, but reserved for the end of life, the final
months of life. So hospice really is essentially end of life care, is palliative care that's applied
at the end of life. But that's just hospice. With palliative care, there's no mention of time. You
just have to be struggling. You just have to be interested in quality of life. You don't have to
be dying anytime soon. This is a huge, huge distinction because of all of our death folks.
Because they think palliative care and end of life care are hospice are the same.
No one wants to talk about it. No one wants to face that because of all the baggage around death.
So consequently, people suffer for years where they could get a lot more support from palliative
care. But because of this misunderstanding, they don't elect palliative care because they think
that's only relevant for them if they're dying soon and nothing could be farther from the truth.
So does that make sense? It really does, yes. And I appreciate that distinction.
Good. What do you think it is about us as a species? I can only speak to us because other
species, I don't think, share our metacognition. But why are we in such denial about death? It's
been said by so many people, we are all terminally ill. And yet most of us, myself, certainly
included, don't act that way at times. We tend to fixate on things that absolutely don't matter.
For many people, there's frank denial of this thing. It's out there with some sort of abstract
idea, but it's certainly nothing that warrants any attention in terms of decisions one makes
today. That's really the first question I have, and then there's other things I want to explore
here with you. But what is your take on our just inability to look at death?
I think for starters, I know in my field and elsewhere, for folks who have kind of dared to
turn their attention to mortality or have been forced to, then you look back on the rest of the
world and you see a world so invested in ignoring this part of life that it can feel a little
perverse. And I think a lot of us are quick to say the world's Americans in particular are in
denial. And there's some truth to that for sure. But I also think we should cut each other some
slack, just physiologically, neurohormonally, we are wired to run away from death. Any threat to
our existence, we have deep wiring that makes us fight that thing or flee it or go limp. So we have
that impulse in us. And then I think on top of that, there's as old as human beings has been this
acknowledge that we die, that any adult in this world, maybe not even just adults, one way or
another, human beings eventually come to the realization that death happens, including their
own death. And I'm not sure that any other species has to live, has to walk through life
feeling that. So it is quite a predicament we humans have. It's elemental. It is at the root
of the Judeo-Christian tradition. It's a root of many religious belief systems, a lot of philosophy
of thought. It's at the root of song and artwork. I mean, this is a huge, huge subject that humans
really, really struggle to wrap their heads around. So I just want to give us plenty of
breath. And I don't want us to be ashamed that we haven't figured out this death thing. So on top of
those old threads, modern times, the last 150 years, medical science, we're sort of a victim of
our own success. Medical science has gotten much better. It's easy to be seduced. My life has been
saved by medicine. It's easy to believe that medicine can forestall death, perhaps indefinitely.
So you throw all these things together and social cues around anti-aging this and that, and you got
to stay healthy and beautiful forever and put all that stuff together. And we've conspired to set up
a pretty tricky relationship to this piece of our nature. No harm, no foul. But I think the reason
to push back on this is A, people die much more miserable than they need to because they haven't
dared to look at this thing called death before it's too late. And because also we have a healthcare
system that it's not an intuitive thing to navigate anymore. And thanks to our technology, it's not
impossible to end up on a series of machines and that by some definition of life, you have a pulse,
but that's not a life that a lot of us want to live is hooked up to machines. So we have this
weird technological moment that you can kind of live forever by some very reduced definition of
life. Anyway, there's a little bit of a rundown why it's so dang hard to turn our attention to this.
But when people do, and I'm coming to the climax here brother, but one of the things you learn
whether through religious and philosophical thinking or frankly in clinical thinking,
whether by choice or by force, once you have to actually try to stare this thing called mortality,
this thing called death in the eye, not only do you realize that, hey, maybe it's not so terrifying
after all, and that you can do it, but it has a secondary effect of once you come to terms with
your time is precious, and that time is relatively short, or at least not endless,
it has a secondary effect of helping you really, really appreciate what you have.
The fact that it ends is what makes it precious. So there are reasons why we don't look at death,
and there are some really good reasons to help each other find a way to do so.
I think that's just such an eloquent description of what I consider to be a huge dialectical
challenge, which is the problem that I focus on BJ in medicine is how to live longer, how to do
so without requiring the heroics of medicine at end of life. So just as you became disillusioned
with medicine, so too did I. But it was for a slightly different reason, which was, boy,
we sure do put a staggering amount of resources and effort into things that with probably one
tenth of this effort could have been forced all or prevented altogether. And I didn't think I could
do anything about it. So I left for a period of time before ultimately coming back to it.
But I think that what you said is I completely agree that we can do both, right? We can do
everything in our power to maximize our lives here, just as medicine allowed you to live that day.
There's a very good chance at a different hospital under different settings, you would have died 30
years ago, but you didn't. Now you're still going to die, just as I am, of course, and everyone
listening to this is going to die. So we can do both. We can figure out a way to live the best
life possible, the longest life possible, should we choose that to be the case. But none of that
diminishes what you've said. And I think that's the part that a lot of people don't appreciate,
is that it's one or the other and it can't be both. Amen. You just hit on a real kind of a
root cause. One of the ways we struggle so much these days is from our structures, our constructs,
our ways of thinking. And as long as we think it's either life or death, that either you love life
and try everything you can do to extend it, or you love death and just completely accept that it's
going to come today. This false dichotomies are the problem. And I'm so with you, and it's one of
the reasons I'm so excited to be invited on your podcast, but it's because our relationship with
death is maybe a problem or just under-realize. But if there's a problem here, it's the false
dichotomy. It's the either or thinking when the both and thinking is really where it's at. So I
love that you and others are trying to think through how to live longer and live better.
I love life. My relationship to death, even my acceptance of death, is only to do with my love
of life. It would be a real shame of a shortcut that if in order to prepare yourself for the
inevitability of death, you somehow stopped loving life. You somehow welcomed depression.
So therefore, you wouldn't love life so much. So therefore, you're ready to die because life
kind of sucks. It could be so, so much better than that. And if we can find a way to include death
into our view of reality, like I don't love death. I love reality. And reality happens to include
death. Therefore, I'll deal with death. I'm in no way concerted around it. I'm in no way incentivized
to make death happen. Again, I appreciate you having this conversation with me. I think there's
a lot to be learned by pushing past the either or of this. You've spent more time with people who
are closer to death than almost anybody listening to this, certainly. You're in a profession that
very few people go into. As you've pointed out, there are many reasons for that. Do you get the
sense that when someone is at the end of their life, they are more afraid of death in the sense
of being gone or the act of dying and presumably what the actual mechanism of death and or suffering
is? Yeah, it's a really great distinction, a very helpful one clinically. Presentation may be
someone's freaked out about dying or some existential anxieties. But of course, as is
the case with these things, it pays to look a little bit more closely and see some things out
here. And one of the major things to tease out is, are you afraid of the dying process, like you're
mentioning here, like the suffering you imply that must happen during the dying process? Is that what
you're picturing? And therefore, is that the source of your anxiety? Or are you really afraid
to be dead? Whether your belief system suggests there's a Judgment Day and a reckoning, perhaps
a hell, perhaps who knows what? Are you afraid of what may be coming next? Are you afraid to be gone?
Are you afraid to miss out? Does it freak you out that the world will go on without you? A major
poll here or a major divide, a crossroads, let's say, is are you afraid of dying or are you afraid
of being dead? The former, one of the reasons that it teases out is the former afraid of dying. Well,
we know a fair amount about that. There's physiology to mark. There are medications to help.
There are ways to help a body come down for a gentle landing, as I say. There's no need to be
miserable and in pain at the end of life. For the most part, we can do a lot with medications. We
can do a lot to ease the suffering at the end of life in the dying process. So the answer, if
that's your fear, then the answer is reassurance. If your concern is being dead, well, I don't have
answers for you, but I can, as a fellow traveler, I can accompany you there. We can think about that
together. We can talk about it. And then we can make a life that responds to that big question.
So if you're afraid of your belief system, as you're afraid of a Judgment Day, we'll let that spur
you to behave a little differently in the time you have left. Or let that help you wade into
non-duality. Let that help you wade into the world beyond yourself. That's my favorite response. If
anyone's interested in living forever, my favorite means to living forever is to think about the
world beyond yourself. Invest yourself in the world beyond yourself. So when your self dies,
that thing you love keeps going. Anyway, this is where it gets really, really fascinating,
the relationship between self and other and what to do about that, religious thinking,
spiritual pursuits. This is what can open up when you admit that you're freaked out to be dead.
It's such an interesting way you explain the idea of, again, for me, it's very clearly the latter,
not the former. And I guess that's just because I have the luxury of medical training. And I
understand where and when one can draw the line for themselves with respect to what measures are
taken, how heroically they are, and obviously the power of medicine to greatly reduce the suffering.
But it's this other piece of missing your family, missing out on future generations, leaving behind
people you love. To me, those are the hardest things. And of course, your point is you can
live through those things, but you have to do something about it. It doesn't happen automatically.
You have to make the investment. And the irony is the time to do that is while we're alive.
Amen. You just gave me chills. You just completed the circle. Yep.
Which almost suggests that palliative care needs to begin much earlier in life.
Amen. Which is why it's such a shame that we forestall and keep it at bay when it's this thing
that could help us so, so much, whether actually a pout of care referral or a pout of care mindset.
But one way or another, finding our way into this subject while we've got plenty of road in front of
us is absolutely the right best way. It seems that there's a continuum where you have life,
you have acute illnesses, more life, acute illnesses, chronic illnesses, life and death.
The hospital and the entire medical system is really only geared to treat with the acute
problems. It has virtually no tool dealing with life or even chronic conditions and certainly
not death. I don't want to get into the why is that the case? We can sit here and debate about
incentives all day long. I think it's straightforward. I mean, I think we understand
that the incentives are such that reimbursement follows the treatment of acute conditions and
to some extent chronic conditions. I guess the more relevant question is, what would have to
change to realign the focus of resources to make it such that medicine could be more about helping
people live and then helping them die when that time comes? As a part and parcel of helping them
live, then relate those two things. So I think a couple of answers to your question. I think one
is in a big office somewhere at HHS when they're trying to redesign a healthcare system and even
redraft a mission statement. I would challenge HHS to read the definition of palliative care and tell
me why the definition of palliative care isn't the mission of all of healthcare. So one answer to
your question is you can see that both the strengths of the healthcare system and the
trouble that comes from it is a design flaw because you and I both know healthcare is littered with
people who really, really care and are trained at the hilt. And yet the care we're able to meet out
too often falls short. I don't think the problem is the people. I think the problem is there's a
design flaw. And for my money, the design flaw has to do with the system is focused on disease,
not on the people dealing with disease. And the second you make it about the person living with
the disease, not the disease itself, well, you've welcomed all sorts of things into the mix beyond
just their physiology and anatomy. You've welcomed their social, emotional, and spiritual
lives into the mix. You've also welcomed your humanness into the mix as being relevant,
you as a clinician being relevant beyond just your technical skills, which will push back on
burnout for one thing. You've also made yourself in service of a human condition, which means for
us clinicians, the expectation management, we're not expected to work miracles. We know that it's
someday everyone's going to die and that that's not a failure for us. We didn't, the person didn't
succumb to the disease and we doctors didn't fail to make them live forever. Then once we align
healthcare with the human condition and we're serving human beings, so much of the trouble
will work itself out because we will be designed around the right thing. So that's one answer to
your question. I think it's that simple and that hard on some level. And then medical scores,
medical training would have to follow suit and revisit how we think about these things.
I mean, for example, think about your medical school training, Peter. 100% of your patients die.
Any rotation that you ever go through, no condition befalls 100% of your patients,
but 100% of our patients suffer. 100% of our patients die. And given that, wouldn't you think
that a responsible medical school curriculum that we would start and end day one and the last day
would be around conversations like we're having now. The pout of care would not need to be a
specialty. It would be baked in to how all of medicine works. So for my money, that's a major
thing that needs to happen. Policy will flow, et cetera. I also think to make that happen and to not
wait for that happen, that we human beings, we people, irrespective of our professions,
need to kind of come together as a society and to take these issues on, especially right now when
we're all so polarized and so divided and so aware about the things that we don't have in common
with each other. What a perfect time to revisit where we actually do have so much in common.
And where we do have so much in common revolves around everything we're talking about right now.
Black, white, rich, poor, young, old, I don't care. These issues affect all of us. This is a genuine
way for us to work on the points in common. So we can make political comments about why now is right
for that. The healthcare system itself can't keep doing what it's doing and can't keep death
the enemy because it's going to lose that war again and again and again. And the one way you can
keep score on that is just cost. Yep. Cost alone is a metric by which we're losing. Healthcare is
obviously one of two things that will either bankrupt the United States if they can't print
their way out of it or create sort of seismic economic shifts. And I do think that part of it
is, as you said, we've taken the wrong strategy in a war that probably ought to be deemed more
of a truce and put our resources in the wrong place. Can I ask you a question on that though?
Yeah. Yeah. Why would you say that we are so focused on acute care and not on chronic care?
If most everybody is going to die of most of chronic conditions, et cetera? I should say,
I think we do focus a lot on chronic care. I just don't think we're good at it. So what I meant to
say was I think where medicine is very good is on acute care. And I think where medicine is
really bad is on chronic care. And I think those are the two things it works on. It has nothing to
do with sort of healthy life to prevent acute or chronic issues. And it has nothing to do with
death. So that's sort of, yeah, just thanks for asking me to clarify that. But yes, I think we
disproportionately focus on chronic despite our relative lack of success with it. Why do we keep
doing that? Do you have a sense? Well, I think in some cases we don't know what to do to prevent
the condition. So certain conditions never show up as acute. Cancer does not show up acutely. I
shouldn't say that it kind of does, but it doesn't really fall under the rubric of acute care medicine
the way appendicitis does. But we don't really have a great sense of cancer. You know, we know
smoking and obesity are the two greatest risk factors for it, but there's many other risk factors,
including chance that we probably don't understand. And even the ones that we do understand,
like obesity, we don't really have the infrastructure to help with prevention. So you talked about how
in medical school we didn't have a single course on dying. We also didn't have a single course on
nutrition or exercise or stress management or the psychology of eating and our relationship to food
and how you can help patients make better choices with nutrition and things like that. So I don't
buy the narrative that we have an obesity crisis just because sort of people are fat, dumb, and
lazy. I think we live in a toxic food environment and we don't have a healthcare system that's
really geared to help people out of it because frankly, physicians aren't compensated to do that.
You just don't have the billable structure in which you can do these things. So instead, I think we
focus on where our tools are and our tools are drugs. Drugs become a good tool to use in a chronic
condition setting. Right. I think I'd add to that, maybe to encapsulate this list three ways. One is
the design flaw that we're the phobic and we see ourselves as victors when we cure something, when
we fix something. So chronic illness by definition is something that we can't fix. So I think it
presents us with a sense of failure, which I think is an emotional barrier to developing it
further. That's one big piece of the design flaw. I think a second big piece of the design flaw is
the way the busyness of medicine goes. We are left to see medicine as a series of transactions,
which in acute care, it makes a lot more sense. In chronic care, it becomes part of the experience.
You're not kicking this thing out of the body. You've got to learn to live with it. So
illness and health becomes protracted over time and therefore becomes an experience. But we're
wired for transactions. We don't have the systems and structures in place to be cultivating
experiences together with our patients. That's the second thing. And I think the third thing
is this reimbursement and we are incentivized away from thinking about care over time. So anyway,
I just want to complete that question for both of us. I think that's why we're where we're at.
Yeah, I appreciate that structure that you've put to it. I want to ask you about
patients that you interact with during hospice. So these are now going to be the patients who are
probably in the final months of their life. And that could be cancer is obviously a very common
pathway that you'll interact with hospice patients. Is that the most common proximate cause of death
for hospice patients in the United States? Cancer? Yes. No, it is no longer the majority.
Until recently, it's less than 50% now. Progressive neurological illnesses are on the rise,
cardiovascular, organ failure, but yeah, fewer than 50% of deaths. The hospice deaths are cancer
at this point. What do patients say most to you? When I was in medical school, I did a stint at the
National Cancer Institute and then I went back there for my formal training fellowship and people
that came to the NCI to where I was and I suspect to elsewhere in the NCI were generally patients
who had progressed through all forms of treatment, all standard treatments. So they had metastatic
disease that had failed to respond to any form of treatment. So therefore they were at the NCI for
experimental treatment. And at least for the type of cancer we worked on, the survival was between
10 and 20%, meaning 80 to 90% of the people we met were going to die very soon within six months,
typically. I remember obviously feeling very attached to many of them and also spending time
with them and asking them questions like what do they wish they could do? How do they want to spend
this time that they have left? And sometimes they would share regrets. And I always remember thinking,
I wish I could write a book about this, just interviewing people like this, but it felt,
it didn't feel right to me. It was one of those things that just felt like it should be shared,
but I wouldn't know how to share it. I suspect you've had more of those discussions than you
can remember. And I wonder what things you've learned from them. These vicarious deathbed
moments. I have a lot of them. I think a lot of us in this field and maybe a mess in general like
to say how privileged we are to be in this position, how lucky we are to have our patients let us in
to this very poignant moments. It's so intimate. So yeah, there's a lot to be said for those moments,
including your wanting to protect those moments and not necessarily ram them into a book. Although
there sure is a way to do that skillfully, the world could benefit from it. But the regrets that
pop in that I see at the end of life, the conventional ones are sure you hear people say
things like, I wish I had spent more time with my family than at the office and things like that.
Yeah, sure. That comes up. But in a way by some, someone's actually in their deathbed.
And again, these days, most of us dying from chronic illnesses, that means we have some
protracted period of time to think about our death. Specifically, we will be introduced to
the thing that will end our life, months or years in advance. And so by the time those folks get
around to their end of their life, they're beyond the sort of pat regrets. They shouldn't work so
much, for example. Oftentimes, if they're regretting anything, they're hanging on to anything,
including regrets. It's more likely, I wish I had dared to love more. I wish I hadn't been
so afraid. I wish I had just let myself be myself. I wish I hadn't been so hard on myself or criticize
myself. Those regrets, they all have something to do in common. And the commonality is, it's sort of
like oftentimes a common pathway is they wish they had let themselves come to terms with death
earlier in their lives, because it would have changed the decisions they made. I think one of
the things that people come to realize on their deathbed, and one of the things that I saw at
getting close to my own was really grasping it in our guts that death is coming no matter what we do.
Even in your work, promoting a longer life, as you said earlier, doesn't mean that death isn't
still coming. It's coming later. Given that, this is the freedom that comes from reckoning with
death, which is, if okay, you're telling me that no matter what I do, if I'm a good person, a bad
person, I eat my veggies, I don't eat my veggies, I smoke, I don't smoke, whatever it is, either way,
if I'm going down, eventually. In other words, if failure is in this way, quote unquote, failure is
guaranteed, then in some ways, the pressure's off. The pressure's on for me to take my life seriously,
but the pressure's off for me to get everything just perfect. There's this biphasic effect that
I see in myself and some of my patients, which is they see the grip that fear has had on them,
distraction is done to them, and they realize that no, man, the only thing I have to lose is
wasting my time. I'm not going to waste my time. I'm going to take this stuff seriously. I'm going
to say what I want to say to people. I'm going to do what I want to do, because if failure is
guaranteed, then I'm no longer, it doesn't make much sense to be afraid of failure anymore,
or not be limited by it, because I'm going to fall either way, so I might as well try.
Death gives me the reason to try and gives me the reason or the way of forgiving myself for,
quote unquote, failing. Really, in this way, it can be a real liberating force, and I see
people grok that, and the regrets have something to do with not coming to that place sooner.
You presumably encounter patients who have the proverbial dying wish, never saw the Grand Canyon,
and I really want to go and see it, never seen the Mona Lisa, and I want to see it, or I've never
taken this vacation with my family. How much of your work is trying to help patients navigate
those wishes medically? For example, is someone strong enough to physically go to the Grand Canyon,
and can you put in a last ditch heroic effect to get them there? How much of that do you do?
Some. I'm involved with an organization called the Dream Foundation out of Santa Barbara, and
what they do for a living as an organization is help make those trips to the Grand Canyon,
or whatever those final wishes actually happen for adults in this country. It's beautiful.
And I have been engaged in some of that with some patients, whether on handful occasions where
someone was here who may have lived here for a long time, but grew up elsewhere and wanted to
get home, as it were, back to the Philippines or back to somewhere else, and helping this sort of
one last trip happen. I've been involved with that a lot. I've been involved with some bedside
weddings in a hospital just before someone died. I've been involved with some trips done to the
Grand Canyon. So some of that, that is true. Some of my job, especially if I can be engaged
with someone soon enough while there's still energy and time to work with, then making those
last wishes happen is great. It's fun. It's great work. It's powerful. It's delightful, and it's
stunning. But I will say, and so I do some of that, but for whatever reason, I'm more engaged with
people around letting go of that wish or that need to go see the Grand Canyon or whatever it
may be, of letting go of the things that they're not going to be able to do, or at least grokking
that fact. So yes, sometimes the response is to mobilize energy to do that thing. I'd say more
often and right alongside that wish is also helping them see the world and see themselves in
the world in such a way that they can let go of those things that they never got to, because they
realize the things that they're not going to get to is a very long list. And on a developmental
level, you've got to find a way to come to terms with all the things you're not going to get to do.
So that's where I spend a lot of my time. Movies lead us to believe that people become enlightened
and hyper-transcendent at the end of life. But my experience with patients at the end of their
lives is that oftentimes they're so heavily medicated that they're not really even able to
communicate much with their loved ones. And that's the price we'll pay to keep them comfortable,
especially patients with metastatic cancer. The pain would be so debilitating, it would be inhumane
to let them suffer without those medications. And frankly, in the circumstances when we're lucky
enough to do so, we can get expressed direction from the patients before they get there that,
hey, I don't want to suffer and I don't want a breathing tube put into my chest. I don't want
to be intubated and I don't want you to do chest compressions on me when my heart stops. I just
want enough medicine to be comfortable. And so you don't have these sort of diving into a person's
soul in the last day of their life kind of thing. Is that your experience also?
Absolutely, it is. There are exceptions, but not many. The last day or two of life is not
necessarily the greatest time to be digging into someone's soul. And I will say, you're right about
medications is a big piece of this. But I will also say, just for your listeners, a refinement
here, again, pushing on the either or kind of thinking, it's not either take meds and be
comfortable or don't take meds and be lucid. Intractable pain is a great route to delirium.
And even if you're not delirious, trying to have an exchange with someone when your body is an
absolute agony is a pretty quixotic experience. I will say that another plug for a pound of care
is with a very expert and judicial use of pain medications, where we can often thread a needle
and get someone comfortable enough, but not so overly medicated that they can't interact.
We just want to name that refinement a little bit. Either way, Peter, your point is still taken.
The very, very final hours of life, you're not generally reviewing much. You're not having big
philosophical conversation at that point in so many ways, whether by medication or force of the
disease, it's too late. Which I think speaks to what you said earlier, that there really is no
time like the present to say what it is you want to say to people who matter. It's not the movie
where your final breath is asking for forgiveness or telling somebody you forgive them or that you
love them. That's very unlikely to happen. That's very unlikely to happen as is anything sort of
cleanly closure. I love pointing this out to folks. One of the things in my world and in
palliative care world, one of the one of the things you would want to forestall with knowing
so much pain is coming as you want to forestall the avoidable regrets and avoidable pains,
but you're not necessarily going to get there in your final breath.
Tell me the story about Randy Sloan. How did you meet him?
Randy was a beautiful young man. I met Randy. He worked at a motorcycle shop.
I first met Randy. One of my wishes for myself once I became an amputee was to get back on a
motorcycle at some point. I've always loved biking. I'd always wanted to get on a motorcycle.
Everyone smiles, swims through a motorcycle shop and see if there was any way to convert a bike.
Every time I walked in there, I couldn't get anyone to take it on. I think they all just freaked out
like, no way, dude. We're not putting you on a death machine. I didn't try that hard, but I
never could get anyone really interested. One day I walked into a place called Scuderia West here in
San Francisco and just met a wholly different energy. These guys were actually interested in
trying to make it happen. Saw it as a creative exercise. That's exactly the spirit you need.
Randy was the mechanic who put his hand up as wanting to help make this happen.
Randy, he was a bike mechanic. He took my bike and he managed to figure out a way for me to operate it
with just one hand by a series of modifications. He helped make this dream come true for me.
It was beautiful for both of us. He loved making it happen and I sure loved that he did. There
was this gorgeous, teary moment when I picked up the bike and rode off in the sunset. It was just
a beautiful, but time limited interaction with Randy. Then not that much longer, I can't remember
now, months or maybe a year later. Randy was in his mid-20s, by the way. Randy ended up somehow
his mother reached me and let me know that Randy was in the hospital and something really big time
was going wrong. Randy and I had remembered each other because we were both moved by this story
and his mom reached out and he knew I was a doctor. So, blah, blah, blah. Eventually I got to Randy's
bedside. Randy had been walking up a hill in San Francisco, found himself a little out of breath,
went to urgent care. They took an x-ray and he had turned out to have mesothelioma.
Which is essentially unheard of in someone in their 20s. I mean, this is a cancer that is
almost exclusively associated with long-term asbestos exposure in elderly folks. I don't
know enough about motorcycles to know if there was asbestos in them, but even if there was,
you'd think this is something that would still be 40 years later. You're right. So, total freakish.
Even if you had had exposure, it's rare to find exposed asbestos these days, much rarer.
But at that age, you just don't have even time to develop the cancer. It takes a while after
exposure. So, just a real mystery how this young man came down with widely metastatic mesothelioma.
Even at the time of diagnosis, scans revealed it was in his brainstem.
He's one of these guys who went from walking, talking to that day was in the hospital on death's
door and people scurrying around trying to make a plan of what to do. I met him. I walked in that
situation. By the time I even got to the hospital, he had had a dose of whole brain radiation
because brainstem lesion was very precarious and they needed immediate care. So, he had already
been radiated within hours. I walked into a situation. Here's a young man trying to deal
with this diagnosis, come to terms with it and all that it meant. It meant that his life was
measured in weeks at that point, right from the time of diagnosis. So, I became his palliative
care doctor and we were together for the rest of the time and we got him into, I saw him into,
at that point, I was working at Zen Hospice Project in San Francisco. He moved in there with us and he
played his life out with us. It was an amazing experience. I think one of the most amazing things
about it, besides the medical like mesothelioma and this young man, blah, blah, blah, the really
interesting stuff was how Randy responded to this diagnosis. He and his mother and I were all,
it just too, didn't make sense. It was too soon. So, we were all gearing up to think that somehow
treatment was going to help him. It was a sober conversation. There was nothing that was going to
help him at this point, except for love. That one dose of whole brain radiation really threw him for
a loop. I'm trying to talk to him about the fact, trying to bridge him to the point, the realization
that he has no good cancer fighting options. You're watching this guy's world shrink miserably by
the second. To find a way out of this tailspin and to find a way forward, we had our dutiful
palliative care conversation, which included a question in there eventually about what was really
important to him. What about him that he want to protect as his body was falling apart? What did he
love most about himself? Somehow the question to Randy became, what are you most proud of in
yourself? As a young man in development, it seemed like an important question. His answer
was immediate. His answer was, I want everybody I ever come into contact know that I love them.
He answered the question immediately. It was remarkable coming out of a 27-year-old bike
mechanic. So, there it was. I said, okay, we need to keep you as comfortable and conscious as
possible for what time you have and be in a position that your friends and people can visit you.
So, that meant let's get you in the hospice house out of your teeny walk-up apartment where
you have three roommates. Let's get you into this hospice house. Let's get you out of the
charade of treatment. Let's treat your symptoms and open up your door and get as many people in
here as you want. That's what we did. He just had a steady stream of visitors. He just basically
became this radiant beam of love for what time he had and just made sure to love as many people as
he humanly could. With that, his mother and his stepfather came out and got married at the
hospice house around the time he died. He got in the bay one more time for a swim. He got to be
with his dog and he let everyone know what Randy meant was love and that became his legacy. He
died smiling and quickly. This all transpired over what felt like hours. What role does
euthanasia play? I ashamed to admit I'm a little bit ignorant about the legality of its state by
state. Obviously, I know that Oregon is a state where it's legal. How many states in the US
have legalized euthanasia or some form of physician assisted suicide?
I believe the number is now nine. I have to double check. Still, it's unfurling as we speak.
There's efforts going on in every state house, but I'm pretty sure the number is nine. The first
was Oregon in 97, California in 2016, and others have followed suit. Montana, Oregon, Colorado,
California, DC, others that I can't remember right now. It's coming slowly but surely state by state.
Has it demonstrably changed the practice of hospice or palliative care or is it almost moot because
so much of threading that needle as you described it, effectively it doesn't happen maybe in as
dramatic a fashion. In the end of life care that you're discussing, for example, in the case of
someone like Randy, if Randy had said, let's say a few weeks sooner, I want to go down the path of
euthanasia, what would have been different than what he ultimately ended up doing at Zen Hospice?
There was a moment there, I could imagine he would have really elected it. The world was falling
apart too quickly. It was too painful for a little while there for Randy to see straight.
The process we can talk, it's a little bit of walking. There's a two week wait. You need to
have two physicians. You need to write a letter. They're fail safes because what the state wants
to avoid is it making it too easy for people to do something that they otherwise might regret
because I think many of us have moments where we just as soon get off the planet, especially when
we're dealing with something like a terminal diagnosis. It's a funny thing where life's ending
soon. Some folks have this response, okay, I'm dying. Now that I realize I'm dying, well, now I
can't die soon enough. It's almost like once you pierce the veil of indefinite life, which people
really long on some levels think they long for, then all of a sudden they're terminal and then
they can't die soon enough. It's sort of a final act of control and a bit of an FU to death.
Well, you think you're inevitable. I'll show you.
It's the quit before getting fired impulse in some ways. There are other ways. There are many
things that drive the impulse, but that's a sort of a side note. But answer your question. I mean,
if Randy enacted this procedure and ended his life, hastened his death before nature otherwise
would have had it, well, Randy would have died sooner. Randy would have been able to schedule
the moment of his death. It would have been something. And on some level that could have
served him. But the realization that Randy had a mission to sort of prove love, to show love,
to be love, he had a reason to keep going. There's a moment where if it had been too easy for him,
he probably would have elected to hasten his death. But because he didn't, and because he let
it play out a little bit longer, he got to a lot more people. He had a lot more final moments with
friends. He got into the bay and he had the pride of playing his body all the way out. He played
every cell all the way out, which for Randy served him very, very well. And I think it makes the
point one of the problems with the dying laws. And let me just pause there too, by the way,
Peter, the language of physician-assisted suicide has gone away in favor of aid in dying
or assisted dying to get rid of the word suicide, emotional baggage around that word. And importantly,
these laws are for people who already have a terminal diagnosis and for whom death is coming
soon. So it's importantly different. But if we had just ceded his wishes and said, oh, sure,
you want to die Randy sooner or later? Yeah, we'll make that happen. Just in the name of
helping him not suffer, we could have made that happen. And it would have been a mistake in his
case, because as I think a lot of us know intuitively or explicitly, a meaningful life,
a good life is not the absence of suffering. Suffering teaches us too much. It's too important
vehicle for us actually. A full life requires it. And I don't mean to castigate anyone who does
choose to hasten their death. For some people, it is exactly the right decision. When it is seen as
a meaningful response, not a flight from suffering, but a moving towards something meaningful. And
for some people, a final act of will is very meaningful. But for more people, what ends up
being more meaningful is them being more than their pain, being more than their suffering,
and letting their body play themselves all the way out and dealing with and adapting every moment
along the way, trimming their sails along the way, letting themselves be changed, letting themselves
grow right up into the moment of their death. That's actually a more meaningful pursuit for
the bulk of people. It's really that pain matters more than being numb. Yeah, yeah. When it comes
down to it, when it comes down to it, for most of us, and this is a realization that came clear to
me when I was in my hospital bed, pain is very obnoxious. And I don't like this stuff. We can
be more than our pain. Pain isn't ultimately avoidable in a full life, like I said, and it can
teach us some things. And really, I'd much rather feel some exceptions, and there's ways to paint
this otherwise, but in general, I'd rather feel something, even if it's pain than feel nothing.
Anesthesia is a way, numbness is a way to die before we have to die. That seems to be a bigger
tragedy to me than is death in the first place. Have you had any experience with the use of
psychedelics in end of life care? Are people doing any research on this? Obviously, I'm aware
of the research on psilocybin in patients with cancer. I believe there was research done
helping with end of life depression. Are you aware of any other agents that are used besides
psilocybin for that research? Anything with MDMA? I'm not sure if, which obviously I know MDMA is
being used to treat PTSD, but what does the scope and breadth of that look like today?
Substances being researched for end of life anxieties, fears of death,
or studying a patient population dealing with terminal illness or serious illness. I can't
quote to you all the latest details of studies. There are studies ongoing for yes for psilocybin,
but also for MDMA. And then related, similar but different, is ketamine, and the way ketamine is
proving its way to new therapeutic values. So yes, I'm most excited around the research on MDMA
and psilocybin. And the research so far, we've got a little ways to go, but the data are pretty darn
stunning. The impact is huge and offers access. The psilocybin stuff is the most remarkable,
I think. One guided session, we're setting matters, dose matters, the integration process matters. It's
not just people going out in the woods and having fun. But with this process, there are really no
adverse events to speak of. People who are gripped by a fear of death, gripped by a sense of
meaninglessness and not belonging and not feeling connected, come out of this one session, losing
their fear of death, feeling part of something larger than themselves, having a totally different
relationship to fear. This is one session. The effect lasts for months. It's not just a chemical
effect per se. We don't have anything remotely like this to offer in medicine. The closest thing
I have in my conventional work as a doctor is someone comes to me with death anxiety, two things
I can do. I can talk them out of it and try to, with enough time, we can find a new way of seeing
themselves in the world, a framework that allows them to feel like they belong in their own framework
that takes time if we can get there at all. The other thing I can do is if you're really anxious,
well, I can numb you out. I can give you Valium or whatever else. I can put a wet blanket on your
system. That's the best we've had to date. I don't have an intervention that helps me connect you to
meaning, connect you to the cosmos, but these medications are offering exactly that and is
beautiful. So we've got a little ways to go, but I am thrilled for this potential.
Are these tools the things you're probably most excited about in your field in terms of being
able to revolutionize how you're able to help the patients who want or need that type of intervention?
Or is there anything else that even rivals this? Yes, there are two things. Strictly speaking,
from a medical, medicationy, medical physiology-ish overlay, the medical lens, I would say the research
going on around these substances, psilocybin, MDMA, ketamine, et cetera, are my favorite thing going.
Maybe even bigger, maybe with other things that gets me more excited is the work going on on the
periphery of healthcare and outside of healthcare. That conversations like the one you and I are
having, Peter, and I thank you for it up and down. One of the things we're doing is we're kicking the
conversation beyond just medicine. It's like we were saying earlier about the design flaw that
medicine focuses on the disease, not the person. One of the great things that happens when we focus
on the person is that we in medicine become part of something larger than ourselves.
We can partner with architects and artists and designers and other disciplines and death doulas
and quasi-medical folks and alternative and integrative medicine folks. All of a sudden,
we are part of a much larger family working on behalf of something much larger than even medicine.
That's where I get really excited that people, that society, that culture is waking up to these
issues. Death has become a medical issue. It doesn't belong there. Suffering and death are
way bigger than medicine. Medicine may have something to offer this. Getting back to your
question, the thing that I'm more excited than anything else is the rise of commerce,
multidisciplinary work, other institutions and vehicles tuning into this idea of life and death
so that medicine doesn't have to carry all that water by itself, that people are going to start
taking care of people and not handing themselves over to doctors to do the trick.
PJ, I really want to thank you because your work and the work of people like you has actually had
quite a profound impact on the way I think about life. I'm in the process of barely putting the
finishing touches on a book about longevity and I've come to the realization lately, it's very
difficult to do this without writing about death in some way, but not as an enemy, but more in a
manner that is symbiotic with life. Maybe not quite a friend, but certainly not a hostile
combatant. I just think the way that you've been able to speak about this so eloquently for many
years now has been a great benefit to not just the people you've helped, which is obvious.
I think those of us who are presumably a little bit further from needing that help.
Pete, I can't wait to read that book, man. And that is right on. I think you will help so many
people. Just this frame shift of finding a way to include death in your view of reality
is one of the great services you can do the world, man. And I, oh, I can't wait to read it.
Well, thanks, PJ. And thanks more than anything else for all of your time this afternoon.
Thanks for having me, Tom. Thank you so much.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiels like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every
Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare
services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice
from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.