Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guests this week are Lauren Miller Rogan and Richard Isaacson. Lauren is an
actress, screenwriter, director, but also a friend and patient. She's the co-founder of Hilarity for
Charity or HFC, a national nonprofit organization whose mission is to care for the families facing
disease of Alzheimer's disease, educate them about living a healthy brain life, and activate the next
generation of Alzheimer's advocates. Richard Isaacson should be a familiar name for some of
you as he was a guest on a previous episode of The Drive in late 2018 when we did a deep dive
into Alzheimer's disease. Many of you have requested follow-up podcasts on this topic. Among
them, this is one. Richard serves as the director of the Alzheimer's Prevention Clinic at Weill
Cornell, New York Presbyterian Hospital, and is an assistant dean at the office of the faculty of
Weill Cornell of Medicine. I've known Lauren for a couple of years. We actually met through Richard,
and the three of us have been talking about doing this podcast for about a year. In fact,
we were going to do it last fall, and then we put it off until the spring, and then COVID got in the
way. So this one's been a long time coming. My intuition was that being able to talk about
Alzheimer's disease with Richard and Lauren simultaneously would be a beautiful way to
discuss the human tragedy of the disease, and also to talk about the science of prevention
and the pathology of the disease. And honestly, by the end of this discussion, I felt we had
really achieved that. I think Lauren's story is both heartbreaking and uplifting for reasons that
will become clear as you listen to this. In this episode, we talk about her journey with her family
history, what led her to Richard, and ultimately what really changed the course of her life with
respect to how she treats prevention. We talk a lot about what preventative measures look like
today, and how we look at the evolving body of literature to figure out how to modify risk. So
if you have even a slight interest in the prevention of Alzheimer's disease, I think you're going to
find this episode both touching and enlightening. So without further delay, please enjoy my
conversation with Lauren Miller Rogan and Richard Isaacson. Lauren and Richard, what a privilege to
be sort of sitting down with you guys right now. We have been kicking around the idea of doing this
for about a year now. COVID kind of got in our way. We were going to do this obviously in person
last year. So while it's long overdue, I think this is just such an exciting opportunity both
to kind of hear from you, Lauren, and kind of understand your personal journey, which you've
basically taken on as your life's mission. And then obviously Richard to have you back on and kind of,
I don't know, I think bring people up to speed on what's happened in the last couple of years. So
thanks both of you for making time today. Thank you for having us. I feel like long time listener,
first time guest. Very excited to be here. Long time listener as well. Yeah, I hang on every word
of most of the podcasts, especially while I had to listen to Tom Dayspring's podcast like 14 times.
I'm still like need to listen to it on repeat. But Lauren, let's start with you. I mean, I want
people to really get an understanding of your story. So I mean, when did you first become aware
that there was something going on in your family that was robbing people of this precious thing
called their mind? Unfortunately, Alzheimer's has been a part of my life as long as I can have my own
memory. My grandfather, my mom's dad had Alzheimer's. My aunt has told me it seems like he showed
symptoms maybe in his late fifties or early sixties. But he was an interesting home. I think from the
time I was around eight or nine, maybe 10. And he passed away when I was 12. But when you're young,
that age to me, his memory issues were almost funny, right? Like he would take his teeth out
at the table. And I thought that was hysterical. And he would, you know, repeat things. And again,
like when you're little, that's funny. And I didn't have any concept of the fact that the reason he had
to go into a nursing home was because he was wandering and that my grandmother couldn't take
care of him. And then after he passed away, my grandmother started showing signs of dementia. And
you know, she was struggling to take care of herself and was clearly wasn't eating. And,
but you know, I was in high school. So again, I wasn't really that aware of the situation and
what was happening. But you know, I was aware when they brought her from her home in South Florida up
to where we were in central Florida to put her in a facility, you know, and how she was curled over
in the seat, sleeping and not aware when I was showing her how I could drive for the first time
and how she eventually stopped being able to walk or talk or feed herself. And my senior year,
I would go visit her every Friday after school and you know, a few other days during the week. But,
you know, when she spent the last year of her life curled up in a bed, obviously not talking or being
able to care for herself in any, any way at all. It was a lot at 18. And but it was still I was
younger and it was my grandmother, you know, I think when you're young and you envision your
grandparents is like, well, they're grandparents. They're, you know, this happens to them, even
though, you know, my, I think my grandmother was 76 maybe. So then she passed away. And then at my
college graduation, when I was 22, my mom was 52. She repeated a story a few times. And, you know,
my mom who was this incredibly smart, vibrant woman who was aggressive about the thing she
wanted in her life. And she didn't take no for an answer type of woman. But throughout her life,
she'd always say, when I get Alzheimer's, when I get Alzheimer's, I always say, stop saying that,
don't say that. Like, and then at my graduation, when she repeated the story a few times, I thought,
oh God, but I didn't say anything, of course. And then, you know, over the next year or two,
it became clear that this repetition was becoming a part of who she was. And she was losing control
of, you know, her ability to teach and to, you know, do any number of things that someone who
is fully functioning in a cognitive way could do. Eventually, we encouraged my dad to take her to a
doctor and, you know, over the course of a year and a half or so, we got as, you know, as much as a
diagnosis as one could get at that time.
You're just out of college. And you're being confronted with the idea that your mom is not
even in her mid fifties yet. And she's already in the early stages of Alzheimer's disease,
something that's already prematurely taken her parents. I'm guessing it's now sort of setting
in that there's something going on in your family, right?
Yeah. I mean, there was a lot of denial, I would say, a lot of fear, a lot of anger, and of course,
a lot of depression. And I think what was really hard about it at the time was my mom wouldn't let
us talk about it. And, you know, at this point, I can only imagine what her identity felt like as a
daughter of Alzheimer's herself, what was driving her at this point. But to me, things were really
starting to become clear in a really scary way at that point. I didn't talk to anyone about it,
because I didn't, I think, you know, when you talk about something, it seems real all of a sudden,
it's really happening.
Even your father?
Oh, God, especially not my dad, because my dad was the most in denial about any of us. You know,
my dad, you know, my parents had, you know, an amazing marriage, and they were best friends and
partners. And he admired my mom for her brain, and for how smart she was, and how passionate she was
about what she did, and how hard she worked. And so, yeah, he was the last one, I think, to come
around. But eventually, a few months after Seth and I started dating, actually, my parents came
out to visit, this was in 2005, to meet him and came out for my birthday. And when I dropped them
off at the airport, and I came back to Seth's apartment, it was the first time I'd said it
out loud that I was afraid my mom was developing Alzheimer's. And it was the first time I cried
about it. And he was like, no, no, she was fine. No, it's fine. And I'm like, you don't know her.
You don't know how the person you met this weekend is different than who she was. And, you know,
it was, I guess, around two years from that point of going to visit, and she'd be worse. It was
clear, you know, at some point, she shouldn't be driving. Eventually, her school decided she
shouldn't be in a traditional classroom anymore. And took her out of that classroom. It was just
who she was, was fading away and changing right in front of her eyes. She couldn't have these long
conversations anymore. She, again, would repeat herself. She would call with the same thing over
and over again. And it was devastating. I was in a very dark place at the time.
Do you have any sense that she was aware of some of these things? For example,
the idea that she could no longer teach her classes and to have that taken away from her
by her peers. Did that register with her? What was happening and why?
Yeah, you know, I never, I didn't have that direct conversation with her about it. I'm sure my dad
did. I think she took that stuff in stride probably to act like a strong independent person
for us. But when she eventually had to retire, I know she wasn't thrilled about it, but she was at
a point where cognitively she wasn't at full function anymore. And so it became a bit easier to
change her life in a way where she didn't question it, which is, you know, really sad to think about.
But I think it was, I had one conversation with her early, early on it, I read in teen magazine,
if there's ever something difficult, you want to talk to your parents about do it in the car
because the drive will eventually end. And so the awkward conversation will naturally end. So I
remember one time I was home in Florida and I was visiting them. It might've been around the time
she was forced to retire and we were driving to Target. And I asked her if she was scared
about getting Alzheimer's. And she told me that she wasn't scared for her.
She was scared for me and my brother and my dad. Because I think she got that at some point
she may not know what's happening and that the weight would be on us. I think she knew that
because of what happened with her dad and her mom. And I can only imagine how terrifying that
was for her. But I, you know, I can't understand where she was at that point, cognitively or
emotionally even, to really know the fear there. So you mentioned that this is around the time
when, I mean, it's now hitting you with the full force. Yeah. And I assume it's much less,
or maybe somewhat, but probably less about what the implications are for you and much more about
the loss of her. Yeah. Which of course, you know, I was in my early twenties, so that was only about
me. I was at a point in my life where I was just starting to become friends with her. She had a
little emotional. She had come out to visit. I moved to LA in January of 2004 and she came
out to visit in March of 2004 during her spring break. And we had such a great time being, you
know, I was 22, but, you know, a grownup. And we went to dinner, just the two of us, like as grownups
and like drank wine and like she wasn't a big drinker. She would drink a sea breeze. I remember.
And like, it felt like I was reaching that point where she was my friend, which I think, you know,
now I have so many girlfriends who their moms are their best friends. And I instantly felt
like that was being taken away from me and was so angry about it. And so jealous of all my friends
who were having those relationships with their moms and felt so hopeless. You know, I would go
online and I would just search like cure for Alzheimer's treatment for Alzheimer's gotta be
there. I know I could find it. Like I'm the kind of person who's like, if I'm going to do so, I'm
going to do it. You know? And like, no, there's something out there. I can find something for her.
And there was nothing like there was nothing. And so it was a really scary, hard time where I felt
like I could do nothing and that this train had left the station for my mom. And that was it.
So I want to give you a chance to just sort of catch your breath a bit. And Richard, I want to
sort of ask you a couple of questions right now, not necessarily specifically about Lauren's mom,
because I want to come to that in some detail later when you actually, when we get to the part
of the story where you and Lauren meet. But I want to just ask you a broader question here,
which is help a listener understand the context of this type of Alzheimer's disease. And by this
type, I mean one that is so clearly familial and also so early and onset. How do you think about
that as a neurologist? What's going through your mind as you think about this type of a case in
terms of genetic predisposition? Let's just, let's just start with the genetics of this.
Sure. So I first have to start with just, I hate this disease. I just like hate it. I hate hearing
stories. Now you're going to make me cry, Lauren. I'm on a podcast. Come on. I'm on record.
Well, no one can see us, so it's fine. Okay, good. So I just hate this disease so much because it's
so insidious. It's so nasty. It's so just, it just, it robs not just the, I mean, it robs the person
of who they are, but it robs the whole family. I mean, just like you just said, it's like it robbed
you of like the good years, like the friendship years. And that's just, so I hate this disease.
Alzheimer's disease starts in the brain decades before the first symptom of memory loss begins.
And I didn't learn that in medical school. I hate to say it, but most doctors don't know that still,
you know, the new diagnostic criteria have been out now for about a decade.
But, you know, when I hear it 52, I say, oh my gosh, what was in our thirties? What was happening in her thirties?
Like, why? Why is this happening? And then I hear the family history and I hear, wow,
her mom and her dad. Why? Why is this happening? And Lauren, we have some small world coincidences,
which we learned about later, but like my brother, he's a neurologist, he's older than me.
He took care of another one of your family members, like on another. So like, why? Why is this? And of
course, the first thing you think about is genetic. And then you think about, well, is this early onset?
What is early onset? I think most people think about Alzheimer's disease and older person's disease
greater than 70, 72, 74, what's the average age? But there's a small tiny sliver, a small, small
group that I would qualify as having early onset Alzheimer's disease due to a genetic reason where
the person usually gets Alzheimer's in their, you know, forties or fifties. But, you know, Lauren,
your family was different and we'll talk about this later. But when I hear a family history like this,
I say, well, why does certain people in one family get it later? And the other people in the family
get it earlier? This is actually earlier onset Alzheimer's and I maybe made that up. But what is
what is it? This person should have been affected in the later years and something is fast forwarding.
Something is, there's like a one plus one equals three here. There's like a mishmash of things
that just like the first thing I think about is why is this happening? And number one, I say, okay,
genetics is there's got to be some genetic something. And then number two is, okay, then
I think about, well, could it be lifestyle? Could it be an exposure to something? Could it be head
trauma? Could it be uncontrolled diabetes, high blood pressure, cholesterol? These are all things
that, you know, just synergize together to potentially make a late onset Alzheimer's case
start earlier. So these are the some of the things like, you know, detective work things that I think
about. But no, it's not typical. What genes do you think about, Richard? What are the suite of genes?
I mean, there's the obvious ones, APOE4, but there are other genes that could be implicated in early
cases. Can you say a little bit about those? Sure. So there's the typical early onset genes,
there's really only three, presenilin one, presenilin two, amyloid precursor protein gene
mutation. I can count on my two hands, how many patients I've seen with that. I've seen over 1500
patients easily, probably close to 2000 patients over the last, you know, 15 plus years. Literally
two hands. It's all I got. Lauren, you actually introduced me to one, an amazing, amazing person,
great individual and someone that I, she may have that gene, but I will not say that she will get
Alzheimer's. So for the first time in my career, I've not only figured out that someone has an
early onset gene, which means you're going to get Alzheimer's, but just wait, our field is making a
lot of progress. So, you know, these three genes are just so rare. That's number one. Most people
that have earlier onset Alzheimer's have a milieu of things. So I would call it polygenic risk. So
ApoE, ApoE4, the variant ApoE4 is the most common genetic risk factor for Alzheimer's disease. Now,
the difference between ApoE4, having one variant or two, I'll explain that in a second, means if you
get the E4, it doesn't mean you're going to get Alzheimer's. It just increases your risk. If you
get pre-Cenilin1, pre-Cenilin2 or amyloid precursor protein gene mutation, sorry for the
long words there, if you get those genes, you get Alzheimer's. That's what the book say, except in
that one person that you introduced me to Lauren, we're going to, we got time. She's in her twenties.
We're going to get this up for her. And those Richard really represent far less than 1% of the
total cases are made up of APP, PSEN1, PSEN2, for what it's worth. I've never actually seen one.
For me, those only exist in the literature. The interesting aside, by the way, is there's,
some people speculate that the index case of Alzheimer's disease was actually one of those.
And some of our understanding of this disease may be incorrect as a result of that, but we'll,
we'll kick that to another discussion. So when you meet a person like Lauren, you're not necessarily
thinking one of those three genes. You were just thinking some aggressive combination of other
things. Yep. And it's, epigenetics would be the word that I think about. So the term epigenetics
encompasses a person's genetics plus the environmental impact, the milieu of what a person
does in their lifestyle or behavior, or what they were exposed to, for example, whether it was a
virus or if it was a traumatic something, or if it was something that triggered the gene to work in
one way or another. And the term polygenic risk means that there are multiple genes that work
together. Now some genes can increase risk and some people, some genes actually decrease risk. So
the future of Alzheimer's disease, well, I believe the future of Alzheimer's disease is based in
precision medicine, using these types of genetic underpinnings, understanding all the individual
genes that impact a person's risk, figuring out what they are, figuring out what their biological
function is, figuring out why it puts a person down the path towards Alzheimer's, and then telling
that person to do A, B, C, X, Y, and Z to get them off the path towards Alzheimer's. That's the future
of Alzheimer's. And I think in a lot of ways, the future is now, but APOE is by far the most well
understood, most well researched, every patient that walks through our doors gets an APOE test,
you know, they're a commercial, like anyone can basically find out what their APOE status is,
just for the listener out there, you get one from mom and one from dad, either an APOE 2,
a 3 or a 4, it's called an allele or a variant. A lot of people call it a mutation, but it's not a
mutation. So you get a 2 or 3 or 4 from mom or dad, and a 4 increases risk a little bit, a 3 is
neutral, and a 2 actually is protective. So if someone comes in as an APOE 3, 3, that's a pretty,
you know, neutral risk, kind of boring, no big deal. APOE 2, 3, okay, maybe they have some
protection. And one 4, APOE 3, 4, for example, increases risk a little bit. And then two 4s,
APOE 4, 4s increases risk more so, but again, genes are not our destiny, we can absolutely win
the tug of war against our genes. And, you know, four 4s, I have dozens of patients in my practice
that I absolutely think that they are not going to get Alzheimer's disease, they, they're going to
be able to do some things to delay it. They also have other genes to protect them. So without
getting too detailed, APOE 4 is important. We personalize care, you know, if someone has a 4,
we're going to tell them to do certain things. Someone doesn't have a 4, we're going to do other
things for them because there are other things that are preferentially effective. But this
polygenic risk is what I'm thinking. So when I hear about Lauren's mom, like what is it? What
are her E4s? Sure. But what else? There's got to be something else. The devil is in the details there.
Dr. Justin Marchegiani, MD, MPH, CHE, MPH, FA, MD
Richard, I want to go back to Lauren to continue this story before I do. Can you explain for folks
that want a bit more of an understanding, what is it about having the E4 variant relative to
the E3 variant that increases risk? So the gene codes for protein that differs in what way from the
what we call the wild type or the E3 variant. So I guess how I would answer that is starting
by basic, what is APOE mean? APOE is apolipoprotein. That means something related to cholesterol,
people who get the gene tested in our practice actually get it through a cardiovascular disease
prevention panel. Peter, you and I have used the same labs. You may be focused more on cardiovascular
disease prevention. I focus more on Alzheimer's disease risk reduction and prevention. But
it's really a cardiovascular risk gene just as much as it is an Alzheimer's risk gene.
So the way that I think about APOE 4 is it increases vascular risk. It increases the likelihood
of a bad pathologic protein called amyloid. It's a sticky stuff that builds up in the brain of a
person with Alzheimer's. And people with this gene are more likely to have accelerated deposition
or accelerated accumulation of this amyloid protein through a, what I would call just in a
basic sense, a cholesterol-like, vascular-like pathway. There's a ton more I can talk about it.
But, you know, once you've seen one person with Alzheimer's, you've seen one person with
Alzheimer's and different people can take different roads to Alzheimer's disease. And
the APOE 4 road is actually something I kind of understand. I kind of get it. I feel good about it.
I know that may sound callous or strange, but like I know what I'm up against. Like, okay,
great. We can do lifestyle things. We can manage cholesterol in a certain way. We can do
all these different things. And I know certain things that work. And I know what I'm up against.
It's the person that actually doesn't have the E4 that I'm like, wow, they're either spared
or they have another gene lurking. How do I find it? And what the heck do I do about it? So
E4 doesn't bother me. And I feel relieved sometimes when we find it in the person.
All right. Well, I think we'll talk a little bit more about this, but,
Lauren, I want to kind of hear more from your story. So as you're now kind of coming to grips
with the fact that your mom is slowly slipping away. And you're also realizing that unlike,
oh, if my mom has premature heart disease for which there is no shortage of treatments,
you're realizing actually your ability to access the best in medical care isn't really going to
do much. What's the temporal course of her progression? So as we get, let's say fast
forward to when you and Seth get married, which is 10 years ago. How is she at that point,
which is still probably putting her in her late fifties, right?
She just turned 60. So at that point, she could still walk. She was,
there were moments where she knew us. No, she knew us. She knew that we were her family and that
we were her loved ones. But she was at that point being fully cared for by my father at that point,
but she could still dress herself and bathe herself and use the restroom. But planning,
I would say planning my wedding was a real emotional turning point for me because it was,
I always was the kind of girl who envisioned my wedding and it was to be this thing. And then my
mom and I would do it together. And that is just not what happened at all to the point where,
I couldn't even have her there when I was getting ready because she would just be wandering. And my
dad had to take her to a separate hair appointment because it would just, would be too disruptive
to get everything together to have her there. But when she walked in, I remember that morning,
I'll back up a bit to say we had a bit of a weekend, our wedding. And Friday night was a small
thing and Saturday and Saturday night, there was a dinner and it was not good. We had taken my mom
from her home, which for an Alzheimer's patient, for anyone with dementia is difficult to take
someone out of their space, their routine, where they know everything and they are familiar with
their, their world. So that of course had put her in a place where I think she was probably
feeling very scared because she didn't understand where she was or what was happening. And at our
rehearsal dinner the night before, I remember her telling me she just wanted to go home,
which was, you know, really hard to handle. But then miraculously, the day of like she walked in
and she called me the bride and she knew that I was the bride and that I think she knew that I
was her daughter, but she knew she felt proud. She knew she felt love. And I have an amazing
photo of her like looking at me and holding my hand. And it's just, she knows that, you know,
there's a connection there, but it wasn't, you know, it wasn't the moment that I had certainly
dreamed of. And I feel like it was my dad and I that walked her down the aisle instead of him and
her walking me down the aisle. And, you know, normally in Jewish weddings, the family stands up
next to the bride and groom. And we didn't do that. We had them sitting next to us because we
knew my mom couldn't do that. So at that point she was, you know, she hadn't, she wasn't teaching
anymore. That was a few years earlier that had ended. So it was, for me, it was a really hard
thing, but luckily she rose to the occasion that day, which, you know, it's interesting throughout
this journey with her. You know, I think people that don't understand the disease, trying to find
some sort of lightness and hope would always be like, but she must have good days sometimes. She
must remember you sometimes. Does she, does she remember you sometimes? And I would always be like,
no, it's gone. Like that's gone. It's not like sometimes you remember like,
oh, I use my legs for walking. Like once that's gone, that's gone. But for whatever reason,
the day of my actual wedding, I will say she was as there as anyone could be in her state. And that
was an amazing thing. But, but overall it was, it was only a few months after that that we encourage
my parents to move out to Los Angeles because, you know, my dad, it was clear that it was killing,
it was going to kill my dad before it killed her. The stress of taking care of her. He always talks
about the plane ride home from our wedding was like the worst five hours of his life.
Because she had had an accident in her seat on the airplane and was acting out and was screaming. And
they had to get help to get off the plane when they landed back in Florida. And it was a, you
know, a pretty horrific time. I mean, these are some of the things that we're going to talk a lot
about Hilarity for Charity and why the focus is on the family, which I think is part of why I'm so
excited about it. And you can ask me a hundred times to do something for it. And I'll always
say yes. So you always apologize. Don't say that. But, but, but I really, I'm really so fond of
organizations that take that step and appreciate what is being done for the family. Too often,
people think the only way to make a difference is to fund research. And clearly that's important,
but it's too easy to ignore that while we're waiting for these things to happen,
people need help in caring for this. And I suppose there's no disease where that's more true than
than this one. Absolutely. Richard, can you just spend a minute kind of explaining
what it is about the deposition of these plaques, the accumulation of the tau?
Why does it lead to this largely predictable set of symptoms that don't just involve almost a folksy
funny loss of memory, right? But also at some of this deeper level of this, what I suspect is fear
and confusion on some level, right? Like why would she be upset on the airplane? Well, I'm guessing on
some level there's a sense of fear, right? There's something is wrong. Why is she not able to
control her bowel or bladder? Like how is this disease wreaking so much havoc on the central
nervous system, Richard? Yeah. So there's actually a couple who I believe were both pathologists,
Brock and Brock, B R A K. And what they did was they kind of came up with the Brock staging of,
of pathology where the, with amyloid protein and then the pathology of Alzheimer's spreads over
different parts of the brain. And, you know, when I was in medical school, I was taught that
Alzheimer's disease, a progressive neurological disease characterized by changes in short term
memory. And then later on that includes changes in some behaviors, neuropsychiatric disease,
changes in sleep. And then the person as the pathology spreads, they can no longer take care
of themselves. What we really now understand about Alzheimer's is it's a much more heterogeneous
disease, meaning wherever the pathology goes, those are the symptoms that manifest. So there are
newer forms of Alzheimer's and they're newer because they're now published in the literature,
but we've seen this for decades. There's one newer form that has something called a
dis-executive syndrome. Well, what does that mean? Executive function is higher order processing,
judgment, planning. You know, you find a wallet on the floor. What do you do with it?
Right. Peter would take the money out, put the money in his pocket, throw the wallet back on
the floor. You know, you know, Lauren, she's very empathetic and compassionate. She'd look at the
license, you know, she'd say, Oh, I'm going to go find this guy. I'm going to go to the ends of the
earth to find this person's wallet. So that's executive function. Maybe depends on how much is
in there. Exactly. That's one form of Alzheimer's. You know, another form of Alzheimer's is part
PART primary age related tauopathy. So we've talked about amyloid, but what about tau? It has
another protein and there's tau and amyloid and neurofibrillary tangles. And then there's glucose
hypometabolism, meaning the glucose, the sugar in the brain, it's just not being efficiently able
to be used to power the brain cells. So depending on where the problem is, you have different
manifestations, cognitive symptoms, I guess. And PART, for example, is primary age related
tauopathy. Again, one more time it's related to age. So it's usually an older people easily 70s,
more likely 80s and 90s. And it's specifically short-term memory. And it's specifically because
that pathology is localized to the memory centers in the brain, the hippocampus, for example,
but that person can still have good executive function. The frontal lobe, the front part of
the brain is working. So it just depends. It depends, you know, for example, there's
when the pathology, when the bad stuff goes to the back part of the brain, that's where the visual
fibers are. So the eyes are in the front, but they have visual protections that go to the back. You
interpret images. Well, when someone can interpret images, they get confused. They act funny. They may
be weird. They may be, you know, confused, but it's not exactly a memory problem. It's a visual
perception problem. So, you know, I don't want to be cheeky, but like, I mean, Richard, no, no,
this is, this is very interesting and I've never really thought of it this way, but as you probably
are aware, we don't really think of cancer as one disease anymore. Right. I mean, I mean, that's,
it's been a while that nobody's thought of cancer as one disease. So breast cancer and colon cancer
have very little in common. I mean, about the only thing they have in common is unregulated cell
growth, but thereafter they're very different diseases, not just in the ability to impact a
different organ. And it sounds like what you're saying is Alzheimer's is not really one disease.
It's kind of an umbrella term that encompasses many different diseases of the brain that have
some common features in the way that cancers, all cancers have some common features that, you know,
cells don't respond to normal signaling. But this notion that someone could have a form of Alzheimer's
that largely spares the frontal cortex and therefore preserves some higher order functioning
versus another person that has something that's not, I mean, listening to this story of Lauren's
mom, just hearing what we've heard so far, how would you think about the etiology or the insult?
Well, I'll try not to bias my answer because I know a lot about Lauren's mom and Lauren's whole
family. But if I just took for face value, what Lauren said that symptoms began with little
repeating of stories and memory glitches around 52 to 54 to where she had to have then a modified
work schedule to then six years later, she's having trouble caring for herself, maybe not
recognizing her daughter, and then having emotional behavioral psychiatric components.
I mean, that sounds like Alzheimer's disease. That sounds like progressive short term memory
loss plus behavior changes plus, you know, other things. So it sounds like she started in the mild
cognitive impairment phase with the symptoms. So there's just three phases of Alzheimer's,
three stages, maybe we should take a step back for listeners. The first stage is actually the
preclinical phase, the pre symptomatic phase where Alzheimer's disease has started in the brain,
but there are no symptoms yet, no clinically apparent symptoms. Believe it or not, there are
46 million Americans with Alzheimer's disease in their brain right now, but no symptoms.
That's crazy. I've never heard that before. That number, that's wow.
Yeah, I try to keep that close to my vest because-
How do we know that, Richard?
That's what the studies say, you know, I don't know, you're the critical appraiser of studies,
I'll have to send you the study and you can tear it apart, Peter.
You're going to bring this one to Journal Club next month.
What a great idea. I love those Journal Clubs.
That sounds like the nerdiest club of all time.
Oh my. And we've discussed you and we've discussed-
It is nerdy.
It is pretty freaking nerdy. And we record it and then we watch it and we-
Oh my God.
I was captain of my math team at Colmack High School.
Well, there you go. Nevermind. It sounds really cool then.
Thank you. Thank you. Also the alma mater of Lauren's mom, high five, go Colmack,
and Lauren's uncle and some others. Anyway, so this preclinical,
pre-symptomatic phase is by far the most important phase, I think, well, maybe to focus on because
that would be prevention of Alzheimer's. You can call it either treating preclinical Alzheimer's or
secondary prevention of Alzheimer's because you're trying to prevent the dementia from happening.
So stage one is preclinical Alzheimer's. Stage two is mild cognitive impairment due to Alzheimer's
where there are enough memory glitches and other changes to where it's noticeable. It's greater
than a standard deviation and a half below the norm, but the person can still take care of
themselves. So I think Lauren, when your mom started having symptoms, she was easily in the
borderline preclinical to MCI stage. And then people have roughly between a 12 and 16%
per year, depending on what study you read, chance of converting from MCI, mild cognitive impairment
due to Alzheimer's to dementia due to Alzheimer's. And the only difference is, is they still have the
symptoms. They're just worse and they can no longer take care of themselves. So, you know, Lauren,
many people would be very pleased and thankful that if symptoms started at 52
and she was able to attend your wedding at 60, I mean, that's parable, but better than it could have
been in the grand scheme. At least she was there, you know, I have friends who, who unfortunately
lost, had weddings without parents there. So because they had lost them already. So, yeah,
absolutely. So, so these are the stages. Okay. It's a staggering number. And whether it's 46 million
or 36 million or whatever the number is, you know, it's not surprising in the sense that if
when you look at how many people are pre-diabetic and you think about how that is one of the
pathways to Alzheimer's disease, sort of the energy dependent pathway, it's very plausible,
especially when you consider the other pathways. Richard, one thing I want to park with you to
come back to is some thinking around how many different variants of the disease there are,
right? Sort of the lipid variant of the disease, the toxin variant, the potentially an infectious
variant, if such, if one such exists. So maybe we'll, I'll let you think about that for a minute.
So Lauren, I want to talk about how you made your way to, to Richard, because that's how you and I
met you and I met through Richard, but I want to know how you and Richard met. Sure. So, okay. I'll
try to keep this somewhat brief. I feel like it might be long. This is a hilarious story. I'm
sorry. I remember this like a video in my mind, but anyway, I don't want to interrupt. So in 2011,
it was the year that I got married. It was the year I shot for a Good Time Call. And it was the
first year that we planned the first Hilarity for Charity event, which was January of 2012. So
2011 was a pivotal year for me. Up until that point, like I said, I had been really dark and
depressed and I'd been trying to work and I, you know, I'm a screenwriter and I was writing, but like
I just spent a lot of time just being pretty dark and pretty upset. And then a friend came to me and
was like, let's throw an event and raise money for Alzheimer's. And I was like, no. But then he wore
me down. Thank God. And we did. And so in January of 2012, we threw our first variety show to raise
money for the Alzheimer's association. And that was, you know, an incredible event. We raised a few
hundred thousand dollars, but was the most incredible part of that was that we were contacted
by young people who felt seen for the first time because they were seeing me in my, you know,
late twenties and my husband in his late twenties talk about Alzheimer's, which, you know, even for
me up until that point, every image of Alzheimer's I had seen was of someone who was old and gray and
not at all related to me in any way that I could understand. So we felt like we had an opportunity
to continue talking and to continue hopefully gathering people and helping them feel like they
too had a place in this disease, which is considered a disease for old people. And so that's when we
kind of decided to form our own little organization, which was a fund within the Alzheimer's
association for many years in 2017 became our own 501c3. But during that time, of course,
we became Alzheimer's advocates and I met many smart people and doctors and scientists and other
advocates who were doing all sorts of incredible work. We became friendly with Maria Shriver,
who of course has always used her platform to raise awareness about Alzheimer's and is so,
so incredible. And I had really sort of gotten to know the Alzheimer's community a bit.
So then my uncle, who is my mom's brother, who was five years older than her,
was starting to show symptoms. Now, my uncle, who was an athlete his whole life, he was, and in his
later life started when he was, I don't know, I guess maybe in his 40s, riding a bike and was a
obsessive bike rider and he was in great shape and he's a big, strong, muscular guy. And we'll get
into some of the other things why Alzheimer's happened in my mom earlier than it did with him,
but he started showing symptoms. And I wasn't allowed to talk about that publicly at the time.
Unfortunately, he passed away in March this year, only a month after my mom and his family, my aunt
and my cousins have fortunately now given permission to tell his story so it can potentially help.
So he was starting to show symptoms and they were on the East coast. So they came to me and said,
what do we do? What do we do at this point? And at this point, by the way, my mom was very advanced
at this point that they were out here. This was, I don't know what Richard, it was 2014, 15, 16 even,
17. And basically I'd reached out to a doctor that I knew was like, my uncle's on the East coast,
I want to get him into the best of the best. Who is it? And this person recommended Richard.
The best of the best looking, I hope.
The best looking Alzheimer's doctor there could, yes, exactly.
Thankfully, this is a podcast.
That's what my uncle was hoping for was the best looking Alzheimer's doctor.
The one with the best phones, I think is what it was really.
Definitely the best phone. Well, I mean, certainly I've listened to that episode where we talk about,
where you guys talked about Richard's phones. Oh God, he's showing one. Everyone's missing it.
There's rhinestones, there's a horse on the back at the top. Are those not rhinestones?
Diamonds, hello.
Oh, diamonds. Excuse me. Those are diamonds.
It's a diamond pillow. Come on.
Anyway, so gave me Richard's name and I went on his website and I found his direct email address.
Because of course, again, I'm not the kind of person who's like, I'm going to be polite and
keep my mouth shut and follow the rules to get to where I need to go. I'm going to do what I got to do.
So I found his direct email address and was like, hi, here's who I am. This is what I've done.
My uncle has Alzheimer's and needs your help. And so he wrote me back right away.
And then of course, then we connected that he was from COMAC and that my mom and my uncle had
gone to the same high school as Richard, which is what a small world. He of course,
got my uncle in there right away and they went on the journey that they went on.
So then I was in LA and then once I connected them, I came to New York a few months later or
something and I said, I'm coming to New York. I want to come see the clinic, come meet you.
And then of course, I'm seeing the clinic and talking to him and I was like, I want in.
I want to be a patient. I want to prevent Alzheimer's. Let me in. Help my brain.
You literally like, I don't know how to do this, but like, like shot out your arm and said like,
take my blood now. Let's do it. And like literally you walked into the clinic. We like literally
stuck a needle. You signed a consent form and then like, it was the quickest, most rapid Alzheimer's
prevention consult in the history of our program. So lucky for me, lucky for me.
What kind of shape was your uncle in at that point in time? I actually didn't realize this
part of the story that that the initial connection with Richard was actually a consultation for your
uncle. Is that presumably because at that point you felt your mom was just advanced enough that
that it. Yeah. No, at that point, my mom was she was fully bedridden. I'm pretty sure at that point
getting everything fed to her fully cared for. There was her train had long left the station.
So your mom at that point would have been in her early sixties, I guess. And your uncle is a little
older, did you say? Yeah. So he's five years older than her. And he was, you know, I would say in that,
that MCI and that mild cognitive impairment space, right, Richard, or even almost a little before
that it was, he was a very functional guy. I, you know, with both my mom and my uncle, and you know,
and you guys can speak to this more about other people, they could both like rise to the, the
occasion in a way. And so, you know, I knew that what my aunt was seeing with my uncle was different
than what I saw, that he could somehow dig deep and put on a show, if you will, and act like he
was still in control. But there were little things, little hints that that wasn't happening. Whereas my
mom, we were far past that point. Richard, let's talk a little bit about now the beginning, you
go down this path of kind of being a detective. So you're never going to get to meet the parents,
the grandparents in this case, but the parents of your first patient, but you know enough about
their story. You're meeting Lauren's uncle. You know about Lauren's mom, though you haven't met her.
How are you now starting to piece together this family? First, for the standpoint of trying to
understand if anything can be done to help Lauren's uncle, but ultimately to really figure
out what to do to help Lauren and her brother. Yeah, this is detective work. This is a spelunking
mission down the deepest, darkest cave with no light. And, you know, instead of a pickaxe,
I don't know, maybe with a plastic fork and knife. Let me take a step back. Lauren, before I met your
mom, I saw a video of your mom, which kind of changed things for me. This was a video of a movie,
actually, that you can maybe talk about. He'd worked on and I had actually watched. I don't
know if it was a clip online or maybe it was something you sent me and seeing the video of
your mom from the, I don't know, you can tell me eight something years before the present that was
so instructive. I mean, I, I don't know how to explain this, but like, I'm not psychic or anything
like that, but I trust my gut. And when I see people sometimes, this is going to sound weird,
but I think it's true. I see genes. I see, I don't know. My gut just feels something and I can,
I don't know if it's just because I've seen the pattern so many times there's genotype, meaning
the genes and the phenotype, which is the, you know, the physical real world manifestations of
genes, but there was something about your mom, her behavior, her mannerisms, her, I don't know,
her, her shape or her face. I mean, I don't want to get too like kooky and weird, but like there
was something that my gut or my subconscious just saw. And your mom was a little confusing to me
because I saw something consistent with Alzheimer's, but there was, you know, my gut said that there's
something else. This is, this is just strange. This is not clearly Alzheimer's. This, this could
be something else. And then when I talked to you, Lauren, about, and really I talked to, you know,
your aunt and your uncle, and I learned all the intricate details, I just learned that this was,
this was more complicated than Alzheimer's. Maybe there's Alzheimer's on one side, but there's
Alzheimer's plus something else on another. And I don't know if, I don't know if I never told you
the story, but your uncle brought in his Komak High School yearbook. I don't know if we're talking
about that. Yeah. And then, I don't know. And then when I was actually at your place in LA, your,
I think your dad found your mom's Komak High School graduation yearbook. And this is going to sound
even kookier, but you can tell in the handwriting, your grandparents signed your mom's yearbook and
your uncle's yearbook. And they were five years apart. And I could tell in the handwriting,
there's like research to support this, but you know, you could just tell by the change in the
handwriting over the years and just the, you know, like Alzheimer's is a neurological disease. There's
other neurological conditions like Parkinson's disease, dementia with Lewy bodies. And in
Parkinson's disease, when you, when you start writing, as you write more and more that the
writing gets smaller and there's like a shaky nature to the writing, this is really hard to
explain. I don't know. Something about the handwriting was just different and about the
word choice. Like, you know, there was a study that looked at nuns and the nuns wrote their
autobiographical sketches and like their late teens. And then depending on analysis of, of their
autobiographies that they wrote, you could predict which nuns were going to get dementia 60 years
later. So there's a lot, you know, I believe Alzheimer's is a life course disease. Yet
literally people with the APOI 4 variant, one or two copies have smaller brains when they're born.
So I know we say Alzheimer's is, you know, starts 20 to 30 years before in the brain.
Well, that may be because of the biomarkers of Alzheimer's that we can detect are noticeable
then. But I believe Alzheimer's is a life course disease. And sorry for the long story here,
but I learned a lot about your family from the clues that I got from those videos and the
handwriting samples of your grandparents. So I guess I would start with that. And then
I think I just said earlier, but my brother brand completely randomly cared for another
one of your family. My great uncle. Your great uncle. I mean, like just completely
strange and bizarre, but you know, I actually talked to my brother about him and we just start
to put the clues together. So, so first we do the detective work and kind of the investigative part.
And then we just do a clinical history. We ask about all sorts of things from medical history
to what are the risk factors or a parent. We did some genetic testing, which was critical.
So we just try to put together lots of different pieces to the puzzle and do as best as we can
with the information we have to personalize or individualize a person's care.
So Richard and Lauren, I don't know if you and if you don't, if you don't have permission to talk
about Lauren's uncle's case, then we don't need to talk about it at all. But if we do so, I'm
curious, Richard, you have this clinical history that is at least for me would be very overwhelming.
I realize that a lot of people walk into your clinic with stories as tragic and as complicated
as this. But what are the things you most want to see come back out of that blood work once you have
a very detailed clinical history? At this point, you've probably established that brother and
sister are on the same pathway, though sister is moving much quicker in Lauren's mom versus uncle.
The apoegenotype comes back. What does it show? And what does that tell you?
All I can say is my brain kept asking why, why, why, why, why, like, why did Lauren's mom have
symptoms at 52? But Lauren's uncle, five years older, start having symptoms in his late 60s,
or maybe it was early 70s. Why, why, why, why, why, why was there this 15 something year old?
What is going on here? So the first thing I think about is, and this is also because of a
genotype phenotype thing, I felt or smelled or whatever it was that there was some E4 or something
apoegenotype something. Or when I saw that video, your mom, I don't know, again, this is weird,
but your mom was E4. I actually thought she was E4. I'll just be frank.
She was for four.
Yeah, I know. Well, I know.
Exactly.
I mean, from the video.
Yeah, from the video. Yeah. And again, I don't, this is weird talking about when it's being
recorded, but like, I don't know, I've seen a lot of patients. So I can just, you know, I can,
I don't know, something subconscious when your uncle walked in for four.
But just to be clear, Richard, did you think that Lauren's mom was for four because of how early
it affected her or because of the fact that she had such a clear history of disease on both sides
of the family? Honestly, I guess what I'm saying now is I saw her on video and the phenotype that
I saw that the, the, her body makeup, her habitus, her structure, again, sounds weird,
but I saw for four, I felt for four. Plus, of course, in my subconscious mind, I knew she
got it early. I knew the parents, I knew her parents, Lauren's grandparents got it later.
So it just fit. And also big, big, big, you heard it here first. No, this is common knowledge.
I hope, or it should become knowledge. Women with the E4 variant, much higher risk.
I mean, women with E4 are very different than men with E4. And I think most people just
completely are not aware of that. And then Lauren, I forget when this came up, but I don't know if I
asked you this, but I said, when did your mom go through menopause? And then you told me about the
hysterectomy and they took the ovaries out. And I said, Oh my goodness, my goodness. I said, wow,
E4, four, even though I don't think we had the genetics at the time, or maybe we did plus the,
you know, surgical menopause, taking out, you know, immediate withdrawal of estrogen and taking out
the ovaries. Back then we had no idea relationship to Alzheimer's or anything else. Plus she's a
woman and there's a synergistic, you know, impact on risk. So it kind of was the perfect storm. But,
but still a four, four plus a woman plus a plus a hysterectomy. There had to have been something else.
And then we went on a spelunking mission to find the something else.
Lauren, how old was your mom when she had a hysterectomy? Was she in her 40s, late 40s?
I want to say she was 46, maybe 47, but I'm pretty sure it was 46.
All right. You've alluded to this just in passing a moment ago. I want you to expand on it a little
bit. You basically created a little bit of a contrast between your uncle and your mom in terms
of lifestyle, your uncle being exercising constantly. Tell us a little bit about your
mom. Obviously you've spoken about her intellectually and you mentioned she didn't
consume much alcohol. What other lifestyle factors do you know about her? Did she sleep well?
Was she under a lot of stress? What was her diet like? How much did she exercise? Did she
smoke? Any other things that you can tell us? I mean, she never, she never smoked. She told me
once she tried to smoke a cigarette in high school and threw up and never did again. So that's why I
never smoked a cigarette. But she did not exercise. We were a big sugar house who had dessert every
night. She probably had cookies most nights after dinner. She used her brain every single day,
but was she constantly learning new things? A little. She taught first grade for 15 years.
And so, you know, sure. Could she have been learning things? Yes. But was she recycling
information that she had already learned potentially? But I think, you know, knowing what I know now,
she got almost no cardio exercise and she ate a lot of sugar. And combining those things with,
you know, her family history, of course, and then of course the hormonal issues that
arose from her hysterectomy, you know, seemed to really put her on the path that she
eventually went down. Do you know if she had any difficulty sleeping prior to the
hysterectomy? I can only imagine afterwards it was devastating. But yeah, I mean, it's funny.
She and my uncle and my grandfather were similar sleepers, I would say, and that they would fall
asleep on the couch every night and then wake up super early. That's as much information that I
got from her. But like, you know, of course, less as I get older, but like I'm the kind of person who
loves to sleep and is very happy to sleep, whereas like she wasn't a big sleeper. She
definitely did herself no favors with her sleep habits, especially again, knowing what we know now.
She did not use her sleep to help her brain at all. I just want to comment one thing. And I talked
to your dad about this at some point. When you looked at your mom when she was in the 80s and 90s,
your mom was not unhealthy by any means. No, no, I don't want to paint the picture of her as being
this like disgustingly unhealthy person who didn't care about herself. It wasn't that,
it just she didn't make the effort that is needed that we know now to, as Richard said, to take
control of the genes that she had been given. In prevention, in the prevention space in
preventative medicine or preventative health, at least the way I think about it is there's normal
and then there's optimal. Your mom for the time, that was kind of the typical, what I would call
your mom now is maybe they heard the term skinny fat, skinny on the outside, fat on the inside.
I don't know what your mom's waist circumference was in high school versus her waist circumference
in her 40s and 50s. Yeah, I can guarantee you it was larger based on my understanding of the
pathology of this disease. But back then that wasn't really talked about or thought about.
In the 80s, it was like when 10,000 steps came about, like who came up with 10,000
sorry, I know who came up with it, but I understand that there's some better than nothing and
calculating, but 10,000 steps is like so antiquated. It's like, it's like, you know,
literally the 80s compared to now we truly understand physical fitness and how to optimize
physical performance. Your mom was not unlike most middle aged women at the time.
You know, and the difference between her and my uncle or even, you know, me and my brother is like,
my mom was never an athlete. Like I was a gymnast growing up. My brother was a baseball player. My
uncle ran track and then he got into cycling and was always a physically active person. Whereas my
mom was an intellectually active person. She read, she, you know, like I said, she was a great
student. She loved to learn and then to teach, but she didn't use her body in a way that perhaps
could have at least delayed what, you know, her genes were leading her toward.
When someone meets me at a cocktail party or I think you asked me that question, Peter,
what are the three things that you tell someone when they, yeah, I refused to answer it. I was
like out walking the dogs the other day and someone, someone asked me the same question.
I'm like, well, but, but the number one thing by far is exercise and physical activity,
but it's not just like, you know, going for a walk. It's, there's physical activity and then
there's physical exercise and the difference is key. Cardiovascular and strength training.
And there's just so many degrees, high intensity interval training specifically for this case,
you know, high intensity interval training is probably the only thing that can move the needle
in terms of certain aspects of cognitive function and people with the APOE4 variant.
And like no one knew any of that even a few years ago, let alone a decade ago. So
optimization of physical activity is key. And your uncle, just so we can paint the picture,
your uncle was like, he was a machine. He was a beast. Yeah. He was rich. I mean,
you know, he could put Pete, I don't know him and Peter next to each other, be close.
You know, I'm scrawny or whatever compared, but he was ripped. He just looked great.
He, his leg muscles were like, Oh my word. Yeah.
My goodness. And because of that, your metabolism is better. All these different things.
Richard, was he three, four or four, four? He was four, four also.
I see. Okay. So this is very interesting, right? Because until you have that information,
you could say, well, maybe the reason everything came to him so much later is he was the three,
four, his sisters, the four, four. And that explains the 15 year gap, but to have them both
be four, four, you're basically looking at gender inclusive of the removal of hormones,
lifestyle factors. It's some, probably some combination of those things that's explaining
it. Can you explain a little bit the gender issue? Again, most people who follow the research will
be very well aware that Alzheimer's disease disproportionately affects women. The answer
that used to be thrown about was, well, that's because women live longer. Anybody who understands
even first order mathematics will realize that the increase in expected lifespan of women does not
fully explain that. So there must be something else. Do you think that it's the loss of hormones
that explains the remainder of that gap? Or do you think it's even something beyond that?
Yeah. So I would have answered that question just like you did with the age thing, you know,
even five, six, seven years ago. And then it was one day on some television, something where
someone kept elbowing me, someone named Maria, our friend Maria Shriver. It's like, no, no,
you got to figure it out. But why do women? No, no, no, two out of every three brains of,
of Alzheimer's or women's brains. And we don't know why Isaac's and go figure it out. And I said,
yes, ma'am, I'll go do it. I think I understand much better now. And in that category of likelihood
is during the perimenopause transition, there are bioenergetic shifts in the brain
that absolutely can predispose a woman to accelerated Alzheimer's pathology.
And we call it the window of opportunity during the perimenopause transition. If we can
intervene the right way at the right time in the right woman, I believe that we can negate
a reasonable amount, if not much of careful with my words, of the negative impact of this
precipitous drop of estrogen, which I believe is neuroprotective, again, the right type of
estrogen, the right whatever the natural estrogen, I believe is protective, whether we get into
hormone replacement, that could be a different part of the conversation and which types and
what this and what that but the bioenergetic shifts during the perimenopause transition,
why do people have perimenopause? What are the symptoms that get hot flashes, right?
Night sweats. Talk about that. Oh, boy. Night sweats.
I don't know what you're talking about.
No, not at all. Irritability, never.
Never.
So all of these different things, it's a brain disease. Perimenopause is a brain condition.
Those are manifestations of the hormone withdrawal in the brain. And those are the
symptoms that brain fog. I used to think, I'll just be very frank, I was completely dead wrong.
Like women that had perimenopause and they had this brain fog thing, maybe they're just not
sleeping, right? Maybe. Well, no, they're not sleeping, right? And their sleep is interrupted
because of this bioenergetic shift. And heck yeah, you're going to have brain fog. And now
we know what it looks like. I hate that term brain fog. It's so nonspecific. You know, it's
problems with processing speed and attention. And that's how I think of it. But perimenopause is a
brain disease. So I think that's really important. And this bioenergetic shift is like, it's like,
if you want to fast forward brain aging, like in a woman in it, sorry, in a susceptible woman,
because not all women are created equal, an E4 for a woman, a surgical menopause, meaning taking
out the ovaries with the, with the, with the uterus. Wow. That's that could do it. Now,
I don't want to say this in all cases. It again, depends on the individual person, but perimenopause
transition is a huge unrealized risk factor for progression to dementia in an Alzheimer's
susceptible woman. And just be careful and listen to those words, because just because you're going
through perimenopause does not mean you're going to get Alzheimer's, but in susceptible people,
it is. And, and I really believe that from a precision medicine perspective, we can intervene
with specific hormones in specific ways. Is it a patch? Is it a gel? Is it a, you know,
all these different things you need estrogen, what type of estrogen from horses from, you know,
from, from natural, from what about progesterone? When do we add it? And these are things that I
talk, I talk to an OBGYN every other week now. I'm a neurologist. What the heck? So, so I could
talk about this for a long time, but just, just know that the, the, this hormone thing is real.
That's where you think the bulk of it is then Richard is, it's less about the age gap or the
age advantage likely, you know, the sort of lifespan advantage women have. And you think it's
the elephant in the room is this enormous hormonal shift. I think that's the most under-recognized
slash largest impact in a lot of women, but I have to take a step back and age is the number
one risk factor for Alzheimer's women plus age. So a 65 year old woman with the APOE4 with at least
one or two APOE4 variants. That's like the perfect storm. Plus you add in this, you know,
the perimenopause transition, but you know, there's individual things when it comes to a woman's life
of, for example, there's more widows than widow worse. And widowhood is a astronomically important
risk factor for cognitive decline and dementia. Also women specifically with abdominal obesity,
let's talk, let's, let's, or sorry, enlarged waist circumference, visceral fat is as the belly size
gets larger, the memory center of the brain gets smaller. And we now know that in women specifically,
women have a 39% increased risk of dementia when they have, you know, enlarged waist
circumference is over a certain degree and, and they're impacted more so than men. When I think
of a woman and I think of body composition, I'm really paying attention to body fat. And I'm not
just paying attention, like weight. I don't care about for women. I care about what's percent body
fat and where is the fat? Is it visceral or is otherwise cellulite on the thighs? I don't care.
Oh, thank God. Belly fat. Thank you. Thank you. Great. You don't have cellulite in your thighs.
You're on the Attia Isaacson program. Thank goodness. This is a podcast. No,
you beat, you beat me in, in the spin clay. You were, you were awesome there. I did.
That was impressive. I was dying. So where the fat is key, like in men, I really believe,
and I think evidence is coming around to support this, but muscle mass in men is more important
as opposed to body fat, especially visceral fat in women as a specific individual sex specific
risk factor to results. So I was going to ask you about that, Richard. Do you think that part of the
sex difference is that men have more lean mass than women? So it's that they have greater capacity
for glucose disposal and that that could be an independent predictor beyond the loss of hormones.
I don't know. I think we need to tease this out. You know, we're honestly doing one of the,
if not the only one of the very few studies where we're looking at, you know, pretty comprehensive
brain imaging on, on women and men between the ages of 40 to 65. Lauren, you don't qualify yet
because you're still a baby. Thank you. But one day you'll, you'll jump in. We're going to be able
to answer this question, I hope in the next five to seven to 10 years or sooner, but I don't know
the answer to that question. So Lauren, you finally decide you also now want to be a part of this
prevention program. You're watching your uncle hopefully have his disease course slowed.
You're watching your mom in the final stages of her life. What is the hardest thing for you to hear
from Richard once you get through that initial diagnostic workup and battery of tests? What are,
what are the things you're now starting to confront about yourself? What do you learn? First of all,
Oh God, where do I begin? I mean, I, I learned a lot. Well, I mean, first of all, I learned my
APOE status, which is that I'm a three, four. Okay. So that means you got a four from mom and
obviously a three from dad. Right. And you know, I felt okay. I didn't throw it. You know, it's
funny. My, my brother had done 23 and me a couple of years before, before we knew Richard before
anything. And he got it back and it was like, you know, and this is early on in 23 me. So I don't
even know if it said APOE four, it said like Alzheimer's risk. Yes. And he freaked out. But
then by a few years later, I think it was like, you know, and it even could have been the information
that came with that along with Richard, which is, this is not the genes that he had been talking
about before, which are you're going to get Alzheimer's. This is even a four, four. This
is a three, four. And there are things that we can do to modify my risk. And so I, again,
as I touched on as someone who's like, if I'm going to do it, I want to do it and dive in on it.
So I, don't get me wrong. I wasn't like, yes, I have a three, four. And so let's celebrate. But
like I felt, you know, okay, I have this information. Science is telling me there's
something I can do. Why don't I do it? But it was easier in the beginning. I kind of,
have I been a patient of the clinic for four or five years, five, five, at least four or five
years. Yeah. At least, you know, when I kind of like half started, I was like, you know,
a little better at my diet and a little less sugar. And you know, when I were, I exercised,
but not, not what I needed to be doing. And then certainly then, and in the year leading up to
when I met you, Peter was, you know, I was directing a movie that year. And that is certainly
not the time where you have all the space in your life to take control of your health. So that it's
certainly, I fell off the wagon during my sitting on my ass in an editing room for eight or nine
hours a day was, I didn't exercise before that. You know what I mean? It felt like power in a way.
And it took me a while to figure out how to harness that power and what lifestyle changes
I needed to adopt and to change. And certainly took both of you at different points in my journey
to help me and guide me. And I'm lucky for that. But to me, it felt exciting. You know, people often
are like, aren't you scared? How do you, why would you want to know blah, blah? And I'm just like,
why don't you want to know science gives us tools. I don't want to live in the dark and not use the
few tools that I've been given at this point. That seems way worse to me. So I felt very lucky
that I was, you know, getting to access your smart brains and of course, other people that I've met
and take some control over my genes. It is an interesting point you raised, Lauren, because,
and I may have even told this story on a podcast before, but I remember maybe 2014 or so I had a
husband wife that were both in the practice and simultaneously coming in and did blood tests on
both of them. And we always do screen for APOE on the way in. And each of them came back three,
four, three, four, they have three children. So one, I'm explaining to them what the E4, E4 means
for them. And I'm also saying, look, you know, your kids are young now, but at some point it's
going to make sense probably in their twenties to do a screen on them, because there's a 25% chance
that each of them will be a four, four, a 50% chance that there'll be three, four, and a 25%
chance there'll be three threes. And I think because their kids were girls, I wasn't so worried
about head trauma. If their kids were boys, I probably would have said I would even test
sooner to really revisit, you know, if they, if, if they're thinking about playing football,
I would probably reconsider that in the case of any four Richard, I'd like to hear your thoughts
on that, by the way. Anyway, the point of the story is I got a real heated call from their PCP
a couple of weeks later saying, how dare you test them for this gene? I mean, what are you trying to
do? We can't do anything about this. So what on earth, what good comes of scaring them with the
fact that they have an E4 gene? And obviously that led to a discussion. I actually think that
person has since then changed, changed their tune a little bit on that front, in large part, thanks
to the work that Richard's done. But Richard, just a quick digression there. Is there, what's
the evidence on people with an E4 gene being better off without head trauma? Not that anybody
does well with more head trauma, but are E4s more susceptible to head trauma? Well, just to take one
step back. I mean, Peter, you, you did the right thing. I mean, this, this is when the conversations
need to start. I mean, for example, eating fatty fish, people with ApoE4s just don't absorb for,
just one example, and I can just soap so many things, but eating fatty fish from early in life,
again, I'm not a pediatrician, so I'm not recommending little kids and 12 and, I don't,
I don't even know what or when to start, but omega-3 fatty acids in E4 brain should be started as early
as possible and at reasonable doses to really protect the brain. Head trauma is something
that's a little confusing. My opinion on this has shifted a little bit. You know, my nephew, Bobby,
my sister asked me about this, you know, should he be playing football? And, you know, of course,
I have some adjutant in my stomach, but you know, I, you know, if you have the four genes, sure,
you may be at higher risk and head trauma may certainly intermingle. Again, epigenetic risk,
head trauma plus E4 potentially can increase risk. These are really difficult conversations to have,
but knowledge is power. Lauren, you felt empowered, you know. Our patients like,
okay, I'm ready. Let's do it. And if I, at least I tried, you know, I mean, it's better to try than
not. When it comes to E4, I don't know when the best age is to learn. I guess that's a, that's a,
that's a tricky question, but you know, the reveal study showed that people that find out their
APOE4 status in the initial six months, maybe there's a little bit more anxiety initially, but,
but, but at the end, there's no negative psychiatric, psychological outcomes. And,
you know, the, the studies that we've published, I mean, I wrote, I wrote our first paper on this in
2011. So like a decade ago, and like just the fact that you could use genetics to personalize
Alzheimer's care, that paper fell on its face. I don't even think it's been cited. Like it's one
of those papers, you know, it just kind of sat. I mean, now we write papers that like specifically
the entire paper is about if you're E4 versus not E4, do this versus that. And, and I don't know,
one day, I hope it's soon. We're going to know all these genes and, and, and people, when they get
their preventative health screenings, we're going to, it's not just E4, we're going to get a whole
bunch of genes and primary care doctors, I hope one day soon, five years, 10 years, who knows,
are going to basically do these genetic screens on multiple genes and give people targeted
personalized plans for disease risk reduction as early as possible. So anyway, I support you doing
E4. I would say though, that most doctors are not aware of this. So it's not exactly the doctor's
fault, but understanding genetic type to personalized care is the future of medicine.
What other genes are there? We've talked about obviously the three that are of greatest concern,
but fortunately the three that virtually nobody's ever going to have to hear about or deal with the
PSEN1, 2 and APP. APOE4 sucks all the air out of the room. There are a couple of other genes,
Richard, in this space that we're just starting to become aware of. Can you speak to a couple of
those and did any of those figure into the detective work you did in Lauren's family?
I learned a lot about Lauren's family and it was in part because of my brother. It was in part
because of actually you and your brother, Lauren. And I just met so many different people. I mean,
I really got to know your family tree pretty well between videos and talking and all this sort of
thing. And your family is one of the first, I would say first 12 to 15 families that we ever really
did some super deep dives on. I mean, I looked at all sorts of different things in your family.
And I guess what I would say is, huh, do I really want to call out one gene or another?
Or even just generally, like even independent of Lauren's family, Richard, when we think about
some of these other genes that are now kind of starting to become of interest to us, Tom40, TNF,
what can you say about these and how they impact our understanding of this disease?
I hesitate to call out any one specific gene because this is a complicated topic, but,
you know, there are around 30 or so Alzheimer's risk genes that have been found that I think are
very important. But aside from just those risk genes, and you know, you could say CLU and PICLAM
or whatever you call it and bin one, and, you know, I could just name a whole bunch and Tom40 is really
important because not all APOE4s are created equal. I believe this is confusing. And it's even been
confusing for me. But the Tom40 that's next to the E4 is really can influence in my opinion, I believe,
I'm not certain, but I believe that the different Tom40 chain length or whatever it is,
one E4 can behave one way and another E4 can have a lower or higher risk depending on the gene next
to it. So there's a lot of confusion here with this polygenic risk thing, but Tom40 is important.
But, you know, when we take a step back, and I look at Alzheimer's as a medical condition,
it's a medical condition that causes neurologic manifestations. I think Alzheimer's is a medical
disease. I love being a neurologist. It's fun. The brain is interesting. I possibly could have
should have been an internal medicine specialist. I am really intrigued by all the lower organs as
the neurologist would say below the neck. No, no, no disrespect to the lungs and the liver and
everything else. But no, it's a medical condition. And whether you're on the lipid path or the
inflammation path or the potentially infectious path or the head trauma path, there's so many
different things that can trigger brain related pathology. So I'm very interested in the vascular
genes, vascular like FTO and other cholesterol LDL and PCSK9 related genes. Like I'm interested
in those things because that can have an increase or decrease depending on polygenic risk.
Longevity genes. What about like Foxo and Clotho? Like there's got to be, there's,
I know that there are genes that kind of protect you against the Alzheimer's risk of the other
genes. So I really look at the metabolism genes. I look at the vascular risk genes in Lauren
specifically. Lauren was one of the first people that we found another gene that kind of co-interacts
with ApoE to even be even more interesting because maybe this gene related to TNF, TNF alpha,
which we can talk about when someone has that TNF alpha gene and also has an ApoE4 gene,
well, they're also at higher risk than someone with E4 without the TNF. So, so again, we're
trying to put the pieces of the puzzle together of why the heck did your mom get this? And we can
pin it on exercise and we can pin it on one thing, but, but it's not just one thing. It's not like
your mom didn't get Alzheimer's because she didn't exercise. Your mom would have gotten
Alzheimer's anyway, if she would have exercised rigorously, which no one knew back then.
Sure. Would she have delayed it? I firmly believe so. But your mom was different than your uncle in
other ways too. Cause you know, your uncle did not have that TNF alpha related gene. And now
because we found this gene, I mean, this is like imprecise science. This is like, I would call it
better than back of a napkin, but not perfect science. We're doing things with you, Lauren,
now that are trying to get ahead of the curve and trying to make that TNF alpha gene have a less of a
negative impact on your trajectory. So between Peter and I, we've really kind of hit you with
certain things that can potentially help that. So I guess what I would say is polygenic risk is
probably the answer. And I think there's something else you've said that the other analogy is not all
E fours are created equal. I don't think that can be overstated enough. And the analogy for in the
cardiovascular world is LP little a I've seen so many patients with elevated LP little A's.
And in some of them, it absolutely tears through the family with premature heart disease that you
can spot a mile away. So just in the same way you look at Lauren's family history and a mile away,
you say it's Apo E four, you'll look at people having heart attacks in their forties and dying
in their fifties from heart disease. And you say that's, that's LP little a until proven otherwise.
And then there's other patients that show up with elevated LP little a very, even very elevated LP
little a normal, apparently normal risk of cardiovascular disease. So even though this is
technically not the correct term, it's almost like there's variable penetration of the gene as well.
So let's go back to kind of the what can you do, Lauren. So let's go back in time. It's now
a couple of years ago, you finished, you're off the the editing floor.
You're off the cruise ship. Weren't you living on a cruise ship for a while?
Too long, too many days. Yes.
It's been about two, three years that you really switch this into overdrive. Yeah. I mean, you've
you've really become the poster child for I'm going to do every single thing in my power every
day to reduce the risk of this beast. I guess I just get the sense from you, like
you don't seem to push back on this. Like you've I guess it's in part because it's come from within
you and not it's not been thrust upon you. Is that do you think that's the reason that it's
been so I want to use the word easy because I don't think it's easy. But yeah, I think when
you see what I have seen over the last 15 years, you know, why wouldn't I do anything I possibly
can to avoid what I saw over the last 15 years? I want to do everything I possibly can to not go
through that myself, to not put that on my husband or my family. And I feel like I've been given an
opportunity to at least try. So why wouldn't I? Well, it is really amazing to watch how Seth
basically acts the same way, right? It's sort of like he's sort of in it with you, right? It's kind
of like, well, okay, you're both on the complete risk reduction pathway. Well, I mean, only since
this pandemic have I really gotten him into exercise in a way and he's still not where I am.
And of course, obviously all of us, I'm not, you know, exercising the way I was before all of this.
But yeah, we eat, we eat, you know, we eat every meal together. So we eat the same things. And he
has certainly changed his eating habits, which has been wonderful. And he supports me. And yeah,
he goes along with it. We don't have the same genes, but like, why wouldn't he also care about
his brain? He's still got one, you know, as, as Richard said, just because he doesn't have a four
doesn't mean he's not at some risk. And so I'm very lucky that I have someone who is supporting me
most of the time. That doesn't mean he's not always like, orders too much at dinner or orders
extra things. And I'm like, I have to have a bite of that. Or, you know, but exercise is always very
supportive of it. But it also speaks to, I think, the difference between having a spouse or a family
member that can kind of go through the journey with you, whether it's cancer, Alzheimer's disease,
heart disease, whatever it is that that a person is really trying to make these lifestyle changes
to to work against. And so we've spoken a lot about exercise, certainly on other podcasts,
we've spoken a lot about nutrition. How does one improve glycemic control? How does one ensure
maximum insulin sensitivity and glucose disposal? Richard, can we talk about some of the other
tools in the toolkit that we have with with Lauren and frankly, a number of the other patients that
we take care of that are high risk in some way. I mean, in our practice, Richard, as you know,
we define patients as high risk, meaning you come into their care, basically, if their family
history is notable, they have at least one copy of the four gene or the rover 60. You check one of
those boxes, Richard is a part of your care, and then we kind of have a protocol that obviously
you're the poster child for Lauren. What are some of the other things that we're doing on that
protocol, Richard? Sure. So to give you an evidence based answer, let's start with that
first. And then we'll go to a case study of Lauren. So within the last year we published
the results of our clinical trial that Lauren, thank you, you're a part of you. Thank you for
participating. You forced your arm upon me, but we said, okay, you have to sign the consent. But
and I think you guys win the prize for the most family members in I think you guys may be tied
for the most family members in the study. But we have a study that we published in the journal
Alzheimer's and dementia, the journal of the Alzheimer's association and Peter, thank you.
You are a coauthor in that study. You're, you're really fundamentally helped me understand and
developed the approach towards maximizing human performance from both not, not just physical
activity, but nutrition. And just, you got me to understand quick shout out for Peter. I give you
all these shout outs, Lauren, cause you're, you're the best, but Peter, quick shout out. You got me
to understand the difference between lifespan, longevity, health span, which is kind of quality
and brain span. And really that's what, that's what we mostly focus on, but there's a lot of
overlap. But what we did is we did a study because we had to prove whether or not this
individualization of care could work. And in this study we found that on average,
people got 21 different interventions. You know, again, that's average, Lauren, how many things do
we tell you to do? Probably around there. I've, I can count to have, I have your list.
Definitely around there. I mean, have on a lot of supplements. And then of course,
there's the lifestyle stuff, the sleep and the food and all this stuff.
I'm just reloading up one of your things from December, 2019. So a major important part of
this is also a regular follow-up. So every six months we repeat body composition measures,
which is, we use the term ABCs of Alzheimer's prevention management. So the A is for
anthropometrics or body composition, body fat, muscle mass, stuff like that. The B is the blood
based biomarkers. We look at your cholesterol markers. We look at your inflammation, your
metabolism, your nutrition, genetics are in there too. And then C is cognitive function. So
we assess and track all of these things. And at each, every six months, depending on what the repeat
is, depending on what your memory function is and what your cholesterol is and all this, we will
keep refining or fine tuning so that we can, you know, this is really an iterative process.
So basically we keep tracking. And then in your case, because of your APOE4 and because of your,
and I have permission to talk about this, I guess. Okay. Great. Because of your APOE4,
we really honed in on exercise and also more high intensity interval training, really, really
focusing on that in terms of nutrition. We, we, and we checked your omega three levels in your
blood, red blood cell, DHA levels and EPA and whatnot. We had you eat fish, but also omega three
fatty acids via capsules, a very specific type and brand that we often recommend. I have nothing to
disclose. I wish I did. I could pay my student loans, but nothing to disclose from any supplement
or vitamin companies, but omega three fatty acids are key, pretty reasonable dose. Omega three is
DHA and EPA based on studies that thankfully this was proven this past year, but we've had you on
this for the last several years that people with the APOE4 gene require higher doses of omega threes.
So even eating fish just wasn't enough. So we also have you on roughly 2000 milligrams or so of DHA
and something or other of EPA. We also put you on a very purified form of coco flavonols that
have been studied in multiple randomized trials. We gave you a very specific type of curcumin,
a type of a more nanoparticle version, again, nothing to disclose, but that may have anti-TNF
alpha effects may help with inflammation. So we put you on a reasonable dose of that. We put you
on specific types of B complex vitamins. This was to address your homocysteine. Homocysteine is an
amino acid in the blood that is an independent risk factor. So if you have high homocysteine,
you are more likely to have brain shrinkage over time and impaired memory function, but only in
people with high homocysteine, we can give B complex vitamins, B12, B6 in tiny amounts, and then
a folic acid. If we can control that and the person has sufficient levels of omega threes,
then you can slow brain shrinkage, brain atrophy and improve memory. So we've modified that risk
factor, homocysteine. We optimized your vitamin D. I think your vitamin D wasn't terrible, but it
was lower than it could be. I think 60% of people, for example, in Florida are vitamin D deficient.
That makes no sense. The first time I saw you, my vitamin D was not good. I can remember that.
Oh, it was like 19 or 17. I remember definitely not good. And I remember being like, I can
I sit outside more and not wear as much sunscreen because I'm obviously, I'm the palest human ever.
And so I wear a lot of sunscreen, but like, we've helped that.
Is there a level, Richard, that you try to do? Do you want to see vitamin D within a certain range?
Yeah, great question. So in a study in neurology, I think it was Little John and other other
studies I can name several. Cedric and Weiler also has some great, great work on this. But
the best that I can do in across the board and in a general answer is, you know, 30 is kind of
normal. But what is optimal? I'm thinking closer to 40 to 50, maybe more likely 50 in someone that
has two APOE for variants. So an APOE for four, based on a study in the European Journal of
Nutrition, a couple years back, he for four is probably preferentially protected or E4 for better
have good vitamin D levels. I'll put it that way at 50 or more, maybe it's 50 to 70. I don't think
we know the exact answers, but a level of 17 to 19 when Lauren first came in to see me was was
definitely not sufficient. Aside from taking vitamin D, we recommend how to take it. It's a
fat soluble vitamin. So take it with a meal with a little bit of fat in it. That's key. Otherwise,
it doesn't help with absorption. I'm getting some sun from from my perspective, you know,
10 to 15 minutes between the hours of 11 to one when the sun is when the UV or whatever it is,
is strongest. There's lots of devil in the details here. But you know, Lauren, we've been able to
completely modify that risk factor. So that's that's been pretty good. And going back to the EPA
issue, do you give whatever amount is needed to reach a certain level in the red blood cell
membrane? Or do you just say, look, we know that E4 is going to have a harder time assimilating,
we're just going to give a higher dose. Again, our patients, we use this stuff very liberally.
I think Lauren is on at least two grams combined EPA DHA. So do you just leave it at the dose? Or
do you like to rely on the Omega quant type assay? I don't know that I have the perfect answer for
this, but I titrate it up based on the person's red blood cell level. I try to get an index of
at least 12 to 14 and higher is probably better. I think orange is like 14 plus, which is awesome.
I also look at the cholesterol. So APO B and Peter and I, I hate disagreeing with Peter on
anything, but I still like LDL P. But I know I've been a convert to APO B. If someone has high APO
B and LDL cholesterol, I really believe that we can even be more liberal on people. People need
it even more. But you know, the study by Hussein Yassin that was just published recently just showed
that you really need to get at least two grams of DHA alone to even get enough. They did a spinal
fluid study. Thankfully, these people volunteered to get spinal taps. And I mean, Lauren, we're
really hitting you with this stuff. And I'm really glad because, you know, the cumulative effect of
APO E4 plus DHA and EPA over time, there's a cumulative effect. And we really started right
with you. So we hedged our bets a little because it was safe and then it was proven, you know,
five years later. So that was cool. But I don't know that I have a great answer. I also look at
Omega six to three ratio. And I know, Peter, I know you and I are may not look at the same
that way. I also look at trans fats in the blood. And I know that that's maybe an imperfect assay
or science, but trans fats are no bueno when it comes to Alzheimer's risk. So I don't know. I
think there's a lot of important aspects to Omega threes and fat assays. But I don't know that I
know the perfect answer on how to how to do it. You spoke briefly about theric human. We tend to
reserve theric human for those higher risk patients versus curcumin for most people.
What's our belief for why theric human? There's been some reasonable data suggesting that
despite the enormous increase in cost when you switched to theric human, it's worth the cost.
This is based on an important study from small Gary small UCLA. And they showed that, you know,
when people randomized to this, you know, it sounds kitschy, but like nanoparticles,
who that sounds cool nanoparticles can get through the blood brain barrier. Well, that sounds like,
in some ways, marketing, but then they did the study and like they had less, you know,
amyloid accumulation. So like, okay, sign me up. Like, it's safe. Yes, it has a cost to it,
but it's not astronomically expensive. You know, I don't know what the exact effect is,
but the effect size was large enough, even though it was a small study to, you know,
when we talk about evidence based and safe, I think there's enough evidence. It's not perfect,
but it's safe. And it's not super, super, super costly. So, and especially with TNF,
should Lauren be on both curcumin longa plus therapy? Like, who knows? Like, I have no idea
because of the TNF, but she's doing so much exercise that maybe we don't need to do it. But
I'm babbling, but basically, I don't know the answer. I just think it's, it's a reasonable
option, even though it's not perfect. Okay. Well, another supplement that I'm a huge fan of
is magnesium L3 and eight. What are your thoughts on that? And I'll explain to folks what it is.
L3 and eight is a transporter that gets magnesium into the brain much more easily. So normally,
if you take magnesium, it's not, you know, going to get too much in the brain. There is actually
some interesting clinical data in humans suggesting that magnesium L3 and eight in patients with MCI
improve symptoms. So again, one has to take a leap of faith to say, well, if you give it to people
prior to MCI, it would even delay progression from phase one to phase two, and potentially from phase
two to phase three. So what are your thoughts on that, Richard? Yeah. So I actually learned a
little bit about this from you. I've been a magnesium glycinate kind of guy for a while,
because just kind of from the headache community as a neurologist, it's very well tolerated and
that kind of thing. But I think the data on three and eight is compelling. I think it may also help
with sleep, if I'm not mistaken. And I've had some success with that. And then some pretty,
shall we say stressed out type A people. So it's not at the very top of my list,
but it's somewhere in the middle ish, you know, middle to it's not super low, but it's
again, evidence based enough and completely safe. So when it comes to Alzheimer's prevention,
we don't want to give anything to anyone that has any degree of risk, because what if they're not
going to get Alzheimer's anyway, then we've done our patients harm and we take the oath, do no harm.
So I'm pro mag three and eight, but I don't have as much evidence that's lower on the evidence list.
How do you think about you've already kind of alluded to this, but I want to make sure we
round it out around what we would call E4 specific maneuvers, right? So let's assume you
have two theoretical patients in front of you that you believe are both at higher risk than you'd
like. One of them is an E4 patient. Another one is not given what we know about E4. How does that
change your thinking? You've already made several points in reference to this. One of them, for
example, is boy, there's no ambiguity around the benefits of exercise in E4 people. People with E4
tend to require higher doses of EPA and DHA. They tend to benefit disproportionately from vitamin D.
Are there any other things that are unique to patients with E4? Yeah. So we wrote a paper on
this that's open access. It's in the journal of prevention of Alzheimer's disease. It's called
clinical application of APOE and Alzheimer's prevention, a precision medicine approach.
Kara Berkowitz is the first author. She's awesome. She was a med student at Cornell. Peter, we lost
her to surgery. I don't know how that happened. You surgeons. But she wrote this terrific paper
and did several other papers with us too. So I mentioned this paper first because this is a
complicated topic. Let's just start by saying physical exercise is, I believe, likely preferentially
effective in people with the E4 variant or more. Brain imaging studies show that E4 carriers
exacerbates the effect of having a sedentary lifestyle in Alzheimer's pathology. So someone
with E4 really, really, really better exercise. And it's like no joke. It's got to be really
important. And the intensity of the exercise is key. Tobacco use, just worse in E4s. I'm not
telling you that a non-carrier can smoke, but I think it's worse. Alcohol use, alcohol is really
confusing and the data on alcohol kind of darts all over the place. But a few drinks a week is
kind of where I'm at now. Men and women may be a little bit different. This is really confusing,
but there's probably an E4 impact. But what I would say that while light to moderate alcohol
consumption, I mean more on the light side, like four to seven drinks, may be beneficial for
non-carriers of E4, decreasing alcohol intake or even abstaining may be even more so helpful for
carriers. But this is tricky and I don't really know the answer to that. Cognitive engagement.
If you don't use it, you'll lose it. Staying cognitively engaged is like critical. There's
some difference with E4s and cognitive engagement strategies, but I think the jury's out a little
bit. The dietary stuff is, you know, just specific dietary types is key. Omega-3 fatty acids we talked
about are probably preferentially effective, but you need to be at higher dose. You know, there's a
randomized trial go underway now to try to understand, you know, the impact of high saturated
fats and high glycemic index diet on cognitive function for E4 carriers, but that's not published
yet. I guess I want to be cautious in saying this, but I think people with E4s are probably,
you have to be more cautious and careful in terms of high saturated fat, you know, MCTs. I'm pro
MCTs if they're the right MCTs, and this is a topic for another discussion. And I'm pro MCTs if
it's not specifically more so likely in people without the E4 variant, there's more window or
more leeway to be able to use them. But MCTs is a really tricky topic, but I personalize MCTs based
on this, but this is a whole thing. So I don't know how much down the rabbit hole to go.
I have another question about, this is one we've all spoken about, and yet I'm still very much
unclear. And I'm curious as to where your thinking is evolving, which is THC in any form, be it edible,
be it inhaled. I mean, what do we know and acknowledging that it's probably complicated,
right? Because there are probably benefits that come in terms of stress reduction. Certainly,
if it facilitates sleep, but what do we know on that front? And are we ever going to get good
answers? Because the epidemiology is obviously heavily negatively biased based on the cohort
that studied. This is a hard one. I'm not negative on THC specifically. I think there's something
with the CBD and THC connection. I think it depends on the amount of CBD versus THC.
If I had to choose, if someone's going to use THC or CBD, edible to me makes more sense because of
less smoking is better. But I don't know, that's just what I believe, but I don't think that's
grounded in perfect science. But I guess I would say, I don't know. If every one study you read
where it helps Alzheimer's pathology, you can read another study where it causes greater pathology.
So I'm not anti CBD THC. I'm not pro. I'm kind of, I'm kind of in the middle. I think it's an
individualized decision. And I think if someone's going to use CBD or THC, because for example,
Hey, when I take it, my sleep is better. I feel better. Okay. But that's subjective. I want to
know objectively, you know, let me see your fitness tracker. Let me see your ring. Let me see your,
whatever you do to track things. And these, these, all these gadgets may or may not work great in
different people, but I think one has to really, the term here would be an end of one study where
you make one specific change and then you compare what happens to that person over the three months,
say, or six months of only taking that one thing. And does cognitive function improve or does what
does sleep metrics improve? I think the THC CBD story is a precision medicine answer.
Well, speaking of cognitive testing, Lauren, how many times now have you been through the
battery of cognitive tests that Richard puts people through?
I don't know. Is that a cognitive test to see if I even know that number?
Maybe, but six, seven times. I don't know if you know that right off the information in front of
you, but something like that enough that I'm starting to learn the tests.
Is it intimidating when you sit down and do it? Cause I've had some patients that don't want to do
it. Well, okay. Because I had a bad time, I visited Richard the day that like father came out,
which was because of a number of reasons, perhaps the most stressful day and emotion,
one of the most emotional days I'd had in a while and it was not good. And my brain was
a million different places. And of course my body was not in the best of shape leading up to that.
And it was bad news. And Richard was so unhappy and so mad at me, but it was a good kick in the
behind to get myself back on track. Cause I had been making progress, then I lost that progress.
So of course the test that I think now I've come in twice since then.
Twice, yeah.
Yeah. I psyched myself up a bit and I'm like, I'm nervous and
get all into it. But fortunately I've done well.
But is that true, Richard? I mean, do we really think like, I guess, do we know that
that the cognitive test reflected her change in effort around the preventative measures or is it
confounded by the fact that she was having a very, very stressful, distracted day, even though both
of those are true, is the test really able to distinguish those things?
And I mean, my blood work wasn't great that day either, but I'll let Richard answer.
Yeah. You know, it's, it's really interesting. And I have the whole trajectory here. I mean,
this is worth its weight in gold, like all these, all this decessed. Now let me take a step back and
talk about cognitive assessments. Now, when we do a cognitive battery related to Alzheimer's
prevention, we use something, it's a modified form of the Alzheimer's prevention cognitive
composite. These are mostly computer-based tests, the NIH toolbox, as well as other kind of
traditional tests that people with mild cognitive complaints kind of come in and intake, but we use
it a battery that is sensitive to detect changes in brain function before symptoms and different
cognitive domains or different cognitive areas are related to Alzheimer's disease pathology,
as well as other things like vascular pathology, vascular cognitive decline, or age-related
cognitive decline. So I'm not going to portend that our cognitive assessment battery is anywhere
close to perfect. It is as good as cognitive testing can be because people can have good days
and bad days. But it's funny, Lauren, like you, I remember you that day. That was all, that was a
whole day. Didn't we do a video shoot that day with, well, that was the day you, you, you filmed
Seth and I went for other blood work and then I just was in such a state. I couldn't even stay.
Oh my what a, that's right. That's right. I remember that day. My in-laws are with us.
Yeah. That was a lot. Yeah. That was a whole, that was a whole day. So I guess what I would say is
there are certain, when someone doesn't sleep well, then the thing that I would expect to have
a bad effect on cognitive testing that day would be related to processing speed and attention.
When someone has, let's just say early Alzheimer's before symptoms, I'm more paying attention to
certain types of memory tasks, certain types of naming tasks. When someone has vascular risk
factors, I'm, I'm more concerned with how are they doing an executive function measures.
So when I see homocysteine and vitamin D and, and the cholesterol, I correlate that or I, I,
I associate that in my brain with different cognitive domains. So this is hard to explain,
but like Lauren, you felt like you did bad that day because maybe emotionally you were whatever,
but looking back on it, if you take that into consideration, it made sense that you were having
a stressful day. However, in the next couple of years, when I think I may have scared you,
because I got upset. I mean, I was concerned. I think you saw the concern. I think, I think
Seth was dead. Yeah. I mean, my, my in-laws were there. They were concerned. Yeah. I mean,
I didn't know what I was going to call your brother. Like what do I do? Like I was, you know,
I didn't want to involve other people with HIPAA and all that kind of stuff. But I was like,
how do I address this? And I just said, I'm sorry you're having a crappy day, but here's the deal.
Like this is, this is what's going on. And I'll be frank. I was getting worried. Things weren't
going in the right direction. You were doing good and then bad and then good and then bad.
And then your cruise ship situation and then the stress. And I said, Lauren, I'm sorry. It's got to
change now. And I think maybe that's when we got Peter involved or maybe a little before that.
We hadn't sat down with Peter. We'd been talking about Peter.
Yeah, that's right. So all I can say is in the, in the two plus years, whatever, since that time,
Peter, I know you've, you've been cautious about cognitive tests because of the variability,
the imprecise nature. And I agree with that, but you can't fake Lauren, your last set of cognitive
tests. You can't fake this. You have optimized your cognitive function in my opinion, period.
Like no discussion. You said there's an element of practice effects. Now I totally agree with that.
There are certain tests because I have a, because I have a four that doesn't help me.
Wow. Look at you little in psych. I can learn.
That's higher order processing.
Dr. Miller Rogan, you're learning. Good job. Correct. EPOE fours are more resistant to practice
effects and also men's brains and women's brains have different strengths and weaknesses, for
example, verbal memory. So when we really digest your trajectory of cognitive function over the
last several years, I'm going to be honest. I don't know that I've really talked about this
too much in public or on the recording, but your brain is functioning. And I, again, you can take
all the practice effects you want. There are certain tests here that I believe are resistant
enough. And it's not like you're taking these every day. You're taking these like every,
you know, six to 12 months and we change it up. We change the versions and stuff like that. So
you have a plateau at some point with the practice effects, but your brain is absolutely without a
doubt, hands down, I have visual proof. Your brain and biomarkers, your blood-based biomarkers,
you're optimized, you're different. Your brain is firing on more cylinders. Like you can even just,
let's just say we'll average out the first three sessions, right? I mean, there's just no compare.
You're more than a standard deviation above normal. Like you've improved, like your processing
My brain is above normal. I know. Yeah. Well, no, I mean, it's interesting because I really want to
see if you feel anything, but can you tell the difference? But the most important test that we
do for age related cognitive decline, you're, you're several years older and I know you're
30 something to 30 something big deal. Well, no, the brain ages in that, in that timeframe.
Your brain is younger now than it was five years ago. Like you're greater than 90th percentile on
all these different tests. Your, you know, your memory function is a standard deviation above the
mean. And when you started out it like was 0.87 standard deviations below the mean. Yeah. I mean,
I remember this Lauren, because I, our very first meeting was at Cornell and we were going over your
results. And I remember we were kind of looking for an explanation for how it could have been so poor.
And the best explanation that you came up with, which frankly, I thought was a viable one was
you said, look, I did well in school, but I did poorly on standardized tests.
And is it possible that my cognitive score is low because I'm not a good standardized test taker.
So it's been very exciting to watch this progression. One element of the standardized
test I want to ask you about Richard is odor. You put another one of our patients through this test
recently. And I was very surprised to learn. So he came back. Is it 10, nine, nine item test, nine.
And in this case, the patient correctly identified eight. And I remember thinking, oh, that's awesome.
And you were like, if it had been seven, I would have been really concerned. And with eight, it was
we're going to do a retest. Why is odor identification so important in this disease?
Yeah, I mean, there's so much subjectivity to cognitive assessments. You could be sleep
deprived. You could be like, you know, distracted by I don't know, you forgot to silence your cell
phone. You could I don't know, it's warm in the room or cold in the room. And Lauren's always
freezing. So, you know, we got to get the temperature just right for Lauren up. Lauren's
coming, you know, regulate the temperature. You don't do that. No, I'm kidding. And then
sets coming all change the temperature, change the thermostat. No, as we get older, we change.
Now he's the cold one. And I'm the hot one. I know I've been huddling during this because the
air is low. But no, it's that's honestly, it's the funniest thing. The older he gets, the colder he
is and the hotter I am. And of course, it used to be different. Anyway, fascinating. So odor is more
objective rather than subjective and odor identification. Like what is that? Well,
it's your ability to recognize a smell and name one of this. And again, in med school,
decreased odor identification. The first thing I thought of was Parkinson's disease.
That's something that's that's common in preclinical Parkinson's. So before someone
gets the tremor and the slow movements and the shuffling gate, meaning the walking is slow and
the rigidity odor identification loss of smell is something that can be a harbinger of badness
for a neurodegenerative disease to come. Well, the studies have shown that loss of smell or lack of
the ability to precisely identify certain smells can be a harbinger of Alzheimer's disease as well.
My mom had a very poor sense of smell and not an amazing sense of taste either. But sense of smell
was she never had a good sense of smell. That's impactful. With COVID, I mean,
it's a different thing. Like, you know, and Peter, you know, you and I talked about this, but
I lost my smell for five, six weeks, which is a little bit longer than than some people. And we
can talk about has your smell returned back to normal. So I'm seven months out now. And, you know,
just for folks know what we're talking about. You had a pretty good case of COVID. I did. Yeah. I had
one of these cases where, oh, I'm fine. Three, four or five days later, I'm like, you know,
okay, cool. I'll exercise tomorrow. And then on day nine, 10, I went through
with my O2 sat dropping and all that stuff. And I'm Peter help and Paul help. And what the heck
I called every doctor in my Rolodex. Um, did an EKG on myself in my office at midnight,
because I wanted to stay the heck out of the ER. My O2 sat was 94 PTSD time, but they wouldn't
have admitted me because it was above 90. But anyway, I had a pretty reasonable case of COVID
and my smell after five weeks started to come back. I mean, like ahead of a thing of bleach,
I smelled nothing. I mean, like zero. I'm like real smell sensitive. Then I had phantom smells
for a while. I was like, Oh, the dog peed. Uh, oh, Bon Bon Kitty. My dog's name is Kitty.
How's Zelda doing, by the way? Well, honestly, I've been worried a few. I don't know if you saw me.
I was checking to see if my microphone has picked up her snoring. Oh, it's right across me. And she
has been snoring so loud this whole time. So if anyone has heard that it's, it's just Zelda. Oh,
no, it's golden. Yeah. Bon Bon had his second snoring surgery, but he's great now. He's awesome.
King Charles Cavalier fan club of America we're talking to right here. Anyway, so I had phantom
smells and then my smell is basically back, but I'm like a little smell sensitive. Can't,
can't explain it so that this COVID may change our ability to use smell sensitivity for Alzheimer's
related testing. But anyway, we'll cross that bridge later. Sorry for the tangent. What about,
what about hearing? Because you see these reports from time to time that say we've got to get more
aggressive with hearing aids in people. The moment a person has even the slightest amount
of hearing deterioration, we've got to correct it. The implication being that hearing loss will have
a causative role in Alzheimer's disease such that correction of it can delay or prevent versus just
the obvious correlation between hearing loss and dementia given the obvious age association. What's
your thought on that? Yeah, I don't, I don't know that I have a perfect answer, but hearing loss
when they've done the studies, the Lancet commission 2020 report came out and basically
show that hearing loss is like the most impactful, modifiable risk factor that they found in their
study, which is like striking, like a huge number of cases of dementia could be potentially reduced
if a person gets early recognition of hearing impairment and gets it addressed. Now, why is
sorry, why is that? Yeah, this is confusing. And this is a quote unquote new risk factor. I mean,
it's been around for the evidence has been emerging for years now, but I don't know. Is
it because you're I hate to say I'm not an expert in this at all, but you're just you disengage,
you can't hear, you kind of you're in your own little world, you have you miss social cues,
you have different interaction levels. I actually don't know the answer to this. And this the
classic line, we need more research to truly be able to figure this out. I mean, I feel like it's
one of those things, Richard, that we because we're constantly updating our protocol. And
I've been thinking for about the past three months, do we need to now take those high risk
patients that we described and say, everyone's got to go to an audiologist. And of course,
the implication is you're going to get people in their 30s and 40s that have low, low, low
grade hearing loss. Are they actually going to want to wear hearing aids or is it just going to
be, hey, we're going to use more noise cancellation stuff and sort of try to protect hearing longer.
But I'm curious as to this. It also strikes me that from the precautionary principle,
there's no downside to protecting your hearing. And as much as one can do that, I don't see a
downside to it. I think we, meaning doctors need to do a little bit of say a better job. Doctors
have it really hard. So this is not doctor's fault. It's like our medical system is in disarray
and broken beyond. I have no idea how to fix it with 10 minutes or 15 minutes per patient. I have
lots of empathy for tremendous empathy for physicians working out there, but in the trenches,
but hearing screening, I think is something that should be part of at some age, at some point,
an evaluation. Real briefly, though, I want to go back to Lauren's odor identification. So
this is a weird comment. And I've never really also said this on a recording, but
Lauren, this is not the first time that I've seen patients that have really firing on all cylinders
done 23 of the 25 things we told you to do, like compliance out to wazoo 10 out of 10.
Your odor identification, this is weird. And this may be a red herring, completely random or whatever.
Your odor identification has improved. I think it's because, and maybe this goes again, goes
against my four. It's because now I know the difference in the cards between the coffee and
the gasoline smell, which used to really throw me off. Gotcha. Okay. So even with an objective test,
we still have subjectivity with learning effects and stuff like that. Now, when I smell it, I'm
like, okay, really be sure, is this the coffee or the gas? All the other ones are easy, but between
those two, those always trip me up. Gotcha. Interesting. You know, just to get back to one
thing, Lauren, yes, I have objective data, but you know, data is only as good as data is. And
all of our tests are imprecise. And Peter and I talk about this a lot. Sure. Your calculated
cardiovascular risk when we put all your numbers in a calculator, much lower. Your calculated
Alzheimer's risk based on the different scales, much lower. Like we're doing a great job. Like in
terms of living longer. Yeah. Not gonna would. Yeah. We are really, we're really doing well.
Do you feel anything different in your brain or not so much? And just be honest. No, no. And,
you know, and I don't, I don't know how much we want to get into any of this, but I'm on my own
hormonal journey and often wonder, you know, if that plays a part in it. I, I've always been
someone who's enjoyed sleep. We kind of talked about that and like, you know, I like sleep and I,
I can, I love a nap as I get older and my hormones become bigger players in my health.
I sometimes think that has to do with it, but overall, do I feel cognitively better? It's hard
to say, but physically I feel better. My overall health is, I can tell that it's better from a
total body energy. The way I can approach a situation, I feel like I have a different type
of body energy. If that makes any sense, cognitively, you know, knock on wood. I fortunately feel like
someone who is pretty in control of their cognition most of the time. So, you know, do I have moments?
Yes. Where I'm like, I feel tired or weird, or even that, you know, like you said, that brain fog,
which I don't think I understand at this point, but the black and white answer is yes, I feel
better. Do I feel greatly better? I'm not sure. I mean, to me, I think there's an emotional piece
here too, right? Which is we go back to 10 years ago, there's this depression that basically
feels like there's something inevitable that's going to happen to you. And I think you know,
by now, Richard and I are very much in the camp of saying there's no reason to believe you're going
to get Alzheimer's disease. Yeah. Like there's really no reason to believe that. If you stay this
course that you're on, you get to be like normal people in their 80s. So maybe that's the greatest
single benefit of all this, is that it changes the way you feel. I wasn't physically in such
rough shape that I could really pinpoint a difference, but emotionally, yes, so much of the
fear has dissipated because I have control in a way that I didn't before. I see my blood work,
you know, I see numbers going from red to green. And that gives me a hope that, you know, I think
translates into my physical being, but also into my cognitive health as well. I don't want us to
close without talking a little bit about hilarity for charity, which we started talking about a
little bit, but I would bring us up to speed on specifically what the mission is, how you decided
to pick the lane that you guys are going to be in. You know, we touched on this a little bit before,
but I have been so fortunate in my terrible journey. I think I've had the best situation of
a horror show that could happen with Alzheimer's and that one, my family was able to afford care
for my mom. And that too, I have, because of my relationships and the advocate that I've become,
I have met smart people like you guys who have helped me take control of my brain health. And so
HFC, what we've done with that is try to help other people be at least a part of that situation. And
so I like to think of HFC as sort of like, this is our non-official, you know, mission statement,
which is like, we're here for your brain today and tomorrow. Meaning that, you know, we're here for
people today through care, through our numerous support groups, which are personalized and which
we really take the time to connect people to people who would understand their situation.
Early on, I went to a support group where, you know, I was like 26 and upset about my mom. And
there was a guy there who was like 56 and who was upset about his mom. And not that I didn't feel
bad for this person, but also like, I did not feel bad for this person, you know, because I was
like, you're 56. You have your mom at 56. Like I'm 26. And so, you know, we really try to recognize
that in our care, we put people together who would understand a situation. And of course,
then there is the other aspect of it, which is, I think what makes the greatest impact in people's
lives today, which is our care program. You know, like I said, my family could afford
care for my mom so that my dad could catch his breath and take a break and go to the grocery
store if he needed or, you know, come have dinner with me if he wanted. And so many people are with
their loved one 24 seven without a break, without relief. And that is a completely
thankless job. And so we provide care for people and provide caregivers to go into people's homes
and give the primary caregiver respite, give them a break. And then there's, of course, how we
invest our dollars in research, which is in brain health. HFC really focuses on activating young
people in the fight against Alzheimer's. We don't think that people should wait till they're older
to start talking about their stories or losing loved ones to Alzheimer's. And they certainly
shouldn't wait, as we've talked about today, to start taking care of their brains. And so we
really do our best to share what we've learned from you guys and educate people that it is never
too early to start taking care of your brain and how important that is. That's really our focus.
I wish that we raised the kind of money that would research a medication that could cure Alzheimer's,
but no one has yet given us five billion dollars. I'm out here ready to receive it if someone is
listening and wants to send it our way. But for now, I'm going to do what is practical, which is
help people today with support and care and teach people how to take care of their brains for
tomorrow. So that's who we are. So people can go to the website. They can obviously donate directly.
Is there any other way people can get involved or be a part? I mean, there are all sorts of events.
Yeah. What else can people do? Yeah. I mean, obviously, this year, the event thing has sort of
taken a turn for all of us and all nonprofits, I think, are feeling the strain of not being able
to host our normal fundraising events. And in the strain of that, a lot of philanthropists who
normally would donate our way feel that they can't this year because they are donating towards
COVID-related organizations or even racial organizations, which please keep donating.
These things are very important. I'm not saying you shouldn't, but at the same time,
people still have brains. And unfortunately, there are still millions of people in this
country with Alzheimer's and their caregivers are in even worse situations now. So what we do is
even more important these days. So yeah, you can go to our website and of course, give us your
hard-earned dollars. We're happy to do something good with them. But we also give people a space to
share their story if they have one. We provide infrastructure if you want to throw your own
Alzheimer's fundraiser. We've had so many amazing individuals over the years who have done their
own fundraisers for whatever speaks to them. One of my favorites is a guy like drove, would you say,
a tuk tuk? Do you say drove a tuk tuk? I guess so. Road one, whatever. Pulled one across India and
raised money for HFC. How cool. But that's what spoke to him. That was organic to him. And Seth
and I always say when it comes to fundraising or philanthropy, like do what's organic to you,
what makes sense for your life. So we provide an infrastructure if you want to raise money for us.
We're happy to help you do it. You know, again, if you need support, you can come to us. We have
so many different options. We have an amazing partnership with the Rosalind Carter Institute
in which we train caregivers. We give them one-on-one caregiving training, which is really,
I think, so invaluable. I mean, the truth is there's no training to be a caregiver. It's
every day is a surprise and who knows, but there are certain tools that we can give people. And
you know, and I think we try to do it all in a way that is approachable. Certainly, you know,
our original name is Hilarity for Charity. Now we're HFC because we want to seem like grownups
and we want people to take us seriously. But we approach everything through a way that, you know,
has some comedy that is certainly our work. But we often say Alzheimer's is so devastating and
it is so sad and people don't want to hear about it. So we'll tell them some jokes and trick them
into laughing. And then all of a sudden we hit them with the facts and tell them how important it is.
And we rope them in that way. I think overall, we're just trying to provide people the hope that
I have found over the years. You know, we started this podcast talking about my dark, devastating
times and like, that's not who I am anymore. And that's not my vision about all of this anymore.
And I think there is so much control that can be had that we did not have even just a few years ago.
And you know, we through HFC are just trying to teach people that they have that control too.
Well, Lauren, Richard, it has been such a pleasure to sit down with you guys today. And it has been
worth every bit of the wait from almost a year ago when we wanted to first do this. And no one would
have imagined a year ago all that was going to happen in the next 12 months. But it's also,
it's also given us a chance to see one more year of your incredible progress, Lauren. So thanks
for being the poster child for what Alzheimer's prevention looks like. Well, we're trying. It's a
journey, right? I don't know if I can be the poster child yet, but maybe in some time we'll see if,
I think, you know, we'll keep going. No pressure. There's poster trial for the journey.
There you go. Well, hey, if we would have done this podcast a year ago, I could have only said
one out of every three cases of Alzheimer's is preventable. But now based on the latest data,
four out of 10 cases of Alzheimer's may be preventable if that person does everything right.
So I'm going to have to change the signature in my email.
I'm sorry.
Is what you're saying to me.
Who wrote that signature? Jeez.
Someone wrote that signature. I don't know who it was.
Unbelievable. I have typos everywhere.
Fired. Peter, thanks for sharing our story. And Lauren, thank you for being courageous. And
you're the one that puts, I mean, I get to sit here at this desk and hang out and like, you know,
whatever. And you actually have to go home and do all the 27 things that Peter and I tell you to do.
So thanks for being a good sport. You do your own things.
Yeah. Got to do what you got to do.
Yeah. And we're really grateful to your family for also feeling that it's been okay for you to
talk about this because I know that these are things people don't want to talk about. And yet,
I think the understanding that, hey, we talk about these things that suck because it makes a
difference because there's a lot of people that are listening to this right now that can relate
to what you're saying. Yeah, I hope so. Well, there's so much that can be done. So I appreciate
the chance to talk about it. All right, guys. Thanks so much. Thanks so much.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only, does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.