Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Dr. Gerald Schulman. Jerry's a professor of medicine and
cellular and molecular physiology at Yale. He's also the co-director of the Yale Diabetes
Research Center. In 2018, he received the Banting Medal for scientific achievement, arguably the
most prestigious award one can win in this field. He's pioneered the use of magnetic resonance
spectroscopy combined with mass spec to noninvasively examine cellular glucose and fat metabolism. Now,
you may ask, why does that matter? And we get to that right at the outset of this interview. If you
want to understand insulin resistance, if you want to understand hyperinsulinemia, type 2 diabetes,
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, you have to understand the movement of glucose and fat.
A way to think about this is to think about it this way. If you go and get a blood test,
even the most fancy blood test imaginable, you're basically looking at a picture, a snapshot,
a moment in time. What these techniques that Jerry and his collaborators have developed over
many years are basically allowing you to watch videos. You can see the flux, you can see the
movement of glucose. Furthermore, they've been able to see those things as they happen inside
even human cells. So I'm going to, I guess, maybe make an apology at the outset of this and say
that this is about as technical an interview as I probably have done in a while. There are probably
only a few interviews that I've done on this podcast that get into more technical weeds than
this one. But unfortunately, that is the price one has to pay if they want to understand arguably
the most important pathologic condition in our species. And I get into what I mean by that in
the interview, so I won't elaborate on that further. We talk a lot about what it is to be
insulin resistant. This term gets thrown around with such ubiquity that you'd think everybody
knows what it means and yet to define it is very complicated. But I think by the end of this
interview, you will undoubtedly understand how to define insulin resistance. And I think you will
have a very good sense of where it begins and what it means in a subclinical versus a clinical
state and what the sequence of events are that lead to a condition in the muscle ultimately
affecting the liver, ultimately affecting the whole body. I'm not going to promise you that
you'll get that on the first listen. I think that might require more than one listen and it probably
requires going through the show notes, which will be littered with fantastic figures. In fact,
as Jerry and I did this interview over zoom for, I don't know, I would say maybe half to two thirds
of the interview, he was sharing slides as we were doing it. And keep in mind, I'm quite familiar
with these concepts. So for someone who's less familiar with these concepts, I think it will be
only that much more valuable. One really nice little bonus thing that came out of this is a
beautiful discussion at the end of metformin, where I actually learned something really profound that
was incredibly relevant to my understanding of metformin in my ongoing interest around the question
of metformin suitability as a longevity agent. I could say more about this, but I think it's just
one of those things where I asked you to sort of take a leap of faith with me that this is important,
even if it feels a little bit like drinking your cough syrup at times. But if you really want to
understand longevity, you're going to have to sort of figure out what insulin resistance means. So
without further delay, please enjoy my very in-depth conversation with Dr. Gerald Schulman.
Jerry, thank you so much for making time to sit down virtually with me today. As I said before we
hopped on, this is a topic that is near and dear to my heart. And frankly, all roads seem to point
to you. And that goes back to, I don't know, at least for me, probably 2011, when I became really
fascinated by this topic. And there aren't a lot of topics where I've personally experienced the
following problem, which is the more I think I understand it, the less I do. So now when someone
says to me, Peter, what's insulin resistance? You know, I can sort of give glib answers to that
question, but the reality of it is I don't think I fully understand what it is. And I don't know
that I can represent to the listener that by the end of this, they will fully understand what
insulin resistance is. But what I think they'll understand is how maybe we can think about it
through the lens of different tissues and what may or may not be going on. And in large part,
I think that's due to the incredible work you've done over your entire career. I guess I'd like to
kind of just start with a little bit of background. You did an MD and a PhD and you're trained as an
endocrinologist, correct? Yeah, that's correct. And then I did residency in medicine at Duke,
fellowship in endocrinology at the Mass General Harvard. And then I've always been interested in
metabolism, diabetes. I guess probably my father was a diabetologist, went to summer camp. He was
the doctor for type one diabetics at an early age, was exposed to problems type one diabetes in my
peers. I was just a camper and saw my peers getting hypoglycemic or getting into issues
with ketoacidosis. So I think I was exposed to metabolism at an early age. I'm sure it left an
impression on me. My father wanted me to become a radiologist because my physics background, but
I ended up staying in metabolism and doing endocrinology. I'm sure you would have done great
things in radiology, but I also think we're far better off for the contributions you've made in
this field. When did this particular question of understanding what insulin resistance meant
and actually starting to differentiate between some of these phenotypes of what is the fate of
glucose in a person with normal metabolism versus what is the fate of ingested glucose in someone
with type two diabetes? When did that question begin to obsess you? And specifically now that's
a sort of change from the patients that you grew up with with type one diabetes.
Studying as an undergraduate medical school, I was always interested in biochemistry, physiology.
I had an experience. I was visiting a medical student at Vanderbilt in the 70s and got interested
in in vivo metabolism, doing study metabolism in awake animals, looking specifically at glucose
and fatty acid turnover, using tracers to actually measure how fast things are being made,
glucose is made, how fast fatty acids are being made in the body and metabolized.
In medical training, you go back to medical school, you learn how to become a good doctor,
take care of patients. But then in your fellowship years, you're back in the lab.
And I really wanted to get back to understand metabolism by looking inside the cell. So
everything I had done prior to then, and most people studying biochemistry, physiology would,
to understand, so diabetes, metabolic disease, I was interested in this question. It's an important
disease, leading cause of blindness, end stage renal disease, leading cause of non-traumatic
loss of limb. The cost to U.S. society is a huge impact and now it's becoming a global problem
as they adapt to Westernized diets and things. And I wanted to look inside the cell, metabolism
inside the cell. And so that took me into the world of nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy.
It actually brought me down to New Haven, where they were just setting up methods, this technique,
to actually look inside living yeast cells. I said, gosh, this, we can adapt this to humans and look
inside metabolism in humans, in liver and muscle and other organs. To specifically get at your
question, I think it's such an important metabolic disease, the most common metabolic disease. And so
someone's who's interested in metabolism, it's a natural segue. I sometimes describe it to patients
as the foundation upon which the major three chronic diseases sit. So you described some ways
in which patients with type 2 diabetes die, specifically through amputations or complications
of amputations, such as infections and obviously through end stage renal disease. But I would
argue that the majority of the mortality through diabetes comes not so much through diabetes, but
through its amplification of atherosclerotic disease, cancer and dementia, all of which are
force multiplied in spades by type 2 diabetes. So the way I explain it to people, and I hope that
by the end of this, you'll help me refine this because it may not be accurate. But I describe
to patients that there is a continuum from hyperinsulinemia to impaired glucose disposal,
to naphyl D and NASH to type 2 diabetes. And that continuum makes up a plane upon which all
chronic disease get worse. If we're going to be serious about the business of delaying the onset
of death, we have to be serious about the business of delaying the onset of chronic disease. And if
we want to do that, we must fix our metabolisms. That's my thesis. Total agreement. You're spot
on. So insulin resistance is the main factor which leads to type 2 diabetes, but it also,
and again, this is give credit to Jerry Reven, who in his 1988 Banting lecture first got everyone's
interest in basically saying insulin resistance is not only leading to diabetes, but as you say,
atherosclerosis, basically hyperlipidemia associated with inflammation, higher acid,
polycystic ovarian disease. Now we can kind of add to that. Now we can talk about naphyl,
or I prefer the term metabolic associated fatty liver disease, MATHL-D. That's going to be the
most common cause of liver disease, liver inflammation, end stage liver disease, and
liver cancer. And finally, another arm for Jerry's circle of insulin resistance and all these arms
budding off of them, heart disease, as we talked about high uric acid, high triglycerides, and high
cholesterol is cancer. So we're now, as you know, seeing huge increases in many forms of cancers,
which are associated with obesity, breast cancer, colon cancer, pancreatic cancer, liver cancer.
And by the bed, it's insulin resistance that's driving the increase in all of these cancers.
Now it's not causing them necessarily, but it's promoting the growth. And again, we have very
strong preclinical evidence for this in animals. You can take animals, Rachel Perry, who was in my
group and now starting her own lab, has taken breast cancer models, human breast cancer models,
colon cancer, put them into mice and just giving them insulin, putting in insulin pumps, and that
the rate of tumor growth is accelerated and you treat them with an insulin sensitizing agents and
you can slow down tumor growth. So I think you're spot on, Peter. Insulin resistance is driving a lot
of disease. And you're also spot on in that that's what's killing our patients with type 2 diabetes.
It is heart disease. These other things are the chronic complications of hyperglycemia, the
blindness, the end stage renal disease and the small vessel disease leading to non-traumatic
loss of limb. Also hyperglycemia, but insulin resistance, which is very common. It's probably
one quarter of our population and one half of our population has it perfectly asymptomatic.
You don't know you have it. We can test for it using sophisticated tools that we can talk about,
but it's a very common phenomenon. So before we launch into what I think is an important
discussion around the fate of glucose under normal conditions, which is the backdrop against which I
think everything we are going to talk about has to be laid out. I'd like you to spend a moment doing
something you're probably not asked to do often, which is at least explain to some extent what the
NMR technique allows you to do because so much of what we're going to talk about today requires
either a leap of faith that you know what you're talking about or at least some sense of how a
scientist is able to actually look at substrates and substrate utilization and substrate movement
in the ways that we have to be able to talk about them at a molecular and cellular level to make
sense. So I know it's a bit complicated, but because it is such a cornerstone of your work,
can you explain what labeling means and how you can measure those labeled molecules in vivo?
In metabolism, the traditional methods, since going back to dates maybe 50 years ago, when you wanted
to measure more than just concentration of a metabolite, you go to your doc, you measure blood
sugar, cholesterol, and it's a static concentration. And what we know is what's much more important
than just measuring concentration is flux. And that's basically production versus uptake by a
tissue and know where something's being made, where it's going. And the traditional approach has been
to put a label on that, whatever you're interested in tracing, the glucose. And so you're used to
basically with the advent of cyclotrons. It really started in California, in Berkeley, they started,
you know, had cyclotrons, they're interested in nuclear theory. The side product is you can make
isotopes. So you can make carbon radio labeled, so it's an emitter, and put that carbon onto a glucose
molecule and then trace it. So for more than 50 years, we've been able to buy radio labeled isotopes
and put a carbon C14, which is radioactive, low dose radiation or tritium, which is a form of
hydrogen, and then give it to a person, an animal, and do blood sampling and actually measure then
turnover of that metabolite. So that's telling us very important information. Many, many important
studies have used this and to dates, we still use this to track production and clearance of whatever
we're labeling. What you can't get from that though, is really what's happening inside the cell,
which is really where I wanted to go. So we've been measuring turnover of metabolites. Again,
that's what I did many years ago, where I first started my interest in metabolism. To do that,
you need to get inside and look at the cell. So the approaches have been traditionally something
called positron emission tomography, which is now used clinically sometimes to track tumor growth,
because tumors take up glucose and you can give a pet emitter of glucose and then see if the tumor
is taking it up. That's radioactive. And again, I'm a clinical physiologist. I prefer not to give
radio labeled substrates, radioactive substrates to volunteers who volunteer for my study. The other
approach was nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy. There were two groups that were pioneering this
kind of work. There was one group in George Rada at Oxford, and this was phosphor centimar. And so
what George was doing, so NMR takes advantage of the fact that the nuclei of certain atoms have
spin properties. And I won't get into all the physics behind this, but they make them behave
like tiny bar magnets. And so when you put them in a strong magnetic field, they tend to line up or
against this magnetic field. And because they have spin properties, they will actually precess in this
magnetic field at a set frequency. If you pulse them at the frequency that they're precessing,
they tip out of this field. And then when they relax, they emit energy that you can pick up with
a little rate with an antenna and basically get chemical information about where that label is
within the molecule. So everything I just said, all you need to understand is you can use this
method to basically measure the amount of the metabolite, more importantly, which, for example,
carbon atom within that glucose molecule is labeled. It has something called chemical shift,
experiences a slightly different magnetic field depending where it is within that glucose molecule.
So for the listeners, all you need to understand is using this method, we're able to get
biochemical information of not only measuring a metabolite, but then using the power of
for example, C13 NMR track the label as it's being metabolized inside the cell. So that's
carbon NMR. So in our bodies, 99% of the carbon in our body is C12, which is NMR invisible, but 1%
is C13, which is NMR visible, has this precession properties. You can use a labeled, for example,
C1 labeled glucose and then track that C1 glucose as it gets into the say muscle cell or liver cell
and gets metabolized and finds its way into glycogen. And then you can measure flux. You can
actually, for the first time in humans non-invasively without any ionizing radiation, measure how much
is going in through measure intracellular pathway flux. Phosphorus NMR as getting back to George
Roddet, George pioneered Phosphorus NMR. There you don't have to give any isotopes. There
you actually see P31, Phosphorus 31 is 100% natural abundant. You see all the phosphorus
that's in solution in our bodies. So for example, when our volunteers go into side of the magnet
and we put a leg or arm into the magnet, we can see all the high energy phosphates in, for example,
ATP and the same triphosphate. There are three phosphates and you can actually see each one of
those phosphates. You can see phosphocreatin has a different chemical shift. You can see inorganic
phosphate and we developed methods. Doug Rothman and others at Yale who I worked with were able to
develop methods measure glucose six phosphate. So we can actually look at one a key intermediate
getting glucose from outside inside. Another method we developed was we can measure intracellular
glucose inside human muscle non-invasively. So by measuring these metabolites, measuring flux,
we can actually then ask the very simple questions, which this is how we started out
in humans. As you say, you know, again, diabetes is an abnormality of metabolism. Glucose is the
metabolite. And we were able to basically ask very simple questions when a person, a human,
which is my favorite model because it's the one most relevant to understanding diabetes and
metabolic disease. When we ingest carbohydrate, how much of that carbohydrate ends up in glycogen
versus oxidation into carbon dioxide or gets converted to lactate through glycolysis. And so
and then more importantly in the patient with or the volunteer with diabetes, how important is that
pathway glucose to glycogen accounting for their insulin resistance? This story is very short.
Before you go there, let's demonstrate clinically a difference between these two people. So let's
take the normal patient without type 2 diabetes, and then let's contrast them with a very similar
person of similar size who has type 2 diabetes. We will feed them both a high carbohydrate meal
in the evening. Let's just assume that that meal contains 100 to 200 grams of carbohydrate. They
will digest their food. We won't really have much insight into what's happening overnight, you will
tell us. But at the next morning, we do a fasting blood glucose level on them. This is now 12 hours
after their meal. The patient who does not have type 2 diabetes might arrive with a blood sugar of
100 milligrams per deciliter, which we will say is normal. His counterpart with type 2 diabetes
may actually at that time have a blood sugar of 200 milligrams per deciliter, which is obviously
abnormal and consistent with the diagnosis of type 2 diabetes. Now of course, that only represents
about an extra 5 grams of glucose in the circulation that is the difference between the 100 and the 200
milligrams per deciliter, which is a small fraction of the, call it 1 to 200 milligrams,
pardon me, grams rather, 5 gram difference. So it's a small fraction of what was ingested the
night before. What is the difference between those two people? Why does one of them have such a hard
time with that extra 5 grams of glucose? What was the fate of glucose in the healthy person to begin
with? How did the body treat it? The body when you take in, and again this is what we were able to
demonstrate by actually measuring glycogen flux in liver and muscle, that ingested in a healthy
individual ends up as mostly liver and muscle glycogen. It takes up muscle and depends on the
size of the meal and how it's being administered, the proportionality between liver and muscle. But
the bottom line, it's 80-90% is stored as glycogen. In the diabetic contrast is there's two processes
that have gone awry. One is that the liver is geared up to make more glucose than it should be
through a process called gluconeogenesis, the conversion of non-glucose precursors like
amino acids, alanine, lactate to glucose. And that process is accelerated, so the liver is making
twice the amount of glucose as it should. And then you have a block in the periphery where the glucose
same amount of insulin is not causing the glucose to be taken up by the muscle. Again, in terms of
flux, what I care most about, production is up and clearance or disappearance is down. And besides
this, also even in some diabetics, insulin is inappropriately low because we know if we give
more insulin, we can overcome these abnormalities. And so the beta cell has also become abnormal in
the established diabetic where it's not making enough insulin. That can be secondary to these
other issues, glucose toxicity and other factors that have caused this beta cell impairment. Because
we know most importantly when we reverse the insulin resistance, this is a very important study,
is we've taken these type 2 diabetics and short-term hypocaloric feeding, 1200 calories a day.
We basically can reverse all these abnormalities through reduction in the topic lipid, which we
can get into molecular mechanisms and reverse their diabetes. And this has now been shown
by many, many other investigators. And most recently, Roy Taylor, my colleague who trained
with us, is now doing this in the primary care clinic back in the UK. But usually you've asked
the question, usually when we talk about diabetes, actually it may be easier to understand when you
start in the young lean 20-year-old who already has insulin resistance. These are the young lean
college students that we study. It's actually easier, I think, for your listeners to understand
if we start with just pure insulin resistance, which we see is the most common thing, as I said,
probably half the people in the US actually have insulin resistance don't know it because they're
asymptomatic. And we even see this in young lean 20-year-olds, Yale undergraduates who volunteer for
our studies, profound insulin resistance in muscle, no problems in liver, and then take you through
the progression from how you just go from insulin resistance in muscle to fatty liver and insulin
resistance in the liver and then progress to type 2 diabetes. That's something we can actually go
through that would be of interest. It would because it actually kind of fits with the way I was going
to try to temporally split this, which would look as follows. When we take a patient who has normal
fasting glucose and normal fasting insulin, and we challenge them with an oral glycemic load,
and then measure insulin and glucose in 30-minute intervals, a lot of times we expose a problem
that seems most easily explained by the muscles inability to assimilate glycogen.
So a person shows up and they have a normal fasting insulin, say it's 5, and their fasting
glucose is, say, 90. You challenge them with 75 to 100 grams of glucose, but say 30 or 60 minutes
later their fasting glucose is 200, their insulin is 70. We call that insulin resistance, and we
impute from that that something has broken down in the pathway that prevents their muscle from taking
in glucose. Now you've done very elegant work to examine all of the possible places that failure
could have taken place. Did it take place at the Glute 4 transporter or one of the mechanisms which
we should discuss how the Glute 4 transporter gets across the cell membrane? Is it a problem
not of bringing glucose in, but really is the problem downstream at hexokinase or glycogen
synthase, things like that. So is that sort of what you're saying, which is can we start with
postprandial hyperglycemia? Yeah, I think we're not even hyperglycemia. This before any abnormal,
just insulin resistance. What I like about the question you asked and how you pointed out,
insulin resistance is the root cause for not only diabetes, but it's going to be the root cause for
all these other abnormalities, fatty liver disease, make us prone, makes a lot of cancers worse,
heart disease. And again, that's the number one killer in this country. It's insulin resistance
that's driving all these things. And not even talking about, even though I'm a diabetologist,
I of course care, I want to fix diabetes, but even before blood sugar goes up, which is how we define
diabetes. Let's understand insulin resistance cause if we can understand insulin resistance,
then that's going to be the best way to fix diabetes, type two diabetes, heart disease,
they're going to make a big impact there, fatty liver disease and slow down cancers.
So let's start with insulin resistance. Okay. What is insulin resistance? So we define it by
giving insulin and we know insulin normally does some effects, makes glucose being taken up by
liver and muscle. And when that same amount of insulin is not doing these things, we say
there's insulin resistance. So you need more insulin than to cause muscle to take up glucose or the
liver to turn off glucose production or take up glucose. And the same thing again, in the fat cell,
what insulin does in the fat cell is that puts the break on breakdown of fat and it's called
that lipolysis or take up glucose to esterify fatty acids into glucose. So these are the three
key insulin responsive organs. And when insulin is not doing that properly, we call that insulin
resistance. And again, keep emphasizing, I think for your listeners, this is probably every other
person in this country or in Western Europe are insulin resistant. Your doctor won't even know
this unless they do careful, maybe studies to assess insulin resistance. Cause you won't pick
this up as the simple plasma glucose test. So what causes resistance? Let's start with muscle.
And the reason I like to start with muscle is when we study our young volunteers, again,
I like them because they're perfectly healthy. They're 20 years of age, 19 to 20. They're lean
because we know everyone who's overweight or obese probably has insulin resistance.
There's so many confounding factors that happen in overweight obesity. These are lean 22, 23 BMI,
lean, non-smoking. So we screen out smoking, no medications, no drugs and sedentary. Because we
know people who exercise, we can reverse insulin resistance and we can talk about how that happens.
So you give these young 20 year olds, let's say you screen, we screen to this date, probably a
thousand, but you get a distribution, given a drink of glucose tolerance, 75 grams. You measure
insulin and you can calculate insulin sensitivity index. It's a crude index and it's kind of a bell
shaped curve. And you have people in the bottom quartile who are insulin resistant by definition,
the top quartile. Then you ask, why are those people in the bottom quartile insulin resistant?
And you measure glycogen synthesis using the methods we talked about briefly, carbon NMR,
give C1 glucose, measure flux into glycogen. And it's already down by 50% compared to the
sensitive ones under matched insulin and glucose concentrations. So they're resistant because they
can't get glucose and glycogen. That's the major pathway. It's not glucose to lactate, not glucose
oxidation. So that's your pathway. Then you want to know where the block in that pathway is. With
phosphorus NMR, we can measure glucose six phosphate inside the cell with a carbon NMR method. We can
measure glucose inside the muscle cell. The reason this is important is we can see where the
biochemical block is. So your listeners all just probably get into a car and they're on the road.
And if there's construction going on, we all know construction piles up after that, whatever that
roadblock is, where the construction is happening. Biochemistry is the same thing. You have a roadblock
and traffic builds up behind it. So we measure G6P to argue, you mentioned about three steps,
synthase, hexokinase and transport, glucose transport. They had all been implicated
to be the roadblock, the step response for the insulin resistance. And so we were able to sort
out which was rate controlling by measuring these intermediates. So if the block is at synthase,
glucose six phosphate should build up and glucose should build up. If the block is at hexokinase,
you should basically have lower G6P and a buildup of glucose. And if the block is at transport,
there should be reductions in both glucose six phosphate and glucose. To a series of studies,
we found in not only these young lean insulin resistant offspring, but obese insulin resistant
individuals as well as individuals with poorly controlled diabetes, G6P, glucose six phosphate
and glucose are both reduced in the muscle cell, in vivo, in humans, implicating transport. That's
where your biochemical block is. So the block is at transport. That's your target to fix if you
want to fix muscle insulin resistance. And the corollary is these other steps are not good
targets, drug targets to go after to fix insulin resistance in muscle. This is the first abnormality
we found in its transport and in these young healthy 20 year olds. And then the question is,
what's wrong with the transport mechanism that led us into the world of lipids? Again, it's been
known for decades that obesity associated with insulin resistance, that's why virtually every
obese adult or child have insulin resistance. There are rare exceptions. And then we basically
found we developed a method to measure fat inside the muscle cell. And that was the best predictor
for insulin resistance in muscle and this block and translocation. Let's give people a quick primer
on normal glucose disposal into a cell. So when the insulin molecule hits the insulin receptor
on the surface, I believe it auto phosphorylates itself, correct? That then signals to insulin
receptor substrate one IRS one inside the cell. So that sends a signal inside the cell, which also
leads to a phosphorylation, which then signals PI three kinase that upregulates PI three kinase.
And that basically leads to a glute four transporter, which you can think of as like a big
tube being shoved up to the surface of the cell across its membrane. And that basically
passively allows glucose in it is not an active transporter, correct? That's correct. Everything
you said is spot on. Basically up until now, we don't know where the breakdown is in that
whole process. All we know is that something is impaired in getting glucose in the cell. But
in terms of is it there's not enough insulin that hits insulin receptor? Is there something wrong
with IRS one with PI three K? Is there something blocking the transporter? We're going to have to
figure that out still. But you've already taken two thirds of this puzzle off the plate by saying
we know it's not downstream of that. That's correct. If you fix the transporter, that's where
the roadblock is. And that's the target. The next set of questions becomes why isn't insulin causing?
And as you point out, this translocation of the glute four transporter to the membrane to allow
glucose to come into the cell through facilitated transport down a gradient. So that's what we can
talk about next if you want to. That's perfect. Can I share my screen with you at this point?
You can. And what we will do, Jerry, is we are going to take everything that you are sharing with
me and we're going to turn these into show notes that will be time stamped to this part of the
discussion because while I guess people like you and I do tend to picture these things in our head
easily, I think for many people it is going to be incredibly helpful to be able to actually look at
some biochemical drawings. I benefit from this greatly. It's still not purely second nature to me.
I like to think in pictures too. So as much as we can help the audience out with graphics,
I think it will be beneficial. So here's a cartoon. I'll walk you through this and stop me.
If you have questions, this is a cartoon of a muscle cell. We went through how insulin normally
works. Insulin binds to the receptor and everything, as you said, we're going to actually show this in
this cartoon. It binds to the receptor. The receptor autophosphorylates, becomes a kinase.
The key substrate for this kinase, since receptor kinase in muscles, insulin receptor substrate one,
which undergoes tyrosine phosphorylation, allows it to bind and activate this other protein,
PI3 kinase, which Lou Cantley discovered. And that's a required step for translocation. So that's
all been worked out. And somehow this is not working. This is broken in the insulin resistant
individual. And again, these young 20 year olds, the patient with diabetes, the obese insulin
resistant individual. And the question is, what's wrong? So I'm going to share with you, at least my
view, which would explain insulin resistance in most situations of lipid induced insulin resistance,
which I think accounts for, I would say, the majority of these patients I see who have type
two diabetes or who obese insulin resistance, or even these young lean insulin resistant offspring.
And so this is the picture. So here, and it relates to fatty fat metabolism. Before I told you,
the other MR method that we developed is actually something called proton NMR. And this is actually,
most of your listeners are very familiar with you. Everyone knows about MRI, magnetic resonance
imaging. This is people go into a scanner and they get very pretty pictures of an organ brain
or some other organ for diagnostic reasons. And it's the same biophysical principles. You're
basically getting this NMR signal from protons and protons are the most abundant NMR visible
nucleus in the body. And it's mostly water we're looking at. So when you're basically getting the
same signal from protons and mostly protons are water and fat. And so an imager gives you this
three-dimensional reconstruction of proton density in water and fat. And that's what gives you the
images. And again, we're doing biochemistry. So we're getting, taking that same kind of information,
but actually looking at individual carbon atoms or phosphorus atoms, or in this case, protons lining
the carbons and triglyceride. It's fat. So what I said, using proton NMR to measure fat inside the
cell, this is different from fat outside the cell. So if you look at a steak and you see the marbling
of fat in a steak, that's fat outside the muscle cell, which you don't see if you look at a steak
is the fat inside the muscle cell. And using NMR, we can actually discern fat outside the cell
versus fat inside the cell. And we can do this in many organs and muscle started to muscle.
And using this approach, we found fat inside the muscle was the best predictor for this block and
transport in all of our volunteers, young people, old people, children, sedentary individuals,
sedentary individuals, fat inside the cells, the best predictor for insulin resistance. And so this
led us into the world of lipids. We're keen to understand then if finding the lipid intermediate
that might do this. And in studies where we took healthy individuals, perfectly normal
sensitivity, we gave them an inter lipid infusion, just raised plasma, fatty acids for three to four
hours and found that after three to four hours, we can make them as insulin resistant as anyone
with type two diabetes. And others had shown that in addition to us. I mean, this is, we weren't the
first to show this, but what we were the first to show is it's due to this block in glycogen
synthesis. And it's the same block, it's that block and transport. Just to be clear, when you deliver
intra lipid, that's intravenous lipid as a triacylglycerol or diacylglycerol? No, this is a
triglyceride. This is an emulsion, a triglyceride emulsion. It's often given to patients for
hyper elementation when they can't eat, you give us energy rich infusion. Just like TPN or something
like that. It's used in TPN often. But what we also do is just a little low dose of heparin to
activate lipoprotein lipase. So all of a sudden, then you can artificially raise fatty acids
twofold, something up to about one and a half millimolar and ask the question, what does this
do? What does this have to do with visit ultra metabolism? And it has profound effects.
So by increasing LPL expression, not expression activity, I did not know that heparin activated
LPL. So by activating LPL with heparin, cool trick to know, I'll keep that in mind,
you're going to get more of that lipid into the muscle cell. You will raise fatty. So what the
heparin does is it causes activation of lipoprotein lipase. And that will then break down the
triglycerides to raise fatty acids and more delivery of fatty acids to all cells in the body.
Okay. So this becomes basically a quick vehicle by which you can deliver lipid directly into the
muscle cell. Exactly. Where you can acutely change that. And again, you can't do this just by getting
fatty acids. Fatty acid turnover is so fast, you can't just infuse fatty acids to significantly
raise. So this is a way we're able to raise fatty acids specifically in vivo, in humans.
And we do this in animals and it's that, so it's a nice pharmacological way of asking the question,
what impact is just simply raising fatty acids for a few hours have on metabolism. And it's
profound. It takes three to four hours before you see this. And then boom, it's you get very
profound insulin resistance. And in our early studies, again, we showed using the same methods
I told you about measuring glucose, six phosphate, measuring intracellular glucose, measuring
glycogen synthesis. We found simply raising fatty acids for three to four hours, blocks glycogen
synthesis, profound insulin resistance, as they say, as anyone with obesity or type two diabetes.
And it's due to the same and acquired block and transport insulin activation, transport,
both G6P and glucose are down. So that to us was a very important lesson because it basically
changed the paradigm because prior to this people, workers, biochemists, you may know the name
Philip Randall, who did some pioneering studies in the sixties at University of Bristol and was
really the first to say, hey, fatty acids may be toxic, may be causing insulin resistance and did
studies in rat tissue, you know, cells, heart tissue, diaphragm muscles taken from rats in vitro,
incubated it with fatty acids and in vitro in the test tube, induced insulin resistance.
The mechanism that they postulated was that it was altering basically oxidation, the TCA cycle
citrate levels would build up and lead to inhibition of phosphofructokinase, which is
a key glycolytic enzyme. The prediction that Randall made was glucose six phosphate should increase,
leading to inhibition of hexokinase. We were interested in that because we said, oh, fat in
our hands is important. We're raising fatty acids and causing resistance. And we see this
really strong relationship between fat in the muscle cell and insulin resistance in all of our
subjects, obese, diabetic, young insulin resistant individuals. And so we wanted to see if his
mechanism, Randall's postulate mechanism translates to humans, because these were all
in vitro studies done in tissues taken from animals. So in a series of studies, we took,
again, the healthy individuals, raised fatty acids through this triglyceride and little dose
of heparin infusion and found just the opposite to what Randall predicted. They got insulin
resistance, which is what he would have said, but not through his mechanism. He said, G6P should go
up. We saw it go down and we saw glucose go down. So it wasn't through inhibition of glycolysis
as he said, it's somehow interfering with the insulin activation of transport. So and again,
same rate controlling step we saw in all of our diabetics and obese individuals and
predybetic individuals. But just to be clear, Jerry, it caused hypoglycemia. The intra lipid
dropped glucose? No. Raising the fatty acids caused insulin resistance, inability of insulin
to stimulate glucose transport. Okay. Okay. Yep. I may have misheard you, but okay.
I'm going to now fast forward. We then took these observations back to the bench. We were able to
replicate this and rodents, rats and mice. And the power, even though I'm most passionate about
our human studies, I'm a clinical physiologist and I care most about understanding what's happening
in humans. The animal models allow you to really interrogate biochemical process. There we can get
tissue out in humans. I like to be non-invasive with our MR methodology, but here sometimes you
need to get tissues to measure activities, phosphorylation events. And, and also you have
the power of mouse genetics. You can knock genes in and out of mice to really rigorously test
hypothesis. I should tell you one experiment before I moved to this cartoon that we did
in humans is we did biopsies in these humans when we raised fatty acids and found this block in
transport and asked the question, is a lipid intermediate fatty acid metabolite interfering
with insulin signaling cascade, which we just discussed receptor and somewhere to PI3 kinase.
And what we found was indeed in healthy individuals just give glucose and insulin.
You get activation of PI3 kinase. This is the step you mentioned. This is the required step
for translocation. And in the follow-up study, same individuals, we raised glucose and insulin
and also raised fatty acids. And then we totally abrogate insulin activation of PI3 kinase.
That study basically in humans in the model we care about is saying, yeah, somehow a fatty acid
metabolite is leading to this block in insulin action somewhere between PI3 kinase and the
receptor. So we've narrowed it down to that. I'll walk you through the steps that I think then are
the biochemical metabolite that's mediating this, the lipid fatty acid mediator that's leading to
this, and then the biochemical mechanism. Does that sound good? Yeah, that sounds fantastic.
Here we have a cartoon of a muscle cell. And my view, again, thinking about flux, it has to do with
relative imbalance. So basically doing focus lipidomics, we zeroed in on this metabolite,
fatty acid metabolite called diacylglycerol. And yeah, I heard you mentioned that before.
It's the precursor, it's the penultimate step in triglyceride synthesis, diacyl, two fatty acids
on a glycerol backbone. This is a bioactive metabolite. It's been known for years to activate
novel PKCs. This is what we found tracked in our animal models with lipid-induced insulin resistance.
Do high fat feeding in a mouse or rat, get muscle insulin resistance. And it was this metabolite
that tracked with insulin resistance. And then we did the lipid, same type of lipid infusion we did
in humans, simply raise plasma fatty acids by giving triglyceride and heparin. We saw acyl-CoA's
go up. We saw DAGs go up. Right when DAGs reached a peak, then we got activation of novel PKCs,
PKC theta and epsilon in the muscle. Then we linked to this block in insulin action,
which I'll show you in a second, at the level of the receptor and one step downstream of the
receptor. The concept that I'd like to impart on you is it's this imbalance between fluxes. So fatty
acids are continuously being delivered to muscle cells. And we're going to do the same thing if we
have time to talk about the liver, because that's the other key insulin-responsive organ. But we'll
start with muscle. Fatty acids are being delivered through fatty acids or even hydrolysis of
triglycerides through LPL, endothelial barrier, delivering more fatty acids to the muscle cell.
When it's the flux of fatty acids into the muscle cell that exceeds the ability of the mitochondria
to oxidize the fat or store this fatty acids acyl-CoA's as triglyceride, you get net
accumulation of diacylglycerol. This is a very important point. Triglycerides are neutral. So
I want to emphasize this. So even though triglycerides often track with insulin resistance,
we've dissociated it inside the muscle cell and liver cell from insulin resistance. It's a marker
for DAGs, typically tracks very well, but it's in a NERP storage form of lipid. So triglycerides
are not the culprit. We've dissociated in liver and muscle, but it's a pretty good marker if you
can't measure the DAGs with mass spec. Let's go back to that for a second. I want to make sure
people understand what we're saying here. So triacylglyceride or triglyceride, those two we
use interchangeably, has this three carbon glycerol backbone with three free fatty acids on it.
That's the way that we very, very efficiently store energy in the most energy dense hydrocarbon
in our body. The DAG by extension has only two of those free fatty acids. What typically sits on
that third carbon and what is it about that confirmation that renders the DAG, in this case
at least, seemingly much more of a problem than the TG or TAG? Basically it's a hydroxyl group,
a simple hydroxyl group. It's the two fatty acids of the DAG that sit into the bile layer,
membrane bile layer, and then the hydrophilic hydroxyl group sits in the cytoplasm. And that's
what then will pull the novel PKCs to the plasma membrane. So that's the troublemaker. That's the
troublemaker. Basically then when you get this imbalance between fatty acid uptake versus
oxidation in the mito versus storage as neutral lipid, you get activation of these two novel
PKCs in muscle, theta and epsilon. Theta blocks insulin action at the level somewhere between the
receptor and iris-1 tyrosine phosphorylation. And epsilon, and we'll get into this for the liver,
directly binds to the insulin receptor and then hits the receptor kinase. If we have a chance,
I'd love to share this with you and your listeners because this I think has important evolutionary
mechanisms behind it. Why does this exist? And it's going to be very important for
survival during starvation. But nevertheless, when both of these NPKCs in muscle are activated,
you have reduced insulin tyrosine phosphorylation of iris-1, less PI through kinase activation.
And as we talked about, then less boot fortranslocation. So to me, the real culprit,
and we've been able to just quickly really test this rigorously, gene knockout, we've been able to
inactivate isoforms, NPKC theta, you get protection. We've been able to block
mitoxidation and you make these animals prone to that buildup insulin resistance. We block
fat entry into the myocyte, inactivate F84, they're protected. You overexpress lipoprotein lipase
in the muscle, more fatty acid delivery muscle specific insulin resistance. And then finally,
if you rev up mitochondrial fat oxidation, let's say through uncoupling, overexpress UCP3
in the muscle, you get protection from insulin resistance and all these track with
DAGs going up or down with the insulin resistance or protection from insulin resistance.
Let's talk a little bit about how we think this is different in an active versus inactive person
because the outset you said, look, when we're trying to find this in the youngest cohort of
patients, these 20 year old basically undergrads at Yale that we're going to study, we screen on
many things, but an important thing we screen for is sedentary behavior. You mentioned that at the
very outset, which leads me to believe that if you did a sampling across the cross country team,
the crew team, you wouldn't find this phenomenon. So what is it about activity or the lack thereof
that presumably points to this elevation of intracellular DAGs that kicks off this cascade?
Let me just show you. So this is where we talked about Reven and his hypothesis of insulin
resistance and how what we wanted was to build on it. Because I'm going to answer your question
about exercise and I want to do two things that I want to show you how exercise reverses this
muscle insulin resistance. But I also want to show you and your listeners why exercise in muscle
actually will prevent fatty liver and liver insulin resistance. I think that this is a
useful segue. And so this is from Jerry Reven's Banting Lecture in 1988. And at that time,
people were still arguing whether insulin resistance was driving all these other things
we see around the circle, atherosclerosis, hypertension, type 2 diabetes, polycystic
ovarian disease, inflammation, or are these just common things clustering together?
So what we wanted to do was actually ask the question, what we see in these young 20 year
olds, these volunteers, is the first thing we see is muscle insulin resistance. And maybe
that's driving atherogenic dyslebigemia, who is going to lead to heart disease, high triglycerides,
low HDL, and non-alcoholic fatty liver disease by changing the fate of ingested carbohydrate
from glycogen to fat. So this is the distribution I was telling you about and healthy young,
sedentary individuals, we're going to get into exercise in a second. We simply take the bottom
quartile, one in four versus the top quartile, and we give them two high carbohydrate meals. And we
say, where's the energy going from that carbohydrate? How is it being stored? Getting at the very first
question you asked me, we can use our NMR to measure changes in fat storage and liver and muscle.
As well as glycogen in liver and muscle. And what we found then is you give them two high carbohydrate
milkshakes, and there's virtually no difference in the plasma glucose concentrations at this late
breakfast and lunchtime high carbohydrate shake. But you can see it's at the expense of severe
hyperinsulinemia is what we talked about. So the reason these young insulin resistant, as well as
every insulin resistant person is perfectly fine is the beta cells are pumping out two to three
times the amount of insulin just to maintain euglycemia. So these beta cells are just being whipped,
working really hard. And that's why no one's diabetic, you're insulin resistant. That's why
virtually every obese insulin resistant person is normal glycemia because the beta cells are working
so hard to maintain this. And you can see that here. The other thing I want to point out is
the insulin levels are given number, you know, so normal, maybe 100 at the peak and maybe 180
at the peak in the resistant individuals. But this is in plasma, the portal vein with the liver
seeds is three times the liver seen huge amounts of insulin in these insulin resistant individuals
just to maintain normal glycemia. We use carbon NMR to look at changes in muscle glycogen and
liver glycogen. You can see, again, young insulin resistant 20 year olds can't get glucose into
muscle glycogen due to a block in transport because they have increased ectopic fat in the
myocyte, the eggs are up, no problem in liver. And then you look at the changes in fat and this
carbohydrate, this is change in liver triglyceride, it's up two and a half, 2.3 fold. You put some
heavy water, stable, heavy water into the milkshake to track de novo lipogenesis. That's
the conversion of glucose to fat. And that's also up greater than two fold. Quick question there.
There was a very famous experiment. It's been so long since I've read it. I certainly know I spent
many hours on it. It was by Mark Hellerstein circa 94 ish. And he looked at this question of
how much carbohydrate could be converted to fat via de novo lipogenesis. And if I recall correctly,
the answer was, at least from that paper, was not that much. But also, I believe one of the criticisms
of that was that he was looking at an insulin sensitive population. Am I remembering that
correctly? Because what you're showing here would suggest the opposite, which suggests that an
insulin resistant person is capable of significant de novo lipogenesis. Everything you've said is
correct. When you're thinking about de novo lipogenesis, two things is you get what conditions
are you studying this? Is it after meal ingestion? Is it in the fasting state when a lot of people
have measured this in the past? It's minimal and it makes sense. It only gears up with substrate
is taking in. And then depending on the type of substrate, you can alter this quite a bit. So
it can be changed by simply putting more fructose, more glucose in the meal by increase
the meal size. Mark's done beautiful work in the past. It is what it is. Those studies are what
they are. But clearly what we're learning here is just as you say, you know, is significant. It's
not the majority of the fat. I think most investigators would agree the majority of fat
synthesis in liver is occurring through a stearification that is fatty acids coming to
the liver, getting corporate into triglyceride. But there is a significant importance for DNL.
And again, especially if you track it chronically in patients who are continuously high carb
feeding, especially high sucrose, high fructose corn syrup, we want to get into that, but
fructose basically gets funneled into the liver, into the DNL pathway. It's ubiquitous. You can
push DNL to be significant and it is a significant contributor to metabolic fatty liver disease.
And it's upregulated with peripheral sensitivity. I think this is the major
message I want to give here is when you have muscle insulin resistance, specifically,
it will drive the liver fat synthesis by DNL. When you have that, when your liver is making
more fat through DNL, it makes more BLDL exports. So plasma triglycerides go up and HDL goes down.
So what I find interesting about this before you go further, Jerry, is this is all from the 2007
PNAS paper by your wife, actually, right? Kit Peterson. Yeah, Kit Peterson. So what I find
interesting about these data is that these patients were euglycemic. I mean, that to me
is the staggering piece of this. These patients are still potentially a decade away from seeing
an interference in glucose homeostasis. They're a decade away from their doctor saying, hey,
your glucose is a little higher than it should be post-prandily, nevermind even at the fast.
And yet they're already seeing an 80% increase in triglyceride, which I just want to sort of
talk a little bit about this clinically. Most laboratory assays will say a triglyceride level
of 150 milligrams per deciliter is considered normal. Well, we don't say that in our practice.
We view anything over 100 as abnormal. That's a red flag. And if your trigs are more than 2x your
HDL cholesterol, that's a very big red flag. Although most people would accept triglycerides
of three or four, if not five times above HDL cholesterol before the sirens would go off.
And yet when you look at these patients, again, euglycemic, you see a difference of approximately
100 to 105 of the trigs in the insulin resistant to 60 in the insulin sensitive. So it's all kind
of right here in front of you, sort of in a way that unfortunately just doesn't get appreciated.
But it's the more intense stuff that's mind boggling to me, which is the two and three-fold
difference we see in de novo lipogenesis, hepatic synthesis of fat, impaired hepatic
glucose sensitivity. And I guess it speaks to the point you made earlier, Jerry, which is
when the portal vein amplification of insulin differences is as big as it is, it becomes
basically a magnifier of everything we're seeing in the periphery. Exactly. Yeah. And our normative
data, in my view, we need to reset what we consider normal is to me, this is when we look at our
insulin sensitive, that's what our normal should be and guiding us. You asked about exercise and
something we're quite passionate about. And I want to kind of tell you how that fits in here.
So again, conceptually, here we have a normal person ingesting carbohydrate. First question,
how is this distributed? It's in glycogen is where you want to store your ingested carbohydrate.
It gets stored in glycogen and liver and muscle. And again, this is one quarter of our young, lean,
healthy volunteers are insulin resistant. And again, if you're overweight or obese, you're there
already because these are lean individuals and that's still one quarter of the population.
You can't get that ingested glucose into glycogen due to this block in transport,
due to the block in DAG, PKC inhibition of insulin signaling. It's diverted to liver.
You have that insulin in the portal vein that's three times periphery, it's up to five,
600 micro units per mil. That turns on SRIBP1C, the master transcriptional regulator of triglyceride
synthesis gears up all the DNL enzymes. So you have increased DNL that leads to this increase.
We just reviewed plasma triglycerides, this reduction in HDL. This is going to set
these healthy individuals up to atherogenic dyslipidemia, heart disease in their 40s and 50s.
With time, it's metabolic associated fatty liver disease now. And again, most common
cause of liver disease now in the world. It's now leading cause of NASH, leading cause of liver
fibrosis, cirrhosis, end stage liver disease and going to be liver cancer. So it's all going to be
metabolic driven and from that hyperinsulinemia in my view. So exercise, can we do anything about this?
This hypothesis is right, we can test it. And so you asked about exercise. So this is a study we did
some years ago, published in the New England Journal, took these young insulin resistant
offspring. And this is with parents with type 2 diabetes. And the Jocelyn group did a really nice
study. They found that if you have two parents with type 2 diabetes, and if you're insulin
resistant, that single parameter is the best predictor whether or not you would go on to
develop type 2 diabetes. So we've tried to study these individuals with our methodology extensively.
And John Luca Persagian, who did this study when he was a fellow with me, took these and just studied
them in the basal state shown here that, you know, again, in the insulin resistant, again,
everyone's hears lean, not smoking, no medications, they're in their 20s and 30s, BMI 23, 24 to factor
out obesity, confounding of factors of obesity, medication, smoking, other things. So young, lean,
healthy individuals, but just parents with diabetes, insulin resistant. You study them,
and in the basal state, take up less than half the amount of glucose in muscle, and it's due to a
block in transport. So same thing as I've gone on and on before in the diabetics and the obese
individuals, this block in transport. And we asked the question, does exercise, can we bypass the
sound normality? And the answer is yes. So here you can see this was after six weeks of being on a
stair master, three 15 minute bouts at about 65% MBO2 max. And here we're normalizing insulin
stimulated muscle glycogen synthesis. And we usually measuring glucose 6-phosphate, we've opened
up that door of getting glucose into the myocyte. So, and I think molecular explanation for this is
this protein called ANPK, which we can talk about, gets activated with exercise. And that has been
shown to cause borotranslocation independent, independent of pediatric kinase. And so we're
kind of short circuiting that block with exercise. To test our overall hypothesis, does muscle
insulin resistance drive fatty liver and DNL and high triglycerides? We took these young insulin
resistant individuals and we showed, John Luca showed in that New England Journal study, even a
single bout, 45 minute bout was sufficient to open up the door to glucose, cause that glute four
translocations. And Rasmus Rabaul, when he was a clinical fellow with me, did one single bout
in these same individuals I showed you before, insulin resistance and muscle.
The ones had high triglycerides, low HDL and prone to increased DNL. With the single bout, we able to
show that that same ingested glucose would lead to more glucose deposition as muscle glycogen.
And we got significant reductions in de nova lipogenesis, significant reductions in liver
triglyceride. I just want to make sure I understand that. And it's relevant to another question I have
about the difference between insulin dependent and independent glucose uptake. So do we know if that
single bout of exercise, which particular piece of the pathway got released? Did it have some direct
effect on the root cause, the DAG or some of the kinases downstream? Was it even further downstream
at the very last step where the transporter gets released? Like where was the actual bottleneck
alleviated with that single bout of exercise? I can speculate in these were human studies.
I can tell you that we opened up the door. We measured glucose 6-phosphate in them and that
goes up. So we opened the door for that defect in insulin stimulating transport is now reversed. So
glucose transporters and the membrane glucose is coming in. What I can't tell you is whether or not
we've altered DAGs and we're getting improved insulin signaling at the level of the receptor
and IRS1. And or is it just AMPK causing this glute IV translocation? If I had to speculate,
I would think most of it is through the latter. We were simply with an acute bout causing AMPK
induced glute IV translocation, which we know happens independent of the kindness. That's
established. So we're short circuiting. We're just causing glute IV right at all the lower mechanisms
to get to the membrane. So we fixed the block in insulin action. I think though with chronic
exercise therapy, we're going to be doing both where we get melt away. The lipid and DAGs go down.
So we have improved insulin signaling as well as more AMPK induced glute IV translocation.
Yeah, I'll tell you just I think I've even discussed this on a previous podcast.
I've had a couple of patients with type 1 diabetes that I've taken care of, not many,
but in the phenotype of patients with type 1 diabetes where there is a significant amount of
exercise, specifically sort of modest intensity aerobic exercise. So a person who is, for example,
doing brisk walking, very brisk walking sort of to the tune of four miles an hour, an hour to two
hours a day. These patients with type 1 diabetes can be virtually free of insulin and maintain
reasonable glycemic control so they can walk around with a hemoglobin A1c of 6%
using maybe 12 units of insulin a day and obviously restricting carbohydrates. But again,
it suggests, I say this, having watched them change the intensity duration of the exercise,
that it seems that that exercise becomes a spigot to how much glucose they can dispose
in their muscle seemingly without insulin. It's almost like a total bypass of the system,
which again, I think to your point is chronic. I don't think this is something we see acutely.
I obviously can't comment on it. The first time I saw it, which was probably about six years ago,
it really sent a light bulb off, which is imagine now being able to maximize both insulin dependent
and insulin independent glucose uptake into a muscle that really becomes a powerful tool to
combat all of this sort of metabolic dysregulation. That's what AMPK does is insulin dependent glucose
uptake. And I can see in combination with reduced carbohydrate consumption, less coming into
the circulation and whatever little comes in is taken care of through AMPK, insulin independent
good for trans location. So that fits. Before we go to the liver, and I do want to actually
talk about how all of this works in the liver. I want to go back to one other thing that you
very briefly touched on, which is the evolutionary explanation for some of this.
That would be best done, if I might say with the liver.
Okay, great. Let's do it because I want to understand this. Yeah.
That's kind of fun. So let's now turn. So I kind of walked you through at least my thinking about
insulin resistance, why it's so important for not only diabetes, but so many diseases. I've shown
you the physiological cause for insulin resistance in muscle can't get glucose in the glycogen.
I've shown you that block is a transport and then I've given you a molecular understanding
of how that insulin resistance and muscle happens. My view is lipid disaglycerol is block leading to
activation of a novel protein kinase C, epsilon, theta blocking insulin signaling. Okay. So let's
now, and then I've shown you how muscle insulin resistance can lead to fat accumulation in liver,
atherogenic, dyslipidema, and fatty liver. Now we know fatty liver is what then leads to insulin
resistance in the liver. And so I want to take you through the molecular basis for how fat and liver
causes insulin resistance. And it's pretty much what's nice now that you understand muscle,
lipid induced muscle insulin resistance, it's pretty close to the same story in liver. So here's a
cartoon of the liver cell. But is the direction of causation, Jerry, in the order in which you're
telling the story, in other words, is the hyperinsulinemia as a result of muscle insulin
resistance? Let me clarify that muscle insulin resistance, which leads to peripheral hyperinsulinemia,
which is accompanied by portal vein hyperinsulinemia, which leads to what you're about to tell us. Is
that the order in which you think this occurs? I do. As I say, this is what we see in our
volunteers as we march through the progression in different stages. We don't see liver abnormalities
in these young 20 year olds. It's all muscle and maybe a little bit of the fat cell, which we'll
come to at the end, but it's the muscle. There's no alterations in the liver until they get fatty
liver. Once they get fatty liver, then we see both insulin resistance in liver and insulin resistance
in muscle. A very important distinction between humans and rodents. We've studied both models quite
extensively. Rodents develop insulin resistance in the reverse direction. They get liver fat first,
liver insulin resistance, and then muscle. Most of the studies done in rodents is a very important
distinction in terms of the progression and very different humans versus rodents. We can talk about
similarities and differences if you want, but we're going to focus mostly on humans for this talk.
And that makes total sense. So it is, again, its peripheral IR, hepatic IR, hepatic consequences,
which then basically amplify it. That's my belief, yeah. And again, leading to this beta cell
compensation, compensation, and then again, something when you get both muscle and liver
insulin resistance and it's increased glucose production by liver, then something happens to
the beta cell. And that's when things really start to spiral where you have very profound
hyperglycemia fasting the postprandial. Here's the cartoon of the liver cell. And again, glucose
transport is not rate controlling, as you know, in the liver cell. Glucose just diffuses in through
Glut2 transporters and the insulin, again, binds the receptor, same thing, autophosphorylation.
The key intermediate there in liver is IRS2 undergoes tyrosine phosphorylation, use cathekinase,
just as you did in muscle like AT2. And in liver, what happens is you have a few things. One,
not shown here is glucokinase translocation. And that we've recently shown is probably very
important for rate control, getting glucose into the hepatocyte. You also get activation of glycogen
synthase and more glycogen synthesis. And then you have this phosphorylation of FOXO,
which is a transcriptional regulator. And that then is excluded from the nucleus and then down
regulates then gluconeogenesis through a transcriptional mechanism. And if we have a
chance, I'd like to come back to this because we have some interesting data that speaks to really
how insulin is inhibiting this key process. So let's now just focus on how lipid causes insulin
resistance in liver. Same metabolite, it's the disaglystrols. They go to activate epsilon,
that's really the major isoform of PKC, novel PKCs in liver, and work by Varmin Samuel when
he was doing his PhD with me in a series of studies. Varmin showed that epsilon binds to
the insulin receptor and directly inhibits the receptor kinase itself. And that then leads to
downstream abnormalities. What I want to share with you now, which I think, and again,
gets into this evolutionary basis for insulin resistance, which I think your listeners might
find interesting is how is epsilon inhibiting the receptor kinase? We worked on this Jesse
Reinhardt and Max Peterson, he was an MD PhD student with me. We did untargeted phosphoproteomics.
And what I'm showing here is the catalytic domain of the insulin receptor. Yeah, I can just describe
it for the listeners. It's a loop. You can picture it as a door over the pocket for the catalytic
domain of the insulin receptor. And this door is closed. IRS1, IRS2 can't go into the pocket for
tyrosine phosphorylation. When insulin binds the receptor, these three tyrosines, the 1158,
the 1162, and the 1163 become phosphorylated, that opens the door, that loop flips out, and then
IRS1, IRS2 go into the pocket and undergo tyrosine phosphorylation to get the rest of the
cascade going. Using untargeted phosphoproteomics, we were able to show Jesse Reinhardt, who is our
collaborator and mass spec maven, identified using purified receptor, purified PKC epsilon,
that when you add activated epsilon to the receptor, you phosphorylate this threonine.
And that got us very excited because, golly, that's one amino acid away from these two tyrosines
that are required for activation receptors, maybe doing something important. And so the other thing
that got us excited about, and here's getting into evolution, is the sequence of the catalytic domain
for the receptor. And it's been conserved all the way from humans down to fruit flies,
those three tyrosines, same position, and that threonine that sits right between the two tyrosines,
1158, 1162, has been conserved all the way, again, from Homo sapiens down to Drosophila,
through evolution, if something's important, it usually hangs around. That's a long time.
So to prove this, we very simply, we did some genetics. Again, that's what you can do is you
can knock a glutamic acid, replace that threonine with glutamic acid, mimic a phosphorylation event,
and that kills the kinase activity. You can mutate the threonine to an alanine so it can't
get phosphorylated, and then you have protection in vitro from epsilon-induced reduction in IRC
activity. And then you can make the mouse. And so here in this paper, we made mice where we replaced
the threonine in that key position, the 11, this is the mouse homologue, the 1150 is the
homologue for the 1160 in humans. So all the threonines are instead alanines. And I won't
get into the data, other say the mice are perfectly normal, normal chow, normal insulin
sensitivity, nothing, you know, normal size, normal growth. But when Max fed these mice a high-fat diet,
the wild-type mice get profound hepatic insulin resistance. And this we see, and everyone else on
the planet sees, you feed mice high-fat diet, even for three days, they get fat accumulation,
DAG accumulation, hepatic insulin resistance. Does it have to have sucrose in it as well,
or just fat? Doesn't need to be. You can make it worse if you add a little sucrose. They like
that in the drinking water, and they have even more fatty liver to put sucrose in the drinking
water. But this is just with fat alone, but it's even more greater when you put sucrose or fructose
or whatever sugar you want in the drinking water. And here, then you can see when you simply mutate
that threonine, now you have perfectly normal hepatic insulin sensitivity as reflected by
insulin's ability to suppress hepatic glucose production. And this is despite the same amount
of liver fat, same amount of liver DAGs in the liver. This tells us that that single amino acid
is doing something very important in terms of mediating lipid-induced insulin resistance.
And this actually just came out this last week, this paper now, just to summarize, where we've
now shown that there's different isoforms. We didn't get into this, into the abdysyl glycerol,
and it really matters which isoform it is and what compartment it is. Just to summarize this
paper that just came out in cell metabolism, we were able to show by measuring the three different
stereoisomers of diisoglycerols. It's really the SN1,2 isoform and measuring these different
isoforms in five different intracellular compartments, the plasma membrane, the cytosol,
lipid droplet, ER, and the mitochondria. It's really specifically the SN1,2 isoform in the
plasma membrane that's important. If you just measure total DAGs, you may easily miss this.
We learned that this recent study, and that we showed both that PKC epsilon is both necessary
and sufficient for this process by doing a knock-in and over expression. But I just want to basically
touch on the question you asked me about. Why do we have insulin resistance? Why should it exist?
And the reason I think it exists is it's protective for us during starvation. When you starve,
this is true pretty much in all mammals, mice, rats, and humans. When we starve, we get fatty
liver. Here in this study, this is Rachel Perry's paper in cell from a couple years ago. Take rats,
just starve them for 48 hours. You have increased lipolysis, more fatty acids delivered to the
liver, hepatic fat accumulation. DAGs we show go up, SN1,2, PKC epsilon translocation, and insulin
resistance in liver. And the main thing that insulin does in the liver is it promotes glucose
uptake and storage as glycogen. When you think about it, that's what you want turned off during
starvation because during starvation, glucose is a very precious molecule, and you want to preserve
this in circulation for the CNS, which is critically in need. It's really the major source of energy
for the CNS. And so by promoting hepatic insulin resistance, we're promoting glucose in circulation
for basically the CNS to operate. And so that to me is why that threonine is preserved all the way
from humans to fruit flies. And I just wanted to show you this cover of nature, this Mexican cave
fish. It's a fun story because after our paper came out, this little fish made the cover of nature.
And what was so fascinating about it, so these little fish, they live inside caves.
They spend most of their life starving. The only time they are able to eat is when something smaller
than them swims in front of the cave, and then they can reach out and grab it and pull it back
into the cave and gobble it up. And these workers who studied this Mexican cave fish found this cave
fish had a mutation in the insulin receptor, had profound hepatic insulin resistance, and they also
went on to say this was important to allow them to survive. In my view, insulin resistance was a
protective mechanism throughout evolution that allowed us to survive all species during starvation,
which was probably the predominant environmental exposure we've had for the last many, many
millennia. And it's only in recent years, recent decades that now we're in this toxic environment
of over nutrition. And it's when these same pathways now are going the opposite direction,
promoting disease by doing what they were at one time was protective. And now they're actually
being told metabolic disease that we just discussed. So I want to make sure I can unpack this a little
bit. So I want to start in the muscle because I think it's easier. And again, we'll even talk
about it in humans, which means we can do it on a sort of different timescale, because obviously 48
hours of fasting in a mouse is a seismic fast, a near fatal fast. But let's say 48 to 72 hours
of fasting in a human, we still would expect to see significant muscle insulin resistance. And
there would be a great reason for that evolutionarily, because you would want to make sure that as much
glucose as possible in that circulation, which by this point is all coming through hepatic glucose
output is not being quote unquote wasted in muscle glycogen synthesis. To your point, every gram of
gluconeogenic substrate that's going through the liver and then coming out the liver should be
preserved for the brain. Because even Cahill's studies show that after 40 days of starvation,
humans were still getting about 40% of CNS energy from glucose, the remainder from ketones. So
glucose never went away as a substrate for the brain. So I think I have a handle on the muscle
side of things. I'm still struggling a little bit to understand the physiologic consequence of hepatic
insulin resistance, and how that feeds into what I think should be an environment that says,
figure out a way to make as much glucose for the CNS as possible. Why does more fat accumulation
in the liver make it better served to protect the brain? So first of all, let me step back. So both
organs during starvation, both liver, even though I focus here on liver, muscle will become insulin
resistant also through increased circulating fatty acids through the mechanisms we talked
about DAGS building up PKC theta. So insulin resistance in all organs are going to preserve
glucose for the CNS. I was just focusing on the threonine here in liver because that's where
Epsilon was taking us. To understand the liver, I want to just take you to another cartoon because
you're asking a very important question about processes, about regulation, how insulin works
in liver. And I think to do this, let me just step back. The conceptual view, again, this is a
cartoon I always like to show how does insulin work. This was from 20 years ago when I was first
studying it, maybe 30 years ago. Insulin binds to receptor magic happens, something happens,
and you have an effect. And so even though insulin has been since its discovery, we're still
trying to really understand what's happening in different tissues, how it works and getting
surprises. So this is the canonical view we just went through of how insulin works on liver, it
binds the receptor, it activates the cascade to promote glycogen synthesis and turn off gluconeogenesis.
And what we're finding is the simple view doesn't explain many things and I think needs modification,
especially in terms of insulin regulating gluconeogenesis, this process that is required
to keep us alive during starvation. Without gluconeogenesis, we're not going to wake up in
the morning because it's gluconeogenesis that supplies glucose for the CNS while we're sleeping.
And certainly during starvation, without this process, we're in trouble.
I don't think that can be overstated, by the way. Let's go back to what you just said.
We couldn't survive, by my calculation, Jerry, we'd have a hard time surviving 10 minutes without
gluconeogenesis as a species. Well, I'll modify that a little bit. As Pashy did, I'd love to hear
you state the importance of gluconeogenesis. No, we know clinically you can. And again,
from the lessons learned from Gene Knockout, unfortunately, there are patients with inherited
disease, Bongariki's disease. As you know, patients who don't have glucose 6-phosphatase,
the last key step getting glucose 6-phosphate out. We do know that can be compatible with life. We
have patients with glucose 6-phosphatase. And the way we keep them alive is just continuously to feed
them. Yeah, that's my point. Without continuous glucose feeding, your lifespan would be measured
in minutes to hours without gluconeogenesis to regulate glucosomastasis. It's critical for
life function. We're on the same page. So let's just talk about then how it's thought to operate
and regulate it. It's also important to be able to modulate it. So we eat a meal, and we have to
suppress gluconeogenesis. Otherwise, glucose would go up to 400 or 500 after eating a carbohydrate
meal. So it has to be a process that's turned on, turned off. And that turned on too much,
you know, in terms of diabetes, because that's what drives fast and hyperglycemia.
Traditionally, pretty much the major textbooks, physiology, biochemistry,
insulin is thought to be turned off gluconeogenesis through transcriptional
mechanisms. And again, this is this FoxO phosphorylation by AKT exclusion from the nucleus.
Then you get downregulation of Pepsi cakes, excuse me, and 6-phosphatase. FoxO is the transcription
regulator for these downregulation. The problem with this view, and again, there's some beautiful
molecular biology, and I'm not going to want to deny that this doesn't happen, but the problem
with this being the predominant regulating mechanism is threefold. One is you can knock out
AKT or FoxO and give insulin to the mouse, and you can still turn off gluconeogenesis in a fasted
mouse, which is totally dependent on gluconeogenesis. That speaks to the fact you don't need
these key insulin signaling pathways to regulate gluconeogenesis. The second thing in terms of its
role in mediating fast in hyperglycemia and diabetes is we got liver from patients with
poorly controlled diabetes. So when patients go in for a Roux-en-Y or bariatric surgery,
the surgeon can take a little piece of liver under direct visualization, so it's very safe,
and give us enough liver to we can do actually protein measurement and enzyme measurements of
Pepsi-K 6-phosphatase, not just message, but actually the proteins themselves. And to my surprise,
I thought all these enzymes from everything I was thinking about biochemistry and at least what I
learned when I was a luxury medical student is I expected Pepsi-K and 6-phosphatase and
fructose 1,6-biphosphatase all to be upregulated two to threefold in the poorly controlled diabetic
that was undergoing ruined bypass surgery compared to the non-diabetic. And we found
no relationship between protein expression of these enzymes, gluconeogenic enzymes,
and at least fasting glucose and insulin and history of diabetes. Finally, when you develop
methods, the flux methods we won't get into to actually quantify this flux of gluconeogenesis,
which has not been easy to measure, by the way, but we have methods now, they're very good to
measure this flux, we can turn off gluconeogenesis within five minutes. And that's much faster than
you'd expect in transcriptional translational mechanisms. Just to kind of talk about how
gluconeogenesis, this is the gluconeogenic pathway lactate to glucose, you can have transcriptional
regulation, you can have substrate regulation. So glycerol we've shown from lipolysis, there is
no rate control. The more glycerol that comes from fat breakdown in the fat cell that fluxes
the liver comes right out of glucose. There's no rate control, it's just all substrate driven.
Redox we've shown in the liver cell regulates gluconeogenesis. And this in a series of studies
that Anilla has done, that's how I think metformin works. And we can talk about that if you're
interested. But finally, I want to emphasize is this allosteric regulation of gluconeogenesis
by Acetyl-CoA. This had been known for decades to be a regulator of pyrovacinoxalase and had kind
of been forgotten because it was very hard to measure and no one looked at it in vivo, because
it's hard to measure in vivo or especially in the diabetic situation. We said, well, wait a minute,
let's go back and look at Acetyl-CoA. We developed the methods tandem mass spec methods, very
sensitive, very specific. To do this and freeze clamp tissues from animals with varying degrees
of diabetes, hyperglycemia. The bottom line is found a very robust relationship between Acetyl-CoA,
which is, as you know, the end product of beta-oxidation. Take fatty acids and break them down
to beta-oxidation, the end product as before it enters the TCA cycle. And there's this very
robust relationship, just all these different studies. But basically every study we do,
we give insulin, we get suppression of Acetyl-CoA. This explains how insulin acutely
suppresses gluconeogenesis. When diabetic models, when you have increased gluconeogenesis,
it's two-fold increases in Acetyl-CoA, but it perfectly follows rates of gluconeogenesis,
which we quantify track perfectly with concentrations of tatic Acetyl-CoA content.
I just want to take you how insulin normally works in the liver cell,
and then how it becomes dysregulated in diabetes. And this is going to answer your question about
how do we distinguish insulin promoting storage as glycogen, yet keeping gluconeogenesis
going for the brain. So this is very important to answer that question. So in my view,
insulin binds the receptor and it has direct effects through the receptor. That is mostly
to promote glucose uptake and storage as glycogen. The effects on gluconeogenesis,
the process that keeps us going during starvation, is really mostly regulated, not through the
receptor in liver, but it's through its effect on the fat cell in the periphery. In studies we've
done in awake rats, and we're translating this to humans, it's really insulin putting the brake on
peripheral lipolysis, less fatty acid delivery to liver, less generation of Acetyl-CoA. And we've
shown this, the more fatty acids that flux the liver track almost perfectly with Acetyl-CoA content,
less pyruvic carboxylase activity. And again, there's about 10-15% of this gluconeogenesis
is simply coming from less glycerol from lipolysis to liver through substrate push.
So you have two very different processes here. One is glycogen synthesis. That's what the
receptor is doing in liver. Gluconeogenesis is mostly 90%, I would say, maybe a little bit of
intrapadic lipolysis regulation, but mostly through its effect to put the brake on peripheral
lipolysis. And this model, by the way, will explain in my view the explanation for all the
controversies of insulin action that have been described through the last decades in mice, where
you knock out AKT in the mouse, insulin still works. You do things to the periphery, fat cell,
and you affect glucose metabolism, gluconeogenesis. All these studies that appear to be conflicting
can be explained if you use this model as a template to understand insulin action.
And again, I have short-term fast and long-term fast. This is important species differentiation.
Mice, and as you pointed this out, Peter, even after an overnight fast, boom, all the glycogen's
gone. Very different from humans. Humans hold on to their glycogen like dogs, probably for two days.
We've done these measurements with starvation in humans. We've shown that it takes about two days
to deplete liver glycogen. When you have glycogen in liver, it's really these direct effects of
insulin on liver will predominate. But as you move to the fasting state, so in a mouse after a 12-hour
fast or longer, and in a human probably have to go 24 or longer fast, then it's really insulin,
these indirect effects will predominate. And this will also explain all the controversies in dogs,
Sherrington, Bergman in terms of direct, indirect. They've each published a dozen papers on going
back and forth, which predominates. This mechanism would explain, I believe, all of those findings.
And then I just want to now show you how I view the dysregulation and diabetes. So now,
typically on the background of obesity, which is what happens in most of our diabetics,
so you have lean individuals who also have this, you have expanded fat stores in the periphery,
but now you have insulin resistance in the fat. So insulin can't put the brake on like
polycystin. We can talk about that mechanism, which we're now working on, but it's going to be very
similar in terms of liver and muscle. But you also have this component of inflammation.
This has been described by many, many individuals. You get crown-like structures, macrophages,
move in, they release TNF alpha IL-6. And what we were able to discern, a lot of people would argue,
it was inflammation. If you go back to the insulin resistance literature 10, 20 years ago,
everyone was discussing inflammation, circulating cytokines, TNF alpha IL-6 resistant, RVP circulating
factors that were released from inflammation driving insulin resistance. What we found is,
again, you can dissociate inflammation from insulin resistance. That's what I spent the
first three decades of my life doing, showing that just ectopic lipid dags would drive insulin
resistance, independent of inflammation. But the transition from just insulin resistance
in liver and muscle to fasting hyperglycemia depends on inflammation. And it's through this
mechanism where now you have localized inflammation in the fat cell. TNF alpha IL-6,
I'm sure there's other things, will promote increased lipolysis in the fat cell.
More lipolysis, more fatty acid, delivery to liver, dags go up, epsilon gets activated. You block
insulin action, so you have less glucose being taken up into glycogen. This is what happens in
virtually most patients with fatty liver disease. But again, what takes you to fasting
hyperglycemia is this, and that's where acetyl-CoA goes up. And again, now your rates of lipolysis,
when you measure turnover, not just fatty acid concentrations, but turnover, palmitate,
turnover production and glycerol turnover, it's up twofold. This increases acetyl-CoA concentrations
twofold. This activates pyruvicovoxalase activity and flux twofold. And then in addition,
your glycerol delivery to liver is up twofold. And now your rates of gluconeogenesis are increased
twofold. And this is now what's driving fasting hyperglycemia in every poorly controlled type
two diabetes. It's this gluconeogenic process that we've shown using many, many methods,
and others have shown this too. This is what now is driving hyperglycemia in type two diabetics.
Okay. I have several questions, Jerry. First, these adipocytes that are undergoing lipolysis,
these are peripheral adipocytes, is that correct?
Yes. You can have situations where even fat in the liver is probably contributing to this,
especially in the lipodistrophic individual, it has no peripheral fat cells. So under conditions,
the liver fat is playing a role, but most of it in most of, you know, I would say garden
bright when I see it, it's going to be peripheral lipolysis.
So when we think about an insulin resistant, obese person with metabolic syndrome, so this is
what, 20% of the US population, maybe even more. We've clearly established they are insulin resistant
in the muscle. We've established that they are insulin resistant in the hepatocyte.
They are obese. So would we still say they are insulin resistant at the fat cell or would we
say they are insulin sensitive at the fat cell because they are correctly undergoing
lipogenesis in the fat cell? They're at least taking up a esterified fat and they're presumably
impairing lipolysis, which is why they retain adipose cell mass. In other words, there's a,
the flux through the fat cell is negative. They're holding onto fat, correct?
Yeah. But I think, and this is a question, a very important question we're going to next.
I would still predict if you do careful studies of measuring rates of lipolysis,
by definition, they will have insulin resistance in the fat cell. And that's because the reason
they're doing everything you just said, they're holding onto fat, they're not happy about it,
the doctor's not happy about it, is because it's at hyperinsulinemia. So their insulin
concentrations are two to three fold. So again, their curve is right shifted. Insulin is doing
the thing, but if you brought them down to normal levels of insulin, then you might see more lipolysis,
not a thing. So I think if you were to do those studies and they've been done, there is peripheral
insulin resistance, but then you superimpose in addition, and I'll just say, I'll share with your
listeners, we're finding actually the same mechanism that we have in liver and muscle.
And we're seeing this in many other tissues too, in the fat cell, the diacylglycerol epsilon pathway
is also accounting for this defect in insulin action in the fat cell. So it's going to actually
be a common mediator. And again, most of the fat, of course, in the fat cells in the lipid droplet.
So again, the plasma membrane, diacylglycerols that lead to epsilon activation in the membrane
of the fat cells. And we're seeing the same thing. And we see those same mice that I showed you before,
the IRC nockemites are protected from lipid induced fat insulin resistance.
On the fat topic, we've talked a lot about the intra myocellular lipid. You've distinguished
it from say, marbling or fat between cells. One thing we haven't spoken about that clinically gets
a lot of attention is visceral fat. So you alluded to doing an MRI. So we do a T1 weighted image of
a person in an MRI gives us a beautiful resolution anatomically of what's happening.
And you can see the difference between a healthy person and an unhealthy person. And one of the
most glaring differences between people on that type of proton imaging is the amount of fat
that is inside the fascia. So you have subcutaneous fat that may not be aesthetically pleasing.
But more importantly, when you go inside the corset of fascia, you have some people that will
have a heavy ring of fat around their kidneys, their spleen, their liver. We call this visceral
fat and the association between this amount of visceral fat and poor health is very well
understood. Whereas there seems to be very little association between subcutaneous fat
and poor health. How does that visceral fat identification square with the intra lipid
myocellular component that you've described so elegantly at a cellular level?
In my view, and everything you said is correct, subq, if you're going to store fat somewhere,
that's the best place to store it. You certainly don't want to keep it inside
liver and muscle cells. In my view, and again, studies have been done to look at the visceral
fat and it's very clear. It is again, a very apple shaped people have visceral fats, a very
good predictor of insulin resistance. It's really more of a marker for intrapatic fat. So anytime
when you're doing your imaging, if you just look at the liver too, they're going to correlate
one to one 99 out of a hundred times. So what you're really doing there is a marker. Now it's
the visceral fat will also pour fatty acids into the portal vein, presumably. And again,
fatty acids, liver portal veins, probably going to lead to increase the acetyl CoA. Again, we'll
contribute some degree to me. The major abnormality is really the fat inside the path. More poorly,
the acetyl CoA within the hepatocyte. I want to give one example that makes this point clearly,
at least to me, the lesson I learned and that's lipodystrophy. And as you know,
that's a situation where there is no fat, no subq fat or visceral fat. These patients
have no visceral fat, huge livers, hepatomegaly, chock full of fat and liver. And again, diabetes
through these mechanisms, acetyl CoA driving gluconeogenesis. And that's independent of this
real fat. So that shows you, you don't need the visceral fat at all to drive this. It's fat in
the hepatocyte. If I depict two molecules that are driving metabolic disease, it's acetyl CoA
driving pervert cobalys. And again, the diisoblisterols activating Epsilon. And again,
it's the Epsilon that drives insulin resistance, no diabetes, no hyperglycemia. Then it's this
accelerated gluconeogenesis through this mechanism that's taking you from just pure insulin resistance
to fastened hyperglycemia and diabetes. So let's again pause there for a moment and unpack
something very profound. If we've just established that the accumulation of liver fat is effectively
the hallmark of death to come. And you just said, acetyl CoA and DAGs are two of the biggest
culprits. Well, acetyl CoA of course, is abundance of nutrient on some level, which speaks to
something you said earlier, you take a patient with type two diabetes, put them on 1200 calories
a day. By definition, that has to lower acetyl CoA that immediately is going to improve things,
which it does, whether that's sustainable indefinitely, we can discuss. And of course,
we've already established where these DAGs are coming from. Again, I want to pause for a moment
on that, because I think a listener of this right now is going to say, guys, you've lost me, okay,
they don't know the difference between Pepsi K, GSK, three, AKT to PI three kinase. I don't think
you have to know those things. I think what you have to understand is that abundance of nutrient
is a relative term. It's not an absolute term. An athlete versus a sedentary person has a very
different amount of what that abundance looks like. I think we've also discussed that not all
nutrients are created equal. You've alluded to it already that sucrose and fructose disproportionately
prime the liver for this. And then of course, we're dealing with carbohydrate metabolism.
This is perhaps an interesting time to also start talking about both the modifications that we can
make. Because again, when we start to think about, you've talked about Western diet and sedentary
behavior a lot. So there's no doubt that there is an our environmental triggers contributing to these
epidemics, which largely began here in the United States, but we have fabulously spread to the West
of the world. And then of course, there's a whole pharmacologic side of this, I would like to revisit
the metformin question. I think it's a very interesting question. Metformin works presumably
by sort of weakly poisoning the mitochondria at complex one that would lead to a redox change
of NAD and NADH, which goes back to something you talked about. But as of this time, at least we
don't really have many exciting compounds in the pipeline for naphyl D, which as you also alluded
to in about 10 years is going to through NASH and cirrhosis be the leading indication for liver
transplant in the United States. Something that when I was in medical school accounted for less
than 2% of liver transplants just 20 years ago in 30 years, admittedly with the advent of a cure
for hep C, it's now leapfrogged into the lead candidate for liver transplant. And yet what are
we doing for it? Not a lot. That's a lot I want to unpack. And as much as you still have time to
discuss it, let's proceed in any order you see fit. To add on to that, I just did a Zoom conference for
University of Pittsburgh and they're a big liver center. And one of their big problems with
transplanting livers is living donors. They're limited by donors because they all have fatty
liver, which they will not transplant because they don't do well. So not only is it the problem in
treating it in terms of at least this most commonly, that's the most common thing that they do, but
that's an aside. So what can we do about this? If we can get our patients to lose weight, this of
course is the best diet and exercise, of course is the best thing. And that's the first thing
I tell my patient. We really drill into them how we can really fix everything that's wrong with
them through this process. And unfortunately, as you know, and I know it just doesn't work in the
vast majority of our patients. So in terms of pharmacology, my view and here again, it's the
liver. If I had to pick one organ to target, it's the liver. As important as muscle insulin resistance
is at the very beginning, if we actually want to reverse the disease and make the biggest impact,
if I had to pick one or it's the liver, if you're going to target probably the easiest organ to
target. The way I think about the liver is in terms of thermodynamics. It's a thermodynamic
problem. It goes back to my physics training and it's really energy in and energy out. The whole
metabolic problem with the liver is this imbalance of energy. Too much energy in relative to the
ability of the hepatocyte, the liver to oxidize the energy and convert it to CO2 or export it.
The one thing the liver is also able to do is export energy as a form of the LDL triglyceride.
If it's energy, how do we fix it? Well, one way, again, we said diet and exercise limit energy in,
that works. And that we talked about, Kit Peterson did this 20 years ago and it's shown many,
many times. To get the patient to stay on this is challenging. Bariatric surgery works, again,
limiting energy in. We just saw a nice study in the New England Journal. There's no magic
to ruin why. It's simply if you pair of feet, individuals lose same amount of weight, same
effect. Everything the bariatric surgery is doing, at least ruin why, is really through
reducing through the weight loss. How can we do this pharmacologically? Well, GLP-1 agonists are
out there now. They're becoming very popular. Their major effect is energy intake. Our patients
eat less because they eat less, they lose weight, induces nausea, mild nausea. Some people get into
issues with vomiting, nausea, mommy have to cut back on the dose. But this is how the GLP-1 agonists,
I believe, are having its major effect is weight loss. And they are what they are. They do accomplish
reversal fatty liver to some degree. They don't normalize, but it does come down in the right
direction. Why do you think the GLP-1 agonists lead to reduced appetite? I just think through
working through a central mechanism, all these gut peptides lead to nausea, vomiting, glucagon,
will do its amount of statin, will do all these things. If you give them a high enough concentrations,
lead to some degree of nausea and vomiting. To me, it's part of the spectrum. And if you just get
it right, you just get people less interested in food and they eat less. Metformin, that's the one
agent we have that lowers gluconegist. I would just come back. It's not complex one. I want to
challenge you on that. We can talk about that. But to me, it's complex one inhibition happens
at millimolar concentrations, clinically not relevant. Our concentrations of metformin in
humans, metformin are about 50 micromolar, 40 to 50 micromolar, not millimolar, which is what inhibits
complex one. I think it's downstream. It does affect the mitochondria, does lead to the redox,
but it's not through the complex one. It's probably indirectly inhibiting mitochondrial
glycerophosphate, the hydrogenase. That's what leads to the redox. But we can come back to that
if you want. I'd love to. That's very interesting. To focus then on other mechanisms, so GLP1,
limit food intake, energy expenditure, SGLT2 inhibitors cause glucose loss in the urine,
400 calories a day loss. So they lose weight. Unfortunately, it seems to plateau after
several weeks and you get very mild reductions in liver fat. Unfortunately, not as much,
but maybe in combination with other things that might be certainly helping the right direction.
My favorite target is to promote mitochondrial inefficiency. And so one of the things we're
working on now is to mitochondria is where you burn the fat. That's the organelle that
burns the fat through oxidation. If you can promote, then the mitochondria be a little bit
less efficient so they have to burn more fat to generate the same amount of ATP. This we've shown
in various forms, preclinical models, mice rats with fatty liver and NASH liver fibrosis. It
reverses fatty liver through these mechanisms, reverses NASH, reverses the insulin resistance
through reductions in diaxis, acetyl-CoA, reverses diabetes and ZDF models. For the NASH world,
it reverses the inflammation and will reverse liver fibrosis. And so I'm very excited about
this because I think it can be done safely. More recently, we've done this in non-human primates
and showed safety and efficacy of this approach in non-human primates. So based on the mechanisms
I've described, I think it fits. And not only what I'm very gratified by is it actually reinforces
the mechanisms I've described here by reversing diabetes, insulin resistance by Lauren Daggs and
acetyl-CoA, but it's also going to be heart healthy. And I want to emphasize this point because
many drugs we have now for naphthal and NASH reduce liver fat, maybe reverse the fibrosis or
slow down the fibrosis, but they may lead to alterations of cholesterol in the wrong
direction. Cholesterol goes up. And again, I have to come back to a nice point you made is
it's heart disease that is killing not only our diabetic, but also fatty liver patients.
It's the heart disease. So whatever we're doing to reverse fixed naphthal, NASH, liver fibrosis,
it has to be heart healthy. And so when you burn fat in liver through this mechanism,
you decrease VLDL export, you lower triglycerides, you raise HDL, and you actually have secondary
beneficial effects on the periphery. So you actually will secondarily improve muscle fat,
reduce muscle fat, muscle insulin resistance. So this again fits into my conceptual view of insulin
resistance and would be I think a nice therapeutic approach that we're going after.
Now does the uncoupling lead to excess Ross creation or anything else? Anytime I hear of
uncoupling in the mitochondria, which is a deliberately induced form of inefficiency,
you wonder, is this an unintended consequence potentially?
So uncoupling by definition, the biophysics of uncoupling, the energy has to go somewhere.
It's dissipated as heat. You're burning more fat, changes in the energy is going to lead to a
little bit of heat production. You will get energy production in the form of heat,
but because it's liver targeted has no effect on body temperature, will not affect whole body
weight. It's interesting, I can just tell the story of uncouplers. Your listeners might be
interested in this. So they were first discovered actually in the early 1900s in the munitions
factories. Europe was getting ready. They knew a world war was coming. The munition factories
were all getting geared up. Some of the workers in the munition factories were getting this dust,
yellow dust on their hands and actually losing weight. They were just going home and despite
eating the usual amount, they're finding their weight was going down and maybe they were sweating
a little bit more, a little diaphoresis. And they went to their doctors and told them about the
weight loss despite eating the same and it's a little bit more diaphoresis, more sweating.
And the doctors just said, what is this yellow dust on your skin? And why don't you just wear
gloves, wash your hands and wear gloves? And they got better. This was dinitrophenol. This was a
substance that was used in the munition factories to make TNT. So dinitro TNT. A physician,
tainter in the 1930s basically said, maybe this is good for weight loss. Actually introduced
dinitrophenol as a weight loss drug. It was available over the counter. It wasn't a prescription.
So anyone could go like buying vitamins, get some BNP for weight loss. It actually worked.
So a lot of people, hundreds of thousands of people took dinitrophenol for weight loss.
And it worked. The paper is published in very good journals. JAMA by tainter and others really
describe its beneficial effects. Unfortunately, and a very big unfortunately is again, one of the
on-target effects we just talked about when you uncouple, you promote heat generation. And this
is in the whole body. DNP is going everywhere and promoting heat generation. Unfortunately,
a handful of these people took too much. They got into problems with hypothermia, increased body
temperature and got very sick from that. And some died with the very first thing, a newly created
FDA 1937. The first act they did was actually to pull DNP from the counters as an over the counter
kind of drug or medication. And the second act they had actually was thalidomide, which they
pulled and now is actually back in the clinic. That was always the problem with DNP. Why again,
we say this is not a good thing. This is a toxic drug and everything else. And as it is, it occurred
to us that the reason it's generating the heat is you're on coupling all the organs in the body.
And what if we just picked one organ, i.e. the liver where the fat is accumulating. This is where
the organ that's driving lipidemia, hyperlipidemia and diabetes. And if we could just melt the fat
away within a liver specific manner, maybe we can have that beneficial effect without the toxicity
and so in a series of studies, we were able to show proof of concept that by simply uncoupling
the liver, you could avoid hyperthermia and all the toxicities that have typically been associated
with the parent compound, DNP, and increase the therapeutic window. Every drug has a therapeutic
window, even aspirin and Tylenol by a hundred fold. Based on this thinking, I think it can be
done very safely and be a treatment for very important metabolic diseases like naphthal and
nash. So the IND has already been filed for this. Is it in phase one human yet? No, no, we're still
exploring preclinical models, thinking potentially about first starting out where there are no
indications for things like lipodystrophy where leptin is not working. So I think my thinking is
I like to go slowly here, hopefully within the next year or two, we may be in humans. I think
initially going after orphan diseases where there simply is no other treatment and that would be
certain forms of lipodystrophy where they get very bad diabetes, naphthal, nash, and especially in
conditions where leptin is not working. Jerry, this has been obviously, as I said, a pretty
technical discussion even by the standards of our podcast. I think the show notes are going to be
integral because your figures, I think frankly, are very helpful. As I said, I understand this
content probably better than most and yet I still find it very helpful to be able to kind of go
through schematics. So I'm going to encourage the listeners to do that. You also have some fantastic
lectures online. I think for the people who really want to go deep into this stuff, I think frankly,
some of your review articles and some of your recent publications are just a great place to go.
As I said at the outset, I just think that this is the nexus from which all diseases stand and
therefore we are really making a mistake if we want to treat chronic diseases in their silos and
just think about atherosclerosis and just think about cancer and just think about Alzheimer's
disease without understanding how these diseases are fed. And unfortunately, that means rolling up
our sleeves and understanding insulin resistance. There's simply no getting around this. If this
topic were easy, you would have presented it in an easier manner. It's not easy. If I were to just
kind of leave you with sort of, we've talked about exercise, we've talked about nutrition,
do you feel strongly about any form of dietary thinking? So for example, I have found clinically
that carbohydrate restriction is a very effective way for patients with insulin resistance to lose
weight, not uniformly, but it's quite effective. It also seems to be easier to adhere to than outright
caloric restriction, though periodic fasting also seems to do a good job. But have you observed
anything similarly from a clinical perspective that fructose restriction specifically or sugar
restriction specifically as a vehicle to weight loss becomes a more effective tool to ultimately
produce what's understood to be efficacious, just some reduction of weight, either as the cause or
effect of the improvement? My thinking here is what I tell my patients is whatever works to everyone
that's so different, different likes, different dislikes. I say look at the scale, whatever works
for you to lose weight, because I know if you lose the weight, your diabetes is going to get better.
So I say you find something, whatever works for you, stick with it. That's the challenge because
we're very successful in the short term getting patients to lose weight. The unfortunate part is
they're able to get the weight off and then three months later, six months later, they come back to
the office and they're right back where they started. So it's a matter of I tell them you have
to find something that works for you, get the weight off, but then you have to be able to stick to it.
And that's where the challenge, a lot of diets, people are able to get on and get the weight off
and they just can't adhere to it for the long term. And so it's a marathon. You have to find something
you like, like it enough to be able to stick with that. That's the most important thing because
we've all seen that where people lose the weight and then a few weeks, months later,
right back to where they started. So everyone has to find what works for them.
I guess I want to come back to the metformin thing because it's so interesting. So you mentioned that
the inhibition of complex one actually is probably not taking place because you actually mentioned
basically a thousand fold difference in concentration. Say a little bit more about that and
why you're then imputing that it's the impact of metformin presumably on NAD and NADH, which
you could also get out of an inhibition of complex one, but via some other mechanism, it sounds like.
Studies that we've done and we're still working on this, clearly most the literature, if you read
on metformin, let's talk about the big picture. So metformin lowers glucose in patients with poorly
controlled diabetes, mostly through inhibition of gluconeogenesis. I think most clinical
physiologists would agree with that. And so we've done studies quantifying gluconeogenesis, both by
NMR, heavy water, multiple methods, same individuals. And that's its major effect,
not through inhibition of glycogenolysis, not through gut biome, its gluconeogenesis.
And the other thing clinically is the more poorly controlled diabetes, the greater the effect. You're
not going to see much effect. There's very confusing studies that have been published in
non-diabetic individuals that find all kinds of other things going on. I don't think that's
clinically relevant. It's gluconeogenesis. So then how does it do gluconeogenesis? So
most the literature, if you read it, virtually all the animals that study mechanism have implicated
complex one. And we've known about guanide inhibition. Metformin is a guanide by guanide,
even before metformin, we had fenformin and other guanides that have been studied. And they will
inhibit complex one, no doubt about it. So, and most have focused on complex one inhibition,
leading to either AMPK activation or buildup of a metabolite that inhibits gluconeogenesis,
or something 99% of the mechanisms have talked about complex one inhibition.
My issue with that is again, not very many studies have done careful measurements of this
most commonly used drug on the planet. For your readership, guanides have been used for diabetes
for hundreds of years. The French lilac extracts have been used 300 years ago, been description.
They didn't know what diabetes was at that time. It wasn't defined, but patients with polyuria,
polydipsia were overweight, treated with the extract, the French lilac, and their symptoms
improved. Most studies, if you look at, were used at millimolar concentrations. And again,
when they look at complex one inhibition, which has been implicated to then lower ATP, raise ADP,
and activate AMPK, it requires millimolar concentrations. And so when you actually measure
metformin in the patient who's taking one gram twice a day, which is your maximal dose, when
pretty much the best efficacious dose, your levels in plasma are about 30 to 50 micromolar.
So you could say even, you know, in portal vein, its pills are taken orally,
give it two to three times that you're still talking about maybe a hundred micromolar,
10 fold less than what all of these studies have been doing, even both the in vitro studies and the
literature and well, the in vivo studies, giving levels that achieve millimolar concentrations.
So yes, you see things, complex one's an important, it's an electron transporter,
it's important for function and health. And you're going to see effects when you inhibit complex one
at those high concentrations. In my view, they're not clinically relevant. So the effects that I do
think are clinically relevant that we have observed at 50 and a hundred micromolar of metformin
are really on the enzyme glycerol three phosphate dehydrogenase, the mitochondrial isiform
that is required to move the protons from outside to inside the mitochondria. And when you inhibit
this enzyme, NADH goes up, NAD goes down. When you have this increase in the cytosolic redox,
you can't get lactate to pyruvate and you can't get glycerol to DHAP. So if I'm right,
it's going to be substrate dependent inhibition of gluconeogenesis. Whereas if you inhibit complex
one and AMPK or whatever mechanism downstream, it should be gluconeogenesis independent of
substrate. And what we've shown both in vitro and in vivo, most importantly in vivo in two or three
different models metformin at these clinically relevant doses and concentrations only inhibit
gluconeogenesis from glycerol and lactate. It doesn't inhibit it from alanine or DHAP
or anything that does not depend on the cytosolic redox state. This also explains why we rarely see
clinically hypoglycemia on patients treated with metformin because there's these alternative
gluconeogenic substrates that can come in alanine can keep coming out. So you never see rarely,
unless they have another agent on top of metformin like insulin or SU, you rarely see it if ever.
And that's why also you see the lactic acidosis, which is a fortunate toxicity of metformin where
again, it's specifically getting that lactate to pyruvate conversion, which is dependent on
the redox state. So that's the mechanism I believe is clinically relevant. And now the last step is
how is it inhibiting this enzyme? And I believe it's actually through an indirect effect on this
enzyme that we'll hopefully have ready for prime time in the year. And do you think that in a
healthy individual who's eating well, is abnormal weight, is insulin sensitive and is exercising
robustly, metformin could actually be counteractive to benefit? That's a profound question. I don't
know the answer to that. And it gets into, I don't know if you're going to take me there in terms of
the use of metformin for aging. Healthy people are taking it for aging now. I think that's why
it's so important to understand this mechanism, then understand the implications of it. It is
redox. Is that a good thing or not for longevity and health? That's a question that remains to be
answered. I find myself very much on the fence with that question while in the insulin resistant
patient, even without diabetes, feeling that this is a very net positive agent. But my personal views
on it just based on clinical observation is that in the person I described earlier, the lean insulin
sensitive, vigorously exercising individual, it may actually not provide benefit. But again,
there are studies in the works that are going to hopefully be able to provide some fidelity to
understanding that. It sounds like you're equally kind of undecided on that as well.
Yes.
Well, Jerry, I can't thank you enough. Again, I say this to many people I interview, but I really
mean it here. It's not just for this discussion and the time you put into it, but obviously much
more importantly for the career and for this incredible body of work that you've amassed
through your pursuit and obviously remarkable collaborations with so many people. I've enjoyed
this discussion immensely. It's actually one of the discussions I'm going to have to probably go
back and listen to again. So I hope that a listener isn't hearing this and isn't discouraged by the
fact that you're at this point in the discussion and you're thinking, oh my God, I might have only
retained half of that. That's okay. I'm going to be listening to this one and I just finished
listening to it now and I'm going to listen to it again. So thank you very much, Jerry, for that.
Thank you, Peter. It's been a pleasure.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.