Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Robert Abbott. Robert is a documentary filmmaker. He's
a director, an amazing storyteller. He's a six time Emmy award winning producer and a director
with over 30 years of experience in sports and entertainment for that matter. He's the co-creator
of E60 on ESPN. He's also the director of the ESPN 30 for 30 documentary, The Last Days of Night,
looking at the untold story behind the scenes, story of Bobby Knight and the events that
ultimately led to his termination from Indiana University. I wanted to talk to Robert for reasons
I will explain in this podcast because you may be wondering what the heck does this have to do
with longevity or anything that has to do with living better. And the short answer is I can't
really explain that in a sentence or two, but it becomes very clear throughout this episode why I
wanted to talk with Robert, who I would consider to be one of the experts now on sort of Bobby
Knight. We talk about a lot of things here, but most of it really is about the investigative work
that went into The Last Days of Night. And of course, some of the things that Robert learned
along the way and basically the 15 years of his career prior to that and why I think that prepared
him to be the right person to do this. There's one note I want to make before we jump into this,
which is there is a lot of profanity in this. That's just the nature of what this episode is
about. So it's a little graphic at times and there is quite a bit of profanity. So I just want
folks to be aware of that. If that upsets them in any way, shape or form, I apologize. And without
further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Robert Mavitt. Hey Robert, it's awesome to sit
down with you today. You're one of the few people that I just sort of randomly reached out to who
actually responded to me. So I was super excited that day when I sent you a direct message on
Twitter and then next day you said, yeah, let's chat. And I really appreciate it because I know
responding to random strangers is always buyer beware. I'm really excited to do this because
once you reached out to me, I listened to some of your podcasts and I said I'd love to do it. So
I'm ready to go. We're going to talk a lot today about a guy named Bobby Knight, who I suspect
most people listening to this know a little bit about or maybe even know a lot about. And I
suspect some of these people will have even seen the unbelievable documentary that you
produced with ESPN the last days of night, which we'll get to in significant detail. But I think
to understand the work that you did there, maybe people need a bit more of an understanding of who
you are as a journalist and some of the other things that you have done. So I'll start with
perhaps the most pedestrian of questions, but what drew you to journalism? Growing up, I was always
a fan of sports and I watched a lot of TV. So I think it was natural that I got into sports
television. I went to Florida State University. I was, to be honest, in my early life golf drove
my life. I was a competitive golfer. I played in the future Masters, Junior Orange Bowl, Tournament
of Champions, all the major tournaments for young people, her juniors. And I decided to walk on and
try to play for Florida State. So I went there for golf. That lasted about a year. It was just so
much work and I got redshirted, played in a couple tournaments. And once I gave it up, I got into
media performance or the communications department at Florida State University. And specifically media
communications was media performance. I wanted to be an on-air kind of sportscaster. And I took a
journalism class, ironically, at Florida A&M University. Florida State didn't offer it. And I
was just fascinated by it. It interested me. I never thought that's where my career would go. My
career started once I graduated. I had done an internship at CNN Sports. And I had done one at a
local TV station. So the day after I graduated, I started at the local TV station as a cameraman,
an editor, an on-air reporter. I was like the nighttime reporter. They would send me to city
commission meetings and a lot of things that bored me to death. And I would always be like, send me to
the high school football game, send me to the high school basketball game or the college game. So I
always wanted to gravitate to sports. I got laid off ironically from that first job. They canceled
the 11 o'clock news, got rid of three quarters of the staff. They decided to play MASH reruns instead
because they would get the same commercial dollars in for MASH. And they didn't have to fund a 30
person newsroom. So I went back to CNN. I started there as an associate producer, then a producer.
And I started to gravitate into becoming a storyteller. First and foremost, I love sports.
And the drama of sports and the stories of sports. But after I covered a number of World Series
Masters, you name the event, that became boring. And I don't want to say unfulfilling, but who wins
and loses is pretty simple. And I always wanted to go deeper. I always wanted to go deeper. So I
started doing profiles, becoming a feature producer, traveling around the country and spending time with
people. I just love the psychology of sports, what makes someone great, what they have to sacrifice
to give it up. And that's kind of what shaped my early career at CNN. Was there ever an experience
where you were deciding, okay, I'm going to do a profile on such and such an athlete, and you finally
get to meet them. And there's a letdown because of either just their personality and doesn't match
what you expected or the depth or introspection that you would be hoping is there isn't there.
I would say I've had that experience myself, not just with athletes, frankly, sometimes with people
in other professions where when you don't know them, you create a persona of them that's probably
unfair. You meet them and you're sort of like, that's arguably the most uninteresting person I've
ever met. Did you ever have that experience with athletes when you were doing this? Dozens of times,
countless times. Interestingly, I started at CNN, excuse me, sports in 1987. On around 91,
they wanted me to go up and head up the New York Bureau. That fell through at the last minute. And
my boss at the time, Jim Walton, called me in and said, hey, I'm sorry, it fell through. I really
wanted that to happen. Would you be interested in covering the Olympics? And I said, sure.
I grew up as a kid watching the Olympics, watching Olga Corbett and Adia Komenic, all of the
profiles. And I didn't realize this until I was much older, probably in my 40s, maybe even my 50s.
How much of an impact that had on me. Like I sat in front and I was fascinated by their human
stories, which Rune Arledge did, Dick Ebersol has since done. And when I got that job, exactly what
you said came true. It was my dream job. And I went and met a number of these Olympic athletes.
And I want to say more often than not, that may be a little unfair, but to become great,
many of them were one dimensional. And they weren't interesting to me. They were either
speed skaters, skated in a circle for six hours a day, went home rested and came back and skated
for two more hours, or weight lifters. I remember I did some pieces on some weight lifters and I'm
like, what do you do? What do you do for fun? And they wake up at six and they have their workout,
then they go and eat, then they rest, then they work out again. And doing those in the early years,
when I did a lot of profiles for the Olympics, I remember the people who fascinated me because
they were just different. And I realized that's what I'm drawn to. People have a story to tell.
The way I describe it is, I'm only interested in a story if it's an onion.
If you can just peel off layer after layer after layer after layer, and the more layers you can
peel off, the more interested that character is to me. I did a piece on a swimmer, Gary Hall Jr.
lived out in Phoenix, and he was just a free spirit. He had taken a VW bus and redone it.
And I found that fascinating. We shot it. It's very visual.
He would wear a boxing robe out in shadow box on the blocks.
He was just a character, and I loved him. And I loved the three, four days I spent with him.
And one day we were there and I said, well, what do you do? He goes, I skateboard a lot. And he's
like, hey, let's bust my little brother out of school. So we rode along with him as he walked
into the principal's office and said, hey, my brother has a doctor's appointment. I need to
get him out and need to get him out now. And he came and we were skateboarding and his little
brother was holding on to the bumper of his VW bus as we're rolling down the street. And guys
like Gary Hall Jr. fascinated me. And so I always gravitated to people like that. I did early on in
91, the winner of 91 for the 92 Winter Olympics. I went up and did, I spent some time with the
Jamaican bobsled team, hung out with them. It was just great because there were a bunch of
characters. Did a story on Prince Albert who drove for Monaco, their bobsled team, the Latvian
bobsled team, because the wall had just come down, communism had ended. And I didn't know this,
but most of the gold medal winning drivers for Russia were Latvian. So for the first time in
their life, they had pride. They're like, if we win a medal, it's for Latvian, not for the Soviet
Union. So when you peel away the layers, that's what interested me as a storyteller. I always
try to gravitate to stories like that. So let's say it's 91 and you're up and running on these
other things. By this point, bringing the story back to our main character, Bobby Knight,
he's already won three national championships, right? Bobby Knight at this point is probably
in his early fifties. He's coached the 84 Olympic men's team. So he's got a gold medal in three
national championships to his name, including that epic season. I forget which one it was,
maybe 77, 76 was the 75 when they went undefeated as well. 75 was they lost one and then 76, they
went undefeated. So how much were you paying attention to this guy, Bobby Knight back in the
early nineties? I was a sports fan as a kid in the 70s. So I don't remember the undefeated season,
but I do remember Isaiah Thomas winning the national title in 81. I do remember him coaching
the Olympic team in 84. I remember vividly reading John Feinstein's book, A Season on the Brink.
I just graduated college. I love to read books and I read a number of not just in sports. I read
everything on the Vietnam War. I could get my hands on across the board. And I remember grabbing
that book and devouring it in a few days. And I was fascinated by him. He would, in the book,
Feinstein painted a picture where Knight would ride somebody, I believe it was Darryl Thomas,
and call him a pussy and you have got no guts or whatever. And then Thomas would go back to his
locker and he'd open it and there'd be a box of tampons in there. And I was just like, whoa,
I couldn't believe what I was reading. And yet, as I thought about it at the time, and this is,
the book came out in 87. As I thought about it, the book ends, Feinstein ends with a line that says,
it always comes back to the question that ends justify the means. And I remember closing the
book and in my own mind saying, yes, he's won three national titles, an Olympic gold medal,
and I've never heard a player speak negatively about him. So when I closed that book, I said,
yes, the ends do justify the means. I had no idea that 13 years later, my boss would give me an
assignment that ultimately I would be asking that same question and presenting it kind of to the
country. You see, to me, that's probably one of the most interesting coincidences of this story,
right? Is that that book comes out, as you said, it's sort of 87, whatever you read it immediately.
And at that point in time, you see the part of the iceberg above the water, again, as you would
learn later, and we would all learn through your work, even in 87, there were plenty of indications
that there were players who had they been asked would have something different to say than maybe
what was presented. But I really love this thing that 13 years later, your world collides with this
guy in a way that you couldn't have imagined. And of course, in the intervening time, a lot would
happen. You would go on to cover the Atlanta Olympics, which in and of itself is kind of an
amazing story, not just because of the bombing, but all that went on there. So fast forward me
a little bit from call it 87 into the 90s. What else are you working on it? Perhaps more importantly,
how is it helping you prepare for what might turn into be one of the most difficult assignments of
your career? After reading that book and leaving the local station going back to CNN, covering a
lot of sports in the moment, and you name the event, I've covered it, and you have to turn stories
quickly, you know, a guy hits a home run in the bottom of the ninth, and within 30 minutes, you
have to have the story written and sent back to Atlanta and then to the world. As a journalist,
I learned to make decisions quickly, not always the right one, but you get a ton of at bats,
and you learn. I always, like I said earlier, gravitated toward telling the story of people,
and the psychology of people, and what makes them tick. I used to sit around, Nick Charles and I
traveled the world. He was the lead anchor in CNN sports. I remember vividly being at the
Cooperstown for the Baseball Hall of Fame and sitting on the back porch, and Nick loved his
wine, and he's having wine and cheese, and we're just talking, and we were knocking around names
of people we wanted to profile, and we talked about Bob Knight. We both wanted to go fishing
with him, wanted to hang out with him, just to see what made him tick and look inside, because
not knowing it at the time, but he was that onion to me that I knew if you peeled away layers that
he would be a fascinating character. Again, not knowing that in 1999, four, six, eight years later,
I would be asked to look into him. Prior to 1999, for the first handful of years I was at CNN,
I covered events, then I became a feature producer, the Olympic producer, and then I started getting
special projects. I did some documentaries for CNN. I did one on Title IX, which is about its,
you know, shoe leather reporting. They were getting rid of then-swim programs,
gymnastic programs to try to balance the scales of Title IX with football, so that was some long-form
storytelling where you spend a lot of time on a story. I also did one that I didn't know the
impact it would have until, actually, I did this film. I did a documentary called Field of Screens,
and it was about the first documentary was so successful for CNN, and we did it on such a small
budget that the documentary department for news wanted us to do more. The World Cup was coming to
the United States, and I was fascinated by soccer hooligans, and so I had pitched a story like,
is this going to be coming to America? I read the book Among the Thugs, if you've never read it,
it's a great read. It's a literary kind of editor who immersed himself among the soccer hooligans
in England and went into the psychology of how those riots start, and it was fascinating to me,
and that's what I wanted to do. But my bosses said, nah, it's not really going to translate to
an American audience, but the idea of fan violence in sports did. So my film became much more about
stalking, death threats. I went and we spent some time, Jim Hubert and I, with Mitch Williams,
who gave up the home run in game six to lose to the Toronto Blue Jays. He and his wife talked about
what it was like. This was the guy that played for the Phillies? Yes, he was the reliever,
wild thing, Mitch Williams. Yep, yep. A real character. Again, he peed all the way layers.
He was a character. He said what he would think, and to sit there and listen, we went out to a
ranch. He had a ranch out in Texas, and he and his wife were there explaining what those days were
like during the World Series. He had given up the home run. He was back at his home in New Jersey,
and he had gotten tons of death threats. His wife said, we lived in an old house and the floors
creaked. She said, I remember vividly him walking around with a gun in his hand, because the wind's
blowing outside and things are creaking and people have been outside the house. So I tried to take
people inside because we hear it. We hear somebody gets a death threat. It doesn't really sink in,
but to really have someone take you behind what that threat is and how it impacts them mentally
and emotionally was fascinating. The other thing I looked into is stalking. This was part of it.
It was kind of like why fans will riot after winning the World Series of the Super Bowl.
What will happen when a fan sends a death threat to an athlete? And the other one was stalking.
We looked at the Monica Seles stabbing. I ended up meeting two of the more fascinating people
I've ever interviewed. Dr. Park Dietz runs a threat assessment group in San Diego, and he's
the psychologist, psychiatrist, and I'm probably going to get his title wrong, who spent 40 hours
interviewing Jeffrey Dahmer so he could prove that what he did was sane, the thought process of what
he did so he couldn't use the insanity play. So just to talk to him over lunch was fascinating to
me. And the other one was Dr. Gavin De Becker. And at the time, he was the one that every star went
to if they got death threats or threatening mail. Madonna, Letterman, all the stars of that era.
And I followed the story of Katerina Witt, who was stalked for three years. So you ask me how
these things prepared me. This is, I spent nine months on this documentary. It wasn't
two days, three days, three weeks, three months. It was a long time. So these documentaries prepared
me in how to tell a story at an hour level, how to tell a story at a two hour level, all the different
places you could take kind of a narrative yard. So I had done those two documentaries at CNN.
Those two things probably prepared me the most for what the assignment I was going to get in 1999.
Now in the 90s, were there other examples that came to you that would ultimately serve as
basically reminders of this idea that the cost of excellence in sports, you know,
were there other examples of sports or athletes even that you covered where you could say, hey,
have we gone too far in society? Have we let this athlete or coach get away with things
simply on the basis of their greatness? And maybe we need to revisit that. I can think of a couple
of examples in retrospect, although I will admit at the time I was blind to it. Who came to your
mind? Who are the two that came to your mind? I think Mike Tyson comes to my mind. I grew up as
a huge boxing fan, like lived for boxing. Absolutely the single most important thing
in my life from the age of 13 onward. When you think about the Mike Tyson of the late 80s and
early 90s, I mean an incredible talent who was completely out of control. And in retrospect,
of course, now with the wisdom of being an old man, it's a very clear understanding of what a
traumatic childhood he had and how that childhood would produce a knife that is very sharp on two
sides. Right. On the one hand, it made him an unbelievably rage filled fighter and he built up
an armor to make sure he could never be hurt again. But without fixing any of the underlying
problems, he basically was going to be a nonstop hurting machine outside the ring as well.
That's certainly one example that comes to me. I think the other one, just sort of looking back
would probably be Tiger Woods. I don't follow golf that closely, but when you look at everything
that sort of unfolded in Tiger's life, call it 10 years ago, you get the sense that this guy who
was such a prodigy may not have had enough people around him that could say, Hey, let's revisit how
you're going to sort of live your life. And things probably just got out of control. But again,
when you're so dominant and you're winning and the money is there and the titles are there,
I think it's easy to overlook these things. So I guess I'm not saying these things to be critical
of the athletes. I'm saying them more as with a little bit of wisdom, I look back and go, huh,
that's interesting. And of course, Knight, I think will end up being arguably one of the most
extreme examples of that. Kind of goes back a little bit to the onion where people,
why do you like Andre Agassi, but not Pete Sampras, because people whose great moments and
worst moments aren't separated by that much are not as fascinating, but you get somebody like
Knight who in one area is brilliant and a genius. And he's exceptional at so many different things.
And he's so flawed and others. That's why people like Tiger, Tyson and Knight fascinated me. I
didn't spend any time around Mike Tyson. We had a group that did a lot of our boxing. Ironically,
I was going to go out for the Tyson Holofield fight, but when he got arrested and incarcerated
for rape, that fight never happened. That was going to be my first time out there. But when
he got out of prison, I did a show for ESPN of him returning to the ring. And I was fascinated by him.
And to this day I am. I have a curiosity, I think like you, into what the environment and the
situation that forms these people. There's things that, as you eloquently said, that it sharpens the
knife and it's on both sides, good and bad. And I always wonder with Mike, if he was surrounded by
better people, would his better character traits have come to the surface? I think you've seen
Mike in the last five to 10 years that he does have a sensitive side. He does have a caring side.
He's not a horrible monster, but there was years where he acted that way. When I did that
documentary, I spoke to the president of HUO Sports at the time. And after the interview ended,
he told some stories of Mike and his guys renting hotel rooms, suites in Philadelphia,
and just marching as many women through there as they could in a three-day span. Told you things
that the general public didn't know what was going on. And he was surrounded by people. I think the
challenge is when you're a cash cow for everyone, they're worried about you making money. They're
not really worried about you and the underlying things that you need to work on that you mentioned.
Because that doesn't make them money. They want to get as much money out of you as they can.
So they're going to let you do what you want until that gravy train of money runs dry. And I think
that's sadly what happened to Mike with Don King or Rory Holloway. I always felt that when you go
back to the beginning of Tyson's career, I mean, look, there's probably nobody who was able to
look at him purely as a person, including custom auto, who was really a father figure to him. But
there was a guy back involved in his life early on, Steve Lott. Most people probably wouldn't
recognize that name unless they're real aficionados of Tyson history back in the mid 80s. But I always
felt like Steve Lott was probably along with maybe even Teddy Atlas were kind of people that
could have kept Tyson on the straight and narrow. He was also managed by these two guys that were
ridiculously shrewd and created kind of a grotesque deal where they took a third of his purses, which
was legally permitted, but obviously by any stretch of the imaginations, completely disgusting. But one
of the two Tyson did have a fond affection for a guy named Jimmy Jacobs who died in early 88. The
other guy, Bill Catean, he had no relationship with. And I always felt that the end of Tyson
was actually the death of Jacobs because DeMato died in 85. He'd already by that point,
kicked Teddy Atlas out of the camp. Actually, DeMato did, which was a huge mistake. He'd canned
Steve Lott on the basis of Don King sort of brainwashing him and then Jimmy Jacobs dies. And then
this is all before the Sphinx fight. The Sphinx fight was really the last fight, in my opinion,
where he went in as a great fighter and everything thereafter was sort of downhill.
Let's turn to Bobby Knight. Let's talk about when this first became the lead thing for you. So is it
easier, I guess, maybe you could give people a little bit of the history of what's happening
tonight in the 90s and then how you're getting brought into it. He won his last national
championship in the late 80s. And in the 90s, he still had good teams, 20 win seasons,
but he started getting bounced in the first or second round of the tournament. And again,
other than being a sports fan, I was never assigned to cover him. I was never, but I followed it like
probably the rest of America. You kind of just kept waiting for him to get that player or get that
sign of class that would put him back on top. He had gone from 76 to 81 to 87. There's five to
six years in between each of those. So in the early 90s, you're like, oh, he's going to come back. And
he just wasn't. And other than just being a sports fan, he really wasn't on my radar. Then in 1999,
Luke Rector announces he's leaving Indiana. For those people who don't know, Luke Rector was the
leading scorer, got the most minutes. He was kind of the star of the team. What year was he in?
Sophomore? He was after his sophomore season, he did leave. That's when my boss, Steve Robinson,
I was at this point at CNN, I did the Olympics, I did special projects, and then wherever they needed
me, because I like variety, I get bored doing the same thing all the time. So, hey, you need somebody
to cover the World Series. I'll go. If you need me to do this, I'll go, hey, if somebody's going
on vacation, you need a line producer in the studio. They'd plug me in there for three weeks.
So I had variety. I had come back from a site survey in Sydney, Australia for the 2000 Olympics.
I went ahead a year in advance to set everything up for CNN. And I had just gotten back and my boss
said, oh, what do you want to do? We're just talking about it. I don't know, a day or two later,
Steve called me in the office and said, hey, Luke Rector just left Indiana. And we talked about it.
And he said, why don't you look in to why? He's the third McDonald's high school all American in
the last two and a half years to leave the program. And he's the most popular player there, getting the
most minutes. Normally, somebody who's unhappy leaves a program. Your leading scorer usually
doesn't leave. And I remember sitting in Steve's office, not being very excited at all about this
assignment. I was just like, it's going to be a waste of time. Steve and I talked about how we
thought it may be more of a story on AAU basketball, and how these athletes are coming out of high
school with inflated egos, big sense of themselves. And they can't play for a guy like Coach Knight
anymore. They have a sense of entitlement. So we thought the story may kind of focus on that.
The explosion of AAU basketball, how these guys are stars now at 16, 17 and 18. And they're not
willing to be coached in college anymore. I vividly remember walking out across the newsroom
of Steve's office back to my desk, just not being that excited, thinking it's going to be a waste of
time. And maybe for the listener, Robert, give people a bit of background on Bobby Knight's
coaching philosophy, starting at West Point, himself obviously winning a national title,
really being a guy that coaches a team, not a star, even though stars came out of the program.
What about his coaching style led you to the conclusion that, hey, a 16 year old high school
star might just be not willing to be coached under that system. What was your preconceived idea?
I thought what I think most people in America thought is these guys just aren't tough enough.
Coach Knight came out of Orville, Ohio. He went to Ohio State and he was a role player on their
national championship team with John Havillacek, Lucas, et cetera. And shortly after that, he went
on to army to coach by the age of 24. He was the head coach at army. And then from there,
he went on to Indiana and he very much took what he learned at army and applied it. The sense of,
I'm going to break you down to nothing and then build you back up into the person I want you to be.
So he was hard on players. It was team before I or me or you. It was very much about his system.
It was very much about unselfish basketball, playing defense, moving your feet. It was about
sharing the basketball. It was about there's no stars on my team. Other than Isaiah Thomas,
I mean, the 76 team had a lot of great players, but Isaiah Thomas was probably, I don't want to
offend anybody who went to IU, probably the only transcendent player that went there. Isaiah was a
little different, but the 87 team, again, they had Steve Alford, et cetera, but there was no
superstar talents. So Knight was all about team basketball and he was very hard. The portrait I
had of Knight in my head and the knowledge I had of him and the assignment, it just kind of added
up that these kids weren't tough enough. They're wimps. They're soft. They're pampered. They're
entitled and they couldn't take it. And that's kind of the message that was put out when they
left. Year and a half, two years earlier, Neil Reed had left and they said he wasn't tough enough.
And then Jason Collier had left and then there's whispers and rumors of why, et cetera. And then
it wasn't until Wrecker left that my boss said, wait a second, something's going on up there. And
Steve had a great sense. Steve Robinson had come from Sports Illustrated when CNN and Sports
Illustrated merged to create CNNSI, a sports network. And he had headed up their investigations
for the magazine. So he had a great sense for news. It wasn't me. I didn't think this was a story he
did. And he said, go look into it. And so that's the mindset I took into it. I knew who Knight was.
I knew how hard he was on players. And I just thought what I was going to find out is these
guys just didn't want to do it. And they wanted to go somewhere where a coach would just roll out
the basketballs, let him play, let him be the star, not play defense, maybe not even work as hard.
So I wasn't excited. I didn't think there was anything there. So when you show up, is Wrecker
already gone? Yes. Is Reed still playing at this point in time? And Reed went to where? Reed went
to Kentucky, if I recall, right? Reed went to, he was recruited by Kentucky, but he went to Southern
Miss. Okay. And Collier was already gone as well. He had gone to Georgia Tech to play for Bobby
Cremins. So Reed, when I called him, he had just finished at Southern Miss. Collier was playing at
Georgia Tech. And Wrecker was transferring at the time he was going to go to Arizona,
got in a horrible accident in Colorado. He decided to stay closer to home. So he enrolled at Iowa
after I started looking into it. So Steve called me into the office the morning after the announcement
that Wrecker left. Interestingly, Wrecker faxed in notice to Coach Knight at midnight,
sent a fax at midnight saying, I'm not returning. It happened to be when Coach
Knight was leaving for a trip for Cuba. And it was just like, that's a weird way to say I'm leaving.
That interested me a little bit. So the next morning, my boss says, Hey, do you see the news?
Luke Wrecker just left. Start making some phone calls, go up there and try to figure out what's
going on. Why are really good players leaving Indiana and Bob Knight's program? That was the
assignment. And what I've learned since then is all great investigative assignments start with
a really simple question. Why did somebody break into the Democratic National Headquarters?
That led to the resignation of Richard Nixon. It's a simple question. And my simple question was,
Steve said, go find out why good players are leaving Coach Knight's program. And it was as
simple as that. It wasn't an investigation. It's just a question. And we thought it would take us
down this society kind of a look at society entitlement. It was not an investigation at all
at the start. But it became an investigation with a couple of my first phone calls. I did a lot of
reading. Two days later, it was a Sunday night. I called and Neil Reed's dad picked up and he and I
talked. And he didn't hold anything back. Terry told me everything. And this was off the record
or on the record. It was off the record. Again, I was just trying to understand the story.
And then I called Neil that Sunday night. And Neil and I talked for about 90 minutes. And in the film,
for those people who haven't seen it, I saved everything. I can't tell you, I probably had a
dozen notebooks from the 18 months I reported this, where I took notes on people's phone calls and
everything. And I saved them all. They were in a box in my basement for 15 years. And when I did the
film, I went back and just opened the box, sat here in my office with three cameras on me, and
just went through every single thing I pulled out. It took like six or seven hours. And it just
refreshed my memory and it became the spine of the film. So Terry Reed spoke to me and then Neil
spoke to me. And what did Neil tell you on that first call? He told me why he went to Indiana.
He loved Indiana. His father was a basketball coach. His father, much like Coach Knight, was a
hard ass. His father admired, I think probably loved Coach Knight's style. And Terry was very
much a coach in the mold of Bob Knight. So much so that the family moved to Bloomington for Neil's
beginning of his high school years, freshman and sophomore. Then he moved back to Louisiana. Neil
became two-time state player of the year. He never made another visit. He knew he was always
going to go to Coach Knight. He wanted to play for Coach Knight. Neil was a tough-minded kid.
The tougher it was, the tougher he got. He wanted to go to Coach Knight, play for Coach Knight
because he wanted to go play for somebody who's going to push him and make him better.
And he told me, you could just tell the love he had for Indiana basketball and specifically Coach
Knight. And that's why he went there. And then we started talking about why he left. And he just
took me through his three seasons there. And he started painting a picture of what it was like
day after day after day after day. There was three things that stuck out to me that became the spine
of my reporting in 1999 and 2000 when I was at CNN. One was that at a practice one day,
they were running a drill. Larry Richardson was a big man. And Coach Knight had always taught Neil
the point guard, hey, talk to your team. Command their presence. Command their attention. You're
running it. And he always wanted him to talk to the players during the play. So they ran this play
where Neil threw a bounce pass into Larry Richardson. Larry made the layup. And Coach
was like, that's great, Larry. That's great, great. And then Coach Knight laid into Neil.
Why the hell didn't you call out his name? Why didn't you talk to him? Why didn't you
basically direct him to what to do? He gave all this praise to Larry and then just laid into Neil
in kind of an unrelenting fashion that was Coach Knight's style. And Neil said, I did. And Knight
was like, no, you didn't. Yes, I did. No, you didn't. Yes, I did. And then Neil made the mistake.
If you look at it as a mistake to say, Larry, did I? And Larry Richardson said, yes, you did.
And that embarrassed Coach Knight. And that's when Coach Knight, according to Neil at this time,
came at him and grabbed him by the throat. That story interested me because if it was true,
it's an assault. I kept talking to Neil about the aftermath and other things that had happened.
And he told me two other stories that jumped off the pages of my notes. One was
that one time he had kicked the president of the University Miles brand out of practice.
Anybody who's been around Indiana basketball knows that practices are closed.
You're not allowed in there and let's Coach Knight let you. There's a padlock and a chain
on the doors. No one's allowed in to see what he does. So one day the University president was
there, brought some people in on a tour and was kind of talking out loud to hit the group that he
was with. And Coach Knight said something to the effect of shut the F up. I don't come into your
office and talk while you're trying to work. Get the hell out of here. And Miles brand and the
people who were with got up and left. And looking back, I don't think Coach Knight like literally
got in his face and said it. I think he said it out loud for the whole gym to hear. He may have
not even been looking at Coach Brand, but the message was sent. At that point I was like,
holy shit, you've got the balls to throw the president out of practice. Like who's running
this school? And then the third story Neil told me is one time they were playing real poorly
and they were in the locker room and Coach Knight came out of a bathroom stall with his pants
around his ankles with toilet paper in his hand. And he had wiped himself and he showed the toilet
paper to the players and said, this is how you guys are playing. You're playing like shit. And
he brandished soiled toilet paper to the team. And those three stories, I mean, jumped off
A, my notes that night and jumped through the phone in the 90 minute call we had. So I had this
all on background off the record, not for attribution, but as I wrote in my note to my
boss, Steve, I said to him and I read it in the film, I go, I think he's going to tell me this
on the record one day. And so that first phone call that I made to Neil Reed, and when he picked
up the phone, all of a sudden it turned from a story in my mind about society entitlement of A,
you pass cabal players, are they willing to be coached? Is night too tough to an investigation?
Did these three things happen? Can I confirm that these three incidents took place?
So when you get off that phone call, what does your intuition tell you? Does your intuition say
this kid is making this up? He's a disgruntled former player. Or does your intuition say,
this is possibly right? The ends no longer justify the means. Which way are you leaning at this point?
50-50, because exactly what you said ran through my mind. I'm like, he's probably disgruntled. Is he
exaggerating? Did it really happen? But he described them in such detail that there was
a lot of validity to what he said. And again, part of what I've learned is if you're going to do a
good investigation, you can't get too excited and you can't get too down. Like you just have to be
even keel. And the one thing I'm proudest of is during this process, I just kept my nose to the
grindstone. I never really looked up. We can talk later. There's three times I kind of popped my
head up and saw what was happening. But the rest of the time when I got off that phone call,
exactly what you said was rushing through my mind. Is he a disgruntled player who's out to get coach
night? Or is there truth to this? And that was kind of my mantra. And as I say in the film,
I got on a plane the next day, I talked to my boss and I'm like, I got to fly to Indiana.
And I'm looking out the window and I was like, is he lying to me? Is this kid lying to me or not?
As I looked out the window, that's what I was thinking. And I was also thinking that if he's
not, there's a story here. That's when I got interested. After that first phone call with
Neil, I said, I have to figure out if he's telling me the truth. And if he is telling me the truth,
how do I turn this into a story where people are willing to sit on camera and talk about it?
So where do you go from there? Do you go to Collier? Do you go to Wrecker? How do you,
I assume they're going to be an easier place to start than any currently active player, right?
Basically what I did is I took a big step back and I said, I have to understand Indiana basketball.
The first person I interviewed is Gary Donner. He passed away just within the last two years.
And he's the first person I sat down with. And he started Hoosier Basketball Magazine. For those
people who don't follow high school and college basketball, it is the thing in the state of
Indiana. High school basketball is the heartbeat of that state. And he follows high school basketball.
Every season he puts out the definitive thing on high school basketball. So he knows all these
kids from seventh, eighth, ninth, tenth grade, all the way through high school. So when I spoke to
him, it was the first interview I did, he just told me what he knew about it. And what he said
that made my initial reporting and is also in the film is that Coach Knight is like Dr. Jekyll and
Mr. Hyde. That he could be the most charming, brilliant person in the world. And then when he
gets behind the closed doors, I told you his practices are closed. When he gets behind the
closed doors, he can lose it and he wants nobody to see that side of him. And what you said earlier,
you'd see the tip of the iceberg, but you never saw the whole iceberg underneath. So everything
he told me led me to believe that there may be truth to what Neil said. But again, as a journalist,
Gary Donner wasn't there. So he can't confirm any of those stories, but he painted a picture in an
environment. I think there may be some validity to what he said. The other thing that gave me a
sense that what Neil may have said is true is because Gary Donner told me, he said, I've known
these kids, many of the in-state kids, and even the out-of-state kids who come there, he follows
recruiting so that they talk to him. A lot of them had gone to the school and they'd see him at an
event or a high school game and they just talked to him. What's it like? What was your time like?
So they talked to him because his magazine doesn't print that, right? So he just told me story after
story after story. So that was the baseline. That first interview kind of was foundational for me,
that it gave me a sense of what it's like and why the administration is afraid of coach Knight.
It didn't confirm what Neil said, but he painted a picture of an atmosphere where what Neil told me
now I understood that it may have happened and it could have, that environment exists.
Now look, it wasn't like Bobby Knight hadn't said and done things up until the point that we're
talking about now that weren't already putting in a mental league beyond what you're hearing from
from Neil Reed, right? I mean in 1988 he made an absolutely ridiculous statement to Connie
Chung on air that, I mean to this day I still can't believe a human would say that, let alone
a guy would say that and still have a job. You remember the statement of course? Yes, ironically
Connie Chung was doing a special on stress and they picked coach Knight because he has a stressful
job or whatever. Somehow the topic of rape came up and coach Knight said something to the effect of
if rape is inevitable, lay back and enjoy it. And what he went on to say is hey, you can't control
it, the plane's down, you can't do anything about it. He would have been fired within 15 minutes in
2020 if that came out and probably in 2005 and probably in 1995, but in 1998 he was the most
powerful man in the state of Indiana. I was aware of that incident. I was aware of the chair throw
a number of years before during a game where he threw the chair across the court while someone
was at the foul line. I didn't know the impact of it and to be honest Peter, I didn't realize
how important that moment was until I did the film 18 years after my reporting. What I learned by
having 18 years of hindsight is that at that point Knight had won three national championships
an Olympic gold medal in 84. In 1987 in my reporting I had uncovered that the Bloomington
Faculty Council was so offended by the John Feinstein book that they wanted to look into
Knight's conduct and they put together kind of a bill of rights for athletes that said no coach
should verbally or mentally abuse their athletes and I uncovered this. This was in 1999 during my
reporting and I was like wow they knew about this in 1987 and I'm reporting on it in 1999.
The timeline is they were looking into kind of reprimanding Coach Knight,
reining him in, knowing he's out of control and what does Knight do? He wins the national
championship. Now they cannot put a saddle on. There's no way the horse is out of the barn and
it is so far down the road that there's no coming back. He was a legend. He was the most powerful
man in the state so when he said that with Connie Chung there was a huge outcry initially. The
president released a tempered statement that said something to the effect of Coach Knight's quote
does not reflect Indiana University. It was very middle of the road kind of. It didn't chastise him
or go after him and what Coach Knight did is he went and interviewed for a job at New Mexico
and as Alexander Wolf, Sports Illustrated basketball writer, he's written so many books on basketball,
one of the best minds in the sport. In my film he said it was a shot across the bow at the president.
Coach Knight was like really you're going to put out a statement about me? I'll go to New Mexico
and let's see what happens. All of a sudden the entire state is up in arms now attacking
the president. Not attacking Coach Knight for what he said but attacking the president like
you're going to drive away Bob Knight. He just won a national championship. Three national
championships and Olympic gold medal and so that shot across the bow gave Knight the power he needed
to survive up until 2000 if that makes sense. They knew about him in 87. They were trying to do
something. He won the national title. He makes a horrible statement to Connie Chung in 88 but he
survives all the way until 2000 and that's because he basically showed who was boss in the state.
The president of the university wasn't. Coach Knight was and a number of presidents changed
during his 29 years in Indiana but Coach Knight remained and that's why he was allowed to exist
through the late 80s and early 90s all the way up until 2000. Did his behavior publicly get worse
over time? I mean you go to YouTube and you can find no shortage of best moments in press
conferences and you could watch that and come away thinking there's not a press conference where
this guy is not unhinged but presumably those are just the highlights. So it was clear that he had
unbelievable disdain for the press when he didn't like their questions. I mean he was unbelievably
rude in a way that you just don't see it even amongst professional athletes. There were many
examples of him just telling a reporter to go fuck themselves. Like you're a fucking idiot. I
mean what the fuck shut the fuck up. That's a dumb fucking question right? Yeah yeah showing up to a
press conference with a bull whip telling everybody he's going to whip his players with it you know
as you said throwing chairs. Having an African-American player this was at the NCAA tournament.
I believe it was Calvert Cheney. He had a player bend over and he went and he's like you can't
touch me. I'm going to do what I want. To answer your question as media grew from the 70s to the 80s
to the 90s up until 2000 we had greater access to him. I don't think he fundamentally changed.
People have asked me this a lot. Was he the same person in 2000 as he was in the early 70s when he
went to Indiana? And I said fundamentally he was the same. What I think changed was he had success
at Army. He came to Indiana had immediate success took him to the Final Four in the second year won
a national title in 76 won two more in Olympic gold medal. So the ends justified the means
during that run from when he first got to Indiana up until 1987. But when he started getting
eliminated in the first or second round of the tournament and these incidents became more and
more public I personally believe he took it out on his players and said it can't be me. I won three
national titles Olympic gold medal. It has to be you. And if you put yourself in the position of
those players I don't know if what he did to Neil Reed's class was any different than what he did
to Kent Benson's class or Isaiah Thomas's class. But you'll put up with a lot of shit all year long
and if you win the national championship you forget about a lot of it and you're a hero forever.
But when you start losing in the first and second round of the tournament you're less willing to
put up with that. So did he change did he get worse. I think what I've come to understand is
in the early 70s and 80s right when he'd push you to your breaking point he'd throw his arm around
you walk out of practice say something to you for 15 seconds and it all went away and you're
willing to run through a wall for him. And next thing you know they're fitting you for a national
championship ring and you're like hey it was all worth it. But in the 90s instead of throwing his
arm around kids there's the tirade that was caught on audio in 91. He took it out on them
and anybody can google you know Bob Knight audio locker room. Yeah this is the one for the Purdue
game. But there's an interesting point about that Robert which is any player that was asked about
that doesn't remember it specifically because they basically say something to the effect of
that happened every day that just happens to be one that got recorded but that's what every single
day in the locker room was like. It's not like okay that was a really bad day and we were really
playing badly and he went a little too far but it stands out and I remembered it's like nobody
actually remembers that discussion. That's one of my questions to Richard Mandeville who played for
five years for Coach Knight. I said you've heard the audio on the internet and he immediately said
that's what I wish everybody who was watching this would understand that that's every day. And what
interests me because I recommend everybody who listens to this go listen to the audio and you
hear the F-bombs and the GDs and all the profanity but listen to how many times Coach Knight says I
or me. Here's a guy from his days at Army. It's about team. It's not about an individual. It's not
about I. It's not about me. And that's what everybody in the state of Indiana and that's what
I admired about him. That it was about teamwork. But in that you will not put me in that fucking
position again. I've had to sit around for a year with an eight and ten record. If you do that to me
again I will run you. It's I and me. I and me. I and me. I and me. And I think that's where Coach Knight
possibly changed in the 90s. He had been so successful that when he started not being successful
in his mind it was it can't be me. It's got to be my players. And then he wasn't throwing his arm
around him. He'd push him to the breaking point in the 70s and 80s and then reel him back in just
enough to push him again to reel him back in to win titles. But in the 90s he didn't do that. And
then come the tournament they were mentally and physically done. And they wanted no part of
winning. A number of players told me that in the 90s when the NCAA tournament would come probably
the greatest three weeks in sports for people who love basketball we didn't care if we lost.
Yeah we wanted to win but if we lost we knew we didn't have to go to practice the next day.
So the silver lining in losing was the season's over and I don't have to listen to that again.
And that's why you saw him lose often in the first and second round in my opinion.
You make a really important point here which is there's this view that Knight is this guy who
places the importance of the team at the highest level. But I think you hit the nail on the head.
I think this was really about his ego. And I think that whether that was something that changed
from the 80s into the 90s I can't speak to that of course perhaps nobody can. But I think a lot of
people who give off this aura of team first team first team first are really quite ego driven when
you really get underneath the surface. And that's a great example. There are times when I find myself
doing the same thing. There are times when I find myself being so ego focused, so focused on myself
that I sort of lose sight of what the purpose is with respect to others. And if you stay in that
state for a very long period of time it's a bad place to be. You're going to behave badly. And
the other point you make is that really he had lost all sense of checks and balances. There was
nobody in that guy's orbit that could offer any sense of sanity. Do you have any sense by the
way of what his private life was like? Because it's one thing for a group of 20-year-olds who
worship you to show up and take that type of abuse. But do we have any sense of what his personal
relationships were like with friends, with family? And was he able to sort of put some sort of
restraint in place with respect to his anger in that setting? Do you have any indication of that?
The only indication I have is he was divorced once previously. When I started doing, again,
after I spoke to Neil Reed, after I flew up to Indiana at first and did a basic kind of
round of interviews to get a sense in the lay of the land, literally I backed up all the way to
Army and started talking to people who knew him there, why he left there. It didn't point to
what my assignment was, was why did three players leave in the last two years, but I wanted to get
a sense of that. I wanted to understand him from head to toe. At one point I got a phone call and
was put in touch with a professor at the school who on background, he has since passed away so
I can share it, at the time he was on a hunting trip with Coach Knight in Argentina and he said,
I don't want to go public, but I just want to make you aware that I was there in a hunting lodge with
he and his son and Coach Knight got in a fight with his son. And I don't have my notes in front
of me. I don't know if he dislocated his shoulder and bloodied his nose, but it wasn't pleasant.
The professor told me, described it to a tee of what took place. At the time I had done my
reporting and CNN had done our initial report. It was a 16-minute piece alleging the three things
that Neil had told me. Coach Knight had grabbed him by the throat, he had kicked the president
out of practice and he had brandished soiled toilet paper. So it's front page news around the country.
Everybody's attacking CNN, me, Neil, Reed, anybody in the piece. And so I start getting phone calls
from people. I'm put in touch with this professor who said, hey, I don't want to go public, but I
want you to know what I know. And again, much like Neil, he told me everything. And I went to
my bosses and said, I got to fly to Argentina to find out if this is true. And we didn't have huge
budgets at CNN Sports at the time. We were getting attacked as if we were going after night.
So my bosses said, hey, just we can't go down there. We can't make it look like we're out to
get him. And I go, I'm not out to get him, but people are calling me. So I kind of went around
my bosses a little bit and called a stringer. A stringer is in the news businesses. We have
contacts at different places, countries, cities, towns around the world that aren't on our staff,
but if we hire them for the day, they'll do work for us. So I found out a stringer for CNN and I
called, I said, can you go over to this hunting lodge? And can you talk to this person? Here's
the phone number, this, this, this, and the stringer came back and said, he confirmed what happened.
He runs a very high end lodge. He doesn't want to bad mouth his very wealthy clients.
But he did confirm to me that he drove them to the hospital and said to coach night,
you're no longer welcome here. And that really, to me, you talked about the tip of the iceberg or
what we see, you asked me about his private life. And I'm like, that was evidence to me that he
couldn't control his temper in his private life. And I wanted to report it. I had two different
people who wouldn't go on the record or confirm it with me at the time. So I couldn't, as a
journalist, I can't report it because I can't definitively confirm it. So what did I do? I called
Christopher Simpson. Christopher Simpson was Miles Brand, right hand man. He was the vice president
of kind of media communications and he was the voice of Indiana University for Miles Brand.
So I'm like, well, at least I'll let him know that I know. So I start poking as a journalist,
poking and prodding and people. I'll never forget it was the day where they would ultimately announce
zero tolerance. And I may be getting ahead of the story, but I'm on the phone with them.
And I said to Christopher Simpson, I said, if coach night can't control his temper,
so much so that he would harm his own son, how can you as a representative of this university
ensure that if mothers and fathers around the country are going to send their sons to play for
him, that they're not going to be safe? And I was appalled at his answer. I was walking on the
sidewalk outside of the, who is the center in Indianapolis where they're going to have the press
conference. And I remember pacing up and down the sidewalk and he said, Robert, that has nothing to
do with his coaching. And I about jumped through the phone at him and I said, how can you not see
the connection and the correlation? They can't control his temper and we'll do that. It's one
of his sons. How can you ensure that kids who come here to play are going to be protected?
We went back and forth at that day, but that gave you a sense of where the university was in
trying to do damage control and protect them. So what ultimately gave you and the senior
leadership at CNN the confidence to publish the story and when was that? So 99, you start looking
at this, how long did it take and how much digging did you need to do before you were willing to write
this? And I don't want to give the story away, but there's a tape in here somewhere. And I can't
remember if the tape came before or after the publication of the piece. I'll back up to April
of 99 is when I get called into Steve's office. Luke record just left the third player in two and
a half years to be gone. Talked to Neil that Sunday night, several days later, fly up to Indiana. And
literally for the next nine months or more, I'm reporting it. And other than peripheral people,
no one's going on camera. No one wants to speak out against coach night. And as I said in the film,
I could hear and feel the fear in their voices as I spoke to them. And that's something that
fascinated me as a journalist. I'm like, why are they so afraid of this guy? Why will they tell me
everything on background or off the record or maybe on the record, but not for attribution,
which means you can use what they say, but not tie their name to it. That drove me. That actually
drove me for a long period of time. I said, there's something here and I have to be patient.
And I have to give Steve Robinson, my boss credit because I did a lot of different things during
this nine months, but he allowed me to pursue this story at my tempo because I knew if I called you,
Peter, and you told me a lot of things, and then I give you the full court press a week later,
trying to get you on camera, you're probably going to say no. I had to play and develop a
relationship with each individual and they're all different. So I had to kind of keep everybody on
the hook until I could start getting, I knew if I got one person on camera, I could probably get
the second. If I got two, I could get the third. And if I got three, I could get five. But who was
going to be the first? So I interviewed professor Murray Sperber. I interviewed other people in and
around campus. And I basically, to be honest, I had the story the first night I called Neil
Reed. Those three things became the backbone of the story. I just had to confirm it. So you asked
earlier at one point, early on, I called Luke Grecker would not speak with me. And even speak
with you on background. Nothing at all. No, no, no. And what about Collier? I spoke to Luke's mother
on background. And I spoke to others who told me that Luke wanted to quit after his freshman year.
And he and his mother went in to speak to Coach Knight about, hey, he doesn't want to play here
anymore. And Coach Knight basically said, I'll change, I'll change, I'll change. I understand,
I'll change. I don't want to lose him. And so Luke decided to stay and year two, nothing changed.
So at the end of year two, Luke wants out. So I had a sense of his story through other players,
through his mother. And then I call Collier. And I was based in Atlanta at CNN in downtown Atlanta,
at the CNN center for anyone who knows Atlanta, Georgia Tech's two miles away, three miles away.
So I get his number and I call him. And he, as I say in the film, he's like, no, no, not interested,
not interested, not interested. And as an investigative reporter, you just don't want
them to hang up. Because if I can keep them on the phone for two minutes, I can keep them on for five.
And you can't keep them on for 10 unless you can keep them on for three. So you just try to tread
water. And I was like, well, how about background? I'm right up the road. Let's grab a cup of coffee.
I'll take you out to dinner. I'll do it. Like I'm just trying anything to get him to say,
okay, I'll talk to you. And he was no, no, no, no, no. And I just I said, Jason, I'm not going to put
your name out there. I'm just trying to understand what it's like to play for Coach Knight. And he
goes, you know what it's like to play for Coach Knight. And I had heard this a number of times
before. And usually it would lead to an hour conversation. So I'm like, Oh, I've broken
through. And he goes, go rent full metal jacket. And then he hung up on me. And for those of you
haven't watched full metal jacket, it's about an army recruit, someone in the military, and they
have a drill sergeant that is just relentless on them. And the army recruit goes crazy, kills
himself kills the drill sergeant. And so I had seen the movie. But right after Luke said that I
was taken back as he hung up the phone. And I went, I think it was the blockbuster still existed back
then rented the movie, brought it home and watched it again, to try to understand what he was talking
about. And that was the extent of my conversation with Jason Collier, you want to know what it's
like to play for Coach Knight rent full metal jacket. So I did. I now knew that Jason wouldn't
speak with me. Luke wouldn't speak with me for now. So I started going through the roster that
year. And I started trying to track down Charlie Miller. He was Neil Reed's roommate at one time.
He was a guard kid out of Miami. And it took me forever to track him down. I called Miami, made a
number of phone calls down there. I heard he was playing in Sweden and Finland and started calling
teams over there. And all of a sudden, I can't even remember how I found out but I heard he was in
Chicago. And I tracked him down and he said, yeah, I'll talk to you. And that was a huge breakthrough
for me, because he went on camera. First, I don't know, 10, 15 minutes, the interview told me how
much he loved Coach Knight. He had the respect for Coach Knight. Coach Knight gave him an opportunity.
Other people didn't. He was just praising Coach Knight. And then I asked him about Neil Reed and
why he left. And he said, yes, he did put his hand around Neil's throat. I don't think he should have
do I think he choked him no. But I don't think he should have done it. So he confirmed that there
was physical contact and he did it on camera. And that was a huge breakthrough for me when I got
Charlie Miller on camera. And once I got Charlie, I was hoping pretty confident that the dominoes
would start to fall. That once, you know, I could go back to Neil and say, hey, Charlie Miller
confirmed what you said. So you're not going to be out there by yourself. And I had called Richard
Mandeville had mentioned earlier he had played for Knight for five years. And I had spoken back
and forth with him a number of times. And he said, No, I'm not interested, blah, blah, blah. And I
came back and I said, Hey, I spoke to Charlie Miller. I spoke to Neil Reed, would you now go
on camera? And then he sat on camera. And so did Neil Reed. So those are the three players that I
got to go on camera. You know, it's probably worth pausing for a moment, because I'm sure the listeners
sort of sitting here wondering, what is it about Bobby Knight? That's so interesting to me, right
on this podcast. I think the reason and I don't even know if I really explained this to you,
Robert, when I reached out to you, but I'm a perfectionist. And I've been that way as long as
I had any sort of conscious awareness of anything. I mean, my mother tells stories about me as a kid
doing things that my siblings didn't do as far as just being such a perfectionist. And also I've had
a terrible temper my entire life. Again, one of those things that I didn't know how to explain it,
especially because neither of my parents have a bad temper and neither of my siblings have a bad
temper. So it's always this sort of weird thing. Like if I'm five years old and I was building a
big Lego tower and it broke, I'd smash it into a million pieces. And I was just utterly pissed off
beyond words when I couldn't do something perfectly. My guess is there are probably a lot of people
listening to this who can relate to that because that phenotype can lead to some pretty good
accomplishments, right? You can become pretty good at sports. You can do really well in school.
You can do really well professionally, but it comes at a great cost. And I think now that I'm
older, I'm becoming more and more and more aware of that cost. So much so that in the past year,
one of the biggest kind of breakthroughs I've had in therapy, which was very difficult,
I consider it the single biggest step function I've ever experienced in my life,
was becoming aware enough of my inner sort of monologue, not dialogue, but monologue with myself.
And I was actually going through my journal because journaling is a pretty big part of what I
sort of do to kind of keep track of myself. I came across a sort of an entry from maybe
seven months ago where my therapist said something to the effect of, look, your lack of
self-compassion is really extreme. I want you to sort of personify that entity inside of your
brain that is constantly berating you. I want you to become more aware of it, and I want you to
actually give it an identity. And without hesitation, the identity was Bobby Knight,
and that assumed the name. So now in the journal, I could refer to Bobby Knight and what Bobby Knight
says to me. Luckily, I've been meditating for a number of years, and meditation gives you enough
of a pause or at least an awareness of the inner voice. So now I just had to listen for it.
And it was really shocking what it would say over some of the most trivial things. People who listen
to this podcast probably aware, like I love archery, I love race car driving, all these things,
even a mistake in one of those things, which are completely inconsequential, right? I'm not a
professional anything. Like I do these things as a pure hobby, but just what I would say to myself
when I make a mistake, it would never be, try again better, you know, do it better the next time.
It would be, you fucking idiot. You are so bad at this. How dare you practice this hard and still
be this shitty. I mean, what is wrong with you? Can you imagine being this bad at something and
caring as much as you do talk about it? And it was just this never ending insult. And so this
idea expanded into something of how like we're all made up of these different pieces of our
personality. You have sort of the child and you, you have this adaptive child, you have this entity
that's trying to become a functional adult. But unfortunately, what I realized was, hey, the
chairman of my board is Bobby Knight. And it's going to be really hard for me to make progress
in life when the chairman of the board inside of my head is Bobby Knight. And somehow seeing your
documentary is I think what allowed me to come up with this idea, you know, again, be able to
put a name and a face to it and a character so that I could literally picture Bobby Knight in
my head screaming at me every time I made mistakes. And that was step one. But then step two was
learning to offer an alternative explanation, which was basically my way of saying you're no
longer the chairman of the board. Thank you very much. In fact, you can leave the board room now.
Now you're still going to be knocking and you're going to be very loud for very long.
We're going to a place where you're not allowed to talk to me that way.
And eventually when you stop talking to me that way, I'm going to stop talking to others that way.
I'm going to stop talking to myself that way. Those are the things. So I throw that interjection in
because I want people to understand like where my fascination comes from with this, because I just
don't believe I'm alone in this. And while Bobby Knight may be one of the most extreme examples of
the outward manifestation of this, I suspect there are many people who can relate to that
inner critic that is brutal and this sort of lack of compassion we can have for ourselves.
Fascinating to me because there's a number of similarities and words that jumped out to me
that make what you just talked about so connected to Coach Knight. The similarities are you talked
about a Lego tower and you would explode. There were stories of Coach Knight, he read every book
in the library when he was a kid supposedly, and he'd play board games with his grandmother and
she'd let him win because if he didn't he'd throw a fit. And the first thing that came to my mind
is that story when you're telling me your story. So the similarities and the connective tissue and you
using him as a character and a name to define it, he's a perfectionist like you said. He has a
terrible temper. That's actually what's his greatest undoing, his temper. I to an extent have some of
those character traits so I could understand Coach Knight. My dad was great but he was a direct
communicator who would yell and it would be tough. I knew he loved me so it wasn't didn't go that deep
into me. I get frustrated quickly when things aren't perfect, when things don't work out well.
I can have a temper. I'm a perfectionist. I could understand Coach Knight at a level.
The one word that you use that jumped out to me a number of times was awareness.
The awareness you've come to realize is powerful and if you're not aware of it you can't help
yourself or help solve it. And when you said that I wrote down that a story came to mind. I
interviewed Dave Kindred. When I did my film I didn't want to interview Knight haters or people
who love Knight. I wanted to interview people who had known him for a long long time and knew
the good side and the bad side, the Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde and Dave Kindred, long-time journalist
at the Atlanta Constitution. I think USA Today, he's known him since the early 70s and he told me
a story where he attended a basketball game in the mid-70s, Indiana versus Kentucky. It was a
famous game where Coach Knight and Joe B. Hall kind of met at mid-court on the sidelines and Knight
kind of cuffed him on the back of the head. There was a photo of it. It was a big deal and Dave
Kindred kept asking Knight about it in the press conference and Knight would not answer it and got
angry and got frustrated. And so Kindred leaves the press conference and he goes to write his story.
So he goes back out onto the court where press row is and he's writing his story with a couple of
other writers and here comes Knight walking across the court. And Kindred looked at the other sports
writers and said this isn't going to go well. This looks like trouble. Not in a bad way but just
observationally. And he said Knight sat down with him and he said how do I get myself into
these situations? And he went on to tell how he and Coach Knight, he's like how does this keep
happening to me? Which led me to believe that Coach Knight had an awareness of his flaws as early as
the mid-70s. Unlike you, he didn't try to address them, maybe he tried to and just couldn't. But that
story I found fascinating. It didn't fit into my reporting because my reporting was on the teens in
the 90s why there's three guys left. But it was a story that never made the film, never made
everything but really told me a lot about Knight. That he very early on knew that there was something
in his nature and his character and that he had a temper and that he would keep putting himself in
situations that maybe after they were over he'd look back and go why the hell did I do that? But
he never got it under control and it ultimately led to his downfall 25 years later. But he was aware of it.
I interviewed an amazing therapist named Terry Reel for the podcast and we've spoken a lot about
this idea of the anesthetic that is anger. So anger is actually kind of an interesting emotion
because in the short run it is actually quite anesthetizing. It overcomes a lot of the inadequacy
that underpins it. Inside there's a hollowness, I think. There's a void that needs to be filled.
There's a grandiosity that stands in the place of a true inner strength. The anger kind of fills
that void and numbs that pain in the short run but it's immediately followed by quite a bit of shame.
If you're any reasonably sane human being, which is to say you do not have true psychopathology,
you have to feel shame after these outbursts. There's no way that Knight isn't screaming
at his players every single day and shoving toilet paper with shit in their face and leaving the
locker room thinking I'm a great guy. No, he's feeling ashamed of what he's doing and as a result
of that he's beating himself up more and it's creating this greater and greater vicious cycle
of needing greater grandiosity to overcome that shame which leads to more outbursts of anger.
That's a very difficult cycle to break and I don't say that to make an excuse for him in any way,
shape, or form or frankly to make excuses for me in times when I've found myself on those roller
coasters but I can just say from personal experience and from observational experience of
countless people it's hard to break that cycle without somebody else to help you do so. You
really need a person who can challenge you and push you or sometimes you need a devastating
crisis. I trained in surgery and I knew people that I trained with whose anger was so bad
that they got into real trouble basically became an existential crisis, a threat to their career.
If you don't get your anger under control it will threaten your career. So my guess is it's just a
combination of all of these things. In that sense he became a victim of his success. His success
kept him far enough away from crisis that there probably wasn't enough impetus to change until
it was too late. You're exactly right and for people who didn't see my original reporting on
CNN or the film, that crisis, I'll back up to April of 99, the following college basketball season,
I released my first story and it has Neil Reed, Charlie Miller, Richard Mandeville, a number of
other people and they make those three allegations. He kicked the president out of practice,
he brandished soil, tore the paper and he grabbed Neil Reed by the throat, chokes Neil Reed.
So those are the allegations in the 16 minutes. Indiana rallies the troops, everybody says it's
not true and we can go back to it in a minute but I'm going to jump to the crisis. So I do that
first piece. I do a second piece and we can talk about it in a minute where I actually get the
videotape that's proof that he grabbed Neil Reed by the throat and that changed the entire narrative
of the nationwide story. Explain for a moment how that makes it to you because that's, I mean look
at this point people who haven't seen the documentary I hope are going to see the documentary
because it's very powerful for reasons we haven't even got to yet by the way. That changes the game
and it's out of a movie how this tape makes it to you. I do my first 16 minute story making those
three allegations. Indiana, all the players, the university, everyone, even people in the media
push back and say it's actually not true, CNN's out to get him. A lot of it wasn't directed at me
or I didn't pay attention but it was directed at Neil Reed, anybody in the piece and CNN in
particular. Once I had heard almost immediately, almost a year before when I heard about the joke,
I was told that a tape exists of it because Indiana tapes all their basketball practices.
They have student managers up in the stands on the sidelines and they videotape it
and Coach Knight analyzes it at night, has his assistant coaches analyze it, shows it to the
players, it's just part of their process. So if something happened on that court chances are it
was captured on video. I had heard about it forever and it's just, I don't know, it's my style as a
reporter that I never want to ask for something if the percentages are that the answer would be no.
So I didn't pursue the video because I thought if I pushed or asked about it, much like I said,
if I was talking to you Peter and tried to push you to go on camera and I got a no, then where
do I go from there? I work every one of my sources, how I feel I can best connect with them, gain their
trust, whatever. So I had heard about the video. I was in Indianapolis to do a site survey for the
Final Four, it was going to be in the Final Four that year and I made the rounds with a number of my
sources at the school and I went out and had lunch and a few beers with one of them and
a source invited me back to their home and I kind of knew what may or may not happen,
but I never let on and somebody goes, hey I want to show you something. I'm like, oh what do you
want to show me? And so I saw the tape of practice from high above, Coach Knight going towards Neil
Reed and Neil Reed's head snapping back and even in that moment I didn't ask for the tape. I didn't
ask for it and people who are listening this may say, how the hell do you not ask for it? You idiot,
are you a moron? Because for a month now CNN's under fire or my reporting is under fire. I just,
I wasn't sure that the answer would be yes here. I'm proud because I've been in this business for
33, 34 years and I've tried my hardest that I'm not perfect, but I try not to use people.
I try not to use people to get something and I think because it took me almost a year to report
this, people got that sense with me who had, the more I talked to somebody and it's not on the
front page or it's not in the news, the more they trusted me so what would they do? The more they
would tell me, the more they would tell their friend, you can trust this guy. Oh you should
call this guy. Oh you have something you should call Robert. That's how I got everything I got
in this story. So in that moment where I watched the video that kind of vindicate my reporting
and shut up all the critics, I didn't ask for it and it was just an instinct of mine.
A number of days later I remember it vividly. We were watching an episode of The Sopranos,
my wife and I and the phone rings and it's my contact talking about
some stuff that was going on and I said, ah just send me the tape. I won't use it until you
get a lawyer and so I made a deal with that person in the moment. Actually to be honest,
let me back up. I had a conversation, I said let me call you back. I called Lester Munson,
who people may know from ESPN, I hired him at ESPN. He used to be, he's a lawyer, he was an
investigative producer for Sports Illustrated, somebody I'd work with at CNNSI. I had the utmost
respect. I go if there's anybody I can trust, it's Lester. He's a lawyer. I said hey Lester,
here's the situation. I may be coming into a possession of a tape that may or may not
be perceived as stolen by somebody. I want to make sure I don't do anything incorrectly and how I get
it blah blah blah. He gave me some great advice. The tape shows up at my house a number of days
later. It's vindication for all my reporting. From the time you get the tape until the tape
is made public is how long? You gave the university a heads up first right? Because they had dug their
heels in and said you guys are wrong. Yeah they had dug their heels in. Everybody was attacking
Neil, CNN, me, anybody in the piece. That Monday I'm at Augusta National for the Masters. So Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday I'm doing all the pre-story coverage for the Masters. But because this night
thing is a number of weeks before our first piece had aired, I was kind of scheduled to leave the
Masters and come back. I come back on a Wednesday and the tape had arrived in my mailbox. I knew
what it was. I popped it in but I didn't really even have to look at it. But I actually didn't
tell my bosses I had it. And people may wonder why because I had given someone my word that I
wouldn't run it until the person got legal advice and called me back. And I trust Steve Robinson and
Jim Walton with my life. Those are my two immediate bosses. I worked for Jim for 14 years and Steve
quarterbacked this whole investigation with me. We're literally the only two people who were
involved. There was no reporter, no nothing. At the end we had an editor that put it together.
But it was just Steve and I. So I trusted them impeccably. But I didn't know if somebody up
the food chain would say we have that tape CNN's and under fire we're running it. I never wanted
anybody to say that I lied to them and that I used them. So the only way to prevent that from
happening and probably being in complete control, whereas a producer I am much of a control free,
I didn't tell my bosses I had it. That's Wednesday, Thursday, Friday morning I get a phone call.
I remember it like it was yesterday. I was walking down the hall of my house. The phone rings and I
pick it up and I can tell them on speakerphone and I hear this is so and so and so and so and so and
it's a law firm. A bunch of names and I'm like here's the moment of truth that I make the right
decision or the wrong decision because I'm in possession of a tape that vindicates my reporting.
But if this phone call goes in another direction and I keep my word I may never be able to show it.
But my instincts told me I was doing the right thing. So there's this long conversation back and
forth and I explained here's how I think it'll all go down. I kind of convinced the people on the
phone call that the best thing to do is let me air the tape. So I go into the office later that day
and I walk into Steve's office and I say I got the tape and he's like what? Rick Davis, he's the head
of standards and practices at CNN, had been there probably close to 40 years. He's still there and
he was involved in all the reporting of the first piece and he says it in an interview I did with
him for the film. He's like we got the tape? Like he's so freaked out that we had it. So I bring
Steve, the head of sports Jim Walton who later became the president of CNN into a room, shut the
door and I play it for him. And I remember Steve going holy shit. And I remember Jim who was the
president of sports would go on to be the president of the network. He just looked at me and he said
you know if you did that at CNN you'd be fired immediately. And we discussed what should happen
and they said hey you got to start working on a second piece and we want to air it Monday.
This is Friday afternoon. So I'm sitting there going okay. So Saturday I'm starting to think
about how I'm going to put together this follow-up piece to my original 16-minute piece. I had just
been at Augusta National on Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and for those who are not members of
the media which is 99.9 percent of the people listening to this. When you cover Augusta you can
drop your name back then it was like into a fishbowl in the media center and they'd pick 20 names out
of that bowl who could play the course Monday morning after the tournament was over. I'm starting
to put together this piece on Saturday and I get a phone call from my colleagues and my best friends
who are covering the event and they go dude they drew your name. You got a tea time at Augusta
National 9 o'clock Monday. So I have to call my boss and say I know you want this piece on Monday
but please for the love of God can I play Augusta and can we air it on Tuesday? And my bosses were
so good they said yes but I hope people understand why I didn't tell my immediate bosses because I
didn't want somebody to overrule their decision and I never wanted anybody who placed their trust
in me to think I fucked them. And the only way I could ensure that a hundred percent
is was to hold the tape and not let anybody know I had it. So we air the piece. I put together the
piece on Tuesday when I get back. We're going to air it on Wednesday or Thursday. I think we were
going to air it on Thursday. My bosses say we have to call Indiana. So I've been reporting this story
for almost a year. My bosses say in order to be fair journalists we have to give them a chance to
respond. I had been battling them for nine months to a year and I go we don't owe them anything.
They should see it like the rest of the world. Like I wanted to throw a haymaker and just have
them watch it on TV like everyone else. And to Rick Davis's credit, Jim Walton's credit, and Steve
Robinson's credit, they push back, push back, push back and say no. To be honorable journalists, to be
fair, we have to give them a chance to respond. So they called Indiana and I kept saying I don't
think this is a good idea. And I said what if they slap an injunction on us for having stolen property
then we may be in possession of a tape that we can't air. So there's back and forth between us
and they're all my bosses so they're going to win. I knew they'd win but I just kept presenting
a front. Plus it was probably personal frustration of all of the roadblocks and hurdles that
Christopher Simpson specifically and the lies he had said to me over the nine months,
ten months of my reporting, or now it was over a year actually, of my reporting that I didn't
think we owed them anything. So we call them and four individuals get on two private planes,
three come out of Bloomington, one was on vacation in Key West and gets on a private plane,
the president of the board of trustees and they all come to Atlanta. When I had gotten the tape
I arranged to have Neil Reed fly into Atlanta to view the tape to verify it. So Neil flies into
Atlanta, I watch the tape with him, I take him into his studio, I play the tape with him, he has
a microphone on, I'm interviewing him while it's playing, probably do 40 minutes of an interview
with him, watch it over and over again, talk to him about it. I need to get Neil Reed out of CNN
Center because the four Indiana board of trustees and vice presidents are on their way in.
They probably passed on I-85 coming to the airport and from the airport about 40 minutes
after I put Neil in a cab, sent him back to the airport, they arrive. Did Neil come by himself?
No, he did come by himself. I called Neil and I said I have something you may be interested in
seeing. There's a ticket waiting for you, I'll have a ticket waiting for you, I'll have a car
waiting for you. So we paid for him to come to CNN but he came by himself and I had spent nine
months with Neil. I had talked to him over those nine months before the initial report had come
out. Now it was another month later. I had talked to him probably a couple times a week. Sometimes
it was just we were just shooting the breeze and Neil later did an interview with ESPN for another
project about it and he told them, yeah Robert and I became friends, we just started talking
and that's my style. If you're real with people and they trust you, they'll tell you anything.
And Neil told me everything and I never reported, I never hung him out to dry, I never betrayed his
confidence in me. In fact, when I got married during this whole time and I went on my honeymoon with
my wife to Turkey and then like a cruise through the Greek islands and I called Neil before that
and then I called him from my honeymoon to say, hey I'm in Europe, he was playing in Holland at the
time. I go can I come by and interview you? This is before the first piece aired. So he and I had
talked forever. So when I called him and said will you come here, he would kind of almost do
anything I asked him to. So he came and watched it and then 40 minutes later that Indiana, two members
of the board of trustees and two vice presidents of the school including Christopher Simpson
came to CNN center to watch the tape. What was their reaction? As I had predicted to my bosses
but they didn't believe me at the time, I said you can't trust them, specifically Christopher
Simpson. So we literally go into a conference room, it's Frederick Eichorn who used to be
the president of the Indiana Bar Association, John Waldo who's the president of the board of trustees,
Christopher Simpson and Terry Kleypex who's a vice president oversaw the athletic department.
The reason I thought they may slap an injunction on us is because Frederick Eichorn was the head,
he was the head of the Indiana State Bar Association at one point. So I knew he's a
lawyer. They may try to legally stop us from doing anything. So when we sat down it's myself,
Steve Robinson, my immediate boss and Jim Walton, the president of sports on the opposite side of
the table of these four and literally as our butts hit the chair on our side of the table,
Christopher Simpson, Miles Brand's right hand man says we understand you're in possession of
stolen property that belongs to Indiana University and we want it returned immediately. I was like
holy shit you have balls coming into our office and fucking dropping that bomb. And I kind of looked
to my bosses and I was just glanced and I was kind of like now you know what I've been dealing with
for the last year. For me I was like you didn't believe me and I'm not going to be able to paint
a picture of how powerful the next 20 seconds was. But without missing a beat because literally
he dropped a nuclear bomb in the room that normally would have put 99.9 percent of the people on the
defensive. Steve Robinson, my immediate boss without missing a beat, there was just a breath of silence
and he said and I'm not going to do it justice but in the most even keeled emotionless tone,
just said something to the effect of well I'm disappointed that you would come in here and say
that we were kind enough to invite you down to view this tape. If you'd like to pursue legal action
we'll escort you out the door to the bank of elevators outside. I'll push the button for the
13th floor and you can speak to our legal department. But before the door opens on the
13th floor this tape will be on CNN, CNN international headline news. We'll send it out to 300 affiliates
around the country. Now did you come here to threaten us or would you like to watch the tape?
In my 34 years of being a journalist I've never seen a more powerful moment by someone I worked
with. I mean Christopher Simpson came in with a lot of balls and my boss literally there was just
a breath of air and then he just surgically castrated him and he just said no what would you like to
do? And so then there was some conversations back and forth. I don't think they expected that answer
for Steve. I looked at Steve with as much admiration as any journalist I ever did in that moment. I
just went wow like how did he not get emotional? How did he not attack them? But he just surgically
cut their legs out from under him castrated him and said do you want to watch the tape?
And then there was some back and forth where Indiana's representatives mostly Christopher
Simpson said well we'd like to watch it in private. And at first Jim Walton said sure we don't have a
problem like that. And then I cleared my voice was like and Jim looked at me and I just shook my head.
And then we adjourned for a second and Steve Jim and I walked out and I go I don't trust him.
And I said oh by the way my source said don't ever let anybody see the actual tape because
it may give them a clue as to who shot it where it came from blah blah blah blah blah. And I actually
I made dubs the tape but I was actually showing them the exact tape so they couldn't say it was
dubbed altered or anything. I'm a journalist unlike you I'm a perfectionist. So I had the tape in a VCR
and so we walked back in and Jim my boss said hey these are going to be the ground rules if you
agree to him. You can watch the tape as many times as you want what happens in this room is off the
record. Robert will be in here with you and operate the machine. We're not going to let you watch it by
yourself. So they agreed and then I didn't think about it at the time. I'm 35 years old I think at
this time. Jim and Steve leave the room and I didn't think about it until years and years later
when somebody asked me about it. And so I'm sitting in there Steve Delson he's an investigative
journalist he worked for ESPN for years he wrote a book and there was a chapter on this and he said
Robert was left alone in a room with four men who wished he was never born. It was a great line
and I was like I never thought of it until I read it in his book. It's the four of them and me. I had
spent a year covering this. I knew everything that was going on in Indiana. I had the tape. I
didn't think anything of it in the moment and once my bosses leave one of them starts asking me
again everything's off the record in this room. So one of them asked me how many games have you been
to how many this how many that and all he was trying to do. I am probably much like you. I'm
a perfectionist my mind races and works really I make connections very very quickly and I'm like
I know what you're trying to do you're trying to find something that you can use to undermine my
credibility to this story and I just said hey everything in this room is off the record. Do
you want to sit here and ask me a bunch of questions or do you want to watch the tape?
And then Christopher Simpson said he wanted to see the tape. He was sitting across the conference
table for me in this big room and he got up. You got to understand I was frustrated that whole day
because I didn't want him there. You know I had argued with my bosses you shouldn't bring him here.
Christopher Simpson's lied to me for a year. I don't trust him then they came in and dropped the
bomb so I'm sitting there going. I didn't want this situation to happen kind of meaning I didn't
want them there. I just wanted him to see it on the air. He gets up and he starts going towards
the tape machine which I had on the floor in the corner like I was in between. I said sit down and
he didn't took another step or two and I said Mr. Simpson sit the fuck down. I don't care what
my bosses say. If you don't sit down right now I'm going to unplug that machine walk out to my car
and drive back to my house and you guys aren't going to see this tape. Did you come here to see
the tape or did you come here to ask me questions? Did you come here to look at the tape? You're not
going to see the tape sit down. You want me to do it. At that point it's probably the only time I
really lost my cool. It was like 10 seconds and I just told him to sit the fuck down because he
was starting to piss me off to be honest. I'm like you don't come into my office and tell me how
things are going to go down. And so he sat back down. I played the tape. They watched it a number
of times. They didn't say anything and even if they did it was off the record so I couldn't report it.
And then we had made an agreement when Jim said you could watch the tape and then afterwards Robert
will interview one of you. So I played the tape for them. We adjourned the meeting and then I went
into a studio and interviewed John Walda. He was heading up the investigation by the school. He was
the head of the board of trustees. I think for five weeks or so he had been investigating it.
As it states in my film my first story came out a month before John Walda, head of the board of
trustees, was quoted in the Indianapolis Star saying I put no stock in what Neil Reed says.
If CNN's saying it then I don't believe it. Something to that effect. So he's on the record
saying he doesn't believe the guy and then he's placed in charge of the investigation
into the guy's allegations. So my first question to him was you've now seen the tape.
Do you put any stock in what Neil Reed says? And John Walda was really good. I got to give him
credit. He was a broken record of just saying we've seen the tape. We're in the middle of
investigation. It's going to be part of our investigation. No matter what question I asked
him he gave me the same answer. You got to understand for 10 months I had been waiting
to interview anyone from Indiana and hold him accountable. And so he started to frustrate me.
I'd ask him is that conduct you want your coaches at Indiana to do? We've seen the tape. We're taking
it part of our it was just this broken record after about four times. I knew I was going to
get nowhere. So then I got to be honest it was just more of self-satisfaction for me because I
kind of had him. So I kind of wanted to squeeze a little bit the balls like I was just for the
longest time I wasn't not proud of it but I wondered if I crossed the line as a journalist.
So I said what do you say to people who want to send their sons to play for Bob Knight? Is
that what's going to happen to him? We're going to look at it. And so I asked a couple of personal
things like to piss him off and prompt him. And ironically I heard Christopher Simpson behind me
say to my bosses he can't ask that. And once I heard I got a reaction out of him I was done with
the interview. I asked about four more questions just to prolong the agony of him standing there.
And then they left and we put the story on about two hours later where we had Neil watching it.
We had the four members of Indiana University watching it. We did our follow-up piece and it
was front page news across the country. Everybody had a still at the grab. Everybody had it but it
was a pretty eventful day having Neil Reed come in and leave having them come in and leave and
having to turn the story around in about an hour or two after that. How long would it be after that
before you realized what you missed the first time which was when you sat down with Neil and
Neil watched the video with you. You comment on this. I think it's actually the most powerful
part of the documentary but I don't recall how long after you realized what you sort of missed
that first time. It's certainly understandable why you would have missed it. There was a lot going
on that day. It was getting Neil in, getting Neil out, getting the bozos from Indiana in, getting
the bozos from Indiana out, getting the story out, the legal stuff, the heated emotions, there's a
million things going on but the human tragedy of this is a guy Reed has to sit down and watch over
and over and over again. One of the most traumatic experiences of his life and for anybody listening
to this who's suffered trauma it's bad enough once and for most people they never have to see it again
or have a visceral reminder of it again and yet Neil had to watch it over and over and over again.
You noticed that later. I noticed it immediately. I had spoken to Neil for 10 months.
To be honest he had probably told me things that he had probably never told anyone else like that's
how close we were with regards to this incident, this moment. There's things he can or can't tell
his parents. He didn't really speak to other teammates. Once he left Indiana he had no contact
really with any of them. In the moment I knew how difficult it was for him. In the moment I knew how
much he trusted me. I knew how far I could push him maybe the right wrong word but dig and pull it out
of him. I knew in the moment how painful it was for him but sadly the focus of that day and to answer
your question probably 15 or 16 years later until I really I truly honestly noticed how I
fucked up or what I didn't do. You have to understand as a journalist you have to be impartial.
I can't be Neil Reed's friend. I have to report the story but in order for him to trust me I have
to spend a lot of time and have this trust. He would tell me anything and everything so when the
first story comes out and he's under fire I spoke to him for a month after that and then when he
comes back in and watches it the purpose of that second story was to say we did a first story where
this young man alleged these three things and everybody said it's factually incorrect. Oh by
the way it was correct and here's why you can see it for yourself. The trainer for Indiana University
after our first story came out said the choking thing never happened you can give me a lie detector
it never happened. We lined up all the people who discounted our original story and our second
story as I say in the film just focused on the journalism of was what we reported right
and was what Neil Reed initially said to us was it factually accurate and that's what the second
piece was. What I say in the film is I missed the human story sitting right in front of me.
I didn't miss it. I knew it was there because I had developed a relationship with Neil. If I could
turn back the clock 20 years or whatever I probably would have done a follow-up piece with Neil
several weeks several months whatever later to say what was this like personally but the original
story was about an investigation and a journalism to show wrongdoing. It was poo poo denied and
attacked. The second piece was to say no it was factually accurate. The third piece I should have
done was this was the damage it did to this young man and as I stayed in the film Neil and I stayed
in touch for a number of years after that and I probably erred on the side of in the moment
keeping him somewhat at arm's distance. There's this balancing act. If you get too close to story
you're going to make mistakes. If you become friends with the people in your story your
credibility is going to be questioned and there's a fine line to walk. Looking back as a human being
and that's why I devoted so much time to it in the film is when I was asked to do this film one of the
first things I did is take out the box where I had all the materials from my reporting and I watched
that and Hilary Horgan who is a producer on the film with me she had worked with me a number of
times at ESPN that I had hired her to work on shows I had done. She was in my office when I
played it. She watched the 40 minutes and said you could just hit play and watch that 40 minutes I
can't take my eyes off of it. To answer your question in a long roundabout way that's really
the moment when I was in this office with Hilary and she watched it and she just said oh my god
look at the trauma on him look at this and that's why when I went to do the film I showed everybody
and I confessed that I fucked up as a journalist and I did the journalistic part of the story but
I missed the human story sitting right in front of me which was Neil. It's just got the saddest
ending in a way I mean it's sort of a bittersweet ending as you walk us through in the documentary
which is that Neil seems to go on and do okay I mean he marries a wonderful woman he has these
great kids he's coaching kids in high school playing basketball he seems to be an amazing
coach the athletes love him and he dies of a massive heart attack at the age of 36. You
just couldn't script something like that it's so tragic and so while there's a part of me that
thinks how amazing is it that this guy who is so traumatized so humiliated manages to not pass
that on to others and that's a big deal most people who traumatize people are themselves
traumatized and he could be someone who stopped the cycle at such a young age is amazing to me
and yet I don't know not knowing anything about him I can't help but wonder was he able to sort
of reconcile all the horrible things that had happened and why did he have to go so soon?
I thought that was the most powerful thing again as I look back I saw so many things
16 17 18 years later as I put the film together and relived my reporting from long ago
and one of the more powerful things to me was what happened that caused Neil Reed to leave Indiana
took everything from him he once told me he said Robert I don't know what's worse
never having your dream come true or having your dream come true and it turning into a nightmare
and that's what happened to him his whole being from probably six seven eight years old on you
can see him in the film in a Bob Knight basketball camp t-shirt when he's under 10 his whole life was
to go there play he said it was an out-of-body experience for him to put on the candy stripe
sweats at Indiana and walk out on your run out onto assembly hall so when it turned into a nightmare
for him he questioned his entire being and everything that his life had led to to that point
when Neil Reed left Bob Knight didn't lose anything but a point guard who he quickly
replaced he still had three national championships an Olympic gold medal he was still in the hall of
fame and yet all these years later he never overcame Indiana firing him for that and yet Neil was able
to put it behind him for 20 plus years Knight wasn't able to put that firing behind him he
finally returned to assembly hall last year but it took him 20 years to come back so he held that
grudge for 20 years whereas Neil struggled for a number of years but ultimately put it behind him
and the abused as you point out the abuse didn't turn into the abuser I went out to California to
the high school where he was a teacher and a coach he only coached basketball one year he coached
football he was mainly the golf team coach and I talked to a number of students I talked to the
principal I talked to the athletic director in many ways he was the pied piper at that school
he would walk through the courtyard and everybody would go hey coach hey coach hey coach they said
he had an infectious smile and it was everything I almost think Neil turned into everything he
wanted coach Knight to be and everything he wanted from coach Knight while Neil was at Indiana
everything he yearned for and a number of the players have said that that a lot of the players
I interviewed in the late 90s to a man they all said I didn't have a relationship with coach off
the basketball court if you look back to the guys on his 75, 76, 16 his 81 team his 87 team
many of them have had relationships over the years with him I think that 90s era because they didn't
have the success he turned on them and never let them get close enough to him I think Neil became
the coach that Bob Knight never became yeah he's won three national championships an Olympic gold
medal and he's in the hall of fame but the kids at pioneer valley high school loved Neil Reed
and I'm not saying that because I'm biased or anything I went out there and I was shocked
by the emotion they still held for them I interviewed one student who said he's been
gone four years I still have the last texts he sent me on my phone I've never deleted him
it's a kid who's a golf pro Neil helped him get a job he played on the golf team for him he said
Neil was a Nike guy he goes every day I only wear Nike so I have Neil I have the Nike swoosh on my
chest or my arm or my hat to remember how I got here it was Neil there's all these stories that
just blew me away as to the man he became before he passed away and at such a young age that's the
part that just amazes me is to put yourself back together after all this it's humbling you sent me
an email a month ago maybe longer and I couldn't believe you dug it up which was the last
tweet that Neil sent about 10 days before he died do you remember that yeah do you have it in front
of you because I don't I can recite it but if you have the exact wording I do so it was six days
after Jerry Sandusky was found guilty in the Penn State scandal and it was 10 days before Neil died
he tweeted I now realize that kids deserve to be punched spit on choked and raped in the shower
so a select few can be worshipped like God's when I first started doing research for the film
I came across that and it it literally took my breath away I mean I read it and read it and read
it again because I found it on Twitter on his Twitter account and then I cross-referenced like
when did he write this and I went oh my god it was 10 days before he passed and then I'm like
why the reference to rape in the shower and then I googled the timeline and I was like oh my god
that was right in the middle of the Jerry Sandusky the Penn State football coach who's now
spending the rest of his life in prison for taking advantage of young men and one of them
that was detailed in the court in the shower and when I read that what it told me is and this is
before I went out to Pioneer Valley High School in California to see what became of Neil Reed I'd
stayed in touch with him for a number of years I'm asked to do the film I come up I read this tweet
and immediately I'm like he died a tortured human being is what that tweet kind of said to me
it never left him it aided his mind it aided his heart it aided his soul he never escaped
what happened to him at Indiana and yet when I went out to speak to his wife Kelly I actually
interviewed his two daughters which was amazing I didn't include it in the film out of respect for
them but it's something that Kelly will have forever them talking about their father I was
amazed because I went out there having read that tweet and when you read that tweet what do you
think of when you know Neil Reed's story and that's what was in his mind and that he tweeted
10 days before his death what comes to your mind it's everything you said which is he is still he
still has PTSD and yet when I went out there that's what I was expecting to hear I interviewed
his best friends I interviewed guys who were in the office with him in the athletic department
I interviewed all the kids I interviewed the principal she said he worked here probably for
three years before I even knew that was him the kid who got choked Kelly told a story his wife
where they were wrestling around on the bed once and she's like he's so much bigger than me I kind
of went up at him and just by where they were her hands kind of went up and was kind of near
his throat and literally he just stopped and she didn't say turn white but she noticed a
distinctive change in him and I included that in the film because it showed me that he did have
PTSD and that moment never left him even where he's in a playful loving moment with his wife
that flashback still came to him I had seen the tweet so I knew even 10 days before he died it
was still in his mind and his heart and his soul and yet when I went out there the story I uncovered
was the exact opposite that he had kept it from everyone and he kept it locked up in a way and
even his best friends would say he rarely ever talked about it he didn't bring anybody down he
didn't wallow in what had happened he wanted to move on from it and admirably he did what do you
think Knight's legacy is going to be I mean I guess just for posterity we can finish the story
somehow to the amazement of any sane person despite having video evidence that Knight chocked a player
which by extension effectively means every other allegation is true somehow this university in its
infinite wisdom decides not to fire him and instead in arguably one of the top 10 acts of
cowardice in the history of at least the modern civilization comes up with this goofy idea of well
you get one more chance but it's going to be under a zero tolerance umbrella I don't think it took
very long for him to violate his zero tolerance right it wasn't it later that year it was in the
fall of 2000 that he grabbed another kid's arm and I don't even want to go into the story it's
so idiotic but the point is it didn't take long for him to violate zero tolerance he got fired and
I gotta tell you I hope that the kids that chanted his name and cursed the kid who got grabbed that
ultimately led to his firing and all the best I hope those kids are able to watch the videos of
themselves 20 years ago and at least have some some degree of appropriate shame and remorse for
the way they behaved he goes on to coach eight years I think at texas tech before retiring and
I don't know he's done some commentary work on ESPN look he's at the end of his life now he's 80
at least to my eye doesn't look too healthy what's his legacy I think it's mixed I think it's very
mixed I want to back up one thing because you spoke earlier about having a devastating crisis
that kind of brings an awakening to someone in a perfect world my reporting of what happened
my getting the tape could have been that moment for coach night I'm an optimist and at that point
as much as I had battled Indiana when they placed him under zero tolerance which means if you do
you know we're going to wipe the slate clean you've been here 29 years we don't want
the faucet just to keep dripping of all these bad things you've done over the 29 years we're
turning it off but if there's one more drip if there's one more outburst you're gone
you would think that would have been the devastating crisis that would have given him an
awareness that he had to get his temper under control and all these things but it didn't when
he grabbed a student that was a public violation of a breaking of zero tolerance I was getting
phone calls almost immediately after zero tolerance of the ways he was breaking zero tolerance
he wasn't showing up to functions I think what ended up happening with coach night is he met with
Miles Brand and kind of for lack of a better term begged and pleaded for his job Miles Brand gave
him one last opportunity partially I believe because what he had accomplished at the school
and partially because he believes Indiana the university system was partially responsible for
allowing it to happen so how can the school allow it to happen forever and then all of a sudden say
you're out of here because of this and again as a journalist I try not to take sides in it but I see
his thought process and giving him one last chance and in a perfect polymeric world he changes
the people around him keep him under control and he breaks Dean Smith's record for all-time wins
at Indiana and this is a learning experience for him but it was anything but immediately after
zero tolerance and keeping his job he resented the people at the school he resented from everything
that everyone told me he was like how dare you humiliate me like this after everything I've done
for the school for 29 years winning national titles graduating young men winning an Olympic
gold medal like how dare you question me and that's where it becomes about I and me and he's
a bully and all that stuff so this could have been that devastating crisis that you talked about
earlier the hope was that it would be but immediately after it wasn't I was getting phone
calls one of them I got that I talk about in the film was that he was suspended for three games
and had to pay a thirty thousand dollar fine so he met with the head of the university council
for the school Dottie Frappweld to decide what games he was going to sit out how he's going to
pay the fine five thousand dollars out of six checks however they were going to do it I was told
he screamed and yelled at her called her to see where did this this this this this and so I get a
phone call that this happened so I can't report it because I don't have two eyewitnesses as a
journalist me I like to have three or four verify it so I can't report it so what do I do I pick up
the phone and I call Dottie Frappweld and it was a great phone call because I don't know if it was
her assistant but whatever picked up the phone goes Dottie Frappweld's office I goes Dottie there
yeah she's standing right here may I ask who's calling I go Robert Abbott from CNN may I ask
what this is regard to oh a meeting she had with Coach Knight I'm put on hold Dottie can't come to
the phone right now can I take a message I said yeah have her call me here's the number because
I don't know this is true I've heard it but I don't know as a journalist I can't report it I
don't know if it's true my phone rang in less than a minute and it was Christopher Simpson
vice president of the school and I remember mouthing into the phone you dumb mother blankety
blank like how stupid are you like I wasn't sure it happened but the fact that he called me back
within like 30 seconds told me yeah now I'm pretty sure it happened now I gotta find out if it did
and when he was ultimately fired it was put in one of the reasons he was fired that exact moment he
berated her etc etc which he denies by the way if you look at Jeremy Sharpe's interview with
Knight I mean just pathological lying just pathological lying probably to the level of
what a psychopath is capable of right again when I go back to what we talked about early what
fascinates me in a story is an onion you could peel away layer of layer upon layer of the genius
the brilliance the perfectionist that is Bob Knight I will say this I interviewed and spoke to
a lot of players throughout his tenure there and I can't think of one that was a punk he recruited
really really quality individuals I remember after my original reporting being how impressed
the body of people I spoke to were and I interviewed Angelo Pizzo for those of you
don't know as a screenwriter he wrote the film Hoosiers which is based on Mylon basketball
Gene Hackman plays the role that was kind of fashion about Bob Knight he also wrote the film
Rudy the Notre Dame kind of walk-on football player I interviewed him and the reason being
is Hoosiers came out right before he won the 1987 national championship and Angelo
told a great story about the academy awards his film was up for I think two academy awards
Dennis Hopper was up for one sorry for the tangent but it's an interesting story so Angelo
is an Indiana grad and so is I believe it's David Onspar is co-writer producer whatever they did the
film so it happens to be the academy awards are being played the night of the national
championship game in Indiana wins and is now in the national championship game so Angelo Pizzo
has to decide do I go to the academy awards where my film's up for two I think it was up for
Dennis Hopper and score a musical score something like that or do I stay home and watch my beloved
Indiana so there was a rehearsal for the academy awards and they gave Dennis Hopper like a Sony
watchman and they said hey when you're there for the rehearsal can you turn on the Sony watchman
and see if you can get ABC or NBC whatever the network is that's going to show the game the night
before so Hopper's in there for the rehearsals and he's like there's no way there's so much RF
in this building you'll never get a signal so the two directors writers producers of the film
stayed home to watch Indiana and didn't go to the academy awards when Knight wins the national
championship that night he invites Angelo Pizzo to a practice and Angelo tells me the story he
goes I go into assembly hall and like I told you it's usually locked and you're not allowed in there
he's sitting way up high and he sees Knight looking at him and he's like god I felt so uncomfortable
and awkward should I be here and he's such a great story teller and he says he almost gets up to
leave but he stays and then a trainer comes up to talk to him right at the end of practice coach
Knight would like to meet you he says he walks down to coach Knight and they start talking I
liked your film blah blah blah he goes what are you doing he goes why he goes I'm going on a
recruiting trip and you're coming with me so he gets in a car with coach Knight I think they
drive to Chicago or maybe they got on a private plane and then flew to Chicago I forget but he
basically spends like the next 10 hours with Knight as he goes on a recruiting trip and he said he
talked about Russian history with Knight for like six straight hours and the reason I bring this up
is in many ways coach Knight is brilliant a genius he's as only god can do give some of us
amazing gifts in one area and so many flaws in another Pizzo talked about how smart he was they
jumped from topic to topic mostly about Russian history and he goes I consider myself a Russian
history buff Knight blew me away with the stuff he knew we rarely talked about basketball
and that's the genius of coach Knight how well-read he was how he can motivate people but ultimately
like Icarus he didn't understand his flaw and he flew too close to the sun he couldn't control his
temper Dave Kindred who I mentioned earlier says in my film he goes he had an anger in him I don't
know where it came from or why it was there but it never left him and that was ultimately his
undoing. Robert the story is it means so much to me on so many levels and it is a cautionary tale
even though Knight is a very extreme example of this I don't think I would have gone to the lengths
to have this podcast with you if I didn't believe that others could benefit from sort of a deeper
examination of this the work you did on this was was amazing I'm so grateful you did it first and
foremost for Neil I think you probably deserve at least some credit for the fact that even though
Neil's life was taken too soon he was validated he got to spend that last 12 years of his life
the last decade of his life knowing that what happened hopefully he understood it wasn't his
fault which is easy to say because cognitively of course it wasn't his fault but that's not always
easy to understand as a victim so first and foremost I thank you for what you did for someone
I've never met but have great affection for and obviously for the rest of us who have benefited
immensely from such an unbelievable story. I owed it to Neil it's as simple as that I owed it to Neil
at one point one of the cuts of the film I got some feedback from ESPN and one executive said
you need to cut that Neil Reed part down to maybe one minute and I was kind of like over my dead
body it's what gives the film its heart and soul I screwed up 16 17 years before by not telling his
story sooner and I feel I owed it to him to make his story part of this film because when somebody
trusts you like that I'm working on another film now where that trust is almost even greater
for the situation the person I'm going to profile is in it's a weight it's a weight on you and as a
journalist you don't want to let that compromise your objectivity I think as a 35 year old
journalist at the time I think I kept Neil possibly too much at a distance not personally
but at least to the rest of the world I felt like if I did a story then I was doing it because
I knew him not because we were friends I was just like I gotta be careful I gotta be careful
and I'm angry with myself because I was too careful and by doing this film at least I told
Neil people who the real Neil Reed was who the Neil Reed I came to know was and as I say at the
end thank you for trusting me to tell your story that's what was the most important thing in the
last days of night to me is the ending and that's what gave the film the heart and soul of it it is
about Bob Knight but it's not about Bob Knight it could be about a local sheriff it could be about
the president it could be about anyone but it was really about a young man who somehow found the
strength to put it behind him and someone who had out all the success in the world more success than
anybody could ever imagine and that human being couldn't put it behind him and to this day is
angry bitter has a temper Neil was the opposite and that juxtaposition has always amazed me as I
look at this story the one kid who had everything taken from him was able to move on and the one
person who in reality had very little taken from him yes he had his job maybe some humiliation
but he still had three national champions an Olympic gold medal hall of fame he just couldn't
move beyond it and it tells you about the character of both individuals Robert thank you very much
this was a great discussion thank you I really enjoyed it thanks for having me
thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive if you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription now to that end membership
benefits include a bunch of things one totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes
that detail every topic paper person thing we discuss on each episode the word on the street is
nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing
these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this the qualities which are a super short podcast that
we release every Tuesday through Friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive this is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without
having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that I
believe in but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that
we continue to trickle in as time goes on if you want to learn more and access these member-only
benefits you can head over to peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter
instagram and facebook all with the id peteratiamd you can also leave us a review on apple podcast
or whatever podcast player you listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes
only it does not constitute the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health
care services including the giving of medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed
the use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk
the content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice
diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any
medical condition they have and they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals
for any such conditions finally I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures
and the companies I invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies
you