Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level
at the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is John Ayanidis. John is by all estimates a polymath.
He's a physician scientist, a writer, and a Stanford University professor. He has extensive
training in mathematics, medicine, epidemiology. He's just generally one of the smartest people
I've ever met, and I've had the luxury of knowing John for probably about nine years. Anytime I get
to interact with him, whether it's over a meal or more formally through various research
collaborations, it's just always an incredible pleasure. John studies scientific research itself,
a process known as meta-research, primarily in clinical medicine, but also somewhat in the
social sciences. He's one of the world's foremost experts on the credibility of medical research.
He's the co-director of the Meta-Research Innovation Center at Stanford. In this episode,
we talk about a lot of things. We talk about his journey from Greece to the United States,
but we talk a lot about some of his seminal papers. You're going to see me reference a number
of papers beginning with, I think, one of the most famous papers. He's written, although by
citation it turns out to not be the most famous. There's actually papers that even exceed it,
which is an amazing paper where he describes through a mathematical model why most published
research in the biomedical field is incorrect, which is obviously out of the gate a staggering
statement. We go on to discuss a number of his other seminal papers and then really kind of
tackle some of the hard issues in medical research, including my favorite topic, nutritional,
epidemiology. As always, John is candid and full of insight. I'm just going to leave it at that and
hope that you trust me and make time to listen to this one. Please, without further delay,
enjoy my discussion with John Ayanese. John, this is really exciting for me to be as close to sitting
down with you as I can be during this time. I've been wanting to interview you for as long as I've
had a podcast and obviously we've known each other for probably close to 10 years now. Of course,
you first came on my radar in 2005 with a paper that we're going to spend a lot of time discussing
today. But before we get to that, how would you describe yourself to people because you have such
a unique background? I think that it's very difficult to know yourself and I've been struggling
on that front for a long time. So I'm trying to be a scientist. I think that this is not an easy
job. It means that you need to reinvent yourself all the time. You need to search for new frontiers,
for new questions, for new ways to correct errors and to correct your previous self
in some way. So under that denominator of scientists in the works, probably it would be
a good place to put my whereabouts. Now, your background is also in mathematics and I think
that's part of my appreciation for you is the rigor with which you bring mathematics to the
study of science. In particular, we're going to discuss some of your work and how you use
mathematical models as tools to create frameworks around this. Now, you were born in the U.S. but
grew up in Greece. Is that correct? Indeed. I was born in New York in New York City,
but I grew up in Athens and I always loved mathematics. I think that mathematics are the
foundation of so many things and they can really transform our approach to questions that
without mathematics, it would be very difficult to make much progress.
How did you navigate your studies? Because you were obviously very prolific in mathematics. If
I recall reading somewhere in one of your bios, you even won the highest honor that a graduating
college student could win in mathematics in Greece at the time. How did you decide to also pursue
something in the biological sciences in parallel as opposed to staying purely in the natural or
philosophical sciences of mathematics? Medicine had the attraction of being a profession where
you can save lives. I think that intellectual curiosity is very interesting, but the ability
to make a difference for human beings and to save lives, to improve their quality of life,
seemed to be, at least in my eyes, as a young person, something that was worthwhile pursuing.
I had a very hard time to choose what pieces of mathematics and science and medicine I could
combine in what I wanted to do. I think that I have tried my hands in very different things. I
have probably failed in all of them, but in some ways I saw that these were complementary. So I
believe that medicine is amazing in terms of its possibilities to help people. You need, however,
very rigorous science. You need very rigorous scientific method to be applied if you want to
get reliable evidence. Then you also need quantitative approaches. You need quantitative
tools to be able to do that. So I think that none of them is possible to dispense without really
losing the hole and losing the opportunity to do something that really matters eventually.
Your parents were physicians as well, is that correct?
Indeed. Both of them were physicians, actually physician scientists. So I did have an early
exposure to an environment where I could hear their stories of clinical exposure. At the same
time, I could see them working on their research. I remember these big tables with scientific papers
spread all over them and with what were the early versions of computerized research. I think that I
had the chance to be exposed to software and computers in an early phase because my father
and my parents were interested in doing research. So you finished medical school and your postgraduate
training also in Greece, or did you do part of that in the United States? I finished medical
school in Greece in Athens, in the National University of Athens. Then I went to Harvard
for residency training and then Tufts Union Medical Center for training in infectious diseases. At the
same time, I was also doing joint training in healthcare research. So it was very interesting
and fascinating years learning from great people. Who were some of the people that you think back
as having shaped your thinking during those years? In the medical school, I had some great teachers.
One of them was the professor of epidemiology, Dimitri Tricopoulos, who was also chair of
epidemiology at Harvard. He had some really great statisticians in his team. So from the first year
at medical school, I went to meet them and tried to use every textbook that they could give me
and every resource that I could play with. In my residency training, I was very fortunate to meet
great physician scientists, especially in infectious diseases. Actually,
Bob Mellering was the physician-in-chief and professor at Harvard, professor of medical
research as well. He was really an amazing personality in terms of his clinical acumen
and his approach to patients. Also, he's very temperate mode of dealing with very serious
problems and dissecting through the evidence in trying to make decisions. And of course,
start with making diagnosis. At the end of my residency training, I had the pleasure to meet
the late Tom Chalmers along with Joe Lau. They were at Tufts at that time and my meeting with
them was really a revelation because they were the ones who were advancing the frontiers of
evidence-based medicine. Evidence-based medicine had just been coined as a term
pretty much by the McMaster team, David Sackett and Gordon Gwyatt. Tom Chalmers was the first
person in the US to design a randomized trial. He was also one of the first to perform meta-analysis
that had a major impact in medical science. At the time that I met them, they had just published
an influential paper on cumulative meta-analysis in the New England Journal of Medicine.
And it was a revelation for me because somehow what they were proposing was mixing mathematics,
rigorous methods, evidence and medicine in one coherent whole, which seemed to be a forlorn
hope until then for me. I was just seeing lots of clinical exposures that there was very little
evidence to guide us. There was no data or very poor data and a lot of expert-based opinion guiding
everything that was being done. And so this is just temporally, I mean, Chalmers died in the
mid-90s. So this is what, the early 90s that you were fortunate enough to meet him? Yes, I met him
in 1992 and he died about five years later. I was grateful that I had the opportunity to work with
him and also with Joseph Lau, who was at that time at Tufts Union Medical Center, which I went
eventually to do my fellowship training. Because there are so many things I want to talk about,
John, and we don't have the luxury of spending 12 hours together, I'm going to fast forward about a
decade. I'm going to fast forward to 2005, to that paper that I alluded to at the outset, which was
the first time your work came onto my radar, which is not to say anything other than that's
just the first time I became aware of sort of the gravity of your thinking. Can you talk a little
bit about that? It was in PLOS ONE, was that paper correct? Yes, it was in PLOS MEDICINE.
PLOS MEDICINE, okay. So this is basically an open source journal that I think another Stanford
professor actually was one of the guys behind this journal, if I recall. Pat Brown was one of the
forces behind PLOS, correct? Well, it was a transformative move at that time, trying to
create a new standard for medical journals. I think that now this has become very widespread
in a way. But I think back then it was something new, something that was a new frontier in a sense.
So you wrote a paper that on the surface seems, I mean, highly provocative, right? The title of
the paper is something to the effect of why most published clinical research is untrue. I mean,
that's the gist of it. Can you walk people through the methodology of this? It's a theoretical paper,
but explain to people who maybe don't have the understanding of mathematics that you do,
how you were able to come to such a stark conclusion, which I want to point out one thing.
I'll give you why I had an easy time believing the results of your paper is my mentor had shared
with me a statistic when I was doing my postdoctoral training, which I found hard to believe, but when
I realized it was true, became the bookend to your claim. And that was at the time something to the
tune of 70% of published papers were never cited again outside of auto citation, meaning outside
of the author citing his or her own work. And if you think about that for a moment, if 70% of work
can't even be cited by one additional person down the line, that tells you it's either irrelevant
or wrong. So again, that's not the same thing that you said, but it at least primed me to kind of
listen to the message you were talking about. So talk a little bit about that paper.
That paper, as you say, it's a mathematical model that is trying to match empirical data that had
accumulated over time, both in my work and also in the work of many other scientists who were
interested to understand the validity of different pieces of research that was being produced.
I think that many of us had been disillusioned that when evidence-based medicine started,
we thought that now we have some tool to be able to get very reliable evidence for decision-making.
And very quickly we realized that biases and results that could not be replicated and results
that were overturned and results that were unreliable were the vast majority. It was not
something uncommon. It was the rule that we had either unreliable evidence or actually, perhaps
even more commonly, no evidence. So it's an effort, that paper, to put a mathematical construct
together that would try to explain what is going on and would also try to predict in some ways
what might happen if some of the circumstances would change in terms of how we do research.
So the model makes for a framework that is trying to calculate what is the chance that if you come
up with a eureka, a statistically significant result that you claim, I have found something,
I have found some effect that is not null. There is some treatment effect here, there's some
not zero that I'm talking about. What are the chances that this is indeed a non-null effect,
that we're not seeing just a red herring? And in order to calculate the chances that this is not
just a red herring, you need to take into account what is your prior chances that you might be
finding something in the field that you're working. There are some fields that probably have
a higher chance of making discoveries compared to others. If you're unlucky to work in a field that
there's nothing to be discovered, you may be wasting your time and publishing one million
papers, but there's nothing to be discovered. So it's going to be one million papers that end up
with nothing. Conversely, there may be other fields that may be more rich in discovery, both the field
and the tools, the methods, and the designs of the studies that we throw at trying to answer
these questions can be informative. The second component is in what environment of power are we
operating? Meaning, is the study large enough to be able to detect non-null effects of some size of
interest? Or maybe there are true effects out there, but our studies are very small and therefore
they're not able to detect these effects. In my experience, until that time, I had seen again and
again lots of very small studies floating around with results that were very questionable, that
could not be matched with other efforts, especially when we were doing larger studies, most of them
seemed to go away. Power is important not only because if you don't have enough power, you cannot
detect things that exist. What is equally bad or probably worse is that if you operate in an
environment of low power, when you do get something detected, it is likely to be false. And here comes
the other factor that is compounding the situation, bias, which means that you have some results that
for whatever reason bias makes them to seem statistically significant while they should not be.
And bias could take zillions of forms. I think that throughout my career I feel like I'm struggling
with bias, with my own biases and with biases that I see in the literature. But bias means that you
could have conscious, unconscious or subconscious reasons why a result that should have been null
somehow is transformed into a significant signal. It could be publication bias, it could be selective
reporting bias, it could be multiple types of confounding bias, it could be information bias,
it could be many many other things that turn null results into seemingly significant results while
they are not. Then you have to take into account the universe of the scientific workforce, where
we're not talking about a single scientist running all the studies, it's not just a single
scientist or a single team. We have currently about 35 million people who have co-authored at
least one scientific paper. We have many many scientists who might be trying to attack the
same scientific question and each one of them is contributing to that evidence. However,
there's an interplay of all these biases with all of these scientists. So if you take into account
that multi-scientist environment, multi-effort environment, you need to account for that in your
calculations. Because if you, for example, say what are the chances that at least one of these
scientists will find some significant signal, this is a very different situation compared to just
having one person taking a shot and just taking a single shot. So this is pretty much what the model
tried to take into account, putting these factors together and then trying to see what you get under
realistic circumstances for these factors. These factors would vary from one field to another. They
would be different, for example, if we're talking about exploratory research with observational data
versus small randomized trials versus very large phase three or even mega trials. It would be
different if we're talking about massive testing like what we do in genetics versus highly focused
testing of just one highly specified pre-registered hypothesis that is being attacked.
Running the calculations, the model shows that in most circumstances, we're both biomedical research,
but I would say most other fields of research are operating. If you get a nominally statistically
significant signal with a traditional p-value of slightly less than 0.05, then the chances that
you have a red herring, that this is not true, that it is a false positive, are higher than 50%.
There is a huge gradient and in some cases it may be much lower. The false positive rate may be
much, much lower and in others it would be much higher. In most circumstances,
the chances that you got it wrong are pretty high. They're very high.
That's actually a very elegant description of that paper. I want to go back and unpack a few
things for people who maybe don't have some of the acumen down. Let's go a bit deeper into what
a p-value is. Everybody hears about it and everybody hears the term statistically significant.
So maybe explain what a p-value is, explain statistical significance and explain why it's
not necessarily the same as clinical significance and why we shouldn't confuse them.
I think that there's major misconceptions around significance. What we care in medicine is clinical
significance, meaning if I do something or if I don't do something, would that make a difference
to my patient or it could be in public health, to the community, to cohorts of people, to healthy
people who want to have preventive measures and so forth. Do I make a difference? Does it matter?
Is it big enough that is worthwhile? The cost, the potential harms, the implementation effort,
perhaps other alternatives that I have, how does that compare to these alternatives? Maybe they're
better or cheaper or easier to implement or have fewer harms. So this is really what we want to
answer. But unfortunately, most of the time we are stuck with trying to answer very plain,
frequentist approach question, which boils down to statistical significance.
Typically, this boils down to a p-value threshold of 0.05 for most scientific fields. Over the years,
there's many scientific fields that have diversified and they have asked for more stringent
levels of statistical significance. A couple of years ago, along with many other people,
we suggested that fields that have not diversified and they do not adjust their levels of statistical
significance to more stringency, by default they should be using a more stringent threshold. For
example, use a threshold of 0.005 instead of 0.05. However, most scientists are trained with
statistics light to use some statistical test that gives you some statistic that eventually
translates to a p-value. And what that p-value means, it needs to be interpreted as what are
the chances that if I had an infinite number of studies like this one, I would get a result that
would be as extreme or more extreme. And even that is not a complete definition because it does not
take into account bias because maybe you would get a result that is as extreme, but it's largely
because of bias. For example, there's many, many fields that you can easily get p-values that are
astronomical. They're not just less than 0.005, but they may be 10 to the minus 100 with some of
the large databases that we have, we can easily get to astronomically small p-values. But this
doesn't mean much. It could just mean that you have bias and this is why you get all these
astronomically low p-values, but they don't really mean that the chance of getting such an extreme
result is extremely implausible and that there is something there. It just means that certainly
there's bias, no more than that. There has been what I call the statistics wars over the last
several decades. People have tried to diminish the emphasis on statistical significance. I think I
have been in the camp of those who have argued that we should diminish emphasis or at least try
to improve the understanding of what that means for people who use and interpret these p-values.
In the last few years, this has become probably more aggressive. Many great methodologies have
suggested that we should completely abandon statistical significance, that we should just ban
the term, never use it again, and just focus on effect sizes, focus on how much uncertainty we
have about effect sizes, focus on perhaps Bayesian interpretation of research. I have been a little
bit reluctant about adopting the ban statistical significance approach because I'm afraid that
we have all these millions of scientists who are probably not very properly trained to understand
statistical significance, but they're completely not trained at all to understand anything else
that would replace it. In some ways, for some types of designs also, I would argue that if you
pre-specify and if you are very careful in registering your hypotheses and you have a
protocol that you deposit, for example, what is happening or should be happening with randomized
trials, and you have worked through this that it makes sense that your hypothesis is clinically
important, that the effect size that you're trying to pick is clinically meaningful, it is clinically
significant, then I would argue that statistical significance and using a p-value threshold,
whatever that is, depending on how you design the study, makes perfect sense. It's actually a very
transparent way of having some rules of the game that then you try to see whether you manage to
succeed or not. So if you remove these rules of the game after the fact in these situations,
it may make things worse because you will have a situation where people will just get some results
and then they will be completely open to interpret them as they wish. And we see that they interpret
them as they wish even now without any rules in the game, or at least by removing those rules
post hoc, but if we could have some rules for some types of research, I think that this is useful.
For other types of research, I'm willing to promote better ways of interpreting results,
but this is not going to happen overnight. We have to take for granted that most scientists
are not really well trained in statistics and they will misuse and misinterpret and misapply
statistics, unfortunately. So we need to find ways that we will minimize the harm, we will minimize
the error, and maximize in medicine the clinically significant pieces, and in other sciences, the true
components of the research enterprise. Now, at the other side of that statistical field is power.
We go from alpha to beta. And you alluded to it earlier, I want to come back to it because you
actually said something very interesting. I think most people who dabble enough in the literature
understand that if you underpower a study, so if you have too few samples, too few subjects,
whatever the case might be, and you fail to reach statistical significance, it's not clear
that you failed to reach statistical significance because you should be rejecting the null
hypothesis or because you didn't have a large enough sample size. So that's always the fear,
right? The fear is that you get a false negative. But you said something else that I thought was
very interesting, if I heard you correctly, which was, no, you actually run the risk of a false
positive as well if you're underpowered. Can you say more about that? Indeed, in an underpowered
environment, you run the risk of having higher rates of false positives if you take the performance
of the field at large, if you take hundreds and thousands of studies that are done in an
underpowered environment, even if you manage to detect the real signals, signals that do exist,
if these signals are detected in an underpowered environment, their estimates will be exaggerated
compared to what the true magnitude is. And in many situations, both in medicine and in other
sciences, it's not important so much to find whether there's some signal at all, which is what
a null hypothesis is trying to work around. But how big is the signal? I mean, if a treatment has
a minuscule benefit, then I wouldn't care about it. I wouldn't use it because the cost and the
harms and everything on the other side of the balance is not making it worth it. So most
scientific fields have been operating in underpowered environments. And there's many reasons
for that. And it varies a little bit from one field to another, but there are some common
denominators. Number one, we have a very large number of scientists. Scientists are competitive.
There's very limited resources for science. It means that each one of us can get a very thin
slice of resources. We need to prove that we can get significant results so as to continue to be
funded and to be able to advance in our career. This means that we are stuck in a situation
where we need to promote seemingly statistically significant results, even if they're not.
We need to do very small studies with these limited resources and then do even more small
studies rather than aim to do a more definitive large study. There's even a disincentive
towards refuting results that are not correct because that means that you feel that you're back
to square zero. You cannot make a claim for continuing your funding. All the incentives,
at least until recently, have been aligned towards performing small studies in very selectively
reported circumstances and with flexibility in the way that results are analyzed and presented. And
I think that this leads to very high rates of results that are either completely false positives
or they may be pointing to some real signal, but the estimate of the magnitude of the signal
is grossly exaggerated. In recent years, we have started seeing the opposite phenomenon as well.
We start seeing some fields that have overpowered studies. Instead of just having very small
studies, in some fields we have big data, which means that you can access medical records from
electronic health records on millions of people or you may have genetic information
that is highly granular and gives you tons of information. And big data are creating an
opposite problem. It means that you're overpowered and you can get statistically significant results
that have no clinical meaning, that have no meaning really. And even with a tiny little bit of bias,
you may get all these signals just because bias is there. So, you're just measuring bias. You're
just getting a big scale assessment of the distribution of bias in your data sets.
That's becoming more of a problem in some specific fields. I think that the growth of this type of
problem will be faster compared to the growth of the problem of small underpowered studies.
I think in most fields, it's a more common problem though,
until now, that we have very small studies rather than very large studies.
Now, you've commented on GWAS studies. Do you want to talk a little bit about that here? It
sort of fits into this a little bit, doesn't it? Genetics was something that I was very interested
in from my early years of doing research because it was a new frontier for quantitative approaches.
Lots of very interesting methodology was being developed in genetics. Many of the questions of
evidence that had been stagnating in other biomedical fields, they had a new opportunity
to give us some new insights with much larger scale evidence in genetics compared to what we
had in the past when we were trying to measure things one at a time, especially genetics was
a fire hose of evidence in some way. So, I found it very exciting. And for many years,
I did a lot of genetic research. I still do some. And very early on, we realized through genetics
that the approach that we had been following in most traditional epidemiology, like looking at
one risk factor at a time and trying to see whether it is associated with some disease outcome,
was not getting very far. We could see in genetic epidemiology of candid genes that most of these
papers that were looking at one or a few genes at a time with association with some outcome, just
trying to cross the threshold of statistical significance and then claiming success,
they were just false positives. We saw that pretty early. It took some time for people to be
convinced. But then they were convinced and genetics took some steps to remedy this. They
decided to do very large studies to start with. They also decided to look at the entire genome,
look at all the factors rather than one at a time. And they also decided to join forces,
not have each scientist try to publish their results alone, but share everything, have a
common protocol, put all the data together to maximize power, to maximize standardization,
to maximize transparency also, and then report the cumulative results from the combined data from
all the teams that had contributed to these large meta-analysis of primary data. So this is a recipe
that I think should be followed by many other fields, especially fields that work with
observational data in epidemiology. And some fields have started moving in that direction as well,
but not necessarily as much as the revolution that happened in genetics and population genomics.
So I was going to actually ask you exactly that question. I was going to save it for a bit later,
but let's do it now. Why did the field of genetics basically have the ability to self-police and
undergo this cultural shift in a way that let's just put every card on the table here. Nutritional
epidemiology has not. I mean nutritional epidemiology, which we're going to spend a lot of time talking
about, is the antithesis of that. And it continues to propagate subpar information, which is probably
the kindest thing I could say about it. So what is it culturally about these two fields that has
produced such stark contrasts in the response to a crisis? There's multiple factors. One reason is
that genetics managed to have better tools for measurement compared to nutritional epidemiology.
We managed to decode the human genome. So we developed platforms that could measure
the entire variability more or less in the human genome with pretty high accuracy. If you have
genotypic platforms that have less than 0.01 percent error rate, this means that you have very
accurate measurement as opposed to nutrition where the traditional tools have been questionnaires or
survey tools that have very high biases, very high recall bias, very low accuracy. And they do not
really capture the diversity of nutritional factors with equal granularity as we can capture the
genetics in their totality of the human genome. The second reason was that I believe in genetics,
there were no strong priors, no strong beliefs, no strong opinions, no strong experts who would
fight with their lives for one gene variant versus another. We had some. I think that some of us
probably might have published about one gene and then we would fiercely defend it because obviously
if you publish a paper, you don't want to be proven wrong. I think it's very human.
But it was nothing compared to the scale that you see in nutrition research where you have a very
strong expert opinion base of people who have created careers and they feel very strongly that
this type of diet is saving lives and it should have policy implications. It should change the
world. It should change our guidelines. It should change everything. Many of these beliefs are
interspersed with religious or cultural or non-scientific beliefs in shaping what we think
is good diet. And as you realize, none of that really exists for genetics. Polymorphism,
RS 2492-14 is unlikely to be endorsed by any religious, cultural, political or dietary
proponents. It's a very different beast. And I think that you can be more neutral with genetics
research because of this objectivity as opposed to nutrition where there's a lot of heavy beliefs
interspersed. Methodologically also, genetics advanced faster. Nutrition has been stuck mostly
in the era of using p-values of 0.05 thresholds and using those thresholds in mostly post hoc
research, research that is not registered, that is selectively presented. People are trained in a way
that they need to play with the data. They need to torture the data. They need to try
to unearth interesting associations. And in some cases, of course, this becomes extreme,
like what we have seen in the Cornell case where it pretty much goes into the situation where you
have fraud. I mean, it's not just poorly done research. It's fraudulent research. But fraudulent
research aside, even research that is not fraudulent in nutrition has some standards of
methods that are pretty suboptimal compared to what genetics has adopted that they decided that
we have such a huge multiplicity that we need to account for that. So we're not going to claim
success for a p-value of 0.05. We will claim success for a p-value of 10 to the minus 8.
And if it's not that low, then forget it. That's not really a finding. We need to get more data
before we can say whether we have a finding or not. Or they decided that they will share data,
that they will create large coalitions of researchers who would all share their data.
They would standardize their data. They will standardize the analysis. They would
perform analysis in a very specific way. And they would also sometimes, actually, I think this is
becoming the norm, have two or three analyst teams analyze the same data and make sure that
they get the same results. These principles and these practices have started being used in fields
like nutrition, but to a much lesser extent. And I think that gradually we will see more of that,
but it's going to take some time. So there's multiple scientific and behavioral and cultural
and statistical and methodological reasons why these fields have not progressed at the same pace
of revolutionizing their research practices. Let's talk a little bit about Austin Bradford Hill.
I'm guessing you didn't have a chance to meet him. He died in 91. Would you have crossed paths
with him at all? No, I didn't have that fortune, unfortunately. Do you think he would be rolling
around in his grave right now if he saw what was being employed based on the criteria he set forth,
which I also want to talk about your thoughts around the revision of these. But even if you
just take his 10 criteria, which we'll go through for a moment as a bit of a background on epidemiology,
do you think that what he had in mind is what we're doing today?
I think that Austin Bradford Hill was very thoughtful. He was one of the fathers of
epidemiology. And of course, he didn't have the measurement tools and the capacity to run research
in such large scale as we do today. But he was spot on in coming up with good questions and asking
the right questions, asking the important questions. So his criteria, I don't think that
he thought of them as criteria. And I don't think that he ever believed that they should be applied
as a hard rule to arbitrate that we have found something that is causal versus something that
is not causal. If you read through the paper, it's a classic. It's very obvious that he has a very
temperate approach, has a very cautious approach. Basically, he says none of these items is really
bulletproof. I can always come up with an example where it doesn't work. And I think that this is
really telling what a great scientist he was, because indeed in science, there's hardly anything
that is bulletproof. I don't know, you know, the laws of gravity might be bulletproof. But even
those as you realize, they're just only down to atomic levels. Yeah, exactly. You know, in the
theory of relativity, they would start failing. So he was very cautious. I think that paper had
tremendous impact. I think that we have not been very cautious in moving forward with many of our
observational associations and the claims that we have made about them. I don't want to give any
holistic perspective. And I don't want to give, let's say, a very negative perspective of epidemiology,
because we run the risk of entering the other side where you will have some science denier saying,
so you're not certain. And therefore, we can have more air pollution, you know, we can have
more pesticides, we can have more. That's not clearly the case. I mean, we have very solid
evidence for many observational associations. There's not the slightest doubt that tobacco is
killing right and left. It's likely to kill one billion people over the last century.
Let's go through tobacco as the poster child for Bradford Hill's criteria. So I'm going to rattle
off the quote unquote criteria and just use tobacco as a way to explain it. So let's start
with strength. How does the association between tobacco and lung cancer fit in terms of causality
vis-a-vis this criteria of strength? It is huge. I mean, we do not see odds ratios of 10,
20 and 30 as we see with tobacco with many types of cancer and with other outcomes like cardiovascular
disease. And I think that that really stands out. And we see that again and again and again. We see
very strong signal. We see signals that are highly replicable. And that's the exception in most of
what we do nowadays in epidemiology. We don't see odds ratios of 20. If I see an odds ratio of 20 in
my calculations, I'm almost certain that I have something wrong. I always go back and check and
I find an error that I have done in some. Yeah. You're probably off by a log if you're getting a
20 nowadays. Probably two log. I think in genetics we are dealing actually with odds ratios of 1.01
at the time. So 1.01 may still be real. And of course, then the question is.
Is it clinically relevant? Yeah. It's unlikely to be clinically relevant,
but how much certainty can you get even for its presence?
So the strength is huge. You really essentially covered the next one, which is consistency.
If you look at all of the studies in the 1950s and the 1960s, they were all really moving in the
same direction. And that's whether you looked at physicians who were smokers, non-physicians who
were smokers, whichever series of data you looked at, you basically saw this 10x multiplier in
smoking. And I think on average it worked out to be about 14x. There was about a 14 times higher
chance. I mean, that's a staggering number. What about specificity? What does specificity refer to
here? I think that if you have such strength and such consistency, I would probably not
worry that much about the rest of the criteria. I think that criteria like specificity or
like analogy, they're far more soft in terms of what they would convey. And also, we just don't
know the nature of nature in how it operates. Many phenomena may be very specific, but it doesn't
have to be so. We should not take for granted that we should see perfect specificity or low
specificity. We see many situations where you have multidimensional situations of causality,
you have multiple factors affecting some outcome, or you have one factor affecting multiple outcomes.
The density of the webs of causality can be highly unpredictable. So I would not worry that
much about other criteria if you have some like strength and consistency being so impressive
in these cases. Now, in most cases, we don't have that, right? We'll get an odds ratio of 1.14,
which of course is a 14% relative increase as opposed to a 14x. So in those situations,
when strength and consistency are out the window, which is essentially true of everything in
nutritional epidemiology, I can't really think of examples in nutritional epi where you have
strength and consistency. Well, major deficiencies I think would belong to the category of very clear
signals, major nutritional deficiencies, if you have like- Yes, yeah, yeah. Very, very, for example.
Sure, sure, yeah. Thiamine deficiency where you're out to lunch, yeah. But do you then look at,
I mean, even biological gradient gets very difficult with the tools of nutritional epi.
Do you start to look at experiment? Plausibilities to me has always struck me as a very dangerous
one because I don't know. It just seems a bit of hand waving. I mean, where do you then look?
I think the first question is whether you can get experimental evidence. To me, that's the priority.
And I realize that in some circumstances when you know that you're dealing with highly likely
harmful factors, you cannot really have equipoise to do randomized trials. But for most situations
in nutrition, to take nutrition as the example that we have been discussing, you can do randomized
trials. And actually, we have done randomized trials. It's not that we're not doing randomized trials.
We have done many thousands of randomized trials. Most of them, unfortunately, are pretty small
and underpowered and they suffer from all the problems that we discussed earlier with
underpowered studies that are selectively reported with no preregistration and with
kind of haphazardly done analysis and reporting. I mean, they're not necessarily better
than observational data that suffer from the same problems. But we also have a substantial number of
very large randomized trials in nutrition. We have over 200 large randomized trials.
Most of those focus on specific nutrients or supplementations. Some are looking at diets like
Mediterranean diet. And with very few exceptions, they do not really show the benefits that were
suspected or were proposed in the observational data. There are exceptions, but there are not that
many. That, to me, suggests that most likely the interpretation that most of the observational
signals are false positives or substantially exaggerated is likely to be true. We shouldn't
be throwing out the baby with the bathwater. There may be some that are worth pursuing and
that may be true. And I think that this means that we need to do more trials. The counter argument
would be that, well, in a randomized trial, especially a large one, especially with long-term
follow-up, people will not adhere to what you tell them to do with their diet or nutrient intake or
supplementation. My response to this is that when it comes to getting evidence about what people
should eat, that lack of adherence is part of the game. It's part of real life. So if a specific
diet is in theory better than another, but people cannot adhere to that, it's not really better
because people cannot use it. So I get the answer to the question that I'm interested in, which is,
is that something that will make a difference? Of course, it does not prove that biochemically,
or in a perfect system, or in the perfect human who is eating like a robot, that would not be
helpful. But I don't care about treating robots. I care about managing and helping real people.
I agree with that completely, John. I would throw in one wrench to that, which is, in a world of so
much ambiguity and misinformation, I do think it's important to separate efficacy from effectiveness.
What you're, of course, saying is, in the real world, only effectiveness matters. So real world
scenarios with real world people. But I still think there is a time and a place for efficacy.
We do have to know what is the optimal treatment under perfect circumstances if we want to have
any chance at, for example, informing policy. I'll give you an example. Food stamps. Should food
stamps preferentially target the use of certain foods over others? Well, again, if you had really
efficacious data saying this type of food is worse than that type of food, you could steer people
towards healthier foods. It could impact the way we subsidize certain foods. In other words, it's
really all about changing the food environment. So it is very hard to follow, I think, any diet
that is not the standard American diet. So any time you opt out of the standard American diet,
whether it be into a Mediterranean diet or a vegetarian diet or a low carbohydrate diet or
basically anything that's not the crap that we're surrounded by requires an enormous effort.
And I think a big part of that is because there is still so much ambiguity around what the optimal
nutritional strategies are. We haven't answered the efficacy question because I think we keep
trying to answer the effectiveness question. I agree. And I think I would not abandon efforts
to get some insights on efficacy, but we're not really getting these insights the way that we have
been doing things. I think that if you want to get answers on efficacy, there are options. One is
through the experimental approach. So you can still run randomized trials, but you can do them
under very controlled supervised circumstances that people are in a physiology or metabolism
clinic, that they're being followed very stringently on what they eat and what happens to them.
And you can measure very carefully these biochemical and physiological responses.
I think that a second approach in the observational world or between the observational and the
randomized is Mendelian randomization studies with the advent of genetics. We have lots of genetic
instruments that may be used to create designs that are fairly equivalent to a randomized design.
So you can get some estimates that are not perfect because Mendelian randomization has its own
assumptions and sometimes these are violated. But at least I think that they go a step
forward in terms of the credibility of the signals that you get. And then you have the pure
observational evidence, which I don't want us to discard it completely. I think that these are data
which you need to use and we just need to interpret them very cautiously. If we use some of the
machinery that we have learned to deploy in other fields, for example, one approach is what I call
the environment-wide or exposure-wide association testing instead of testing and reporting on one
nutrient at a time. You just run an analysis of all the nutrients that you have collected information
on and you can also do it for all the outcomes that you have collected information on. So that
would be an exposure outcome-wide association study and then you report the results taking into
account the multiplicity and also the correlation structure between all these different exposures
and outcomes. You get a far more transparent and complete picture and if you get signals that seem
to be recurrent and replicable across multiple datasets, multiple cohorts that you run these
analysis, you start having higher chances of these signals to be reflecting some reality. Still,
it's not going to be perfect because of all the problems that we mentioned. But it is better
compared to what we do now where we just go after finding yet one more association one at a time and
coming up with yet another paper that is likely to be very low credibility.
John, if your 2005 paper on the frequency with which we were going to come across valid scientific
publications is arguably the one that's, is that your most cited paper?
No, it's not the most highly cited. It's received I think close to 10,000 citations but,
for example, the Prisma statement for meta-analysis has received far more.
Okay. Well, if that, I was going to assume that the 2005 paper was the most cited but I was going
to say the most entertaining is your 2012 paper which is the systematic cookbook review.
Again, this is just one of those things where I remember the moment this paper came out and just
the absolute belly laughing that I had reading this and frankly the sadness I had reading this
because it is a sarcastic commentary in a way on a problem that I think plagues this entire field.
In this paper, you basically, I don't know if it was randomly but you selected basically 50 common
ingredients from a cookbook. Was there any method behind how you did this or was it purely random?
Well, we use the Boston cookbook that has been published since the 19th century and we
randomly chose ingredients by selecting pages and then within those the recipes and the
ingredients that were in these recipes. So, yes, it is 50 ingredients, a random choice thereof,
and trying to map how many of those have had published studies in the scientific literature
in terms of their association with cancer risk. And not surprisingly, almost all of them had
some published studies associating them with cancer risk. Even the exceptions were probably
exceptions because of the way that we searched. For example, we didn't find any study on
on vanilla but there were studies on vanillin. So, if we had changed with a, if we had screened with
the names of the biochemical constituents of these ingredients probably, I guess all of them
might have had some studies associating them with cancer risk. How was this paper received
by the nutritional epidemiology community? I think it created lots of enemies and lots of friends
and I'm grateful for the enemies who some of them have pushed back with constructive comments. I
think that most people realize that we have a problem. I think that even people who disagree
with me on nutrition, I have great respect for them and I'm sure that they're well intentioned.
I think that at the bottom of their heart, it's not that they want to do harm. They want to save
lives. They want to improve nutrition. They want to improve our world. So, I think that it should
be feasible to reach some synthesis of these different approaches and these different trends.
And I do see that even people who have used traditional methods do start using some of
the methods that we have proposed. For example, these exposure-wide approaches or trying to come
up with large consortia and meta-analysis of multiple cohorts to strengthen the results and
the standardization of the results. I worry a little bit about some of the transparency of these
efforts. To give you one example, I have always argued that if you can have large-scale meta-analysis
of multiple teams, ideally all the teams joining forces and publishing a common analysis with common
standards and ideally these would be the best standards and the best statistical tools thrown
at the analysis, this is much better than having fragmented publications. So, in some questions of
nutrition, I have seen that happen, but here's what goes wrong. The invitation goes to other
investigators who have already found results that square with the beliefs of the inviting
investigator. So, there may be 3,000 teams out there and the invitation goes to the 100 teams
that have claimed and believe that there is that association. And then these data are cleaned,
combined, and analyzed in the way that has found the significant association already.
And you have a conclusion with an astronomically low p-value that here it is. We have concluded
that our claim for a significant association is indeed true and here's a large meta-analysis.
Now, this is equally misleading or even more misleading than the single studies because you
have cherry-picked studies based on what you already know to be the case. And putting them
together, you just magnify the cherry-picking. You just solidify the cherry-picking. So, one has
to be very cautious. Magnitude and amount of evidence alone does not make things better.
Actually, it can make things worse. You need to ask what is the foundational construct of how that
evidence has been generated and identified and synthesized. And in some cases, it may be worse
than the single small studies that are fragmented because some of them may not be affected by the
same biases. There also seem to be institutional issues around this. I mean, your alma mater
has a very strong point of view on nutritional epidemiology. I think this is unavoidable. There
are schools of thought in any scientific field and Harvard has an amazing team of nutritional
epidemiologists. I have great respect for them, even though probably we do not agree on many
issues. I think that we should look beyond, let's say, the personal differences or opinion
differences. I think that my opinion has less weight than anyone else's weight in that regard.
If I want to be true to my standards, I'm not trying to promote something because it is an
opinion. What I'm arguing is for better data, for better evidence, for better synthesis,
and more unbiased steps in generating the evidence, synthesizing the evidence, and interpreting it.
And I'm willing to see whatever result emerges by that process. I'm not committed to any particular
result. I would be extremely happy if we do these steps and we come up with a conclusion that
99% of the nutritional associations that were proposed were actually correct. I have absolutely
no problem with that if we do it the right way. What I'm worried is resistance to doing it the
right way. I think your point earlier though about the difference between, say, how the genetics
community and the nutrition community were able to approach this problem, I don't think you can
forget your second point, which is it's very difficult to overcome prior beliefs. When an
individual has made an entire career of a set of beliefs, I think it requires a very special
person to be able to say that may have been incorrect. And that is independent of what
that belief is, by the way. That can be a belief that may be correct or may be fundamentally
incorrect. It's funny. I recently saw this thing on Netflix. It was the documentary about this
D.B. Cooper case. Do you remember? Do you know this D.B. Cooper case? It's the only unsolved
act of US aviation crime that's never been solved. Did you know this case, John? The guy who
hijacked an airplane and then jumped out the back in 1971?
I may have heard of it somewhere, but yeah, I don't recall it very well.
Well, it's interesting in that this guy hijacks an airplane with a bomb and requests that the
plane be landed while they pick up $200,000 in four parachutes. He then gets the plane to take
back off and jumps out the back with the money. And he's never been found. Nine years later,
they found a little bit of the money. That's the only real clue. And this documentary focused on
four suspects, four of many suspects. And you basically hear the story of each of the four
suspects and each of the people who today are making the case for why it was their uncle or
their husband or whatever. And my wife and I are watching this and we're thinking it's interesting.
And at the end, I just said to her, I said, you know, this is a great
sort of example of human nature, which is I believe every one of those people truly believes
that it was their relative or friend or whomever who was D.B. Cooper. And yet I think all of them
are wrong. I think each of those four suspects is categorically not the person. And yet each of
them, I am convinced by their sincerity. And I think that's the problem is I don't think science
should be able to be that way. That's the problem I think I have with epidemiology is that I guess
I'm just not convinced it's a science in the way that we talk about science. Well, we have to be
cautious because we are human and scientists have beliefs. And I think that there's nothing wrong
with having beliefs. I think the issue is, can we map these beliefs? Can we be transparent?
Can we be as much restrained about how these beliefs are influencing the contact of our
research and the way that we interpret our findings? It will never be perfect. We're not perfect. And
I think that aiming to be perfect is not tenable. But at a minimum, we should try to impose as many
safeguards in the process as to minimize the chances that we will fool ourselves, not fool
others, but fool ourselves to start with as Feynman would say. This is not easy in fields that have a
very deeply entrenched belief system. And I think nutrition is one such. Again, there's no bad
intention here. People are well-intentioned. They want to do good. I will open a parenthesis. Of
course, there is some bad intentions. There's big food. There's industry who wants to promote
their products and sell whatever they produce. And that's a different story. And it is another,
a huge confounder both in nutrition and in other fields that we have very high penetrance of
financial conflicts. But I think that non-financial conflict can also be important. And
at a minimum, we should try to be transparent about them, try to communicate both to the external
world, but also to our own selves what might be our non-financial conflicts and beliefs in starting
to go down a specific path of investigation and a specific interpretation of results.
You referred to it very, very briefly earlier. What were the exact details of the case of Brian
Wonsick at Cornell? That was a lot to do. And it seemed that that went one step further. That
seemed like there was something quite deliberate going on. Well, in that case, it was revealed
based on the communication of that professor with his students that practically he was urging them
to cut corners and to torture the data until they would get some nice looking result. And
practically he was packaging nice looking results as soon as they would become available based on
that data torturing process. So the data torturing was the central force in generating these dozens
of papers that were creating a lot of interest and probably they were very influential, many of them
in terms of decision making. But if you create results and significance in that fashion,
obviously the chances that these would be reproducible results is very, very limited.
Yeah. And of course, he was a very prominent person in the field. It makes you wonder how often
is this going on with someone maybe less prominent where they're part of that 35 million people who
are out there authoring the, what are we about 100,000 papers a month make their way onto PubMed?
I mean, it's an avalanche, right? We have a huge production of scientific papers, as you say. And
if you look across all sciences, probably we're talking about easily 5 million papers added every
year. And the number is accelerating every single year. Of course, very few of them are both valid
and useful. And it's very difficult to sort through all that mountain of published information.
I think that research practices are substandard in most scientific fields for most of the research
being done. There's a number of surveys that have been conducted asking whether fraud is happening
and whether suboptimal research practices are being applied. The results are different depending
on whether you ask the person being interviewed on whether they are doing this or whether people
in their immediate environment are doing this. So fraud, I think is uncommon. I don't think that
fraud is a common thing in science. It does happen now and then, but I don't think that it is a major
threat in terms of the frequency. It is a threat in terms of the visibility that it gets and the
damage that it gets to the reputation of science as an enterprise. But it's not common. What is
extremely common is questionable research practices or harmful research practices, which means cutting
corners in different ways. And depending on how exactly you define that, the percentage of people
who might be cutting corners at some point is extremely high. It may be approaching even 100%
if you define it very broadly. And if you include situations where people are not really cognizant
about the damage that they do or the suboptimal character of the approach that they're taking and
how it subverts the results and or the conclusions of the study. Now, how do you deal with that? Do
you deal with that with putting people away to jail or making them lose their jobs or making them pay
$1 million fines? I don't think that that would work because you would probably need to fire the
vast majority of the scientific workforce. And all of these are good people. They're not there
because they're frauds. But you need to work through training, through sensitizing the community,
having a grassroots movement about realizing what the problems are, how you can avoid these traps,
and how you can use better methods, how you can use better inference tools, and how you can
enhance the credibility of your field at large. Not only your own research, but the whole field
needs to move to a higher level. And I think that no scientific field is perfect. There are different
stages of maturity, at different stages of engagement with better methods. And this is happening
in a continuous basis. It's an evolution process. So it's not at one time that we did one thing and
then science is going to be clean and perfect from now on. It is a continuous struggle. And
every day you can do things better or you can do things worse.
Of those 35 million people who are out there publishing science today, how many of them do
you think are really fit to be principal investigators and be the ones that are making
the decisions about where the resources go, what the questions are that should be asked,
and what the real and final interpretation is. I mean, that has to be a relatively small
fraction of that large number, right? Well, 35 million is the number of author IDs in Scopus.
And even that one is a biased estimate. Like any estimate, it could be that you have a much,
much smaller number of people who are what we call principal investigators. The vast majority
of people who have authored at least one scientific paper have just authored a single
scientific paper and they have just been co-authors. So they may be students or staff
or supporting staff in larger enterprises and they never assume their role of leading research
or designing research or being the key players in doing research. There's a much smaller core
of people who I would call principal investigators. We're talking probably at a global level, if you
take all sciences into account, probably there are less than 1 million. But still, this is a
huge number, of course. Their level of training, their level of how familiar they are with best
methods, their beliefs and priors and biases, it's very difficult to fathom. Some people argue that
we need less research that probably we should cut back and really be more demanding and asking
for credentials and for training and for methodological rigor for people to be able
to lead research teams. I'm a bit skeptical about any approach that is starting with a claim,
we need to cut back on research because I think that research and science eventually is the best
thing that has happened to humans. Science is the best thing that has happened to humans.
I think that if we say we need to cut back on research because research is suboptimal,
we may end up in a situation where you create an even worse environment,
where you have even more limited resources and you still have all these millions of people
struggling to get these even more limited resources, which means that they have even
more incentives to cut corners, they have even more incentives to come up with striking,
splashing results, and then you have an even more unreliable literature.
So, less is not necessarily the solution, actually it may be problematic. Improved standards,
improved circumstances of doing research, an improved environment of doing research is probably
what we should struggle for, creating the background where someone who's really a great scientist
and knows what he or she is doing will get support and will be allowed to thrive.
Also, allowed to look at things that have a high risk of failing. I think that if we continue
incentivizing people to get significant results, no matter how that is defined, we are incentivizing
people to do the wrong thing. We should incentivize them to try really interesting ideas and to have
a high chance of failing. This is perfectly fine. I think if you don't fail, you're not going to
succeed. So, we need to be very careful with interventions that happen at a science-wide
level or even discipline-wide level. We do not want to destroy science, we want to improve science,
and some of the solutions, they run the risk of doing harm sometimes.
Based on your comment about the risk appetite that belongs in science,
to me, it suggests an important role for philanthropy because industry obviously has
a very clear risk appetite that is going to be driven by a financial return. By definition,
everybody involved in that is a fiduciary, whether it be to a private or public shareholder,
and therefore, it's not the time to take risk for the sake of discovery.
Conversely, at the other end of that spectrum, it might seem like the government in the pure
public sector should be funding risk. But given the legislative process by which that
money is given out and the lack of scientific training that is in the people who are ultimately
decision-makers for that money, it also seems like a suboptimal place to generate risk. That
seems to be the place where you actually want to demonstrate a continued winning career, even if
you're not advancing knowledge in the most insightful way. What that leaves is an enormous
gap for risk, which I think has to be filled with philanthropic work. Do you agree with that?
I agree that philanthropy is very important. No strings attached to philanthropy can really be
catalytic in generating science that would be very difficult to fund otherwise. Of course,
public funding is also essential, and I think that we should make our best to make a convincing case
that public funding should increase and not decrease. As I said, decreasing public funding
makes things far, far worse for many reasons. I think that we need to realign some of our
priorities on what is being funded with each one of these mechanisms. Currently, a lot of public
funding is given to generate translational products that are then exploited immediately by
companies who make money out of them. Conversely, the testing of these products is paid by the
industry. I find that very problematic because the industry is financing and controlling the studies,
primarily randomized trials or other types of evaluation research that are judging whether
these products that they're making money of are going to be promoted, used, become
blockbusters and so forth, which inherently has a tremendous conflict. I would argue that the
industry should really pay more for the translational research, for developing products through the
early phases, and then public funding should go to testing whether these products are really worth
it, whether they are beneficial, whether they have benefits, whether they have no harms or very limited
harms. That research needs to be done with funding and unconflicted investigators, ideally through
public funds. Of course, philanthropy can also contribute to that. Philanthropy, I think, can
play a major role in allowing people to pursue high-risk ideas and things that probably
other funders would have a hard time to fund. I think that public funds should also go to high-risk
ideas. The public should be informed that science is a very high-risk enterprise. If you try to
create a narrative, and I think that this is the traditional narrative, that money from taxpayers
are used only for paying research grants, that each one of them is delivering some important
deliverables. I think this is a false narrative. Most grants, if they really look at interesting
questions, they will deliver nothing. Or at least they will deliver that, sorry, we tried,
we spent so much time, we spent so much effort, but we didn't really find something that is
interesting. We'll try again. We did our best. We had the best tools. We had the best scientists.
We applied the best methods. But we didn't find the new laws of physics. We didn't find a new drug.
We didn't find a new diagnostic test. We found nothing. That should be a very valid conclusion.
If you do it the right way, with the right tools, with the right methods, with the best scientists
being involved, putting down legitimate effort, we should be able to say we found nothing. But
out of 1,000 grants, we have five that found something. And that's what makes the difference.
It's not that each one of them made a huge contribution. It is these five out of 1,000
in some fields, and in other fields, obviously, maybe a higher yield that eventually transformed
the world. I mean, this seems like a bit of a communications problem, because that's clearly
the venture capital model that seems to work very well, which is on any given fund, your fund is
made back by one company or one bet. It's not an average. It's a very asymmetric bet. And similarly,
when you look at other landmark public high-risk funding things, the Manhattan Project, the Space
Project, these were upsettingly high-risk projects. And yet, I don't get the sense that the public
wasn't standing behind those. So it almost seems like there's a disconnect in the way scientists
communicate their work to the public versus the way NASA did. I mean, NASA was a PR machine.
And obviously, in the case of the Manhattan Project, I think you're in the duress of war.
But we can't lose sight of the fact that the scientific community was the one that stood up.
The physicists of the day are the ones that said to Roosevelt, like, this has to be done.
I mean, Einstein took a stand. So I don't know. I guess it all comes back to scientists need to
lead a bit and lead to be better communicators with the public, right?
Science communication is a very difficult business. And I think that especially in environments that
are polarized, that have lots of conflicts, inherent conflicts, lots of stakeholders in
in the community are trying to achieve the most for themselves and for their own benefits.
It can be very tricky. Scientists have a voice, but that voice is often drowned in the middle of
all the screams and Twitter and social media and media and agendas and lobbies and everything.
How do we strengthen that? I think that there's two paths here. One is to use the same tricks as
lobbies do. And the other is to stick to our guns and behave as scientists. We are scientists,
we should behave as scientists. I cannot prove that one is better than the other. I think that
both myself and many others feel very uneasy when we are told to really cross the borders
of science and try to become communicators that are lobbying even for science. It's not easy.
You want to avoid exaggeration. You want to say that I don't know. I'm doing research because I
don't know. I'm an expert, but I don't know. And this is why I believe that we need to know, because
these are questions that could make a difference for you. How do you tell people that most likely
I will fail, that most likely a hundred people like me will fail, but maybe one will succeed.
We need to keep our honesty. We need to make communication clear-cut. We need to also fight
against people who are not scientists and who are promising much more. And they would say that,
oh, you need to do this because it will be clearly a success. And they're not scientists, but they're
very good lobbies. It's very difficult. It's difficult times for science. It's difficult
times to defend science. I think that we need to defend our method. We need to defend our principles.
We need to defend the honesty of science in trying to communicate it rather than build
exaggerated promises or narratives that are not realistic. Then even if we do get the funds,
we have just told people lies. I completely agree. I don't think what you and I are saying
is mutually exclusive. I think that's the point. You said it a moment ago, Feynman's famous line
that the most important rule in science is not to fool anyone. And that starts with yourself.
You're the easiest person to fool. And once you fooled yourself, the game is over.
I think the humility that you talk about communicating with the public is the necessary
step. I guess for me, just having my daughter who's now just starting to understand or ask
questions about science is so much fun to be able to talk about this process of discovery and to
remind ourselves that it's not innate. This is not an innate skill. This is something. This
methodology didn't exist 500 years ago. So for all but 0.001% of our genetic lineage, we didn't
even have this concept. So that gives us a little bit of empathy for people who have no training,
because if you weren't trained in something, there's no chance you're going to understand
it without this explanation. But I feel strongly that there can't be a vacuum,
because the vacuum always gets filled. And if the scientists aren't the one speaking,
if the good scientists aren't the one speaking, then it's either going to be the bad ones and or the
charlatans who will. Before we leave EPI, there's one thing I want to go back to that I think is
another really interesting paper of yours. This is one from two years ago. This is the challenge
of reforming nutritional epidemiologic research. And this is the one where you looked at the
single foods and the claims that emerged in terms of epidemiology. Some of these things
were simply absurd. Do you remember this paper that I'm talking about, John? You've written
a couple along these lines. But this is the one where you found a publication that suggested
eating 12 hazelnuts per day extended life by 12 years, which was the same as drinking three
cups of coffee and eating one mandarin orange per day could extend lifespan by five years.
Whereas consuming one egg would shorten it by six years and two strips of bacon would shorten life
by a decade, which, by the way, was more than smoking. How do you explain these results? And
more importantly, what does it tell us again about this process? Well, these estimates obviously
are tongue in cheek. They're not real estimates. They're a very crude translation of what the
average person in the community would get if they see the numbers that are reported,
typically with relative risks in the communication of these findings. They're not epidemiologically
sound. The true translation to change in life expectancy would be much smaller. But even then,
they would probably be too big compared to what the real benefits might be or the real harms might
be with these nutrients. I think it just shows the magnitude of the problem that if you have a
system that is so complicated with so inaccurate measurements, with so convoluted and overtly
correlated variables with selective reporting and biases superimposed, you get a situation pretty much
like what we described in the nutrients and cancer risk where you get an implausible big picture,
where you're talking about huge effects that are unlikely to be true. So it goes back to what we
have been discussing about how you remedy that situation, how you bring better methods and better
training and better inferences to that land of irreproducible results. Now in, gosh, it might
have been 2013, 14, a very interesting study was published called Predemed, which we'll spend a
minute on. It was interesting in that it was a clinical trial. It had three arms and it relied
on hard outcomes. Hard outcomes meaning mortality or morbidity of some sort rather than just soft
outcomes like a biomarker. If you had told me before the results came out, this is the study,
you're going to have a low fat arm and two Mediterranean arms that are going to be split
this way and this way, and we're going to be looking at primary prevention. I would have said
the likelihood you'll see a difference in these three groups is quite low because it just didn't
strike me as a very robust design. But I guess to the author's credit, they had selected people
that were sick enough that within, I think they had planned to go as long as seven or so years,
but under five years they ended up stopping this study given that the two arms in the Mediterranean
arm, one that was randomized to receive olive oil, the other, I believe, received nuts, performed
significantly better than the low fat arm. And that's sort of how the story went until a couple
of years later. What happened then? So here you have a situation where I have to disclose my
own bias that I love the Mediterranean diet and I have been a believer that this should be a great
diet to use. I mean, I grew up in Athens and obviously it's something that I enjoy personally
a lot. And I would be very happy to see huge benefits with it. For many years I was touting
these results as here you go, you have a large trial that can show you big benefits on a clinical
outcome. And actually this is Mediterranean diet, which is the diet that I prefer personally,
even better. And just to make the point, it was both statistically and clinically very significant.
Indeed. Beautiful result, very nice looking, and I was very, very happy with that. I would use it
as an argument that here, here's how you can do it the right way. And so clinically relevant
results. But then it was realized that unfortunately this trial was not really a randomized trial.
The randomization had been subverted that a number of people had not actually been randomized because
of problems in the way that they were recruited. And therefore the data were problematic. You had
a design where some of the trial was randomized and some of the trial was actually observational.
So, the journal of medicine retracted and republished the study with lots of additional
analysis that tried to take care of that subversion of randomization in different ways, excluding these
people from the calculations and also using approaches to try to correct for the imposed
observational nature of some of the data. The results did not change much, but it creates,
of course, a very uneasy feeling that if really the Cram-de-La-Cram trial, the one that I adored
and I admired, had such a major problem, such a major basic, unbelievably simple problem in its very
fundamental structure of how it was run. How much trust can you put on other aspects of the trial
that require even more sophistication and even more care, for example, arbitration of outcomes
or how you count outcomes. As you say, this is a trial that originally was reported with limited
follow-up compared to the original intention. It was stopped at an interim analysis. The trial has
had lengthier follow-up. It has published a very large number of papers as secondary analysis,
but still we lack what I would like to see as a credible result. It's a tenuous, partly randomized
trial and unfortunately doesn't have the same credibility now compared to what I thought when
it was a truly randomized trial and there was one outcome that was reported and that seemed to be
very nice. Now it's a partly randomized, partly subverted trial with 200-300 publications
floating around with very different claims each time, most of them looking very nice but
fragmented into that space of secondary analysis. It doesn't mean that Mediterranean diet does not
work. I still like to eat things that fit to a Mediterranean diet and this is my bias.
It just gives one example of how things can go wrong even when you have good intentions. I think
that I can see that people really wanted to do it wrong but one has to be very cautious.
Yeah. I think for me, the takeaway, if I remember some of the details, which I might not, one of
the big issues was the randomization around the inner household subjects. You couldn't have people
in the same house eating the different diets, which is a totally reasonable thought. It just
strikes me as sloppiness that it wasn't done correctly in the first place. The cost and
duration of doing a study like that is so significant that it's just a shame that on
the first go, it's not nailed because it could be seven years at $100 million to do that again.
This is true but one has to take into account that in such an experiment, you have a very large
number of people who are involved and their level of methodological training and their ability to
understand what needs to be done may vary quite a bit. It's very difficult to secure that everyone
involved in all the sites involved in the trial would do the right thing. I think that this is an
issue also for other randomized trials that are multi-center. Very often now, we realize that
because of the funding structure, since as we said, there's very little funding from public
agencies, most of the multi-center trials are done by the industry. They try to impose some
rigor and some standards, but they also have to recruit patients from a very large number of sites,
sometimes from countries and from teams that have no expertise in clinical research.
Then you can have situations where a lot of the data may not necessarily be fraudulent,
but they're collected by people who are not trained, who have no expertise, who don't know
what they're doing. Sometimes depending on the study design, especially with unmasked trials or
trials that lack allocation concealment or both, you can have severe bias interfere even in studies
that seemingly appear to be like the creme de la creme of large-scale experimental research.
John, let's move on to one last topic, at least for now, which is the events of 2020.
In early April, I had this idea talking with someone on my team, which was,
boy, the seroprevalence of this thing might be far higher than the confirmed cases of this thing.
And if that were true, it would mean that the mortality from this virus is significantly
lower than what we believe. This was at a time when I think there was still a widespread belief
that five to 10% of people infected with this virus would be killed. And there were basically
a nonstop barrage of models suggesting two to three million Americans would die of this by the
end of the year. The first person I reached out to was David Allison. And I said, hey, David,
what do you think about doing an assessment of seropositivity in New York City? And he said,
let's call John Ayanetes. So we gave you a call that afternoon. It was a Saturday afternoon. We
all hopped on a Zoom and you said, well, guess what? I'm doing this right now in Santa Clara.
And I don't think it had been published yet, right? I mean, I think you had just basically
got the data, right? I believe there was about that time. Yes. Tell me a little bit about that
study and what did it show? Because it was certainly one of the first studies to suggest
that basically the seropositivity was much higher than the confirmed cases.
This is a pair of two studies, actually. One was done in Santa Clara and the other was done in LA
County. And both of them, the design aimed to collect a substantial number of participants
and try to see how many of them had antibodies to the virus, which means that they had been
infected perhaps at least a couple of weeks ago. And they were studies that Aaron Ben-David and
Jay Bhattacharya led. And also we had colleagues from the University of South California also
leading the study in LA County. They were studies that I thought were very important to do. I was
just one of many co-investigators, but I feel very proud to have worked with that team. They
were very devoted and they really put together in the field an amazing amount of effort and very
readily could get some results that would be very useful to tell us more about how widely spread the
viruses. The results, I'm not sure whether you would call them surprising, shocking, anticipated.
Depends on what your prior would be. Personally, I was open to the possibilities of any result.
I had no clue how widely spread the virus would be. And this is why I thought these studies were
so essential. I had already published more than a month ago that by that time that we just don't
know. We just don't know whether we're talking about a disease that is very widely spread or
very limited in its spread, which also translates in an inverse mode to its infection fatality rate.
If it's very widely spread, the infection fatality rate per person is much lower. If it is very
limited in its spread, it means that fewer people are affected, but the infection fatality rate would
be very high. So whatever the answer would be, it would be an interesting answer. And the result was
that the virus was very widely spread, far more common compared to what we thought based on the
number of tests that we were doing and the number of PCR documented cases at that time.
In the early months of the pandemic, we were doing actually very few tests. So it's not surprising at
all that the under ascertainment would be huge. I think that once we started doing more tests and or
in countries that did more testing, the under ascertainment was different compared to places
that were not doing much testing or were doing close to no testing at all. I think that the result
was amazing. I felt that that was a very unique moment seeing these results when I first saw that
that's what we got, that it was about 50 times more common than we thought based on the documented
cases. But obviously generated a lot of attention and a lot of animosity because people had very
strong priors. I think it was very unfortunate that all that happened in a situation of a highly
polarized, toxic political environment. Somehow people were aligned with different political
beliefs as if a political belief should also be aligned with a scientific fact. It was just
completely horrible. So it created massive social media and media attention, both good and bad.
And I think that we were bombarded with comments, both good and bad, and criticism. I'm really
grateful for the criticism because obviously these were very delicate results that we had to
be sure that we had the strongest documentation for what we were saying. And we went through a
number of iterations to try to address these criticisms in the best possible way. In the long
term, with several months down the road, inside we see that these results are practically completely
validated. We have now a very large number of seroprevalence studies that have been done
in very different places around the world. We see that those studies that were done in early days
had, as I said, the worst under-essertainment. We had tremendous under-essertainment in several
places around the world. Even in Santa Clara, there's another data set that was included in
the national survey of a study that was published in The Lancet about a month ago on hemodialysis
patients. And the infection rate, if you translated, that was a couple of months after
our study, if you translate it to an infection fatality rate, is exactly identical to what we
had observed in early April. So the study has been validated. It has proven that the virus is
very rapidly and very widely spreading virus. And you need to deal with it based on that profile.
It is a virus that can infect huge numbers of people. My estimate is as of early December,
probably we may have close to 1 billion people who have already been infected, more or less,
around the world. And there's a very steep risk gradient. There's lots of people who have
practically no risk or minimal risk of having a bad outcome. And there are some people who have
tremendous risk of being devastated. We have, for example, people in nursing homes who have
25% infection fatality rate. One out of four of these people, if they're infected,
they will die. So it was one of the most interesting experiences in my career,
both of the fascination about seeing these results and also the fascination
and some of the intimidation of some of the reaction to these results in a very toxic
environment, unfortunately. I don't necessarily mean by name, but what forces were the most
critical? Presumably these would be entities or individuals that wanted to continue to promote
the idea that the risk here warranted greater shutdown, slowdown, helped me understand a little
bit more where some of the vitriol came from. I think that there were many scientists who made
useful comments. And as I said, I'm very grateful for these comments because they helped improve the
paper. And then there were many people in social media that include some scientists who actually,
however, were not epidemiologists. Unfortunately, in the middle of this pandemic, we have seen lots
of scientists who have no relationship to epidemiology become kind of Twitter or Facebook
epidemiologists all of a sudden and have very vocal opinions about how things should be done.
I remember a scientist who was probably working in physics or not, who was sending emails every
two hours to the principal investigator and I was CC'd in them saying, you have not corrected the
paper yet. And every two hours, you have not corrected the paper yet. I mean, his comment was
wrong to start with. But as we were working on revisions, as you realize, we did that with
ultra speed responding within record time to create the revised version and to post it. But even
posting it takes five days, more or less. But what do you think was at the root of this
anger directed towards you and the team? Unfortunately, I think that the main reasons
were not scientific. I think that most of the animosity was related to the toxic political
environment at the moment. And personally, I feel that it is extremely important to
completely dissociate science from politics. Science should be free to say what has been found
with all the limitations and all the caveats, but be precise and accurate.
I would never want to think about what a politician is saying in a given time or given
circumstances and then modify my findings based on what one politician or another politician is
saying. So I think that one of the attacks that I received was that I have conservative ideology,
which is like the most stupendous claim that I can think of, you know, looking at my track record
and how much I have written about climate change and climate urgency and emergency and the problem
with gun sales and actually, you know, gun sales becoming worse in the environment of the pandemic
and the need to promote science and the need to diminish injustice and the need to provide
health, good health to all people and to decrease poverty. You know, claimingly that I'm a supporter
of conservative ideology, sick conservative ideology is completely weird. And then smearing
of all sorts that the owner of an airline company had given five thousand dollars to Stanford,
which I was not even aware of. The funding of the trial, which I was not even the PI,
was through a crowdsourcing mechanism going to the Stanford Development Office, which I'd never
heard of who were the people who had funded that. And of course, none of that money came to me or to
all the other investigators who completely volunteered our time. We have received zero
dollars for our research, but tons of smearing. Sorry, just to clarify, John, you're saying the
accusation was that because an airline had contributed five thousand dollars to Stanford,
for which you saw none of it, that your assessment was really a way to tell everybody
that the airlines should be back to flying. Yes. But, you know, I heard about it when
the bus did report. Yeah, of course. Yeah, of course. No, I get it. I get it.
So it's very weird. And, you know, because of all the attacks that we received, you know,
I received tons of emails that were hate mail and some of them threatening to me and my family.
My mother, she's 86 years old and there was a hoax circulated in social media
that she had died of coronavirus and her friends started calling at home to ask when the funeral
would be. And when she heard that from multiple friends, she had a life threatening, hypertensive
crisis. So these people really had a very toxic response that did a lot of damage to me and to
my family and to others as well. And I think that it was very unfortunate. I asked Stanford to try to
find out what was going on. And there was a fact finding process to try to realize, you know, why
is that happening? And of course, it concluded that there was absolutely no conflict of interest
and nothing that had gone wrong in terms of any potential conflict of interest. But this doesn't
really solve the more major problem. For me, the most major problem is how do we protect
scientists? It's not about me. It is about other scientists, some of them even more prominently
attacked. I think one example is Tony Fauci. He was my supervisor. I have tremendous respect for him.
He was my supervisor when I was at NIAID at NIH. He's a brilliant scientist and he has been
ferociously attacked. There's other scientists who are much younger. They're not, let's say,
as powerful. They would be very afraid to disseminate their scientific findings objectively
if they have to ponder what the environment is at the moment and what do different politicians say
and how will my results be seen. We need to protect those. We need to protect people who
would be very much afraid to talk and they would be silenced if we see examples that, you know,
can you see what happened to Johnny and Edie's or what happened to Tony Fauci? If I were to say
something, I would be completely devastated. So I think that we need to be tolerant. We need to
give science an opportunity to do its job, to find useful information, to correct mistakes,
or improve on methods. I mean, this is part of the scientific process, but not really throw all
that smearing and all that vicious vitriol to scientists. It's very dangerous. Regardless of
whether it comes from people in one or another political party or one in another ideology,
it ends up being the same. It ends up being populist attacks of the worst possible sort,
regardless of whether they come from the left or right or middle or whatever part of the
political spectrum. Well, I'm very sorry to hear that you had to go through that, especially at
the level of your family. I was actually, I knew that you had been attacked a little bit. I was not
aware that it had spread to the extent that you described it. What do we do going forward here? I
mean, it still seems to be a largely partisan issue. There's a very clear left versus right
approach to this that seems mostly science agnostic. I think it's viewed as unwise to have
a changing opinion outside of science. I mean, in science, that's a hallmark of a great thinker.
Someone who can change their mind in the presence of new information, that's a core competency of
doing good science. In fact, much of what we've spoken about today is the toxicity of not being
able to update your priors and change your mind in the face of new information. But yet somehow in
politics, that is considered the biggest liability of all time. Somehow in politics, anytime you
change your mind, it's wishy washy and you're weak and you don't know your ideology. There seems to
be an incompatibility here. In a crisis moment like this, which is this was a crisis that seems
to bring these things to the fore, right? It is true. I don't want to see that in a negative
light necessarily because somehow the coronavirus crisis has brought science to the limelight in some
positive ways as well. I think that people do discuss more about science. It has become a topic
of great interest. People see that their lives depend on science. They feel that their world
depends on science. What will happen in the immediate future and mid-range future depends
on science and how we interpret science and how we use science. In a way, suddenly we have had
hundreds of millions, if not billions of people become interested in science acutely.
But obviously most of those, unfortunately, given our horrible science education, they have no
science education and they use the tools of their traditional society discourse, which is
largely political and sectorized, to try to deal with scientific questions. This is an explosive
mix. I think it creates a great opportunity to communicate more science and better science.
At the same time, it makes science a hostage of all these lobbying forces and all of this turmoil
that is happening in the community. Well, John, what are you most optimistic about?
You have lots of time left in your career. You're going to go on and do many more great things.
You're going to be a provocateur. What are you most excited and optimistic about in terms of
the future of science and the type of work that you're looking to advance?
Well, I'm very excited to make sure that, and it does happen, that there's so many things that I
don't know. And every day I realize that there's even more things that I don't know. I think that
so far, if that continues happening and every day I can find out about more things that I don't know,
things that I thought were so, but actually they were wrong and I need to correct them and find
ways to correct them, then I really look forward to a good future for science and a good future for
humans. I think that we're just at the beginning. We are just at the beginning of knowledge. And
I feel like a little kid who just wants to learn a little bit more, a little bit more each time.
Well, John, the last time we were together in person, we were in Palo Alto and we had a
Mediterranean dinner. So I hope that sometime in 2021, that'll bring us another chance for another
flaky white fish and some lemon potatoes and whatever other yummy things we had that evening.
That would be wonderful. And I hope that it does increase life expectancy as well,
although even if it doesn't, I think it's worth it.
John, thanks so much for your time today.
Thank you, Peter.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper,
person thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every
Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward
slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.