Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Phil Maffetone. Phil is an author, coach, health
practitioner. He wears many hats. Many of you will probably recognize him as he's written a
number of books, the 80s, 90s, and today, basically covering a number of aspects of exercise, sports
medicine, biofeedback, nutrition. I first probably came across Phil's work when I was in college,
and I was interested in aerobic training, trying to improve my cycling performance at the time,
and became pretty interested in the way he was advocating for a very low intensity relative to
what I was doing approach, which of course today in hindsight seems to be quite the logical thing
to do. Phil's background is in biology, has a doctorate in chiropractic, and he also has
trained in Chinese medicine and kinesiology. He was in private practice for about two decades,
and he's now a consultant, along with continuing to write, doing independent research and lecturing.
In this episode, we talk about his journey, how he became interested in this, both as an athlete
himself and then ultimately as a coach. We get into what is maximal aerobic function,
and this overlaps very closely. In fact, you could argue this is a very similar way to describe
the zone to something we speak about in a previous podcast, but coming at it through a sort of
different lens and using heart rate as opposed to lactate to measure it. We get into the importance
of fuel partitioning in addition to different levels of intensity. We talk a little bit about
marathon times and how they've changed over time and what that probably tells us about training.
So I hope you'll enjoy this episode. And without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with
Phil Maffeten. All right, Phil, thanks so much for making time so late in your day. You're in,
where are you? Are you in Portugal right now? I'm in Lisbon, Portugal, and they don't have
dinner here till 9 or 10 at night, which I usually skip. So it's just past lunch for me.
It's great to be with you. So thanks, Peter, for having me. Well, I've been wanting to speak with
you for quite some time. And we've got a lot of listeners who have been excited about getting you
on. A lot of questions have come about. We've talked a lot about aerobic efficiency on this
podcast because obviously it's such an important part of delaying the aging process. So even if
you take it out of the context of performance, I think today we'll talk about both of these things,
performance and health. But it's obviously something that you've been working on for such
a long time. It's been central to the work you've done. But I want to go back and give folks a bit
of a sense of how you cut your teeth on this stuff. So you're obviously an avid runner yourself,
correct? I've been running since high school, I guess. And from track and field in high school
and college. And then when I got out and into practice, I thought, you know, this road running
stuff looks interesting. I'm starting to see patients. Let me let me see what's going on.
And I, you know, I jumped into a 5k and it was a complete disaster because I was a track runner.
And what do we know about distance? And gradually I progressed to the marathon. I trained for a 6
day running race on a track because I had been working with some ultra runners,
Stu Middleman in particular. And it looked like such an exciting event. I thought this, you know,
I'm going to do this. Then I can, you know, my bio could read, I've run everything from 200 meters
to six days. I thought that was cool. Of course, I was by that time, I was so busy with with treating
other athletes that I was just not able to get the time on the training. All the training was on a
track because the race was on a track. Yeah. Tell people what a six day race is. Yeah. A six day race
is a running race where you run on the track and the person who accumulates the most miles or
kilometers is the winner. You can run as you please. You can start and stop anytime. You can
sleep if you want. If you can stay awake, good luck. And I trained some people and it was for
me a fascinating thing clinically. It was really akin to having a mouse in a lab where you, you
know, you do something to this mouse and then you put them back in the cage and have them run on the
wheel for a while. And then you take them out and you do something else, measure something. And,
you know, it was such a great learning experience for me. And it was a great opportunity to really
hone my skills of observation in terms of gait and talking to an athlete, finding out when they
really were tired, unlike what they said. It was just so many really fascinating things. And then
the idea of doing the race seemed quite interesting. And I just ran out of training time. And so what
is the ideal strategy in my mind right now, I'm going through multiple ideas for how one could
approach a six day race. And, you know, one idea that comes to mind is you simply walk 18 hours a
day and sleep six hours a day, or, you know, you walk 20, sleep four and never put yourself under
incredible duress, but also never go too fast. The sort of slow and steady wins the race approach.
And then alternatively, you can see something crazy where you, you know, actually take out a
reasonable clip and run for, you know, an hour and take an hour off. But of course, in that scenario,
you don't really get a full recovery. So what did you discover was the optimal scenario for covering
the most amount of ground in six days? What I discovered was you start the race by walking.
And now you're the only runner who's walking. The gun goes off, everybody starts running,
you're left walking. And that was always a kind of a comical scene for me. And the runners I worked
with, Stu Middleman in particular, who has the maybe still has the American record for that
distance. They were a little embarrassed in the beginning, but the strategy was to start slow,
gradually run faster, start jogging, gradually hit a certain plateau using the heart rate,
that maximum aerobic heart rate that we can talk about at some point. So very easy, relatively easy,
relatively low heart rate. And then now you're two hours into the first run, maybe three hours,
and then you start cooling down. And you take a half an hour to cool down, basically just the
opposite of what you did in the beginning. And now you can get off the track and take a very
short break, and then get back on the track and do the same thing. And that segment would sometimes
be elongated in the beginning in particular, because people are kind of jittery and they want
to do something, and taking a break is not something they want to do. And so there's no
hard running, certainly there's no high heart rate, high intensity training, you do see that in
other athletes. And that's how the days go by. That's it. So you spend a fair amount of time
walking. And with Stu in particular, as an example, Stu really liked the idea of going for 36 hours
without sleep. And I said, okay, let's try it. And it worked out well. So we did that. And then we
took a longer break before getting back into a 24 hour cycle. I'll tell you the interesting thing
for me is that it was exhausting for me, because I really had to be awake longer than he did,
because I couldn't sleep when he slept, because we had a specific time frame for him to sleep,
sometimes as short as seven minutes. And I needed to be awake when he was waking up, because
sometimes he didn't know where he was. And so for me, it was quite a stress. You're interfering
with your circadian rhythm so much that you could literally hallucinate after day four by day five,
potentially. And I've done that. So it's a very different kind of event than most runners have
ever experienced. Yeah, it sounds a lot like Ram, the race across America in cycling, which I
interviewed a guy named Mike Trevino a while ago, who has done Ram a number of times. And his stories
are very similar to that. And again, very different strategies that many cyclists will take. But there's
nobody at the end of that that's not in a significant world of pain. And the hallucinations can lead to
crashes and all sorts of crazy things. And it's pretty high stakes racing. It's an obvious
indication of significant brain stress. But I think the key is to, like with everything else,
individualize it with your athlete. And like I said, Stu had this idea that he wanted to go for 36
hours, which we had talked about a lot beforehand. And that became part of the strategy, because
that's something that he wanted to do. And the way we did it seemed like we weren't going to
sacrifice his health much. And so it was okay for me. And I think in in, whether you're on a bike or
running or whatever you you you need to as a coach as a clinician, and in that kind of race, I served
as a clinician because I did things like biofeedback, neuromuscular biofeedback, obviously, there's
significant stress in that area of the body. You still want to allow the athlete to voice,
you know, how they would like to do this race. And then you want to voice how you think it should
be done. You come to some meeting of the minds. But for me, it was always, I'm not willing to
sacrifice the health of this athlete, because that's, that's against what I do as a clinician.
As a coach, I want him to perform his best. And he was running about 100 miles a day for six days.
That's that's not a bad performance. Wow. At what point did your thinking start to transition from
the training of peak athletes to sort of a broader set of metrics or parameters that could be
applicable to health? Or did that not occur in sort of the fashion I've sort of described it?
It occurred the opposite way. I always loved sports. I love sports myself, I competed at a
very high level. I played other sports. And in undergraduate school, my goal was, hey, I want to
study and get out into the world. And my goal is to help people. It was my goal was to help people
with their health. And I knew there was this fitness thing. And I wasn't sure how it goes
together. But I, I didn't focus it. The athlete component was not really there. And in those early,
early days, when I got into practice and started seeing athletes who were injured, they were local
athletes who were, you know, they were they were five 10k runners, half marathon runners, some of
them were marathoners, you know, this was the boom in the 70s. And there were a lot of patients
because there were a lot of injuries. And so my focus was, why are they getting injured? And I
would gradually see better and better athletes locally. That led to two things. One, some of
those athletes got really good and attained a national class level. And, and then they referred
people that they knew who were professionals. And I started seeing pro athletes who were in
running, of course, because that was the big thing back then. But there was this thing on the west
coast called the triathlon, which just fascinated me to death because I was a swimmer and I was a
cyclist and a runner. And to have three events to work with was just, it was exciting. And I started
seeing some local people who were, you know, I was in the New York City area. So I was on the east
coast where it took a while for the word of triathlon to get there. And when it did, there were some
athletes and that was a lot of fun as well. So this is now sort of late 70s, right? When the
triathlon movement starting in Hawaii, kind of migrating over to California and the west coast.
Yep. And it was still new. It was crazy. And all we, all we really knew about it were these,
these three guys in a bar who were arguing about who's the better athlete, the swimmer,
the cyclist or the runner. And, you know, and that, I don't know how accurate that story is,
but supposedly that's, that's how the event started. And interestingly enough, early on,
there was a double iron man. I worked with somebody who, who did that, but yeah, that was late 70s and
then into the eighties. And by then I was seeing some professionals in most sports by then,
certainly by the, by the mid eighties, I had seen professionals in all sports.
And by the mid eighties, what fraction of your practice is professional athletes or athletes
competing at a very high level versus normal people who are coming to you saying I'm overweight
or I have diabetes or something like that. Gosh, I have to, you know, by then my clinic
was so busy. I was taking on associates or had other doctors in the clinic. You know,
my goal was for them to treat the local patients I had because I was now starting to travel with
athletes, which I hadn't, hadn't done. Mark Allen was a patient of mine by that point. And
I think it was 83. I'd been doing some sports clinics on the road in various cities. San Diego
was one and that's where I first met Mark and Paul and Newbie Frazier and some of those other
folks who were just getting going. And so by the mid eighties, I was on the road a lot.
And certainly by the mid eighties, I was in Boulder every summer because that's where a
lot of athletes went. And so I went there. So by that point, most of the patients I had were
competitive athletes who I was working one on one with. And I was doing a lot of lecturing,
starting to do a lot of writing as well. So at what point did you sort of, I would say,
congeal the idea that said, hey, we need to train at a lower level of intensity for longer
periods of time. You know, we're going to get into obviously the methodology, but I want to talk even
broader than that, which is, did you look at athletes and say, wait a minute, something's a
muck here. These people are training too much or either either volume is too high or intensity is
too high, but something is off and we need to do something that's sort of counterintuitive,
which is dial this back in one or both of those metrics. Was there, did you sort of see that in
the eighties? Oh, I saw it before the eighties. I saw it quite early because I was seeing these
people who were were able to run a marathon in whatever time. And that was like, wow, this guy
could run a marathon. What an example of optimal health. Well, it wasn't because they were broken
down. They were getting sick. You may remember, I mean, back then, you know, it was a badge of
courage to have a high white blood count because you are a runner. And I, I started putting all
these things together and it was pretty clear that something wasn't right. Cooper's aerobic
revolution was not, something wasn't working. You don't just go out and train and everything falls
into place. These people were falling apart. So that, that was in the seventies when I started
seeing that. And I was having a hard time understanding that relationship between being
healthy and being fit. And when I ran the New York city marathon in 1980 and I crossed the finish line,
it just hit me. These athletes are fit, but unhealthy. And that whole concept of fit, but unhealthy and
fitness and health are two separate definitions and they need to be balanced. Whether you're
a grandmother who goes out for a walk four or five times a week, or you're training for the
race of your life as a professional, it's all the same. And many of the things that I developed,
like the, the MIF tests, for example, were never meant for athletes. They were meant for the
average person because I thought whatever we're doing to this person to help them get healthier,
we need an indication, not just a blood test. We don't want to know if their blood picture looks
better. You want a functional test. We want a functional test that at the time didn't really
exist. And so the functional test for me was that they were going to be able to walk faster at the
same low heart rate than they could a month or two earlier. And that was, that was the big thing. And
then soon after that, I said, Hey, wait a minute. These guys are running faster now at the same
heart rate. And I thought, wow, this is, this is interesting.
Can you give folks an explanation? Let's assume that people aren't entirely clear on the nomenclature
between aerobic and anaerobic fitness. This will allow us to, I think more accurately talk about
what submaximal means and maximal and all of these things. People have heard the term VO two max,
but I think it's important to give a bit of a context for where that'll fit on the spectrum.
So can you explain to folks what we mean by aerobic and anaerobic systems?
Yeah. And, and, and I don't want to go into the, the microbe definition, which is where
a lot of us have learned those terms, you know, there are aerobic microbes and anaerobic microbes.
So the anaerobic microbes are without oxygen. And when patients would say, well, I, I want to do
some anaerobic training. I'd say, well, what is, what is that? They said, well, what's without
oxygen. I said, you mean you can hold your breath while you're doing the intervals. And so
we need a better definition. And my definition became fat burning was, was associated with
aerobic and all of the factors that are associated with fat burning. So the aerobic muscle fibers in
the mitochondria and the ability to convert fatty acids into energy, into ATP, and anaerobic was the
glucose side. And that was simple enough. It wasn't scientific enough, but it was simple enough
for what people needed to understand. And especially when we can come up with a heart rate
that says, well, if you go over this heart rate, you're drifting into that anaerobic state. And if
you stay under it, you're in an aerobic state. And therefore you're training your body to burn more
fat as an energy source. And therefore you're going to store less fat and, and you're going to
get rid of any excess fat and so on and so forth. Can you explain to folks what the VO2 max is?
Because I want to spend some time explaining why it's not a great predictor of much,
despite the fact that it certainly produces boasting rights. It produces for sure,
boasting rights. It's a number that people talk about. Everybody talks about it and hardly anybody
gets tested. And almost nobody gets tested with some regularity so they could do something with
the numbers. We can define it academically, which doesn't tell you much, but it's a test that is,
was developed a long time ago. And so there's a lot of tests around. And the real question is,
what does it really mean? And I'm not sure it means a whole, I didn't do many of those tests.
So I, you know, I had an academic education and, and I knew about VO2 max and I knew about
all this traditional stuff, the 220 formula, which I used in the very beginning because I thought that
was the science of, of exercise physiology and quickly learned it wasn't. And VO2 max was right
there and, and VO2 max became the tradition. I think it was the tradition back then. I don't
remember when it was first developed. It was by Hill, wasn't it? Back in.
I actually don't know who developed it in 1920s. But for listeners, I think it's,
it's a relatively straightforward test to administer provided you have the machinery and
the machinery is complicated because you have to be able to isolate gases very well,
specifically oxygen and carbon dioxide. So the test is normally done on either a treadmill
or a stationary bike where you can control the resistance or the, the load that the athlete is
under. The challenge is creating an airtight seal around their nose and their mouth,
because what you're really doing with the test is you want to measure how much oxygen is coming
out of their respiratory system and how much CO2 is coming out because you know how much is going
in. And therefore the difference is the amount of oxygen consumed. Now, if you're sitting here at
rest, you have a VO2, an amount of oxygen that's consumed. And the purpose of the test is to ramp
up the level of exertion until you reach the maximum level of oxygen consumption. So VO2 max
is simply the maximum amount of O2 consumed. And the difference between a very fit person and a
non-fit person is the fitter you are, the more oxygen you're able to consume. And that's basically
a function of your muscles. It's what can the muscles do? So I think a lot of people erroneously
think this is a test of the heart and lungs, but it's not really a test of the heart and lungs,
right? The lungs is where the gas exchange is happening. The heart is the circulatory pump.
It's really a test of what your muscles can do in terms of utilizing that oxygen. And to your point,
it's how much fat oxidation can happen because that's where you're utilizing the oxygen is in
the mitochondria to oxidize fat. But all of that said, the research actually says that you can't
predict marathon finish time by VO2 max. You're right. And people don't like hearing that because
they have this idea that this set, now this VO2 max is directly associated with performance. So
they need to rev up their VO2 max by doing hard training, which will get them performing better.
And that, you know, that's where the whole system breaks down. That's the problem we have. This VO2
max is a, it's something we have been worshiping and we're worshiping the wrong thing.
So tell folks what MAF stands for. MAF stands for maximum aerobic function.
And in essence, the goal of being healthy, the goal of being fit is to develop the aerobic system.
This is what our ancestors did. This is how we got here. We developed a really
incredibly powerful aerobic system by doing the things in our lifestyle that drive that aerobic
system to develop, which includes eating more fat, not eating much carbohydrate, eating moderate
amounts of protein, maybe even relatively small amounts of protein for the earlier humans,
because we were, we were not the hunters in those early stages, but we, we certainly ate a large
amount of fat and we didn't sprint after animals. We jog after animals. And so all of that is how we,
we developed, we developed bigger brains, bigger bodies. We developed bodies that
had great longevity and a higher level of health to match that longevity. And it doesn't take long
when you start reading about this. And it was really an anthropology course, I think, that I
first started reading this kind of stuff. And it was really quite fascinating because I said, well,
if that's what they were doing, why are we doing all this other stuff now? And that sort of got me
thinking about this as an undergraduate student, because it seemed pretty clear what our ancestors
were doing and the fact that they were doing it for so long, you know, just what happened between
some time ago and now, how did we get into the mess we're in? And so the concept of maximum aerobic
function has been really with me for, for quite some time. When I was working with runners, which
is almost all the athletes I worked with, certainly in the seventies, I started talking about the pace
that these athletes could run at with this given heart rate that I had come up with,
this aerobic heart rate. And I called it the maximum aerobic heart rate. And so the pace
they were running was the maximum aerobic pace. And how did you come up with that heart rate?
That heart rate was derived in combination of a physical exam in my office. I want to know how
healthy they were. I want to know about their history. What did their labs look like, their
posture, their strength and so forth. And then I would go out to the track and I would monitor
their heart rate. I'd monitor their gait while we use different heart rates. And so I'd see them at
a 120 heart rate. I'd look at their gait, I'd say this is, it's a pretty good gait. And then we'd go
to 130. That's a pretty good gait, maybe even a little better. And then they'd go to 140. And I'd
start seeing irregularities. And then I'd bring them back to 130 and I'd see a nice smooth gait
again. And I'd put all that together and I'd assign them a certain MAF heart rate and they would go
train. And then I would test them again to see if it correlated. And it was a long process. And it
would not be for two or three years when I developed a formula, which I never used personally
because I always wanted to do it manually, but they correlated so well. And you may have heard
me say, I was lecturing one day about this and how I came up with this heart rate and what it meant and
how people were benefiting from it. And somebody said, well, how do we come up with that heart
rate? And I didn't have an answer. And I started realizing that, well, there's probably some simple
mathematical process that I can go through to use the athletes I had. I already know their heart
rate. Let's plug in the numbers. And the 180 formula was born. I tweaked that for a couple
of years. And the formula you see today is basically the same formula that existed in the early 80s.
Let's go through it in a bit more detail, just to make sure folks understand what we're saying.
You're saying that a person is going to be at their maximum aerobic output, so meaning they're
going to be maximally fat oxidizing at an approximate heart rate of 180 minus their age,
plus or minus a few modifications. So I believe there are a handful of these. If you're recovering
from an illness or you're kind of in an overtrained situation, you might actually need to discount that
by another 10, right? It might be 170 minus your age. Correct. The key is that you want to
individualize it. So you begin with 180 minus the age, which has no meaning, like the 220 formula.
You subtract your age from 220 and they say it's your maximum heart rate or whatever. Your max
heart rate. And of course, it's not most of the time. So 180 minus the age has no meaning. It's
just a means to the end. But you now want to individualize it to your health and fitness
needs. So if you're recovering from an illness, if you're severely overtrained, if you're in rehab,
you want to subtract another 10 from that. But if you're not in that category and you only have
the typical two or three colds a year, you might have asthma or seasonal allergies, you might be
overfat, you might be training for a while and then you kind of, you lose time, you can't train,
and then you get back into it. And in that category, you subtract another five, all the way
to the competitive athlete who has no health problems, who has been progressing quite well,
they can add five to that number. So in the, you know, that formula, what's important for people
is to follow the formula and be honest. That's the hardest part is to be honest. So if you're
on medication, for example, you've got to subtract your age from 180 and you've got to subtract
another 10. And what kind of meditation does it matter? Doesn't matter. That's the thing.
People will say, well, I'm only on this and that's not really affecting my heart rate or,
or I don't have to be on it. Or I, I don't know what, you know, if you're on medication,
you subtract 10. And if you get healthy along the way by training this way, and now you can
get off your medication, well, now you could redo the formula because now you're no longer
on medication, you're healthier. Let's have a look at the 180 formula again and modify it as
needed. You know, it's like doing a history on a patient. The most important thing is that they
be honest, because if you don't get the right information, you're, you're in trouble.
So it's kind of amazing to me, by the way, that you were able to do so much with heart rate back
in the seventies and eighties. What, what did you even use for heart rate monitors or were people
just manually checking their heart rate doing these tests? Well, yeah, I began manually checking
heart rates. There were some finger units that were not very accurate. There's some clips you
put on the ear. They were not accurate. Unlike the ear buds that are used today, picking up the
heart rate in the ear canal is a good measure. And I finally got a heart monitor that was used
in cardiac rehab in hospitals. And it was a big obnoxious, you know, double strap. One went over
the shoulder, one went around the chest and it had this box that was in the middle. And it, you know,
all you got was the heart rate. You could see it in this tiny window and you can hear the thing
beeping. And it would be several years before the wireless monitors came out, which I think was
late in 83 maybe. And when I first started using this heart monitor, I had one in my office. It
was like having, you know, I had a stethoscope. Okay. And I used it when I needed to use it. And
so I had this heart monitor and I would use it, go to the track, put it on an athlete, we'd use it,
take it off, put it on another athlete. And I, silly me, I thought, well, okay, once they
feel what 130 heart rate or 150 heart rate is like, they'll be able to train that way.
Well, that didn't work. So then I started lending out the heart monitor and then I had to buy another
one. And then I had like three of them. You know, it was like, you have three heart monitors? Yeah,
I have three in my office. It was like the old, you know, 1950s people had one television and if
somebody had two television, it was like, you mean you have two TVs? Wow. That's, you know,
you know, then people started buying them. They said, I'm going to train with this.
Because when I trained with it, I feel better. I'm not tired. I'm, you know, my back doesn't hurt
anymore. And blah, blah, blah. It progressed that way. And then when the wireless heart monitors
came out, everybody wanted to buy one, which was interesting. So the formula, the math formula of
180 minus age, and then adjusted based on all the factors, is a way to basically gauge the intensity.
How did you then prescribe volume? And how did you not only prescribe the volume there,
but determine how much volume to add in that was at a higher intensity?
That's an interesting question. It really began early on when I had no intention of coaching.
I didn't want to be a coach. You know, I want to be a clinician and fix people's knees and help them,
you know, get off blood pressure medications or whatever. And with athletes, I thought if I could
just keep them from getting injured, they'll just perform better because, you know, that seemed to
be the thing that slowed them down getting some physical injury. And I realized that
I was treating symptoms. I was, I was really, you know, it was against my nature to, to do that. I
was, I was fixing some runner's knee and they go out and train. And then I'd see them again in my
clinic a month later with the same knee problem. I said, well, what, what did you do? He said, well,
I just did my normal training. And, you know, eventually I said, well, let me look at your
training and people would write down their schedules and I would start looking at it.
And I realized that I didn't, I needed to have some input on this schedule because
what they're doing was excessive. They were literally over training. And so I became a coach
and I didn't want to be like a regular coach where I'd give out a schedule. I wanted them,
like I said earlier with, with, with Stu Middleman, I wanted the athlete to be part of the process,
you know, I wanted to say, well, what would you like to do with your training? And they bring in
their schedule and I'd look at it and I would just say, let me get this straight. You work 60
hours a week. You have three kids and a house and you do all these social things and you're trying
to run a hundred miles a week. That doesn't make sense. You either have to get rid of your kids,
get rid of your family, get rid of your job, or reduce the number of miles you're running.
And so, you know, I got a lot of laughs and we, we went on and I found that people
could do a lot less training, add a lot less intensity and perform in a race a whole lot better.
And it didn't take long to see that. You know, it's like a taper. When you taper, you get stronger.
Well, when you cut somebody's schedule down, they can get more out of their training. And so,
it worked that way. And so the big issue was really this aerobic system stuff. How do you build
the best aerobic system? Of course, I had been familiar with Arthur Lydiard,
who was a patient in my clinic actually at one point. And so I knew about this concept of the
aerobic base and, and it just seemed to make a lot of sense. And what I found through working
with a number of patients that if they, if they do their traditional two days a week of
interval training on the track, they never got faster at the same heart rate like these other
people did, who seemed to excel quite quickly from, from one month to the next, they could be running
starting at a nine minute a mile pace at their MAF heart rate. They might be running 830 a month
later, same heart rate, month later, now they're running at an eight minute pace.
Okay, so I want to pause there for a sec. So when the athlete makes progress, when they're doing
their MAF test, which again, I just want to remind everybody, because we're, we're talking about both
an MAF heart rate, but then the MAF test, and these are very important concepts. So let's go
back. So I figure out either through a very bespoke manner or using the formula that my
MAF heart rate is 130. I go out and I'm going to do my training at 130, and I'm running a nine minute
mile. The question becomes, while keeping my heart rate at 130, can I get faster? Can I go from a nine
minute mile to an 830 mile to an eight minute mile? And if I can do that while staying at 130,
by definition, I have become aerobically fitter and more efficient, correct?
Correct.
Now, is there a point at which you begin to adjust up the heart rate and say, Peter, I want you to now train at 132?
Or do you keep me at 130 and see how far we can drive that down until I plateau? How do you make that decision?
I keep you at 130 because I've determined that 130 is a good number for you because you're
progressing now. Can we cheat a little bit up to 132 and 133, only to find out two months later
that you're back to where you were? I don't want to spend that time because at some point I've had
enough experience to know that's not a good use of our time. So we're going to stay at 130,
and we're going to allow your body to develop that aerobic system. The question people often have is,
well, how do I run faster at the same heart rate? It doesn't make sense. And the answer is that
you're able to generate a lot of energy from fat. You're building the aerobic system, so you're
increasing fat burning. Now you have more energy. You have the steam engine, the more wood or coal
you throw in there, the more that engine can go and the faster it can go. And you will progress,
and you'll month after month get faster and faster. At some point you will hit a plateau. And
early on I realized it took three, four, five, six months before people hit a plateau.
So there are two issues. One is, do we keep allowing the body to get faster and faster?
Which for an endurance athlete is the greatest benefit they can obtain. Because if they can go
faster at a submax pace, they can go faster at a max pace. Let's unpack that for a minute.
Let's unpack that. That's a very, very important statement. Can you talk about some of the
experiences you've had to establish that? And again, actually before we do that, Phil,
let's talk about why that's relevant. You're running a 10k. Let's say at the very competitive
level, a 10k is, depending on how competitive obviously, it can be sub 30 minutes. But if
you're kind of a recreational athlete who's running competitively, you're going to be in the 32,
33, 34 minute range. By definition, you're running well above your math target. Is it necessarily
true that if you take the top 10 finishers of that race and then a week later, have them
run at their math heart rate, they'll cover greater distances as a function of what they
ran in the 10k race. In other words, do we have evidence that that's true? Because if it is,
it's a remarkable statement, right? We do have evidence that that is true. Hypothetically,
you have the outlier who's this guy who can't run nine minutes without hitting a 180 heart rate.
These are the people who are over-trained enough to be in that sympathetic state.
They get into a 10k and they run a PR at amazing feet. How could, you know, I've run a minute and
a half faster in my, you know, these are the people that are ready to fall apart at any minute.
And I've seen them. These are also the people who are ready to drop dead of a heart attack.
And so if we take those outliers away, then yes, we have this hierarchy of athletes who have a
increasingly better submax condition that corresponds to their race pace.
If that's true, then, Phil, it would really lend credence to the idea that even if you're training
for a 5k or a 10k, you still want to push your math protocol. It still matters how much you can,
how much distance you can cover at that lower heart rate and lower intensity where you are
running at your maximum fat oxidation and maximum aerobic capacity.
Yeah. And I think it's pretty clear now that submax performance predicts maximum performance.
How far down can you go even for a miler? I think it comes down to how much fat burning
do we need? And even for a mile, there's a lot of fat burning taking place in a one mile race.
I want to ask you about fat. When I was in medical school, the conventional wisdom
was that fat oxidation could not exceed one gram per minute. Now, I didn't think much of it,
but many years later when I underwent an enormous dietary switch and I went from being a kind of
ultra distance athlete, basically mainlining carbohydrates, so probably consuming,
I would say, five bottles of Powerade a day. So let's say if I was training four hours a day,
I would go through five liters of Powerade plus CytoMax plus Hammer Perpetuum, like basically all
of these very high carbohydrate formulas, rotting my gut. And when I would do my VO2 max testing,
which I did pretty frequently, you get a lot of data on the way up to VO2 max. You're getting all
of your fuel partitioning data because you're getting VO2 and VCO2. So I know how many calories
I'm expending at every level of intensity, and I know what the mixture is of carbohydrate versus
fat. So clearly in that state, I was nowhere near oxidizing one gram of fat per minute. In fact,
I was pretty much only oxidizing glucose the entire level. In other words, even at my low
intensity, I was still a glucose oxidizer. Fast forward years, several years, I've tried
something totally radical. I've gone on a ketogenic diet. I've done it for not just a while,
but actually for three years. And I've become very adapted to it such that I can function at high
and low intensity. And I'm now doing the same thing. I'm repeating VO2 max testing, but on this
ketogenic diet, and I hit a fat oxidation, which is still submaximal. So it's just below my VO2 max,
but my max fat ox was 1.73 grams per minute. And I remember thinking, how is that even possible?
Now, of course, I would go on to learn that world-class athletes training on a very low
carbohydrate diet were able to hit 2, 2.1, even 2.2 grams per minute, which I found interesting.
It basically said that this conventional wisdom we have about sports nutrition and sports science
is largely predicated on assumptions of what people are eating that aren't necessarily the
optimal way to go about doing it. It's a very good point. And I mean, you and I came to that
same conclusion in different ways. And we also had the same studies to look at, the same lab
tests to do. And unfortunately, we had a lot of the same subjects, or we read about
studies that use the same subjects, which were big carbohydrate eaters that distorted the research
completely. But all along the way, I knew there was something about fat. And the question is,
well, how could we really measure it? And I knew we could do it in the lab. My clinic was in the
middle of, I mean, I was in the New York City suburbs at the time. So I occasionally had access
to a lab, occasionally could get somebody in there to test. And occasionally, they would say,
wow, this is amazing. How could this person burn so much fat? We don't understand this.
It must be a problem. And then, you know, as the months and years went by, you know,
it was not a problem anymore. This was great. And so all along the way, for me, it was always,
I know what's going on. I know this athlete's getting healthy. I know they're burning more
fat because they're running faster at the same MAF heart rate. And now we're starting to see it be
measured. And it was a point where I said, I can't be the scientist. I'm not really a scientist.
I do wear that hat, but I'm too busy being a clinician and coming up with all these
crazy tests. And still my primary concern was helping people get healthy and fit. And if it was
an athlete, it meant they were going to perform better, but not by sacrificing their health. And
if they were not an athlete, we still had a lot of work to do. And it was only after a while that I
started thinking more scientifically. I always thought scientifically, depending on who you ask,
you know, if you ask a scientist, they would say, well, I'm not, I'm not being very scientific when
I explain this MAF heart rate. And if I ask a clinician, they say, you know, you're, you're too
scientific about this. So I gradually became more and more scientific only because A, it was fun,
especially reading the new research. And B, it was much better for me as a clinician to explain
things in scientific terms. I still had that scientific mentality of this is how we communicate
to the rest of the world from a scientific standpoint. So the fat burning component became
that factor that we can measure more and more. And like the story you told of the changes you made
and how it affected fat burning, you know, I started gathering that kind of data and started
writing more as a clinician, you can't publish papers. You just can't, you know, your brain is
unable to, to spend time doing that because you're spending so much time doing other things. And it
wasn't until after I left my clinic, because healthcare was getting so bad, I just couldn't
do that anymore. And I, I ended up only working with, with athletes. And so healthcare was really
out of the picture in many ways. And then I was able to spend more time thinking and writing
scientifically and start publishing more. I wrote a textbook, I started publishing more
scientific papers and talking about all this with a scientific hat on rather than merely a
clinical hat. Although a lot of the scientific things I've written are clinical oriented,
because that's still my goal is to help people. And one of the ways of helping people is to help
other clinicians who can then in turn help their patients. There's something about this nutritional
component that I think creates a lot of confusion for people, which is that it tends to be in flux.
So it's not constant. When I was young, so call it the first athletic phase of my life, which I
would say is about age 13 to 18. So between the ages of 13 to 18, I was indestructible, just like
most 13, you know, to 18 year olds are you can do anything, there is no such thing as overtraining,
nor is there such a thing as overeating. I could consume such comical amounts of food. And they
were really not of high quality at all, right? So, you know, breakfast would be a box of cereal into
large Tupperware bowl the entire box. I mean, six or seven sandwiches for lunch every day. So a whole
loaf of bread turned into sandwiches plus French fries plus a one gallon thing of orange juice.
I mean, just disgusting quantities of food, but absolutely no impairment of performance or health,
at least by any measurable amount. But by the time I'm in the sort of second and third phase of
my life into my late 20s and my 30s, my tolerance for that amount of carbohydrate went down.
And so even though I was still exercising a lot, certainly by any normal standard, you know,
I metabolically became quite sick. And I became the example of that guy who can't outrun his bad
diet. Although in my case, I was out swimming it, I was trying to out swim it or out ride it.
And so how did you then either as a coach or as a clinician trying to help just a normal person
calibrate not just the intensity of exercise, not just the duration of exercise, but now this
third layer, which is specifically what is the carbohydrate tolerance of the individual,
given that one, two people can be similar and vary in a number of ways and yet be different in that
regard. And secondly, any given individual is likely going to see a deterioration of that over
a deterioration of that over time. Sure. And we we all become more insulin resistant
as the years go by. I like to call it carbohydrate intolerance, because as soon as you say insulin
resistance to the average person, they either shut down or they panic or they totally ignore you,
because that's a hard, it's a hard term to relate to because they can't relate to it.
Carbohydrate intolerance, at least when you say you're not tolerating the level of the amount of
carbohydrates you're eating. So you need to cut down. They can relate to that. They may not be
happy, but they can relate to that. But the more important factor was one that I already
knew about, although I didn't know how to apply it to patients. But I already knew
going again, going back to undergraduate school where this idea of holism, you know,
it came from philosophy, really, for me, this holistic idea showed up one day. And I think
out of that came this idea that we're all individuals and we all have uniquenesses.
And I carried that with me into my clinical world. And there wasn't much to do, you know,
to measure insulin resistance back then meant going into the hospital and having a glucose
clamp test. That was just unheard of. They laughed at me when I sent patients to the cardiologist
because I wanted to see, I want to measure heart rate variability in this patient because
I think there's an autonomic problem. Well, half of them didn't have any problem, but the other
half did. And they said, well, gee, how do you know that? You know these things as a clinician
because you do a good evaluation. You assess the patient and you spend a lot of time talking to
the patient, something that's not done anymore. It wasn't done much back then either. But by
doing that, you learn about the patient. You learn about so many things, including insulin resistance.
How sensitive are they to insulin? How do they respond? An obvious example is a New York City
executive works in an office all day, training for a marathon, goes out for lunch, comes back,
and is so tired that he has to put his head on the desk and literally fall asleep.
Obviously, Bob, what did you have for lunch? Well, you start putting two and two together and it's
not that hard. And then just like the MAF test where you want to see what is this person capable
of doing at this given heart rate, I came up with another challenge, which was a food challenge
called the two-week test. Okay, Bob, I want you to not eat those things at lunch anymore. I don't
even want to have you eat those things for breakfast. In fact, let's take away all the junk
food from your diet and take and cut way down on the natural carbohydrates like lentils and beans
and rice and fruits and fruit juice, etc. And we'll do it just for two weeks. It's a challenge. We want
to see how you respond. So we gather all the signs and symptoms that are not normal. I fall asleep
after meals. I fall asleep easily at night because I'm so exhausted, but I wake up at 2am, etc., etc.
Okay, let's put these things on the table. Let's do this two-week test after the two weeks of eating
that way. Let's look at all these signs and symptoms. Are any of them better or any of them worse?
Well, yeah, three-quarters of them are better. Of all the miracles I've seen in clinical practice,
the two-week test is one of them because you see these people become new people after a very short
period of time. It's really amazing. I mean, it's because insulin is involved. Insulin has immediate
effects. Carbohydrates have immediate effects. The two meal effect with, you know, it's just,
it's an almost an instant change. So now you've gathered more information. You're still assessing
the patient, but now we can start individualizing things more and more. And that process was just
ongoing. And again, I always wanted to enlist the patient. So I wanted to say, okay, you've done
this two-week test. You're feeling so much better after two weeks. Now we want you to add some lentils
to your midday meal or add a small piece of fruit at breakfast or whatever. And let's see how you
feel. Let's see if some of those signs and symptoms come back with just one piece of fruit or let's
see if you've lost 10 pounds. You're starting to gain after a couple of weeks of only having a
little bit of carbohydrate, whatever. But I want to enlist them in the process. I want them to use
their instincts and intuition, which we all have, to understand what it feels like to eat too much
carbohydrate before you've gotten there. One more bite of this apple and I'm in trouble. I want you
to know that. I think it's a very important thing. It's a very human thing. And so that holistic
component, that individualizing aspect of my work has always been there. And in many ways, it makes
it easier. People might say, well, if you just give somebody a diet, it doesn't get any easier
than that. Well, it doesn't get any rewarding when you do that either. So it was a very important
part. And it still is a very important part, even though I'm not sitting with patients one-on-one
anymore, usually. I may do some consulting, but I am writing. I am still lecturing. And I could take
that component of individualization, of holism, and get those points across to people so they can
take that and run with it, so to speak. Now, I, again, mentioned that I spent all this time on
a very low carbohydrate diet and saw enormous improvements in my aerobic fitness. When it was
all said and done, my anaerobic fitness, my higher level intensity fitness, did not deteriorate,
but it took a very long time for that to come around. And the conclusion I drew from that was
athletes who were heavily involved in glycolytic activity really ought not restrict
carbohydrates as much as, say, athletes who are doing things that can be done at a much more
aerobic level. Now, a couple of years ago, you were part of a study that sort of flew in the face of my
assumptions because it was a very short study. It was a four-week study, and it put athletes on a
very low carbohydrate diet. They averaged less than 10% and maybe 15% protein. So they were, you know,
if they weren't on a ketogenic diet, they were very close to it, and they were doing high
intensity interval training. And you guys didn't find any difference between the groups, suggesting
that this amount of carbohydrate restriction did not impair performance. What can you say about
that study? It was a good study. Part of it, actually, we published a separate paper on it,
showing that the high fat diet did not have any adverse effect on inflammation. But that study
really came from this idea that athletes can still burn high amounts of fat when they do interval
training. Paul Larson did, you know, that's how I met Paul. They did a study some time ago. They
showed that high intensity training can still produce large amounts of, relatively speaking,
fat burning, as opposed to, you know, burning 100% carbohydrate, like you were mentioning
earlier. I sent him an email and I said, yeah, well, I sent him an athlete I had worked on who
we had done some lab studies on. And I don't remember the numbers, but at about a 180 heart rate
in this 36 year old athlete, he was burning a lot of fat, relatively speaking. And I said, yeah,
here's an example of what I found clinically. And, you know, and so we've known this for a long
time, it's good to see that you're doing this. And he wrote me back and we've been colleagues
ever since. And he was in that study. So it was a study that showed what we already knew clinically
in a sense. And we wanted to demonstrate it from a lab standpoint. Do you remember how many
participants were in that study? I want to say 20, but that seems so long ago.
Okay. Yeah. So, I mean, it would be interesting to see if with a larger sample size, that is still
the case. And obviously, at different levels of the athletes in coming, right? In other words,
is that true of recreational athletes only? Is it also true of high level athletes?
Yeah, these were students, I think Jeff has done, Jeff Volek has done some studies with the higher
level athletes, with some ultra athletes. Again, they're not running as fast, but they're running
at a max level. These were students. And these were subjects who the ones who were on the very
low carbohydrate diet were only there for a month. And my feeling is we really should have gone
longer. I think we could have seen different results, but they're only there for a month. A
month is long enough for some people, but not long enough for others. And there's a good argument to
make that, you know, it should be two months or even three months to really stabilize that metabolic
change, but whatever. It was a good study. And, you know, like other studies, somebody will see it
and say, Hey, this should be done with more people. Just like you said, let's get more numbers. Let's
get a wider age group. Let's get beginners athletes, you know, middle of the pack runners,
professional athletes. Professional athletes are really hard to get because they don't want to do
this. They don't want to go into a lab and do that. But from a clinical standpoint, I love all these
studies. I love being involved with them. But for me, the bottom line is, can you the athlete run
faster at the same submax heart rate? In fact, I don't care what you do with your training or your
diet. If you could run faster at the same heart rate as the months go by, whatever you're doing
is working. Keep doing it. So that MAF test is so powerful that that's really the only thing you have
to sell people on. And then when they start seeing that they're not getting faster, or when they see
they've gotten faster, and now they're going to start doing some weight training, fatiguing type
weight training, or they're doing some intervals, and then they get slower. You know, now you've got
their attention. Now you say, yeah, see, do you understand what's happening? And, you know, they
start feeling it because they say, well, you know, I felt it wasn't quite right. Or I didn't feel
comfortable doing that. So when I first started using a heart monitor, I thought this is interesting.
This is biofeedback, by definition, we're going to listen to or we're going to look at our heart rate,
and we're going to respond to what that heart rate does. And the goal is to be able to do that
without this heart monitor. So I thought really these heart monitors were just a one use, maybe
spend a whole week doing it. Now you know how to run at 130 heart rate. It never happened. Once in
a while I see an athlete who knows exactly where they are. They know exactly when they could run
at that max fat burning level. And I've always been amazed by that. And there's some good ones
and some mediocre runners who were able to do that. But most people, we are in a no pain,
no gain world. And we're seeing injuries because someone watches the New York City marathon on TV.
And the next day they go out and they want to run like that lead pack runner. They want to stride
out like, you know, come on, man, you can't even break four hours in the marathon. No wonder you
got injured. Speaking of the marathon, I want to talk about this book you wrote in 2014, which was
just such a brilliant idea. The title of the book is 159, The Sub 2-Hour Marathon is Within Reach.
Here's how it will go down and what it can teach all runners about training and racing. And of
course, five years later in October of 2019, Kip Chogge goes and runs 159.40. Now we can explain
to people who care about the nuance that it was not technically a sub two in a world record pace.
It was sort of a contrived example of what could be done under the most optimal conditions. It was
not a race, but there's simply no denying that what Kip Chogge did was unbelievable. He had tried
a year earlier and I believe came very close, was probably two double oh, I don't know, 40 seconds
or something. Yeah, yeah. He was pretty close. He was under two oh one. So let's put aside the
technicality of how this wasn't a world record in the typical sense of how world records are
running marathons, but instead just focus on what you thought needed to happen in 2014,
why you thought this was achievable and maybe what we learned from Kip Chogge. Well, I had
originally written an article called the 159 marathon back in the 90s. It was half, I wouldn't
say that it was a kind of a joke, but it was half goof, but half serious because the lead pack runners
were running faster and faster. World records were being broken all the time. There was no
evidence that said this is going to stop. We're going to hit a plateau and we're not going to
get any faster. There were people who thought that. I don't know where they got those ideas from,
but we started seeing the fact that age group runners were not getting faster and I thought
that was interesting. And when you start putting numbers together, such as what if you wore a
lighter shoe or what if you were three pounds lighter or what if you were shorter or what if
your body type was this and of course what if you were a better fat burner, how much more energy
would you have? And then again, the next obvious step is, well, what does your MAF test need to be
to run under two hours? And I was getting some runners who were starting to hit
five minute pace for their MAF test. They're running five minutes a mile at their MAF heart rate.
And so I thought there's no indication that they're reaching a limit, that they're hitting a plateau
in performance. So why couldn't it keep going? And that's really where the idea went and it turned
into a book. And I'm not sure it was a book that sold very well. I think in the 90s when I wrote
that article, a lot of people just asked me why I even wrote it. This is silly. We're not going to
see a 159 marathon in our lifetime. And I said, well, how long do you plan on living? So I think
what this runner did was amazing. I don't like what he did. I don't like the whole idea behind it.
I still know that a runner is going to do it in Berlin or London on the right day.
And it's relatively soon it's going to happen. And I'll be much happier to see that.
And you're just saying you're not happy with the way it was done because of the sort of contrived
nature of it. Yeah, it was an advertisement. I'm not opposed to advertising, but it was
more like a circus. And I think it took away from professional running as a sport.
That's what I didn't like about it. Yeah, it was a Nike commercial for sure.
Do we know much about Kipchoge's nutrition or other factors that we could extrapolate from?
For example, in a two hour race, even at the level he's exerting himself, he technically
doesn't really need calories. Fluids should be enough. Do we know if he actually consumed
glucose during that race? I'm not aware of what he consumed, if anything.
If properly trained, obviously he was burning a lot of fat. If properly trained, he wouldn't
have needed any added nutrition, maybe not even water. Water is this interesting thing
because it has a lot of weight. And if you dehydrate a small amount, the time factor is
significant enough where you're running faster. There's this window, and I don't know if it's
2% dehydration from a weight standpoint or what it might be. You have this game of dehydrating,
but not impairing performance. And as a result, you're getting lighter, and so you're going to
be able to run faster. It's all about performance. If you can prevent impairment of performance,
that's where you want to be. But I don't have information. My impression with the
the Kenyans, with the East Africans, is that if you look back in history, we've got all these
areas of the world that have taken their place on the world stage of great runners.
And now it's the Kenyans. The question is, number one, who's going to be next?
Because somebody else will be next. But the real question is, why have all these countries come and
gone? And my feeling is that in Kenya, you know, it's a very poor country. These young men and
women have an opportunity to become kings in their own country with the money they make on racing.
And they go from race to race, and they race all the time, and they burn out. And it's really sad.
But I think that's what's happened. And the ones I've met along the way at, you know, at the races
and at different events, a lot of them are burned out. But they're going to make as much as they can
make as a job. And that's it. Imagine being able to take one of those athletes and train them,
I'd want to say properly, but train them more effectively. I think you'd have a two hour
marathon broken already in a real race. When you look at somebody like Kip Choggy or guys at this
top level, though, there is a longevity to them, which is they're, you know, spoken with really
world class marathoners. And many of them will sort of acknowledge they might only have a dozen
marathons in them, you know, in their entire career, where they're going to really be able to run at a
certain level. And that's, you know, that says, look, I might only have 12 marathons over 15 years
in me that are truly world class performances. And that's that's sort of a different philosophy
than the churn and burn philosophy. Like look at Meb when he won the Boston Marathon. I mean, he was
what, 39? How old was Kip Choggy when he went under two? I mean, he was in his mid 30s, wasn't he?
Yeah, and that's what that's what I you know, in the book, I wrote this, this is the makeup of a
159 marathon or someone who's in their 30s, not someone who's in their 20s, not somebody who could
run a great 10k. They had almost had to have run a great 10k when they were younger. But now that
they're 35, and they they've built this great endurance base. Now they've got the best of
everything. And so yeah, I my feeling is that you're you're in your mid to late 30s and maybe
even 40s. Man, I've just I've worked with some incredible 40 year olds who have won some races
and you know, history has shown these people and people are, you know, often say, well, these are
amazing people. They're outliers. I don't think they're outliers. I think it's I think it's the
norm. So I want to talk a little bit about a term that you were you've used it a couple times today.
And I've heard you, you know, or seen you write about it before, which is you don't like the term
overweight. You like the term over fat. You're very clear to talk about it's adipose tissue,
we should be concerned with not mass. How do you think about that in the overall context of health,
you know, we we tend to focus on weight. You know, if we get one more layer sophisticated,
we look at body mass index, which of course is a highly flawed metric. But where do you see the
trends in fatness? And how does that factor into maybe what you said earlier, which is
at the level of recreational athletes, we're not really seeing much improvement in performance.
Are those related? I think they're related in terms of the diminishing performance of age group
athletes. The problem clearly the over fat condition can typically add weight to the body.
So that's going to affect running performance. But more significantly, those people with excess body
fat have some downstream problems that can be very serious. We're talking about chronic disease.
So along the way to chronic disease, you have blood fat abnormalities, blood sugar abnormalities,
blood pressure abnormalities. And these things then lead to chronic diseases. So of course,
in that situation, people are not going to be performing their best. Over fat, excess body fat
also impairs the immune system. So people tend to get sick more often. And Paul Larson and I wrote
a paper on this regarding COVID early on in the spring, actually. And people with excess body fat
also have physical impairment problems more frequently. And so we're talking about the
basic simple injury that plantar fasciitis and also pain patterns, although back pain
on the less serious all the way to the arthrititis that are affecting runners. But again,
in an injured athlete, you're not going to perform your best. So these things are going to,
over the years, show diminishing performance in age groupers. And it's, number one, that's really
sad to see. Number two, it's even more sad to not be acknowledged. I just don't see people talking
about this. I don't understand why. I think people are starting to acknowledge that it always takes
longer. I guess someone like you who's sort of been clinically at the forefront of a lot of these
things, it seems like what's taking so long because you're seeing these things many years before.
But for example, sugar consumption is actually declining. But it sometimes takes a while for
this decline to necessarily translate into some of the health benefits. And furthermore,
these things are so multifaceted, right? I think that I don't actually know the data on this,
so I'm kind of making this up. But I would guess that you can sometimes see an improvement in one
parameter and a deterioration in others. For example, activity levels might be declining even
while certain elements of nutrition improve. And so the net effect of that could be a reduction or
something we didn't talk about, sleep, quality of sleep could be declining. And that can sort of
offset any benefit that we see. But this idea that health and performance are not necessarily
the same thing is something I see a lot of people struggle with it, right? I see a lot of people who
are not very healthy believe that the key to getting healthier is to train for a marathon
or train for an Ironman or train for this bike race or train for this event. And it usually puts
me in a bit of an awkward position because on the one hand, I'm so grateful that they have found
something to do to be active and to train for. And I don't want to discourage that. But I also
want them to understand that there's nothing especially healthy about doing an Ironman and
that one doesn't need to do that to be healthy. So do you have a message for folks around that?
Well, I have a lot of messages for them around that. But the main one is that they don't have
to do it just like you said. And in fact, all they have to do is start walking around the block.
And the benefits, the fat burning benefits that they'll get from that are huge, but also
that the food is more important. And so they need to look at the big picture. And of course,
they need to look at stress also. But the food is such a such a key factor in all of this. And
going back to the question you asked me, what is MAF, maximum aerobic function? How can we maximize
our aerobic system? Well, two of the components of lifestyle are food and exercise. And sure,
stress, stress is a very important factor. And yeah, you can't smoke cigarettes and drink too
much alcohol. But food and exercise are keys. And it's really, really simple. Just don't eat junk
food and take it easy out there. Well, Phil, on that note, I think we've given folks a lot
to think about today. And I want to thank you for your time. You're going to be ready for dinner
soon, which it sounds like you skip anyway, right? Yeah, I'm here when they will be starting to eat
dinner soon. I'll be watching, which is okay, because I'm not hungry. But thank you, Peter.
I enjoy your work. I have for quite some time. And thanks for having me on. It's been great.
Thank you, Phil. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing
these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that
we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed
on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only, does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use
of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.