Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level
at the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Dr. Hussein Yazin. Hussein is an associate professor in the
Department of Medicine at the Keck School of Medicine at USC. His lab has focused for almost a
decade now on lipid metabolism and nutrition and the effect these have on cognition and the risk
of developing Alzheimer's disease, paying specific attention to the ApoE4 allele. Many of you listening
to this podcast will no doubt be familiar with ApoE4 genotypes. We've spoken about this at great
length in a number of podcasts. This is really the deep dive into E4, what the implications are.
I actually wanted to speak with Hussein after we were part of a journal club where he presented a
couple of papers that he authored that were simply beyond fascinating. It was definitely one of the
deepest dives I'd ever seen into the inner workings of EPA and DHA's role in the brain. Now,
we do get to that near the end of the podcast, but I realize that it's important for people to really
understand a lot about the brain. I would consider this a fundamental core coursework on
brain biology. We really explain the architecture of the brain, the energy systems of the brain,
and what goes wrong, what are the various things that go wrong, because it's not just one thing
as a person develops Alzheimer's disease. Then we get into what ApoE is and then why we might have
these three different variants or isoforms of it, E2, E3, and E4, and what turns out to be different
depending on which of those you have. The obvious thing, of course, is your risk for Alzheimer's
disease, but why? We have a little side tangent that goes into the role of EPA in cardiovascular
disease with or without DHA, and then bring it back to this discussion around the role of DHA
in Alzheimer's disease and also what some of the specific things that we understand to date
with respect to patients that have E4 and what they can do to reduce risk. I'm going to give you
a warning upfront. Unfortunately, if you're anything like me, you're going to come away from
this episode. I think frustrated that our state of knowledge is still so pedestrian, but nevertheless,
this is a very important discussion and I certainly learned a lot in it and it will actually have an
impact on how I think about taking care of my patients. So without further delay, please enjoy
my conversation with Hussein Yazim. Hussein, thanks so much for making time to sit down today.
I'm really looking forward to this. Obviously, I had the pleasure of doing Journal Club with you
a few weeks ago, which is what made me realize we needed to do this for a much broader audience.
Let's go back to the beginning a little bit though. I'm curious as to what got you interested
in this space. I know you grew up in Lebanon. Did you do medical school there as well as college?
Yeah. Thank you, Peter, for the invitation. I'm happy to be part of your show. Yes, I grew up in
Beirut, Lebanon. That's my medical school. And then shortly after moved to the US to
do some residency training and followed by a fellowship. And then I got to where I am right
now. Tell me a little bit about that path. Your fellowship was in what? I trained in endocrinology.
I come from a family with strong heart disease and diabetes. So I decided to sub-specialize in
lipid disorders. And I studied lipids for a good of two to three years before
I had the opportunity to study brain lipids and I switched from blood lipids to the brain.
Well, this is a topic that I think a lot of people are interested in because I remember 10 years ago
when you would check an APOE genotype on somebody, it was a very unusual thing to do.
Today, it's not as unusual. It's probably still not incredibly common that people are walking
around knowing their APOE genotype, but it's certainly, I mean, it seems a log order more
common than it was a decade ago. And I suspect a decade from now, that might be one of the genes
that kind of everybody knows about themselves. So where do you think is a good place to start?
I think this topic is complicated enough that it probably warrants at least some discussion of
what makes up the brain. Like we talk about neuronal cells, we talk about glial cells. Can
you maybe help explain the architecture of the brain so that as we get into the different types
of cells, what a blood brain barrier means, where CSF resides, these things will become
important in this discussion. And I think we should assume that most people listening don't
necessarily understand those things. Sure. So you first asked about the APOE genotype and
I have seen in my practice calls, I would say even monthly from people who did 23andMe and found out
that they are E4 carriers and they wanted to know more. So I not uncommonly get calls to figure out
what is it that I have APOE4, what does that mean for my brain? You typically see in the report
some discussion that they are at an increased risk of Alzheimer's disease and people are
interested to figure out if there's anything they can do. So yes, APOE4 will be something important
to deal with. Now regarding the brain itself, the brain is a unique compartment that is mostly a
lipid organ. So by weight, the brain contains a large amount of lipids from cholesterol, which is
a sterol, to different forms of fatty acids. And the brain is largely composed of three types of
cells, although it's much more than that. But the main cells are the neurons, which are responsible
for firing and forming synapses, which regulate how the brain functions. The neurons cannot do
their own function had it not been for helper cells. And these include in general glial cells.
Glial cells could be astrocytes and these are cells which are tightly associated with neurons
and they regulate the energy, storage, production, and so forth that the neuron would need to keep
firing. Astrocytes have a lot of functions but they're mostly viewed as taking up glucose or
fat and providing substrates that the neuron could use to be able to generate ATP and keep firing.
And then you've got the glial cells, the micro glial cells, which have gained a lot of traction
in the last decade or so because they have been linked to neurodegenerative diseases such as
Alzheimer's disease. And glial cells are immune cells responsible for cleaning up, whether it's
going to be a beta or an infection. These immune cells have the responsibility of making sure that
the house is in order. There's also the oligodendrocytes and other kinds of cells
but those three cells are the main type of cells that we study in the brain.
The brain is surrounded by a blood-brain barrier and this is an important concept because the
brain is protected from the outside of the brain and for a good reason. The brain needs to have a
stable environment to be able to function. The blood-brain barrier regulates what gets in and out
of the brain and stands as a barrier to prevent toxic proteins, infectious organisms, and other
things from getting free access. The blood-brain barrier separates the blood vessels and the blood
inside the blood vessels from the brain and it's composed of capillary cells. These are endothelial
cells which have a lining of tight junctions. These are very tight in the sense that they would
act as a barrier, followed by pericytes which surround those endothelial cells and these are
supporting cells for the endothelium to maintain the integrity of the blood-brain barrier and around
those you have the neural cells or wall cells which make up the matrix surrounding those two
cell types and maintains the integrity as well of the blood-brain barrier. So you've got this
elaborate system that is designed to protect the brain and to maintain a stable environment.
Now finally cerebrospinal fluid is in a simplistic way the sewage system of the brain.
When the brain receives its metabolites, its nutrients from the circulation,
it crosses the blood-brain barrier through the junction of the endothelial cells into brain cells
that is a fluid surrounding brain cells that we call the interstitial fluid.
Brain cells will take up whatever they need, whether it's an astrocyte, a microglia, or a neuron,
and produce some byproducts. One of the commonly studied byproducts are A-beta proteins which are
accumulating in diseases like Alzheimer's. Those byproducts will then get cleared into the CSF.
The CSF or cerebrospinal fluid, as I mentioned before, is a form of a system that allows drainage
from the brain cells from the interstitial fluid. It's run by a pump. That pump is in a system known
as the choroid plexus. The choroid plexus will be pumping clear water-like fluid into the CSF,
and this motion of movement of the fluid throughout the brain washes the brain off. At some point,
the choroid plexus interferes with the blood circulation to clear off these metabolites
from the CSF back into the blood for excretion. So if we take A-beta amyloid peptides, for example,
they're produced by the neuron as the neuron is firing. These are peptides which come off the
membrane of a neuron, and then they leak into the CSF, and then from the CSF they get into the blood,
and the blood clears those A-beta peptides through the liver or other organs.
This constant CSF activity is critical for maintaining the sewage system of the brain in
order. So I hope I have addressed some of the questions that you were asking.
Yeah, absolutely. We can even talk about some illnesses that occur that get in the way of this.
For example, sometimes children are born with abnormalities that make it very difficult for
them to clear CSF, or children can be born with malformations that obstruct the flow of CSF,
and they develop conditions where some of these compartments within the brain
expand and enlarge, and it's a very intricate system. In situations like that, for example,
you have to come up with other ways to drain the system, and some of these children require shunts,
where you have to place an exogenous tube into their brain and drain it into their abdomen or
something like that. It's all such an amazing organ. I remember I had one rotation in general
surgery where we did a month of neurosurgery, and it is quite remarkable when you're operating on
the brain and you remove the Dura, the brain is a bloodless organ. So it looks unlike any other
organ, like when you're operating on the kidney and you get right down to the kidney, you still
see the sort of pulp-like redness of the kidney, or the lung, or the liver, any of these other
organs, but the brain is quite distinct in that it doesn't have that, and once that Dura is peeled
back and you see it bathing in this CSF, it looks unusually sterile, which is not to say, of course,
as you cut into the parenchyma, you wouldn't get blood, but at that level, it's not. You mentioned
something earlier, and I want to just make sure we put it in context, which is that by weight,
the brain is disproportionately lipid-laden relative to other organs. So let's make sure
people understand what that means. Every cell in our body has a bilayer of cholesterol that makes
up its cell membrane. That's what allows it to have fluidity. That's what allows it to hold
transporters across its cell membrane, etc. How does, say, a cardiac myocyte, the muscle cell of a
heart, differ in terms of its lipid content from either the neuron or the astrocyte or the microglia?
What is it about these cells in the brain that structurally requires such an abundance of lipid
and cholesterol? That's a fundamentally important question, and it actually begs to ask perhaps a
slightly different question. How is the brain functionally different than a myocyte? And
one way to look at this question is to understand that the brain operates by firing. So you're
looking at perhaps an electric system where you have wires connected to each other, and these
wires have to fire constantly. And by firing, you need electricity to move from one piece of the
wire to the other. This requires specific cables. In our modern-day language, you need a form of
fiber optics or high-speed wiring that allows this firing to happen in instantaneous
manners, and it's carefully regulated and separated by location, by speed, and by changes in a micro
environment. To be able to achieve this delicate and elaborate map of wires attached to each other,
you need lipids. Specifically, for example, if we're talking about a neuron, we're talking about
myelin. If we're talking about synapse, we're talking about a synaptosome. That's a synapse
body. The synaptosome by itself, to be able to conduct and depolarize, meaning to change the
electric potential across the cell membrane, it requires a certain environment of lipids
that allows it to do the signaling, allows the glutamate or glutamine to go inside the cell,
and then release certain mediators to open certain channels, for example, calcium channels.
So this particular environment necessitates that you have an elaborate system of lipids
that facilitate this process. This is a very taxing system, meaning that to be able to
constantly talk to me through this podcast, you would need an immense amount of ATP.
The extraction of glucose and the utilization of lipids is adapted to be able to answer this
this particular environment. In contrast, a cardiac myocyte, outside of its being regulated by
the foci that regulates heartbeats in the atria and so forth, the AV node and other areas,
the cardiac myocyte is simply a mechanical cell that has to pump all the time to be able to maintain
a certain pressure and blood flow. So that environment by itself requires strong
cytoskeletal elements such as actin or myosin that are efficiently packaged for pumping
and may require less lipids than the wiring that we discussed in the brain.
Yeah, so I think that's a very elegant way to explain that basically every cell in the body,
whether it be, as you said, a myocyte in the heart, or a cell in the kidney, or a cell in
the liver, or a cell in the lung, or a cell of skeletal muscle, all of those things have a
function that is contractile, gas exchange, filtration, something like that. The brain's
entire function is electron potentials and electricity. So it would make sense, as you said,
that every facet of the brain has to be optimized for signal transduction.
And that includes not just the myelination of the sheaths in the neurons, but even all of the other
cells that would facilitate for rapid potential and recurrence of normal electron gradients.
The brain, I mean, I think there's a statistic that we all learn in medical school, right, it weighs
about 2% of our body weight, and yet is probably responsible for something on the order of 20% of
our energy consumption. Again, you've provided a very elegant explanation for why that's the case.
Why is it that this tiny, tiny organ is so energy demanding? How does the brain utilize energy?
So what, let's talk a little bit about how substrate makes its way to the brain. And let's
contrast it just very quickly with, you know, pick a myocyte in your leg, right? It can take glucose
out of circulation. It can either with or without insulin bring that glucose molecule through a
Glut4 transmitter directly into the cytoplasm. It can, depending on the speed at which it requires ATP,
it can very rapidly take that to pyruvate and ultimately to lactate, or it can more slowly
take the pyruvate into the mitochondria and generate more ATP there. It can do the same
thing with fatty acids. Of course, with fatty acids, it's going to go from an acetyl CoA pathway
into the mitochondria and take these two carbon units into ATP. So the muscles have lots of options
for fuel. Even in a case of starvation, they can use ketones, but basically glucose, fatty acids,
lactate, all of these things are fuels. And they go directly to the cell. And then within the cell,
you have aerobic and anaerobic pathways, if you're talking about glycolysis, you sort of alluded to
it already, but the brain already has one thing that makes it an extra step, which is there's a
blood brain barrier. So it's not even like the glucose goes directly there through the capillary.
So how does the brain extract energy from circulation? And how does it differ from the
rest of the body in its fuel partitioning? I would say that I am not an expert in this field,
but I'll give you my two cents. This is a complex question. And I would beg to help the listeners
understand that this is a complex topic that even as we speak, there's a huge gap in knowledge.
But my understanding is that the brain prefers glucose as the predominant source of energy.
And that by itself is regulated differently than the rest of the body. The rest of the body
have a system by which insulin regulates specific transporters known as glute fours, as you mentioned.
And glute four allows an insulin dependent mechanism to enter glucose into pumping muscles
or adipocytes. And that responds to the outside environment, meaning you can induce glute four
expression by exercising. You can induce glute four expression by changes in body weight.
At the blood brain barrier, glute four plays a minor to no role in glucose uptake. The blood
brain barrier, in contrast, has a predominance of glute ones. Glute one expression is not controlled
by what you eat. It's not controlled by how you exercise to a large extent. And it's not controlled
by the same mechanisms that govern insulin regulated glucose signaling, partly because
your brain cannot be moody in its choices. It has to have a constant supply of glucose.
Now, glute one expression can be regulated and it's largely regulated to protect the brain.
Meaning if you are faced with a situation that is systemic hyperglycemia such as type 2 diabetes,
the brain protects itself by reducing glute one expression at the blood brain barrier.
The opposite holds true. If you are, for some reason, going through a prolonged fasting period
where you're dipping into glycogen stores and you're hypoglycemic, the brain up regulates
glute one at the blood brain barrier to extract as much as possible all the glucose in your
circulation to maintain a relatively constant amount of glucose in the brain. Now, during
physiological states, the glucose in the brain is relatively not, does not fluctuate that much,
although it does fluctuate, but it doesn't fluctuate as much as that in plasma.
During diseased states, such as Alzheimer's, for example, leakage or destruction of the
blood brain barrier associates with destruction in the glute one transporters and the brain now
struggles in capturing glucose from the system, which leads to a whole new cascade that we might
argue is a diseased cascade. It's compensatory, but it's responding to a glucose shortage.
So in that regards, glucose regulation in the brain differs from the circulation.
Now, another fundamental aspect to understand is that the brain is not efficient in utilizing fat
as a source of ATP. One thing that you notice after you dissect the brain is that you don't find,
you don't find fat depots that you find in your adipose tissue. Yes, it's a fatty organ,
but there aren't really storage sites of fat. It does not store fat. To a large extent,
there are lipid droplets in the brain, but they are more dynamic than the adipose tissue that we
have outside. And it prefers not to use fat as a source of ATP. It prefers to use fat to integrate
into the myelin sheath or the synoptosome to regulate membrane fluidity to help with depolarization.
Nevertheless, when the brain goes through crises and they can't use glucose, they have a mechanism
to extract ATP from fat. But the result is a price tag. The result is oxidative stress.
The brain has a complicated system, as we mentioned before, that consists of astrocytes and neurons
and glial cells and all sorts of stuff. And they have partitioned their roles. A neuron
is like your athlete who needs to run a marathon at a certain speed. Now, for that athlete to
succeed, he needs to have water bottles staged at every juncture or a mile. He used to have helpers
with towels, helpers with whatever it is for the athlete to be able to do the whole 23 mile if it's
a marathon. Astrocytes, the helper cells of neurons, would take up the glucose and process it to make
lactate and then shuttle the lactate into the neuron because the neuron says, I can digest
lactate more efficiently than the glucose and I can produce ATP with less damage. So the neuronal
favorite food is lactate and not glucose. But glucose gets into the astrocyte where it is
shuttled and changed into lactate. When glucose is no longer there, and we're talking about
prolonged fasting and glycogen depletion, the brain becomes very efficient in extracting ketone
bodies through the blood-brain barrier to maintain its firing and to avoid someone from getting into
a coma-like state. So, in a nutshell, to summarize what I just said, the brain does its best to
regulate its glucose content that is not dependent on insulin signaling. Number two, the brain
prefers glucose and not fat as a source of energy. And number three, when glucose is not available,
it extracts all the ketone bodies that are produced from fatty acid oxidation outside the brain to
maintain itself going. So a couple of other things to follow up on that. So actually, I didn't realize
that Glute-1 was basically regulated by peripheral glucose concentration. That's actually super
interesting. And I also didn't realize that the neurons were getting their lactate from the
astrocytes. So I assume the implication of that is as the astrocytes take glucose to make pyruvate,
to make lactate, the astrocytes are keeping the ATP from that process rendered to themselves
while transporting or donating the lactate to the neuron. Is that what's happening?
Yeah. And then what about the microglial cells? Are they using glucose or are they using the
residual lactate? I don't know what the source of energy for microglial cells. I am not sure
how they use that energy production. And do you have a sense just broadly what the distribution
is of ATP consumption between the glial cells and the neurons? I mean, I know that the glial
cells grossly outnumber the neurons in terms of the numbers of cells, but do you have a sense,
is it like a 50-50 division of energy consumption? I don't know. I don't want to provide an inaccurate
response, so I don't know. Okay. So we have a pretty good handle on what's going on here now.
You've done a great job, I think, giving us a primer on both the structure of the brain
and now energy. So let's get into this idea of what is ApoE? And let's talk about it not as a
gene right now, but let's talk about it as an ApoLipa protein, and then we can talk about the
genetics of it later. But what is this thing called ApoE? Your interest is also in cardiovascular
disease. This is a podcast in which we talk a lot about it, so we can even contrast for the listener
what ApoB is. Most people listening to this are very familiar with what ApoB is, this ApoLipa
protein that wraps lipoproteins and defines a subclass of them that morphologically distinct
that lineage of the VLDL to the IDL to the LDL. But what's ApoE? What is that ApoLipa protein?
That's a fascinating question, and that has been the focus of my own research for the past
six or seven years. So ApoE is, I like to give analogies, if you don't mind. Do you like music?
Sure. Before COVID, how often do you go listen to an orchestra playing the
mat or any of the fancy places? And New York has beautiful music too. Well, I'm not a fancy music
guy, but I like to go to concerts prior to COVID, but I don't know if that'll fit in with the
analogy. Well, the analogy I was trying to make is that for an orchestra to play efficiently,
it needs conductors. My father asked me a few months ago, and he's by no means a musician or
any of you have never played a music instrument, but he was telling me, what is that conductor
doing? I mean, can't they play without the conductor? So if I were to ask you, and if you
allow me a minute to sit in your shoes, what is the conductor doing? That's a great question.
First of all, I would assume he is vital. And secondly, I would assume that he is somehow
managing the timing of all of the different sections within the orchestra. And not just
the timing, but if one is crescendoing and the other is decrescendoing. So I suspect there's just
many more moving pieces that say a rock band where you have one guitar, one bass, one drum,
maybe a keyboard and a singer. Absolutely. And in the lipoprotein orchestra,
A-Pole B would be one of the principal players. Let's assume it's your violinist. A-Pole A would
be your piano player. And you need both. Sometimes you need the violinist to run the show,
and you need piano for certain pieces. But what puts the orchestra together in the peripheral
circulation, largely two conductors in this case, A-Pole and A-Pole C-3. What A-Pole E and A-Pole C-3
do is that they regulate the speed of which things are happening. They're different than A-Pole B,
because you can argue they're promiscuous. A-Pole B is matted to LDL particles,
maybe to some extent, VLDL, LDL, and this whole pipeline. A-Pole A1, to a large extent,
is matted to the HDL family of particles. Now A-Pole E and A-Pole C-3, also known as exchangeable
lipoproteins, are not. They can jump from different populations of lipoproteins. And by taking
different roles, they can decide whether a lipoprotein is going to stay in the circulation,
and that would be your A-Pole C-3, or get cleared, and that would be your A-Pole. So this is a
simplified version, because I think in real life it's way more complex. But the reason why A-Pole
has been elusive and difficult to study is because of its multiple roles, and it appears on HDL,
it can appear on LDL, it can appear on IDL, it can appear on VLDL, it changes whether you're
fasting or postprandial, and it determines to some extent the fate of your lipoprotein.
So if we take a second to imagine, you know, what happens after we drink a milkshake.
So when you drink a milkshake, you're absorbing all the fat from the milk, and you're packaging
it into chylomicrons, which are known to carry A-Pole B48. A-Pole B48 will then have to circulate
and eventually get cleared by forming remnants. As A-Pole B48, the chylomicron,
containing particles circulating, it starts changing its A-Pole lipoprotein composition.
In the beginning, it would have a larger amount of A-Pole C-3, which would maintain it from getting
lipolized. And at some point, when it gets to a certain size, HDL will donate the A-Pole
and allow that remnant to get taken up by an A-Pole receptor into the liver.
Typical A-Pole receptors include LRP1. That also happens with VLDL particles.
When they are produced, when they are large, they acquire an A-Pole C-3 that blocks lipoprotein
lipase. And as they shrink in size, A-Pole C-3 will fall off, A-Pole would get reassembled,
and that will assist this VLDL particle of getting cleared. One of the fundamental aspects of
metabolic syndrome is an inefficient process where these particles are the A-Pole's and
the A-Pole C-3s are not as mobile, and you end up having an A-Pole C-3 enriched small dense LDL
particle that is not cleared. So we're talking now about A-Pole in the blood. So that A-Pole
in the blood has maybe a different role than the A-Pole in the brain.
By the way, before we go to the brain, Hussein, I'm very familiar with A-Pole C-3 in the scenarios
you've described it, and frankly, I'm quite hopeful that in the near future, we'll have A-Pole
C-3 assays in the periphery as an increase in our armamentarium as we try to use biomarkers
to better understand cardiovascular disease risk. And can A-Pole C-3 levels be a part of residual
risk? Once you've minimized A-Pole B, will A-Pole C-3 tell us something above and beyond it? And as
you said, it tracks so closely with insulin resistance and metabolic syndrome. I'm less
familiar with A-Pole in the periphery and wasn't actually aware of just how promiscuous it was.
It seems to have affinity for a number of receptors at the liver. Doesn't it also have
affinity for the LDL receptor itself? It does have an affinity for the LDL receptor, but its
affinity is higher for LRP1, which is one of the LDL receptor family members. Yeah, A-Pole
is a bit more complicated than the rest of the lipoproteins because it can take many shapes and
forms, and the affinities can change based on lipid binding. It has two arms, an N-terminus,
a C-terminus. Typically, the N-terminus binds to the receptor, and the C-terminus is buried
inside the lipid core of a lipoprotein particle. It can dislodge and become lipid-free, or it can
lipidate. These interactions are critical to our understanding of how A-Pole functions.
The reason why we've had an investment in science in A-Pole largely is due to A-Pole4, because that
mutation that substitutes the arginine, the cysteine with the arginine, changes how A-Pole
folds and unfolds and starts to carry in weapons. Now, we can measure the concentration of A-Pole
B in the circulation. We can measure the concentration of A-Pole A in circulation.
And in fact, as you said, A-Pole B is so predictably linked to LpA, VLDL, IDL, and LDL
that we effectively use A-Pole concentration as a surrogate for LDL concentration, and we
effectively use A-Pole1 concentration as a surrogate for HDL concentration. What does A-Pole
concentration mean? I mean, to my knowledge, there is no commercial assay to measure A-Pole
concentration in the periphery, but should you measure it in the lab, what would it tell you?
It's like asking me, what instrument does the conductor play? Does he?
Not at the time he's conducting. He plays them all, I suppose, but indirectly.
Right. So the A-Pole concentration is elusive because it doesn't matter what the concentration
is. That doesn't tell you the same amount of information that A-Pole B or A-Pole A1 does.
There is a one-to-one correlation ratio between every A-Pole B particle and every LDL particle.
So you're really closely estimating how much LDL particles there is by measuring A-Pole B.
A-Pole A is a little bit more complex. It's not one-to-one, it could be one-to-four,
but you can estimate with every four A-Pole A1, A-Pole lipoproteins, one HDL particle.
Now, when we talk about A-Pole, what are we talking about? A-Pole HDL, A-Pole free, A-Pole VLDL,
A-Pole ideal, A-Pole LDL. So if you have at one given concentration tons of A-Pole on HDL,
you have a completely different phenotype than if you have it on VLDL. Because as we mentioned with
the conductor is trying to now make all the orchestra work, they have to stretch themselves
and they have to make the violinist play harder, or they have to make the piano pick up at certain
point. You can't make an assessment of the function of A-Pole by just measuring its concentrations.
And to some extent that holds true for A-Pole C3, although A-Pole C3 at extremes of measurements
is more predictable and could be useful toward understanding residual risk in metabolic diseases,
but A-Pole is more elusive. So what is A-Pole, again, the A-Pole lipoprotein? We'll wait until
we understand this a bit better before we get down to the genetic isoforms. What is A-Pole
doing in the brain? How does the conductor regulate things in the brain? Oh, so that conductor
analogy may not hold because we don't have our traditional LDL, VLDL in the brain. We only have
A-Pole lipoprotein particles that you may argue are completely different than what you're finding
in plasma. Some group of scientists believe that A-Pole lipoproteins in the brain are HDL,
but that by itself also is not accurate. They could have the size of HDL, but the composition
might be very different. So A-Pole in the brain is not facilitating clearance of lipids or the rate
by which lipolysis is happening. Its role in the brain is largely supporting the astrocytes. So
astrocytes are supporting neurons, but for astrocytes to support neurons, they need a mechanism that can
efficiently cross-talk different cell types, and A-Pole happens to be able to do many different
things. For example, an A-Pole in a glial cell can regulate through the exchange of lipids how
inflammatory the glial cell is going to be. An A-Pole in an astrocyte can take out cholesterol
from the astrocyte and give it through an LRP1-mediated uptake in the neuron to the neuron itself.
ApoE's are notorious for being robust. One of the earliest studies I have done, maybe seven,
eight years ago, was cutting the nerve of a rat model, and at that point we did a mass spec
experiment and found out one of the largest changes in hundreds, if not thousands, of proteins after
you just take a neuron and cut it, are drastic changes in A-Pole. A-Pole exponentially goes up
after damage. Whether it's a stroke, whether it's an artificial severing of a nerve, A-Pole will be
released at very high rates to make sure repair is going to happen. A-Pole uses its flexibility,
structural flexibility to transport lipids, uses its structural flexibility to regulate what
receptors and transporters the cell can actually express. One fundamental difference between A-Pole
B and A-Pole is that A-Pole B, once it's taken up by a liver cell, typically goes and gets a lysosomal
degradation pathway, and that biology by Goldstein and others have led to therapies including
statins and later PCSK9 inhibitors because A-Pole B can get degraded in the lysosome.
And if you can figure out how A-Pole B is degraded, you can make a medication. Now one fundamental
difference about A-Pole B from A-Pole E is that A-Pole E to a large extent escapes degradation,
and once it's taken up by a liver cell or an astrocyte or a neuron, it recycles back.
So it's a notorious A-Pole lipoprotein that can get inside the cell and then outside the cell,
recycling most of the time. And by recycling, maybe the conducted analogy or the thermostat
analogy works. It controls or fine-tunes how much lipids there is in the cell, and it fine-tunes
a lot of different pathways which are tied to lipid metabolism,
most importantly the inflammatory pathway. Now I assume the blood-brain barrier prevents
peripheral A-Pole from entering the brain and vice versa? The dogma says yes, but our research,
recent research suggests that A-Pole E4 but not A-Pole E3 might be able to slip.
Slip through all of those tight junctions? No, not through the tight junctions. The affinity
of A-Pole E4 to the LRP1 is quite higher than A-Pole E3 and A-Pole E2, and LRP1 is expressed
at the blood-brain barrier. So it could hack the system and get through the endothelial LRP1
into the brain. And do we have a sense of what the half-life is of A-Pole? I mean A-Pole,
as you said, is a relatively short half-life. I mean it's even without medication, it's life,
it's residence time and circulation is probably less than a week before it's going to get
recycled vis-a-vis the liver. How long is A-Pole hanging around?
That's a complicated question. The answer to that is which particle are we talking about?
Well, I'm actually saying the A-Pole itself in any form, whether it be free or bound to something
else, the actual A-Pole can, it sounds like what you're saying is it can be around for a very long
period of time and take multiple forms. Yeah, so if it's a lipid-free form, A-Pole can be rapidly
excreted or disappeared from the circulation. If it's bound to HDL, it tends to hang longer.
If it's bound to VLDL, it tends to hang out less because VLDL clearance rates are faster than
that of HDL. And this is a manage, so A-Pole is converting those properties to the lipoprotein
that's actually going to. All right, let's now talk a bit about the genetics that regulate
these different isoforms because A-Pole is a protein that exists in different forms and
that's not true of all of our genes. Now, thousands and thousands of years ago, say hundreds of
thousands of years ago, there was really only one isoform to the best of our knowledge, correct?
And that's the one that today we give the moniker E4 to, is that correct? That's right.
So just for the sake of argument, a couple hundred thousand years ago, all of our ancestors had one
version of this gene, so you had two copies of the E4 because you have two copies of every gene.
And what do we believe was the reason for that? I mean, presumably evolution has strong pressure.
Do we have a sense of what an A-Pole E4, well, actually before we do that, Hussein, let's ask
maybe the more relevant question, which is when did that change and what was the next isoform to
show up and do we have a sense of why? So I'm not an evolutionary biologist to give you
accurate responses, but I can probably ask the first question better than the second question.
And I think fundamentally I was alluding to in a few minutes ago to an important inflammatory
function for A-Pole E. A-Pole E is capable of turning a cell into an acute inflammatory state,
especially glial cells or immune cells, such as the macrophage. When the cell expresses A-Pole E,
it changes quite substantially its lipid content and it might be better equipped to become an
inflamed cell or the opposite. When the cell exchanges A-Pole E, it's also better equipped
to be a less inflamed cell. I know these are contradicting statements, but you have to realize
that A-Pole E can regulate things. You know, you can turn your thermostat on and off. It's not
one thing or the other. It could be in different forms depending on the situation,
on the interaction, on the time. It can flip because of its structural flexibility. Now A-Pole E4,
which is our ancestral variant, has a greater capacity to aggregate than A-Pole E3 and A-Pole E2.
This aggregation means that they're not suspended in solution favors a strong inflammatory response.
So when A-Pole E4 starts aggregating inside a microglia, it makes an acute inflammatory response
much more efficient and much more directed toward what the microglia is fighting. So let's step back
and imagine that we are 300,000 to 200,000 years ago. And then out of every 10, 20 births,
few are surviving and the others are dying. From peripheral sepsis, from other forms of infection,
we know now that A-Pole E4 women had a better chance of giving child births and protection from
peripheral sepsis compared to non-E4 women in the slums of Brazil or in certain areas in Africa.
We know that based on studies that E4 confers some form of an advantage. We also know that those who
have had E4 may have had better luck surviving not only parasitic infections. So in certain
countries in Nigeria, people who have had the E4 and is anophilia tend to be much healthier
than E4 carriers without is anophilia. And more importantly, non-E4 carriers with is anophilia.
So if you are living in a place where parasites are common and they're constantly testing your
immune system, you are much better off carrying the A-Pole E4 allele than not.
Locally, the macrophage is much better equipped to deal with the parasite. And importantly,
your brain is much better equipped to deal with whether it's TB, meningitis, and the mother would
be better equipped to fight a septic event during childbirth. So from that perspective,
ApoE4 is our ancestral gene. Now what happened over the last few hundred thousand years,
perhaps maybe over the last few hundred years, and let's not go far, we turned from a septic
environment to gradually an aseptic environment. And the second change that happened is that we've
prolonged our lifespan. And I know that you have a deal interest in aging. So we have now,
it's surprising to me reading from history books that just a hundred years ago, we're not talking
a hundred thousand years ago, a hundred years ago, the mean age was something of the 47. Am I
making things up? Does that make sense to you? It depends on where you look, but it was a little
more than 47, a hundred years ago in the developed world. But you're right. I mean, I think about,
you could say about a hundred to 150 years ago was really when we saw a big uptick in lifespan.
Right. So if that's the case, and let's assume we're not talking about the the kings and queens
in England, and let's talk about those people living in Nigeria or in Africa, anywhere you
or in Brazil. And let's imagine that these people have several milestones that they have to go
through to be able to survive to their next decade. And you would notice two things. One,
that APU-E4 carriers are surviving better. Two, that you're not seeing a disadvantage of APU-E4,
because these people are not living to 80. Some of them would probably die at 50 or 60 or 70,
but certainly they may not have the resources to make it to 96. So what happens to E4 carriers
when they're dying at 60 or 65? I mean, what I'm trying to say is, what doesn't happen to APU-E4
carriers when they're dying at 65? They don't get Alzheimer's. In that regards, it might provide
a plausible explanation of why this ancestral gene worked for us in the past, but may not work for us
in this modern aging population. It's always been confusing to me why there was any evolutionary
pressure to create variants of E3 and E2, because the best of my reading is that the E3 showed up
about 50,000 years ago, and E2 showed up about 10,000 years ago. And again, from a functional
standpoint, 10,000, 50,000, and 100,000 are basically the same. Nobody was really living
long enough to recoup the benefit of Alzheimer's disease risk reduction going from 300,000 years
ago to 50,000 to 10,000. No, I would look at that from a different perspective. I would,
again, no anthropologist, and my knowledge is really as mediocre as any of your readers or listeners.
I would look at it as mass movement and change in environment. From 200,000 years to 100,000 years
ago, there was mass movement from the African continents all the way to Europe, and that was
associated with a drastic change in diet. My understanding is that there was a heavily
favored meat consumption, including fish, in the rift valleys in Africa and in the savannas. And
when they moved to a plant-based diet in Northern Europe and where they started farming, I think
that put pressure on APOE4 and allowed APOE3 and APOE2 to be more successful. And this is a
slightly different twist because APOE4, as much as it's very strong against inflammation, it thrives
on a specific dietary lipid-providing environment. And remember that APOE4, one of the fundamental
aspects that we learned from Alzheimer's is that APOE4 makes Glute 1 less successful at the
blood-brain barrier. So what APOE4 does, it somehow tells the brain, you know, I don't want you to be
eating sugar all the time. You have to be more resilient and rely on fat. And again, this is a
hypothesis. This is not based on true hard science, but the idea is that our ancestral APOE4
diets matched APOE4. And then when they moved to a plant-based diet, the effect of APOE4 on Glute 1
was now counterintuitive. Now there's more carbohydrates and you want something that
will help Glute 1 and not oppose it. And APOE3 and APOE2 would actually favor a more robust
Glute 1 expression of the blood-brain barrier, which means they favor a more glucose utilization
of the brain. So when did it first become apparent, either to epidemiologists or neurologists or
anybody else studying it for that matter, that these three isoforms predicted a very different
risk of Alzheimer's disease in modern humans? The story is we're in the late 80s and this is a time
where genetics is gaining traction. You know, I recently watched a very nice series, I think,
on PBS Masterpieces discussing how a revolution in genetic fingerprinting changed how we do policing,
figured out who is guilty and who's not. And that happened. What's interesting is that this
science was happening between 81 and 84. So around 1988-89, a researcher at Duke by the name of
Alan Rosas was running an Alzheimer's group and had access to a very robust, at that time robust
enough, obviously now it's not robust at all, but he had the ability to genetically profile a large
number of common variants of people dying with and without Alzheimer's. At that point in time,
he publishes a case series, a few hundreds, with and without Alzheimer's and identifies that
patients with Alzheimer's had substantially higher ApoE4 compared to non-Alzheimer's. And,
you know, remember that we have known ApoE4 since the 60s. So this is not a new discovery,
but we didn't know anything about ApoE4 and Alzheimer's disease until that time.
So he meets a lot of backlash because the prevailing hypothesis at that time is that Alzheimer's
is amyloid accumulating and leading to the amyloid cascade hypothesis where you form
amyloid plaques and then you get taut angles. And the field at that point was heavily vested in this
amyloid hypothesis. So Alan Rosas later on, a few years later, publishes a larger study,
which contains now longitudinal follow-up people, you know, progressing to disease and confirms the
observation that if you are an ApoE4 carrier, chances of getting Alzheimer's are substantially
higher than if you are a non-ApoE4 carrier. And we're talking about late onset Alzheimer's disease,
the most common form, which happens after the age of 60. So at that time, Alan Rosas cemented
his name as among those who identified the association of ApoE4 with AD. Do you have a
rough sense at the time, and I think it's probably quite different today, but do you have a broad
sense at the time of what the hazard ratios were of E44 versus 34 versus 33? I don't think the
hazard ratios would change substantially in a matter of two to three decades. So what we know
now is that if you have two copies of ApoE4, your chance of getting Alzheimer's increases 12 fold.
If you have one copy of ApoE4, your chance of having Alzheimer's increases anywhere from two to
four fold. And what does that matter, by the way, if it's a four, two, or a four, three? Yeah, so four,
three means you have one copy of ApoE4. And the question becomes a little difficult when you have
two, four, because two is supposed to be protective. Those who have ApoE2 are protected
from getting Alzheimer's disease. So the two, four carriers sometimes behave as four, sometimes
behave as two, and this might have to do with how well these proteins are getting expressed inside
the cells. And potentially other genes as well, like Tom40 or FGF and things like that that seem
to also play a role here, but or frankly, things that we haven't understood, like you see families
with a very involved family history, and they might only have one copy of the E4, but it's,
it's a, it behaves in a very virulent way. I mean, you see the same thing in cardiovascular disease
where some families have LP little a, and the level is not particularly high, but it still behaves
very aggressively. And you'll see other families where LP little a is, I mean, astronomically high,
and yet they seem largely spared of premature atherosclerosis. Correct. So I think one way to
rephrase the question is, how do we explain that not all ApoE4 carriers have the same risk of
Alzheimer's disease? And that's largely seen by ethnicity. So people who live in Nigeria,
for example, the risk of having Alzheimer's disease is substantially less than people who
live in the US or in Japan. The Hispanic Latino Latinx population carrying an E4 does not produce
the same risk of AD compared to white people or Japanese people carrying the ApoE4. So how do we
explain that? And that's a fundamentally important question. And as you just alluded to or noted,
ApoE4 is part of a gene locus that in other words, it's part of a haplotype.
That's a section of a chromosome where a bunch of gene variants are getting co-inherited.
They are within the same locus. So ApoE4 is found on chromosome 19. Around ApoE4 is approximately
20 to 30 different gene variants that happen to be co-inherited with ApoE4. And the description
between these gene variants are described by what we call linkage disequilibrium. If the
linkage disequilibrium is closer to one, it means every time you have ApoE4, let's assume now we're
talking about the long version of Tom40, you can have the long version of Tom40 expressed with it.
Now that linkage disequilibrium is what differs between ethnicities and can largely also explain
why certain ethnicities develop disease and certain don't. So as humans or generations are
getting interbred and crossed, the fidelity of this linkage disequilibrium can start getting
breached. Meaning now you can start introducing the short version of Tom40 next to ApoE4.
Or you can start introducing another version of ApoC1 or ApoC2 or ApoC3. All these are in the
same location as the ApoE, together with again another 20 to 30 other genes. So that doesn't
diminish the importance of ApoE4, but tells us that ApoE4 by itself may not be sufficient to
provide disease. It has to be in an environment that promotes its pathogenicity.
And all things equal, from a clinical perspective, we are more worried when someone of Asian or
Caucasian ethnicity has it versus someone of Latin or African descent. Is that a fair assessment?
Again, it's an oversimplification, but just based on the epidemiology and also based on frankly,
potentially what you said earlier, which is the origin of the gene. This is a gene that
takes its roots very early in our ancestry and offered an important protection.
And potentially by the time we migrated to a more northern climate, some of that protection
was less necessary. Again, that's a teleologic sort of hand waving rationalization. But is that
a safe assessment that everything you're saying risk is just going to be higher in Caucasians and Asians?
I wouldn't go with a blank statement. Maybe in general, yes, but maybe there are what we call
either gene-gene interactions or gene environment interactions that have to take into account.
Let me give you a simple example. In a Colombian study, they show that ApoE4 by itself may not
substantially increase the risk of Alzheimer's disease, but since diabetes is prevalent in a
certain city in Colombia, diabetics who were ApoE4 carriers had substantial increase in AD risk
compared to diabetics alone or ApoE4 carriers alone. And this is an example of a gene by
environment interaction. So just to be sure we got that right, E4 with diabetes was higher risk
than E4 without diabetes and higher risk than diabetes without E4. Yes. By way of comparison,
do you recall what the risk was of E4 without diabetes to diabetes without E4, which was second?
I don't recall the numbers, but I can tell you they were not striking at all. So when I actually
looked at the data, the E4 risk by itself seemed barely above non-E4 carriers. So if you looked at
it and you'd say, this is a healthy Colombian who's farming all day long, lean, and they have
absolutely no metabolic diseases, the E4 is doing nothing. Yeah. You mentioned something earlier
that I thought was super fascinating. I want to come back to it, which is some of the diet
interactions. So let's go back to where you left it, which was when talking about it through the
lens of the E4 carrier. The first thing you mentioned is, look, E4 makes GLUT1 less successful
at the blood-brain barrier. And you've already established for us that GLUT1 is basically
regulated by peripheral glucose concentration. Its purpose is to make sure that when glucose is
in low abundance, the brain gets first dibs on it, and that when glucose is in overly high
abundance, the brain is protected from it. So now you have an E4, you have a person who's an E4
variant, they're less sensitive to that mechanism. Presumably that means in an environment richer in
glucose, they're less able to appropriately partition fuel. Is that a safe assessment?
Yes. You can argue that in an environment that is rich of glucose, or maybe in a different term,
an insulin resistant environment, E4 carriers are less capable of regulating by many mechanisms in
gluting GLUT1, the fluctuations in glucose, and they're more susceptible to disease. But by no
means this is a restricted relationship of APOE4 to GLUT1, because we also know from studies that
we have done in others, that APOE4 also affect the transporters that transport omega-3 fatty
acids into the brain. Now we're going to come to that in a moment, because that of course is,
I mean, in many ways, one of the most interesting things to now talk about. But before we go there,
I do want to come back to this idea of, do we have an understanding of type 2 diabetes, which is
simply a very extreme version of insulin resistance and metabolic dysregulation, does it
disproportionately then, I hate to use the word, but punish carriers of APOE4 versus E3 versus E2?
Is that clearly established in the epidemiology? I don't think so.
I wouldn't look at it as type 2 diabetes is a distinct disease that punishes APOE4, because type
2 diabetes to me is a syndrome, not a disease. So what are we talking about? And it's frankly a
pretty significant spectrum for that matter. Correct. So are we talking about an individual
who is consuming a large amount of carbohydrates who gets type 2 diabetes? Are we talking about
APOE4 itself? Because as you probably may know, APOE4 by itself creates a system with aging that
makes an individual insulin resistant. So in one regards, APOE4 could be a factor for why a certain
person may get type 2 diabetes. So in that regards, APOE4 is not conspiring with type 2 diabetes
it might be behind type 2 diabetes. So you have to look at type 2 diabetes from a more individualized
causal, what's causing type 2 diabetes here? Is it the diet? Is it genetics? And how is APOE4
interacting with this phenotype is probably more complicated than an A1c and the genotype
in the large population. Because when you look deep enough into these studies, you find quite
a bit of discordant results that makes it hard to explain. You sort of alluded to it earlier that
the E4 carriers as they migrated, ancestrally say out of Africa or even out of South America,
were primarily consuming a diet lower in carbohydrates, presumably higher in protein
and fat. Do we have any reason to believe today that there is a rationale for matching diet to
genotype? So right now in major studies that looked at APOE4 dietary patterns in the Western world,
they don't differ by genotype. So if you're looking at the US or Europe, an APOE4 carrier
may well likely be eating a similar diet, a non-carrier. Now would that lead to the same
detrimental effect? Yeah, sorry. My question is less about the existing dietary pattern and more
of the prospective ask of is there a reason to change dietary pattern to produce a better outcome?
Yes, of course. So this is part of what we're studying is how does APOE4 interact with the
diet and how that interaction can change disease processes. And what we know is that the first
concept that your listeners should be aware of is that APOE4 is a disease of aging.
Do you mean Alzheimer's disease is a disease of aging?
Or? Alzheimer's disease is a disease of aging, but APOE4 risk of developing Alzheimer's and aging
related diseases is fundamentally based on the aged model. Younger 35 year olds, APOE4 carriers,
to my knowledge, do not have frank presentations of a disease. A younger APOE4 carrier who could
be myself or you or anybody else could be fully functional. It's only when you hit a certain age
that APOE4 carriers start to have problems and not all of them. So the majority of APOE4 carriers,
you may argue, are surviving, they're striving, they're doing okay. So there's only a subset of
APOE4 carriers who are aging and getting disease. So then the question is, who are these people?
How do we explain them? Is it only generics or is there a dietary genetic interaction?
And I think the answer to this question has to do with what is happening with these people as they
age. Are they developing other diseases? Are they, for example, we know that an APOE4 carriers who
happen to be the victim of a traumatic brain injury has much worse outcomes than that without
traumatic brain injury. We know that an APOE4 carrier possibly with type 2 diabetes may have
worse outcomes than an APOE4 carrier without. But again, as I mentioned to you, this is a little bit
more complicated because not all type 2 diabetes is the same. We know that an APOE4 carrier who
may have a second head could be a genetic second head. They're inheriting another protein that
increases the risk of Alzheimer's disease. Now their path toward disease is much more accelerated.
So what we also know is that as we age, our ability, ourselves,
lose the ability to regenerate and to sustain a certain status. And that is associated with
lapses in energy production. That is associated with several complications, which include at the
blood-brain barrier, a reduced ability to express those Glut1 transporters, Omega-3 transporters,
and even ketone body transporters. So the aging APOE4 individual who has second and third heads
is now straining the brain and leading to an environment where in this situation
the diet may make a difference. Another angle to look at this question is there are certain diets
and you know coming from the cardiovascular background, we both agree that there are certain
diets that can accelerate aging or create a form of stress that can be the second head that APOE4
carriers are exposed to accelerate toward an aging brain that is diseased. I know the answers
may not be crystal clear, but the diet interaction with APOE4 is contingent upon aging and a second
or a third head. But what seems interesting and what you just said to me is a big part of the
manner in which APOE4 transmits its risk to the individual is through an energy crisis.
Much of what you said had to do with substrate. It had to do with reducing
the utilization of and or access to substrate. Is that a fair assessment? That is one hypothesis.
It's a prevailing energy hypothesis that links APOE4 with disease and aging. There are other
hypotheses which do not have to be exclusive of this hypothesis, meaning that you could also have
an energy slash inflammation differences that predispose APOE4 to neuroinflammation
and that by itself could lead to an accelerated disease pathway. You could also have an APOE4
backslash. It could be a vascular component here as well. Yeah, a vascular or leakage component.
There's a group at USC where I work that has shown that there is leakage in the
blood-brain barrier allowing toxins to get into the brain and shrink cells. That is by itself
non-exclusively related to the dietary or the inflammation. We do not want to say,
this is it and that's only it. It is plausible that there are multiple heads,
but you could look at it from different angles. Well, not only that, I mean those hits are
synergistic and in the wrong direction. If you have leaky blood-brain barrier and you're more
predisposed to inflammation, which again, as you pointed out, was very helpful 300,000 years ago
when we were fraught with parasites, you now have two hits within the same hit, which is you're more
likely to get toxins across the blood-brain barrier, which is bad in and of itself. Then secondly,
you're more likely to have an overreactive immune response to it. If you couple that
with say a third hit of neuronal energy starvation, these things begin to circle.
Let's pivot for a moment now to another enormous area of focus for you, which is the role of omega
3 fatty acids. This is such an interesting topic. There's nobody listening to this who hasn't heard
of omega 3 fatty acids. Even if they haven't heard of them in exactly those terms, people have
certainly heard the terms EPA and DHA. There's no shortage of confusion about these things.
I guess for the odd person who maybe just doesn't know exactly what we're talking about, can you
give just a brief overview of what EPA and DHA are and why we spend so much time and energy
trying to study and understand their role in human health? There isn't really a short answer
to a complicated question like this one, but in a nutshell, when you break down the components of
the brain, you find that a significant portion, in some studies 50 or 40 percent of the brain is
composed of polyunsaturated fatty acids such as DHA, EPA, and arachidonic acid AA. The EPA, DHA,
and add to that alpha linoleic acid ALA are known as omega 3s. In contrast, arachidonic acid is in
omega 6. So the brain is highly enriched in both omega 3s and omega 6s, and you contemplate why.
Why do we have so much of these fatty acids in the brain? And the fundamental answer has to do
with membrane fluidity. Having polyunsaturated fatty acids in neuronal membrane facilitates
to a large extent the neuronal firing that we just talked about in the beginning. So this
composition of fat allows the brain or the neurons to conduct their work very efficiently.
So DHA is the predominant building block, the most commonly found omega 3 in the brain.
EPA is not that common. DHA or docosa hexanoic acid is given that name because of the number
of fatty acids and the number of double bonds. It's six. EPA has five of, and we're talking about
the location of the double bonds in the structure of DHA or EPA. EPA is not very abundant
in the brain, but that doesn't mean it's not very important. EPA is less abundant but has
perhaps stronger anti-inflammatory effects than DHA. There is limited interconversion between DHA
and EPA, but DHA can become EPA. And also EPA can become DHA, but that process is also limited.
The reason people talk about omega 3s and they make a big deal out of it is because the human
body doesn't have an efficient system to make them from scratch. In fact, you can't make them
from scratch. If you want to make them, you need a precursor known as alpha-alinoic acids or ALA
by a group of desaturases. ALA can get transformed into DHA and EPA. However, it is widely believed
that only 0.5% of DHA and EPA are made from conversion of ALA. That number though, you have
to take it with a grain of salt because there might be evidence that in diets vegetarians or
vegans who do not eat fish, that conversion rate may actually be much higher. But despite that,
that conversion rate has not been documented to exceed 5%. So at the most, 5% of DHA and EPA
can come from ALA, although most people argue that it's only 0.5%. So what does that mean for us?
If we can't make DHA and EPA and we rely on diet to get them, what does it mean that we are not
getting them? So what I've just alluded to is the US diet. And you probably know as much as I do
even more that the US diet is not enriched in DHA or EPA. The consumption of DHA and EPA in the US,
I can give you an example, DHA is averaging 100 milligrams per day, is low. That consumption
may not provide enough omega-3s to the brain. And the question is, does that result in disease?
And the answer is likely, yes. Now what we don't know is the supplementing people with omega-3s
make a difference. And the answer to that question is, at this point we don't know that that makes a
difference. Simply because research on supplements have not panned out. It's very conflicted. There
are positive studies, there are negative studies, and the supplements themselves are quite distinct
and different in production and concentrations and quantities and qualities. So I know I have
alluded to a lot of different aspects of this field, but the answer to your question is that
these omega-3 fatty acids are important for the brain. We can't make them efficiently and we're
not consuming enough of them. And as you also alluded to, when we supplement them, they can come
in various forms, right? We can get them from microalgae, which tend to be triglyceride based.
We can refine them from fish oils directly, which are ethyl esters, or they can come from
krill oils, which are phospholipid based. Does that sound about right? Yes, yes. You can get
omega-3s from all these sources. It basically has to be marine. I mean, that's sort of the bottom
line is it has to have some sort of tie to algae or microalgae either being consumed by other
things like fish. And it's funny, I sort of remember many years ago reading something very
interesting that explained why EPA and DHA had to have some sort of a marine origin predominantly,
and it had to do with the formation of the third carbon double bond. And I can't remember any more
than that. Does that ring a bell, anything about this? I can tell you that the complexity of the
structural distribution of these double bonds requires a certain machinery to make them that
is present in algae. Now, why wouldn't other species make it? I don't know. Yeah, it had to do exactly
with the very, very complex carbon fixation that only algae could do. Let's start with what we know.
You have a pretty good sense that people who have higher levels of EPA and DHA from consumption of
fish have better outcomes than people who don't. Do we know that pretty well? I don't know. I honestly
don't know if this is very clear. What my knowledge is, is that the opposite might be closer to truth,
meaning that people who don't eat at all fish or seafood or omega-3 rich diets might be at a higher
increased risk of disease as opposed to the other statement, which means people who eat a lot of them
have less disease. So what I'm trying to point out is that there could be a deficiency state that
predisposes somebody to disease, but once you meet that threshold, you may or may not get much more
benefit. Yeah. So in other words, you can get scurvy from insufficient vitamin C, but there's
probably little evidence to suggest that supplementing vitamin C offers health protection and benefit
beyond the RDA. Yes. By the way, for what it's worth, I believe that's true with vitamin C. I
think there's no evidence to suggest it's helpful in massive doses. Nevertheless, there's been no
shortage of attempts to study this question, and there have been some significant studies that have
gone to great lengths to do this. Now, although we're talking about the brain, you are no stranger
to the heart. So can we pivot for a moment to talk about a very interesting study published
probably about 18 months ago that looked at a very high dose of EPA, four grams, in individuals
with elevated triglycerides and a number of other risks. And I have to be honest with you, to my
surprise, produced kind of an amazing outcome. It was not what I expected. Of course, I'm speaking
about the REDUCE-IT study. Do you want to give people just a quick overview of that study and
what it found and what your thoughts are on that study? So the background is some Japanese studies
over a decade ago has suggested that a certain EPA to arachidonic acid ratio was associated with
substantially less cardiovascular disease in certain regions in Japan. And there were some trials
in Japan at that point that have attempted supplementing EPA, and the results were positive,
but they were not conclusive. So they were using something around two grams of EPA,
and they found out some trends which were very exciting, but again, they were not strong enough
to make an official recommendation. So somehow this led to a concerted effort in the US to try
to answer this question. Can we give high doses of EPA to mimic this ratio that they found in Japan
of EPA consumption and translate into less cardiovascular events? So it became an interesting
question to pursue, and the REDUCE-IT investigators decided to go ahead and run a large
multi-center trial where they gave four grams of pure EPA, and they selected people who they
thought would benefit the most from this intervention, and those included people with
diabetes, high triglycerides, because EPA is known to lower triglycerides, and they monitored them for
cardiovascular events over a period of a few years. And they found out that compared to their placebo
arm, those who were given four grams of EPA per day did substantially better. The study had one
flaw, and I don't know if it's a fatal flaw or not, I think that needs to be figured out. The placebo
in that arm was not your typical placebo. So typically when you do omega-3 or fatty acid
intervention trials, the most common placebo is corn oil, soybean oil, and in this case,
so they used mineral oil, and they were criticized at the time of publication whether EPA indeed
reduced cardiovascular events or did mineral oil increase cardiovascular events. Before we leave
that, let's understand that a bit more. So corn oil, safflower, canola, those are more E6 than E3.
They have a little bit of ALA in them, and they still have some monounsaturated fats in them, but
is it safe to say that they're probably more than 50% omega-6? Yes, but the concentrations given in
them is not high. The concentration of E6 is really a low amount. These people are not consuming
grams of E6. And what's mineral oils breakdown? What's it formed from? I mean, my only interaction
with mineral oil is to polish my cutting board, you know, or to make sure my cutting board doesn't
get too dry. Yeah, I mean, to be honest with you, I don't know. But all of this came after the fact.
We've never considered in our trials mineral oil because it was never an option, and it was very
obscure that that mineral oil was chosen in that trial to be the placebo. And I don't think they
even thought about this until the study was published. And then people started asking.
I see. Yeah. And I mean, I think mineral oil, frankly, is totally different. I mean,
I don't, it's probably more resembles like a petroleum based product or something like that.
I don't think it's like a fatty acid in the sense that corn oil is or anything like that.
Yeah, that is odd that they would use that. But they were given presumably four grams of
mineral oil every day as well in a placebo. Right. And I think the decision to make or to
create mineral oil as the placebo at that point in time was not thought of from a health perspective,
but mostly from maybe what's available or economic or matching the taste of the intervention itself.
So there was indeed thinking about what would happen if you added so much mineral oil.
In a study like this one. And I think the investigators have regretted that decision,
but in hindsight is always 20, 20. Yeah. And it's certainly a plausible explanation,
given just how significant the effect was in reduce it. I mean, it was wasn't the absolute
risk reduction, something on the order of 4% or something like that. I mean, it was
an exit. It was certainly on par with what you see in some of the most potent drug trials.
Yes. Yes. And this was surprising. And what's important is in science, you always have to be
skeptical and you always need to find whether any particular study can be replicated or not before
you make strong recommendations and adopt any drastic change in how you are consuming certain
things or whether it's a medication or a diet or a supplement. So the company was able to make
very strong claims that high doses of EPA are important addition to the standard management of
diabetes, cardiovascular disease, atherosclerosis at the time of its publication, and even urged
the FDA to add that indication, which the FDA appeared to agree to. But at the same time,
other studies were going on the pipeline to confirm, although they did not use the same
identical ethyl ester EPA, because that is perhaps patented by the company that made
that particular drug. And I don't want to mention any particular drug in the show because I'm not
trying to promote anything. So long story short, what we have learned from the American Heart
Association a few months ago is that high doses of EPA did not translate into cardiovascular
benefit when compared to corn oil or the other standard form of. Now you're referring to the
strength trial, correct? Yes. Now, was that a high dose of EPA or was that EPA and DHA combined?
It was predominantly a high dose EPA, although I think there was DHA in it. The predominant form
that was given was EPA. And what was the dose? That was four grams omega three. Yeah, I think
you're right. I think it was probably about three grams and one gram is my recollection.
Yeah, I can look at them. I do not want to give your listeners any inaccurate information. So if
you like, we could just look up, but it was a predominantly EPA supplement. Yeah. And as you
said, when compared to a corn oil, that study showed essentially zero difference between them.
So again, what's different, right? So it begs the question, is the mineral oil the problem in the
first study was the dose not correct through or the ratio of three to one of EPA to DHA?
Is it simply irrelevant? To your point earlier, maybe these people didn't have a deficiency
and supplementing to excess made no difference. The other thing is these were relatively sick
patients, right? These were patients that I can't recall off the top of my head what the
strength patients looked like. But if they were anything like the reduce it patients,
which I remember more, I mean, almost 80% of these patients had type two diabetes,
all of them had dyslipidemia. So the other argument is, is four years of treating patients
that are at high, high risk of major adverse cardiac event, enough time to steer the shift.
Are you better off treating people in their forties for two decades to try to mitigate that risk?
And I think, frankly, that question probably becomes even more interesting from the standpoint
of brain health and heart health, right? Where we have fewer options. Let me tell you that how I
think about this, and it may or may not make sense to you or to your readers. When we're talking
about reduce it or EPA, are we talking about a supplement or are we talking about a drug?
In the case of reduce it, it's a drug. I mean, that's a pharmaceutical prescribed drug.
Right. So this distinction is important because if we're talking about a drug,
then we are thinking about the cascade. We're thinking of you give a status, you inhibit
HMG coa reductase, you decrease the expression of the L or you increase the expression of the LDL
receptor in the liver, and then you suck cholesterol circulating by LDL or VLDL particles,
and you excrete it. You lower LDL cholesterol. You decrease small dense on atherogenic LDL
cholesterol particles that translate into less atherosclerosis. And then this translates into
less cardiovascular events. This is the prevailing hypothesis of how we view statins work. Now,
if I were to ask you, how does EPA work? How does it reduce cardiovascular events? And if we can
come up with a cascade similar to that of statins, I think we can argue that you could use HIDO's EPA
as a drug. But if we're stuttering and we can't really map the actual cycle, we might be fishing
for results. Yeah. And it's also interesting when, I mean, I don't think this analysis has been done,
but it would be a clever study would be like a pairing study where you take the same patients,
of course, and you pair one group to phenofibrate to another with HIDO's EPA such that they get
equal reduction of triglycerides and you ask the question, does that make a difference? In other
words, how much of this benefit, if any, comes from the triglyceride reduction, which all things
equal, is going to lower APO-B concentration as you reduce the lipid carrying capacity of lipoprotein.
And is that the mechanism? Now, again, that's more of a thought experiment. I can't imagine
anybody would go and do the actual study of trilipix versus vicepa, but you're right. We don't
have a very clear mechanistic pathway for why this would make sense. One possibility, although I'm
not trying to be against or for EPA, I'm just trying to think out loud, one possibility is that
EPA has potent anti-inflammatory effects. And it is plausible that EPA, not by any triglyceride
lowering potential, but by a local anti-inflammatory effect on the plaques, has resulted in less plaque
rupture and less events. But again, these are all ideas because we don't fully understand what
happened and why they did get substantial reduction in the events. Now, this is irrelevant because,
you know, to me, I don't study right now cardiovascular disease and I'm not trying to
understand exactly an application for EPA on patients at risk of heart disease. But my lab
is more interested in figuring out a link between omega-3s and the brain. And the reason why I
brought to reduce it, or we brought this example of high dose EPA and cardiovascular disease,
is to contrast completely different systems. Unlike cardiovascular disease, where you have a
very well described process where you have a plaque that ruptures and you get an event,
your typical Alzheimer's dementia is often a chronic low-grade slow process that happens over
years and that eventually manifests in loss of function of daily activities, cognitive deficits,
and so forth. The role of DHA in this disease is more closer to the analogy that you used with
scurvy. In landmark studies done decades ago at NIH, they showed when you took a mouse model and
you deprived the pregnant mice from DHA completely, and then you looked at her
offsprings, they found that these baby litters, the offsprings of the mouse, had a condition that
we call microcephaly, where the brain failed to form and develop and was very small. When you
looked under the microscope, you found out that these neurons formed from a DHA deficient diet
were not making enough synapses under the microscope compared to neurons who were exposed
to a deficient or a non-deficient or a regular child diet when the mother was nursing or having
the children in utero. So that by itself told us that DHA deficiency is detrimental to the function
of the brain. Now we also know from many studies that in humans during development not having
enough polyunsaturated fatty acids, whether it's lactating breast milk or in the diet itself,
was associated with poorer outcomes in school. And these are large studies published in the 90s,
which have led the FDA in 2001 or 2002, I believe, to agree to the recommendation of supplementing
infant formula with both DHA and arachidonic acid AA. So any listeners who has bought
infant formula or any have used infant formula and if they look at the actual formula, they see the
tag DHA and AA fortified. So the concept that there is something called DHA or EPA or omega-3
deficiency exists is probably solid. Now what's less known or more confusing or more difficult
to ascertain is that what age range does this deficiency make the largest impact and how does
aging affect that deficiency question? So to put this question in a different perspective,
the brain develops rapidly from conception to possibly three to five years. And by the age of
six, the human brain is almost fully developed. And then you start slowly accreting. Accretion
refers to the tension of lipids and material such as protein in the structure of the brain,
where it's not exchanging with plasma anymore or blood. So it's kind of stuck in the brain.
So the accretion of lipids or omega-3s in the brain slows considerably between the ages of
six all the way to 12 and 13. And then beyond that, the pools are relatively stable and expansion of
brain size is very slow. And then after certain age cutoffs like 60s and above, you start seeing
the opposite where atrophy starts to happen with aging. So we can clearly visualize that figure and
grasp the concept that during rapid accretion of lipids, it's really important for babies and
kids to get exposed to enough omega-3s to allow the brain to fully develop. And that doesn't have
to be supplementation. That could well be a good diet. Now what happens between the ages of six
and 60 is quite elusive, meaning that what happens to a population that is 35 that is
completely not consuming any omega-3s? Are they in any diseased states? And I can't point out a
single large study that can say yes. All what I can point out too is a myriad of small studies
which show discrepant results. Some studies suggest that are subtle cognitive impairments.
Other studies suggest anxiety disorders, mood disorders, depression. But other studies don't
find these associations. So that tells us that the role of omega-3 in the diet between the ages of
six and 60 is more difficult to understand. Now that doesn't mean it's not important.
Is there any scenario in which having lower consumption of EPA and DHA is beneficial in
those small studies? Or is this basically a difference of neutral to negative?
I think it's the latter, neutral to negative. But I think the concept that I haven't discussed yet,
but might be important to understand, is that the half-life of lipids in the brain
is quite different than the half-life of lipids in different compartments in the body. So for
example, if you take DHA or EPA and you study after somebody is injected or consumed, labeled
DHA or EPA, how long does it take for the DHA or EPA to disappear from blood? You understand that
it takes a matter of weeks. Within three to six weeks that dose will disappear and the opposite
is true. It takes three to six weeks for the dose to reach plateauing or saturation kinetics after
being fed a maximal dose of DHA or EPA. So that has to do with the half-life of these lipids on
the transporting proteins such as HDL. So HDL may define the half-life because it's going to be the
major carrier of phospholipids. Now when we talk about other compartments such as the brain,
that may not be the case. The amount of time that DHA hangs out in neuronal membranes is
substantially longer than the amount of time that DHA hangs out on the surface of a phospholipid on
HDL or with an albumin carrier and blood. And you know if we think about this more deeply,
that makes sense. We do not want brains that are fluctuating with DHA and AA. We want a stable
depot of lipids that does not dramatically fluctuate. So what does that mean? That means
if you took somebody in a trial where they're not consuming DHA or EPA and then you gave them
high doses of DHA and EPA and you know if you look at these trials they range anywhere from 12 weeks
to a year and the majority are three months or six months, it's not surprising that these trials
are finding not much. And in fact when they find something, most of the time it's either a gut
effect or an inflammatory effect because some of these omega-3s have anti-inflammatory effects.
So that presents a distinct challenge to the omega-3 field is that we may not have the resources to do
a five or a ten year study. But we are privy to epidemiology studies which can give us a longer
vision of what happens to those who consume enough omega-3s versus those who don't consume
omega-3s at all. And then I'll just layer in the question to bring it back to our discussion of APOE,
do we have a flavor to add to this which is how does everything you say change in the context of
APOE type, if at all? It does. So this is what my lab is particularly interested in solving,
which is what is the best diet that we can give an APOE for a carrier to actually prevent cognitive
decline. So we've been doing studies to examine this from multiple angles and one of the studies
that we found is that we took younger 35 year old APOE4 carriers and injected them with labeled DHA
into their blood. And we estimated how much DHA is getting into the brain using a PET scan.
And what we found is that younger APOE4 carriers had greater uptake of DHA in their brain compared
to non-carriers, meaning that a younger cognitively normal APOE4 carrier is sucking all the DHA it can
take from blood to maintain a certain form of cognitive profile, to maintain your normal
cognitive behavior. And APOE4 carriers love the DHA it's seeing in blood and the brain of an
E4 carrier is on fire. It's firing more and it is using the DHA that is sucked from the blood.
And that could probably provide us some deep insights about our ancestors and their diets. I
mean we know that APOE4 carrier rate is highest in Africa. We know that E4 carriers in Africa were
consuming possibly more fish and meat than E4 carriers in Asia or E4 carriers in Europe. So
in that regard we looked at epidemiology studies and found you know a relatively large epidemiology
study from Finland suggesting that E4 carriers who consumed a good amount of fatty fish combined with
red leafy vegetables antioxidants, when you looked at these individuals two decades or more into the
future when they were 60, those who were consuming the highest amounts of omega-3s from fish and other
sources in the diet had substantially and significantly less disease than those who were not.
So to us that gave us insights that perhaps the younger APOE4 brain loves to consume omega-3s.
Now I hope the story ends here and you know that that gives us a nice recommendation but it doesn't
because we were continuously studying APOE4 carriers across the age spectrum and what we
found is that after a certain age and I would say this goes anywhere from 55 to 70, the ability of
the APOE4 brain to capture APOE4 from blood gets compromised and this happens around the same time.
That the GLUT1 receptors are compromised. This happens around the same time that the blood
brain barrier itself starts to get compromised because you have to imagine that the blood
brain barrier is tightly coupled so when it starts disintegrating your GLUT1s are not working,
your omega-3 transporters are not working. So what does that mean? So we were part of a large
randomized clinical trial where patients with mild Alzheimer's disease were fed
high doses of DHA versus placebo over a period of a year and a half and what that trial found
is that in this trial two grams of omega-3s had no effect on everyone, zero effect. The trial was
negative, was published in 2010 in JAMA and the lead author was Joe Quinn. When we looked at that
trial we tried to understand how the APOE4 affected the response and in that trial APOE4
carriers had zero response and non-carriers appeared to improve on the primary outcome,
the ADAS-COG and on the secondary outcome which is the MLSE. So in that trial APOE4 carriers were
less likely to respond than non-carriers. And again the age of those participants was what?
These people were between 65 and 80.
Got it. And was that DHA only or EPA and DHA in that two grams?
That was DHA only.
And what you said earlier about the young people massively assimilating DHA, was that also shown
with EPA or only DHA?
We were only studying DHA. For the main reason is that the DHA is the main omega-3 that makes the
building blocks of synapses in the brain and EPA more behaves as a signaling molecule that's
anti-inflammatory. So an application for EPA in the brain may be quite different than DHA.
So if you're more focused on vascular disease and perhaps the small embolic or thrombotic
atherosclerotic strokes then an EPA application may make more sense. But if you're looking at
the synapse and what it requires to form neurotransmission we think from a DHA perspective.
So what you just described fits with the previous observation which is
there may be a critical window in which DHA is essential and once you're outside of that window
you lose the ability to integrate or assimilate DHA at about the same time your blood-brain
barrier is failing and your ability to regulate even glucose is beginning to diminish.
Absolutely. So you hit it right on. We are actively doing a large trial that we have called
Prevent E4 to partially address this question. If we took younger April E4 carriers before they have
dementia or before they have clinical symptoms can we show any effect on the brain? And we had this
immensely challenging question of should we look at 30 to 40 year olds or should we look at
55 to 70 year olds? And in 2017 we made the decision to look at the 55 to 70 year olds because
those people do cognitively decline with time. So we have the opportunity within two to three years
to figure out if they're dropping. If we did this trial in a 35 year old we may end up with a futile
study because neither arm would change. So we are running a big risk though. It is plausible that
between the ages of 55 and 70 you're still too late. So where do you hold this? Where do you go?
E4 is unknown but Prevent E4 is ongoing. It started in 2019 and unfortunately now because of
Covid we had to hold and Los Angeles had a substantial share of Covid cases. So we have
we had to hold recruitment in the last six months but hopefully you know we hope to open recruitment
again in the next few months. The study will possibly wrap up in 2023 and get published
between 2024 and 2025. So that's an ongoing effort where we're giving two grams high dose DHA
based on a pilot study that we have done before showing that you need higher doses of DHA to get
into the brain. In APOE 4 carriers who do not have cognitive disease yet they may have mild
disease but definitely not dementia. And to see whether APOE you know high dose DHA supplementation
can slow down the progression of disease in this population. So again of course the experiment that
can't be done is taking the 35 year old E4 carriers putting them on DHA for the rest of their lives
because you're basically giving them DHEA at the time when you know they can assimilate it and
following them for long enough to see a hard outcome which is is there a meaningful reduction
in the actual disease we care about studying. Since that experiment can't be done and will
never be done we then have to basically think about this through the lens of this is a question
that medicine does not have a tool to solve through the neat package called the clinical trial.
Yeah the way to approach this problem would actually be finding surrogate biomarkers that
you believe and trust that will hold long and behold. For example we now maybe in the last five
years have finally agreed that LDL cholesterol is a good target to lower for cardiovascular disease
prevention. Although every now and then you'd get somebody who shows you lower LDL cholesterol may
not translate into cardiovascular events but for the most of people in the field agree that lowering
an LDL cholesterol by a statin or by azetamide or by any other measurement can associate with
less atherosclerosis. Can we find a biomarker in 35-45 year old individuals a brain biomarker
where if you change it you would convince most people that this may protect you against dementia
or cognitive decline a couple of decades. That's a fundamentally important question that needs to
be tackled because without brain biomarkers we may not be able to answer these complicated questions.
I mean I'm a bit skeptical that we're going to find anything anytime soon that fits exactly
that description and I think it's worth noting that one of the first drugs ever approved to lower
LDL did so but did not reduce events. I'm blanking on the name of the drug but it actually
was a drug that inhibited the enzyme that converted desmosterol to cholesterol. I think
it's something called delta 60 saturase or something and in doing so it did lower cholesterol
and by extension LDL cholesterol although frankly at the time they probably only looked at total
cholesterol but events actually went up presumably because desmosterol went up so much and acted as
a sterile that had the same oxidizing properties. In the end you know events matter but you're right
look most drugs today that lower ApoB also reduce events but in the absence of such a biomarker
or functional study you know it doesn't have to be a biomarker I guess if you had
you know an imaging study or a functional study that you know could matter you know
hippocampal volume if we believe that that was sensitive enough but absent that it still comes
down to a question of what's the asymmetry of risk on each side right so option one is do nothing
option two is either through diet or supplement take a given amount of DHA what is the downside
of the latter what is the downside of the former I think those are questions that we have to spend
more time thinking about because I don't think that clinical trials can give us answers to some
of the most important questions facing disease prevention yeah and so this is exactly where
diseases like Alzheimer's disease or vascular dementia or any form of dementia represents a deep
painstaking challenge compared to atherosclerosis where you can have an event within a couple of
years and still see an effect on plaque reduction lower event rates whether it's MI or amputations
or strokes dementia on the other hand is much more subtle much more complicated and requires
completely new set of tools and as we speak there's a massive amount of brain imaging studies
from functional MRIs to PET scans that are looking at different tracers including amyloid
and tau which to date have not really panned out in the AD field but with the premise that we can
find a biomarker that if you can modulate can predict something a decade later so one more
thing that I just want to share with you before we wrap up is that you know my lab has also done
very exciting studies that will be published in the next two to three months showing that the
older apoE4 brain once it gets into the dementia stage starts upregulating enzymes that facilitates
its own auto digestion because of the failure in utilizing glucose as a source of energy
we find that enzymes like phospholipase A2 are upregulated and activated in the apoE4 brain
to perhaps extract fatty acids from its own myelin sheath to produce ATP and that tells us
about that the recommendations that we should give the younger apoE4 carrier may be completely
different than a recommendation that we give an older apoE4 carrier who is in a state of energy
deprivation and energy failure say a little bit more about that I mean you're talking about someone
who now actually is in the stages of early cognitive decline who presumably I mean when
you say auto digesting I mean you're referring to an enzymatic degradation of the cell
yes so what we did is in the last three years we've looked at enzymes that control omega 3s
and omega 6s in the brain and we found out that a specific enzyme known as phospholipase A2
which is the calcium dependent version of phospholipase A2 is strongly upregulated in
Alzheimer disease brains who carry the apoE4 genotype compared to
non-alzheimer disease brains who carry the apoE4 genotype so we had access to a large database of
brain tissues from rush rush has one of the largest Alzheimer disease research centers in the country
and we looked at many enzymes and stumbled across CPLA2 and showed that CPLA2 is hyper activated
or phosphorylated in E4AD brains so you've got the apoE4 carriers who developed AD as opposed to
the apoE4 carrier who died without AD and we found that the apoE4 AD brain activates these
enzymes which take away fatty acids from the phospholipid membrane and then perhaps
degrades the fatty acid to be used for many reasons to us the most obvious reason why you
are extracting fatty acids from phospholipid is possibly to generate ATP now there is a side effect
to doing that and that would be neuroinflammation and oxidative stress and i assume that this is
something you're not seeing in the non-E4 carrier who is in this in the comparable stage of dementia
we are not seeing the same pattern of activation in a non-E4 carrier who has a comparable state of
dementia that's correct now there's a lot of people out there who are talking about things
like ketone supplementation so not using not necessarily using ketosis in its nutritional
or starvation form but even using exogenous ketones as a supplemental fuel is there any
reason to believe that that or a nutritional approach to ketosis would be a benefit to somebody
with E4 especially when they're in that second wave or is the answer well by anything that's
going to prevent glucose from getting into the brain sufficiently is probably going to prevent
ketones from getting there too you have you know fantastic insights and questions so i think
people have thought about ketone meals ketone body meals for treatment of dementia and the
largest studies to date have shown that E4 carriers once they have the disease are reluctant
or less likely to benefit from the supplementation compared to non-carriers and exactly to your point
it is possible that the degenerating blood-brain barrier is compromising the transport of ketone
bodies the same way it has compromised glucose and the same way it has compromised omega-3 fatty
acids so that makes us think that the aging Alzheimer's disease brain is a late stage that
is refractory to the unless you are trying to fix the fundamental issue that is related to
nutrient transport by a medication or an intervention dietary interventions at this stage
may not be very effective and highlights the importance of getting the right intervention
before you get to that stage to prevent it from happening i hate being asked questions like i'm
about to ask you so forgive me but you know that everybody listening to this and by definition
about 25 percent of these people listening to this are going to be a carrier of at least one
variant of E4 so this is a very relevant question what do you recommend to people let's just limit
this to people who are you know have no stage of disease i mean you've certainly made the case for
dha yeah so i don't recommend omega-3 supplementation for a simple reason we don't have the evidence to
sub to actually support once we publish or others publish high quality evidence supporting going to
to a pharmacy and picking up a supplement until that happens i don't think we have the evidence
to support omega-3 supplements but what i do recommend though is for people to take at least
one serving of fatty fish per week we know from epidemiology apoE4 carriers who consume
one serving of fatty fish per week may be providing enough omega-3s to their brains
and helping themselves long term is there anything else that you have learned in your travels
vis-a-vis exercise other things within nutrition i know that's not the focus of your research but
do we know anything about the E4 carriers being more benefited if such a term exists
through exercise i mean we know the importance of exercise in Alzheimer's prevention is enormous
but do we know if E4s bend one way or the other in that wind we don't have high quality randomized
clinical trials but we may have some epidemiology studies Morris and his team at WashU have shown
in a PET study this is an imaging study where you scan amyloid load in the brain that apoE4 carriers
who exercise has have less amyloid plaque buildup compared to apoE4 carriers who do not exercise
now again we would need an intervention to demonstrate that but as we discussed in a minute
it's very difficult to find younger apoE4 carriers put them in a lifestyle intervention and then
look at the outcome three to four to a decade later logistically it's complicated and expensive
we also know from a Swedish group that looked at multiple factors of what determines pathology in
apoE4 carriers and they concluded that a high level of education hypertension control
protected apoE4 carriers from dementia compared to apoE4 carriers who had less education and
worse blood pressure control so to answer your question i think if you knew at birth that you
had apoE4 if your parents knew and you have the ethnicity the risk the family history the best
advice that we have is to maintain an adequate omega-3 consumption from fatty fish not supplements
to make sure that the blood pressure is controlled and to make sure that there is some at least
minimal amount of exercise carried out throughout the lifespan to provide a modifiable element to
the apoE4 and when we talk about modifying apoE4 risk we often are referring to modifying the
vascular effects of apoE4 so not only will you get cardiovascular benefit but you will also get
brain benefit because the blood vessels in Alzheimer's disease have as much of a role as
the actual neurons and astrocytes and so forth. Hussein this has been very interesting again i
think a lot of people are going to find this to be relevant to themselves or to people that they
care about i won't lie it's a little frustrating that we're still so early in the in the study of
this something that is so relevant and i believe probably quite preventable if we had a better sense
of what the interventions were and i think you're absolutely right biomarkers and or other functional
imaging studies would really speed things up if we could do clinical trials in two years and get
answers we'd be a lot better often if we had to study people over the course of their lifetime
or rely on epidemiology which is fraught with so many challenges that make it very difficult to
disentangle causal relationships but nevertheless this has been illuminating and i thank you greatly
for your your generosity of time and effort absolutely thank you for inviting me it was a
pleasure talking to you thank you for listening to this week's episode of the drive if you're
interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that
allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads it's our goal
to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription now to that end membership
benefits include a bunch of things one totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic paper person thing we discuss on each episode the word on the street is nobody's
show notes rival these monthly ama episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes
completely access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this the qualities which are a super short podcast that we release
every tuesday through friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on previous
episodes of the drive this is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back
and necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that i believe in but for which i'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on if you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can head
over to peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook
all with the id peteratiamd you can also leave us a review on apple podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes only does not constitute the
practice of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including the giving of
medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk the content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should
not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have
and they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
finally i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies i invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies
are