Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Welcome to this week's episode of The Drive.
My guest this week is one of my dearest friends, Dr. Paul Conti.
Paul is a brilliant psychiatrist.
In fact, I often refer to him as the single best psychiatrist I've ever come in contact
with and I've met some many very sharp people over the years.
I've long wanted to have Paul on the podcast.
I've always wanted to interview Paul just in general because there's not that many people
who I find myself having discussions with and I think to myself, how can this discussion
be shared with others?
And throughout this interview, you'll hear us even comment to that effect, which is God,
it's almost like we're not even talking in front of microphones.
This is exactly the kind of conversation we find ourselves having so often.
Paul's a very special person.
He doesn't get into great detail, but his life has been shaped by a number of really,
really tragic events, a couple of which he alludes to here, many of which he does not.
In fact, some of the most tragic events in Paul's life he does not allude to, but I think
the point that comes across here is that Paul is one of the most empathetic, kind, giving
individuals and his understanding of the human condition is really unparalleled.
In keeping with one of the general themes here, which is longevity of which health span
and happiness are important components, we go really deep on this topic.
We talk about what is meant by trauma.
Many people just think of trauma as, you know, you got hit by a car or something like that,
but we get really into emotional trauma.
We talk a lot about shame, which is the result of trauma and what it ends up doing.
We talk a lot about depression, suicide, and a number of other topics that are closely
related to this.
I do think at times this is a little bit heavy, but we really don't get into any of the technical
stuff that I thought we might get into in large part just because I think there was
so much to talk about without getting into the neurobiology.
I do think that Paul and I will need to sit down again in the future and get a lot deeper
on some of those other topics that I also thought would be interesting, and I suspect
a number of you will find very interesting.
So again, this is not a deep podcast from a technical standpoint, though we do get into
some of the heavier stuff.
Unfortunately, Paul is not someone you're really going to find much about on social
media.
Paul is someone whom can be contacted through his office, of course, and will provide that
contact information for folks who do want to reach out to his office.
But the good news is Paul is really considering writing a book.
And after we finished recording this podcast, we spent another 20 minutes talking about
the book he wants to write.
And the gist of it is the book is exactly about the stuff we talked about today.
So I couldn't be more encouraging of Paul doing this, and I think that the world will
be a better place for that.
So I hope you enjoy this episode half as much as I enjoyed listening to Paul talk about all
of these things.
And I think almost anybody will find something of great value in this episode.
Hey Paul, how are you, man?
I'm doing well, Peter.
Thank you for having me.
You're a super trooper here.
You have laryngitis.
I do indeed have laryngitis.
I am persevering, and I appreciate your patience in persevering with me.
Well, luckily, I guess luckily is the wrong word, but most people here don't know what
you sound like normally, so they probably won't even know that you're that.
I'm only bringing it up because I know you're straining a lot to speak, but this is such
an important topic.
We didn't really want to put it off, but you know, the two of us were so busy, even though
we're in New York often, that we could both have a night when we don't have something
else to do, I think makes this worth it.
So thank you.
It's my pleasure.
And even though I sound like the godfather, I'm still going to do my best to come across
as open and honest in a way that's not quite consistent with the godfather.
Although you did pull one old school Italian trick a moment ago, which was as you came in
my apartment, you beeline for the kitchen.
What did you do with the aspirin?
I gargled with hot water and aspirin, just like my grandmother told me to do.
She gets credit.
If people can understand me, credit goes to my grandmother.
All right.
So there you have it, your first old Italian old school trick on what to do with laryngitis
to take some boiling water, smash some baby aspirin into it and gargle it.
They didn't teach us that in medical school, but I'm still doing it.
All right.
So speaking of medical school, you and I have now known each other for 21 years.
Amazing.
Yeah, almost exactly 21 years.
And I think the relationship that you, me and the other five coconuts had in our med
school class, the seven of us probably in some ways really annoyed most of our med school
classmates because we were, we became close like within the first week of school and never
separated.
We were an inseparable group of knuckleheads.
I strongly agree that that annoyed people.
Yes.
Yeah.
But we're fortunate and I feel blessed to have met all of you guys and in particular,
probably all of the seven of us now, I think you and I by far spend the most time together
because so much of our work clinically overlaps.
I don't want to go deep so soon, but I think I feel like I have to.
So I'll never forget the first day we met all med students on day one are sort of nervously
talking about why they're here and blah, blah, blah.
Truthfully, most med students don't really know what they want to be when they grow up.
They have sort of figured out they want to be doctors and that's about it.
But there were some of us that knew I wasn't really one of them.
I kind of knew I wanted to do something in oncology.
I thought at the time pediatric oncology.
One of our buddies decided on day one, he was a plastic surgeon and that is exactly
what he is today.
You said the most interesting thing I'd ever heard, which was that you wanted to be a psychiatrist.
And I just remember thinking, I didn't know people went to med school to become psychiatrists.
I thought that was sort of a lifestyle choice that they made later on or something like
that.
But you were adamant about it.
Why was that the case?
I think it represented a search for truth.
I think it represented a search for truth and probably a response to some of the difficult
things in my life and to a lot of the dissatisfaction that I was feeling with achievement, with
my personal life, my professional life from top to bottom.
There was a sense of wanting to understand things more.
And I think it's interesting, you talk about how quickly this group of us became really
fast friends.
And I think there was a commonality there that we'd all had some life experience and
in different ways as we came to learn, we'd all really been through a lot.
And I think we were coming into medical school, searching for something and trying to find
something for ourselves through doing things that are good for other people.
And I understand that the idea is that's why people go to medical school.
And I'm not saying other people weren't doing that, right?
But we'd all been through a fair amount.
And I think it's the suffering component that drove the ability to maybe be open and honest
earlier with one another and to form bonds that were based upon the searching that we
were all doing that drove all of us to change career, to do something different than what
we might've thought we were doing as a response to an internal need.
And I think ultimately as a response to trauma.
It's interesting you bring that up.
I mean, I always knew this, but I guess I sort of forgot until you re-primed it.
None of us were pre-meds and all of us were a little older.
We were all a couple of years older because we'd all, in some cases, like in Bobby's
case, I mean, Christ, he'd been a mountaineering instructor for a decade or something like
that.
Zolly had been in the army for four years, same with Jason, all these guys.
Sorry to be calling all our boys out here on the show.
But yeah, none of us had just come through.
Right.
And certainly people can go through a lot by the time they're out of infancy, right?
So it's not as if people need to be out of school, do different things in order to really
gain life experience.
But I think the choices that each of us made were choices that came from a place of drive
and ambition, but ultimately that were colored by very personal things.
And I think led each of us to really want something more.
And I think we came to medical school in part to find that.
And I don't think that there's a distinction between what are the things that we do for
other people and the things that we do for ourselves.
I think that that's a false dichotomy that follows through sort of Western logic, that
things have to be one thing or another.
And I think often the best things that we do for others we do in a search for some healing
or soothing in ourselves.
And I think that that was part and parcel of all of us, was part and parcel of many
people that you and I went to medical school with, trained with.
But I think it's what made the seven of us fast friends.
And I think it's why there's remained a strong bond in part because that searching and that
desire to do for self through doing for others, I think really hasn't changed.
So what were you doing before medical school?
In other words, you studied, you were an undergrad and you went to Penn, you studied math, and
then you moved to New York.
You were working in finance, right?
Yeah, I minored in math.
I majored in political science and I studied a lot of history and a lot of literature.
And what I didn't realize was that the attraction to me of everything that I was studying was
really the allure of people.
I studied World War II a lot and for a while I thought I wanted to go to grad school and
be a World War II historian.
And at some point I realized what fascinated me was the people, right?
The people who were driving the action, good, bad, or otherwise.
The people who were caught in the crossfires, the millions of people who were part of that
event.
And what I realized over time was that there was a commonality of drive about understanding
what was leading people to do things or how people were responding to things.
And oddly enough, it may seem odd, but I think math is kind of part of that too, right?
That there are things that happen inside of people and there are aspects of our choice,
our choices that we design with a certain linearity.
And ultimately, there are complex functions in all of us that make things that we might
think are predictable, very unpredictable.
And I only kind of realized that in retrospect.
When I graduated from school I had some really wonderful job.
And I came out in 1991 and there was a little bit of an economic downturn and I was fortunate
to get a job with a good consulting firm.
And I just thought, okay, that's where I'm going to go, that I'm going to have this business
career.
And if it's with my father having been entrepreneurial and had a business career, and I just thought
like, okay, that's for me and I'm going to make my way doing that.
So then what changed?
What changed is it really, really did not make me happy.
And I say that with no criticism or aspergian whatsoever to people for whom it doesn't make
happy.
But there was something very much missing from it for me.
And I think that was the intensity of human interaction and so the intensity of human
struggle.
And what I found is I did that for four years and I took some time in the middle and I traveled
for several months because I was kind of trying to figure something out, like why am I not
happy?
And I came back and I took a better job with the same company.
So as time went on, I had more authority, I was making more money, I was doing more
interesting things and I was less happy.
And it really became quite stark to me that unless I was delving into the intensity of
what's going on inside of people, I wasn't going to be happy.
And I think what I didn't really fully realize was that that was going to be a way of kind
of delving into the things going on inside of me.
And as you know and you and I've talked about many, many times, there were some traumatic
things that happened during that time that really just brought to the fore to me, I want
to understand better and I want to be able to help soothe things in other people.
And what I didn't realize at the time was that wasn't a way of saying, oh, I'll be selfless
and altruistic, right?
And that's going to save the day for me.
But really, that also, what I didn't realize at the time was the mirror that it would put
up that would allow me to just get access to help that I didn't have before, be open
and communicative and understand myself in ways that it wasn't necessarily programmed
to do.
I mean, I was programmed to work hard, achieve, not be weak, right?
And that inability to express, right?
Even to myself, let alone to other people, was ultimately draining the life from me and
actually did drain the life in terms of actual death from some people around me that I very
much cared about.
And in some ways, I was rebelling against that way of being in the world and that way of
teaching people to be in the world.
And I had some, I think, inkling of understanding of that, but it more came through anger and
rejection of things and it came through an understanding through the lens of compassion
that we've kind of structured our society in a way that makes it very, very difficult
to live in, I think.
You're alluding to, obviously, something I know is very difficult and we've talked about
it a lot.
I don't know that we need to necessarily go into great detail here, but in the span of
a year, if I recall, you lost your brother and your best friend.
My brother died by suicide and about a year later, one of my closest friends, so this
same, a close group of friends growing up, sort of like we had in medical school, but
there were a group of us and one of those very, very close friends from childhood also
died and he didn't die by suicide, but there was sort of that same kind of desperate recklessness
that I saw this common root in those two deaths and they confused me and infuriated
me and made me feel very helpless and vulnerable and wanting to be able to understand better
and to kind of fight against this thing that made it so hard for people to get help and
to be vulnerable.
And that was really the commonality is both of the people who died had real and significant
needs inside of them that came about naturally, right?
Like something you would never criticize a person for having those needs or those struggles,
but there just wasn't a venue of getting real acknowledgement and help for any of that.
So that kind of silent bravado and silent struggle became very real to me that, oh,
that leads to death, right?
I mean, it doesn't all the time lead to death, but at least to death way more often than
is even remotely acceptable.
I mean, I think as we've discussed it, sometimes it can lead to death immediately, like in
these cases, and sometimes it can lead to a functional death, which is you're still
technically alive, you know, you still respire, but you're effectively dead.
In many ways, that's probably the more endemic, more sinister, more destructive over the long
term, given its sheer volume problem, right?
Oh, absolutely.
I think the deaths that we see in front of us as like, actually, okay, that person is
not breathing anymore, are there a viscerally moving hallmark of what is so pervasive in
our society.
And I do think that I didn't understand that then, that in many ways, the way our society
is structured and the way our metrices of achievement are structured really beckons
us to death in life, to losing touch with the basics of our own value system and essentially
to incessant striving and not incessant striving to achieve, although we may see it that way,
but incessant striving to not pause and to not feel the vulnerability that I think is
so pervasive now.
I mean, even in the 20 years, you know, since we went to medical school, I mean, you think
about how pervasive media is, right?
I mean, how there's just marker after marker after marker after marker that says that you're
not good enough, you don't have enough, you're too vulnerable, you know, there could be terrorist
attack anytime your kids could be killed, we could die.
I mean, it's one stimulus after another that tells us not to stop and to really value ourselves
by the things that we really value.
We get through med school and true to your word, you get a psychiatry residency spot,
you decide to stay at Stanford in part because your wife was still, your soon to be wife,
you guys weren't married yet, but your girlfriend was a couple of years behind us in med school
and you end up spending half your time at Stanford and then your wife matches at Harvard
so you go and finish your residency at Harvard.
So whenever I'm telling patients about you and I'm probably bastardizing all of my knowledge,
which is so limited in this field, but I say, you know, one of the things about Paul that's
so unique is he did half of his training at Stanford, which is probably one of the foremost
institutions when it comes to understanding the neurobiology and the pharmaconeurobiology
and the pharmacology of psychiatry and then does the other half at Harvard, which is sort
of a more old school, but you know, a place that specializes so much in the psychotherapy.
Is that an act, am I making that up when I say that?
Because I've just decided to take the liberty and say that about you.
It sounds good, so please keep saying it.
No, no, actually I think that there is truth to that and there's even more, there's more
truth to that the longer I get from it and the more I reflect on it.
I think that, you know, I am not a very positive or hopeful person about the state of the field
that I'm in, which I think does not broadly enough train people in brain biology, not
just in the use of medicines, but in what those medicines actually do and on a very
real level, what are those medicines doing as interventions in the brain, in the many,
many systems of the brain, in the cascade of effects that occur in the brain?
And we don't think about structural neurobiology.
We don't think about neurochemistry in general.
So there's that part of the field that often gets ignored.
And then the other side is the psychology.
There has been a debate of should psychiatrists still be trained in psychotherapy?
I mean, I see this come up and I just think that it's, fuck, we're putting it crazy to
consider having people that are, that are schlepping medicines to other people that
aren't thinking about what it's like to really try and understand someone and what are the
paradigms of understanding other humans, right?
The kind of things that are valid and have a scientific basis for them, but that are
not hardcore brain biology.
And I was very, very fortunate to learn so much neurobiology at Stanford and to have
that integrated into my training.
But when I got to Harvard, I was struck by that several very like prominent, influential
people there who were influential over, like, for example, whether I graduated, right?
We're like really shocked at how much brain biology I knew and really shocked at how much
psychology I didn't know.
And even though I had sought out some of this on my own, being in a place that was kind
of steeped in an older analytic tradition really helped me kind of embrace this belief
that understanding psychology and certainly from the perspective of what's psychodynamic,
right?
The things that influence and motivate us that are in our unconscious, you know, the
gigantic part of the iceberg that's underneath the water, but that is most deterministic
of our behaviors and our choices and our feelings.
And being able to integrate that with the brain biology upon which it rests, I think
is, I think it's the way to at least try and have the most broad set of abilities to try
and help people.
And in some ways it was very fortuitous for me to split my time between those two places
and to find a couple very, very good people who took it upon themselves to try and teach
me in a short period of time what maybe I should have learned over a longer period of
time.
When those of us who are not trained in this discipline think back to, you know, our psych
101 class or something as undergrads in college, you get introduced to all of the luminaries
in the field.
And one of the things I still remember was sort of the id ego, superego stuff.
How much of that stuff is still relevant today?
I mean, even sometimes when you and I talk, we still, and again when we talk about personal
things, this idea of ego still comes up.
I mean, you and I both completely separate to all of this discussion because we won't
go down this path, it just takes too long, but we share an enormous interest in psychedelics
and the promise that they hold for people.
And of course one of the hallmarks of this is dissolution of ego.
So when you think about what someone like me or someone who's listening to this who
doesn't have the training thinks at a very crude level of the id ego, superego, how much
does that still apply to how you think about these problems?
I think it applies tremendously on a foundational level.
And the problems we often run into are often about semantics and even among experienced
psychiatrists, the definition of words and terms can obscure any understanding.
So for example, in the Freudian concept of the ego, it's much more the whole self.
It's the part of self that one can bring in a conscious way to bear on the questions and
issues at hand.
It's the part of self that can mediate between the different poles, right?
So it may be about gratification, the superego may be about what you should or shouldn't
do, but ideally it's the ego, the whole self that pulls that together.
And that's a very different use of the term ego than how it often is used these days where
ego is a sense of self that essentially indicates a defense mechanism.
And the idea of dissolution of the ego through the use of psychedelics is not dissolution
of the classic psychodynamic or Freudian ego, which is like the whole self at its most poised
and comprehensively aware and empowered.
It's more the dissolution of ego as defense that we build up over time.
I think a shocking number of defense mechanisms that serve us well at the time, but that ultimately
are an unhealthy part of the foundation that then gets built upon.
So for example, a sense of insecurity in childhood and I'm not good enough and I need to achieve
more and I need to please people.
We build so much around that, that defines us in a certain way, for example, right?
That tells us that we must be perfect and we beat up on ourselves over less than perfect
because that's how we're going to make ourselves perfect.
Right?
And then you can think of all the things that build on top of that, which could be maladaptive
friendships, maladaptive romantic relationships, maladaptive career choices, right?
There's so much that we can build on top of that.
And then in a very strong sense, it's almost as if like the true us, right?
The Freudian ego is surrounded by, you know, 90 story high walls that are built to protect
us, but actually protect us from real connection with self and others and real understanding.
And some of what the psychedelics, it seems through the phenomenology, the people's experiences,
the research, right?
When you put all of that together and you look at it with the brain imaging and the
knowledge we have about brain biology is in an amazing way, they can take down those defenses,
which if not done in, you know, a therapeutic and a controlled setting obviously can be
dangerous, but in the right setting opens one up to an experience of self and an experience
of the truth of self that is no longer walled off by all of these unhealthy defenses.
So I mean, it's a long answer to the question, but yes, what's going on in our unconscious,
what's going on deep in our brain, the things that we're not consciously aware of are so
deeply impactful.
So Freud certainly didn't get everything right, but this concept of the unconscious pulls
on us and the ability to integrate those things in a healthy ego that can actually decide
and choose, I think is as relevant or more so than ever when there's so many pulls away
from authenticity of the self.
And then the hope of psychotherapy, just shared human experience and psychedelics is to be
able to take those defenses down so we can have an experience of self that reflects who
we truly are, which the vast majority of the time involves acknowledgement of the things
that we're ashamed of, the vulnerabilities, the things that we've ensured ourselves against,
which are often the very things that keep us away from happiness.
You know, as you know, I'm writing a book now and it's not a particularly easy thing
to do.
I think it's probably hard even for someone who's a natural writer, but certainly for
someone like me, it's very difficult.
And I'm toying with a chapter that I've been really, really flailing with for the past
three weeks.
It may not end up in the book because I just don't know how to write it, but it's a chapter
that centers around the experience I had in Kentucky, which might seem like an obscure
thing to write about in a book about longevity.
But of course, as I've become very clear on lately, I don't think all of this obsession
with longevity and living longer and living better means a lick if you're miserable.
And so much of our misery is self-imposed.
And I think obviously you are the reason I went there.
I would never have done what was required to go through that experience were it not
for you insisting on it.
And frankly, even had you insisted on it, you know, at a different time without the
confluence of events that led to it, I probably could never have done that because the vulnerability
that's required to do and to go there and you even put me in touch with another patient
who you had sent, who had gone.
Again, the thing that amazed me about that was how long I had lived my life, never even
considering the idea that there can be a child that gets wounded, that wounded child develops
in an adoptive child.
And sometimes that adoptive child is the one that shows up in the adult body and not as
opposed to a functional adult.
Yes.
I guess I just sort of feel like I'm neo in the matrix.
And after I've gone through this whole experience, I see my life in a totally different way.
And I realize, oh my God, like all of that achievement, all of that perfectionism, all
of those things I was chasing, it's basically a kid trying to protect you.
And I've certainly not held out any hope that it's going to be ever fully resolved.
I mean, I'm not, I don't know, maybe I'm just too pessimistic.
It's going to get better.
I'm absolutely confident because it has gotten better.
But it just strikes me as so hardwired that it kind of makes me wonder, like, is this
something that's getting worse or is this something that has always existed in our civilizations,
in our societies, and only now because so many of our other needs are being met?
You know, none of us that are list, if you're listening to this podcast, you're probably
not worried about where your next meal is going to come from.
You're probably not worried about a plague.
You're probably not worried about, hopefully you're not worried about a civil war or something
like that.
So is it just that our basic needs, you know, of Maslow's hierarchy of needs, they've been
met and so now we have the quote unquote luxury of worrying about self actualization and what
does happiness mean and what does it mean to be fulfilled and content that we're now
realizing this?
Or do you think there are things that are actually making it worse today and there are
more wounded kids out there and more adults that are effectively nothing more than adoptive
kids?
It's such a fascinating question.
And I mean, of course, I don't know the answer, but I do suspect that we are making it worse
for ourselves in ways that we haven't intended.
So of course, I'm all for opportunity, meaning like we are numbing ours, we have more net
agents to numb and soothe ourselves.
We've made more opportunity for ourselves in certain ways.
And that opportunity is a wonderful thing in many ways, but every good thing has its
potential for a downside and something that can work against or even negate the good thing.
So for example, as far as I know, for generations, the people in my family lived up in the hills
of central Italy and as far as I can tell, most of them were shepherds, right?
And we could look at that and say, look, there's a limitation to what they could achieve.
And how fortunate am I that people sailed across the Atlantic and now I go to college
and I have a business career and then I go back to school and I take undergraduate classes
and I apply to medical school after all of that and I get in and you could list forever
the additional opportunities that I have that people didn't have before.
And that's wonderful and I certainly would not argue against opportunity, right?
But it also brings greater opportunity to run away from the things that plague us.
So for example, you and I, and probably many, many, if not most of the people listening
to this podcast are driven to be powerful.
So okay, some of the motivation for what I do or what you do is intellectual curiosity,
the desire to help others, the desire to learn about self, right?
But a significant aspect of the strength of the fuel in the tank, right, is running from
something, right?
It's running from vulnerability.
Because there's more opportunity, there are higher expectations.
And I think there were high expectations for both of us, not that I am arguing against,
you know, the fact that our families instilled in us conscientiousness and ambition, but
I think we internalize that as must be perfect, must achieve more.
Like when is enough enough and it becomes very, very unclear and it becomes very easy
to run from things.
And you know, it's that that I think that the modern world doesn't actually help us
define what we are striving for.
So more striving, more power, whatever that means, right?
It could mean money, it could mean prestige and titles, influence, whatever it means,
like more of that by definition becomes better.
And we live in a world that constantly reminds us of our vulnerability.
So there's never a time.
I mean, my guess is having spent time, you know, in places where like people are shepherds,
right?
And people do have these simpler lives.
And sure, they don't have the opportunities we have, but there are ways that I often can
see them at the end of the day, feel a sense that the day is over and that what's the
days exigencies are over the days, ambitions are over, right?
They're like things are okay and it's time to rest and there'll be tomorrow.
And I think most of us don't have that feeling.
You know, most of my life when I fall asleep, I'm exhausted and I have a sense that, well,
now I need to sleep for a little bit so that I can get up and strive more.
And I don't think there's any way if we're honest with ourselves that we can frame that
as, oh, that's a drive to something.
No, that's a drive away from something, right?
And it's running away from ourselves and it's running away from our problems.
And we don't even know what those problems are.
And the fact that, as you know, I have a pretty diverse practice, right?
That like really, I think spans the spectrum of psychiatric and neuropsychiatric things.
And I absolutely believe and I've come to believe more and more and more and more as
time goes on that 80% of what I treat is trauma.
80% of what ails me, 80% of what ails you, 80% of what ails the world around us is all
trauma.
There's another 20% that might be a head injury, schizophrenia, you know, the complications
of physical injuries, biological determinants of addiction.
But none of those things, even those things that seem and are very biologically determined
are free of the impact of trauma.
And the rest of it I think is purely trauma.
It's manifestation is anxiety, depression, panic attacks, choices to abuse substances,
choices to do things that are unhealthy, whether it's overeating or it's cutting or it's gambling
or whatever it is that we're doing.
So much of that is driven by trauma.
And I think that, you know, yes, it's an opinion, right?
It's not something I can prove that you can prove like a, you know, like a math problem,
right?
If you really look at it and you look at what's going on at the root of what ails people,
I think it becomes self-evident that I think there actually is a way of proving that, which
is just look at what's really going on in people instead of categorizing them.
You know, there's a DSM-5 that's a half a city block long that just looks to like, look,
if we flip through it, I don't know how many diagnoses you and I would have between us,
right?
Because it's designed to capture everybody multiple times over.
But categorizing what ails somebody and putting a number on it is not understanding them.
That is not synonymous with understanding them.
This is the tragedy of your profession, right?
Yes.
That's the direction it's going in.
It's designed to categorize.
If you categorize something, you can put a number on it, right?
And then you can get 20 bucks for insurance and you haven't actually understood people.
I think that both the practitioners in my field and the people who come to care deserve
better than what the field gives them.
And we've stepped away from really trying to understand people.
And I'll give you an anecdote.
I was very, very fortunate when I was interviewed for Stanford, I was interviewed by Peter Rosenbaum,
who was an emeritus professor of psychiatry.
This was in medical school or for residency?
No, for medical school.
For medical school.
Yeah.
And we got along really, really well and he's a wonderful person.
And later on, when I decided to become a psychiatrist, I told him, you know, I got his email out
of the archives and I told him and he sent me some redacted histories of patients.
And he wanted me to understand that, yes, there have been so many biological advances.
There's space age, neuroimaging.
There's an understanding of brain biology that was unimaginable 30, 40 years ago.
But if you look at what they were writing about people, they really evokes a human being.
Whereas very often now, when I look at reports of people, I can't tell anything.
It's just it's an inventory of signs and symptoms that you could conclude anything from.
And then a number gets put on top of it.
And yes, I mean, I'm being critical of the field as I'm saying this.
But in many ways, it's a societal criticism.
It's a criticism of a society that dumps things down and that doesn't respond to the individual,
whether it's the incessant phone trees that prevent us from ever solving any problems,
no matter what it is, whether it's my bank or it's the phone company.
I mean, when do you actually connect?
And I think it's that isolation that is a societal malady and it affects psychiatry,
which is a very bad thing because psychiatry is trying to help us have better mental health.
And we're kind of disarming its ability to do that, I think.
And then it pervades our society in a way that leads to isolation and desperation.
And if I think if you look at suicide rates and just levels of general misery,
I mean, I don't want to glorify the past, including the recent past,
but it's pretty hard to look at that and to think that there's not something here that's getting worse.
Yeah, well, I mean, touching on that, there was an article in the Wall Street Journal recently
after the sort of very close to back to back suicides of Kate Spade and Anthony Bourdain.
And it showed some stats from the CDC.
So these are obviously US based statistics.
But when you looked at men and women between the ages of 40 and 60 across the board,
there was about a 30% increase in the rate of suicide.
I don't want to be misquoted on this.
So it was either a decade or two decades, but it was a relatively recent period of time.
And in my approach to longevity, it's very cluj, right?
I mean, I'm kind of a hack if you really stop to think about it.
I don't have like some single magic pill that I think can make you live longer.
Instead, it's like a whole bunch of reverse engineered problems.
And one of them is, you know, it's you figure out what it is that's going to kill you and start to back out of that.
And so I spend a lot of time pouring over actuarial tables and looking over mortality trends and trying to understand how they're shifting.
Where are we, quote unquote, winning and where are we losing?
And it seems to me that, you know, even though most of my energy focuses on three things, atherosclerotic disease, cancer and neurodegenerative disease,
the only disease that shows up in every single decade as a top 10 cause of death outside of the first decade.
So birth to nine is suicide accidents do as well.
And but but but I think the suicide thing, but the nature of accidents, by the way, changes so much from beginning to end that it's a very different, you know, in other words, the accidents that kill, you know, 30 year olds and 40 year olds are quite different from the accidents that kill 80 year olds and 90 year olds.
And sorry to interrupt, but how many of those accidents, especially ones that are killing younger people are what we might call parasuicidal, right?
It's people being reckless and getting killed because their mental state is such that they're not invested in staying alive.
Not only that, so that's a great point.
The other point is when you look at the top three causes of accidental death, it is automotive accident, falling and accidental ingestion, which, of course, begs the question, how many accidental ingestions are not accidental?
When I was in college, a friend that I grew up with his dad shot himself in the head.
I remember the Sunday afternoon that had happened.
He literally they all went out to church like a normal day, went out for lunch after and then when they got back home, his dad went out to the shed and shot himself in the head.
Probably one of the saddest lessons I ever learned was maybe two months later during finals, my mom said so and so my friend is not doing well.
He's really down in the dumps.
You ought to come home and see him this weekend.
And I still to this day just cannot I can't believe what I'm admitting and acknowledging now.
It's so embarrassing and painful to say this.
But I said, Mom, look, I'm in the middle of finals here.
You know, I got to graduate first in my class.
I have to be the best engineer that ever lived.
I'll be done in two weeks.
I'll see him then.
A week later, he was dead.
Oh, my gosh, I'm so sorry.
Now, we don't know, you know, I don't know that he'll get counted as a quote unquote.
Suicide because it was alcohol, barbiturates, you know, it was like a cocktail of drugs in his system and he just never woke up.
And again, I only tell that story not because it's, you know, it's just such a sad.
It's a sad reminder to me to how to prioritize.
It's that overnight change the way I prioritize things in life.
But it also begs the question, you know, his death might not be one that actually gets counted as a suicide, but I would call it a suicide.
Absolutely.
I mean, the deaths by suicide are in general the ones that are just very clearly suicide.
Right. Yeah. But if you if there's a note written that the gunpowder is on the hand as the gun points at the head.
Yeah. Right. But so many deaths that are not labeled as suicide actually are suicide.
And so many that aren't someone saying I'm going to kill myself now are the result of an approach to one's life that doesn't value it and wants it to end.
What gets called Paris suicide.
When when you when you add those things together, those numbers just undoubtedly are strikingly higher than the shockingly high numbers that we're reading now.
And I've always kept a mental note of if someone I know, you know, which includes again, I don't make much of a distinction for people in my personal life, my patients, people I consult to.
I mean, just humans, right. Of what they died of on the death certificate versus what they really died of.
Right. And it might be auto accident, accidental overdose fall.
Right. And I'm looking at it. You know, that person died of Madoff that they're so ashamed of what happened to them when they were swindled and humiliated.
Right. That person died of rape that was never adequately addressed.
And the sense of shame and the sense of misery that was imparted on them was never addressed.
That person died of childhood bullying.
Right. That was so intense.
They they they decided that they were this awful, reprehensible person in sixth grade.
And that never changed.
I mean, every now and then the actual cause of death matches what what is is, you know, my brain registers as the real cause of death.
But very, very often there's a difference there.
And and the difference I account for by the role of trauma, right.
The role of trauma that pushes people to either end their life or to move towards the end of their life,
even if they're not overtly acknowledging that they're doing that, which can be a clever way of not having to feel accountable.
Right. If the religion says, don't commit suicide.
Well, it's ultimately it was an accident or well, I don't want to leave my kids.
Ultimately, it's an accident to me.
And I'm not saying that in any negative way, but we don't help people to understand what's going on inside of them.
Right. And you know, you're talking about how you run your practice and how you try and understand the routes to not just
a longevity, but the healthy longevity.
And, you know, and I would argue, I mean, my take on that is that you actually have become the best engineer, because what you're doing is, as you said,
your reverse engineering to ways of living longer and being healthier.
And with so many complex variables, I'm not so sure if it's possible to figure that out without reverse engineering.
And I view it as a marker of your I truly mean this, your intense and incredible thoroughness
that you look beyond the factors and the reasons for the factors and the reasons that underlie the factors and the reasons.
And it's I think what leads you to have me here instead of someone who could talk more about oncology or cardiovascular pathology.
Right. The realization that what undergirds a tremendous amount of the things that actually take someone's quality of life or take their life ultimately has a root in in mental health.
Right. That people who are depressed are more likely to have cardiovascular disease and more likely to die of accidents and more likely to become addicted.
Right. People who've been through terrible trauma are more likely for all of those things to happen.
The role of stress and its impact on the immune system and the growth of cancer cells.
Right. There's a level underneath the things to which we attribute morbidity and mortality that strongly influence morbidity and mortality.
And I believe that's true.
I mean, I think that 80 percent of what I treat is trauma.
But I actually think I don't know what the numbers are, but I think more than 50 percent of what everyone treats any doctor more than 50 percent of what walks through that door is ultimately resting in misery inside of that person that I would attribute to trauma.
And again, it's not my way of saying, oh, we're all suffering.
And in some way that it just kind of denigrates, you know, you know, when really awful things happen to people.
I mean, the problem is we don't take stock of really awful things that happen to people like most of the time.
And even when those things are something so overt as, you know, an assault, a terrible loss, we can ignore even those things, let alone the impact of, you know, loss of a parent as a child, loss of a friend who moves away, loss of a pet.
I mean, like these are things sometimes that that you ask somebody what their inner life is like 20, 25 years later.
And that thing may go through their head a thousand times.
And it may be that the loss of the pet is symbolic of they will have no stability, no peace, no freedom.
So then it becomes, you know, becomes the internal symbol of their sense of hopelessness in life or their sense of infinite striving with no hope of getting where they want to go.
So so I don't mean to say that in some I don't know trite way, but I mean to say it in a way that I do think if you sit with individual people, you see the depth of that and you see the pervasiveness of it.
When you recommended that I needed to go to Kentucky, needed to go to this place, the bridge to recovery, which we'll be sure to link to in the show notes here, because I really think if anybody takes anything away from this and they even
have a suspicion that they're some of their actions, some of their pain could be sort of driven by trauma that had occurred earlier in life.
I want to make sure that people at least pick up the phone, give them a call and at least commit the time to doing an intake interview with them.
But I mean, I was so incredibly resistant to this idea, right?
It was this idea that how could there really be anything wrong with me?
Look at how hard I work.
Look at how quote unquote successful I am.
And by that, I just meant like I'm not an alcoholic.
I don't have a drug problem.
I'm not a gambler.
Like I don't have any of these overt signs of pathology.
Yeah, I've got these other things that are kind of pathologic, but I can mostly keep them in check.
But I kind of remember when I did my intake call with them how pissed off I got.
And that to me, there was there was two things.
Right.
So the first is I'm talking to this poor woman whose job it is to just do a basic screening call.
But she's asking me a lot of questions.
Nobody's ever asked me and questions.
I don't want to answer.
And at one point she asked me a question.
I won't tell you what the question was, but my answer was fuck you.
Like that was just my answer.
Right.
Like and when I later told that story once I finally got there, everybody thought that was so funny because they're like, wow, she asked you a question about X.
And she found out you have X and a bad temper.
It's like this really great anger management and this other thing.
Check.
But that was also kind of the reason that was certainly one of the things that made me think.
Because as you recall, you know, you wanted me to go and I agreed to go and then I backed out.
And, you know, it's just like this had been something that had been on the table for years.
And I just refused to acknowledge this needed to be done.
And I think part of it was the semantics.
Right. It's like, what does trauma mean?
We get so far in our lives.
Our skin gets so thick that I think people get into different patterns.
And for me, I know the pattern was minimization.
You know, I didn't forget any of the stuff that got me there.
I just didn't think it mattered.
You know, when they talk about trauma at the bridge, they really refer to it in five roots.
So the first route is abuse, which can be physical, emotional, sexual, spiritual.
You talk about neglect, abandonment, enmeshment, and the witnessing of tragic events.
And so I think it'd be impossible to think that somebody listening to this hasn't experienced
at least some of one of those branches and many of us more than one.
For me, the single most powerful way to let my guard down was because we're now, what,
three or four days into the most intense experience of my life, which is 13 hours a
day of group therapy.
And I had still sort of, I mean, I was there, so I'd shown up, but I wasn't happy, but I'd
refused to sort of even have a discussion about any of this stuff.
I was happy to listen to other people, but I wasn't going to get into it.
And one of the counselors, and I had these two amazing counselors, Jeff and Julie, I
can't remember if it was Jeff or Julie, but one of them said something to the effect of,
you know, if such and such, because we were talking about an event in my life, if such
and such occurred to your son, Reese, because Reese is four, about the age that I was, would
you think that was okay?
It's a very different question, right?
It's one thing when it's like, look, that happened.
I'm over it.
Come on.
Look at, blah, blah, blah.
I could even rationalize.
Look, these things have made me more resilient.
This has given me a chip on my shoulder.
This has given me an edge.
But when they turn it into, you have a kid and that, and it's so interesting because
just last week I was having dinner with a friend in Malibu and he opened up to me about
something incredibly personal and private that I'd never known, which was that his wife
had had a really difficult year.
She'd relapsed in her smoking.
A whole bunch of other stuff had completely fallen off the rails in their lives, but in
particular in her life.
We get through the whole dinner and he tells me everything about the story and it's just
a heartbreaking story.
And then he alludes to a fact that was clearly the trigger, which was his wife had been abused
very badly by her stepfather, had been sexually abused nonstop.
It started when she was seven years old.
Earlier this year, their daughter turned seven and it completely triggered this because,
and again, if I'd heard that before, I would have been like, come on, that sounds like
sort of psycho-babble nonsense.
How is it that seeing your daughter at the same age that you were at when something happened
could do that?
I mean, do you see this often?
Oh, sure.
Yeah, absolutely.
And to kind of lead up to addressing that, I want to comment on a couple of things, right?
One, you said that the woman who was asking you the questions, okay, she learned, okay,
there's this issue and then she learns about anger, right?
I would frame that a little differently.
I would say that there's a very skilled clinician that is doing the same thing over the telephone
that we might do physically examining a patient, right?
And he touched, does it hurt here?
Does it hurt there?
I mean, if you get where it hurts and we're not, even if we're very gentle about it, right?
At times the person has a reaction, right?
And then you learn like, oh, you hurt there, right?
And that's why you reacted that way.
And I think that's what she learned.
She said, is it hurt here?
Is it hurt here?
And then she went, oh, shit, it really hurts there.
And it tells us something, right?
And what it tells a good mental health clinician is where there's shame and fear, right?
And shame is extremely powerful.
And technically it's an aroused affect.
I mean, the word aroused, it's not purely a sexual word.
I mean, it often gets used in that way because the idea is say something can turn a person
on that you didn't choose to have turn you on, right?
But the idea of aroused affect is something that's created in you without your volition.
Someone shoves you, you get angry, right?
Someone shows you really hard, you might get afraid, right?
There are things that make a certain, what gets called affect, but colloquially a feeling
inside of us that we don't have a choice over.
And there's an incredible automaticity to that.
And that's like, what you're talking about with, okay, like, what is this trauma thing
and what is it doing, right?
It's not necessarily what happens.
It's what does it make you feel?
And my guess is, and I don't know, I don't know the person you're talking about, but
probably that person is carrying some sense of shame over what happened to her.
Because at the age of seven, there's not the cognitive capacity of deciding, look, what's
going on happening to me is wrong.
The child needs to make sense of it, right?
And often how the child makes sense of it is to decide somehow that it makes sense or
what's happening to them is deserved, or it's their fault, right?
Or it's the way it should be, right?
And that evolves into a sense of shame that the problem here is me.
Someone's hurting me in some way, whatever's happening to me, it doesn't feel good.
And it's my fault.
And then it creates a sense of shame that does not give a damn about the clock or the
calendar or levels of achievement.
You have a trillion dollars and 15 PhDs, right?
It does not make a difference unless that shame is directly addressed.
So that's really the answer, right?
Is what has happened to a person and what is it triggering inside of them?
The same way there's pretty good literature that talks about someone is shot, right?
How much does it hurt?
And like, clearly it hurts more if there's no damn reason to have been shot, right?
Like if you try to save somebody and you get shot, then people tend to feel less pain because
there's a sense that it makes sense in some way, that this bad thing has happened, but
something good has come of it.
Or I was trying to do something good, right?
It doesn't seem senseless and sadistic.
And that sense of absurdity, the sense of evoked shame or aroused affect of shame, the
sense of an aroused affect of fear, the sense of absurdity and meaninglessness is what then
creates the trauma that stays with someone and kind of like, it's not even like a ghost
shadowing, you know?
It's like, you know, just imagine someone who like can't stand you, that just shadows
you all the time and says awful things.
And that's essentially what this kind of thing evolves into.
And it's that that, you know, that raises that triggering that if there's still a sense
of shame and now the daughter is seven years old, you know, what does that make the person
feel like, right?
And it identifies with the daughter, they still identify as the hurt child, but now
they're supposed to take care of a child who's vulnerable because that child has reached
the age at which they were hurt.
I mean, it's very, very triggering for reasons that make damn good sense.
So you've seen this where people's trigger is that the child that reaches an age at which
some traumatic event occurred.
Yes, it's very common because that is a trigger that they say, okay, it's my job to make sure
that does not happen to them.
But I am still in the throes of it.
Right?
So then, well, I am the traumatized seven year old child who is supposed to protect
the seven year old child.
That's terrifying.
It's terrifying.
And then the part of the brain that is terrified says, look, this absolutely could happen to
your child.
And you can't protect them.
And then, you know, the brain, again, the brain doesn't care about the clock and the
calendar.
So that trauma is very, very, very real to the person.
And it's very immediate.
It doesn't matter if it was two days ago or if it was 30 years ago, it's just as immediate.
And we also lose sight of that.
And many times I hear people say, well, that couldn't still be bothering me.
It was what, two months ago, two years ago, 50 years ago.
And the answer to that is it does not matter one bit how long ago it was.
If it instilled terror, shame, a sense of responsibility for something that wasn't the
person's responsibility, then, you know, my guess is we could probably live to be a thousand
years old and that would still be with us.
And again, very germane to your practice is that's one of the things that often prevents
us from living longer, right?
It's that kind of internal stress that leads not only to suicide and para-suicide, but
also to the kind of stress that contributes to cardiovascular disease, to cancer, to autoimmune
problems, right, to all the things that ultimately, you know, if you look at the population as
a whole that chips away at our health, at our healthy lifespan and at our lifespan.
I still remember to this day, the very, very first patient we ever collaborated on, which
of course was such an interesting experience for me that it's what basically led to you
and I being so close at the hip in terms of like how many patients we overlap with.
But I obviously won't use her name, but the woman in San Diego that I was taking care
of, very interesting case.
I think most of my patients are incredibly nice people, but she would certainly be on
the short list of like the nicest, just a very, very special woman.
And there were a lot of things that didn't look metabolically right.
Frankly, her chief complaint when she came to me was, you know, she just wanted to have
more energy.
She wanted to feel better.
Her father had died prematurely of heart disease.
She wanted to make sure that was not going to be her.
And we got to it.
We changed her nutrition and we fixed her hypothyroidism and we tweaked a bunch of
things and everything on paper looked right, but we couldn't eradicate certain things.
There was still a degree of inflammation in her body.
There was still a degree of insulin resistance.
I probably hadn't seen a patient who could be so compliant with her nutritional plan
as she was.
And the only one of her meds I couldn't really offer any input on was she was on an SSRI
I think.
I don't remember which one.
It was well butrin if I can remember actually.
I think this had been prescribed by her family doctor like 10 years earlier or something
like that.
But I remember one day thinking about what she talked about when her dad died when she
was in medical school.
She was a physician.
And it cleared me on this particular day, which was like a year after the first time
I'd heard this story that like that had that I didn't know to use the word trauma, but
that was clearly a traumatizing event in her life.
My first thought was actually I thought of these zucker rats, which I thought of these
experiments that occurred.
What I couldn't understand was why in the world is this woman who's doing everything
right seemingly have a metabolic rate of a slug?
It was like she's doing everything by the book and the only way that we could infer
what's going on with her is that her metabolic rate has shut down because she's no longer
hypothyroid.
All these other things have been fixed.
And I thought about these zucker rats where they sustain certain lesions into parts of
the hypothalamus and they can alter the metabolic rate.
And so I floated the idea by you and you said, look, anything is plausible.
And to make a long story short, I introduced the patient to you.
She came up, she saw you.
And over the course of the next six months without making any change in the thyroid meds,
in the nutrition, in the exercise, she probably lost 30 pounds.
And she looked like a different person.
In fact, I remember when I got her Christmas card with her and her family.
At first I thought, I don't know who this is.
Why am I getting a Christmas card from a random person?
And I mean, what do you remember about that case?
Maybe not even the specifics, but just like, were you as surprised by that as I was?
You know, I think the fact that I wasn't is just indicative of, it's not indicative of
like some genius that I figured things out that other people haven't.
It's just indicative of things that I have witnessed that utterly shocked me at the time
that lead to what I would describe as more than a healthy respect, but an utter reverence
for the impact of what the brain can do to the body.
And a couple of examples are paralysis of a limb.
I mean, I've seen people, seen cases in my training and subsequently taken care of people
who do something that they find reprehensible or almost do something that could have been
disastrous and then the limb that they did it with is paralyzed.
And now it's like, it's 10 years later and the limb hasn't moved in 10 years.
I mean, the nerves haven't been severed, but they may as well have been those contractures
and everything else.
I mean, when you see that the brain can like shut off vision, right?
The brain can shut off movement to a limb.
You know, these are really shocking things.
And I think that we as a society, like we just don't appreciate how much impact over
all aspects of our functioning, some of the things that torment us inside can have.
So there was something tormenting this lovely woman that was like shutting her metabolism
off.
And in many ways I get it, it's like, it's a shocking thing.
And it would have knocked me off my feet if I hadn't been like seeing paralyzed limbs before.
And you know, things that really kind of told me things that to be honest really made me
angry.
Like, how is it that I consider myself to be a curious person?
I mean, even look before psychiatric training, right?
And I'm a well-read person.
I'm a well-traveled person.
I'm interested in other people.
I took a broad curriculum in college.
Like how is it that I didn't understand these things of what our brain and what does that
mean?
It means what our brain in the context of trauma, which is about evoke, shame, fear,
think about things we're talking about in the patients where we've had these kinds of
experiences, right?
And even in ourselves, think about the impact of shame and fear and what it does to us.
And people don't tell us that.
So then a person feels ashamed, right?
That they're eating less and they can't lose weight.
They feel ashamed that they're sleeping, but they're not well rested.
They feel ashamed that they want to be patient with their kids and they can't be as patient
as they want.
I mean, I could go on and list thousands and thousands of things.
And what we often don't, again, don't appreciate is where's all that coming from?
And has anyone ever asked about it?
I'll give you a quick aside that I saw a person in my practice several years, maybe
five years ago or so, very, very intelligent person, very capable, academically accomplished
who was working many, many, many levels underneath where he could, would have been operating
in a $10 an hour job and somebody, you know, who should be running a company.
Not dramatic.
And you know, I was, I don't know how many people had seen and talked to this person
before, right?
And I asked him a question and you know, we had been talking, so it's not like it came
out of the blue, but, but I asked him, you know, how many times a day do you say something
to yourself inside?
That's some version of like, I suck.
And this response was also, I'm a piece of shit.
And his answer was like, he stopped and he says hundreds, hundreds of times all the way
to the job, all the way back in the shower before he goes, when he's back at home with
his kids nonstop, you know, that was all trauma based.
And it was based upon belittling, bullying, all things that had happened.
I mean, you could take a trauma history from this person and not like no one's ever shot
him.
No one's ever sexually assaulted him.
Like it was, oh, there's no trauma.
Oh no.
There was gigantic trauma.
And if you're saying something to yourself over and over and over again, that is, that
is profoundly negative and that makes you feel vulnerable, ashamed, inadequate.
How are you supposed to be at your best?
How does it affect your brain?
How does it affect your endocrine system?
How does it affect your immune system?
How does it affect your vasculature?
The answer is dramatically.
And then you look at this person who now was aware of substandard role performance and
now he feels worse about himself.
And by going after that, we were actually able to change everything.
I mean, that the person's life is dramatically different.
If you look at what he's doing for a living now, you're like, okay, that's, you know,
that's something that seems more commensurate.
And in this person, it doesn't represent the endless striving of you who never, you know,
achieve enough, right?
In this person, it represents something that makes him feel whole, that this wasn't, you
know, his ability to be something he could feel proud of, to support his family in a
way he could feel proud of.
It wasn't taken away from him.
But if you looked at what was the etiology of that problem, it absolutely wasn't single
digit ages.
And it doesn't matter that this was like three or more decades along, right?
It was with him hundreds of times a day.
And that's why these things don't surprise me.
And you know, I've had an increased awareness over time of my own inner voice that, you
know, I may as well have somebody, you know, behind me all the time.
I mean, I've been trying to alter this and some, some of us with your help and a couple
of other people around us, you know, it's kind of gotten better.
And the realization that I carry around with me a voice that tells me how shitty I am for
everything that's not utterly perfect from the moment I wake up to the moment I go to
sleep has created a lot of misery in my life and has created unhealthy situations.
And you know, at times real risk to my life and limb for me.
So you know, I'm a huge believer that the reality and the truth that we're living,
I say that the reality and what we view as truth that, that we're living in is often
not apparent to anyone around us and nor is it apparent to ourselves.
And if we make that apparent, then we can make some decisions about it, which is why
that woman was able to lose weight is because we, we started talking about like what was
actually going on inside of her.
And you know, in a certain person, if you are intensely ashamed and feel inadequate
from the moment you wake up to the moment you fall asleep, you probably eat 20 calories
a day and you're going to gain weight.
That's the part that just blows my mind in her case.
The other thing with this stuff that I think it's worth people who are listening to understanding
and it's so important.
I certainly didn't understand it until the past year.
I think I wasn't so naive to know that I wasn't so, so, so maybe naive is the wrong word.
I wasn't so ignorant to think that, look, bad things happen.
I got it.
But my sort of blinder based mentality was I can prevent that exact set of things from
happening to the next generation, to my kids.
And of course the irony of it is you learn that trauma almost always comes out in some
orthogonal way.
And so it's not necessarily that the child of the alcoholic becomes the alcoholic.
In the case of the woman that I was just talking about earlier, who when she saw her daughter
turn seven triggered all these flashbacks of the sexual abuse.
I think the probability that that mother is going to go ahead and sexually abuse her daughter
because she was sexually abused by her stepfather, I think the probability of that is close to
zero.
That is not how the shame will be transferred to the next generation.
It will not be through the same root cause.
It will come out in something different.
And to me, that's the part of this thing that is so, it's such an epidemic.
Terrence Reel, who we've talked about a lot in his book, which I've talked about on other
podcasts, one of the most important books I've ever read.
I don't want to talk about it.
He talks about this, the number of generations it takes for shame to sort of work itself
out.
And it's like, this happened to the grandfather.
This happened to the mother.
This happened to the child.
This idea of shame transference through trauma is, I don't know, I guess like I said, even
though I don't do this for a living, it occupies more and more of my time because I spend more
and more of my time thinking about it with the patients that I'm lucky enough to get
this close to.
And truthfully, there are some of my patients I just don't get close enough to to understand
this part of their lives.
But I want to because I realize so much of what we do without knowing this becomes quite
futile.
Absolutely.
I mean, if the manifest, if the only thing we were guarding against was the manifestation
of something that we recognize, things would be different.
I mean, I think the number of generations to get rid of shame without intervention,
you know, is either infinite or there's just some, you know, it's practically infinite.
Right.
Because why would something like that change unless it's understood?
Now people at times can intuitively understand.
I mean, there are things that can intervene, but otherwise you're absolutely right.
I mean, it finds a way out.
Right.
So the person who was sheltered and over controlled as a child and that led to say, you know,
big problems of rebellion and then something traumatic happens.
Maybe if they don't understand it, they may overcompensate with the sort of freedom and
what seems like opportunity for their own kids.
But what actually puts them inadvertently in danger, just as the person who was neglected
and was then left in situation of danger may over control their kids and then the kids
rebel and the same thing happens.
I mean, if we don't understand it, there's a very good chance that it will find a way
to get us.
And you know, sometimes that's something dramatic.
And you know, I see these cases like, oh my gosh, like this person did the opposite thing.
Their parents didn't look the same thing happens.
Right.
And a lot of times, you know, I think most human suffering and most bad outcomes, you
know, happen with a fizzle, not a bang.
And I think that's part of the really the biggest sadness of it is the things that we
don't know are the person who just languishes, who doesn't have a strong sense of self and
is burdened with regret.
And that's the story.
I mean, there's so much about this that because we don't talk about it, we don't educate ourselves
about it.
We just let be perpetuated.
And in many ways, like I'm not trying to say, oh, this is all easy to address.
Right.
But some of this I think is low hanging fruit of, look, why are we not talking about these
things?
Right.
Why is it that we enter medical school and you have all these like overly powerful guys
and you know, we don't think of it like, what are we all defending against?
Like, why do we have to be so powerful all the time?
What are we guarding against?
Why is it that we feel ashamed if we're not powerful?
Right.
And not, you know, if we're not perfect, if we're not the best, right.
Why is it?
And and and, you know, and I'm not saying, gee, let's let's have some like soft way of
going about life and then people aren't driven to achieve things.
But it's it's a lot of it is based on this lie that like, what doesn't kill us makes
us stronger.
OK, that is a lie.
Sometimes something doesn't kill us and makes us stronger.
You know, we can get an infection.
It doesn't kill us.
We develop antibodies.
It can happen on a biological level.
It can happen with a life tribulation.
But my experience in my own life and in the people around me that I take care of or my
friends, family, patients, like the humans in my life is that bad things that don't kill
us often make us weaker.
All right.
They hurt us.
And if we don't acknowledge that, what has this thing done to me?
Right.
Then we put it under the surface and we soldier forward.
And for a lot of people, you know, what does that mean?
I mean, it does mean languishing.
And oftentimes for people who maybe are blessed with more drive and perseverance.
Sure it means we drive ourselves to achievement.
But amidst all that achievement, we remain miserable because the hurt part of us is is
like still what we're living in every moment, every most of the time we're living in that
hurt person.
But that hurt person is festooned in a way that doesn't look like that.
And if you think about very powerful things in culture, you know, the Wizard of Oz, you
know, like such a cultural touchstone across generations, even the emperor's new clothes.
I mean, we're infatuated with things looking some way, but being another way, you know,
things looking strong and powerful, but being weak and vulnerable.
And part of our infatuation with that is it can take the fear out of some of the things
that scare us.
But I think an even bigger part of that is that we often identify with that.
We identify with, you know, festooning ourselves, look how great I am.
And like, you know, really, I'm not festooned in anything, right?
I mean, there's like, there's a pathetic nakedness to some of it, right?
But but we sort of posture that way, right?
And we posture that way in order to show ourselves up.
And if I see a commonality between like how you and I practice medicine, and how the vast
majority of I think good doctors practice medicine is it's not hiding vulnerability.
I do not feel in any way, shape or form healthier than the vast majority of my patients.
I mean, some people, yes, I've had a bad head injury, have schizophrenia, okay?
I don't feel any better necessarily healthier to them a lot of the time.
But there's an identified problem that we want to address and treat that can let the
person feel a greater sense of wholeness.
Okay, that's valid.
But most of the people that I encounter are just struggling the same way that I am.
And, you know, there really is no difference, except that person may do something, maybe
someday I need an architect, a financial manager, you know, a lawyer, whatever it is that they're
doing, but we're no different.
It just happens to be like, okay, this thing I do brings them to come to me for help about
this certain thing.
But we're all people are trying to make our way and survive in the world.
And often some of the people who I feel are most put together are not the people that
you might think, right?
They're the people who if you look at their achievements, you know, you're not going to
be wowed by it necessarily.
But they're people who have a greater sense of wholeness.
They're people who have maybe spent more time and effort on themselves.
And again, this is not an anti-ambition agenda that I have here.
What I absolutely am saying is that very, very high levels of achievement are a marker
in my brain for suspicion that this person is defending against something.
And you know, that's the reason why I thought that you should go to the bridge.
It's the reason why trauma therapy is part of my psychotherapy.
It's the reason why at some point I should go to the bridge too, right?
I mean, this...
You know what the nickname for that place is?
You're the first person who told me I send a bunch of people there and no one tells me
this and then you do.
Do you want to...
It has two nicknames, Camp Misery and The Crying Factory.
Yeah, the key to the Crying Factory.
And you know, it points out that making ourselves healthier often is difficult.
It does involve misery.
It involves tears and exposure of things we're ashamed of.
And you know, of all the places that I have sent people in, you know, at this point in
almost two decade career, you know, I think that they are the most effective or among
the most effective of places.
And I think part of it is because they don't shy away from that.
I remember something you said to me because you suggested, look, there are two or three
places where I think you could go.
Here's why I think the bridge is the best for you.
And one of the reasons was...
Oh, I'm almost embarrassed to admit live, you know, to people, to so many people what
I asked you.
You know, Paul, when I looked at these other places, the bridge seems unique in that the
socioeconomics of it look very different from where I've come from, meaning I'm not going
to be there with other people who have gone to medical school or gone to law school or
whatever.
Will I have enough in common with the other people there?
And you said, that's exactly why I think you should go there.
And I didn't understand that.
So I go there.
And of course, the first rule is everybody has a roommate.
Well, I don't want a goddamn roommate.
I'm 45 years old.
I'm past that course.
Right. I did that.
I did summer camp already.
I don't want a roommate.
So I have my assistant call over and say, hey, we'll pay extra, but he needs a solo
room to which they sort of said, thanks for telling us how to do our job.
That ain't the way it works.
He gets a roommate.
Right.
Again, everything that they did that I thought was pure torture turned out to be perfect.
There was exactly what you said.
I had to be around people who I could relate to intellectually, who I couldn't relate to
intellectually, who I had a similar education to, to whom I did not.
But in the end, what I realized was we are all the same.
And that is such a banal, glib, idiotic statement.
But it's fucking true.
We are all the same.
My roommate, I swear for the first three days, I thought, I don't have one thing in common
with this guy.
I loved him out of the gate.
I mean, he was just an amazing guy.
But it's like, we don't have anything in common.
And that's fine.
I mean, it didn't make me like him any less.
But two weeks later, I realized, oh, actually, we have more in common than I would have ever
dreamed we have.
The reason we look like we have nothing in common is perhaps some innate wiring, perhaps
some stochastic events.
But in the end, we took very different divergent paths.
You know, mine led me to college.
His did not.
My weaknesses led me in a different area than his did.
One of the things that I found most powerful, and I'm bringing this back to a point you
made earlier, was in addition to 13 hours of camp misery every day, seven days a week,
you get to go to a 12-step meeting every single night.
And you get to pick what it is.
So they're not going to tell you which one you're going to, but you're either going to
AA or Al-Anon or CODA or NA or SA or SLA.
You're going.
I think you got one night off a week.
I think Sunday night, you got spared the meeting.
I remember thinking the first few times, like, I'm so tired.
I'm just so emotionally exhausted that, you know, it's 7 p.m. or 8 p.m.
All I want to do is go lay on my shitty bunk bed and sleep.
But they're like, nope, you got to go.
And you're a guy, by the way, who could work what?
How many hours constantly as a surgical resident?
Yeah, this was a different level of fatigue.
So the fact that you're that exhausted speaks to like, what's going on, the magnitude of
what's going on inside of you.
I find that to be like, fascinating and a great proof of concept.
Yeah.
This in many ways hurt more than swimming the Catalina Channel every day.
Wow.
Okay, that's saying something, right?
But what I realized when it was all said and done, because I ended up being quite surprised
at how much I really got out of being in these 12-step meetings.
When I wasn't a participant, every meeting I went to was an open meeting.
I never once spoke, never once.
But I was so moved by the vulnerability of these people.
Now, again, part of that might be an artifact of the fact that we were two hours outside
of the nearest civilization.
I mean, we're an hour outside of Bowling Green, Kentucky.
We were in a place that I don't even, I wouldn't know how to find on a map if my life depended
on it.
But I couldn't believe the vulnerability in these meetings.
I think in many ways that is an antidote to shame.
It is the beginning of it.
And fast forward five months, I'm back.
I'm back into my life.
And obviously much of my life has changed as a result of this.
But look, we still struggle.
We're still always thinking about these things.
And I remember my therapist in San Diego said something that I thought was so profound.
She goes, Peter, part of the problem with you is you're always the smartest guy in the
room.
Now, she was sort of mocking me.
She wasn't actually telling me how the smartest guy in the room.
She's like, you basically are always the one on point.
You're the one talking.
You're the one giving the advice.
You're the one who everyone's looking to for the answer.
And the problem with that is, like, you never get the chance to listen and not say a word
and not have anybody even give a shit that you're in the room.
And I was like, you know, that's the key.
That's the thing I miss about the 12-step meeting was nobody gave a shit that I was
in the room.
And even if I was and I said, yeah, my name is Peter, it's like, great.
Thanks for being here, Peter.
You were no better or no worse than anybody else in this room.
And so in many ways, I feel like and again, I don't think it has to be the 12-step stuff.
I know people are going to listen to this and say, oh, 12 steps, a bunch of nonsense.
What works for you works for you.
But the point is there is really something to be said for that type of vulnerability
in a group where nothing else matters.
It doesn't matter how much money you have.
It doesn't matter how many degrees you have.
It doesn't matter what you've done.
I mean, none of those has been.
And of course, the next place where that became the most riveting to me was on this
prison visit that I went to, which we've talked about as well.
And again, just another great example of how in that moment, in a moment of redemption,
all that matters is where it was where you are in that moment.
And I just find that again, as I'm sitting here and listening to all of the things you're
saying, of course, my mind is immediately going to, okay, what can we do?
What can we do?
What can someone listening to this do?
Can someone listening to this who's identifying with this saying, you know what, like maybe
that thing that happened to me when I was 10 or maybe this behavior that I have that's
on the surface reasonable, but underneath the surface is maladaptive.
Maybe that needs to be revisited.
And again, if the answer is they need to seek therapy, fine.
But what else can people do?
I think that it's so important to try and take stock of how are we trying to separate
ourselves from other people?
I mean, think about the things you're saying.
It's very interesting.
And people listening to this who know you will know that this is true.
And for the people who don't know you, please, I would ask, take my word for this.
I mean, you are the least entitled, condescending human being, right?
I mean, you do not feel superior to other people.
I don't think I've seen one wit of that in the two decades I've known you.
So why is it that you want a private room and that you want to be different?
It's a reflex.
And the reflex is like, I've got to stand out in some way because that's what allows
me not to feel superior, but to not feel ashamed.
And that's often what is driving us.
And it drives good things, right?
I mean, your expertise and often being the focus in the room because you have things
to say, to offer is like, these are good things.
But they're also driven by the need to separate ourselves.
And it's not that both of those sides of the coin have to come together, but if we're
not aware, they do come together.
And then you're doing something by reflex that is the exact opposite of what you need.
What you need is to be part of the humanity around you, right?
What you need is to relate to people.
What you need is to feel that, my God, I mean, I'm a human who suffers from human things
like these people around me, some of whom are nothing like me.
Some of whom may be like me, but none of that matters.
We're all people and our suffering is shared.
That takes away the unique stigma of the things that you are suffering from.
But your reflex, as mine has been, and as is the case in many people who are sort of
driven to differentiate themselves, is to differentiate yourself so that you guarantee
loneliness.
And, you know, that's what people, I think, really should try and be aware of is when are
we differentiating ourselves from the world around us because we are trying to escape
from something, but in doing so we isolate ourselves.
And we don't get a chance to just be human.
We don't get a chance to just be people.
Like, you know, the people who are there at the bridge with you had trauma and suffering,
and they needed to express emotions, and they needed to cry, and they needed to get angry.
And you did too, right?
And I have too, and so many people need that to heal, but we work so hard to separate ourselves
from that.
And that's what I think, you know, if there's one thing like a person's going to be attuned
to is how much are you separating yourself from the humanity around you?
You know, groups of people, when people have agendas or are angry, can feel threatening
and intimidating.
But there are many places that people gather in order to feel some sense of openness and
shared humanity.
And that's really what we're all seeking.
You know, I know you know this, but seven, eight years ago, and I had a clinic that myself
and my practice partner built, you know, to be relatively sizable, and we were doing a
lot of individualized treatment, and we were running groups.
And the groups we were running were around addiction.
And we were absolutely adamant that we did not stratify people by what they were addicted
to.
So gambling, cutting sex, cocaine, it doesn't matter.
Nor did we stratify people by age, socioeconomic status.
And it was a pressure to do that.
Because certain other people who had more resources, right, like wanted that, not realizing
that what they were asking for was, it was the very thing that was going to stand in
the way of their ability to get help.
You told me this exact story when I called you up to say, wait a minute, I don't think
the bridge is the place for me.
Yeah.
And I should be going to this place or that place.
And you said, no, what you're missing is you absolutely need to be around people who on
the surface you think you're different from to realize that you're not.
Right.
And it's an advantage that people have if they're at a stage of life or for whatever
reason, they're not in a socioeconomic class that allows them to differentiate because
they don't strive for something that stands in their way.
And I think back on that venture, which over about five years, my partner and I, and we
had 30 people or so in some way, shape, or form, we're working for us by the end.
We all really slaved away to make that place as good as it could be.
And when I think back on it, I think the proudest moment, people have asked me this
like, oh, that was so difficult.
And so some people who know me and kind of know what we struggled through and like some
of the people ask, what do you feel good about?
And the same image comes to mind is I remember a young woman who I think she was 19 who really
had struggled and was trying to find her way and had been on the streets and to the outward
look of things, piercings and tattoos and all the kind of things that kind of mark her
attempts to differentiate herself to say, okay, stay away from me in a way that she
was using to separate herself.
And God, she had made so much progress, so much progress in embracing who she was and
not feeling ashamed of who she was and not feeling responsible for things that happened
to her that she had no control over.
And I remember her, I walked by kind of late one day after groups had let out and she was
having this like really intense conversation with a neurosurgeon.
And it was so clear that she was teaching him a lot of things.
And you know, when he was in sort of wrapped attention, and it's a marker for me of like
our shared humanness is like, you know, if you look at him and you look at her, you say,
okay, the things they've achieved, he's clearly he's the authority.
He's got a CV a half a half a mile long, right?
And you know, this woman has been struggling to stay off the streets.
She had done more work on herself.
So she had a lot to teach him.
And I have found that again, it sounds trite, but the things that I have learned through
the course of my work, so much of them have just come from people who have been through
such difficulties and have learned things about themselves that I hadn't yet learned,
not at all tied to any metric other than that.
And I think that's part of the secret of it.
And we don't do these things anymore.
We don't have places where people can come and even get some mental health education,
some idea of like, what ails them in terms of trauma, like we don't as a society acknowledge
this.
So then it becomes some like shocking rarity when somebody finds their way to it.
And I just I'm astounded by that, that we should be like setting a roadmap with like
really gigantic arrows for all of us.
But you know, a person has to stumble upon it or come across it inadvertently.
In many ways, I think I'll forever be grateful.
I mean, forever be grateful to you for making this happen, because I guess some people just
they need a greater degree of immersion to finally break down.
I think I could have spent two hours a week in therapy for the rest of my life and never,
ever come close to what finally takes place when you're doing 13 hours a day plus 12
step meetings.
And not only that, it's like every meal, you're sitting there with the same group of people.
We only got coffee once a day, 7am was coffee time.
And it was like, I would get up at four and work out.
And then I'd be, you know, waiting to have my coffee at seven.
And there were like six of us that showed up for coffee every morning.
And the other thing about this place that was so amazing, which really ties into what
you're saying is everyone who works there, obviously not just the counselors and the
therapists, but the kitchen staff, the custodial staff, the people that worked at the barn
where we did equine therapy, every one of them had themselves been a client there.
Wow, I didn't know that.
Unbelievable shared experience.
Like we are all the same at this place.
Wow.
And isn't there comfort in that, right?
Absolutely.
And can you be some exception who deserves shame for being something less than perfect
when you fully apprehend that reality?
It can't be, right?
You know, you said something a moment ago that made me think of one of my favorite talks.
So, you know, you and I, you know that I'm the biggest fan of David Foster Wallace, this
person who I've just, I've just always been kind of so amazed by his insight.
I just, you know, here's a guy who was not a trained psychiatrist.
He's a writer and yet his insights into humanity go beyond almost anything.
I think you couldn't learn this stuff in a textbook.
And you know, I've been asked before, like if you could bring anybody back from the dead,
you know, of recent era, right?
Who would it be?
And I think it would be him.
You know, if I could, if I could go back in time and spend a day with anybody, it would
probably be with David Foster Wallace.
He has a very famous commencement speech from 2005 that he delivered at Kenyon College titled
This is Water.
And in it, he talks about the fact that we're, I think he, the way he describes it is there's
no such thing as atheism.
We are all worshiping some God.
Do you worship money?
Power your body, you know, your physical allure.
And he almost makes the case that at least if you pick a God to worship, the harm to
you might be less.
Because if it is money you worship, you'll never have enough.
If it's power you worship, you'll never feel strong enough.
If it's intellect that you worship, you'll always feel like a fraud.
And I remember listening to this for the very first time, which was many years ago and thinking,
yeah, I get that.
Like I really get that.
Like I, I know I'm not alone, but I think a lot of people who place their self worth
and their intellect, you think, what if people find out I'm not that smart?
Like I'm just a fraud.
And you know, it's again, it's just, it just speaks to this entire nature of humanity.
And of course the tragedy in the case of David Foster Wallace is that he ends up taking his
own life by suicide three years after he gave that talk.
Now totally unrelated.
I want to play something for you.
So I was actually just listening to this today.
I had, I hadn't come across this before, but this is an interview with David Foster Wallace
and Terry Gross from NPR.
I believe it was 97.
So it was like a year or two after Infinite Jest came out.
So I want to play this for you if I can cue it up on my phone here.
Because I thought of you as soon as I heard this.
Right.
Okay, here we go.
You know, I really like the way you talk, you write about a pleasure and how difficult
it can be to, to really achieve.
You write about pleasure in the Infinite Jest, your, your, your latest novel.
You know, thinking, you know, one of the things relating to that in Infinite Jest,
one of the characters finds that, that marijuana is, marijuana is no longer a pleasurable experience.
It just makes them terribly self-conscious and therefore anxious.
And I'm wondering what happens to you when you do something that's supposed to give you
pleasure and that just makes you uncomfortable or anxious.
Boy, I'm not really even sure how to respond to that.
Look, a lot of the impetus for writing Infinite Jest was just the fact that, that I was about
30 and I had a lot of friends who were about 30 and we'd all, you know, been grotesquely
over-educated and privileged our whole lives and had better healthcare and more money than
our parents did.
And we were all extraordinarily sad.
I think it has something to do with, with being raised in an era when really the ultimate
value seems to be, I mean, a successful life is, let's see, you make a lot of money and
you have a really attractive spouse or you get, you get infamous or famous in some way
so that it's a life where you basically experience as much pleasure as possible, which ends up,
which ends up being sort of empty and low calorie.
The reason I don't like talking about it discursively is it sounds very banal and cliche, you know,
when you say it out loud that way.
Believe it or not, this was, this came as something of an epiphany to us at around age
30, sitting around talking about why on earth we were so miserable when we'd been so lucky.
Well, when did you realize that all the, all the benefits you had in an educated middle
class life weren't bringing you happiness?
Well, I, look, I guess it, I guess it sort of depends on what you mean by happiness.
I mean, it's not like we were walking around fingering razor blades or anything like that,
but it just sort of seems as if we sort of knew how happy our parents were and we would
compare our lives with our parents and see that at least on the surface, we're according
to the criteria that the culture lays down for a successful happy life.
We were actually doing better than a lot of them were.
And so why on earth were we so miserable?
I don't think, you know, I don't mean to suggest that, that it was, you know, a state of constant
clinical depression or that we all felt that we were supposed to be blissfully happy all
the time.
There was just, I have a very weird and amateur sense that, that an enormous part of like
my generation and the generation right after mine is just an extremely sad sort of lost
generation, which when you think about the material comforts and the political freedoms
that we enjoy is just strange.
I could listen to interviews with David, well indefinitely, but it's interesting that I
came across that today for the first time.
Again, I don't know how I missed it today, just literally today.
And you know, I knew that we were going to be speaking this evening and I thought, you
know, I'm going to put Paul on the spot and play that forum and ask him not just to explain
that, but even more broadly, what the heck is going on, right?
Why?
I mean, let's take a step back.
It would seem to me that suicide is the least likely cause of demise for our species, just
given our evolution.
I mean, it seems to me that we are wired to survive.
So in other words, and again, I'm certainly not being critical of suicide.
I have nothing but empathy for obviously anyone who commits suicide.
It strikes me as the saddest thing ever, but I don't understand it.
Like I don't, I don't understand how it can be so prevalent when we must be so wired to
not want it, when we must be so wired to want to survive.
And it, I remember very recently, I remember having this thought probably in the wake of
the, you know, these high profile suicides, which, you know, I remember when Robin Williams
killed himself, the same sort of thoughts go through my mind, which is, did our ancestors
do this?
Is suicide a symptom of our civilization?
Is what David Foster Wallace is talking about here, even comparing ourselves to one generation
ago, are we less happy or do we just have greater expectations?
And those expectations being unmet is what makes us feel unhappier.
Again, it's, I mean, it's so complicated.
And I want to start off by saying like, by no means do I attest to any expertise, right?
Or a right to offer an opinion that's more valuable than anyone else's.
But the thoughts that occurred to be is, you know, we're wired to survive as long as we
see meaning in survival.
And I am not here trying to glorify struggle, but there is something around struggle that
gives meaning.
You know, people who struggle to survive in war zones, you don't have people who see meaning
in survival, they see meaning in what they're fighting for.
You know, Viktor Frankl writing mens, search for meaning, right?
It's like, if you don't have meaning, then why would you struggle to survive?
And it's not a lengthy extrapolation of that to say, if you don't have meaning, why are
you interested in surviving?
Have you read Tribe by Sebastian Younger?
I have not.
I probably should.
And I've been told several times I should.
I just haven't gotten to it yet.
But I mean, I understand.
I think I think this is sort of part of what he's getting at.
Yeah, that that we OK, for example, I really I mean, it's interesting, right, given what
I do for a living that like, I don't know how I value myself.
I don't know how to value myself and whether I'm succeeding or not.
I mean, is that what my family of origin thinks of me?
How much time I spend with them?
I've certainly ranged far afield and left the place I grew up in order to achieve things
and do things.
Should I be proud of that?
If I have I not been a good friend or family member to the people I grew up with, do I
value myself by what other people think of me?
How many patients I feel I can help the health of my relationship with the people I love
as adults?
The kind of parent I am, kind of husband I am.
How much money I have?
How many people want me to offer some expert opinion on something?
It's like I have no idea.
I have no idea whatsoever.
And it occurs to me sometimes that I'll bet all those ancestors of mine really knew how
to value themselves.
Like, are the sheep safe?
Is there a roof over our heads?
And again, I mean, I'm not glorifying the lack of opportunity, you know, the lack of
like a basic medical care right in generations past.
But there is something very, very concrete about that.
And when people go through struggle, when we often most worry about them is when the
struggle is over.
When people feel like I made it through that, you know, whatever that was, maybe that was
chemotherapy.
Maybe that was the death of someone close to them.
Maybe it was a particularly trying time at home or in their career.
You know, people will persevere when they see meaning in their struggle.
But when there's not a struggle, the struggle is over or we're not particularly struggling
for something.
How do you value yourself?
And I think often we don't even know enough to answer the question.
I mean, like you and I have never sat down and talked about this.
We spent a lot of time together.
We've been closed for two decades.
Like, why do we not talk about this?
In part because we don't understand how meaningful it is.
Right.
So we value ourselves by persevering.
But that's endless.
Right.
I mean, as you said, you there's always more of things to have.
So at a certain point, that can seem very, very hollow.
And I think that in many ways that's the disease of the modern civilization.
I mean, even when we grew up the time of the Cold War, I mean, I grew up with this very
like clear idea.
And I get that, you know, it was a simplistic idea.
Right.
The West is good.
And, you know, we fight for democracy and, you know, the Soviets are bad.
And I get that this is not the case.
I mean, I spent time in Russia and in Eastern Europe.
And I get like the people are people.
But it wasn't easy.
It was an easier algorithm to grow up in.
And it instilled faith in in America and faith in what we stood for.
And and as we get older and wiser, we all learn about the hypocrisy of life and the
the truths of life and, you know, learning of, you know, I remember learning about like
things that America had done in Central America.
Right.
And, you know, I'm feeling a sense of like, oh, my God, we are not this force of good.
And it doesn't mean that we were a force of evil.
It means that the situation was far more complicated, but it provided a heuristic.
And even that was something that kind of made sense.
I mean, I can remember the Olympics coming around and like feeling this sense of, OK,
like it's are we going to beat the East Germans and the Russians?
And, you know, there was just a sense of dichotomization, which is why people who want to control other
people know to make struggle.
Right.
You make an enemy.
So this is all a double edged sword.
And you can make meaning in ways that is not valid.
Right.
You say, OK, those people are bad.
Let's go kill them.
And that's a way of making meaning for people.
It's not an honest or a moral way.
But what I'm trying to point out is that we see value to our struggle if we see meaning.
And I think that for a long time, even as people got wisdom and in greater knowledge
of things like hypocrisy and they're really the truth of the world, I think we still saw
greater meaning.
And I'm not so sure that we do as much now.
You know, I think that things are much more nebulous and then it's hard to get around
the idea of, well, do I really matter?
You know, what am I doing?
What am I standing for?
What's what's really the difference?
And I just think, look, that can happen at any time.
And probably it did happen back when everybody lived in caves.
But I think we're much, much more susceptible to it because we don't have some sense of
community and we don't have a sense of community.
I mean, it's interesting, right?
People have written about why do human beings, when we're so focused on survival, right?
There's a lot of people that will spontaneously risk their life for somebody else.
Jump into the river, right?
Try and rescue somebody.
Why do we do that?
I think the answer is because in that moment we see we see very clearly defined, a very
lucid meaning to our actions.
And I think that that's like very, very profound.
And I think it's the opposite.
I see that as the opposite of suicide, which is, which doesn't mean, I mean, it can happen
for a lot of reasons, right?
People can be very depressed and, and, you know, the delusions of lack of worth.
I mean, again, it's very complicated and I'm not trying to trivialize it.
But I think a lot of what promotes suicide is the absence of meaning, which I see as
the opposite of someone who's taking good care of themselves and maybe wants to stay
alive very much so, but will risk their life to help someone else.
That's a focus of meaning, that there's a compelling meaning right now.
Right.
And a lot of those parents who want to be there for their child would jump in a river
for someone else, like as they see a child.
So, you know, it's that just capturing of the attention, like this is meaningful.
Look at this.
I, this is a chance I will make a difference now.
Right.
And I'm willing to take a chance to do that.
And I think it's very, very different than how a lot of people feel.
I think also socioeconomic demographics.
I mean, if you think that I don't know what the exact numbers are, but I think that's
the difference between the two.
I mean, if you think that I don't know what the exact numbers are, but you know what percentage
of people in this country, you know, I was sort of reading the reports around like a
$500 unexpected bill, right?
And like, just people can't survive that, right?
Like they're not going to get medical care.
They're not going to, you know, service the car and then they can't get to work or they're
not going to, you know, they can't live a life that we would consider acceptable, you
know, with an unexpected in the grand scheme of things, otherwise surmountable amount of
money that's needed.
And you know, I think that's a very, very hard way to live that, that, you know, a lot
of what we're talking about is Foster Wallace was talking about of like, well, we have so
much opportunity and we don't have to struggle, right?
But if you are struggling to put food on the table and you know, you know that if somebody
needs to go to the emergency room, how the hell are you going to get enough food?
That's a struggle.
It's very hard to see meaning it.
It's a struggle that seems like denigration.
I mean, it's, it's, you're going to struggle.
Whereas it's different.
Our ancestors, if they had to struggle through a famine or drought, I mean, it was just, that
was just the, that was the gods, right?
That was nature.
That was the season and they were in it together.
Right.
And it's not like you were struggling because of the drought, but your neighbor was, you
know, rolling around in a, you know, whatever the equivalent of the Ferrari would be.
Right.
And I think it's so, you know, it's so in a way baffling, right?
That, look, I hate the thought that how many people are there that 500 yard medical
building, they can't put food on the table.
You know, yet, you know, I'm fortunate to live in relative plenty compared to that,
but I don't know how to bridge that gap.
There's not a sense of community and sure, like we can donate and we can do things for
free and all of this, but, but like, we don't have a sense of what does that mean?
And how do we change that?
And how do we make that better?
And my sense is that I actually feel quite insecure.
Do I have enough if my kids need something, right?
Do I have enough if you know, things really go south and it becomes unsafe to live here.
I have a sense of vulnerability.
What does someone feel like who has the same sense of conscientiousness towards the
people that they love through $500 can sink.
So I'm not trying to make specific points about that, but really to, to point out
what I view as just a tremendous sense of isolation.
And it's not a disease of plenty.
I mean, I think it's a disease that affect people who have enough and that affects
people who don't have enough, even worse.
And then that, that lack of shared sense of community, a lack of being in it
together, you know, it may sound hokey, but, but through most of life, that's how
people live.
I mean, unfortunately, Paul, everything you just said, doesn't really seem to
offer a foreseeable remedy to this.
And if today we're seeing 30% more suicide or thereabouts than we were a
couple of decades ago, is there anything on the horizon that's going to curb that
trend or is suicide going to become an increasingly greater part of our humanity
and, and perhaps worse yet for every person who actually kills themselves.
What if there's nine people who are in that category we described earlier is
basically functionally dead.
And then you think of the effect of the suicide.
What's the trickle down effect of that on the next generation?
I do think that there are ways to make this better.
And I feel strongly and passionately about them.
You and I have talked about some of them and I'm fortunate to have dialogues with
people who can really kind of help make a difference in this way.
Again, do I know that it's the right way?
No, I don't, but it's the best I can think of.
Which is, you know, it's a simplification, right?
Like we don't have places where people could come together and have shared
experience and have a sense of community.
Like what about places where there are people to facilitate human connection and
education, even about the basics of what's going on inside of people.
And there's a couple of comfortable couches and a pot of coffee.
These are not expensive things.
I mean, you think about it in this country, what things cost.
Go get an X-ray, $700, right?
I mean, we've built up so much cost around things, so much liability, so much
that prevents really basic, simple things from happening.
And we've lost the basics of community support.
I mean, there was an era before you and I were practicing medicine.
So before I was, before I was a psychiatrist, right?
Where, where there were community support centers and they were publicly funded and
they didn't cost very much money in the grand scheme of things.
And there were places where people who are pretty mentally ill could go for
support. Not only do we not have places like that for you and me and the other
people who are managing to function, we don't even have those places for people
who are really mentally ill.
So we don't provide a nidus in the community for the basics of what I would
call psychoeducation and for the ability to do that in a way that really links
human beings and looks at what their needs are.
You know, how many times have I seen where a person who, if they overdose or
they slit their wrists, right, that the world will pay a million dollars for
their intensive care unit stay.
But what we will not do is buy them the $300 alternator that could fix the car
that allows them to not have to go back to the abusive household situation that
leads to the suicide attempt that society pays a million dollars for.
Like a lot of what we do is utterly absurd as a society.
It's not even cost efficient.
If you took out care and concern for human beings and said, look, let's factor
that out, it's absurd.
You know, it's like, you know, you throw away $10,000 to get a dollar.
And that's how we operate as a society.
And I think that if we're going to survive our own progress, you know, as a
species or certainly in this country, we're going to do things that are around
mutuality and community support.
And we're going to do things where people who have something can help people who
don't, and maybe that's $300 to buy an alternator.
You know, maybe it's not that maybe it's somebody who doesn't have the education
or resources that you or I might have who share some wisdom that they've learned.
I mean, it's not just, oh, the people who have do things for the people who haven't.
I mean, we all have and we all don't have.
And I'm not trying to trivialize the struggles of people who can't put food on
the table, like that's what we need to work so that that's not the case.
And it's actually not that hard to do.
But at the same time, we need to recognize that the people, that some of the things
that we've done through drive to separate us, make us lonely and isolate us.
And I think you and I have as many emotional needs and as many struggles that
can be soothed by other people as somebody does who might identify as
underprivileged or ill, right?
Like I said, we're all in it together.
And but we work so damn hard to separate ourselves and you end up with maybe not
everybody, but most people feeling some sense of loneliness and isolation.
It's a, there's no easy antidote.
You and I have spoken a lot about the idea of creating a tribe.
We think about the seven of us from medical school and it was like, we had this
fantasy, like what if we all could get jobs, not only in the same city, but like
we could all live on the same block and we could all just sort of be one family.
The kids could go between the homes interchangeably, meals were consumed
interchangeably, like it was just, you know, creating a tribe in the way that it
would have existed 10,000 years ago.
But you know, we still put our shirts and ties on in the morning and go to work, but
you, but there's this closeness that seems so distant right now.
I mean, you and I are so fortunate because of the geography in which we work
that at least a few times a month we get to have a meal together, but that is
harder and harder to do with friends.
And I suspect that there are many people who go months, if not years, without
really getting to do that because it's just too busy.
There's just too much to do.
That's mission critical.
Right.
And there again is the automaticity of a value system that, you know, I struggle
very much with how many people do I care about who've been really important in my
life. And I think, and I, and theirs that we exchange two emails a year.
I mean, why, right?
Why is, why do I not take two weeks every three months and go around and see people
I care about?
Like, why don't we do that?
And I think, again, I think I do think that all paths, I mean, even not all paths,
but I think the majority of these paths lead back to trauma, that there's a way in
which I feel too insecure to do that.
I'll step away from my work and maybe it won't be as good at my work or opportunities
will pass me by and I'll earn less.
And all these things that actually make no sense whatsoever, but it's not as if I
can stop them from driving me.
And, and, and I want to sound futile about that.
I mean, I think like there are things that we can do, right?
And I think like you and I do some things that we might not have done even a couple of
years ago, right?
But do I think that we do enough of it?
No, I don't.
And you think about those other people that, you know, we were in school with and care
very much about and then think about people who weren't like sort of in that group that
we know well and knew well and care very much about.
How much do we really see of them?
Right.
Almost nothing.
And, you know, it's a strange thing to, to have so much automaticity to our value
system and we might think, well, I never decided I don't value that.
And I value, you know, another day of work overseeing those people.
Okay.
I never actually put words to it, but I've decided it right.
Because I act in accordance with that decision.
And yes, I'd like to be healthier about those things.
But I think the answer is as a, is as a community that we start teaching ourselves
and teaching people how to be healthier about those things, because you can still
be very good at what you do.
Very successful, move society ahead.
All these things that we want to do if we achieve and have a better sense of balance
and mutuality, which is why a lot of these fantasies and it's what kids say in kindergarten
to their best friend, like we're going to live next door to one another, right?
Okay.
We're still saying that in medical school after.
We're fricking 45 year old dudes and we still say the same thing.
Right.
Because I think we still have the same needs within us and we still have the same
fears of loneliness and isolation and struggle in isolation.
So the fantasy is still there.
I think because there's meaning to the fantasy, it's a recurrent fantasy in a
lot of people that tells us something about our desperate sense of isolation.
And I have no basis to back this up and it probably is politically incorrect to say
this, but I actually don't give a shit.
You can be married.
You can have the perfect spouse.
You can have all that stuff going on.
But, and I say this only being able to speak from my vantage point, which is as a
male, I think that there are certain needs that can't be met by your spouse.
There are certain needs that like, and again, I think my wife doesn't even like
hearing that like she'd like to believe, understandably, that every problem I have
emotionally can be rectified by discussing it with her.
But I do think there's something different that I think there's a, maybe even a
degree of vulnerability that exists outside of that relationship and, or maybe
even there's just something gender specific, like a guy needs to be with a
guy sometimes a girl needs to be with a girl sometimes, as far as like truly
talking about some of these things.
And I think that for many people as they get older, as they have families, as they
have kids, as they have careers, they lose sight with those other people.
Meaning the woman loses touch with her female friends who I think can offer her
something that her husband cannot, even if they're the most well-adjusted couple.
And similarly, I mean, I can't tell you the premium I place on the time I get to
spend with my male friends.
And it's hard because as you said, it often comes at the expense of time with
your family.
I mean, every minute I'm here in New York right now, you and I are here.
We're not with our families.
Right.
I mean, I think that that is a human problem.
I mean, I think that we, you know, we can, we see it through our own lens.
Right.
But I don't think it's based upon gender, gender, socioeconomic class, sexual
orientation.
I mean, I think it's a human problem that there's a fallacy that says that we're
supposed to enter, you know, a committed relationship, which already think about
like there are people who, you know, might not be able to do that, right?
Might not want to do this.
So we're already saying de facto that that's not okay.
So think how many people were invalidating already.
Then we say, okay, even if you do that, we're going to put so much pressure to be
everything to one another, that, that we guarantee almost a sense of a failure or
of inadequacy.
Why should your lovely, wonderful wife think that she can be everything?
To you, right?
Like that's just not how humans work, but somehow society has told her that.
And then it engenders some negative feeling because both you and she being
healthy people need a broader set of connections, but we're taught to kind of
hunker down and that's what we're supposed to do.
And then when we're getting away and we're doing these things with our friends,
that there's, there's something about that that seems kind of trivialized because
we don't, we don't live in communities where, and look,
think about it.
I haven't thought about this before.
We think about in medical school when we were kind of living in a community and
we did spend time, like if we were friends, then I spent time with Jill and
you spent time with Brooke.
We were in a community.
So there was more of a sense of communality and now we don't have that as
much like that's not the way it's supposed to be in a sense.
And then it engenders these unrealistic expectations of self and others.
And the question I would most ask about that, I don't know the answer to it.
Why don't we continue to live in a communal way?
And I think that that's some of what, you know, communities offer people, right?
Communities that are based around religion or based around shared interests.
Those can be very, very good things for people.
Of course, like anything else, the other side of that sword is they can, you know,
that's, they can be used to create cults and how about like affiliate, right?
And people are desperate to affiliate.
So, you know, I think if there isn't health and balance, then, you know, we see
more the negative side of things.
We don't have enough community affiliation.
So there are a lot of people who get caught up in cult or cult like things,
you know, more than we would know more than we necessarily know on the surface,
because there are a lot of things like that that don't get defined as such or
don't get acknowledged as such.
They just don't come to attention, but there's a desperation for connection and
for a multiplicity of connection and a variety of connection.
And we live in a way often that really makes no sense.
There's no reason why should one person be everything to one other person?
You know, life is more complicated and more interesting and richer than that.
Are there any books that you would recommend people read?
I mean, I have my sort of list of go to books that I've suggested to people over
time. I certainly hope that anybody who's listening to this that thinks that some
trauma in their life has continued to sort of yield its grip around their neck.
We'll look into some of these trauma based treatment facilities and ultimately
seek out therapists who themselves are well versed in trauma based therapy.
Again, you don't have to go to an inpatient place to start, but I've since
learned the importance of trying to vet therapists to find out who truly
understands this, but what other resources, whether it be books or
facilities or anything like, I mean, what,
what kind of things can we, can we leave people with to think about as they begin
to navigate their own path?
I mean, like I said, I suspect there's going to be some people for whom this
episode scratches a scab a little bit, creates a little bit of bleeding.
What do they do now?
I think it's so important to take stock of one's inner dialogue.
We can say things to ourselves hundreds and hundreds and thousands of times over
and never stop and reflect that we're saying it to ourselves.
So I think thinking about what's going on inside of us and talking to people that
are close to us.
I mean, most people have people that they can talk to more openly than they're
talking to, and that can be complemented with professionals.
I mean, I think anyone who has no problems or issues whatsoever should never have
psychotherapy, right?
Which is, you know, my way of trying to be clever and saying every damn human on
the planet should have psychotherapy, right?
Because it's a way of understanding ourselves better.
It's a way of being able to commune with someone without feeling the pressure that
we're burdening them, like, you know, personal and professional relationships
help us understand each other better.
Go to a 12 step meeting, helps a person understand oneself better, even for no
other reason by the feeling of shared humanity.
Some of those things, which may sound kind of basic, I think are just of inordinate
importance, an ordinate importance of take stock of what's inside of you, connect
with people around you.
That may sound trite, but most of us are not doing it or not doing nearly enough of
it.
And in terms of literature or books, I mean, I, I tend to have very, very few book
recommendations.
I'll say a couple of the standards that I say when people ask me, I would consider
reading the K-Muse, the plague.
You know, the plague is about a city that is afflicted by the plague, but it is also
about the afflictions of all of us that are we all living amidst the plague and are we
all living amidst threat to our life and health and safety?
Yes, we are.
And, and I think it is, it's a way of potentially thinking about and framing things
inside of us, this feeling often of being beset upon and needing a sense of community
and a sense of mutuality that we often don't acknowledge.
And I think for that reason, the book is of tremendous value.
Somewhat of a very different recommendation is read some short stories by Katherine
Mansfield.
I think that, yes, Chekhov was a wonderful, brilliant short story writer, but my
favorite in terms of evoking the realness of being human, the subtle nuances of human
interaction, I think is actually best evoked by Mansfield.
And I think if we're searching for a way of identifying with our own humanity, I think
those two authors can help us get there.
So it's not the most typical literature to recommend, but I think exploring things that
great writers have written that help elucidate our humanity is a good thing if one is trying
to gain a greater grasp on what's going on inside of us and what may be really driving
us to misery.
And I think those things engender compassion and compassion for self is what can
ultimately lead somebody to take that step of getting help.
Right.
Is we have to feel like, hey, there's something going on inside of me that I've been
hiding and that I feel really ashamed of that I don't want to feel ashamed of anymore.
And I don't want to hide anymore.
And in general, people won't take that step unless they've engendered some
compassion for themselves.
Paul, there are so many other things I want to talk about.
I'm looking at my little notepad here where I had just scribbled down other things to
talk about that.
Amazingly, we literally did not get through half of what I wanted to talk about.
We didn't get into, you know, the real understanding of distress tolerance, the
completely nuanced geeky discussions that we have over dinner about all of the
different pharmacokinetics of every class of drug and every neurotransmitter.
I think the only real remedy for this is we have to do this again.
So I think there needs to be a part two of this discussion where we can get into all
of these other things.
And perhaps between now and then I could try and become less annoyingly long winded.
No, no, no, no, no.
No, I'll work on that before our next one.
Despite the short tenure of this podcast, I've already been given feedback by a few
friends who have said, Peter, we are really loving your podcast, but can you
shorten it? I would really like to just have a 30 minute podcast.
And I've said, honestly, I appreciate your feedback, but that's not what I'm trying
to do here.
One is I want these conversations to be the conversations that we have.
And what we just discussed tonight, the only thing that separates it from a normal
discussion is we have these microphones in front of us and we're not eating a meal.
Right. It is very similar to conversation you and I had three weeks ago while we were
sitting around the same table eating really good Indian food.
Right. Now, the fact that I'm in the middle of a one week fast makes that image
particularly distressing to me right now.
I don't appreciate that, but I just see part of how I keep myself in business is by
causing trauma.
Yeah, you just you just cost a shit ton of trauma in me by reminding me of that
incredible lamb vindaloo that I was eating sitting right where you're sitting now.
And I'm not going to have any of it tonight because I'm going to I want you to go home
and have something.
I'm going to.
Well, Paul, I can't thank you enough for all of the insights you've brought to all of
these topics from depression, suicide, trauma, shame, all of these things that are, I
think, near and dear to our hearts, but more importantly, kind of near and dear to the
hearts of pretty much everyone who's listening.
I know I said there's a lot more I'd like to get into.
I think we should certainly plan to sit down again and talk more about this stuff.
I I believe that there's a lot here that that people can take with them and hopefully at
least take some steps that that kind of improve the quality of their lives.
I've said it before, I will continue to say it.
I don't think it makes much sense to fixate on living longer if you can't on some level
rectify being happier.
And that seems to be, you know, if we talk about diabetes and all these other things
being diseases of civilization, there may be no greater disease of civilization than
our unhappiness.
Yeah, it's probably a good time for me to say, you know, what I truly believe, which is
I'm honored that you have had me on here.
And I really do mean that I do think that the things that I have to say from the mental
health perspective, not because I'm saying them, but because mental health undergirds
our ability to live good lives are so important.
And I think it's a testament to, you know, your sort of relentless drive to understand
things better that make a difference to the lives of the people that you take care of
that has you looking at elements of the substructure that people often ignore.
So I consider it an honor and a privilege to be on your podcast and to be able to talk
about things that I think are really are so important and that are just so often overlooked.
So I thank you for the opportunity to get the word out in a way that I hope ultimately
help some people.
Thank you.
Paul, I have no doubt that it will.
Thank you for your generosity of time and insight.
Welcome.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com.
What's a nerd safari, you ask?
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email
where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've read and all
things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD,
but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnoses or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition they
have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of
my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash about.