Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. I guess this week is Senator Bill Frist. Senator Frist is a former transplant
surgeon. He's a pilot, though we don't even get into that in this episode. It's just a whole other
amazing story. Obviously, a politician, businessman, healthcare policy expert. He's truly a Renaissance
man, as you'll see. He graduated from Princeton and Harvard Medical School, went on to study at
Stanford where he learned transplant surgery from the pioneering transplant surgeon of our era,
Norman Shumway, before heading over to Vanderbilt where he created the largest transplant program
east of the Mississippi. He did that till the early 90s when he up and ran for the US Senate
in 1994, having never held public office before. And perhaps even more remarkably than that,
he was elected as the 18th Senate Majority Leader in 2002, taking him from the single least senior
person in the US Senate to the most senior person. We spend a lot of time talking about his journey
through medicine and ultimately 12 years in the Senate through some of the difficult policy
decisions and the controversial decisions that were made. Since leaving the Senate in 2006,
Bill has done a number of things. He sits on the board of more not-for-profits, for-profit
companies than you can count on, probably spent a decade really focused on private equity before
now shifting his attention to more venture-based funding. He also hosts a podcast called A Second
Opinion. And we get into about two thirds of what I had wanted to get into here. That's how
much I wanted to talk about, but it's really a remarkable discussion. And one of the most
interesting things about Bill that we do touch on here is that in 2005, he effectively called
the pandemic. He really laid it out through his experience in studying HIV and creating policy
around HIV. He was an instrumental part of PEPFAR, which we talk about as well. And also his
experience with the anthrax scare post 9-11. And he basically looked at these examples coupled with
what he saw on a lot of his travel to Africa, which he had done as a physician and basically said,
look, it's not going to be a question of if we have a major pandemic, it's a question of when.
And these were the things that needed to be in place. And these are the likely things that are
going to happen. And unfortunately, a lot of those things came true and we weren't really ready. So
we spend a little bit of time on that. And finally, we talk a little bit about just the current state
of politics. And even though this isn't a podcast about politics, I think most people in the current
environment can't help but acknowledging that we're in a bit of a strange environment. And we talk a
little bit about his optimism as to how things might get better in the future. So without further
delay, please enjoy my conversation with Senator Bill Frist.
Bill, thank you so much for making time to sit down with me. I know today was,
you had a lot of things going on in your personal life. So I appreciate that we didn't
reschedule this, but it would have totally been understood if we needed to.
Great to be with you, Peter.
By the way, it feels weird calling you Bill. I always feel like I need to call you Senator Frist,
but the first time we spoke, you were adamant that I call you Bill. So I'll tell you a funny
story. When I left residency, I had such a hard time not calling people Mr. So-and-so,
just because you talked to your patients that way, right? Like Mr. Jones, Mrs. Smith,
we're here to talk about this. And then when I got out in the real world, people were like,
you can just call people by their first name. Was that a difficult transition for you?
You know, there's two things come to mind. Number one, the most common thing I get,
do you get called Senator or doctor? People who want to be formal. And of course, I say,
Bill, but that is a harder one because in the Senate, especially today, people have kind of
down on the respect world and doctor is still pretty much up there. So I say, well, doctor,
but you're supposed to call a senator, et cetera, et cetera. But then I remember going to Mass
General up in Boston, being from Nashville, Tennessee, and being from Nashville, I called
everybody out of respect, Mr. If they were four years older than me, and it may sound crazy to
a lot of people. Listen, that's just sort of the Southern way of doing it. And I remember going
down and working with a cardiac surgeon and right in the middle of the case, I said, yes, sir.
And you're not supposed to say, sir, either. It's kind of like the Mr. And then he turned around
and he said, don't you ever, ever say, sir, to me again. It just depends on where you are.
You're exactly right. At what point did you realize growing up that you wanted to be a doctor,
let alone a surgeon? You know, I had a real sort of fortunate circumstance. And then I was last to
five children. And my dad was a family practitioner, a doctor. And my older brother, who was 15 years
older than me, went into medicine. So he was a doctor. My middle brother ended up going on the
cardiac surgery. So he was in this track. And so I pretty much assumed I would go into medicine or
nursing or the healing profession from very early on for that reason. I saw the gratification. I saw
the way when dad would come home at night, what he would talk about in terms of healing and giving
people hope. So that was just always stuck in my mind. And I thought about other things. And when
I jumped up to college, I majored in public and international affairs. And so when I tried other
things, I always came right back to the healing profession in some shape or form.
So when you were an undergrad, you were not a pre-med. And Princeton is pretty well known for
international affairs and things. So you were kind of in the epicenter of where one would go to
study such things. But that didn't sway you from medicine. Did it plant a seed that ultimately
there would be more for you to do then medicine? You know, in high school and in the early years
of college, I interned in Washington, DC, for Congressman Joe Evans from Tennessee at the time.
I spent a summer writing for a newspaper, the Nashville banner, no longer a daily newspaper
here in Nashville. So throughout, it was always being interested in the broader aspects of medicine,
of being a doctor. And I had no idea, and I didn't have any master plan with it. But I guess at every
stage, and now that I look back, it gets reflected in my life that I always had other parallel
interests going on. And as you probably know, and recall, I'm a little older than you are,
it wasn't all that popular at the time when you were in medical school to have these other
interests. You know, to basically say, well, I want to go write an op-ed on some technology
when your professor is sitting there of medicine. And basically, the only thing in the world is
medicine. So it was always challenging. And not being in a pre-med track at Princeton,
but still wanting to go to medical school, even the medical schools had a little bit of bias about
coming in at that time, very different today, if you didn't demonstrate working in a lab and
all those other pre-med track things in those college years. And so what was it like for you?
Mass General obviously is one of the pillars of American medicine. If my memory serves me correctly,
isn't Mass General the second oldest hospital in the United States, or is it the third oldest?
Yeah. I don't know, but it's there in the tradition and is all there as well.
And so you've got this Northeast training, and then you go way out West for training in
cardiac surgery. What was that experience like back? This would have been early 80s that you
went out to Stanford?
Early 80s, and it's actually interesting in many ways, mainly in retrospect, of course, but I went
to Harvard Medical School, and then I did the six years at Mass General and did my cardiac
fellowship at Mass General. But when I was just entering that fellowship, it was fascinating
from an ethical standpoint that the community there had decided with the board of trustees of
the hospital that they were not going to do heart transplants. And you know, I'd kind of stayed at
Mass General because they'd done the early kidney transplant work in America there, had great
immunologists, and then I was, you know, 10 years into this, and then all of a sudden the board of
trustees and the broader community said it's too experimental. It hasn't proven itself. We can
vaccinate a million people, I'm exaggerating a little bit, for the cost of one transplant,
and therefore they put a moratorium.
Now, what was the mortality at that time? Because Bernard's first heart transplant was in 67?
66, 67 was when Christian Bernard down in South Africa did the first transplant, and then after
that there were a hundred done in Texas, and then most of those patients died, so it was kind of
shut down. And what was happening with Shumway at the time? What was he doing in the 70s?
Another fascinating story, and Norman Shumway, who was my mentor at Stanford at the time,
was really outside of the mainstream of cardiac surgeons, and you know this, but again bringing
our listeners in a little bit. He had worked diligently for about 10 years in the laboratory,
figuring out this heart transplant world, systematically with discipline, not taking
it to people until they figured out the science. And then Christian Bernard came in, he watched a
little bit of this, he was from South Africa, and more in an opportunist way, he said, well,
it looks like Shumway's figured it out, so I'm going to go back to South Africa and do it. And so
he did it. Shumway, from that mid-60s to when I got involved in the early 80s, systematically had
a program where other programs would do a hundred or fifty or thirty, like out in Texas, and then
they would just leave it totally because the patients died. Well, Shumway would ask the
question, why are they dying? He would figure it out, so he was doing about 10 a year,
or 15 a year, and figured out the science, so with the immunology of it, the cardiac biopsies,
the instruments of it, and in a very deliberate way. And I tell that long story because it really
had a huge impact on me that the science is really fundamental. It's important. Until you
get the science right, you should not be taking this to the clinical world. Know the facts, get
rid of the misinformation, do clinical trials, don't prematurely take things to the field.
And so at Mass General, they saw a 50 percent mortality, very expensive procedure of this
moving hearts around and the immunology and the equipment that was required. And they said the
greatest good for the most people is to not do heart transplants at Mass General, or Peter
Bent Brigham, or Beth Israel, or Boston City. To me, from my perspective, I said,
are you kidding me? You know, we have the opportunity to, in a very ethical way, figure out
heart transplantation in a way that can save hundreds of thousands of lives. If you don't
get a heart transplant, you die within six months. If you get it, you can live 10, 15, 20, 30 years.
People I transplanted, you know, 28 years ago were still alive here in Nashville and around the
country. So I got fed, I didn't get fed up. I did get fed up. But instead of staying at Mass
General, I said, I'm going to California to train with this one person in America who systematically
had spent 20 years developing heart transplantation and continue to do that
because the overall field, the overall heart transplant world continues to evolve.
I mean, to me, it's just such an amazing story within medicine to go back to the first transplants
within kidney and then to look at heart. And in some ways, liver was almost the most ridiculous
of them in terms of the complexity of it. You know, I don't know if you have like a bucket list
of people you wish you could have met or interviewed who are no longer alive. And I'm sure you probably
met Thomas Starzell, but if I think about people I wish I could have met, Thomas Starzell would be
very high on that list. I don't know if you ever read his book Puzzle People, but I can't recommend
it highly enough to people who love stories about the history of medicine. To me, it is,
it sounds so much like what you described Shumway doing, which is systematically in the face of
nonstop failure, watching, you know, bad outcome after bad outcome after bad outcome, but in patients
for whom there is no other choice. I mean, there is no such thing as an extracorporeal liver.
So if a person is in liver failure, they are going to die. There is no temporizing measure.
And I don't remember the numbers because it's been so long since I read it, even for the second time,
it's a book I've read twice. But I, one thing that stuck with me when I read it, which is,
one is the belief that you have to have that this is going to get better.
And two, just the personality trait that says I'm not going to get broken by short term failure
after failure after failure, because I'm seeing some other progress and whether it is,
look, we're making strides in immunology because back in the early eighties, what was your two,
what was your immunosuppressive regimen? I mean, prednisone and, and MMP, I mean,
what you didn't have much. Well, and it comes back and we're seeing it today with today's
technology, which is even moving faster, but these great breakthroughs, which require this
deliberate thinking in the spite of these challenges that seem insurmountable, there were
technological mechanical ones like doing a cardiac biopsy. All these patients were dying
early on because the heart would reject, get inflamed right afterwards. And so then the typical
surgeon would walk away from that and say, I'm not doing this. Some way said, okay,
let's figure out the inflammation. So developed an instrument that you can go through the neck
into the heart. Sounds terrible, but it's real simple. It can do it in three minutes and figured
out how to, to, to address the inflammation, to diagnose it and treat it. And then you,
in the medicines that you mentioned, when I started in the transplant world and success was
not that good early on, it got better, but we were using two drugs. One was called prednisone or
steroids that most people have taken or understand. And the other is Imuran. And we didn't have a new
drug that came along in about 1982, which is cyclosporine. When you added that drug, which was
serendipitously discovered from a fungus over in I think Sweden or Switzerland, when you added
that to the cocktail, all of a sudden the mortality, which may have been at 50% went to 20%. Just that
one addition, because if you can adjust the immunological treatment and make it where it's
not as severe, you don't push down the immune system so much where people would die from infections.
But I think the important point in all of this, which I think you're leading and I'm sort of
feeding into is, is that science is this evolutionary process. And that the greats,
the Starsville, Tom Starsville, University of Pittsburgh did all transplants, but the world
icon leader in liver transplants, which was about two or three years behind our transplants,
and the Norman Shumways of the world had that deliberate, that disciplined, that focused process
in taking these insurmountable challenges that were impossible to do. And systematically over
a period of time, capturing the best of the best, even when there are lots of losses along the way,
ultimately be successful. This is just kind of a broader historical question of surgery. When you
think back of the last 150 years of surgery, the modern era, right? And you think about the giant
the Blalox, the Halsteads, the Shumways, Linnehan, Starsville. I mean, these people,
they had step function changes in the field, their existence and the teams around them,
right? When you talk about a surgeon, you have to talk about the critical care staff,
the anesthesiology staff. I mean, no surgeon can do what they do alone, but they fundamentally
changed surgery. Do you believe that there are any more step functions ahead in surgery?
Are there sort of from a technical standpoint or combination of technology, medicine, instrumentation,
like, is there something that you think is still an untapped opportunity in the way that, you know,
we're talking about what Shumway or Starsville did, for example? Yeah, you know, it's good. The
transplant world is a dramatic world that we've talked about where I would go take a heart out of
one person who is brain dead and then replace a diseased heart and a living person totally. And
even me describing it is pretty gross. I mean, it's brutal. I mean, you're talking about lifting
a heart out of somebody and putting it in there. And I say, yes, I've done hundreds and hundreds
of times. And then people say, it doesn't sound right. It is amazing, though. I mean, it's worth
pausing on that for a moment. It is, it's hard to believe. And I haven't participated in nearly as
many as you. So maybe it gets old after a while, but it wouldn't surprise me if every time you did
it, it still felt magical. Yeah. It probably never wore off in terms of what you just explained. It's
profound. Never. I think you don't have to have faith, really. People will jump to that immediately.
But the idea of me getting a call, and not me, this is done by everybody now at that time,
not that many, but now it's done in every major hospital around. But getting a call flying off
in the middle of the night, taking a heart out of somebody, putting it in a bucket with ice around
it, and then putting it on an airplane, traveling for three hours, coming back, opening up a patient,
and spending 45 minutes, putting the heart in. It's just like a piece of meat you're setting in
the chest. And then you just step back. And as you warm the patient up, the body up, all of a
sudden, that inner piece of meat that you've been carrying, and it's terribly been described it that
way, all of a sudden, slowly, that sort of magical moment, it would begin like a bag of worms just
kind of moving around. And then, bang, all of a sudden, it would start beating rhythmically,
you know, 70 beats a minute and pumping blood throughout the body. And then that patient goes
home a week later. And then, you know, it's miraculous. So I agree with it. And you can't
fully explain it, but it is. But it took the shumways and the storzels and people like that
to do that. And then my generation, which came right beyond that. And then beyond the transplant
world, there are other great innovations. You remember, and I don't know exactly when you were
doing your surgery, but taking out gallbladders, we used to do these big incisions and these bloody
pills and hip replacements. I mean, how that's been revolutionized through scopes and minimally
invasive surgery. So that will probably continue with more robotic surgery. But I think the really
exciting things will be at the cellular level of regenerative medicine, instead of replacing that
heart, keeping that old heart in the person, injecting some of the cells in there, understanding
what the Human Genome Project delivered to us back in the early 2000s, with some manipulation,
having those cells that you put in there, liven up and energize the dead cells that are there.
That kind of breakthrough is going to really be exciting coming forward. So is that surgery or
I'm not sure it's it takes things down to almost a synthetic biology world, which to me is where
things are really exciting in terms of at the level of the cellular interaction and and surgically
putting in it, whether it's mitochondria, a lot of things we're talking about with
COVID and vaccines and all today, that's sort of where so much of the future is, I think.
So when you got to Stanford, was Bruce Wrights there or had he already left for Hopkins?
He was leaving at exactly that time. At that time at Stanford, as you know, there were four cardiac
surgeons and some way the cardiac surgeon who was father to them all. Most of the people had
gravitated there because of his approach, bangs out of outside of the norm. Not a lot of respect
for tradition, for tradition's sake. Big believer in team approach. In Boston, you have to work 10
years to get to put in a stitch. You had to wait your time on the East Coast. If you were good at
it and you were a first year intern, if you were a fourth year medical student and some way saw you
operate, he would let you do what he wouldn't let a resident with 10 years of training do
if you could do it. So it was more kind of merit based there. All of that approach. And so that
was the culture that he built. Huge respect for nurses, huge respect. It wasn't about him. It was
about the people around him. He said he was the world's greatest first assistant. And for those
who don't follow surgery, the first assistant is the person who's across from the main surgeon
who kind of helps the main surgeon do the work. And what he was saying basically, it's not about me.
It's about us as a team. And Bruce Wright came out of that tradition and he had just led and of
course, didn't know him well because he went to Hopkins after that. So you finish getting your,
basically your transplant training at Stanford and then you head back to, is it Vanderbilt? You go
straight to, yeah. And you serve there on the faculty for quite some time and you're building
a program obviously, right? There was no transplant program. Yeah. You're building.
No. Yeah. At that time we had the Stanford program and there were few other programs around the East
of Mississippi. There were no established real programs. In Tennessee, there was no heart
transplant program. So built a program on the model of Stanford in heart transplants. And,
and I want to come back to where you're going. But once we mastered heart transplants, this whole
field of lung transplants three years later had never been done, never been successful, but because
of that drug cyclist form, we were able to do that. That's what Bruce and Norm did together,
right? They did the first heart lung transplant. They did heart lung lung. Ironically, you have
the heart lung. Lung is heart lung. Yeah. So you have the heart. It seemed like taking a lung would
be easier, but it's not. So the combined heart lung where you take them both. And that's what
Bruce Rides and Shumway did. And that's what I brought back to Vanderbilt. Was there any
resistance to this given what you just described on the East coast being kind of a bias towards,
hey, this is still very costly on a cost per life basis. There's probably more efficient things
that we can do with resources. Nowhere in this have we talked about where insurance companies are,
how are insurance companies thinking about this type of a procedure at that time?
It was interesting. So insurance and the payers, you have Medicare, government, Medicaid, and then
you have the commercial payers. At that time, it was still investigational. So Medicare,
our government did not reimburse for transplants. It was regarded as experimental for about eight
years. And they did a very smart thing. They designated certain centers to figure it out.
And then once the survival was sufficient and you were you were qualified as a center of excellence,
then they would start reimbursing you. The payer system was a little bit the same thing. And I was
again, lucky and I wouldn't have come to Vanderbilt if it hadn't been that far sort of thinking ahead.
They basically said, Bill, to get the program up, you've done, you know, scores and scores of heart
transplants you were trained by the best for your first 10 transplants, because we know this is
just the opposite of Mass General. We know this is lifesaving to thousands and thousands of people
dying across America. We also know that it's not 99% successful. But what we'll do for your first
10 transplants to get your program up and running, we will cover you if the insurance does not. And
so that gave me enough to and we did maybe six and then it started being reimbursed. And then
over a period of about eight years, every commercial payer, Medicare and Medicaid began to reimburse
because they had the outcomes 100% mortality, everybody would die who needed to transplant,
everybody would die within six months without it. And if you got it, you on average, 80% of the time
would live at least five years. And if you got beyond that would live 10, 15, 20 or 30 years.
What was the pressure like on you during those first transplants? I mean, here you are. It's one
thing when you're at Stanford and you're under the umbrella of Shumway and this incredible
environment he's built, which as you said, you've got the best anesthesiologists, you've got the
best nurses, you've got the best perfusionists, like everything that is needed to support that
program, you have the best of and the culture is already there. And you're a fellow within that
system. And now you have to go out and hang your own shingle and you have to now train everybody
to do what you took for, I'm not saying you took it for granted, right? But what one could have
easily taken for granted at Stanford. And all of a sudden now you're the operating surgeon. You don't
have Shumway first assisting you and you don't have a lot of time to figure this out. You can't take 50
transplants to get it worked out. Do you remember what those first few days were like? I mean,
that must have been unbelievable stress because it's two stresses. It's the obvious stress of,
I got to save this person's life, but there's even, there's a bigger thing at stake, which is
enough bad outcomes and this program gets shut down and we don't know what that means for the
future transplantation. Yeah. And there was an additional burden that at that time Shumway was
training the great cardiac surgeons. They weren't great. They were young people like me at the time,
but just like Bruce Wright, who we talked about, he didn't send them to Hopkins, but Bruce came
out of this very interesting culture where team was very important, where humility was very
important. That's juxtaposed the way most people think about cardiac surgeons who are in there,
you know, high pressure type A throwing instruments. You never saw that. And so when I came to Vanderbilt
east of Mississippi, Bruce was up in the Hopkins. All of a sudden all over the country, people said,
why don't we go to these guys instead of going out to California? So all of a sudden within a year of
me being at Vanderbilt, starting a program from scratch, I was getting referrals, you know,
hundreds of people coming in saying, I want the Shumway approach. Shumway says, you know,
you're as good as he is, you know, that's the way he would talk could coming in. But to answer your
question, it comes back to what I threw in about Shumway saying he was the best first assistant.
I came here, there was a guy by the name of Walter Merrill. Walter Merrill was Hopkins trained,
excellent surgeon, pediatric surgeon, adult surgeon, and he could do it all. He was gifted,
the most humble person in the world. And Walter had come out to Stanford to watch me operate,
to kind of learn about the program for Vanderbilt. And so we had this dialogue. And from day one for
the next 10 years, there wouldn't be a transplant that we did. And we did hearts and heart lungs,
and we did lungs, we did infant transplant, we were transplanting kids or babies at two days of
age and three days of age. There was never a transplant that I was involved with that Walter
Merrill wasn't there. Linked side by side, sort of this alter ego. And with that, and building the
team with nurses and perfusionists to sort of share this same Shumway mentality of team first,
keep it simple, stupid, don't be afraid to double dribble. If you don't get it perfect the first time,
go back and do it again. And it's worth saying all that a little bit because I want to jump ahead
a little bit because that program after I left has continued to grow 10 years, 15, 20 years later
to where that program today is the largest heart transplant program in America. It does more heart
transplants than in any center that people are listening to us in their cities today. And it
has nothing to do with me really, but it's taking that experience, which again, you understand that
what the residence experience is and the young faculty is, if you're lucky enough to have a
mentor and you can capture that culture and you go out and apply it. So I replicated exactly what
I saw at Stanford to get it up and running those first two years, worked with a great team. And
then with that, we were on the cutting edge of the early lung transplants, early heart lung transplants.
And then ultimately, obviously we added liver to it and we had bone marrow already. We had a pancreas
and became a large multi-organ transplant center. Now, where was DeBakey and Cooley in the midst of
this? When did the big Texas centers participate? They were early and it fits with Texas and they
were great surgeons and they are up there and they would say they're above Starsil and in some way
just because their egos were big and they were excellent surgeons and they did these incremental
leaps in surgery and vascular surgery. Both of them, they're in the same town in Houston, Texas,
and they, which fits with the ego, the confidence and ability, jumped on transplants as soon as
Shumway did the first one in America. Christian Bernard did one a few months later, Shumway did one
and then Shumway was going to continue along 15 a year, the way he was doing it. Deliberate, let's
learn, iterative process. But DeBakey and Cooley said, well, listen, this thing looks pretty good,
seems to work pretty well and so they did in Texas, this is all in the late 60s. So remember,
this was all 67, 68 and between 68 and about 69, they did I think 110 heart transplants in
competition with each other. Do it big, do it Texas style and then all those patients died
and they died, which comes back to the story. Shumway was out there figuring out how to treat
the heart rejection, this inflammation using that little, that little cannula he puts through the
neck and they didn't have the patients for that. And so they shut their programs down and went on
to other things. And then in the late 70s started doing a few and then the 80s kind of picked up
where everybody else did. I mean, the whole story of DeBakey and Cooley, I don't know if there's a
book about it, but if there is, I'd love to read it. The rivalry between them is unbelievable,
right? I mean, it's two legends in cardiac surgery, both of whom will tell you that they're the
greatest of all time. Did they ever reconcile before DeBakey, I think DeBakey died first, right?
Yeah, they did. And the hospitals were right across the street and never did really. I think
when DeBakey or Cooley got a medal of honor that there was some kind of congratulations that went
on, but in essence never, never did. Yeah, it's interesting. I never met DeBakey, but I met Cooley
because he trained at Hopkins. And so every night when you're on call, when you'd be walking through
the Blalock hallway, Hopkins is such a storied place. There's never a piece of tradition that's
not enough, right? And you'd see these pictures of the young Denton Cooley and he was just
upsettingly handsome, right? So sure enough, we're at the American College of Surgeons one year
and each, as you know, every university or every medical school has their own thing. So you'd go
to the Vanderbilt one and you'd probably go stop at the Stanford one and you'd go stop at the MGH
one. And so at the Hopkins one Cooley shows up and I'm there with my closest friend from residency
who happens to be a cardiac surgery fellow about to go and embark on his pediatric cardiac fellowship.
And Cooley was talking with both of us and he says, Oh, what year are you in? And I think I was in my
third year or something. And he says to my friend, Jorge Salazar, what year are you in? And Jorge
says, well, I'm in my ninth year. Cause that's, you know, at the time by that point it's nine years
just to do adult cardiac surgery. And then he said, and then you're going to go off and do
pediatric cardiac, I think is another two years at UCSF. And he's like, gosh, that's just unbelievable.
I mean, back in my day, it only took six years to become a cardiac surgeon. Now, admittedly,
I was better than everybody else. And he just went on, but he said it completely seriously. Like
there was no irony in that statement. And we got such a kick out of that, but I guess there's
some truth to it. I mean, he was a gifted surgeon. Yeah. And he did really, there are icons and
contributed so much and there are hundreds of thousands of people alive today because of people
they've trained and procedures they've done and really amazing icons in that field of cardiac
surgery. They probably won't ever be anybody like them again. And cardiac surgery has changed so much.
It's one of the reasons, but they were just two talented prodigy type surgeons.
Do you think that medicine can no longer attract that caliber of individual? Like has the
profession changed such that the best and the brightest would never consider medicine today?
I'm not close enough to what the hot shot college kid is doing today, but given, for example,
the incredible changes we've seen in technology, is it really the case that the coolies and the
debakes and the some ways of the world, if they were 20 years old today, would be going to Silicon
Valley or would be going to Boston and going into biotech startups. Like, there are other ways to
serve people that don't involve literally going into medicine. And I, do you ever think about that?
Like, is there, has there been some sort of passing of the torch in terms of the war for talent?
You know, when you think of the Starzels, the DeBakeys and Shumway and the great surgeons,
you think of great athletes. You think of the athletic part of it. In part, they're using their
hands. They want you, you got to be fast, deliberate, you got to keep it simple. You got to be right.
And I think because of technology, that's less important. I think the fact that we're operating
through telescopes and soon microscopes, when you asked your earlier question, that the sort of
athletic, competitive hero on the field, cowboyish sort of approach, I think we're beyond that.
Just the most of the big sort of blood and guts, that kind of imagery is passed by. But to go back
to your question, no, I think medicine still, it may be in some ways even more so because
we've opened up this whole world of biology, synthetic biology, and at the cellular level,
the regenerative medicine and the use of stem cells, all of these things are going to attract,
and they're going to be, they're going to go in as medicine because they want to heal.
They want to be a part of something bigger than themselves and not just behind a microscope,
that I think it's going to continue to attract great, great people. And if you look at,
at least here in Vanderbilt, where I'm familiar with medical school applications,
they're all time high right now. And people say yes, but the quality is not there. And
the attraction of making a lot of money or doing the next Uber or Airbnb is out there.
I think all of that's right. But I think we're going to continue to see,
and maybe even see an increase in the overall quality of people applying to medical school
and then going to medical school and then entering these fields.
I'll ask you the question I get asked all the time, and I think you can answer it with
frankly, a far better lens, which is, what advice do you have for somebody today who wants to go
into medicine, doesn't quite know how they want to do it based on all you've seen and what you see
in the future, in the landscape. And now we're getting ahead of ourselves because we haven't
got to this part of the discussion where we're going to talk about policy and things like that.
But given what you know about the profession of medicine and also the landscape of payers,
hospital systems, consolidation of these things, at risk versus not at risk reimbursement,
all these things, what do you say to somebody? Do you say go forth and conquer? Do you say,
here's a hedge that you want to have in place? I mean, what advice do you have for somebody to
be successful? You know where you started is probably still my philosophy and I'm still
active in teaching here and mentoring a lot of people in medicine and in health. And I think
staying broad, I kind of fell into that because I knew what my track was going to be in medicine.
And therefore I wanted to do journalism and I wanted to try the policy world and wanted to go
to Washington and wanted to write about technology all at the time I was going to medical school.
Then it was harder, as we said, because there was a stigma almost against it. And today I think
the professors in medical school understand that the best, whether it's on the social side or even
on the technical side, the best are people who bring broad experiences, have the curious mind
that isn't narrowed down to just one area, to you know, just cardiac surgery or just
bypass surgery or valves, but has that curiosity throughout life. So I'd still continue to
encourage people to live as broadly as possible, to develop those interests, to look for your
talents. And if they're outside of medicine, figure out some way either as a hobby or something on
the side or write an article every week about it to keep that going. And I guess because I have
jumped around so much and kind of changed career every 10 to 12 years, that I see how in truth
it's all the same thing. It's all health and it's all healing and it's all giving hope. There's lots
of different ways to do it. Let's fast forward a little bit to call it the early 90s. Do you have
a sense at this point that you want to make a run for Senate or how were you starting to think about
a transition into elected office? It's interesting. My goal was never to be in the United States Senate
ever, ever, ever. And I'd spent right at 10 years learning all the surgery in medical school and
how to do transplants and how to do surgery and then about 10 years here at Vanderbilt.
And we built a transplant center, a multi-organ transplant center that was a great foundation for
the future. And then I just began to ask myself, I did not serve in Vietnam, which a lot of people
just right above me had done. I've not been in the service. I've not done anything actively other
than learn to be a doctor and spend 18 hours a day doing it for those years. And I said given
that I was running a large transplant center and doing a lot of good, I felt what would be the one
other thing that one might do to affect health, maybe not of an individual, but health of a
community or health of a population. And I said, well, do you go run a university? I'd been on the
board of Princeton University as a young alumnus and sort of solved the power there and thought
about that. No, because that's don't think I could reach quite enough people. And so I systematically
eliminated doing anything. A new policy could do it because policy could affect the world.
And I'd seen that back 20 years before when I'd been an intern during the college years. And so
I said the only place is really the United States Senate. I have a job. I know what I can do. But if
you could get to that position, not to change health care necessarily, not to at the time it
was Clinton care and all sorts of political issues. And it really wasn't for that reason.
It really was an extension of what I saw as a little boy when my dad would come home. And that
was in the days they had doctor's bags and he would sit down exhausted and say, you know,
the greatest gratification has been able to give somebody hope. And all of a sudden I said,
policy can do that. And so I jumped in. Nobody in my family had ever served in public office.
Nobody had run for public office. They were not overly partisan. My mom was probably more
of a Democrat. My dad was probably more Republican. And I was probably neither. You know, I was
just out there doing heart surgery every day. So it really was an extension of that earlier
poll, probably genetic in some way of wanting to serve and that being a way to serve a population.
And, you know, it sounds kind of patting yourself on the shoulder now in retrospect, but
that was what was going through my mind. And I didn't have anybody look to my dad said,
are you crazy? And he's no longer alive. He died 20 years ago. But he said, you know,
you're at the top of the world in surgery and innovation and running a large laboratory and
writing papers. And, you know, why would you leave that to go into this world of policy? And
the answer then was what it is now. Also said, I wasn't going to stay forever. I said, you know,
I'm not a politician. I love policy and I want to affect change and I want to innovate, but I
only I only want to go do it for 10 years. And that's how I took the leap.
The Senate is the highest piece of Congress. So to, you know, I could, it's almost easier to
understand if you said, look, I'm going to go run for the House of Representatives. I don't know how
many seats are there in the House of Representatives in Tennessee?
Nine. Okay. But to say to say I'm going to be one of the two people running for Senate is kind of
remarkable. How long of a process was that? So the election was 96. When did you have to get
serious about this? Is this like a two year process, a one year process?
I spent a year and a half. I had to leave. I didn't have to leave, but you either do it or you
don't. And this is the advice I give people. If you're going to get go all in. So probably about
two and a half years before I started talking, the problem I had is my parents didn't really buy into
it. My family really didn't because kind of hard to understand. So who do you talk to? And there
hadn't been a physician elected to the United States Senate. One hundred people, two from every
state. There hadn't been a physician elected to the Senate since 1928. So I didn't have anybody
to call or go see who'd gone through this eye of the needle medical school and internship and
residency and fellowship and practice. And that made it hard. And maybe that was a good thing.
They may have said, get out of here. Don't do it. But that was hard. And so I systematically took
about a year. This one I'm still practicing. And I went to see Howard Baker. He'd been majority
leader of the United States Senate before a centrist. I went and talked to Lamar Alexander
at the time who had been governor, but he hadn't been in the Senate. I ultimately recruited him
run for the Senate and went and talked to Al Gore at the time, who was a senator and had great
conversations. And my fundamental question was, am I right or is this just like, you know, dreams?
And to the one they said to tough business, half the people are going to hate you all the time,
and half are going to like you. And to me, very different than medicine. But if you're really
serious about it, you ought to do it. Howard Baker, who was just an amazing guy. And again,
he was also from Tennessee. He the first time he didn't listen to me very much. And or he
politely did the second time politely. And then about the third or fourth time I went to say,
he finally said, okay, you must be interested in go ahead and make the jump.
I mean, you're having a chance to speak with Al Gore when he's the vice president at this point.
No, he was still it was right during that period of time. And that was going to open up a seat,
actually in Tennessee at the time he was still in the Senate, because this was in the early 90s.
Oh, this is before 92 then even. Wow. Exactly. And this all 91. And then ultimately, that seat
opened up and then I had an option of running for that seat, which is an open seats easier to win
because you got two people in there that nobody knows. And it's sort of a flip of the coin or the
other seat. And I don't know exactly why, but I went the less traditional route and challenged and
incumbent. And I know why because I was the fresh face and he was the person who'd been around for
18 years. But it was unconventional to go that route at the time. So you ran in 94 against the
incumbent. Is that correct? Yeah. And you won by a pretty hefty margin, correct? Yeah, that was,
I had a primary with six others. Yeah, I was going to ask you about the primary. What was the primary
like back then compared to, for example, what primaries are like today, which is a fight to
the extreme. Thank goodness. It's not today where people are get pushed out Tennessee until recently
and it's changed in the last four years, but until recently, Tennessee had produced senators that were
in the center. The eastern part of the state was more Republican. The Western was more Democratic.
The middle where I live was sort of in the middle. So if you were versatile enough to move through
that state, your politics tended to be very principle and it might be principle Democrat
or Republican, but you're pretty much going to be appealing to a broad range of people. So in our
primary, there were six people all out of that same ilk. My disadvantage was that I was an outsider.
I hadn't played my political dues with the Republican Party. Number one, I was from middle
Tennessee and not east Tennessee. And then that was it. So, but the race was very different. And in
that primary, just interestingly enough, was the person who I ultimately recruited to the United
States Senate, Bob Corker. And Bob Corker and I, he was an outsider and I was an outsider. He and I
were in the primary. So it started at six, came down to two. All races are tough races. He always
say that ours was a clean race and ours was a hundred percent cleaner than these races today.
But it's all just hand-to-hand combat, this politics stuff. And so I don't want to over idealize
the way it was, but we were out of this extreme sort of polar opposites where in a primary,
somebody's driven to the either extreme right or extreme left. Do you remember what the main
policy issues that you were running on in the primary and then ultimately in the general that
year in 94? And that comes to the other thing. So, and because ultimately one, which nobody had
expected, nobody, chances were probably one in a hundred. And the other thing that did happen,
that it didn't start that way when I jumped in, but at the end in 1994 ended up being a lot of
Republicans coming in. So I was part of that wave. I was still the least expected. I was the only
person to be an incumbent United States Senator who came in and so ultimately won, but there was
the luck end of it being at the right place at the right time as well. And so the policy issues,
ironically, when you look at today, were balance the budget. Over time, eliminate the debt,
keep taxes small. So those were sort of the big issues. They were these big physical issues that
were out there. Welfare reform, which just talked about in that period of time, ultimately the bill
passed about three or four years later, but those are the sort of the three big issues.
And just to go back to the first point you made, what you're really saying is, look,
in 94, two years into a president's term, the opposite party generally has a tailwind at that
first midterm election, correct? That's correct. For example, I remember in 2010, two years into
Obama's term, you get a little bit of that tailwind for Republicans and vice versa. So this in 94 was
the same thing. Now, how did you learn the mechanics of the US Senate? I mean, I got to tell
you, I find this stuff really interesting, Bill, just in part because I grew up in another country
and I have an inferiority complex. I didn't learn US history growing up. So you asked my daughter,
she's like, dad, why are you always grilling me on US history? And it's like, hey, I'm trying to
learn this stuff with you. But oh my God, trying to figure out what the whip does versus the minority
leader versus this and what this means in this bill versus that. I mean, it just strikes me as
when you go straight into the US Senate, that's like going straight into the major leagues,
never playing AAA, AA, and little league baseball. Like how do you learn all of that stuff? I mean,
was that the scare? I mean, if the first time you're doing a transplant by yourself is scary,
I would think the first day you're sitting on the floor of the US Senate is 10 times more scary.
Yeah, it was, I guess when I was first running, I didn't know if I'd win or not. And then about a
week out, I felt it that I knew I would win. So that the worst part was the first, the November to
January equivalent 22nd or January 4th, not knowing what all this is about. The Senate doesn't have a
Robert Rules of Orders. There's not a book you read. There's a little book of rules and you'll
hear, you know, you hear about it every two years after pass the rules. But it's like a 30-page book.
The real book is precedent that's set. And precedent is experience. It's being around its
age, its knowledge, it is, you know, all the other stuff that I had zero. You gave me a 30-page book,
you know, it's like it like in medicine or going to a new rotation in your residency, you know,
you just hop in and do it and you do it fast and you do it hard and you may do it for a month,
you'll have to switch the next month. So that would have been easy. The challenge of the Senate
is that it's not a book that you can read. And I had the disadvantage of not having anybody I knew
in the Senate either, no friends, no, no sort of colleagues. In retrospect, that's all a real
advantage. I was able to come in as an outsider, as a physician, somebody who has looked at to be
trusted, somebody that has looked at to be fair, somebody who learns predominantly, not the way a
typical politician does it, that I know better than you. It's I got to listen. If the patient
comes in the door, which I had done for the previous 20 years, I want to size them up. I want
to listen. I want to look at the body language. I don't want to say anything until they give me
that chief complaint or that last, you know, look or question as they go out the door. And all of
that, which is second nature, it's part of being a physician or being a healer or a nurse, is that
listing that empathy component is part of the culture, but really the being it is in the DNA
of physicians and nurses and counselors and healers. The room I walked into had 63 lawyers,
63 lawyers. I walked into that chamber and and that chamber, every chair was full with somebody
who for 10 years had been arguing legal cases and all. And so you'd say that's a disadvantage.
Again, it ended up being a pretty big advantage. And I didn't realize it at the time, but by
listening very carefully, by working with trust and upholding that trust, because I came in with this
image and the reality of being a physician, people would come to me and they'd say, what do you think?
And you know, how, what is your look on this from the outside? You've been around patients every day,
20 different patients every day for the last 20 years of your life and you've listened to them.
You know, I've been in the United States Senate about as far from real people as you can get.
And so all of that came as real advantages. And again, I didn't know it. There hadn't been a doctor
there. I told you since, you know, 1928 or elected since 1928. So that was it. And kind of stuck with
that throughout. But it wasn't the health care issues. When there was a health care issue,
it would all come to me immediately because the time health care was probably, I don't know, 16%
of our economy. And yet there was nobody in the chamber who'd ever taken care of a patient or
written a prescription or been involved at all. And so that kind of information gravitated
for me as well. You know, you mentioned that 63% of the Senate were lawyers, 1% physicians.
It's probably a dated statistic, so I don't know what it is today, but I can't imagine
it's far from this. But the last time I looked at the stats, when you looked at the entire Congress,
both the House and the Senate combined, slightly less than 1% had any training in secondary
education. So whether it be an undergraduate degree in science or an advanced degree like yours,
why do you think that is? Well, you know, it's interesting. And then right now there are three
physicians in the Senate. And so I kind of broke the glass ceiling and that's been three or four.
And in the House are 14. So it's clearly more than what it was when I... So it's more. But if
you look at historically, and you sort of start now and go backwards in 50-year increments,
I won't exaggerate, but I'll give you just the image. In the first 50 years of our country,
the sort of 17, sort of 50 to 18 or 1810, there were, I think like 25 or 24 physicians in the
Senate over a six-year period in and out. If you look at the next 50 years, 1800 to 1850,
it was 12, about half of that. And if you look at 1850 to 1900, it's about half of that. And then
1900 to 1950, it was about half of that, so it got down to one. So it hadn't always been that way.
But over time, as medicine got more specialized, as some of the stigma that we talked about earlier,
that if you're in medicine, even if you could look at policy with the AMA, the American Medical
Association, you're not a serious doctor. That was kind of the stigma. So people were discouraged,
and then doctors wanted to focus on their work, and therefore they didn't put themselves out there.
And then even after I got there, you know, physicians don't support the political system
that much. They don't get involved in the policy or politics, and I think it's been to the detriment
of patients in America, because physicians are the best voice for 300 million people,
because they're listening to their problems and their challenges and the socioeconomic and the
diversity issues. And so they should be more interested. And so I don't think it's really
that the body itself had a version to them. It's really that people from the science world didn't
move in that direction. And there are good reasons not to. I mean, it tears your life apart.
I mean, you give up all your privacy, families are destroyed. Yeah, 50% of the country hating you,
not hating you, exaggerating. But well, certainly today. Today, you really do. So I can't fully
explain it. But I can tell you what the sort of issues that that we are confronted with today,
and the issues that I ultimately, you know, even my 12 year period we addressed,
I was not the lone voice. But I spent a lot of time explaining what science is. And as science
was progressing, and technology was progressing, ethical issues were involved, they would gravitate
naturally to the person sitting next to you if they happen to be a doctor on the on the chamber
floor. There's just been too few of them, I would say over time. When you think about that first term
in the Senate from 94 to 2000, you alluded to it earlier, you came into this saying, without any
ambiguity, you were hoping to serve two terms in the Senate, not a day longer, and you were never
going to seek higher office thereafter. Why were you so confident to make that assertion? I mean,
most people who would serve in the Senate would want to maybe keep their options open and say,
you know, look, maybe if things go well, there's I'd stay for a third term or I'd seek higher office.
Why were you so adamant about this 12 year limit? Yeah, I actually told the people of Tennessee,
7 million people, I'll serve for 12 years. I've got a job, I believed very much in a concept called
the citizen legislator. The concept that somebody goes, it's at the federal level, that goes, they
leave their home, they leave the people, they stay in touch with them, but they go to Washington, D.C.
to serve as a citizen legislator, the citizen, the broad experiences, the trials, the tribulations,
the challenges, the understanding, the empathy, and applying all that to help shape the laws of
the land. And then after I've done that, go back and live under the laws that I've passed or we've
passed. And that's just a philosophy. And I believe that today, not for everybody, but I think the
majority of people in the Senate benefits from it. And I think people benefit from it, not to get
locked up in this very almost encapsulated environment of the Senate or the House of
Representatives itself. It was just clear to me. And that perspective came from medicine, the breath
that a clinical person has in taking care of acute medicine and chronic medicine and mental
and issues in the transplant world, you're taking care of all of that, that the world is much broader
and that you've got a job to do. And after it's done, leave, let somebody else who may be brighter
or smarter or bring their citizen legislature experiences there. Social media was a philosophy
for me and the right one to do. It did allow me in my last term to focus on, instead of
fundraising and having to cast votes in a certain way that looked politically good and that sort of
thing, which is just part of the business. It allowed me to just have a clean slate, do what I
thought was right and move ahead. So would you endorse the idea of term limits? I mean, this
idea, if we just said, look, no Senator can ever serve more than two terms, no member of Congress
can ever serve more than six terms if you wanted to keep it equal at 12 years. I mean, I've heard
many people suggest that that could be one piece of the remedy to some of the situations we find
ourselves in. I mean, I personally, I find that to be a very appealing idea. And initially I did too.
And you asked about those first days going in. And I think of those first days, just as an aside,
my dad, who was a doctor came up to visit me and he said on my door, it said, Mr. Bill Frist,
another one said the honorable Bill Frist. And there's been these gold plates on the door and
on your chair on the Senate floor. And he walked around and he grabbed me by the arm. He walked me
back down the hall and said, son, you know, Bill, I love the fact that you're in the United States
Senate. I may not have wanted you to be here, but you need to change that. Take that back off and
put Dr. Bill Frist there. And so that whole whole world of being a senator for a period of time,
sort of running the occupying the office, but not owning the office was was one to answer your
question. No, I think term limits would be a huge mistake of the United States Senate.
This job is, is, is complicated and it's equally complicated to heart surgery and, and, and other
things that I've done. The breadth of knowledge to be really good at it. And you can't know everything,
but ultimately every law of the land, every federal law of the land is going to come through
you, everyone. And that is really tough. The procedures we talked about the rule book and the
books of precedence and the things that aren't written down. When I came in and then jumping
ahead, when I got into leadership, all of a sudden, who did I turn to? I'm not smart enough. I'm sort
of, you know, average sort of intelligence overall. And I work really hard. And so I would turn to
the person who had been there for 18 years or 24 years. And I would ask what it was like 20 years
ago or 25 years ago, what is the precedent itself and not go to some staff member who's
25 years old, who's very good, but hadn't been around. And that would not have been possible.
That would not have been possible if there weren't a handful or 20 or 30. I don't know what the number
is of people that are there. And so the system works pretty good. When you have this, this, this,
this crucible, this, this mixture of people like me who say, I'm not staying any longer. Or Bob
Corker, who I helped recruit to the Senate who said, you know, I'm just going to stay for, for 12
years. And then go back and do other things. But I do think this add mixture is important because
of the complexity of the job. In that first term, what was the camaraderie like between parties? You
hear stories of, I'm in the middle of reading a book about Abraham Lincoln right now. And
maybe these books somewhat romanticize it, but obviously there have been huge swings in sort of
how partisan the country has been. But there are these periods of time in which politicians of
opposite parties still socialize together. There was still a degree of respect that existed, even
if you disagreed on policy. As you kind of alluded to it earlier, you might spend the week in DC
without your family. And that would be a time when these would be your colleagues and you'd go home
on the weekend sort of thing. I mean, what was that environment like? And how much time did you
spend with members of the opposite party, your own party, and what were those relationships
like? And above all else, how did that influence your ability to bring your empathy to the side of,
Hey, I understand another person's point of view, even if I don't agree with it.
Yeah, it's really important. And like you, you don't want to over romanticize the past and
recent events, you're asking the same question. Is that the way it's always been? Or is this brand new?
And the first six years in the last six years were different for me. I served under two presidents,
one a Democrat, President Clinton, and the other President Bush are with them. And it wasn't because
of them, but it was because of impart media, and because of the impart the internet impart.
Initially, it was cable TV. As we had more of this sort of real time, nothing could be done behind
closed doors. If I wanted to take a trip called a code out a fact finding trip to Africa, and I've
spent a lot of time in Africa, I would take and go on a trip with four Democrats, senators, and four
Republicans. And we would go to four countries in Africa. And we'd be together, we travel together,
we would share meals together, we would have discussions together. And over the period of
sort of that 12 years, but over a period of about four or five years, that became the junket. And so
every New York Times, Wall Street or anybody would come and say you're spending taxpayer dollars
by having a vacation over in Southern Sudan. Anybody who's been to Southern Sudan knows
that ain't a vacation. Yeah, no, exactly. But you know, it's easy when you're in this sort of fully
exposed media world in real time, where it's hard to counter everything. And so that really
contributed a lot. So early on, probably the first four years, a lot more of that having dinners. And
these aren't like Georgetown parties. And I were talking about in the Senate dining room, sitting
together. And then over that 12 year period, much, much less of that. And it's gotten much, much worse
since then. I'm still very close to a number of senators. And it's gotten much, much worse since
then. But the trend began to change right through that period of time. And really the scrutiny of
the media played a role in that. Of course, the critic will argue, well, isn't that the job of the
media to bring the critical eye to it? I mean, what is that balance between the media holding
politicians accountable versus actually creating a counterproductive environment where it
polarizes everybody more and creates distance between them? How do we think about this?
Well, we're seeing it play out. And I think you're exactly right. The transparency is critically
important. And past politics is playing that out in our history. That, you know, hiding things
in the long run is unhealthy and destructive to our government, to the fundamentals of our
democracy. I think what changed it all is that what we're seeing today more than even when I was there,
but is the misinformation that campaigns if the media like on this whole thing of
codels being junkets make the accusation. There's no way really to counter it. And if misinformation
is put out there and it's in real time. And again, this is the period of time before Twitter and
before Facebook and all. But if you put the information out, it was much harder to counter,
but it was same sort of stuff. It was misinformation that was there. Therefore,
the institutional structure, the corporate structure of having one lunch together,
which we used to do Democrat and Republican ultimately evolved into the Republicans going
to one room and Democrats going to another room, something they already did for business,
but that joint room of getting together disappeared. And that's unhealthy. And
there are ways that you can fix that. I won't jump ahead with that, but there are ways that
you can fix that. And it does have to be fixed. And it comes back to this being a doctor, I think
the empathy word really does come back to this connectedness. Doesn't mean you have to agree,
but this connected of saying two sides of things and you just less empathy in the corporate
structure of the United States Senate today. What committees did you sit on in your first term in
the Senate? Yeah, it's interesting. I sat on the banking committee. Actually, I had been on the
board of a bank ironically before, but it's not the reason I went on it. But Pete Domenic, he was on
it. And when I was choosing my committees, the way committees are chosen, I was 100th in seniority.
So I had 99 people about me. Were you the only freshman Senator elected in 94? No,
there were others elected, but the ones, if you've served in public office before, you get credit
for it. If you've been a governor, you get credit for it. Yeah. So you are the lowest totem pole.
Yeah. I mean, I thought I was okay being a heart surgeon and taking care of people and saving their
lives. When I got up there, boy, they could care less, especially when it came to committee choice
or it came to anything that had to do with appropriations or power and that sort of thing.
But the committees I ended on were great committees. One was the banking committee.
Fascinating time and always a good committee has no power per se, but a really important committee
in terms of constituents back at home. And the health committee, the health education,
labor pension committee, which is health. And that it did include things like I chaired the
subcommittee on disability policy. And, you know, for the whole United States of America,
every law of the disability world had to come through that particular committee. And then went
to foreign affairs with about two years later and stayed on that throughout because I had done so
much travel to other countries doing medical work and it fit there. But those were the ones in the
first few years that I was on and learned a tremendous amount. And then in the last four to
a year or six, joined the commerce committee and the commerce committee, that was the time there was
telecommunication and all of the great reform that was going on then.
I've resisted asking you this question before, because I wanted to ask you for the first time
during this discussion, how is it that someone so young and so junior in tenure can become
the Senate majority leader at such an early time in their tenure? So I guess walk me through the
late nineties, you're obviously going for reelection. You won by quite a healthy margin,
but what were the string of events that allowed you to go from being still a relatively junior
senator to being, you could argue the second most powerful person in Washington after the president?
Yeah, it's an interesting sort of line narrative in large part because that was not my goal.
And if you're going to start with 100th and GRT and jump to number one in a period of
six years, that just sounds crazy. And it is crazy. And Lyndon Johnson did it, but he'd spent
all those years over in the House of Representatives, but they come in.
By the way, LBJ was generally considered one of the most effective Senate majority leaders.
Some people still wonder how he actually managed to take the vice presidency as such a step down.
And of course, how history would have been different had he not, but yeah.
Yeah. But the sequence of events was I won reelection at the time there, Bob Dole,
who is just an iconic leader as well. And Trent Lott and others were sort of the Trent
Lott representative, a younger generation, but all very senior to me were sort of added
to each other and competitive and sort of the intra-family politics and class office sort of
stuff. And I didn't pay any attention to that really. What I was interested in, and I use this
in different ways today now that I'm out of politics. So if I'm on a board, I like to go
to the nomination committee that the future of a body of an institution, if you really say,
how I want to affect a board, a nonprofit board or a for-profit board or the United States Senate,
a hundred people, the best thing to do is to get involved in the determination of who's in the
room and who is not. And therefore in leadership, the sort of fourth or fifth position down,
depending on how you look at it, in the row of Republicans, say there are about 50 Republicans
there, is a more political position called the National Republican Senatorial Committee.
But they're in charge of the 33 elections, that one person is, and they get selected by the body
to choose the next generation of senators. Not choose them, but you recruit them. And, you know,
I recruited Lamar Alexander, I recruited Elizabeth Dole, I recruited John Thun.
Maybe they would have ended up there, but maybe probably for most of them they would not.
And so I ran for a leadership office then, and that leadership, again, I came there to do policy,
to pass big stuff that would help people in health and welfare and lift them up in education.
So I said, let's do that position for two years, then I could come back and do policy the last
four. And so that year, six years in, between sixth and eighth year, we did what you implied,
or you suggested earlier, I ran that group, I represented the United States Senate in every
state, I had to raise money for the Senatorial Committee. But we won that year 11 seats,
11 Republican seats. It was the first midterm of George W. Bush. As you said earlier,
there's a huge bias for the Democrats to win. Right, but 9-11 shifted it, I'm sure.
It was all sorts of macro everything coming up. But we won, and we won big. And so I worked it
hard. And again, it's been a heart surgery, not trained to do that sort of thing. But I traveled
and I recruited people and I'd go to New York, I'd go to North Carolina, I'd go to Nebraska,
I'd sit down with 10 people who wanted to run the United States Senate, I'd spend hours with
them. I talked to their families and their spouses and say yes, and say this isn't going to work out
for you. And then I have to raise money as well, state to state and say this is important to support
these campaigns. And both parties have this. Is the expectation at that point that if you broke
even that would be a victory to not give up seats in your first midterm? No, no, no, no,
you were going, you were in it to win it. Yeah, no, well, no, the expectation was,
it's very unlikely to even break even in the first midterm of any party of the president, just,
you know, just historically nine out of 10 times loses seats. So I wanted to keep the losses to a
minimum. I wish I could say which to break even. But we won and we picked up seats. And with that,
I developed a certain credibility among my people. People weren't jealous of me either, because I'm
just a doctor doing his best. You know, good guy can bring people together, can bring the
Democrat can be Republican together. But, you know, when my historical precedent, not, you know,
nothing great in the family started breaking down. And without going into details, there was a lot of
dissension in the party. And it was mostly with behind closed doors in these caucuses. And when
it came to elect the majority leader, I again, I didn't want to be majority leader. It wasn't my
goal. In fact, if you go to be in leadership, it's hard to do big policy. It's hard to do the sort
of things I ended up doing HIV, AIDS, PEPFAR, these huge things that affect millions of people.
If you're the leader, you look at what McConnell, if you're whoever's the leadership,
Schumer and McConnell today, and whoever it will be, you know, as people listen to this in the
future, they don't have time to do the legislation or the policy. They're out there managing,
hurting these cats, being the leader. So I didn't want to do that. I only had 12,
I only had four years to go. I didn't want to spend four years hurting cats. But when it came
down to the election, there were five people who wanted to be majority leader. And all of them,
to be majority leader, you had a majority vote. And one might have 12 votes, and one might have
nine, and one might have eight, one had four and six, and then you get together with other people.
And I wouldn't have part of any of that. But then it got down to where nobody had the votes.
And people came to me and I had a group of people because I'd come off these Senate races with
credentials. They said, well, what about you? And then all of a sudden, all these, all four of the
other people came to me and said, if you will do it, they said, I can't win. And if you are
interested, we want you to be a majority leader. So I haven't really told that story publicly,
but I think it is important for people to humanize as the place. You know, this is no
different than elections and life and things are fair and things are unfair. And luck is a part of
it. But that's the that's the story. It did not have the credentials, didn't want it,
did want the two year job. So I could go back to policy, but the two year job did well, but got
lucky, really lucky. And one, and then at the end of the day, because in part because of this
doctor thing, they also saw me as somebody that is non-threatening. They said, this guy comes in,
I want to stay here forever. They would say to themselves, this is my job. This is my pinnacle
in life. And my pinnacle in life is doing heart transplants, you know, out the window, going to
the Vanderbilt and saving lives every day by just doing my job. And but this was the pinnacle in
life to a lot of people. And so they probably said, well, you know, if I give him my people,
and I worked with him for four years, when I leave, I might be the one that he said should be
the next majority leader. As you alluded to earlier, these next four years while your Senate
majority leader are quite busy and potentially one of the signature things you're a part of is PEPFAR,
which you've alluded to now. I've always found it interesting how little Americans understand PEPFAR.
And yet, you know, when you talk to people in Africa, it's a very different picture you get
there, right? I mean, I think when you go to the parts of Africa that have been impacted by it,
they hold the administration in such high regard. And yet for some reason, it doesn't get, I think,
the attention it deserved domestically. Do you agree with my assessment? And if so,
why do you think that might be the case? I partially agree. Yeah. You know, PEPFAR.
Let's start with telling people what it is. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We're talking about HIV AIDS.
And it makes sense being the only doctor in the Senate that people would come to me early on. And
I had spent years going to Africa, spending two to three weeks a year, taking care of people,
doing surgery, training people, worked with a group called Samaritan's Purse initially,
and then other groups on my own and throughout Africa, mainly in South Sudan and a province
called the Louis Province there, but also in Ethiopia and South Africa and Botswana.
And I would see people dying there a lot. And there was no testing for HIV AIDS at the time.
And then I came to the United States Senate and worked with President Clinton. And President
Clinton said, yeah, it's a big issue. And we'd put maybe a couple of hundred million dollars into it,
but never did anything about it. And then this right wing, not really right wing, this middle,
but right wing George Bush came. And President Bush, this is 2000, had never been to Africa.
Maybe he'd been one time when his dad was president for a night. In conversations with him and other
people, Tony Fauci, who everybody's heard a lot about today, was a huge part of it. I'd bring
pictures back of people dying of HIV AIDS. But the story at that time was that three million people,
three million were dying every single year because of a little virus that in 1980, in 1981,
we didn't even know what it was. We had never seen it in the United States. But with three million
people dying of that and a couple of million dying of tuberculosis and one in malaria,
this was by far the biggest killer globally of a disease. And so President Bush basically listened
to the stories, focused on it, sent Tony Fauci down to Africa. You know, is this something we
could do something about? He came back in a surprise way at the State of the Union missions,
2003. When I was majority leader, I knew it and probably five or six other people knew it.
Basically said, I'm going to make the single largest commitment to a single disease that's
ever been made by a president of the United States. This little cagey virus, HIV AIDS.
At the time, Republicans and faith-based people, you know, thought it was a disease of gays and was
bad. And the Jesse Helms of the world basically said it was, you know, a call from God and
punishment and all. The left wasn't doing anything about it, but they talk about it,
but nobody would step. So President Bush, I wrote the Senate bill and I, but a lot of others got
together and passed this legislation about six months later in record time, jumping ahead. 20
million people are alive today because of that five page bill that surprised everybody coming
out of this president. And it's no small figure. I mean, we're talking, you said, you know,
Clinton put a hundred million into this. I mean, your bill put $60 billion into this,
if I'm not mistaken. Is that right? Oh, we were spending about 200 million a year. And again,
President Clinton was right on all the issues. And later after he left office, as you know,
made a big issue about it and still has done unbelievable things to the Clinton Foundation
for it. But at the time there were just so many other things going on. So it's been about 200
million. And then that first year with President Bush that we got it through the first year,
$3 billion and then $3 billion a year for five years. And then over time is the $65 billion
because subsequent presidents have continued with that program coming forward.
But the interesting thing is it came from way out to the right and it came from a people who brought
the left and the right together in a bipartisan way. And when I brought it to the floor of the
Senate, you know, it was close, but it was bipartisan and it passed. And when the house
passed it, so it will be legacy and legacy changing. And then the spinoffs from it,
all that money is spent. It's not just on HIV, age, it's on tuberculosis, malaria,
infrastructure, surveillance, putting clinics in cities and communities and villages and towns
all over the world, not just Africa, but Russia, China and around the world.
Now, one of the things that put you at a little bit of odds with the party was when you broke
with the party's views on stem cell research. Initially your view was in line with the Republican
Party, which was to be against stem cell research. You changed that view and in the process,
presumably upset people in the party. So I guess I'd start with what changed your mind.
Yeah, you know, it's interesting to sort of go through what stem cell research is because
the changing of the minds or the switching of positions or sort of the role of a senator is
one that's kind of worth going through. So I had come to the Senate as a position,
I know brain death well because all of them, I don't have patients, I'm involved in all of those.
I am in immunology. When I came to the Senate, I was in and did things like disability policy
and health. So people came to me on this particular issue coming in. And there was an
amendment back in 1996, which basically banned federal funding of embryonic stem cell research,
not adult stem cells. Embryonic stem cells being the ones that were just discovered in 1998. So
this is fairly new at the time. And the beauty about those embryonic stem cells, they do something
that no other cell had ever done. And that is you could take it and it could become a liver or a
heart or a pancreas. You could kind of channel it in those directions. And the second thing,
it was like a, back in those days, we'd say it's like a copying machine. You can make unlimited
copies of it. No other cell ever in the history of man had we discovered. So then you had people
who said these cells are powerful, going back to the heart transplant. Why not take a few of those
stem cells, stick it in the heart, make that heart come alive. The problem is it had never been done
before. And ethically, people didn't know whether it can be done or should be done. But if you had
Parkinson's disease, neurodegenerative disease, the hope for everybody, including me as a scientist
who kind of lived in this world was tremendous. So the question was, how do you take these embryonic
stem cells and in an ethical construct, allow that research to go forward. And that was always the
issue. And do you do it with federal monies or you do it with state monies or local monies? So the
issue is all what happens at the federal level. See that amendment and then President Bush came
out in 2001 and he said, we're going to fund embryonic stem cells for the first time. We're
only going to do very little. We're going to limit it because we don't know if these cells are good
or bad. That's sort of one line. The more important line at the time was, is it ethical?
The embryonic stem cells, the only way you could get them is by creating an embryo and then
destroying the embryo. So you can see real quickly where this is going. You got pro-life, pro-choice,
50-50 in America. Pro-life people said that the embryo has the full genetic code. It is all you
got to do is nourish it. It is a human. It may be early on, but it's in the first stage of development.
So the ethical issues there were Americans believe that or half of America believes
it has sort of moral value of some sort. Do you allow embryo mills to be created? And so that's
where the ethical issue is, a fascinating issue. So Bush said, no, we can't do that. Let's restrict
the number of cells. And he said, here's 78 cell lines because they've already been created,
but let's not destroy any more embryos or create and destroy embryos. And so he limited 78 lines.
So I endorsed that. And about two months before that, and this was all written up in the
Wall Street Journal because it was all new science and political. I'd written,
gone to the floor of the Senate and said, I think that here by 10 principles, let's put them forward
and engage federal funding. State funding is okay. And local funding is okay. That's outside.
But for federal funding, let's limit it like Bush limited. He limited to 78 cell lines.
I said, instead of doing that, let's sort of stay with the times and use these blast
assists or these little embryos that are used in fertility clinics that are otherwise going
to be thrown away. But they're still, they're still pluripotent. These are still completely
pluripotent stem cells. Exactly. You create five of them. You implant a couple. The other three
are thrown away, discarded. So my argument in my 10 principles that I went to the floor in 2000
was that used those. So Bush came out with something different. He limited to 78 cell lines.
So I endorsed that because at least we were getting federal funding of stem cells. And then
we jumped four years later. And this is what's really interesting to me. And this is really
important, I think, for our senators today. Science changes over time. You learn things.
There are better techniques. There's evolution of knowledge. You clinical trials prove things.
And it got to be four years later that it was clear those 78 cell lines didn't work.
They were contaminated by mouse cells. Only about 22 of them ended up being good.
And therefore, what was intended to be sort of a limited opening of the door for federal funding,
in my mind, had failed because science had demonstrated those cell lines were not sufficient.
So I pulled my 10 principles back out, again went back to the floor of the Senate,
put those 10 principles out there. And the reason it became such a big politicized issue
is that President Bush did not agree with me and the majority of the Senate and the majority of the
House. We passed in 2005 a bill called the I think it was the Stem Cell Research Enhancement Act.
It passed. It says you could use these blastocysts. An ethical construct was set up. You got consent
set up. And then that bill passed, overwhelmingly bipartisan, but it was vetoed by President Bush.
And so then people said that Princeton and Bush are in totally different areas. But from the day one,
the embryonic stem cells to me have been a heart transplant, certainly one of the most exciting
science that had come by in 10 years. But when this whole ethical issue came up,
out of both my own beliefs, you know, when you have nascent life in an embryo and you had these
embryo mills being created, women were being paid $400 to create embryos to have them destroyed.
And there was no mechanism, discipline mechanism around that that we had to create that. And
ultimately it got created. And now we jump, you know, 10, 15 years later, the same principles that
I had put in in 2000 and 2005, the ones out there. And that's where that research has gone.
And in retrospect, it's probably been pretty good in the sense that the stem cells eventually are
going to live up to the promise, but we're 17 years later and adult stem cells are used in bone marrow
and cord blood is being used. That has no ethical issues around it. It's these embryonic stem cells.
And with the research that's out there, it's 17 years later and some good things are happening,
but still there's no embryonic stem cells being used to treat the Alzheimer's in Parkinson's.
Yeah. I mean, it's such a hard problem, right? The challenge is how do you instruct the stem cell?
Where is the instruction set that says, I want you to go and replicate 32 times, 32 doublings and
become cardiac myocytes. And this subset of you are going to go on to develop Prickinji fibers
and this set of you will not. I mean, we're still so far from cracking the code of what the
instruction set looks like to the stem cell. So this is step one of 10, basically, in terms of that.
But it's hard to tell people that. And as a policymaker, you have to make the decision. You
have to set up the construct or you're not going to fund funding, but you literally have thousands
of people who are dying and they have the chronic diseases and then they have a group of people
telling them that within two years, this was all in early 2000s, within two years, your Parkinson's
could be or your neurological injuries severing of the spinal cord can be cured with these cells.
And therefore we need to open up the field and forget destruction of embryos or all these moral
concepts of life. And that's the tough job of a policymaker. You got a hundred regular people
who, some are smart, some are not, that are maybe not perfectly representative of people,
but they got to make these decisions. So it's the sort of thing that at the end of the day,
we increased federal funding for stem cells, constructs were put around it, imperfect. His
approach was different than mine. People made a big deal about it at the time, but at the end of
the day, I think it ended up working out pretty, pretty well and learned a lot. And it comes back
to science a lot. And these fields that are just so promising. I mentioned synthetic biology and
we think of CRISPR technology today and the creation of kids with blue eyes and brains that
are good in math and all, all of which we could do. But how do you slow that down? How do you bring
the discussions, not just to the capital and not just to the academic centers, but to, to Main
Street and get the right ethical constructs. And that's what our policy, I'm not a policymaker now
in that sense, but that's what these people in Washington do. That's what we hire them to do.
And that's what we need to hold them accountable and they need to do it the best way they can at
point in time. So things are going to shift with time. In that particular one, I luckily, I did
the same 10 principles in 2000 as I did in 2005 when I passed the bill. It got vetoed by the way,
so I lost, but ultimately back under President Obama, the same bill was taken out and passed.
What are the restrictions on a president's ability to veto? Can a president veto any amount of
majority, any Senate majority? He can, if the 99 senators are in favor of a bill, the president can
still veto it. Well, yeah, it's a good point because you, if you could have a majority of the votes for
it or a super majority, but you have to have two thirds or three points come back. So if you veto,
you have to take a whole nother vote and then override that veto. So he or she has that
intervening time to put pressure on people and change that. Another very complex issue that you
weighed in on, which ties into your past, which is this idea of end of life, right? I mean,
it's funny, I remember a really complicated case when I was in medical school at Stanford,
which involved a patient who was more or less brain dead, but there was a very complicated
family dynamic. And I don't, I don't remember the exact details, but it was one of those scenarios
where every ethicist in the hospital had been in that room to try to talk to that
family and resolve the withdrawal of support. And interestingly, even though this case had
nothing to do with cardiac surgery, ultimately the person that came in and mediated it was Bruce
Wright. And it's an interesting story because again, here's Bruce Wright. At the time he was
the chair of cardiac surgery at Stanford. He had by now come back from Hopkins and you know him. So
this probably isn't surprising to you, but you don't think of like the chair of cardiac surgery
being the warm fuzzy, but he was like the most soft-spoken human alive. Like you would never
see him and think that that's the guy who did the first heart lung transplant or anything like that.
But it was sort of like, I don't know, he spent, you know, two hours with this family and everybody
had come to a point of comfort that in the case of that patient support should be withdrawn.
So of course, as a transplant surgeon, you are intimately familiar with what the criteria are
for brain death, what makes a donor, what does not make a donor, et cetera. And so again, here you
are now Senate majority leader and a very public case comes up. This case of this young woman,
Terry Shivo, and I guess just for folks who don't remember this, and you can correct me on some of
the details, but my recollection, because I was in residency, this was such a big discussion for us.
This is a young, healthy woman who I guess unbeknownst to a lot of people had an eating
disorder. So she had bulimia and through lots of repetitive purging had developed profound
hypokalemia. So very low potassium. So she's otherwise looks perfectly healthy on the outside,
but I believe her potassium got as low as two to 2.5 milliequivalents, which not surprisingly put
her into an immediate cardiac arrhythmia and arrest. By the time the paramedics arrive
and resuscitate her because she's so young and healthy, they can get her heart beating again,
but her brain has been without oxygen for minutes. No one really knows. This was in 1990,
if my memory serves me correctly, fast forward a few years. Now her husband, Michael and her
parents, whose names I don't remember, are basically having a different point of view
about what to do. And the husband believes, you know, she's going to be in a persistent vegetative
state for the rest of her life. This is not what her wishes were. She's being fed through a tube.
The parents feel otherwise, and it just keeps escalating its way through courts and it gets
higher and higher and higher and higher. I don't remember exactly how it got to the point where
Congress was now being asked to weigh in, but maybe you can pick up the story of how this
basically rose to a national story and frankly, even potentially involve the US Congress.
Yeah, it is a fascinating story. And this is one again, and Peter, I haven't
talked about a lot in part because it is complicated and you do need the sort of the
time and we can do it very quickly, but. No, no, no, we don't have to do it quickly. Yeah, yeah,
you know. But now it is fascinating case and because it has implications for everybody listening
to us today, everybody, and it will be having even greater implications in the future as technology
can do these miraculous things. Here it was miraculous in the sense that she could even be
kept alive on a ventilator for a long period of time. But increasingly, it's going to get more
complex because technology and science is going to give us these tools to use. So lots of lessons,
and so it is worth going through it. So you're exactly right. 1990 Terry Shavo collapsed hypokalemia
for just a persistent vegetative state is a medical term. It's an important term here because
the law uses it. But for people who are listening to us, you know, you're on a ventilator and you
can move and I open your eyes, but it's just you have to be supported overall with both feeding
tube as well as a ventilator. And Michael, her husband, you know, did everything, at least in
my review at the time. He took her to UCLA, took her to multiple centers and for rehabilitation.
And then three years later in 1993, he'd given up basically. And I don't know, I wouldn't have
both found me. And this is 10 years later that I got involved. And but the issue was exactly as you
described that all of Terry's blood relatives, the mother, the father, the brother, the sister
objected to Michael putting her on a DNR or removing the tube. Do not resuscitate or remove
the tube. So you had this dichotomy of walking the room just like you said Bruce did. You had on one
side one person who by the law says if she's in a persistent vegetative state, the husband can make
the decision. On the other side of the room, you had all the mother and father who raised her,
who cared for her brother, her sister, who said, no, she's responding to us. She's alive, touch her,
feel her, look in her eyes. She recognizes us. And so the parents and Michael disagreed on
their impression. They also disagreed because she had, and this is what the implication is,
everybody listened to sort of this part, she had nothing written down. She had no living will,
no advance directive. And therefore you had the parents and everybody says, well, of course,
she's a devout Catholic. She values life. And you had the four of them saying, you know,
we'll support her, we'll take care of it, financially we'll take care of it. And then you
had Michael who by the law would have that responsibility of saying DNR or not.
I just want to interject there for a second. I think it's such an important point you made,
and I had actually scribbled notes down to bring it up, so I'm glad you did.
I don't think you and I as doctors could overstate the importance of an advance directive enough.
And I think a lot of these issues could be resolved if, well, you don't have to worry
about it, you go through this exercise. I mean, my wife and I did this 12 years ago,
sat there in a lawyer's office and spent an hour going through what we wanted and what we didn't
want down to the levels of detail that is comical, right? Now, not everybody has the luxury that
might not have the medical, my wife's a nurse. So, you know, we could talk about it through,
well, this is, I would tolerate this many line changes at this many weeks of a trach and this
feeding tube, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. But it is very important, I think, to do this. And
hospitals are getting better at it now for people admitted electively to at least have a box that
you check that says, do you have an advanced directive? But I think everybody should have one
of these things because the time to build the roof is when the sun is shining. And the time to have
this discussion is when clear heads prevail. And it's hard, you just have to do it. People don't
like to think about death or where they're going to be buried or wills. This is one that out of
respect for your loved ones. And it plays out here. And I'll mention again, because I'll come
back to it because it had real implications. But they had nothing, the interpretation of
one set of relatives and then the husband were very different. So, jump ahead seven years,
her feeding tube was taken out, then a court, these courts that you said came in and they replaced it.
At the time then, 33 medical specialties, and this is why I had to go back and review all this
eventually, came forward and had affidavits that her condition was not beyond some sense of
recovery that she could improve. And so, seeing that complicates things a little bit because she's
in this either minimally conscious state or persistent vegetative state. So, in 2003,
the court ordered five doctors, these are state courts, ordered five doctors to test Terry,
two appointed by Michael, the husband, and two appointed by the family. And then one
appointed by the judge, three to two, they said she was in a persistent vegetative state,
they'll be okay to withdraw therapy, take the tube out, take her off the ventilator.
The two who voted against that said no, she's in a minimally conscious state and can recover.
So, she stayed alive for about six days and during this six days, it became this huge global issue.
It went to the state of Florida, the state, the equivalent of their house and senate,
the legislators got together and actually passed a law in that six-day period that gave
governor, Governor Bush at that time, the order to put the feeding tube back in.
All this is over a six-day period. The Supreme Court there struck that down. And again, this
is kind of the politics and you say, oh gosh, as you said, the Bruce Wright's of the world,
these sorts of decisions as a physician, and I'm talking about one who's run disability policy for
America, who's been in brain death, who's been in the whole field of transplant, whose whole
career has been around life or death. These decisions should best be made by a family with
a directive, with a physician or a caregiver, maybe with a faith person in that room. But this got
elevated throughout the politics. You had Pope John Paul made a statement on behalf of the family
and the sanctity of life and that they would support her and that was their belief.
The brother, the sister, the parents said, keep her alive and that they would support it financially.
Somebody gave $2 million or said they would give $2 million to support her. So that's that. So of
course, coming back, being the only doctor in the Senate, and maybe it was one more at the time,
and knowing brain death, I was involved in all those discussions. And when I was at Stanford,
the ethical issues, the disability policy, the only physician. So I didn't want to do it because
I don't think it should be done. It should be really rare, really exceptional, but this had
become a global issue on the news every night. And again, it was a long time ago at this point,
2003. So I asked myself at that point, does the government have the right to terminate life
when the family objects to it, if they'll financially take it? And that was kind of
where I came down to. And the question is, which part of the family do you listen to? The one that
the law would give it to, ultimately, it would be the husband or all of the siblings and the loved
ones and the people who lived with her and taken care of her and large, large part. And it's a
little bit like coming back to the transplant world. If I walked into a room to remove a donor
heart to bring it back to Vanderbilt to transplant it, and I walked in the room and the patient was
there in the operating room. And there was a spouse who said, no, she said, take the heart.
It's okay. But the rest of the family said, no, we don't want you to desecrate, you know, the body
of our loved ones and take the heart. Even though the law would say I could do it, you know,
under these donor laws that we have, I wouldn't do it. Of course I wouldn't do it. I wouldn't,
to me, it's just not the right thing. So what did I do? Have you ever been in a situation like that,
by the way, where the legal spouse, the person with the legal right to authorize the transplant
says yes, and a group of others say no? It's fairly fair. As you can imagine, it's fairly
rare, but it's common. And so no, I did not. I would not take off in the airplane tonight
if I knew talking to the donor counselors up there that the family disagreed, although legally,
it says so I avoided it totally. And others may have done it, but I would not do it. But yes,
it's not that, you know, as you can imagine, you get six members of a family and they all disagree
about something unless you have a Bruce Wright's walk out and you've described that well. So the
first thing I'd go faster. The first thing I did is I called the last neurologist to examine her.
And he said she's not in a persistent vegetative state. It's a mentally conscious state.
What is the difference there? I mean, I want to just kind of make sure some people understand
what we're talking about. She has some brainstem function. For example, if you touched her cornea,
she'd blink. Presumably if you injected ice water in her ears, you'd get a doll's eye reflex.
Did she have a gag reflex? She had a minimal gag reflex, which, you know, so she had,
the definition is not by a single test. So it is a clinical test. And there are certain tests that
you just ran through, three of them. There are certain tests that you do, but things like an MRI
and PET scan, she hadn't had any of that. She ultimately had them after she died and she did
have very, very serious disease, but it's a tough diagnosis and that's the world we live in.
Oh, so that CT scan that we see of her head that shows basically it's mostly fluid. There's no
brain matter. That was post-mortem. Yeah, after. See, that was after. Six months later, because
then it all surged up again, as you can imagine. So to talk to the neurologist, he was just having
me the last neurologist. I personally, as majority of you are met with a brother, he was clearly
going to be coming to us. The house had already sort of called for the case. I talked to the family
and the family said, don't terminate her. I looked at the medical records again, just because I was
curious about it. And it was clear that she had not had an MRI, had not had a CT scan, had not
done any of the current things. Remember this happened back in 1990. So I checked what I did.
It was there now. And so I checked with the Senate leadership. Harry Reid was the Democrat at the time,
became bipartisan, the house led on a bill. I'll come back to what the bill was. And we had a bill
and it was bipartisan. It was supported unanimously in the United States Senate,
overwhelming majority, both parties in the House of Representatives. And 15 neurologists had signed
an affidavit and all of that that said she needed an independent current evaluation that she hadn't
been evaluated recently. So really controversial, even among my staff, they said, what in the world
are we doing? And I said, I know, you know, but this has come to us and it's at an issue that
cannot be resolved. And I said, it should be rare. It should be decided locally the way,
you know, for 20 years in medicine that I'd been able to decide life and death decisions,
which I was in this field that you do. Bill passed unanimously in the Senate, in the House,
I think it was like 210 to 50 something bipartisan. What it did, the bill itself guaranteed a process
and not an outcome. And so it basically didn't say keep her alive. It basically said she needs
an exam that is truly independent, not with courts and not done by politicians. And once that exam
is done, if she's in a persistent vegetative state, then remove the tube if that's what the
husband wanted. And if not, the family should be listened to the extended family should be
lifted to. So the outcome, it passed the United States Senate, it went to the federal courts,
they denied the petition and the feeding tube was removed, and she was allowed to die.
So that's the story. So it's an interest you went in and on reflection, you know, again,
publicly, I don't go through this. And I've written some about it, because I've written a
lot about brain death issues and persistent vegetative state. But as a policymaker, it the
story captures this sometimes necessary conflict and this very real tension between the rule of law
and the law basically said, well, the husband can decide, and this broader consideration of ethics
and morality and in this world of increasing technology and the ambiguity of not having any
sort of thing written down. So in retrospect, people ask me because a lot of people say that's
got to be the biggest mistake you did in 12 years. And I say I kind of just avoid it and move on.
But in retrospect, the fact that it had come, I'd probably do the same thing and pass the same bill,
set up a process and not an outcome. And I was the only person in the Senate at the time who
taken two oaths. And one of those oaths was to the Constitution, the life, liberty, pursuit of
happiness, the oath that all those 62 lawyers and everybody take in the Senate. But I'd also
taken this other oath, this Hippocratic oath to protect life and to do no harm. And when it's,
when there's ambivalence around that, and when the family wishes otherwise, and it's true
ambivalence, I will opt on life. And I will opt on what I would interpret as life, others may not.
And this has got to be exceptional and rare and it has been in retrospect, and those kind of cases
haven't made it back to Congress. And these decisions clearly, clearly, clearly are best made
locally. The other challenge, I'll close on that is the politics made it worse because you had
the Chris Matthews of the world who would go out every night and, you know, big sort of Democrat
and sort of after people and he would, he would say, here you have Senator Prist, Prist playing
doctor in the United States Senate. You know, he's one of those other Republicans. And then the
Republicans would shoot back from the House and say, oh, this is a great case because it shows
right to life. What I did and what I tried to do with these, and it's hard to do, is to separate
the politics from the policy, to separate the politics from the science. And it shows, this
case shows that this inherent tension and challenge to our policymakers who are, are,
whether it's at the state level or local level or federal level, are given our trust to make
decisions like this and to have appropriate oversight. The decision should be locally though,
as much as possible. Yeah. I mean, I definitely agree with that. My personal views notwithstanding
on this case, which is that I think that I can't understand how a CT scan wasn't done, you know,
in the late nineties, frankly, to have, you know, made it so obvious as to what the state of her
brain was. I think the interesting point here is that you were probably the least political in my
view in that because that's the advantage of being in your final term in a Senate when you've
publicly declared you'll never run for another office is you don't technically have a political
dog in the fight anyway. So even though your viewpoint was viewed as political, actually,
I think it was, those were your personal views and people are free to disagree with them or agree
with them. But I didn't think of it as necessarily a party view because you, I don't think there was
anybody in the US Senate that had less of a stake in what the party felt. That was just sort of, you,
you were voting your conscience and we may disagree with that, but I don't think it was political.
Yeah. And, you know, you know, issues, all the issues and even with impeachment back in the past,
people have a hard time understanding that politics is a part of our democracy. And you wish,
and with things so partisan, everybody wished, not everybody, but so many of us wish you could push
this extreme partisanship out of it. But even things like impeachment, there's a political
nature to it. It was intended to have this political thing and politics and policy can't
be separated totally. And that's why I come back to this tension that has to be there and this
discernment and this past experience and not arguing, you know, the law to the extreme that
you can't see a larger picture because laws are imperfect as well. And that's the sort of
representatives that I think we do, we need to aspire to and then elect and have people get
involved enough in politics that they can elect those sorts of people to these bodies of Congress,
of Senate or governors or state assemblies. It's so hard to believe that we are now in the
20th year since 9-11. I want to go back to that Tuesday morning for you, because I think anyone
can remember, you know, anyone of a certain age can remember every detail of it. But I can't imagine
what it's like to have been a member of the United States government at the time, let alone a senator.
What do you remember about that morning and what was running through your mind as
this thing was unfolding? I still have nightmares about it. We all have the anxiety, like we feel
with, you know, COVID and other things, but the nightmares experience of having an assault
that we have no idea how big it is, how deadly it can be, coupled with being in a position of having
to make decisions at that point in time. You're a United States senator. The security at that time
rests 100% with the president and a co-equal branch of government, the Congress,
and with inadequate information, no information having to make decisions there. So the fright of
it, my first thoughts when it hit, I was out in front of the Capitol and over to another senator's
office in the first plane hit and I fly and fly a lot. And it'd be really unusual for somebody to
hit a building, World Trade Center, but it could be done or it could be a suicide mission.
You even thought that during the first, because when the first plane hit, I remember, I was in
the trauma bay at Hopkins and I remember someone coming in and saying it and I had just assumed
it was like a Cessna had hit on a foggy day. Did you know that it was an actual passenger plane?
No, not at first. I was in an adjacent room. I was outside of the Capitol in an adjacent room
and somebody just said, you know, should you stop your meeting because the plane hit the cap,
same thing is what you said. Then when we figured out that it was an airliner and then shortly
thereafter the second one hit, I was in leadership at the time. I was in the top five of leadership
at that time doing the Senatorial Committee. So at that level, you get briefings beyond what
other senators get. And then when you're a majority leader, you give a different higher level
briefings. So I knew that a lot was going on in the world and that there was a lot of noise on
the internet, but not nothing that you'd think about, but I knew the capacity that this wasn't
just like a small thing. This was really going to reflect the world. And then when there were two,
always when there are two in life, there's going to be a third in these sorts of things. And so
that was it. So my first thoughts were that the second was, and at the same time and probably
really first were my kids because my kids were in school over in Washington over near where the
vice president lives. And it's near the cathedral. And I knew if they're going after us to go after
Pentagon, they're going to hit any sort of symbolic sites and that they went to school right there. So
of course, concern to worry about them. And then that was it. Then there was this long period of
time where we got together and were shepherded to an offsite secure location. And people, there's
certain people in leadership that are identified. So if there is an atomic bomb or if something
happens, we can refashion government. So those people are taken to a secure location.
A few senators, a few House members, a few Supreme Court justices, the president or the vice president.
And I was not part of that particular group, but it was at that level. And it was as intense as
anything in the surgery that had gone awry that I'd ever done. And I wouldn't panic there,
but this world of not having any information, no intelligence, essentially no intelligence,
and not knowing where it's coming from and not knowing what was going to sue over the next 12
hours. And it's different than anything at the operating room at the table. And there you're
doing life and death things every day. This was different. Do you recall like what you went through
over the next two or three days? Because I mean, I think back to it and I've been thinking a lot
about as we approach the 20 year anniversary, the stuff I want to talk about with my daughter who
obviously was born after. And in some ways it feels like it was yesterday because there are things
about 9 11 I remember as though they literally happened a week ago. Like there, I remember
exactly where I stood. I remember exactly what the TV looked like. I remember moments that evening,
cause none of us left the hospital for two days. You still were in a state of, are there going to
be people coming here? Do we need to be here? And then there are other things that are a total blur.
So I can only imagine in your situation that's amplified a hundred X, but do you also have
sort of pockets of that period of time that are almost a blur or does everything still sort of
fit nice and neatly and linearly into your recollection of the weeks that unfolded from that?
Yeah, no, it's an interesting question. I think the difference was that we knew we had to act.
And the first thing that we needed to do quickly, we didn't know if this was a single actor,
a single state, a single group, a country, multiple countries, and we didn't have the
intelligence. And so once we found out we didn't have the intelligence, which was, was pretty quick.
We had to pretty much assume that we were going to all be taken out. And by us, it's not us. We
don't matter, but it's the United States of America. So you go after New York, you go after
Washington, D.C., you destroy the Congress, you find the president. So ours was how in the first
six hours, eight hours, actually that night, how we could display to the world that this is terrible
and unprecedented and has to be addressed. And so we said, how do you do that? So we all stayed at
the Capitol. We went to the front steps of the Capitol. And this is the sort of thing that does
bring Democrat and Republicans together. I mean, really close to together and nothing else sort of
matters. We're talking about the safety and security of our country and maybe the
existential, the future of our country. And so we went out and I remember obviously the,
the people you think are, are, who are there, the leadership was there, of course. And the people
were there, but the John Lewis's of the world, you know, spoke and we displayed to the world
that, that you can try to take us out, but you can't take us out. And I think that was really
important. We did that after the anthrax attacks, other attacks, we sort of did that. But I think
it's really important to make that statement to the world to, to stand strong. And then it was,
it was, it was, but once we knew we could reconstitute government, if something worse
happened, it really was just sort of systematic of up and run. This is how much intelligence we have,
making decisions, should we hit how fast we should hit, should we hit it all coming back?
If we hit what's going to come at us next? So it was a busy time. And then I had family, as I said,
that, that was always in the back of my mind, just being in Washington, DC.
One of the things that you said that really stands out to me is the amazing lack of partisanship
that existed for a brief window of time following the attacks of 9 11. And obviously you could say,
well, it was an external attack directed directly at the United States. But does it surprise you
that a pandemic like COVID didn't have any of that effect of unifying the country? There was,
I can't, at least politically, it doesn't seem to have done anything to have unified
people. It's driven people further apart. And yet it's an enormous existential crisis. Do you think
this is different because a pandemic is not a nation state and it doesn't affect the U.S.
exclusively? I think when you can externalize your enemy or the assailant in some way,
brings people together. You've got an image, you can create an image. They're, they're out there.
There's somebody there. There's an embodiment of something that, that is external to you that you
can project towards and receive sort of incoming on. When you have the virus itself, you don't have
that because the virus is this cagey little thing that knows no borders, that is truly global, that
does, does not discriminate at all. And there's no sort of externalization of it. There's no sort
of setting it up and putting it on the table and saying, saying, let's do it. I think the other,
the other big thing, and there's no reason to get into the politics of it, I think the leadership
was different as well in our government. The communication was very different. And that,
to me, has been the most disappointing. When I look at the big assaults on our country
that were on our soil here, whether it was anthrax with 14 or 15 people dying here and hit our
capital, whether it is 9-11 and now the pandemic, my biggest disappointment has been the lack,
or maybe just the difference in the type of leadership that was demonstrated. And it's
leadership slash communication, how things are articulated and the like. And I think that plays
a big role. I think that if there had been a call to action with appropriate communication,
leadership, trust, empathy, understanding that this pandemic could have been externalized,
and we would probably have more rallying around it instead of this, you know, what you see on
social media and internet and television, which continues to this day.
In 2005, you quite accurately predicted what we're seeing now. You referenced the 1918 Spanish flu,
and you said it was not a question of if, but rather a question of when we would experience
another pandemic, another virus specifically. You very astutely pointed out that these 10 things
are basically going to happen. There's going to be complete and total social chaos. There's going
to be supply chain disruption, boom, boom, boom, boom, boom. And a pandemic preparedness strategy
should include stockpiles of antiviral medications, all of these other things. It's easy to blame
one party or the other, but the reality of it is no administration's really ever taken that seriously,
have they? People have taken it seriously. I'd say both administrations have, and this may come
back to where we started, that my experience coming in was colored by things like HIV AIDS,
killing three million people a year, was characterized by anthrax, which when it hit
the Capitol and knowing the potential of what it could do. The lack of preparedness was just
crystal clear to me just based on my past experience. And so what I did in 2005, as you
said, 20 different speeches I gave, all basically out the same speech, but I gave them on the East
Coast, West Coast, Silicon Valley, the Florida United States Senate, far reaches like Nantucket,
the red forest of California, everywhere. It was essentially the same speech, as you said. It was
called the Manhattan Project. It did predict it was going to come because of this admixture of birds
and animals and transportation around the world. So it's clear. It's clear from a medical standpoint.
And just to be clear, you thought it was inevitable just from these factors, not necessarily even
bioterrorism. I mean, you were thinking that would be another potential way, but it was, yeah.
Yeah. And I used the bioterrorism a little bit because I'd talk about that as well,
because you could intentionally manufacture any of this. You hook it onto a virus or hook it onto
smallpox where you have something that's real transmissible. And it's not that hard to do. It's
real easy to do. You can do it in a room, 8 by 12 foot room with simple things. And so the
bioterrorism at the time, because of 9-11 and all the things that had gone on, it was clear we needed
to worry about that, especially with smallpox, because Russia had a supply of smallpox it could
use. But no, this was outside of that. This was sort of coupled with that, because the same things
that you need are the communications, the infrastructure, the stockpiling, the virology,
the research and development, the antiviral agents, the manufacturing capacity, all the things.
These are all the things that as I say to them now, people say, oh, yeah, check, check, check.
That's with COVID. And the point is, and I called it a Manhattan Project in each of these speeches.
And as I said on the floor, I left the Senate the next year and work has been done and people
have tried to do pieces of it, but nobody has really stayed on it. But the six proposals I
testified before, Lamar Alexander's committee, about the next pandemic, about three months ago,
because right now is the time we have to talk about the next pandemic, there will be another
pandemic. And will we be prepared? And we all know, and especially political people, that,
you know, it's only the snake that's at your foot that you're scared of. Once the snake goes off in
the trees, you just lose that sense of sort of urgency there. So from the scientific standpoint,
I mean, that wasn't any great. I mean, we say this like I could say it, I wrote it down
and I wrote what we should do and what we should do, we didn't do. And therefore, it's, you know,
it's interesting to go back. My biggest fear is that you write that same talk and you give that
same talk or somebody does, and there's nothing done after that. And I don't think that'd be the
case, but it's going to take, you know, a constituents and people saying this is an
existential threat. This is, you know, this COVID thing is not a deadly virus. I mean,
I say that. I mean, that's my fear, right? Is we kind of, and you say this and it sounds horrible,
but we dodged a bullet here. This virus is quite a wimpy virus relative to the Spanish flu or the
Hong Kong flu or SARS-1 or MERS. And there's a sweet spot. Obviously, if a virus is so deadly,
that it basically knocks trans, like if it's an Ebola virus, in many ways, those are less
threatening because they kill people so quickly. But there's an inverted U shape of lethality and
SARS-CoV-2 is actually quite far to one side, which is it's so non-lethal that it's so contagious. But
you take its lethality up one order of magnitude, it still wouldn't, especially if it has a long
latency, it's a devastating virus. I mean, it kills tens of millions of people. And I think you're
absolutely right about the snake at your feet. Like there is a certain amount of political capital
that probably exists now in 2021 to really say, okay, well, how much money is the government
willing to spend to make sure that the next time this happens, we're not on our heels?
Yeah, exactly. And it was funny with Lamar's committee, he ran the health committee,
was chair of it, the health committee. And he took a lot of heat. I listened to it. I love not being
there because I can sit there, listen to the hearing and give my testimony. But half the
people would say, Lamar, this is crazy, looking for the next pandemic, seeing what we should do.
We've got a pandemic now. And he said, well, of course we do. And we're doing everything we can,
but look what history has led us to. And there are clearly things to do, but how you get people to
stay on it and understand. And there's simple things, infrastructure. Right now, things like
vaccine distribution, which has been so challenging, that's the sort of thing,
and public health infrastructure locally, there are fewer public health people on full-time payroll
in our communities today, wherever you are right now, than there were eight years ago.
Public health people, public health has been the stepchild of health and welfare and healing. That
is inverted now in people appreciate it, but we're going to actually deliver on it,
not just next year and not just put more funding in it, but really do it over a period of time.
And that's the challenge. And again, getting people to these bodies and opening those bodies up to,
whether it's more scientists, more thoughtful people, people getting other experiences from life
and having them participate in supporting them in those positions.
So I want to kind of go back to just this broader topic of the political world we live in today
versus the political world you entered and left, which is in some ways not that long ago,
but yet seems like an awful long time ago, frankly. If you think about the historical arc of politics,
which I frequently try to do and think back to the worst of times, and maybe this isn't so bad, but
help me understand, gauge your level of optimism for me in terms of this infrastructure, right?
Which is the two-party system, the systems that are in place that have rewarded the extremes
and punished the compromises, the tools that amplify it, social media, cable news, all these
other things that we could, everybody can rattle off all the things that could be broken today.
How optimistic are you that if we can both agree that where things are today is suboptimal,
it's going to get better? Yeah, you know, I, on my podcast, I ask people the sort of optimism
question a lot and 90 out of 100 say they're optimistic about things. That's really interesting.
And so I'm slowly going to answer it because I think you have to be really, really careful
on the, first of all, I am optimistic. And again, it's my nature and I tend to get involved in things
that seem to be challenging and I love just working with them and bringing people in and
things tend to work out pretty well. So I feel good about it. I think the next few years are
going to be really difficult and probably not get a lot better and may get worse. I think if you look
at structures that are contributing to it, we're going to figure it out. And I don't blame social
media, but it's an accelerant and the way we are going to figure out in some way to curate
social media in a way that still allows freedom of expression and free speech,
but where it can't be used in the negative ways, whether it's in partisanship or misinformation.
I feel good about that. And part of it is in discussions with people in the sort of Facebook
direct world and the Amazon world and the Google world and the Netflix world. It's going to take a
little bit further. I think we're going to get better there. When we get better, that will put
us in much better standing because if we're still on the curve of getting worse and it may get worse
and other, you know, this world populism, it may get a little bit worse, but it will get better.
And I'm optimistic about that. Leadership, I think it's going to take a while. I'll tell you
just a real quick story. When I was in the Senate, things are partisan again. We don't want to
idealize the past, but President Bush and President Clinton did not do this as much,
but President Bush came in and we were in sort of this, you know, 9-11 sort of world, but came in
and every other Friday would take three people from the Senate leadership or four, two Republicans,
two Democrats, and from the House leadership. And every Friday do breakfast with them quietly,
no press right off the Oval Office. And it was uncomfortable. You'd have the,
I shouldn't mention anything, but you'd have the people who are the leaders around the table. And,
you know, people like Nancy Pelosi and President Bush sit side by side for breakfast for an hour.
There's a little bit of attention there. But I, and this was before the Iraq War and things got
really complicated in so many ways, but for that period of time, things seem to be so much better.
Really uncomfortable and people, I don't know if people have talked about that either,
but what I say that and preface that because I do think if you have a president of the United
States, President Obama didn't do it and President Trump didn't do it. President Biden, it looks like
he would do something like that, but you know, you just don't know. But I do think if you had,
at that level, not at the level of Chuck Schumer and Mitch McConnell, you know, it's too ingrained
there. But at that level, you pull people together and said, I'm willing to lose my next
election as president of the United States. And again, take, take President Biden or President
like soon to be President Biden out of it. If you had somebody like that who stayed with it,
it would make a difference. It gives cover for people below. It gives cover for the majority
leader and a minority leader and the speaker and the Democratic leaders in the House. And that's
not that hard. I mean, that kind of makes it sound simple to do, but sort of my experience
in my thoughts, it could be as easy as that to begin the turn the tide. And I think we'll,
we'll see that. I don't know if we've been the short term or long term or how long people will
be around, but it takes that sort of courage to do it, to say, I would, you know, I'm willing to
sacrifice a second term or something like that. That's a big sacrifice though, isn't it? I mean,
that's not something to take lightly. Yeah, it is. But you know, it's gotten to the point that,
you know, how you elect somebody who really will do that from a very partisan group, it's makes it
hard, but it's doable. And we're talking about regular people and people who, you know, can be
reasonable and not always, it depends on the individual. But for those two reasons, I'm
optimistic because I think it can be done. I think it probably will be done, but I, and it can be done
pretty quickly. I think there's a real call from people for this sort of bringing people together.
Doesn't mean sacrifice your principles. It doesn't mean sacrifice your party. It just means come to
the table and be able to have a discussion and have a disagreement and leave, you know, as we did sort
of more of my first term than in my second term in the Senate, sort of shaking hands after you have
a big debate on the floor of the Senate. You know, there's so many other things I wanted to chat
about and we're really, we've gone a lot longer than I thought we would to this chapter, but we
really have only covered a couple of the chapters of your life. There's an entire chapter that
follows what you did in the Senate, which is in some ways the busiest chapter of your life
in the last 15 years. I guess just for the sake of brevity, what has been the most interesting
project you've worked on? Because you've, you know, you're, you're doing venture capital,
you're on the board of for profits, not for profits. You're a part of the bipartisan
policy center, which is an organization I'm quite familiar with and quite impressed with. I mean,
your commitments span so much. What has been the most interesting and I guess,
what have you brought from the two previous chapters to it?
Yeah, that's a great question because people, it's a little bit like they look at you probably,
if you look at your past, you know, you've done different things and you've tried different
things and is there any sort of narrative or thematic that sort of goes through that? And
for me, it goes back, I'm sure, to this whole image of healing and health and hope and all and,
you know, it sounds a little bit gimmicky and all, but it does come back to that. In my mind,
learning to be a doctor, sort of practicing the transplant world, that was 10 years learning and
10 years delivering and then 10 years and 12 years in politics and then 10 years in sort of
the private equity world and then the last five years in venture capital, all of it's around health
and healing. Everything I do, everything. And so what I did when I left the Senate, I said, now,
what is the next step? I, you know, smartly said 12 years in the Senate. So I said,
putting together my past experiences, what if there's one thing that could be done
to change the course of history? And this is thinking big and it's not the sort of thing you
tell anybody at the time. What would it be? And, you know, based on 20 trips to Africa and the
global experience and all and HIV AIDS globally, and I came back to one thing and it was K through
12 education and globally, probably K through 12 education for girls. And if you're going to spend,
you know, a increment of time with my experiences, where would it be? So what I did is started a
foundation. It's called State Collaborative on Reformative Education. It's by far the biggest
thing in the state. Now I started, but got really smart people and good people, dedicated people to
run it. And with that, it has had an impact where Tennessee has for the last 10 years shown
dramatic, dramatic improvement in K through 12 education and been recognized as such.
So that is a little bit out of health care, but the nexus between health and education is so real.
The health feeding into being better educated, the more educated sort of better health,
it just feeds together and I see it and the data is good. So that's sort of the one big bucket that
I've made a conscious decision. If you look in the investing world, what I do is focus on mission
directed health service companies, not pharmaceutical companies, not molecules, not devices, not, you
know, all of that. And so I start around companies, I start companies and support companies that have
a mission of taking people, usually vulnerable populations and lifting them up. And the one that
I'll just mention, because you asked for one, is one that kind of comes back to the things we've
talked about is palliative health care. In our country today, most people do not die the way
they would want to die. Hospice the last seven days, four days, three days is really good in
America. Finally, after, you know, 50 years is really good. But in this world of chronic disease,
where people are living and as you described so well in your talks, you push that down slope on
the chronic disease and the aging out as far as you can. But at some point you come to those graphs
that you draw and you're going to bring things to a close in its chronic disease. So think of it at
that last year of life, that last eight months of life, and it's called palliative health care in
hospitals. Traditionally, if you're at Vanderbilt or Stanford or Mass General or your local hospital
of people listening today, you can get good palliative health care. But if you live 30 miles
away or 50 miles away or 100 miles away, you can't. And you're sitting there with a chronic disease,
you're going downhill, your family, if you have family local that don't know what to do.
And so what we did is create from scratch a company that focused and is now the largest
palliative, non-hospice related palliative health in communities in the country. And it started with
this full circle sort of thing. It started with when I mentioned that I had hundreds of people
being referred to me back in those early transplant years right over here at Vanderbilt.
They were coming in, but I can only transplant one every four or five days. I didn't have enough donor
hearts. So I had 50 or 60 people coming in who were going to die within six months flying in,
coming in, saying, we need a transplant. And I say, I don't have enough donor hearts. And so I had to
learn how to take care of them, prolong their life and getting the stuff right, the nutrition right,
the exercise right, the mental health, the spiritual health right. All of a sudden they
started living not just six months, you know, they wouldn't come here if the doctor hadn't
told me six months, but they live eight months, nine months, 12 months. So seeing that, and then
I lost my mind and went to the Senate. And then I got out of the Senate, I came back and we're still
in the same place. Nobody had developed a palliative health care system for the last year, eight months
of life that looked at the spiritual, that looked at the mental, that looked at the nutritional,
that looked at the exercise and sort of general acute care, medical care as well. And so that's
sort of a good example of the sort of companies that I believe in. It ties things together,
there are needs that are out there, there are lots of other areas, you know, like that out there.
The area of the frail elderly today who don't need palliative care is doing another company
right now, just a year old, because they've got social determinant, $35,000 of that cost
plus $35,000 of medical cost, but nobody's put all that together to treat them holistically.
So you know, those are the sort of examples that are exciting to me that are really no different
than the innovation of the new ideas and the execution, which is most important, of doing
a heart transplant and figuring out how to, you know, some way figuring out that cardiac biopsy to
determine inflammation and then developing a new drug like cyclosporine, which revolutionizes that
field. It's doing it in the business world where you have access to capital, you can move fast,
you're not slowed down by government. So it's pretty exciting.
Bill, if ever there was a Renaissance man, you are that man. And I still think in many ways,
I know you don't agree with the idea of term limits and maybe that's not the answer, but
there really is something to be said for having people in the government who haven't spent their
entire lives in government. And I don't know, I think the trajectory of your career is very
interesting and maybe we'd all be better served if you were still in government, although I don't
know that you'd still want to be in government. I can tell by the look on your face, you're probably
glad you're not. Yeah, I'm just fine.
Now it's been a pleasure speaking with you today and thanks for all your service.
Oh great. It's really a tremendous honor to be with you and the stories we talked about,
I really haven't told and discussed, but because of my huge respect for the nature of your
podcast, it's a real honor to be with you. Thank you. Thank you for listening to this week's
episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss,
we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content
without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price
of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally
kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss
on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or
Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed
that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which
are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best
questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to
everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to
endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.