Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Alex, thanks so much for making time today to sit down and be part of our inaugural video podcast
here. This is, I hope it's not a long run for a short slide. So far it's been a long run,
but I have a feeling it's going to be a long slide too.
Well, thanks for having me on Peter. I really appreciate it. And yeah, this is going to be fun.
So about two years ago, was it two years ago? Yeah, it would have been. It would have been
like February of 19. I read your book Endure, which I literally couldn't put down. I think
I read it in two days. And I was just, I mean, it was, it was fantastic. And since that time,
I've become such a huge fan. You're a very prolific writer. I don't know how you do it.
If you just go to sort of, you know, search your name and go through all the magazine articles,
you're right. It's just a wonder you can do so much. There are so many things I want to talk
about today. But I want to kind of start with just a bit of your background because you know,
you don't have a typical background, right? You have a PhD in physics.
Yeah, yeah. Probably the least useful PhD in physics anyone has ever, ever attained. But yeah,
no, I come from a different place in some ways, I would say.
You're a collegiate runner and we actually have some friends in common because I think we're of
the same generation. Remind me, did you go to, did you go to Waterloo? Did you go to Guelph?
Where did you go to? I went to McGill for undergrad and then grad school in England.
Okay. But yeah, we come from the same, same part of the world. It's a, it's a, it's a small pool.
So I think we've interacted with a few of the same people.
Yeah. And I think some of my friends probably ran cross country against you and, you know,
ran track and stuff like that. So for how long was track sort of your passion?
I would say it was the most important thing in my life until I was 28. At that point,
and until that point I was still, I would have put anything and everything aside if it meant,
like, you know, I mean, I'm embarrassed to say it now. I made my brother reschedule his wedding
for, for a track meet. After 28, I kept training seriously until my early thirties. I still run
six days a week, train, race, all that. But yeah, 28 was, it was, until then it was the most
important thing in my life. And when did that start? What age were you? Was this like sixth
grade? You know, I mean, how serious were you in grade school? Yeah. I mean, I like to say,
I did win a race in senior kindergarten. I beat Stephen Mills, who's a nice kid, but a big kid.
And I was like, wow, I beat the big kid. So I've always been the guy who liked to run around. Then
I ran elementary school cross country, which involved showing up for a race once a year. And
I did well in that. I started, I joined a track club when I was 15, the University of Toronto
track club with the idea that I would train for three months because I was in a lucky position
because my birthday was after September 1st. So I could compete with the people a year younger
than myself. And I thought, well, let's, you know, let's use leverage every edge I've got. I'll train
hard for these three months, see if I can stomp on these grade nines. And it worked. I ran well,
and I kind of got hooked and realized that I wasn't going to quit after three months.
Where did you go to high school in Toronto? I went to a school called University of Toronto
Schools, which is a very, very small school. It's academically focused. From an athletic
perspective, the really nice thing is if you want to be on a team, you're on the team. Like it's,
the qualifying process for school teams was going right through the hallways and basically like
press gangs trying to get enough people for a team. So when you went to college, obviously
McGill is a great academic school in Canada. They don't have athletic scholarships. Was it a
difficult decision to say, Hey, I'm going to stay in Canada for university or try to go to a US
school where I could sort of parlay some of my running talents to actually get some money for
school. Yeah, there's a couple of factors that played into that. One is that I got mononucleosis
in my last year of high school. I missed basically my entire final year of high school.
So I was a very, very good grade 11 runner. And then back then in Ontario, there were 13 grades,
but the high school I went to only went up to grade 12 basically. So I graduated from high
school without ever having competed as a senior in high school. So I wasn't good enough to,
that's a long rambling way of saying I wasn't good enough to get a scholarship to any reasonable
place in the United States. So that discussion wasn't even really open to me. Whether I would
have, it's an alternative scenario that I would have been attracted by the idea for sure,
but that door wasn't open to me anyway. And when you showed up at McGill, what was sort of your
specialty? I know you were a miler. How competitive were you at the 800? How competitive were you at
5K and other distances away from the mile? I was a 1500 meter runner when I showed up and with the
assumption that I would be moving up to 5,000 any minute now, that I didn't have a lot of sprint
speed. I was a strength oriented 1500 meter runner. As it turns out, the coach at McGill was an X400
meter, 400, 800 guy. And his training was very sprint oriented. It was long recoveries and
all out intervals. And so I actually ran better at 800 than I expected I would, but it was pretty
clear that 1500 was kind of the low end of my sweet spot. I had so many friends who ran,
and many of them said that the 800 was the most painful race there was. And I guess in swimming,
that's comparable to the 200. And I think there's something to be said for that, that sub two minute
all out effort is really an unpleasant physiologic existence, which we're going to talk a lot about
that physiology. But would you agree with that having run so many distances?
A hundred percent, a hundred percent. The most painful race that I could run was the 800. And
I also think about this in the context of workouts, specifically at McGill talking about more sprint
oriented workouts, longer rest, these sort of hard two minute efforts. If I wanted an easy workout,
the intuition would be like, oh, you want to ask your coach for more recovery or whatever. And it
was the opposite for me. It's like, if the workout seemed too hard, can we cut the rest in half?
Because then I know we're not going to be in that very high lactate regime, which is, you know,
a two minute all out effort is the single way to get the highest possible lactate levels. And so
and to me, that's synonymous with extreme suffering. I'd rather run a marathon than an
800 in some ways. Yes. I found when I used to tweak around with lactate levels, I found that
my personal best best as the highest lactate was doing a 200 I am in swimming. So 200, 200 individual
medley, because it's upper and lower body with all four strokes. It's that 200. So, you know,
two minutes of unbearable pain you could get your your personal best lactate could be achieved with
that. Personal worst call it. And yeah, I think that's something a lot of people don't. There's
a there's an assumption that the longer equals harder. And it's like, man, no, there's a whole
different world of pain that you can get into in the if you're willing to push yourself hard in
those those two minute efforts, two to ten minute efforts. Now, in your book, Endure, you talk about
a very interesting almost a throwaway meat, you know, we would call these dual meats and swimming,
right? And it was sort of, again, I don't know if this was the turning point for you, but but it's
sort of as you read it, it comes across as a moment when you first realize there's more to this than
just the numbers, like there's something going on in my head that is changing the speed that I run
in. Was that I mean, I want to hear the story. I want people to hear the story. But was that a big
aha moment for you? Or was that just the first of many steps along a pathway? I'd say it was a huge
aha moment for me at the at that time. But I'm not sure I understood what the aha was. I knew that
there's like, this is strange. And in hindsight, I realized that this is what was that I'm sure
we'll dig into this. But it was, you know, this this started my movement away from just like,
we can calculate everything from physiology that that endurance is a little more complicated than
the equations that you might start with. Well, tell the story because it's, I mean, again, you
write about it so eloquently, but it's, it's kind of hard to believe, especially as someone who I'm
not a runner, and I'm not, you know, I'm not good at anything. But I still understand physiology
quite well. And as the story is unfolding, you're thinking there's a mistake. So so yeah, walk us
through that night. So yeah, as you said, totally meanings meaningless meat. Didn't have any big
goals. But I was at that point, this was third year university. And for about four years, almost
three and a half years, I'd been running between 401, 402, 403 for 1500 meters, 1500 meters is
about 17 seconds shorter than a mile. So we're talking like, as it's kind of like the poor man's
four minute mile, it's a significant barrier for runners, but it's not at the level of a four minute
mile. And so for me, it was like, that was kind of a career goal. I wanted to break four minutes,
if I could get into the threes, I felt like, okay, I could, I would have achieved something
significant. And but like I said, ever since high school, I'd been running very close, couldn't quite
do it. And at this meaningless meet, there was no competition whatsoever, it was going to be, I was
going to win the race no matter what. And it's sort of at the last minute, I said, well, I might as
well go hard and just see what I can do. And it's unlikely to do anything special in this context,
but I'll go hard. And indoor track is 200 meters long. So you get splits every about 30 seconds.
And I came through the first lap, and the timekeeper called out 27 seconds for 200 meters,
which is, it's about five seconds faster than four minute pace, which is an eternity, an absolute
eternity. 27 seconds is extremely fast. And it's a terrible way to start a 1500 meters race,
if you're trying to run sub four minutes. And so I had conflicting motions of like, oh, God,
you idiot with, oh, I actually feel surprisingly relaxed, but I need to dial it back. Because
presumably, Alex, you'd run 27s in practice as splits, and you know what 27 feels like. And so
on some level, you're thinking, I feel really good, because this doesn't feel as fast as 27, right?
Yeah. So you absolutely have a, you're dialed into what 27 should feel like. But you, and this is
maybe an early clue, that you also know that nothing feels the same in a race, that there's
some magic that happens in a race, and something that should have felt impossible will feel relaxed.
And so you can kind of dismiss those discrepancies and say, well, this is the magic of the race. We
don't know where it comes from, but it's the magic. And same thing in the second lap, I came through
in 57 seconds, which is way too fast, but I still felt relatively like, good. And third lap, 127.
And so at that point, the two things were happening. One is that I realized I was having a
really good day. And two, I realized that the splits were no longer meaningful to me,
because you memorize the splits for the races you think you're going to run. At that point,
I didn't know what 127 extrapolated to. And so the best decision I maybe made in my racing life
was like, stop listening to the splits. This is a special day. Run, put your head down and go for
it. So I did stop listening to the splits and I hammered home and I ran 352, which was nine seconds
faster than my personal best at the time. And again, you really have to emphasize that a one
second personal best would have been a huge victory for me. And you know, you don't know
what he PBs by nine seconds after they've been training hard for four years, five years. So
it was just absolutely mind boggling. And you know, to cut to the chase, the postscript of the story is
chatting to one of my teammates afterwards who had taken my splits for me so that I could,
as you do, you put them in your training log and you plot them in Lotus one, two, three,
and you analyze them obsessively for months. So I wanted to get my splits and he's like,
yeah, pretty good race. And I was like, yeah, I can't believe I went out in 27 seconds. He's
like, he didn't go out in 27 seconds. You were like 30 seconds. What second lap, 60 seconds. What?
So at the time, my theory was that this was a meat in Quebec in Sherbrooke. And so it was like,
oh, the guy was maybe translating from French to English. And there was a three second lag.
Maybe he just missed the start with his watch. I don't know what happened, but he basically
tricked me. He fooled me into thinking I was having this amazing day. And then I did. And so
that was what, and in itself, that was like a very bizarre circumstance. And then the question
is what happens after that? Do I become a four minute runner again? Or can I run 352 again?
And the answer is neither. I ran 349 in my next 1500 and I ran 344 in the race after that,
which qualified me for the Olympic trials that summer. So that's why I say you asked,
was this an aha moment? And it's like, I knew right at the time, it's like something has changed.
And somehow, so I knew it changed my career as an athlete. But then in hindsight, I realized it
also changed my understanding of what this whole endeavor was about and what we were trying to
optimize. Yeah, that's I mean, I still I still sort of struggle with that. And of course, you want to
extrapolate that does the same thing apply to strength sports? Well, presumably it does,
right? Could you easily trick somebody into thinking, you know, someone who thinks, oh,
I could just never break 500 pounds for a deadlift and they're sort of forever stuck at
four hundred ninety five pounds. But is there anything really preventing them from deadlifting
550 pounds, which would be as much of a breakthrough if they simply believe that that's how much weight
was if they simply believed that it was only four hundred seventy five pounds on the bar.
So I should add a postscript here is that the book came out my old coach from high school who I've
you know, I continue to stay in touch with. He's a very big influence in my life.
He read the book and he's like, show me your training log, like which lots of people have said,
right? Like, come on, this wasn't all in your head. And I was like, OK, here's my training
log. You remember it. Check it out. You tell me, was I ready to run three fifty two?
Because there wasn't a big discontinuity in my training. It wasn't like I knew I was fitter.
I knew I should be able to break four minutes. But there wasn't like I suddenly
was doing workouts way faster. And he looked through it. And his conclusion was, you know,
Alex, you were in shape to run mid three fifties for sure. You were not in shape to run. You were
not doing workouts that predicted three forty four. So in a way, the first breakthrough might have
been a lot in some ways, just catching up to the ways I was holding myself back the way, you know,
I was I was overthinking things, stressing out all these things that people do in in competitive
scenarios. I caught up to what I should be doing. And then that gave me so much confidence that I
kind of slingshotted right past where I should have been. And I was able to, you know, there's
always a conversion between what are you doing in in workouts versus what can you do in races?
Everyone should be able to do more in a competitive scenario than they can do on a rainy Tuesday night
in Stoke or whatever. And I think the best conversions I ever had, the time when I was
competing the farthest above my sort of baseline workout fitness was in the months after that
breakthrough because I was just riding that high. And I believed I was, you know, semi invincible.
And then this is ninety six, right? Yeah. So you go to the Olympic trials for the fifteen hundred.
How did you run there? It's on YouTube. It's the worst. It's horrible. I came.
I can't remember if it was dead last or eleventh in the final. I made the final, which was OK.
And, you know, when I look back to it, you can see me on I'm on the standing line next to Graham
Hood, who's the Canadian record holder at the time. And so the camera lingers on Graham Hood.
So you can see me the whole time. And I just look I think I might have written this book.
I can't remember. But it looks like I'm like waking up from a dream and looking around and,
you know, in my pajamas or something like that. I just you know, I don't belong. I'm there.
You know, I don't believe I belong there. A year later, I came back to to the national
championships. And by that time, I'd had a year to consolidate. No, I belong. I'm a guy who runs
in the low three forties. And that time I ran. Well, I ran. I ran. I came forth. That was probably
my that was my best finish at outdoor nationals. And it was it just took a while for my confidence
to fully catch up to me, I think that was so that there was. Yeah, that was how that played out.
And did you end up running the actual mile, the like the 1604 or whatever that the sort of the
non-metric mile? Because you would have by that point broken the four minute mile, right?
If you're poking your finger into a raw wound. Oh, God, I'm sorry.
If you take my best fifteen hundred and you put it plug it into the official conversions tables,
it suggests that I would have run four flat point zero one. I I I deprecate those that entirely. I
don't believe it at all. I'm confident that on that day I'll go to my grave saying I would have
run three fifty nine point nine that day. But in terms of miles, you know, the thing is there aren't
the miles just not very frequently run. I ran two competitive miles in my career, one, an indoor
mile indoor like early season when I was in college. And then about four years later, so
ninety seven, I ran my best. I was that I got a knee injury was out ninety eight, ninety nine,
two thousand two thousand one. I was trying to come back and it was a slow process. And I ran
a mile in Oregon at Hayward Field, which is the sort of most famous place. It's a good place to
go sub four, but I did not. I ran like four or six. I just wasn't back to my to my champion.
Those are the only two miles I ran in my career. You also and I regret it. It's a big thing like
four minute miles. It's a very big thing. How many people have broken four minutes for the mile?
Roughly in history. It's a good question. I'm going to say I think it's a few thousand. It's
it's fewer than more people have stood on top of Everest. I think is the thing that people tend to
say. I think that's still true. I think there's something like eight hundred or nine hundred
Americans and globally two to four thousand. I could I could be wrong, but that's my my gut
gut memory. So by the time you're you know, into the mid to late 90s, you're now a PhD student,
I'm guessing. Did you go straight into the program? I went straight there and I did a PhD in Britain
where PhDs are it's kind of a PhD light. There are it's not as rigorous as a full North American PhD.
I mean, it's it's hard in many ways, but it's it's different. So I did a three year PhD
from ninety seven to two thousand. And what what was the issue we're scratching there?
Were you a PhD student in undergrad? I'm sorry, were you were a physics student in undergrad?
Yeah. Yeah. So I studied at McGill. You have to choose pretty early. And so I declared from I did
pretty much all physics in second, third and fourth year. Not necessarily. I mean, I enjoyed it.
But this was one of those things for me that I didn't know what I wanted to do. And one of the
pieces of advice I got coming out of high school is if you don't know, want to don't know what you
want to do, do the hardest thing possible, because you can study physics and then become a journalist,
but you cannot study journalism and then become a physicist or, you know, in it's there. There's a
gradient and you can't you can you can only slide in one direction. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. So
that, you know, and the memory that I have, I have a brother who's who's five years older than me.
So he was finishing university when I was finishing high school and I had actually applied in
I think I applied to McGill in history initially, but my brother had a friend who was finishing up
in physics at McGill. And she she told him that in her class, there'd been like 60 guys and five,
60 men and five women starting the program. And they graduated four men and four women. I thought,
that sounds hard. I'm switching my my major to physics. So that that's kind of how that started.
And then coming out of undergrad, I really just didn't know what I wanted to do. I applied to a
bunch of things, again, in a variety of fields. But because I'd studied physics and undergrad,
the best opportunity I got was to go and do a PhD in physics. And I thought it would be a
reasonable way of allowing me to continue my running career. And it would be a chance to go
overseas and see a new culture and have fun. And, and, you know, and I was, I was certainly
willing to give physics a shot. I was considering physics as a career, but my decision was, was
framed in a way that even if I left physics, which I did end up in, in the end doing,
I had zero regrets about spending three years in England, studying physics.
How did your training change when you went to England versus
Canada? What were the, what were the sort of most, what were the biggest changes you experienced?
Yeah, that's actually a really interesting question, because there's some huge culture
changes in terms of the actual, like how much do you run and stuff? Not as big a deal, but
you get to Cambridge and I, you know, I show up for that first meeting with the team and I meet
the, the, the training secretary and I'm like, what do you mean training secretary? Well,
he's the guy who's going to set our workouts. Like, what do you mean? What about, we don't have
a coach? It's like, no, the, the student, the, the athletic scene there is student run. So there's,
there's a kind of a continuum in, in many things between the U S at one extreme,
Britain and the, at the other extreme in Canada is often in the middle. And so sports in the U S
collegiate sports are a big, big deal as, you know, as you know, and, um, sports are not collegiate
sports or a medium deal in Canada and they're not a big deal in, in the UK. And so going there was,
you know, an eye and open opener in many ways. It's like, we're going to the national
championships. So we have to hire, you know, we have to rent a van and then arrange a youth
hostel where we can sleep the night before the championships. Like that's not how collegiate
sports work in the U S it's not even how they work in Canada, but the, the, the flip side is you,
you have a lot of autonomy and you take responsibility for your training and your
success. You, you're not, uh, a sort of acolyte or, or baby just being sort of fed what to do from,
from day to day. And so I, you know, I don't have a systematic study to, to support this,
but I think the, the retention in terms of the lifelong retention, the people, the way,
the extent to which people develop lifelong habits and lifelong love of sport and activity
and competition, I think is much higher because you learn to be autonomous in university as
opposed to the classic thing in the U S is you're there for four years, you're representing your,
your, your college and then college ends and it's like, all right, I'm going to go work a job. And,
and there's no feeling that you haven't, there's no encouragement to stay involved in, in sport
and you haven't developed the skills required to self motivate, self organize, you know, book that
youth hostel or whatever the case may be. So, um, that was the, that was the biggest change I'd say.
So as you're wrapping up your, your PhD in physics, um, you have to make another decision,
right? Which is, am I going to go back to the U S or Canada, do a post-doc and then get on
presumably an academic track? Um, do I want to take this and move into industry where I can
utilize this? Cause obviously at the time there was probably no shortage of things that PhD in
physics could have been doing in Silicon Valley or wall street, right? Both would have been the
hay days. Um, what, you know, or do something altogether different. So how did you, how did
you approach that decision? Yeah. So, I mean, you're right. This was, you know, making these
decisions in 99 and early 2000, and my PhD was in semiconductor physics. It was, you know, it was a
good time to be in semiconductor physics. And, and there was also, there's definitely the pull of
both consulting and finance, which is, you know, just the same way that it happens with Ivy league,
students in the States in Britain. If you're at Oxbridge, they're, they're lining up to,
to offer you vast sums of money. Um, like I said at the top, running was the most important thing
in my life until I was 28. So, uh, I considered some job offers, um, but I wanted to focus on
running and I was very, very fortunate to, uh, I have parents who, who, who had a house, they were
willing to have me move back in and see what happened. So I spent, and at this point I was
coming back from this three year injury process. I was, so I had been on a trajectory that I thought
was pointing, you know, favorably by in 98, but then by 2000, when I was finished my PhD early 2001,
um, I'd been out for a few years and it wasn't clear. And I just wanted to give myself one year
to see if I could get back on that track of someone who might have a shot of making the Olympics.
So I moved back home. I did some tutoring of high school students, but basically I, uh, I ran and I
went to the library and I checked out, they had, they had a couple racks of, uh, world classics.
So I basically went through their entire rack of classic books, you know, 19th century literature,
20th century literature, all the stuff that I didn't get to do as a physics student as,
you know, as an undergrad, this is not a, this was not a liberal arts program where I had,
had time to pursue a bunch of things. It was all physics and math. So I spent a year
running. It was fun. I qualified for some national teams. I read a lot of books and I did a lot of
thinking about what I wanted to do. And after a year, I hadn't made the progress running wise
that could justify like, well, that could pay for an apartment, for example. So I was like,
yeah, okay, I'm 25 now it's it's or 24, whatever it was. Um, I need to do something else. And I,
so at that point I ended up applying for some postdocs and I ended up taking one
at the university of Maryland, uh, sponsored by the national security agency.
In quantum computing. And, uh, you know, again, it was sort of a hedge bets. It was like, I'll,
I'll take this and because the research sounds really interesting and the people are fun and
it may lead to a physics career, but it sounds fun enough. And the one thing about academic life is
if you're, if you choose, you can make other things like running your priority. And so I, I,
I went and I trained with a very, very good training group led by a guy named Matt Centrowitt senior
whose, whose son went on to win the Olympic gold medal in the 1500 in 2016. And, uh, so I spent
two and a half years there in physics, kind of giving physics and a shot, but also be as a way of,
you know, as much as I say running was the most important thing in my life until I was 28,
it was never the only thing in my life. And I also always wanted to be continuing to develop
in other ways and sort of, um, making sure that my CV wasn't going to be too empty, uh,
at the inevitable point when I, when I had to move on. So, so yeah. So I took a postdoc at that
point and went back into physics. And then when you get to the end of that period of time,
presumably is that when you pivoted to journalism as the next step? And if so, I mean, how in the
world did you gain the confidence to do that? Because, um, that's, I mean, we've, we've
established that the gradient generally points in one direction and physics might be harder than
journalism, but I don't know that that's necessarily true at the individual level. Right.
And yeah, it doesn't, it doesn't impress anybody that you can, you know, solve the
Navy or Stokes equation if you, if you're, if your job is to write an article. Um, so it's,
it's always hard to kind of write history in retrospect because you, you see the patterns
that you didn't see at the time. And so I'm never sure how accurately can I can explain
why I decided to do this. But there were a couple of things I did have, uh, the starting of an
interest in journalism. I hadn't pursued it earlier. I wasn't like doing student newspapers in college
or anything, but I liked the idea of writing and I'd actually, this is one thing that marks me as
unusual. I think as I had enjoyed writing up my PhD, everyone else was like, Oh, I love doing
experiments, but I hate writing it up. I was like, man, those experiments were hard, but it's kind of
fun trying to explain why I was doing what I was doing, which is very hard to explain. Uh, so I
kind of thought I might like writing and I'd written a couple of it's, it's a stretch to call
them freelance pieces because they're basically like I'd written a back of the magazine piece for
physics world. And I'd written a piece for athletics magazine, which is a track magazine in
Canada. And then I apply. And so I thought I'd like to give journalism a shot. So I applied for
a bunch of internships. And as you were saying, um, you know, it actually doesn't work as clearly
as you might think. I didn't get any of these internships. And I thought, okay, this is my,
my hopes of trying journalism or stalling. How am I getting, you know, do I need to sit up late at
night and write articles and prove that I can do it? And I ended up kind of deciding that it was a
credentialing issue and both a credentialing issue and an urgency issue. I needed to jump into the
deep end and force myself to survive as a journalist and also have some way of showing people that I
wasn't just a dilettante, even though I was at the time, but I needed to show them that I was serious
about journalism that, that, that I had decided to do it. And then I was going to learn the basic
skills. So from while I was in, while I was doing my postdoc, I applied to a few different
journalism schools for, for master's programs. And, uh, uh, that was helped along by the fact
that this was 2004 by this time. And, uh, I was, uh, it was gonna, I was timing it in such a way
that it's like, well, I'm going to give one last shot to make the Olympics. And if it doesn't,
Olympic trials are ended July. I'll start journalism school, uh, right after that. But
what ended up happening is I got a stress fracture in my lower back three months before
the Olympic trials. Um, which meant I was out for 10 weeks and then I did about two weeks of jogging
and then went to the Olympic trials and just sort of as a farewell to running. Um, but that made it
easier because I knew that at that point my Olympic dreams were over, were officially over,
you know, some might say they were, they were over before they even started. But, um, so the,
you know, I'd been deciding that I didn't want to continue on with physics and I was considering
journalism and then the end of running marked a natural transition for me, or at least the end of
that part of that, my, my track career, um, left something that I wanted something else to be
passionate about to be, um, to, to sort of pour that part of myself into. And I guess the one other
story I'll, I'll relate is that I actually remember at some point that year we were working long hours
in the lab, you know, sometimes it was 12, 14 hours in the lab and I would leave to do my runs
or whatever. And I remember coming into the lab one morning, you know, after we'd been there late,
we'd all been there late the night before. And one of the guys asking me like, Oh, did you see that
story in physics today about, you know, whatever? I was like, no, no, I was in the lab for 16 hours,
you know, 14 hours or whatever it was yesterday. I went home. I did not think about physics. I had
zero interest in reading about physics when I got home and I kind of realized, Oh, wait, that's what
some of these other guys do. They love it. It's their passion. And then that's great,
but it's not mine. And so I needed to find something that, uh, or I wanted to find something
that, that, that I wanted to keep doing where the, you know, where the work and the play
overlapped a little bit. And I, you know, I thought about things like music that I care about a lot
and about running that I obviously care about a lot. And I thought, what is the possible way
that I can have a chance of maybe pursuing some of these interests of mine in a professional way.
And journalism seemed that that's what I think what pointed me to journalism is that it wouldn't
be easy, but there may be a chance that I could end up writing about running or travel or music
or something like that. Now, at this point, Alex, you've obviously got tons of athletic
experience as a runner. Your background in physics means you're, there's nothing quantitatively you
can't understand. Had you at this point delved into the physiology of running or was that not
yet something you had really fully explored the depths of yet? By the standards of what I would
say now is no, I didn't have a clue. I knew nothing. Now I was the kind of guy who when I got into
running in high school, I got books about running. And, you know, one of the first books I got was
Tim Nokes is the Laura or Tim Nokes is Laura of running, which is 900 and something pages. And
the first 300 pages or so or physiology. I didn't really understand the physiology when I went
through it, but I was familiar with the terms. And there's some other, I'm looking over at my shelf
right now. I can, you know, I've still got my original 1990 copy of Laura of running right there.
And there's a book called Better Training for Distance Runners, which is written, co-written
by a physiologist, which, so I had read all that stuff and I had this, so I could talk this sort of,
I don't know how to put this. I could talk about VO2 max and lactate threshold with other people
who were interested in this stuff, but I wouldn't say I had a deep understanding of where it came
from. I had a superficial acquaintance with the concepts. So begins another apprenticeship,
basically, which is now you're getting to learn physiology as you start to write more and more
about these topics. Yeah. And then there was, you know, this was not right away, I will say. I did
one year of journalism school, and then I had 16 months as an intern at a newspaper called the
Ottawa Citizen, which had a great internship program at the time. And I was, you know, covering
car accidents and dog fashion shows and, you know, what have you. I learned to write. I learned to
write on deadline. I wrote, you know, 250 stories or something. You mentioned being prolific. Like
when you're the lowest man on the totem pole at a daily newspaper, you learn to write fast, you know,
multiple stories a day. And then, you know, my internship finished and I became freelance,
not because I had a bold vision, but because there were no jobs. And, you know, initially,
my first contact through a friend was with the bottom line, which you may, your subscription
may have lapsed, but it's Canada's accounting monthly. So I went to some conferences on like
forensic accounting and stuff like that. And so I didn't immediately, because in a sense,
I was running away from physics and running was still a bit of a, you know, a tender spot. I sort
of poured so much into it. So I wasn't looking to necessarily immerse myself right away in these
things. And it's only, I would say it was about 2008. So a couple of years after I finished
journalism school and after I finished my newspaper internship that I started to get into writing about
the science of running to sort of bring those two interests together.
Go back to that internship at the Ottawa Citizen. I want to understand a little bit more about
what you learned in journalism school as it pertained to teaching you how to write. And then
what you learned sort of during that internship where you're, you know, you're, you're on the
ground, right? It's the, it's the, it's the rubber meeting the road, so to speak. What were the two
different skill sets there? And how can somebody, I'm asking this for purely selfish reasons,
by the way, how can somebody who's constantly interested in improving their writing learn from
that, if they're neither able to go to journalism school nor take a formal internship for a
newspaper where they have an editor that's giving them feedback constantly, presumably.
Yeah. So I would say what I got out of journalism school was an understanding of the jargon for one
thing, but also the forms. We tend to think of writing as, as a, you know, you think of what you
want to say, and then you write it down. In high school, a lot of us learned the, you know, the,
the hamburger essay. There's five paragraphs and introduction. Then there's three main points and
there's a conclusion. And in each, you have a topic sentence in each paragraph, yada, yada, yada. So
there's this really rigid structure. And what I don't think I realized until I went to journalism
school is that there are underlying forms for most of the articles we read. And a news story
has a very specific form. It's called the inverted pyramid and a feature article with the kind of
thing you read in the New Yorker or something. It also has a certain form. Now, for good writers,
that form is invisible and that form is also played with and your expectations are, are,
you know, dashed. Sometimes you, you think, you know, where the story is going and then it goes
somewhere else yet. And so on and so on. The point isn't that you need to be slavishly
sort of following those forms, but you need to understand what the forms are. So you can
understand when you're deviating from them, you're doing it on purpose and you can understand
what a reader's expectation is, even if the reader himself or herself doesn't realize what that
expectation is. And so there's things like, yeah, you need to have a billboard paragraph that tells
the reader what to expect. And it depends. Anyway, I'll just sum up by saying that I learned about
form. Now learning about form is not the same as, as mastering the form. And so you go to, to an
internship at a daily paper and actually, you know, good internships, hopefully you're getting an
editor who's looking at your stuff and you're getting a little feedback, but the real, the
reality is it's, it's a, you know, it's a daily beast. And there's not a lot of time for that,
but you're writing sometimes three stories in a day, but certainly typically a story a day,
you're rarely getting more than a day to write a story. And you're getting a sense from, from
editors and from other people of what's working and what's not. And you can see what's working
and what's not. And so there's the just doing it part of it. But I think that would have been
harder to benefit from if I didn't have a sense of, of, of what the structures are
that, that you're, that you're trying to transcend. You're trying to be more than just
plugging in the pieces of a, of a jigsaw puzzle. But I mean, I, I give a talk on science writing
a while ago to some, some postdocs and, and some grad students. And I was, you know, really the,
the main point I wanted to get to them is that every piece of writing has form, whether it's a,
you know, a grant application or a, you know, a scientific publication, or particularly,
particularly a lot of scientists are interested in communicating their, their, their results to
a wider public. And they have to understand what the, you know, if they're writing for a newspaper
op-ed page, what, what is the form? And I, and I guess the other thing I say said in that context
is also understanding who the audience is. So, and that those two things are interlinked. If you,
if you understand who the audience is, you understand what their expectations are in terms
of what the piece is going to flow like. So anyway, that's what that boils down to is,
is obviously doing lots of it, but also trying to look at the writing that you like, the stuff that
when, if you, if you see a book or an article that, that, that you like, or that explains things
clearly, trying to, trying to break down like, so what are they doing here? What, what makes this
work? You know, did they have a particular, you know, a particularly good introduction section or,
you know, whatever the case may be. So reading critically, I guess is what I'm saying.
I almost wonder if it's somewhat like athletes where you could have the same debate about good
writers being born versus made, you know, I, in terms of scientific writers, I, I think
Sid Mukherjee is incredible. And I read his stuff and I, I, it's no different than, you know,
watching a remarkable athlete do something and you sort of think to yourself, there's probably
no way ever that I could write like that. Even if I devoted the every waking moment of my remaining
life to this study, any more than I could swim or bike or run as well as, you know, the most
amazing athlete I see doing those things. Do you, do you think that there's a parallel there?
I think there's a parallel and I would extend the parallel, which is that
we can look at Michael Phelps swimming and say, I will never be able to swim like that. But it's
a mistake to then say swimming is all, all genetic and therefore I am doomed not to get better at
swimming than I am right now. And, and most people don't come anywhere close to fulfilling their
quote unquote genetic potential. So for sure. And I, you know, especially when I read fiction or when
I read nonfiction by good fiction writers who know how to write nonfiction, if it's not to get too
confusing and the level of language and just imagery, to be honest, it's sometimes a little
depressing to me because it's, I feel the same as you. I'm like, yeah, there's nothing, there's no
amount of, you know, workshops or practice that it will make me write like that. And so I think
another thing is just to kind of, I don't know, this, maybe this is to defeat us, but own who you
are. And so I know that for me, I'm not a poetic writer, but what I hope to be is a very clear
expository and explanatory writer. So I will never paint the picture that I really admire in some
other writers writing, but hopefully I can, I can excel at it at another aspect of it.
Yeah, no, that's actually a great way to compare the two. So with that, let's, let's go into some
of this stuff around, well, let's just start with sort of something you've already alluded to.
Let's explain what it is, talk about how much it matters, and then kind of get into some examples.
So let's, let's start with a term that many people have heard before, but I don't think most people
understand what VO two max really means. And eventually we're going to talk about running
efficiency and lactate threshold, and we're going to get into all this stuff. But let's, let's make
sure people understand what VO two max is both in an absolute term, and then in a manner that we
normalize it by, by weight and what it is and what it isn't, how it's measured and how it matters.
And maybe we'll even talk about some notable exceptions. Sure. Yeah. So VO two max is the
one physiological parameter that anyone who's involved in endurance has heard of and, and has
some sense of, and the, the sort of the first order analogy is it's kind of the size of your engine.
So physiologically VO two max is telling you how much oxygen or how quickly you can take oxygen
from the air into your lungs, pump it, get it into your blood, pump it to your muscles, and then have
your muscles use it in the metabolic processes that will provide energy to move you to do whatever
you want to do. So it's, it's a rate. It's how much oxygen per unit time can you process absolutely
flat out. Now the sort of backstory here is it was, it was first sort of discussed or measured
in the 1920s by a guy named AV Hill, who was actually a very good runner. And the observation
that he made is if you have someone, you ask someone to go out and run at a, at a gentle pace,
they'll consume, let's say two liters of oxygen per per minute. Then you tell them to speed up. Now
they're doing three liters of oxygen per minute. Tell them to speed up again. And now they're going
pretty much, maybe not as fast as they can, but they're going fast and they're using four liters
of oxygen per minute. And so you tell them to speed up again and you measure it and they're like, oh,
they're only using four liters of oxygen a minute. Just like last time. So speed up again. And they're
still just using four liters of oxygen a minute. There's a plateau. There's a point at which even
though you're working harder, you're not using any more oxygen. And so this plateau looks like
it's a physiological limitation and it probably is in some sense, you know, it's a controversial
thing, but basically you've reached a point where no matter how hard you push yourself, you can't
get more oxygen. And so you can still go faster because you're starting to use other forms of
energy, but this is the limits of your aerobic system. This tells you, well, what it tells you,
we can get into, it's not clear what it tells you, but it tells you, it tells you exactly what
I just said. It tells you how much, how much oxygen you can use. Does that tell you exactly
how fast you can run? No, there's a, there are a lot of other factors, but it's, that tells you
what sort of aerobic engine you have to play with. Now people have, you know, I mean, as I remember
in high school, I mean, we would sort of talk about, well, which athletes have the highest VO2 max?
Is it the Norwegian cross country skiers? Is the professional runners and cyclists and things like
that. But people are usually used to hearing these numbers reported, not in liters per minute,
but in milliliters per minute per kilogram. So give an example. So people understand those
differences. Cause we usually talk about the outliers is a, is a number that's a bigger number
than two liters or five liters. It would be, you know, sort of 75, 80 milliliters per year. Just
explain to people how, how those are different. Sure. So I'll use my own numbers. When I, you
know, typically when I was tested, I could get about a little bit more than five liters per minute.
So 5.1, 5.2, if I remember correctly. Now, if you compared me to a rower, the row would make me look
pathetic because the rower would be using seven liters a minute or more. But the rower is also
huge, you know, twice my size or whatever. And, and, and so that doesn't necessarily mean that
that rower is better at using oxygen for me because the rower has way more muscle. And so the
rower is, is, is the amount of oxygen reaching any given muscle cell may be lower. So if you want to
compare apples to apples between athletes of different sizes, you divide at least for a crude
approximation, you just divide by weight. And so the numbers we usually hear are rather than
liters of oxygen per minute, it's milliliters of oxygen per minute per kilogram of body weight.
So for me, five liters of oxygen per per minute works out to something like 80 milliliters
of oxygen per minute per kilogram of body weight. So, and, and, you know, there's a whole rabbit
hole to go into is to say, well, why are we dividing by whole body weight? Because, you know,
there's a bunch of things like skeleton, you know, there's not an organs and stuff that don't scale.
The adipose tissue doesn't matter. I mean, you could argue a better comparison would be
total liters per minute divided by lean mass divided by time or normalized to time. And then
you're, you know, you're at least getting the metabolically active tissue, presumably.
Yeah. And, and, you know, there's papers where they do things like let's divide by weight to
the power of 0.68 or 0.7, which is another way of getting it effectively. It's a way of approximating
just the lean mass, the metabolically active tissue. So, and you can go down that rabbit hole,
but as, as, as I suspect what you'll want to get to is like at a certain point, it, it, it doesn't
matter that much anyway. So we don't need to, to like view, you can't just measure someone's view
to max and know how fast they're going to race. So it's, it's, it's useful, but it's not, it's
especially for comparing between people. Now comparing within yourself, it tells you something
if you've increased or if your view to max has decreased, but in that sense, it doesn't matter
what, what you're dividing by. I remember there was a guy that I used to ride with, and this was
not that long ago, maybe five or six years ago when I was still, you know, somewhat competitive,
at least with myself. Um, and, uh, actually it's funny. My number was just like yours,
except I was heavier. So I was about 5.1 to 5.2 liters, but I weighed more. So that worked out to
about 70 mils per MiG per KIG was my VO two max. His was 55 to 60, but I, there was never a day
that I could ride faster than him. Not one there simply. And I always felt like, although we did
the test so many times, I kept feeling like the machine must've been broken on him. Like I knew
my 70 was about right because I'd been tested so much. And that was lower than it had been when I
was younger. So it seemed appropriate, but I was always convinced that that there's no way he's
only 55. The reality of it is he may well have been, and he may have simply been a far more
efficient athlete, which we're going to get into. Um, before we get to the story of Oscar Svensson,
let's talk a little bit about historically what people have believed the limits are of VO two max.
Yeah, you know what? We don't, I mean, we don't even have to go very far historically to get into
a whole mudslide of, of confusion and debate and, and, and disagreement. Um, there's, there's a lot
of places along the, the way that, that could in some circumstances be the bottleneck. Uh, normally
people tend to assume that, um, so what, what is it that causes VO two max to plateau is essentially
I think what we're talking about. And, and, and just one thing I should add here, it's like,
why is that interesting? It's because you think, well, if you want to measure endurance,
just have someone run a mile or whatever, you know, as hard as they can. But any test like that
depends on motivation, depends on whether you pace it right. There's all these factors that come into
it. The nice thing about VO two max is that in theory it's independent of, uh, of motivation.
That's why people, that's why scientists like it. Cause it doesn't matter if, if, if, you know,
the, the, the subject doesn't really care about the study. If you see a plateau, you know,
that's, that's a property of their body and not a product of whether they were excited about
the study. So the question, yeah, the question is this plateau, what is it that causes it? And
it could be in the lungs, it could be the heart, it could be the circulation, it could be the
muscles ability to extract it. And I don't want to pretend that I know the answer because it's
still controversial that the picture that emerges is that almost every part along this cascade
is engineered right to the point more or less to what it needs to be. And so if you perturb any of
those, uh, those elements, it could, you can get limitations. So for example, the conventional
wisdom is that your lungs are not a limitation. You can always breathe enough in. And so then
the question is, can you, uh, uh, diffuse enough oxygen from your lungs into your bloodstream and
so on and so forth. Um, there are situations where, and it's been for decades, it's been
conventional wisdom that the lungs don't respond to training because they're overbuilt. Uh, there
was just a paper published a big review, uh, in the last month or two, arguing that, you know,
in some cases the lungs aren't overbuilt. And one of the situations is highly trained endurance
athletes. They can be limited by their ability to, uh, to, to get enough oxygen in. And you can also
run into situations where an athlete is so fit, their heart is so strong, it can, uh, it pumps
blood past your lungs so quickly that it doesn't have time to fully stock up on oxygen. You get
something called exercise induced arterial hypoxemia. So this, this is usually an issue
at altitude, but in elite endurance athletes is actually about half of them exhibited even at sea
level. So they're already running into a limitation just in getting oxygen from their lungs to their
bloodstream. And then at every stage of the way, there can be limitations if anything is knocked
off kilter, uh, and, and certainly right down to the ability of the muscles to first extract the
oxygen from the bloodstream and then to, to make use of it metabolically in the, in the mitochondria.
So it's there, there isn't one single answer, which is why you get these debates because everyone is
going to say, I have evidence that this is the limit. It's like, yeah, but I have evidence that
this is the limit and that's the limit and they're all the limit. Yeah. I've always wanted to see the
experiment where you took a group of athletes and maybe this has been done. Um, and you, you run them
all to max and then you reduce the FIO two of the incoming oxygen. So normally we do it with room
air. So you're getting a fractional inhalation of oxygen is 21%. And the way, of course, just for the
listener, the way these things work is the way they're calculating how much oxygen is being
consumed as they're measuring the, uh, the concentration of oxygen on the way out. So you're
calculating the Delta. And so I've always thought, well, wouldn't it be interesting to start
selectively dropping FIO two 21%, 20%, 19%, 18%. Now, presumably if the lungs aren't the limitation,
you should still see the same absolute Delta and you could at least start to eliminate one of those
variables, which would be FIO two and capillary exchange. And then you start pointing to some of
these other variables. Again, I'm sure somebody has done this experiment, but, uh, I don't know
what it yielded. Yeah. Probably not with the fine tooth comb that, that, that you're suggesting
people have compared, you know, 21% to 10% or whatever and 15%. And, uh, yeah, it's hard. I
mean, it's interesting. It's, it's interesting when you go to altitude or, or, you know, or the
equivalent, when you reduce the amount of oxygen, uh, funny things happen. Like there's, you know,
the, the first thing you would think would happen is like, you can't get enough oxygen. So you're
going to go anaerobic sooner. You're going to produce more lactate. And yet the opposite happens.
There's something called the lactate paradox. If you, if you try and exercise to exhaustion
at lower levels of altitude, you actually give up when your lactate levels are lower than you
would at sea level. And so, and, and there's debate about what causes this and even whether it's a
real thing. But the, the picture that, that makes sense to me is, is that it's, these things are not
just about how much oxygen is making it to the muscle. It's also like, what is the, what is your
brain oxygen level? And so you're, you're getting these other circuit breakers that are starting to
come down. They're not even on this path from mouth to lungs to, to blood to, to muscle. There,
there's other factors that are saying, whoa, wait a second. Oxygen is getting a little low. So we're
going to actually cut off the supply to the muscles or reduce it in order to make sure that
we don't get stupid. So prior to Oscar, how, how, because I want to talk about this kid,
his story is so interesting and you wrote a, you wrote a great article about it. And I've,
I've read many articles about him, including articles in, you know, physiologic journals.
You'd had a couple sort of freaks in nature out there in the nineties, right? So
90 plus milliliters per per kilogram per minute of a VO two max. What happens in
sort of a garden variety day of December, 2012, do you remember, do you remember when this,
when he shows up to a training lab, he's what, how old is he? He's like 17 or something.
It's like 17. I think he was, he was a former downhill skier who had taken like a talent
screen to see whether he'd be suitable for something like cycling. And he'd, I think he'd
scored just untrained just off, off the downhill slopes. He was 74 or something like that,
74 milliliters per kilogram per minute. And, and so that he passed. And so he started training as
a cyclist as a teenager and then, you know, pretty quickly scored 83, then 85, then 92.
And then he ended up scoring the initial reports that was he, were that he scored 97.5. But I think
when the science scientific journal came out, they said it was 96.7. Yeah. Which either way
was still higher than had ever been recorded in human history. And well, and so, and you know,
one thing we should, we should say is there are reports of people in their nineties, but reports
VO two max high, high VO two max numbers are they, they sprout very easily because it's hard to do
these tests. Right. And in fact, a lot of the tests that people, the garden variety machinery
used to do these tests is not designed to handle seven liters of oxygen per minute. And so you get
spurious results and you get, so the, the, the previous King was a guy named Bjorn Dally, a Norwegian,
the greatest cross country skier in history, who in the late nineties reputedly tested 90s, 96, 96.0,
or 96.6, depending on who you ask. This was never published in a journal. This was basically,
the, the Norwegian ski team leaked it to the press as a kind of PR move. And I asked a guy who,
who was working in Norway at the time and he said, they didn't believe the machine. He, he,
he didn't believe the machine was correctly calculated, calibrated, but he, he think he
figured they decided that it was a good PR move anyway. So, so when we're talking about high
numbers and there's, you know, Matt Carpenter, 92, Kelly and journey, every, there's a lot of people
who have high numbers, virtually none of them are published in the scientific literature.
The highest values, you know, you go back to the seventies where, uh, some, some of the great
runners were tested and you get, you know, Steve Prefontaine was 84 and there aren't a lot of
published values above the high eighties. So 96.7 is like, it's higher than the rumors,
but it's way higher than the verified numbers. So the first thing they did the next day is
they disassemble the machine, the metabolic cart and send it back to the manufacturer to get it
calibrated to find out if they, you know, are we nuts? Is this real? Is this true? And it came back
that yeah, it's working and all the other tests that Matt did.
Yeah, exactly. All the other tests that were done in that day were all within line.
Yeah. So, you know, so they figured this is real. And so they, they eventually, I mean,
this, the story is longer after his retirement, they, they, they published the data and shared it,
which was pretty cool. Well, I think the other thing it was very compelling was he was tested
again several months later. He put on two and a half kilos. So his number came down into the
eighties, but his absolute level of maximal oxygen consumption had barely come down. He went from
something like 7.2 liters to 7.1 liters. But the number came down from, you know, call it whatever
it was, 96 and change to 89 and change, which was accounted for by the gain in weight, which again,
is effectively like repeating the test and getting the same result.
I agree. To me, to me, that's the, actually the number one piece of data is that, that test,
that off season test a few months later, later in that year, it's like, okay, well,
he's doing the same amount of oxygen. We understand that people can put on weight and lose weight,
but the absolute value of 7.2 or whatever is suggests that this was a real number. And,
and, you know, the other thing to say is after he, as at 17 or whatever it was, after he clocked
that 96 couple of weeks later, he goes to the world junior championships and wins the time trial
there. So on the surface, it's like that goes to show if you have a big engine, you're going to be
a superstar. But of course the flip side of that and where I, the reason I brought this up was to
say, why do most people listening to this who might even be able to recognize the, you know,
the best time trialists in the world, the Bradley Wiggins of the world, you know, no longer active,
but you know, the, the, the people who go on to win grand tours and stuff, why don't we know this
guy's name? Yeah. So he turned pro, you know, when he turned 20 with an, he was with an under 23 team
called Joker. He was an okay cyclist. He did, he had some good results. He had some bad results.
I think it probably didn't help that, you know, he got a lot of attention for this VO two max
value. So I think the expectations were probably out of line with, with what was reasonable, both
from his own expectations and, and other people's, and he ended up retiring. I think he was 23,
maybe like he took a break and then he officially announced his retirement when he was around 23,
went back to university and he's done. He's, he's gone. So the aftermath was that there was a,
a paper published, I don't know if I think it was about a year ago that sort of reanalyze or responded
to when they published his data and said, well, let's look at not just his history of VO two max
values. Let's look at his efficiency at each point along the line. So over the course of three or
three years or whatever it was where he had multiple VO two max tests. And you see this
expected pattern, he starts at 74 and he goes 80 something, 80 something, 90 something, 96.
And then he comes back down the ladder. He, you know, by the time he, after he retired from
cycling, he was back down to 77. So he's right back where he started. That's it. That's a simple
story. But if you look at the efficiency, you get a much more interesting story, which is that
he started out at his most efficient when he was untrained. And the more he trained,
the less efficient he got, meaning that he could, he could deliver more oxygen to his
muscles. He could, he could deliver more aerobic energy, but he, he used more aerobic energy
in order to maintain a given pace. So, so let's, let's make sure folks understand how that's
calculated. So now you look at a different graph where on the X axis you show wattage,
which is the universal metric of output in cycling. And on the Y axis, you show oxygen consumption.
And so now you're looking at a graph that says for a given output, how much oxygen, how much
input do you need to get this output? And an athlete over time should get better and better
for a fixed wattage. You want to see what's called PVO to come down. So power at a given VO2
should actually come down as you get better in running. This would be the V VO2 you want to get
faster as, as, so for a given oxygen consumption, you want velocity to go up just as you would want
power to go up. I might've said it backwards earlier, but I think you know what I'm saying.
And, and so I gotta be honest with you. I was actually very surprised by that. I would have,
I wouldn't, I would have been less surprised if it had been unchanged, but I was very surprised
that it deteriorated. Yeah. And there's, there's lots of debates about whether you can improve it,
but to actually see it get worse was, was so clearly and so kind of monotonically, there was
inverse relationship was definitely surprising. And it actually plays into a longstanding debate,
which is the question of, is there an inverse relationship between VO2 max and economy or
inefficiency? So if you, if you build your engine bigger, do you necessarily end up with a less
efficient engine? And this debate has been going on for a couple of decades now and there's still
no consensus. And one, so one way of, because if you look at, if you just take a bunch of elite
athletes and you measure their economy, whether it's runners or cyclists and you measure their
VO2 max, you tend to see an inverse relationship. The people who have the highest VO2 max tend to
have slightly lower, slightly worse economies and people, and the people who have the best economy
tend to have slightly worse VO2 max. There's a lot of possible explanations for this. One is that
you don't tend to hit the lottery twice. So if you happen to have a VO2 max that's 92, then
you're not, you're, you're, you're not that lucky. You're not going to have the best possible economy.
And if you're only looking at elite athletes, that means that everyone else there is going to
have something special. So if they don't have the best VO2 max by definition, they have to have a
great economy because they have to have something that's exceptional. And so you see this inverse
relationship that either you have good economy or you have good VO2 max.
Just to be clear, that's because we've selected for people whose dot product of those two things
is the best in the world. Yeah. To be in this, if you're looking at elite athletes, they have to
have won at least one lottery, but they're unlikely to win two lotteries because we're already looking
at the 0.001%. So it's, it's, it's, it's highly unlikely that you're going to have hit the lottery
twice. But so what the Oscars Fenson data points to is, is a different explanation, which is that
there's actually a trade-off that if you're optimizing one physiological parameter, it may
come at the cost of the other physiological parameter that the training he did, which we can
sort of surmise must have been pretty good for increasing VO2 max because he got such a high one,
may have actually been bad for his economy, not in the sense that his, you know, his legs were
wobbling or he was had bad, you know, motion, but at a metabolic level that, and there was a paper
published. So the, again, in response to the Fenson case study, reanalyzing his data and pointing to a
potential cell level explanation of what's happening to certain enzymes at a given point.
The biochemistry, frankly, is beyond me, you know, to, to, to fully understand. But basically what
they're saying is if your mitochondria are being stressed to the, if you're, if you're doing a lot
of training that requires very high, like VO2 max level outputs, your metabolism, your cells need to
make choices to produce high output instead of to be as efficient as possible. And over time,
that's what you'll get better at and you'll lose that efficiency. And so you'll, you'll pay a slight
penalty for, for optimizing your training for VO2 max. Yeah. So that was, that was, that was
kind of my take, which was not knowing more about his training was what would happen if you took
that engine, if you took that, that genetic gift and instead of maximizing on VO2 max and pushing
him from, I mean, a guy that gets out of bed in the morning or falls off a log at 74 is a freak
of nature. But instead of pushing him to 96, you train him and he'd, he'd get up to 85 or 90 maybe,
but you put much more effort into sort of zone two where you're right at lactate of two. So you push
him. And by the way, for him, that would be like, if you looked, I remember looking in the paper and
applied physiology, I mean, you know, he's spending a lot of time in the three to 400 watt range,
but he could have probably been in the sort of 300 to about the 300 watt range where he's still
just under two millimole of lactate, but he's dramatically increasing mitochondrial efficiency.
And if that represented two thirds of his volume, yes, he'd have a lower VO2 max,
but he might've been a better cyclist. Yeah. I think certainly putting on the hindsight
spectacles, I, you know, a hundred percent agree, but whatever he did, he paid too high a price
for that VO2 max. I mean, but just by definition, it didn't work out. And it certainly, again,
we don't know exactly what his training was, but that makes a lot of sense to me. And I think,
and I think it sort of agrees, and you've talked a lot about this, but with the sort of prevailing
wisdom among endurance athletes is that yeah, you know, 80% of your training should be easy,
conversational pace and, you know, what means you use to figure out what pace that is may depend,
or may vary, but yeah, he needed to be doing something that was going to,
at worst, not penalize his efficiency as much as he did.
I mean, I just remember even as an adult, like whenever I wanted to go and have a VO2 max test
just for ego, you wanted it to be as high as it could. Like I would alter my training for four
weeks and lose a couple kilos. Like it's lose two kilos and start doing four to six minute
all out intervals. That was the recipe for raising VO2 max. So abandon all low end and it's
four minutes all out, six minutes mild. And, but those are killing workouts. Those really crush you.
So yeah, there was just like kind of a formula to make it happen. So, so let's,
let's pivot now and talk about something you've also written about that I find
completely amazing from a physiologic standpoint, which is the sub two attempt
and the incredible effort of Kipchoge. So I don't even know where to begin this story,
but again, let's just assume for a moment that listeners aren't familiar with who Kipchoge is,
aren't even familiar with the difference between an official marathon versus a contrived Nike
marathon. Start from the beginning. Okay. So the very beginning, I'll give you the, the,
the medium long version of the story. The very beginning is that in 2014, I wrote an article
for runners world. It was like 10 pages long. I spent months on it analyzing the prospects for
a sub two hour marathon and, you know, talking to a bunch of experts, crunching data, blah, blah,
blah. What would it take? And at the end of that article, my prediction was that it would be
physiologically possible to run a sub two hour marathon and that it would happen sometime around
2075. So that, that was my context and the con, you know, the, I'll, I'll, I'll take ownership of the,
of the prediction, but that's, that's the general sense was that, yeah, it's possible, but it's not
going to happen for a long time. And just to be clear, Alex, what was the world record at the time
and did your prediction speak to an official marathon or any form of marathon? Yeah. Yeah. So
I was thinking about marathons as they are currently run. Although in my article, what I
said is, look, if, if we're going to, if it's going to happen, it's going to happen on an optimized
course. You're not just going to go to any old course. So you're going to choose a course that
optimizes temperature. It optimizes terrain. It optimizes curvature. So there's a lot of things,
you know, you knew right away the way marathons were run and mostly continue to be run. There's
fat on the bone in a way that there isn't in sports like track or, you know, if you look at
the Tour de France, there's fat on the bone, but no one cares about the time compared to track
cycling where everything is optimized. So marathons is, are this kind of anomaly where they're run in
a Tour de France style in a very uncontrolled environment with, which differs from, from race
to race. And yet we care about time. So, and I think that's maybe an anachronism that's going
to fade away a little bit as we realize that, you know, you can, you can run a lot faster if you
optimize the course. But anyway, to answer your question, the world record was 202 57 by a guy
named Dennis Camato. So we're talking three minutes away from a sub two. If you say, how long did it
take us to come down three minutes? Well, when in the mid eighties, I think it was 1986, the world
record was 206 50 by a bologna and in symbol. So we're talking a timescale 86, 90, 30 years to go
four minutes. Yeah, or, or yeah, exactly. So we're looking at, and, and of course the, the things are
getting optimized as we go. So the cur, you expect the curve to be leveling out, the, you know,
there's less and less low hanging fruit to get. So in 2016, uh, I, I heard, I got an assignment
from runners world to, to go report on this top secret Nike project, um, which ended up,
it was, it was something they called breaking to it's a race they held in spring of 2017.
And their mission was basically they'd spent about two or three years, 20 people full time
working on it, trying to, uh, I don't know how to say it to engineer a sub two hour marathon.
And so they had a started with a huge talent search. They, they sponsor a large fraction of
the world's best runners. So they brought 20 something of their best runners to labs to
measure their VO two max and their economy and various other things and, uh, pick three runners.
And then they, they, they went around the world, uh, testing possible courses. They ended up
settling on a formula one racetrack in Northern Italy. It was Monza. It was, yeah. With, with,
which, which I think is where they, the, the highest speed ever reached that's on a,
yeah. So, so if you, I'm obsessed with formula one. So if you, uh, if you're interested,
Monza is the fastest formula one circuit. You don't look at the maximum speed. You look at the
fastest average speed. So Monza has the fastest average speed of any formula one circuit. There
are other characteristics that make formula one circuits interesting, which have the highest G
forces, which have the highest straightaway speeds, those things, but yeah, Monza has the fastest,
highest average speed. And of course, doesn't have much elevation change, which is probably even more
important, right? Yeah. So they use the junior loop, I think it was called at that at Monza. So
not the full one, because that was the straightest possible with just the barely perceptible curves.
I think it was about a mile and a half loop or something like that. Um, it's also like that,
you know, the, it doesn't have much elevation change. It's, it's close to sea level, but it's
not close to the sea, which makes the weather a little more predictable. Um, they, they optimized
a lot of different things. You know, they're trying to optimize the nutrition, the in-race
nutrition, the aerodynamics, they're like doing things like sticking bump adhesive bumps onto
the legs of the runners to try and reduce the air, the drag when they're swinging their legs back and
forth. Some of it's a little ridiculous. Um, some of it was significant. Uh, the two significant
things were they were going to have, uh, I think it was one, two, three, four, five, five pace,
it was five or seven pacemakers running, running in front of the, the, yeah. So basically, uh, yeah,
uh, blocking the wind for the chosen runners for the whole way. Now you can't hire someone to run
at sub two hour marathon in order to run a sub two hour marathon. So they had to have
runners dropping out every couple of laps and new runners swapping in. That's not allowed according
to, uh, the rule, the official rules of marathoning. So that's the main reason that this race that
Nike had planned was it was not and is not considered a world record. Um, because it
doesn't obey those rules. And then the other, the other factor, the big factor is they introduced
a new, uh, a whole new type of shoe that had a curved carbon fiber plate embedded in the sole
that improves running economy. In other words, it allows you to burn less energy
to sustain a given pace by about 4% on average. So put all these things together and all of a
sudden it's like, we don't actually need the runners to be that much faster than two or two
57. If all these things we've come up with work, we should be able to slice three minutes off the
time with the shoes and the drafting and the course and the weather and all these sorts of things.
Um, the three run of the three runners, they ended up selecting Elliott Kipchoge is,
was the reigning Olympic champion. And he was also probably the most consistent in the best
marathoner in the world at that time. He was, I think he had the second, second or third fastest
time in history at that point. And then they had a couple of other guys who had good, good lab
values. One of them had the best running efficiency ever measured. Um, but neither of those guys
ended up being a factor. Kipchoge ended up running two flat 25 at this Nike breaking two race. So 25
seconds, uh, two and a half minutes faster than the world record didn't run sub two, but was that
was considered a victory because it was like nobody thought anyone would even with all the
sort of science and tech, nobody thought that it would actually add up to a human running that fast.
So then there was a, a sequel in, in 2019, uh, funded by the petrochemical company in EOS instead
of Nike in, in Vienna, which basically replicated most of what breaking two had done. They only
brought Kipchoge in. They had a few different things. They had a new pair of shoes, um, which
is what became a very, very controversial. And this time Kipchoge ran one 59 40. Um, so he ran
a sub two marathon and it, and it, it, uh, has, has sort of galvanized and polarized the running
world because, uh, Kipchoge is the greatest marathoner in history, I would say, but these,
these events, uh, left a bad taste in the mouths of a lot of people, both for their, the sort of
circus like quality, but also because of the shoes, the shoes became, uh, very controversial
because it's not clear whether shoes that make you 4% more efficient with a carbon fiber plate
embedded in them are, are within the spirit of the sport or within the rules of the sport.
I mean, this sounds an awful lot like where swimming was in 2008 and 2009, when the tech
suits from basically 2000 to 2008 had gotten so quick that by 2009, Fina said, this is going to
be the, this world championships in 09 will be the last time there are technical suits and away
they went. And actually there are still some world records that stand, you know, 12 years later, uh,
nearly 12 years later from, from those two. The surprising thing to me is that, is that all,
not all of them stand because I am at the time I remember interviewing some swimmers and saying,
so, you know, how does it feel? Do you think you will never again set a personal best? There was
this sense that, uh, banning those suits would, would just completely, uh, change the record book.
But it has turned out that swimming has continued to advance. I guess there's advances in pool
technology and stuff like that, but, uh, um, but yeah, it's exactly analogous debate. You know,
what role should the equipment play in a sport that is not like formula one that is,
whose, whose inherent, uh, attraction is its simplicity.
But to play devil's advocate, right? I mean, um, would, would the current running shoes you
would wear if you were out to, if you were to go out and run a marathon, would they offer a 4%
efficiency over leather you would strap to your feet? It's a good question. I,
I think they would, they would raise my chance of getting to the finish without injuring myself
because cushioning is, is the big advance. The better or maybe the more, the more sort of pointed
analogy is, um, cinder tracks in the, were common until the sixties. Then you have all
weather tracks. I mean, it's, it's, it's, it's apples to, to, to, to pairs or whatever. Um, so I think
Yeah. Or look, we're looking at cycling, right? I mean, consider a bicycle today versus a bicycle
20 years ago, not a hundred years ago, just look. I mean, if you look at the, the, the, the, the,
the bikes written in the late nineties versus today, they, they're not even the same thing.
I mean, they're, they're not even close. Well, the hour record is such a classic example of that
because cycling did try and say, you know what, let's make it about the cyclist, not the cyclists.
We're going to all ride the 1972 Eddie Merck special and for the hour record and the response
to the cycling world was like, okay, we're not interested in the hour record anymore. Forget
about it. It's, it's, it's uninteresting to us to go ride this stupid 1972 bike. Um, and until they
changed the rules again in whatever it was, 2015 or something. And all of a sudden everyone's like,
Hey, all right. Now we're, now we're interesting. And so yeah, yeah. I mean, I think the, the key
that, that, that I would say in agreeing with you is that anyone who thinks that
the progress of the sport over the last 10 years, much less 50 years, much less a hundred years
is all about, well, we've learned more and we're digging deeper is kidding themselves. Technology
is baked into the improvement curve changes in circumstances, environment, and technology are
baked into those curves right from the get-go. Now you can still, you can acknowledge that and
still say, yeah, I want the, I understand the curves going like this, but I don't want it to go,
to drop off a cliff. And the world records have been absolutely knocked silly in the last two
years since the issues have become common. I still think it's, you know, I think it was a
tough call to, I don't think it was obvious that you could ban them until they'd already been used
enough to realize that, Oh, wait, this is real. Uh, this is a big advantage by which time it was
kind of too late to ban them. Because the thing is, I mean, as a guy who follows this stuff
relatively closely, I'm used to press releases every year, if not every day that promise to
upend the sport, and this is going to be the newest, greatest, latest, best thing. It's, you
know, so you ignore that stuff. And so even if Nike had said, Hey, by the way, um, just a heads up
to world athletics, we've got these shoes and they're crazy. Are they, you know, is it okay that
we introduce them? And all the ingredients of the shoes were, had been, are things that had been
used before. So there was nothing like, there was no like coiled spring in it. Carbon fiber plates
had been used before, including to set world records. So there was nothing, it's just Nike got
the recipe, right. They got it so right that it, it changed the sport and it in the long run,
things will settle back into parody and we won't worry about it. But there was a period about 2016
to 2019 where it's like, if you didn't have the right shoes, you probably weren't going to win
the race. And that, that is a little unfortunate. So where do you, I mean, where do you think this
all fits into your prediction, whatever year that was 2014, I mean, where do you, when do you think
two hours will be broken on a legitimate road course with full marathon rules that will
constitute a world record? So that means it also has to be a marathon that ends and starts in the
same place. It can't be a, you know, one and done downhill like Boston or something like that.
Um, is that, do you, do you revise your estimate of whatever year you gave?
Oh yeah, for sure. No, it's not going to be 2075, which coincidentally was going to be my
hundredth birthday. So maybe that was subconsciously influencing me, but the answer depends on what
you define as legit. Is there something illegitimate about holding a marathon on a loop course?
I don't see it. I mean, marathons, you know, it used to be, they were a big deal in like Madison
Square Garden back in the late 1800s. You know, there's nothing inherent about saying
you shouldn't run it in a circle. Um, yes, we love the big city marathon experience and it brings
the people together, yada, yada, yada. But if you're trying to break the two hour marathon,
the goal is not to, you know, be inclusive. Um, so there's things like that. Uh, here's another
thing they did. They said, we don't have a start time. We're not, we're not starting Saturday at,
at 7am. We're starting sometime between Friday at 7am and Sunday at 7am or whatever. And we're
going to look at the weather forecast and we're going to make a call the day before,
like 12 hours before, so we can get the absolute optimal weather. Is that cheating or is that
smart having a launch window? So there's a lot of things like that. The key thing I think is,
um, two key things. One is pacemaking. You can't have people jumping in halfway. That's the number
one thing they have to change for me to consider it like a legit sub two hour marathon. So you're
going to have to attract like the second best runners in the world to go and to have them work
together so that, you know, one group is leading through halfway. And then the second group is
going to lead, uh, you know, to 30 K or something, something, and then they're going to drop out and
and the chosen runners do it alone. So you're going to have to optimize that to do that. You're
going to need a ton of money. And more generally, you're going to need a ton of money to put on it.
I would estimate Nike spent tens of millions of dollars on its breaking two race.
So my 20 75 prediction did not bake any of that stuff into it. But now that we've had a sub two
and now that the official world record is two Oh one 39, if I'm remembering correctly,
you know, we're within shouting distance of the two hour. I think some of those other factors may
come together that someone tries to put together a breaking two style race that still falls within
the bounds of legitimate. So I would say that could happen anytime in the next 10 years.
When's it going to happen? Just like it's a race. We showed up to Berlin or Boston or New York or
whatever. And someone happens to run sub two. I think that's still a long way away because
again, the progress has not been in humanity. The progress has been in understanding where the fat
on the bone is and cutting that away systematically. So if you take away all technology, what is the
difference between Roger Bannister and the fastest Myler today? Again, get rid of shoes,
get rid of all of that. As a species, we have not evolved. So how much of that difference is
technology? How much of it is training, nutrition, everything else you'd bake into it? I mean,
what would be the buckets you would you would classify as the improvements? And what is the,
I don't even know what the mile record is today. Mile records 343. So 17 seconds.
Yeah. So for Bannister to today, the biggest bucket bar none is training.
Bannister is reputedly an under reporter. There was this sort of whiff of amateurism where admitting
you were training too hard was not done. But even if you take with a grain of salt as reports,
it was sort of half an hour a day, go out and do 10 by 600 or 10 by 400 meters. So we're talking
four or five miles a day, five, six days a week. Maybe he was doing more than that sometimes,
but he was training at a level, a very, very light level. And even one of his contemporaries was
Emil Zatapek who was a check runner. Just a legend. I mean, yeah, absolutely. Arguably the greatest
runner ever. Yeah, exactly. He was starting to push the boundaries of how hard you could train.
He was a guy who was going out and doing 60 by 400 instead of 10 by 400. And so it's not like
nobody understood that training worked, but Bannister versus today, it's training is the difference.
Cinder's maybe a second to lap, like the track quality, the quality of the spikes,
negligible and nutrition for a mile. It's not just not that big a deal for a four minute race.
If you fast forward to the sixties, by the sixties, you've got people like Jim Ryan who ran 351 for
the mile as a teenager. He's training like a beast. Most people could not handle, even modern
milers would not dare to train as hard as hard as he trained. He survived it as a result.
He was doing, so when I say, so Roger Bannister was 10 by 400 meters. Emil Zatapek was 60 by 400
meters, but they were mostly really slow. It was like another form of endurance. Jim Ryan was 40
by 400 meters, but they were all hard. They were all as close to as hard as Bannister was doing.
On what recovery?
I don't want to claim that I remembered, but we're talking like one to two minutes,
probably or 400 meter jog. It was a very interval based program, but hard, really, really hard.
What would he run those 400s in? How many of them would be sub 60 seconds, all of them?
No, not sub 60. He'd probably be doing those in like 66, 64. I don't know the exact times,
but it's at that volume in the context of high mileage, he was doing them at a pace that was
extremely challenging, not the Zatapek style of just let's get tough and not worry about the pace.
Zatapek's the guy who's in the laundry tub, just doing high knees in the laundry tub,
or holding his breath between phone poles on his run. He was all about just making stuff hard,
whereas Ryan was taking that to a systematic level. We're going to train hard, but we're going
to do it systematically with his coach, Bobby Timmons. I'd say you can't make much distinction
between the training of the 1960s and the training of today. There were people who were training
probably as hard in the 60s. If you take Jim Ryan's mile, 351, Cinder's subtract four seconds, 347,
the American record's 346.8 or something like that. By the 60s, training was mature.
All the other stuff that we worry about, all the nutritional aids and pneumatic compression devices
and ice baths and stuff, I'm not saying it doesn't help on an individual basis, but you can't see it
in the record curves or anything like that. Those things don't show up. Those don't leave a mark
in the big statistical picture. Do you ever follow horse racing at all? Do you ever follow
the times that horses run and things like that? That's exactly the comparison I was thinking of,
which is that they've stagnated since the 50s, right? Secretariat is hands down the fastest horse
that's ever run. I read a very interesting argument on, I don't know, it was probably on
Tate Silver's 365 a few years ago that actually made the point that we're getting further from
Secretariat now because we're actually seeing less diverse breeding of horses.
You're just bringing less genes to the gene pool. Of course, Secretariat's genes were pretty unique.
It was an X-linked, so it was a sex-linked X chromosome gift that he had genetically. That's
why his male offspring didn't do anything special, but his female offsprings that would go on to pass
X chromosomes to males a generation later actually were somewhat special.
Secretariat's times were unbelievable. When you think about it through the lens of even running,
to run a mile and a quarter and to negative split by mile, all five miles, the winning Secretariat's
winning times at Belmont, I don't think any horse will come close to that.
It's important to note that whatever amount of money we have in the running world that is
compelling us to or allowing us to optimize nutrition and training, and yet there's way
more running in horse racing. If there were physiological advances that allowed us to run
faster, they would be using those on horses. The post-training massage or whatever, if that helped
horses, they'd be getting it, or they probably are.
Going back to your experience, let's bring it back to this idea of what you're now learning
about endurance. You are back as a journalist now, and you're fully ready to go back and visit your
running roots. In the research for your book, what are you learning about your experience
on a rainy night in Quebec? How are you able to put that in the context of
what the limits of endurance are? I guess the start would be, maybe to pick up the thread even
a little earlier, is I finally started to write about running, and I was doing it in a very
conventional way, the sort of what heart rate should you do your tempo run at and things like
that. What it meant is that I was starting to look at the literature and reading some papers.
I came across a paper, and again, maybe 2007, 2008, it was a debate, and I think it was in
the Journal of Physiology. The topic of the debate was, does dehydration impair endurance
performance? I just remember being like, what is this like April Fool's? Of course, dehydration
impairs endurance performance. It was a pro and con, and the con was Tim Noakes arguing. It was
a very notable contrarian scientist, let's say, from the University of Cape Town.
He was arguing that, no, we have not shown that dehydration itself impairs performance,
thirst impairs performance if you're thirsty, but if you drink enough that you're not thirsty,
and even if you're dehydrated, even if you've lost a bunch of weight,
that doesn't impair performance. He went through all the literature, all the famous studies that
show dehydration and there's performance going back to the Second World War. You look and it's
like, well, they were all thirsty. They were all stuck in a sauna and not allowed to drink.
Anyway, all of which is to say, all of a sudden, I was like, oh, wait, one of my fundamental tenets
or one of the things that I thought was beyond debate is debatable. I started reading a little
more and following this thread, and I discovered that Tim Noakes had proposed this idea called
the central governor model, which was in a nutshell, it's that when you run as hard as you
can or exercise in other forms as hard as you can, the reason you stop or the reason you slow down
or the reason you aren't able to go faster is not because your legs aren't capable of going faster.
It's because your brain is protecting you. It's putting on the brakes before you push so hard
that your heart runs out of oxygen or whatever the case may be. This was highly controversial. It was
a fringe theory at the time, but that's when I started to make the connection to my race in
Quebec, my 1500 breakthrough and the whole career of why do I have a good race one week and a bad
race the next week, even when physically there's nothing different? Why does it feel like sometimes
I'm able to dig deeper? If it's just multiply your VO2 max by your running economy, divide by your
lactate threshold or whatever, there shouldn't be any change. These things don't change from week
to week. That got me interested in the role of the brain. Now, let me just jump ahead and say the
central governor model, people don't really talk about that anymore. It was a model that emphasized
the importance of the brain in understanding the limits of endurance, which has then led to a whole
bunch of further research, which is what captivated me because it's like nobody needed another article
on VO2 max is oxygen or whatever. Although I shouldn't say that because I've written a few
articles about VO2 max. But what struck me as interesting and what even in by 2009, I was like,
this should be a book about this that tries to explain this to all the people like me who I know
are interested in this stuff, but haven't, don't realize that there's this debate going on in the
literature about how do we bring the brain in, not just in a sense of like you have to really want it
to try really hard, but to understand how the brain is influencing or controlling or playing a part
in determining the limits of endurance. Where do you think this fits into health?
So there's, I mean, this is clearly an important topic when we're talking about sports, right? When
we're talking about endurance sports, like running and cycling and swimming, the purpose of the sport
is to be fast, is to have endurance and speed at that right combination. Many of the people
listening to this podcast are no longer competing. You know, you're still competing, but most people
aren't. I don't compete at anything anymore. But I hate the term, but quote unquote cardio exercise
or endurance based exercise, we would still agree is still an important pillar of health.
So how do you, how do you think about that? And more importantly, how do you think about what you've
studied applying to health? And one of the things I want to talk about, because it's so interesting,
of course, is at some point is exercise become counterproductive and maybe even what are the
benefits specifically, you know, for example, energetics efficiency with metabolism and how
that can fight disease. So in any way, you want to start that discussion, like how do you start
to think about it both scientifically and even personally? Yeah. So that's a big bite that you
want. That's you you've mapped out the next three hours of our conversation. Yes. So one thing I
would say is, I mean, look, I don't want to oversell it and say, you must understand, you know, your
your absolute limits in order to be healthy. But I do think in terms of,
if we think about the barriers to exercise, the barriers to being physically active, I think for
a lot of people, there's a if you interpret the distress signals you feel when you start exercising
as signs that your body is reaching its limit, that's a very distressing thing. You know, if
you're like, I'm going to start an exercise program, I'm going to start brisk walking, I'm going to
start running, and you feel you're panting, you're out of breath, your legs are burning, you know,
I'm going to die, and you stop. And so I think understanding that these, it's not so much about
how to change your limits, but understanding what those limits represent understanding that they are
not signs that you're going to die. These are just, this is just information. This is because I would
say, and I haven't thought this through, maybe it's not true, but I would say, off the top of my head,
any meaningful form of exercise that's going to do you substantial amounts of good is going to involve
dealing with discomfort in one form or another. And if you can get to a place where you understand
that the feelings of discomfort are not signs that something is going wrong with your body,
but they are just information, they are telling you where you are on the road to reaching your
limits, and you don't have to go to your limits, but you also don't have to stop, you're allowed to
just interpret that as information and say, okay, understood, I'm out of breath, but I can keep going.
So I think, to me at least, that's a useful insight to take from this. Now, we can get deeper
than into, you've raised some very interesting and controversial questions about how much exercise
is good, what kind of exercise do we need to do? I don't know where you want to start with that.
Well, let's, because we don't have three hours, although I mean, when we meet in person and share
a meal, we certainly will take those three hours. But let's start with two opposing points of view
with respect to exercise. So one point of view says the exercise longevity curve is J-shaped.
So at the far end of the spectrum, no exercise is a really bad thing for mortality.
As you increase exercise, mortality improves, improves, improves, improves, improves, improves,
and then it kind of gets to your best all-cause mortality. And if you continue to increase
exercising beyond a certain volume, this is generally discussed in volume of exercise,
you actually see a little uptick in mortality, suggesting that once you go beyond a certain
point, again, I want to stress this is in volume of exercise, you don't get any more benefit and
you may actually have more harm. And a lot of times this is harm that comes in the form of
cardiac dysrhythmia, it could be even atherosclerosis through endothelial damage, fibrosis,
things like that. There's another body of literature that says, no, it's more or less a
monotonically improving curve. And again, we all agree that at one end of the spectrum,
having, you know, really poor cardiovascular fitness, again, we could measure this in VO2 max
or something like that, as that improves, and you get fitter and fitter and fitter and fitter,
all-cause mortality goes lower and lower and lower, and there is no J to that curve.
How do you think about reconciling those? And I want to point out at the outset,
this is a discussion that only really impacts like 1% of the population, because 99% of the
population are on the side of the curve where they could always benefit from exercising more.
But you know, you, for example, might be one of those people who's in the 1% where, I don't know,
what's your weekly mileage right now? Unfortunately, it's only probably about 20
miles. So even James O'Keefe would give me a pass. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So walk me through how you
think about that, because I have to be honest with you. I've seen examples of, you know,
those athletes who go a little bit too far, who probably have a genetic susceptibility to
dysrhythmia, and then they go on and get these dysrhythmias. But at the same time, they're few
and far in between. So I don't, I don't, I'm still a bit on the fence about this one. Again,
just purely from an intellectual standpoint, I don't think it applies to me anymore. It probably
did at some point. So it's a good question. And it's an important one. And there's a couple,
a few things I want to say first, I'm a runner, right? So take, take what I say, understand where
I'm coming from. I'm also a human, like I don't want to die. So I'm trying, I try to look at this
data as impa as dispassionately as possible. So, but, but I, obviously I, my knee jerk reaction is
like, let's find holes in this data that suggests running is bad. So I get that on the table. Second,
there's no doubt that there's a reverse j curve. If you try to run 2820 hours a day, it's not going
to be good for you. So like it's nothing is good for you if you push it far enough. So the real
question is where do the extremes or where does the uptick happen? Third thing I want to say is
this, this, the data on this, this showing that, you know, you do a little bit, you get some benefits
and the more you do that it gets worse and worse. One really interesting thing that came out of that
and there were a few studies in about eight years ago that showed that is that actually the dose you
need to get most of the health benefits is very small. And I do think that's an important message.
You do not need to train or for, or run marathons in order to be optimally healthy, at least to within
the 90% or whatever, you're going to get most of what you get from a very modest amount of exercise.
And so that's a great message. So, okay. Now then, can you quantify that by the way, in terms of,
in terms of running, let's, let's put some numbers to that. If you're talking about a person who
maybe was active in high school and college, but you know, they're, they're 10 or 20 years out of
that. They've been caught up in the challenges of starting their career, starting their family,
et cetera. They wake up, they're 40 years old and their waist is five inches bigger. They've got
metabolic syndrome. They're not in dire straits. It's not like they're going to die in the next
10 years, but they've got the message which says, Hey, the one thing that is really missing is your
exercise. What, what would you say if they see him to you and said, Alex, just tell me the minimum
effective dose. I don't want to run any weekend races. I like running. I used to love it or rowing
or whatever their activity is. How many hours or how many miles do I need to do a week to just get
the benefit that some of the, you know, 80% of the benefits with 20% of the efforts.
Yeah. So, so the Cooper Clinic study, which was like 50,000 people or so, uh, that came out
four or five years ago, their number was five to 10 minutes a day. I don't fully believe that,
but that, that was their number. So they're talking, you're talking like an hour a week.
And that's just, you know, going out for a run. I personally, maybe we can get into this.
That's not my definition of an optimal exercise routine. I would include some high intensity
stuff, you know, and strength is another thing. But, um, so there, there's making some claims
that would have very, very low minimum effective dose. Personally, I would say, so I, like I said,
I'm probably running about 20 miles a week right now, which is six days a week, you know, half an
hour with a couple of hard days. I think that's on the, to me, that's on the low end of, of, I,
I think I would be healthier if I did more at this point. Um, and it's just, you think you would,
you would actually be healthier. I know you'd be a better runner, but would you be a healthier,
would you, would you live longer? I think, I think I would now. I think if I, if I had to,
the first thing I would do, if, you know, if I was, if I had instant motivation powder that I was
going to dust on myself, I would get, I would up my strength, my, my strength training routine.
That would be the first thing I do if longevity was my first priority. Oh, I'm sorry. I misunderstood.
So you wouldn't necessarily run more. You would take extra time and add it in the weight room or
do something else? No, I would run more. Like if I was prioritizing, I would prioritize strength
first, but I think if I could also, if I also changed, you know, I think for me, because,
because I'm come from a background where I'm already, I'm used to running 20 miles a week,
doesn't stress me very much. You know, it just slows down my decline. I think I could benefit
from, let's say one long, longer run a week or something like that. This is gut feeler. Let's
not, you know, I don't want to, this is not supported by anything other than my gut,
but the, so the five to 10 minutes a day, it might be, it's definitely the right place to start
if you're the 45 year old, you know, sedentary, you know, getting back into it, but I think you,
you might want to push something a little higher, a little higher than that. Or certainly if you're
doing, if you're doing 60 minutes a week, I wouldn't do it in five to 10 minute chunks. I would do some
20 minute chunks or whatever. And what do we know about injury prevention in that person?
That probably they're going to get injured because they're going to, because they're going to find
that they're no matter how metabolically unfit they are, they're probably going to find that they
gain metabolic fitness more quickly than they gain, you know, tendon stiffness and, and, and muscle
strength and things like that. So in a sense, that's an even more reason to, to sort of take that
guideline seriously. I mean, I'm talking about running, which, because I love, you're less likely
to get injured if you go cycling or something like that. That's obviously, there's other,
other ways of mitigating the, the injury thing. But yeah, from, so, but let me, let me just
cast some doubt on the, on the J shape thing. There, there were two main studies on which this
whole J curve hypothesis was founded. One was the Copenhagen study and, and one was the
Cooper Clinic study. The Copenhagen study initially, it came out saying running is great and more
running is better. And then they reanalyzed it with a new co-author and, and they concluded that
running too much or too fast was bad. That was based on, there were two deaths in the,
in the group that ran too fast. Like this is not the, the confidence interval was essentially infinite,
like, but there's a more serious problem and that, and it's one that affects the Cooper Clinic
data too, which is that when you're, when you have a big study of 50,000 people who were just
randomly selected, they're not all the same. They all have different characteristics. So you have
to find some way of adjusting for various characteristics. And without going too far
down the rabbit hole, basically they statistically adjusted initially at least for things like
cholesterol levels, weight, blood sugar levels, blood pressure, because you want to, you know,
it's meaningless if you compare like we had this, you know, the non runners died sooner than the
runners, but they were also 20 pounds heavier and had all these other risk factors. So you want to
equalize it. But there's a problem that if you equalize it, you're a bit, you're, you're
essentially saying, well, what are the health benefits of exercise if you don't do any exercise?
Because the health benefits are of exercise are precisely in helping you regulate things like
blood pressure and blood sugar and controversially, but I would say weight also.
So essentially, I mean, to me, that was statistical misconduct, like that, that, so you're,
you're saying if you take the people who exercise and you subtract, you basically penalize them for
having lower weight, better lipids, better blood sugar, better blood pressure, sure. So you, you
bring them in line so that they're just as overweight and just have all the other risk
factors. Then you see this J curve. Now, when they actually published the data in a peer-reviewed
journal two years after it was presented, they'd eliminated that, that statistical method and the
J curve had disappeared. You no longer saw the J curve. Now, you know, I don't, I don't want to
just dismiss and say, therefore there's nothing to see. I'm just saying that if we're talking
about where the curve happens, if you do that kind of statistical adjustment, which is the equivalent
of saying like, I want to know whether smoking causes cancer, but I can't compare those smokers
and non-smokers because the smokers have more lung cancer. So let's artificially equalize it
and pretend that the smokers just have just as much cancer that, I mean, that you can't basically
in statistical terms, you can't adjust for a variable, a mediating variable, a variable that's
affected by the thing you're trying to measure. So, sorry, I mean, as you can tell, this is,
this is a topic I get excited about. No, no, it is. And I've read what you've written about it,
which is why I wanted to bring it up. I have a slightly different take on it, which is less about
everything you've said and more of the practical issue. Because the practical issue is the one I
get asked about a lot, which is, am I exercising too much? Right? This is the person asking the
question. And so again, let's pause it for a moment that 99% of people are not exercising too much and
don't even possess the fortitude to exercise too much, right? They don't, the pain tolerance isn't
there, the obsession with exercise isn't there. So for 99% of people, we'd like to get them to
exercise more or stay the same. We're dealing with 1% of the population, many of whom I know and one
of whom I used to be, that we're kind of the hyper exercisers. Here's the bigger point I would make.
It's probably less relevant, whether or not they're spending too many hours cycling, swimming,
running, etc. Usually people in this sense, it's not the number of hours they're spending.
It's the portfolio allocation of how they're spending it. That's the bigger problem.
It's that they're not well rounded, and they're not actually in pursuit of longevity. So the
reality of it is, is training for the Tour de France going to increase your longevity?
Absolutely not. No way. Like those guys finished the tour anemic, osteopenic, their upper bodies
are emaciated, their posture is horrible. There's nothing about that that is setting you up to be
an octogenarian that kicks ass. Nothing whatsoever. So their physiologic marvels, but their health
span sucks, right? So that's using that as an extreme. What do I would be extrapolate that to
the 40 year old who just can't hang up the dreams of being a professional athlete who's out there,
running or riding or doing all of that stuff nonstop, but at the expense of maybe not doing
some pilates to work on core strength. I hate the term, but you know what, and just for people
understand what I'm saying, like not working on stability, not spending any time in the weight
room, really working on strength, not varying the intensity of their workouts to work different
energy systems. So to me, that's the bigger issue with people who are exercising too much. It's
probably not that they're at that little tip of a J that may or may not exist. It's that they're
squandering their time. It's like having all of this money, but you're invested. You have a lousy
portfolio. Yeah. Okay. I agree with a lot of that. One thing I'll say is the important question
you're implicitly asking there is what's your goal, right? Like what are you training for?
Well, that's what I said, longevity. This was all predicated towards living a longer,
healthier life and meaning not winning races or whatever.
I would 100% agree. If someone comes to me and says, I want to optimize my exercise program for
longevity, like I said before, there's no way I would tell them you should be training for a
marathon. That's not because I think training for a marathon is bad, but like you said, it's an
opportunity cost of other things you could be doing that a lot of other things you could be
doing that would probably work better. So I think it's really important to disabuse people of the
notion that in order to optimize your health, you should run a marathon. But where I bridle
with the media coverage of that stream of research is that that's different from saying
that people who are training for a marathon because they want to run a marathon or because
they want to run a marathon as fast as possible should stop because that's bad. So it's like,
of the category of people who have unhealthy behaviors who we should intervene to save them
from themselves, it's like people who are training for a marathon to me are not even close to being
in the same category as people like me who are sitting at a desk for eight hours a day or whatever
the case may be. So it's like there's a difference between optimizing and avoiding serious problems.
The one other thing I should acknowledge is, and you alluded to it, is there are other issues
potential issues with lots of endurance training and arrhythmias is one of them and there's better
evidence that that's a real thing. So there may be downsides to training really hard. On balance,
overall, I would say I don't lie awake at night worrying about people who are running
50 miles a week. Yeah, you're right. You should worry far more about people who are
eating poorly, smoking, who are stressed out of their minds and don't have coping mechanisms for
them. Yeah, there's not many people that you should be worrying about more or less rather.
And if I think of the people I know who, let's say, run the equivalent of 50 miles a week or more,
I can't think of any of them who would say, I'm doing this because I think this is what I need
in order to optimize my health span or lifespan. They obviously hope it's healthy, but I think if
you're training for a marathon, most of them are doing it for competition or not self-competition
in a way. And it sort of reminds me of some, you discussed this a little bit, I think, in your
conversation with James O'Keefe, the sort of what's great about tennis and badminton and volleyball or
whatever, it's the social element of it. And I think, sure, on average, running is a solitary
sport, but for me, it's my primary social outlet. It's where I meet my friends, it's where I get
together and catch up on the week on an easy run. So I think that's true for a lot of people who,
once you get into that 50 miles a week, not for everyone, but for a lot of people, it's a social
element. It's pleasurable, it's a stress reliever. So it goes beyond the... If you take that away,
I'm not sure it nets out as positive.
You know, one of the things that I think is... I don't know that we'll ever know an answer. I
don't know that we'll ever have an answer to the question, but I think one of the challenges of
trying to reconcile all of these disparate data sources is it's all apples and oranges with respect
to the metrics, right? It's you're comparing hours of exercise a week to mileage run to true
measures of fitness like VO2 max. I guess the question is, and I've thought a lot about this,
I'd be very curious to your thoughts. If you could reverse engineer where you want your VO2 max to
be when you're 90, what would it be? Because if you have a sense of what your VO2 max should be
when you're 90, you kind of know what it needs to be when you're 80, 70, 60, blah, blah, blah, blah,
all the way back. And, you know, at that point, it's not necessarily about how fast you want to
run a mile, though you may say, look, when I'm 90, I still want to run a nine minute mile. I don't
know. But it really starts to get into the activities of daily living and how much pain
are you willing to tolerate to walk up two flights of stairs with your groceries?
And I suspect... So I know for me, and I don't know for me, I hypothesize for me that when I'm 90,
the real risk is that I won't be able to get up out of a chair more than that I won't have the
VO2 max. And there are people that they've... I don't remember the exact numbers, but there are
thresholds of VO2 max below which they hypothesize that you can't... I can't remember if it's like
18 or maybe it's nine or something like that, where it's like, at this point, you've crossed
the sort of mortality news where we think you're going to die in a few years because you can't do
activities of daily living. So there is some research into that. But for me, as just my personal,
I can look at myself and say, you know what, Alex, far before your VO2 max is too low,
you're going to be the guy who falls on the floor and can't get up. And so, again,
from a health perspective, that's why I said, the next thing I... If I had magic motivation dust,
it would be like, you need to put on some muscle mass. And for other people, it would be totally
different. There are people I know who don't necessarily exercise a lot, but who just have
a lot more muscle mass than me. And it's like, you need to make sure your aerobic fitness is
taken care of. And maybe you don't need to worry as much as me about muscle mass. So there's...
Yeah, but I mean, I agree. You figure out where you want to be. And for all those different things,
so I'm doing exactly what you said, except I'm doing it for muscle mass. And I'm like,
ooh, this trajectory is not good. And of course, part of that's predicated on the idea that we
know there's an inevitability of decline. So if you do nothing, you're going to lose X pounds of
muscle per decade, if you're lucky, with a tailwind. If you train really hard, you might be able to
reduce it to this amount of loss. And if you really go crazy, you might even be able to keep it flat.
But here's the scenario under which that occurs. What do you think is the... I mean, I assume there
are pretty clear tables on what the decade by decade drop of maximum aerobic output is.
There are. I mean, the problem with the tables is that they draw a nice smooth line. You lose,
I think it's 9% per decade or something like that, at least in the... Once you get into your 70s,
it gets steeper. There's an inflection point. The sort of revised thinking is that that works
on a population level. But what actually happens is the decline is not that steep for any individual.
But what happens is you have certain events in your life. You have an...
You get an injury and you stop training for six months and then you're hosed.
Yeah. So either you have reduced activity for six months or you have bedrest for a week,
which can be disastrous, and you lose 7% in the course of a week and you only get 2% back.
And so it's this punctuated decline. And so, I mean, that puts a lot of emphasis. It sort of
points to the idea of really taking care to avoid, to the extent possible, obviously, to avoid these
events. Because you can actually, in the absence of those events, the decline doesn't have to be
that steep. You can hang on probably better than people used to think.
Can you say more about that? Because I don't think this point can be stressed enough.
Realistically, how much aerobic capacity, maximal aerobic capacity, can a person lose with a couple
weeks of inactivity? And what's the difference between being bedridden versus going on vacation
to Europe where you're not, quote unquote, training, but you're still walking every day?
Like neither of those is exercise per se, but one is active and one is complete inactivity.
Bedrest is terrifying. There's a guy named Luke Van Loon in the Netherlands. His focus is muscular
strength, but he's done a bunch of bedrest studies. And I saw him give a talk once and he had this
great anecdote about, it's really hard to get old people to put on muscle, but they just managed to
finish this two and a half year study where they got, I can't remember, some fairly large number of
septuagenarians, octogenarians to do strength training. And they'd put on like two and a half
kilograms of muscle, which is a huge victory. And they were feeling really good about it.
And then the results came in for their one week bedrest study and they'd lost like 2.6 kilograms
of muscle in one week. So it's like they did this like Herculean effort to shepherd these
people through strength training for a long period of time with full support. Man, whatever it is,
grandma gets pneumonia and is in hospital for a week, bam, she's lost a year of training or
whatever the case may be. So I don't have the numbers at hand for V2 max. I think it's like
up to 20, maybe 10 to 20% in that range if you stop training for a month. It depends where you're
starting though. If you're well-trained for a short period of time, you'll lose it quickly.
If you haven't been training, then resting doesn't make any difference. And if you're well-trained
for a long, long period of time, then you have structural adaptations that are going to take
a lot longer to disappear. So there's no one number for anyone. And the one thing I would add
is that this is not a recommendation that you should never take a break from exercise,
that you should be obsessive and train 365 days a year. Certainly if you're training hard,
if you're training as a marathoner, say, man, you should take a week or two off. And off doesn't
mean bed rest. It means play a couple of games of tennis, go for walks, chill out, go for some bike
rides or whatever. So you shouldn't be terrified of missing a day, but you should be terrified of
bed rest. Luke Van Loon, one of the things he said is like, if you're on bed rest, hospitals
should be forcing you, if you're at all possible, to walk down the hallway to get your meal. Even
just walking down the hallway is infinitely better than not moving at all. Got. Never more
sort of relevant than what we're seeing today with so many people in hospitals and a lot of the
isolation stuff that's going on. Let's go back to something you said about strength. What do you
think matters more, strength or muscle mass? So there's a study I wrote about recently,
I would hesitate to claim it as the absolute truth, but that analyzed, I think it put together
like six different cohorts with a total of about 50,000 people. So pretty good data. And they found
that strength was actually a better predictor than muscle mass. So it's better to have the
functionality to be able to push yourself up out of the chair than it is to have a bunch of muscle
if you're not good at using it. I'm sure that's maybe not true at the margins. If you lose enough
muscle mass, then you become limited by your actual muscle mass. But I think for a lot of
people, they have enough muscle mass, but they're untrained. The neuromuscular connections are not
optimized. And so they're not strong, even though they have enough actual flesh there.
And was that for all cause mortality or yeah. So that's interesting. I mean, that doesn't sound like
a crazy conclusion. I generally try to say, look, I think both of these things are important for
different reasons. I think of strength as you described that it's that functional, it's the
difference between the person who slips down the flight of stairs, but has the strength to grab the
rail and prevent that from being a lethal injury or the type of injury that puts them in the hospital
for a month. You know, grip strength is just so highly correlated, at least with survival. And I
think a lot of it has to do with that kind of stuff, getting up out of the chair, getting up off
the floor at the same side or the flip side of that is I think muscle mass speaks to some of the
other physiologic things like glycogen stores and glucose disposal and glucose homeostasis in general
and insulin sensitivity. So again, I, you know, I rail against the idea that, you know, people say,
I just, I'm okay being strong. I just don't want to be big. And it's sort of like the myth of
accidental muscle, you know, I wish I had that problem. It's like, Oh, I looked at a gym and I
accidentally put on 10 pounds of muscle. I hear people saying that. And I'm like, I wouldn't worry
about that. Anything else about injury? I mean, you've written a lot about this in terms of
different, you know, competing theories around injury. And do you think, how much do you think
it varies by sport? And I guess most importantly, what is the implication for people who tend to
get injured in life? Not, you know, they're, they're walking down the street and they pull a calf
muscle versus they're, you know, out there doing your tempo run. Yeah. So for me, so I've been,
willingly run, willingly embroiled in lots of debates about injuries over the last
decade and a half. And a lot of them focus on things like running shoes, the proper running
form, you know, it's, is, is the height of your insole going to affect your risk of injury. And
that stuff's fun. And it's, it's not, it's not zero impact, but I think to me, there's a guy
named Ben O'Nig, who's a sort of famous biomechanist who's done a lot of work on running injuries and
stuff. And his take in one of his studies was that, look, 80% of running injuries are
what he would call training, are originally a result of what he would call training errors.
So yeah, it's nice, you know, there's 20% to work with on, you know, shoes or whatever, you know,
prehabilitation and balance, yada, yada, yada. Most of, most of what we need to worry about is
doing too much too soon. That's an, you know, and that's an oversimplification. But certainly when
we're talking about overuse injuries, you know, I'm not talking about like getting tackled on the
football field. So I mean, I really think, especially for people who are, so for people
who are starting out or ramping up an exercise program, just that, that, that, that patience is
so important and that understanding that you will probably overestimate what you can accomplish in
the short term. And you'll probably underestimate what you can accomplish in the longterm.
But if you do, and if you fall into that trap, you're dramatically raising your injury risk,
because you're going to try and ramp up too quickly. Because again, you can gain metabolic
fitness more quickly than you can alter the structure of your joints and ligaments and
things like that. So I mean, that's, if there's one takeaway message, it would be like,
it's not about the magical gadget or the new way of running or the, you know, the measuring device,
it's like, just be patient, be smart. You know, you get home, you have something that's aching,
you don't want to miss the next day's session and you don't want to become, it's always a,
a balance, right? Between being, am I being lazy or am I being safe? Well,
you want to err on the side of safe, certainly, until you start getting a better handle on which
aches and pains are normal and which ones aren't. I mean, there's a whole other,
you know, we can get into things like, you know, balance training or training load monitoring.
Well, let's, yeah, let's talk about acute versus chronic load training. I mean, I used to have a
program called training peaks that would track this for me. So it saw every single day,
how many miles I rode and it actually did it more by kilojoules than miles. So it was total energy
expenditure. But if you were giving someone some guidance, some rules of thumb, if they were
becoming active and we'd have to get into the formulas, but just using the principles of acute
versus chronic load balance, how would you help them think through everything you just said with
these metrics? So the background is that the rule of thumb that they used to teach runners is the
10% rule, never increase your mileage more than 10%. And it's a rule that makes no sense at the,
at the margins. Like if you, if you start by running one mile, then you know, you're never going
to get above five miles in your lifetime or whatever. But yeah, so I think that's a really
basically idea is trying to avoid the too much too soon problem. Now, this idea of an acute to
chronic workload ratio is a sort of more sophisticated version of that. And the idea is,
how much are you doing now versus how much is your body used to? And, you know, the way that
the papers, the academic papers do it is what's your weekly load, whether you do it in joules or
miles or minutes, and what's your average weekly load over the last four weeks. And this is when
they started publishing this, I was like, Hey, that's, I designed my own training log back in
the nineties and printed it out. And that's the two things I had at the bottom was kilometers that
week and average four week average kilometers. And it's not because it gets you. Why did you settle
on four weeks, by the way, as opposed to three weeks or five weeks? How did you arrive at that?
Do you remember? Yeah, you know, there was no deep thinking involved that it was basically a week
versus a month. And, and, you know, you can, you can argue it that, yeah, you need at least, you
need a decent amount of time because otherwise you have one week where you miss a couple of days
due to injury. And then all of a sudden your four week average is totally skewed. Or if it's a three
week, you know, if there are something and five weeks at a six weeks, you know, at a certain point,
you're moving so far back that your body don't no longer cares what you were capable of doing
eight weeks ago, or at least not as much. So four weeks, it's just a, you know, that it's kind of a
four, if you've done something for four weeks in a row and you're feeling okay, then you can,
you kind of assume that yeah, your body's able to handle that load. And so then this allows you,
it's just a quick way of seeing if there's any deviations. It's like, Oh, my, you know, my,
this week I did 50% more than my four week average. That's, that's a bad, bad song. It doesn't
mean you're going to get injured. There's all sorts of contextual things you have to consider
in it. But having that as one input into your larger matrix of all the things that you're
considering, like, do I feel any aches and pains? Am I what's my absolute load, not just the ratio,
but is this more than I've ever done before? And, you know, all the, you consider all those things.
And I think that acute to chronic ratio, or just to put it more simply, keeping track of how much
you're how hard you're going now versus how hard you've been going in the previous month,
or how much you've been doing, let's say, is useful. Now, I should add that there's controversy
in the literature. There's a bunch of people who say that the supposed predictive value of
acute to chronic workload ratio is a statistical artifact. It may be, it may not be, I'm not too
worried about that. To me, this is not about statistical predictive power. It's just about
keeping an eye on, on trends and knowing if you're, if you're way out of whack with what you've been
doing before. And as a general rule, you know, let's say if you're 20% higher, that's time to
start making sure you know what you're doing. Yeah. Or just, you know, and backing it off,
maybe that next week. Yeah. I mean, you know, unless you have some compelling reason to think
that you can handle that, if you're, if you're exceeding 20%, then probably, yeah, be cautious
and ideally back off. So you alluded to it earlier, but let's talk a little bit about high
intensity interval training. It's getting a lot of attention today, obviously. You know, most
people are familiar with what a Tabata is, though Tabata himself is not the guy that actually designed
the protocol, but everybody still refers to it by his name. Where do you think this fits into the
hierarchy of, again, not a specific athlete who's, you know, training to run the mile or the marathon,
but a person who's trying to be healthy. How much of a, how much of a shortcut efficiency gain is it?
Again, let's, let's use the Tabata interval as an example, where you're going all out for 20 seconds,
resting for 10 and repeating it eight times. And by the way, wouldn't we argue from your research
and endure that you can't technically go all out for 20 seconds, that you're, you're really,
I've started when I do all out intervals, I now limit them to 10 seconds because I
actually started paying attention and realizing I was subconsciously pacing myself at 20 second
all outs. But anyway, that's, that's, I don't know what you think about that, that, that idea,
but I remember reading in your book that, that wasn't the case that we technically can't go all
out for 20 seconds. It certainly doesn't seem that way. And, you know, like, look, Usain Bolt
or world-class sprinters don't go as fast. I mean, it's complicated by the curve, but they go,
they don't set world records en route to 200 meters. They're pacing themselves even for 20
seconds. I just have to tell one quick story about Tabata. I was at a conference and at the
poster session where the researchers are in front of their posters talking about it. And I was, it
was a research on the, from the McMaster group, which has popularized high intensity interval
training. And one of the postdocs was there explaining his interval, high intensity interval
training research. And someone came up and asked him a question and handed him his business card
at the time. And I noticed the postdoc, he looked down as he was answering the question, he glanced
at him with the business card and his eyebrows just went like halfway up his forehead. And I
peeked over and it was like, Oh, that's Tabata. That's cool. I didn't realize this was a real
person. So he was, he was there, you know, asking questions about intervals. Anyway, where do I
think intervals fit? I think they're super important. When circa 2008, when high intensity
intervals started to be a big buzzword, I was like, how is this a buzzword? That's how runners
train. Like one of the studies out of the McMaster group was like, let's do 10 times a minute. It's
like, that's the Roger Bannister. That's what, that's how he broke the four minute mile in 1954.
What's new about this, but it was new to a lot of people. A lot of people were like, I need to go
45 minutes. I need to go an hour and to do this, I need to die. So there is, let me put it this way.
I guess what I was really good at is the compression of that, right? It's the, I don't know if you saw
this, well, I'll let you finish this, but then I'll bring it to where I'm going, which is what
are the limits of how much you can shrink. Yeah. Well, I'll just, I'll just say that as two general
points. One is that as a runner, one thing I know is that you will never ever run fast relative to
your abilities if you don't do interval training. The second thing I would say is you probably won't
run as fast as you could if you only do interval training. Now, some people do do only interval
training, but that's usually they're doing it so slowly that it's not different from just doing a
sustained thing. So to me, when you look at the studies, it's like, let's compare eight weeks of
three interval workouts a week to eight weeks of three 45 minute sustained sessions. It's like,
okay, that's interesting. It's useful to know, but I really don't think that's what is optimized and
what we should be comparing it to. What about one short sprint interval session, one medium interval
session, and one 45 minute session? That's, or some portfolio is to me, because there's pretty
clear evidence that you can get to the same or some of the same health outcomes. You can get the
same improvement in insulin sensitivity say, but the mechanisms may be different if you're doing
a sprint interval session versus, or if you're doing sprint interval training versus sustained
training. And so it's like, well, if you've got two different mechanisms, let's hit them both
because presumably we're going to get a little one plus one is going to be at least equal to,
1.2 or something like that. So I think interval, I would 100% recommend to anyone that they should
be including some form of interval training in their routine. If they're interested in health
or performance, I wouldn't necessarily recommend it. It's the only thing unless they, that's what
they want to do. I would put it as part of a portfolio. And as far as the sprint stuff goes,
we can talk about this, but it's like, it has been funny to watch the, it's not like one upmanship,
it's one downmanship. How short can we make this? Like, okay, I thought about interval training for
a millisecond last night. Look, I got fitter. It's amazing. Well, that's only a, it's only a,
a slight exaggeration from a study that came out recently from actually from, from here in UT
Austin, um, Ed Coyle, who is a, is a physiologist and published a study looking at four seconds
all out 56 seconds of rest. So it's on the minute, every minute on the minute, but only four seconds
all out. And this was done, I believe for 15 minutes. And then they progressed to basically
four seconds all out twice a minute. So you go four seconds all out, 26 seconds of rest, repeat,
you know, for 20 minutes, something to that effect. Um, again, I, you know, here's my take on these
things. It comes down to a concept you raised earlier, which is there's an opportunity cost to
them. It, they're usually comparing that to doing nothing. And is that better than sitting on the
couch? Yes. But if you gave a, if you gave me 40 minutes a day, could I come up with a more
efficient way to get a benefit? I probably could. And then it becomes a question of what's the
efficacy versus effectiveness of this intervention. And I think that's the other piece of this,
right? Which is, I think people like you and I like exercise so much that we get to focus all of our
effort or interest on efficacy. What is actually going to do the best, produce the best results
when adhered to perfectly. But I accept the fact that many people don't enjoy exercise. And therefore
the real world applicability of a problem becomes its effectiveness. It's not what can be done in a
laboratory for six weeks when you're a paid subject. It's what are you going to be willing to do on your
own when you have to rely on your own sprinkling of motivation dust day in and day out. And so
I guess on some level, that's where I've become a little bit more accepting of the fact that, hey,
if people are willing to do shorter interval workouts, provided they don't get injured,
that's always the fear I have when people jump right into these high intensity interval workouts
without any of the foundational strength that goes into it. If the alternative is doing nothing,
well, then it's better. But I guess secretly, I just hope that I can convince people that they're
better off learning to love exercise, which again, I think is why a book like yours is so great,
right? It explains like how we evolved and, you know, the more we can think about reconciling
what we are today with what we spent a million years becoming, perhaps the less foreign that feels.
So I think you've put your finger on exactly the issue, which is it's yeah, it's not about
what does better in this lab context. It's what will people do. And I actually,
I'm a little bit skeptical that four seconds at the intensity that you have to do those intervals
is more acceptable to the average person than, then let's say one minute. So
going back to a little history on the hit stuff, the first hit protocol was windgate test,
which is like 30 seconds all out. And anyone who's done a windgate test, you know,
if you do it in the lab, they're screaming at you. It's like, you know, we're going to shoot your
mother. If you don't go as hard as you can and you get every people puke after windgate tests.
So the original protocol was four windgate tests with seven minutes rest. Because that's how hard
they are going back. It's like what we were saying earlier about how hard an 800 meter race,
a two meter, two minute race can be compared to like a marathon. You can really suffer in those
30 seconds. And so when they're like, well, okay, it works in the lab, but in real life,
what's, what are people going to do? Their answer initially wasn't like we should make it shorter.
It was, well, the intensity that people can actually get to in real life, we should,
that's where the 60 second on 60 second off protocol came from. Because it's like,
it's easier for people to accept 60 seconds pretty hard than it is to expect them to imagine the,
you know, homicidal drill surgeon behind them yelling at them to get all of it out of themselves
in 30 seconds. Now you're going down to let's say there's been 20 seconds, there's been 10 seconds,
there's been four seconds. It takes, it's hard, it takes a lot of motivation, you have to be
a hundred percent on to get the most out of this four second or 10 second or whatever interval. So
there's a lot of debate understandably about like, okay, well, which is it that people will do? Would
they rather do 20 minutes at medium or, you know, 40 minutes easy or four seconds hard? I think
there's a lot of debate because there's different, there's a lot of different people, people like
different things. And some people are, love that, that, that power thing and that that's great. And,
and again, like you said, it's, I don't think it's as good as doing a mixed portfolio of things.
But I think it's, it's pretty good. And if they'll do it, that's great. But I think the, the, the
assumption of this race to the bottom of how, how short can you make the interval is that people
like it more. And I'm not sure that's true for everyone. I love your comment about, I thought
about high intensity intervals for a second last night. I will say this, one of the things that I
think is a big challenge here is most people aren't clear on the, the why they just want to
do the what, you know, this is sort of the going back to my pet peeve of people confusing strategy
for tactics. And I don't, I think if people don't understand the benefits of the different types of
exercises and the why you're doing them, you know, actually reverse engineering what the purpose is.
So you're thinking about the 90 year old version of you in a chair, he needs to get up. Well, that
gives you the motivation to do strength training. And if you didn't have the aerobic conditioning,
you'd start to think, well, once I get up out of said chair, what do I want to do? Oh, I might
actually want to go and walk around the block with my grandchild. Oh, well, what would that involve?
Well, at my house, there's a hill and that hill goes from here to there. And what if I want to
stick them in a wagon and pull them like that's actually going to require aerobic capacity. And
that hill is pretty short. So it's actually going to be pretty intense. Like it actually requires it
near maximal effort for me. And so I just think that the more people can tether what it is they
are doing this for to something real, it becomes a little easier to do these abstract workouts.
Because otherwise, like, what are we doing? Right? Like once you stop competing in something,
which is, you know, a fraction of the percent of the population, all this exercise stuff becomes
abstract. And frankly, you know, the practice of medicine doesn't do a great job communicating the
why. Right? I mean, most, most people know they should exercise, but I don't think they've really
had a great explanation as to, you know, for example, fighting cancer, when you're fit is
probably a lot easier than fighting cancer when you're not fit, simply based on the energetics of
your immune system. Most people don't know that. And therefore, it's a bit abstract why they should
be exercising so much. Yeah, I mean, you could say the definition of insanity is telling people
that exercise is good for them yet again, and hoping that that on its own is going to convince
people to exercise it. It's clear that doesn't work. So I think, you know, what you say is right,
you need to make it visceral and to relate to things that people care about. And so that
people care about different things. So you have to understand what each person cares about,
and then find out what the right exercise for them is that's going to connect for them.
Last thing I want to ask you about Alex is basically the merger of the two careers you've
had. I've probably been pretty critical of your profession, which is science journalists,
or journalists who cover science, let's put it that way. Because truthfully, I think most of them
are really bad. And I think many of them actually border on negligent and I think they cause,
on some levels, more harm than good to the public. I mean, obviously, I don't put you in that category
and there are many people I don't put in that category who I think are excellent at science
journalism, but they're really in the minority. So most of the sensationalized headlines,
you know, and frankly, even the news stories that just don't have the detail that I think
should at least be covered in a news story, given the understanding that very few people
are going to go back to the primary source and read it, places an enormous responsibility on
scientific journalism. Do you think there's a systematic way to make this process better?
Oh, that's a that's a heavy question. The problem is, are these my perception is the
problem? And this is self-serving since I'm a science journalist, is that
journalism now follows the audience. And I started out in 2006, let's say, just at the point where
news organizations were first starting to be able to see how many people clicked on a story.
And this was one of the great catastrophes of journalism in some ways, because it's terrifying
to find out what people click on. It's unhealthy for the news organizations to find out what people
click on. I can remember so that the big newspaper in Canada is the Globe and Mail. And, you know,
early on, as newspapers went online, they started to, you know, people realized it's kind of nice to
have what are the top 10 most clicked on stories. So then you can go and, and I remember when the
Globe, as far as I remember, I don't know the exact timeline, but shortly after they introduced
this feature, I was like, how is it that the top 10 stories on the Globe and Mail website,
like three of them are about Britney Spears, two of them are about like, you know, it was just like,
I thought the Globe and Mail is supposed to be the kind of highbrow newspaper in Canada. And it
looks like it's a bunch of simpering morons who are clicking. But then I look at what I click on
sometimes, and sometimes you're just tired and you click on this sort of craziest thing. So anyway,
sorry, I'm drifting off the point here, which is that to fix science journalism, you need,
or to encourage good science journalism, you need people to read good science journalism. And
I think newspapers are realizing that following the audience has turned out to be a bad move,
because they've ended up losing the trust in audience. But by giving people what they thought
they wanted, you ended up basically giving them crap and then having people recognize that they
were being fed crap and then kind of rebel against it. So like, where I started my journalism, my
science, my sports science journalism career, in some sense was I started a blog on WordPress in
like, I don't know, 2008 or something, where I was just like, you know what, I can't write this in a
newspaper article. But on this blog, I know there are people who are interested in the details of
what the study says. I'm going to have the key figure from the study. And I'm going to say how
many people were in the, you know, how many subjects there were and what their characteristics
were and what the intervention was. And that's the blog that became, it got taken on to Runner's
World in 2012, and then moved over to Outside in 2017. It turned out there was an audience for that,
which is encouraging. So I think, I guess I'm not answering your question at all, which is how do
you fix it? But I think that the finding an audience that appreciates it is, or at least having some,
I don't know, let's see, what am I trying to say here? That the news organizations aren't going to
insist on scientifically qualified journalists, unless there's repercussions or feedback when
there's bad journalism. And I think the initial signals were the opposite. They were actually
getting feedback that the less complicated it was, and the more sensational it was, the more feedback
they got. So maybe, you know, to try and actually give one concrete answer to your question is that
the move away from advertising and towards subscription based models, I think has helped,
and hopefully will continue to help move away from like, just let's do what's most sensational to
let's do what's most, let's give people a filling meal that, you know, that they're not going to be
hungry 10 minutes later. So maybe that trend is a good one in some ways.
Yeah. And look, I don't know that I expected you to have an answer because this is a question I've
thought about for a decade, actually, probably around 2011 is when I started really becoming
frustrated with journalism and science, which is not to say that's when it started. I think that's
just when I began to notice it enough and realize that the signal to noise ratio had fallen to
zero. And I, you know, and of course to this, you know, if you ask my friends, there's no better way
to drive me nuts than just a forward me a headline and without even a question, like as though somehow
I'm supposed to read this idiotic headline and know what your question is of me. But, uh, yeah,
look, I still get three of those a day. So, um, anyway, Alex, this has been, this has been awesome.
I have, like I said, I've wanted to sit down with you for a couple of years since I read Endure and
I can't recommend it highly enough. I find it riveting. Um, I think you're a, you're a, you're
a great writer and a great storyteller. And that that's to me, I think one of the gems of reading a
book like that is you, you're reading about science, but you're also reading it in the context of
amazing stories, personal stories, stories of other, uh, individuals. So thank you very much for
that contribution and, and, and all of your amazing stuff on outside, which I, I, again,
I can't get over how prolific you are. And it's just, it's, it's gem after gem.
Well, thanks Peter. It's been a real privilege to have a chance to talk to you and I've, I've
appreciated your work over the years and I really, I'm glad we had a chance to, uh, to talk and I'm
just sorry, my answers were so rambling. Not at all. Thanks Alex. Thanks Peter.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely
access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The qualities, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday
through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head
over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.