Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Michael. Thanks for coming all the way out to Austin to work on some DNS for a few
days with me and Beth.
Thanks for having me. Thank you.
Been wanting to sit down for quite a while. And obviously the events of 2020 kind of got
in the way of that. But maybe just start for folks by giving a little bit of your background.
You grew up in Northern California, right?
Yeah, grew up in Northern California and eventually went to school down in San Diego
at UC San Diego.
What sports did you play growing up?
My primary sport or the sport that I was most passionate about was tennis. And interested
in that from an early age and played other sports, other organized sports. But tennis
was the one that I was drawn to and had the passion for. So early on, specialized in that,
played lots of junior tennis tournaments, trained a lot, eventually played in college.
And that obsession or passion kind of drove me to the way that I practice today. I'm a
chiropractor. I'm based out of San Diego, California, as you know. I kind of specialize
in rehabilitation, sports medicine. I am also, so I have the private practice there. I'm
fortunate enough to also be able to spend some time on the PGA Tour and the World Surf
League Tour as part of their sports medicine crew or team. And also fortunate enough to
be part of USA Surfing Performance Committee, helping with assessing and training the US
athletes, the surfing athletes for the upcoming Olympics.
Cool. Today, obviously, the thing we want to talk about is this super kind of deep dive into
something called dynamic neuromuscular stabilization. Now, folks listening to this have
probably heard me talk about this in the past. If they follow me on social media, they'll notice
from time to time I'm doing movements that probably look a little silly. Sometimes working
with you or working with Beth or working with another colleague of ours, Michael Stromsness,
is actually how we all met. But I think for the purpose of this discussion, let's assume a
person has never heard of DNS, has never heard of the Prague School or any of these things. Can you,
in a somewhat succinct but not terribly brief manner, explain to people how all of this school
of rehabilitation coalesced around this idea of what we call DNS? So going back to the founding
fathers of the Prague School and what these various insights were that each of them had and
how that came together.
Okay, so DNS or dynamic neuromuscular stabilization built on some pioneers of functional
rehabilitation. There's many that have been part of the Prague School of Rehabilitation, but I
think talking about the influence on the development of dynamic neuromuscular stabilization by
Professor Pavel Kolodz, who runs the rehabilitation department at Prague School at this time. I think
we need to go back post World War II, Cold War era 1950s is where Prague School of Rehabilitation was
really founded. And it was founded as part of the medical faculty of Charles University in Prague, in
Czech Republic, or formerly Czechoslovakia, and now Czech Republic. And being post World War II, Cold
War era, so they were in Eastern Europe behind the wall. That may have been a factor for their, not
reliance, but tendency towards the use of observation in both diagnosis, both observation and
palpation for diagnosis and treatment. All three of these pioneers were neurologists.
And who were the three?
So the three of Vladimir Yanda, Karl Levitt and Belklav Vojta. Professor Yanda, he had a keen sense of
observation. And he formulated concepts and principles that tied into postural habituation,
specifically the tendency for specific musculature to tend towards tightness and other musculature to
tend towards weakness. And he termed this upper cross and lower cross syndrome. So for example,
with an upper cross syndrome, meaning the neck and shoulder region with demands of life and the
tendency towards postural habituation, such as with sustained seated postures, there's a tendency
towards the muscles in the back of the neck, the occipital muscles, the sternocleidomastoid muscle,
which is the muscle that also attaches to the skull and down to the sternoclavicular joint,
the pec muscles, the upper traps, that musculature would tend towards a tightening or overactivation.
Other musculature in the upper extremity, the serratus, which attaches to the ribs and in the
back of the scapula, the deep neck flexors, the middle and lower traps would have a tendency to
tend towards a weakness. And with that tendency towards overutilization or hypertonicity and
underutilization, inhibition, weakness, he also recognized that that would affect the
quality of movement throughout the kinematic chain and subsequently would lead to overload
in specific areas throughout that kinematic chain. So that was a big contribution on his part,
his colleague. Where would those places of overload be? So if you have this tightness in
the muscles you've described, the weakness in the muscles you've described, what is the consequence
of that? Where does that load get distributed? Right. So with that imbalance and that postural
tendency towards postural habituation, you would see a tendency to overload in the transitional
areas throughout the spine and throughout the extremity. So it didn't go into the specifics for
lower cross syndrome. Lower cross syndrome, you have a tendency for the hip flexor complex to
be overactive, tightened. So the psoas, iliopsoas, rectus femoris, the
back extensor musculature will also tend towards tightness. And then the weakness or the inhibition
will tend to be towards the lower abdominal region and the gluteal region. So looking at it globally,
you would see a tendency to overload again throughout the extremity,
throughout the extremities so that the hip joint, the knee joint,
but also specifically dealing with the spine, the lumbar sacral region, thoracic lumbar region,
and the cervical thoracic region, all the areas where you see the transition of the curvatures,
lordosis and kyphosis. And with that tendency for overload, you will get repetitive stresses on
the passive structures within that kinematic chain. So as a clinician, we know that if you
tend to image these areas or if you image the spine, these are the areas that tend to have the
most degenerative changes or the most disc pathology. And those changes aren't usually
traumatic. They're not acute. They're accumulated over time. So the observation of these postural
patterns or postural syndromes, and then the recognition of the dysfunction with movement
efficiency that it caused led him to develop specific treatments, both exercise wise and manual
wise to address those issues. His colleague, Carl Levitt. But Yanda also had suffered polio as a
youngster, didn't he? Yeah. So he had suffered the residual effects, the post polio type syndrome.
And that was probably a motivation for his passion for rehabilitation,
his passion for the observation of movement. His colleague, Carl Levitt, also a neurologist,
he shared that observation palpation,
not technique, but tendency to utilize that for diagnosis and treatment. He specifically focused
on joint dysfunction, soft tissue dysfunction as it related to those upper and lower cross syndromes.
So he developed specific mobilization techniques for both the joint and the soft tissues,
addressing what they were seeing with those postural, postural habituation and movement dysfunction.
The third kind of pioneer, also a neurologist, but also a pediatric neurologist was Valcla Vojta.
And his observations observing the ontogenesis or the development of motor function after birth
during the first 12 months where the postural or postural foundations are established neurologically,
he developed a specific test called postural reactions where he could tell the quality or the
health of the maturation of the central nervous system during that period of time. And by doing
this, he could assess whether there was pathology or a healthy developing central nervous system.
So he developed seven specific postural reaction tests, developed and modified some other ones,
utilized primitive reflexes and just observation, observation of the infant during development
to be able to recognize the biological age, meaning the maturation of that central nervous system
as compared to the chronological age. So for example, if you had a six month old infant
that was moving and reacting like a six week old infant, that would be an indication that there
was some central nervous system pathology. His focus was on treatment of the cerebral palsy,
infant and patient. And he was able to utilize that observation, those
observation of the postural reactions, the assessment of the primitive reflexes to
recognize early on before it would manifest clinically so that interventions could be taken
earlier on to take advantage of the neuroplasticity, the ability of the brain to
form motor engrams more efficiently and work around those central lesions that you see with
cerebral palsy. So he, all three of these kind of founding members or founders of Prague School
of Rehabilitation were Professor Kolodz, Kolodz's colleagues, mentors in structures, they shared
patients, they discussed cases and Pavel Kolodz developed or evolved all that knowledge and
experience into what we call dynamic neuromuscular stabilization today. Now before Pavel came along,
what was the, so fast forward this started in the 50s, but fast forward to the 90s.
So the Prague School is well established, you have these sort of founding fathers, so to speak.
What were the applications of the Prague School at that time? How much of it was rehabilitation
for kids with cerebral palsy or rehabilitation for people who were injured versus prehabilitation
for athletes? Like what was the breadth of the applicability of the Prague School?
Right, so Prague School was, it's a group of clinicians and probably more of the early 90s,
the application was primarily rehabilitation, cerebral palsy, general population,
with Pavel, Professor Kolodz just to go in a little bit of his background.
Again, he's the head of Prague School of Rehabilitation, he's also head clinician
for the Czech Olympic teams and Czech national sports teams, hockey, soccer,
men's and women's tennis. He himself was a high level, Olympic level gymnast. So
he, his work, he's a pediatric physiotherapist as well. His work with those three pioneers,
his experience as an athlete, his experience treating cerebral palsy and infants,
he took that or started to apply that base of knowledge to the athletic population. And the
focus of and the thinking of these founders of Prague School and Prague School today is
it's the influence of the central nervous system is huge and kind of king as far as the
facilitating the efficiency of transfer of load throughout that kinematic chain.
So early on, the focus was more rehabilitation over multiple populations.
But maybe late 90s, early 2000s, Pavel started to apply those teachings to that athletic population.
And there's meaning to an uninjured athletic population or to an injured athletic population?
Probably at that time, more of an injured population to kind of stand out athletes that
he was able to work with and integrate his concepts and principles of dynamic stability
were John Lesney. I say that right. He was an Olympic javelin thrower, three time gold
medal winner still holds the record for javelin 98.48 meters, I believe. And the other one is
Yomir Yager, who hockey player, Czech hockey player. He was able to help and work with them,
help them rehabilitate from injuries, but then also integrate the concepts and principles of
dynamic neuromuscular stabilization to one, decrease the risk of re-injury, but two, also
provide the potential for better performance. And we can talk about specifics of those concepts
and principles. Yeah, let's let's so we're into the early 2000s, where now Pavel's basically
taking some of the fundamental principles from the Prague school and creating this
this new discipline. Let's use each of the words to explain to people what this is. So dynamic,
of course, is movement, right? It's not just static. It applies to in motion neuromuscular,
I think explains the connection between the nervous system, both the central nervous system
and the peripheral nervous system, but really, as you said, an emphasis on the central nervous
system, and how that connects to the muscular system. So a lot of people, I think assume that
acts of strength are purely muscular, and they don't realize the neurologic control of those
things. For me personally, the hardest one to explain to an unsuspecting audience is stabilization.
Now I have a way that I like to explain it, but I want to hear you go first.
Okay. So I think it's important to talk about the utilization of developmental kinesiology
as a way to explain posture and explain dynamic stabilization. When we're first born,
functionally and structurally, we are immature. So our central nervous system is still maturing.
Our bones are still forming. The first weeks of life, first four to six weeks of life,
the lower central nervous system structures, the brainstem level is kind of dominant. So primitive
reflexes are dominant. So examples of that suck reflex, gag reflex, grasping,
obviously being able to blink. I mean, the most primitive reflexes that our species, I mean,
we take these for granted. So they help keep us alive during that period of time.
So as that central nervous system matures, and if it's maturing in a healthy way,
by a three month period of time, actually, let me go back, usually starting maybe eight weeks,
we start to facilitate the synergy, coordination and timing of the deep stabilizing group of
musculature. And that's diaphragm, pelvic floor, the entire dominant wall, the intersegmental spinal
musculature that runs throughout the entire spine. All right, I'm going to stop you right here. We
are going to talk about these things so much that I want to make sure people understand them. So
let's go back to the first one. Everybody's heard of their diaphragm. But let's put some actual
metrics to it. It's a dome shaped muscle, it's a striated muscle, but it has kind of a non muscular
part as well. But I think what most people don't appreciate is how big it is, right? Yeah. And how
I can't even remember, it's been, you know, back when I was, you know, in school, I had to know
every attachment of it. But it, did you recall how far it attaches down and up on the on both the
on both the ribs and the vertebral bodies? Yeah, so the diaphragm, just think of it like a big
parachute or a big sheath of muscle that separates the abdominal cavity from the heart and lungs.
The attachments, it has attachments on the lower six ribs on the back of the xiphoid process,
which is a little bone at the end of the sternum. And then also attachments on L1, L2,
vertebra. So that's right around the thoracic lumbar junction.
So that's just an enormous expanse of attachment attachments being, you know, where the muscles
attach and anchor, and therefore that gives you a sense of what their lever capacity is, what they
can actually contract. Right. So that there's those attachments, and then there's a central tendon,
that when the diaphragm activates, so one of the primary functions is respiration.
So I go to take a breath in, that diaphragm activates, descends, the central tendon drops,
the lungs expand that change in pressure, you're able to draw air into the lungs. And then there's
a recoil of the diaphragm and the air comes out. So there's a primary respiratory function.
During the first weeks of development or ontogenesis, which is the study of motor
development after birth, there's primary respite, it's primary respiratory function.
The central nervous system has not matured to the point to create the synergy with within the other
deep stabilizing group of musculatures, musculature, to create that fixed point through the trunk and
the pelvis. So by, by around three months period of time, that central nervous system has matured
to the point where now the hardwired genetic ingrained motor programs start to manifest
themselves. So we start to see this coordinated activity of that deep group of musculature.
So what are the other, what are the, what, so we've now, I mean, for me, and I think for many people,
a very helpful image is that of a cylinder and the strongest possible cylinder, right, would have
a big top, a big bottom, and a beautifully symmetric, you know, side compartment to it,
right? A lousy cylinder would have a tiny little bottom, a big top and a dented middle. So if a
diaphragm formulates the top of that cylinder, what makes up the bottom of that cylinder?
So the bottom of the cylinder, we're looking at the pelvic floor, which is an area of musculature,
basically where we, the babies come out and that musculature will coordinate the
regulation or management of intra-abdominal pressure that is created with the descending
of the diaphragm. So the diaphragm, three, three main functions, respiration, but there's also
obviously this huge postural function where it descends even more and creates an intra-abdominal
pressure so that when that pressure is created, that diaph, the pelvic floor will eccentrically
load, meaning it's active, but musculature is active, but stretches. You can think of it like
wind blowing into a sail where the wind blows into the sail, it opens and activates and then
it holds and maintains the pressure. But then at the same time, we have the entire abdominal wall,
which consists of the rectus muscles, our six pack muscles, our oblique musculature, which is
musculature that crosses the body, comes up and has attachments under the thoracic cage or the rib cage.
And then a big one called transverse abdominis, which wraps around from the back, the thoracolumbar
fascia around to the front. So as that diaphragm descends to facilitate a stabilizing function,
that intra-abdominal pressure is created, that musculature reacts to the pressure,
there's an eccentric load and then an isometric. And then as we coordinate, so we have respiratory
function, postural function, but we have to now coordinate between both respiratory and postural
functions. So our central nervous system, our brain needs to manage that pressure to provide
enough stability, but also allow the diaphragm to also allow the lungs to expand.
This coordination is usually where we see people kind of falling apart. And if they fall apart,
they'll tend towards what Yanda saw, which is that over-utilization. So in the lower cross syndrome of
the extensor musculature and the flexor musculature, because we lose that synergy of that deep
stabilization. And if we lose that synergy and that ability to create that fixed point,
then our brains will do their jobs, which is to find a way to still move and do tasks that we need
to do. But in doing so, we'll go to more of a high threshold or like I described more of a
compensatory pattern. So developmentally, that three month period of time is where we ideally
will have that synergy, coordination and timing of that deep group of musculature that will allow
the infant to create a fixed point through the trunk and the pelvis. And then also with that
management of that intrandatal pressure, there's a loading on the front of the spine. And with that
loading, we get an uprighting effect throughout the spine. So then the intersegmental spinal
musculature are eccentrically loading and managing that pressure against the spine to help with that
uprighting effect and that unloading effect. Let's again make sure people know exactly what
we mean because we're going to use the terms a lot. When you talk about eccentrically versus
concentrically loading, I mean, to me, the easiest way to define is just using the definitions,
right? So a muscle is concentrically loaded when it's getting shorter as it's being loaded,
eccentrically is getting longer as it's being loaded. So for example, a bicep curl, this is the
concentric phase of loading. This is the eccentric phase of loading. And I think what a lot of people
take for granted is both of those are important. But most people when training tend to emphasize
the concentric and don't realize the eccentric. I heard a great story. I think it was actually
from Michael Strom'sness that when a group of US weightlifters visited a group of Eastern European
weightlifters, I don't know, maybe it was even you that told this story, they realized that they were
counting reps differently. So the American lifters would consider a rep one is up and down. So that
was they were putting all their effort into the concentric, but then, you know, more or less dropping
the weight on the way down, not really focusing on the effort to put the weight down. And the
Eastern European lifters were doing the opposite, right? They were counting it as two reps. It's up,
one, down, two. So it was just as much effort into that eccentric. And, you know, it's not to say one
is right or wrong because they serve different purposes. Obviously, more emphasis on the eccentric
will create more hypertrophy. So there are times that you want both. But again, when you look at,
for example, and we'll get to this, I'm sure, but when you look at hip abduction, the importance of
being able to eccentrically control that is such an important part of injury prevention. And you can
spend all the time in the world working on concentrically doing that. So later today, when
we actually do some stuff on the mat, you'll have some exercises to demonstrate that.
Yeah. Yeah. So what the observation, having knowledge of the developmental kinesiology or
the ontogenesis and watching that maturation of the central nervous system and with that
healthy maturation, seeing the synergy of the deep stabilization, providing that fixed point,
and then allowing efficient transfer of force and load throughout that trunk and pelvis area.
What these pioneers, Voita, Yanda, Levitt, Colaj, noticed was the importance of the quality,
basically training that central nervous system. Because if you can facilitate that ideal
stabilization, stereotype and synergy, then you provide what Professor Colaj calls
centration throughout that chain of movement, throughout that kinematic chain. And what he
describes centration as is, for example, let's say you have the hip joint, is the ability to maintain
an ideal position of the femur and the acetabulum, which is the hip joint,
throughout that full range of motion. In order to do that, you need a synergy or a nice interplay
between agonist and antagonist, like you described the biceps curl. So an interplay between
concentric, eccentric activity of the opposing musculature around the joint to help maintain
that position. And if that is compromised throughout any part of that kinematic chain,
it's going to affect the quality of centration or transfer of force and load
above and below that region. The quality of that synergy coordination timing of that deep
stabilization is what Prague school is focusing on with assessment and with their treatment methods.
And this is based out of that observation of developmental kinesiology, which is the
neurophysiological aspects of the maturing locomotor system. So that's there. They utilize that as their
definition of dynamic movement, dynamic posture, ideal posture.
Let's go back to the three month old infant and start talking about what
normal developmental milestones are through the lens of DNS and
picking it up at three months. So what is a three month old infant starting to demonstrate and how
is that progressing as they become six months, nine months a year, et cetera? Right. So at three
months with that ability to create that fixed point, now the larger, longer musculature and larger
muscle groups have something to anchor off of. So creating that fixed point, for example,
allows the infant to now turn their head and fix their gaze prior to that during those first weeks
of life. You know, there's the ability to fix their gaze is not there by three months providing
that stable point. Now they can turn, fix their gaze. And now they start to get more of the
somatosensory input from the environment, which is going to trigger an external cue or a drive to
start to explore. The infant at that period of time can lift their legs out of the base of support.
So they can, you'll see a triple flexion. So 90 degrees at the hip, 90 degrees at the knee,
neutral position of the ankle joint or subtalar joint. They'll be able to bring their hands
together and bring their hands to their mouth along. And let's explain what's actually required
to do that because again, most adults would take that for granted. But what is it neuromuscularly
that is being hardwired in that three month old infant that is pretty impressive. And when you
really stop to think about it, that they're able to bring both legs up, coordinate that movement.
And by the way, are they necessarily doing that the way, you know, a 50 year old person would do
that if you laid them on their back? Like having now watched a lot of infants, they tend to all
kind of do it in a very similar way, whereas adults tend to not do it in a certain way.
Right. So neurologically, the coordination and timing of that deep stabilization
group of musculature needs to be on point to be able to create a fixed point so that the,
again, the larger muscle groups can anchor off that to bring the legs up. Now, the infant has
different, you know, there's a different thoracic cage size at that point, their head in relation
to their body is bigger, their limb length is bigger. They're still growing the, the bones are
still forming. So that's much different than a 50 year old. Our lip proportions are different,
our mobility is going to be different. We may have different body proportions, you know, mobility,
but we, we all went through these developmental milestones and
most of us develop our central nervous system in a healthy way. So we still have those same motor
patterns that our central nervous system is going to want to kick into. Some of the efficiency
of accessing those nice stereotypical motor patterns that we're born with can be compromised
due to soft tissue dysfunction, rigidity, lack of range of motion throughout the, throughout our joints,
you know, postural habituation that Yanda described. All that factors into our, can override
the access to those ideal patterns. What Prague school tries to do is with the specific assessments,
assess that efficiency of that deep stabilization system, whatever age that we're at, and then
utilize specific, what we call active exercises, which are based off of the developmental milestones,
which we'll get back to in a second, to utilize specific points of support and positioning
to help wake up or facilitate those patterns that we still have as adults.
So three months of age is the start of that ability to create a sagittal stabilization.
Tell people what sagittal means versus quorum. So sagittal is kind of like straight ahead.
Frontal plane would be if you're on your side or to the side, and then there's transverse plane,
which is, think about rotating in the transverse plane. So what happens now is they approach six
months of age. So three months, you see the start, four months, that coordination is usually complete
for four, four and a half months. Once you, they've completed that, that ideal
facilitation of a fixed point. Now they start to be able to utilize the oblique slings,
and you'll start to see some differentiation in the pelvis and the limbs. And as that
synergy gets more and more efficient, which means better, better management of that intra-abdominal
pressure, you'll see the hips coming up into higher position, the legs coming up into,
being able to come up into a higher position. The infant's range of reach will improve as well.
At four months, they're able to touch the groin area. At five months, they can reach their knees.
At six months, they can reach their feet. And then by seven months, they're bringing the foot
to the mouth. There's enough synergy.
And just to be clear, most people would say, is that just a result of increasing flexibility?
But really the answer is not so much that they have more flexibility. They are quite flexible
at birth. It's more that they now have the motor control and the stability to coordinate something
that is everywhere from shoulder to foot or hand to foot, basically.
And do it in an efficient manner. So you're a parent and you remember when the kids were
developing, and I get this all the time. They're like, oh, my son was rolling all the way over at
three months. That is possible. They can normally, well, not normally, but ideally at that six month
period of time, there's enough of that synergy and coordination and timing that the infant,
you'll see the infant at that time rolling onto its stomach. Now they could maybe do it at three
months, but they're not going to do it with that coordination and that efficiency of transfer of
force and load. You may see them turn and kind of revert back to more of that newborn posture,
meaning they're finding a way to turn. They're using more of a compensatory pattern to make
that action happen. Kind of the same thing you see with movement with adults. If the
the synergy, coordination, timing of deep stabilization is not on point, they find a
way to move. But when they move, as with the first weeks of life, the newborn infant, you'll see
anterior pelvic tilt. You see a flaring of the rib cage, the shoulders, you'll see elevation,
protraction, and reclamation or extension through the cervical spine. The newborn, when they look
or when they move, the whole body is moving. They don't have that ability to create that fixed point,
but they're still able to make movements as they're going through the developmental milestones
with that motivation or that drive to move and explore their environment. They may find ways to
reach that toy, but not be creating ideal centration and stabilization.
With the central nervous system maturation, it's not like at three months, four months, six months,
boom, they wake up and automatically they're in this perfect synergy, coordination, timing.
As that central nervous system is maturing, there's thousands of trials and errors. They're
forming the brain mapping and motor engrams, finding the right points of support as the
coordination of the central nervous system is kicking in. You may see at the beginning of
six months and they're turning, maybe they're not able to keep the alignment of the diaphragms
during the turning, but they're still able to do it. Maybe by then three weeks into it, now their
coordination and timing has become more efficient and better and they're able to make that turn
with a better quality of activation. How does it go from there? What gets them to crawling and
ultimately standing? What you see with the developmental milestones, at the start of three
months, we talked about with the newborn, you have more of the lower central nervous system
structures are maturing. At three months, we see more maturation in the subcortical region of the
central nervous system and that's where we get the manifestation of these postural foundations.
So as that central nervous system matures, certain milestones, three months, four months,
five, six, seven, you'll see the infant starting to be able to attain higher, more unstable positions.
And these developmental milestones are moving towards basically the verticalization process,
going from either supine on the back or prone and then working their way up trial and error,
learning with that healthy central nervous system maturation where at seven months,
they're able to come to their side. Eight months, they come up into what we call a high oblique sit
position. Nine months, they're able to crawl. 10, 11 months, you'll see them being able to attain
like a kneeling position. 12 months, they're squatting. 13, 14 months, they're standing.
And then 14, 16 months, on average, you see the start of of ambulation. Now this is variable.
Some kids, my son was walking at 10 months. There's maybe 15 months, 16 months. So there's
variability within these milestones of where we see the infants. But on average,
these specific points, you'll see a specific competency in stability and reaching or moving
towards that verticalization process. Now, if you exclude cases of pathology like CP and things
like that, where there are injuries that are preventing the neuromuscular development and
the achievement of these milestones, is it more or less the case that all kids who are
given the fair chance to sort of explore and go about these things naturally will reach a certain
age, call it two or three. And they'll be quite healthy from a dynamic and movement standpoint.
Like is it, for example, like yesterday we spent a bunch of time looking at my three and a half year
old and frankly, it's a clinic and movement at that age, right? Is it safe to assume basically
all three year olds move really, really well? Like they haven't started to get into the habituated
movement patterns that will begin to destroy them, right? Yeah. So, Vojta and others talk about
usually what they see is around 70% of new infants are going to have that healthy central
nervous system maturation, go through the first weeks of life, the postural foundations,
the three to 12 months, the subcortical, and then from two, four, six, six years of age,
you have more of the cortical maturation where you see fine motor dexterity and movement,
ability to write and you see the language develop and you see motor learning.
So, sorry, the subcortical phase goes till about two?
Three to 12 months is where we see these postural foundations. After that, you start to get that
cortical integration maturation, but the motor learning and the process, I mean, it's like two
to six, but I mean, and beyond. Now, I'm surprised to hear you say only 70%. Right. So, this is,
I don't know if I can say the study, maybe it's their observation.
So, they talk about 70% normal maturation. The other 30%, it's a spectrum. So, you'll have on
one end, the CP child or the CNS pathology, but then there's this spectrum on the other end of
the spectrum. Yanda called it minimal brain dysfunction. I think it's also called central
coordination disorder. So, there's maybe not that ideal development, but again, there's a spectrum
to that. So, that may manifest during that, when we see the cortical time of central nervous system
maturation, maybe there is learning disabilities or not as efficient movement patterns. And this is
something that Prague school, as far as a curriculum, there's a whole pediatrics section
with their curriculum, which they go deeper into that aspect of observation and specific
utilization of treatment options. So, usually with a healthy central nervous system maturation
and a good environment for the child to explore movement and the variability of movement and do
the trial and error and find their ideal points of support, you're going to see this nice,
healthy maturation. Things that may compromise that, I mean, we see in modern society and culture,
a kid who's in their car seat six hours a day or maybe doesn't have that environment where they
can explore and crack. I think another one that I remember Michael sharing with me was when kids
are sped up on milestones. So, for example, those seats that prematurely prop kids into a seated
position, well, even before that little bobby chair, and again, we're all guilty of this. I know we
stuck our kids in these things, at least the first two, because when our third kid came along, I was
already interested in DNS, so then he became sort of the observation for DNS. But with our first two,
yeah, you're going to stick them in those silly seated chairs and they don't have the support.
Before they're ready.
Before they're ready, so they can't even support their own weight, so they're in this slouch
position and then you put them in those things. We called it the circle of neglect, so it's like
the thing where they're standing before they should be standing. So all of these things
actually interfere with the normal neuromuscular development. Putting kids in shoes too early
probably does a tremendous disservice to them.
Right. So ideally, they're going to have an environment where they're going to kind of figure
this out themselves. Verse, you know, another one is the little walkers that they'll hold on to and
walk. You know, ideally, they're going to play with their environment and with that combination
of healthy central nervous system maturation, find those ideal points of support and be able to
utilize those motor patterns that are manifested with that healthy central nervous system.
So the environment that we have children in is key. And this, I mean, you can take this
and look at, you know, just our society just as adults.
Well, yeah, let's go from, okay, so we can put them in shoes too early, put them in silly sit-up
seats in the circle of neglect and give them walkers. And then another huge set of insults
come when they go to school, right? Because now they're sitting in chairs for six or seven hours
a day. And what does that do for, you know, a six or seven year old, which is unfortunately,
by the time they're six, they're sort of sitting in chairs six hours a day at least. So what is that
doing to interfere with this process? So this is where you start to see the start of that postural
syndromes. You know, when we get into those sustained seated postures, one of the main things
that happens during those developmental milestones with healthy central nervous system maturation is
we're able to lie and keep alignment or approximation of the pelvic floor and the
thoracic diaphragm. The more efficiently we do that, the more efficiently we manage
intermodal pressure and uprighting throughout the spine. And then again, transfer of force and load.
If we fall into repetitive postures or postural habituation, which as a society is
kind of a bit prevalent, gravity is going to win. No matter how nice the chair is,
we're going to start to fall into that slumping posture. And when we get into that slumping
posture, the shoulder is coming forward. That is actually going to create an inhibition of the
diaphragm's ability to descend. And again, we need that descending of the healthy
and ideal descending of the diaphragm for both respiration and stabilization. So if we start
getting that descending becomes inhibited due to the postural habituation, our brain is going to
find a way to get air to the lungs. So it'll start to kick in the accessory breathing musculature,
which is that the sternocleidomastoid, upper traps, muscles called the scalenes,
which attached here, cervical spine and the upper two ribs. You'll see the pec minor also
start to help to lift the thoracic cage to help get the expansion to get the air. So again,
the brain starts to do its job, which we need air, we're going to use these guys to get the air.
And it's a good short term kind of survival strategy. But if we do it often enough,
that becomes the go to pattern. So you'll see a change in respiratory pattern, meaning
decreased utilization of full expansion of the diaphragm, and more of a pattern of over utilizing
the accessory breathing musculature, which this can occur quite young. I mean, I think when we,
you know, we were joking about it yesterday, but you look at my youngest, I mean, his abdomen is
huge. And that's obviously an enormous asset to him, you can see it when he breathes, it's his
it's abdominal expansion more than it is thoracic expansion, right? These, you know,
a child that age, if doing thing, you know, if developing normally is not using any of these
accessory respiratory muscles. And there's something about this anchor point being in
the abdomen, right? I mean, one of the first things I learned in DNS was how to regain
intra abdominal pressure through eccentric loading of that cylinder. And I don't think it
had ever been presented to me how important that was, because prior to that, any amount of
perceived intra abdominal pressure had been acquired through concentric loading.
Right. So for example, when trying to pick up something heavy, you can you can take two
strategies to that. I think I think most people would agree, if you want to pick up 300 pounds
right now, you must generate pressure in the abdomen. I don't I don't think anybody would
assume that you could pick up 300 pounds, which is twice your body weight, without generating
pressure here. But how you do it matters. Right. So explain those differences. And again,
either with or without the developmental lens. But I but I think that the developmental lens
is always a great way to think about how kids move. Right. So if you think about developmentally,
and how that stabilizing stereotype evolves, think of it as a an inside out strategy,
you're creating an intra abdominal pressure to load the abdominal wall. And then with the loading
of the abdominal wall eccentric isometric. And then there's this interplay of all that activity
concentric, eccentric isometric to manage that pressure for whatever task that you need to,
to do. So if I'm sitting here, and I'm going to pick up that pen,
I don't I need some function of stabilization to then, you know, move this limb,
try to provide a fixed point for my anterior posterior slings to provide a nice position for
the shoulder girdle to then, again, get that synergy throughout the kinematic chain and pick
up the pen. So there's a certain amount of management of that intermural pressure that I
need. If I go to like the chairs that we're sitting in that we moved earlier, this is a lot more weight,
I'm going to need a lot more coordination and management and creation of intra abdominal
pressure to create the fixed point to transfer the ground reactive forces through my lower
extremities through my trunk and pelvis to you know, my arms holding holding the chair. So there's
more facilitation of that intermural pressure. So that's what we see developmentally, that quality
of stabilization, and that stabilization, it's not static, it's dynamic, we should be able to
manage that intermural pressure through full extension, full rotation, full flexion. That's
the beauty of that dynamic neuromuscular stability. And that's what we see with our
that quality we see in the high level athletes. We can also create stability by bracing. And if
you think about bracing, if someone's going to punch me in the stomach, I may go for a cone centric.
And where the abdominal wall shortens and tightens, I'm still creating a stabilizing function.
And I can still use that to, you know, move objects or prepare prepare for for impact. When
it comes to dynamic movement, the the inside out strategy in the central nervous system management
of that stabilization allows me to create the stability efficiently where I need it,
but then also be able to, for example, relaxed my extremity. So with with high level movers athletes,
you see they'll have nice postural foundations, they also have very nice cortical function or
body awareness. So the fetters, Kelly Slater's and surfing, they have that ability to their
movement looks fluid and effortless. So they have that ability to relax and efficiently stabilize
where they need to stabilize. Sometimes you need to incorporate that bracing strategy on top of
the the facilitation of intramodal pressure for excessive loads where we go beyond our threshold,
our functional threshold, meaning our ability to keep that quality of stabilization.
When we go beyond that ability, we go into what we call the functional gap. And when we go into
the functional gap, that's where we see more of that high threshold strategy, maybe bracing
strategy to get the job done, to get that weight up, to maybe kick that ball a little extra harder.
Training wise and athletics, that's where those athletes spend a lot of time because they're
always they're kind of pushing that threshold all the time. So you'll see with athletes,
a tendency, if they're spending all their time training, competing in that functional gap beyond
the the ability to maintain the more more efficient transfer of force and load, then
that pattern, that high threshold compensatory pattern,
becomes the starts to become the norm with everything picking up the pencil.
So one of the things that we try to do, or I try to do as far as with training and rehabilitation,
not just with the athletes, but with, you know, a general population is help them facilitate that
quality of stabilization so they can increase that threshold of being able to main, you know,
stay within that that functional threshold or that functional capacity. So that when they do
have to go into the functional gap and go to those compensatory patterns, it's not all the time.
Well, let's let's talk about an elite athlete. And again, I think the thing with the really the
most elite is they don't have to train in DNS. A lot of them are just doing this naturally. I mean,
that's sort of what makes Roger Federer great. And one of the hallmarks of that greatness is
injury prevention. It's not just the greatness at what they do. It's the longevity with which they
can do it. Yes. So when I lecture, I use Federer as an example, you know, you look at his career,
just longevity and injury wise, you know, when he has been injured, but usually you see a quick
recovery. Going back to Yager and Jalesny, Jalesny had a 20 year career in javelin, which I don't
think is very common. Yager is 48. He's still playing the with Yager and Jalesny,
Pablo working with them, the emphasis was on the awareness, the facilitation of this ideal
stabilizing pattern, the timing of movement, the centration throughout the kinematic chain. And
then with that the ability to we call differentiate, you know, within, for example, the pelvis over that
femoral head. So the focus was with them was the quality over quantity, I guess you can say.
What percentage of his time do you think, because obviously Federer has just an unbelievable
functional capacity. How long how often do you think he is in excess of that in that gap zone
where he is using compensatory movements that are putting long term stability at risk?
So I think when you see you see those athletes that rise to the top, they have that you watch
Federer, for example, you see the point that the creating the point of support, the positioning,
the alignment of everything. He's creating naturally that centration and that transfer
of force and load. There is times maybe he gets out of position or a little extra hardware, he's
going to go into that functional gap. He's naturally has a functional, huge functional
capacity where he can maintain that. I think with him, you also and this goes to training,
he has a good team. He has trainers that, you know, are programming certain things in a way
and giving him certain things so that he can still facilitate that quality of movement and build
strength capacity on top of that. One thing that I see, for example, out on the PGA tour,
I'll see, you know, players that have good programs, good coaching, you know, they'll tend
to stay within that functional capacity. They're still pushing it and still, you know, with them,
it's just repetitive motion, which partial habituation, repetitive motion, injury are
things that compromise that synergy and coordination of that dynamic stability.
So if you have good programming, dosing, loading, timing, recovery, then and on top of that,
you have amazing, you know, potty awareness and cortical function, you're going to see longevity
and you're going to see nice quality of movement. What I see on the other end is players, athletes,
poor training programs, over training, you know, spending too much time in the functional gap,
you know, falling into what my colleague Rich Ulm talks about, the extensor compression syndrome,
which you see a lot with lifting with the power athletes, which he works with a lot of.
Then you see, when you have that reliance on that higher threshold, you see more incidence of injury,
longer recovery, verse the opposite, the Federer's. Yeah, they get injured, but they recover fairly
quickly. And that's what you see again, Jager and Jalesny are nice examples of that both checks
and Pavel working with them, you know, over this 20 year period of time, integrating and putting
in his ideas and his experience with everything that we talked about with those, you know,
rehabilitation pioneers into these athletes, kind of like a little, you know, test subject,
so to speak. So now, you Prague school and DNS practitioners, that's what we're trying to help
integrate with our athletes with the general population. So what percentage of people that
you work with are coming with an injury, and therefore in need of rehabilitation, where you're
now applying DNS to presumably go back to, hey, this is where the breakdown was, let's go back
to where that breakdown would have occurred developmentally and go back and rebuild those
steps. So we're gonna, you're gonna learn how to stabilize your neck or stabilize your head using
the stabilizing muscles appropriately, you're going to learn how to generate concentric
intra abdominal pressure, and you're going to learn how to centrate ipsilaterally and
contralaterally and all of these things. And then what percentage of your patients are not coming
with an injury, but are coming for performance enhancement and saying, you know, I just can't
throw this fastball any faster than 89 miles per hour. And the only way I'm going to get that
faster is if I can create a better whip between my right hand and my left leg and hip, you know,
so those are two ends of the spectrum. And how do you spend your time on those? Right. So
majority of people are coming to me because pain and injury, what happens especially with the
athletes, once we address that, once we calm down, whether it's if it's acute or chronic injury,
we come, we decrease pain and and utilize the the there's different manual methods within DNS and
then integrating the exercises that are based off of those developmental milestones. Once they get
to a certain point, ideally, I'm going to work with a trainer or with the coach. And hopefully
they're on the same, you know, mindset, so that they can then progress to the strength training to
the specific technique. More and more, these athletes are, you know, it's a combination of
once they're out of pain, we work with the quality of stabilization and movement and transfer of force
and load. Let's take a group of let's say 100 athletes who come to you in pain. Again, just
looking for rough numbers, what percentage of them will buy into the thesis of this very
non-traditional way of rehabilitating is going to help what percentage of that what of that 100 will
stay with the program to get better? Right? Not enough. So what's the no 10 20%? Maybe that's it?
Yeah, what I see happening, you know, for example, Major League Baseball is integrating
DNS more and more. So in San Diego, with the Padres, I started to consult with them a bit.
There's a hitting coach for the Dodgers that comes in and we kind of workshop ideas
where, you know, he's integrating the DNS concepts and principles. So it's starting to get recognized
more for that value, as far as the performance enhancement aspects of it.
Culturally within sport, what I see, especially in the West, there's, you know, they want numbers,
they want, okay, what's their peak? What's their lift? You know, what's their
their strength capacity, which is important. But I think it's also important to, again,
like integrate those to the quality of movement and stability, and then increasing that, you know,
their their strength thresholds. But even just with an injury. So if you let's just say 100
athletes that are, you know, let's say gymnasts and hockey players and football players that
come in with lower back pain, you're saying only 20 of those would stick with the program
until they got better. 80 of them would abandon the program before they improved.
A lot of times, and just across the patient population, a lot of times, once people are out
of pain, it's kind of out of sight out of mind, they go back, they go back into their patterns.
That's what I'm trying to differentiate, which is how many of them just stick with it long enough
to get out of pain. The next question I'm going to ask is, once out of pain, how many of them
stick with the program and switch basically from rehab to prehab? So going back to that,
one of my goals, especially with the athlete, once they're out of pain, we develop a
prehabilitation kind of program. And we utilize those, again, going back to the knowledge of
developmental kinesiology and developmental milestones, which later will actually go through.
So based on what I'm seeing with their insufficiencies and with the insufficiency of
with the insufficiency of that coordination of stabilization, I will give them certain things,
certain sequences of movements and exercises that they practice with awareness to facilitate
better strategy for stability. And then that's part of their movement preparation,
or prehabilitation before, whether it's their strength training, or their technique training,
or going out and performing. And so that's a larger percentage, because that's part of
what I kind of program into the rehabilitation. So some athletes will get that and they're okay,
great, this is this is good, I'm going to go do it. And then occasionally, they're coming back
and getting maybe we're adding to it based on what how they're functioning. Now,
other athletes, they want more. And that's that that's that smaller percentage. Part of it too,
probably access, you know, availability. As far as being able to be, you know, in San Diego and
working one on one with me. So, you know, there's, there's different factors that will
tie into how much they're they're doing. But within the whole treatment protocol,
rehabilitation protocol, I'm giving them things that they should then integrate into their programs.
What is the most common chief complaint of a person that walks into your office? Is it lower
back pain? That would be my guess. Yeah, majority is low back. Okay, so what are the most common
causes of lower back pain that you see? Across the board, if if they're suffering from
you know, low back pain, whether it's acute or chronic, usually there's an underlying pattern
of that lack of or the inefficient activation of the deep stabilizing system,
and more of a tendency towards that extension compression, you know, activation, that over
activation of flexor extensor. So you know, you know, you know what that means in a bit more detail,
given the ubiquity of this injury, and the probability that 80% of the people listening
to this have already experienced back pain or will experience back pain in their lives. I want
to make sure if people take nothing away from this podcast, they understand the etiology of lower
back pain. Yeah. So unless you've had a let's say a car accident or a fall, that's like an acute
injury. That can be a cause of low back pain. The majority that I see, it's more of a
chronic overload over time, that if we have that strategy of flex too much flexor extensor activity,
which compromises the positioning of the inter segmental, the joints and the transfer
of force and load, then with the compensatory pattern, we'll see more of a hinging in through
that lumbar sacral region. And with that hinging, over time, it's like if you keep bending a spoon,
you know, it's gonna break, you weaken the structure. So, you know, take a disc.
Yeah, let's talk about the actual anatomy. And I yesterday I said I wished I'd brought a skeleton.
So the sacrum is basically a single bone, it's actually fused. So at one point, it was multiple
sacred with the ilium. Right. So you have this sort of one fused sacrum. And then you have these
five lumbar discs numbered one through five. Now, between each of those lumbar vertebral
bodies is a disc. And then there's one between the fifth lumbar vertebral body and the sacrum. So
we refer to them as you know, l3 l4 is the disc between three and four and l5 s1 is the disc
between there, right? Behind each of these vertebral bodies. So these these vertebral bodies are sort
of held in place by the discs, but then also by the facet joints that run behind them. And it's
really difficult to show this, we'll probably have to pull up some images to make this easier
for people to see. But the the facet joints, and then and then sort of the lamina, which are these
those sort of longer bones, hold it all together, but they don't really provide this support. I think
the support is probably at the facet joints and at the disc interfaces. That probably fair?
Yeah. And then think of all the musculature as a scaffolding. Yeah. And the you know, the
levers and you know, that help with that stabilization and then the activation of
that deep stabilization as an uprighting effect. And let's talk about which muscles are on the
front of that. So if you were to cut me open here, and let's just say you pull everything out of the
way. So you pull my bow out of the way you pull everything and you go right down onto my
spine. What are the muscles you're going to see that are attached to the anterior or front portion
of my vertebral bodies? So two two main ones that we can talk about is the psoas, which
attaches to those transverse processes of the lumbar spine. And then the quadratus lumborum,
which also attaches to those processes. Both of those, they, with those attachments, they
also come up and they attach right where the diaphragm attaches the cruor of the diaphragm.
So, you know, if you, again, maybe you can pull up those images and put it on the show notes.
So you see the, all those kind of coalescing in that thoracic lumbar region. If, if I have that
ideal activation of that descending of the diaphragm and the facilitation of that inch
abdominal pressure, that pressure again loads the abdominal wall and creates that fixed point that
the psoas and the quadratus are anchoring off of. If that's compromised, they don't have anything to
anchor off of. And then you see that excessive extension and that overload of those facet joints.
And with exaggerate what the extension posture looks like so people can see it. So your hips will
your hips will move forward. So if you picture your pelvis as a bowl, you're tipping the bowl
forward, tipping the bowl forward. And then if you think of your rib cage, rib cage is coming forward
as well. So your spine, which normally has a bend in it, gets more of a bend. Excessive. Yeah. And
with that oblique position of the diaphragm and the pelvic floor, now there's a mechanical
disadvantage of the abdominal wall. So we took a cylinder that's supposed to sit like this
and we made it go like this. So now the tendency is going to be the extensor over activity
and the flexor, the psoas. So now you're just getting this repetitive compression on those
facet joints and the disc is getting this repetitive hinging flexion. And then in the
center of the disc, we have the fluid or the nucleus working its way through those
antiafibers as they weaken. And then that's where you get the disc protrusions or, you know,
it's, uh, substance can leak out and the body will, you know, go into that, that spat, that
protective spasm also. So you'll, you'll see the disc injury, but then you also see over time,
facet hypertrophy. So the, the degenerative changes and the accumulation of, of bony material,
trying to help stabilize. So part of my story and kind of discovering, uh, drove me into,
utilizing DNS, discovering Prague school, I developed what was called a spondylolysis,
which is a, uh, uh, stress fracture in the spine, part of the, the, the pars, which is kind of
that, that arch that attaches the vertebra and then the, to the facet joints. So for me
with overtraining, uh, poor recovery, uh, poor postural foundations, um, I was premature and,
um, looking back, knowing what I know now, looking at pictures or videos of myself, I could see that,
that compensatory pattern. It didn't catch up to me till, till college, you know, especially as
we're younger, we have a huge ability to compensate and we can get away with stuff.
But in college it caught up to me with, uh, um, with that, that stress fracture. So, um,
I was kind of like the poster boy of upper and lower cross syndrome and lack of efficient, uh,
stabilizing strategy. I had plenty of motivation and drive and practice, you know, hour upon hour,
but at a certain point, you know, structure overload of, you know, in that, that for me,
L4 L5 region that gave way, when that gave way, um, then I went into this whole chronic pain cycle
and it wasn't until, uh, you know, I went orthopedist, uh, physical therapists,
chiropractic, all of them helped in their own way, but it was, I was missing, I knew there was
something missing. So probably for selfish reasons, I went into this profession trying to figure out
my own pain and try to figure out how to recover. And, uh, you know, in, in medical school and same
chiropractic school first year, you're just getting bombarded with all anatomy, physiology,
functional biomechanics. All of it was amazing and interesting, but I'm like, this isn't helping me.
It wasn't until the second year where I was introduced to, uh, Prague school,
Yanda and Levitt and what they were teaching, it was like, oh, finally something made sense. And
just intuitively it made sense to, to what I was dealing with. So I started to, you know, learn more
and more about that while I was in school, uh, incorporating some of the treatment methods and
the exercises and that, that got me, you know, further along of kind of pulling myself out of,
my own kind of chronic pain. And then in, once I was out of school, uh, 97, 98,
after a few years, there was a clinician, Dr. Leibenson taking small groups over to Prague
to learn from those, the, you know, those pioneers and those, those Prague therapists.
Um, so I was able to go over there. I believe it was like an eight day, uh, intensive kind of
lectures and workshops. Got to see Levitt. Uh, but unfortunately the year before, uh, Yanda had
passed away and I believe Vojta passed away, I think early 2000, 2000, 2001. Um, but that's,
that was my first introduction to, uh, professor Pablo Colaj. And at that time it was his ideas
talking about developmental kinesiology and then utilizing that, that knowledge to develop the
assessments and the treatment strategies, not only, you know, to the cerebral palsy population,
but then he was talking about the adults and then, and then the sports population. So
once I saw that again, that was like another light bulb and another piece of that puzzle for me to,
to work my way out of it, out of my own, uh, situation. Um, and then from 2003,
basically I've watched this evolution of DNS, the concepts and principles turn into the actual name
and then the curriculum of where we're at now. Now you're, you're quite senior within the,
the, the, the sort of international community of DNS. Uh, you're one of only
18 international instructors. Isn't that about right? Yeah. What, what are the different levels
of certification within DNS, the highest level being where you're at that's can anybody attain
that level or do you have to, you know, be a chiropractor, a physician or an osteopathic
physician? Like what are the, yeah. So there's, there's three tracks of the dynamic neuromuscular
stabilization curriculum. One is a clinical track. It's a DNS, a B and C. And then the fourth course
is a D course, which you actually go to Prague and it's like an intensive, uh, with the, with the
Prague therapists. Um, there's a specific exercise sport, uh, sequence of courses. There's three
courses there. The first one is focused in clinicians only type of thing. The second one
is designed for trainers as well as clinicians because ideally we, we designed that one
because we want the two populations working together and on the same page. Um, but it's a
little more focused towards, uh, you know, less manual and more of what, how you can integrate
it into a training program. The third is, uh, pediatrics, where are you going to utilize the
DNS handling skills with, with infants? And that's a, uh, series of, um, I believe three courses with
a fourth culminating in, in Prague. Um, so that curriculum, I believe started come about 2009.
And then off of that, we have specialty courses, uh, where we integrate, you know, um, different
things. One of Prague school's goals, it's, you know, they don't want DNS to be a, this is a DNS
technique. These are concepts and principles that professor collage, you know, building on those,
those founders and his experience and his, his ideas. Um, it's meant to be integrated into
everything else because it can, that's one thing I love about it is, um, you can easily integrate
it into the good work that you're already doing, whether you're a trainer, whether you're a clinician
and you do a specific technique, you know, for example, the Prague through the school therapists,
they did, they do visceral mobilization. They have specific soft tissue and mobilization
techniques, and they're constantly exploring and trying to evolve, you know, the, the teaching and
the, and the integration. So, um, it's a, a nice knowledge base and skillset to have, uh, again,
to enhance what you're already doing. And so, I mean, this afternoon, we're going to go down
and actually demonstrate a lot of this stuff by video, because I think that it's really challenging
to talk about this stuff. It's just not that amenable to a discussion. Um, it really has to be shown.
Um, and frankly, even showing it as challenging, I think experiencing it is, uh, is the gold standard.
That's the, that's the ultimate. Um, it's not just movements. It's not just specific exercises,
but it's facilitating the awareness of the, um, the ideal stabilization and the support. Um,
and then with that, you know, with, with my patients or whether it's training, um, I want
my patients or my athletes to feel the, that synergy and feel that, uh, ability to stabilize
where they need to, but then also relax where they need to. And it's a, there's a little bit of a
process. It's not a cookie cutter thing. Like just do this, this, this. Um, you have to put some work
into it and you have to practice it both as a patient and as a clinician or trainer. And I guess
that would be, you know, maybe, uh, one of the drawbacks for people is, um, you know, everything
out there, people are doing, doing good work and trying to help people. Um, and if they have
something that's working for them and we introduce these concepts and principles and they're not
easily integrated, then, um, maybe they don't, they don't adapt them or they'll adapt a portion
of them, which is fine as well. Um, but it's, it's something that, uh, in the curriculum,
uh, you know, we try to emphasize the need for, um, you know, uh, feeling and, and practicing the,
the movements that we can show later. I mean, I can only speak for myself, um, but I wonder if
my generalization is correct. I think my guess would be that the people who come to DNS late in life
with an injury get better, but then stick with it are probably people who like to really tinker,
tinker with things and like to toil away and don't necessarily need quick results, but can
sort of anchor to a philosophy. They sort of have faith in it and then they can sort of keep
pursuing it because, um, it, a, you don't, it, it, it feels a lot of the time like you're not doing
much, you know? And I think for someone who's used to, you know, being quite impatient with what they,
you know, I want results today and, you know, Hey, I just started CrossFit and two days later I'm
doing power cleans. Like this is awesome. Um, and, and if, if that's the, if that's the dopamine surge
that a person needs, they're gonna, I think they're going to struggle with a system where you might
spend a week, you know, daily practicing, learning how to breathe again. Um, and you'll never stop
practicing that by the way, you'll never stop practicing, you know, a really great breathing
pattern and a really great pattern of accessing these deep stabilizing muscles we've spoken about
and practicing all of these infant like movements. And yes, it gets more challenging over time and
you do these flows that become quite enjoyable, um, and can be very challenging. I mean, they're,
most of these things I still can't even do actually, especially with weight. Um, but I don't know,
I guess I would say, I always think of, um, things in medicine through the lens of efficacy
and effectiveness. So efficacy is how well does something work if it's adhered to correctly?
Effectiveness is if you just throw it out in the real world, how well does it work?
To me, DNS might be the single most efficacious thing I have ever come across as far as,
you know, healing injury and preventing injury. I'm not sure if it's the most effective thing,
which is not a knock on it, but the point is to your point earlier, a lot of people aren't going
to do it, you know, especially once you get them out of pain, they're not going to want to stay
with it. Now, I don't know why that is. Um, but that's the thing that I would hope that DNS can
improve upon in the next decade. It's only a decade old, but it's like, how do we take this
thing that is so efficacious? Again, meaning if a person actually does it, they're going to get
better. It's almost impossible not to fix back pain, neck pain, shoulder pain, like all of these
injuries, they're going to get better. Where, where we want to do it is make sure that hey,
people, you know, we want 90% of people to be able to stick to it once they start.
Part of that is with the curriculum, whether you're a clinician or a trainer,
the part of the process is with the assessment, you're training your eye just like a good coach
will recognize, um, you know, something not right with the runner or the tennis player or the golf
swing. Um, you know, you can, uh, DNS will have the specific assessment and those specific exercises
based off of development. Once you develop your eye and recognize where the insufficiencies are,
you can recognize that insufficiency of stability within the, the swing within the running within
the, the lift. So you can, in my opinion, um, you can get to the point where you can utilize these
concepts and principles, communicate them in a way, you know, to the deadlift or, um, to the runner
where, uh, you can help them in that manner. Maybe they're not doing the specific developmental
movement, but you're giving them ideas as far as loading, queuing that will facilitate that, um,
that efficiency. So, um, and that's the challenge you're dealing with in major league baseball is
you know, that there's a way to get an extra four miles an hour out of a pitch,
but you also know that that athlete probably doesn't want to, or doesn't have the time to,
maybe I would argue they should have the time to, but maybe doesn't want to go back and do
all of the fundamental movements and master what a, what an infant does. So now your challenge is
while you're on the pitching mound, how do I put a principle in you that's going to create
a little more whip like stability? Right. Part of that is training up the staff that will be
dealing with that athlete full, full time, the more, uh, skilled and, you know, movement towards
mastery of that, the better it's going to be for the people that they work with. So part of that is
that process, that education, that, that learning process. And, um, that's what I see,
you know, people starting to, to ask for, to, to help with, because a lot of people will,
will take the coursework and they're like, Oh man, yeah, that's, that's awesome. How do I
integrate it? And that's also, um, part of the curriculum we've created kind of specialty
courses. So for example, um, there's certain expertise within Prague school. We have a Prague
therapist that, um, focuses on the running athlete. We have one of the instructors dance
professionally. So we have, uh, you know, a dance specific exercise sport course we've done golf.
We've done, uh, baseball. Uh, Dr. Ohm has a strength specific lifting specific course talking
about that integration. So we're, we're trying to create, um, uh, kind of that curriculum to help
with that integration. Cause if we just have the standard courses, you know, more of that's going
to tend to be clinical. Um, and, uh, but if we show how to actually do the integration within
the specialty course, whoever's working with those athletes or an athlete themselves,
that's going to be, we're going to be able to communicate it better. Cause they understand
that, um, you know, that sport we even done, we've done, uh, you know, a hockey specific,
um, one of the check therapists works with the national check national hockey team.
So obviously huge, you know, experience. And then we, we show the integration. So
that's part of that evolution of trying to communicate these concepts and principles
better, help people integrate them better so that we can again, enhance what we're
doing with our patients and with our athletes are with our, you know,
people that want to focus on performance. Well, Michael, this has been, this has been
interesting and I think it's going to get a lot more interesting when we, when we go and roll
around in the mats a little bit. And, and, um, I think give a little bit more of a visual explanation
of what a lot of this stuff looks like. So thanks so much for sharing your insights and, uh,
keeping up the fight. Thank you. That went faster than I thought. And I just feel like we scratched
the surface. So I know, I know. Looking forward to, to showing it, to help people, uh, understand
it a little bit better. Thank you. Yeah. And, and hopefully once people see it, they'll want to take
that next step, which is feeling it. And I, I true, I truly think that only when you feel this,
do you, do you understand it? And I think that's true of not just DNS. I think that's true of
PRI and FRC and all these other things that we've spoken about that in my mind all have a place in
both the world of rehab and a prehab. Yeah. If you, if you can feel it, then you can start to
integrate it and, you know, create that, that, uh, new pattern. Awesome. Thank you.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of the drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing
these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this. The qualities, which are a super short podcast
that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics and
tactics discussed on previous episodes of the drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.