Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey Steve, it's awesome to see you today, although I was really hoping we were going
to be able to figure out a way to do this in person if we waited long enough, but at
some point I just thought we just need to sit down and do this and videos almost as
good. So anyway, thanks so much for making time.
So excited to be here. Really looking forward to it.
I feel like I haven't seen you in person in, it's been too long. It's probably been four
years.
I think it was we drove around in that really noisy car of yours was the last time that
I was with you. The little tiny thing that made so much noise. You know what I'm talking
about?
Yeah, I sure do. Didn't go very fast, but it made a lot of noise for going slow.
So I think a lot of listeners probably are familiar with you, of course. They're familiar
with you through obviously your books, podcasts, things like that. But maybe it's worth actually
telling people a little bit about how you got interested in the study of economics.
And obviously it's through that study that your work became available to a much broader
swath of the population than just sort of economists. So what got you interested in
studying economics?
So I was never interested in economics and probably still not interested in economics,
but the way I became an economist was really through the back door. I was the worst kind
of student in college. I mean, I got good grades. I got into Harvard. I got good grades
at Harvard, but I didn't care about learning at all. All I really cared about was gaming
the system. And I had learned that the best way to pick classes was to find the classes
that everybody took because it turned out those were both really good classes in general
and really easy. And it just happened that at Harvard, Act 10, the introductory economics
course was exactly one of those courses. So I took it not because I was interested in
economics, but just because my rule of thumb was to take classes like that. And I remember
roughly, I don't know, the fifth or the sixth lecture was on this topic called comparative
advantage. And as the teacher walked us through it, I was just disgusted. And I thought, my
God, this is the easiest topic in the entire world. I have literally known about the concept
of comparative advantage since I was five years old. I mean, I understood it deeply in
my soul. I didn't know the name, like he was putting a name on it. And I remember at the
time going through and actually thinking, this is such a travesty. My parents are paying
this much per lecture at Harvard. It was a big number for this total drivel. Like this
is just an insult. And as I was walking out of the room, my best friend at college was
in the same class and he walked out next to me and he said, Oh my God, that lecture was
crazy. I said, I know how could they teach us such drivel? He said, no, that was the
most confusing thing I've ever heard. I don't think I couldn't understand that in a million
years. And I had this moment of clarity where I said, wait a second. I actually think like
an economist. And though, even though I've never been interested in the topic from that
moment on, it became clear and clear to me that I was just born thinking like an economist.
And it's not advice I would give to other people in general. I don't think it's great
advice to just do what you're good at, but I was so lazy and so intellectually unmotivated
that for me, it turned out not to be a bad path was just to say, well, who cares what
I'm interested in? Cause I wasn't really that interested in anything. Uh, let's just go
be an economist. And, um, and I didn't go willingly. I didn't, it took a long time for
me to be an academic economist. I, I graduated, I did management consulting. It was only my
deep disgust and hatred with management consulting, which in desperation, as I look for any exit,
I thought, well, the only thing I can even think of to get out of here is to go get a
PhD in economics, uh, which is what led me to get a PhD in economics. And if I had known
what it meant to compute a PhD in economics, I never would have done it. It was only complete
ignorance of what I was getting myself into that, that led me down that path, which turned
out to be a lucky path. I mean, things couldn't almost not have turned out better for me,
but it was only a series of mistakes, miscalculations and ignorance that, that led me to this lucky
place. But, but Steve, there's a lot of, um, I mean, there's a lot of, there's gotta be
some challenge and pain and resilience that requires doing everything you just described.
So, okay, maybe Econ 101 or whatever the course was, was a breeze, but at some point, you
know, you're taking senior courses at Harvard in economics. Were they challenging? Did you find
them interesting? I mean, what was kind of going through your mind as you're plotting your way
through undergrad? You know, I, I didn't ever intend to be an academic economist, so I didn't
approach it the way a normal, like someone who, who, who wants to be an academic economist
approached it, taking a bunch of math. So it turns out at the highest level of economics is all about
math. And I didn't take, I didn't take any math. I took exactly one math class at Harvard. It was
called math 1A. It was because I got a two on the calculus AP exam and I couldn't place out. And so
it was really high school calculus. It was the lowest math class they offered at Harvard. And, um,
and I did do quite well in that class. It was essentially me and the, the football team and the
hockey team were the only people who placed into that. And I smoked those guys, but, um, so I just
did, I just had fun. And honestly, in college, I just had fun. And I liked the economics classes
and they were, and they were easy for me because the intuition, economic intuition has always come
pretty easily, especially in microeconomics, uh, pretty easily. And, um, and the classes just weren't
that hard. They didn't require much math. I didn't know any math. And it was, I mean, college in general
for me was just so much fun. Uh, I, I had good friends and good times and it was easy and I,
independence and I just, you know, for me, those were the best four years of my life and I didn't
take school too seriously, but I did well. So, you know, it was all, that was just a breeze. It was the
shock of reality, the real world. I had no idea how unfun the real world was going to be when I
actually got into it. Uh, but college was fun. That is so funny to hear you say that I, I, I will
forever maintain that college was the worst four years of my life. And I hope I can say that now,
meaning that there will be no four year period that is still in front of me. That's going to be
as bad as those four years were. But I, I always enjoy hearing people talk about college being the
best four years of their lives. Um, you mentioned microeconomics, um, is maybe now is as good a time
as any to explain to people the difference between micro and macroeconomics because it is almost a
disservice to talk about economics as though it's one broad topic. Yeah, you're absolutely right.
And that, so microeconomics, well, let's start with macroeconomics. That's what most people think
of when they think of economics. They think about inflation and, uh, and unemployment, unemployment
and economic growth. Okay. And, and those are really important fundamental problems. Um, but they are,
they turn out to be incredibly hard problems because the degree of complexity in the macro
economy, you can think the macro economy is almost infinite, right? So it's, it's, it's this complex
system built up of billions of individual actors and you've got companies, you've got, look, it's
just a mess. Okay. And it turns out just making a long short, very short, a long story, very short
that, um, that we haven't made much headway and really understanding it. Because we've, we've
approached the profession with a kind of discipline, which says every model of macroeconomics
needs to start with foundations that are really, um, rational in, in the, in the base micro
foundations. And it turns out, I think the problems are just too hard and that approach in the end
isn't going to win. Okay. But what is microeconomics? Microeconomics is instead the study of individual
decision-making. So in a, in a world in which there's scarcity and there's competition, how do
I decide how to spend my income? How do I decide what job to do and, and how many hours of, of work
I want to do? How do firms decide what to make and where to locate and things like that? So these are
much smaller decisions and for me, much more intuitive decisions. Um, and, and they're able
to be analyzed both with the, the formal models of economics, which historically have been very
heavily predicated on rationality simply because it makes the math easy, along with the last 40
years of behavioral economics, where, uh, we've introduced a lot more psychology and mistakes and,
and a lot more freedom into the models that we use. But anyway, so, um, really they're almost
distinct micro and macroeconomics, uh, because, uh, really macro in the end is, is
really complicated. Not to make all my macro colleagues incredibly angry at me,
but very self-referential referential models because the problems are so hard that you need
to abstract so greatly to try to deal with the macro problems that I think we don't have a good
handle on them. So I've really steered clear of the macro problems to focus on the individual
decision-making, which is, I think both in my own life, much more relevant, but also I got something
to say because I have some intuition for it. So is there a hierarchy within economics, the way,
you know, so in physics, you sort of have sort of the theoretical physicists and the experimental
physicists and Nobel prizes will go back and forth between the two of those. Um, how does that work
in economics? Do, do we disproportionate amount of Nobel prizes or whatever the highest, I mean,
I guess the Nobel, it's not technically a prize, but it's close enough. When you look at the
highest levels of excellence and awards that are given in the entire field, do they disproportionately
lie on one side of those or the other? So historically economics has been a,
an entirely theoretical discipline. And so the highest status positions historically have been
in theory. Okay. Uh, where I make the distinction between theory and the analysis of data and
econometrics and actually trying to, you know, take messy data and, and make sense of it.
With the data revolution and the emergence of econometrics, it's been, uh, I think I switched
in the profession. So there are two big prizes in economics. There's a Nobel prize and then
there's something called the job. It's Clark medal, which is given to the, the most
influential economist under the age of four. You've won that prize, correct? I did win that. Yeah.
And, um, and so that more reflects what's going on in the present time. And so those prizes,
the Clark medal has, um, mostly gone in the last 20, 30 years, not always, but often to people at
the intersection of theory and data, which I think really is, is where the action is, um, in
economics. It's people who can make sense of data, but are looking at it through a lens of economics
and pushing economic thinking in that way. I think, um, I don't know if anyone cares about
this, but economics is really at a crossroads because it turned out when data analysis
really started to emerge and we could start to say things about causality and ways we couldn't
before the empirical part of economics really took off, but all of the easy stuff has been done.
And so we kind of estimated most of the parameters that we care about. And so the question is what
comes next. And what's happening in economics is that the push has been in the direction of,
okay, it's not enough to just estimate what's happened in the world in the past. That's really
what, what empirical economics is really good at is saying, I can look at what's happened in the
past. I can estimate a number, and then I can build models to try and say why now the task is
become greater. We should say, I'd not, I don't just want to understand the past.
I want to be able to build a model that has the flexibility to tell me what would have happened
if instead of the U S being a democracy, we were a dictatorship. Okay. So things that are so far out
of the realm of what actually happened, that it's almost like science fiction. And so what economists
do now is they're asked not just to estimate parameters really well, but to embed those
parameters into models, which then have enough degrees of freedom that you can start to imagine
if I turn this dial to that tile, what would happen. And I actually personally think that's
a terrible direction because I think, um, I think what has made economics great is that it's easy to
understand the estimates we create and you can say whether you like them or not based on fact
or the approach or whatever. But I think when we get into these more fanciful models, I think we're
going to end up running into a huge dead end is that, um, is that they're really too complicated
to be estimated well. And so we're just going to get into fantasy land of, of creating things that
are really not, um, grounded in fact. So, um, there's a famous physicist and it's been attributed
to so many that I actually don't know who really said it, but, uh, the, the spirit of the quote is
all models are wrong. Some are useful. Um, and I feel like economics is certainly a discipline
in which that applies, um, and suffers greatly. Um, I mean, look, look, even things, even something
that I think was much simpler to try to understand was, you know, the extent to which coronavirus was
going to be, um, a problem. I mean, those initial models were out to lunch. Um, and it's, I don't
fault the people who tried to put those models together, the epidemiologists who worked on these
models, but you know, the sensitivity around so many variables was so great that you couldn't
even begin to extrapolate. And when you did it, it, the only thing I think the models helped you
understand was how impossible it would be to predict what was going on. And if nothing else,
it was going to show you what parameters mattered, but that, that was about the extent of what you
could extract from that, which was, you know, the rate at which this thing spreads and the length of
time that it can lay dormant, those things are going to matter a lot. And by the way, what we
should have taken from that is earlier and more aggressive testing was a better solution as opposed
to trying to pontificate or estimate whether 60 million Americans were going to get it in 5 million
we're going to die versus 1 million we're going to die. I mean, those were, that was sort of the
wrong thing to be thinking about, but again, all that's easy in hindsight, but I, but I hear you
in terms of how that could be frustrating in, in, in this profession. Yeah. I mean, I have a very
strong view about the relationship between data and theory. And my view is that the sensible way
to do things is to make a really sharp distinction between the two that we should really understand
you go to the data and you just understand what the three, five, nine, 12 facts are. And in my view
is that those 12 facts should be things that if any reasonable person looked at the data,
you'd more or less agree on those facts. And to just establish that that is the role of data
analysis is to understand those facts. And obviously there's, you know, you want to get it
in the direction of causality and whatnot, but you never do that with the data alone. The data alone
are never enough except except in a randomized experiment to tell you about causality and, and
rarely in economics do we get to do randomized experiments. And then I think if you can all agree
on the facts, then I'm all in favor of models going forward. Because if I write down a model
that is built off of the 12 facts I see, it turns out it's really easy, the kind of models that
economists write down for other economists to say, okay, I understand whether that's a good model or
bad model, what it's sensitive to and whatnot. And, and if you make this bifurcation between
understanding the facts and then going into what, what those facts imply, because we really care not
about the facts themselves, but we care about the implications of those facts for the future or
what they tell us about causality or whatnot. I think it's a really powerful model. It's not
the model that we use in economics and it's definitely not the model we use, say in journalism,
that it's often incredibly hard or in debate, right? So it's often incredibly hard when a debate
is going on to understand are these people disagreeing about the facts or are they disagreeing
about the implication of the facts? And so like if I had my dream about how we would do journalism,
every newspaper article would basically have a separate little feature that just said, these
are the five facts on which I am writing this article. And then it would be easy to, for me,
say if it's an area I'm expert in to say, oh, well, those facts don't make any sense or for a fact
checker to affect them, or in a debate to say, Hey, before we debate, I would like each of the
participants to lay out the 10 facts that they believe to be true and see if they disagree with
each other's facts. If they disagree about facts, then we're in a very different situation than if
we disagree about the implications of those facts. And somehow I think that's gotten a lot like that
distinction. I've never really heard anyone talk about it except for me, because I'm probably not
important, but it strikes me as being really, really important. Well, let's use an example of
that where I think you and Dubner have gotten to some crosshairs of people is around climate change.
I mean, you wrote about this, God, has it been 10 years ago now? I've lost track. Yeah. Was it
super for economics or? Yeah, super for economics. So I think it's been about 10 years. Okay. So
let's go back to, let's start with some facts. What did you actually write? Because I think
that's been very misconstrued over time. Yeah. Okay. So one thing you can never trust is for people
to tell you the truth about what they've done in the past. Number one, because they're going to
lie, but number two, they don't even, like my, I don't really know what I've been, I haven't looked
back at that book in a long time either, but here's what I think we wrote. So we basically wrote that
at that time, there was evidence that the planet was getting warmer, but certainly it was not
completely open and shut. And we said, but look, we're not scientists. And what we thought was that
the people talking about climate change were asking the wrong question, right? What people
talking about climate change were saying is how do we reduce the amount of carbon we put in the air?
Okay. Which actually wasn't the right question. The real quick, right question was
the planet is too hot. We're not happy about the planet, that the planet is getting hotter.
What is the best way to cool down the planet? To me, that was really the right question. And like
the example I give is, um, you know, so I've had a lot of, I have a lot of babies, I have six kids. So
some of the kids, they poop all the time. Okay. And it's a problem. Okay. And so in, in, because
they poop on the floor all day long, it's a real problem. Okay. So you could say, well,
to solve that problem, let's figure out how to keep kids from pooping or how to stuff the poop
back in the kid or whatever. It's like, but the answer is like, how do you get the poop? So it
doesn't go on the ground. Well, it's a diaper. Okay. And it's like very different answer than
if you get worried about like, well, poo shouldn't exist. So I think the same with carbon, the carbon
is coming out and you don't necessarily have to stuff the carbon back in. If you can find another
way to cool the planet, starting from that premise, we then talked to real scientists who
knew something who were working on what's called geoengineering. So these are ways to try to cool
the planet. Okay. And look, they're not perfect in all sorts of ways, but these really smart guys
have, have come up with a lot of clever plans that we might potentially be able to cool the planet.
So things like putting sulfur dioxide into the stratosphere turns out super cheaply,
couple hundred million dollars a year, we could put sulfur dioxide in the stratosphere. It,
it mimics, but in a much more efficient way, what big volcanic eruptions like Mount Pinatubo have done.
And, and that could cool the planet. Another, like the best idea I think that was out there
was it turns out that, that certain kinds of clouds that have the right kind of reflectivity
in the right level can actually reflect a bunch of sunlight back and, and oceans are really dark.
So they absorb lots of heat. Clouds are really light. They reflect a lot of heat. So
a scientist to come up with a plan, never been tested even in the 10 years since we did it,
where a bunch of solar powered dinghies would troll around in the ocean controlled by GPS,
throwing up salt from the water, which then seats the clouds, which then leads to a bunch of clouds
over the ocean, which you know, his claim, their claim from simulations is that that would be
enough. 10,000 of those dinghies would be enough to offset all of, of, of climate change. Lebomi.
Look, all of these are probably short-term solutions relative to a real solution,
scientific solution or behavioral solution to, to try and deal with, with climate change.
But so that's what we wrote about. And, and admittedly, in retrospect, I regret that we
wrote about it in such a lighthearted way. I didn't realize that environmentalists had no
sense of humor. And so you couldn't like poke fun at mistakes they'd made in the past or,
and so we really aggravated a lot of people. But, but what we, what we did was we unleashed
this incredible machinery that there was a whole machinery around the environmental movement,
which, which basically decided we were enemy number, public enemy number one, and then set
out to destroy us, not really worried about what we actually said or whether we were right. I mean,
I think, I do think 10 years later, almost everyone now thinks that geoengineering is likely
to be part of the solution. And it was interesting. One of the magazines, I think it was the Atlantic
Monthly, basically wrote an article about us saying that we were the most evil, stupid
morons who've ever existed in the history of the planet. Four years later, the same, the same
magazine wrote essentially our chapter in our book with the exact same examples we had used
with no citation at all of the fact we had written about it, saying how geoengineering was going to
be part of the future. So I think, I think it's good not to worry about whether you're right or
you're credit for it. I think you just have to be happy that the movement, although way too slow,
has been in the right direction. I think for what's, what's inevitable is that the problem
of climate change is one which will not, I claim, ever be solved by behavior change,
because it's all about what economists call externalities, that my own behavior has almost
no effect on me and a negative effect on the rest of the world. And I would say there's never in
the history of mankind been a problem that is fundamentally about externalities, which has been
solved by telling people, you should just do the right thing. And hoping that suddenly everyone
is just going to start doing the right thing. Just literally has never happened. I don't,
any reason I think it's going to start now. Yeah, that's interesting. Can you think of any
examples where humans behave in that way? Where they do the right thing to help other people?
Yes, even if it inconveniences them. Are there any? Can we think?
I mean, there are social norms like on the roads. People don't really cut in line very much,
you know, a little bit, but I don't think it's because-
But is that also because there's direct feedback?
Exactly. Because people yell at you because it's uncomfortable. I mean,
but you know, very few things where we have private benefit and look at little things we
do around the edges and certainly do it for family members and whatnot. But
I really think, honestly, if you look at every big problem that's been solved for mankind,
I challenge you to find one that wasn't solved by technology. And it goes from everything from
disease to, I mean, I think, you know, you know much more about this than me. But if you think
about the benefits, health benefits that have come from behavior change versus technology,
invention, discovery, like I got to believe, you know, smoking being maybe the one example where
in the face of overwhelming evidence, it still took what, 40 years for people to cut down on
smoking and still a lot of people- Well, and I would argue that it wasn't really due to just a
straight- It wasn't the knowledge that tobacco killed that actually led to the reduction. In
fact, if you look at the timeline of this, it's an interesting case study in behavior change. So I
think the Surgeon General's report on smoking, which was the first really unambiguous declaration
that smoking killed. It had been suspected in the 40s and 50s, but it wasn't until, I want to say
about 65-ish that you couldn't argue it anymore. I mean, we're talking hazard ratios of 14X,
right? Like there's nothing in biology that produces a hazard ratio of 14X outside of
parachuting without parachutes. This is going to end in a bad way. And if there was really no
change in tobacco use after that for five, six more years, the first real dent in tobacco use
came with advertising. When a law was passed that said you couldn't advertise, a tobacco company
couldn't advertise tobacco unless the commercial was juxtaposed with an anti-tobacco ad. And it
turned out the anti-tobacco ads were so successful that the tobacco companies voluntarily stopped
advertising. And that was the first step in the reduction of tobacco. And then of course,
you threw in other things, which was laws that said, hey, you can't have tobacco sitting at the
counter. It has to be way behind. And obviously then you had excise taxes that were imposed,
and then you had other environmental things you can't smoke on airplanes. And so you could even
make the case that the reduction in smoking has been less about behavior change and more about a
change in the default environment around it, which just speaks more to your point.
Yeah. No, I think that's true. And I think also what's changed in the end is it used to be cool
to smoke. And now, look, if you smoke, people think you're crazy, right? So I think that those
social norms, again, speaking to your point, the costs and the benefits of smoking have changed
dramatically. And if anything, it's surprising how little behavior change has followed that as
opposed to how much. I mean, look at, I mean, again, we're in your territory in that mind,
but look at diabetes and how little behavior change has been in response to diabetes. It's
surprising in many ways. Let's go back to this climate change issue, because again,
it's very interesting. And it's one of those things, I think, like nutrition, where
there's a very gray area between true scientific expertise and propaganda.
What is it about the use of science as a propaganda? I mean, frankly, I think in fact,
I'm somewhat, what's the word? I think I'm somewhat sympathetic to people who
are kind of losing faith in the scientific process a little bit. I'm talking lay people,
people who have never studied science, but who are sort of sick and tired of hearing scientists
stand up on TV and say something and they're a little bit skeptical. And so if you're sort of
an elitist, you look at them and you say, well, they're morons. How can they not believe in
science? But the reality of it is they've kind of been a bit misled, haven't they? And I think that
this, like you look at the, using science as kind of a weapon, I guess, has become a bit
problematic, right? Yeah. Honestly, I think the, I'm more favorable towards climate science
than I used to be. So climate science suffers from the exact same thing that macroeconomics does,
which is that there's observations, but really much of it is based on these models and the models
can't possibly have the kind of specificity because it's such a complex system to understand.
So like most of the leading models at the time we were looking at it had carbon dioxide in it,
but nothing about water vapor. And it turns out that many people think water vapor is more
important than the interaction between carbon dioxide and water vapor would be more important
than anything. But the model is just like computing power and the complexity was too much.
But I give some credit to, like there's a part of climate science which is focused on measurement,
measuring the temperature of the oceans, the rising of the oceans. And I think that's kind
of been done well. Now, what you're talking about though, is that there's such a blurring
of the line between the job of measuring climate change and advocating on TV or in the newspapers
for what that means for public policy. And those are very different tasks. And you, I think as a
scientist, you want to be very careful about moving from one role to the other. And I think
what climate science as an observer, a pretty close observer has done a very poor job on
is helping people, lay people understand when one is in advocacy role versus when one is in
a scientific role. And the same people have played both roles. And I think really it's
an unusual branch of science because the people who go into climate science almost always share
this view that the climate's really important and we should protect it and we should be doing
things not to have climate change. Which is different, I think, from say physics, where
physicists don't have an inherent belief about whether the universe should be expanding or
contracting or whether a particular particle should or should not exist. It's just like that's
a different thing. So, and the other thing I think which has been completely unrealistic
and really problematic for climate science is that they don't think about economics enough.
And they don't think about the reality of human behavior and how difficult it will be to have
behavior change. And they don't think well about the cost of changing our economy. So the cost of
going to a zero car, a net carbon world are really, really big. And we pay those costs right away.
And I'm not saying that we shouldn't necessarily try to do that. It might actually be a good idea
to do it. But to ignore the fact that it's an incredibly expensive solution that's being offered,
I think has been part of the problem because it hasn't really, it's been a mix of ignoring that.
And at this or at the same time saying, look, those costs are good because we're a moral,
humans are awful, humans are ruining the planet and we should suffer for the fact we should have
an enormous contraction in the economy. A gal Gore was upset that there are way too many kinds of
cereal being sold in the grocery store. That's sinful that there are so many choices about cereal.
But it's like a weird religious thing about we should suffer. And again, I think that doesn't
work well to people who maybe aren't convinced or who don't want to suffer. So honestly, I think,
you know, I think if I were able to do one thing in the world, I tried to do it and I failed at it,
it would be to have a sensible approach to figuring out whether there is a cheap solution
to climate change. Because right now, all we're talking about are incredibly expensive ones,
like complete rethinking of capitalism, like, you know, and, you know,
and I don't think that the capitalist structure has worked well on trying to solve the problem of
like is if we put or let me put it, I think we should take if it were up to me, if I were
president, the first thing I would do is I would have what I call a a Manhattan project for climate
change. And I would try to convince the 1000 smartest scientists in the world to stop whatever
they're doing, and to work on climate change, and to put them in a place like Los Alamos,
and to give them resources and it because it's a hard problem. And it's an interdisciplinary
problem. And say, look, for five years, let's just work and let's figure out whether or not
there's going to be a great way to do carbon sequestration, or to do something, you know,
I don't know, something out of the box to do it. And like, either either I think we'll get a solution
in five years, or we'll figure out, oh, crap, this is never going to work. Like we have no way out of
this other than other than stopping to produce carbon or living with the world. Look, and that's
important information to know because if I knew that the only way out of this was we were going
to have, you know, live with the carbon we put in there, then then the willingness of public policy
to impose enormous costs on carbon producing behavior should go away up. But I kind of doubt
that's true. I have a lot of faith in science. I think we had the best 1000 scientists within
five years, we would come up with a reasonably cost effective way to deal with carbon, we'd pull it
out of the air in some way, shape or form. And we kind of like have the thing solved, or we know
we're never going to solve it. I don't disagree with you, Steve, I think where I'm a little less
optimistic than you, and I love the idea of a Manhattan project for this. I'd back up one step
and reiterate what you said earlier, because I think it's so important. I phrase it in a somewhat
different way, but I like how you discussed it, which is we confuse the objective, the strategy,
and the tactics all day long. I mean, that to me is like, if we were going to list the 10 human
failures, just as a species, it's that we are not wired to differentiate between objectives,
strategies and tactics. And so that's why 10 years ago you were getting lambasted for talking
about geoengineering, which is a tactic, because the only tactic that was being discussed
was the reduction of carbon. And you were saying, well, wait a minute, if you really want,
we've lost sight of the objective. The objective is to slow warming, and warming is a much bigger
problem than just how much carbon is in the atmosphere that also deals with insulation.
So let's look at different tactics, right? So notwithstanding that problem, I think my biggest
fear, Steve, is there's no question that in five years a well-staffed, well-resourced team could
come up with what solutions might look like. I just don't know that it could ever be implemented
from a policy perspective. I mean, for example, I mean, I don't think anybody who's really studied
energy seriously disagrees that nuclear energy, next gen, I'm not talking about like the nuclear
reactors of 70 years ago. I don't think there's anybody who doesn't think that next gen nuclear
would play an important role in electricity generation. But it's just not a politically
palatable solution. I don't know where geoengineering falls on that spectrum either, for that matter.
So that would be my fear is you'd come up with solutions, but then you'd still be at kind of a
gridlock in the implementation of these things. Yeah, so that is a good point, and that is
possible. I do think, however, that even in that world, there is a real insurance value
in this investment now. So we might not be able to come up with a sensible policy now,
but if in 20 years, all of a sudden, the ice shelf on Greenland just like begins to slide into the
ocean and things are desperate, then I believe that we will, so my prediction is we will do
something like my Manhattan Project for climate change. The question is, when will we do it? Will
we do it as we're staring down catastrophe, or will we do it in advance and potentially either
avoid catastrophe or at least get five years earlier? I mean, not that different than COVID,
so for my podcast, I interviewed Mansif Slaoui, and I don't know, six or seven years ago,
he proposed, well, why don't we have in the bank a vaccine for like everything we'd ever want,
but not make very much of it, just like have a little bit around so we know how to do it.
Look, and everyone laughed at him and said, how can you suggest that? That would cost
500 million dollars. We can't waste 500 million dollars. Then you come to a world where the US
government is bleeding six billion dollars a day in deficits, and that would have been like
literally the best investment of all time probably if we had done it. So I think that kind of insurance
policy I think would be valuable even in a world of gridlock and poor policy making.
I agree completely because the one thing that I think we haven't stated here, but I think we both
agree on is this is such an asymmetric risk that it has to be taken seriously. That's probably the
thing that bothers me the most about the other argument, the people on the other side of the
argument that say, well, we don't have enough certainty, therefore it should be status quo
business as usual, ignore this. It's true. I think the uncertainty, the error bars on these
projections are bigger than people lead us to believe, but it's so asymmetric. It's so
non-linear if this goes wrong that you have to take that seriously.
There are very few things in economics that shocked me, but something that shocked me was
an analysis done a long time ago, this was 10 years ago and more, where an economist,
and I'm embarrassed because I can't remember exactly who it was, just worked through the kinds
of utility functions, so the basic models that economists use, and said in a world in which bad
things happen, how much are you willing to pay to avoid bad things? And it is completely shocking.
I'm making these numbers up, but I think they're in the right ballpark. So if you have something
like a 1% chance of dying, how much will you pay? How much would you pay of your total wealth
to avoid a 1% chance of dying today? Can't you know the answer isn't 1%, it's more like 10 or
15%. And as it goes up to 5%, you're willing to pay like 50% of your wealth to avoid it, because
once you die, you're like done, so it's like otherwise really long flow. And it's very
counterintuitive. It really caught me off guard and it really changed my thinking about the
importance of dealing with climate change. Because I was kind of of, look, you know,
climate change is all in the future, we discount the future, you know, why worry about it? But once
I saw that, it really changed my perspective on it. So I've come to think that this investment,
and the other thing to stress is that the cost of R&D is so low compared to the cost of
disaster and of implementation, that to do the R&D is just a no brainer, right? So I think for
for a billion dollars a year, my guess is you could fund, you know, you could fund this Manhattan
project for a billion dollars. It's like the kind of money that actual philanthropists could do,
as opposed to even government having to do. Look, if you actually wanted to put whatever solution is
discovered into practice, it would probably be enormously expensive. But to figure out the answer
is just like trivial. And the same is true of COVID, like, you know, talking to people who did
the vaccines, I think at Modan, it took them like a day or two to come up with the vaccine, you know,
and all the costs are in the testing and the production. But the actual R&D part is so cheap
compared to everything else that to not invest in it just seems like a real mistake, first order
mistake to me. Agree. I'm glad we got off on that tangent, because I actually did want to talk
about that at some point, but it came up, it came up kind of quick. But I want to now go back to
the beginning of the story, right? So you graduate from college, you go off to work in
management consulting, which if I remember, you described as slightly, only slightly less
uncomfortable than a root canal without no vecane. It's so painful that it in fact, exposes you to a
PhD. So you go off to MIT. So you basically just didn't leave Boston, you went from, you know,
Harvard to consulting to MIT. So you really have a pension for these cold winters. And then what
did you decide to study in your PhD? Because now you actually you got to get serious, right? You
actually have to pick a problem and work on it. So I have to say, I didn't like consulting,
but I learned something incredibly important in it. And I learned it from the guy who happened to
have the cubicle next to me, a guy named Jeff Thomas, who I'm still friends with. And he taught
me how to look at the world strategically. And it was weird. I never did that before. It never
occurred to me to do it. But then I got to grad school. And I did have a fundamental understanding
while everybody else was really busy working on problem sets. And essentially, these were all
people who got in straight A's their whole life. And they figured, well, what worked for me before,
that's what I got to keep on doing in grad school, because that's how I'm going to get ahead.
And I looked at it. And partly it helped that I knew no math. And I was completely overmatched.
And I was like the worst I was I was I'm not exaggerating when I say that my classmates
sat down about a month into it. And my friend Austin Goolsby, who's now gotten famous as part
of the Obama administration, later told me that they went through the list of people in the class
and tried to decide who is least likely to succeed. And like I was a unanimous choice that I was going
to be the worst one. And but look, I had a great approach, which is I understood that you had to
create research had to go from being a consumer of knowledge to a producer of knowledge. And,
and, you know, and I also was kind of still, you know, I have to say, I didn't really, I wasn't
internally motivated. So what I did was I said, well, look, who's at the top of the hierarchy,
I might as well try to be that guy. And it turned out that that was macro economics at MIT at the
time. So for the first semester, I tried to be a macro economist. And it became so clear to me so
quickly that I was never going to be a macro economist, because I always thought that nobody
had intuition for macro economics until I started talking to some of the people at MIT who actually
understood, oh, the exchange rate between the the euro and the dollar goes up, then that's going
to trickle through and how's that going to affect, you know, immigration like, oh, my god, like, it
made no sense to me. So I quit, I was smart enough, I've always been smart enough to fail quickly. So
I like realized I couldn't be a macro economist. The theorists were number two. And so I tried to
be a theorist, and I actually spent a little longer being a theorist, actually wrote a couple
papers being a theorist. And again, it became really clear to me that I didn't have what it
took to be a theorist. So then I said, well, kind of the only thing left is doing data analysis. And
it turned out I should have been smart enough to know that from the beginning, because I was a
weird kid. I, I, the only thing I like to do was sit in my room, and essentially study data, like,
as I look back on it, I would, this is how weird I was when I was, when I was maybe eight,
I asked for and received a pocket calculator as my birthday present. And it was overjoyed. When I
was maybe like nine, I graduated to a scientific calculator. And my pastime was I was into baseball,
is I would go through and I would, by manually typing into a scientific calculator, I type in
a column of, of like wins for a team. And then one by one, I would type in each of the statistics,
like the team batting average or the team, you know, number of triples, and compute the partial
correlation between those two. And, and, and what my dad wanted, my dad came home from work,
he would ask me what the correlations were between the variables I computed. Like,
that was how I spent my time. So it should have been obvious to me, that's what I want to do.
And the other thing I did was when I was in is I, I would use data to try and answer real problems.
Like when I was in college, I became obsessed with the racetrack. And I would try to, you know,
use data to win at the racetrack, which wasn't very significant. But like, I should have been
obvious to me that I, that I should have gravitated to, to, to doing empirical research. But,
but I didn't, because I was still caught up in this idea of, well, of a status. So finally,
I just said, look, I'll do what I'm good at. But, but honestly, I was so far behind the people
around me. It was an interesting experience. It's kind of a satellite, but it's interesting.
I'd been used to being really good at most of the things I did academically. And,
and it happens for almost everyone. You, you, you some, you get to a point where you look around
and you realize you were the dumbest person in the room and how you deal with that is really
important. And strangely, and I don't know why that was roughly the greatest feeling I've ever
had in my life. When I looked around and I was the dumbest person in the room, it was just sense
of joy. It was really interesting. Somehow I think maybe I had felt pressure my whole life.
Once I was a dumbest person in the room, I felt like, wow, I can do whatever I want. Like I don't,
you know, I can, it's just, it was such a joy to be around such talented people.
And it freed me up to be myself. And instead of always trying to follow the crowd, I started
doing what I liked and what did I, and I thought, well, what do I like? And I said, well, I don't
know. I like watching the TV show cops. I love to show cops. I watch it every day. Like, well,
why don't I do research on it? And so I somehow like found myself and I began just studying the
things I liked and, and much to my amazement, even though no other economists were really studying
those questions, I really thought it was a, it was a one way ticket to, to like getting a PhD
and then doing something outside of academics. Because, you know, why would it be the case that
if these were topics, no one else researched, they'd be interested in. But I didn't, you know,
I knew I couldn't compete on a level footing with these amazing people around me. So I had to
compete on like in my own space. And in my shock, people liked it, you know, and they were excited
about it. It got published in good journals. And, and I'm, I honestly, I look back and I say, I'm so
lucky to have been so far below the bar that I didn't try to, I didn't try to do what I think
most people do and what I had a tendency to do, which was to try to be like, figure out what I
should be, because that's what other people are. And I just was myself and it was such a great
lesson. And I've really practiced being myself ever since. Looking sometimes it works and sometimes
it doesn't, but I, but the great thing about life is when things don't work, you can take a different
path. And so it's just, you know, so I just try to be myself and, and I stopped doing stuff when
being myself isn't a good recipe for it. So when you got to Chicago, I mean, that must have been
another difficult decision because Chicago is a powerhouse in economics, right? You could have
taken your sort of offbeat approach to economics and gone someplace that is where you're not going
to be surrounded by a bunch of Nobel laureates. So why did you, I mean, were you so secure in your
kind of off the beaten path approach that you said, Hey, I might as well go to another cold winter
city and be around smart people, but I, but not have to compete with them. I mean, that,
what was the, what was the decision like there? You know, so I had a lot of choices
and I loved Cambridge and I had been at Harvard and MIT and, and I really, what had happened is
I'd given a couple of, of, of presentations at Chicago and I had been shocked at how different
the questions I got were. And I, I really went to Chicago because I wanted to get to know the enemy.
At that time, so, so Gary Becker was one of the most influential economists of the, of,
of the last 50 years. And he's since passed away, but was a real mentor to me. He was demonized. I
mean, I think when I first met him, I expected him to be a monster and it turned out, well,
he wasn't, he was super smart and he asked great questions. And, and so I, I very self-constantly
said, I'm going to go to Chicago and I'm going to get to know the enemy from the inside for a couple
of years before I go back to Harvard. And what I hadn't anticipated is that the thinking that goes
on at Chicago, it looks like it's really simple. It looks like one could learn it. I thought, look,
I'm good at economics. I can learn this, but I, I take even 25 years later, I'm still not very good
at the kind of deep thinking that is done in Chicago economics. And, and I love it. And I
think it's powerful, but I'm still more of a spectator than an actual doer of it. And I really
got, I really got co-opted into the spirit of Chicago. But in some sense, I will, I will say
that I've never, I've always been probably unreasonably overly confident in, in my own
ability. And, and I was very, I always had ease. Like I was going to do what I was going to do
and I thought I could do it better at Chicago than anywhere else. But it was, but I will say
it was, it was unusual. So at that time, I think it must have been seven or 10 years since someone
who had a lot of options had chosen to go to Chicago economics over another place, including
the Chicago business school, which was really getting most of the town. And, and one of my
advisors, so I told one of my advisors at Harvard, I was going to go to Chicago. And he said,
if you do that, I will never speak to you again. And I said, why? And he said, because if you do
that, it shows that you are so effing stupid that you're not worth me wasting my breath. And it was
interesting. That was how weird it was to do that decision. But I did it. And he was happy to talk
with me, you know, never stopped talking to me. And I think he would agree. I probably did the
right thing. But, but, but, you know, it's funny now, because it used to be there were these
enormous differences between departments. Now I think they're all kind of the same Chicago, Harvard,
MIT, Stanford, Princeton. I mean, they're, yeah, they're like all these great departments. We've
all like blurred the lines together. Not so different, but I, you know, but, but at the time,
there really was a distinctive personality that for me was really, you know, really special. I'm
so glad I did it. And I think it's, I've been a huge beneficiary of it. Do you think the field
is better that the elite 10 programs have become more homogeneous? Or do you think it produced,
did more for the field when you had these very distinctive schools of thinking and Stanford had
its way of doing it and Chicago had its way and Harvard had its way? It's a great question. Such
a hard, such a hard question. I remember, I remember maybe five for 10 years into my coming
to Chicago, Milton Friedman came back and he was bemoaning the fact not just that Chicago was
becoming more like other places, but really that what was distinctive about Chicago, what's called
Chicago price theory, was basically dying out and how awful that was. And one of my colleagues,
super smart colleagues, Casey Mulligan said, Milton, I thought you believed in market.
It sounds to me like, like price is losing. And I thought, wow, that is exactly right.
And even Milton Friedman in the end didn't really believe in markets when markets moved against him.
I don't know. I do think. Like it sort of used to be that way in medicine, right? There was a
very clear line between East Coast medicine and West Coast medicine. And there was a very
different way cardiac surgery was done in Minnesota versus Stanford versus Boston. I mean,
those were so different and they produced remarkable innovations in a sense. And I just,
you know, so it. Yeah. No, I think you're right. Like letting, I think these diversity of approaches
are useful because the number one, there's data, right? It's like, let's, let's especially take
more something like cardiac surgery where you get real data. Look, you know, whether people are
living or dying. And so you actually can figure out whether one is better than the other. So in
that world, for sure, I think this diversity of views is really, really important. Now you might
say, look, it doesn't have to be across departments. It can be within department, right? You have one
brilliant surgeon innovating in this way or that way. But I do think in general that it's this,
this diversity of views is good and it's especially good in a dynamic world, right? Because in a world
that's static, it's kind of like doesn't matter as much. But when something radical happens,
then often one model is much better situated than the other to deal with whatever this radical
occurrence happens. Some new disease or some, I don't know, maybe, maybe radical things tend not
to happen so much in medicine, but you know, sometimes radical things happen in the economy.
And so I think it's, it's important. Again, I don't know how interested your listeners are
in macroeconomics, but I think macroeconomics is a case where Chicago style macro more or less one.
And so all of the world of macro now looks a lot like what was going on in Chicago 40 years ago.
And I think that's been a problem because I think there isn't this diversity of thinking that puts
you maybe in a better situation as different kinds of macroeconomic problems arise to have
a range of possible approaches and solutions to it. So yeah, I think, so here's that. I think it
probably would be better if there were greater differences between the departments, but the,
but it's one of these things where like the facts of life are that it's impossible to maintain that
equilibrium because there are all sorts of private forces that are pushing, pushing for this
homogeneity that you just can't, so like, you just, like, there's no easy way to fight it
in some sense. And so even though you wish it would happen, it's hard to see how to make it happen.
So let's, let's go on to talk a little bit about a colleague of yours outside of the world of
economics, Steve Dubner. How did you guys meet? So Dubner approached me to write an article about
me for the New York Times. This is after I'd won the Clark medal, but well before free economics.
And, and I really was incredibly hesitant to, to accept the, the invitation because I just didn't,
I didn't really like to be written about, there was no, I didn't have anything to sell,
so I didn't really, I wasn't in the business of trying to market myself. And, and in the end,
I have this, my mom though, really likes it when I'm in the newspaper and on TV and stuff. And so
I really, I remember thinking, Oh God, I'll take this hit from my mom. Cause it will make my mom
so happy if there's a piece about me in the New York Times magazine. And, and then Dubner came out
and it was unlike any experience I had ever had with a journalist. I honestly think he had read
every academic paper I'd ever read. I mean, I'm talking about like 50 papers and he came out and
he ended out interviewing me for, I don't think I'm exaggerating if I say maybe 25 hours over three
days. And there was never a silence. So I would, he would ask me a question. I would answer it.
And as soon as I answered it, he would ask me another question. And this went on for 25 hours
and it was unbelievably painful to me because it's like, it was the last thing I wanted to do.
And I thought he was going to say for three hours, not 25. And, and one of the notable things about
it is that I literally did not ask him a question for the first 24 and a half hours. And I only
thought of him as like this, this parasite that was like sucking the life out of me. And after 24
and a half hours, I actually had the thought to say, well, like, who have you written about before?
And he started telling me these fantastic stories. He was the only guy who had been able to interview
the Unabomber and he had been in a rock band like, and he was really interesting. And I,
and I learned something there, which is like, especially when you're tired of being asked
questions, ask the questions yourself. It's almost always more interesting to ask the questions than
to answer them. But still we parted and I would have said I would never see that guy again. I mean,
we were not friendly in any way. There was no like meeting of the minds or anything.
But he did write a piece about me in the New York times that people loved. And he gets so pissed at
me because I always say like he created this, this personality about me as this incredible
wonder boy genius who you give me a problem. I type away at my computer. I solve it an hour later.
And, and people love that persona. And even though it was completely and totally off, I mean,
it wasn't right at all. But, but like, I've been writing that for the last 15 years. So I can't
complain. Like I've, I've milked it for everything I could. And people loved it. And then we ended
up, you know, not, you know, not through an easy Bible. We ended up deciding to write Freakonomics
together, not because we had some passion to tell our story, but just because we both wanted to
make some bucks and, and the publishers were willing to pass to write this book. And, and in
the end, we had an amazing agent, Suzanne Gluck, who I interviewed for my podcast,
people I mostly admire. And like, she, you know, we relive that story. But she just like totally
out negotiated the publishers. And there we were with a super lucrative book deal.
And no idea at all what we're going to write about. We like had no conception of what this
book was going to be. And I think part of the fun of it was that we both assumed that we had just
pulled off like a bank heist and that like no one was ever going to read this book. And so we
could do whatever we wanted, because it wasn't like my colleagues cared what I wrote about this
book that no one would read. And he was like a serious, you know, memoirist and his, you know,
people would understand he was just doing this to make some cash and they wouldn't hold it against
them. And it freed us up, I think, to write a book that was very different than what we would have
written if we actually had the fear that people were going to read it and judge us based on, on,
on what we wrote. So we had a lot more fun with them. We would have otherwise. And we kind of
broke a bunch of rules and we were super lucky, I think, to be in the right place at the right time
to have a book that ended up selling a whole bunch of copies.
Did it come out in 05 or 06?
Oh, I don't know. I mean, I, I don't know. I mean, no idea.
I'm so good at dates. Usually I can almost, I think probably, I mean, I remember reading it as
soon as it came out. I still remember where I first learned about it. I remember, it's, it's,
it's so odd that I would remember this, but I was in the OR waiting for a patient to wake up,
you know, waiting to come out of anesthesia. So, you know, we'd finished operating and it was,
you know, I was just sort of writing the orders to get ready to take the patient to
the recovery room. And the chief resident said, I just read this book for economics.
You got to read it. It is unbelievable. It's totally incredible. And he just started raving
about it. And so I just went and picked it up and I couldn't put it down. I mean, it was just,
and it was very unusual for me to read anything outside of medicine. You know, it was very hard
for me to make time to do anything that wasn't immediately related to sort of what I needed to,
to do for work. What, so I'm trying to think which my favorite one was in there.
Which one did you guys get the most blowback on? Was it the seat belt one, the car seat one? Did
that, did that create the most blowback? You know, we literally had like three lines on, on car seats.
We had one, one paragraph on car seats and that probably did create about as much negative
feedback as anything. Strangely, we really thought abortion was going to be the lightning rod and
everyone was going to get upset about it, but abortion and crime. But, but it turned out that
when we actually, well, the backstory is that when, when I couldn't control the story, like when the
media reported on my academic results about abortion and crime, which by the way, that was,
that was in the late nineties, wasn't it? Or early 2000s, but the actual 2000, 2001. Yeah.
And that, in that decade. And, and, and we had no control over the way it was portrayed. It was
deeply mis-portrayed. It was simplified and it was a, it was a nightmare. It just, it, it triggered
hostility from all corners of the, of the right and the left. And, and it just kind of made us
look stupid because it was easy to parody it because if you didn't understand how simple and
obvious things we were talking about and how powerful they were in the data, we kind of looked
like we were crazy people and in part because nobody talks publicly about abortion unless they
have a, a stake in it, right? So all of the conversation about abortion is either stridently
pro-life or stridently pro-choice, but like we didn't have a stake. We were just doing something
really different, which is, we said something simple, which is the abortion was legalized in the
U S and it turns out that there's this really strong relationship between unwantedness. So if
a kid is unwanted by his or her parents that they tend to have a hard life. And after abortion was
legalized, there appears to have been a dramatic decline in number of unwanted children that were
born. And so just like in a simple empirical like statement of fact, fewer unwanted children with
legalized abortion should lead to less crime. 18 years later, you know, it's, it's like gotta be
true. It's not hard to see why that's true. It's just a matter of is it a big number or a small
number. And, and back in the unbelievable calculations, Sota said it could be a really
big number based on other studies of unwantedness. And when you looked at the data, not perfect,
we obviously didn't want to randomize experiment. We didn't get to choose who didn't didn't get
abortions. We looked at, you know, things like, you know, after Roe versus Wade happened, you
look exactly at some states, it was easy to get abortion. Some states it was hard. And then you
look 20 years later and you see that well, for the first 15 years, the crime patterns look really
similar between those states. And they only started to diverge once the kids who were
exposed to legalized abortion were old enough to have, you know, start killing crimes. So like,
you know, it was a really simple, straightforward paper that almost anyone could look at the data
and make some sense of whether what we were doing was reasonable and sensible. And so when we
actually got to tell our story in free economics, nobody complained. And what was really interesting,
not just from a data perspective, but from a storytelling perspective, is it was one of the
great successes of storytelling in that people who were pro choice read that chapter and would
pat me on the back and say how amazing it like what a great chapter that was and how it pushed
the pro choice agenda. And people who are pro life would slap me on the back and say, you know,
I'm glad someone finally told the truth about pro life. And it was interesting, the exact same
chapter was read totally different. And everybody liked it. It was, I gotta say, of all the things
I've ever done, that that was one of the weirdest and most unexpected things that ever happened,
is that we wrote something that everybody liked when we expected everybody to hate it. So I
honestly, we didn't get so free economics, we wrote all these stories, and people just liked it. And
we, you know, we kind of had this, like, we offended lots of groups, like we talked about
how real estate agents were like the KKK. But like in a lighthearted way that even most of the
real estate agents didn't get that mad at us. And I got invited to speak at the National Realtors
Association. So it was like, everyone's like a good sport about it. Then we wrote a second book,
people got super pissed off, because I guess we hit a little closer to home with stuff like climate
change. Then we wrote a third book. And by that time, we had alienated everyone. It turns out that
there was someone- It's the third one's think like a freak, right? Yeah. So by that time,
every person on the right and the left thought we were jerks by the time we were done with the third
one, which is more or less why we stopped writing books, because we had gone from, oh, these are
these fun-loving economists who poke punted everything to like, those jerks, they're like,
offended me deeply, and I'm never going to buy another book from them again. And then remember,
one night we were having dinner, this was at my house in San Diego years ago, maybe six or seven
years ago. And I think you were toying with the idea of writing a fourth book about like the
Freakonomics approach to golf. And you really spent the entire night trying to convince me to
be the protagonist of that book. Do you remember this discussion? Oh my God, yeah. So I actually
wrote large chunks of a book about the Freakonomics of golf and liked it and enjoyed doing it because
I love and loved golf and I wasn't that good at it, but at the age of 40, I really, in a semi-serious
way, dedicated myself to becoming a professional golfer and never got nearly good enough, but
improved a lot. But I knew I couldn't do it based on physical talent. I knew I had to do it based on
being smart and using data in a particular way. And so I've developed all of these sets of tools
that I think could be really helpful to a golfer. And what I needed was I needed someone who had
amazing physical talent and was a complete maniac in the sense that I know you are, I'm like willing
to put 10,000% into anything that you started. And I thought, well, what a great chapter would be to
take someone who's never golfed before and to see how good you could get, that person could get in
a year. And you were my number one, you were my number one student. We talked about it seriously.
I mean, I really did consider it just out of curiosity, which was if I devoted one year to
this, like I had devoted one year to swimming, like how far could you get in a year if you were
willing to put in two to three hours a day, a very deliberate practice, especially with your
guidance, which as I understood it was going to make a lot of shortcuts. But in the end, I think
my fear was just the addiction that would come of that. Like golf, golf is one of those things that
just, it could consume someone like me. It would be a terrible waste of your talent as well. So I
only did, I did eventually take on a one student and it's a funny story. So Larry Summers, who was
the secretary of the treasury and the president of Harvard and whatnot. So he came to Chicago one
one time to give a speech. And this is not too many years ago when he was, was and is incredibly
eminent. And I got an email that was addressed to like five Nobel laureates, the president of the
university and to me, demanding our presence when he comes to entertain him or, you know,
that like, I don't know. So he could, he could hold court or whatever. And I, and I was completely
befuddled at how I got on this list of these folks. So I showed up and I was maybe the fourth one to
arrive and he was deep in conversation with a couple of our Nobel laureates and the president.
And he literally like stopped. I walked in the room and he like broke off the conversation. And
he said, sorry, gentlemen, this is who I need to talk to. And I'm like, wow, like my stature and
the profession of economics is really going up. And he says, Steve, I'm this, I don't even really
know him. I've talked to him like twice in my entire life. He says, Steve, I have been needing
to talk to you. I'm like, wow, I'm like, what, what, what am I going to tell Larry Summers? And he says,
I've heard that you're the one guy in the world who can get my handicap from 20 down to five in
golf. How are we going to do that? And it was hilarious that the thing he cared about was golf.
And so I had failed with you, Peter. I thought, okay, what a great chapter this will be. I'm
taking Larry Summers from a 20 handicap down to a five. And he turned out to be the worst student
that ever existed in the planet. He would, he like wouldn't do anything. Like he, I sent him all my
stuff. We worked out, you know, we were going to work out plans for talking and like he wouldn't
practice. It was, he was the exact opposite. Like the reasons I wanted you to be my student,
were the exact reasons that Larry turned out not to be a very good student. Let's hold on to this.
There may be a day, you know, I don't know, maybe when my kids are in college or something,
and I have a little bit more bandwidth, I might be willing to pick this up. But I,
you have me very intrigued by this. The title Freakonomics, you got that from your sister, right?
I did. So my sister, who unfortunately has since passed away from cancer, she was,
she was a force of nature. She, she was, you know, it's funny, when you grow up, you're around a
relatively small set of people and you kind of gauge your own stature in the world relative to
people around you. And my sister was so amazing that I always thought I must be like below average
in terms of creativity and things because like relative to her, I was awful. And, and so,
but, but she was also odd in the sense that she didn't, she didn't really function that well in
the world. Like she wasn't that successful in traditional metrics, because she was kind of,
she was a little bit like Robin Williams. Like, like the person most like her that I've ever,
you know, seen is Robin Williams and that she was incredibly creative, but like, I don't know,
didn't necessarily fit in that well with how the world worked. So anyway, we tried to write this
book about nothing, right? So this was a book where we, we didn't have a theme and we were just,
you know, we didn't have a title. That's for sure. We had the worst set of titles.
And, and I knew immediately my sister was the only one who would come up with a title for this book.
And so I told her what we were doing. And she came back a half an hour later with, I would say,
10 titles that were better than any title we had come up with. But she basically just said,
look, but the title of the book is for economics. And I'm like, you're right. The title of the book
is for economics. And, and even Dubner was, you know, okay, yeah, for economics that works.
So we went to the publishers and they just flipped. They're like, we paid way too much for this book
to call it for economics. They like refuse the title. They fought it. And it was months of back
and forth before they grudgingly said that they'd call this book for economics. Well, what, what,
what were they advocating for? What were some of their titles? Do you remember? Oh my God. You know,
the one we were at, I think I was forgetting. So I was, um, um, uh, I think, I think one of the
leading candidates just to put you where, how bad we were off was E-Ray vision. Like we're E stood
for economics. And I think that was a not ruled out title before for economics. Um, but, uh,
but in the end, I think that, you know, I understand this same book with a different
title. Why does salt no copies? I mean, it's, it's, um, public life in general publishing
specifically, you just a huge luck component to it. Um, it depends on, like, I think our book,
you know, little things happen that made all the difference. Um, we got a good review in the wall
street journal. Um, the guy went on the daily show with John Stewart and somehow he like made
it seem really cool. And like little things happen with books that kind of determine whether they
fly or they don't fly. And, um, and I think, I think we, we ran back time and, uh, and thought
about this book and it going on, I think 99 times out of a hundred, it would probably wouldn't have
sold very many books. We're just like super lucky in a lot of things that happen. I mean,
I mean, I think it was a good book. I might like the book. I'm not trying to say it's a bad book,
but, um, but what is really amazing is if you actually sit down and read books and so people
send me books all the time because they want me to blurb them. It's incredible how good these books
are. Like, you know, random books that I expect to be awful. There's so many good books and, and,
um, look at, nobody reads them and, uh, you know, so many good podcasts that nobody listened to, but
it's just really hard in the clutter of this world to, to break, to break through. And, um,
and I think the, you know, the, the tightness of the correlation between how good something is and
how much attention it gets much lower than I think most people give credit for.
Steve, something you've been talking about quite a bit lately, we spoke about it when I was on your
podcast. I've heard you speak about it on other podcasts, um, is kind of our shared appreciation
in mental health and how underappreciated it is. Um, how long has this been something that's kind of
been, at least to you as important as I think it is now, is this recent or is it something that's
always really mattered and you've only kind of come to appreciate how underutilized these tools are?
Yeah. So I, um, look, I was raised, um, by a father who was like no nonsense and, um, the,
the idea of therapy, I mean, such an embarrassment. Oh my God. I mean, like no real man would ever
think about, uh, you know, certainly crying. Like, like I would, you were not allowed to cry. And,
you know, but you, you had a grandfather that committed suicide. Was it your father's father
or your mother's father? My father's father who, no, but it wasn't a mental, like my father,
my grandfather's suicide was not a mental health issue. My grandfather, uh, who loved life more
than anything and was, I don't know, maybe 90 years old, his wife who he loved dearly had terminal
cancer. And so he decided to commit suicide, not out of unhappiness, just because he had lived a
great life and he was satisfied and he didn't want to be a burden on people. So, so it wasn't,
it was in no sense, it was, it was actually in some sense the opposite. It was, it was, it was,
um, like it just a, an acceptance of that, that death is part of the national, like in many ways,
he was extremely far along in the mental health, uh, domain because he like accepted death as being
a natural part of the cycle of life and was not troubled by it. Um, I think honestly, for me,
the big change was, um, I got divorced and I met, met my wife Suzanne who, um,
is much more in tune with these issues and got me thinking about them in a way that I never had
before, whether it's the kind of more esoteric stuff in the, in kind of the, um, spiritual domain
or purely about mental health. And, um, and I somehow shook off like a lifetime of, uh, of,
of teaching, which told me that mental health was a joke and you just gotta like bite through it.
And, uh, and came to appreciate, you know, seven years ago, really is when I started thinking about
these issues. And, uh, I think you're right in saying that I've come to believe now that they are,
you know, dramatically more important than our education system or our society has traditionally
given them credit for. So you've, you've spoken about this a little bit. I mean, you've spoken
about it with me and you've explained that you'd be even comfortable talking about it today,
but you know, one of your children struggles with an eating disorder. Um, how hard has that been for
you and how have you sort of navigated your appreciation for mental health with both her
struggle, um, and your struggle? Because I, I, I think that's hard for both of you in different
ways, obviously. You know, it's interesting that I, um, I'm really, if there's one thing I'm really
good at, it's make it's the, um, I forget the, um, Serenity, the Serenity prayer. I'm really good at
understanding the difference between things I can and cannot control and not worrying very much
about the ones I can control. And if there's one thing that was clear to me that I could not control
directly, it was, um, my daughter's eating disorder and that no amount of trying to push or pull or
whatever was going to do it. So it was weird. I really, I approached it with a real calm. Um,
I mean, it was, you know, awful to watch. Um, but I didn't struggle in the way that I think most
parents struggle, which is the feeling of like, I should be doing something about it. And, um,
I honestly just, I mean, it was, it, it, you know, it's, look, these are often lethal, you know, that,
that, um, you know, and she was a, you know, incredibly accomplished as an anorexic. She,
she, she was extremely effective at, um, at, um, you know, at torturing herself.
And in a weird way, I think, um, that, that calm was helpful, um, in, in letting her be comfortable
with me about it. And eventually I think I played, you know, some very small role in her recovery. I
mean, obviously 99.999% of recovery was her own. Um, but, uh, so in a way it was, it was odd. I mean,
that's probably not the answer you expected me to give, but, um, but in a strange way that was not,
um, I, you know, I, maybe more generally with my adult children, I, I really am maybe better than
most parents at understanding that they're their own people and that they live their own lives and
that I'm just an observer and, um, you know, I can offer advice, but not, you know, but I have no
control over it. Um, so I don't know. Where do you, where do you think that transition takes place
age wise? I mean, I, you know, a friend of mine, Rick Elias, who was on this podcast once said
something that has stuck with me. I don't, I don't think a day, maybe two days would go by that. I
don't think of what he said, which is raising children is playing a game of tug of war that you
have to lose. Um, and you know, but he, and he said it more eloquently, but you know, it was like,
you, you lose it gradually, obviously. Right. So you're resting, you know, when you're holding the
tug of war with your five year old, you're, you're still winning, but, and with your 13 year old,
you're really starting to slip. And by the time it's the child's 18, it's their rope, right? Or
whatever. Um, you seem to have navigated that better than most, perhaps.
Yeah. I think, you know, I had a, I had a son who died when he was one and that was far and away,
like a million times, a thousand times harder than anything I've ever experienced. Um, in part,
because your own, like your real job as a parent, in some sense, your biggest job is to keep your
children safe. And it was so difficult for me to navigate the knowing that I had not kept him
safe. And I, and he was my first son and six kids later. Um, I think, I think that really affected
my parenting and, you know, he didn't die because I was abusive or neglectful. He died because of a,
a terrible disease, meningitis that came out of nowhere and, and I couldn't protect him from it.
And, and I, and I think there's one or two ways you can go. Um, you can become incredibly
fearful. Like I just happened to watch Finding Nemo yesterday with my kids. And so it's like,
you can be like Marlon, the dad in Nemo who becomes incredibly protective and doesn't want
Nemo to do anything. Or you can just understand that the world is one of uncertainty and of loss
and of, um, risk. And I really, for whatever reason, I went that second way and I just said,
look, I can't control the world around me and I'm just going to do the best I can
knowing that that's true. And I think so even from a very young age with my kids, I, um,
I have a lot of acceptance of their autonomy and their independence and the, and the fact that I
can't mold them the way I'd like to or shape them. Um, so I think, um, so even with, look,
do I want my four year old to do what I tell her to do? I get super pissed off when she doesn't,
um, you know, go to bed when I tell her yes. But on the other hand, I put an enormous value
on that autonomy and that independence. And, um, and when I'm, you know, calm and quiet, uh,
I'm more or less for better, worse putty in her hands and we'll do essentially whatever she'll
want because I think a big part of her growing up in life is, is learning to have control over
situations and what better, what better way for to learn about control than to, um, then to be able
to, to have some control in her interactions with me, which is totally different than the way I was
raised. I think in the way, um, that, um, maybe I would have raised kids absent the death of my
son Andrew, but, but I really have gone in that direction. How deliberate was that process when
he died that you made a, what sounds like a very conscious or even the subconscious decision to
accept it, um, and move on without, you know, as you said, basically, well, well, look, I, I back up
and say the following, right? I mean, I, I think one could say that many parents who lose a child
are never the same again. And I don't say that in a glib way. You're not the same again. So let me
rephrase that no parent who loses a child is the same again, but you could make the case that many
parents are so damaged after that, that, that they're, they're even externally never the same again.
Most people, I mean, I know this about you, but my guess is many people would interact with you
and never know that you'd lost a son. Um, so, I mean, what strikes me about it, Steve, is that
it's the, one of the core tenants of, of, of something called dialectical behavioral therapy,
which I've become very fond of, which is this idea called radical acceptance, which is super hard,
but it, as its name suggests, radical acceptance is basically just radically accepting things, not
saying that they're good. Radical acceptance doesn't mean it's good that my wife got cancer.
It's, I radically accept that she got cancer. Um, I, I work on this every day and it's the hardest
thing in the world. It's super hard. Um, it's even hard with silly things, by the way. You know what
I mean? Like it's even hard with the most irrelevant things at times. Um, so I want to understand that
a bit more. How did you possibly come to that type of profound radical acceptance of something
so awful? So it certainly wasn't conscious. It, it, you know, and I wasn't, I think,
it wasn't from deep thinking or anything. I just, I would say it happened. And in many ways,
I would say my hunch is that radical acceptance of, um, big things, it must, must be easier than
radical acceptance of little things because it's so obviously beyond control. Um, look, uh, my son
had died. There was definitely no undoing that. And, um, and I think it, it, it, um, I, I, I, I have
no real self-awareness, um, of how it happened. Uh, it just did. And it wasn't, I didn't work at it.
Let me put it that way. I didn't work at it. It wasn't something like where I went to therapy
and I came to eventually accept it. Just, just happened. I mean, it was, um, um, almost, um,
disjoint from the grief. Uh, I mean, the grief is one thing. The grief is real and is, you know,
semi-permanent, but how, how you, how you, how you, how you behave in other situations,
to me, that's just, you know, I don't know why, but that's just how I reacted to it. Um,
if that makes some sense, um, it was, it was really long before I consciously invested any time
effort, resources into thinking about mental health or about, um, you know, about more
spiritual things for lack of a better word. In the time that you've now come back and reflected
more heavily on these issues around mental health in the past, as you said, seven years,
have you learned anything new about that experience when Andrew died?
Yeah, you know, I've never literally, I have not thought about it in those, I mean, obviously I
think about his death all the time, but, um, but I've never, I've never, um,
I've never tried to make any sense of it. Um, um, uh, that's the answer. I literally, uh,
haven't thought about the way in which I processed it. Um, I haven't really talked about it. I mean,
other than talking to you right now, I'm not sure. Um, I've talked about his death and, um,
the aftermath of it, but I've really never talked or in many ways thought about, um,
much about the implications of it in a weird way. Um, probably seems strange, but it's, uh,
it's, it's true. What do you think would be necessary to infuse this idea of self-care and
mental health into education? You talked earlier about how this might be even more important than
education, which I don't think anybody would argue is not itself important. How would you,
how would you operationalize that if you were education czar, you know, whatever that might be,
then you, you had to hold over the entire K through 12 system. How would you infuse this type of,
this type of thinking? Let me take a step back and just first make the case for it.
Cause I think that's worth with doing. I think we went back to square one and we thought about what
we should, what we should teach children about navigating the world. We would
radically overhaul the curriculum and like we'd change math and stuff, but, but, but much more
fundamentally, I think we would try to teach them the set of skills that will make them happy
and able to resolve conflict with other people and to, you know, you know, just get along in the
world. I think like, at least for my kids, I'm much more worried about that than whether they're
like really good at calculus. That matters less to me that they have a good lives and they're,
and they know, they know themselves and they make good choices and like that. I think that wasn't
the spirit when we started school. And so our curriculum is very much built off of things from
a hundred years ago and this wasn't in the air and maybe we didn't have the tools then. Okay.
So that's my case for why I think we should be teaching. So, and that doesn't answer your
question at all about how to do that. Okay. It's just my belief that as a parent or as a school,
our goal should be that we raise well-adjusted kids who have a set of tools that are helping
them cope with the world around them. Okay. And, and that many adults like you and me have made a
lot of investment in these tools later in our lives. And maybe we could reduce the need for that
if we had invested more earlier as a society in that. Okay. How did that, I have no idea. I mean,
it's like impossible because it's impossible to change anything. What's the problem? The problem
is that time during the day is scarce in school and every minute you spend focusing on mental
health or self care, whatever is a minute taken away from something else. And that's really hard
to do. The second thing is who in the world actually knows how to do this? Well, I'm not,
I'm not sure I know how to do this well. And even if I did know a person who knew how to do this well,
how do I know how to scale it? Absolutely not. I don't know what kind of training you give teachers
or who you'd hire. So like, I think it's, it's very amorphous in my mind. It's, it's a belief
that it's important. And I think it'll be a long, let's just say y'all agree it should happen. It
will be a long arduous process. What I believe the right way to do it is for the department of
education to mandate, like we have for the common core and math and math, that we should have a
common core and mental health and that there should be these 17 things that are hit each year,
you know, different ones for anything. Like, no, obviously this is the kind of thing where I think
maybe you'd want to experimentation, right? So let a bunch of models run, see what seems to work and,
you know, and grow into it. I would be very much in favor of that where we encouraged
subsidized school districts to try out things and encourage innovation. But I think we're,
I think we're a long ways away from that. I had the privilege of talking to the Biden transition
team not too long ago about education. And, and I threw out three or four ideas and I,
and they, they, they listened quite intently to each of the ideas, except for the mental
health ones. Like they could not get away. They could not get off that topic fast enough.
I like total silence in the room when I, when I suggested that as an important thing to do.
Have you ever gone back and spoken with your dad? Because your dad is still spry as can be.
Doesn't he still work? He's still practicing. Yeah, my dad is still a practicing physician
at the VA hospital. So have you ever gone back to your dad and revisited this idea of mental health
and his lack of interest in this topic? I haven't, you know, it's funny. So I'm,
I'm actually thinking hard about interviewing my dad for my podcast and, and, and I'm pondering.
So it seems, so it's, it's funny. I feel like somehow doing it via podcast should be the opposite,
but I somehow feel like, well, if I'm doing it on the podcast, I can ask my dad all sorts of
questions that I couldn't ask him otherwise, which clearly like logically it makes no sense at all.
Why would recording something and playing it for hundreds of thousands of people
put questions on the table instead of taking them off the table? But in a weird way,
I think somehow it would be easier for me to ask my dad these questions like this in the context
of a podcast. And we'll see what happens. I, I, he's a very reluctant potential podcast guest.
And, and I'm not sure he can do technology well enough to hit the button to actually record it
on his end. So we'll see whether it happened, but not literally never talked to my father about any
of these issues ever. Super interesting. I've not talked to my father about my sister's death
or his father and mother's death. Just, we're a, we're a family that doesn't talk about stuff
like that. We're, you know, we were, it was a nice enough family, but the word love never,
never used in my household except with reference to the family dog.
People love the dog, but you would never ever say you loved another family member.
Now, how different is that with your current children and your current family? Is that
different? So I have self-consciously been very different about that, that, that, that,
I tell my kids and they tell me they love me, you know, every time we hang up the phone or whatever,
which I don't know if that matters for anything, but it is, it is, that is like,
I don't do that many things self-consciously in my life, but that is one that I very self-consciously
tried to, tried to propagate was the idea that you could express your feelings of,
of love and affection to, in my, in my current, you know, in my family, the family I, I'm the
father figure. So you're fond of decision making. What's the best decision you've ever made in your
life and what's the worst decision you've ever made in your life? I'm probably going to give you
a terrible answer to this. I think my worst decisions, I'm too embarrassed to talk about.
That's fine. I probably wouldn't be able to publicly admit that.
But I've made a lot of like, look, I will tell you all of my worst decisions have been about
inaction, not action. I know that, that, that like I have not made, I've never made a terrible,
of the hundred worst decisions I've made, I'm sure that 99 of them were not doing something
as opposed to doing something. Interesting. There are very few really bad things I've done.
By the way, I feel the opposite, Steve. My worst decisions have been decisions of bad action,
not inaction, but that's interesting. And what's the best decision you think you've ever made or a
subset of the best decisions you've ever made? I think the, I don't know if you'd actually call
a decision, but the decision, it's sort of a decision to not care what people think about me.
It's not a decision in like, oh, I went back to school, I didn't go back to school, but,
but I somehow just made a choice. It's a choice. I don't know if you call it a choice. I made a choice
to just not care what other people thought about me. And which was a big choice for me because
like most high school kids, I, all I cared about was what other people thought about me.
And at some point I just broke with that and, and was happy to live with the consequences.
And it's been, it's, it's just a, it's just a great way to live. To, it just frees you up from,
from so much burden. I think all of my best decisions I wanted have relieved burden.
I'll give you another one, which is trivial in comparison, but important is I used to be super
cheap. I used to worry about every transaction I made and like prided myself on being frugal
and thinking about, oh, you know, should I spend that dollar on a bottled water in the airport or
not? And at some point I just said, Hey, this is like, I could free up a lot of mind space. If,
if I just didn't worry about decisions that were like under $5 and it was hard for me to do, but
I said, look, I'm going to stop. If it's under $5 when I start to go into this friends, I'm going
to forget about it. And then I moved it up to like 10 or 20. And like the highest, like for me,
it's like the higher, the better. And it is just so liberating for me that I just have this rule
of thumb that like, if it's under some, you know, ridiculously large amount of money, I just don't
worry about it. And, and look, it adds up. I probably, you know, I, I waste tens of thousands,
if not more dollars a year, because I'm not getting these decisions right. And that's awesome
because I free up, you know, 10% of my time to do whatever the hell I want. And I love doing the
stuff I do. And, and it's, it's just super liberating. So I think many of the things I'd
like are these things that have been liberating where I stop worrying about stuff. And maybe it's
not that far off than your idea of radical acceptance. Like, I don't know, it's like not
radical acceptance, but it's like, it's just a total acceptance that there's going to be these
total acceptance that there's going to be these imperfections. I'm just not going to worry about
getting things exactly right. Now, do you think in general, we as a species are good at decision
making? What is there a way to, to evaluate this? I mean, like,
Good compared to what I'm not sure, but good compared to compared to optimal? No, we're
terrible. I mean, it's like, it's like behavioral economics of the last 40, 50 years shows how bad
we are at making decisions. And I think the best evidence of this is the people who know
the most about decision making. So whether it's this really prominent economist who've, you know,
thought enormous amounts about backward induction and, and optimized behavior in dynamic systems,
or whether it's Danny Kahneman, who has spent more time thinking about behavior. These are the worst
decision makers I've ever seen. I mean, Kahneman even is like very forthright. He said, like,
the reason I studied decision making is that I'm awful at it. And with everything that he's
learned, he's still awful at it. And so I think, yeah, I don't think, I don't think humans are good
at making decisions. And, and I think we can arm ourselves with tools. Like there are a lot of,
a lot of economics is really common sense codified into helping you make better decisions. I think a
fair amount of psychology and pop psychology is that as well. But look, and there's no one who
talks more than me about how we don't quit enough and, you know, and how people get, get stuck in
bad situations. I know that. And I, and I have so much trouble quitting. I mean, it's stuff I should
quit. I just, I eventually do quit it, but it takes me usually like on average two years longer to quit
something than, than I know what I know. I should have quit it two years before I do it. I can, I
understand all of the problems. I understand exactly what the situation is and the, you know, but,
but to overcome the complexity of the brain and all these forces, it's super hard to make good
decisions. What do you think, do you think there's an evolutionary force behind them?
I think that the evolutionary, when, when we were evolving, the kind of choices you had to make are
so different than the ones that we face now, that it's not a surprise that evolution would not
necessarily be our friend in, in these kinds of decisions. I mean, just, I don't know, I don't
know anything about it really, but my sense is that evolution has not been our friend in the
nutrition realm, right? Because we evolved in a, in an environment of scarcity and now we live in an
environment of plenty and all of the triggers we get from evolutionary triggers we get are the wrong
ones. And I, you know, probably that's the same with decision-making, right? We, we, we, we evolved
in settings where we were like facing life and death problems all the time. I mean, I think one
of the hugest problems that we face mental health wise is this is trauma and, and, and people are
stuck in, in a trauma mode and reacting to trauma, which evolutionary is probably fantastic because
the kind of challenges we faced in, and when we were evolving were short-term, incredibly intense
risks that you needed to marshal everything in your, in your body, in your mind to fight.
But now, now those aren't typically the kind of risks that we're, we're, or challenges we're
facing. And so people end up using the wrong set of tools that the body is just not configured well
for the kind of chronic, you know, chronic settings of, we live in of, of, you know, of too many people,
too much information, you know, constant fears and threats around itself. Like, I don't know
much about it, but, but like I, I think there's zero reason to think that evolution is our friend
when it comes to difficult, complex decisions. It's going to be just didn't, like how complex
could the decisions have been when we were evolving? I mean, I look back at it, like this
is maybe off track, but it was something that really struck me. I went to Australia for a while
and, and, and was talking with some guides as we went around Ayrus Rock, Uduru, and, and talking
about how basically the Aboriginal life had not changed hardly at all over the course of, of,
I don't know, 5,000 years or something. And it was interesting to think about, like, you, you don't
need much innovation at all, but you, you innovate 1% per generation and over 5,000 years, life is
completely transformed. So it's like, there's literally no innovation going on. I mean, there's
things like they didn't have the wheel because in the bush, the wheel didn't do you very much good.
So like, there was interesting to hear about, but it just, it really hit home for me that observation,
which is modern life and this idea of progress and, and, and innovation and being better off than
your parents. Like that's a super, super modern idea. Not at all one associated with, with mankind's
existence over, you know, huge, you know, except for this tiny sliver of, of kind of post-industrial
life that we're in. It makes it almost impossible to fathom what another hundred years looks like
for exactly that reason. The non, again, the non-linearity of what the acceleration of
technology has been like in 100 years and what it, what it looks, looks like going forward.
Now, speaking of a lack of progress, this is totally off topic, but what you said kind of
made me think about this. Let's talk about horse racing for a minute. You're, you're kind of a fan.
Did you get to see secretariat at one point? I did. Yeah. So I was, so when I was in college,
I wrote my undergraduate thesis on thoroughbred breeding and, and it just happened to be the best
library was in Lexington, Kentucky. And that's where secretariat was. And, and I was, I was,
I didn't really understand how the world worked very well. I just figured I could show up at
Claiborne Farms and they would invite me to go see. So I showed up unannounced at Claiborne Farms
and I said, I would like to see secretariat. And, and they looked at me like I was crazy.
And like two seconds later, one of the part owners of secretariat happened to drive up behind me and,
and like walk up to them and say, Hey, we were just going to go say hi to secretariat.
And, and for whatever reason, instead of like showing me away, they said, well,
this is like total clown here thinks he should be secretary too. Do you mind if you text a line?
Like, okay, why don't you get, so I did, I did get the meet, cause it's funny. I was six when
secretariat won the triple clown frown. It's one of my sports memory. Absolutely. I remember where
I was. And, and I remember it in part because for whatever reason in the Belmont, I had chosen
secretariat as the horse that I thought would win, you know, probably based on heavy guidance from
adults who had suddenly like led me to think he should win. And then that was the race he won by
31 or whatever it was. And, and, and I still remember that vividly. And so it was, I'm not,
I'm not like, I'm not a very good sports fan in the sense that I not very good at remembering names
of players and whatnot, or heavy heroes, but, but secretary was always one of my heroes. And then he
died. I don't know when he died. It was, I would have gone there in 1988. Yeah. So he didn't live
very much longer after that. Yeah. He was only 19 when he died. Why, I mean, you wrote about
thoroughbred breeding. Why do you think that secretariat was the peak of thoroughbreds and
they've never gotten note, no horses ever approached secretary its speeds. I mean,
I think for the listener, just to put in context, what's the triple crown, you've got the Kentucky
Derby, the Preakness, the Belmont to win all three of those. And the three of those take place over
what about six weeks, months. Yeah. So to win these three races, which get longer, I mean,
technically, I guess the it's a mile and a quarter, a mile and three eights, and then a mile and a half.
So for horses, that's a pretty big difference in distance. So that's speed and endurance.
In a short period of time. I mean, it's very difficult to win all three of those.
Secretariat came along and won in 1973, but did, you know, to this day has the record for the
fastest time in each. I think in the Kentucky Derby, what to me is remarkable is negative
splitting each quarter mile successively. So each of the five quarters was faster and faster and
faster and faster and faster. And then in the Belmont, not only running 224, which is like
six seconds faster than, you know, American Pharaoh won it, but also winning by whatever 30, 31
lengths. No horses come close to this. Why do you think that is?
So I don't know if I had it. So there are a couple of things to think about. So I've actually dabbled
with trying to think about, could you more in a smarter way do breeding of horses. So the way they
decide what horse to breed to another is not extremely scientific. They kind of look at the
horse and they have some ideas. And so my hunch is that it's not particularly well done. Although
just like with humans, there's an enormous amount of assortative mating, right? So it's not like
they mate the worst mares to the best studs. I mean, they make the best and the best, you know,
in the same way that the, you know, the best basketball players end up, you know, getting
married to the, you know, volleyball star. And then who knows what kind of amazing offspring
they're going to have. I think probably the best explanation for it would be that in contrast to
human sports, I'm not sure there's been any advances in training techniques for horses
in the last 40 or 50 years. Now maybe there have been, but they're not obvious to an outside
observer. And I've always won, like I have this, like I have a few little secret dreams. And one
of my secret dreams, which sounds like a Disney movie or something, is that I would buy a horse
an average thoroughbred. And I would train that horse the way Peter Attia trains for ultra marathons.
And the horse would actually turn out to be really good. I mean, I don't really know much
about horse training, but I don't think I'm greatly exaggerating when I say that the way
that horses are currently trained is they stand in their stall for something like 23 and a half
hours a day. And like roughly once every day or two, they bring them out of the stall and they
trot around and they run. And sometimes they run fast, but they don't tend to run fast for more
than like three eighths of a mile. Even though their actual races are going to be a mile, a mile
and a quarter, they only, like when they train, they only run three eighths of a mile. And I don't,
and I think these horses spend almost no time swimming. So you might say, look, the legs are
fragile because the legs are fragile. You can't like run them all the time. But like in my little
fantasy world, I've got a horse sized pool with a strong current going against it. And my, you know,
you know, my horse Silver or whatever, you know, whatever the horses that I have in my Disney movie,
it's swimming in the water like four hours a day. And I've got him hooked up to oxygen monitors. And
he's like, you know, he's doing that's an interesting point, right? You put some zone
to training and build some aerobic capacity, Miticon, real efficiency. I mean, that's,
look, I don't think it's, I mean, I don't know enough about it to say if what you're saying
is correct or not, that there haven't been advances in 50 years. It's hard to believe there haven't
been, but I don't know. I mean, it would be interesting. I think though, if you,
let's forget about the golf project. I think it would be super fun if you and I, because I think
like, I'm not going to learn, you already know a lot about how humans work. And I'm sure you could
figure out really quickly how horses work. And it will be, I think it would be so much fun to buy
some, you know, to claim, okay, because these horses when they run, you can claim them for like
$5,000, take some total illusion. Well, the problem is for the triple crown, you gotta be a
three year old. So you can't really do it. You just gotta take some completely un, unspecial horse.
And, and what we'd really want to do is we'd want to win the triple crown, like four years in a row,
doing our aerobic training. Look, if it were humans, like imagine, just, just imagine you go back
to, uh, you know, I don't know, to, to the time when, uh, you know, you know much more than me,
but like when Roger Bannister was starting the four minute mile. And I think there's still like
not very good training going on at all at that time. I mean, I may be crazy, but is it not true
that good high school runners in the U S. Yeah. So I think, I think, I think, I think in the case
of humans, we can definitely say that the biggest difference between Roger Bannister and a good
collegiate runner today is knowledge of training much more than equipment or nutrition for sure.
Because so it would be true. Like if you could magically understand
fitness and training and take today's fitness and training and take like a run of relatively good
athlete, but nothing special. I think you could have won the Olympic gold medal in, in, um, a
range of sports. That would be my conjecture. Take a good athlete and, and, and, and like, like, like,
uh, like a college, a good college caliber athlete. And with, and the difference between like swimming
would be probably a good example. Like I think you probably the best, like the, the hundredth of
the thousandth best swimmer today is probably better than the best swimmer in the world 50
years ago in terms of times. I don't know. You wouldn't know. Yeah. I'd have to go back. Yeah.
Yeah. So like, that's what I'm saying. So you take an hour, like a good, but not great horse.
And it seems like you could, if you could get the same kind of advances in training,
you would just, I mean, I guess the other thing is how much of an outlier with secretariat, right?
I mean, I think there's still some debate about was his greatness, how much of it was due to the
size of his heart. Unfortunately, his heart was not weighed at autopsy, but the same that, that did
the autopsy on secretariat several years later, did the autopsy on sham, who was the horse that
finished second, it was basically the second best horse in the world in 1973. And sham had a pretty
large heart and he said secretariat's heart was at least 15% larger, which basically put secretariat's
heart at twice the size of a normal heart. And it's interesting that has been linked to an X chromosome,
which may partially explain why secretariat's immediate male offspring weren't that special
because his male offspring would have got his Y chromosome. His female would have got the X and
only if that X made it into a male two generations later would that have been particularly fast horse,
which I think also gets to your point about the lack of sophistication around breeding.
I don't know why I find this stuff so interesting. I think there's just something so beautiful about
these horses, but in particular secretariat, I've always been so enamored with. And in fact, when
our middle son before he was born, I was really lobbying hard for the middle name secretariat.
That didn't even get a prayer, but I lobbied really hard for it.
Maybe if you lived in communist Russia, you would have had more of a better chance with the middle
name secretariat. Okay, Steve, a couple of last questions for you here, because I've been taking
up too much of your time. What do you think is the most interesting question
on your mind that you don't have a clue of what the answer is?
I don't have a clue. So this is just pure weird, but something I think about. Actually,
I think of it with you because it's your influence that led me in this direction because you
introduced me to Sam Harris's work. And there was a few paragraphs in Sam Harris's book,
Waking Up, which have intrigued me, which I don't really know anything about, but I find them
intriguing. So this is what I find really interesting. So he talks about how the left
side of the brain has the ability to speak and the right side of the brain
doesn't have the capability to express itself through speech. And I'm sure there's a lot more
to it than that, but it's a starting point. That simple observation, I find interesting because it
got me thinking about the degree to which our lives are mediated through speech. So obviously,
when I talk to you, I have to use speech, but my own inner life is incredibly dictated through
speech. So I'm putting words on everything. As I go through my life, it's not just this idea of
chatter in the back of our head and like, is there some monkey on my back telling me I'm a
loser or whatever. That's not really what I'm talking about. It's much more about that in general,
when I look at a computer, I put the word computer on it. So then it just got me interested in the
question of, well, he kind of makes a little suggestion that it's possible that you could
think of the right side of the brain as being held as a slave dominated by the left hand side of the
brain. Like the right hand side of the brain has all sorts of interesting things it could do,
but because it can't speak, it's relegated to this awful subsidiary role. And so I just got
interested in the idea of how could I introduce myself to the right side of my brain? How could
I actually get to meet that part of my brain? Which I don't even, like I know nothing about how the
brain works. I don't even know if that makes sense, but like given infinite time, which I don't have,
it's actually, I think that's one of the things I would pursue. So I've pursued it like in a little
way, which is I found it was actually quite easy with concentration to train myself to be silent.
Silent in thought, you mean?
So what I want to do, so I want to think, I just don't want to think with words. So it's a way,
so I think it's slightly, like I don't understand meditation and all the different kinds of
meditation, but I think what I'm trying to do is slightly different than what most people are
trying to do. I'm not going to quiet my brain. What I'm trying to do is I'm trying to observe
the world with all of my senses, but observe them without, but free of language. Okay. So that,
look, it's totally possible as I, I don't know, peel a potato. Like I know how to peel a potato
without calling a potato, without using the word peel, you know, and almost everything we do in
life, even I think in some sense, listening, I can kind of, I don't know about listening, but like
most things I can do on my own, I don't need language, but I constantly have language as my
partner. And, and so it was an interesting and surprisingly easy task to on demand, be able to
try to put words aside and be word free. I won't say that I can do it like at will or perfectly,
but, but I was better at doing that than I thought I'd be. And, and what followed was kind of
interesting and intriguing and, and, and increased my interest in the question as opposed to
decrease it, which is, I find that it's very difficult for me to be unhappy or angry
without words, that words are really critical to feeling victimized, to feeling like,
like it's not that I don't feel angry, but I feel very, very differently in the absence of words
and with words. And it's, and I can prostrate. So anyway, that's probably a crazy answer to what
you just asked, but, but that's, it's something I have a hunch that it might be important.
I have no clue about how to actually do it well. I'm sure there are probably gurus out there who
could maybe help me do it, but I've actually never really heard anyone else talk about it
explicitly in, in that way. But, you know, but so when I'm trying to go to sleep,
it's kind of thing where when I try to go to sleep at night, I spend maybe five minutes a day
playing around with this. And, and, and I, I think it's been good for me in a weird way.
Well, I think that last observation about how the, the reduction of nomenclature around a negative
emotion or an emotion, let's not that anger is a negative emotion, but a negatively valenced
emotion at least can reduce its impact. That, that alone is super interesting as an observation.
The other, the other thing I'd say is that strikes me as something that could be probably augmented
by medication, right? There, there could be certain plants or drugs or chemicals
that would probably really augment that state. So we'll leave it at that. That's interesting.
That's really interesting. Maybe you can help me with some of those.
You last thing I want to ask you, Steve, you've mentioned numerous times that the random
controlled experiment, you know, the RCT, the gold standard of medicine is a tool that is
virtually never available to the economist for obvious reasons. The scale would be enormous.
If you could put all of that aside for a moment, if you truly had billions of dollars
and all the time in the world, what experiment would you conduct?
So it's funny, you know, cause I don't actually have big ideas about economics. I think economics
isn't where I would go with something like that because in some fundamental way, I think we
understand what's understandable about the economy. I mean, it isn't, it's not a lack of
resources that makes it hard to understand the macro economy. It's the fact that we have exactly
one of them, right? So absent a set of parallel universes, I don't think we're ever going to find
out through data or experimentation. So look, if you give me a different choice, which is,
hey, if you had, if you could be God and create enormous number of parallel universes,
then I would have a bunch of interesting macro experiments that I might want to do.
I really think, so for me, when I think about big problems, they're much more off and like,
like I think that they're rarely about randomization. I really think the things I, I would,
but let me give you an example where maybe there's more you really talking about, but like,
I think, well, how we really blew it with COVID is that we didn't look, so what have we done? Well,
we used randomized trials to figure out that we have really good vaccines. Okay. But we didn't
even, I fought with Montsef Slawey about this, but look, I think we were idiots not to do challenge
trials where we actually went out and learned much more quickly by giving, you know, giving people
vaccines and giving them COVID and seeing if it works, you know, like I think we were foolish
given, given the, the stakes not to do that. But much more fundamentally, I think that we have
ruled out medical ethics and societal views have ruled out really sensible, like, like when we want
to know the answers, the best way is a randomized experiment. Okay. So there's so many, and you and
I have talked about a little bit on my pocket as well. There's so many cases around COVID where we
just don't know the basic facts about, like, I think you made a big point about the six feet
thing, like six feet away, like somebody just made that up and we live with it. Or another one that
just came up as there's a great op-ed piece that said, well, why is everyone still wearing terrible
masks? Because like at the beginning people, you know, like we're told, well, don't wear a mask
because a mask won't help you anyway. Which was obviously idiotic because we were really being
told that because they didn't want us buying up all the good masks because they wanted to give
them the frontline health professionals. Of course, if they didn't work, why are the frontline
health professionals wearing them? But I just think there's like the real missed opportunity in COVID
was not to take the approach that I think is like 100% accepted, which is the best way we are able to
learn given the constraints of society about COVID is by doing clever little natural experiments
where we look at some particular airplane and some particular person we know got COVID and then
we go in and do contact tracing to figure out how bad it was. Look, the best way to figure out whether
airplanes are dangerous is to put people on airplanes, some who have COVID and some don't,
and to figure out who gets it. I mean, and people are like, oh, you can't do that. But look, when
the stakes are high enough and you got, you know, especially with COVID, but this brings it back to
the field of economics, you would argue if you pay people enough as volunteers, there's going to be a
subset of people that are going to say, yeah, my risk of getting COVID and something really bad
happening is sufficiently low enough that I'm willing to be one of the healthy volunteers on
that airplane who risks getting COVID. And of course, we would argue, well, that might not be
medically ethical, but you're saying desperate times call for desperate measures. There's a way
to solve these problems economically. Yeah. And then, you know, Monteslawy who ran Operation
Warp Speed said, yeah, but that's no good because then you just have the healthy people and that
might not tell you anything. But look, there are plenty of people who are really, really sick
and who are worried about their, their dependence and what's going to happen to their family.
But there are plenty of people who know their life expectancy is four months,
who are going to be willing to get exposed to COVID if you say, well, take care of your family,
you know, if you die from. So, like, I think I have a, I know I'm completely out of step with a
mainstream medical ethics on this, but I think, I think medical ethics gets it really wrong
because when they think about money, they think about small amounts of money. And it's probably
wrong. Like if you, if you're willing to offer people a hundred dollars to do this, then the
only people are going to do it are going to be drug addicts and uneducated people who don't
understand. But look, if you, when the stakes are as high as COVID, you can offer people $10,000,
$100,000. I mean, you can offer enough money that everyone's going to be lining up to do it.
And if everybody's lining up, then I think medical ethics no longer has a real, a real
stake in this because, you know, it's just a different problem when everyone is volunteering
to do it. Volunteering because you're paying enough money, but then almost every issue of
medical ethics fades away when, when you got a surplus of people volunteering.
You know, I never thought about it that way until you said it, Steve, that is a fantastic
point. Institutional review boards, IRBs are adamant about making sure honorariums are very
small in studies to prevent coercion. That's their big stick is you can't overpay people.
Otherwise it's coercive. But the irony of it is, it is coercive if it's low and it disproportionately
targets the most vulnerable. Exactly. It's so true. And, and I, I mean, on organ donation,
this has been something I've harped on for a long time. People, people are really terrified
of the idea of a market for organs for like live donors and kidneys. And every horror story they
tell is a horror story that's embedded in the idea that there's going to, it's going to be exploited.
Look, and that's because the price, the price, the market price would be too low. This is actually
an odd case in which you want to enforce an actual price, which is way above the market price,
because the value to our meta, you know, better than me, the amount we spend on dialysis and the
amount of suffering associated with it. It's like some even like measurable percentage of GDP,
like one or 2% of GDP or some crazy thing like that. And, and the value of a really good,
healthy, live kidney to society is enormous. It's, you know, on the order of, I don't know,
you know, hundreds of thousands of dollars at least. So you could easily pay people a hundred
thousand dollars for a good kidney. And if you did that, I think you might have, I don't know,
might have 10 million people who would, 50 million people who would sign up to be kidney donors in
that world. And in a world in which, you know, Wall Street stockbrokers are signing up to donate
their kidneys, not donate, I mean, not altruistic, they just want a hundred grand. Look, in that
world, the whole medical ethics is turned upside down. And the weird thing is I cannot get anyone
to take that scenario seriously, even though to me, it seems completely and totally obvious that
if we could do it someplace, if we could get, you know, I don't know, you know, Guatemala or,
you know, or Singapore, Mozambique or someplace to just do that in one place, I bet it would work
great. And that one example could lead the rest of the world to follow. But we are so far from any
place being willing to try it. I mean, the closest is Iran, interestingly, ironically, Iran is one
place on the planet that's paid for organs, but not the way I would do it. Not that it's the most
important problem in the world. That is a fan, like along with training that horse, Silver, to win the
Kentucky Derby. That's another of my fantasies, is a world in which I create this market for
live donors. All right. So on that note, Steve, we've got three huge problems to follow up on.
We've got to, in order, figure out how to create a really good scratch five golfer in 12 months.
We've got to figure out how to take a B player horse as a one-year-old and get a triple crown
by age three. And we've got to figure out a market for organ donation with a really, really,
really high price premium paid for kidneys. Let me just add number four is we got to figure out how
to do this Manhattan project for climate change. That's the most important one. I'm going to
personally spend more time thinking about that one than the other three, but that's awesome. To
come out of this podcast with four great problems to work on is more than we bargained for.
My prediction, the only one we're going to solve is going to be that five handicap golfer. When you
get burned out and you get tired of doing everything else. The other three, I'm not too optimistic.
Steve, thanks so much for sitting down today. It was awesome.
Thank you, Pete. It's awesome. It's always so much fun to talk to.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail
every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's
show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple
Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.