Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Well, Chris, we've been talking about doing this for probably two years now. So I'm really
happy to finally sit down with you though. We had always thought we'd be doing it in
person, but decided just didn't want to wait any longer.
I agree.
But no, I miss you dearly. And I think during our discussion today, people are going to
get to understand why you've played such an important role in my development. I guess
let's just, I'll just state for everyone that you were one of my senior residents, what
we call chief residents when I was going through my training at Hopkins. And I think on other
podcasts, people have probably heard me mention you. I've certainly talked about you on Jaco's
podcast several years ago. I've talked about you on this podcast and usually in the context
of what I consider to be the most remarkable leadership. Residency was not without its stresses
and stressors. And I think we have lots of great memories from it, but also some not
so great ones. And therefore anything that could have been done by those around us to
make the process better was always appreciated. And I think we'll get to that later, but let's
just start by telling folks like how you even got interested in medicine, let alone
surgery.
Yeah. Well, first of all, thank you so much for the invitation. It's awesome even virtually
to get to hang out with you and reminisce a little bit, but also talk about our work.
And I'm really proud of the work you've done with this podcast. It's been so impactful
to patients, providers. It's just a cool way to see your leadership and impact extend.
Yeah, medicine for me was something I stumbled to. So I grew up in the DC area. My dad is
a retired Presbyterian minister. My mom was a medical social worker. The only other physician
in my family is my grandfather, who was an internist and researcher in St. Louis. And
I went to college without a clear plan other than wanting to play college soccer, which
is what I was fortunate enough to do. And I had imparted to me by my parents that they
would support whatever I chose to do, but wanted it to be something that served other
people. And through the course of my studies did come to medicine for some of the somewhat
cliche reasons. It was a really exciting, challenging field that appealed to the problem
solver or the scientist in me, but first and foremost was a way to serve people. And
came to surgery very late too. In medical school, I was one of those people that liked
everything and was fascinated by all fields, but really became attracted to what fortunately
I think still sustains me today. And that is that being a surgeon provides this really
unique opportunity to enter people's lives in their scariest kind of darkest moments
and to have the privilege to be able to walk that with them and try to help them navigate
that time and to have skill in some cases to solve the problem. And I think that was
remarkable to me. I was struck by the challenge of it and was fortunate to make the decision
to train in surgery and end up at Hopkins, where as I totally agree with how you described
it, it was like the one hand kind of forged us into the people we are today, but also
was difficult and challenging. And that's partially also what made it the experience
it was.
Yeah. How did you pick Hopkins? I know everybody who, I mean, I guess you could say Hopkins
sort of picks people and not the other way around, but how did you at least have the
desire to go to such a rigorous program? Was it something that said, Hey, once I've committed
to doing this, I might as well go to the best place.
Yeah, it was a combination of things. As I mentioned, I decided a little late in medical
school that I wanted to train in general surgery and I went and consulted with the
program director at my medical school, who was John Tarpley, kind of a legendary general
surgeon at Vanderbilt, who had spent a lot of his career in Africa actually doing mission
work and surgery. And I went to meet with him and to be honest with you, the goal of
that meeting was to have him tell me that I even had a shot at staying at Vanderbilt.
That was my kind of what I thought would be the best I could do. And we talked for a long
time. He's a wonderful person, wanted to hear about my goals. And he said, I think partially
a jest, but he said, you know what? I think we need to send you back to the mothership
because he had trained at Hopkins and he still carried with very passionate memories
about the training there and the kind of standard of clinical excellence that the training programs
there represented. And so I was fortunate enough to get an interview and was obviously
impressed with the history and the emphasis on clinical excellence. But like you, I think
I was also really attracted to the idea of mentorship and one individual in particular,
Keith Lillemoe, who was the program director at the time, now the chair of surgery at Massachusetts
General Hospital. I really got the feeling that he was invested in the development and
training of his residents, not only as surgeons, but also as individuals and as leaders. And
exactly like you said, kind of once I got that sense, I wanted to swim in that pool,
so to speak, figuring that I would gain as much from obviously the terrific history and
mentors and training environment, but also the individuals who we were lucky to train
next to. I mean, I think when you feel like you're just running with superstars every
day, that does push you to be the best possible physician, surgeon, person you can be. And
I can think of so many individuals just like you that inspired me to push myself to beyond
kind of expectations that I probably even had for myself at that period of time.
Yeah, I mean, there's no doubt during this discussion, Chris, I'm going to have to embarrass
the hell out of you because the reality of it is you were definitely, and you're just going to
be too modest to accept it, but you were certainly in a league of your own, even amongst that caliber
of individual. So it's one thing to say you played for the Yankees, it's another thing to say you
were Mickey Mantle or Joe DiMaggio. And I think to me, one of the things I want to dig into today
is for many of us, certainly myself, I'd put in that category, you show up with all of these ideas
about what you can be and what this process is like. And some role in the way, a tiny piece of you
gets a little broken. You lose a little bit of your humanity, your tolerance for distress goes
down, the empathy goes down a little bit, your tolerance for others around you, even on the same
team goes down a little bit, whether it's your tolerance for an error that a nurse makes, your
tolerance for an error that the lab makes. I mean, I just watched in myself over five years, a degradation
of humanity that in my case led to a very extreme outcome, which was departing. I can safely say
you're the only person in whom I didn't witness that. And simultaneously, you were the best of the
best. So it's it's to me, that's just an unusual combination that I definitely want to understand
that a bit more.
Well, I mean, that's very kind of you. I didn't feel that way. Which is, I guess, true of all of us,
you don't. The battle you're waging within is, you know, different than what everybody sees on the
outside. You know, I mean, I think, you know, one way of asking that question is kind of what
sustained me during that time period, what, you know, kept all of us going, but me in particular,
you know, I, I definitely had a, you know, overwhelming sense from day one of arriving in
Baltimore. And this speaks to kind of my medical training in general, but certainly specifically
our residency, that I felt like, you know, I was very lucky to be there, you know, that there were,
there were hundreds of qualified individuals who could have taken that spot. And, and other and
probably thousands of other individuals who, who didn't get the opportunities I did to get to that
spot. And so I felt, you know, obligated, if that's the right word, to kind of maximize that entire
experience. You know, I also felt the, the burden, if you will, of, of the expectations of those
around me, you know, I mean, the, the, the expectations of those that were training us, our
colleagues, etc. You know, I always, I, one of the things I said to Dr. Little, Dr. Cameron, when I
left was, you know, thank you for your high expectations. Like, that's really what drove me
to achieve things that I didn't necessarily think were within me. I will say though, that the last
thing, and this, this is true to this day, so it's not specific to residency, is that I have always
found, fortunately, that what recenters me when medicine gets hard, because it does get difficult,
whether you practice in a, you know, busy primary care practice, where you're cramming through 40
patients a day, or you're doing operations where a wrong move leads, can lead to somebody's death,
you know, there are, there are good days and bad days, and there are pressures that can do all the
things to you that you alluded to. But what has always re-centered me is the patience. I mean, to
be honest, that, that privilege that I was speaking of earlier of being invited into people's lives,
in these crazy moments, and actually having the opportunity to intervene. And somehow, even in the
thick of residency, when you're like, how can you know, why is it that this lab I ordered 14 hours
ago has still hasn't been done? Or, you know, why can't I find the x-rays that were just on this desk,
like two hours ago? You know, or what are all the other crazy things that we had to deal with? Or why,
why is there no food to eat at 11 o'clock at a 24 seven operation? You know, the thing that always
kind of re-centered me is reminding me that, you know, the people upstairs in those beds,
headed a lot worse off than I did. And, you know, I think that, that the privilege of being involved
in their care is kind of what re-centered me and still does today. You know, when I have
days like that, that is always what is able to kind of pull me back to the right frame of mind.
Another thing that I think made you very special, that wasn't, that I think was actually distinct
from everything you're describing, everything you're describing was on incredible visible display.
But you could have, I think had all of those characteristics, and you wouldn't have created
the magnet that someone like me felt. Now, I can't speak for the other residents, but I just,
it would be hard for me to imagine. I'm the only one that felt this way. But I just remember any
time my rotation card showed I was going to be your junior resident, it didn't matter what the
rotation was. I couldn't wait for that month to arrive. And so that speaks to something a little
different. And I mean, like, let's go back to, you went to Northwestern, if I recall, right, for
college. And so you're a division one athlete, you're playing soccer. Were you the team leader?
I was a captain. You know, I think I was not the best player on the team, at least on my college
teams, for sure. But I do feel very lucky that I was, you know, elected to represent the team and
to serve in, you know, a leadership role, at least as it as it is within the context of an athletic
team. You know, I do think that one of the things that has always been true for me, you know, and
this dates back to, you know, sports as a kid, and, you know, and to be honest, as part of the reason
why I chose to be a transplant surgeon, is that I always migrated to team, you know, collaborative
activities. You know, I was, I was never an individual sport athlete, you know, I swam a
bit, I played tennis a bit, but I never kind of like was captivated by those sports in the same
way that I was of just being on a team. And in fact, you know, both, there were multiple times in my
development as a young kid, playing soccer in the DC area, which is a very competitive kind of
soccer environment, you know, where I was lucky to kind of be on the some of the teams that I was
on playing with, you know, elite players. But being on that team being in that environment, you know,
seemed to pull the best out of me. And, and I think that was true in residency, too, you know,
what I relished the most was like, you know, yeah, it was five in the morning, but you showed up and
there was Peter and there was Megan and there, you know, it was your team. And it was like, you know,
this like you felt like you were, you know, unstoppable to some degree, even though you
were, you know, doing what at times seemed a possible task. And, and I feel the same way
about transplant, you know, I feel like the part of the reason I chose that it was clear that
no one can accomplish what it takes to take a liver transplant patient from, you know,
from their diagnosis to listing to to operation to recovery to, you know, transform and
transform them to a new life afterwards, without, you know, a really highly functioning team. And
that that is what always has kind of inspired me to, you know, give my best because I feel like
I'm in a team where other people are doing the same thing. I mean, there's a story I'll tell that
I would imagine you don't recall because it was so commonplace. But it, it really stood out to me
as an example of what like a great leader would do. So you'll have to you'll have to forgive me for
explaining a process that you understand Oh, too well, but most people don't, which is actually
I'm going to have you explain it. Tell folks what the M&M conference was every Tuesday morning.
Yeah, so. So you're referring to what what it Hopkins was called morbidity and mortality
conference, which is a, you know, I think there are versions of that throughout medicine, but in
surgery, it is a unique part of the culture. So I think one of the things that makes surgeons
and surgery unique as a discipline is the sense of ownership, accountability, responsibility for
the outcomes of the patients that you're privileged to care for. And so morbidity and
mortality conference was a weekly conference where we reviewed essentially patients' stories,
patients' cases, particularly patients that had suboptimal outcomes, whether it was a
a complication as, as hopefully routine as a wound complication or something that they would,
would extend their recovery, but they would recover from fully to a, to a death related to
a surgical procedure or, or at least to a diagnosis that we tried to address with a
surgical procedure. And I think, you know, every my former chair here at Michigan, Mike Mahon,
used to say that, you know, you can look into this into a department soul by attending their,
you know, morbidity and mortality conference. It is, it becomes the kind of cultural event
of the department because you get a sense for what that level is of accountability is,
is the conference spent kind of blaming the anesthesiologist or the nurse or, you know,
or the patients' comorbid conditions, or is the, is the discussion about what we could do better
next time to make the patient's outcome better. And I think, you know, there are
lots of examples that, you know, I'm sure you and I could regale for four hours of kind of how
lessons learned in that room, you know, in the morning, you know, shaped the way we think about
medicine, the way we think about responsibility, you know, all kinds of other things. One thing I
always admired is that the chair who was there for most of the time, we were there, John Cameron,
he would often be the, the moderator of morbidity and mortality conference. And he always led,
as you recall, with his own cases, which is, you know, a remarkable example of
the level of accountability that I think he was trying to, to encourage among the, the faculty and
residents there. Yeah, that's one of the things that stood out to me because I went to medical
school at Stanford, and it was just a different culture. It wasn't nearly as rigorous. And so even
in medical school, you would still attend that during your surgical rotations. But it, it was not
the conference that I saw at Hopkins, which was, I mean, this was the most intense hour of the week,
and it was taking place outside of the operating room. So this, this was kind of the story that,
that I'll, that I'll tell that kind of always, it just remains to this day etched in my mind. So
you and I, this is by this point, you're now the trauma fellow. So you have now finished residency,
you are now staying at Hopkins for another year to do what can only be described as the craziest
fellowship ever. It's a hepatobiliary oncology fellowship combined with trauma every third night,
as if that weren't enough. And it's either July or August. So it's very early in the academic year.
I'm the third year resident, so I'm kind of your most senior resident on that service. And
you're the ACS. And so you're functioning like the attending. And we had just come on that
morning to receive sign off from the team that was leaving. And, you know, we both recall just how
chaotic that could be, right? You know, you've got people that are just getting shot two hours
earlier, you got to run to the OR with them, and you're being told about these all this patient,
this patient, this patient. And I mean, almost as a matter of fact, one of those patients was being
discharged that day. And it was sort of like this person on this floor is going to go home in a
couple of hours. Nobody needs to go and even see that person. You not only went and saw that person,
but realized something was wrong. And it pains me that I don't remember what was wrong. But
either you sense that this person had a compartment syndrome that got missed. I think they'd been hit
by a car that day before or something like that. You sensed something that was missed.
For you to be the one to go and catch it was out of this world, right? Never would the attending go
and be the one to go and check on the patient whose discharge paperwork is already signed to
go home. But you did that. You caught the misdiagnosis, took the patient to the operating room,
operated, you know, probably saved his leg. You then presented that case at M&M several weeks later.
But the part that blew my mind was you never mentioned the circumstances around which
this patient came into our care. In other words, there was no blaming. There was no,
well, you know, Mr. Smith was about to be discharged, but I decided to go and make sure
he was okay and realized he actually had a compartment syndrome and needed surgery to save
his leg. Instead, it was you presented it as though it was your fault, as though you had missed it.
And I honestly, it sounds crazy. That was one of the moments when I realized I don't I'm not good
enough to be in this profession. You know, maybe none of us are. But but I don't know if you remember
that case, but yeah, I do actually now that you recall it. And it was the circumstances were as you
described, it was one of those crazy days where 35 things are happening. And, you know, we we were
all over 34 of them. Unfortunately, the 35th was this poor guy who was, you know, getting ready to
be wheeled out of the hospital. And yeah, I mean, I think, you know, I don't remember the circumstances
of the M&M discussion, but I but I do certainly carry the, you know, philosophy in my work
currently. And, you know, certainly that, you know, there is not value in kind of assigning
blame to individuals, there's only value in recognizing opportunity for us as a system,
as a team to get better. And, and partially, it's because, you know, I think, you know,
if I were to throw stones in that case, you know, I could walk out of that conference and an hour
later be the one responsible for kind of generating, you know, a similar or worse complication. So I
think there's some humility that has to enter into understanding that no one has all the answers,
nor should be expected to kind of catch everything. In fact, one of the things that I think has one of
the, as you know, one of the criticisms of the M&M morbidity mortality culture is that at least
historically, it had been a little bit too much about assigning individual blame and not about
recognizing opportunity for change. But I do think that that over time, I've seen that change. And
certainly the way morbidity and mortality conferences are run now, for example, at my
institution and others I've visited are much more focused on what's right for the patient than
rather, you know, who can we, who's, you know, who do we have to kind of string up for, you know,
this particular mistake, which is, which is number one, better for patients. Number two,
sets a better example for the, for the trainees and learners in the room that are, that are
trying to do this and just as a, is an important piece of creating the right culture where
everybody's kind of oars are moving in the same direction. At what point during residency,
did you decide that it was going to be transplant medicine versus the other things that you had
clearly shown, you know, a fantastic predilection for such as pancreatic surgery, liver surgery,
and all facets of surgical oncology in the GI tract? Yeah. I mean, honestly, I was, I was greedy.
I kind of wanted to do, do it all. You know, I, I, when I entered Hopkins, I had developed an
interest in, in diseases of the hepatobiliary system and upper GI tract. So that was another
thing that clearly drove my, my interest in that residency where they had such expertise and, and
kind of a, you know, concentration of experts in those diseases. It was, you know, I, I did my
intern year rotation in transplant, and then again, a third year rotation in transplant.
My fellow as an intern and then my junior attending as a third year was one of the people
who's men, you know, one of the most important influences on my professional career,
who's Bob Montgomery, now the head of transplantation at, at NYU and a, you know,
and a transformative figure in our field over the last couple of decades. And, you know,
partially it was his example of, you know, what I thought I could aspire to be as a transplant
surgeon. Partially, it was realizing that the distance from kind of bench to bedside and
transplantation is really short. You know, it was unlike anything that I had, had seen even in,
in a very innovative, progressive, you know, surgical department. And finally, you know,
specifically speaking to my previous interest, I did see liver transplantation specifically as
being completely complimentary to, to being a comprehensive about abiliary surgeon and, and,
physician for patients with, you know, have had abiliary disease. You know, it's interesting.
In other parts of the world, it's pretty commonplace for a patibiliary surgeons and
liver transplant surgeons to be the same individuals, you know, in the U S just with
training tracks changing over time and such, there are, there tend to be surgical oncologists
who do a patibiliary surgery and transplant surgeons who may do some abatibiliary surgery,
but I clearly thought it would make me a more complete surgeon and physician to,
to train in both. And I've been very lucky. I mean, this isn't something that can happen
necessarily at every institution, but I've, I've straddled that line in my career too.
I, about half my clinical practices is, uh, a patibiliary surgery, surgery of the liver,
bile duct and pancreas for mostly for cancer, but other benign diseases and then liver
transplantation. So, you know, I feel like I won the lottery, you know, I'm kind of walking
that line, you know, uh, to be able to combine those disciplines.
Um, tell folks a little bit about what you mean by bench to bedside and that,
that distance being short. Uh, it's a term we throw around a lot in medicine, but
its significance is huge. I want to make sure people understand it.
Yeah, no, it's, it's a great point. I mean, I mean, part of it is just understanding the history,
right? So, you know, transplantation as a field is very young, you know, so the first kidney
transplants were done in the 1950s. The first liver, heart, and lung transplants attempted in
the 1960s, none of which were particularly successful until the 1980s related to, uh,
all sorts of important changes, but particularly the development of effective immunosuppression.
And then all of, once it became a, a feasible and successful, uh, medical intervention,
then developing all of the systems around, uh, uh, making that a reality for more people and
extending that to people with organ failure, uh, of various causes. So, so here we are,
you know, surgical residents in the 1990s in a field that really is about 10 years old in terms
of kind of being operationally, uh, uh, you know, expanding enough to, to, to really be a reality
at most major medical, you know, uh, major medical centers. And so, you know, you would see,
you would see things being discussed kind of in morning reporter rounds or like, you know,
now this is a really tricky case of acute rejection. We haven't tried X yet. And then
you would see we try X and, you know, it would work or not work. And we just, or there were
surgical techniques, you know, living donor liver transplantation, basically part of a major part
of my practice now was created in the, you know, 1990s and early 2000s. So, so I think the ability
to see innovation become reality in very, um, you know, uh, rapid form was, was number one, inspiring.
I mean, you felt like you were doing something that was, that was new and innovative and just
really incredible, but also, um, you know, I think to be honest, it made you feel like you could
potentially have some impact in the development of, uh, of a field that, um, was nascent. And, you know,
uh, I would put myself in maybe the second or third generation of transplanters, you know,
in terms of its history, which is, which is a very, you know, I feel very fortunate to be
kind of a witness to that history and participate in some of it, um, moving forward.
Let's use kidney as an example to explain to people kind of the challenges today. Um,
you know, we take kidney transplants almost for granted because the success rate is so high. In
fact, even when I was a resident, um, you know, if, if, if, if you demonstrated that you had enough
of this skill and the interest, you know, even the transplant fellow would let you as the,
you know, mid-level resident or the senior resident general surgery do kidney transplants.
You mentioned Bob Montgomery. There was a stretch on transplant where Bob and I did 13 consecutive
kidney transplants together in a period of like four days. Um, so the fact that, you know,
kind of a knuckle dragger like me could have been doing this speaks to how well it works today.
But as you said, this is a procedure that even in the 1960s carry carried with it a mortality of,
you know, more than 50%. So let's break down for people the evolution of this, uh, from sort of
the technical evolution, right? There was, it was only what maybe a little over a hundred years ago
that the anastomosis was even understood, um, to then the complications of acute rejection,
chronic rejection, and even understanding what the immune system is, is doing. So,
and then we're going to get to liver after, because of course, liver takes it to a whole
new level in all regards. Well, I think, you know, kidney transplantation is kind of the,
the best example of all the, the challenges that you just alluded to. It was also, um,
the, the first solid organ at least that, that, um, appealed to, you know, the earliest pioneers
in the field as something that, you know, it seemed feasible to give someone an extra kidney
like that. You could kind of imagine a way technically to make that work as opposed to
doing, you know, what we now do for say, harder liver transplantation, where you're doing an
orthotopic transplant, you're literally taking out the prior organ and putting in the new one.
That's a little different than a heterotopic kidney transplant, where you're giving them an
extra organ and hoping that replaces the function. Yeah, we should, people probably don't understand
that, but when we do kidney transplants, we don't go in to the retroperitoneum, take out the old
kidneys, we're putting the new kidney basically in their pelvis, attaching it to the blood vessels
in the pelvis and taking the little tube that drains urine and just putting that into the
bladder, the ureter. And obviously that's much easier than if you were going to remove the old
kidneys and put the new kidney in their place, given the location of the kidneys. Yeah, I mean,
I think it really was, to make kidney transplantation feasible was a collision of, you know,
lots of hard work by multiple individuals, some of whom thinking about what you just said, literally
what are the technical details of taking an organ out of a either living or deceased donor,
mitigating the injury that goes from cutting off its blood supply until you're able to restore it
into the recipient's body. So there's this whole concept of kind of the technique,
the preservation, and then the implantation. And then parallel to that was this whole question of,
well, how do we handle the immunologic consequences of that? And so the series of events that occurred
and allowed kidney transplantation to be a reality were really that the kind of technical and
preservation elements came to fruition before we figured out the immunologic elements. And in fact,
the first kidney transplant, as you know, performed in 1954 at Brigham and Women's Hospital by Joseph
Murray, who eventually won the Nobel Prize, was in identical twins, right? So he had two brothers,
one brother who had kidney failure, another brother who was healthy, took one of the healthy
brother's kidneys and transplanted it into the sick brother. And, you know, that proof of principle
was what created even kind of the possibility, the vision that transplantation could work,
because we understood the technical and preservation challenges of actually taking
an organ out of one person's body and putting it into someone else.
Murray was a plastic surgeon, wasn't he?
Yeah, Joseph Murray was a plastic surgeon. And interestingly, although he and his colleagues
figured out this technical piece, what attracted him to transplant was the concept of tissue
transfer and the immunology of that. So a lot of the early work in immunology was done with skin
grafts and kind of understanding why you could take a skin graft from your own body and put it
somewhere and it would live. But if you took a skin graft from someone else's body and put it
on a site, it would generally not live. And so there was this whole kind of cadre of
clinician scientists who were interested in that question, including interestingly plastic surgeons
like Joseph Murray. So he became involved in that with a group of other surgeons, including
some folks who had vascular expertise and others and kind of conceived and developed
in preclinical models and animals, this idea of putting a kidney in the pelvis and attaching it
to the blood vessels and bladder, and then pulled it off in a human. And a lot of, if you look at
the history of kidney transplantation through the 1950s and into the 1960s, most of the kidney
transplants performed were between twins, which, you know, there's a limited supply of available
organs there. So you can see right there that that was going to be a capacity problem. But,
you know, for example, the first kidney transplant at the University of Michigan was performed in
1963 between two twin sisters who a few years ago we were celebrating our 5,000th transplanted
organ at the University of Michigan. And those two sisters came back, you know, to celebrate that
event. So, I mean, it was a remarkable achievement, but it was a little bit of a false pretense because
none of the immunologic barriers were being confronted. And really what happened over the
next four decades were the development of effective immunosuppression to make that a reality. And as
you alluded to, it's pretty remarkable to think that, you know, in the 1960s and 70s and into the
early 80s, kidney transplants were being done and there were success stories. The field worked out
how to understand who had preformed antibodies to particular donors so you could avoid those and
pick kind of pairs that might be more successful. There were increasingly sophisticated immunosuppression
strategies that did work, you know, and drugs that were available like steroids and azathioprine,
you know, were making transplantation a possibility. But it's pretty remarkable to think in comparison
to what we expect now that in the 1960s and 70s, if you look at some of the published series,
there were mortality rates, mortality rates, meaning the patient died after kidney
transplantation of 50, 60, even 70 percent. So it's not only that they lost their graft,
but the consequences of the operation, the immunosuppression, subsequent usually infections,
you know, was making these procedures highly morbid and unsuccessful, at least at rates that
we would think of as acceptable now. And what was the life expectancy if you opted for dialysis in
the 1960s? How long could you be expected to survive? It's a great question. And, you know,
the first and most important kind of answer to that question is the assumption that you could
get dialysis, you know. So dialysis was not available everywhere. It was largely centered
around hospitals that had the ability to provide that service. You know, dialysis care was not
routinely covered by insurers. In fact, it wasn't until kind of a quirky rider to the
act, to the law that created Medicare in the 1960s that patients with dialysis even had the
option, the ability to get health insurance. So it was hard to get dialysis. And then the
survival on dialysis, due to the challenges of infection from repeated access, the hemodynamic
consequences and cardiovascular consequences, we know of what were then, you know, more crude,
primitive dialysis machines, was such that the life expectancy was probably measured in months
to years, you know. So two to four years might be, you know, a very successful outcome for someone on
dialysis. You know, the average life expectancy if you take all commerce for an individual on
dialysis now is about 10 years or so. But again, that is partially affected by the fact that
dialysis is more freely available. You know, people, elderly individuals and people with
other comorbid disease have access to dialysis. They wouldn't have had. So it was, there were no
good solutions, you know, for patients with organ failure in those times.
So I want to make sure people really get a sense of what these immune based challenges were.
We take it all for granted today because we can rattle off all MHC-2, MHC-1 complexes,
and that stuff's been worked out in the most elegant manner. But in the 1960s, that was not
the case. Maybe start by explaining ABO incompatibility, because I think that's something
people understand. If you came in the hospital and you'd lost blood and we wanted to give you a
blood transfusion, we couldn't just willy-nilly give you anybody's blood. We'd have to make sure
that the blood type matched. That's not entirely true. If you had, you know, we could give you O
negative blood no matter what. But walk people through kind of ABO, which would be the, in my
mind at least, the simplest form of antibody mediated rejection. And then let's use that as
a way to explain what was actually happening to all those non-twin transplants.
Yeah, so that's a great model to start with. So if you think about it in really basic forms, you know,
our immune system has evolved to recognize self, recognize our own tissues, and has been primed to
recognize things that do not look like us, mostly to be able to fight off viruses and, you know,
other environmental challenges. But that unfortunately makes it difficult for something
like transplantation. So in the case of blood compatibility, we carry a blood of a particular
type. It has to do with the kind of the protein signature on the coating of those red blood cells.
And we know that if you give someone who carries blood of a certain type a blood type that is
incompatible, so let's make it the simplest, someone who has blood type A, someone who has blood type B,
and you give the individual with blood type A blood from an individual with blood type B,
they will have antibodies that attack those blood cells and essentially destroy the blood cells
because they think they are recognized as foreign. It's more complex than that because there's also
these things called the the RA chantogens, which are kind of what make blood positive and negative.
And you're correct that blood type O, individuals who do not have blood type O, do not have preformed
antibodies to that donor pool. So that is kind of the universal donor pool. But it was figuring out
that incompatibility understanding that was kind of the first step in understanding how you would
potentially take an organ out of one individual and place it into another. And this is still true
to this day, that kind of step one in matching a donor and recipient is knowing their blood type
because that's kind of the first step. It gets more complicated than that for all the reasons
you alluded to, because it turns out those are not the only proteins on the surfaces of those cells
that are recognized by our immune system. And in particular, this group of protein called
human leukocyte antigens, which is what you were alluding to, or HLA types, is what kind of in a
very crude way determines one individual from another, that profile. And so the history of this
is pretty interesting, going back to my skin graft analogy. So what investigators around the
turn of the century were figuring out is again, so you could take a skin graft from elsewhere in your
body and it would tend to work. You could take a skin graft from somewhere else, from another
individual, it did not work. Then even more interestingly, if you took a second skin graft
from that same individual and put it on, it died faster. It's as if the body was primed to destroy
that new skin graft. Kind of sounds like a vaccine, huh? Yeah, exactly. So it was kind of the second,
exactly, it's the same principle. So it was just kind of the second hit hypothesis that the body,
the immune system, learned to recognize this foreign tissue and the immune system was even more
effective in eliminating it. And it was that whole series of experiments that led to this,
these concepts right in the middle of the last century, where the question was, and this was
debated by individuals much smarter than us, many of whom now have no Nobel prizes after their name,
but you know, so was there something circulating in the donor, in sorry, in the recipients
serum that found this tissue antibodies, was the theory, attacked this tissue, set off the
immune cascade, destroyed the tissue? Or was it more complicated than that? Was there kind of like
we've learned about in embryology from thymic development, was there some sort of priming event
that had to take place where the body presented this foreign tissue to the immune system and then
the immune system learned how to recognize it as self or foreign and destroy it. And that debate
went on for decades. So just to separate that, right, in the case of blood incompatibility,
it was pretty easy to figure out that it was just these soluble circulating antibodies. They weren't
quote unquote smart. They were just floating around and you could do it in a test tube. That's
right. So you have a blood type A with its little A antigen and if the recipient has an anti A,
it grabs onto it and these things precipitate out a solution to this reaction. And of course,
now the question that you're posing is, is that how it works on organs or is there something more
complicated where there's another actor? Correct. And the reason that that was such a
kind of fundamental question, because if you believed it was like the blood analogy and that,
okay, so if we could identify the patients that had preformed antibodies, preformed proteins in
their serum that were going to ruin this opportunity, then, well, that's great. Then we
can select out the patients that have that reaction and use the organ to transplant others.
So that's the concept of what is now called and transplant a cross match. So the idea of taking
donor cells, recipient serum, mixing them in an assay and determining whether or not
that serum lices those cells. And that is more or less the technique that is used to cross match
individuals to match, you know, as you'll hear people talk about, oh, I want to donate a kidney
to my uncle or something. I wonder if I'm a match. That's to some degree, what they're talking
about is whether or not that assay says that they have, that their uncle in this case, doesn't have
preformed antibodies that are going to destroy their cells. So that would explain kind of that
initial screening step. But what was, and the other thing that that helped explain is why
sometimes when you would do a transplant, either in animals or eventually in humans,
there was this phenomenon, which came to be known as hyperacute rejection, where you would put the
organ in, you would take the clamps off, the organ would fill with blood, it looks like you've won
the game, and then it would immediately start to thrombose and die, essentially. That process called
hyperacute rejection was figured out was because of the circulating antibodies to those HLA engines
of the donor. So that made some sense. We can try to figure that out. What didn't make sense is you
would do the transplant, you would get past that hyperacute stage, the organs working, and then
a day later, three days later, six months later, the organ would fail from acute rejection.
So basically the same process, but with a different kind of lead time. And it was after
much debate in the field, the nuances of which are more sophisticated than I can explain, but it was
figured out that what was actually happening was not this circulating, what we came to call antibody
mediated or humoral rejection, but actually was happening on a cellular level, so-called cellular
rejection. And as we learned eventually over time, that had to do with kind of what we now learn in
basic immunology, antigen presenting cell with carrying an antigen from the foreign tissue,
in this case the donor tissue, immune mediator cells. And we discovered and learned eventually
they were T cells, that recognition priming the immune system to form injury either by various
means, cytokines, eventual antibody formation, etc. And that was what was destroying organs in
that kind of subacute phase. And as we figured out over the course of decades, the drugs that we had
to blunt that initial immune response, high dose steroids, I refer days of thioprine, they tried
total body irradiation at some of the early stages. That was Franny Moore that was doing that.
Exactly. At the Brigham. Those weren't effective in preventing that cellular level rejection.
And it was only later, really the 1980s, that we developed immunosuppressive agents
that were selective enough to interfere with that cellular reaction. And it was then that transplant
really became a reality because now you had the ability to sustain an organ beyond just weeks to
months and you're looking at more long-term survival. So really the turning points are twofold,
right? One, it's the knowledge of what's happening because certainly by the 80s it was not a technical
challenge to be able to remove a kidney, transport a kidney and put it in. By the way,
was Wisconsin's solution already around by the 80s or did that come later?
Yeah. Yeah. So the, or at least the predecessors of Wisconsin's solution and the other.
Tell folks what that is and why that matters so much as well.
Yeah. So the theory is, you know, you take an organ out of the donor body, whether deceased or living,
you flush the blood cells and such out of it so that it doesn't clot. You then store it on ice
and transport it to the recipient and put it in. And there were all kinds of initial thoughts
about, well, do you just put it in saline essentially and transport it to the other room?
And what they found was that, and this was experimentation that happened over decades,
was that there was, there were cellular processes occurring both as kind of at the time from
when ischemia begins, when the vessels are clamped and the organ is coming out
and before blood flow and oxygen is restored to the organ. There were cellular processes occurring
that could be mitigated by creating preservation solutions, essentially saline, that was fortified
with particular molecules. And, you know, the history of all this is beyond me, but literally
they tried, you know, it's like making Gatorade. They tried, you know, different electrolyte
solutions and additives and other nutrients until they figured out which mitigated that ischemic
time the best. And the crazy thing to think about, and this gets to alludes to something maybe we
could talk about later in terms of, you know, where is preservation going in the future? But
the crazy thing is we're pretty much more or less doing that now, you know, so some of the fluid
solutions and some of the, you know, minor details of what additives are in the fluid has changed.
But that's essentially the way we've been preserving organs since the 1960s, 70s, you know,
which is pretty remarkable that that was one, as you said, one of the early barriers figured out
in the field. So once this notion of the HLA system is understood and we understand these different
types of compatibilities, a drug is discovered and it's, you know, my favorite drug on the planet
happens to come from basically a fungus. This is another drug that came from a fungus, but a
different one. The drug is called Cyclosporin. And I think you could make the case, but I'd like
to hear your take on it because you know this field so much better than I do. But if I were
telling the story, I would say that was the turning point was the advent of Cyclosporin. Do
you agree with that or do you think that I'm overstating that? No, 100%. You know, so as
you said, and similar to the stories of drug development that happened in other circumstances,
you know, this was a recognized compound that, you know, had been experimented in a number of
different lines of investigation. And an investigator who's really one of the central
figures in the history of transplant named Sir Roy Calm in Cambridge
performed a series of preclinical experiments that showed that using this medication
prevented rejection in transplant models. And what eventually was discovered is that it was
interfering with the cascade that occurred when that foreign antigen was presented to the
recipient T cell. And in other words, it was a more selective immunosuppressant, so directly
interfering with the cascade of events that happens downstream of the T cell receptor.
And it specifically inhibited IL-2 secretion? It affects IL-2 secretion, but there's actually
some interesting debate about how the calcineurin inhibitors, so Cyclosporin and then its eventual
cousin, Taq-Lymis, works. You know, they both function at the level of what are called
immunophilins, these, you know, soluble intracellular components. And although they affect
both kind of the activation of cytokines after that T cell recognition, including IL-2, they also
seem to have other effects on the affinity of the binding of the T cell receptor. They have
systemic effects that are kind of interesting, like for example Taq-Lymis, the other medication
I mentioned, you know, has a potent vasoconstrictor effect in certain organs. So we probably don't
fully understand its impact, but certainly the central component of its mechanism was
interfering with the cascade that occurs after T cell receptor binding. And you're absolutely
right, like it literally was a game changer overnight. So, you know, if you look at papers
written in the 1980s about kidney transplant outcomes, there's literally an inflection point.
You went from recipients having one-year graft survival rates, even with kind of the best
immunosuppressive regimens that had been figured out at that point, one-year graft survival rates
probably in the 70-ish, 60% range. Boom, you know, 90% overnight just with the addition
of cyclosporine and then, you know, eventually refining kind of some of the multidrug regimens.
So it was a complete game changer. It not only revolutionized the impact of kidney transplantation,
which from a public health standpoint is clearly the most impactful organ we transplant, you know,
the number of patients with end-stage renal disease, the number of patients with chronic kidney
disease, you know, from a public health standpoint kidney transplantation is just a fundamental
important medical therapy. But so not only did it make that a reality and make it a preferred
alternative to dialysis, it also reinvigorated the other solid organ transplant,
other solid organ transplants as being a reality. So, you know, liver transplantation, which is
essentially had been on a more or less enforced hiatus through the 60s and 70s,
heart transplantation similarly, lung transplantation as well, the confidence that
now that we understood some of the technical and kind of patient-related factors that dictated the
success of the operation to now also have the promise that those organs would last more than,
you know, 90 days, you know, reinvigorated those fields completely. And, you know, again, you know,
almost overnight over the course of years, you started to see liver transplant programs,
heart transplant programs, lung transplant programs pop up at major medical centers all
throughout the country in the 1980s and into the early 1990s. So that was really the revolution
that occurred because of that drug development. When we look at the demand for kidney
transplantation today, what percentage of it is chronic versus acute kidney failure?
Yeah, so the vast majority is chronic. So there are occasions where patients can get acute
renal injury from, you know, traumatic events, other medical catastrophes, or they get acute
kidney injury in the chronic in this case of sepsis or something that they otherwise recover from.
And that does, you know, we still see, and we still see occasionally patients who get,
for example, post-reptococcal glomerular arthritis or other diseases that are more
linked to kind of an acute event. The vast majority of kidney transplants in the United
States, the primary indication is diabetes or hypertension. So this is chronic kidney disease
as a consequence of those comorbid conditions, which is one of the reasons, again, from a public
health standpoint, that the impact of kidney transplantation is massive, you know, so you have
a hundred thousand people roughly waiting for a kidney transplant in the United States.
You probably have four fold that are there about on dialysis, and then probably ten fold that number
with chronic kidney disease. So the potential impact of having an effective and durable
therapy for chronic kidney disease is remarkable. And I think it's really important to consider as
a public health problem. Yeah, I can't agree with you more, Chris. And about three years ago,
I sort of had this obvious epiphany. I say obvious because I'm sort of thinking, why did it take me so long to do the math?
But I realized if my interest clinically is trying to figure out how to help people live longer and live better,
you've got to start thinking about what are the things that you have to plan for. So if you're
flying a glider where you know you want to cross a 200-foot chasm, but now all of a sudden you say,
well, I want that chasm to be 300 feet, you have to start thinking about how much higher does that
glider need to fly. And one of the things that really occurred to me was kidney function.
We sort of have in the back of our minds, you know, look, if a person reaches the finish line of life
and their glomerular filtration rate is 40, great. You know, they don't need dialysis, they're doing
just fine. And if we think that an average life expectancy should be 71 or something, and we think
that, hey, we're going to tolerate a person's GFR being in the low 40s when they're in their early
70s, that's great. But if we're trying to figure out a way to help people live and live well into
their 90s or beyond, that becomes a very unacceptable GFR. You're going to run into trouble.
And so, you know, looking at cystatin C beyond just creatinine and other biomarkers and looking
at microalbumin in the urine twice a year, I mean, we do all these things, but even though they seem
kind of crazy, because it's how you sort of start to catch that early, early, oh, look, you know what,
your blood pressure of 130 over 85 is not really acceptable. That's that's that's going to take you
from a GFR of 95 to 85 in the next decade. And we consider that to be too precipitous a decline.
So unfortunately, my view is that I think the demand for kidneys is only going to go up as we
see the rampant explosion of prediabetes and metabolic syndrome. Yeah, I totally agree with
you. I think, and there's so many kind of wrinkles to that question to think about. I mean, the first
is that is the obvious statement that as you preach better than anybody, we don't do preventative care,
you know, in this country very well. And we particularly don't do it for things where we
don't have reliable measures, you know, so to your point, you know, we use serum creatinine as kind of
our best guess at kidney function. There's lots of reasons why that's a poor indicator. You know,
it's not it's very dependent on muscle mass and other variables that that allow you that prevent
you from using some sort of kind of normalized number as an acceptable range. There are more
sensitive markers, as you alluded to, there there's now I think, fortunately, finally being recognized
the whole question of how creatinine and GFR and race interacts and how that needs to be accommodated
for. So, so you're right. So number one, we don't measure it well. So therefore we don't appreciate
the size of the problem. Number two is we, again, this is kind of a situation where transplant is a
victim of its own success. You know, as transplantation has gotten more successful, transplant centers
around the country, transplant providers and and just the medical community in general has started
to say, well, you know, why don't we provide kidney transplants for 70 year olds if there are
otherwise, you know, healthy individuals because their life expectancy might be 20 years from that
point. So and that's that, I think, the collision of that and then the what you alluded to this
pre-diabetes metabolic syndrome, you know, progressive kidney dysfunction in an aging
population is going to create an enormous demand for kidney transplantation. You know, we
transplanted an 81 year old a few weeks ago. And I remember as I was looking at the
census, I don't do kidney transplant very commonly as part of my clinical practice.
I was looking at the census, I was like, wait a minute, is that is this gentleman 10 years out
from a transplant back in the hospital for some other reason? Or did we actually transplant this?
But the point is, there are individuals who are healthy, functional people otherwise who have
whose life, you know, part of what we're talking about is survival benefit, right? You compare
their survival on dialysis to their survival with the transplant. Transplant is going to win almost
every time, you know, as long as they can tolerate the operation of the immunosuppression. So,
so it isn't it isn't it kind of remarkable to think of the scope of that problem, and particularly
to take a longevity lens on it, you know, it's it's really kind of an interesting
challenge to think about for the next, you know, 20-30 years of transplantation.
So before we get on to liver, which is such an amazing story as well, I want to I want to wrap a
few things up on on kidney. So let's let's talk about the evolution from cyclosporine to to
Prograph or Tacolimus, as you discussed, and where we are today on some of the most common
immunosuppressive regimens. And then I also want to touch on this idea of not just living donors,
but the live donor swaps and stuff, because I'll tell you one of the things that I'll never forget
from my intern rotation on transplant, which like you captivated me beyond words, I mean,
transplant was never even something on my radar before residency. And for the entire time I was
in residency, it was always one of those things was like, I could see myself doing this. This is
so cool. And it was actually, I think it was Bob Montgomery as well that shared this with me,
which was a live donor zero out of six HLA match is always going to be six out of six cadaveric
match. And I remember thinking, how is that possible? Now, tell folks what I just said,
explain what I just said to people. And more importantly, explain why it's true.
Yeah, so it's, it's pretty remarkable to consider the impact of living donation. And, and the
to your earlier question, kind of figuring out the appropriate place for living donation
as transplantation moves forward. So kidney transplantation, encounter distinction,
deliver transplantation, but in kidney transplantation, living donation has been part of
kidney transplantation from its origins, you know, so as I alluded to already, the
first transplant done between identical twins, living donation remained a part of the development
of kidney transplantation, and then really took off in the 1990s, we witnessed it happening.
With the development of the laparoscopic donor nephrectomy operation,
a procedure pioneered by two individuals at Hopkins, Lou Cavusi and Lloyd Ratner, who, and that,
you know, having a procedure that was of such tremendous benefit to the recipient,
that then was safe, and, you know, a smoother recovery for the donor, you know, really allowed
that to explode. And if you look at kidney transplantation in the United States now,
you know, so let's say 18 to 20,000 patients a year undergo kidney transplant in the United
States, and it's actually about half and half living donors and deceased donors. And, and that's
probably with under realizing the potential of living donation for all the reasons you said. So
part of what you're leading to is if you kind of compare head to head, let's say you have a patient
on dialysis, a patient who receives a deceased donor kidney transplant, and a patient who receives
a living donor kidney transplant, you know, let's say the starting line is the same for all three
of those. And let's say that they're similar age, similar comorbid conditions, similar misappressive
regimen for the transplant recipients. So the benefits are pretty clear, the dialysis curve is
going to drop off pretty quickly. So the, in fact, the studies that have shown that where the
dialysis and transplant curves cross, even with the risks of undergoing a surgical procedure and
starting immunosuppression occurs in less than a year. It's probably in somewhere between 90 and
250 days, depending on patient characteristics. So, so that's clear dialysis loses. What's
interesting then is that there's a difference between the deceased and living donor curves.
And that's what you were kind of so fascinated about. And the reasons for that are many,
but it probably speaks to the fact that even with all of the best technique in advances,
there is really no way to mitigate the fact that a deceased donor that goes through the process and
the trauma of brain death or donation after cardiac death gets removed from that individual's
body preserved, put on ice, transported to another center, and then sewn into the recipient.
And that interval of time can be six to 48, 72 hours in some circumstances, as opposed to a living
donor elective operation, side by side or sequential operating rooms, you know, the, the,
that kidney is in a healthy environment with a healthy normal person, normal vital signs.
We dissect out the kidney, clamp the blood vessels, take it out of the body, flush it,
walk it over to the recipient's room. And sometimes it's sewn in in under an hour,
you know, so the time, the ischemic time from coming out of the donor's body to into the
recipient. And it turns out that ischemic period is critical and is really almost linearly related
to the graft survival. Part of that is probably due to the, the consequences just of the ischemia
reperfusion injury and kind of literally knocking off some nephrons just from that process. Part of
it, it also is, as we've learned, is that that ischemia reperfusion injury cascade that starts
is a priming event for the immune system. So not only do deceased donor kidneys kind of pound for
pound compared to living donor kidneys take that initial hit from the ischemia reperfusion injury,
they're also more prone to rejection. You see more immunologic injury. They, they, they're,
it depends on the circumstance. They often require more immunosuppression, you know,
greater frequency of rejection. So it really is almost like two different products from a
recipient's point of view. And so, you know, I think if you had your druthers, you know, as a person
in need of a kidney transplant, you would want to have the access and the opportunity to get a
living donor any day of the week, if that is possible to you. And this other point though,
is to narrow that gap between the two. It's that with the, with the deceased donor,
you at least try to maximize the immunocompatibility. And with the living donor, you have much more
flexibility. Correct. That's exactly right. So, you know, what you were describing is kind of
the situation that you, the story you alluded to with Bob, is you're comparing a, a living donor
kidney, so optimal conditions of the transplant, but not a perfect immunologic situation, at least
from looking an HLA alone, versus a deceased donor kidney that immunologically is a home run. That's
about as good a situation as you can get, but still takes that ischemic hit. And, and we can't
make up for that. So even the best immunologic situation can't mitigate that, which I think is
a realization that doesn't always kind of come to fruition, but is again, one of the reasons why we
feel comfortable really pushing every kidney transplant candidate to, to think very seriously
about exploring options for a living donation. It's also what's led to some of the things you
alluded to, you know, paired kidney exchanges and other things to try and expand the, the
compatibility of donors and recipients. Let's, let's use an example to, to explain that to people,
because it's really quite fascinating. And, and we trained very close to some of the people who
really did a lot of the work behind optimizing the mathematical algorithms around that. So
let's pretend that, you know, you called me tomorrow and said, Peter, you're not going to
believe this, but you know, I'm kind of at the end of my rope with my kidneys and I'm gonna,
you know, I'm gonna need to have a transplant. And, and I, you know, I was sad. I thought about it.
I decided, you know what, I, there's, there's no greater way that I want to be able to thank Chris
for all he's done for me than to give him a kidney. And I've got two and I'm perfectly healthy and I'm
willing to part with one of them. So I call you up and I say, Chris, I want to give you one of my
kidneys. I want to be a living donor to you. So we would go and meet with the transplant team and
they would do some tests. And what if they discovered that I was a lousy match for you?
We didn't even have the same blood type, nevermind HLA compatibility. What would be some of the
options we would explore? Yeah. So that, so the circumstance you're talking about is this really
kind of frustrating scenario where, where a kidney transplant candidate has done the right things.
They've taken care of themselves. They've gotten to a transplant center. They're listed, you know,
for transplant, we think they're a good candidate. They've even gone to the effort that you just
described of identifying living donors and the living donor or donors that they identify are not
compatible with them or at least safely. So as you said, they might be of a different blood type.
Let's say, you know, I'm an A and you're a B. That's just not a barrier that we're used to
crossing at least with any kind of reasonable likelihood of the success rates we were discussing
earlier. It may also be that, that you, you know, I have preformed antibodies to HLA antigens that,
that you have. And as it turns out, there's certain populations that are more prone to that,
to that challenge. So it's a, it's a really frustrating challenge because here it is,
it's like you have this, you know, you've got this diamond in the rough, but you can't apply it,
you know. And so what some really smart people figured out, well, if I've got two pairs
and they're incompatible with each other, but happen to be compatible with the opposite. So let's say
that, you know, we're an A and a B and there's another pair over here that's a B and an A and
by all other measures are compatible. Is it reasonable to swap those kidneys and, and those
sorts of swap, kidney swaps or paired exchange began in the 1990s and really took off in the
2000s because it allowed people to avail themselves of broader opportunities for transplant.
Now, what you're alluding to in terms of the kind of the mathematics of it is you can imagine
there's some ethical quandaries there. So let's say, so you come forward to donate me a kidney,
you're an extremely healthy person, you've taken good care of yourself. I assume Jill has approved
this at some point. I haven't asked her, but you know, she can't wait to say hi to you after this
podcast. So I think she would let me donate to you. That's, that's an important part of the discussion.
But then let's say the pair that we were talking about exchanging with is, you know, someone about
our age who needs a kidney and their 75 year old father, you know, so I swapped to them this,
you know, perfectly healthy kidney from someone who's in good health and younger.
And I get in exchange for that a 75 year old kidney. Now, for some of the reasons we just
talked about, it might still be in my best interest to take that living donor kidney,
but you can imagine that there are differences in quality and then to add even more complexity to it
what if let's say the individual that you would be donating to across the swap,
you just by coincidence are a perfect match for, you know, HLA match across the board.
But that individual that I'm swapping for, I have, it's three out of six.
It's exactly or, or, or maybe there's even, you know, we, there's very sophisticated
assays that actually can look for low levels of what we call donor specific antibodies that
let's say that I've got some, you know, low level antibodies to that individual.
Is it worth the, the swap? Is it worth the extremis oppression? I would need to make that
a reality to make that pair exchange work. And so some smart people, including colleagues of ours
that we both know, Dorie Segev and his wife, Summer Gentry, who's a mathematician started
thinking about that. Like, so could we, could we start putting some value on those exchanges
and create networks of individuals? It's kind of like the dating game for kidneys where you
come forward with your donor and the algorithm looks at all the other possible pairs and tries
to match individuals in a way that maximizes predicted outcome. And there are now net national
networks that facilitate those sorts of exchanges and have really expanded kidney
transplantation in ways that I don't think even we would have predicted watching it back in the
1990s. You know, for example, there was a day, maybe three weeks ago where I did a laparoscopic
donor and a frectomy operation. So removed a kidney from an individual. That morning,
one of my colleagues was doing a similar operation in another room. Both those kidneys shipped out.
To other institutions, two kidneys came back later and our colleagues put them in later in the day
into two of our recipients. So it was like, you know, we've completely dissociated the donor
operation from the recipient operation, which from a patient's perspective is great, you know? And so
the donors don't have to travel. The recipients have more access to organs. And, you know, I think
thinking about how that is applied and expanded has really been a game changer for kidney
transplantation access. Chris, is there any serious discussion about opening up a market
for kidney donation? So everything we just described is it's happening through altruism.
I would give you my kidney because I love you. But is there a serious discussion that says,
look, what if I've just decided, you know what? Like, I'm willing to gamble, but I don't need a kidney.
I don't know a given individual, but for a big enough sum of money, I'm willing to part with my kidney.
Are those discussions even entertained?
Yeah, so it's a great question. And this is a frequently debated and
never resolved kind of debate in transplantation. So to put some framework behind that question,
so when transplantation started to become a successful medical intervention, so we're talking
now 70s into the 1980s development of Cyclosporin, we then started to think about, so, okay, this is
a successful venture. We now have organ donation laws that exist around the country. We need to
create networks to make sure that a liver that becomes available in Utah is accessible to the
patient in Michigan, as it to California or other circumstances. So there was a whole infrastructure
put around that challenge. The legality of it was, and the decision that was made at the time
these laws were passed, that it was illegal to sell an organ. And the reasons that that principle
was upheld is kind of central to transplantation, particularly in the United States, but in most
countries around the world, is that the belief was that organ donation was a gift. It was a
decision. So the kind of ethical decision was, or principle was, that the donor has autonomy over
that decision and makes it freely. The concern about allowing people to pay for organs, like
on an open market, was that can potentially be coercive and can create markets where individuals
who have lower standing in society or are economically disadvantaged, then are put in
this position where they can be selling their organs to achieve some game. And actually,
just literally this last weekend, there was an article in the New York Times about
the growth of kidney transplantation in Afghanistan, and that is exactly what happened.
They have kind of turned away from understanding relationships between donors and recipients,
and that's what's happened, that wealthy people who have the resources are paying
poor people for their kidneys and then not certainly caring for them afterwards. So
as a general principle, the transplant community has decided against paying for organs
as the principle being that it's coercive. Now, there's lots of people that disagree with that
on general principle and say, well, why don't we just create a better system, allow some exchange
of compensation to donors? And I think we are slowly migrating towards some version of that.
So to give you a few examples, the legality of this has been so tight that it's been impossible
even for donors to be reimbursed for transportation to the transplant center or time off work or other
sacrifices that they had to personally make that had nothing to do with the actual donation,
but just to facilitate that occurring. And there are now laws being passed in states and other
and other initiatives, either through advocacy groups. There's a national group that does
advocacy for living donors and provides resources and support for travel to transplant centers and
reimbursement for time away from work and such. But what if we created a principle where, say,
for example, a living donor is compensated with some agreed upon amount of money that compensates
for the time of their recovery? And I think there may come a time that some version of that becomes
a reality. There's also principles of should living donation provide special kind of health
care benefits to individuals over time. Maybe it qualifies you for discounted public insurance
or something so that you can never lose health insurance if you were to, God forbid, have a
problem yourself down the road. So I think there are some versions of this that will come to fruition
gradually. But I think at least in the United States, our medical legal environment and the
principles behind transplantation will not permit an open market for buying and selling of organs.
I like that idea about providing ongoing medical coverage. It's funny, whenever the debate comes
up about whether we should be paying NC2A athletes, especially football players, they generate so much
revenue for the university and then they get spanked if they accept a $50 gift from a booster.
I've always thought one solution to that is fine. If you don't want to pay athletes for playing
sports at a university, you should at least cover their medical bills for the rest of their lives.
Like if an athlete suffers some consequence as a result of playing sports, which many of them do,
we should at least make sure that we take care of them if we're going to profit off them to the
course of that. Tell folks a little bit about if it's still the case, I assume it's still the case,
there are some states in which you're better off and more likely to get an organ, like a liver,
for example, than other states. How does that work? And what would be the best states to live in if
you're vying for an organ versus the worst? Right. So fortunately, that is changing rapidly. And it's
changing rapidly because it's been a focus of intentional policy change. So it's not like when
we were in residency where it was almost comical. Correct. So I think part of the issue is simply
a supply and demand issue. So if you look, for example, at California, a state with a huge
population, and there is such a demand for transplant that if you kind of imagine California
is just its own unit, it's almost like the organ donation supply in California would never meet
the demand. That's true in other major, particularly urban population centers like New
York and parts of the East Coast. There are other parts of the country, and they tend to be in the
Midwest, but there's some other locations in the South as well, where just based on population size,
the amount of individuals in need of an organ transplant is modest compared to the supply of
organ donors. And I think that has created this disparity where depending on where you live,
you may have better access to organ in various places. The solution to that, obviously,
is to change the system. So in other words, the way that organ donation is coordinated nationally
is through these organizations called Organ Procurement Organizations, or OPOs. There's
58 of them in the country. Some of them are pretty easily understandable, like Michigan has,
for example, one OPO that covers the whole state. There's like six in Texas. So it's a little bit
of a confusing network. But the point is those are the organizations, nonprofit organizations,
that are responsible for identifying organ donors and facilitating the gift from procurement
to transplant. And then the waiting list, you hear people say that they're on the waiting list for
an organ. The way that an organ is actually placed is every time an organ donor becomes available,
the list is run according to a predetermined algorithm of how that particular organ is
prioritized. And the problem, at least historically, is that that list has been run
largely locally or regionally first, and only then kind of offered out more broadly. And so
what has changed in heart, lung, and liver transplantation and is about to change in kidney
transplantation is those kind of relatively artificial state or regional boundaries have
just gotten destroyed. And so now the way organs are allocated are literally by concentric circles.
So they offer it based on distance from the donor hospital. And that has created some interesting
phenomena. I mean, the good news is, to your point, is that the geographic variation that exists across
the country has decreased. So it's not as important now to go to a certain place if you know you need
a liver transplant, for example. It also has created a system where if you're really sick,
you know, at the top of the list for liver transplantation, for example, you're going to
get transplanted quickly because you've got access to this broad swath of organ toners.
The challenge is kind of the people that are medium sick, some of whom are still quite ill
from their disease, who have all these sicker people kind of ahead of them on the list getting
transplanted. And that speaks to the kind of need for expanding the donor pool, alternative donor
sources, more living donation than a case of kidney and liver transplantation to kind of meet
that need. So the system has gotten more fair, but it's only exposed the need even more, I guess,
is the best way to say it. That's good to hear because it definitely struck me as a pretty unjust
system, you know, 20 years ago, especially with liver, where you could, you know, it was almost
like the yeah, it reminded me of some great injustice. You alluded to brain death earlier,
we've been remiss in not, I think, explaining to people a little bit what that means. And
especially now as we sort of talk a little bit about liver, where a much greater number of the
transplantations are from non-living donors, the donors are non-living. So what does it mean to be
brain dead? And how does that factor into, from a legal standpoint, what does it mean? And then from
a physiologic and biologic standpoint, what does it mean? Yeah, so it's interesting. You would think
that this would be like something you could flip to page one in, you know, medical textbook, and
there would be, you know, but it's actually been a relatively kind of complex set of definitions to
come to. And the importance of establishing brain death was in many ways driven by the development
of transplantation. Because if we were going to use organ deceased organ donors for transplant,
we needed to establish clearly defined ways that these were individuals that could not recover,
you know, we're not going to be salvageable such that they could then go on to be organ donors.
And to be even more specific about that, the whole question of what defines death, you know,
so is death when the heart stops or is or do we consider death when the brain has lost function
and control? And what has developed over time? And so just to clarify that for people, right, the first thing you said is when the heart stops is what we call
cardiopulmonary death. So a person has a heart attack, the heart stops, cardiopulmonary death. A person has cancer,
eventually leads to cardiopulmonary death. Correct. This brain death thing, how does it show up?
Give people examples of the physical way, the physiologic ways people get there.
Yeah, so it's a kind of confusing concept. How can the body be alive but the brain be dead? And there are
a whole number of circumstances where that can occur. But essentially the kind of central
component of the definition is that the brain sustains an injury. That could be from anoxia,
from an anoxic event. It can be literally from a traumatic event, you know, a penetrating injury,
a devastating head trauma. It can be from an intracranial event, a bleed or such, such that
the pressure in the brain and the injury that evolves in the brain increases to a point that
blood flow and oxygen delivery to the brain stops. And so all the cellular processes that are occurring
kind of from literally the skull base up have stopped. And, you know, there are clinical ways
to define that diagnosis. So there are characteristic neurologic manifestations of brain death.
You know, the kind of classic ones that you see on TV are the, you know, the blown pupils as someone's
brain has swollen to no longer allow blood flow into the skull.
You know, there are core bodily functions that the brain drives, such as respiratory drive,
that are part of that definition as well as a bunch of additional primitive reflexes. And
really what evolved over time is a clinical definition of brain death that includes multiple
elements, including that the donor has, or sorry, that the individual has to be, you know,
hemodynamically stable. They can't be hypothermic. They can't be in some metabolic condition that
could confuse the issue. But then the central focus of it is this thing called an apnea test,
where they literally stop the mechanical breathing support and see whether or not the individual
generates the drive to breathe on their own. And so there are clinical brain death exams that
that physicians are used to doing to document that. And then there are ancillary studies that
can actually show that blood flow has stopped into the brain. And I think coming to a consensus
on that definition was really critical to allow the establishment of what equates with death.
So the loss of the function of that individual, even if their other physiologic functions,
like their heart beating, are maintained. And establishing that diagnosis then allowed the
step to go from, well, if they are brain dead, but they still have present circulation, can we then
move to organ procurement? Because in the absence of that, you could kind of ethically equate organ
procurement as prompting death, right? So in other words, if these individuals are not yet dead,
organ procurement is expediting their death, which with their death, which violates all the
principles of kind of autonomy and the principle of organ donation that transplantation is built on.
So there's a couple of things there I just want to highlight before you go on, Chris,
just so people understand. Brain death still requires cardiopulmonary support, right? That's
the very important thing people need to understand. A brain dead individual is not going to be laying
in a bed, their brain not functioning, yet somehow they're alive. By definition, if your brain is
dead and you are not on full cardiorespiratory support, you will be dead within moments.
So that's why this APNIC test is done while they're hooked up to a respirator that is just
turned off, but not disconnected. They will fail to breathe as you point out, they will fail the
APNIC test, and then they'll be resumed on cardiopulmonary support because of course the goal
is to continue to oxygenate their body perfectly to maintain the appropriate levels of tissue
health. The other thing that's worth mentioning, if you watch TV, you might be lulled into thinking
that the same set of doctors that are trying to understand if you're brain dead and trying to take
care of you after whatever accident you had that led to the situation you're in have anything to do
with the doctors that are coming along to take the kid in your liver. Because that would seem
a little grotesque. Explain that sort of line between those two teams of physicians because
you and I have been multiple times on both sides of that. We've been taking care of those patients
in the ICU that are going to become donors, and then we've been on the other side where you're
now part of the team that's harvesting organs. Correct. It's a clear ethical principle that is
central to not only the kind of effective operationalizing of transplant, but also to
the establishment of the public trust that is critical to allowing transplantation to exist.
And the way I explain that to transplant families and organ donor families is that
the systems are completely separate with an opportunity for integration in between that only
occurs when certain events has happened in the individual's care. So number one, the concept of
brain death has to be thought about to begin with. That's part of the diagnostic evaluation of
that individual. The brain death exam needs to be confirmed. The family and or patient through
previous documentation has identified that individual as an organ donor, and only then
after those steps is the transplant machinery or specifically the organ procurement organization
involved. So I think some people have the concern, well gosh, are the people that want more organs
for transplant going to somehow interfere in the decisions that are made about this
individual who's undergone some tragedy that's leading to the end of their life.
And the reality of that is fortunately that we have no impact on that on that decision.
The I think the other principle that occurs is that then the care of that individual body,
because if there been declared brain death we consider the individual, then passes from the
caregivers, the health care team that's been caring for them, to the organ procurement
organization and their team and then eventually to the transplant teams and to the procurement.
So there's a clear transition from when they go from an individual under the care of the ICU team
or the teams that are caring for them to the individual's responsibility it is to facilitate
the gift of transplant. And I think in situations that fortunately occur more and more often where
either the individual themself have already identified on their driver's license or through
conversations with their family that they in the event of a tragedy they want to be an organ donor
or families come forward and I always think this is incredibly generous. I mean this usually occurs
out of the worst day of their life and they come forward to say that they would want their loved
one to be an organ donor. Nothing happens on the transplant side until all those steps have occurred.
And so I think it's really kind of critical to understand that it is worth alluding to the concept
of donation after cardiac death which is where that gets a little more confusing. So there are
there are individuals who have suffered a life-threatening event, a devastating head trauma,
but that has not caused brain death, other medical conditions where the care team and the caregivers
have decided that their life is not salvageable but they're not technically brain death and that's
always been a conundrum because what if those individuals want to donate their organs but they
don't meet this very strict criteria that we've established as a important principle to allow
organ donation. And what has evolved in the United States and around the world
over time is this concept of donation after cardiac death. And importantly there still needs
to be the establishment of death before we can procure organs to again separate the process of
declaring death from the process of procuring organs. And so what happens in a donation after
cardiac death situation is the family chooses to withdraw care, care is withdrawn, the individual
then expires over some period of time and then depending on the circumstances of that individual's
death, how quickly it happens, etc. If we then believe it's appropriate to still utilize those
organs, organ procurement can occur and those decisions are all made before withdrawal of care.
So in other words the family has decided to proceed with pursuing organ donation,
the arrangements have been made to have the teams and individuals available there
to procure the organs and preserve the organs appropriately but nothing happens until that
individual is declared dead by a provider that has nothing to do with the transplant team. So I think
even in the case of donation after cardiac death we've kept that very clear delineation between
individuals caring for the patient and individuals processing the gift of the donor for transplant.
You alluded to something earlier which reminds me of one of the sadder stories when I was
in residency actually when this happened. So my mom, one of my mom's closest friends,
her son who was five years younger than me so I grew up together was driving home
one morning after a night shift and fell asleep, crashed and died an immediate brain death
and his mom, single mom, no relationship to his father, had to make this what can only be
described as you said the worst day of your life and now you have to make a decision and
you know I'll never forget she made this decision to have every single aspect of her son
donated you know cornea, skin, his liver was split into two so two people benefited from his
liver as both kidneys, heart, lungs. It's always stuck with me and if that wasn't enough a couple
years later I would go on to meet a friend that I ended up working with actually who lost his son
to his he was in a jeep accident, rollover jeep and same thing you know he and his wife had to
make this awful decision about their 21 year old son who had just died and without hesitation they
did the same thing which was you know every piece of our son Aaron it was his name is going to be
you know donated to help someone else and what was especially amazing in the case of
of this couple I think I can say their names I don't I think they're actually quite vocal about
this Jeff and Tina Webster is that they got to know every one of the recipients
and as I got to know them and got to know the stories I was just you know I was just blown
away by it and again I'm someone who's been around this stuff right like it's not like I
haven't seen these things before but you know the the man who got his liver has a tattoo of their
son on his arm you know it's that kind of stuff right and it's it's just it's it is hard to believe
I mean do people ever ask you Chris hey should I should I check that box on my driver's license
and and like how do you talk to people about those decisions? Yeah it's a great question and it is
one that I that I get asked and actually my oldest daughter tells me she occasionally gets
asked now I guess because people know her dad's a transplant surgeon but you know I think you know
I think so what are the reasons that people hesitate to to do that and I think some of it is what
we already alluded to is kind of the the concern or the mythology that somehow it'll affect their
own health care and and you know sometimes I'll answer questions about that but but I always try
to focus on the the profound impact that transplantation can have and try to share with them
what I've learned from donor families over the year and one of the privileges of the
position I am in now is that I do get to occasionally do advocacy work and other
other opportunities to meet donor families so families like you just told of the Webster's that
have a history of a family member who was an organ donor and many of them can you know poignantly
tell of the the process they walk through with that decision making and the memories of their loved
one but one of the things that donor families you know really universally share is that their
experience of organ donation whether or not they were able to meet the eventual recipients of their
loved one's organs but that the experience of organ donation and knowing that their loved one's
organs went on live on in another individual and saved their life is the only good thing about
what was otherwise the worst day of their lives and I've heard that actual phrasing repeated
by multiple families by multiple individuals who had to say goodbye to their you know son daughter
sister brother you know husband wife but took some solace in the fact that you were honoring
their life by passing on the gift of their organs to another individual so I think it's important
for people to hear that it is really a can be a transformative gift I think the other thing I share
with people and let them make their own decisions is that you know there is an incredible need for
organ donation you know so there are currently more than a hundred thousand you know people waiting
on the waiting list for the various organs and and you know each year there are you know less than
you know 40 percent or so of that number done you know and the the need only grows each year the gap
between donation and supply grows each year furthermore the outcomes of the individuals
who get transplanted improves each year so not only do we have this tremendous need for individuals
dying of organ failure but the life that they can look forward to is in most cases you know
incredibly good you know restoring them back to you know life expectancies that approximate
normal and qualities of life that in many cases are totally normal so I mean I think that's the
vision I try to share with people when they're considering organ donation but acknowledge that
it's a very personal decision and people have to be comfortable with that I do encourage people
if they feel passionately about it to make the decision themselves because I can tell you
like you said you know we've been on both sides of this that that walking through that decision
making with someone's loved one who is in you know the middle of the night in a foreign hospital
trying to make the decision about the wishes of their loved one isn't is an impossible task so
the more that you can you know register yourself or and communicate that to your family the actual
easier you make it on your loved ones god forbid they end up in that situation having to facilitate
that gift yeah I think that's the point you can think of this as an advanced directive which
actually is the biggest service you can give to people around you so that they don't have to
there's no ambiguity about what your wishes are so we've talked a lot about kidney but I you know
I think I'd be remiss if we didn't spend some time talking about the liver which is really the bread
and butter of your clinical practice and it's certainly one of the most technically demanding
operations in the field it's no surprise then that the most amazing surgical resident I ever
got the train alongside is doing the pinnacle of what surgery offers let's go back to the 1960s
there's a young guy it's 1963 there's this guy nobody's ever heard of thomas starzel
um he's he's plugging away at this operation he actually I think if I'm not mistaken was the
first guy to figure out that you could add prednisone to imuran and actually increase survival to levels
that were still abysmal by today's standards but reasonable you know I think he was getting 70
survival at one year but four years later a three-year-old boy dies on the operating table bleeds to
death and at that point people sort of had enough and there was kind of as you alluded to earlier
this moratorium on liver transplants until we figure this out more let's start with the technical
aspect of it what is it about the liver that is so difficult to surgically implant yeah so I mean
the liver is the largest solid organ in the body it has some interesting anatomical nuances it has
a dual blood supply so it's supplied by the hepatic artery which is a major branch essentially off the
aorta as well as the portal vein which is the blood drainage of all of the intestinal blood flow
and the reason that returns through the liver is the liver is the filter essentially the metabolic
filter for the the metabolites absorbed in the GI tract it then lives on top of the vena cava the
major vein returning blood from the lower part of the body back to the heart and actually sits right
below the diaphragm right below the right atrium where it has this complex venous network that
drains into the vena cava so it's it's anatomically made not to be messed with in some ways is the
way you'll hear people talk about it I mean and in addition to that you then have all the intrahepatic
anatomy which you know which can be profoundly complex as well but the thing that makes liver
transplantation really the challenge that it is surgically is not so much the anatomy which you
know fortunately with experience you learn how to navigate it's the fact that liver failure
at least the the diseases for which we most commonly transplant so the development of
cirrhosis or the end stages of chronic liver injury and fibrosis leads not only to synthetic
failure of the liver so the liver loses the ability to process some of those metabolites
it loses its ability to make new proteins including some of the proteins that help your
blood clot and other important functions but because the liver is become this scarred
fibrotic organ all of that blood flow that's returning from the intestines has to make its
way through what used to be this soft compliant sponge and is now literally the consistency of a
rock and so the what happens is you develop this condition called portal hypertension where the
the blood the pressure in the portal venous system increases such that it tries to find
other ways back to the heart and so it it forms collateral channels that's those collateral
channels are what what form the varices or varicosities that that develop in the GI tract
that can lead to life-threatening hemorrhage in liver patients it's what leads to the formation
of ascites or the fluid retention that you see in patients with liver disease with these huge
protuberance distended abdomens and it also makes the surgical field this kind of rat's nest of
collateral venous vessels so so you've got the challenge of a large you know organ with
challenging anatomy you have the challenge of this condition that makes the dissection and the
predilection towards bleeding even higher and then you have the synthetic function which is
occurs in the setting of a you're doing this operation the setting of an individual who's
not making normally normal clotting factors so it's really both the circumstance of the
technical challenge but more more often the the the circumstances and the in which you're doing
it and you know as you know liver failure leads to cakkexia and muscle loss so these are debilitated
sick patients that you're then doing a big operation on in suboptimal conditions and so
the fact that tom starzel and his contemporaries took that operation on in the 1960s when
electrocottery wasn't really a thing most hospitals didn't really have blood banks
we didn't even have kind of critical care anesthesia at least with any you know
resemblance to what it is now i mean it's pretty remarkable that that was even conceptualized much
less achieved technically and as you alluded to it was really their realization that not only was
the procedure so technically demanding that the risk of early mortality was quite high but you
were doing it in a immunologic setting that just was not successful and so you know even the patients
that survived the operation in the early recovery there were really no survivors past 90 days in
the first you know dozens of transplants done which is what led to the moratorium on liver
transplantation that occurred in the late 60s and i would add one other thing to punctuate everything
you said chris which is not only are these the sickest patients i've ever seen i mean these
patients are staggeringly sick but they lack something that every other sick patient has
prior to a transplantation so whether we're talking about cardiac transplantation
pulmonary transplantation pancreatic transplantation renal transplantation
all of those organs have some form of extracorporeal support that is offered to them
to at least bridge the gap or tune them up a little bit prior to surgery the liver remains
the only major organ with no form of extracorporeal support now i i could spend an hour giving you my
theories as to why that's the case i think it speaks i'll give you the punch line i think it
speaks to one particular function of the liver although i think there are many but i think the
one that just can't be done by a machine is the regulation of blood glucose it is so complicated
to manage gluconeogenesis glycogen storage i mean you have to be able to regulate something to
the milligram level with with seconds to spare there are probably a dozen other reasons but
you know every attempt at extracorporeal liver support has failed including some crazy stories
that you know i heard from god one of our one of the transplant surgeons i remember it might have
been montgomery even told a story about the baboon yeah that's that's a mel williams story
oh that's right that's right mel williams why don't you tell folks that story actually it's
just the scariest thing so um you know what you're alluding to is exactly correct so there have been
all kinds of uh both mechanical and even you know in atomic models trying to address
liver dysfunction or to bridge that gap you know from liver failure to transplant and nothing has
worked real well i mean essentially we've tried you know uh what's been called liver dialysis
so in other words trying to remove some of the toxins from the bloodstream that the liver is
responsible for filtering we've we've tried things that do address the portal hypertension
so at least you kind of alleviate that problem but nothing has replaced the synthetic function
that you describe so one of the obvious kind of conjectures well what if well then we need a
physiologic solution to this could we support patients particularly patients with acute liver
failure where the injury is acute and the liver is this incredible organ in that it does have this
regenerative capacity hepatocytes will replenish over time so the thinking was well if someone
comes in with a tylenol overdose or an acute viral toxicity to their liver could we just bridge them
long enough until those new hepatocytes start to come into play and so it was under that principle
that the concept of well can we do some sort of extracorporeal model to support these patients
and so Mel Williams who was the he was a contemporary and a student of David Hume
who was one of the godfathers of liver or excuse me of transplant and transplant immunology
specifically Christian Barnard who did the first heart transplant actually trained in his lab
and Dr. Williams you know worked there as well and then eventually came to Hopkins and started
the transplant program at Johns Hopkins he was a kidney transplant recipient eventually himself
received a living donor kidney from his wife and unfortunately died recently you know later in age
not related to his transplant a remarkable kind of luminary figure and one of the best storytellers
you know you've ever heard but he tells the story of that they decided well why don't we address
acute liver failure by hooking up the patient to a extracorporeal essentially you know bypass circuit
and put a baboon on the other side of the circulation so the baboon's liver would
essentially filter the toxins out they'd be the blood would be returned to the individual
and that would address their acute liver failure and so they worked on this prep and they did all
kinds of preclinical studies and eventually they had somebody come in with acute liver failure
and you know I don't know the specifics of IRB regulations at that time but sure enough they
got approval to to do this and one of the things they quickly realized is and I don't know any of
the veterinary medicine behind this but you can't sedate a baboon very easily you know it takes her
culean doses of you know sedatives so and you can't have a baboon running around the medical ICU
unit at Johns Hopkins hospital so they decided and maybe what wasn't the most ingenious method to
put the baboon in a body cast so they would at least the baboon would be frozen to the bed
so they do the preparation and you know unbelievably it starts to work so the the
patient's encephalopathy clears the patient starts to wake up so this poor individual wakes up in the
ICU at Johns Hopkins he doesn't know what's happened to him looks over and there's a baboon
lying next to him in the bed next to him so what does he do he tries to get up and start pulling at
lines so the solution they decided to that is they actually put him in a body cast too so there was
a baboon and this poor individual in a body cast in the ICU next next to each other at Johns
Hopkins and that that was a short-lived series of experiments but it did prove the principle
that that would work you know that the that if you had an actual functional liver
in cross circulation with an individual and actually he went on to do some preparations
between for example family members if a family member came in with acute liver failure you
could put him in cross circulation with you know a sibling or something and some of those did
did work and maintain those patients it also led to the principle that is part of a
investigational product now that created this essential a dialysis column populated with
hepatocytes you know with with kind of a hepatocyte stem cell line that populates the hepatocytes and
that has been shown at least in some studies to at least provide some limited short-term support
as well so but the principle behind what you said is absolutely right that we have not figured out
how to provide extracorporeal support for liver patients so they really are the patients that
face death if they are not able to be transplanted in a timely fashion one of the most stark memories
i have from residency on the on the side of patients that would ultimately need a transplant
was probably my second year in the old sick you and a young woman came in she was 21 years old
she'd overdosed on tylenol and it's funny when you realize how dangerous tylenol is and yet how
willy-nilly it's available you know the you know this of course but just for folks listening the
ld50 the lethal dose at which 50 of the population would be dead from a drug that's a you know that
one would know that for every drug out there what's the ld50 of fentanyl what's the ld50
well the ld50 of tylenol might only be 10 to 20 times beyond what you would normally take for
your headache and so the ease with which a person can end their life with with tylenol is is is
staggeringly high and as was the case in with this with this girl you know i think she broke
up with her boyfriend and took a bottle of tylenol and by the time she sort of realized
that this was a bad idea it was too late and there was the saddest memory i have chris as the
following before she really went into acute liver failure and and then suffered sort of the
encephalopathy that would then rob her of her cognition while we waited for a transplant
there was a lucid period of time when her pt you know inr ptt were through the roof lft's were
through the roof and it was very clear she was going to die without a liver transplant and yet
she was cognizant enough to know that and i don't remember how big that window was but it it was it
it existed now we could have been wrong maybe she was going to recover but but it turned out
she ended up getting transplanted um and it was it was just amazing to see her wake up from that
and realize like she had another lease on life and you could say i mean look someone could say well
she made a dumb mistake you know and maybe she didn't deserve another chance but of course
i would say who among us hasn't done really dumb things yeah um it's so true it's it's you know
fortunately acute liver failure only accounts for about five percent of the liver transplants
done in the united states so it's a relatively uncommon situation in part because the liver is
pretty resilient so sometimes even a catastrophic you know overdose if with good critical care and
other measures many of those patients will recover but um you know we are often faced with the
situation where just exactly like you described a person comes in with a tylenol overdose it's an
intentional overdose or at least as you know suicidal type gesture um and we have to make
the decision with limited information about whether or not we think they're an appropriate
transplant candidate and you know occasionally there are reasons why they're not you know
uncontrolled comorbid disease or maybe you know other factors but usually it's exactly the
circumstance you described it's a young distressed person who reacted badly to a
you know a particular event and it makes a very impulsive decision impulsive decision with a with
a freely available drug like out of their medicine cabinet you know and i think the approach of our
center which i think is true of most transplant centers is to give those patients the benefit of
the doubt and try and get them to transplant rapidly and then use all the appropriate resources
afterwards to help support them and make sure that any mental health issues and such are addressed so
they are tragic and dramatic circumstances they can be incredibly rewarding you know transplants
as you would imagine though to see them literally get transformed you know from the transplant
transplant chris when you and i were in medical school and residency for that matter
it seemed abundantly clear that hepatitis c was going to overwhelm the liver transplant
infrastructure within the united states today there's good news and there's bad news the good
news is that hepatitis c is not going to overwhelm the liver transplant infrastructure of the united
states the bad news is that something else is going to do that and that's naphaldy and nash
can you tell us the twin stories of these two things and and uh how is it that that uh that
something that we believed could never be cured got cured yep and then how is it that this thing
that we didn't know existed 20 years ago is going to be if it not already is the leading indication
for liver transplant in the developed world it's such a kind of at once compelling but also
humbling story and i'll in telling it i'll add even a third actor that you know is is part of
this as well so um hepatitis c as as you alluded to uh you know a viral illness um blood-borne
illness that can um this has kind of an interesting history some people that are exposed to to
so hepatitis c rarely causes an acute illness fortunately some people that are exposed to it
can clear the virus so spontaneously clear the virus but the majority are left with chronic
viremia and subsequent uh inflammation which is which is silent for years and in some cases
decades so the the kind of history of this in the united states is that people were exposed to this
you know in the 70s and 80s either due to a time when the blood supply was not really tested for
as stringently and they acquired it through blood transfusion or they acquired it from
use of ivy drugs or other exposures but then went about their life and then here they are
20 30 years later with cirrhosis and eventual complications of cirrhosis and indication for
transplant and the and for about 20 years that was the predominant indication for transplant in
the united states which was a challenge because the medications we had to treat hepatitis c were not
particularly effective you know response rates of 15 to 30 percent or so so every one of those
patients got recurrent hepatitis c after their transplant and many went on to develop graft
failure you know and cirrhosis essentially of their transplant graft so it was a it was a
particularly frustrating clinical problem because there was this enormous need but also we were only
kind of partially solving the problem and you know what has happened and what you're alluding to is
in the last 10 years essentially was the development of these direct anti antiviral agents that have
transformed the field of hepatitis c and it's you know you can make some arguments about what's
the greatest medical advance we've witnessed in our you know medical career but that's up in the
top two or three yeah i don't i don't think i could think of something more impressive in my
i mean maybe you could argue the the you know retroviral regimens that made hiv a chronic disease
instead of a could rival it but but i mean this is transformative so you take patients who were on
a certain path towards liver failure and death cure their viremia and what we what we actually
anticipated would happen was that all the patients who already had cirrhosis would eventually go on
to need transplant anyway but what we've seen is a precipitous drop in the number of patients needing
transplant for hepatitis c because once they clear the virus their liver does you know
re-compensate and repair somewhat and the patients that are not cirrhotic or with advanced
fibrosis yet are never going to get there so it is it is truly a curative situation so that drop has
happened precipitously over the last you know three to five years it has been replaced you know
nearly completely by actually two diseases the the first and the one that has this kind of
incredible broad public health impact is is the is non-alcoholic fatty liver disease or the concept
of fatty deposition in the liver that leads to chronic inflammation and kind of just like a
chronic virus you know ongoing inflammation fibrosis eventually cirrhosis and with the
obesity epidemic and other associated diseases the prediction is that by 2030 or so it will become
the leading indication for liver transplantation and we've already seen that curve start to
inflect up pretty highly the only thing that makes the story a little more interesting or
frustrating is there's another curve that over the last several years has inflected even you know at
a steeper slope and that is the the incidence of alcohol related liver disease which is has always
been you know a important cause of liver disease in the united states but unfortunately and you
know whether you blame it on the economic downturn in the late 2000s or other factors you know really
have seen an explosion of alcohol related liver disease made worse by the way by the pandemic
and i think that has occurred at a time when transplant centers have adapted their approach
to patients with alcohol related liver disease to make it a little less of kind of this
terrible spanish inquisition kind of approach to you know you're either in or out you know if we
think you're committed to sobriety to a system where we have developed resources mental health
professionals counselors and such to support people in their sobriety to allow them to get
transplanted successfully so you know i hope that that curve plateaus we unfortunately don't have
an intervention for fatty liver disease that i see breaking that you know the slope of that curve
quickly and you know it has changed our field because you know the the population of patients
with fatty liver disease is much different than the patient the population with chronic liver
disease of other causes whether it's alcohol hepatitis c you know most of those patients have
liver disease and the consequences of liver disease but usually fortunately not much in
the way of other morbidity whereas you take the fatty liver disease patient population
they are first of all often obese which you know poses surgical risk and other challenges but on
top of that they have all the other manifestations of their metabolic syndrome they have cardiovascular
disease hypo-lipidemia etc which poses you know medical management challenges both for
making sure we select patients that are likely to be successful with transplant but also with
caring for them afterwards i mean the you'll hear the comments said that we're we've kind of
converted our liver transplant population to look a lot more like our kidney transplant population
because they're dealing with these cardiovascular comorbidities and other things that are just
that are threatening their long-term survival as much as their liver disease and immunosuppression
is you know i sort of think that the the the uptick in alcohol associated liver disease or
affoldy say is kind of the parallel but gets less attention than what we're seeing with the
opiate crisis so i think the the opiate crisis is i i think it's easy and understandable that you
would throw the manufacturers under the bus and in truth they deserve to be thrown under the bus
and you can throw the physicians under the bus who make who prescribe them to freely and that's
fair as well but the elephant in the room is the why right like why is it that people are
self-medicating with opiates that are made too freely available etc and i think with opiates
because the outcomes can be quite binary and stark in the nature of the overdose the nature
of the death it becomes very easy to focus on that but acute alcohol toxicity is virtually unheard of
very few people will drink themselves to death in a moment right much more common of course is
the chronic toxicity of alcohol and i think that you know you're one of the few specialists within
medicine as a transplant doc or a hepatologist who actually gets to see what that looks like
but i think it doesn't really register for most people that they're basically two and two sides
of the same coin yeah i totally agree with you and i think we unfortunately um it's it's that
perception that they're different or the fact that we kind of both medically and society-wise treat
them differently has prevented us from addressing the problem with the appropriate attention it needs
you know one of our hepatologists here at the university of michigan jessica melinger who's
who's really dedicated her career to understanding alcohol related liver disease
as she has refined kind of her approach to the evaluation and management of these diseases you
know she really makes the sense that the the um emphasizes the point that this is a behavioral
disease you know uh you could argue nash can be a behavioral disease in some cases as well
but therefore the resources have to be put forth to address the behavioral disease
um and i think you know we have kind of largely turned a blind eye at um the impact of alcohol
related liver disease and alcohol use disorder in our society because of the just the factors you
said it's a it's a freely available you know substance you know it's you don't have to go
you know the the machinations and just kind of destruction that people have to go through their
life to get opiates that's that's not the case for alcohol you can go to the 7-eleven and get you
know that the the kind of equivalently damaging dose you know there and i think it's made the
problem much harder to address and i i am glad to see the transplant community and the medical
community kind of re pivoting in our focus towards trying to help people address the the the reasons
you know why they're involved in this cycle because it is tragic and one of the things
that's most notable about the alcohol related liver disease population now is they are ridiculously
young you know so not only have they drank enough to destroy their liver but they've drank enough to
destroy their liver in their 20s and 30s and you know which is a which is a little different than
kind of the kind of classic you know 65 year old guy who's been drinking all his life and you know
gets to the end of his life that's right most of us think of the mickey mantle story where
you know it's it's exactly what you described but no i think i think it is the same disease
and yet one uh one population numbs with an acute numbing agent opiates that have an acute toxicity
and the other numbs with a chronic numbing agent that has a chronic toxicity and yeah to consider
to somehow put those into different silos um yeah when i think the underlying conditions are
similar is is probably slowing our progress yeah i totally agree i totally agree chris i think
the last thing i want to talk about from a transplant perspective and there's so much
i want to talk about but i want to be respectful of your time and i know you've got to head off to
a meeting shortly um you talked about the team right one of the things about transplant that
attracted you to it was the team and i think it's probably not obvious to people how big that is
it's obvious to me because i got to see it during residency but i don't think there's a field of
medicine that has a bigger team when you encompass i mean the only one that i could maybe think of
would be like that would rival it might be pediatric cardiac surgery where you just have
such you know the the overlap is huge but but even that might not be as big as what we're
talking about here in terms of the perfusionists and the surgeons and the anesthesiologists and
the nursing and the icu and then the logistics associated with organ procurement it's an enormous
team um and you lost a number of team members a while ago shortly shortly after you got to michigan
um i think that story is obviously tragic but also highlights the incredible risk that goes into this
do you mind telling that story a little bit yeah sure so what you're referring to was a
in june of 2007 we had a team that had flown from michigan to wisconsin to retrieve lungs for one of
our recipients they had actually procured the lungs they had just taken off from milwaukee and
um you know had a tragic set of circumstances that happened to the plane and tried to
turn it around and get back to milwaukee and essentially crashed into lake michigan
that shortly thereafter and all six individuals on board died and it does
um there's a there's a story in there about how important teamwork is in
transplantation you know so six people lost their life as one small part of trying to get this
uh set of lungs to a recipient there were two pilots on board who passed away
um two of our perfusion staff so individuals who are responsible for the the coordination of kind
of the procurement operation the handling of the organ its preservation transport back to the
recipient team and then two surgeons there was a cardiac surgeon and actually a fellow um who died
in that accident as well and i can tell you that um you know first and foremost it's it's hard to
speak about it now without um getting emotional it was the uh you know most devastating event that
i've ever witnessed professionally you know directly um you know there was a patient on the
table chest open on the table as the lungs were flying back that operation had to be stopped
uh you know one of our coordinators who was the person responsible for you know sorting all these
logistics was the person who figured out that the plane had gone down and that had to tell our team
you know what had occurred it was uh devastating you know to to to put it mildly not to mention
most importantly the loss that those families sustained um you know i think um it it shook us
all in a way that i think is still relevant we still celebrate the lives of those individuals
here at michigan every june um it did uh you know if there is any good news about that event
um it did two things one of one of which i think was um kind of more immediate and personal and
that is it really made apparent to all of us here and i think in the broader transplant community
how precious you know the each member of our team is and how important their contributions are and
how much they put at stake to make these incredible you know events of organ transplants happen
the second thing is it made our field pause and figure out you know do we need to be doing things
differently you know do we need to be shipping teams all over the country to procure organs
when there are qualified surgeons you know right next to where that that organ may have come from
do we need to reconsider how we travel you know in terms of the the um the expertise of the flight
teams and such and the and the actual flight uh um the planes themselves um and it's and it has
motivated differences for example in the liver community now we used to fly out every time there
was an organ to dig it you know we would go to wherever that donor hospital is now more than 50
percent of the time you know one of our colleagues at another center procures that organ for us and
ships it to us which which is the way that it should be i mean i think if you were a lay person
looking at the system you're like wait a minute why are you shipping teams all over the stuff when
you have qualified people right there so it has motivated change in our community that that i think
needs to continue to evolve but you're absolutely right that it it puts a it's a it was a terrible
event to remind us of the kind of sanctity and importance of our teams for sure
chris i want to thank you for for for sharing that story um it's hard to believe it was 13 and
a half years ago i i mean i remember like it was yesterday so i can't imagine how approximate it
feels to you as well um this has been wonderful to sit down with you and talk about this um i
i always enjoy our times together and i have the fondest memories of sitting in that empty cafeteria
two in the morning between traumas and again as long as i was sitting there with you it was always
enjoyable it was never like i can't wait to get back to the call room and try to get 10 minutes
of sleep it was like i'd rather be sitting here with chris absorbing his wisdom even if it means
getting no sleep tonight so um that wisdom continues and i know that you're you're surrounded
by patients that are i hope they realize how lucky they are to have you as their doc i'm sure they do
no you're very generous peter and i just want to say how um grateful i am for you
inviting me i also really am grateful for you using your platform to to highlight the importance
of organ donation and the the miracle really that it is that that uh transplantation works
and so i'm i'm grateful for the opportunity and most of all just to see you and reminisce a little
bit so thank you thank you for listening to this week's episode of the drive if you're interested
in diving deeper into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription now to that end membership benefits
include a bunch of things one totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic paper person thing we discuss on each episode the word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these monthly ama episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely
access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this the qualies which are a super short podcast that we release every tuesday
through friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of the drive this is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that i believe in but for which i'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on if you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can head
over to peter atia md.com forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook
all with the id peter atia md you can also leave us a review on apple podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including the giving of
medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk the content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have and
they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
finally i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies i invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies