Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
All right, Jake. Looking forward to talking about a lot of things today here. Thanks for
taking time out of work today. I know it's a busy time of year for you guys.
My pleasure, man. I'm definitely looking forward to it.
So I don't even know where to begin, man. I almost feel like the easiest way to begin
this is to have people get to know your story a little bit the way I've gotten to know it.
We're both Canadians. I guess we have that going for us, for better or worse.
Yeah. I was reading my son a book yesterday about Canada that one of his Canadian cousins
got him. I was trying to explain to him, Canada is like the United States. It has provinces
instead of states. He wanted to know which one I was from. I'm pointing to
Toronto and all this stuff. Then he's looking at the northern part and he's like, well,
what's up there? I was like, yeah, that's the Arctic. Most people don't live up there,
but of course most people isn't Jake. You're growing up in the Arctic, right? Which is not normal.
Yeah. We grew up in a small town called Rainbow Lake. Rainbow Lake was technically in the Arctic
circle right up on the northern Alberta border, closer to the North West territories. Who was it?
I was just having a conversation yesterday with somebody about ice fishing. You try and explain
ice fishing to your kid and they're just like, what are you talking about? You just sit in a box,
like in a hole that's potentially like four feet deep. Oh, that was the conversation you were having
yesterday was, I remember my dad at six feet tall having one of the ice augers where you cut that
hole in the ice and him going all the way down, like burying it at six feet and being like, damn
it, and like pulling it out of the hole and not getting to the water. Like that's how cold it
was. And we were, it was a great conversation because I can't wait to introduce my kids to
that. It's such a, it's such an amazing experience and obviously lots of resilience comes from living
in a place like that. But yeah, we started out, my dad was in the oil industry and he, we moved
around a lot, but it was mostly in northern Alberta and we ended up in a town called Rainbow Lake.
That was a seven hour drive from any other town. Meaning you were seven hours north of Edmonton?
Oh no, we were, we were 14 hours north of Edmonton. So you weren't going to like Oilers games or
anything. I went to one Oilers game. I got to, I got to see, I would have been eight or nine and we
drove all the way down. It took like a day and a half and I got to see Gretzky and Messier and like
I can still remember walking in and not under understanding why they were so big. Like having
never been to like a professional sports game before and, and like just seeing on TV, like you
walk in and the players are huge. Like they just look like giants. So yeah, it was, but part of
that isolation was, my dad was a subsistence hunter. And like, I mean, ultimately I think where
this, that's where this conversation goes, but we, like my dad every single year would shoot a moose
and that's what we ate all winter long. And we would go down to a place closer to Calgary for the
summer, just to get out of the, like, you remember you got mosquitoes like this big, right? Just to
get out of there. And I remember my mom having to essentially pack for eight months, like eight to
nine months, she would be collecting groceries like all summer long. And we'd had a huge trailer
that we'd take back up with us to this small town. I think it was only a couple thousand people. And
part of that was she wasn't bringing any stakes. Like she, like I remember telling a story, like we
ate pheasant pablum as kids and moose meat. And yeah, so we were definitely, we were definitely way
up there. What kind of chores did you have as a kid? Cause I'm like, this morning I asked my
daughter to do the dishwasher and then it's like taking the trash out. Like these are sort of the,
these are the chores you do if you live in Toronto or Austin. What are the chores of the Arctic?
Well, there was always the inside chores and I remember getting relegated to the bathroom and
with three boys, that was always a mess. But like, I remember having to clean bathrooms, but I remember,
did you ever have to shovel the roof? No, I never, I was the snow shoveler and I loved shoveling snow
growing up because it was such a good workout. It was amazing, but I never, I guess we never had
enough snow that the roof was at structural risk. So one of the regular chores was you had to shovel
the roof. And so you had to like get up there and you would like, you could never do it like from the
top. Cause like, if everything came, you'd like do it in the bottom. Yeah. And then you would of
course strategically do it. So you would pile it all up so you could jump off after and have fun.
But I remember several winters, the, like the snow bank connected to the roof and we were able to like
snowboard off the roof into the snow bank. And like we had all like igloos and it was such a,
yeah, such an interesting experience to live up there. And then you remember, like I can remember
being so cold, like you would stop moving. Like I think the early on sets of like hypothermia and
like having to like come in the house and get warmed up and then go back outside. Like I remember
my dad telling us like, if you start to feel tired, you need to come in the house. And he realized that
was potentially like the early onset of hypothermia. And we just thought like, oh, if we're tired,
we should come in the house. Did you live in proximity to people who were generationally there,
Inuit? I don't know what we would call, I don't know. I mean, we called them Inuit when I was
growing up. I don't know if there's, there's maybe some new politically correct term for Eskimo Inuit.
No, we didn't. I think we were primarily in these oil towns. I remember meeting them because it was
odd as like a function of diversity. I mean, it was amazing, but no, it wasn't something that we were
really connected to at that point. Yeah. The reason I was asking is I would have been so curious to
know what their hunting methods were and what their, you know, cause you want to talk about
people who have truly adapted to that climate. Yeah. And for eight to 10 months, there's not a
single leafy green available. Like you want to chew on a pine cone, it's fine. But, and I, and I
think, and I don't know this fair, obviously the vast majority of their diet was meat. Cause that
was the only thing available. I, I can remember the taste of moose meat, like moose, moose, the
nickname up there was, they were called swamp donkeys because the vast majority of the summer,
they spent their time in swamps and they're eating all of these like legumes or lily pads or all of
these things that were floating around. And there was like a really distinct taste to them. It was
so interesting. So, and then all of a sudden everything would melt. Like it was this extreme
melt off. Everything would be like absolutely muddy for an entire month. Like you couldn't move
anywhere. Like it was such a mess. I just remember my mom yelling at us about like mud being in the
house and then we'd pack up and head south for the summer. And it was this, this, this cycle for
several years before I moved out to Nova Scotia, Canada on the East coast of Canada. When we were
16.
Yeah. So, uh, the other thing that came out of reading my son, this story yesterday, um, was
explaining to him that I'd never been East of Quebec city, which is kind of weird. Like I grew
up in Canada, but you know, go to Montreal, went to Quebec, Quebec city once, never been to Nova
Scotia, which I always, is something I always want to see. Um, because the East coast of Canada
looks breathtaking to me in many ways. Uh, you know, I'd love to see, you know, St. John's, I'd like
to go to the very tip of Canada. Um, so Nova Scotia is obviously like, you might as well be moving to
the Caribbean from the Arctic. Um, but it's still cold water, right?
Yeah. Yeah. It's, I mean, it's, it's, there's still like slush that forms in this, like in the sea
water during the winter. It's still absolutely freezing and there were still tons of snow, but
the temperatures were just so much more moderate throughout the year. There was like, there wasn't
these crazy, you know, ups and downs. And that was where, uh, talk about freezing. That was where we
started. I started surfing. Like you've, you've experienced this in the great lakes. Like the
biggest waves were like these wind waves and went like wind swell on a lake was like the greatest
thing ever as a kid. You were just like, these are the biggest waves of my life. And we showed up in,
I remember like getting to Canada and one of the first things my dad did was take us to the beach.
And I think he already knew what was going to happen and took us to the beach and we just
couldn't believe like the size of these waves and we were playing in the waves. And then
we thought we saw seals out at one of the points. And then one of these seals stands up on a surf
board. Cause they're in like a full black wetsuit. And one of these seals like stand, and I can
remember it. Like they stand up on the surfboard and me and my like little brother looked at each
other and we were just like, like we were done. We were like, we need to do that. And that started
a long and, um, semi dangerous career in surfing in Nova Scotia. It was just so cold and the best
swell was always during the winter months. And we couldn't afford like good wetsuits and we used to
wear toques. What are they called? Beanies here in Hawaii. We used to wear a toque in the water
and try not to duck dive thinking that like that would help. And how many millimeters were your
wetsuits? Well, we didn't have any to start. So we would go for as long as we could like
end of September, October, and then like you literally couldn't even get in the water. It
was so cold. And then I remember getting the first, the first wetsuit I got was an old Navy dive suit
and it was four millimeters and like literally could not move my arms. Like it was just like,
it was so thick. And, um, but we, I mean, we didn't, my parents couldn't afford any of that stuff. Like
I wasn't even, I wasn't, I couldn't extend my hockey career because my dad couldn't afford
skates fast enough. We were growing out of them. Like, um, the first surfboard we made, we went to
what is Canadian Tire, went to Canadian Tire and bought a bunch of styrofoam and duct taped it
together. And that was like our first surfboard. Um, and then gradually things got better. Like
we started, instead of shoveling snow for money, I started a little grass cutting company of my own
in our neighborhood and we started saving money and we were able to buy like our first real wetsuit
and then buy like our first like real surfboard. And, um, yeah, it was, and just fell in love with
the ocean. And then obviously, I mean, it's jumping forward, but the move to Hawaii after that,
you can imagine the university of Hawaii calling and saying, who wants you to come out here?
I was like, wait, where, where do I sign? Well, so let's, yeah, let's, let's back up for a second
in all of this business. Where do you discover your passion for volleyball? Because that's
obviously what got you out to Hawaii. Yeah. Um, the last year we were in Northern Alberta. Um,
you know how it goes. You always do what your older brother does, right? You've got, you've got
an older brother or is it younger? No, no, I'm the oldest. You're the oldest. So whatever Josh did,
I did. And Josh started playing volleyball. And, um, I remember just going to a couple practices
and I don't know if it's cause we jumped on the trampoline so much as a kid or I did martial arts
for a while. I did Taekwondo. We picked it up pretty fast cause we were coordinated and then we
moved and it was probably my saving grace when we moved to Nova Scotia because it was a skillset I
had that let me meet a whole bunch of people. And I think my parents just doubled down on it saying
like, we're just going to stick them in a whole bunch of volleyball. Like whether it was, you know,
middle school or club ball, it was just, it was just such a great way to integrate us into a new
community at the age of, you know, 15, 16 when it's pretty awkward. So, and, and that was it. It was
just a sport that, and I did, I think every other sport under the sun, like through high school,
but it was the one that stuck. And it was one of those things like, you know, driving or bow
hunting for, for you. Like you just, you, you just never hesitate to do more and more and more of it.
So it was something that we fall in love with and got to do that at a really high level for
like through the teens, including like Canada's youth Olympic program and then like junior Olympic
programs. And then it was actually at a junior Olympic program that the university of Hawaii
saw me play. And you know, what was hilarious is I found out later what sealed the deal was
I sent them. So Tino Reyes, who was like the assistant coach, I sent him pictures of us
surfing with icebergs in the background. And, and I, I guess they were on the fence about me
because I'm small, like I'm only six feet tall. And he had to, like he fought for me saying,
if this kid can do this, whatever we're going to get, like the level of resiliency we're going
to get out of him is going to be like, it's going to be worth it, even if we're losing a couple
inches. So he had helped me get there. And I'm, volleyball has taken me all over the world. It's
been, it's been amazing. So, so you arrived to this amazing division one volleyball school at
literally the furthest place you can go. I don't think you can stay in North America and go further
than Nova Scotia to Oahu. Can you, I mean, I guess you could have gone to, you know,
maybe somewhere or something. Yeah. Yeah. But, but, okay. So you've gone as far as possible.
How much of a culture shock is that? And how quickly do you kind of assimilate?
Because, because there's actually kind of some similarities, I think, in the culture as well,
yeah, absolutely. I think the initial shocks were tiny. Like, I remember, oh, here's a good one.
When I came on my recruiting trip, they were obviously really smart. They were like,
here's the university. Here's this amazing stadium that holds 10,000 people. They got like their best
attendance for volleyball in the country. And then they take me to the beach and they're like,
here's a pair of board shorts and here's a surfboard. Go for it. We're going to pick up
like tomorrow. And they had dropped me off at my hotel and you'll love this as a Canadian.
I go to put the board shorts on and I'm like, well, where's the liner?
Like, where's the white stuff? Like, where's the liner? And obviously every pair of shorts
I'm wearing, like we didn't even, board shirts didn't exist in Canada in 1999. And like,
I remember like being so confused and I was like, well, must mean I have to wear my underwear with
these things, which of course you're not supposed to do. So I put the tighty whities on underneath
the board shorts, tie them up, head out to like Kaiser bowls, which is like a straight local break.
Like it was right in front of the hotel and I'm paddling out with like the tighty whities hanging
out the back and like locals are looking at me and just shaking their head like, oh, what are we,
like and pasty white. So like there were definitely some incremental culture shocks,
including realizing that your shorts didn't have to have liners in them. And then when I got to
the University of Hawaii, so that would, recruiting trip was the spring before. And then when I arrived
in September, also like a accidental shock, which turned out to be the best, probably the best thing
in my life was they, they messed up my dorm assignment and they put me, and this is where
like all of the folks you know, come into play. They put me in the dorm for all of the local kids
that didn't have good enough grades. So they were taking the summer program to get into school and
they happened to throw me in the wing with all the Molokai kids. And I mean, hey, like I had never
on the recruiting trip was so short. Like I remember seeing different things, but like
I had never been around a Polynesian population before. And you're astounded how big these people
are. And so I remember walking in the front door at Johnson Hall and opening up the door.
They're all sitting around playing music. They're playing like playing their ukulele and one of the
the biggest person I've ever seen in my life, like six, two, 300 pounds had an ukulele that looked
like this big, like he's playing music. And they're like, you in the right place? And I was like,
Johnson Hall B they're like, yeah, I was like room 201. And I was like, yeah. And there's just like
dead silence and there's like eight of them. And they're like, the biggest one was like, boy,
we're going to eat you. And I was just like, and true Molokai fashion, true Aloha fashion,
best friends, like literally after that statement, they're like, well, you're here. We're going to
take care of you. And that's like, there's this resounding theme here that they'll always give
somebody the chance up front. They will always assume you have your like everybody's best
interest in mind until you don't. And it was the best thing that ever happened in my life.
Like they, they took me under their wing and I mean, everything like all of the best parts of
my life have come from walking into the wrong dorm for sure. Let's hit pause for one second and give
people a little bit of an understanding about what is so unique about Molokai because for many
people listening to this podcast, they'll certainly understand the big Island Kona and most people
have, you know, they've gone to Hawaii, they've probably been to Maui and people understand that
you know, Honolulu sits on Oahu and that's the most populous Island. So, you know, you've sort
of got these three islands that get all of the attention. But then there's some other islands
that are a little less understood and sort of, you know, you go into the more exotic, you go out to
Kauai and people would maybe even go to Lanai, but Molokai is very rarely touched. I feel privileged
to have been there several times. It to me is a very special place, but I don't think,
I think it's worth spending a few moments diving into what you just talked about, which is tell us
about this island both from its geography and perhaps more importantly, its culture and why
you would, you know, why that would lead you to conclude what you've concluded since.
Sure. I mean, no part of what I'm about to say is going to justify how special that place is. I'll
start there. It's 10 miles by 30 miles. I think it's about 180,000 acres and there are 7,000 people
and that population has, I think, stayed the same for a long time and of those 7,000 people,
I would guess 6,000 of them are true locals. Like it is very much an island of like a local
population and certainly one of the higher per density populations of Hawaiians as well.
It is what makes it so special is they have fought for years and years and years to keep Molokai
the exact same way it has always been. There isn't like, there's no stoplights.
There's no major resorts. I mean, there's a few that came up in the 80s.
No escalators. There's actually a town ordinance that says no building can exceed the height of
the tallest palm tree on the island. Yes. The people there are so active in maintaining this
community. There's no people on Molokai that are hungry, but you don't see homeless people
downtown. It's an extraordinary place. They really do care for all of the members of their community
as best they can. And on top of that is I think the vast majority of the food there,
maybe not vast majority, but I'd say 50-50 comes from the ocean or comes from the land.
So they're either a subsistence hunting. So there's deer, black buck, goats and pigs on that island.
Or more importantly, the ocean, they have the longest standing reef in Hawaii on the south
shore of Molokai. The ocean is teeming with, I mean, it's still teeming with fish and people
are constantly eating it. So all of these things, like they've fought to protect all of these natural
resources. They fought to protect their way of life because Molokai's beaches are extraordinary.
There's no, they're probably the nicest in the state. You could easily put up a Ritz Carlton
or something else there, but the community has said no. And they've taken-
There was a failed attempt to put up a fancy resort on the north shore, wasn't there?
Yeah. Yeah. La'al Point, and they fought for years and years and years and they won. And
that comes with consequences as a function of economics and they don't care.
Like everybody said, this is the way we want to live. The community at large has said,
we don't need to look like a Waikiki. We don't need to look like a Maui.
And coming from northern Alberta, coming from a place that you're eating, and Canada as a whole,
I think, there were so many similarities in culture. I think that's what made it really easy for
me to assimilate into that place and find so much comfort in those visits. And part of that was
the east coast of Canada was so damn far that I couldn't afford, but I couldn't go back. It was
just too much of a haul to go back and forth. So every long weekend or Christmas break or
anything, they picked me up and the family said, you're coming with us. And it was just an
overnight, they call it Hanai. It's a Hawaiian word for adoption. So I was Hanai by the same family
as Mike, good friend of mine, incredible human being, incredible hunter. So I was Hanai by that
same family. And it's history. I've been a part of that family as long as I've been a part of
that family in Canada. So yeah, just so lucky and so fortunate to get to be a part of that place.
I grew up, I think, part of my adult life. I grew up as a function of that place and the cultural
values it has. Yeah, well, we're going to come back to Mike, I'm sure, because he's certainly one
of my favorite people on the planet. And some of my favorite images are just the thoughts of Mike as
a teenager. Like the concept of high school Mike is so funny to me. Just, oh, man, it was the best.
Yeah, I love that idea. And yeah, we can, we'll definitely get back into that for sure. So,
let's just briefly kind of get through. So you end up having a very successful career at the
University of Hawaii. Do you guys win the NCAA title during one of your years, right?
Oh, man. Yeah, we win it and then it gets taken back. Oh, I don't think I knew that part.
A little bit of a, like, well, it's a long story, but we win the title. Some rules get changed
after the title is won for political reasons. Then they take the title away. It was a mess,
but yeah, we were top three in the country every single year. An incredible program,
you know, integrating that into like just regular college life as a whole,
tossing on top of that, like a student athlete schedule. I think lots of lessons learned there
as well. And then obviously post college, I continued that career into Europe. But that
entire time, like being, you know, being able to go to Molokai and learning more about that culture,
learning more about access to your, um, yeah, it was, it was, it was an amazing experience.
And as an athlete, and I don't think I really realized this till like the third year,
because your first two years, you're, you're still 19 and 20. You're probably, you're an idiot. Anyway,
I remember in my third year thinking, I feel so much better when I have deer meat in my freezer.
So we were going back and hunting and bring it like we're broke, like I had to starve through
college without access to your like, we were going back hunting, jumping on like the super tiny plane,
like filling up coolers that were way overweight. And then like bargaining with people on our floor
for freezer space. We're like, Hey, we'll give you a couple pounds if like you store 10 pounds in your
freezer. Um, and I remember in my, in my third year, as I like, I think I started like realizing
how the benefits of building strength and lifting weights and all of those things. And I remember
thinking like, man, I feel so much better when I have access to your year. Um, yeah. So they kind
of all got intertwined and, and, um, college was, yeah, college was just such an amazing experience
to combine those two things. You know, obviously we're going to talk in such depth about access
to your, at the time, how much did you understand? Was it frankly, just like, Oh yeah, this is kind
of a local pest here. And you know, this is something that we hunt here because it's so prevalent or did
how much did you understand the history of how they got there and what the true significance
ecologically was? But did you, did you know any of that at the time? I honestly didn't. It was,
it was, it was entirely recreational. It was only later. It was only later when I saw like the first
instance of like, there's these, there's these periods where there's too many access to your,
and essentially they'll lay down and die. They don't have any feed. It was only when I started
seeing the impact that I started saying, wait a second, because that, that animal on the island
of Molokai is, is, is revered. Like nobody's running around Molokai calling it an invasive
species. That's been a part of that culture for a hundred plus years. They find extreme value in it.
They understand the detriment that it's there. And I think there's hope for better,
more or better management options in the future. But the family, when the family introduced me to
it, they didn't introduce it to me as the idea of it's an invasive pest we need to control.
It was introduced as this is an amazing resource that we get to utilize and something we really
enjoy recreationally. And so that, and I didn't know anything more than that. It wasn't, again,
it wasn't until I experienced or saw some of those things that started to kind of put it together.
So post-college, you go off to Europe, you're playing professional volleyball and you,
you decide you're going to try out for the Canadian Olympic team. Obviously you don't get,
you don't get to make that choice just willy nilly. You have to be invited. You're good enough.
You, you go to camp and you come up one short, right? Yeah. Which by anybody's standard is
remarkable, right? To be the, to be the, the last guy that almost made it to the Olympic team.
And Canada's a very good team in volleyball, right? Like it's not like, you know, it's sort of,
I always say like, yeah, it's like in swimming in the United States, that poor person who finishes
third at the Olympic trials, because the United States only takes two per event. That person who
finishes third would easily be in the finals for most events in swimming. So it's sort of similar.
Yeah. Is, is it, how heartbreaking is this?
I mean, I was, I was honest. I don't think I've ever talked about this with anybody. I was
devastated. Like I flew, I closed my contract in Bali a month early, flew back to Canada to like,
make it to tryouts. I thought I had like an incredible tryout and they just had this guy
that it, and his guy had looked up to, he just had this guy there for eight years and he was
so calm and such a phenom and how, and Canada had one of its best teams ever. So it wasn't like,
this is going to be a building year. This was like, we're going to try and get our best placement in
the Olympics ever. And they did. And they just, yeah, they said, you're one short. And it was
amazing because that was the last goal I had. That was the last goal I had for my volleyball
career after, who even knows hundreds of thousands of hours. I just remember thinking like, what now?
Like, and the first thing was, well, I'm going to Molokai. Like, it was like, I had zero plans.
Like my plan was I was going to stay in Canada for the indefinitely and trained with the Olympic
team. Like that was the plan. Like I had, had you thought past that this was Oh four, I'm guessing.
Yeah. Yeah. So this is Athens game. So it was your, did you think that, okay, I'm going to make the
Olympic team. We're going to go off to Athens. I'm going to come back and then I'm going to do what
did you think I'm going to coach or did you always think you were going to go back to Hawaii?
I, so I had to take a little step back because my, my capstone class in college
for marketing and management. I wrote a business plan that actually one to
mimic the model of New Zealand and domesticate access to year. And so, and so near the end of
college, I started to formulate these ideas of how I was going to manage or what, what could we do?
That was a better option. And so the two years in Europe, I started, I started a nonprofit called
the access dear Institute. And well, you're, you're a good buddy. So I can tell you this.
It was a complete, it was a complete farce because nobody would give me any of the studies out of
India. So now you get like those little snippets. When you go on Google, you can like pull up a
study and you get the snippet, but you can't download the whole thing. Well, like through the
capstone class in college, I was trying to collect all of this like population information on access
dear or biological. Like I was trying to, like, I was trying to figure it out and nobody would give
me any information. So I started a nonprofit called the access to Institute. So when I emailed
somebody, I could say, Hey, this is Jake Mus with the, I'm the executive director of the access dear
Institute. I'm still in college now. We'd love to get this study to incorporate with what we're
doing here in Hawaii. And all of a sudden, like, I just like all of these studies started flooding
in. I was like, this is amazing. So I had all of this information and that came with me to Europe.
That was like kind of my pastime in Europe was digging into all of those things. So to answer
your question of what was the plan after that? It was at that point, it was, okay, what can, what can
we do? That was like the next obsession and passion was what can we do to better manage access dear?
So that was already a thought part of the thought process. So there was a little bit of a backdrop
when, you know, I remember sitting in front of the two coaches and them saying, yeah, you're, you're
not going to make it. And like, I didn't even have a return flight. Because like, this is one way.
And I called my mom and I said, I'm going to Hawaii. And interestingly enough,
I landed, went straight to Molokai and four days later, met my wife on Molokai.
And that started, I mean, started a whole bunch of things, but spent the summer there,
played another year in Europe. And while in Europe, she said, well, what are we doing? Like,
let's go home and let's go home and do this thing. Let's make babies. Let's just do it. And that was
it. Like, that was the trigger to say, okay, like we're going home. So that's how I found my back,
my way back to Hawaii permanently was, I mean, through that, like through Molokai and my wife is
from Molokai. And access to was already like, it was already there. Well, I didn't know, I didn't
know what I was going to do, but it was there. So let's, let's now go back and explain to folks
what these access dear are, how they got to Hawaii, how many of them there are, where they are,
because again, now it starts to kind of dovetail into my obsession, which is relatively new. This
is an obsession for me personally, that's only been going on for two years. And that coincides
with when you and I met. So before you give the real story, I will just say at a distance that
my attraction to access to your can only be described as a love at first sight.
It's, you know, growing up in Canada, you see white tail all day long.
I mean, I basically just saw them as things not to hit with your car.
That was basically like, you know, this is like, this is a thing you don't want to hit. Right.
And they weren't an issue in Toronto where I grew up, but because my dad had a quarry outside of
Toronto, my dad had a couple of quarries north of Toronto where we would spend some time.
That's where you would really see, you know, the white tail. But it was something very different
the first time I laid eyes on an axis deer, which was, oh, that's a totally different animal.
Like that's regal. Right. That's, that's breathtaking. And obviously, as we get more
and more into this discussion, when you start to talk about what it means to hunt that deer and
what it means to harvest that deer and what it means to eat that deer again, it just lives in
kind of its own category. But this is obviously not a species of deer that is native to Hawaii.
So how did it get there and where did it come from? Okay. 1868, King Kamehameha V
hired the Mathison Trading Company to get them out of India. My wife, Ku'u,
she translates Hawaiian newspapers. Odd sidebar here, only 5% of Hawaii's newspapers are
translated. So 95% of their history is buried in there. So she helps translate newspapers,
but she's found she can search them digitally by Hawaiian words. So she's found all these incredible
articles and the article explains them like coming down the Yangtze River on a boat called the Lakh
Nagar, them arriving on Oahu. There were, there were two bucks and five does. And just for folks
who maybe aren't familiar with deer, the bucks are the males, the females are the does.
Yeah. And so they stay on the ship on Oahu. And actually, on the way from Oahu to Molokai,
a baby buck was born and they named it King Kamehameha V. And they arrive on Molokai. And
so they're only placed on the island of Molokai. None were put on Oahu. And they put a kapu,
they put a restriction on harvesting them for the local people there. They were there at that
point, the King's deer. And they didn't understand, like they didn't understand this animal. I don't,
I still don't know why he sought this particular animal. At that point, Hawaii was trading with
people all over the Pacific and they could have done whitetail or else. I mean, who knows?
So it's really interesting to understand, like, I don't know why he picked that particular animal,
but I mean, it is beautiful.
It's exactly. Yeah. And maybe that's what it was. But they get to the small island of Molokai and
they start to proliferate very quickly. And I think as early as, I think it was 1898,
there's articles about them thinking there was estimating there were 7,000 deer and they were
already decimating what they were describing in the upland forests. And the subsequent year,
there's an article about them hiring shooters. They called them sharpshooters from California.
And the sharpshooters from California recorded killing 5,000 deer. And it's amazing, like,
at the same time, a couple of years later, there's an article in the then, what would have been like
territorial government about them arguing over the management of access deer. And two of actually
the Hawaiian reps were saying, we have to do something about this. Like, they're going to
continue to destroy our upland forests. So as far back as, what is that? That's a hundred years ago.
As far back as a hundred years ago, people were already recognizing the impacts access deer were
having on the communities. And then- What's their replication cycle? How long is their gestation
cycle? How many babies and, you know, blah, blah, blah. Gestational period is 238 days.
It's very similar to humans. Yeah. Right? Yeah. So three fawns,
sort of three baby deer every two years. They don't do twins. But what makes access deer so
prolific, and they're one of the very few deer species on the planet that are like this, is
a deer every year, it's called casting their antlers. So a deer every year, their antlers fall off.
And during that period where the antlers fall off, their testosterone levels drop,
and their sperm is not viable for reproduction. And so you'll see those long periods. And I'm sure
that's evolutionary of throw. So throughout the winters, et cetera, et cetera. So access deer are
a tropical species. And when they cast their antlers, their testosterone levels stay high
enough to breed year round. So their population dynamics look like 33% a year. Like they look
like those hockey stick curves once they get started. And I'm sure Kim Kimeh, Kim Kimeh,
the fifth had no idea that was the case. And you toss in, I mean, you've seen these animals,
they're extraordinarily healthy. The worst, we take data on every single animal we harvest.
And of the 15,000 deer we've harvested of those those of those females, 89% are lactating or
pregnant at the time of harvest. So they are such a prolific species. And then you put them in Hawaii
where there's obviously no predators, perfect feed, they can jump six to eight foot fences and move
wherever they need to maintain their own health. And you've got a pretty astounding invasive species,
but also resource. So, well, that's part of the thing too, is they, I sort of try to, the other
day I posted something on Instagram, something archery related, and someone asked a comment,
which was, I don't see the sport in this. Like I don't, how hard can it be to shoot a deer with a
bow and an arrow? But they didn't, they were, they were actually very inquisitive. Like it,
again, I'm not normally one to get into discussions on Instagram, but you could tell this person really
asked from a point of inquisition. And that's not an uncommon question. And I say, I didn't get into
it on Instagram, but if someone asked me that question, I typically say, look, you're absolutely
right. I mean, there are some animals where, you know, shooting a pig isn't the hardest thing in a
world, but every animal does have a superpower and you need to know that. So for example, with pigs,
their superpower is smell. They can smell you at a very great distance. And so if you are not down
wind of them, they will sniff you out. You don't just walk up to a pig and take a shot at it. You
have to at least use the smell, its capacity for smell, which is so far in excess of ours, your
advantage. We've talked about Muflon, right? Muflon have a superpower of sight. It's sort of
comical what they can see. The thing I sort of explain to people when they ask me, why are you
so interested in this axis here is I say, as far as I can tell, they have three superpowers.
Their sense of smell, their vision, and their hearing. They're, they're preternatural. I mean,
this animal is so superior to us on at least those three senses that it's about as hard as
any animal to get within a hundred yards of. It's, it's, you know, it's, it's, you have to be doing
everything right to get within a hundred yards of it. And that's not close enough to take a shot,
by the way, with the bow. So then you really have to do something heroic if you want to be able to
take that shot. So that's sort of an aside, but I think it comes to this point, which is this is
an animal that spent a billion years evolving to escape tigers and, you know, and jaguars.
Yes. It's like it, it honed its skill in an evolutionary environment that was remarkable.
And, you know, when you consider how clumsy we would be relative to the animals, it evolved to
avoid the, you know, in some ways, you know, it's, it's amazing. We can ever get near them.
Yeah. And it goes a little bit deeper because you look at, I mean, tigers are probably
one of the most efficient predators on the planet, but then you look at how access deer,
like what their natural habitat is. And there are these, there are fringe grazers throughout the
Indian like forests and plains. So they had to evolve all of these evasive skills in thick jungle.
And like I see it some, like, I think there's a fourth sense sometime because I'm like,
they didn't see me. They didn't hear me. The wind's perfect. I'm like, they're like, there's no way.
And I think they like to evade tigers in dense brush and foliage and like they would have had to
have such incredible observational skills. And I think that's where you see it in, like in India,
they team up with monkeys and they use like monkeys as alarms in Hawaii. They'll team up
with like minor birds. Like they are so advanced and you're right, like a hundred yards and you're
like, this is amazing. And then even if inside of 50 yards, they can dodge an aerial unless they are
completely oblivious. So you, I mean, we've, how many times? We'll come back to that. Yeah. Yeah.
We'll come back to that for sure. I agree with you, by the way. I think there's a pattern
recognition that they have that other animals might not have to the same extent, which is
it's like they know in a certain situation, even if they can't smell, see, or hear you,
there's the potential risk that something could be there and that's enough to make them skittish.
And yeah, they are, that's amazing. They are relying on third party information.
Like they're not relying on just their own. They're so tuned in to their environment. And I think it
plays into, they have one of the smallest home range of deer as well. So they encompass and
they're highly opportunistic. So they'll bounce around from area to area. So I think when they
find places that are safe and they recognize that both as a function of probably like feed and water,
but what inputs they're getting from their surrounding environment, they stay there.
Yeah. So to the person's point on Instagram, I mean, you hear this from every hunter, like if you can
successfully harvest an axis deer, you can, you can, with a bow, you can do almost any other animal
on the planet. And to your credit, you're getting pretty good at it, my friend.
So when did you, so let's go back to your arrival to Molokai. Are you now back in contact with Mikey?
Have you guys decided, hey, like, what is he doing at this point in time? Because obviously I know
where I want to go with this story is how you guys get into basically the rescue side of this.
And the most amazing story is where we're going to go with those axis deer that make their way
over to the big Island. So, so, so help me, you know, help me with that path.
Well, Mikey is always my first call. And so, and so for the folks listening, like Mikey is
the second adopted son to this family. So we're both like an adopted son to this family.
And Mikey's my first, one of my first phone calls after knowing I wasn't, I was going to Molokai
because I'm like, Mikey, what are you doing? I'm coming home. The plan was we were going to put
our backpacks on and we were going to go hunt at least four or five areas that we'd never been to.
We weren't even sure if you could walk to, but we're like, we're going to find out what's over
there. And I met my wife and Mikey was like, what happened to our plans? And I'm like, well,
but the, the Mikey was always that first call for me. He was, he was my partner. And so in,
in coming back, it actually took a little while. I, there was no opportunity rate in front of me
and I didn't have, like I had a little bit of money saved up via, via volleyball, but
there were, I also didn't have like the answer yet. I didn't, I didn't quite know what, what was
going to do. So like it was always this like instance of learning more. And Mikey was my
hunting partner and Mike actually great story. I actually bought and sold a real estate publication
for a year. Who knows? I then got a job managing a pest control company and the, the, so doing
fumigations, those huge tarps on your back. And the place was a mess. Guess who the first
person I called was, I was like, Mikey, you're going to be my lead fumigator. We're going to
show everybody like Mikey's putting like 200 pound tarps on his back and like going up and down
ladders, like he's a squirrel. And we, me and Mikey crushed that business for three or four years
or about three years. And then in and amongst doing all that, somebody, the access to your
interest, it was still going. We were collecting all of this information. We're starting to actually
help other folks better understand access to your, with the information we were collecting.
And then somebody illegally dropped off deer on the big Island, which is, you know, all of the
islands can fit within the big Island. It's the big Island for a reason is Hawaii Island.
Somebody illegally drops off access deer. And we happen to be, you know, the access deer Institute,
but me and Mike happened to be the experts on access deer maybe accidentally.
Okay. Wait, pause. I want to come back to this right away, but I, I don't think I knew that,
I think I didn't know the story about you being the access to your Institute. I love that. And
we're going to come up with a logo. Nick is going to come up with a logo for that.
I've got a t-shirt. It's so old. You can have it. Like I actually like made t-shirts.
But, but I think one part of the story we missed was that by this point in time,
two other islands are now inhabited by access deer. Lanai and Maui. How and when did that happen
relative to the 1860s with the initial introduction to Molokai? Yeah, great, great step back.
In the 1920s, the then I, the then owner of the Island of Lanai, a really amazing story
about how they round up all the deer, but they chose to introduce deer from Molokai to Lanai.
And Lanai is half the size of Molokai. Very, very shortly that population became
fully established at what we can, like what we call carrying capacity.
The overall population of deer is only going up and down each year with available feed and,
or how many fawns are surviving. And a survey, five years ago, there was 21,000
access deer on this very, very small Island. Which topographically doesn't have anything
in common with Molokai. I mean, Molokai, I believe has the tallest, the highest freshwater
waterfalls in the world. I mean, it looks like something out of Jurassic Park. It is not,
it is not anything like what people think of when they think of Hawaii.
Yeah. So yeah, absolutely. And I think to that point shows how adaptable access deer really are
to become established so quickly, regardless of the environment. So the next phase, which is
really interesting. So deer are introduced to Maui in the 1960s, but under controversy,
you think by now there's common knowledge that this is not, like there are issues with this animal.
And they had, if I remember correctly, they had about 20 deer in a pen on Ladei
and 10 of them were slated for Maui and 10 of them were slated for the big Island.
And the Cattlemen's Association on the big Island. And I remember reading stories about like
national park reps from across the country. Like there's this huge outcry on the big Island that
said, no way, we're not bringing this animal to the big Island. It'll be detrimental. And
this is the state now. So this isn't like a private introduction. This is the state saying,
we think it's in the Island's best interest to move more of these access deer around.
So long story short, the big Island says, no, they get introduced to the Island of Maui. Maui is
460,000 acres. So the population on Maui is still what we consider an emerging population. So they're
continuing to grow. They haven't reached carrying capacity. And in, so this year we estimate the
population on Maui to be about 60,000 deer, but the population will max out at 210,000 deer.
And essentially Maui is another very dynamic landscape that looks in some areas completely
different than Molokai. But they'll find all of those places and they'll fill themselves in unless
we're able to, you know, get ahead of that. So, and just to round it out, where is, where is
Molokai today? Population wise? It's an estimate. So, cause we don't have a full survey, but I would
say Molokai is at about 60 to 70,000 deer. And remember there's only 7,000 people and probably
the best way, Oh, this will be really interesting. How far are you from what they consider Texas
Hill Country? Isn't it outside Austin? Yeah. We're three hours from, I mean, we're, we're,
it depends a bit, but we're three hours from where the access deer are in Texas, which is,
I think the only other state that has access deer, right? I don't think any other state in the U.S.
has access here besides Hawaii and Texas. No, where I'm going with this is I remember reading
a whole bunch of studies on deer densities per acre and Texas Hill Country had the densest deer
acreage or densest number of deer per acre at about six per 100 acres. And like Wisconsin and
Mississippi was behind that Hawaii in established areas has 25 deer per hundred acres. So at least
3X, whatever the densest deer populations on the continent are. Well, so, so yeah,
that's how they get to the three main islands. And then in 2000 and I think it was 2010 or 11
was when that introduction by private individuals, it wasn't the state. They decided they were going
to trap deer on Maui, fly them to, excuse me, the big island via helicopter, drop them off.
How many deer did they take?
They dropped off four.
Two and two.
And three and one, three does in a buck. And nobody, and they do it quietly
and nobody finds out about it till about a year and a half later.
And that's when it started, like, that's when there was like, wait, there's a camera trap image.
Actually, a rancher saw it. They called me and Mike because we were already closely tied to,
I mean, both my wife's family and my Hanai family are in the conservation community. And so we found
out about it right away. And everybody said, if you got any chance of like finding these things,
here's the two guys to ask. And we went out and looked in the area. Now, remember,
it's actually, actually, I remember doing this, the area they dropped them off, they didn't know
where they were. Somebody had just seen one in passing on the road. The area was the size of
Molokai. It was 70 square miles was like the management area. So I remember like getting to
the first one and be like, we think there's deer in here. And then they were like, oh,
it's like a 70 square mile area. And I just remember thinking, how the hell are we going
to find these animals? And we're and me and Mike already knew how, how extraordinary these animals
were to find even when there were there's thousands of them. Yeah, I mean, it's safe to say at this
point, you and Mike know almost as much as any two people about their behavior. Now going back to Mike
growing up on Molokai, I mean, literally walking to school every day hunting, eating this animal
every day. I mean, and I've hunted with Mike, which is one of the most remarkable experiences
anyone can have. This is basically a guy who knows everything. This is the closest human to an
axis deer. Like he's almost able to sprout antlers of his own. That's as close as we will get in our
evolution to them. He just knows where they go. Yeah. So they reach out to you guys, but this is
the government that this is basically the state is saying, we have a problem because we've got these
three potentially more deer on the big island. And if this thing's left unchecked, it's going to be
a catastrophe. Millions of deer. Yeah. And the big island being like our primary egg hub, our primary
food hub for, and these obviously acts of deer eat almost anything. So it started a three year
project and it took us three years to find those animals. And I mean, you, you know how difficult it
is like to wake up every morning and either like walk quietly enough and in tune enough to like
assume you're going to see something or sit quietly enough. Like, so you can like the,
the level of like, I just remember being so exhausted mentally and we went a year and a half
before we saw a deer and you know, Mike, like, so it's like, they're not here. There's no way.
Like it was this constant mental battle. It was like, we literally hunted almost every single day
for a year and a half without seeing an animal. Yeah. What I think is amazing about that is
everything you just said, which includes the idea that at some level in the back of your mind,
you have to be entertaining the thought they didn't survive. Right. And you could be sitting
here looking for a skeleton. Yeah. And, and I remember like sitting across, like I remember
me and Mike being probably the perfect partners for this. Cause whenever I was like, there's not
a chance, man. We've walked this place eight times, but part of it, it was so big and it, it's these,
it was an area that has, it's very, very windy. So there's windblown trees over the vast majority
of the area. So think about a Briar Grove or what are they called? It literally was like doing yoga
all day long. Like you were crawling in and through all of these trees, which deer love.
So it was like physically exhausting, but then it was mentally exhausting. Cause you're only
covering a certain amount of acres. You're looking for like a single piece of scat or like deer
feces. You're looking for like a single rub. You're looking for like anything that would tell you
that they're there. And what we didn't know was they had found a safe spot and were encompassing
like it was less than a hundred acres, Peter. And so we were looking in like, but part of,
I think what's important of this story is at the point we were like, there has to be a better way.
That's when we learned and started like working with the military for the Fleur equipment.
And the Fleur equipment was ultimately what found them for us. So Fleur equipment picks up
infrared or heat signatures from bodies, and then they'll translate that into an electrical
optical image for you to be able to view. And the military was involved. Like it was such a big deal.
And the military loaned us one of their binocular units. And me and Mike were like,
it was that instant realization. Like, how did we ever do this without this thing? And that
ultimately over a period of a couple of months, we were able to start chunking off huge areas of land
in being able to view with great detail these areas from a thermography standpoint. And that's
how we found them. Do you remember that first day that you actually saw one? Oh, it was crazy
because Mike was looking through it and it was, we're doing all of this in the middle of the night
because you can only really use Fleur effectively in the middle of the night. And I'm kind of have
my seat back in the Tacoma. And I see Mike take his eyes off the binocular unit and then put his
eyes on and then take his eyes off. And he turned around and he looked like he'd seen a ghost.
He looked so purple. I didn't even know what it was. I thought he saw a dead body or something.
And the only reason we saw it, it was a buck in velvet. And the velvet antler has so much blood
in it. It's so hot. And it was like five miles away. And we just saw this velvet antler in this
super dense cover. And Mike was like, that's a deer. I think that's a deer. And so I got on
the binocular and we had been training for this forever. And so I stayed there and we got on the
hooked up via radio. And basically over the next four hours, Mike went down. I guided him in like
via binocular unit. And while he was going down there, we saw several other deer. I think it was
two, three more. And yeah, Mike was able to find and get that buck. He just missed the doe that
was with it. But we then knew like, it was a brand new realization. Like they're here.
How many deer were there at the time? Was it still just four or had they reproduced like crazy?
It was still just four actually. It ended up being five. But at the time,
there were only four that we knew of. And it still took you another year and a half to capture them
all. Yeah, because we weren't smart enough. We bumped their home range and they moved several
miles away and we had to go find them again. Like, I mean, at some point like the state of Hawaii
forgotten that they've hired you to do this. Like, I mean, this is three years. This is the longest
contractor job ever, right? I think everybody assumed we weren't going to do it. And for a
couple of reasons, one, and this is not me. I don't want to talk poorly about invasive species are such
a prolific issue here in Hawaii. You think everything evolved here over millennia, like
anything we introduce is just like, it's such a disaster. It doesn't matter if it's a frog or a
plant. There's so much money spent on invasive species every year. And the vast, vast majority
of it, I would say the projects aren't what we would consider to be successful. Like we don't
eradicate that animal. And then you talk like on top of that, you assume like everybody's
basic knowledge of access to your were like, these things are impossible to find.
I think everybody assumed it wasn't going to happen anyway. So we had like a minuscule budget,
because me and Mike rolling around like in an old Tacoma that we actually wasn't like that was
lended to us with like half ass equipment. Me and like Mike's shoes have duct tape all over them.
Funding boosted pretty quick after we got the first year, but
I think everybody just assumed we would fail. And I think we would have had it not been for
like, I think just some of the resiliency with came with my and Mike's partnership.
Like I would be like, there's no like, this is it like there's this is a waste of time and Mike
would be like, ah, let's just check over here. And then Mike would be like, this is ridiculous.
Like we're not going to find anything. But like, you know what, let's like, and I think that
partnership was what ultimately got us to the first year. And then once we like once we knew
there were more deer, it took 10 years we were going to find the rest of those deer.
And so part of that process with that Fleur equipment was now we were able to
and we didn't realize how important the Fleur equipment would be for us in our lives.
Is that because you didn't appreciate how nocturnal they were or you didn't realize
what an advantage you could have with that asymmetry of information at night?
You nailed both of it. We didn't understand how much more active they were at night. We didn't
understand all of the behavior cues of what was happening at night. And then on top of it,
we started to realize really quickly through repetition, wait, that's the same pig we saw
via like we're doing these surveys via helicopter. That's the same pig we saw three days ago.
Wait, that's the same goat we saw three days ago. So there was like we started to then realize how
accurate their equipment was in its detection rates. And so on top of being able to find more
animals, we're also getting significantly more confident in what we weren't seeing,
that we weren't missing anything. So we were able to start a certification process to be like,
we know they're not here. And ultimately, when me and Mike realized, wait, this thing is accurate
enough that we can trust it. It started like narrowing down thousands of thousands of acres
to like, wait, they're not here. We know we can go to the next place. When you're walking on the
ground, and me and Mike are 20 feet apart, and I can't see him, like you're constantly
questioning, did I miss something, right? So that was ultimately what led to finding the rest of
those deer. And then that tool equated to like developing survey procedures for it,
which didn't exist anywhere else. And I remember, and that also me what brought it to my but I
remember like finding and like removing that last deer. And me and Mike looking at each other, like,
and we knew we were like, oh, shit, we got them all.
How did you know that was the last one? Because it would suggest that these animals were so under
stress that they didn't reproduce if they were together, but not, I mean, they certainly had
ample time to reproduce, right? Yeah. We were confident that was the last one in that area.
During the process of those three years, we had sightings all over the Big Island that
people thought were deer. There's no way I can say there's no deer on the Big Island.
I can confidently say at the time we were done that project, we were,
well, the guy, the helicopter pilot that dropped it off, who ended up being our best friend,
got his restitution was 300 hours in a helicopter with us.
So like, think about when you sit in your car, like how much area you can cover, like we can cover
10,000 acres in an hour. We were, we were recertifying acreage almost 10 times over
with equipment we believe was like 95% accurate in detection rates. We knew we did like,
we were getting so confident, like we were getting so good. We were marking beehives
as our detection protocol. Okay. We're going back into this area. If we find the same beehive,
we're at a thousand feet in the air. If we can find that same beehive in this area,
we'll consider that we didn't miss anything. Wow. So, so we're starting to, yeah. I think
ultimately that's what gave us the confidence to say we're done. And I'm not sure, but anecdotally
now eight years later, there hasn't been another sighting in the area. And man, talk about life
lessons. Like waking up every morning or actually to the second half of the project, waking up every
night at like six, eating dinner with your family, and then rolling out for 12 hours of using that
floor equipment, like not knowing what you were going to find, you know, for three, like a three
year hunt. It was any, yeah, apart from athletics, I think any level of resiliency I have
probably came from, came from that project for sure. What did your wife think? I mean,
was this what she had signed up for? The, the nighttime working husband and you're on the big
island. Was that something that she, is that a, is that a, has she always wanted to stay on Malakai?
Her family in her teenage years, some of them moved to the big island, most importantly her mom
and her mom are very close. And we love Malakai, but it takes like, there isn't, there wasn't,
there wasn't any opportunity at that point. Like after we were married, we had, we were married on
Malakai. Like there wasn't, there wasn't anything for us to do. Like there were no, there's no jobs
on Malakai. Like, and if they are, they're, they're, they're like, somebody's already lined up for
whenever that position opens up. So part of it was we needed to, we had planned to start a family
and wanted to start a life and we knew we needed a little bit more opportunity to do so. We went to
the big island and a lot of her family were here. So we did that. My wife, and I'll give her a shout
out here. And maybe, you know, it's interesting because I remember you telling me something about
Jill, like unrelenting support. It, like there is no way I'm where I'm at. I think I could probably
say this about you without that level of support. Like it was always, if that's what we're doing,
that's what we're doing. And she is extraordinarily talented. She's one of the best writers I know.
She's a graphic designer. She's a genealogist. Like she constantly is putting things aside for,
and now, and she's, she's our co-founder at this company and one of our most important people, but
she constantly put things aside for what this was. But part of it was, these were huge
ecological and community issues. And, and she was behind me a hundred percent.
Um, yeah, it would have never happened without her. Cause no, I mean, convincing any
significant other to sleep by themselves every single night, and then you roll in
an absolute mess in the morning is not, is not conducive. So, and, and, and I remember you telling
me a long time ago that you didn't even take a day off for the first year, right? Oh yeah.
It was seven days a week. It was a contract. Yeah. Yeah. Because, well, I mean, we thought we were
going to find him in the first week. We're like, Oh, they saw him over here. Me and Mike, you were
like, we're going to walk every single day for 12 hours till we find them. And I can remember like
finishing the first month, like by the end of the first month, we were already like, Oh, there's no
deer here. That guy didn't see something. But what, what ended up spurring on the rest of it was
me and Mike look through the entire, and this is why Mike is so good.
Mike said, if there is a deer here, it's going to walk right there. We're going to put up a camera
trap. So not like we're going to put up a hundred camera traps and see, I think we had three camera
traps. Mike was like, if there is a deer here, he's going to walk right there. I think like
thousands of acres and sure enough, like month four, we got a camera trap image of a deer.
And that's like, that was hard evidence. And we were, we were honestly as surprised as anybody
at that point. And we're like, there's deer here. And so that obviously spurred on everything else
that went along with it. So it was, yeah, I mean, you think, oh, me and you've done some really hard
four day hunts together. And at the end of that four days, you're just like, it was,
it was, it was,
Now I have a better understanding of why after a hard four day hunt, that's hard for me.
You look like you've been sitting at the beach all day. That puts that into perspective.
So you guys go back to Maui and is there something about the burden of access deer there that has you
start to focus your effort and refine your thinking about what you and Mike can be doing
specifically there? Because at this point in time, it's safe to say there's no real concerted
strategy around what to do. Right? You have this animal that, and by the way, in Maui,
I don't think, correct me if I'm wrong, but I don't think the relationship between
the people of Maui and the access deer is as affectionate as it might be on Molokai. Right?
I mean, I think the destruction is much greater.
Yeah. I mean, the first meeting I went to on Maui, they were, won't mention the person, but
calling them spotted rats. Like I think they had already for sure found value within the subsistence
community as that, but they were dropped off in the central area for all ranching. And so they,
they obviously directly compete with cattle for feed and they break fences and, and they started
to see that, that population grow pretty quickly. And so the, excuse me, the move from
the big Island to Maui was primarily because of opportunity. What ended up happening is the
ranchers on Maui who were of course watching this closely and saying, don't let these things get
established on the big Island. One particular rancher on Maui said, wait, you guys actually got
it done. Like you guys might know what you're doing. Like right as we closed that project,
they said, we've got tens of thousands of deer over here. We don't care what you do with them,
just come and shoot them. And I mean, we couldn't do that. Like all of the,
all of the learnings and experience and like cultural values that we, like that came from
Molokai were still very much like a part of who we were. And so for a rancher to be able to say like,
well, just shoot them all, like bury them. We don't care. That was like, and we had already had,
like I'd already done some research on like Europe has an extensive venison industry. New
Zealand has an extensive venison industry and already had like thought that thought process.
And that, but that was the trigger to say, wait, there's gotta be a better way.
Because by this point that was already happening on other, on Lanai. They were basically shooting
these things out of helicopters and just letting them die on the, I mean, it, it sort of became
this issue of, look, these things are causing so much damage. And I also want to get into some of
the specifics of the damage, because as I would learn, and I was surprised to learn this, it wasn't
just, Hey, they're competing for the same resources as the cattle, which is the, you know, the business
here, but it's how that would even trickle into the ecology of the ocean. That was completely new
to me. And I, I simply wouldn't have understood the nitrogen balance and the change and all of that.
Um, so yeah, it's the, the farmers understandably are saying, look, I don't care what has to happen
if the government is willing to get into helicopters with AR 15s and shoot these things out of the air.
I'm happy to have the carcasses laying around and, and explain a little bit more about what the
full extent of the life cycle is in terms of the disruption to the native species there from
basically land to water. Um, yeah. So, I mean, we have to take a little bit of a step back in terms
of evolution in that Hawaii is the most isolated landmass on the planet. Everything here evolved
like kind of textbook adaptive radiation, like everything over here has evolved over millennia
to, to be best suited for its environment right here, which included no large mammals apart from
a bat and certainly no grazing herbivores. So like we have mints that are mintless, like we are,
and now we are the endangered species capital of the world. We have more endangered species
per acre here than anywhere else in the world. I think we're, I think 30% of the endangered species
list in the U S is all plants, birds from Hawaii. And that is a function of the introduction of
non-native species and how they affect biodiversity. So the impact of access deer, you know, Peter,
probably the most influential impact to our communities as a whole is at the very top of
our mountains. And you've been to one of those places. They are, again, as one of the most
isolated land masses, water is probably, I mean, you guys had some issues with water this week.
Like water is one of the most important things for us as a community. And you guys had snow on
Haleakala recently, right? We still do. Yeah. Yeah. Um, amazing. What water is, and the Hawaiians
knew this, the word for wealth was a vai vai. It was water in, in like four, four native Hawaiians.
Our watersheds are our most important resource and those watersheds developed. It was, it's almost
like in this permaculture fashion where there's these three layers and they've developed to
capture all of this fog and rain. And they go directly into our aquifers, any ungulate deer
included, ungulate being a cloven hoofed animal. So goats, pigs, deer, et cetera, et cetera.
Any ungulate in our forests, it might as well be a salad bar. Like they, like they literally can
eat anything. There are no protections. Those plants have developed no protections for themselves.
And once those animals affect the efficiency of our waterfeds, they affect how much water they
capture at a significant rate. So their, their most profound effect is in our mountains and
affecting how that ecosystem collects water. And so as we come down the hill, that's when they
start interacting with our ranchers and farmers. And like we talked about, they directly compete
for feed at a rate of about seven to one. Every seven deer equates to about one cow. But there's
a lettuce farmer can lose 10 acres of lettuce overnight when a herd of a thousand deer come in.
Like they'll absolutely decimate that. Fencing is optional for deer. Like we've seen deer hop over
six foot fences like nothing. So this downstream effect of them impacting how we capture water
and then them impacting our food systems all the time, they're also degrading the, like the
understory. And what happens when we have large rain events is all of the sediment, all of our
soil, I mean, if there's anything more valuable than water, it's soil. All of the soil that have
taken tens of thousands of years to form on this tiny island, especially like coming from lava rock,
all of the soil, all of this incredibly valuable top soil will run off into our oceans.
And it doesn't even stop there. There's like deer scat are extremely high in nitrogen. You
kind of mentioned this, like the downstream effect of not only the soil depositing on our reefs,
but also the impact of like the nitrogen from like thousands of deer's feces starts to bleach
our reefs as well. And I can't say for sure there's a direct link between like that nitrogen
and how it affects it. We know that may be the case with soil, but more than anything,
thousands of pounds of sediment come down in these events. And when you fly over our islands,
I fly every week, you just see these crazy plumes, like miles and miles wide of this red dirt that
is just going out and covering the reefs. And well, guess what's important about our reef systems,
apart from obviously the incredible ecosystems they support food, we've lost significant amounts
of reef and the fish that then go along with them. So there's this, they call it maukatu makai,
there's this downstream effect of their impact. That is, I mean, I don't think we completely
understand the cumulative impact, like, but it's, we can see it every time these events happen and
we can see it when we're in watersheds and part of understand, like, yeah. And then,
so that understanding was obviously what spurred on, you know, the want to better manage them,
but along with it is, like we talked about, they're a food resource. So they're not only a food
resource, but they're impacting our food security. And so it's just like when they're imbalanced,
it's a double-edged sword in that they're being, they're significantly detrimental and they're
impacting our food security here as the most isolated landmass on the planet. So it's just all,
the vast majority of their impact is not a net positive for our communities when you're at such
imbalance in these populations. And as you were coming into sort of your deeper and deeper
understanding of this, you're also continuing to develop with Mike this unbelievable credibility
with the community in terms of, like, it just blows my mind what you guys continue to do. So now fast
forward to the volcano eruptions. And so, so, so let's talk a little bit about what happened
and what, what type of a threat that was to livestock and what, you know, you guys are doing
with helicopters. I mean, this, this, this is the stuff that's out of movies. Then again, I think,
I'm not asking you to tell the story from the sake of boasting about what you've done, but I think,
I think it kind of continues to round out the story of, you know, these are guys who
first and foremost are here to protect Hawaii. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, with Mike as a partner,
we just develop a knack to get things done. And like, there was so much problem solving. And as
we developed solutions for access to deer and what one of the, a couple of years in, we had a
large eruption on Kilauea on the big Island and we had already developed, it was the first of its kind.
It was a live cattle net capture system. You gotta imagine a cow is a really big thing.
And basically what it was, if I can explain this properly, it was, it was, it was a large
metal frame, a circular frame with a triangle net. And there was, it was attached to the tip of the
net. So the top of the cone and it was attached to the frame of the circular structure. And what
would happen is via helicopter, we would put the cone over the animal. We would release the top of
the net. The net would fall down. The animal would walk out to the end of the net and then we would
pick up the frame and it would be sitting in this like perfect cradle. A little hammock.
Yeah. So it had like, it was a little hammock ride. Well, we had a, several years ago, we had a
very unexpected and very quick moving lava flow. We're talking, it was about 500 yards wide
moving at 50 miles an hour. And it, and it ended up completely destroying an entire community.
Like it's gone. There are no remnants of it. It just completely wiped the whole community out.
And it was this amazing community. It's there still, it was a significant loss for the community,
but in the process, two lava flows formed and they cut off a huge portion of a ranching area
and including homes and a bunch of things in there. And the state needed a solution for,
they wanted to find a way for these animals not to die. And me and Mike of course said,
well, we can do that. Having zero context. Well, we can go and do that. And I remember
driving out the first morning. So we bring in all of the equipment, like got it in the back of the
truck and we're driving out early in the morning and it looked like Armageddon, like the entire
sky in the middle of the night was red and roiling and like it was creating, there was so much heat.
It was creating its own weather system. It was lightning. Like it was, it was such an odd
experience to be driving towards it with the idea that we were going to fly around and pick these
animals up flying over these 50 mile an hour lava flows. But me and Mike were like, yeah,
we can do it. And at that point, we, hookah was already a part of our team and you've met hookah.
So now we're talking the dream team here.
And hookah's like, boys, we're going to be lava cowboys. And you know, hookah, I'm just like,
oh man. But I think we needed that level of positivity. Like what we were facing
was fairly substantial and it was risky. And I was never going to risk any of my guy's life.
Ultimately, it was my responsibility. I wasn't going to risk any of their life for a cow.
But long story short, we get on site, we use the Fleur really quickly to figure out how many
animals are there and where they are. And then we come back and we hook the net up. And there's
lots of good stories, but probably the first one is probably the most interesting. We go over to
find the first one and we were working with a helicopter pilot we'd only work with a couple
times before, but he was he was amazing. And he goes and he puts the net over. How long do you
have? Like what's the distance? How close do you need to be to the cow? Well, we need to be,
it's a hundred foot line under the, so it's this, this cone is hanging under the cow. And there's
like your eye level with like lava flows. And there's, there was something called fissure eight.
There's like fissure eight is blowing in front of you, like a couple thousand yards, like, and you're
seeing like chunks of magma going everywhere. And like you're seeing the ground heat up on two sides
and how is that? The pilots going and not interfering with what the pilots able to do
in terms of stabilizing the helicopter. Because the cows had moved themselves into the internal
area between the two flows. So we were coming over the first lava flow and like the helicopter
went like this, like there was so much heat coming off the flow. It was like, like it was tossing the
helicopter three, 400 feet in the air, like almost instantly. And so we get to the inside and
constantly they're like, are you sure we're good? I'm like, if you're good, I'm good. And there's
GoPro video of all of this. So he makes not the mistake, but the cow he happened to catch first
was a huge bull. And it was right at the max lifting capacity of the helicopter. But once that
bull, he has a 2000 pound animal, once that bull is in the helicopter or in the net system,
it's fairly difficult to get out by yourself. And the, well, it wasn't CO2. I can't remember what
the, what chemical we were most worried about or what gas we were most worried about, but we all
had like indicators while we're wearing like indicators. And like, I remember like having to
get on the ground and like seeing blue spots, like the gas levels were fairly dangerous as well. So
we didn't want to get on the ground. We wanted to be where airflow was good. And so he says,
like he goes to pick it up and he can get it off the ground and he's moving and he's like,
what do you want to do? And I was like, can you get this thing across the lava flow without me
getting on the ground? And he's like, I think so. And I'm just like, son of a bitch. Like,
he's like, here's what we're going to do. We're going to use the heat from the flow to lift us up.
And I'm thinking, well, what if that doesn't work? Like we're going to barbecue this cow.
Like, and he was like, he was confident. And I've learned along the years, like
you trust your pilot, like they're the ones that's going to keep you safe. And so this cow is flying
under the helicopter at a hundred feet. So we're only a hundred and fit, you know,
250 feet above the ground. And as we get to the flow, sure enough, the helicopter just goes
and it lifts straight up. And I look down and it's like depth perception is pretty tough at
that point. When I look down and the entire cow, I thought lit up with smoke. And I had thought,
I thought whole, like I was like, what did we just do? Like we just burnt this cow.
I cannot believe like, and like state officials, humane society, everybody is at the corral
system on the other side where we're bringing this cow in. And I'm just like, I didn't know
what to do. Like, this is going to sound terrible. I honestly contemplated like if it was dead,
just dropping it in the lava flow. And so we're flying over this lava flow. And like,
all I see is smoke coming from this cow. And what I didn't realize is it was steam.
I had forgot that it was raining and the cow had water all over it. And I realized as we got over
the flow, all of the steam came off the cow and the cow was fine. Like it's just sitting there
in its hammock. And we brought that cow in. So the way it works is it's hanging in its cradle
with the frame above it like this. And you put it down and then you put the frame right back over
it. And it just stands up and walks up. And so this cow just stand, and we have all of this on
video, this cow just stands up, walks out like nothing wrong, walks over, starts grabbing some
feed like that's on the side. And we had never done it before. And like, Oka and Mike are looking at
me like I was the first one in the helicopter and they're like, is it going to work? I'm like,
it works. And then we spent, we had four separate missions to get out all of the cows
over a period of like a week or two. And I think we ended up doing
40 or 50 cows. And like the stories are just like, imagine like Oka every morning
thriving on this like lava, like he had like lava cowboys on his coolers. Like it was, but
to the rancher, that was potentially going to lose it all. And to communities that were seeing
all of this loss, like there was not like, there was just all of this loss from this flow.
It became this really interesting rallying point for the local community. There's like,
A, it was probably like fantastical to see, but B, like, it's like, wait,
we're like, we're not going to lose it all. We're going to get some of this stuff back.
And I think it's a, yeah, a long line of projects and innovations that are like,
yeah, we can, I think we can do that. And we just, we just had a knack of like figuring it out as we
go. Cause there was certainly some bumps in that road. You imagine like me, Mike and Oka standing
around with no, like with very limited math experience between the three of us. And we're
looking at this huge cargo net and like these pipes. And we're like, I think we argued for like
three hours before we built this thing. I just, I just, I just wish I was there for that. Like that
is cause I know how much fun it is to just be sitting around the campfire talking about the,
that stove that we like that the, the sure stove, like it's called and getting into the math of that.
So this is, I'm going to talk about the stakes being high. So, so how do you go from that to
where you are now, which is you've created this company called Maui Nui, which is effectively
an unbelievably efficient, humane way to opera to operationalize the harvesting of access deer
for, for food at a USDA certification, which is, uh, it's important for people to understand,
like you and I could go out and hunt access deer, but that doesn't really mean anything because
that's, even if you had a hundred people hunting these things, you, you can't sell that to somebody
like a restaurant isn't going to do that. There's food safety issues. So, um, how did you get to
the, the, the formation of what it is you're, you're doing now, which is by that point,
this is about now when you and I are getting to meet each other. Yeah. Um, well, it was a little
bit, a little bit before, a little bit before then, because after we finished the project on the big
island and we went to, we were getting those inquiries from Maui and like the light bulb went
off like, Hey, there's gotta be a better way. So we understood population dynamics. We understood
what we were dealing with. Like from an animal standpoint, the question was like, why can't we
eat these things? And we understood the legality of it. So in on the continent, all native game
mammals are owned by the public. So, you know, somebody, a resident of Bozeman, Montana owns the
elk that's on private property in on a, on a ranch somewhere else. Like the state owns that animal and
therefore you own that animal as a non-native invasive species in Hawaii. The ownership of
that animal falls to the private landowner where that animal lies essentially. And also the
management of it. So you can ask, but the state isn't responsible to manage that animal on private
property. State is really only responsible to manage that animal in on, in public spaces. So we,
we are not allowed to operate on public land. So we only operate in privacy. And I think it's really
important to understand, um, the difference. So we knew that the landowner owned the animal.
And so I remember one of the first calls to the USDA where I was like, Hey,
we want to be able to manage these animals. What rules would we have to follow? And what would we
have to provide in order to have this animal be USDA inspected? And the guy, I remember the guy,
he actually laughed. He just said, here's the meat inspection act from 1930. It's the federal meat
inspection act. If you can follow these rules somehow, we'll give you guys a shot. And so
it's this thick. And so I remember like reading it nonstop for several days and like finding the
couple of spots in there that require humane handling and all of the things that come into
the process of like, um, harvesting an animal or like rendering an animal. And I was like,
I think we can do this. And I, I called them back and explained the process. Like we have this
amazing floor equipment where we can see these animals. I believe we can render these animals.
So one of the most important things is we have to follow all of the rules of a brick and mortar
facility, but in the field for wild harvesting, which the most important thing is how that animal
dies. And it has to be done. It has to be the terminology is rendered immediately unconscious,
but it has to be shot in the head. It has to break the skull cap. So it dies immediately.
And they doubted whether or not we could do that. And if we couldn't do it efficient efficiently,
they essentially shut you down overnight. It's one of the most important things.
And the other part of that was we needed a USDA certified slaughter facility.
When I did the math on it all, um, it wasn't possible to use the current facilities on Maui.
So there were two major hiccups to start was like, a, can we do this efficiently enough? And B,
well, my wife let me re mortgage my house to buy a slaughter facility, a mobile slaughter facility.
And at the beginning, both those answers were no. I didn't, I wasn't willing to re mortgage the house
knowing that we might not be efficient enough to harvest these animals. Cause we didn't know yet.
Right. So the way we started that venture and it wasn't perfect. Everything we do,
it isn't perfect. The way we started the understanding and moving forward to be able
to help those ranchers was just through pet food. So we were able to test a lot of these
theories create, it wasn't a lot, but like a super tiny margin for me and Mike to operate and
get to understand what that looked like. And then it was only after six to eight months of keeping
data every single night on, like I was huge on this, like keeping data every single night on
proficiency rates and miles and occurrences. Like it wasn't until I could justify the requirements
for the USDA that I called the USDA back and said, I want you guys to come view our process.
And if it's approved, I will get the USDA slaughter facility. They came out, they were
blown away by our process. So a combination of flurry equipment to view the animal. And again,
this is happening all at night. Yeah. Let's, let's, let's actually explain to people what this is. And,
you know, at the outset of this podcast in the introduction, I explained that we're going to
get a little bit graphic here. And I think, you know, this would be one of those moments in time
where if you're, you know, if this, if this is a subject matter, that's very sensitive, please
hit a little bit of forward on the podcast. But unfortunately, you know, I think if you,
if you choose to eat meat, which most of us do, I think you need to be familiar with what that
entails. And I always feel that it's, it's, it's wrong to consume meat without having some sense
of what's involved. And if you go to a grocery store and you buy a piece of steak, you can't
just assume that piece of steak, you know, just showed up there without a lot of work. And, and
and I think when you contrast how that piece of steak showed up there or how that chicken breast
showed up there with the work that you guys are doing in the field, you get a real sense of what
the difference is and why a USDA inspector can show up and say, which I know he has said,
I've never seen anything like this ever in the history of the USDA. So, so what was your strategy?
So, so how is it that you can most humanely hunt an animal?
Okay. We have to follow a certain set of rules. So the inspection portion of what we do in the
field is called an, is called an anti-mortem inspection. And in that inspection process,
the inspector has to be able to view that, that, that, that animal is healthy. It has to be able
to view that is, it's both like at rest and in motion. And typically that is done in a corral.
So if you think about what a typical bro, like brick and mortar looks like, there are a whole
bunch of cows that get trailored in from somewhere else. They're sitting in a corral system and the
inspector is able to go outside, look at these animals very closely, view them, determine that
they're, they're safe for human consumption. They're healthy. And then that animal, unfortunate, like
this is kind of the graphic part is that animal goes into a shoot system, goes into a press,
or sometimes it's hung up alive. And then that animal is rendered immediately unconscious with
a stun or a bolt gun. And that looks like in most cases, and I know people are trying to get better
at this, but that looks like in most cases, an animal that is stressed and unhealthy to be like,
it's in this press and it's moving around. And that animal and an employee has to then render
that animal immediately unconscious. We had to follow those rules. Our process for that same
anti-mortem inspection is we don't pen our animals. We don't bait our animals over a period of years.
We knew if we cover enough miles, we'll see enough deer and have enough opportunities to
harvest them. So translation, the animals you harvest are a hundred percent in their natural
environment. They're not in a high fence area, let alone a pen. They're not being baited. You're not
leaving food to lure them in. They're literally just out in the evening roaming about. Yes.
And I think this is probably one of the favorite parts about what we do is,
and it's similar to hunting, we're driving around looking for animals. And if we come over a hill
and that animal is, this group of animals is 50 yards away and we scare them, they hear the bike
or they hear whatever else, they'll run away. That animal is not like that. Animal is already in a
stressed state and it runs away and we're not able to harvest it. But if we come over that same
hill two night later and an animal is out at 200 yards and they don't hear us or they're not
stressed and they stand there, that's the indicator for us that we're able to start the anti-mortem
process. And what that looks like is that same Fleur binocular unit that can pick up a deer at
six miles. We use that for inspection with extraordinary detail. Like we can see abscesses,
we can see old scarring, we can tell if they're pregnant. Like the level of detail is actually
better than an inspector standing looking at an animal in a corral to determine whether or not
it's healthy. So the inspector is staring at this screen, all of the lights are off and he says,
yep, all of these are healthy. You can guys can go ahead. So there's a pause there. Again,
that animal isn't stressed, so it's not going anywhere. And then what we learned over years
and years is we then have to render that animal immediately unconscious, which is shoot it in the
head. But that animal is in a zero stress situation and dies immediately. Which is important to
distinguish from archery. In archery, you think about like you've taken me on some amazing hunts
where I've had what for archery would be considered a perfect shot where you go lung, heart, lung.
But that animal doesn't die immediately. It takes 10 seconds to die. And if you're anything but
perfect in archery, if you hit, say one lung, but not the other lung or not the heart and the lung,
I mean, it could be much longer. But at least I've never had an experience in archery where an
animal died in less than a millisecond. It's always a few seconds even with perfection.
And that's, I think, in part because of the nature of archery. The type of death that an animal
suffers from an arrow is that of hemorrhagic shock. So they die from blood loss. Now there's
exceptions to that rule. You can die from a tamponade, but it's still some form of hemorrhagic shock.
But this is different from the wound that you inflict on the animal because when you're putting
a high power ballistic, which is a bullet into the head, that's a central nervous system death.
So that animal is dying immediately because the brain swells. And so that's a brain death versus
a cardiopulmonary death. And that's why it's an immediate and instantaneous death. And by
definition, there is simply no more humane way to die because as you point out, that animal has
absolutely no knowledge that that is happening. And the moment it happens, they cease to have
awareness of anything. Yeah. And so not only are they not aware and great explanation,
but the animals that are with them in a herd, like they die,
like there isn't like they don't even jolt. They just, they literally just drop straight down.
And in almost every case, the animals that are with them won't even move.
That's the part when you first told me, Jake, I couldn't imagine because I assumed
you came up on a herd of six animals. You would shoot one, it would die. The others would scatter.
That was it for the night with that group. You would have to then drive for another 30
minutes to find another group. But I was amazed to learn that no, you could probably shoot all of
them because A, it's so dark, they don't see anything. And two, there's no movement by the
animal other than just falling to the ground. And that must be a common enough sound to the other
deer that it's not, it doesn't alert them or frighten them. Yeah. So every situation is a
little bit different and it's highly dependent on moon phase and the amount of illumination and
what they can see more importantly, they feel safer, most often not running. I mean, they don't
have perfect night vision. It's pretty phenomenal, but they'll feel safer most often staying there.
And so in most instances, you've never heard of 10 will, will typically harvest three or four of
those animals. And so that inspector has viewed that the process, the, excuse me, the floor
equipment is so good that the friction from the bullet passing through the air creates a tracer.
So the inspector is actually able to see the bullet path and it like, and it hitting the head.
And one thing to, to be clear on here is we're not, we're not perfect.
We've, but we've trained to be imperfect. So we don't injure any animals. And so what that means
is typically where the perfect target would be central to that brain cap system. We, we train
ourselves to miss 30% of the time. A perfect evening of shooting is at 70% efficiency.
But the miss is always high.
The miss is always high and there's never any consequence of that. So that was what we,
and that was hard for us to learn and develop the skillset that a perfect miss was still perfect.
Cause it's an odd feeling to be like, Oh, I missed. And then there's so much pressure
that surrounds shooting each evening. It, we had to train ourselves to understand that
imperfection was actually the best way to go about harvesting this animal.
The other thing that amazes me in that case, Oh, sorry, go ahead, Jake.
No, no, I was going to say that's what allows us that imperfection is what allows us to meet
the proficiency level of a brick and mortar for the rendering process.
Well, that's actually what I was going to ask you is isn't, isn't your level of proficiency
better than any brick and mortar? Because from a humane perspective, I think you said in the
entire time you've done this operation, there has only been one bullet that hit the animal,
but didn't hit it in the skull. And it was a shot to the neck, which still resulted in an immediate
death. So for all intents and purposes, it was the exact same, but it was off the target.
Is that correct? Still? Yeah. Um, yeah. We've only ever been written up again, like once for that
infraction. And part of that is also, so we, we trained for those imperfections, but we also
trained for the scenario. So I think me and you have talked about this like Mondays when we're
making the conversion from being awake to like working nights, my expectation for the boys is to
shoot at 50%. And what that does is it increases their margin of error for something like bad,
not to happen. Cause we now know through poor sleep, it absolutely affects our nervous system
and our reaction time. And we actually didn't, I didn't completely understand that until you
did that podcast with Matthew Walker, which was so cool. Um, so a brick and mortar facility is asked
to operate at a 95% efficiency. We are operating right now at a 99.99, well, functionally you're
operating at a 100% efficiency. And to think that a 95% efficiency is all that's being asked. That
means one out of 20 animals is not dying in a humane way. Isn't that what that means? Yeah.
Or requires like a, they may be unconscious, but they may require an immediate. And I think that's
really different. I mean, that's going, I won't speak about anybody else's operation. I'm sure
there are, I think I'm sure everybody would aim to be perfect in those scenarios, but anecdotally,
I've actually had the opportunity to work in a brick and mortar. Um, an animal that comes into
a pen stressed out and is moving around even at point blank range is significantly harder than
an animal that is at rest and just like unaware and staring. And part of that's also is we have such a,
the shooter has, has to have such an intimate understanding of access to your behavior. Like
a right ear starts to dip and you know, like the head is going to go like a nose starts to go up
and you know, it's going to start nosing. Like there is, there are half millisecond instances
that you have to understand. This isn't something where I could bring in a military sniper and you
can operate at this efficiency. I need a military sniper plus an access to your expert in order to
take those shots. And that's why for so long that was Mike and me. And now you've met Kalena, like
it's, it requires a very specific skill set. And what's the typical range? You're 100 to
a hundred or 500. Yeah. A hundred to prop. Now it's, it's about 200 max. Oh, so what we're
learning very close with the, you're using a three Oh eight three Oh eight. Yeah. And it's not
because we're not effective past that range. We're only given a three hour window to harvest at night.
What we've learned in collecting data is we carry almost every single one of these deer on our backs
and it's an awesome way for the guys to connect with each animal as we're doing the process.
But there's also, it's also very technical in that we don't want any bruising. We don't want to,
we go to all of this effort. Like we don't want to like affect carcass quality after all of that
work. And so you're carrying, I mean, like that last buck that you shot, you saw me do it that
process. You're carrying a 200 pound animal on your back over extremely varying terrain.
And the record should show that's why you had to carry my buck because I couldn't carry this 200
pound buck for that first part of the train. There was, it just speaks to how pathetic I am.
Yeah. No, no, no. But I mean, we've developed like the perfect way to pick up a deer. Like it took us
hundreds, if not thousands of animals to figure that out. And so back to my point of range,
at 200 yards for with a 200 pound animal, you're getting back to the bike or truck exhausted.
And so what we learned was we could actually harvest more deer in a given night,
skipping the animals that we're seeing out past 200 yards, assuming, and we knew this through data
collected, we are going to see more animals at closer yardage. So we have like all of these
parameters in place, these harvesting systems in place that allow us to be in a situation where
in starting an evening, we really don't know where any animals are. Like we talked about,
we're not baiting them and we have this very stringent process with the USDA. We've had to
collect crazy amounts of data to be able to like do so efficiency on a likely basis. And even then,
it'll vary. I mean, the USDA just continues to be amazed by your process because you're basically
self imposing things that no one else really would think to do. Yeah. And I think that just
continues to amaze me. I guess I want to shift gears for a moment and just now talk a little
bit about bringing it back to sort of my interest in this type of meat, which was,
you know, like I'm still relatively new to hunting, but as you know, I've taken a real
keen interest in the harvesting part of it. I'm very fascinated by the anatomy and just
the differences in the meat. And there's something that's very different about access deer.
In some ways, it sort of spoils you with respect to other types of meat.
It seems infinitely cleaner, healthier. The animal itself seems to be, you know,
very clean. There seems to be something about its meat that's unique. Now, as I've gotten to learn
over time, a big part of that has to do with the intramuscular fat content. You know, most people
who have tried venison say, oh, you know, it's okay, but it's a little bit gamey, you know,
certainly black tail more than white tail and, you know, probably.
But access deer sort of exists in its own camp, which is not particularly gamey at all.
And I suspect this, you know, it's basically 0.4% intramuscular fat. I mean, it's a very
unique animal in that regard. How much have you been able to learn about their eating habits and
how that contributes to what you're seeing in terms of the meat quality beyond what you just
said. So everything you just said speaks to why they don't have these high levels of cortisol
and lactate at harvest, which definitely contribute to the sort of some of the taste that you can
have in wild animal. You've basically eliminated the lactate cortisol response completely.
But now we're talking about something that's much more long term, you know, plays a much
longer term role in the development of the muscle. Yeah. Yeah. And to your point there,
that conversion of glycogen stores as that animal goes through rigamortis and what,
and you can walk me through this, but what I assume is like that muscle trying to continue
to do something. So pulling on ATP and that ATP, a function of that process being lactate
that lactate is so important as that, as that animal, that rigamortis process gradually takes
place over 16 to 24 hours. And the pH level of that meat, the pH level of that meat in,
like it completely changes color and texture in animals that are stressed and don't have that
gradual process to go through. So yeah, it's amazing there, but to, to the point of what they eat,
man. Didn't you guys have a camera on, on a deer one? Yeah. So there's so many,
I'm just trying to figure out where to start. So we, so we've done two, what are called satellite
telemetry video callers. The company called the company was low tax. It was the first,
some of the first like iridium satellite callers. And what that allowed us to do was a understand
home range and, and like how often they're drinking and when, and what are their resting.
But there was a tiny little camera that sat right under the bottom of the collar. And we got in 10
second increments, 48 hours of footage of what they were eating. And what was astonishing,
and we already knew this based on studies in India, they are primarily grass eaters,
which is not the case for most deer species, which are primarily browsers.
Browsers being they're looking for legumes and shrubs and trees that they're constantly pulling
on different plant species. Access deer are primarily grass eaters. And I think when you talk
about what like little intramuscular fat they do have, it's interesting to see, and we're only
learning this now, like there's high omega threes in there because they're eating so much leafy
greens. And I think that's attributed to them primarily being grass eaters. But what's,
what's crazy, and we've seen this via the collar, and we've seen this like anecdotally is how,
how intelligent, that's awesome. I never get to have these conversations. It's how intelligent
of an eater they are. And I think that comes down to like these crazy acute senses. So for example,
we've seen me and you together have seen after walking three miles down a hill with do all over
our boots, we walk through an access to your trail, which for all intents and purposes, there should
be no scent on our boot, our boots are soaked, and I'm wearing boots and you're wearing socks.
Like, that's another story. And an animal not even interacting with that specific spot,
but five yards away, that deer is picking up the scent from that boot mark, which was three hours
earlier. And we see this in like the both the satellites, they are so picky in what they're
eating, not, and not even between different plant species, but within the same species.
So they're going up to one of their favorite little legumes is called glycine. They're going
up to a patch of glycine. And they have unlimited feed. So they're not eating like voraciously,
like a cow or something. They're going up to a particular like group of glycine. And they're
saying like, they're smelling, smelling, smelling saying, Oh, I'm going to eat this small patch
right here. And I think what we don't understand is an animal that is that intelligent
in what it eats, how that impacts its nutritional value. And we're starting to kind of see that with
some of the results we're seeing. But I think that plays into how extraordinarily healthy they are.
The vast majority of other animals look at like a, you've seen a pig now in a field,
or it seems like some go a pig plowing through a field. It's not stopping to plow in particular
areas. It's getting started. And it's just going to bulldoze its way through the entire thing.
Yeah, I think this, this is, this was a really transformational thing for me. So I think I've
talked about this on the podcast with, with John Dudley once, but I took up archery because I
wanted to do archery. That was all I wanted to do. Like, I just wanted to shoot a bow.
And it struck me as the type of thing that, you know, you could spend a lifetime never coming
close to perfection. And it was, you know, just it scratched every itch for my obsession.
It was only two years after I took up archery. And all I was doing was plowing target after
target after target after target that I, you know, got invited on a hunting trip, which I'd been
invited many times prior to and was like, why would I go waste four days to go and take two shots
when I can take 150 shots a day in my backyard? Didn't seem like a good idea. But I got talked
into it and JR, as you know, close friend of mine was like, no, no, this would be good for you. So
let's do it. So we go and we do this thing. And as you know, it just sort of changed everything
for me in many ways. But among them is it really changed how I thought about food, because I got
to see on that one first hunting trip, you know, I'm shooting pigs, goats, sheep,
axis deer. I mean, I got to see everything from the lowest to the highest and eat it all
and realize it's hard to be healthier than the animal you're eating. And it's hard for the animal
to be healthier than what it's eating. Like, you know, this is not an accidental process.
And it's never been the same since. And I was talking to my wife the other day.
My appetite for store bought meat has never been the same since that trip.
And I think that's true for a lot of people that experience really good wild game, be it axis deer
or elk, which would be for me personally, my two favorite, I think axis deer and elk live in a
different category from every other type of wild game. But like even chickens, right? Like we had
chickens back in San Diego. They couldn't have lived a better existence. I mean, you know, the
the amount of space that they had, the amount of care we took of them, they're eating some organic,
ridiculously expensive, overpriced feed plus our leftover fruits and vegetables like they're living
large. They're making us these beautiful eggs. I had zero desire to eat one of them
because they lived in filth. I mean, all they did was eat their poop all day, right? It just didn't
appeal to me. Even going to the store and having a steak, it's like, yeah, it's not that I don't eat
those things anymore. But like the idea of my appetite for the 32 ounce ribeye has pivoted a
little more towards the eight ounce filet. Whereas if I can eat elk and if I can eat axis deer that
to me is far better. And I think part of it is the taste acquires once you kind of start to
understand what's going into it. But I also think a part of it is just you can't disconnect from
what the process was like to produce that food that winds up on your table. And I just realized,
even if I'm buying the most organic, grass fed, beautiful steak, it didn't have the same stress
free existence that that axis deer had or that elk had. But again, with elk, it's a different
situation. You have to go out and hunt it yourself. You don't have the luxury of, you know, doing the
USDA certification. So I mean, did you experience that or was that, is that so far in your rear view
mirror that what I'm saying doesn't make sense? No, definitely. And anecdotally, I think it was my
third year of college. And I think I mentioned this before. When I stopped pouring in Hawaii,
axis deer for most folks is just teriyaki. So like, you pour a whole bunch of sugar and you
pour a whole bunch of shoyu. When I stopped doing that and I started eating it like just straight
steaks every night. And it admittedly it was because I had ran out of money. You couldn't
afford the teriyaki sauce. No, I couldn't afford the cafeteria anymore. So I became a dorm advisor
to try and like, anyway, I ran out of money and at 60 bucks a pot for the plane flight and being
able to bring back a hundred pounds of meat. It was like a no brainer. And so by no means was it
on purpose. But when I started eating it the right way, I started noticing it. And I think at the age
of what would have been like 20, I started getting stronger and I was really challenging my body as a
function of like my vertical. And like I realized as a small player, like I needed to start taking
some of that seriously if I was going to like take the next step. By the way, what is the vertical
of a six foot tall national level volleyball player? At its peak, it was 43 inches. I was going to say,
is it possible it was over 40 inches? Holy cow. Yeah. My vertical is 12 inches. Yeah, it's not the
case by any means anymore. But I can, I think fondly look back at pictures when I was playing
in the Netherlands, Netherlands already being the tallest people on the planet. I had two players
beside me that were six, 11 and seven feet and have these really cool pictures of blocking. So
you're jumping up and putting your hands over the net and our hands are at the same height
and our heads kind of match. And then our bodies start changing proportion and my feet are at like
their mid thigh and hip level. And it's just like these comical. Anyway, the,
I started to notice like I was recovering better. And at that point, it had almost happened
simultaneously. I think I've told you about this. We, we had the opportunity to train with
the Olympic sprinting team. And I don't recommend this for anybody, but they did this workout called
gravity drops. And so they were incorporating gravity into all of their workouts where
we would be squatting and you would fall to 90 degrees and you'd try and stand up as quickly as
possible. And never in my life have I felt like every day I was sore. And at that point, it was
hard to make like these physical gains and every day I was sore. And then I like, I remember making
this transition to like, I just needed more food. Like I could feel it and I started eating the right
way. And then I started noticing like I got so strong and I went from 190 pounds to 220 and it
was all muscle and it was a function of this workout. And I think the use of this ingredient.
Well, that's interesting because very recently, like me in the last four or five months,
you sent me the nutritional information from the company that has been looking at the bone broth
because, you know, one of the things that you've done with this company that I think is so amazing
is you've taken this notion of nose to tail to a whole new level, right? So it's like, okay,
there's a 200 pound axis deer that yields what? How many pounds of meat for the human?
Yeah. I mean, the bucks are on the big side of typical axis deer is about 60 pounds whole
carcass and will yield about 50 pounds for a typical human, but there's also hides and hooves
and awful and all kinds of things. Yeah. So you've got the pet food, you've got the dog chews.
And then I remember saying like, where's the bone broth? And then all of a sudden, you know,
you start making this bone broth and what did they say? How did they evaluate that bone broth?
Which by the way, I can't stop drinking it. Yeah. I've never been a bone broth. Yeah. Yeah.
It's amazing. So we have to send all things into the USDA labs for testing and they evaluate that
and then they'll put that on your nutritional panel. And we sent in the first batch of bones
and they called us and they didn't call it outright. They had thought we adulterated the bones.
They had thought we had done something because they tested so high in protein per ounce.
And it was statistically like an anomaly. And so we didn't know what was going on. So we sent them,
I think we sent them a second batch or they retested it. And in the end, it tested 33% higher
in protein per ounce than the best regenerative beef bones on the market. And I say regenerative
because there is something to a regenerative agricultural process with cattle where there's
additional soil health. And I believe that soil health translates into your food,
but that animal is still given the grass it's going to eat. It doesn't have a choice.
So we got the results back and we didn't have an explanation for it. And I mean,
that's a statistical anomaly. I think between what we'd call conventional beef and regenerative beef
is about 3%. Usually they'll see a difference, but 33% is. And so essentially at like 25 grams of
protein per, I think it's a hundred ounces or something. No, I think it's less. No, no, no.
I think it's less volume. Yeah, yeah, much less volume. Yeah, it would be 16 ounces or something.
16 ounces. Yeah, yeah. You're in like, you're in protein powder care category as a function of
protein per calorie. So we're, I think we're just, and I'm not a nutritionist, like I'm not a
biologist. I only know what I've seen over like thousands and thousands of hours of like interacting
with this animal. Coming back to the previous conversation is I think their level of intelligence
in what they eat is translating to their nutritional value. And we're just starting
to see that like me and you were emailing back the other day, like I don't even know where to start
to better understand their fatty acid levels and how I know there's important ratios of like omega
sixes to omega threes. I don't know enough about it, but I already seeing indicators that we might
have something special there as well. And why when we're eating it, I don't feel like I need to
go get like a slab of salmon, even though like I'll have one every once in a while. Like I feel
like I'm getting a complete nutritional profile from that animal and we're eating it. And my wife,
my wife laughs. She calls us wegans now. So if it's not wild and it's not vegetables, we're not
eating it. That's actually funny because I'll tell you one of the great joys I have is introducing
people to this and people fit into different categories, right? So you've got just your
friends who are over for dinner and they'll eat anything and whatever. And then that's great.
And in that category, it's usually, hey, we're having venison and they're like, oh, I don't know.
I don't love that. It's a little gamey. And I'm like, that's cool. Just tell me what you think.
And then they're always like, no, that's totally different than anything I've ever had.
But truthfully, one of the more enjoyable experiences that I had was during our quarantine
when our nanny was staying with us. This is at the early part of the quarantine when for
two months we all just sort of hunkered down and our nanny is a vegan. And so luckily we've got an
infinite supply of vegetables and non-animal matter and stuff like that. But we would sort of,
she'd have her dinner, we'd have ours. And we were at the time, I had 500 pounds of access
here in our freezer. So we were basically eating this every single day. Because we had just come
back from that huge trip in December. But eventually she was like, she wanted to try it
because we would talk about it over dinner. We would have this type of a discussion.
And I think for totally understandable reasons, her opposition to eating meat was, look,
she had some health concerns, but she also had great concerns over how the animals are treated.
And so night after night, she's sort of asking questions about this and asking questions about
this. And then she's like, look, can I try some of course? And needless to say, she loved it. She had
these two awesome dogs that stayed with us. And it was like, hands down, it was cracked to the dogs.
So I became the dog's best friends because I'm giving them venison treats every night.
But to me, that was like, it was very special experience. It was like, look, everybody's,
I respect whatever choice a person makes with respect to what they want to eat and don't want
to eat and what the reasons are. But it's also important to understand not all meat is created
equal. And I think this is just sort of an example of that.
I think we share that experience in, I had seen that in the past, personally, and people,
and it did, it really took them listening and understanding. And I think they recognized
like the crazy lengths we go to, to make the process technically humane. But
we love these animals. The relationship with them started in this place where there was nothing but
respect for them. We didn't understand the negative portions of that relationship to our ecosystems and
ecology. And that's still very much the case for me. It's a continual drive to like, how do we better
manage this animal for us and net positive? But now with Maui Nui, we're seeing these
testimonials coming in. And most of most times it's like them writing to us individually, like
via the website, or I get a phone call. And they're just like, it's been 20 years. And I decided to
have meat after watching your video, or after hearing you like talk here. And I mean, that's not
to my credit, like I've had amazing people help us along the way. But I think, I think, and they'll
mention like, Oh, I watched cow spirits, something along the way told them it was no longer okay to
eat meat. And it's been such an amazing experience for them to see our process. And I think the
intent in what we're trying to do, and be like, wait, this is like, this is an opportunity to eat
meat again. And I completely respect like, everybody's body is different. And you know
this better than anybody. And maybe like, being a vegan works in most instances. But I think for the
vast majority of people, it's important they get this protein, right? And again, you would know
better than me, but it's been, yeah, it's been such a, it's been such an awesome experience that like,
have somebody come to you with that level of trust and be like, I'm going to introduce this
into my life again after 20 years. And you'd be like, wow, like, thank you so much. Like, we're
so glad we can like do that for you and help bring that into your home. And that's the big part of
this is our mission is to balance populations. Our mission isn't to get rid of these animals. Like,
we find them is an incredible resource for our communities when balanced. And the only way we do
that is people need to eat them. So what does balance look like, Jake? You know, Lani is in
balance at about 20,000 animals. You know, Molokai, he said it's about 60,000. It's out of balance
right now. It seems that's, that seems to be past capacity because my recollection from talking
with you and Mikey and others is there's basically access deer dying on the side of the roads in
Molokai. So it's, it's past that capacity. And then Maui, I think you said was one,
there was 60 on the way to 210. Was that right?
Yeah. So yeah.
What does sustainability look like?
So it's a super nuanced subject because we don't, we don't have the capacity to manage deer on all
lands. So like we talked about, we're not, we're, it's, it's illegal for us to operate on public
land. And honestly, I support that. We don't ever want to affect resource availability for a
subsistence hunter. And anecdotally, we see on public lands on Maui, it's pretty hard to find a
deer. Like, I think there are, like, I think there's a scenario where subsistence hunters play a huge
role in what balance look like. And, but we also don't dictate balance on a private landowners
property either. They own that animal. What we're able to do is say, here's how many animals you
have. You look, we understand how they, what they're doing as a liability, as a function of dry
feed or watersheds or fencing or like our roadways. Oh, what a mess. We say, this is how many animals
you have. How many do you want? And then they say to us, well, let's, let's try and bring this from
6,000 to 2,000 and see what it looks like. And because we're able to manage them with such
precision via these aerial surveys, we're able to toggle that balance based on, like we're going
through a pronounced drought right now. We're bringing down numbers in the areas we're working
in. But one of my favorite things we talk about, like, you know, apart from like these, this vegan
conversation, one of my absolute favorite things is we walk into a meeting with a rancher that is
calling an animal spotted rat and it only presents liability to them, right? Like, of course,
their cowboys enjoy harvesting. Like there's, there's of course value in, in them as a, as
something being able to hunt. By the time we leave that room, that animal has value because our
harvesting process, we pay, it's not a lot, but we pay them a small amount per pound for that animal
so that they find, so that they find value in that animal. And we didn't have to do that.
In other words, it's more valuable for them to let you harvest it humanely than for them to just,
you know, shoot it and leave it, you know, leave it sitting there.
Exactly. So at balance, so in, in varying this balance each year with rainfall and ingress and
all of the different things that happen at balance, the rancher is happy because more importantly,
he has optimal soil health and no runoff and he's not losing feed, but he's also making like,
he's, he's seeing a small amount of additional value from this animal. And that combination,
when we talk about like what balance looks like on a large scale, we have several ranchers that are
saying like, come help us. We just, we're not there yet. We need to grow. So A, we need to like,
grow our harvesting capacity. And we have the system to do that now, but B, we need more people
to eat these animals with us and bring them into their homes. And in, in that scenario, we'll be
able to achieve balance by both growing and then working with all these private landowners. And
each one, that's the best part. Each one's going to make their own choice. That's not up to me to
decide what balance looks like for that family or individual or board or whatever it is. That's up
to the private landowner. What we do know is if we're able to grow large enough and we are able to
operate on most of the private lands, between all of them, we can find a population level that is
also best suited for our community. Because I mean, Molokai is a great example. I mean, Maui is well
right now too, but the lights, like sun goes down. Everybody on that place is doing 10 miles an hour.
There are so many deer on the road. Like the, the, the risks to like hitting a deer is like at those
densities we discussed is profound. And you know, on Maui, you can do 55, 65 miles an hour. So as a
function of like our watershed health and sediment, like the net present value of this species that
balance makes sense. It doesn't make sense to eradicate them. We talked about food security.
I understand this is like a hard conversation too, because we're also the endangered species
capital of the world. So there's, there's a very real conversation. If I was a conservationist,
I would say, get rid of all of these invasive species and let's work to bring back or rehabilitate
the endangered species in these same spaces. Is it even technically feasible, Jake? If,
if the Hawaiian government decided tomorrow, we don't want to single access deer here by 2030,
could that be done technically? No way. They're, they're, they're just,
they're too smart. I mean, we were able to accomplish that because they were in such low numbers.
On the big Island, there's no, I don't believe there's a way to do that. So there's no choice,
but to find balance and balance looks like I support the idea that there shouldn't be deer
in our watersheds. There's nothing more value as an isolated landmass and a community trying to be
self-suspicious, especially through COVID. Like there, we've donated 50,000 pounds of venison,
like over a hundred thousand meals through COVID because food banks were empty. Like,
like Hawaii's economy teeters on absolute disaster because we're so dependent on tourism.
And when COVID hit and we shut the door, like the vast majority of our community was in trouble.
So there, there's, there's this nuance between, yes, like there's ecosystems and ecology we have
to respect and every native species has a right to exist in its own place, but there's also
economics and food security. So it's, it's finding a balance for where these animals should be in the
long run. And that's where we produce food. It's not in our mountain where we depend on water.
That's just my opinion. But yeah, so the conversation of balance isn't just like,
what's the deer density in this particular place? The conversation of balance is like,
how do you interact with all of these things across your communities and ecosystems and all
of these other things? And I think that story about, you know, the, the amount of food that
was donated during COVID is kind of another example of this. I think it's part of why Maui Nui has
been in such high favor with, with local people, because, you know, that's a big step back for a
business that's trying to grow to basically give away, you know, an enormous chunk of its product.
You know, it's one thing if you're Nike and you're, you know, 50 years into your existence and you're
going to give away 5% of your shoes for free or something, this is totally different. But at the
same time, it was sort of a no brainer. Yeah, because it, you know, it basically just meant,
look, we're going to delay the growth of the business by a year and a half, but we're doing
the same thing. And it's, it still serves the same mission, which is you're feeding people
and you're managing a population. Yeah. And you're right. Like there wasn't even like a choice.
And to everybody's credit on the team, because, because people have to, like, we need to grow
at a profitable, healthy margin so we can scale and achieve that mission of balance. But
it was like an overnight, like it was like an instant decision because a hunter can't,
in Hawaii, a hunter can't go harvest an animal and take it into the food bank for a donation.
It's like the, the food safety requirements are far too stringent. And so probably one of the
things we were most proud of is we had created this system and tool that in a time of need
as a function of food security, we could call on it instantly. Yeah. That's the point. Because if
you didn't have that USDA certification already set up, you wouldn't have been able to have,
you could have all the deer in the world. You couldn't do anything with them.
Yeah. And that's not to say subsistence hunters didn't rally to harvest more animals themselves
and get them into the community, but doing so in a, at a, at a recreational or subsistence level
versus a commercial level is like 50,000 pounds of food in eight months is like, that's a lot of,
that's a lot of meat. And that's not possible in, without like systems for food safety and
slaughtering and all the other things that go into it. So as we look to our communities 20 years
from now and either weather instability or governmental, all of the different things that
are happening in our world economy, especially like the conversation of domestic production,
like having it at home in Hawaii and a resource we can always call on, it's important.
And when we look at the total value of access deer for our communities, that's important.
And that all interacts with this idea of balance. Like, and again, there's no perfect answer one way
or the other, but man, were we happy, like rolling two full pallets of venison into the food bank with
an empty freezer. We were just like the boys, you've met the boys. Like you imagine the smile on like
big Eddie's face, who's been like a community member for, you know, 40 years and him being
able to like have this impact at like a time of need. It's awesome. Like you feel amazing.
Jake, this has been, it's been amazing for me to sort of be a minuscule part of this journey
alongside for, you know, a couple of years and getting to know you and, you know, having you
share this story has been great because I've never heard it in one piece and there are even
pieces of this that I hadn't heard before. So I know folks are going to, you know, have their
curiosity peaked by this and maybe some belief systems challenged, but that's, if you're not
doing that, then what are you doing? Yeah, absolutely. And I think you underestimate
the impact you've had. You know, it took us seven years to figure out a harvesting system, but
being able to take that next step in understanding how you move this into somebody's home and what
e-commerce looks like and all of these other things, like the resource you've helped us
find. We would not be here without your help and the rest of the group. And we can't thank you
enough for that. And we're, I mean, we're just excited to see what the next couple of years look
like and how we can move that mission forward and what continued good we can do within our
communities. And yeah, we can't thank you enough, but I really appreciate it.
Well, I need more bone broth because like my wife has pretty much consumed all the bone broth you
said. She doesn't even let me have it anymore. It's sort of like her little secret drink.
So yeah, well, we can, we can make that happen for sure. Thanks brother.
Ah, thank you, Peter. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're
interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that
allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our
goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription. To that end,
membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast
show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The
word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything
episodes, hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on.
If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to
peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram,
Facebook, all with the ID Peteratiamd. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or
whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only,
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare
services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use
of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The
content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any
medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures
and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.