Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Are you ready for another AMA? I am. I see the agenda and I'm going to share my concern
up front, which is I think it's a little ambitious. We're going to attempt to cover two topics,
typically each of which I think is their own AMA. So if by the time we get through
this, it's so big that it is two AMAs, the person listening will say, what were they
talking about? They just covered one topic. So as it stands at this moment, we're going
to attempt to get through both everything that has to do with fat oxidation and fat
flux and all these things you're going to explain in a second. And we're even going
to try to tackle the entire topic of nicotine. So let's see if we can do it.
I feel like ambitious is the right word, but yeah, let's give it a shot. So the first topic
is fat flux. And I think a lot of questions come in about this and there's a few variations
on a theme. So I'll just I'll summarize a few of these questions for you. The first
question is why does an oxidation of fat necessarily mean you're losing total body
fat? If I eat a low carb diet and become a quote fat burning machine, end quote, why
don't I always lose fat on this diet? Another way of saying this too is the question is
if I'm in ketosis, doesn't it mean I'm burning fat? And just for the record, this is this
question came in from ketogenic man inside joke. So look, we get this question in one
form or another constantly. So I think that's why we decided to just dedicate an entire
segment to this because it's super important and it is it's confusing. Right. So just to
be clear, let's just get the punchline out of the way first. You can absolutely be in
ketosis and gain weight. You can absolutely be quote unquote fat burning machine and still
accumulate fat. Let's go one step further and accept the fact that we're going to use
a bit of shorthand here, which is gaining weight and gaining fat. We're going to talk
about interchangeably. Is that fair? Because I mean, when people say I want to lose weight,
what they really mean is I want to lose fat. I mean, when people say I want to gain weight,
they usually mean I want to gain muscle. So if we can simplify this a little bit and say that
people rarely want to lose muscle and gain fat, I think it helps to think about this kind of like
an engineering problem, which is always dangerous in biology because engineering is frankly cleaner
and neater than biology. But I do think that we can simplify this problem without rendering
our simplification unhelpful and in doing so really start to understand the ins and outs of this. So
if we take the example you gave Bob, which is a person who says, hey, you know, I want to lose
excess body fat and the approach I'm taking is a ketogenic diet or some form of low carbohydrate
diet, does it guarantee that I'm going to lose weight? Well, again, let's break it down. We already
said the first thing is losing weight means losing fat. And now let's break that down one step
further. How do you lose fat? So broadly speaking, there would be two approaches to this. One would
be to reduce the total number of fat cells. Another way would be to shrink the fat cells. Now,
the former is most typically something that is done with liposuction. So that's really the way
we lose fat cells is you cut a whole bunch of them out. By the way, there were some interesting
studies that were done a little over a decade ago, one published in the New England Journal of
Medicine that demonstrated that there was a totally different metabolic effect of those two
approaches. So I don't remember the details of it. But basically, one group lost a significant amount
of total body fat having the fat cut out. The other group lost it by, you know, a dietary
intervention that took the same amount of fat off. So at the end, they both had the same body
composition directionally, but one had done it through reducing the number of fat cells, one had
done it by shrinking the fat cells. Can you guess if there was a difference between them, Bob?
I think there might be, although I'm tipped off because I think it was a New England Journal of
Medicine paper. It was. Yeah, it was one of the authors. That's right. And yeah, there's a profound
difference. So we should never confuse the metabolic benefits that come from reducing the
size of adipose tissue with reducing the amount of it. The former, in the case of liposuction,
is really a cosmetic procedure, whereas the latter, of course, is has cosmetic benefits,
but much more importantly, is a metabolic improvement. Okay. So if you accept everything
I just said, then we can simplify this problem into how do you shrink a fat cell? Is that fair?
I think so. All right. So now let's understand the fat cell. And again, let's go back to how an
engineer would think about this. An engineer would think about this by drawing a boundary
around this and looking at the boundary conditions and effectively understanding what goes in and
what comes out. Mass cannot be created from nothing and mass cannot disintegrate into nothing.
So if a fat cell gets larger, there is a net accumulation of fat in that cell relative to how
much goes out of it. And the converse is true. So again, silly example, but if you have a room
and the room has a hundred people in it and there were people traveling in and out of the room
constantly, if you want to understand if that room is increasing or decreasing in the number of people
in it, you need to understand at every point for which there's an entry or exit, what is happening.
And by doing that, you can understand what is the net increase or decrease. And I like to refer to
that as flux. And I won't get into why that's not a technical, technically that's not a perfect
definition of flux, but it's sort of the way my brain works is to sort of borrow that term from
physics and basically say, look, we're going to talk about this through the lens of fat flux. What
is the flux of fatty acid substrate into and out of a fat cell? And can we infer the behavior of that
fat cell in response to that? So I guess before I go on, Bob, I just want to make sure, does that
seem like anything you want to add to that or does that seem like a reasonable way to go after this?
I think that makes sense. A couple of things. So you alluded to it that when we talk about weight
loss or weight gain or fat loss or fat gain, a lot of times we'll hear about calories in, calories
out, right? They amount of basically if more energy is entering the system than leaving it,
the system is getting bigger and vice versa. If more energy is leaving the system than entering
it, it's more or less getting smaller. And what you're talking about is at the level of the adipose
tissue. So we're talking about how much fat is going into the adipose tissue and how much is
being released and also how much is being trapped we'll get to. I think that's important. And the
second thing too is I'm glad that you use the word flux because you have an amazing, I don't know if
you mentioned it, but you have an amazing blog post on this topic, which is the lessons of fat
flux. And when we move your blog posts over to peteratiamd.com and I was privileged to adding
the header images to the blog posts. And in this case, I took the liberty of since you used the
word flux, I have a picture of the flux capacitor in the DeLorean, which I'm sure you know that it's
what makes time travel possible. We could cover that in another episode. It's also an important
concept, but those are a couple of things that I would add.
If we didn't understand fat flux, there would be no flux capacitor. And I mean, Marty might still
actually be in the future in the past. I don't even recall.
Okay. It depends on which one you're watching.
It depends on which version. There you go. Okay. So let's start this discussion with a more
technical look at what I'm talking about. And then I'm going to simplify this. So Bob, I think you
have a great figure of what's actually called white adipose tissue or WAT. And I'll explain
what that is in a moment. But if you don't mind, can you just pull it up and share your screen so
that I can see it and everybody viewing this can also see it. Yes, it is up. Okay. So what going on
in this diagram? First, let's start by why this is called white adipose tissue. So tissue makes
sense adipose fat, but why white? Well, white is to contrast it from brown. So when you're talking
about fat, you always want to differentiate between WAT and BAT. At some point, we will
undoubtedly do a lengthy discussion on BAT. BAT is very interesting. It is a form of adipose tissue
that is not as prevalent as WAT, but it has really unique metabolic properties, namely a higher
concentration of mitochondria and therefore a much greater metabolic activity. Bob, you and I
have spent a ton of time doing our own research on BAT as it pertains to cold adaptation and a
whole bunch of other things around that. So let's back burner that, but I think it's worth coming
back to in another episode. So what we're focusing on is what most people think of when they think
of fat, which is, you know, and again, if anyone's ever watched surgery on TV or something like that,
and, you know, or had a lipoma yanked out of their arm, you can see it's a glistening yellow,
relatively acellular structure. And if you look at under a microscope, it looks surprisingly simple.
So even though, as we now know, white adipose tissue is an endocrine organ, right? It is way
more complicated than it looks under a microscope. Under a light microscope, it looks like a bunch
of nothing. So what you see here, if you look closely, is two sides, right? You have an inside,
and I don't mean inside, I mean an inside, like a going into it side, and you have an outside.
And again, I don't mean an outside, I mean a going outside. So on the left hand side of this drawing,
and by the way, if you're listening to this on audio, I would encourage you to, you know,
sort of watch it on video or a minimum, maybe hit pause and now go and look at the show notes
where you'll see this diagram. But on the left hand side of this page, you could largely think
of this as having two doors, okay? So the upper left door and the lower left door are two ways
that the fat cell gets fatter. And on the right hand side of this page, you have the exit door.
This is how the fat cell gets skinnier. So let's talk about each of these doors.
Thank you for listening to today's sneak peek AMA episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in hearing the complete version of this AMA, you'll want to become a member. We created a
membership program to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
Membership benefits are many and beyond the complete episodes of the AMA each month,
they include the following. Ridiculously comprehensive podcast show notes that detail
every topic, paper, person, and thing we discuss on each episode of The Drive.
Access to our private podcast feed, The Qualies, which were a super short podcast,
typically less than five minutes, released every Tuesday through Friday, which highlight the best
questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is particularly
important for those of you who haven't heard all of the back episodes. It becomes a great way to
go back and filter and decide which ones you want to listen to in detail. Really steep discount
codes for products I use and believe in, but for which I don't get paid to endorse, and benefits
that we continue to add over time. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Lastly, if you're already a member,
but you're hearing this, it means you haven't downloaded our member-only podcast feed where
you can get the full access to the AMA and you don't have to listen to this. You can download
that at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash members. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.