Hey, everyone, welcome to the drive podcast.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Peter, it's really great to have you back again.
Every time you and I sit down, whether it's on the podcast or just on the
phone, I get the sense we could go on for hours.
Um, I want to really talk about a bunch of things today, but I want to start our
discussion with a broader topic than just Corona virus or SARS-CoV-2, COVID,
things like that, which I know is a topic you are still front lines on.
And, uh, I don't think a day goes by that you're not being, uh, sought
after for your opinion on things.
And we will certainly get to many of those things later today.
But I, but again, I want to start with a topic that was near and dear to your
heart long before the Corona virus emerged in this fashion, which is the
topic of vaccines and vaccine safety.
Now, recently I had Brian Deere on the podcast and I think for many people,
it was an illuminating discussion.
Um, because, you know, Brian himself is not particularly a vaccine advocate.
He's very clear about that.
He's just an advocate for good science.
And I think his, his work, uh, uncovering the web of lies and, uh, deceit surrounding
the work of, uh, Andrew Wakefield is, is really unparalleled, especially when one
considers the depths to which it was scrutinized both scientifically and even
in the court of law.
Um, so I think the first thing I really want to understand Peter is why is it
that after the complete, um, debunking of everything that Andrew Wakefield did
said published, et cetera, why is this still an issue?
Why is it that in a post Andrew Wakefield world, most polls would suggest
somewhere on the neighborhood, correct me if I'm wrong, 20% of, uh, Americans
still believe there's a relationship between vaccines and autism.
Yeah, I think what, what's happened, and it's actually a very profound question.
And I agree, Brian's work was extremely important and, and then the scientific
community came in in a big way, debunking all of the assertions.
And one of the things about the anti-vaccine lobby that it spawned or that
it ignited, at least in the modern sense is that they kept from then on, they kept
on moving the goalposts.
So it began in its modern form, uh, in 1998 with the Wakefield paper asserting
that measles, mumps, rubella vaccine causes autism by repli- the live virus
vaccine replicating in the colon.
The scientific community respond in a very vigorous, robust way, publishing
multiple papers, large cohort studies showing that kids who were autistic, and I
got involved in it cause I have a daughter with autism and, you know, kids who are autistic
are no more likely to have gotten the MMR vaccine than kids who were not.
And similarly, kids who get the MMR vaccines are no more likely to become
autistic than kids who don't and really sound epidemiologic studies, but then they
switched, they flipped, they said, okay, well, it's not really MMR.
Vaccine, they had Robert F.
Kennedy and a group of people saying it's the thimerosal preservative in vaccine.
And then it switched again to spacing vaccines too close together.
Then switched again to alumin vaccines.
And now what you're starting to see is even shifting away a bit from autism saying
that vaccines cause something called chronic illness or looking at the HPV vaccine for
cervical cancer and other cancers.
And then seeing it causes infertility or miscarriages.
And each time the scientific community responds.
And what they do is to maintain momentum, to reenergize, they keep on shifting.
And the concern for me now is they're not even looking at this from a pseudoscience
point of view.
What they're now focusing on is the politicization of it.
So with this, and we'll talk more about it, but it's starting around 2014, 2015, they
managed to glom onto the Republican Tea Party and to make it a politicized movement around
these concepts of health freedom and medical freedom.
And that's what we're dealing with today now.
And that's why you've got all the craziness on Fox News the last four or five nights with
Tucker Carlson going on this rant against vaccines and Laura Ingraham going on this rant
against me and Tony Fauci.
And so this is a problem in that they have this adaptability and they create these versions
1.0, 2.0, 3.0 of the anti-vaccine movement.
But the autism piece never entirely left.
That's still its legacy fake assertion that still haunts us today.
Well, I mean, I think given how deep Brian went into the discussion specifically of MMR
and autism, that relationship, I don't think anything else needs to be said on that topic.
And obviously for anybody who's listening to this that still has questions around that,
I would highly recommend that they go back and watch that video, listen to that podcast,
read the book and truthfully, and I don't say this to be, I don't know how to say this
delicately, but I think if after assimilating all of that work, you still believe that there's
a relationship between that vaccine and autism, there's probably nothing that can be said
that can dissuade you from that.
And I would just leave it at that and agree to disagree.
But let's focus on some of the other things that you've brought up.
Do you have a preference for where you'd like to begin?
Would you like to start with thimerosal?
Yeah, I mean, you can, but it always comes down to the same few things.
I mean, what happens is each time the scientific, and in the case of both Brian Deere and the
MMR, in addition to the scientific community refuting it on the basis of large cohort studies
and prospective studies, what he was able to do was show nefarious intent, which was
extremely helpful because knowing that what's happened since then is the anti-vaccine movement
has grown so much larger than Wakefield.
Now you've got dedicated anti-vaccine groups, national anti-vaccine groups like Children's
Health Defense and ICANN and those kinds of things.
But then you also have local political action committees, PACs, that are linked to far right
wing extremism.
So it's become this very complicated ecosystem or web, and now it's even gone beyond the
United States.
So yeah, I mean, we could go into why thimerosal is not linked to autism, and then we could
go into why spacing vaccines is not related to autism or what autism is and how it begins
in early fetal brain development.
But it won't stop the momentum of the anti-vaccine movement because they light a fire, they cause
damage and then they move on, and that's their modus operandi.
Yeah, I don't disagree with that, Peter.
I guess the way I think about the role I'd like us to play in this discussion is I don't
think we're here to stop the anti-vaccine movement.
What I'd like to do is help parents who frankly are inundated with information and can't distinguish
between signal and noise, at least come to a place where we can have an honest discussion
about it.
Because I really do want to have that discussion, and I think the order in which you actually
just went through them is a very elegant way to talk about this, right?
Which is let's spend a few minutes on thimerosal, let's spend a few minutes on some of these
other claims, and then let's actually talk about autism because there is no denying the
fact that the incidence and prevalence of autism are increasing.
And we should talk about what some of the plausible reasons for that are and why the
scientific community has been able to rule out these claims that are being put forth.
Because again, I have great empathy for the parent who's listening to this, who is confused.
And that doesn't necessarily mean just the parents of children with autism, but that's
the parent who's trying to decide, what am I supposed to do here?
Am I supposed to get my kid vaccinated?
And am I supposed to get them vaccinated at this pace?
Does my kid really need 3H or hep C, pardon me, hep B vaccines in the span of six months?
And so I think just having an open, honest discussion about that is by no means going
to dissuade the 20% of people who are clearly in the camp that says vaccines are evil.
But I do believe that there's a very confused group of people in the middle, and I hope
we can talk about that.
So is it safe to say that post Wakefield, because I'm trying to go back and remember
the timeline, it was around 2007, 2008, that every claim of Wakefield had been pretty
much debunked, correct?
And to your point, it wasn't just debunked scientifically, but it had been made clear
that he had lied and he had manipulated data, as had O'Leary, and this was one big house
of cards.
Yeah, the Lancet paper was retracted, I think, in 2010.
Okay, 2010.
Although I think there was an expression of concern put out by the Lancet a few years
before the maybe 2004, I can't remember exactly.
And the basis for the retraction is, they didn't really spell it out that much.
They basically said the results are no longer valid.
I don't think the retraction letter issued by the Lancet went into all of the investigation
that the medical counsel had done and for Wakefield to be struck off the register.
I don't think the retraction mentioned anything about the Brian Deer paper.
Yeah, I think it was Deer's reporting.
And frankly, the most damning evidence was the lawsuits, right?
It was the complete inability of Wakefield to maintain any legal argument against the
people who were accusing him of fraud.
And so let's put that aside and let's move forward.
Let's start by telling people what thimerosal is and what is it doing in a vaccine?
Well first of all, thimerosal is really not in childhood vaccines anymore.
No, but what was it?
There is a flu vaccine.
So what happens is if you're giving vaccines in multiple, if you have a multidose vial
of vaccines whereby you've got a vial of vaccine that could be given to six or seven or 20
people, each time you're introducing a needle into that vial through a rubber stopper, potentially
you're introducing bacteria.
And the worry is that if you do that enough that there could be some bacterial growth
or overgrowth into the vial.
So you need to put some preservative in to that's non-toxic that could be, that will
kill the bacteria.
And when thimerosal was discovered, it was considered quite an advance in terms of allowing
you to vaccinate large populations.
And the bottom line was it was taken out, the manufacturers took it out of the vials
just because of all the bad publicity swarming around it.
There was never evidence to show that it was a problem, but I think the thinking was that
we don't really need it.
We can give single dose vials instead.
Let's just take it off the table.
And in fact, that was done there still.
Some of the flu vaccines still have thimerosal in the US, but I think that that's about,
not all of them, you can still get a single dose vial for flu vaccine and take that as
well.
But there was never ever any shown association between thimerosal and any untoward effect
in terms, certainly in terms of autism.
Thimerosal was one of the big push, one of the big pushes from Bobby Kennedy Jr., correct?
Wasn't this really his initial cause and his initial fight?
I think so.
I think he got into it because he's an environmental law attorney and looks at toxic waste.
And I think when he saw the mercury word, he probably got a link to Minamata disease,
which is remember back in Japan several decades ago, there was a lot of mercury exposure in
fish and young kids who were exposed to what's called methylmercury, either during pregnancy,
I think it was during pregnancy, the kids that were born were born with intellectual
deficits.
And that was a syndrome associated with it, was called Minamata disease.
And so I think probably people in his camp put two and two together and they said, well,
probably autism must be some form of Minamata disease, even though it's not the same, maybe
there's enough there that it could be due to thimerosal.
But again, the large cohort studies showed absolutely no linkage with autism.
And ultimately we know why is because we know autism is associated with prenatal events
that it's just we have, well, we could talk about it.
Yeah, we'll come to that.
But that's the, that's how he got involved.
And there were books about it.
There were a couple of books making these assertions.
And it also, and then once again, it started gaining a lot of momentum, very much like
the way Wakefield did a decade before.
And I think the first publication, which I write about in my book, Vaccines Did Not
Cause Rachel's Autism, kind of points that out.
I should get the book in front of me.
I could read it right to you.
Hold on.
This is the book, the last, not this book I published, but the last one.
It's called Vaccines Did Not Cause Rachel's Autism.
And I go into it a bit.
And while you're looking for that, Peter, I'll just clarify for listeners the difference
between methyl mercury, organic mercury, inorganic mercury, because you made the point
that thimerosal is a form, it's an organic mercury.
And there's sort of a difference between organic and inorganic mercury, right?
That's correct.
And most of the toxicity that we see when people are over consuming fish that are high
on the food chain, such as large tuna, swordfish, shark, is organic mercury.
It is methyl mercury, not inorganic mercury.
Right.
So Minamata disease, which was named after a city in Japan, it resulted from a chemical
plants industrial release of methyl mercury, which is different from thimerosal, which
is a totally different compound.
It's ethyl mercury.
And it was in wastewater, and it accumulated in a bay where fish and shellfish lived and
were consumed as seafood.
And large scale methyl mercury ingestions in pregnant mothers caused a congenital syndrome
causing neurologic disease in the form of gait motor disturbances, in some cases even
coma and death.
And so there was a paper that was published at that time in a journal called Medical Hypotheses
that first proposed that maybe autism could be related to thimerosal, because even though
it's not methyl mercury, maybe it's ethyl mercury doing this.
And that was in 2001 that the paper got published, so three years after the Wakefield assertion.
And so this was a pretty common preservative, but then it was subsequently taken out.
And what was interesting is even after it was taken out, the rates of autism never went
down.
That's pretty clear.
And there were again, large cohort studies showing absolutely no link with thimerosal.
And all of that said, Peter, I certainly wouldn't want to suggest that the paper in 2001 and
even the work that followed was anything but reasonable.
I mean, that's the purpose of medicine, right?
I mean, you see something like autism, you look for plausible associations, and you see
a neurologic disease that is associated with mercury.
It's entirely reasonable to formulate a hypothesis that says this other thing that looks kind
of like it could be it.
Yeah.
And the paper was published in a journal called Medical Hypotheses.
Exactly.
I mean, it's completely reasonable.
It's the stuff that follows that's challenging, right?
It's after the scientific community goes to great lengths and great attempts to seek the
truth and publishes paper after paper after paper and mainstream scientific journals,
that the anti-vaccine groups refuse to acknowledge its cling to their debunked hypothesis.
And their only response is, well, the scientists must be paid off by the pharma companies or
the journals must be paid off by the pharma companies or the editors must be paid off
by the pharma companies.
And so they resort to conspiracies rather than, okay, I get it.
Let's move on.
Let's try to figure out what really causes autism.
And they've never shown that intellectual curiosity about what really does cause autism,
and they continually discount the massive amount of scientific work that's gone into
really uncovering what autism is.
Or we get into kind of the deeper why, because that's a big part of what I want to understand.
And there's two deep whys here, run around autism and one around this sort of latent
distrust and the path that any two individuals can, you know, there's a fork in the road,
right, where one person can be very influenced by data.
They can think sort of probabilistically, they can think in terms of uncertainty, they
can accept and reason their way through these things.
And then there's another person who's going to cling to a belief in the presence of emerging
data that refute that hypothesis and they'll continue to come up with an excuse.
And I really want to try hard not to pass a moral judgment in either case, but there's
clearly an anti-science sentiment that is growing and that is fostering this.
Before we get to that, let's go to the next point, which is, Thimerosal I believe was
electively removed in about two, like very early in the 2000s, right?
It was-
I think it was actually removed two years before the medical hypothesis paper.
I think it was removed in 1999 actually, or at least it was, that process was started.
So it had already been underway.
So what was the next position of the goalpost after Thimerosal?
So then it was this concept of greening our vaccines or making them more, I don't know
why they use the word green, I guess, making them more eco-friendly.
And that the third major hypothesis was that kids were becoming autistic because of antigen
overload, that somehow they were getting too many vaccines at once.
This was overwhelming the immune system and somehow that led to autism, which again, never
made a lot of sense to me how something, because in an- and they say it's leading to inflammation.
And I always would point out that we've seen what the brains of kids on the autism spectrum
looks like.
I've seen my own daughters, CT and MRI scans in her workup of autism.
And we know what inflammation looks like.
You can see inflammation on a- or evidence of inflammation or at least blood on a CT
or MRI.
And we know what herpes encephalitis looks like and autism doesn't do that.
It's not an inflammatory state of the brain.
And so that one never made any sense either.
And then there were several other people who came into this, people like the pediatrician,
Dr. Bob Seer started writing books about how we have to space vaccines further apart and
had written a number of books about that as well.
But again, it- well, first it never had plausibility and- but that's still out there today.
And if you go on amazon.com and look at books on vaccinations, I think those books are still
top sellers.
Now, in the case of thimerosal, at least there was a plausible explanation that was put forth
as a hypothesis.
When the hypothesis for spacing was put forth, was there some epidemiologic data that suggested
this?
I'm not aware of it.
And the problem was, we didn't have clinical trial data to support the spacing of the vaccines.
The protocol, the current vaccine regimen, the schedule, is based on years and years
of studies confirming immunogenicity and protection.
It's also based on years and years of studies showing that there's no immunological interference.
In other words, if you give a pair of two vaccines together, that one doesn't interfere
with the other.
So, you're very carefully orchestrated dance.
And then these guys come in with these WACO schedules without any scientific basis.
And then, you know, it forces the scientific community to try to reevaluate whether you're
still getting the same immunogenicity or not, and also the immunological interference.
So in addition, so it's not just a matter of saying, well, what difference does it make
because kids are getting the same vaccines.
It's unclear whether they're going to be just as effective or safe as the, as that
very carefully orchestrated dance that was developed jointly by the FDA and CDC.
That's a very interesting point, Peter, and frankly, not one I'd ever considered.
I get asked not infrequently by patients about vaccinating their children on the schedule.
And these are not people who think vaccines are causing autism, but they do have some
concern presumably just based on things that they've read, heard, et cetera, that say,
hey, does my kid really need to have all of these shots in the first nine months of life?
And their belief, which is not unreasonable, is isn't this just a way to ensure kids get
their vaccines?
Because during the first year of life, the parent is so much more likely to come in for
well baby checks and, you know, they're going to have much more frequent contact with their
pediatrician and that that's the reason that this schedule is being imposed on us as opposed
to any really biologically necessary.
Again, I use the example of Hep B, which, you know, most kids are really not at risk
of Hep B, right?
Unless they're, you know.
Well, let me give you a different H disease as an example.
So Haemophilus influenza type B, it's a bacterial cause of meningitis.
Back in the Pleistocene era when I was a house officer, I was a pediatric house officer
at Mass General, in 87, 88, I would be admitting a kid with Haemophilus influenza type B meningitis
to my service every couple of weeks.
And Mass General was one of the oldest pediatric residencies.
They called it the children's service.
And back then, you know, the house officer did everything.
You had to do the lumbar puncture.
You had to look at the cerebral spinal fluid.
Under the microscope, you had to do the Gram stain and eventually sent to the lab, but
to confirm it.
But you would basically make the diagnosis right then and there.
And when you did it, your heart sank because you knew that there was a high likelihood
that kid was going to have permanent neurologic injury or might not even survive.
And it took a big emotional toll on me and my fellow house staff to have these young,
you know, healthy infants now get Haemophilus influenza type B meningitis.
And at that time, we didn't have a vaccine that worked in infants.
There was the capsule of the Haemophilus influenza type B, the polyribophosphate capsule, but
it was shown that it wasn't immunogenic in infants.
So it was still licensed as a vaccine for older kids to catch the few older kids that
could still make an immune response, but it didn't work in infants.
Why is that, by the way?
Because you needed, it turns out, you need to haptenize it onto protein.
And that's what John Robinson, Rachel Schneerson did at the National Institute of Child Health
and Development, NIH, they figured that out and developed a conjugate vaccine that now
worked in infants, which now you could start vaccinating.
But until at that time, you didn't have anything that worked in young infants.
So all you could do at that time is take a prophylactic antibiotic called rifampicin,
which had the unpleasant effect of turning your urine orange and reddish orange.
And and at that time, I had my first son born Matthew and we were living right across
the street from Mass General.
And I was terrified that I was going to bring Haemophilus influenza type B home.
So I took rifampicin all the time and I peed orange for two years practically to the point
where one of the first and only fights I've ever had with Anne was my wife was permanent.
And she accused me of permanently staining the toilet bowl orange because I was taking
that antimicrobial.
And then this miracle occurred.
The miracle was, you know, John Robinson, Rachelle Schneerson, also David Smith and
Porter Anderson in Rochester figured out that if they attach that polyribophosphate capsule
to protein and haptenize it, now you get T cell responses in infants and it works.
And that happened.
That vaccine was licensed in 1989 as I was finishing my house off-retro training for
infants, for young infants.
And now it's part of that early vaccination schedule.
By the time I finished my, then I went to Yale for my pediatric infectious disease fellowship.
I had a lab there and then I was a junior attending at Yale Children's Hospital.
By the time I started rounding as an attending two years later, the disease was gone.
It basically, I taught the house staff about it purely for historical interest, just like
the old guys at Mass General taught me about diphtheria and tetanus.
That's how dramatic it was because we added it to the infant schedule.
And I think that's a good example of, you know, these infant vaccines.
You know, to get a vaccine through, to be licensed by the FDA, you know, to file that
biologics license application for those very expensive.
Second, it's a hot, lots of review.
It has to go through the biologic license process of the FDA.
It's got to go through the VRPAC committee of the FDA for review.
It then goes to the Centers for Disease Control and the ICIP, the Advisory Committee and Immunization
Practices.
There's a lot of smart people that are looking at all of this to say, do we really need this?
What's the cost effectiveness?
What's the benefit to society?
What's the benefit to child health?
So these are not decisions that are made lightly or, you know, these are things which are carefully
thought out.
So you don't think that there's some consideration given to this is a window in which the probability
of vaccination is greater just due to exposure.
Again, I bring up Hep B just because, you know, you and I didn't get our Hep B vaccines
until we were adults, right?
And of course, I don't know when you got yours, but for me, I think I got it in medical school.
It was just in time given our exposure to Hep B is enormous once you're in the medical
system because it's, you know, it's transmitted just like HIV.
And depending on where you trained, you might be in a population.
I think I first got mine when I was, we were keeping 11 Shanghai in China for parasitic
diseases.
And I think going off to China frequently, there's a lot of Hepatitis B, I think that
may have been when I got mine.
But you're right.
Back then, you know, we weren't giving it to infants.
And so I guess my question is, and again, I'm just saying this to try to take the side
of the parent, right?
I'm trying to put myself in the shoes of the parent who says this is too much.
And again, to be clear, this is not the parent who says vaccines are evil.
My kid will never get vaccinated.
This is the parent who's saying, is this a little too much too soon?
Does a child really need a Hep B vaccine as an infant?
What is the probability that a child will be exposed to Hepatitis B?
The only example I can think of is a child whose parent is in the healthcare system or
frankly in the, you know, is an IV drug user who is, who is themselves a high risk for
Hep B and who is not vaccinated.
But outside of that, you could certainly make the case that a person does not need a Hep
B vaccine until they're, you know, an adolescent or at least a, you know, a youngster in school,
correct?
Right.
But let's take a step back.
Let's look at that example of the homophilus influenza type B. No doubt, no question in
your mind that that's what we needed to do.
Absolutely.
Especially given the risk is highest to that patient.
I mean, that's an amazing example of that, right?
Right.
So, so the vast majority of vaccines are not given for trivial reasons or no vaccine is
given for a trivial reason.
No, no.
And Hep B would not be trivial.
The need is, the need is more apparent for some than the others.
The exact reason why Hepatitis B was selected for young infants, you know, I wasn't, I wasn't
at the table when that decision was made.
It may be that there was enough at risk populations that it's very hard to cherry pick individuals
when there's so many people who absolutely need it, that, that it just becomes easier
to vaccinate the whole population rather than say, okay, well, you're in a specific at risk
ethnic group or you're in a specific at risk occupational hazard.
On the other hand, when you look at what that vaccine is, it, you know, it's, it's a, about
as low risk of vaccine as you can imagine.
It's a recombinant.
And we, we make vaccines like this all the time.
It's a recombinant protein vaccine produced in yeast.
It's been around almost four decades.
It's been given the hundreds of millions of children with a really fabulous safety record.
So you know, is, are you, what are you losing?
I guess is the, is the other way to put it.
Right.
Let's talk a little bit about HPV.
This is some people hailed this vaccine as a miracle given the relationship between the
human papilloma virus, at least three strains of the human papilloma virus and cervical
cancer.
This is not an insignificant cancer for women.
Sadly, many of us know women who have either died as a result of this disease or have been
who have lost their reproductive capacity as a result of this disease.
So and furthermore, I think many men might even know the anxiety that a, that a pap smear
has caused their partner if it has shown one of the high risk strains, you know, 16, 18,
a number of these things.
So I, I, I think for many of us when the HP vaccine came along, it was a really big deal.
I mean, this was, this was fantastic news.
Can you talk through some of the controversy surrounding it both from a scientific standpoint,
but also from a moral, ethical, religious, political standpoint?
Cause I think that to me, HPV might be one of the best examples of the intersection of
all of those forces.
Yeah.
So it came, you know, it was, it was about preventing this.
So HPV induced cancers like cervical cancer, laryngeal cancers are predominantly sexually
transmitted cancers there.
So if you look at infectious causes of cancer, roughly about 16% of all cancers are caused
by infectious disease agents like hepatitis B, like, like HPV.
And the numbers go up all the time because we get better and better at discovering infectious
agents that cause cancer.
So in Africa, about a third of the cancers are of infectious origin.
And this was developed by a group at the National Cancer Institute, including someone who's
very dear to me, Doug Lowry.
And they were able to show that vaccinating against this virus would, can prevent infection
of the virus and therefore will likely prevent cancer.
And now new studies have shown indeed it's born out that indeed it does prevent cervical
cancer.
And on a daily basis, the Australian government has now launched a program where they think
they can eliminate cervical cancer from the continent of Australia by 2030.
So that's really exciting to actually eliminate a cancer through, through the vaccination
process.
The issue has come up, you have to vaccinate originally, it was mainly focused on cervical
cancers rather than the cancers and that would develop in males.
And so the recommendation was you want to have those girls vaccinated before their sexual
debut before they start having intercourse as they get to be teenagers or young adults.
And so you want to get them when they're nine or 10 year old little girls in time to make
certain that everybody gets, gets vaccinated.
And I think that, that did not go over well with a lot of people because they now realized,
you know, they're, they're a nice little nine, 10 year old girl is one day going to be a
woman who is sexually active.
And I think that was, that was hard for some people.
But in fact, it has a remarkable ability of saving lives and, and preventing cervical
cancer.
And that's why Australia has been implementing that in the US.
In contrast, what's happened is we've allowed we have, we have, well, we have a couple of
problems.
First of all, we're a big country.
The the access to the vaccine is not everything we'd like in rural areas.
It's not everything we'd like, especially among underrepresented minorities.
And so there's a, there's an access issue.
But the other big thing is this has been targeted now by the anti-vaccine lobby.
And they have tried to come up with fake assertion after fake assertion that's not supported
by the scientific data.
So they claimed it was causing autoimmunity.
They claimed it's causing mis- they linked a lot of it to female reproductive health
issues.
They said it was causing infertility.
It was causing miscarriage.
And again, one by one, the scientific community had to do those big cohort studies to refute
all of those links.
I guess this is as good a time as any, Peter, to ask the first of several meta questions,
which is why.
Wait, you didn't give me feedback.
So was that convincing or, or, or were you still unimpressed?
I mean, I mean, what do you think the issue is?
No, I, I, I think that's a great point.
And I say that as a father of a 12 year old, right?
A 12 year old girl, which again, I, I, I was just sort of joking with my mom this morning.
I, I, you know how your iPhone will give you, it'll give you like a flashback picture or
video from some time in the past.
And so this, this morning it sent me a video of my daughter when she was, well, she would
have been seven and her brother, her young, her, the next guy would have been one.
So seven year old and one year old and there was the beach playing.
And it's like the cutest thing on the face of the earth.
And I probably watched the video like seven times and then I sent it to my mom and I said,
I'll remember when she was this little, you know, my mom made some comment like, yeah,
enjoy it now.
Cause you know, five, six years she's going to be in college and blah, blah, blah.
So I get that.
There is nothing to me that is both simultaneously amazing and sad as the, the, the, the natural
loss of a game of tug of war that goes on between a parent and a child, right?
As my friend Rick Elias described it, you're, you're playing tug of war and you have to
lose by the time the kid's about 18.
It's slow, but you got to, you know, so, so I can see that like I, I have, I, I, again,
I'm trying to put myself in the shoes of the person who thinks this doesn't make sense.
And I think there's an argument that they would make that would say, well, I don't want
my child.
I don't want my daughter.
Let's just, again, I think this, this is an important issue that we should explain why
both male and female, it's relevant to both.
But if we're just taking it through the lens that I think it first came through, which
is my daughter is 12, I do not want her to be sexually active until she is, when I come
up with some arbitrary age, like 18.
Or I am not going to have her vaccinated until she's 18.
Another point of view is in an ideal world, I would prefer she's not sexually active until
she's mature enough to handle that.
I don't know when that is, but it sure as hell isn't 12.
Therefore I don't want her to get, I don't want her to have this vaccine at 12, but the
downside of, of not vaccinating her in time is she could be cursed with a lifetime of,
of asymmetry, right?
There's an asymmetric bet here and it's, it's, it's, I just, I can understand why some parents
might struggle with that, even though I tend to think in terms of risk and probabilities,
maybe more than the average person.
Right, right.
I totally agree with everything you've said.
I think the problem now is that you've got these anti-vaccine groups specifically targeting
HPV, including I think now you've got children's, I forget which it is, whether it's Kennedy
or this organization is now, I saw it on his Twitter, he's filing some big class action
suit against Merck and company for the HPV vaccine.
What's the claim?
I don't remember, but you know, again, this is, this is what's going on right now.
And with, you know, I'm not aware of any evidence to support all of these things like infertility
or miscarriages or autoimmunity.
What's really interesting also is the anti-vaccine groups have now copy pasted those assertions
onto the COVID-19 vaccine.
So they could be pretty lazy.
So they're just basically saying the same thing they did with, because I guess it works
for them that in that Pyrrhic way.
So but, but as a result of that are, and like I said, it's not the only thing because we
have access and rural and underrepresented minority groups.
But you know, we're going the wrong way with HPV vaccine.
We're not even close to thinking about creating a cervical cancer elimination strategy.
You mentioned laryngeal cancer as well.
I don't think enough people understand the threat of that.
Frankly, all upper airway cancer, right?
I mean, you're talking about cancers of the soft palate.
You're talking about lots of head and neck cancers are on the rise.
I can't remember exactly the stat, but I want to say like the second or third largest
growing cancer in young men is head and neck cancer on account of sexually transmitted
disease.
Yeah.
And if you talk to, you know, the head and neck surgeons, we're right next to MD Anderson
Cancer Center and within this Texas Medical Center, it's devastating.
The very aggressive surgeries that you have to do.
It's really heartbreaking.
By the way, we never finished the one thing about the autism, which was you made the statement
autism is on the rise.
I think it's important to clarify that.
I think we're clearly getting better at diagnosing autism.
I'm not convinced that the incidence of autism is truly increasing.
Yeah.
And we're going to, we'll talk about it in detail.
I've got, yeah, there's a lot of when I come back to an autism, we're not abandoning that.
But thank you for clarifying that.
So yeah, coming back to this point I wanted to make, which is meta question number one.
Why do call it 20% of the population and an entire cottage industry of lobbies, you know,
lobbying groups, packs, et cetera, come out so hard against this one class of drug, whereas
we don't see it for antibiotics, right?
Where are the 20% of people who think penicillin is evil and the companies that make Zofran
or you're not Zofran, but you know, pick your favorite.
Yeah.
Or similarly, like where are the companies that are coming out against insulin, exogenous
insulin that all these diabetics are using?
Because look, I'm going to be a skeptic for a moment.
I don't think there's a greater mismatch between drug companies doing wrong and profiting
and overcharging patients for a medication than insulin.
Like I think the economics of insulin are an embarrassment to how pharma works.
Where's the rage?
Like where are the 20% of Americans that aren't losing their mind over what Novo Nordisk is
doing?
Yeah.
What is it about vaccines in particular that brings out so much ire, so much skepticism
and so much anti-science rhetoric?
I think, well, I don't know that I have all the answers, but I think part of it is the
fact that you're giving vaccines to, not for all, not in all cases, but in most cases,
you're giving vaccines to well individuals to prevent them from getting sick.
So you're giving something that's not always intuitively obvious that they need because
as opposed to insulin, as opposed to penicillin, somebody is sick and somebody needs a treatment.
So this is being so that you understand, but for a vaccine, you're preventing somebody
from getting sick.
And I think that simple feature is a big component of it.
I think the other is the fact that so many vaccines are mandatory for school entry.
So there's that kind of loss of choice that you feel it's being imposed on you.
And so those two things become pretty easy to exploit.
Unless you've got really strong vaccine advocacy activities in your community, it's pretty
easy for an anti-vaccine group to cherry pick those two things.
And then when you have conditions like autism and people want to understand how did this
happen, particularly the regressive form where kids seem to be developing normally and have
normal milestones and then regress, this is easy pickings for an anti-vaccine group to
come along.
So as an example, if...
So for instance, back in the 1900s in the UK, they started anti-compulsory vaccination
leaks and this extended to the US.
So I think it's a combination of the fact that they're preventative, not therapeutic,
and the mandate component.
And I think those two are a toxic mix that get people...
Some people upset about vaccines, particularly in this environment, which now dominates the
internet.
I mean, in the past when you had an anti-compulsory vaccination leak, you could go to your physician,
the physician would explain why that's all nonsense and why you should get vaccinated.
Now we've got something called the internet.
Now we've got something called social media that dominates our lives.
And you've got Amazon now as the single largest promoter of fake anti-vaccine COVID conspiracy
books.
So most of the information you're getting now on a daily basis is actually anti-vaccine,
anti-science information.
But again, I'm still trying to understand why the disdain for science is so prevalent.
So hear me out on another thought experiment.
If the president says, I want to...
I'm using this because it's the current example.
If the president says, I have a legislative agenda that's going to propose a multi-trillion
dollar infrastructure bill, you may not think that's the best idea.
Well, you're going to oppose that through legislative action.
You're going to oppose that through lobbying.
Maybe that's not a great example.
I guess what I'm trying to get at is why...
If you're opposed to vaccines, I can at least understand the argument around medical freedom
because you could at least stand up and say, look, I'm opposed to being told I have to
take a drug to prevent an illness I don't have.
And then you could at least argue the merits of the individual versus society.
To me, that's a more palatable argument.
But the complete anti-science part, maybe because I'm a scientist, is just harder for
me to empathize with.
It's harder for me to put myself in those footsteps because I can't think that way.
But I want to because I think it's important to be able to think that way and not be dismissive
of it if that makes sense.
Yeah.
So here's what I think happened, which is I think maybe because of my activities and
I'm not alone.
Others were involved in this.
There was a lot of effort to debunk the links between vaccines and autism and HPV vaccine
and all the craziness that they asserted it caused.
And I think it was taking some steam out of the anti-vaccine movement.
But you still had enough parents in places like Orange County that were scared about
vaccines causing autism that it allowed a measles epidemic to erupt.
And it was a pretty bad epidemic in Orange County end of 2014, 2015.
It was linked, I think the origins may have been Disneyland where the epidemic came from.
What happened was the California legislature responded appropriately, I think, and said,
you know what?
We're allowing these vaccine exemptions, but it's getting out of hand.
And now it's causing a measles epidemic.
And measles is a bad actor, right?
It's got a significant mortality and permanent disability, deafness and other things.
And they shut down the vaccine exemption.
And I think that helped re-energize the anti-vaccine movement because I think they were losing
some steam around autism.
And they saw this as an opportunity to rebuild, to reinvent themselves.
And they reinvented themselves as a political movement around health freedom, medical freedom.
And that's, and it really amplified in Texas.
So where I am, and it took off with, they created political action committees like Texans
for Vaccine Choice.
It started getting, and the PACs started getting other PAC money and they, the PACs were giving
PACs the other PACs money.
And so there was a lot of money flowing and it was very powerful.
And they were able to convince the Republican Tea Party in Texas, which is a very powerful
group to adopt this issue as a platform issue.
And that's when it really started to accelerate.
And you started to see PACs form not only in Texas, but also in Oklahoma, other Western
States as well.
So it was more of a Western state phenomenon than anywhere else.
And so your political allegiance, your identity actually became tied to not vaccinating your
kid or to be skeptical of vaccines.
And then it all really blew up last year because those same anti-vaccine groups then
started going up against masks and social distancing again under this health freedom,
medical freedom banner.
And now it became a full on anti-science movement.
And you really saw this happen starting in around last summer when the epidemic moved
into the Southern States and people showed their political allegiance to the Republican
Party by defying masks and social distancing.
And then it went up in the upper Midwest as well.
And you had that story, that awful story of the ICU nurse in tears being interviewed,
talking about one of her ICU patients who's dying, words were COVID-19 is a hoax.
So that's when you started to see this kind of mainstreaming of what was a fringe group
around health freedom, medical freedom in 2015, and now become a major platform of the
Republican Party going up against science.
And then you saw the targeting of scientists.
That's when they began really going after Tony, Dr. Fauci, they began going after Bill
Gates.
They started going after me quite a bit.
And now this thing is steamrolling.
You had Tucker Carlson last week going on this whole rant about vaccines and questioning
vaccines and Laura Ingraham at Fox News went after me a couple of nights ago.
Specifically saying what, you have to forgive me if I don't follow this stuff too closely.
Yeah, well, it's pretty unpalatable stuff.
They would say that we misled the public, that we got it wrong, that we didn't understand
the epidemic, and then they would parade out all the great Barrington stuff about no lockdowns.
Even though none of us ever said lockdowns, they create these straw men that say we're
trying to lock everybody down and we're hurting our economy.
And along with that, they're saying that what's going on with these vaccines?
And so tying, and again, this is a throwback to 2015 when it was first linked to political
extremism on the far right.
So what was started out as an anti-vaccine movement is now a movement against any kind
of public health intervention and demonizing scientists and basically calling us the boogeyman
in that.
And it's continuing now.
This was exported last summer to Europe.
You had these anti-mask, anti-vaccine protests, which for the first time used that same American
language in Berlin and Paris and Trafalgar Square in London.
You had the New York Times reporting how it's linked to QAnon and other far right wing extremist
groups.
And so this really concerns me.
And then of course, to make it all the more complicated is the fact that now you've got
the US and British intelligence talking about Putin's government has been lobbying this
whole program of what's being called weaponized health communication on our internet in order
to destabilize the country and destabilize other democracies.
And so what was kind of a fringe group arising out of the Tea Party in Texas is now, I don't
know what you want to call it, whether it's an anti-science empire or confederacy that
has lots of moving parts to it.
But I'm concerned about the direction that continues to and the fact that it continues
to build.
Do you think this is just a sort of very vocal part of the Republican Party or do you think
this actually represents an entire political party?
I mean, it seems hard to me that this could represent an entire political party given
the heterogeneity of beliefs that would exist across that from fiscal conservatives, social
conservatives, I mean, all of these things.
Yeah.
And the fact that the Republican Party historically has not been anti-science, right?
I mean, the National Academy of Sciences was started in the Lincoln administration.
Eisenhower launched NASA.
George W. Bush launched PEPFAR.
So this seems new to me.
And I don't know how much it's pervasive in the Republican Party.
Certainly it's become now a major component of Fox News in the evening.
And as recently as last year, I was going on Fox News almost every day on a pretty regular
basis.
And I didn't see it until the disinformation campaign came out of the Trump White House.
When they said COVID was around a year ago, last year, when they said COVID was a hoax
or the flu and attributed the COVID deaths to other causes or you had Kayleigh McEnany
say the hospitalizations were all elective, catch up in elective surgeries and discrediting
masks.
And then later on in the summer, they brought out Scott Atlas.
So there was no question about it, this very deliberate disinformation campaign coming
out of the Trump White House.
And I was one of the first to call it out, not because I'm so brilliant, but because
I've been going up against these anti-vaccine guys for years and they've become, unfortunately,
by default an expert in anti-science disinformation campaigns and can recognize it.
I see it accelerating and I can't say whether it's across the whole Republican party, but
it's a lot more pervasive now among Republicans than it's ever been.
And then what's the evidence?
Well, the evidence is now the PBS NewsHour teamed up with NPR and Marist and they've
now found that if you look at the single most vaccine hesitant group in the United States,
this was just last week, it's what's called white Republicans.
So it's around, I think it was 41% of white, a significant percentage of white Republicans
are saying they're not going to get vaccinated.
And that's not the first poll.
I mean, we did one with a group of Texas A&M, I'm not a social scientist, but we teamed
up with a group of social scientists at Texas A&M led by Tim Callahan in the School of
Public Health, found the same thing.
I think we call them Trump voters and Kaiser Family Foundation also found the same thing
twice that it's, so this is the number one vaccine.
Now I've seen another poll that suggested, and it didn't slice the data by race and party,
it sliced it by race and party separately.
And it found the greatest predictor was indeed Republican party association, but the second
was African American.
Right.
What's the best explanation for that?
And what's more now it's coming down.
So whereas it's still staying, so what's happened that you're absolutely right.
So about two, three months ago, African American groups and white Republicans were sort of
neck and neck and who was the most vaccine hesitant.
And it stayed up among Republicans, but it's been coming down among the African American
groups.
And one of the things I've been going on, lots of podcasts and radio shows that reach
black and brown audiences.
And I was on one last night with a Baptist church in Richmond, Virginia, and I asked
the pastor, I said, are you seeing less of it now?
He goes, definitely it's coming down.
And I said, what do you think is happening?
Well, he goes, well, doc, I think part of it is people like you, you know, reaching
out to black and brown communities.
But the other is a lot of the clergy have created a sort of an informal network now.
And we're really hitting hard on the need to get vaccinated.
So I think that that may be part of it.
But initially it was quite high.
And I think part of, you know, what the reasons were, I don't entirely understand, you know,
what's often said is it's around structural and historic racism and that horrible legacy
of Tuskegee.
I think the other thing that I've seen now is deliberate targeting of African American
groups by the anti vaccine lobby.
And now I just saw on the internet, there's a new quote, documentary where I, you know,
clicked on the trailer and it's got people getting the Pfizer BioNTech vaccine that it
switches right away to Tuskegee experimentation.
So by it's kind of making that that links, I think it could do a lot of damage.
So but it seems to be somewhat resolving, but it's still really high among the those
group of Republicans.
And you saw it, you know, when COVID-19 accelerated in the summer in the southern states and in
upper Midwest in the fall.
So what's going on?
And I'm worried that now you've got, again, people tying their allegiance to the Republican
Party or their identity to being against scientists and science.
And this is not good for the country.
Yeah, there are a few things I want to say.
And one thing to add, the thing that we haven't mentioned yet that I think is worth mentioning
is the enormous measles outbreak in Minnesota that occurred in the Somali community.
But I think that story doesn't get enough attention because I guess it's now been enough
years.
But I've always found that to be an unbelievably sad story in some ways more sad than the Orange
County outbreak, because this was this was really a deliberate targeting of a community
of immigrants, you know, not facile with the language.
And the measles outbreak was terrible there.
And I guess that's the thing I've always struggled with.
If you just put your common sense hat on every time a community gets targeted to stop taking,
in this case, the MMR vaccine, a measles outbreak shows up.
Yeah.
And that was sort of the, Paul Offit always calls it the canary in the coal mine.
And I think he's right.
It's because it's got such a high reproductive number of 12 to 18.
Yeah, it's crazy.
I mean, as soon as the vaccination coverage goes down, measles finds it.
And that was really, that was the first time I think that you saw the anti-vaccine groups
targeting specific ethnic groups.
So Lena Sun at the Washington Post back in 2017 reported that Wakefield, who had kind
of disappeared for a while, was at town hall meetings.
I don't know if he organized them or if the Smalley immigrant community organized them.
But you know, there he was piling on and brought down vaccine coverage from over 90%.
Washington Post reported to 40%.
Guess what's going to happen?
It was, and I think it was 21 kids that landed in the hospital.
And then it happened again in 2018, 2019, they began targeting Orthodox Jewish groups
in New York and New Jersey.
And what they did was just so offensive.
They started parading around in these phony yellow Jewish stars, like the Holocaust, with
the word Vax written in it.
And Vax was written like Hebrew letters and started comparing vaccines to the Holocaust.
And that caused this massive measles epidemic across, both in Muncie, New York by the Tamponsie
Bridge and then in Brooklyn.
And I think there were 18 people in the ICU because of that 50 hospitalizations.
So this has become the new modus opera.
And then in 2019, you saw these series of Harlem vaccine forums that they organized
and even held one in the Riverside Church, which is on the Upper West Side in New York,
near Columbia University.
It's one of the iconic churches in the history of the civil rights movement, the Reverend
Sloan Coffin, and somehow got access there and held a rally there.
So all of that has caused a lot of damage.
Now this new quote documentary that's coming out.
So I'm very concerned.
So you've got these, as I say, these multiple facets.
You've got the health freedom component expanding now across the Republican Party, now into
Western Europe.
You've got the Russians fueling this with their systematic weaponized health communication.
And now you've got the specific targeting of racial and ethnic groups and causing a
lot of damage.
And the problem is it takes time to explain, right?
I can't give you a 30 second UNICEF commercial about this.
How long have we been talking a full hour now?
You kind of get it now, but it takes time to unfold and explain.
And the problem is it makes people very uncomfortable.
It made me uncomfortable, right?
When I was going on CNN and MSNBC in last year at this time, I didn't want to call out
the White House for their disinformation campaign.
What we're told as scientists is, hey, Peter, just stick to the science.
You're not a political guy.
You're not an expert in White House Washington politics.
What are you doing?
You can't do that.
But being an expert in anti-science disinformation campaigns by being targeted by these guys,
Robert F. Kennedy Jr. calls me on his Instagram, called me the OG villain, the original gangster
villain.
So that's who you're talking to today.
I had a look up what OG meant.
So I unfortunately became a bit of an expert in anti-science disinformation campaigns.
I could smell them on a mile away and I saw this.
I said, I know what this is.
You saw Peter Navarro out there with all the Chinese conspiracies.
I said, we're being gaslighted here.
I said to Anne, my wife, I said, I don't know what to do.
This is taking me to a very dark place.
I'm supposed to only talk about the science.
She saw upset I was getting.
She said, Peter, if you don't say anything and you find out all this massive loss of
life from COVID and didn't do all you can to stop it, you're going to hate yourself.
That's all I needed to hear.
And then I really went after it and it took me to a very dark place.
In part because at that time you weren't getting a lot of backing.
I didn't get a lot of backing from the academic and professional societies because that's
not what they do.
So I really felt out there alone.
Later on, I think when it became safe, other people came to my support.
But in the beginning it was a very lonely kind of thing to do.
I'm glad I did it, but it took emotionally, it really knocked the crap out of me.
It was very tough to do that because the truth is I'm not that ideologically driven politically.
I was in Washington for 10 years and as chair of microbiology at GW and one thing I learned
in Washington, if you want to get anything done, you reach across the aisle.
So we got a lot of neglected tropical disease legislation passed and I would think nothing
of going to Sam Brownback who is now he's the governor of Kansas.
Back then he was a very conservative senator from Kansas.
He would hold a prayer breakfast meeting and I'd go to that and I would speak and then
I'd go across the way and talk to Senator Leahy's people who's this very liberal senator
from Vermont.
Back then nobody thought twice about those kinds of things, but it's not happening anymore.
So to be able to have to tear into what was going on with the Trump White House and it
was often perceived as I was just being somebody in the Democratic camp, which wasn't the case,
but I understand why it was perceived that way.
And now what's interesting is whenever I have something with the Biden administration,
I think is not quite right, then I get beat up a lot from my colleagues on the left and
there's a lot more of those who say, you know, what are you doing after a while?
We've been through, how can you criticize the Biden White House?
I'm really criticizing.
I think they're doing a good job, but there are things that need to be changed as well.
So it's very tough to, it's very tough not, it's very tough to, if your focus is only
on saving lives and doing whatever you can to save lives, that's very tough.
Because it means if you're sincere about that, you go on Newsmax and you go on Fox
News, which I've been doing, or, and you go on a radio podcast and that reach black and
brown audiences.
That's what I've been doing.
So, and hopefully at the end of it all, I'll be okay, but it's not easy doing this.
Peter, is there a historical precedent for such a distrust of science?
I mean, that, you know, given that the scientific method has only been around for, call it 400
years, that doesn't give us a great opportunity to look for such things.
But even in the last century or two, have we ever seen such massive distrust for the
establishment of science?
I haven't seen this distrust systematically.
Certainly there's been a lot of pushback or anger around certain things scientists have
said.
Like, for instance, with, during colonial times, when Cotton Mather tried to vaccinate
the Massachusetts colony against smallpox, people were very aggressive with him and they
actually threw a firebomb into his window around that particular issue.
So yeah, that's gone up and down in American history, but I've just not seen this systematic
distrust of science and scientists and the targeting of scientists and the mainstreaming
of anti-science.
That's kind of worrisome.
And of course, a lot of this is because now we have this new era of the internet and social
media and Amazon and all those kinds of things doing a lot of damage.
So kind of want to pivot a little bit to something very personal for you.
How old is Rachel now?
Now she's 28.
28.
So let's go back in time, 28 years.
Tell me what you remember about her birth and the first few years of her life.
So when she was, so by the time Rachel was born, I had already had two other kids.
And I remember Ann saying, always feeling that something was off, that she wasn't as
huggy or clingy as the other kids were, but didn't really come to medical attention till
around 19 months of age.
That's when the pediatrician clearly saw developmental delays and referred us to special
services and ultimately I was at Yale, which is, I was an assistant professor then running
a lab and that was hard for me because I was going off to China and keeping a lab in China.
And now having a child with a medical issue was really tough.
We had to give up going to China and reconfigure our program.
But at Yale, that's also the home of the Yale Child Study Center, which is one of the big
thought leader places for autism.
And she was referred eventually to the Yale Child Study Center where the world's experts
on autism, people like Fred Volkmar and Donald Cohen and Linda Mays.
There was a child psychiatry fellow in Wendy Levine who really looked into this very carefully
and she was clear that she was on the autism spectrum.
And it's a little tougher to diagnose for girls than boys because girls tend to be more
verbal.
So oftentimes boys- Was she verbal at 19 months?
Was she appropriately verbal?
Well, she wasn't always appropriate, but she was always verbal.
She would repeat, there's a lot of echolalia, she would repeat things, but she had reason-
To this day, she's got reasonably normal language skills.
It's just her performance IQ is really, really low.
And so that's one of the big issues with Rachel.
It's the intellectual disabilities that go with autism, in her case that go with autism.
And in fact, that's a very interesting side story about Rachel is the whole ecosystem
of girls and women on the autism spectrum because the older literature says it was 10
to one boys to girls.
And that's because boys are so floored in their presentation and symptoms.
Girls can camouflage it better, they can mask it better, they are often verbal, but they
have very high rates of comorbidities like obsessive compulsive disorder or ADHD, attention
deficit hyperactivity disorder, or even a lot of the teenage girls with bulimia and
eating disorders.
Now many of them may be on the autism spectrum, so we're getting better at it.
So it used to be 10 to one.
Now I think it's moving closer to three to one boys to girls and some say it may even
approach parity or something close to parity, like 1.5.
But it's way underdiagnosed.
And Alison Singer has the Autism Science Foundation has been supporting efforts to
really call great, because she has a daughter on the autism spectrum, to look at this in
more detail because it is so underdiagnosed.
But in Rachel's case, it finally came to diagnosis at 19 months of age.
I got very interested in that because when you look back then at the CDC definition of autism,
it's I don't think it's on the website anymore, but I guess a couple of years ago, it was still
there. It said most kids on the autism spectrum were diagnosed 18 or 24 months of age.
And I got very interested in that because there was a research group at the University of North
Carolina Chapel Hill run by this guy named Piven, P-I-V-E-N, who was able to show that that
clinical expression of autism coincided with a big increase in brain volume expansion.
So you could actually follow this on serial MRI.
And that's important because a lot of parents will remember when their kid was diagnosed with
autism, especially the regressive form, because that's so true, not just all slowing of milestones,
but actually loss of milestones.
They'll remember that their kid got vaccinated, maybe with measles or something else around that
time and want to link the two.
But now this group at UNC Chapel Hill can go back much earlier, back to infancy and show that
there's already those changes happening in the brain.
And now, of course, we can show prenatally.
So Eric Korczewski's group at UCSD and multiple groups now the Broad Institute at Harvard MIT has identified about
100 genes linked to autism spectrum disorder all involved in early fetal brain development.
Many of them involved in neuronal communication.
So a lot of neuronal cytoskeleton genes, for instance.
So we did whole exome sequencing on Rachel and Ann and I at Baylor Genetics.
And identified a neuronal cytoskeleton gene, a non-red cell spectrum, a neuronal spectrum, which makes a lot more sense in
terms of understanding neuronal communications and that sort of thing.
So I think what happens is you see the activation of genes in early fetal brain development.
And that sets into motion a progression.
But that full clinical expression of it doesn't happen till around 18, 19 months of age often.
And that's not unusual for neuropsychiatric conditions.
I mean, look at schizophrenia, for instance, which oftentimes, you know, kids with schizophrenia are not diagnosed to
adolescents or even young adults.
And so this is how the brain works.
I think I'm not a neuroscientist, but that's that's my take on this.
What I mean, just on a personal level, how how did you cope with this realization?
And did it ever cause you to question anything that you were doing or was it very clear?
Like, were you able to sort of distance it or think about it through kind of a scientific lens, even though it was something very
personal and it, you know, it became it went from being, you know, this is the scientific literature in its entirety to this is my
daughter.
Yeah, well, back in the 90s, we knew a lot less about autism than we know now and all the things that I told you about a lot of it has only
come to light in the last few years.
And then the Wakefield paper came out.
And I remember that because I think Rachel was about five years old at the time.
And, you know, and it was all over the papers.
And of course, Anne was asking me about it.
And to me, it never made sense.
It said, how can it be that I mean, I mean, they called it pervasive developmental disorder back then for a reason, because it was indeed
pervasive. And and you could see that, you know, that a lot of these kids were macrocephalic.
They have enlarged heads.
And so this was clearly a neuro anatomical condition.
I mean, you knew that there were shifts in Purkinje fibers and and and there were structural alterations in the brain of kids with
autism. How can it be that a vaccine you give it one year of age would would cause that?
It just never made any sense to me.
There was never. And so for me, there was never the plausibility.
But the full weight of scientific evidence wasn't there.
I mean, that was my opinion more than any.
And it turns out more or less to be true.
And and but so that's why I was one of the early adopters of saying there is no way in hell it's going to be M.M.R.
vaccine. And and it just doesn't make any sense.
It's going to sound like a strange question, but was there a part of you that almost wished it was so that you might be able to say this would be
amazing if we knew this?
Because again, at the time, Wakefield proposed this.
He wasn't even saying that all vaccination was bad.
He was simply saying they should be separate vaccines.
Don't put measles, mumps, rubella in one shot.
Give them separately.
This was his first thesis.
And so even wearing your hat as an infectious disease physician, if if if you could have
believed that the answer was M.M.R.
combined causes autism.
And while it won't save my daughter to know that I could spare every other parent, because clearly, you know, you you you you exude the ethos of wanting to help everyone.
All we have to do is separate these vaccines and we could solve it.
I mean, was there was there a part of you that just wanted this to be true?
Not necessarily.
I mean, I you know, if if it made sense to me and and.
If if there was a logical explanation and yeah, if we knew there was a simple intervention, sure, but it was just so outrageous at the time that it wasn't even on my on on my radar screen at that time to think in that way.
I just knew that it had to be genetic or maybe an epigenetic basis.
And and by the way, that's a real treat trying to explain epigenetics to lay audiences.
Start talking about micro RNAs and histone deacetylation.
That one I'm still working on.
But, you know, so the epigenetic component is another one that's important.
But again, all of that had to be prenatal.
And and I remember having some conversations with some of the anti vaccine people and then saying it had to be prenatal.
And then they said and I said, yes, we do give some prenatal vaccines like flu vaccine.
And then they the immediate response was aha.
And I said, no, I mean, you know, again, I don't see how an immunization during pregnancy could be linked to that.
And now the scientific data supports shows there's no link.
So let's let's talk a little bit about the autism is still such a complicated thing in terms of people even understanding what it means.
So the definition has has morphed a little bit.
So today we talk about ASD being a spectrum.
Right. And and it's gotten a very complicated because, you know, there's this whole concept out there of neurodiversity.
And so there are many in the autism community who bristle if you even try to describe it as a pathologic condition, they say, no, this is just an example of neurodiversity.
People are are different. And and and I understand that.
And so the what I try to emphasize with Rachel, it's it's the not the autism per se that's incapacitating.
It's it's it's the in her case, you know, she's got clear and profound intellectual disability.
She can barely read. She can't count numbers. She can't do simple math.
She can't you know, when she goes to the store to buy something, she will hand them a fistful of single dollar bills and say here because she doesn't know how to count the money.
She no matter how hard we've tried to train her to do that, she doesn't understand the value of things.
And so she depends on the goodness of the merchants in our local Montrose neighborhood have been great.
You know, they kind of know Rachel.
So it's in her case, it's the intellectual, profound intellectual disabilities that make it tough and make us worry because, you know, the other piece to this is now she's an adult with autism and intellectual disabilities.
And the special services and all that kind of stuff really falls off the radar screen because we have no plan for her right now.
We don't know, you know, we've tried to have her in a residential facility, which, you know, I think did an OK job, but she was just too her.
Her behavior was too uncooperative.
And finally, they had to kind of kick her out.
And so now she's with us. And what worries me is I don't know what is going to happen after, you know, and are no are no longer here.
We don't there's no roadmap for what you do with an adult with this with intellectual disabilities.
And that that really worries me, especially in Texas.
It's just not strong with services of those kind.
And maybe it's better up in the Northeast and we've heard New York and Massachusetts.
But trying to work that as a huge, huge heavy burden on us.
How is the diagnosis made today?
So if if a parent today or a pediatrician today suspects that something is not normal, you know, whether it be language delay, you know, changes in behavior, emotional regulation, eye contact, all the things that would, you know, flag someone.
What is the actual process by which a diagnosis is made?
And what does this something that shows up in the DSM?
I mean, how what is the what is the criteria for diagnosis?
It's still in the DSM.
The DSM is still not as strong as it could be, especially for girls, especially for little girls.
But presumably, presumably it you get the child gets referred to something called birth to three, which is an early intervention program.
And at some point, they get medical attention typically to a behavioral pediatrician, maybe a child psychiatrist.
Only there are only about six of them left on the planet.
There's a huge need for more child psychiatrists.
I tell my medical students to go into child psychiatry with the hope that one of them goes goes into it.
There's a it's a that's a real crisis as well.
But and and then the diagnosis is made along along the way of limited social interactions, in some cases, lack of speech, although again with girls and women, it's different.
So there are a list of criteria that you can look at.
What's on the differential diagnosis?
Like, what are what are they trying to is it a diagnosis of exclusion where they're just basically saying, here are a bunch of things that could present with this pattern and we're going to rule them all out.
And that which remains is ASD or or, you know, because when you think about so many things like it's not like Down syndrome where there's such a clear phenotype and genotype, right?
Like it's unmistakable.
This is much more nuanced.
Well, I think in in our ears and future years, you know, we'll make whole exome sequencing so much more available that I think any time you have a child like that, you'll get a whole exome sequencing and we'll actually be able
to potentially target it to a specific gene.
In some cases, that may be useful because there's could be pharmacological intervention in case there's something that is impairing abilities and can be targeted.
Can you explain why that's important?
Why whole exome sequencing is relevant versus just, quote unquote, a genetic sequence?
Well, because with whole exome sequencing, you're getting the gene of every you're getting the full sequence of every expressed gene.
And what that does for you is identifies rare mutations that you wouldn't pick up just by looking at at chromosomes.
And so it's a very powerful technology.
At this point, it only picks up around 40 percent of.
So if you have autism and you do whole exome sequencing, my understanding is you only see a mutation maybe 30, 40 percent of the time because there's other things going on, including the non expressed genes.
So exome sequencing just looks at the express genes.
But if you do the whole genome, potentially you could pick up additional additional ones as well.
So we're still in the early stages of that.
And what's very interesting in that was some children's hospitals are looking at the possibility of doing whole exome sequencing and every child they admit for whatever cause, because we're learning so much about the genetics and epigenetics, not only of autism, but but so many other conditions.
Right now, you're left with what I consider to be a somewhat rudimentary list of criteria from the DSM.
And I'll never forget, Peter, I once had a lecture from a from a child psychiatrist and when I was in medical school at Cornell and and I remember him saying, you know, we're going to look upon the DSM is such a anachronistic or out of touch document for child psychiatry.
It just doesn't cut.
It's just really falls down for child psychiatric disorders.
And that was, you know, in the 1980s, you know, maybe it's moved on since then.
I'd be curious to hear from a child psychiatrist today what they think about the SM, but I'll never forget that that comment.
And and when you look at the DSM criteria, they're just not really robust for so many childhood conditions.
And again, this whole concept of neurodiversity is not reflected in the DSM like like it needs to be.
It'll get refined.
And I think that combining with whole exome sequencing and that combining with all the developments in neuropsychiatric medications, I think this things will look very different 10 years from now and then 10 years again from from then.
Do you have a sense, ballpark, how many children that are born today?
What what will be the incidence of autism in the cohort of kids born in 2021?
Well, I think one is, you know, the the number that's thrown out there now, what is it, one in 62?
I can't remember the latest surprise.
Yeah, I mean, it's it's it seems remarkably high.
Well, remember, it could come close to doubling because we're not we're way undercounting all the girls with girls and women with autism.
So it wouldn't surprise me that it would go down to something like one in 30 or now.
What do we think that was in 1980, for example?
Yeah, I don't even know, but very rare because, you know, the criteria change, you know, before there was a very strict criteria about nonverbal boys with certain repetitive behaviors.
And we've enlarged so much and then it's going to get very murky.
Right. Because we're going to go, you know, now with this whole picture of neurodiversity, at what point is it a condition that warrants criteria under the under DSM?
And what is it just being neurodiverse?
And and and I don't know that there's going to be a cutoff, right?
It's always going to be that that gray zone.
So I talked to my my my oldest daughter a lot who's an assistant professor at UCLA.
She has a P.M.M.M.M.M.I.
She's got a PhD in developmental psychology and works at the Center for Disabilities.
And this is this is a real struggle and and difficult to get your arms around.
But I think we still need a lot of brilliance around the around these points.
At what point is it something that you diagnose in the DSM?
And at what point is it not?
And and I don't have the answers to that right now.
When you consider something like Alzheimer's disease and you look at the change in prevalence over the last 50 years, it's you know, there are many factors involved.
Right. People are living longer.
The diagnosis is much more.
We have many more tools to make the diagnosis.
And then there are also factors that many of us, myself included, believe are actually increasing the incidence.
So the prevalence is higher because people live longer because we diagnose more.
But because the true incidence is increasing.
And why do you think and by that, I'm just curious.
Why do you why do you think that is?
Because I think many of the risk factors for Alzheimer's disease are increasing dramatically.
So vascular disease, metabolic disease being the two among obesity.
Yeah. Yeah. As we see insulin resistance increase, as we see a dyslipidemia increase and all of the things that accompany it,
I think we're actually creating more neuropathology.
We're actually working with a group at Baylor because, you know, we make vaccines.
There's a group at Baylor College of Medicine run by David Corey, who also has a collaboration with Europeans that have shown some evidence of fungal involvement, even Canada,
because there are some of the plaques that you see in the beta amyloid has got fungal sequences as well.
And so, you know, what is the role of aspergillus and yeast forming fungi in this is getting very interesting.
Yeah, I think that Alzheimer's disease is probably the for lack of a better word, the final common pathway of many.
There are many roads to it.
Many different.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. And I do think that there's absolutely a sort of toxic version of it as well that may actually include infectious agents or environmental toxins and things like that.
So well, the hope, you know, with fungal disease, you could do something about that.
You could vaccinate, for instance, get fungal disease.
Could would that could a fungal vaccine become a, you know, help with reducing neurodegenerative disease?
So that's one of the things that we're starting to look at.
So using that as a model for thought, how do you now think about autism?
Right. Is it that, hey, we're clearly more attuned to this.
So we're making we're making the diagnosis more.
But do you also think there's an increase in the incidence?
In other words, is there an environmental trigger that is either triggering this with or without manipulating the genome?
So now we're going to have to talk about what epigenetics means.
So people understand that you can have an environmental trigger that comes along, triggers a condition for which there's a genetic susceptibility
that does not alter the genome or one that does so and alters the genome.
So what do you think is actually happening and what are some of the plausible explanations?
Well, before I answer that, let me just say just because this isn't complicated enough to make it even more complicated,
there's a there's a group at Geisinger in Pennsylvania that's been looking at a number of psychiatric conditions
and they've identified groups of people who families that have the same genetic mutation.
Yet one individual has been diagnosed with autism and other schizophrenia and another some other condition.
I forget it was addictive behavior or something along those lines.
So so you're right.
It you know, the genetics is dominant, but I think there are epigenetic factors that that could have some influencing role.
And most likely it's going on in pregnancy.
So so when you talk about epigenetics, that doesn't discount entirely environmental factors.
But but if it is, it's environmental factors happening in pregnancy.
So explain why it has to be an environmental factor in pregnancy versus an environmental factor post utero.
Because I think and and again, I'm not a neuroscientist, but I think the structural changes in the brain and and is already well underway by the time the baby's born.
So that there are processes that are set into when you look at all the work coming out of, you know, Eric or Chesney's lab and other labs there.
It's clearly showing that this is going on pretty early fetal early on in fetal brain development, maybe as late as the second trimester.
But but but happening in utero.
And that's where all the action is occurring so that if it is an environmental if there is environmental influences, it's most likely something happening in pregnancy.
So if if if you're a parent or a soon to be parent and you're listening to this, you're terrified.
Right. I mean, it's terrifying enough to think that during the first six months of your pregnancy, the first and second trimester, so many things can go wrong.
I mean, obviously, during the first trimester, you're mostly just thinking about not miscarrying.
And then once you sort of get through, call it week eight, nine, ten, and you're thinking, OK, well, we're almost halfway to the point of knowing we're not going to be confident we're not going to miscarry.
Then you start to think about big structural stuff.
Is the heart OK? Does this thing have four chambers? Is the brain of normal size?
You know, to think that there's some environmental trigger that could take a genetically susceptible fetus and render them autistic.
I can't imagine how that doesn't produce an incredible amount of speculation and consternation.
Right. But but but I think you have to be careful with your language.
So it's not just genetically susceptible. The genes are there and they're.
Are these deterministic? They're causing autism.
There might be some environmental influences that could that could affect expression through epigenetics.
But it's not so simple as to say genetic susceptibility.
I don't think it's it's quite I don't think it's quite that straightforward.
How deterministic do we think these genes are, then?
I can't I can't give you us. I can't give I know you're what you're looking for.
You're looking for an 80 20 90 10 70 30.
And I don't I don't think I don't think we know that.
I mean, it's polygenic, presumably. What do we think here?
Well, in Rachel's case, it seemed to be so far as what we know, it's a single gene.
And I think that's true. But but they're not all the same gene.
So the point is the Broad Institute, Harvard, MIT paper, which I think was in cell identified about 100 genes.
But the common denominator was they seem to be all involved in early fetal brain development,
all and all except for one in the cortex of the brain, most involved in early excitatory and inhibitory neurons and a lot of them in neuronal cytoskeleton.
So so there's a lot there there. I mean, it's clearly the genes are dominant.
Whether or not there's some epigenetic influences that can affect, you know, whether it's full on expression of autism or whether there's schizophrenic components to it.
I think that that that may be likely as well, but it's not as simple as saying just genetic susceptibility and it's overwhelmingly the environmental factor.
I think it's the other way around. I think it's overwhelmingly the genetics is the dominant factor.
And yes, deterministic. And maybe there are some epigenetic influences.
So if that's the case, then there would be really two reasonable explanations for the for an increase in the incidence of autism.
I mean, do you believe that there has been an increase in the incidence of autism over the last 40 or 50 years, a true increase in incidence, not diagnosis?
No, I've not seen any evidence for that. But I can, you know, I concede it's it's tough to prove given, you know, you know, and I and I get different.
Some of the things I ask are teachers, you know, are you seeing more autism and most teachers will say, yeah, I'm seeing a lot more autism.
But I think a lot of that is due to more awareness.
I think a lot of things that we now call call autism.
We didn't call autism back then. I mean, we use the R word a lot right there, mentally retarded or this or that.
And now we realize they're on the autism spectrum.
There's also this component and some teachers have told me, you've said, well, if you want to get special services for your kid, you have to label it as autism.
Otherwise, they're not eligible for special services.
And how much of that is going on is hard for me to know either.
But I think overall, and again, as I point out, as we get better with diagnosing girls and women with autism, those numbers are going to go through the roof yet again.
So how how how heritable do you believe the transmission of this is?
Is this something where, you know, it's sort of like eye color where a child can be born with green eyes to a parent of blue and brown eyes?
How how do the genes transmit?
What's the best guess? Yeah, again, not an expert.
I mean, in some cases, I think just spontaneous mutations.
I think others, you know, when Rachel was diagnosed with autism, you know, and said, you know, clearly, it's your side of the family.
And I said, what do you mean? What about your what about your uncle?
So and so. And so there was those kinds of discussions.
So, yeah, hard to know. I mean, I think I think clearly you see autism in in parents of kids with autism.
And it may not be fully diagnosed, but you definitely see that a lot of times.
And I think that that's quite common. And has a theory that autism is more common among people of intellectual accomplishment.
And and maybe there's some truth to that.
But I think it's just bias on the basis of people that, you know, I've been at a university my whole life and is always running into academics.
So I can understand why she thinks that. But I don't think that's been well established.
That's really interesting, Peter. I actually took it as I guess I took it as a given that there was a true increase in the incidence of autism,
though not as significant as what the perception is, because this was also the perception is also being driven by, as you say, just a tremendous increase in awareness,
diagnostic criteria becoming broader, more things being included.
Right. So, for example, what used to be called Asperger's is now technically a part of ASD.
Right. Right. But I guess the question is, how would you ever sort it out?
That's the that's the other problem. I think it's, you know, I guess what you could look if you had specific genetic markers that you could look at.
That would be something you can hang on to and say, is the increase in certain genetic markers going up?
And but that's not trivial to look at either. But I've always felt that there's been no true increase, but there may be some evidence for it.
So let's pivot to a little bit of the current around Covid.
As we stand here today, Peter, we're well on the path to most Americans who want to be vaccinated are getting pretty close to being vaccinated.
By the way, what's the latest on the vaccination of children?
Where is the CDC on that? What do we know about the vaccine?
How many of the current vaccines as we stand here today?
Really, there are three that are used in the US, correct?
I think the AstraZeneca one is not used in the United States.
That's right. It hasn't gone through emergency.
They haven't applied for emergency use authorization.
I'm worried about that vaccine for reasons that we can talk about.
But then there's the Novavax vaccine.
So and there could be as many as five by the spring.
The in terms of kids, Pfizer just released data showing high levels of efficacy and adolescence, 12 to 15.
But there were small numbers. There was around twelve hundred in the vaccine group, twelve hundred in the control group.
And there were 18 cases of Covid in the in the control group, none in the vaccinated group.
And on that basis, in their press release, they said 100 percent efficacy.
I'm sure that won't hold up. I mean, it's too small a number.
One of the interesting things about the about the kids, though, in those those adolescents,
the virus neutralizing antibody titers are really high, like twelve hundred, so higher than older adults.
So that may be a factor as well.
And we're now starting to get our arms around correlates of protection that really high levels of virus neutralizing antibody seem roughly to correlate with efficacy.
Is that consistent with your belief, Peter, that this would be more B cell mediated than T cell mediated?
Well, I think T cells have a role.
I mean, I think in virus neutralizing antibody may not be everything,
but if you don't have high levels of virus neutralizing antibody, you're not going to get protection.
And the problem with comparing those virus neutralizing antibodies is.
Is when you look at the actual papers.
They compare it with convalescent serum titers and they're all over the map.
And so so now there's a paper up on Med Archive that does something very simple,
which is rather than just give the absolute value for the geometric mean titers,
whether it's against pseudo virus or whether it's whether it's against plaque reduction neutralization titers,
what they do is they do a ratio of the virus neutralizing antibody titers against the vaccine versus the virus neutralizing antibody titers on the convalescent to kind of normalize it.
And there's this very nice curve that's been generated that shows you need to get it,
that the level of virus neutralizing antibodies has to be at least as high as the convalescent and preferably about one point five or two to get really high levels of protection.
And I think that's probably what we're looking at.
So it's not quite a true correlate of protection, but I think we're moving in that direction.
And the adolescents get really high levels of virus neutralizing the antibody.
And did that Pfizer study give two shots or one?
I think it was two. OK, it's two.
So now that we're out of the gate and millions of people have been vaccinated, do you have any preference or concern over any of the vaccines?
You obviously mentioned AstraZeneca, which I want to hear about, but let's start with the U.S. vaccines.
Any reason to believe that one is better than the other?
In fact, I'll share with you something that I found very interesting, which was the J and J vaccine, which is a single vaccine.
And that that vaccine, well, the headline is lower efficacy.
If you actually look at the absolute risk reduction as opposed to the relative risk reduction is at least as efficacious as Pfizer and Moderna.
I found that to be very interesting.
And I'm surprised how that was sort of omitted from all the press.
Yeah. And I and I also think it's hard to compare because it's a single dose.
It's being given a single dose versus the two doses.
And I'm and it wouldn't surprise me if that J and J vaccine ultimately becomes a two dose vaccine down the line because you may want to give a booster for one of the variants as well.
And in two doses, the virus neutralizing antibody titers is really, really high.
And it'll be as good or in terms of protection as as Pfizer and Moderna.
Certainly, I think the single to me, the single dose J and J looks better than the single dose Pfizer and Moderna.
Not by much. The bottom line is they're all good. They're all good vaccines.
And I also think don't be surprised if later on we're going to need a boost for all of them.
So there'll be a third dose of the Moderna Pfizer vaccine or a second dose of the J and J.
And what that will do is it'll elevate virus neutralizing antibody titers higher.
It'll create more durability of protection, I think.
And that boost will be reconfigured for the South African or the and the Brazilian variant, which are not here in a big way in the U.S.,
but may become a bigger problem down the line right now.
It's the U.K. variant, the B.1.1.7 variant that's accelerating.
All of the operational warp speed vaccines work really well against the U.K. variant.
That's because that variant has not mutated through its spike protein.
Well, it has. So the U.K. variant has a single amino acid substitution in in in an aromatic amino out creating an aromatic amino acid.
And that seems to reduce the level of virus neutralizing antibody.
I don't know if I have a mechanism to show you pictures.
Yeah. Do you know how to share a screen on Zoom?
Yeah, I have a really cool graphic.
It's a little bit of molecular biology, but not but not much.
I I just showed this at a at a pediatric Grand Rounds at Columbia this morning.
And to me, it it it helps people understand it.
But it's as I often like to say, it's not a 30 second UNICEF commercial.
So this is a paper that's up in BioArchive, a preprint server and looking at the B.1.1.7 variant.
And so looking and what in the spike protein, what there is, there's an amino acid substitution in the 501 position.
What went from a nespera gene to a tyrosine and a tyrosine is an aromatic amino acid.
It has a ring to it and they're able to show model it with the receptor, the angiotensin converting enzyme.
It's got a nice strong bond there.
Yeah, there's a ring ring interaction.
So it's these pi pi, these pi electrons that circulate in aromatic rings that are interacting with each other.
In addition, there's a hydrogen bond.
And the reason I love this so much is, you know, all of all we're talking about with this big acceleration of cases going up in Michigan and affecting younger people and higher mortality and morbidity.
It's a bit of a simplification, but then again, it's not.
It's all coming down to pi pi interactions between between two aromatic rings in in in two tyrosines.
Right. It's actually kind of let's just make sure people understand this because not everybody understands biochemistry, right?
Each amino acid is coded for by it.
There's a code, right?
So you have three nucleotides that code for an amino acid.
And if you know, so it sounds like one of those gets changed and it changed the amino acid.
And I can't remember. Did you say it started at three anneine or which?
Yeah, it was. So this is the wild type or the original lineages.
Now it's switching over to a tyrosine.
It's basically.
Yeah. So it went from from three anneine to tyrosine.
And then all of a sudden that changes, literally changes the shape, but also creates kind of an electrochemical attraction that wasn't there before.
And so all of a sudden the spike protein has a greater basically a greater attraction to the ACE2.
Receptor.
Right. Which which was presumably translates into better virus entry and maybe more virus replication.
And that's why you're getting more severe disease.
And and it's affecting younger younger people are getting sicker as well.
The good news is the virus neutralizing antibodies to the original spike protein seems to still work well against this B1 1 7 variant.
So we're going to take this picture now and zoom out a bit.
So now this is this is the spike protein, which is a trimer.
Actually, let me show you a real picture of it so you so you can see what it looks like.
This is what this is the trimeric spike protein.
So these are these little purple pink flowers on top.
Each one is a trimeric spike protein.
And now we're going to show it again here.
And they've got each one has its own receptor binding domain.
And now what's going to happen is only one of the receptor binding domains flips up and binds to the receptor to the ACE2 receptor.
And here's that one amino acid substitution again that I blew up on on the previous slide.
And so if you had the wild type on here, Peter, it would show it would look the same, but it would look the same.
You would just have a lower affinity there.
Yeah. And you wouldn't see this.
This wouldn't be marked as having this mutation.
But the point is the antibodies to all of the original lineages from the vaccines seem to work just as well.
It could still neutralize this interaction.
The problem comes in now with the other variants that are coming up from South Africa and in Brazil, the P1 variant from Brazil and the B1351.
That's got a second amino acid substitution over here, which is going which is creating a lysine.
And that I think is creating extra levels of electrostatic interaction.
So the binding potentially is even tighter.
And this now is interfering with the ability of antibodies to neutralize.
So the virus neutralizing antibody titer goes down and that translates to decreased inefficacy.
So when you look at the published numbers, these are some of the numbers here of the level of efficacy against the original.
I'll call that original slash UK, which is probably roughly about the same versus the South African variant.
And that's why you see it going down.
Wow. So this is interesting.
Let's digest this for a second.
So Pfizer and Moderna take an enormous reduction against that variant.
Well, no, no, let's let's be careful.
So the so the Novavax and J&J, that's actual efficacy, published efficacy data.
OK. In the case of Pfizer and Moderna,
what you're looking at here is declines in levels of virus neutralizing antibody in vitro.
Thanks for clarifying that.
So these are in vitro studies and and that, yeah, that's very important.
And it's still because the level of virus neutralizing antibodies so high to begin with,
there's enough residual that it's just still getting good protection.
And I but we don't yet have the clinical data to see.
Well, now Pfizer issued a press release yesterday saying they think in a very small set,
it seems to work really well against the South African variant.
And which makes sense given the high levels of virus neutralizing antibody to begin with.
Tell me why you think the AstraZeneca takes the biggest hit here then.
Yeah, so the AstraZeneca started out with, you know, in some cases, not as high levels of virus neutralizing antibody.
And a study was done in South Africa showing only 10 percent basically ineffective against the South African variant.
But, you know, talking to the Oxford people, one of the things they say is it's a little unfair because they only tested it against moderate and mild disease.
And they feel that if you were to test against severe illness, it would still be very effective.
And they counter that the J&J results were mostly looking at severe illness.
And if they had if they if if they like J&J had looked at severe illness, they would have come up with similar numbers.
But, you know, I guess we have to wait and see what what happens with that.
The bigger issue with the AstraZeneca vaccine is is just public perception around the cerebral thrombosis that is being reported out of Europe.
And I think that's causing a lot of a lot of damage.
You know, and it's in it and it goes back and forth.
You know, the German government through their Paul Ehrlich Institute pointed out you had six, I think, was six cases of of sinus venous thrombosis,
which is a rare condition in the vaccinated group, and they suspended it.
And then several other European countries did.
And that had big ramifications, especially for Africa.
You know, Francophone Africa listens to what's going on in France and et cetera.
And I was going on a number of podcasts, not podcasts, but zoom conferences with groups in Africa.
And they were very concerned about the AstraZeneca because that was supposed to be a workhorse vaccine for low and low and middle income countries.
The European medicine agencies came along and said, no, no, it looks OK.
It's, you know, it's we think, you know, this is not related to the vaccine.
But then in Science magazine, two excellent science journals, Gretchen Vogel and Kai Kupperschmitt, looked at this and, you know,
have identified about, you know, they wrote about 31 cases of cerebral venous thrombosis.
And, you know, clearly, you know, more clearly showing it could be linked to the vaccine is a very rare event.
But but still that that can really alter public perception, especially in light of all of the very aggressive anti vaccine activities that are happening.
So I don't know what the US is going to do at this point.
I hope they do authorize it for emergency release, even if they never use it in the US.
And the reason is, if the US declines or if that derails, I think you could have a chilling effect on Latin America and Africa,
because we don't have a lot of vaccines out there. That's that's why we came along with our recombinant protein vaccine,
because they're not a lot of options. The big issue is for the Astra.
You know, if you look at what's going to be made for low and middle income countries, there are not a lot of choices out there.
I mean, the two mRNA vaccines, it's still a new technology.
We're not going to be able to scale it up in a big way for Africa and Latin America.
Yes, I mean, it's great. They, you know, Pfizer donated two hundred and thirty thousand doses to Rwanda.
It was fantastic. But look at the numbers. There's one point one billion people in sub-Saharan Africa, six hundred and fifty million people in Latin America.
We're going to need four billion doses of vaccines.
Where's that going to come from? It's not going to come from the mRNA vaccines.
Is the refrigeration also a problem?
Yeah, the fact that you have the that onerous freezer requirement and then, you know, the J and J is having, you know, some issues in scaling up production.
You know, part of the problem was when the science policymakers were looking at this, they went so heavy on the innovation.
And they wound up producing a lot of really cool vaccines that are highly effective.
But in terms of durability for scale up to make four billion doses, I don't think that was high enough on their radar screen and didn't realize that when you use a brand new technology, it's really hard to move to four billion doses.
And that's why I'm hoping our vaccine comes along, you know, which is, you know, in part, you know, a couple of donors came to me after your after one of the podcasts I did with you.
And that was game changing for us because it allowed us to adapt our coronavirus program for vaccines who are making for SARS and mares to this recombinant protein vaccine for covid-19.
What's the what's the vehicle?
It's recombinant protein in yeast, just like the hepatitis B vaccine.
And you could produce a ton of it.
They could they have capacity for producing 100 million doses a day, a month.
And it's looking really good in clinical trials and in non-human primate trials.
I can't talk about it yet, but it should be out soon.
And hopefully that will come in and make a big difference, because I'm really scared that we have nothing for Africa and Latin America.
I mean, what's amazing is how I had to, you know, struggle for funding.
I mean, I was spending a good part of last year just trying to keep the program going because it was so hard to get funds for what was so obviously needed, which is a low cost, unfussy, durable vaccine for low and middle income countries.
And, you know, because of your podcast groups like, you know, the
the Tita's vodka came through with some funding.
They're based in Austin and an anonymous donor and a couple of others.
So now the Claybrook Foundation is helping us in a big way.
There are Texas Foundation and in the J.P.B. Foundation and a few others.
So that that was game changing.
So, Peter, based on everything you're saying, it sounds like the biggest concern right now would have to be Brazil followed by Africa.
You didn't unless I missed it.
Did you explain the mutation in Brazil and the efficacy that any of the current vaccines would have against it notwithstanding the scale up limitations?
Yeah, a couple of things.
So the P1 variant in Brazil has those same two amino acid changes in the South African.
So I kind of think of them as brother sister issues.
So we're going to have so dealing with South Africa will also have will will hopefully take care of Brazil as well.
One other thing I wanted to mention is, you know, the the global policymakers did a good job of creating this COVAX sharing facility.
It's really quite brilliant in its design.
I think that's not the issue, you know, because they were really worried about equity.
The equity issue, I think, was more of the fact that we didn't ensure there was enough vaccine available for the COVAX sharing facility.
And that's that's really the problem right now.
And hopefully we can come in and address it and and and and take care of this, because if we don't figure out a way to vaccinate the rest of the world, if we only vaccinate North America and Europe, it's going to be a catastrophe.
This virus is going to continue to circulate and cause tremendous humanitarian destruction, but also who knows what other variants could evolve as well as a consequence of allowing that to go unfettered.
What what drives the evolutionary pressure here of this of these mutations?
Is it just standard Darwinian behavior where enough mutations occur and they're escaping because these mutations like how does the mutagenicity of this virus
compare to influenza? It seems far less than influenza. Is that safe?
Yeah. So a lot of us were surprised by by the variants.
We thought that we hadn't really seen this as much in coronaviruses.
What some people speculate is it happened because of an immunocompromised individual who, you know, had a lot more virus replication in their system and that combining even possibly
with receiving plasma convalescent therapy that put some kind of selective pressure on it.
And that's kind of a hypothesis that's out there, but, you know, it's not strong.
I don't think we really know that for certain at this point.
The good news is the way I see it is a lot of the viruses are converging to the same mutations.
So my hope and it's only a hope and there's I know many consensus in the scientific community is that if we make a booster to this South African slash P1 Brazil variant,
we might be done at that point that there won't be this continual evolution for totally something different.
But but I don't think we know that for certain.
So the good news also is it looks like our vaccine seems to give pretty good levels of virus neutralizing antibody to the South African variant as well.
So we're making the booster for it for the South African just in case, but we may not need it.
We'll see. And we don't know how often we would need the booster.
It could be every six months, every 12 months, every 18 months.
It's too soon to tell, obviously, until we have longitudinal data looking at the neutralizing antibodies.
Yeah, I mean, my dream situation is we give this one boost beyond the original vaccine series later this year, next year, and then we're done that it won't have to be every year.
But like anything else, we'll just have to monitor and follow it.
But, you know, people say it's going to be like flu where you have to vaccinate every year.
And at this point, I don't think so.
But I can't say for certain because in the case of the flu, that's driven more by the mutagenicity than the lack of BESOL response, isn't it?
Well, in the case of the flu, you're getting these wholesale antigenic shifts.
So it's really like a totally different virus.
And there's this carefully orchestrated dance where you that we have in place to monitor flu virus strains, you know, maybe coming out of Asia and then quickly transmitting the message to the pharmaceutical manufacturers who make a whole different vaccine every year.
It's really quite extraordinary.
I don't think we're going to need to do that for coronavirus vaccines.
That's at least that's my hope. But we'll see how this unfolds.
But one thing's for certain, if you look at the if you look at what's available for Africa and Latin America right now, it's it's not good.
And so I've been talking to a colleague, Patrick Shung Shin, who's in Los Angeles.
And he's really interested to see, can we build out vaccine development capacity in Africa or maybe Latin America?
Because right now there's no vaccines made on the African continent and very not enough in Latin, not nearly enough in Latin America, not much in the Middle East.
And we've learned that if you only rely on the multinational companies, even with that great Covax sharing facility, they're they're not going to make.
They're not going to make new vaccines for the world, at least in rapid time frame.
I mean, they still it's amazing. They do what they do.
I mean, Gavi, the Gavi Alliance for Vaccine in the World's Children depends heavily on the multinational companies.
They do a great job. But we we need parallel mechanisms in place like new vaccine development production facilities in locally in Africa and Latin America.
And that's something I'm very that we've been working a lot in this concept of vaccine diplomacy and building that out.
Well, Peter, I know that we have a real hard stop in time because you've got another obligation, but I'm really happy that we were able to spend a couple hours together.
We covered a lot of ground and we actually got through half of what I wanted to talk about.
So I consider that a win. It was an only half.
OK, well, I'm always happy to come back. You know, I love I love being on your podcast one because I learned so much from you.
And and the thing I really appreciate is you you ask questions that I just never would have thought of on my own.
And, you know, after you ask it, I say, why don't I know that I should have?
I mean, that's so obvious that's that I should know that because it's the right question to ask.
So you have this amazing talent for asking the right questions.
I appreciate that. All right. Well, thanks very much again for everything, Peter.
And I'm sure we will be talking again soon. OK, thanks so much.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription.
To that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things.
One totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person thing we discuss on each episode.
The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this.
The qualities, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive.
This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on.
If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe.
You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD.
You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only.
It does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing or other professional health care services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously.
For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up to date and active list of such companies.