Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Sarah. Welcome to the show. I'm super excited to be speaking with you today. This
has the potential, of course, to be a 10-hour podcast, which it won't be, but I think that
speaks to the depth of insight that you've got into so many topics that I actually want
to talk about. Thank you. It's great to be here.
In thinking long and hard about how to navigate all the threads I want to pull on, I figured
we would just start with the nerdiest of all topics, which is something that I know you're
so passionate about, and yet I don't think gets nearly enough attention. That is basically
the role of dietary intake of both carbohydrate and fats and the relationship that has on
the distribution of fatty acids within the body. Let me just start by asking, why is
that even of interest to you? Well, it's significant interest because it
really hits at one of the things people criticize a low-carb, high-fat diet about is, oh my
goodness, you'll get more fat in your muscles, in your liver, and it's going to lead to increased
insulin resistance, and thereby default going to lead to increased cardiovascular disease.
We know that a therapeutic carbohydrate restricted diet brings down so many cardiovascular risk
biomarkers that we're all used to hearing about. Okay, it decreases triglycerides. Okay,
it actually can reverse type 2 diabetes in most cases, and certainly significantly improve
glycemic control in all. But fatty acids, that's not something that's talked about all that
often. And what is talked about all that often is this idea of you are what you eat, right? We
hear that still every day. Remember, you are what you eat. And this example of what happens when you
consume saturated fat in the matrix of a diet that includes carbohydrate restriction is so against
that long worn out idea of you are what you eat. And so fatty acids play a critical role. Study after
study will show us in cardiovascular risk and in future diabetes risk as well. But again, it's not
discussed because fatty acids are confusing, let's face it, okay? And most people would rather just
fall back on this idea, you are what you eat, which just really flies counter to what the
evidence in the peer reviewed published literature says. So maybe taking even a greater step back
from that, Sarah, what is it that attracted you personally as a physician towards the management
of type 2 diabetes? Because, I mean, that's how you and I got to know each other was through a
company that you're a big part of called Virta Health, which I'm sure at some point today we
will talk about. But what attracted you to this patient population? And how is it that you stumbled
upon the idea that there was perhaps another way to treat patients with type 2 diabetes that was not
kind of the standard treatment, which was chasing glycemic control with insulin or
insulin increasing drugs? Well, I tell you, it's by accident. If you had told me 20 years ago that
I'd be playing this role in the healthcare system, I probably wouldn't have believed you. So it goes
back again to the fact that for a very long time, I mean, I've been in the world of obesity care
for well over 25 years now. And just the first half of that was telling people that the way to
fix everything was to eat a low calorie, low fat diet. I grew up as a product of the 80s,
like so many people where that was the dogma and there was no other way. And of course,
entering into college and grad school where I got both my bachelor's and master's in exercise
physiology, I mean, that's what we were taught. Moving on to med school, reaffirmed once again.
So when I went into practice as a primary care physician, I'm board certified in internal
medicine, it was more the same. But again, it was so frustrating to me, all along the way,
really to be continually giving this advice and then have people show up being worse.
I'm not making them healthier, I'm making them or I'm watching them become more unhealthy. And that
was depressing. And it was really quickly became just to the point where it was like, I can't
continue on with primary care for the rest of my life because I felt like a legal drug dealer.
I got really lucky here. Okay. I like to say a lot of my pivots are pivoted on anger, right?
Pivots in my career. And I was really angry at what was happening on the primary care level.
And as luck would have it at Indiana University Health, they knew about my background, knew about
my past work in obesity care and asked me to start a program, obesity program. And I jumped at the
opportunity and I was lucky to be able to take some time off over the next year, spend time
figuring out what was this going to look like? How are we going to tackle the untackable, if you will,
problem that is obesity? And I started sticking my nose in the literature, which is something that
every physician wants to do, but not every physician is afforded the time. Let's face it,
we are just boom, boom, boom, see patients. There's just such a busy lifestyle in everything
right now, but I was given a chance to step back some. So I had time to prepare for this. And in
that I discovered carbohydrate restriction as a means to weight loss initially. I listened to some
lectures by Dr. Steve Finney and Jeff Fullik. And I was like, whoa, that makes total physiologic
sense. And so boy, did I dig deeper into this. I read everything I could get my hands on and really
came to the conclusion, which required a lot of cognitive dissidents overcoming that what I had
been saying, you know, for well over a decade to so many people was really not founded on good
science. And that the field of carbohydrate restriction while still relatively in its
infancy at the time showed much more promise. And so we opened the clinic as a carbohydrate
restricted clinic. But the fact of the matter is, although people were losing weight, what we were
seeing that was so much more meaningful was that people's diabetes was like going away. They were
having normal blood sugar. We were pulling them off of insulin at rates that I could never have
believed had I not been the physician who was taking care of these patients. I was astronaut.
Sarah, just a couple of questions.
Hundreds of units of insulin.
Sorry, just to interject. Did you, first of all, there's two questions, I guess I want to ask you.
One, were these patients primarily patients with type 2 diabetes or was it primarily obesity
of which a subset had diabetes? And secondly, how much resistance did you have in your own institution
when you showed up and said, hey, I know you guys brought me in to do this thing. I'm going to do it.
But oh, by the way, my secret sauce is going to be this at the time, very unconventional approach.
Great question. So as you probably can imagine, when patients come into an obesity clinic,
most all of them, if not all of them, have some form of metabolic disease,
you know, the biggest being type 2 diabetes. So we were seeing type 2 diabetes all of the time,
consistently daily. And you're right. I had to take precautions because again, this was 10 years ago.
And not as much about carbohydrate restriction was known at that time, certainly among general
practicing physicians in any discipline, really. And so I knew that I had to head off the potential
resistance that was going to come. There was just no question of it. So I actually went about and
spent an entire summer meeting with all the departments in our local med center and giving
them a 15 minute slide presentation of when your patient comes back, says that Dr. Hallberg told
them to eat a lot of fat and not a lot of carbohydrates, that I wasn't crazy, that this
was actually based on evidence. And here it was. And you know, Peter, you'd be surprised. I didn't
get any pushback. I actually pushed it even to the next level. I was part at that time of the
ambulatory quality committee at our institution. And I actually brought up a amendment that all
patients with metabolic disease should at least be provided the option of trying this if they wanted.
And it passed unanimously. I mean, people got it. Once they had time to pause, take a look at the
physiology behind this and realize, okay, yeah, that makes a lot of sense. So it changed my life.
Right. And again, I like to always say my career is built of inflection points of anger.
And as we were seeing these huge changes of diabetes and patients just resolving their
diabetes, I became really angry because I was like, where is this? Where is this in the guidelines?
How come I've never heard of this before? I mean, this is, you know, I mean, I hate to be
like over dramatic, but it truly is quite miraculous for a disease that everyone thought
was chronic and progressive to see people recover from it. It's quite astounding.
And so I decided that I needed to get into research. So actually, to start off with,
I called Purdue University's nutrition program and asked one of the researchers there if they
wanted to help me on just an early unfunded pilot study to prove my point, looking at metabolic
improvements and looking at financial improvements too, because obviously, if people weren't taking
all this medicine, they weren't costing themselves and of course the healthcare system as a whole as
much money. And so I talked about that study presented at the National Lipid Association
quite a long time ago, talked about it actually in my TED talk, and then was speaking at the
Obesity Medicine Association quite a long time ago and actually met Dr. Steve Finney.
And that really changed the course of my life as well.
So all this time, you're sort of putting into practice what Steve and Jeff had been writing
about for a long time. And obviously, Steve is someone I've been dying to have on the podcast,
and we were actually supposed to do it at one point in time, and then scheduling got in the way.
But I didn't realize that you had already sort of gone down this path and yet hadn't actually
met him because I took the opposite approach, which was when I started kind of implementing some of
these treatments, I'm just a bull in a china shop. I just reached out to Steve right away.
I might have been one of the first people to get a copy of the book that he and Jeff wrote in 2011.
I think I got a pre-print of that book, which I still have by the way. The Art and Science.
The Art and Science book, which I have. It might have more highlights and
post-its in it than any book I own. Because I think like you, I was kind of going through the,
this can't be. There's something so counterintuitive to this that I need to read this over
and over and over, going to make sure I get it. So it's funny that that's the case. Now, tell me,
were you at this time going to ADA meetings, the American Diabetes Association meetings?
And when you would discuss what you were seeing in your practice with your peers,
who were also on the front lines, taking a more traditional approach,
how was your experience being, how was that met? Well, it's interesting. If someone,
if I was speaking with someone who took care of obesity patients for obesity, they were totally,
I get it. I'm doing the same thing to some varying degree. But when you moved out of that
space to other sub-specialists, the first thing was, oh yeah, their diabetes will go away, but
you're going to kill them with heart disease. Or, oh, we all know it works. I'll never forget one
of the leaders in the endocrine movement said, look, we all know it works. This is not a secret,
but nobody can stay with it. And I was like, I don't know here in my practice. I have thousands
of patients that would beg to differ with that. And so those are the feedback that I got. And so
one of the things was I knew that there had to be even more research done. I mean, we had wonderful
pioneers in Steve and Jeff and Eric from Duke, Westman. But we needed even more. They needed to
be larger trials. They needed to really specifically focus on patients with type 2 diabetes, because I
was convinced almost from the get-go that that is the target population here, because that's where
we see the biggest improvements. And so this CHANCE meeting with Steve at a obesity medicine
association conference led to a dinner and led to funding of the large clinical trial that
we're actually wrapping up in the next couple of months. Right now we're at the tail end of our
five-year data collection of the longest and largest trial looking at nutritional ketosis as
a means of reversing type 2 diabetes and prediabetes, which I'll just kind of stick in really quick here.
Today actually happens to be the day that the prediabetes paper was published. So I'm really
proud to say this is the eighth paper already that's come out of this large trial, started by
a CHANCE encounter at a conference. And we haven't published the prediabetes results until today. So
this was a paper that looks at the first two years of prediabetes utilizing remote continuous support
to help patients adhere to a diet aimed at nutritional ketosis. And Sarah, these are
patients defined as prediabetic by hemoglobin A1c? Correct. And that's being defined as 5.7 to 6.4,
is that the range? That's correct. Okay. Tell people what that means. I think most people
are aware of what a hemoglobin A1c is, but what does that translate to in an average glucose
approximately? Yeah. So we really start to get, for example, fasting. That's the one most people
are familiar with. And once you get a fasting glucose over 110, that's the worrisome
prediabetes range. And I do have to say here though, that doesn't mean normal glucoses
are okay for everyone. And I think you've had many people on here talking about the perils
of insulin resistance and how it starts to cause significant problems in people who still have
normal blood sugars. And I just think that's such an important point and can't be overstated again.
But in this study, we're looking at people who had insulin resistance long enough that their
pancreas and the beta cells could not keep up with the insulin that was needed to keep blood
sugar normal and their blood sugar started to rise. Not yet to the level where a diagnosis of
type 2 diabetes could be made, but once again where we see the impact of insulin resistance
affecting the body's ability to keep blood sugar normal due to pancreas being overworked
for far too long. And if we believe that, I mean, I don't know what the latest numbers are, but I'm
guessing it's still about 10% of the US population has type 2 diabetes. Is that approximately correct
or is it, are we more than 10% now? Approximately with also the caveat of much more concerning
levels in different minority populations, which of course hopefully we'll get a chance to talk
about later is just a huge goal with improving health equity in this country. So if it's 10%
in all comers, do you have a sense of what it is in Hispanic and African-American populations?
Yeah, it gets even higher. It's well into the teens and those and Pacific Islanders as well.
So these are populations that, you know, we need to be paying attention of course to everyone who
has type 2 diabetes, but we also need to be paying attention to who's at greater risk.
So what percentage of the population do we believe is in the pre-di-formally in the pre-diabetic
camp, which again, I think what you said a moment ago is very important for people to understand.
If we go back to the podcast with Jerry Shulman, which is one of my favorite discussions ever on
the topic of insulin resistance. I mean, Jerry really laid out elegantly the long time course
of this disease. And even, you know, even if you have normal fasting glucose and fasting insulin,
but that early sign of elevated postprandial insulin is really that early sign of insulin
resistance that will then lead to postprandial glucose elevations. And even that can still
exist in the presence of normal fasting glucose. So to your point, by the time someone registers
as a pre-diabetic, quote unquote, I mean, this has been a process that's been going on for 5 to
10 years. What is our belief about how many or what percentage of Americans just to make it,
you know, American centric for a moment, what percentage of Americans are in that bucket?
Well, I tell you, you know, studies, recent studies will show us that over 50% of Americans,
adult Americans have diabetes or prediabetes. And a study released a couple of years ago,
and I mean, this, this should shock everyone to its core based on NHANES data that 88%
of Americans are not in optimal metabolic health. I mean, let me say that again. 88%
of adult Americans are not in optimal metabolic health. And that is by looking at NHANES data
and taking a look at the criteria for metabolic syndrome. And so, you know, the 12% are those
who didn't meet any of the criteria for metabolic syndrome. Okay. I mean, that's frightening. Yeah,
so I was going to, I was going to ask you if that's exactly what it meant. So just let's state
for the, for the listener, what metabolic syndrome is. We've certainly discussed it on this podcast,
but it would be great to remind people, what are those 12% doing? They have none of the following
five, right? They have normal blood pressure, though they do not have elevated blood pressure.
And again, and they're not on medication, they're not taking medication to lower blood pressure.
And normal is now being much more stringently defined, but I believe the latest CDC definition
of normal is less than 130 over 80. In our practice, we advocate less than 120 over 80.
They have normal fasting glucose, and that's defined as less than 100. They have normal
triglycerides, which are being defined as less than 150. We argue in our practice, that's very
high. And anything over 100 is elevated. Totally agree. They have normal HDL cholesterol, which for
men is defined as greater than 40 milligrams per deciliter for women greater than 50 milligrams per
deciliter. And they do not have truncal obesity. And I forget, I think for men that's defined as
40 inches of waist circumference in women 36. I don't know if that's, if that's still the latest.
Well, yeah. And I will also point out one really important thing here when it comes to waist
circumference too. And the definition of metabolic syndrome, and it little bit goes back to what I
was saying before about the consideration of minorities in different ethnic populations,
which is we have to take the, that into account, even when we're defining metabolic syndrome.
Because for Southeast Asians, they are defined as having metabolic syndrome at a much lower
waist circumference. And for African Americans, we need to really consider as well because they tend,
even in the face of having insulin resistance, they tend to have normal triglycerides and HDL.
And so again, you know, we can't be treating everybody the same, but we often do.
Yeah, I'm glad you pointed that out. I still remember it was about 10 years ago when I
learned that lesson, which was, you know, taking care of an African American patient who had
about the most uncontrolled diabetes I'd ever seen, you know, hemoglobin A1C of 14%. This is
a person who's basically going to have their limbs amputated in the next hour. Triglycerides of 89.
Just, yeah, just totally normal. You look at their lipid panel, you wouldn't think anything is wrong.
Right. And so that's the thing is they can get missed. And so, you know, knowing this and
educating people on things like this, again, goes back to our working on health equities.
And it's so important and so often not something people take into account. And just going back to
prediabetes, you know, the most frustrating thing, I shouldn't say that it's one of the most
frustrating things. There are many things about our healthcare system I could enter into the most
frustrating. But one of them is patients coming in to see me whose lab showed prediabetes. And I
said, oh, you have prediabetes. Oh, no, no, no. My physician said I was fine. And so the, the fact
that we don't appreciate that by the time you get to prediabetes, there's some really serious things
going on here. You know, their, their vision is being impacted. You know, their nerves are being
impacted. You know, these are things we can't just say, oh, they haven't, they haven't gotten
bad enough to bother with because they're not at, you know, the criteria for type 2 diabetes yet.
I mean, we have to pay attention. And so if that's one thing, if there's any, you know, physicians
listening, which I know that there are, don't ignore any elevation in blood sugar. That means
there's been a problem for a long time already. And, and, and patients should be also hypervigilant
about this. I mean, I've seen patients in that prediabetic camp, and this is using an example
of a male patient when they're, when their insulin sensitivity is restored and their blood glucose,
you know, comes down by an average of 10 milligrams per deciliter, they'll say, wow,
I have better erections all of a sudden. And that speaks to even the microvascular damage that's
being done long before you get to diabetes. You know, I actually was exchanging emails with a
really good ophthalmologist recently and kind of trying to ask how far are we away from being able
to use retinal imaging as a screening tool for early, early, early microvascular disease? Because
I think the hemoglobin A1c is just far too crude a metric for this. And I actually have seen some
interesting literature, and I'm sure you've seen even more of it that suggests that this is, you
know, if you look at the microvascular in the eye, it might be one of the earliest warning signs of
when things go awry. And so in an ideal world, I would love it if, you know, we had, you know,
tech that basically allowed for quick and easy evaluation of that. So that to your point,
it doesn't really matter if your trigs are up or down and your waist is big or not, like let's
look at the actual place where the damage is taking place and make the assessment on an
individualized basis, as opposed to using these sort of population based metrics,
which move in the right direction, but for any one individual can be quite misleading.
Yeah. And then I love the eye discussion because, you know, one of the other, I think,
really important questions is once we do get to damage, can we make it better? Can we make it
better, you know, without and skip some of the horrors of having diabetic eye disease for
millions of patients? I mean, that is a really burning question for me. And one that I think we
need to really explore. Yeah, indeed. So with that background, let's kind of dive into some of this
nerdy, nerdy fatty acid stuff. And I got to tell you, I find this stuff really interesting in part
because I think it's complicated enough to make sense of just the eating side of this stuff. In
other words, you know, just for the listener, you know, I think people that have listened to this
podcast, we've done a number of shows that have dealt with fatty acids. People probably understand
that there are saturated fats, monounsaturated fats and polyunsaturated fats. The saturated
fats have no double bonds. So that means every carbon is fully saturated with hydrogen. The
monounsaturated have one and only one unsaturation. So one double bond and then the polys have at least
two of these double bonds. But it's the manner in which these things can be made from each other
that becomes quite interesting, isn't it? It's really the way that you can ingest one form and
it can be turned into another. So I'm wondering if the easiest place to begin this discussion
is to introduce what the fate of a very common fat in our body is, which is the C16 saturated fat. So
can you talk a little bit about how abundant that is and what our body's options are for? What it's
called? Let's start with the nomenclature. What does what does pure C16 look like? That's
palmitolytic acid. And so it's really interesting what happens. And do you mind if I jump on and
share screen here? Yes, please. A little bit more about it. Yeah, that would make it easier for
everybody, I'm sure. I want to start by talking about saturated fatty acids in general. Okay.
And what we know is that going back here to the basics and looking at the liver,
when we have incorporation of saturated fatty acids into our triglycerides,
okay, that is correlated with insulin resistance and adiposity, okay, likely reflecting accelerated
hepatic de novo lipogenesis, okay, or also it can be what is actually returned to the liver. So
really two. We certainly know that hepatic de novo lipogenesis is a big part of the problem
when it comes to elevated triglycerides, but we can also make these with some what is delivered
exactly back to the liver. And so when we see saturated fatty acids, okay, as a makeup of
triglycerides or maybe even the phospholipids there, we say, oh my goodness, that's a marker of
increased saturated fatty acid consumption, right? These people are eating a high saturated fat diet.
And that seems to make sense. And this is the problem with a lot of things in science in general,
and nutrition science is no different, is that just because it seems to make sense doesn't mean
it's the way things actually work, okay? Sarah, can I explain a technical point on this slide that
you and I will take for granted, but I want to make sure that a listener understands. Absolutely,
please do. So when a patient goes and gets their blood drawn, let's just say they get a standard
lipid panel, it will spit out the following values. Total cholesterol equals 200 milligrams per
deciliter. LDL cholesterol equals 140 milligrams per deciliter. Triglycerides equal 150 milligrams
per deciliter. HDL cholesterol is 35 milligrams per deciliter. And VLDL cholesterol, if I remember
the numbers I just spit out, would be 25 milligrams per deciliter. In other words, the VLDL cholesterol,
HDL cholesterol, and LDL cholesterol sum to the total, and then the triglycerides are independent.
What I want to make sure people understand is those are all found within the lipoproteins.
So VLDL cholesterol is the amount of cholesterol ester contained within the very low density
lipoprotein. LDL cholesterol is the total content of cholesterol ester found within the low density
lipoprotein, etc., for the HDL. Here's the part that's really interesting. We always check these
things fasting because when it comes to measuring the triglyceride, we want to eliminate what's in
the chylomicron. We want to eliminate the immediately absorbed triglyceride from the gut.
And by doing that, we basically capture what you have on this photo. When we measure a triglyceride,
for all intents and purposes, we are basically measuring the 90% of triglycerides that are
captured within the VLDL. Let me restate that because that was a bit rambling. When you go to
the doctor and get your blood tested, and it says your triglycerides are 150 milligrams per deciliter,
that's basically saying, look, 90% of that 150 milligrams per deciliter is within your VLDL
cholesterol. Some of that is in intermediate density lipoprotein, but that's virtually
non-existent. There's a trace of that in the LDL cholesterol and even a smaller trace in the HDL,
but it's the lion's share is in the VLDL cholesterol. And as you're going to explain to us,
this process of de novo lipogenesis, the conduit from fat being made in the liver and exported,
that conduit is the VLDL particle. That's going to become very important in this discussion.
Absolutely. Absolutely. Yeah, and that's really important. Thank you for the precursor explanation
because this is technical stuff and that is really important for people to understand.
So then the next question really becomes, okay, so if we have a high saturated fatty acid content
within the VLDL, again, it's being in the triglycerides, the phospholipid membrane,
wherever we find it, where did the saturated fatty acids come from? Is it directly from
consumption? And I just want to first point out before we get into maybe more of the technical
stuff, some of the clinical trials that can help us understand this a little bit better.
And so this is one of my favorites by Dr. Brittany Volk that was published a while ago. And it's
really great because this was a feeding study. So, you know, they kept track of what the patients
were eating. It wasn't a free for all. Are they eating what they were telling them to eat or not?
They provided all of their food. And this was patients with metabolic syndrome. They went
through six feeding phases. And so they did a run-in with a very low carbohydrate diet for everyone,
less than 50 grams of carbohydrates a day. And every three weeks they increased the carbohydrates
in the diet all the way up to 346 grams, which was C6 feeding phase. The other thing to note here
is the saturated fat content. So when we were at the low carbohydrate end here in C1,
they were consuming 84 grams of saturated fatty acids a day. Okay. So that blows away any guideline
on saturated fat. I mean, so far above what anyone would consider at goal. And then we get down to the
C6 and we're much less 32 grams. Again, what happens to the fatty acids as people are run
through these six phases? And Sarah, just to be clear, this is basically an isocaloric feeding
study, which means as you're ratcheting up the content of carbohydrate, you're commensurately
reducing at a caloric level, the amount of saturated fat, right? I believe this study did
not change the number of calories they were consuming or did it? Correct. They did not.
And so what happened to the saturated fatty acid levels in the blood and for that matter,
other fatty acid levels in the blood. So what happened over these six phases? Okay. So here we
have saturated fatty acid levels marked. Okay. So here's the baseline at that run-in. Okay. And we
see when we have the very high saturated fat level, very low carbohydrate. Okay. Here we go.
And what's really interesting is what happens as we march along here down to C6. And if you
remember, this is much lower saturated fatty acid content of the diet. Okay. Much higher
carbohydrate intake. What we see is that it's actually the saturated fatty acid content is
actually higher with the lower saturated fat intake. And we're going to come back and talk
to about the science behind that. But I think it's really important for people to see this clinically.
And then maybe when we get into a little bit more of the nitty gritty, it can make more sense. Okay.
I mean, it's actually statistically insignificant in terms of C16, right? Which is the dominant
saturated fatty acid. So, so palmitic acid, it trended towards an increase as saturated fat,
dietary saturated fat went down and carbohydrate went up, but it didn't reach significance. And
the only one that actually did significantly increase was C14, right? Yeah. Actually, C16,
one as well. And that one is we're going to send a little bit of time. Oh, yes. But, but, but,
but yeah, yeah, yeah. No, but as a saturated fat, it was really just, yeah.
Oh, as a saturated fat. Yes. Yeah. So. But the point of this is we didn't have these really high
levels of serum saturated fatty acids when we were consuming, when these participants were
consuming this very high saturated fat diet. Yeah. I mean, essentially, and this is important,
it stays the same. If anything, there's a trend, okay, to higher serum saturated fat
in the low fat arm. Okay. But certainly we do not see a rise in the high intake of saturated fat.
That's super important. And again, it goes against what I was saying earlier on, you know, you are
what you eat. Well, okay. If that's true, then when I consume a very high level of saturated
fatty acids, why am I not seeing that again in the blood in the serum? Why are we not seeing that?
And what's nice in this study is you've exhaustively looked at where the fatty acids are. So obviously
the most efficient place we store fatty acids is in the triglyceride, but you also store it within
the cholesterol ester and it's obviously in the phospholipid as well. But regardless of where you
look, you see no association between dietary saturated fat and fatty acid composition with
respect to saturated fat. That's right. That's right. And I want to really quick draw attention
here to one more that we are going to be talking more about and that's 16, one. That's palmitoleic
acid. And we're going to talk more about why that's important. But as we can see here, when we
follow that across, it significantly rises when we have less saturated fat and more carbohydrates.
And you can see that is statistically significantly different in every place that we're looking.
So moving on, when we take here a low saturated fat diet, low fat, low saturated fat diet,
and we compare it to a low carbohydrate, high saturated fat diet over 12 weeks. This is from
Jeff Volek's group from 2008. And what I like here is you can see very readily with these pie
charts exactly what the content of the two diets were. So again, we really have it flipped, you know,
high carbohydrate, low carbohydrate, low fat here on the left to a very high intake of fat on the
right. And again, below it, the two different levels of saturated fat that we're comparing,
12 grams to three times as high in the low carb diet at 36. So then these are both, these are both
really low calorie studies. Was this an ad lib feeding study or were these deliberately calorie
restricted? How was this study done? Yeah, these were both that wanted the calorie intake of
the two studies to be the same. So as you can see, there are about 1500 calories apiece. And were
they deliberately calorie restricted? Yes. Okay. So what we can see here is that what we have,
when we take a look at these two arms is taking a look on the right to the change in serum saturated
fatty acids. We can see in the carb restricted diet, you know, significant decrease versus the
low fat diet. So again, in the much higher saturated fatty acid arm, we see a significant
decrease down. Okay. Whereas we do see a drop in the saturated fatty low saturated fatty
acid intake group, but not nearly as much as we see with the carbohydrate restricted group.
Once again, you know, arguing against you are what you eat. And I want to now get in a little
bit more to this, what I think is actually even more important, which is the change in the
palmitic acid, excuse me, palmitoleic acid, get all these palm messed up when I try to talk about
it easier to just think of it as 16, one. Yeah. So, so palmitoleic acid is 16, zero. Palmitoleic
acid is 16, one. They look almost the same except that palmitoleic, the 16, one has that double bond
at the end seven position. And you're going to explain in a moment, which enzyme does that and
why that matters. Right. Right. Absolutely. You know, what is it about this? It's not a,
it's not a saturated fatty acid. So why do we care so much? What happens to 16, one,
but it's pretty evident here, what happens first of all. And then we'll talk about why
what happens is that with 16, one in the high saturated fatty acid group, it drops significantly
where in the low fat group, again, low saturated fatty acid group, it actually goes up. And this
is a statistically significant difference. Okay. Much more significant even as we look
than the change in the serum fatty acids. All right. So now I'm going to pull up a graph
of these results to look at it a little better. And then I want to get into the actual science of it.
This is the very low carbohydrate arm on the left and it is the low fat arm on the right.
And so what we see here, when we look at total saturated fatty acids, is that it has dropped,
okay, 5% between the low carbohydrate group and the low fat group, total saturated fatty acids.
What about the 16, one? And what we see here with the 16, one in much more significant
statistically is that we see between a low carbohydrate diet and a low fat diet,
that we have a more significant decrease in the 16, one with the low carbohydrate higher fat diet.
Now, so there's a couple of things going on here. Any questions or comments for there? Yeah. Yeah.
I think there's a couple of things going on for people that are going to be overwhelmed by this
table. And I apologize if you're just listening to this without watching it on video, I'll do my
best to explain what's going on here. So the first thing to notice here is both of these
groups of patients started out with quite elevated triglycerides. So in the first group, in the group
that was randomized to the very low carbohydrate diet, their average triglyceride at the start of
this study was 211 milligrams per deciliter. That's sky high. At the end of 12 weeks, it was down to
about 104 milligrams per deciliter. It fell by about 50%. Conversely, the group that started out
in the low fat arm, also very high triglycerides to start 187 milligrams per deciliter. By the end
of 12 weeks, they saw about a 20% reduction to about 150 milligrams per deciliter. Now this is
where these tables get a little bit confusing because the table is showing both the relative
and absolute reduction of the relative or constitutive fatty acid, in this case 16-0 and 16-1
and 7-2 we're talking about. What does that mean in English? It means that when you look at the total
amount of saturated fat reduction on a relative basis, both groups saw a slight reduction. But
it was statistically more significant in one group than the other. The low carb group was a 12%
reduction versus 5% in the low fat group. On an absolute basis, that difference was even greater
because the low carb group had such a significant reduction in total triglyceride as well. That's
the dominant source of where you're going to see these fatty acids. Of course, the reverse is true
when it comes to 16-1. Let's now ask the question, Sarah, what is it about palmitoleic acid
that you think is such an important biomarker? Because we wouldn't be having this discussion
if you didn't think we should be paying attention to this. Yeah, I think it's a really important
biomarker and if you would allow me, let me point out one other thing here regarding the triglycerides
because clearly the low carbohydrate arm decreased more in the triglycerides. The low fat arm
decreased too, which may come as a surprise to your listeners because we do associate low fat
with an increase in triglycerides. But I do want to remind everyone that this was a calorie
restricted. This was around 1500 calories. So that drop in the low fat diet arm, although maybe not
what we were expected, does make sense with the reduction in calories overall. Now, let's go back
and talk more about your question. I think palmitoleic acid, or again that's that 16-1,
is really not appreciated as the health predictor that it really is. So let's go through, I'm going
to just jump ahead a little bit here. So palmitoleic, or we like to call it POA, is a product of
something called sterile CoA desaturase. And sterile CoA desaturase is going to determine
what is going to happen with some of the fatty acids in our system. Specifically,
what's going to happen to POA? Now what we know ahead is that sterile CoA desaturase
is actually an independent marker of triglyceridemia and abdominal adiposity. So in other words,
an independent marker of all those things that go along with insulin resistance. So if we have a
high levels of sterile CoA desaturase activity, right there we got to start thinking things may be
concerning even if someone has a normal blood sugar. Because right now I think one of the
important things based on the earlier part of our conversation where we say so many times these
things are missed, people can still have normal blood sugars, it's going to be really important.
You know, number one that we make everyone aware that a normal blood sugar doesn't mean that you
are healthy. But number two, what are some easy ways and some easy markers maybe that we can check
to know that we're headed for trouble even before we have blood sugar go up. Okay so plasma
triglycerides and let's take a look at again POA in those plasma triglycerides
in the way of looking at it in core tiles. So again low versus high and what we can see is the POA
all right the byproduct of sterile CoA desaturase is much higher the higher the triglycerides are.
Very important so if your triglycerides are really high again what's happening very likely
is that your POA is elevated as well okay brought about by increased activity of sterile
CoA desaturase. And this shouldn't be surprising right because if you look at the very you know
unfriendly diagrams of fatty acid metabolism one of the first steps we see in the conversion
of or elongation of fatty acids is the conversion of C16O palmitic acid into C161 palmitoleic acid
and seven through an enzyme that has two names I guess depending on the name of nomenclature right
so delta 9 desaturase desaturate the number nine carbon from the delta end also known as sterile
CoA desaturase which I think is the more popular name is SCD1 right. And if you go down that
pathway what you're basically doing is bundling and packaging fat to leave the liver right.
Yes and here is one of the that is an interesting point because the question is if we're trying to
change the serum saturated fats into something else okay I mean the body is obviously doing that
one would have to wonder is that a protection mechanism why do we want to do that?
Yeah to me that's a great question Sarah it seems counterintuitive if I'm going to be obvious because
we would think that a saturated fat is much safer it's inert there's no chance of reactive
oxygen species can be formed out of it. Why is it our body even if we wanted to export fat from
the liver which we could argue all the reasons that's not a great idea why would we go to the
trouble of this conversion? All right well let's go through it really quick and then get to answering
that question because I think it's really important and really sheds light on why we need to be paying
more attention to the all-important POA and of course the precursors and enzymes that act in its
creation. So let's go through if you will this cartoon that I know looks really busy initially
but let me just kind of run through it starting here in the intestine and remember you know we'll
start off by saying our focus in healthcare and in nutrition recommendations for so long has been
low fat low fat more carbohydrates higher carbohydrates well let's take a look in the
intestine at those carbohydrates changing the focus for a minute. So they come in rapidly
absorbed carbohydrates or even are slowly absorbed carbohydrates are starches okay and what happens
when they come in right as glucose that feeds in again through glute two into the pancreas
pushing out more insulin insulin then feeds into the liver and what we get here okay is going
through it a big big part of this is SREBP1 okay and I don't know if we need to get that technical
but we'll lead here to that enzyme we were talking about the SCD1 or sterile coa desaturase
increasing okay very important and it comes about through other means as well fructose coming in
through glute five or glucose coming directly into the liver through glute two they're all
feeding into this by slightly different mechanisms to increase this SCD1. Now we're going to look
more at the process in a different way so we have increased hepatic first of all saturated fat
okay here's our 16-0 the saturated fat all right increase hepatic levels of this
what gets turned on as from the past cartoon we get that SCD1 activity increasing that leads to
this increase in POA all right coming down here what's the end game here increased VLDL
all right same thing over here looking at it different we see again SCD1 if it's blocked
we won't see that all right we'll see a decrease in VLDL and this again has to do if this SCD
enzyme is blocked we're going to have an increase in the saturate a decrease in our POA okay but
again what we have when we're consuming the high carbohydrates even if they're the again
more refined carbohydrates or the less rapidly absorbed carbohydrates this is the path that we
wind up going on 16-1 is or 16-0 saturated fat is elevated and it turns on this cascade leading to
increase in VLDL I'll pause there before we go on if you had any comments that you wanted to add
here yeah again I think you know for folks that are watching this it's going to make a bit more
sense and if you're not I just want to make sure we're bringing you along for the ride so
you know in the liver when you are taking C16 or C18 but let's just keep the discussion simple
and start with a saturated C16 it's the first committed step is going through SCD1 as an enzyme
and it adds that double bond it makes a few more steps along the way but ultimately it is
increasing a process of lipogenesis it is making more lipid it is increasing the amount of lipid
within the cholesterol ester and the triglyceride it is being exported from the liver so in response
to your question Sarah is this protective I guess the answer looks like the body is saying well gosh
I would rather get this fat out of the liver than keep it in the liver and we know that it's not
fully successful in doing that because of course although it hasn't come up yet on this discussion
everything we've talked about today runs hand in hand with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease
which is truly an epidemic at the moment but I suspect that the body is still doing its best
even in the case of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease to try to export this fat as much as
possible the triglyceride is a very efficient place to store it I've always believed obesity
is a protective mechanism I think that obesity is not the cause of metabolic illness but the
result of it which is not to say that the inflammatory environment that comes with it
doesn't pour more gasoline on that fire but I you know it is my belief that everything we're
talking about here is the body's aim to protect itself from an abundance of nutrition and so
that's how I read this is the body is doing and specifically the liver which is I arguably the
most important organ in this situation and the liver is really trying to protect us and it's
saying I'm making so much extra fat right now because you as my individual are so far above
your carbohydrate consumption tolerance your tolerance for carbohydrate consumption and this
is the most efficient thing I can do which is turn that into fat send it out via the VLDL get that
into the adipose site and yeah you're going to be a little bit fatter and it's going to come with
some downstream problems but in the short term it's protecting me the liver do you would you
agree with my teleologic view of that? I 100% would agree with it and again you know it's I
think that we're going to have more and more details on this coming out very very soon in
many research projects that are currently ongoing but what it really comes down to is you know we
want to know what an individual's carbohydrate tolerance is okay I mean that's key to personalization
right does everybody need to be very low carbohydrate low carbohydrate I mean where does we
can say population level what happens in large clinical trials but what's happening with the
individual because let's face it Peter and you know you and I as practicing clinicians know this
when you're sitting with one patient in front of you you can go over group data from a clinical
trial and that's important part of the decision making but the only thing that really matters
is what's going to happen with the patient right in front of you we really want to know what the
individualized reaction is going to be you know we know that this happens with a carbohydrate
consumption above a certain threshold but what that certain threshold is in the individual we
don't know and based on these pathways you know what is the marker we want to be looking at
actually it's probably POA surprisingly not a fatty acid but what this tells us is that when
someone has consumed carbohydrates above their individual tolerance that POA level is going to
be a great biomarker it's going to go up as again a protective mechanism in the liver our livers are
really I mean you know we talk about livers all the time so related to insulin resistance it's just
always amazing just how sophisticated and how our livers although we think of them as producing
things that aren't necessarily good for us and that may be true they're also really working for
us as well and so again I want to also go back on one other thing that you said and the other
thing that you said is so this comes you know before the adiposity and I think that that is
such an important point and one I like to preach every opportunity I can get it but this is starting
to happen before people gain a lot of weight okay this is a disease process in and of itself that
causes obesity so you know we have to really take that into account when we're in the office with
someone who's struggling for with obesity and I know Peter you take this really to heart of
approaching and treating these patients without bias and as I do but it's it's so important for
other providers to be looking themselves in the mirror and asking themselves you know what are
the biases I hold against patients who come to me struggling with their weight and what do I really
know about the science and what it really one must conclude is that this is not their fault okay
these are things that happened beforehand and they're suffering the consequences of it and the
problem is the consequence is on full view for everyone to see it's not something that they can
hide and that makes them so vulnerable to bias in health care and again one of the other things I
come back to is part of our whole battle in health equity. So Sarah I want to keep digging into this
idea because it's so interesting to me of having a leading indicator for you know this early early
early warning sign you know I mean I we talked about it at the outset of this discussion which
is you know in some ways the tragedy of using hemoglobin A1c as the marker of when somebody
gets on the radar I mean you said it yourself patients will show up and nobody's ringing the
bell until their hemoglobin A1c is above 6.5 but I mean that literally is happening 10, 15 maybe 20
years after there were early early molecular warning signs and if measuring palmitoleic acid
is one of them that's exactly the kind of stuff that I find interesting because in our practice
we use cgm a lot so continuous glucose monitoring is kind of you know we don't you know non-diabetics
are wearing cgm like it's no tomorrow in our practice because of that exact reason we're
basically holding them to a very high standard of average glucose and high excursions and all these
sorts of things. I want to go back to something that you alluded to which is the association
between palmitoleic acid and triglyceride is so tight that would we miss for example
african-american patients do we know if they are failing to synthesize cc16-1 in the way a white
patient is? Wouldn't we love to know that there's not been a good trial looking at that I mean one
of the problems that we have in research in general is that we tend to focus on white people
right you know and actually worse middle or upper middle class white people. So there are a lot of
questions with this in specific populations. There have been a couple of studies recently
coming out looking specifically at what we're talking about POA and its marker for future
problems and predictor of future diabetes and other issues. One was a study recently published
called the panic study looking at levels in childhood and seeing how they translate to health
consequences you know decades down the road and then there was another study I believe it was from
the netherlands where they looked at POA levels at 50 to correlate them with c-reactive protein
levels at age 70 right and what we see is what we would expect based on our our discussion here
which is the POA was a predictor of problems down the road in people who were healthy when their POA
was elevated or healthy so we thought you know what we really want to know ahead of time and I
know this is very meaningful to you and your practice is I want the person who's healthy
so I can get to tell them how to stay healthy okay we we talk a lot about you know trying to
work on people who are already so so to speak behind the eight ball and we want to work them
out and we want to regress their disease clearly an important goal but we also really if we're
going to make a difference again with the individual and population-wide we need to know who's headed
for trouble. Well I mean this is again I hope there's an ongoing effort here because I think
this is the future of medicine right I mean I think the future of medicine has to be coming up
with tools that allow us to take broad sweeping you know population-based insights and very quickly
target individuals and if we have biomarkers like this that can say look the moment this is triggered
above a certain level it doesn't really matter what your glucose is and your insulin might still
be normal this is time to intervene and then of course the second part of that equation is what's
the right intervention and how do we pair people to the right intervention and and again you and
I have a very similar set of experiences which is patients with hyperinsulinemia and elevated
glucose generally respond well to carbohydrate restriction. My practice also focuses so much on
the role of glucose disposal and non-insulin dependent glucose disposal through exercise
and I know that you know that that's probably not a surprise to many people is is sort of correcting
the sleep exercise nutrition trifecta and then adding to that the the role of cortisol in all of
this so I don't know I think this is I think this is a very hard problem to solve that's the bad
news but I think the good news is if you get this one right you get a leg up on every chronic disease
so your risk of heart disease cancer Alzheimer's disease all go down
and and so it's worth this enormous effort to to continue pushing on these questions
and I think you know on that note too you know and when we talk about individualization and
risk prediction before we're seeing our classic you know biomarker issues come up has to do I'll
circle it back to carbohydrate restriction because we know very low levels of carbohydrate restriction
can you know reverse the disease process bring about normal glycemia in patients and be able to
get them off of medications but we could put a risk predictor like POA into wider use okay
which would give a person their individual carbohydrate threshold what if it didn't need
to be as low what if we caught them earlier in the disease process and we're like hey buddy
you go over you know 175 you know that's where trouble comes in rather than you know you need to
stay very low um you know indefinitely because we've caught you on the spectrum of the disease
you know so late and this is what we really need to do to control this to keep your glucose normal
without the use of these many medications especially insulin I want to ask you other
question on this Sarah um and again I don't know if it applies to patients that you've treated
with diabetes or those in the pre-diabetes category but have you have you treated patients
for long enough on ketogenic or very low carbohydrate diets who showed up in a state
of metabolic disarray ran through a lengthy period of this so you know maybe spent years on a
carbohydrate restricted protocol and everything gets better so they you know the weight goes
along for the ride but obviously and more importantly their metabolic markers improve
and they gradually reintroduce some amount of carbohydrate back in the diet and all of a sudden
they're fine almost as though you reset them during a long enough period uh how often do you
see that and what do you think is the best explanation for that see it all the time and
the best explanation for it is what is their insulin reserve what is their insulin reserve
so you know the majority of people um can go ahead you know starting out even at long-standing
diabetes um reverse their disease get normal glycemia um get off of all their medications
and then slowly reintroduce carbohydrates as long as they have functioning beta cells
okay the problem is you know the longer you've had diabetes clearly is a risk factor for this
and we can you know we see evidence of that in the bariatric surgery literature as well
i mean there's been so many studies looking at um beta cells um but you know and the fascinating
thing is who is getting back some of their beta cell function in other words maybe their beta
cells were only dormant and were able to you know wake them up again versus which are
gone and not coming back i mean the fact that people were on the incredibly high dose of insulin
okay starting on a very low carbohydrate diet and then they got better right away
okay a lot of the change is swift but they couldn't get off insulin and it was just years
went by right and they're just staying on this much lower level of insulin and then all of a sudden
they come off of it i mean we logic would tell us that some sort of beta cell function has returned
it took a long time reset the system help them heal you know i mean we don't completely understand
this there's so many great scientists looking at this right now but we still don't have a certain
answer you know because the answers on the personalized level is how many are mine are
dormant how many of mine are dead right what's it going to take for me to wake these up you know
if it's impossible i'd like to know that because that sets expectations ahead of time right you
can get a lot better but there's always going to be a little insulin in your life it doesn't mean
if they are someone who doesn't have any insulin production capacity that they can't get a lot
healthier but they may not ever be able to get off of insulin and so that's where it gets down
once again into that nitty gritty personalization aspect and wouldn't that be nice to know but i
think that the answer to the larger question is you know why is this happening that some people
can start to eat carbohydrates not anywhere near to where they were but they're able to put some
back into their diets versus people who can't is beta cell function um and i think something in
there that you said is very important that i don't think historically has been communicated
well enough to patients which is that insulin while an amazing and important hormone is not
benign and there's a big difference between taking 100 units of insulin a day to achieve normal
glycemia and taking 20 units of insulin a day to achieve normal glycemia and you'll take the
ladder over the former all day every day non-negotiable um and some patients will say well gosh i'm still
on insulin this hasn't worked and not realizing no you've had a five-fold reduction in your insulin
requirement that's an enormous improvement in your health outcome not and let's put the economics
aside the economics are enormous but ignore that for a moment just in terms of health outcomes
uh the the negative effects of hyperinsulinemia um yeah and it i just what would want to say
with that you know if we really think about the way we we manage diabetes okay rather than work
to actually reverse the disease process and get people off of medication i mean management
constantly leads to more and more and more insulin which we know i mean on the outward the the
appearance of it is that people gain more weight when they go on more insulin but you know if we
really get down to the nuts and bolts when we take someone with type 2 diabetes whose glucose is out
of control to the point where we need to put them on insulin the mandatory discussion that needs to
occur is i'm going to put this medic i'm going to give this medication this insulin that you're
going to inject to you okay um and i'm going to do that because your blood sugars are so high that
they could acutely kill you okay put you into the hospital put you at risk of all these complications
but i just want you to know you're more likely to die on insulin that's what we need to tell people
that's the truth and you know that would have changed the approach a lot of patients want to
take and it would certainly if if providers were forced to look at it that way when they're staring
each individual person in the face maybe they would treat it differently as well yeah i i i
agree um so i want to talk about um something that that is you know been such a big part of your life
in the last few years and people who don't know you may be almost surprised at where we're going
in this discussion now but you know this discussion could basically continue down the path if we could
talk more about diabetes we could end this discussion here and and people would say wow
that's a really insightful thoughtful person but but there's a whole other side uh to to your
experience with healthcare sarah that started uh gosh four year almost four years ago um and i'll
tell it from just i'll tell the beginning of the story just from my end so you and i obviously
met each other uh through verta you're you know an early part of the the creation of this this
company which is basically scaling up a way to remotely treat patients with type 2 diabetes
uh this is a company of that that steve finney is also a co-founder of along with jeff olek i believe
i have a minimal involvement in that company i'm a small investor and and at one point was an advisor
but it was during one of these advisory meetings that you and i happen to be sitting next to each
other now we've met many times before that but i do remember this very well it was i think june of
2017 it was up in san francisco a large u-shaped uh table in the room and you know it was a two-day
ordeal and you were sitting to my left and that gave us more time than than most times to be
chatting about this that and the other thing and uh you looked in perfect health as always and
at the end of the second day i said goodbye and see you next time and blah blah blah blah blah
and then about a month later i heard from a mutual friend that you had been diagnosed
with lung cancer um and i just about fell off my chair so can you tell people what happened
that summer the summer of 2017 yeah so you know i'll just start by saying i i've been someone
who's taken taking care of themselves to um the max you know all my life eaten well i've kept my
weight in a normal weight you know even nine months pregnant i would have still been considered normal
weight um exercise like crazy competed in you know half marathons triathlons olympic distance
you know i did everything right never smoked you know um never drank to excess um and you know it
was it was june 30th so right after that it was june 30th of 2017 i was having a normal day i was
went to exercise i had a big irb meeting in the morning went home um due to my wonderfully
full house of three kids and uh took a business call in the basement because that's was that's
always my escape place you know um where it can be a little less noisy and all of a sudden i couldn't
talk and i i couldn't figure out what was going on i knew something wasn't right but um i i couldn't
speak and um all i know is that i hung up the phone at some point because i was embarrassed i was
remember thinking there he's gonna think i'm drunk um and uh i hung up the phone and you know
the next thing i remember was being in the car with my husband and him saying i don't think we
could take you to urgent care i have just very flashes of this day and the next memory is in the
trauma bay at the hospital the hospital that i work at um where i had seen patients many many
times and i'll have to tell you the other thing is the last time i had been in that particular
trauma bay was when i brought my then four-year-old daughter in or my husband did i met them um via
an ambulance after a traumatic brain injury so it was like a very bad place for me although my
daughter completely recovered and i remember screaming at my husband that they're wrong
they're wrong and i wanted to see the computer because what had happened when they first came
in is they thought it was a stroke and so my poor husband was all the sudden tasked with you know
are you going to give her clot busting medication or not um because we think she's having a stroke
but lo and behold the imaging showed a really large tumor in my brain um and um then they
imaged the rest of me and it turns out i had multiple tumors in my chest um and so you know
they presumed you know correctly at that point that this was lung cancer but i also needed emergency
brain surgery and this is all you know i i i remember most of this by people telling me about it
so um anyway the next day i did um had a virgin brain surgery and then
you know i being a physician in lung cancer you know i was like that can't possibly be you know
i have never smoked you know how do i have lung cancer i am the healthiest person i know i remember
being in the hospital because of course you know you're on drugs and everything else and and
shock and everything and i kept saying look at my nails these are the healthiest nails you've ever
seen how can this be a person who's sick because somehow that was like just one example you know
of how that's impossible talk about the stages of grief and denial right and um being a physician
and knowing what lung cancer meant the next thing that came out of my mouth is i want to move to
oregon because i was like i know what this means for me and i know what this means for my family
and i don't want to play any part in this i don't want them suffering can you tell folks what you
mean by that not everybody might understand the implication of what you're saying yeah i wanted to
go to oregon because they had physician assisted suicide because i you know i knew i have treated
so many patients with lung cancer i knew the horrible end i knew what this meant you know um
especially when it spread yeah and it had spread everywhere i mean i had stage four lung cancer
you know the day before i had been fine a hundred percent fine that morning i had exercised
vigorously and suddenly i'm in the hospital recovering from a brain surgery being told
that i have a rapidly fatal disease and you know all you can think of in that moment of panic is
your family right and so you know my only thought was i don't want to watch i don't want them to
watch me go i want them to remember mom and so i mean there began my so far almost four year journey
of a new me you know i cancer changes you so i'm not that person you know and and one of the many
things is sometimes at this point in time you know i mourn that person i mean one of the things
that i think is very shocking for people to understand is that it's probably between 12
to 14 percent of people who get lung cancer are not smokers um and they all tend to get a certain
type of lung cancer you know lung cancer is broadly divided histologically by small cell and large cell
or non small cell i'm sorry and within the non small cell there's large cell adenocarcinoma
squamous cell and most of the people like you who are not smokers get this type of adenocarcinoma
non small cell and it is really shocking to think that given the prevalence of lung cancer
and the lethality of lung cancer lung cancer kills more people than any other cancer and i believe
that's true for male and female still um to think that i mean by far yeah to think that such a high
percentage 12 to 14 percent could be non-smokers uh tells us this the severity of this um i also
think it's worth reiterating something you've said which is sort of the miracle of the fact that
we're sitting here having this discussion four years later the uh median survival meaning if you
took you know a hundred people um with stage four which means a type of cancer that has spread from
its original site of origin and in your case it went to your brain which is a particularly
devastating place for this cancer to grow the median survival of people with stage four lung
cancer is probably 12 months or less correct well it depends on what kind of lung cancer that you
have but yeah i mean um in sometimes even eight months or less um and um those were the stats
that i knew when i was first diagnosed and you know one of the things that i'll say is non-smoking
lung cancer is growing at scary rates it's being diagnosed and it hits people in their prime
it's growing rapidly especially in young women so it's hitting a lot of moms much more common in
women than it is in men although it does happen in men happens in caucasian and asian women
predominantly and the interesting thing is most of the people that it impacts are thin
and in shape or athletes do we have any insight into why no and and it's one of the things that's
not being investigated as much you know when you look at okay you know what studies have been out
there oh we get the typical you know it's raid on it's you know um you know being next to a smoker
i never was okay my father was a smoker he quit smoking the day i was born and never went back
i was not raised around smoke um so you know you the fact of who it's impacting and and the fact
that the the demographics of the people that it's impacting are the healthy people you know
unlike what we associate with you know our epidemic of insulin resistance that's not who
these people are we know that insulin resistance is responsible for a huge number of cancers and
cancer rises that's not this you know and so you know it's it's young women um and again who have
presumably done everything right um and it's just it's something that is not getting enough press
i know the guardian did a big story about it about a year ago um but otherwise it's not getting
the attention it deserves and these women really wind up um with two different kinds of cancer
they wind up with egfr driven cancer that's epidermal growth factor receptor
or they wind up with something called alc positive cancer i have the egfr specifically
something called egfr exon 19 mutation and the thing i didn't know at diagnosis because again i
had been focused on obesity and metabolic disease and diabetes for so long um you know i hadn't been
seeing as many people with active cancer as i did when i was in primary care um and so i was quite
frankly behind um on some of the newer treatments and newer diagnoses if you will and we're talking
the genomics um of cancer um but for egfr cancer there was something called a targeted therapy
this class of medications is called tyrosine kinase inhibitors and you know people can go on them
and they can get better okay they can even in many cases have all of the cancer go away
okay doesn't mean they're cured though because it always comes back and so after initially
you know again going through all these i mean i'll tell you the denial grief stage well i want to i
want to actually ask you exactly about that sarah i want to go back to what is it like when you are
recovering in the hospital from the brain surgery because i assume they had not taken out the primary
tumors in your lungs they were just alleviating the most life-threatening symptom you had at the
moment which was a mass inside a part of your body that can't accommodate a mass which is why you had
a seizure um so they take that out you're recovering from a surgery that by itself is difficult to
recover from but then coupled with the knowledge of here's this disease and my lungs are full of
this what do you remember of those days overwhelming grief to the point of not being able to think
and again it's it's you know of course i come and approach everything in life as a mother
right i mean and and i'm not saying as a mother only like fathers would do the same thing but you
approach every problem in life through what it means for your children how how old were your
children at the time sarah they were seven twelve and fourteen and they needed me they still need me
um and so the grief is overwhelming about what i quickly realized is i'm gonna break my children's
heart and there's not a thing i can do about it and to have that realization because it comes quick
and have to sit with that
is a grief i can't i can't even explain and so i mean initially i just was i couldn't handle
the grief i i had to be denial in denial i came home from the hospital i had just been discharged
from icu and i walked seven miles the day i got home and my fema see i i can't be sick
i i just got out of the brain surgery i'm still on medication i walked seven miles today i'm
healthy i don't know what you people are talking about what did your kids know at this time had
your husband already spoken with them well sadly enough and i actually didn't find this out until
quite a bit later they are the ones who found me in the basement so you know talk about
not telling the children we had that was never an option for us
so you know they knew i was having surgery that there was a tumor in my brain and that this was
cancer this is not good um and that's a lot for a kid to unpack right especially a kid you know
especially a kid you know again it's it's hard for any kid to unpack but you know one of the things
i remember when my kids were going through each of their own everyone kid goes through at the phase
of what if something happens to you mommy what if something happens to your daddy right all kids go
through that and the one thing we used to kind of laugh together my husband and i about that
say oh honey your mommy and daddy are the healthiest people um we are so healthy you know you don't
need to worry about that and and i remember that you know it's one of the one of the first things
that you think of when you're put in this situation is oh my god you know they have to unpack this
in that context and it's hard to be a teen it's hard to be a seven-year-old but to be one who's
mother suddenly had a you know diagnosis of advanced cancer and we it was a hard decision
on what to do but you know in talking and how do we handle the kids but the one thing we decided
together i mean my husband and i um is that we were never going to lie to them you know we were
always going to tell them the truth because i thought that the worst thing for a kid is to
constantly be wondering if something if there's going to be a huge shoe that drops and so we told
them we tried to open up the lines of communication they mostly didn't want to talk about it
um but we told them that we were making that promise to them and we have never never
gone back on that problem and promise and never will i mean that's one that it's really important
to me we may delay telling them something for a little bit until we really know the facts but
as soon as we really know the facts they're going to hear about it so um anyway i mean
i mean you know and over time in grief you learn to accept many things
you know my husband and i our dream had been to retire to a farm and make gourmet butter
like that's what we were going to do that was going to be the second career right
and you learn to make peace with that's not the case anymore you know our we always used to joke
that the way we wanted to die was 95 years old on the way home from a skiing trip
in a fiery car accident where our kids would not have to deal with the bodies right the cremation
the two for one a twofer it was going to be on the way home because we were going to be
having fun up until that point um and um you know you so that's acceptance you know you're
not going to retire you're not going to have all these things but you can't accept that you're not
going to be a mom impossible now at some point i'm guessing kind of the problem solver and you
started saying like hey i'm gonna learn as much as can be known about this um and we're gonna
talk about this in the context of the asymmetry that exists um i just had a discussion about this
with you know we have a weekly meeting in our practice with all the providers and you know we
just had this weird situation recently where you know basically a patient of ours who has another
physician uh was kind of caught in the middle of a recommendation that turned out not to be the
right recommendation and you know we were able to get them a referral to somebody else who basically
got them out of a very unnecessary surgery and we were just sort of thinking man like we're so glad
that that patient was able to dodge that bullet you know they were going to have a surgery that
they totally didn't need um that's a very big surgery with lots of risks and we realized like
the asymmetry of knowledge in medicine is so overwhelming that it is it's it's it's not even
just about money or education outside of medicine like a smart person still has a hard time digesting
medical literature um and i know like i said we're going to talk about this but i you know you
very quickly must have figured out hey i have this egfr 19 deletion so we no longer talk about this
as you have lung cancer or you have adno or you have non-small cell we're really going to refer
to it by its mutation and everything will come down to how do we treat that how long was that
process for you to say i'm gonna i don't know if this is the right word but i'm gonna partition
my grief and my problem solving brains and i'll i'll do both of them but i'll i'll you know i'll
move back and forth pretty quick it happened pretty quick um which is okay you know this is terminal
right you have to come to to grasp but that but terminal when right and what can i do to control
the when but when you say that sarah did you really come to that realization so soon because
technically life is terminal i mean there's nobody listening to this podcast watching this video
who isn't going to die so that's all terminal but when you say that do you mean that immediately
and without question or reservation you felt that you would not live a normal life expectancy there
was no hail mary out there that was gonna you know take you to being the 95 year old skier
um yeah i mean i i think just the reading and understanding although the advances that that
this was going to be terminal really soon you know in my life and i was only 46 at the time
and you know my first thing was just please let me make it to 50 i'm 49 you're gonna be 50 soon
yeah i'm gonna be 50 um in the not too distant future so you know that was like my first one
was just like okay let's let's but right from the beginning i'll tell you the when was 11 years
okay and and that has not left i just i don't need to be 95 i can accept all those things that i'm
going to miss out on by not growing old i just need 11 years which to everyone was unrealistic
but why 11 years because my youngest would be graduated so so immediately
my goal was i can't settle for less than 11 years i have to make it to 11 years and so in became
that like my war cry 11 years 11 years i have to make it 11 years and so you know it started
i mean and that started me on a path of so much so the first thing i thought in reading all the i
mean read everything is i got to get this primary tumor out you know i'm considered inoperable but
we know that having this primary tumor here increases my risk for mutations okay remember
i said that the tyrosine kinase inhibitors or the tkis they work amazingly well but only so long
you know somewhere between eight and say you know on average eight and with the more advanced ones
you know at the long and it's like you know 24 to 30 months okay um so that's not enough time
that doesn't get me to 11 so i was like okay you know this is increasing the risk for mutation
which is how these develop resistance to the tyrosine kinase inhibitors and remind me sarah
you because i remember you emailing me probably by august and and starting to you know explain
some of the details you had your biggest tumor was like five centimeters that's a monster tumor
how how many tumors did you have it was six centimeters or you had six tumors i had it was
six centimeters which is amazing in the sense that i never had pain from it you know it never i never
had a cough probably because you were so healthy i think so because you know i this talk about
being caught out of the blue you know there just wasn't this premonition of something is awry and
i'm just not addressing it and so the standard of care sorry to interrupt was just that you know
we typically don't operate on patients with metastatic tumors it's it doesn't the only
reason they operated on your brain was it was an acute way to save your life i think it's hard for
patients listening to this to understand that but that's sort of the that's the playbook in oncology
right when a patient shows up with metastatic cancer they're considered not surgical candidates
and this was the exception and not the rule you were going to be dead probably within days if
they didn't operate on your brain but all this time afterwards you still have these this burden
of tumors in your lung and now the question is can we improve your prognosis and maybe that doesn't
mean you live to 95 but can we reduce can we make your cancer less resistant to therapy by taking
the majority of the cancer cells out of your body right you know um and and decreasing the tumor
burden because really quickly the tki got rid of every single small tumor i had them throughout
you know like paint splatters on throughout both lungs and they were gone in a matter of weeks
that's staggering isn't it i mean it is it's it's remarkable but the you know again the primary
tumor was huge so um i had unfortunately the large tumor in my brain was not the only one i had two
other ones that they radiated um they didn't need to be surgically removed they were small they
could be radiated and then i set about trying to find someone who would take out this primary tumor
um can i can i ask you about the stereotactic radiation sarah that's i mean we glossed over
that but that's not a benign process either did you suffer nausea from that what how difficult
was your stereotactic treatment did you take it all in stride i did great with the treatment
to the brain i didn't have any issues you know i did have issues at the beginning but they were
more to the tki you know one of the things with every specialist that i saw you know
they couldn't believe it or they told me if i saw them earlier it wasn't going to happen
you know at least you'll keep your hair all my hair fell out like it wasn't supposed to happen
like your hair is not supposed to fall out with tki it's all my hair fell out anyway so the brain
radiation went fine um and then i met a surgeon who was going to take out the primary tumor for
the reasons that i was saying we just anything to decrease the risk of you know um developing a
mutation that keeps me from being sensitive to the tki's and so i went in you know for surgery in
september and i can remember her saying we're gonna take this tumor out we're gonna take out
your right upper lobe unless of course we've seen that there's disease in the mediastinum
but there was no disease on the PET scan in the mediastinum so she was feeling pretty positive
about being able to take that out but i knew for several weeks beforehand that that was a possibility
and just so folks know what we're saying on the on the right hand side you've got these three
lobes here but they drain into these lymph nodes that are in this middle structure called the
mediastinum and so you had this monster tumor that was going to require the entire upper right lobe
to be taken out but if the surgeon felt that on visual inspection at least or maybe even sampling
nodes that any of those nodes had cancer it was her opinion that this is really futile because now
we know it's already escaped the lung it doesn't matter so so you went into that surgery knowing
you could wake up with a huge scar in your chest chest tubes coming out and the cancer is still in
your right and that happened and that was i mean it was terrible i mean you know i kept apparently
you know under the influence i mean everyone told me i was so hysterical screaming in the recovery
room i'm a mom you can't let this happen to me i'm a mom that's all i kept saying and i of course
don't remember any of this but they had to actually take me away put me in a private room
and and that was all that i kept saying and um so you know i had to come home and
learn to accept that um i now was bald and um i was definitely fell into
a deep depression but at the same time you know i refused to completely give up i mean like for
example i went back to work at the clinic the same month that i had brain surgery you know which
you know which sounds crazy but this is part of this whole process and then but after the surgery
failure i i mean i was it was that was terrible um and then i didn't really recover back into my
determined place until a really very specific moment and that was just a couple of weeks before
my diagnosis um i had been selected to be an aspen health innovator fellow which was
i mean this is among the higher highest honors for your work you know this is the aspen institute is
you know a place that brings together thinkers in all kinds of disciplines and you know to be chosen
to represent people who are innovating in the health care space was i mean such an honor
and in order to do that you had to commit to four weeks of leadership sessions in the next two years
which of course at the time i was like of course sign me up but as that first session inched closer
it was in november i i was so what do i do i couldn't make up my mind i literally didn't make
up my mind for sure until i sat i got on the airplane and because i was ready to run back
because it was like i'm going to leave my kids for almost a week i've terminal cancer and at
that point i decided you can live feeling sorry for yourself and of all the things that you're
going to lose or you can go out and live and your kids are going to be better for it this is what
really made me decide your kids are going to be better if you choose to live and so that was the
moment sitting on that plane seat crying never i've cried on a lot of planes that's this diagnosis
deciding i just chose to live this was a moment i made my choice now i gotta stick with it
and that's how i've tried to live my life since then because i you know i have a platform i had a
platform i had done what i feel was a lot of good for a lot of people and it wasn't finished
and i knew that this was good for my children and i'll tell you one of the most impactful moments
of my whole life happened before my diagnosis and it was one of these times where we were at the
dinner table and the lottery happened to be one of those you know hyper inflated lotteries oh my
god you can win you know bajillion dollars and so my husband and i were at the dinner table joking
around about it right i mean we don't play the lottery but we were joking around we should buy
tickets you know we could retire we could retire and here at the time was my 13 year old son at
the dinner table and he got really upset about us discussing this you can't retire mom you're doing
so much good for the world how could you even think of it i've never been so that is a defining
moment of my life and and and like i was like oh my god you know at the time i just i was so taken
aback by that and um certainly that weighed heavily on my decision to get on that plane
and to continue doing what i'm doing um and what i'm doing has morphed since my cancer diagnosis
into an even greater focus on health equity because of my experience as a cancer patient
and someone who is privileged because i'll tell you you have a much greater chance of surviving
cancer if you are uh has privilege uh you know one of the lucky ones and i didn't realize
the stark differences until i became a patient i want to talk about that in some detail sarah
but i i want to also understand how it is that we're still talking today frankly in other words
how have you managed to um stay in an equilibrium with this disease right i've always i mean let me
let me share with you a couple of things that i i i've always struggled with when thinking about
cancer i i'm not fond of the language that we sometimes use around cancer and that we beat
cancer and that you know we can't give up and things like that because it almost suggests
that the patients who don't survive cancer have somehow given up and i i just i i i just don't
find that in my experience having taken care of many patients with cancer to be true i think
um i just you know it doesn't make sense to me um and i think the way that you said it and described
it earlier makes the most sense which is basically finding a way to coexist with your cancer for as
long as possible um and you've exceeded all odds and i i want to kind of understand that journey
a little bit more um you you know i it's it's one thing to to go through the tyrosin kinase inhibitor
have this immediate response um that's remarkable but then get this setback you know three months
later where your primary is not only still there but you actually realize now there's there's
mediastinal involvement um which basically means there's no question you have cancer cells
elsewhere in your body um it's not like they stop when they get to the lymph nodes so pick the story
up for us in terms of what your ongoing treatment has been like like how have you stayed in this
state of uh of equilibrium so to speak yeah so i haven't okay um on many occasions i haven't um
uh but so so after the surgery um the next thing that happened is they found another brain tumor
um there's argument as to whether it was there from the get-go or um
uh whether um it was something new um but either way they decided it would be considered
um that the first line tki that they had put me on um had failed me um and so i got switched to
i got more radiation to the brain and i was switched to um and the newest tki happens to
be called osamertnib or chagrissow i was put on that in november um right before i went off for
my first aspen leadership conference um and i had decided that i do not accept being a sitting duck
because what the cancer world then you know wants is for a patient like me
to just sit and wait for the cancer to come back right that's what you're doing you know it's
coming back there's no question about it and you know what's coming back soon and you know you are
just waiting and i couldn't accept that as a mother i think i could accept it as a human but
i couldn't accept it as a mother and so i went on a journey to find someone who could treat me
in the most aggressive way possible who shared my view that sitting around and waiting for this to
come back was totally unacceptable i traveled the country i saw everybody let me tell you first of
all of course that shows i have means to do that right that a lot of other people don't
and i actually along the way met another mother physician my age just a bit younger
younger kids who had the same attitude towards it i refused to accept this we sort of became a
team so to speak and wound up by complete serendipity meeting a group of physicians
who really felt that the way to treat this long term was to be constantly battling it with
something new so in other words you know the the cancer dogma right now is you put people on
something at the highest dose possible and you keep going until it doesn't work anymore
that that's how we deal with cancer and then we switch and it's the same thing over again
and the idea is what if we hit it with less and then change it up all the time
right and this goes to the idea of beating the mutations before they can get you
so
thankfully i had a physician here at home who was willing to say okay that that is worth a shot
february of 2018 2019 okay because it took a long time to get to this point right of searching
trying to find something i started chemo regular chemo i went through the regular
cycles of chemo and then when i was done with that i immediately went to anti estrogen therapy
okay because i had a very specific mutation besides the egfr1 and there was a medication
to treat it it just so happened to be a breast cancer medication but it was the same mutation
for either cancer so immediately upon stopping the chemo i went on the anti estrogen therapy
so i was put into early menopause with the number of you know regular medications lupron full of
strant and then i was started on a medication called padlicyclib okay which again is primarily
a breast cancer medication but was targeting one of my very specific secondary mutations
i was on that for the summer and all this time i'm still on the tigris or asamertinib that never
stopped as soon as the eight weeks of that was over with i went back on chemo but very different
low dose chemo single agent very low dose which agent so the first one was cisplatin
okay and you know everyone says oh cisplatin you know you're you know you're gonna do terrible on
this i mean this is harsh and it is but you know i did fine i did fine i was able to still you know
i mean i'm not saying i wasn't tired you know i've basically been nauseous for the last almost
four years every single day you know it's just you learn to manage that you know so i learn to
manage it i learned to manage you know being tired um and the things that came along i still
traveled for work i still did i was still able to do everything um i just i can't imagine i can't
like i i could tell you some really crazy stories of of things i had to do while traveling to
accommodate how i was feeling um that nobody knew about at the time but anyway um some really wacky
stuff that you do but you just you manage you you figure it out right you improvise lots of
improvising um and then um i got switched to another after eight weeks got switched to gem
cytobine or gemsar which again these are so crazy you just don't think of this because that's a drug
that's typically used in pancreatic cancer right well yeah and it can be used in lung cancer i mean
it just depends on the mutation i think that's the point right right right right yeah um that
believe it or not there's no standard chemo for lung cancer it's can you believe that there's not
a standard like standard of care regimen so the thing is i wasn't doing any outlandish things here
okay these are all treatments for lung cancer okay i mean like like you said gems are is used
more for other things but this is not an outlandish thing that's never heard of for lung cancer i mean
same with cisplatin i mean um none of these things are you know you know i was oh my goodness
we're gonna you know do something you know that's never ever been done before you know so to speak
and and at this point which is now the fall of 2019 where if you go and get a PET scan where do
you actually have tumor in your body at this point so yeah let me back up for a second because well
the quick answer is i had no tumor okay there was no tumor anywhere and to back up is that
the chagrissow this is pre-chemo had stopped shrinking my primary tumor in March of 2018
so this was you know almost a year before i began chemo and so since they wouldn't surgically
operated to get it out i had it radiated again you know i was lucky enough to have a radiation
oncologist who worked with me and um and like i said i tolerated brain chemo well the same was
not the case brain radiation for lung to the lung yeah the radiation i had real issues um
and interestingly enough you know we were leaving for to hike the Inca trail
and May of that year so i had had radiation that we're leaving to hike the Inca trail and i started
having kind of bad chest pain it was like like a day or two before we hiked the Inca trail i was
like okay i'm sure this is just reflux i'm going to take some reflux medication and then i was like
look okay if it's not if it's more you know what a better place to die than surrounded by your family
you know on the Inca trail and all the beauties of the Andes mountains okay i can accept this
let's go you know i didn't even tell anyone i was like going forward and um did that successfully
you know um it was great my eight-year-old tootling along you know she was always the
fastest of any of us we went with our friends and um uh i mean amazing experience i just have
to say that those things especially if you can get kids in it i'll never forget that when we all got
back and we went and checked into the JW because we were like give me a shower a very clean bed and a
spa my middle child my daughter said to all of the adults i developed my third eye during that
it was one of those experiences like you don't normally think you're going to get that out of a
you know she was what 14 at the time that's that we were all like what
but anyway so it was a super special time i was still having pain and then my rest of my family
flew home i actually had to fly um from Lisbon to Switzerland because i had a conference i had to go
to and at that conference things started to get really bad um i made it through but you know
not with again some funny stories that of how i accommodated to it because i was having crushing
pain that home turns out of course i had some rare i had this rare complication where actually
impacted my bones and my radiation oncologist said the only treatment for this is to put you
on long-term opioid therapy and i was like oh no thanks i will accommodate there was no way i was
doing that so i had to get through that which was a which that was a little bit of a saga but anyway
i had no disease then after that radiation none and so i was in this state they call it NAD
or NED excuse me no evidence of disease i like to always say ned right i had i was ned for a really
long time i had no evidence of disease it was a great place to be right still on treatment still
trying to do everything to keep this from coming back and started gems are and you know everybody
had said all these terrible things about cisplatin and gems are was 10 times worse everyone was like
you'll be a breeze gems are as a breeze compared to cisplatin you you are really the exact opposite
of everybody because yeah i mean we used to tell patients gems are is it's non-chemo yeah
yeah everybody tolerates gems are i can still remember sitting because i was too feeling too
crappy to drive my mother driving to pick me up to take me to chemo one day sitting on my front
porch and throwing up in a plant on the way to chemo there are nutrients in there sarah that are
very good for the plant so i wouldn't i wouldn't tell bad about that that's very it's a very healthy
part of the carbon cycle i'm sure but i was determined to you know keep on i was really close
to getting switched to tax calls which you know i'm like this is gonna have that'll be better
um and um so then had to take another trip um for another meeting and had lots of friends there
and i can remember them standing behind me after we had eaten and they were pushing me up this hill
in san francisco because i literally couldn't walk and i kept thinking to myself i'm a hypochondriac
this is just because i'm anemic you know whatever um i was super short of breath
but i'm like okay i had convinced myself i was making it all up in my mind
i fly back from that trip and the very next morning head in for chemo and they immediately said oh my
god no chemo you know everything is a mess my i you know my liver numbers were through the roof
my kidney numbers were you know high um i had pancytopenia so bad um how anemic were you sarah
so i was like six at this point okay i mean it was bad you know really bad the low sixes at this
right and just so the listener understands yeah the the normal would be 13 or 14 of ahemoglobin
and you're six so that's really low and your platelets were how low 23 which means you basically
don't have the ability to form a single clot right you know i was a disaster and the funny
thing is i was still up and doing okay you know what i mean i was tired i was shortness of breath
with activity but i was doing okay and they sent me home and i was like
that doesn't seem right am i crazy that i shouldn't be home so of course i call some of
my other physician friends aha privilege right because i was getting sent home
um and they're like oh my god we're admitting you right now
right so i actually get a backdoor admission to the hospital
and a complete workup starting right then you know i had to be i had to have a thoracentesis
drained a whole bunch from my lungs that was unknown when i got sent home so you had tons
of fluid around your lungs that's tons of fluid around my lungs yeah um and once i was admitted
i was promptly transferred to icu things were going downhill i had to be put on bypass so i
had multi-organ failure i you know had respiratory failure liver failure kidney failure i was a big
failure okay everything was bad and was this believed to be the result of your body's response
to the tumor or the chemo it was the gems are so i got taken care of in the hospital
i i just want to cry to think about the care i got it was so wonderful you know and i got i just
had the best team i would have died you know nobody can believe that this was well over a year ago now
and i'm healthy with no persistent failures um because i was near death you know and um i was
in the icu for a really long time and everyone every day it went from i think your kidneys are
rebound to uh 50 50 they're never going to be normal i was on plasma free assist and it turned
out i had something called atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome and you know to just explain
you know over 70 percent of people are either dead or on dialysis you know right away i mean it's
it's got an incredible mortality right incredible it's incredibly difficult to treat
um uh and so you know outcomes are you're dead or you're on permanent dialysis
um and so i was put on a new medication after you know going through kidney biopsies all these
kinds of things in the hospital um sent home uh did outpatient plasma for recess for a while
and then things miraculously started getting better right not miraculously it was because of
this medication i was brought um of course that meant an infusion every eight weeks and
the worst part to me is it meant no one would put me back on chemo just just they wouldn't put
you on gems are they wouldn't put you on anything wouldn't put me on anything and to me that was
devastating because i said you know well kidney failure is one thing but you know having this
cancer that we know come back is another so that was another hard pill to swallow and you know
long story short i got better i went to um a genetic um pharmacogenetics which is where they
actually take a look at what your genetic profile is in in response to different drugs and it turns
out i had a genetic mutation hey i i have lots of them um uh it turns out i had a genetic mutation
that didn't allow the gems are to break down so i was getting toxic doses of this and i was on a
very low dose but the thing is that um i couldn't get rid of it so normally if you see atypical
hemolytic uremic syndrome with gems are it's after months and months of treatment and i got
this within four weeks why because i was getting mega doses of it because my body couldn't get
rid of it due to this mutation it was the explanation wow so you know and they said
there's no reason you can't take any other chemo this is very specific to gems are but that was
that sit in weight mode back to sit in weight mode and it took another year but the cancer came back
back in september of 2020 and um uh here's my story from that which really made me so determined
to work even harder for health equity here i am a physician able to grasp really difficult concepts
able to read and scour the literature and know what i'm looking for
able to call at a moment time you know anytime someone to help me sort through something i didn't
understand or help maybe refer me to someone you know i had all the resources in the world
and the reoccurrence was in september even with all my constant pushing and self-advocacy
okay the one thing is i had by by the time i was diagnosed with cancer i was an expert patient
advocate expert hardcore and you know one of the other advantages i had is it didn't take much to
switch that and to become a self-advocate an advocate for myself so i was diagnosed in
mid-september with a reoccurrence i did not get on a clinical trial until um i i got started
um i i got started december 30th
that's a four month delay that's a four month delay for me
and in hindsight
now looking back before i was panicked right and i couldn't really i was like something has to get
done something has to get done something has to get done i can look back in hindsight and say
how many people die during that time
how many people who don't have the advantages i had just die during that delay
how many i shudder and i i just want to cry and what i've done is i've reached out to other
cancer patients to say has anyone else been in this situation and i find out it happens all of
the time it seems that we have a really good system as i experienced when someone is diagnosed
with cancer they get a health nap a cancer navigator you know they get all these things
and we're boom boom boom boom boom but when that cancer comes back it's kind of like the system
seems to give up on you i had to advocate advocate the heck out of getting a biopsy done
a biopsy that would be enough tissue to make me eligible for a clinical trial
that would actually get me a full genomics report i mean that wasn't going to happen
i'm telling you i had to get almost obnoxious about it and the stories that i'm getting from
people are the same where was the recurrence in my right upper lobe and so they had to get you
had to get another lung biopsy to to do this and can i ask you another thing sarah what has been
you obviously have health insurance but i assume that there's been a non-trivial amount of out of
pocket costs as well in the last four years oh yeah do you do you have a sense of what the out
of pocket cost has been for your care tens of thousands of dollars which obviously speaks to
another challenge i don't know if this is still true but it certainly was true at one point that
the greatest source of personal bankruptcy in the united states is health care an inability to pay
her health care costs and a cancer diagnosis is so high up there i would have to believe that cancer
is the leading subset of that as well so you know it just so now i'm like especially when i got
feedback that i'm not alone in this it wasn't just me you know and again i always keep saying in the
backdrop of i am um one of the privileged and and i was put in this situation and the fact of the
matter is by the time the reoccurrence was diagnosed to the time i finally got treated
i had progressed so much that i had compression in my bronchus i couldn't get up a flight of stairs
without desaturating i mean this all just happened i was in horrible shape which of course again and
remember i'm starting out you know before my diagnosis in general i was so healthy and so
it just is which gives me an advantage in this which gives me a significant advantage in this
but it goes back to that question of how many people just die sarah you're very um
realistic about the fact that your time on this earth is less than it should be right a 49 year
old otherwise healthy person who's done all the you know done the right things for their health
should have another 40 years on this planet and at least statistically speaking that's that's not
doesn't seem likely it suggests to me that you're very cognizant of how you spend your time
uh so should take a moment to thank you for spending a couple hours with me here
but how do you now think about the time that you allocate to your family
to your work in the diabetes community and now to this third important pillar to you which is
cancer advocacy how are you how are you how are you managing that and how do you how do you think
about how to even balance that because i think time is the most important currency i think
everybody can appreciate that in a vague sense it is the great equalizer um but of course most of us
can't appreciate it the way you can because you have a real visceral appreciation for it that
comes exactly with this type of an illness um and so therefore i think that your appreciation
for the balancing act of what you described earlier which is living your life to the fullest
regardless of its duration that's your legacy that's what your kids are going to remember about
their mom being the advocate for other patients so that in 10 years when another Sarah Halberg
gets this diagnosis even if she doesn't have your education or your means she can have an
extension of life the way you do i it's it's a bit overwhelming for me to think about how i would do
that because as i put myself in your shoes my intuition is i'd want to retreat from everything
outside of life everything outside of my family like i i i would imagine uh and and it's hard to
put yourself in another person's shoes without being there but my intuition is i would say i
don't care about anything outside of the walls of this house and i would take a selfish approach in
some ways i think and you've done this very selfless thing which is continuing to sort of
prioritize everything else as well um how do you do that well a couple of things you know
number one believe it or not originally it was it was actually hard to be around my kids
when i was so deep in grief because and that sounds crazy right that sounds counterintuitive but
they reminded me of everything i was going to lose right they were the they were what i didn't want to
lose and so it was challenging and i i knew i had overcome that you know and that that that was
that was a big motivator for me to not be you know thinking about that um in thinking in that way
and i i'm happy to say i i clearly have overcome that but um my kids come first you know i'll drop
anything and everything if they need me now but i also think again and i go back to sort of what i
alluded to before they need to see me um not letting not getting knocked out by the stressors
and bad things in life you know i mean bad things happen to good people you know i like
i said there's been a pivot in every part of my career based on anger and i certainly am angry
about this but what do you do with it that's that's what's going to be the important question in life
you can take anger you can take all these things and you can get lost and buried in it okay or you
can try to turn it into you know something else and i have to say i haven't become as big a cancer
advocate yet and i'm working on it but the reason for that is and this was a question i had to ask
myself a long time ago which is shouldn't you be a cancer advocate now was but i have a platform
for diabetes and damn it that's important too all these people suffering from this is important
so i can't just say i'm going to switch away from a platform that i have to one where i don't yet it
doesn't mean i'm ignoring it but it's like it makes me want to work more again for health equity
because it spans both right it has to do with both diabetes um and cancer you know um and and
that is so important so yeah how i spend my time is really critical and i want to say it's not like
i'm i don't want to paint the picture that oh my gosh i'm the superwoman i have a terminal cancer
and yay life is great no you know when people ask how i'm doing okay if i say okay you know
i'm doing okay there's never good or never great okay and that's just where i live right now
i'm definitely not sitting around and feeling sorry for myself okay definitely not not enjoying
things in life but great is hard to think about you know great is hard to think about now and
you know the some people say well i'm so cancer really helped me get a new perspective on life
and what i care about and you know i'm happy to say i don't know that i got that okay i mean
having cancer sucks and i'm still mad about it and you know sometimes i have to sit and have
a pity party every once in a while because the fact of the matter is i loved my life
pre-cancer and i think i was living every minute of it i think i cherished my children
i cherished vacations i mean you know that i cherish travel and showing my children travel
and that's you know that's a bit of a wonderful thing and it's also like a dagger too it's not
like i've gotten some new life and new perspective that's so different from my old damn it i liked
my old life and i liked the old me and it's still a little hard to get used to who this person is now
she's still motivated
she still exercises although not doing the things i used to
she loves her children with as much passion as one could have but i'm i'm fundamentally different
it's tough
sarah you've uh
you know you've you've said a lot of things that uh
you know obviously resonate um
and i think we'll we'll resonate with a lot of people
so i i want to i want to thank you from the bottom of my heart
and uh certainly wish you the best thanks i appreciate it it's uh it's been it's been
great knowing you through this journey as well you are uh as many of your colleagues
uh have have undoubtedly told you and we've certainly discussed it behind your back
you are an inspiration and nobody wants to hear that because nobody wants to be the inspiration
you just want to be the normal person but uh you are an inspiration yeah yeah well thank you for
setting aside time thank you yeah and i mean i thank you so much for having me on i mean
believe it or not this is the first time i've told my story you know um in any way shape or form so
i have been kind of preparing for this um and i i'm glad i did it and so thank you for
giving me an opportunity to do that and
thank you thank you for trusting us thank you for trusting me and the listeners
thank you for listening to this week's episode of the drive if you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription now to that end membership
benefits include a bunch of things one totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic paper person thing we discuss on each episode the word on the street is nobody's
show notes rival these monthly ama episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes
completely access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to
listen to spiel's like this the qualies which are a super short podcast that we release every tuesday
through friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of the drive this is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that i believe in but for which i'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time
goes on if you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can head over to
peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook all
with the id peteratiamd you can also leave us a review on apple podcast or whatever podcast player
you listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes only does not constitute
the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including
the giving of medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk the content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should
not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have
and they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
finally i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies i invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies