Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Lane. Awesome to be sitting down with you today, at least virtually. I've been looking
forward to speaking with you for actually about two and a half years. I know Dom introduced
us a long time ago. We were trying to do this in person at some point, and then one thing
led to another. It became COVID, and then all of a sudden I realized you don't have
to be in person to do a podcast, though I do wish we were in person because I suspect
this will be a really long discussion and a great one. First off, I just want to say
one thing that I think people sometimes assume is that people like you and I have so much
in terms of viewpoints that are vastly different. I spent a lot of time reading your material
and watching your videos, and I followed your work for quite some time. I would actually
say that there are very few things that I think you and I don't see eye to eye on. Maybe
some of those things will come up today. I think they'd be very interesting. But I also
think the level of nuance and sophistication you bring to this subject matter is exciting,
which is why I want to talk with you about so many things. But I kind of want to start
by letting listeners understand a little bit about who you are and why I think you're qualified
to speak on so many subject matters. Let's just talk about, you grew up outside of Chicago,
if I recall?
Actually, in southern Indiana. I'm from Evansville originally. So 20 minutes from Illinois and
five minutes from Kentucky.
Impressive. Wow. That's not often you can straddle that many borders, right? What kind
of sports did you play growing up?
Baseball was my primary one. I played since I was five and I leathered in high school.
But it was, I would never say that sports came naturally to me. It was definitely something
I really had to work at. And that may be apparent for my baseball aficionados out there. I was
a five foot 10 right handed first baseman. So that's not your prototypical first baseman.
But I really enjoyed baseball and it kind of stoked my competitive fire. And then I
also did run cross country in high school as well, which definitely not the sport that
you would pick as the precursor to strength sports and bodybuilding. But those were at
the time kind of like the ones that I sucked the least at, I guess is the way I'll put
it in terms of natural ability. And yeah, baseball was my real passion, though, growing
up. That's what I really enjoyed.
Was it during baseball and, you know, learning to get conditioned for baseball that you kind
of discovered the weight room and your talents in the weight room?
So I would actually say no, that was more so I was very, very much picked on. And I
would say like borderline like emotionally abused by my peers growing up. I was a nerdy
kid. I had ADHD. I was talkative. I was goofy. And so when you're you know, all that stuff
can help you when you get older, because being different is good when you're older. But when
you're young, being different is not so much fun. So I got picked on a lot, didn't really
get much attention from girls. And just to be quite frank, I started lifting weights
just to hopefully have people stop picking on me and and get some dates and lifting weights
didn't do either of those things. But I developed a passion for weight training. And I wouldn't
say it was something that like really, really came naturally. I was never like a hyper responder
or anything like that. But I just I really, really enjoyed it. And I'd always been somebody
who in my scholastics, I wouldn't say things really came that easy to me either, because
probably a little bit because of my ADHD. But I was able I did find at a young age that
through sheer volume of work, I could overcome a lot of that stuff. And so I really appreciated
lifting weights, I guess from the perspective of the work investment to the payoff, compared
to how much talent was needed, seemed to be a lower threshold. So it didn't, you know,
if you're five foot 10, right handed, and you're trying to pitch in the big leagues,
you're pretty limited, you know, now, certainly there are limitations in terms of like hypertrophy
and strength building. But for me, it just, it felt more fair, I guess, in terms of level
of work you get in versus what you see. And then in terms of, I think the other thing
is, it's very measurable. If you go if you if you lifted a certain amount today, and
in two months, you go in and you're lifting, you know, 10% more than that. That's a very
hard outcome. There's no, there's no I think I'm getting better. It's like, no, I am getting
better. And so I think, you know, I appreciated kind of that black and white to weightlifting.
You know, I can sort of appreciate so many of the things that you just said, and among them is sort
of an early discovery for training. For me, it was more boxing, that was the thing that kind of
drew me in young, but but in parallel to that strength training and endurance training, both
became supportive pillars to boxing. I was fortunate, I think, and that I found great mentors
that, you know, introduced me to powerlifting when I was young, they were older men that trained
in a gym at the university that I trained at when I was 13 and 14 years old. Did you find mentors
like that who kind of took you under their wing to keep you safe and also explain the sport and,
you know, give you some common sense around training? I would say the first few years, no,
actually, when I, you know, I, I always joke that, you know, I think I didn't we didn't have a lot of
money growing up. And, you know, I didn't really have, you know, Southern Indiana wasn't really a
hotbed of fitness information. And I'll go ahead and date myself. I'm 39 years old. So when I
started was, you know, you know, in the late 90s. And so I mean, basically, what you had was,
was bodybuilding magazines. And I really couldn't afford a subscription to those either. So I
actually the first thing I ever did when I got the weightlifting was I walked down to my local
library, literally walked down to my local library and checked out books on weight training.
Do you remember some of the books you checked out?
Oh, man. I wish I did. But I don't. And actually, I would say like,
the what I do remember, especially for one particular book, which was,
it's kind of like basics of strength training or something like that.
What that bad actually, you know, we have really advanced our understanding of weight training,
but, you know, the basics, progressive overload, that sort of stuff is still still relatively
similar. And I remember the book did talk about periodization, which at that time kind of was
not a new concept in athletics, but for weightlifting was a new concept. And so anyways,
like that, that was kind of like my first few years was a little bit self guided, or when I had
lifting classes, they did offer a class on lifting in high school. It was kind of just doing what
whenever the football team was doing, basically. But obviously, I still got stronger, just because
if you're consistent, you will get stronger, regardless of what you're doing. And then at 19,
I ended my first bodybuilding competition as a teenager. And just by pure serendipity,
I was I wanted to compete in drug tested bodybuilding, I don't have any, I always have to
give this caveat. You know, I've always been drug free in terms of anabolic steroids,
growth hormones, you know, all that kind of stuff. No performance enhancing drugs.
I don't have any problem with anybody who does it as long as they compete in untested
organizations. That's my my caveat. I always just chose to compete drug tested because
I just never felt called to be Mr. Olympia or anything like that. And I, you know, again,
I don't, this is my own personal ethos. I'm not judging anybody who's ever done performance
enhancing drugs. I just wouldn't have felt good about myself. That's, that's the only thing I can
say. And I'm not saying that anybody who's done that shouldn't feel good about themselves. I just
knew I wouldn't feel good about myself. So with that out of the way, I was doing a drug tested
bodybuilding show and pretty much the only natural bodybuilding evidence based natural
bodybuilding coach lived in my hometown. And his name was Dr. Joe Klimzetsky. And I reached out to
him because he wrote for the natural bodybuilding magazines. And he helped prep me for the show.
I won the teenage division and the novice division. And I was hooked, of course. But also
he, I mean, Dr. Joe wasn't right about everything, obviously, but the crux of his information and
being, you know, being so focused on being evidence based and, you know, not necessarily buying into
dogma, that sort of thing. That definitely did help me. And just listening to him talk about,
you know, the physiology of, you know, for example, a water depletion is something very
common amongst bodybuilders. And, you know, the first meeting we ever had, he's like,
yeah, I don't do that because I don't think it's a good idea. And he listed out all the
physiological reasons why he didn't think it was a good idea. And it made a lot of sense. So
but I remember listening to that thinking, man, I don't know any of this stuff. Like I would love to
to know more about this. And so I think meeting Joe, that was part of the reason that I really
wanted to learn more about the human body and push more in academics. And he had a PhD.
And I think that was kind of like the first seed of maybe I want to go even further than just like
an undergraduate degree or something like that. So there are actually several things in there that
I want to go back and revisit. I'll start with the latter. You mentioned ADHD, were you was school
kind of hard for you? And was this a big step forward to think, hey, not only am I going to go
to college, but I'm probably going to want to do a PhD to follow in this guy's footsteps, not
we're not necessarily following his footsteps, but to really go deep into something scientific.
Ah, I think by the time I got to college, I had developed really good study habits. And so let me
back up. Yeah, school was difficult for me. It was very difficult for me to stay focused. But
I think just through sheer effect of my parents basically beating into my head from a young age,
you are going to college and you are going to get an education, you know, that sort of thing. And,
you know, not I don't want to sell like it was an overbearing parent sort of thing. It was just,
they were very committed to my education, but it was never like, oh, you need to go be a doctor or
you need to go do this, you need to go that. It was just, we want you to get educated. And I wanted
to get educated too. I was the first person in my family, even like my extended family,
ever to even go to college. And so I think the ADHD made it tough at first. And I never got
bad grades in school, but I struggled in terms of the teachers would really complain about,
you know, how my lack of attention, my lack of focus, those sorts of things. And I,
so I found for me, when I had to study, I really had to spend a lot more time than most of the
students my age were doing. So I took, for example, advanced chemistry in high school,
and I'll never forget this conversation. We had a test coming up and I had studied for probably
a total of like 15 hours, I'd say for this test, which in high school is a lot for a test,
at least for me, seemed like a lot. And I remember talking to a friend of mine who got the same grade
I did on the test. And he was like, yeah, you know, I studied a little bit about last night.
And I was thinking, man, if I studied just last night, I would have failed this test, you know.
So it did seem like I had to do more work and it might not even been more work. I just,
if I tried to sit down for like eight hours, I remember my roommate, my freshman year in college,
great guy, he's now a head, he was the head of medicine at Naples General for several years,
but he could sit down for eight hours straight, have complete silence and just study the whole
time. If I tried to do that, I'd get about 30 minutes of productive studying in. So I had to
learn to kind of break things up. And I'm not saying this works for everybody with ADHD, but
for me, it worked. So I would get distracted so easily that I just stopped trying to fight that
and I allowed myself to get distracted, but I'd always come back. So I would do 30, but no more
than 45 minutes at a block. I would do that and then I would take 15 minutes and I would let myself,
you know, browse the internet or read something else or watch some TV or something like that.
But I would always put a timer on and I would go back when it was time. And that seemed to really
work personally for me. So by the time I got to college, I had, I kind of had figured out what
worked for me studying wise. And I went to a college called Eckerd College, which is a private
school in St. Petersburg, Florida, which was, you know, on the ranking, it was very selective
at a high quality school, all this kind of stuff. And so I was petrified because I'm this kid from
Southern Indiana. I've never been anywhere really. And I have no idea how I'm going to stack up
against, you know, students from other places like, you know, the Northeast and that sort of thing.
So I was so petrified. I studied so hard. I got A's. I still remember this. I got A's on my first
11 tests I ever had in college because I was so petrified about failing. So I think by that point,
I had already had good study habits. You know, I did take like Ritalin and Adderall growing up.
And I do think those helped a little bit. The only, I always joke, like the only problem with like
Adderall is whatever I was doing when it kicked in was what I was going to be doing for the next
eight hours. You know, so if I, I remember one day I was, I was looking up fantasy football rankings,
first year I ever played fantasy football. And that I did that all day, all day when it kicked in.
And I went from worst to first in fantasy football that year. And so anyways, but by the time I got
to grad school, I was kind of able to wean myself off that. I think the last time I ever took any
medication was 15 years ago. And I think a lot of it, you know, I don't judge anybody who takes
medication for it because like I said, I think it did help. But I think I just got to the point with
my study habits where I didn't really feel like I needed it. And yeah, so I just think the fact
that I had to struggle a little bit when I was young actually really helped me and kind of like
carterized me in terms of like being able to deal with some adversity. And I think that's what really
helped me when I went to college and then grad school. So I'm going to put on the back burner
for a moment some of the stuff I want to come back to with respect to your training history and
continue down this sort of academic thread. Talking a little bit about the decisions you made
to then pursue higher education beyond a bachelor's degree and how you decided to,
for example, pick a PhD and then further decide what what area you wanted to study.
So this is just like one of those things where you look back and you go, wow, I really stumbled
into doing some of the right things having no freaking concept of what I was doing at the time.
So when I originally went to school, I went for I went to Eckerd because I wanted to study marine
science. When I was growing up, I wanted to be a shark biologist. Like I that was my passion with
sharks. I still love fishing and I still love going out and and being in the wild with sharks
and that sort of thing. In fact, one of my goals is to dive with a great white shark at some point.
Did you see that? Did you see that Nat Geo special that tracked or that it was based on something
that happened in Hawaii, I think two years ago where that whale came ashore. They took it. This
was off Honolulu or off Oahu. They took it five miles out and they went out there to study the
tiger sharks that would be feeding off it. And lo and behold, like the largest great white ever
came up upon it. Oh, you must see this. We'll link to it in the show notes. This is one of those
things where one day I was walking through the playroom and my kids were fixated on it. And I
sat down for two minutes to watch it. And then an hour later, I'm still watching it. Couldn't stop,
but I won't spoil it for you then. I'll just I'll just leave it at that and say you will go
bananas watching this thing. And it's it's yeah. Cool. Yeah. I think I watched Jaws about 8,000
times when I was a kid. So I probably will enjoy it. I still get excited for shark week whenever
it comes up. So anyway, I went to Eckard for that. And I remember I interviewed at Florida Institute
of Technology as well. And one of the professors there actually studied great white sharks. And
you know, he I'm very thankful for this guy. I can't remember his name, but he said,
look, I'm not telling you not to do this. I'm just going to be honest with you about
what I do. He said, I've got a job that maybe one in 10 people in the entire world have.
I don't get paid great for it. And it was really hard to get. Now, I'm not saying you can't get
that. But what I would recommend to you is if you're truly passionate about this, go to a degree
in a more general science and then go specialize when you get to graduate school. He said, because
if you start general, you'll still have the base that you need for grad school.
And if you're still really passionate about this, you're going to need the grad school
education anyway. And I thought, okay, well, that's not a bad idea. And so I actually went,
instead of marine science, I started in biology. And then my first year I had a general chemistry
professor named Chris Knobble. And I actually still keep in touch with him to this day here
and there. And we were in lab one day and I think he really liked me, like just my attitude.
And he said, Lane, come here. He's like, I know you're doing biology. He's like, what you need to
do is biochemistry. And I was like, well, why do I, you know, I'm a freshman. I have no idea what
I'm doing. Like, why do I want to do biochemistry? He said, well, let me do it this way. He's like,
if you decide that you don't want to go to grad school and you have a biology degree,
you look like a pre-med who didn't get into med school when you go to get a job. He said, but
if you get a degree in biochemistry, the world is your oyster. You can get any job that you'd be
able to get in biology, you can get with biochemistry and then some. And if you want to go
to grad school, you have that option, this and that, by the way, I'm not slamming on biology
students out there. If you love biology and that's what you want to do, no worries. This is just what
he said. So anyways, I was like, okay. So I switched to biochemistry and my second year,
I took organic chemistry and I had a great professor for organic chemistry. It was very hard.
He was not easy, but he was firm but fair. And I, if I look back, my best mentors were always firm
but fair. And I got a B in the class, but at the end of the semester, he asked if I wanted to come
do research with him over the summer. And I was kind of like, well, why do you want me? I, you know,
I got a B. He's like, you asked a lot of questions. You were engaged. He said grades matter, but at the
end of the day, I want students who are passionate and work hard. And I saw how hard you worked.
So I went and did research with him over the summer. That was my first kind of foray into research.
Didn't get anything done because, you know, it's 10 weeks and it's my first experience in research.
So I got to deal with a lot of frustration and stuff not working. But I got to do research with
him for two years over the next two summers. And when I got to my junior year of college,
I think having that idea of, okay, what happens next? I had started writing articles for
bodybuilding.com. Again, that's another whole other conversation of serendipity. And I knew I was
really passionate about bodybuilding because during that time, like I said, I'd gotten into
competing and whatnot. And but I was thinking, well, I don't feel like I'm going to be a
professional. I don't feel like I really know anything. I just I had crested the Dunning
Kruger and I was down in the valley, you know. By the way, that's such a great, that's such a
great point to make. Why don't you explain to people who don't understand what the Dunning
Kruger curve looks like and what it means? Yeah. So if you look at any subject and I'm
generalizing very much. So if Dunning or Kruger listens to this, I apologize if I butcher it. But
essentially, so the Dunning Kruger curve is basically perceived knowledge versus actual
knowledge. And the really interesting thing is when we start in a subject, since we are aware
that we have no knowledge, our perceived knowledge pretty much aligns with how much
knowledge we have, which is none. But pretty quickly, our perceived knowledge skyrockets.
It goes very, very high, usually after about six to 12 months of being involved in a particular
subject. And we get to this. Some people never get to this inflection point where it starts to come
back down. But eventually, if you keep learning and keep learning and keep learning, you realize,
oh wow, I didn't know as much as I thought I did because I thought I knew that. But then this
contradicts it. And so you start having this like downward turn, even though you're learning more,
your actual knowledge is going up, your perception of your knowledge starts going down. And I would
say my third year of graduate school was where it got to the very bottom. This is where it got to
the very bottom. And interestingly, if you look at the Dunning-Kruger effect, you, I have a friend
named Jeremy Linneke, he's a professor at Ole Miss, and he always says, once you drink from the
fountain of knowledge, you will thirst for the ignorance you once had. And you never, your
perception of your knowledge, if you continue learning, will never reach that initial crest
that you had that first six to 12 months where you thought you had kind of everything figured out.
I just can't agree with that more. Bob Kaplan often says, and I'm sure he's paraphrasing
somebody that the further you get from shore, the deeper the water gets. And again, it's a
slightly different way of saying basically the same idea. And I, again, what I thought I knew
about nutrition 10 years ago relative to what I know today, in absolute terms, I know infinitely
more today, but in relative terms, ie the perceived terms, it's basically to the point where
I pretty much think I know nothing. Now I know that's not true, but there are days when I think
I actually don't know nothing because to your point, you're constantly looking for the example
that contradicts your belief system. And so you have a belief system, which is well, you know,
under this condition or this condition, or these set of conditions, this must be true.
There's always going to be an exception to that. There is something else though, I think,
I mean, I think unfortunately, social media has created a lot of people who shout really
loudly from the top of the Dunning Kruger, that initial peak of the Dunning Kruger curve.
And I'm not sure if it's just blind stupidity, willful ignorance or what, but I think there are
a lot of people who have no interest in moving forward, right? And that's unfortunate, but
I think that makes it very difficult for people who want to learn because it makes the signal
noise problem very difficult. You know, for example, nobody really wants to hear uncertainty.
Like if someone's in the market for knowledge, do you want to hear it from that person
whose absolute knowledge is high, their perceived knowledge is perhaps low,
and they caveat things that they talk about? Or do you want to hear that person who's nine months
into their, you know, resurrection of knowledge and speaks like they know everything, you know,
you're you're you we tend to gravitate more towards that person. So I find this phenomenon
very interesting. And I just had to make sure we spent a moment on that based on your reference.
We had a guy named Alan Levinovitz on our podcast, who's a professor of religious studies, but
not to get too far down the rabbit hole on that. But he he's done a few books about naturalism and
how we kind of even without evidence default to believing that something that's natural,
even though he talks about how we can't really define that is better. And one of the things he
talked about was, if you want to look for people who know what they're talking about, and it is
difficult, as you said, because there's this sea of information out there. Look for people who seem
unsure. He's like, it's he's like, it's a complete paradox, right? Because what another friend of
mine, Greg Knuckles said, he said, what we're what if people are really good at when they talk to
somebody quickly, they can determine whether or not that person knows more about a subject than they
do. What we're really bad at is if two people have more knowledge on a subject than we do,
and they're in disagreement, we have a lot of problem picking out who is more knowledgeable
of the two, we tend to just default to whatever our bias is, which, by the way, is why debates tend
to be a very unhelpful forum. Yeah, I don't. I always tell people, debates favor people who can
speak well. Debates, debates tend to favor people who can speak well. And at the end of the day, I
mean, it doesn't matter what's talking about religion, politics, nutrition. 95% of the people
are going to go with whatever their perception was before the debate. And then that little 5% of the
independents are going to make their decision usually based not necessarily off evidence,
because, I mean, if you don't have a PhD in something or an advanced degree, you know,
if two people are citing studies, who do you go with? It's very, very difficult. So,
yeah, so just all that to say, I didn't feel like I really knew anything,
is three years into my biochemistry degree, even though I was getting good grades and
didn't know what I wanted to do with my life. I knew I wanted to be in the fitness industry,
like I was very passionate about bodybuilding, but I had no idea how I was going to make a living
doing that because at that time, you know, this is circa 2003, you know, the people who made money
in the fitness industry, either you owned a supplement company, you owned a gym, you were
a personal trainer, or, you know, you wrote for a publication or something like that, you know.
And I didn't have the capital to start a supplement company or the wherewithal to do that. And I
didn't really want to be a personal trainer. And so I just kind of was like, well, if I go to
graduate school, I'll learn more. Maybe I won't feel so stupid. And I can delay the real world a
little bit longer, figure out what the heck I actually want to do. And hopefully, I won't be
in the unemployment line if I have a master's or PhD. And that was that was literally my logic.
Now, how did you how did you toggle between because I could see at that moment in time,
you choosing between two paths, right? You could have gone very deep down the exercise
physiology path. And you could have gone very deep down the nutrition path, you chose the
ladder, of course, curious as to how you thought about it at the time. Yeah, I think probably the
magazine shaped some of my bias, there was a lot of focus on nutrition as opposed to training. And
even to this day, you know, this could be a little bit of selection bias. But I get a lot more
questions about nutrition than I ever do about training. And even like me, like people were like,
I hear it, well, it's 80% nutrition, 20% training. And I'm like, Listen, I have a PhD in nutrition,
I will tell you, training is the most powerful thing for your health and body composition that
you can possibly do. You know, a protein you want, you can do all these modifications with your diet,
you want, if you don't train, the changes to body comp are going to be pretty minimal, you know,
in terms of you can lose fat, but you're also going to lose a little bit of lean body mass with
it when you when you diet. And you can gain lean body mass, but you're also going to gain body fat
with it. You know, resistance training specifically is the most powerful tool you have to change your
body composition. And I would actually argue your overall health as well. But at the time, I was very
focused on nutrition and specifically had just started kind of reading studies on muscle protein
synthesis, just I was always a skinny kid growing up, you know, I wasn't a fat kid, I was I was a
skinny kid growing up. And so I was mostly focused on how do I build more muscle? How do I maximize
muscle building? I wasn't really focused on how do I get super late? Wait, let me that that goes back
to a question I wanted to ask you earlier, Lane. We kind of glossed over the fact that at 19, you
win a drug free amateur bodybuilding contest, which happened to be your first. When did you start
lifting weight seriously? How old were you? So I started and stopped because I got my first
girlfriend. So I started when I was like 15 years old, stopped when I was 16, because I got my first
girlfriend. And then I picked it back up when I was 17, almost 18, and then never dropped it out
after that. Okay, so when you go to that second pickup, give me a sense of your, your height,
your weight, your body comp, and then contrast that with what you looked at what you looked like
at 19. So I actually remember exactly how much I weighed, I was about I was right under five foot
10. I'm now five foot 10 and a half. So I essentially was pretty much stopped growing.
And I was 152 pounds. And I remember that because the day I picked back up weight weight training
was in November of I want to say 1998. No, 1999. And it was at a bigger, faster, stronger seminar
that came to my school, because I decided to get back into strength training because my girlfriend
had dumped me very shallow reasoning. And they weighed us at the bigger, faster, stronger
seminar. And for whatever reason, I always remember that now when I started originally,
I was 140 pounds as a freshman, I started lifting some weights. But at this when I picked it up
and never dropped it, I was 152 pounds. And then for my first show, I, I had peaked in the off
season, I guess it would have been two or three years later, two years later, at 200 pounds.
And I competed at 175 pounds, probably something like that. And I was by that time I grew an extra
half inch and was five foot 10 and a half. And yeah, so I guess it would have been about two
and a half years later when I when I hit that hit that mark. And, you know, I did by the end of my
high school career had gotten to be like one of the I was a bigger guys in the class, but a little
more muscular than other people, but other people had started to notice. But specifically my upper
body because my legs were still terrible. Because for the first year, I didn't really train them
because you know, leg training sucks. Was there a point when you just discovered you had a gift of
strength, you know, I remember talking to Mark and Chris Bell. And on the podcast with them,
I talked about these brothers that were around when I grew up, they were they were an age above
me. So they weren't my peers. But by the time I was a teenager, they were in their 20s. And they
were always in the gym when I was there. And there were four of them and they were freaks of nature.
Now, they were also all of them taking Herculean doses of anabolic steroids. But I saw them both
on and off steroids. And the steroids simply took their God given abilities and made them
out of this world. But I mean, I'll never forget one of the brothers,
who at the time was in residency, he was doing his residency in emergency in emergency medicine.
So he was very he was his training volume was a fraction of what it was when he was in college,
he would still come into the gym between shifts, narrow grip 315 for 12 cold, like it was nothing,
you know, on his way to squatting 505 for like, unwrapped, by the way. And like, there was just
a genetic gift that these guys had. And I sort of assumed like, yes, they train very hard. But pretty
early on, they knew that they were strong. And it was clear just based on the hereditary nature,
did you I mean, you're you're you're your best totals nearly 1800 pounds, correct? Yeah. So,
again, I don't want to for a moment, take away from how hard you work, because I know how hard
you work. But was there something that clicked in and said, I'm way better at this naturally than
I will be at baseball?
Um, so I would say actually, no, it never never clicked at that time. There was because I never
had like, I never had a period of time where my gains were just crazy. I never really had that.
What happened was, I saw that when I was very consistent and very steady, I had very steady
increases. And so it was never like, oh, you know, we I put, you know, 50 pounds on my bench press
in six months, it's like, oh, this is the thing I'm I'm doing now. It was just a very steady
progression. And I think that was actually good for me, honestly, because I think if I'd had a
lot of success right out of the gate, I might not have pushed as hard or been as consistent, because
it's kind of this weird paradox with me, the harder something is the more I want to do it.
So, and I do see this as it comes naturally to people, and they don't have those kind of
resistance early on, in terms of having to overcome like plateaus and frustration and setbacks.
And I encountered all those pretty early on. And I think having a little taste of that
enabled me to push through much bigger setbacks in the future. So honestly, I can't think of a
time when I ever was like, wow, this is now I will tell you, when I got to college, and was
training consistently and able to really eat consistently, because even though, you know,
it's calorically dense food, I was trying to build muscle like that. I wasn't really concerned about
the fact that, you know, I'm eating more calories, because one, I was using them. And two,
I just wanted to be bigger. Like I didn't care if I put on a little bit of body fat.
So there was a point when I got to college where I was like, you know what, maybe,
maybe I can do this, because I would look at, you know, some of the other, I'd search online to try
and find any like teenage bodybuilders, you know, and I look at it, come to find out partly
delusionally, because people on stage photos always look way less impressive than they
actually look in person. But I would wait way less or way more? Oh, way less. So if you see an
actual like, you know, competitive bodybuilder in person compared to how they look on stage in the
photos, usually way more impressive in person, in terms of their girth or definition, muscle size,
muscularity, everything. Oh, that's so that's counterintuitive to me. I don't really follow. I
mean, yeah, basically, I think the last bodybuilder I sort of paid any attention to was, God, well,
let's see, maybe Lee Haney when I was a kid growing up, right? And I paid attention to Lee Haney and
Dorian Yates, probably after Dorian Yates, I stopped paying attention to bodybuilding. So I
didn't I've never seen someone of that stature in person. Yeah, blow your mind. It really it really
does. Like, obviously, it's extremely impressive in magazines. And some of the gym photos that they
take with a lighting is set up really well. You can look at that and go, Okay, that's crazy,
compared to even the stage photos. But yeah, so anyway, I had this. I'm looking at these other
guys that are about my age. And I'm like, you know what, he's a little bit better than me. But I'm,
I'm kind of there. You know, I'm kind of kind of right there. Now, again, take my legs out of the
equation, because my legs were awful at the time. But my upper body was there, basically. And so I
was like, Okay, well, maybe this thing, maybe I could be good at this, right? And, you know,
come to find out, I'm sure genetics are just as important in hypertrophy as they are with
hitting a baseball or shooting a basketball, whatever have you. But at the time, my mentality
was, this is more about work ethic and translates better. And so I was more committed to putting
that energy into it. And as far as like, strength goes, and where I felt like I might have a gift.
Honestly, I think that a lot of my gift was, and again, this could be just hyperbole on my part,
I think a lot of the gift was, I'm just really stubborn. And I could tolerate a lot of training
volume, I actually today went back and looked at what I was doing before I went to the IPF World
Championships, which is essentially like the Super Bowl for powerlifting. And that was in 2015.
And I was able to get a gold medal in the squat and actually set a world squat record at the time,
which was 668 pounds. And I weighed in at 201 and a half pounds when I hit it. And like,
I tallied up how many sets I did that week with over 500 pounds between squat and deadlift. And
it was 34 sets the week you hit that lift. And well, sorry, in the two weeks before that,
so I was kind of in my overreaching phase. And I just remember looking back at that and thinking
like how bad I wanted that and just how much volume of work I did. And I think, again, I think
I was just able to tolerate some really insane style training. And I think my body was a little
bit more resilient. I think my mind was a little bit more resilient. I think that helped me a lot,
because there was a lot of, there was a lot of setbacks along the way. And that was, you know,
obviously, I was in my mid thirties when I did that compared to being a teenager, but there was
never like a year where my squat just went, you know, it was always just kind of a slow,
steady progression. And this was from the kid who had skinny legs, you know what I mean? And,
but I had, you know, endured, I had two herniated discs in my neck, I had multiple herniated discs
in my lower back, I had hip injuries, you know, everything, you know, you can imagine of lifting
heavy weights and still managed to be able to go do that. But I think the fact that I endured
some of those setbacks really early on in my career, actually, like, really helped me be able
to, you know, deal with it. Because one of my big rants I get off on is everybody's like, have more
confidence in yourself. And when I always tell people like you can't build confidence out of
nothing. If you've failed at everything you ever tried in your entire life, why would you have
confidence, right? So I try to tell people like, look, start small, you know, just like say, I'm
going to show up to like, if it's exercise, I'm going to show up every day this week, you know,
regardless of how I feel, I'm going to go do it. Or five days, whatever, pick your number. Okay,
you do that. There's just a tiny smidgen of confidence you get from that. And then you build
that over time. Okay, well, I'm going to, you know, squat 200 pounds, okay, and then you hit that.
And then maybe you get some aches and pains. Okay, well, I'm going to rehab this, I'm going to go
through this. And then you get through that and you get stronger, right? And so if you do that
over time, every little thing that you go through might feel insignificant in terms of what it means
to you at that time. But when you look back, you can draw on that. And I think, you know, I always
tell people, I don't think I would have had the success I did in business or social media or
academia if I hadn't done weightlifting, because that taught me so much about other things in life.
So I realized I went down a big rabbit hole there. But no, I think that makes a ton of sense. And
I get asked sometimes, you know, what's the most important lesson I learned growing up with respect
to ultimately being successful academically. And I was not successful at all in school until my last
year of high school, because I didn't actually plan to go to university, I wanted to become a
professional boxer. So that obviously, there was no need to go to university. But I think like you,
I had an unusual gift for tolerating a lot of training, and a surprising lack of confidence
in myself, which is what drove the training, it was sort of an insecurity that's like, the other
guy's gonna train three hours a day, I'm gonna train six hours a day. But when I finally did
decide to go to college, it actually seemed really easy, compared to getting up at 430 every morning
and running 10 miles and going to the gym this many hours and sparring this many rounds every
day and doing 400 pushups before bed every night and all of those things. If you know, if you have
to go from doing that to just studying four hours a day, you already have the what I call that kind
of the habit infrastructure and the discipline infrastructure to do that. And I do think that
translates. So that's why I think personally, I just, at least with my own kids, I think, you know,
I'm delighted when they take up an interest in something, whether it be, you know, my daughter's
case, music and sports. You know, even if you never end up being a professional athlete or
drummer or whatever it is, it's really building and wiring a discipline around that, which
obviously you've demonstrated. Give me another sense of just in terms of I'm still
you have to forgive me, but I just most people who don't lift won't appreciate the magnitude of the
numbers you're talking about, right, like a 700 pound squat when you are 200 pounds and you are
drug free. That's the thing we have to keep re emphasizing. And I appreciate the way you've
talked about this. I've read a lot of what you've talked about with respect to the use of
performance enhancing drugs. And at least to me, it's never come across as haughty or, you know,
holier than thou. It's been, hey, look, this is my choice. And your only real pet peeve is people
who cheat and basically enter drug free bodybuilding competitions while using drugs, which is,
you know, in a sport like bodybuilding, where you truly have a choice that strikes me as nonsensical.
Exactly. But let's go back to when you're 19. How much could you squat, deadlift and bench?
With clear, I mean, under, you know, and I don't mean bench where you're bouncing off your chest.
I mean, under clear guidance and rules. So the interesting thing was I was a really good bench
presser in high school. And as a competitive power lifter, 15 years later, bench press was my worst
lift. So I peaked early. I hit a 300 pound bench press in high school. Now that was not with a
pause. If I'm thinking about what I could pause, probably would have been like 285 or something
like that 280. My squat, I managed so I didn't really train squat that much because legs hurt.
And I I'm I have so my body type, I have a very long femur to shin ratio as well as a shorter torso.
And essentially what that's going to mean is when you squat, the bar must stay over your mid foot if
you're going to not fall forwards or backwards. And so that means that I have to lean forward quite
a bit when I squat. And so it's not it's not a pretty squat when I was when especially when I
was in high school, it didn't know how to use, you know, hinge correctly and use my hips and whatnot.
So I mean, basically, I was able to squat 315 folded over as a as a as a high schooler. So
I mean, that's pretty strong for a high schooler, but it wasn't it was barely to depth if that.
And definitely not the way you would teach it to somebody. And as far as deadlift, I didn't really
deadlift in high school. I don't think I I'm trying to think about if I ever actually deadlifted.
I think maybe sporadically, maybe I could have hit three plates, but I'm not sure. I do know that
I kind of started doing it in college. And I think I hit like a 405 pound deadlift, you know,
before I left college. And I think when I I want to say that I hit like a 385 pound squat when I
finished college. So there's no again, you can see like it's not that's amazing. Yeah,
that's those are very mortal numbers, right? That's a that's a very slow and steady trajectory.
To obviously where you are now, and it probably reflects
kind of muscle maturity and also technique maturity. You mentioned earlier in passing
that you had a couple of herniations, both cervical and lumbar. Did any of them require surgery?
No, and actually, I, you know, I'm full disclosure, I'm not a pain expert or, you know,
an orthopedist. I think I got some really good advice to not get surgery by the initial person
I saw from my neck. And actually, so Dr. Joe, my coach, he was also a physical therapist.
And he said, Listen, because the so the first doctor I went to when I had my disc herniation,
I played rugby in college. And that's what I got it from. I had two disc herniations. And I had
lost, I remember, basically, I had a stinger. And I couldn't even pick up a chair with my left hand
in my dorm room without slipping out of my hand, I lost about 40% of my strength on this left side.
And I mean, the first doctor I went to was like, Yeah, you know, you probably won't get back all
the strength that you had. And I remember thinking, why don't you just stab me in the heart instead,
you know, like it'd been easier. But you know, I talked to Dr. Joe and Joe was like, Listen,
you know, you have to understand these doctors are used to dealing with your average person who's
not going to do the rehab, who's not going to do the work, who's not going to push themselves,
he said, that's not you, you will get back, you will hit PRs in the future. You know, this is,
this is not a death sentence for your lifting career. Okay. And sure enough, six months later,
I was, you know, I did the rehab and I was I was hitting PRs again. And then my lumbar herniations,
I actually saw Stu McGill, who's one of the more well known experts on on lower back pain. And,
you know, he did an in person assessment of me and he basically said, Listen, you know, you've,
yeah, you've got, you've got some herniations, but so do about 60% of all people who are over
the age of 30. Did you have any loss of strength going down your legs? Did you have any true sciatic
pain or I never had radiating pain. I was very localized. But I mean, when it flared up,
it was like 10 out of 10 could not get up off my floor. I mean, I, I tell people at my lowest
point, I went from literally not being able to move off my side on my floor to squatting 668
pounds, you know, at a point later in time. What was the what was the delta between those time periods?
Uh, so with my lower back, it's it has kind of been a little bit of an ongoing issue. So the first
time it really hit me was in 2015. The first really bad incident I had was actually a week
out from the Arnold Pro. And I had been crushing weights in training. I mean, I was, I was very
convinced I was going to squat like 680 or 690. I had hit 600 for five in training on squat. I had
hit 675 deadlift for four. I mean, I was smashing weights. And the last heavy training session
before the Arnold so I was going to compete on the Friday of the Arnold classic. And the Friday
before was my last heavy training session. And I finished my squats, I went to go do bench press,
and I still remember, like I laid down, I was like, little tight, that's weird. And it kind of
progressively got worse through the day, to the point when I woke up the next day, I couldn't move.
And I was like, Oh, my God, I have to pull all this meat, you know, this and that.
And once the initial kind of inflammation went down, you know, a few days later, I went in,
I was like, all right, basically, three days before the meet, I said, I'm going to go in and try to
hit my openers. And if I can't hit them, then we're just going to call it. And I hit them. I went
and did the meat, I actually won. Just so people know what we're talking about. This was a bodybuilding
meat, not a powerlifting meat, correct? No, this was power was this. Okay, okay. Yeah, yeah. So I
went in and hit a long story, but I actually ended up tying the world record at that meet, due to an
error by my coach in terms of attempt selection, no hate towards my coach, everybody makes mistakes,
but in any case, I actually did end up winning the meat and squatting 661 pounds that meet.
But then that lower back issue kind of dogged me, it was never as bad as it was the initial time.
But I had so that was the Arnold's that was in March, I had the world championships coming up
in June. And that injury kind of dogged me on and on through my training. And I got to a point
where I had to take four weeks off squatting and deadlifting. And I got I started back squatting
and deadlifting with four weeks to go for the world championships. And again, I don't want to
belabor too long, but essentially, I like I was missing weights early on in that training, that
final training cycle, there were like 100 pounds less than what I needed to squat at world. But I,
you know, thankfully, again, had so many setbacks, you know, early in my lifting career, that I just
kind of convinced myself that, okay, well, we're just going to keep showing up, we're going to see
what happens, you know, and ended up going in and hitting a world record on squat and actually got
a got a gold medal in squat, got a silver medal overall. And, you know, obviously did really well.
And then a couple years after that, during training, this was during a very stressful
period of my life. And actually, they have shown that like stress, lack of sleep,
all that plays into your level of pain sensitivity. I hurt my back and had
some other things happen. And I mean, that basically got to the point where I couldn't
move for a couple days. And that's when I kind of took it this is in December of 2017. And I took a
step I didn't really take a step back, I took pretty much nine months off of any kind of spine
loading, probably excessive probably didn't need to go that long. But then built back up and in
2019 hit a 666 pound squat, the 727 pound deadlift at nationals. So, you know, I think,
I think a lot of people get injuries, especially like these soft tissue injuries, and they
they, you know, hear doctors or, or, you know, people that are operating off of pain science from,
you know, decades ago, say, well, just stop lifting, or just stop doing whatever, you know,
athletic thing that you do. And I don't think it's a death sentence for most people. I mean,
if you look at, especially with regards to back injuries, I mean, if you go MRI 100 people that
are over the age of 35, about half of them will have herniated disc that they don't even realize,
because they're asymptomatic. So I think, you know, obviously, if you're having pain, you know,
trying to trying to treat the source of that in terms of is it is it could I don't want to get too
far down the rabbit hole, because this isn't my area of expertise. But well, let me ask you this
question. In your case, do you have a sense what it was about the lifts that was specifically
causing the pain? So, you know, sometimes you can actually identify what the issue is in the
individual that is through an axial loading pattern driving the pain. So it could be, you know,
one of my favorite examples is right people who can't generate enough intra abdominal pressure,
or who can't create, you know, who might have too much lordosis in the spine. When they're under
an axial load, or they can't, they can't generate enough articulation between l one and T 12. Right,
so they don't have the segmental control within the spine. So they sent it they tend to generate
disproportionate load at hinge points, like, were you able to look at yourself and say, Okay, well,
like, you know, presumably, I'm hurting my making this up, right, but I'm saying presumably, I'm
hurting myself under the height, you know, when I'm over 500 pounds, I'm not really hurting myself
when I'm, you know, doing 405 for 10. And when I'm and this is how my form changes when I go from
doing 405 to 595. And I think that's what it is that's precipitating this injury. And I'm going
to work on not just rehabbing the injury, but modifying the form. I mean, was there were you
able to do some sort of an analysis like that? I mean, lumbar flexion definitely was kind of
a triggering for the pain. But if we look at like, the biopsychosocial model of pain,
it gets really murky, because I mean, they've shown that you can have tissue damage and no pain,
and you can have pain with very little tissue damage. So I think part of it was just, I had
that initial injury to the disc, but then I probably didn't give myself enough time to
desensitize myself to that pain and just kept hammering at it. And the research, it's interesting,
the research actually shows that one of the best things you can do for low back pain is resistance
training. Like that's actually one of the best things you can do. But if you are so if you're
doing it with a load that increases that pain, then it's going to make it worse. So I think that the
the what people probably need to take away is that if you're having pain, and again,
this isn't my area of expertise, I take this from people I've learned from, but modify the load and
see if that reduces your pain, modify the tempo, modify the the range of motion. And then if none
of those things do then try to modify the exercise selection. And my problem was I was so dogged
about I need to do squat, bench press and deadlift, I need to work through this pain,
and I made it worse for a period of time. Now, you know, like to think I'm a little bit wiser
in my old age. Now I don't just try to work through it, I say okay, you know, if I'm having
a great example is I had some hip pain that I'd been dealing with for about six to seven months.
And the way it finally got better was I said, okay, I'm going to stop doing full range of
motion squats full speed, I'm going to try and take it back to what can I do with kind of a
minimal amount of pain, like a two or three out of 10, right, something that doesn't cause pain,
but I can still get some work in. And for me, that was like, above parallel pin squats. So basically,
I bring it down, nice and slow, pause at the pins and then come up. And I started out doing those.
And then the next week, you know, I'd either increase the load, or I would lower the pins.
And I did that for probably about six weeks. And then I got to the point where, okay,
it's not hurting as much, I'm going to try and do without the pins, above parallel regular squat,
with tempo, like three second descent, right, taking that that speed away from it.
I did that for like three, four weeks, pain went down, and then basically got to the point where
I could do a full squat with no pain. And so again, I'm not, you know, I don't have a randomized
control group to compare this to, it could be I could, if I would have just done nothing, I would
have gotten the same benefits, who knows. But I think just because you have pain doesn't mean you
can't do something. And I based on what some of the pain specialists have said, you're probably
better off doing something than nothing if you can, because if you just take time away from training,
you end up detraining. So when you come back, you're not as practice at the lifts,
and you might end up hurting yourself again. So that's kind of the approach I take is modifying
those variables and seems to be seems to be working okay. I'm you know, I always tell people like this
stuff's like a puzzle. And I'm still, you know, I've spent the last few years working through some
injuries and just trying to figure out, okay, how can I make this puzzle work so that I can be,
you know, you know, compete as an athlete again? Yeah, I agree with that completely. I think the
worst thing one can do under virtually any circumstances completely stop the activity.
I find that moving from two legs to one leg becomes a great tool in my toolkit when I'm hurting.
So moving to much more split squat, you know, single leg activity, I mean, even something,
even if you look at something like a leg press, right, so you know, you're sort of an inverted
doing a leg press, that's an exercise where you can load up stupid amounts of weight.
If I'm feeling anything that's not right there, I'll happily go to a single leg where you're
going to typically use not half, but a third the weight at a single leg. And, you know, all of a
sudden, those things that were hurting when you were doing it with two legs kind of stop hurting,
in my opinion, you're getting virtually the same benefit potentially more because you're
evening out any thing that wasn't right there. And I've noticed that I think I can say without
exception, things get better. Again, for me, it also requires a very careful examination of what
the root problem was. I guess the last question I have for you on this very specific topic before I
get into a whole bunch of other things that we're going to talk about is the overlap and or
detraction between powerlifting and bodybuilding. So you've competed at such a high level in these
two sports that have a very clear overlap, but also have a pretty different point of optimization.
I mean, bodybuilding is a very subjective sport, where it's about how you look. And at the end of
the day, nobody cares how strong you are when you're standing on that stage. Conversely,
powerlifting, which of course requires a lot of strength, nobody really cares how you look. So
both of those athletes pay unbelievable attention to how much weight they lift. But they're serving
a very different purpose. You're one of the people who has excelled at both. I've met people who are
excellent at one or the other, more on the power side, I should say than the bodybuilding side.
So I'm curious as to what some of the trade offs are that you have to make and and sort of a
hypothetical lane. If you what would be the closest length of time you could have between the two if
you wanted to be at your best in each? Great, great, great question. So I think the overlap is that
the obvious one is that to look muscular, you have to have a lot of muscle and contractile
tissue is what's needed to move weight. Right. So the more there is a little bit of debate about
this, but the consensus is is that hypertrophy does matter for strength training. So the more muscle
you have, the more weight you're going to be able to lift. I think that the trade off is that
bodybuilding is a much more forgiving sport in so far as. I mean, you can you can skin the cat
a thousand different ways. If you don't want to squat, you can hack squat. You don't want to
hack squat. You can split squat. It is simply about creating tension on that muscle, getting
the requisite volume in and progressive overload. Now people hear progressive overload and they
think weight, but progressive overload takes many forms. And the major one of which is volume
in particular volume load, which is basically for all intents and purposes, number of hard sets,
number of sets that approach failure. So you can do that many different ways. If you're hurting
on a certain exercise, hey, change it up. Try something different. Find something that you can
do without pain or find something that you really enjoy. Right. There's a lot of different ways to
skin a cat. When it comes to powerlifting, you can do some accessory movements and whatnot,
but you still have to do the major lifts. You still have to be very well trained. The major lifts.
Otherwise you're not going to perform your best on meat day. And so I think that
bodybuilding in a way is a little bit more demanding mentally because the hug, like
if you've never, if people out there listening, if you've never been like insanely shredded,
you cannot imagine the levels of hunger and low energy that these people go through. And that I
have been through. I'm talking about so hungry that you literally think about it from the moment
you wake up to the moment you go to sleep. And then it wakes you up at night. I'm talking about
such low energy that I can remember one time I was like, I had finished my training session. I
was probably a few weeks out from a show. I was sitting on my couch and the remote control was
and the remote control was probably five feet away from me. And there was a terrible show on
that I did not want to watch. And I watched the entire thing because I did not feel like getting
up to get the remote. And that kind of serves into like metabolic adaptation and reductions in
non-exercise activity, thermogenesis. And just give people a sense, Lane, of how many calories a day
you might be ingesting during that period of your training cycle and for how long that would last.
Yeah. So I, you know, my last, my last show I did, I competed as a pro natural bodybuilder in 2010.
So it's been a while. And I won the IFP international, the heavyweight division,
and then I, I ended up doing the IFP world championships and placed top five in the heavyweight
division. And it's difficult because it's like the amount of calories you start on is not going
to be what you end up finishing on. I think the lowest my calories got was just around 1900.
Now that may not sound that bad, but keep in mind, you know, we're talking about somebody who is,
you know, probably over 185 pounds of lean body mass, you know, quite a bit of lean body mass.
And training how many hours per day?
Two hours a day, you know, minimum. So I mean, that was pretty much all I had energy for,
you know, I'd go in the gym and train for two hours. And that would be all she wrote, you know,
and I'd muster up. I can remember going in and doing a cardio session one night.
I got on the elliptical, I started going and the only way I can describe this is it felt soul
sucking. And I went for what I felt like must have been 40 minutes. And I looked down at the
clock and it said three minutes, three minutes. And I just remember thinking, how, how can I do
this? I mean, like, so tired that like, or even like I would stand up and I would get lightheaded
because my blood pressure was so low, you know, it's a very, so I think bodybuilding is very
difficult in that that that doesn't leave you, right? Powerlifting is difficult in that it beats
your body up. But once you're done at the gym, other than you're like rehab work and some other
stuff, I mean, you can kind of leave it at the gym, you know. So they're really difficult sports,
but for for slightly different reasons, you know, again, bodybuilding is more forgiving in that
it doesn't really matter what exercises you do, as long as you get in enough, right? And you can
kind of skin that cat multiple different ways. I mean, we've we've seen bodybuilders be successful
through every different methodology. You know, Dorian Yates never squatted. I mean, he talked
about it. He only did leg press, right? Leg press and leg extensions. Whereas Ronnie Coleman,
you know, squatted, you know, tons of weight. So I think that the the appeal for me for bodybuilding
was that mental challenge, you know, basically how much could you suffer?
And then the appeal and powerlifting was this is not subjective. I mean, it is a little bit
subjective, because you can argue squat depth is subjective, you can argue that deadlift lockouts
are right, but far, far less subjective, far less subjective. And I mean, I've had that,
you know, the order of the competition is you get three attempts on each lift,
and it goes squat bench press deadlift. And it's progressive, meaning, if you pick a weight,
and you miss it, you can't go down. So you can only go up. But I've been I've been in those big
meets where it comes down to the very last deadlift. And it's like, either you pull it or you don't.
And that determines if you win or not. I mean, I've had that experience. It's unbelievable.
And so to me, I probably prefer that only because I'm, I'm doing what I trained to do, right? Like in
bodybuilding, I'm doing something different than I trained to do. What I needed to do to get to that
bodybuilding stage is way different than what I'm going to do on stage. Whereas powerlifting,
I'm just doing what I've done, right? Like this is just a showcase. So now to your question,
how far apart could you do well in them? And let me add one more question, which is what order would
you pick? You get to pick the order of which you do the two contests and what the minimum space is
to optimize both. So that's going to be so individually dependent, right? Because, you know,
for me at my weight class in powerlifting, 93 kilograms or 205 pounds, I'm pretty lean at that
body weight. So what I would say is that I would probably, if I was going to do this, I would do a
meat. I maintain this body weight with some level of effort, but mostly pretty easily. I would do
the meat and then I would start prepping for a show. And how much longer would you need after
that meat? How long would it take for you to be stage ready? It depends on how hard I wanted to
push it and what level. If I was wanting to really maximize lean body mass retention,
I'd probably want six months, I would say. Because what people don't realize is we look at like,
we look at these diet studies and we see how much lean body mass gets lost versus fat mass.
And people don't realize that a lot of this depends on how much body fat you're starting with,
and then it changes, the curve changes. So if you're somebody who's overweight or obese,
you don't really need to worry about losing too much lean body mass because you have such a
reservoir of energy to pull from that your body doesn't really see the need to start pulling from
lean body mass. But if you're somebody who's at, and I'll use my caliper measurements for all the
internet experts out there, I realize that the numbers I'm going to give you are not the true
numbers, but I don't care. It's what I'm referring to. I'm just using it as a reference point.
I always have to qualify this when I get body fat numbers. So I can go from 15% body fat to 7% body
fat, and it's extremely easy. No problems. I lose very minimal lean body mass from 7% to 5%. Now,
I'm probably losing 20% to 30% of that weight is lean body mass. When you get down to the
shredded area where you're just when you literally tried to squeeze off that last little bit of body
fat, you might be losing just as much lean body mass as you are fat mass. So for me, what I would
do, and I didn't do this years ago because I didn't even know about this tool, is I actually
implement a lot of what's called diet breaks. So those would be periods of eating at maintenance.
So basically a level of calories where you're not going to add back fat tissue, but you can eat more
than you did previously. So I had pretty good success with this the past year because I dropped
30 pounds. I went up a weight class in powerlifting and then came back down. And so basically I would
diet for two or three weeks pretty aggressively, try to lose like a pound and a half, two pounds
each week. And then I would take one or two or three weeks and eat just at a maintenance
level of calories, which for me is about 32, 33, 3400. And that worked extremely well for me,
extremely well for keeping my strength. And so if I was getting ready for a bodybuilding show,
I probably wouldn't use those too much if I was like coming down from a higher body fat. But as
I approach, as I would be approaching that lower level of body fat, I would be starting to put
these in more and more frequently. So that's why I would give myself so much time, even though I
only need to drop about maybe 12, 15 pounds from where I'm at right now. I would probably spend
more time at maintenance than I did in a deficit. Because when you get to those low levels of body
fat, the best way I can describe it is like if you have a wet towel, when you start squeezing,
water comes out very easily. This is this acts almost a perfect example of adipose tissue,
because if you take somebody who's overweight obese, what do you have? You have a lot of free
fatty acids getting released into the bloodstream. You have very, very expanded fat tissue. So when
you start, you start reading that rag out, it comes off very easily. But then when you get down
to the ends, and you're just trying to get that last little bit of water out, to get the same
amount of water out, you have to put in monumental levels of effort compared to what you did at the
beginning. So I guess that's kind of a huge qualifier of why I want so much time to be in my house.
I mean, the one thing that you said, Lane, that actually surprised me, and I want to think about
this through the lens of some examples, because I thought we could use examples of people like,
you know, kind of people that hypotheticals are patients of mine, I was surprised that you said
going from 15% to 7% body fat could be done without much loss of lean tissue. That is really impressive.
Yeah, for me. And is that is that just a function of how hard you're training at the same time?
Is that just something that you would attribute to your genetics? Because it's, you know, it's not
due to exogenous testosterone, which would obviously be one tool that would enable that
kind of lean mass retention. Yeah, so I think the first thing is,
it probably depends a lot on what your body fat set point is, or settling point. So for those
who aren't familiar, body fat set point theory is essentially that you kind of have this
relatively tight range of homeostatic body fat that your body will defend. And once you start to
drop below that range, it's when you really start to feel the negative effects of caloric restriction
in terms of your hunger goes up, your BMR drops, your non-exercise activity, thermogenesis drops,
your libido drops, you start to have those negative side effects. For me, you know, I would say that
my again, on calipers, that the low end of my body fat set point is probably around 7%. And the high
end is probably around 11. And how does that correlate with DEXA for you? Do you do you know
how the caliper numbers correlate with DEXA? Probably about 3% more on a DEXA, I would say,
kind of 10 to 14% is your DEXA sweet spot. So yeah, something like that. And in a show,
by the way, you're below 4%. Is that what I would infer from what you said earlier?
On calipers, the lowest I've caliper, it was like just over 2% body fat. So so call it 45% by DEXA,
potentially, probably maybe five or six. Yeah, something like that. And again, that's something
I don't really I let the internet worry about that. Because at the end of the day, it's just
about the visual aspect, right? Although I would guess I would guess below that lane, because
as recently as 10 years ago, I was 7.1% on DEXA, I mean, repeatedly, like 7.1 to 7.8 by DEXA.
And I still remember what I looked like then, nothing like what a bodybuilder looks like. So
I would easily believe that by DEXA, a bodybuilder could be 4%. Possible. I just I remember, so there
was a guy, he's another natural bodybuilder named Alberto Dunez. And if you ever saw pictures of this
guy, like I'm talking like veins visible vascularity in his glutes, right? Yeah. So like that. Yeah,
that's crazy. And he was going he went and got a DEXA done. And I remember he was asking people
like, what do you think I'm going to be and people were like, Oh, 2% 3%. And he and he was six,
you know, on a DEXA. So the question is, then I'd have to ask how much of that was visceral versus
subcutaneous. Possible. The other thing is people though, people need to appreciate is the level of
air that's in those measurements. Yeah, you know, there is an inherent level of error in those
measurements. But yeah, that's, that's, that's counterintuitive for that level of what you
describe in terms of vascularity. Yeah. Yeah. So, so who knows? But I think if you are somebody who
your body naturally likes to be at a little bit of a higher body fat percentage, you may see some
lean body mass loss, you know, add a similar body fat to what I am able to retain more at. Right. So
now this is me just completely speculating, because there's so little data on this,
because studies are just so restrictive in terms of what you can actually measure. And I think that
this is this is another point that people don't fully appreciate is that, you know, scientific
studies are really big blunt instruments. Like you, you, you can, you are really, if you're doing
a scientific study, you're only supposed to modify a couple of variables, if that, because otherwise
you just have no idea if what you're observing is due to the, the, the variables that you want to
test. Otherwise you might as well just go to observational data. And so they're just, when it
comes to this kind of stuff, there's so little data out there. And so this kind of is pulling from my
opinions based on some randomized control trials, I've seen some case studies I've seen and some
mechanistic data, some animal data, you know, and I'm, I always like to tell people when I'm,
when I'm kind of going out in a limb, because I don't want to state it as fact if I, if I'm not
sure if it's fact, but I would say that, you know, the differences we see and how much people can
retain with lean body mass. I think part of it's due to what their natural body fat set point level
is. Because as we exit that lower end of our body fat set point, if the body likes to keep a certain
level of body fat, then it makes sense that it might start pulling a little bit more energy from
lean tissue compared to fat tissue if it's starting to defend that body fat. Now, there are
quite a few things we can do to overcome this, like resistance training, right? Like that's a big one.
And I think some of the decrements we see in lean body mass with dieting is one, a lot of these
studies don't do resistance training, or when people are dieting and they're starting to feel
worse because their lower energy, their training volume drops, their training intensity drops,
and that's probably part of it. And I think the other thing is too, like, I will say going from
like 15% to seven on calipers, I did lose some lean body mass, but you know, my relative strength
didn't really change. So what's likely is, you know, a lot of people don't realize lean body mass
is not the same thing as muscle mass. Lean body mass is all non fat tissues, that's skin, bone,
organ weight, all that stuff, and including your body water. And a lot of I think what we see with
lean body mass loss is water, gut tissue, liver, those those tissues shrink in response to caloric
restriction. And so I think most people don't appreciate the glycogen, the amount of glycogen
you can lose and how much water tracks with glycogen. So you lose, let's say you lose half
your glycogen volume. Do you take the mass of that multiply it by three to four, that's the total mass
that's lost given the water as well, not to mention the plasma loss that comes with plasma contraction.
Yeah, I mean, we see that like in ketogenic diet studies, like Kevin Hall's study, you know,
there was a loss of lean body mass, but even I in, you know, you know me, I'm very critical of,
of, you know, zealots and nutrition. And so when I've criticized, you know, ketogenic diet stuff,
I've even still said, you know, in this Kevin Hall study, well, that's most of that is probably water,
you know, because if like you said, if you lose glycogen, you're losing quite a bit of water with
that, right? No, I wonder if you would agree with an observation that I have found for which I
haven't found data to support, but truthfully, I haven't been on a huge hunt for it, but it's
been very empirical for me. So I've gone through various different phases of fasting, where I'm
doing it for different purposes, right? So I'm not doing it for body composition or anything other
than, you know, sort of ramping up autophagy. So basically kind of periodic fasting for health
benefits. And the thing that I've noticed is, and let's just use, I would typically do like a seven
day, five to seven day water only fast each quarter. And what I noticed was, provided I did
resistance training every single day during that fast, so I dramatically changed my training,
because I would normally be alternating between cardio and resistance. But if on those fasting
days, the only thing I did was resistance training. And specifically, I focused on the biggest lifts
possible. So deadlift is my favorite lift. So I would even deadlift every other day,
and mostly just focus on the biggest muscles. I had to go a lot slower. So I had to take, I needed
much more rest between sets, but I could actually still move the exact same amount of weight. So I
didn't get any weaker. It seemed to minimize the loss of lean mass, certainly muscle. I shouldn't
say that I lost water weight, but I did not appear to lose muscle mass. My thinking was that that I
was at least counter balancing the effect of mTOR reduction that was coming through the nutrient
pathway through a different stimulus. Does that, and again, we're going to talk a lot about mTOR,
because of course, your work in leucine ties right into my interest around nutrient sensing.
Does my observation fit with your observations and your experiences?
So we have to, I always try to put things in context, right? So I think if you're looking at,
you know, losing actual contractile tissue, once you've built it, what it takes to maintain muscle
tissue is very minimal compared to what it takes to actually build it. So it does not necessarily
surprise me, especially because, you know, this gets into kind of like power of suggestion, placebo,
your own personal feelings about stuff, because you view fasting as such a positive that you
wouldn't have a reduction in strength, because you probably really haven't lost contractile tissue
in that period of time. Now, if I take somebody, now it's important to point out that you are a,
I would say, a well-trained person, but not somebody who pushes the, like your goal isn't
to push the upper limit of hypertrophy. Would I be correct in that? Absolutely. Nor strength for
that matter. Right. So, and this is where some of the misinterpretations come from what I say
to people. So I had this the other day. I'll say, okay, do I think that somebody could build strength,
maintain it, doing that sort of thing? Absolutely. A lot of that just comes down to boils down to
being really consistent with your resistance training. If somebody says to me, I want to be
the most muscular, strongest human I possibly can be, do I think that that is still the best
thing that they could do? No, I do not. But again, it's important to qualify both those things,
because I realized that one audience, even though I have more of that audience, is a very small,
specific subsection of the actual number of people. But when I say that, what people hear is,
Lane says you can't get strong fasting. And I have to always say, no, no, that's not what I'm
saying. You absolutely can. Do I think that you could get as big and strong doing that as someone
who is, you know, consuming nutrients regularly? I don't think so. But we probably will never get
a randomized control lifelong randomized control trial on that. So I can't say for certain.
Well, actually, I agree with you on that. And in fact, you know, when the when the when we turned
into the new year this year, you know, I went and got a DEXA scan and looked at myself in January of
this year. And I was like, God, I'm kind of amazed over the last decade how much muscle mass I've
lost. So I am on January 4 of this year, I weighed the exact same amount that I weighed 10 years ago
in May of 2011. So for all intents and purposes, over a decade, my body weight was unchanged.
I'm embarrassed to tell you how much my body fat went up, right? It went from about 7% to 16%
over a decade. So you can do the math, right? Like it's pretty straightforward. I got fatter,
I lost muscle. Now, I'm not going to beat myself up too much. A lot has happened in a decade,
right? I used to train four and a half to five hours a day, I now train maybe 90 minutes per day,
I have very different priorities, my goals are totally different. But you know, I talked about
it with Beth Lewis, who I work with, and I was like, Look, and she was like, Look, we got to get
some more muscle on you, dude, it's kind of getting pathetic. So her first thing was no more fasting
for a while, right? That was basically her first suggestion, which is like, we got to take a break
from the monthly fasting, because that's probably not helping your lean tissue. And if we want that
to be a goal, which is, is there any reason we shouldn't be able to put five pounds of muscle on
you in the next year? Her view is I think we can do this, but you can't be fasting every month for
three to five days. So I think that's completely in line with what you're saying, which is an
optimization issue. It's you know, and I've heard you talk about this with respect to plant versus
animal protein, and it gets always taken out of context. I just had this discussion the other day,
so again, what I'll let you state the argument again, because you'll probably do a better
job stating your own words than I will, you know, stating your words for you.
Yeah, so I kind of had this discussion with somebody who, you know, was saying, well,
if you look at the randomized control trials, you know, plant versus animal, it just doesn't
make a difference if total protein is equated. And what I've said to people is, okay, I understand
that randomized control trials are the gold standard. If we are looking at resistance-trained
individuals, eight weeks in terms of looking at actual muscle mass is such a short period of time.
Okay, now I understand my bias is I did work in Lucene, I was funded by the egg and dairy councils,
all that kind of stuff. So I'm sure that any conspiracy theorists out there will have a field
day, but I would never tell somebody you can't build muscle with plant protein. Of course you
can. Just go look at those plant-based bodybuilders you can look at who have extremely
impressive physique, so obviously you can do it, right? Now, can you build just as much muscle with
plant protein? I think you can. However, it's probably going to require more planning on your
part, and just a little bit more attention to detail because of the factors of limiting
amino acids, low leucine content, those sorts of things. Do I think all things being equal
animal protein is probably a superior form of protein? I do. That being said, that is a small
sliver of what actually contributes to hypertrophy. Consistent resistance training and progressive
overload is by far the most dominant factor. But we can barely oftentimes not even pick out
differences. We know volume is important. We know volume weekly set number is important.
We can't even pick out differences in hypertrophy sometimes with different volume protocols.
What makes you think we're going to pick out differences in actual hypertrophy in eight weeks
from protein sources where calories and total protein are equated? And so what I've said is,
I think the studies are probably a little bit underpowered and shorter on time to actually show
the differences we want to show. Now, I'm not saying they're bad studies. I'm just saying this
is a limitation. That's all. Yeah. So actually, I was going to say that a second ago, but I didn't
want to interrupt you when you were talking about the limitations of some of these RCTs. And I was
going to add the limitation you just mentioned, which is it's hard enough to control the variables.
But the other thing is the tighter you put the grip on controlling the variables, by definition,
in a real world, the shorter the study must become. So you look at Kevin Hall's studies,
well, Kevin is doing studies at the highest level that they can be done. So these are patients that
are in patients. And I know this very well. I'm very close friends with Kevin. I have a very clear
understanding of how the board runs both his ward at NIH and also several others around the country.
I've even spent time inside the metabolic chambers personally to experience this. And yeah,
we're talking about the highest level of precision inside a chamber that does indirect calorimetry.
The reality of it is you can't put somebody in this situation for a year. And so when it comes to
going back to exercise, if we think that, you know, the difference in a person over six months might
be two to three pounds of muscle mass under perfect conditions, it's going to be very difficult to
tease that out in eight weeks. The other thing I would say going back to protein that I've always
struggled with, and I want to actually get your opinion on this because this is something that
I want to know how much this matters both personally and also professionally for my patients,
is I have to suspect at least when it comes to leucine, timing must matter. And I'll in a moment,
I'll come back to why I've been curious about this, just based on what we now understand about
how leucine and cestrin two work in triggering mTORC1. So there becomes this whole other variable,
which is when we talk about plant versus animal, does it matter where in relation to training we're
taking that? Does it matter, you know, meal timing, specifically training timing and all of those other
things? So let's actually maybe use this as an opportunity to now talk about kind of your work
in graduate school and what it's taught you about muscle protein synthesis and the importance of
leucine because I think even the most, you know, sort of casual observer of bro science has heard
of a branched chain amino acid. And, you know, if you click one level below a branched chain amino
acid, you'll know that there are three of them. And one of them happens to be called leucine.
And people I think would gather that somehow taking those things is good for muscle.
But my guess is that's about the level at which most people stop understanding it.
So let's talk about what is muscle protein synthesis, what is the role of leucine and,
and I also want to even dive deeper into that, which is how does the body preserve leucine,
what do leucine levels look like during the course of a day in response to a meal a fast, etc.
Great question. So muscle protein synthesis is basically what it sounds like it is the
synthesis of muscle proteins from amino acid substrates. And, you know, you can separate it
in terms of like what you look at in research, you can you can do what's called mixed muscle
protein synthesis, which is what we did, which is where you're really taking the entirety of a muscle
and you're grinding it up and you're homogenizing it and then you're, you're basically using in the
studies we use stable isotopes to assess this we used D5 phenylalanine, which is basically a
deuterated one of the hydrogens on the phenylalanine is deuterated and you can basically you're looking
at how much of that label gets incorporated into the, the mixed muscle of the, of the,
or sorry, the mixed muscle versus how much is in the precursor pool, which is the intracellular
fluid, and that rate divided by a time factor will tell you what the rate of muscle protein
synthesis is. And on a kind of a more broad level protein synthesis starts in your DNA,
because your DNA codes for those proteins that are going to be synthesized. So, for example,
let's say you go and you do a resistance training session, we know that in response to resistance
training you have an increase in muscle protein synthesis, that resistance training is triggering
something. It's probably a cascade of things that are telling your DNA, we need to adapt to this
stressor. So we are going to increase the transcription of these, you know, specific
DNA sequences to the messenger. And I'm really, really abbreviating this, because you get the
introns, extrons, mRNA degradation, all this kind of stuff, but it gets transcribed to an mRNA
sequence, which is then read by a ribosome. And that ribosome based on the mRNA is going to bring
amino acids in and hook them together to build these new proteins. So in the case of, you know,
let's say you go and you do resistance training, you know, myosin, actin, these contractile
proteins, you're going to need those as part of your adaptation to that stressor. And so those
are going to be some of the things that are going to be built during muscle protein synthesis.
Now, my work specifically was in animals, and I'll tell you why, and you kind of alluded to it
earlier. So we actually, I have a research review that's going to be coming out on my website. One
of the things I'm very proud of is we have a 50 page guide on how to read research. And we have
a Venn diagram in there. And in the Venn diagram, we have highly controlled, high subject number,
long duration. And what you find is the only way you can get all those to overlap is if you do
animal studies. So if you want, if you want tightly controlled and a high subject number,
it's going to be really short in humans. If you want long duration, and tightly controlled,
it's going to be very few subjects. If you want, you know, you can kind of get the gist of it.
So for I decided I wanted to do animals because I was more kind of interested in
finding out the mechanisms of this stuff. And so, you know, you can do one of the reasons I liked
using rats was one, they're a good model for human protein metabolism. A lot of the stuff in rats has
then been validated in humans. There are some differences. But I can teach a rat to meal feed,
meaning they eat discrete meals. I can get them to eat what I want them to eat. And then I can
measure what I want to measure. And I can poke and prod them and do all that kind of stuff,
as long as it's okay with the IACUC, which is basically the IRB for animals. And so what we
were interested in was what you kind of talked about, like how important is leucine? Because at
that time, the you know, the mid 2000s, there had been quite a bit of work done by my advisor,
Dr. Don Lehman, as well as the Penn State group, which was Leonard Jefferson and Scott Kimball,
looking at, okay, we know if we give purified solutions of leucine, they increase mTOR activity,
and we see an increase in muscle protein synthesis. But one, what does that mean for
complete meals where you have protein, carbohydrate and fat? What does it mean in the context of
different protein sources? And then what does actually even matter for tissue weights? Right?
Like you actually actually see differences in actual tissue. And so one of the some of those
work we did was one, we looked at the duration of muscle protein synthesis in response to
a complete meal. And that was really interesting. Actually, that was one of the things I was
dead wrong about what I thought I was going to see versus what I actually saw.
And so we saw like even with weight, so weight protein, which is thought of as a fast protein,
basically, we saw an increase in muscle protein synthesis that peaked at 90 minutes post meal,
and then by 180 minutes or three hours had gone back down the baseline, which has since been
validated in humans. That's about what we see in humans as well. Now, now, Lane, let me just ask
you a question there for a sec before you go further. Do we have a sense of after the training
stimulus ends, how long that transcriptional stress is in place to continue muscle protein
synthesis provided enough substrate is available? In other words, when do we become substrate
available? Substrate limited, I'm sorry. So this is really interesting because it's so hard to
assess. Because so part of the reason that this stuff is so hard to measure is in humans, you
basically have to have a steady state in order to measure muscle protein synthesis, because there's
certain assumptions you have to make about the isotope that you're using to assess it, the precursor
pool and the actual protein bound label. And so that requires what we call a nutritional steady
state. So if you want to assess a muscle protein synthesis in response to exercise, you're going
to be found that. Yeah, but let's say you could give somebody an intravenous infusion of all amino
acids. So I guess there'd be two questions, right? We start with one question, which is we don't care
which amino acid is, but we'll give you enough of all of them so that you're not going to be limited
by a given amino acid. And then we just going to give you an IV infusion. So the second you finish
the highest stress workout, we just keep running it out. And then we're tracking over time muscle
protein synthesis, that would be one experiment that would be interesting. And then the second one
would be playing with which amino acids are the most important there. Does that kind of make sense?
So we kind of have a pretty good idea of like the time course of muscle protein synthesis in
response to an exercise bout when it comes to mixed muscle protein synthesis. So I'm going to
make a very important caveat here in a second. And it appears to be pretty similar for, sorry,
so the peak, so the change percentage is about, it increases, it's different from study to study,
but about a hundred to a hundred and fifty percent increase in muscle protein synthesis.
That peak is about the same for trained versus untrained, but the untrained duration
lasts much longer. So it's still not back to baseline in studies by 48, well, some studies
it's back to baseline at 48 hours. In other studies, there's still a statistical difference
at 48 hours. So we think basically in untrained people, it's about 48 to 72 hour response.
The interesting thing is in trained people, that initial robust response comes back down
about 10 to 12 hours and at 24 hours is basically not different from baseline. So
this is now that's for mixed muscle protein synthesis. Now here's the rub for myofibrillar
protein synthesis, because you can separate that out during your analysis. So we're talking about
actual contractile muscle proteins, because mixed muscle protein synthesis includes all
cytoplasmic proteins, mitochondrial proteins, all these sorts of things. The myofibrillar protein
synthesis, they actually don't know how long it lasts because they've only assessed it up to 16
hours post. And so far, neither group has returned to baseline, although they have assessed the area
under the curve and it's greater area under the curve for untrained versus trained. Now,
the rub on that is if we look at, I know you're asking about nutrient availability.
No, no. Yeah, we'll keep going with this point, though.
The rub on that is none of these are addressing the other side of protein balance, which is
protein degradation. Now, what's really interesting is during the first approximately six weeks of
resistance training, you don't see much hypertrophy in people who are training. You see
strength improvements, but you don't really see hypertrophy. And what's really interesting is in
the initial phases of training, you have an increase, a robust increase in muscle protein
synthesis, but you also have a very robust increase in protein degradation. And so the thought process
is because this is such a big stressor, a massive stressor, if you've never resisted to train before,
I mean, everybody knows the first time they went and did a leg workout, you couldn't walk for a few
days after that. You have to completely, it's almost like your muscles doing a complete overhaul
of those proteins. And so you have such a robust, degradatory response because there are so many
damaged proteins or proteins that need to be, I guess, improved, that it's almost like you're
doing this protein turnover, futile cycle kind of remodeling. And then what we see is after six weeks,
at the end of six weeks, that increase in degradation goes way down. And that's actually,
I mean, again, I can't say for certain, but that coincides with when we start seeing
the big improvements in hypertrophy. So, so all things equal, sorry to interrupt, all things equal,
if a person is consuming roughly the same amount of protein during that phase and their training
volume and intensity is roughly the same, is it safe to say during that first period you described
they are going to be in a negative nitrogen balance versus a neutral, potentially nitrogen
balance? Like if you were evaluating them with a nitrogen cart, like how are you, would that show
up as a nitrogen excretion in that first phase? Or are they recycling it? So probably, probably not,
probably not. It's probably going to be pretty, they're probably going to be nitrogen positive
a little bit. But here, here's where this stuff gets so, so complicated because we know that in
muscle protein synthesis, about seven out of every eight amino acids used to create a new protein
are recycled from degraded proteins. So when we look at, okay, exogenous amino acids or exogenous
dietary protein, and we think about it as muscle building, I think most people think about, okay,
I'm eating this protein and this is going to get incorporated into my tissue and that's what's
going to make me big and strong. It's a lot more complicated than that. In fact, about the most
amino acids you can deposit in muscle tissue. If you, let me back up. If you look at somebody who
added 50 pounds of muscle tissue in a year, right? That's a ton of muscle. Even for somebody on
steroids, I think we can agree that's a ton of muscle. When you account for the fact that muscle
tissue is about 70% water and about 30% protein, you're basically looking at about 10 grams of
amino acids deposited in muscle per day. It's very underwhelming. Oh, I'm sorry. Sorry. That'd be for
about 25 pounds of muscle a year, I think. Still extremely impressive. Sure. But, but there are two
different points there that I want to get at. The first point is the one you're making, which is no
matter how much muscle mass you put on, it's never going to be impressive relative to the amount of
amino acids you took in. There's a second point you're making, which I find even more interesting
potentially, which is the actual fate of the ingested amino acid and how much is being recycled
versus not. So the analog here, but you're going to love this lane. I didn't even think this would
come up and I know you're going to love it. You want to know my favorite thing that drives me nuts
about people when they just rave about a ketogenic diet is the differentiation between
reesterification, lipolysis, and fat oxidation. So here's the example, right? If you're on a
ketogenic diet and you're mainlining fat, you can very easily gain weight because if you're ingesting
so much fat that it exceeds your ability to oxidize fat, regardless of where that fat source
is being oxidized, meaning endogenous versus exogenous, it doesn't really matter. And in fact,
a ketogenic diet can still produce a ton of fat oxidation without oxidizing the endogenous source
that you want to oxidize in the first place. And by the way, a lot of the triglyceride contained
within the adipocyte gets recycled so it can be liberated as free fatty acid and then be
reesterified with glycerol back into it. So actually, it becomes kind of a nice analogy here.
A hundred percent.
I just don't think I knew it was true on the amino acid side as well.
Yeah. So you're making an analogy that is, I don't know if I've ever used it before,
but it's bang on. I mean, there's differences, of course, but I think a lot of this boils down to
people think of metabolism as like on and off switches. And it's like, that's think about like
dimmer switches, like nothing. People think like when you're losing fat, that means that fat
burning is ramped up and fat storage is all the way down at zero. No, you are always burning and
storing fat simultaneously. Same thing. You are always synthesizing protein and degrading it at
the same time. Now, it's the relative rates of each that are going to determine if you deposit
versus lose fat or protein.
So let me then bring it back to that analogy because I just did a podcast on this with Bob
Kaplan recently, and we talked about it in terms of fat flux. So we talked about three states,
a person who is in neutral fat flux. So they are neither gaining nor losing fat tissue,
negative fat flux and positive flat flux. So you're either gaining fat mass, losing fat mass,
or maintaining the same. And we talked about it through the lens of de novo lipogenesis,
reesterification, lipolysis. Nope. None of that says anything about oxidation that's happening
outside. And that can feed into substrate pools. What we then talked about was how many hormones
are regulating these different steps. So what happens when insulin goes up and down? What happens
when epinephrine goes up and down when norepinephrine goes up and down when hormone sensitive
lipase goes up and down when cortisol goes up and down testosterone, lipoprotein, lipase, etc.
So in other words, these are all regulated hormonally, some of them outside the cell. So
insulin obviously is acting outside the cell. You know, LPL is outside the cell, HSL inside the cell,
etc. Tell me about the hormonal regulation on the same unit of muscle. The most obvious difference,
of course, is that testosterone works inside the cell, right? So let's start with testosterone,
but then I want to talk about all of the hormones that impact this. Specifically,
I want to make sure we at least touch on cortisol and estradiol at some point. But let's start with
testosterone because it plays such an important role in that transcriptive drive.
Yeah, so I think the one thing I want to say before we start on this is keep in mind that
when we're talking about all these hormones, and this goes for fat tissue or muscle tissue,
what you are seeing on the surface in terms of the actual outcome is the result of the summation of
all of those signals, right? So people get hung up on, say, insulin, or they get hung up on leucine,
or they get hung up on, you know, one particular thing, and then they get confused when they see
a paradoxical outcome, right? So a great example of that is Kevin Hall's study on fat loss, looking
at, you know, where they showed that insulin was 26% higher, but those people actually ended up
losing, like, I would call it a non-significant greater amount of actual fat mass than people who
are on a ketogenic diet. People say, well, how can that be true, right? And it's like, okay, well,
you got to remember that insulin is just one input. It's not the only input. And the same
thing goes for building muscle and muscle tissue. So with regards to testosterone, what's interesting
about testosterone is I actually reviewed a study recently where- Yeah, the study by Stu Phillips
that looked at androgen receptor density. Yeah, so that's- Which, by the way, I still don't understand
something, which I'm hoping you can explain. Why would androgen receptor density be higher in
someone getting exogenous testosterone? You would think that someone taking exogenous testosterone
would have a paradoxically negative response in that they would down-regulate androgen receptors.
I'll let you maybe go back and explain it from the beginning, because the listener might not
be familiar with the thesis of the work. Yeah, so essentially, you know, when you have-
When testosterone gets into the cell, it's converted, and then that in-product binds with
the androgen receptor, and then it can attach to the DNA increasing transcription of different
proteins, right? So basically, you're ramping up your capacity for, amongst other things,
increasing muscle proteins. That's different than how leucine acts nutritionally, because
leucine is a signal also that happens inside the cell, but it's more of a short-term signal.
Now, to answer your question specifically, what I've seen proposed is that when you have enough
testosterone available, what tends to happen is the androgen receptors of regulate to meet the
demand for metabolizing that testosterone, and that the regulation of the excess testosterone,
think about the negative feedback loop, functions more so on like luteinizing hormone and the
gonads and that sort of thing, right? So if I had to hazard a guess, that would be my guess that the
that the regulation in terms of trying to tamp that down, because think about if you're not getting
exogenous testosterone, if you're not getting exogenous testosterone, then there's probably
not that same negative feedback regulation loop. And so I always hate it when people go,
well, it makes sense because there's tons of stuff in metabolism. They say, well, it makes sense that
it ends up not working out in the study. But to me, it would make sense that the muscle might
increase its androgen receptor density to meet that testosterone load or that free testosterone
load. So long as you're not having so much testosterone, that's not negatively feeding
back to the gonads and limit, reducing luteinizing hormone or increasing aromatization, those sorts
of things. And I will straight up say, I am not a testosterone expert, so I could be getting this
dead wrong. But I think the more to the point of Stu Phillips work is that muscle growth
appears to be mostly intrinsically regulated. And I think in the late 90s, early 2000s, what people
were really focused on was systemic, what they thought was systemic regulation of muscle growth,
right? Your systemic levels of testosterone, IGF-1, and even like the acute responses,
we know, for example, resistance exercise will increase testosterone for 30 or 60 minutes. And
it used to be thought, well, that is what's driving these responses of hypertrophy. And through a few
elegantly designed studies, a lot of them by Stu Phillips, we know that that's probably not the
case, that this is probably an effect of tension. Now, what's interesting about muscle growth is if
we're going to have that tension that's driving muscle growth, there has to be a translation of
that contractile force into a chemical signal. So we call that mechanotransduction, right? And so this
is where I know you we had talked about it a little bit earlier, mechano growth factor probably comes
in. So IGF-1, systemic IGF-1 and growth hormone are not anabolic to skeletal muscle. People don't
realize this. Let's pause here because this is, I want to make sure people understand what we're
talking about. And this is such an important topic. I don't want to rush it. So let's go back to the
beginning and assume that the listener here doesn't fully understand where growth hormone comes from,
right? And what it does in the liver, what IGF does. So let's go back and explain,
you know, the endocrine versus, well, we'll get to the endocrine versus autocrine function of IGF,
but just back up two steps with where you are, Elaine. Sure. So we know that like growth hormone
increases in response to certain things like fasting, resistance training, exercise in general,
sleep potentially. Sure, sure. All those things, right? And people kind of looked at that as,
okay, well, we should be aiming to increase growth hormone for these things. And we know
that growth hormone increases the liver production of IGF-1. And IGF-1 has always been thought of as
the master hormone that is increasing muscle mass. When they look at studies, even where they give
exogenous growth hormone, what you see is you see an increase in lean body mass, but not an increase
in skeletal muscle mass. So the increase in lean body mass is completely accounted for by an
increase in body water and connective tissue. So now you can argue there might be some benefits to
connective tissue and that sort of thing. And I would argue organ weight as well, right? I mean,
we see, we see liver hypertrophy and other things like that as well.
So when it comes to growth hormone, I actually had an article about this years ago in my site about
how growth hormone was an anabolic. And I got a lot of bodybuilding dogma people getting really
upset about that because they don't understand, and this is pervasive even among scientists,
people who don't understand the concept of a localized response versus a systemic response,
or people who don't understand an acute response versus a chronic response.
We're going to talk about this with respect to cortisol as well.
And in-tour signaling, I'm not sure. So growth hormone, not anabolic to skeletal muscle. And
the growth hormone response to exercise appears to be mostly substrate driven. That it's that
growth hormone probably increases as a response exercise to increase lipolysis to liberate free
fatty acids for use as an energy substrate. Now, here's where people get confused. The IGF-1,
the autocrine IGF-1 that is released by the muscle tissue itself in response to mechanical tension
is very anabolic. So let me just explain for a moment to people the difference between endocrine,
paracrine, and autocrine. So the endocrine function of something is when a hormone gets released
and its effect is all throughout the body. So insulin is a great example, right? So the
pancreas, the beta cell releases insulin, insulin goes and acts on all sorts of cells in the body.
Paracrine is when something, when a hormone gets released and it only impacts the cells right next
to it. And autocrine is on itself, as you would guess. Now, going back to what you said earlier,
the one way we explain this to patients is IGF-1 is the integral of growth hormone. So if you want
to get a sense of how much growth hormone is floating around, to a first order approximation,
you get a sense of how much IGF somebody has, you get a sense of how much IGF is being produced by
the liver. And to your point, that's all systemic or what we would really think of as an endocrine,
IGF. Now what you're about to talk about is something that, frankly, never really gets talked
about. Yeah. So IGF-1 autocrine or paracrine IGF-1 that gets released by the muscle tissue itself
is also called mechano growth factor. And that is very anabolic to muscle tissue. But again,
it's a very localized intrinsic response. And it makes sense from, to me, again, here we go,
it makes sense from a teleological perspective. If you place a stress on a particular muscle tissue,
like your legs, it does not make sense to me that your arms will grow because you may not need your
arms. Like if you're a, I don't know, if you're a tribe and you're having to climb something in
the, or whatever, you know, you're using your legs much more than your arms, muscle tissue
is an energetically expensive tissue to maintain. It takes more energy, more ATP, more calories.
It is a futile cycle, meaning that to maintain it, you actually have to increase synthesis and
breakdown because you're having more proteins that are misfolded and whatnot that need to be broken
down. That whole thing takes more energy. And so that's why we tell people, if you want to be able
to eat more calories, hey, build some more muscle because to maintain that takes more.
So it does not make sense from a evolutionary perspective because evolution doesn't care if
you're jacked. It cares if you can live long enough to pass on your genetic material. It does
not make sense that you would build a different tissue in response to a localized effect of
training. And that we see that we see that if you train your legs, your arms don't get bigger.
We know that. And if you train one leg, the other one doesn't get bigger, right? In fact,
some of the best resistance training studies are where they use unilateral training and the person's
non-trained legs serves as the own individual's control because you're accounting for genetic
variations by doing that. So yeah. And then we have another probably component of mechanotransduction
is probably phosphatidic acid. So phosphatidic acid is stored in the Z disc of the skeletal muscle,
which if you look at a... Let's back up. Yeah. Let's remind people how actin myosin work and then
where the Z disc fits in. Because I forgot you and I got so into the weeds. It was my bad. I should
have reminded us that we should go back and... That's okay. That's okay. It's fun for me. So
the contractile unit of a muscle tissue is what's called a sarcomere. And if you look at a sarcomere,
you kind of have these two ends, which are called Z discs. And in between, you have actin and myosin,
which overlap. And then for lack of a better term, when you contract, it's basically actin and myosin
hooked together and pulling. Okay. Now I'm again, I'm really generalizing and I'm sure there's an
exercise physiologist out there who's going to throw up their lunch, hearing me describe it that
way. But for all... I feel that that's a reasonable comparison. Now, each sarcomere is separated by
the Z disc. Okay. The Z disc is where something called phosphatidic acid is stored. And
if you were going to try to transfer a mechanical signal to a chemical signal,
it makes sense that you would store this stuff in the Z disc because that is where a lot of that
mechanical tension is going to be felt. So in response to that mechanical tension, again,
based on mechanistic studies, we believe what happens is that causes phosphatidic acid to be
released and phosphatidic acid is a stimulator of mTOR. So we think again that these two things are
some of the more major regulators of mechanotransduction in terms of how a muscle actually
gets built. And then of course, we have other regulators. Testosterone doesn't really regulate
mTOR that I'm aware of. It works more on the transcriptional level. We have things like
insulin affects mTOR, although it doesn't seem to be a powerful enough signal to actually impact
muscle building if insulin has an effect. It's probably more so on the protein breakdown side
of things. In fact, if you look at studies looking at carbohydrate ingestion, we don't really see
increases in muscle protein synthesis. So if you just give pure carbohydrate, even up to like 100
grams of glucose, even though you get a pretty good rise in insulin, it doesn't seem to affect
muscle protein synthesis, but it does seem to inhibit protein degradation. In fact, there was
a study in resistance training, I think, on a Bob Wolf's lab in like 2004, and they did what's
called AV balance. So arteriovenous balance is where basically you're infusing a stable isotope
and you're looking at essentially how much of that label is going into the muscle and then how much
is coming out, right? And so you can determine the net balance. And if you take a biopsy as well,
you can determine the fractional rate of protein synthesis and then by basically subtraction can
determine what breakdown is. So what they saw was when they gave a large amount of carbohydrates,
people who had resistance trained, they went from a negative protein balance to almost
to big or sorry, they went from having an increase in muscle protein breakdown to basically back to
baseline and muscle protein breakdown and synthesis didn't change. Now, now, Lane, if you did that in
combination with protein, would that be a better strategy to hit it at both ends where you would
reduce degradation and increase synthesis? And is that an argument for combining carbohydrate and
protein after a resistance training as opposed to just protein? So here's where it gets very
complicated because there probably is some degradation that is needed in order to remodel
and actually make things better. However, really, we need to go to the kind of the hard outcome
studies. So there's only really two studies I know of that examined like a protein and calorie
equated low carbohydrate diet versus a protein calorie equated non low carbohydrate diet. And
it was it was ketogenic. So they measured blood ketones and saw they went up. And this was,
I think, 12 weeks by somebody. Vargas was the author. And they did see less lean body mass
accrual in the ketogenic diet group. Now, they still increased lean body mass. That's important
to know. But the group that was getting carbohydrate or more carbohydrates had more lean body mass. Now,
the caveat to that is carbohydrates have make you store glycogen. So was it just water or was it
contractile tissue? Now, in the second study, they did see a difference in like one rep max squat,
and I think bench press as well. So that kind of suggests that perhaps there is something
different in terms of actual contractile tissue. But this is an area that's going to need to be
studied a lot more. And again, I don't want anybody to straw man what I'm saying. I'm not saying you
can't build muscle on a ketogenic diet. You absolutely can. You can probably build a really
good amount of muscle. But can you build as much as if you're including carbohydrate? Possibly not.
And it may have something to do with carbohydrates effect or insulin effect on
blunting muscle protein breakdown. The other thing I'll add to that, again, based on my experience,
and you've probably talked about this with Dom, is I think one of the challenges of studying
ketogenic diets is the length of time it takes to adapt to them. I went on a ketogenic diet in May
of 2011 as an experiment. And I was committed to doing it for 12 weeks. And I mean, five weeks in,
I had I was so miserable, my wife was like, what are you doing? And why? And you know,
all the standard mistakes I was making, and the first being I made no reduction in training volume.
And I was already training at the level of a maniac, right? So I mean, ridiculous training volume,
and I made zero reduction in it. And I was, I mean, just staggeringly and upsettingly miserable.
And at 12 weeks, I finally crested the first hill, which was the aerobic hill. So at the time,
it was cycling and swimming were the two sports. And I at 12 weeks, I just got to the point where
I could get my aerobic base back to where it was 12 weeks earlier. But anaerobically, I was nowhere
near what I was 12 weeks earlier. I won't put you on the spot and make you guess. But if I were
going to make you guess how long do you well, first of all, I decided to stay with the diet,
because I became so interested in the physiology of it. And I wanted to see like, what is it going
to take to return back to my previous level of anaerobic fitness, it took 18 months. And I want
to be clear, this is 18 months without one day of deviation. I would end up staying on this diet for
three years with one day of deviation. My wife's birthday, I ended up having a bunch of cake. But
for three years to stay on this one, you know, incredibly restrictive diet,
it took half of that period of time just to get back to where I was anaerobically.
So it speaks to how difficult I think it is to study any of this stuff. And by the way,
was I perfectly controlling my exercise during that period of time? No, it's quite possible
that some of those changes had to do with other variables. So I don't know, sometimes I just think
this this stuff is so complicated, we should we should focus on the biggest picture questions and
try to get at them. But then there's times when we get into discussions like this, and I'm like,
no, these details are the most interesting part of this, right? Especially on this side of the
equation, because this is this is an area I know so little about. That's why I was very excited to
discuss it with you. Yeah, so I think that, you know, for the majority of the audience, I think
that and that's why I try to provide so much context when I talk about this stuff. And I,
I don't talk about the ketogenic diet study and also not say, hey, you can still build muscle on
it, right? Because I don't want people to take away, like you said, you can't build muscle on a
ketogenic diet, and then they go out and they see somebody who built a bunch of muscle, they go,
okay, well, this doesn't make sense. Right? So I think that's why the nuance is very important.
Like you said, we're in the details, right? Because that's what's interesting to us,
because we kind of hopefully know some of the like the major things, right?
It's the same as testosterone, right? You could say the same thing. You'd be like,
do you need to take exogenous to talk testosterone to be a bodybuilder? Nope. Look at all the
examples. But if your goal is to be the biggest, the strongest, I have news for you. Go and get
yourself to some testosterone, sip, unite and get ready to start smacking 1000 milligrams every
single week. I mean, that's the reality of it, you know, so and again, that that's spoken
without prejudice, it's simply biochemistry. Yeah. And anecdote plays into this and anecdote
is important. And I'm about to discuss yours a little bit. But I always tell people like be just
be, be cautious with anecdote. I'm not saying that your anecdote doesn't matter. But what I am saying
is everyone knows somebody who smoked every single day of their life till they were 90, right? And
live to a ripe old age. Does that mean that it's okay to smoke? Or do we think that's the best thing
for longevity? We certainly do not, right? So when we're, when we're making broad recommendations,
we're doing that based on the consensus of the evidence. But we, we also need to understand that
there will be outliers that fall outside that. And that's where you know, individualization comes in.
So I think one of the things that we really are struggling with right now, and I kind of challenged
the low carb community on this a while back, because one of my pet peeves is I'm not saying
that there's not such a thing as ketogenic adaptation or fat adaptation that may take longer.
What I'm saying is we need a hard metric for it. We really need some kind of hard metric to explain
this. Because if we look at things like, okay, let's look at blood ketones, it's clearly not
that. Yeah, yeah, it's clearly not blood ketones. It's not lipolysis. It's not. I mean, my only
regret because we see fat oxidation, fat oxidation within six days. No, no, it's none of the things
that we understand. I mean, my biggest regret about the experiment I did, because I'm never going to
be repeating it, is I wish at the time I had the thought and wherewithal to have taken muscle
biopsies and collected, you know, ample amounts of tissue for all the future proteomics, metabolomics,
every omic you can think of to have been done down the line. It still would have only been an
N of one. But to me, if that 18 month transition was something beyond psychological, and let's
be honest, it could have been psychological too, right? Could have been if it was anything other
than psychological, I suspect the answer is far deeper than in any of the things that typically
get talked about. Yeah, so I think if I was going to explain your kind of 18 months to get back to
anaerobic, right. So first off, I think it's important to note that when it comes to when it
comes to exercise, there's some diverging information in terms of the ketogenic diet,
low carb diet, whether or not it's bad for exercise, I think we can pretty conclusively
say that for ultra endurance, there doesn't seem to be a downside to it. It also doesn't seem to
be superior, it kind of boils down to personal preference and what the person likes. When it
comes to aerobic exercise, at least from what I've seen, if you're under 60% of your VO2 max,
you're probably safe in terms of getting the most out of your exercise after you're fat adapted.
When it comes to over 70%, that's where we start to get into where it becomes much more difficult
to perform well or as optimally as you can on a ketogenic diet. And of course, yes, if you,
like somebody sent me something said, well, look at Sean Baker, he's deadlifting 500 pounds for
nine reps, and he's 50 years old, you know, like, how do you explain that? And I said,
okay, again, this is why we have randomized control trials, because I'm not saying that he's
not strong. And I'm not saying that you can't get strong and that you can't do some heavy
weights for higher reps. What the question you need to ask yourself is, is he as strong as he
possibly could have been if he was doing something different? Because just the sheer magnitude of
resistance training consistently for a long period of time, you will get very strong. It doesn't
matter what diet you're on, you will get strong or relatively strong for what you started at.
So the question always has to be, are we talking about, can you do something? Or was this the best
thing that you could possibly do? Because those are two different questions, right? It's like when
people talk about how much protein do I need? Well, you only need about 50 grams a day if we're
talking about preventing you from being in a negative nitrogen balance. But what's optimal
for health or lean body mass? So that's a very different question, right? So I think that when,
I guess if I could implore the listeners, just always remember that when you see something that
you think contradicts or that you think is it doesn't fit. What is the person saying? Are they
talking about optimizing or are they talking about, can you actually do this? Because if somebody says,
well, you can't get strong in ketogenic diet, I'd say, well, you're an idiot. Of course you can.
Right? I mean, look at Dom. Dom, I've seen him deadlift 700 pounds multiple times with no
carbohydrate intake, right? So it's obviously not true. The other thing I always encourage
people to think about on this front is the relative to what comparison, which is a slight
variation on what you said. So I know you had a great video out there, which we'll link to on
critiquing the documentary Game Changers, which unfortunately, I just think was such a horrible,
horrible piece of propaganda. And I say that not as someone who's against a plant based diet,
I think much like you, but someone who is very much against disgusting science. And I found that
to be a demonstration of utter nonsense. But, you know, when we wrote something about this,
one of the comments was, or one of the points we tried to make was, you know, one of the biggest
challenges of studying nutrition in general is what are you comparing it to? And if you compare
diet X to the standard American diet, almost by definition, diet X is going to look amazing.
Because the standard American diet is such an awful diet. And I just, you know, I thought it
was such an insincere attempt to talk about a form of nutrition that obviously has many benefits.
But but when it's done in that way, it's pretty bad. And we probably won't have time to go into
it today. But you I thought did such a great job of going into some of the real challenges of that,
with at a level that most people didn't write, like, a lot of the criticisms of that movie are
so obvious and easy, but you actually went deep in them. So we'll make sure people people go and look
at that. I want to change gears for a second and come back to this cortisol thing. Because I think
this is a very misunderstood hormone. And I know you've written about this. And I think it's worth
getting the listener up to speed on cortisol. We tend to look at this very black and white.
So let's give the extremes. So there's something called an Addisonian crisis, right? Someone gets
a bad infection, they have an injury to their adrenal gland, they can't make cortisol acutely,
they're going to die, they are hands down going to die. The only way to rescue that patient
is to give them massive doses of hydrocortisone or hydrocortisone equivalent. And that very much
speaks to the medical necessity of cortisol. Let's look at the other extreme. Let's look at
Cushing's disease. So you can have Cushing's disease or Cushing's syndrome, where either at
the pituitary gland or at the adrenal gland, rampant amounts of cortisol are made and nobody
would dispute the pathology of that state. This is a person who develops basically a ball of fat
on the back of their neck. That's basically the size of a basketball, excessive fat accumulation,
all sorts of metabolic dysregulation. Again, nobody would dispute that that is a problem.
Fortunately, very few people are in either of those states. So let's now talk about
physiologic levels of cortisol and their impact on muscle protein synthesis and something you
said earlier, which I found very interesting, which was tolerating pain, pain threshold,
training resilience and things like that. Yeah, so we have to think about the function of cortisol
on its root, which is a stress hormone, right? So you're secreting hormone,
secortisol in response to some kind of stressor. When it comes again, so this is a great example
of acute versus chronic. Okay. When it comes to somebody who's getting very low sleep,
overall unhealthy lifestyle, smoke, whatever, they're going to have high levels of cortisol
and that can be problematic from the, or very high levels of stress. Because now,
like think about what stress used to mean. Stress used to mean, oh crap, there's that thing that's
going to kill me. I need to run. And so your body would produce cortisol for a myriad of
different reasons. Part of that was just a fuel mobilization response. It mobilizes glucose,
free fatty acids, those sorts of things. It's just trying to get as much fuel in the bloodstream
as it can. Now, when it comes to Cushing's, for example, because, or at least my best guess is,
and there may be studies on this, I haven't looked super in detail on it. My best guess is,
it's not necessarily that you're accumulating fat, you're redistributing it, right? Like it's going
to weird places. That's right. The legs become incredibly thin, the abdomen and the upper back
become incredibly full. Right. So you actually see this in like, people who have, oh God,
what do you call it? Why can't I think of the name? Oh, like, okay. So your adipose doesn't just sit
on nothing. It sits on the extracellular matrix. If you do liposuction, it destroys that matrix.
And so people go, oh, well you can't gain fat back. You can't gain it back there. But you start,
if you regain it, you start gaining it in very odd places. And so what you're looking at is a
redistribution because cortisol, going back to cortisol, if you have high cortisol because
you're stressed constantly and your, your body is still operating on genes from, you know,
a million years ago, that's telling you we're stressed, must be something coming to kill us.
So we're going to liberate a bunch of energy into the bloodstream. Well, well, then it's still got,
if you're not going to use it, if it doesn't get used, it's got to be put back somewhere. Right.
And so now you can have it started to be deposited in strange places possibly.
Now, when it comes to exercise specifically, it's a stressor. Exercise is a stressor. It makes sense
that it would increase your cortisol. But people have kind of taken the say, well, we need to limit
cortisol as much as possible. So remember, there used to be the old, I don't know if you remember
this, but it was like, don't train more than an hour because at that point cortisol starts to go
up, starts to spike. I miss that entire memo and school of thought, fortunately. So interestingly,
so we've referenced Stu Phillips a few times now. He did the study, I want to say 10 years ago and
looked at different hormones and how they associated with actual hypertrophy. So he looked at
or sorry. So the post exercise increases in systemic hormones. So he looked at testosterone,
IGF-1, growth hormone, cortisol. And I think that was it. Guess which hormone was most closely
associated with hypertrophy? I'm absolutely cortisol, hands down. But of course, I'm familiar with the paper, but yes.
Right. And yeah, the interpretation is, again, is it that cortisol is producing hypertrophy or is it
cortisol is in response to the stress that is producing hypertrophy? So that's, again, this
seems paradoxical because people see an association, they automatically think, well, there must be a cause
there. Not necessarily at all. These two things are happening in parallel. So what it means is the
resistance training session that is going to produce the most amount of stress, the most amount
of adaptation is probably going to produce the most cortisol and possibly the most hypertrophy
if it's repeated. Right. So cortisol, like we know that it will impede muscle protein synthesis. But
again, that is cortisol acts transcriptionally like testosterone. It is actually a steroid hormone.
In fact, people get confused because they're like, well, he got a steroid injection before his tennis
match. And people are like, they're not just just not injecting with testosterone. They're giving him
cortisol so he can go out and play because it reduces inflammation in that particular area.
Well, cortisol is more of a long term hormone. It's acting transcriptionally. So it's what you need
to be worried about are long term, low level elevations in cortisol. And people make this
mistake with anything they make it with mTOR. A lot of the vegan doctors get all up in arms about
mTOR, you know, getting stimulated by leucine. And that's going to give you cancer.
You don't understand tissue specifics. And you don't understand acute versus chronic.
I just want to make a funny comment there. I was at a meeting and a very famous vegan doctor who
I obviously won't name came up to me and chastised me for the idea that I would ever suggest someone
ingest five grams of leucine during a workout because of its negative effect on mTOR. And how
that could be bad for a person's health. And I just had to sit there and smile and see. Yeah,
I just don't have it in me sometimes to tell people to shut up.
A lot of this is really reductionist thinking. You know what I mean? And this happens for all
different. If I can switch gears just a little bit, because I think this is really important for
people here. People want to isolate out nutrients as being good or bad. And I would really implore
people that nutrients are not necessarily good or bad. Context matters. And what really matters
is lifestyle and overall eating patterns. That is what matters. You cannot possibly
think that in a diet where there are thousands of different nutrients that we ingest,
that it's one thing is causing all the problems that we're having.
Right? And this, whether it's leucine or sugar or whatever. Because when you isolate out these
things, you can find mechanistic data to support almost anything you want. But even things that we
think we know, like I remember when I got to grad school and I was like, high fructose corn syrup
independently fattening. It doesn't matter the calories, anything like that. And again,
do I think high fructose corn syrup is good? Absolutely not. I think it's hyper palatable.
I think people overeat it. But if you look at the studies pretty closely, it seems to mostly be an
energy thing that it just provides too much energy. Now people hear that and they think it's a
dismissal of it, you know, like that I'm condoning it or something like that. And I'm not condoning
it. I'm just saying that if you isolate it out and you keep people's calories the same, it doesn't
seem to have the same effect. But do people who eat a lot of high fructose corn syrup keep their
calories the same? Of course not. They eat more calories than other people. They also usually
eat more processed foods, more fats, all that sort of thing. So a great study that I think came
out a couple of years ago that I think really highlights this point was a study where they
looked at all, I think it was cancer incidents from any form of cancer. And it was in Canada,
100,000 people cohort, and they looked at low meat intake versus high meat intake. And I think it
was in quartiles, so four different levels. And I mean, we know this, if you do that, what you tend
to find is that meat is meat intakes associated with cancer. Now the problem is people who eat
high amounts of meat tend to have an overall unhealthy lifestyle in general. They're less
likely to exercise and more likely to smoke. They're more likely to eat processed foods because most
of the meat is coming from fast food, that sort of thing. But what was cool about this was they
also compared it with the lowest to highest quartiles of fruit and vegetable intake. And what
they found was that at the highest level of meat intake, but also that also consumed the highest
level of fruit and vegetable intake, they had the same risk for cancer as the lowest level of meat
intake with a high level of fruit and vegetable intake. So basically what that tends to suggest
is that to me, we need to look at eating patterns much more so than we look at individual nutrients.
And that if you're looking for one nutrient to explain disease incidents, this sort of stuff,
you really need to look at the whole diet. And people who eat sugar, like when I say that sugar
isn't inherently bad for you, I mean from a purely mechanical, if I take 50 grams out of somebody's
diet of starchy carbohydrate and I just put sugar into it, or the same equal calories from fats and
I just put sugar in there, do I think anything bad is going to happen? Probably not. But that's
not how people eat. So I'm talking mechanistically and people think I'm making a recommendation.
So all that to say, it's really important to understand how limited nutritional studies are.
And you mentioned it, when you're talking about trying to pick out these really granular details,
you're talking about a study that's so restrictive, it's really hard to generalize the results to the
average person. So when you look at studies that are generalizable to the average population,
you can't control that many variables because it has to be free living. And if it has to be free
living, I mean it's very hard to pick out differences because dietary adherence tends to
be so low. So I know I went off on a really big divergent rant, but acute versus chronic,
localized versus systemic. People just don't understand the differences and this includes
scientists. I mean even like inflammation, a great example of this is on the Joe Rogan
Game Changers debate where John Wilkes was talking about inflammation. He said,
if you're training for exercise and you're having higher levels of inflammation from that
and then you go and eat meat afterwards, like now you're compounding that inflammation.
And I just remember thinking, you just don't understand the difference between acute versus
chronic. These aren't even the same types of inflammation, right? Like your acute
inflammatory response from exercise means nothing. Well, it actually doesn't mean nothing.
It's beneficial actually.
Exercise it. Yeah, yeah. So here's the crazy thing about exercise. If you were an alien and
you didn't know anything about exercise, but you knew about human physiology and I told you,
hey, I'm going to make you do something that increases your blood pressure, increases your
heart rate, increases your free radical production, increases your inflammation,
all these different things, you would go, that's horrible. Don't do it. But what is exercise?
It's almost like a vaccine, right? You give a controlled dose of a stressor and your body
adapts to that stressor by getting better at handling it. So what do we see in people who
exercise regularly? They have lower resting heart rate. They have lower blood pressure.
They have lower levels of inflammation, those sorts of things. And nutritionally,
I question like these studies that look at inflammatory response and response in terms
of post-meal injection. I really go, how much does that actually mean?
Yeah, I think this stuff means absolutely nothing. I think that, you know, when you think about the
time course of something and you tell me that you measured somebody's IGF one or IGF six an
hour after a meal and in two hours. Yeah, I agree with you completely. It's totally nonsense. And
by the way, your point about exercise, I think comes back to what you said when you were making
that decision between nutrition science and exercise science, which was, look, exercise
probably is the best drug we have. I agree emphatically with that. I think that when you
think about the the hormesis that comes from exercise, like I just I don't believe we will
ever be able to develop a drug that is that remarkable. It is simply unbelievable what it
can do. No, I mean, look at it like almost any dietary intervention, unless you're unless you're
okay with just small improvements to see big improvements, you pretty much got to lose body
fat like that. That's that's that's that's what the crux of it is. With exercise, you get massive
improvements with zero loss of weight. You can see big improvements. And so, you know, I just
implore people what are the what are the and this goes for like kind of the two opposing ends like
you're like plant based kind of really emphatic supporters and then like low carb supporters.
I hear a lot of people they'll spend so much time, you know, on these granular details of diet and
they say, well, I don't I don't resistance exercise. I don't have time for it. And I'm like,
you got time to stress over your diet on Twitter on Twitter for two hours, but you don't have time
to go into the gym, or just do some push ups at home like you are missing out on the most powerful
tool you have to improve your health and body composition. And even like there was a study by
Wolf looking at longevity over age 65 and found a direct association, the most powerful predictor
of longevity after age 65 was how much lean body mass you had. That was the most powerful
predictor of who lived the longest after age 65 was your level of lean body. Yeah, and there are
lots of studies that go beyond just the sarcopenia and look at like grip strength and and things like
that. So yeah, I completely agree. And I love the idea, by the way of in between Twitter feuds over
your nutritional views, you have to do some push ups. That's that could be the solution to this
problem. I want to talk a little bit about I'm sorry, we're just I keep saying we're going to
wrap this up and we're not I'm sorry, we're going to wrap this up at some point. One thing that I've
been really impressed with in following you lane is the what's the right word I want to use
the the deliberate nature with which you approach things. So I've seen pictures of you
where I think like he doesn't even look like a human being he's so ripped and shredded. And I've
seen pictures of you where you look kind of chubby. And you've been very clear and said,
I'm going through different phases. I'm very deliberate about what I do. This is a phase
where I am adding a ton of lean mass and with it comes some body fat. And right now I'm taking it
off. But one, you're very deliberate. So nothing's haphazard. And two, you really emphasize the
importance of consistency. So how do I stay consistent, because it's it doesn't take nearly
as much work to preserve muscle mass once you have it. But you and I talked about this with Alex
Hutchinson on a previous podcast. One of the things I fear the most for my patients as they age is any
sort of injury or illness that takes them out of exercise, because the deconditioning that occurs
when someone doesn't do anything for a month is devastating. So can you can you put some numbers
to that? Because I believe you've spoken about this, which is what is the effort required to maintain?
And I'm not talking about show, you know, like 4% body fat on a stage I'm talking about. And again,
we'll use your numbers as an example, you happen to be, you know, great to begin with. But, you know,
for you to stay at 13 14% body fat is not the end of the world. It's not a huge sacrifice,
but it requires being diligent still. What does that mean to you? And how do you advise your
clients around that? So there's a few layers to this. When it comes to resistance training,
I mean, this is really just anything in life resistance training taught me so much about just
life overall, right? So the same people who come up with bio hacks of how you can like get to your
goal in 12 weeks or whatever, in the financial world, they're the same people who are like,
hey, join my pyramid scheme and earn six figures from home doing one hour of work a week.
Most reasonable people know that that's not how you acquire wealth, right? You acquire wealth
through if you're, you know, Thomas J. Stanley's I use fiscal examples, because I just find it's
easier for people. But 80% of millionaires are first generation self made. And most of them
got there, not through getting lucky, but the fact that they saved more money than they earned,
they were consistent, and they did that for a long period of time. Now, that is the granular,
mechanistic way of doing it kind of like how we talk about calories in calories out, right?
But what it takes to get that consistency is modification to behavior, right? Because for the
same reason that somebody binges on whatever, donuts, chocolate cakes, cookies, whatever,
is the same reason that somebody who also knows, hey, in order for me to save money,
I need to earn more than I spend, still goes out and blows 1500 bucks on a shopping spree after a
stressful week, right? Because they have a habit and an association with something. And so I think
people need to understand that consistency is the most important thing. But to create that
consistency, you have to change your habits. You have to create habits. I read a review,
systematic review by a gal named Marie Shpeckley. And I'm going to give myself a pat in the back
here for a second, because she actually said that she went back to school after reading my book,
Fat Loss Forever. And it's what inspired her to do her PhD work, which is pretty awesome.
And she did a systematic review of looking at people who lost weight and kept it off.
So some of the commonalities of that. And a lot of it was what you expected, consistency,
ability to embrace challenges rather than running from them, or viewing challenges as part of the
process. I think a lot of people, when setbacks occur or challenges occur, they feel that that's
abnormal as opposed to embracing it as part of this process. But then something that was in the
paper that I hadn't thought about before, that I think is so critical to developing that consistency
and making a change, forming a new identity. So the people who lost weight and kept it off
said that they had to form a new identity. And I really chewed on this for a while. And do you
know Ethan Suplete? No, but I was just about to say James Clear is the first person who made that
point clear to me, no pun intended. And of all the things in James's book, that one actually
appealed to me the most, which was, it's not about discipline. Well, I always knew it wasn't about
discipline and willpower, because those things are going to fade over time. But this piece around,
and let's use exercise as the example, it's going from, oh, I have to do this thing, I have to do
this thing too. I'm a person who exercises, I'm a fit person. That's the transition that makes it
easier to do day in and day out. And that's probably why I've never struggled with exercise.
I struggle with the opposite. I really struggle to take a day off. I think to be completely
transparent, I'm always going to struggle with food a little bit. I haven't had the full identity
switch in food, but I think I was born with, or at least it was etched in my brain when I was so
young due to my insecurities around exercise. So I think you said something very poignant there.
You just put in your mind, this is what I do. This is what I do. This is part of who I am.
And so Ethan Suplete, he's an actor, and he was in, you probably, if you've seen the movie,
Remember the Titans? Yeah, yeah, yeah. Oh, yes, yes, yes. I know who you're talking about now.
He lost a staggering amount of weight, like I almost an unrecognizable amount of weight.
He's Jack now, right? So I talked to him pretty frequently. And he has a thing he puts on his
Instagram, he's here, he's say I killed my clone today. And I asked him about that, because I read
Marie's paper. And then I made this connection, because I always wondered what he meant by killed
my clone today. And I said, is this what you mean, that you formed a new identity that you killed the
old person that you were, and he said, that is exactly what I mean. Because you cannot create a
new life, a new identity, or you cannot create a new life, and you cannot have a physical and
overall change in your life without fun, while still dragging those behaviors behind you, right?
Let's take a basic example, an alcoholic, right? If you decide, if an alcoholic decides tomorrow,
I don't want to be this anymore. You have to change everything. You can't just, okay, I want
to stop drinking. No, no, your entire identity has been around. I go to a bar, I hang out with my
friends after work, they probably drink, my family probably drank growing up, that's where I learned
it from. Now you've got to change everything. You are not going to be able to be this new person
while still dragging your old behaviors behind you. And I think a lot of people try to do that
when it comes to nutrition, and maybe even exercise. It's, well, I want things to change,
but I don't want to give up my three glasses of wine tonight, or I don't want to give up this,
or I don't want to give up that. What I always tell people is like, listen,
the great thing about nutrition is you get to pick what you sacrifice, okay? So for me,
what made it easy for me, and I always tell people, you should pick the form of restriction
that feels easiest to you. I don't care what anybody else feels like. For me, if I'm able to
eat whatever foods I want, as long as I control portion size and track my calories and macros and
whatnot, that feels easy. That is not difficult for me to maintain like a lean physique and athletic.
But for other people, that may be extremely tedious, difficult. It may feel labor intensive.
To me, it doesn't. What feels labor intensive to me is saying, okay, Lane, you can't have
processed food ever again, or you can't have carbs, or you can't have fats or whatever.
But for other people, some people, I hear it all the time, say, I did X diet, ketogenic diet,
and it felt easy. I did intermittent fasting. I was never hungry. I felt easy. Cool. Great. Just
don't assume that what was easy for you is going to be easy for everybody else because this,
you know, I thought flexible dieting was going to be the solution for everybody because it was easy
for me. So I arrogantly assumed that it'd be that way for everybody else. I think everybody goes
through that. That's sort of like, you know, you seek out your own echo chamber sort of thing,
right? And you find these people who had the same, that had the same experience as you,
and you assume everybody's like that. It turns out, no, no, people were quite different.
So find the, you get to pick the type of restriction, find what feels easiest and try
not to get too caught up in, well, this diet increases fat oxidation and insulin and like
all these little things we talked about. Cause at the end of the day, if you've ever lost weight
and then regained it, why did it happen? It didn't happen because you didn't get your
macronutrient ratio perfect or your nutrient timing. Was it down? It happened because you
stopped being consistent with the behaviors that you implemented. That's what happened.
And the same thing goes with exercise. People tell me all the time, like, man,
Lane, I wish I was motivated like you. I'm like, ha. I would say that I, I love lifting
weights and that makes it easier to be motivated. I acquired that love through years. But I don't
always love it. Just like I'm not always happy with my spouse, right? Like some days we fight.
Doesn't mean I don't love her overall. It just means some days we get annoyed at each other.
Some days I'm unhappy with weightlifting. I don't want to do it. However, I always tell people,
and I'm not saying you can never take a day off. Of course, you know, if you need a day off to reset
whatever, that's fine. You just got to be careful that that doesn't turn into weeks and months and
years. Right? And here's the comparison I use. I don't have to be motivated to go into training.
It's part of what I do. Just like I don't have to be motivated and pump myself up to brush my teeth.
Do you know why? Because it's a very simple equation. If I don't brush my teeth,
they're going to go to crap. Just like if I don't exercise, my body's going to go to crap.
So it doesn't, it is not for me, it is not a question of motivation. It is a question of
what do I want and what are the actions that are required to get what I want.
And if my actions do not line up with what is needed and the amount of work that is needed,
it's very simple. I'm not going to get what I want. And it's on a fundamental level,
it's that simple. But getting people to one, buy in and two, get past the stage where you start,
you've got that honeymoon phase and everything feels good. You're like, yeah, I'm going to do this.
And then you hit your first challenge or your first setback or your scale fluctuate. Actually,
during the systematic review, participants talked about how seeing the scale fluctuate. Well,
it was a difficult thing to get over. And some people would quit because they would gain three
pounds when in reality, they probably just had a bad weigh in day. That's why this is why I actually
tell people weigh in every single day and take the average because the average is not going to
fluctuate that much. So anyways, no, I think I think those are just those are those are great
points. Yeah. The point of this all is that consistency is the fundamental you can do.
You could have any diet, you could have any training system. If you're consistent, you're going to see
results. I use this comparison. I'll throw it back to you on this one. If I said to you, Peter,
I want you to go out and become the best three point shooter you possibly can be.
You cannot get any instruction. You can't read any books. You can't get a coach, nothing. But if
all you did every single day for three hours a day for 10 years was go out and shoot three pointers,
you probably wouldn't be in the NBA. But I bet you'd be pretty damn good at shooting three pointers.
You know what I mean? I would agree with that. Hopefully better than I am now. Because right now
I'm not joking. My 12 year old daughter is probably the same as me at shooting three
pointers, which means by the time she's 13, she might be better than me. Well, I think that's the
that's the other thing for people to keep in mind is use other people's stories for inspiration, but
be very careful about comparing yourself. Because what you need to ask yourself is
can I get better? Try not to ask yourself, can I be like X person? Because the answer might be no.
But here's the rub. You'll never know unless you put in the decade worth of work, right? Like when
I started out, I had people tell me, why are you lifting weights? You're skinny. You'll never be
never be jacked. And then even when I got into powerlifting, people were like, look at how long
your legs are. Look at how you squat. You will never be good at this. If I were to listen to that,
I never would have set a gold medal in the squat. I never I never would have done that.
Now that world record got broken and I may never get it back. Very good chance I'll never get it
back. But I got a lot farther than I ever could have imagined just through sheer consistency.
I did a lot of stuff wrong, but sheer mass effect of work and consistency can make up for a lot of
shortcomings. And I think a lot of people out there have paralysis by analysis and they never
just start because they're so intimidated by all the information that's out there.
Lane, we actually got through a third of the stuff I wanted to talk about today. And I'm going to
make it I'm going to make an on the field decision that we're going to probably have to sit down
again. Because I want to talk about a lot of things I want to talk about creatine, I want to
talk about catsu or occlusion training, I want to talk about really nuanced stuff around the
differences between the size of a muscle, the strength of a muscle and the metabolic function
of a muscle. There are a lot of other things I want to go into with you. And I also wanted to go a
little deeper into this sort of leucine signaling stuff. But to even scratch this, I know, I know.
And to go to go into that stuff superficially now doesn't do it justice. So why don't we just agree
to do this again at some point? Sure. All right, man. Well, listen, this has been a ton of fun for
me. I hope it's been enjoyable for you. And thank you for making the time. Thank you. I appreciate it.
I enjoyed it. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. To that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail
every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's
show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures
and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.