Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Amanda. Thank you so much for making time to chat with me today. From the first
time I heard you speak, I knew I wanted to have you on the podcast. You probably don't
even remember when that was, do you?
Well, I think it was that Zoom thing for HFC, right?
That's right. That's right. It was hilarity for charity. Somehow, I was considered an
expert. You clearly are an expert. You and me and Richard Isaacson were a part of a discussion
in the days when we no longer do physical panel discussions. I just thought, wow, I
was really blown away by a lot of your insights because they went beyond just the obvious
topics we discussed, which are the research around what's the cause of Alzheimer's disease,
how do you prevent it, what are the treatment? All those things are relevant and all those
things are things that you speak to. I think what impressed me was the attention you brought
to the impact that Alzheimer's disease has on the family just as much as it does the
patient. Certainly, that's something I want to talk about today. Before we get to that,
tell us a little bit about your background. You specialize in geriatric psychiatry, which
are not often things you think about, right? People think about psychiatry, they think about
forensic psychiatry, they think about more of the DSM-5 type of psychiatry. How did you
get interested in that? I grew up in Philadelphia and I had very active grandparents. They owned
a nursing home. A lot of people think grandparents in a nursing home, my own and operated in
a nursing home. Just from a young age, being around them and their friends and seeing the
vibrant lives they led even into their 70s and 80s, that to me was normal aging. I never thought
of anything different until I was in medical school and I really saw the pathologic side of
aging and the things that can go wrong as we get older, as well as I want to say an attitude of
ageism among a lot of the attending physicians that we trained under. There was this sort of
epiphany I had one day. I remember I was in Bryn Mawr Hospital in the emergency room and the
attending sent me in to talk to a woman who had come in from a nursing home with chest pain. That
was all I knew. So I went in and I talked to her and I got the history and I went and I
presented the case to the attending in rounds and he just laughed at me and he was like,
you went in the wrong room. He's like, the lady I'm talking about doesn't make any sense. And I
was like, actually she does. She just doesn't have her dentures in because the EMTs forgot to bring
them. But if you actually sat there and took the time to listen to her, she told a very normal
coherent story about how she was eating lunch and she felt pain and went to her shoulder. So she
called the nurse. And so that for me was so enlightening because I realized how quick
people are to brush off the elderly and it kind of lit a fire in me, so to speak, so that that
became my passion. So for the rest of medical school, I made sure that my elective rotations
were geriatrics and working with older people in different aspects of it. And one of my favorite
experiences was on the geriatric psychiatry unit where I got to work with dementia patients and
psychotic patients. And I just found that personally I had more patients for them because
of their life stories and the things that they've been through. And it just sort of led me down this
path to where I am now. And there are lots of ways as you experienced, I suppose, to interact
with patients in a geriatric setting. Obviously internal medicine, you could go down that path
through cardiology. You could certainly go down that path through other subspecialties.
When you were doing the psychiatric work, was it understood at the time that a part of dementia
is behavioral changes and other things like that? Or how was, I guess I'm struggling with my question
because I know what it is and I can't make it come out. How much was it understood that Alzheimer's
disease had a behavioral component that would be under the purview of psychiatric care? I guess
I think it was fairly well established. The part that was the bigger problem was that there wasn't
much that we could do about the cognitive side of things. And fortunately that's changed some in
the time that I've been doing this. So I graduated from med school in 1997, which was actually the
year that denepazil or Airecept was first approved. So kind of witnessed the evolution
of Alzheimer's treatments in that time. But certainly from the behavioral standpoint,
the behavior problems that can occur in people with dementia have always been treatable.
Anxiety, depression, psychosis, those have frequently been reasons for hospitalization
and often were the reason that we saw people on the geriatric psychiatry unit because they were
imagining things that weren't there or acting out on delusions that they had, that people were spying
on them and they were taking apart the stealing tiles in their apartment to find these wires that
weren't really there and all that kind of thing. So we've always been able to treat that and
fortunately there's also been improvement in some of the options there. Not ideally, but to the
point where we can control some of those behaviors so people can have a better quality of life and
so that caregivers can have a little more peace of mind as well.
Is it common that a patient is known to have dementia and we'll get to how that's diagnosed
in such a moment, but a patient is known to have this diagnosis of dementia, either Alzheimer's
dementia or some non-Alzheimer's form and then they begin to exhibit some of the symptoms you've
described so that when they're coming in for evaluation, you're not going to be able to
evaluate the diagnosis of dementia. You're not going to be able to evaluate the evaluation.
You're not going through a lengthy differential diagnosis to rule out schizophrenia or other forms
of psychosis. Or is it sometimes the case that actually the presenting feature of the dementia
can be some of these psychotic symptoms you describe where they feel, hey someone's talking
the answer is both. Sometimes people will have a course of dementia that after a few years they'll
start to develop some of these behavioral symptoms. Some people never get them and some people do
actually present with them. Often with the latter, what will usually happen is they'll go be seen by
a community psychiatrist or somebody else and get diagnosed with schizophrenia or bipolar illness
or something that does not have an onset in the mid-70s. And so usually they'll be misdiagnosed for
a couple of years until it becomes really apparent that that's not the primary problem,
that there is an underlying neurodegenerative process. I can't sort of imagine, because I
haven't been close enough to it, what it's like for a patient in the early stages of dementia.
I've seen patients in the later stages where at least on the outside it seems that they're
quite removed from what's happening and paradoxically they don't appear to be suffering very much.
But is it safe to assume that it's quite unnerving in the early stages and that that might actually
be what's driving some of this behavior? Is there a legitimate and understandable fear of something
is wrong but I don't understand what it is? Yeah, I mean sometimes. So some people are always
blissfully unaware throughout the entire course of their illness. You know, I can't tell you how
many times I see a patient and they sit down in my office and I'm like, so what brings you in today?
And they're like, my wife? Because there's nothing wrong with me, I'm fine. They have no idea why
they're there, even in the very mild stages. Whereas some people are so acutely aware that
something's not right and sometimes they know for two or three years before we can even find
any discernible changes on their testing. You know, they're like, I know something's wrong with me.
And a lot of times they're right. You know, sometimes they're just anxious because a family
member had it or they're worried, but a lot of times, you know, they're very in tune to what's
happening. And I think you're right. Usually those are the people that suffer the most because they
know what's happening to them and they don't like it and they know what they're facing. You know,
some patients are extremely insightful and really are aware of what's happening, aware that they're
losing things that they used to be able to do or that things aren't coming as quickly. Even yesterday,
weirdly, I had two patients with Lewy body dementia, which is a type of dementia that has
sort of parts of Alzheimer's, parts of Parkinson's and some very prominent visual hallucinations.
And whereas oftentimes when people have hallucinations or false beliefs to them,
they're real and they don't know that they're not real. Both of these patients were like,
I see things that aren't there and it drives me crazy. Like they knew, you know, this one woman
has people all over her living room and she can't find a piece of furniture to sit down on because
these people are sitting there and she knows they're not real. But yet she feels like she
has to ask them to move in order to sit on her own furniture. But she was insightful enough to
be able to say, I know they're not there and I know my family members don't see them. So
it's really variable. Let's talk a little bit about how one makes the clinical diagnosis
first of dementia and then how one starts to separate out Alzheimer's from Lewy body from
presumably an unspecified form of dementia. So starting with the former, what is the clinical
definition in the diagnosis of dementia? So dementia is an umbrella term that just sort
of describes changes in memory and other areas of cognition and it represents a change from how you
used to be so you weren't born with it and it interferes with your day-to-day function. So there
are many causes of dementia. Alzheimer's far and away the most common. So although there have been
advancements in many of our tests and more sophisticated imaging techniques and blood
biomarkers that are coming along, the real crux of diagnosis is a good clinical interview with a
patient and with an observer. So usually it's a spouse or an adult child or a loved one who has
observed changes over time. In interviewing them separately, that's key separately because otherwise
the most important information is left out, you know, because they don't want to hurt the loved
one's feelings or whatever. So getting a good clinical interview from the patient,
informant, doing some cognitive testing to look for patterns that support one diagnosis over another
and then doing some brain imaging to look for certain things like strokes or shrinking in
certain parts of the brain as well as some lab tests to rule out reversible causes of memory loss,
thyroid disturbance, vitamin deficiencies, things like that, syphilis, although frankly I've stopped
really testing for that because it's just tertiary syphilis is so uncommon these days.
And once we do all that, generally speaking, you know, we have a pretty accurate diagnostic,
you know, chance of getting the right, you know, label for them. Sometimes we need formal neuropsych
testing with a neuropsychologist. Sometimes we do need PET scanning to look at certain patterns.
For example, frontotemporal dementia is one where people often present with relatively
preserved memory but significant changes in language or behavior. And usually, you know,
within a minute I can diagnose them because the loved one will say, well, his memory is not so
bad but and it's either, you know, he can't really talk anymore, which can also happen in
Alzheimer's fairly early in some people. Or, you know, I'm embarrassed to take him to church
because he'll get up and take the microphone from the pastor and, you know, you almost know, okay,
this is FTD. Those are often the people that erroneously get diagnosed with bipolar illness
because of these sudden and really profound behavior changes. Problems with judgment,
where they get labeled as being manic because they're spending lots of money or they're,
you know, responding to every publisher's clearinghouse thing that comes in the mail.
You know, so there's these typical sort of stories and behaviors that we see that kind of
support one diagnosis over another. So Amanda, there's a lot in there and I kind of want to
go over that in a bit more detail. So to make sure I'm understanding this and obviously the
listener as well, the first thing I heard you really say there was the absolute importance of
the clinical story. So unlike cancer where the diagnosis is made typically off imaging
and then ultimately through a tissue sample, right, the gold standard is a histological
diagnosis. That's not the case in Alzheimer's disease. We don't do biopsies of the brain.
I also didn't hear you talk about CSF sampling,
sampling the cerebrospinal fluid to look for amyloid beta or tau. Anything you want to say
about that before we continue down this rabbit hole? Well, yeah, I mean, there are a few things
I can say about that. First of all, you know, certainly it is extremely helpful in the diagnostic
process to have, you know, formal tests like CSF or amyloid PET in terms of confirming a diagnosis,
you know, although we certainly don't do brain biopsies. Unlike when I graduated when you
literally could only see amyloid at autopsy under a microscope, we now do have the ability to image
amyloid in living patients, which has, you know, and I know we're going to talk about research later,
allowed us to really go much earlier in the process and design some prevention trials
based on targeting people who have brain amyloid but don't yet have memory symptoms. So it's been
a really amazing revolution as far as that goes. However, from a cost standpoint, although it's a
test I can order, it's not covered by any insurance and would cost a patient about $4,000 out of pocket.
So other than doing it, you know, in the context of a clinical trial, it's really not realistic
for many of the patients. As far as CSF goes, you know, there is a good correlation between
the PET and CSF findings. Because I am a geriatric psychiatrist and not a neurologist,
I'm not typically doing lumbar punctures as part of my practice. Generally speaking, between the
other markers such as, you know, MRI imaging and PET, FDG PET, which measures how well the brain
is using glucose as its fuel and has different patterns supporting one diagnosis over another,
and that is usually covered by some insurance, we're able to make a diagnosis without the additional
markers such as CSF. But there are times when it is helpful and when we do refer people
to neurology specifically for that. So this clinical diagnosis is so important in a way that
it's not really as important in the other major chronic diseases, right? When a patient comes in
and they're being diagnosed with diabetes or NAFLD, nobody's really taking a great clinical history.
You're sort of assuming you know how they got there. But here you're having that discussion,
as you described, both with the patient and with someone who can give some of these details you're
looking for. So I kind of want to identify some of these patterns. Now, I guess the textbook cases are
first thing is a loss of short-term memory, I'm assuming. Is that the textbook version of
Alzheimer's dementia? Yes, I mean in Alzheimer's disease usually people start to complain of
forgetfulness repeating. So a loved one might say, well he you know he asked me
what time this appointment was four times since yesterday kind of thing. But he can remember you
know all the names of his high school football teammates. That's very classic. So the preservation
of long-term memory with difficulty with short-term memory. Now, Amanda, how do you differentiate
distraction from the path to dementia? Because if there's one thing I've heard so often from
patients, it's I you know I just got introduced to this person and I can't remember their name and it
used to be so easy for me to remember names or you know my wife told me to do this thing and I
just completely spaced on it. And you know my in my practice most of those patients when they're
saying that tend to be distracted. There tends to be something else going on. It's really not the
prodrom to sort of dementia. But obviously in your practice specifically that's one can't assume that.
Do you have a way that you try to differentiate that? Well, I think it has to be taken in context
with all of the other information. I mean quite frankly it happens to me too. You know literally
yesterday I thought it was Friday because I knew I was normally on Friday I wear sweatpants and a
USF thing and I knew I wanted to not wear that for this podcast today. And so I was in my Friday
outfit yesterday and so at one point I literally was like oh it's Friday. And then I was like oh
no it's not Friday. But I'm not worried that I have dementia. I was distracted. I'm busy. I have a lot
of things going on. And so you know all those kinds of things happen to all of us. So it has to be
looked at in the context of you know A the fact that some of this does happen with normal aging.
The fact that you know stress, a bad night's sleep, all that kind of stuff can affect it.
And the other part of it is the frequency and intensity of it. You know if it's the exception
rather than the rule it's probably not dementia. But when that becomes sort of how you are and
what happens every day then it's more concerning. You alluded to, I think you alluded to MRI and
although you didn't state it explicitly, were you talking about hippocampal volume or other
brain matter loss? Was that kind of what you were getting at?
Yeah the typical things that we look for in an MRI when evaluating for dementia. A is
ruling out vascular disease or quantifying the amount of it. So we all get with aging
some amount of tiny little strokes. And I know that sounds scary. But as we get older you know
for various reasons high blood pressure, high cholesterol, smoking, diabetes, and even just
normal aging there can be blocking of blood vessels, changes in circulation that cause us to
have these tiny little infarcts. These are not anything you would notice. You would never
have symptoms. You wouldn't go to the hospital. But there can be an accumulation of them. And
there's a certain amount that's sort of normal and it's extremely mild or scattered. But then
when they start to coalesce or they start to extend into cortical areas,
parts of the brain that sort of matter more in terms of critical thinking,
then they can be symptomatic. So that's one of the things that we look at is how much vascular
disease. Another thing that we look at is how much shrinking there is both globally and then
as you mentioned in the hippocampus which is where short-term memories are kind of formed and
before they go off elsewhere. And so there is, you know, it is known that that shrinking in
the hippocampus particularly disproportionately to shrinking elsewhere can be a biomarker of
Alzheimer's disease. Now there are sometimes people who have hippocampal atrophy and turn out to be
amyloid negative. So there are these other pathologies that could be considered, they call
it hippocampal sclerosis. Some people have that from a stroke. Some people have it potentially
from chronic traumatic encephalopathy and other buildup of other abnormal proteins beside amyloid
in the brain that kind of affect memory as well. I want to come back to the amyloid negative case
in a second. Is hippocampal volume a reliable marker to check progress? So for example,
if you had a patient that was high risk theoretically, so I don't know if you're
seeing people who are high risk but don't have symptoms yet, but if you had a patient who is high
risk, you did an MRI, you got a baseline so to speak, you had their hippocampal volume, would
tracking that over time for changes, reductions presumably, would that provide any meaningful
insight? Sometimes but not always. So other things can affect hippocampal volume. For example,
people who are chronically exposed to elevated levels of cortisol or stress hormone,
people who have post-traumatic stress disorder, we know they have smaller
hippocampi than people who don't have that. And so there are times when we can track hippocampal
volume over the course of progression of Alzheimer's and the shrinking sort of correlates
with the amount of cognitive impairment, but sometimes not. Sometimes we have people who
are very impaired and their brain doesn't really look that bad. And sometimes we have people who
look like they shouldn't be able to put on their own pants based on what the brain looks like,
but they seem fine. So it's again, one of those things that really has to be taken
in context with all of the other information and part of the reason why the clinical
evaluation and interview and the intangible stuff is so important.
And just to be clear, the diagnosis is, it requires the clinical story with or without amyloid.
And so when you look at the Venn diagram of people with amyloid and people with clinical
symptoms suggestive of dementia and you line them up, there's an overlap, but it's not a perfect
union. And what that tells us is that amyloid is neither necessary nor sufficient for Alzheimer's
disease, correct? Well, amyloid is necessary for Alzheimer's disease. It's not necessary
for dementia, but if you look at the definition pathologically of what Alzheimer's is,
it is the plaques, the amyloid plaques and the tau tangles in the brain. So that was what's
required pathologically to make a diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease.
But that diagnosis will only be made post-mortem technically?
Technically, yeah. But that's why the advent of amyloid imaging has been so helpful in terms of
making that formal diagnosis in living people, which is obviously more helpful for them.
You know, the correlation, I believe in one of the studies with Amivid,
Flurbetapyr, which was one of the first amyloid imaging ligands that came out, the correlation
between the PET and their... These were people who were kind enough to donate their brains
after they passed to compare to what their PET scan looked like. And it was a correlation of about
97%. So meaning when they were alive, they had an amyloid PET scan. Yes. And an amyloid PET scan,
unlike FDG PET, where you're putting radio labeled glucose, here you're putting an antibody to amyloid
as their tracer, correct? Yes. And so they had this scan while they were alive, and you then had
a distribution of people that had this much amyloid, that much amyloid, et cetera. But all
of them, to be clear, had a diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease based clinically, correct?
Right. They had a suspected diagnosis of Alzheimer's, and then they underwent the PET, and then
they donated their brains. And then on exam... The correlation between...
So what we're missing there, of course, is the control of people who had amyloid in their brains
that would go on to have amyloid on autopsy, but didn't have Alzheimer's disease. Do we have a rough
sense of how big a population that is? I've had a hard time finding this, by the way. What percentage
of people on autopsy have amyloid in their brain, but did not have dementia during their life?
I don't know, honestly. But I think more than you would expect, because... So what we know about
amyloid, and one of the reasons that amyloid imaging has been so helpful, is because it's
helped us understand that amyloid starts to build up 10, 15, 20 years before you start to have
symptoms of forgetfulness and other cognitive symptoms. And so it's this process where
it's occurring, and then it reaches a critical mass. And there's a lot of debate scientifically
about what that critical mass is, or what the downstream effects of amyloid build up. There's
some people who think that you can have as much amyloid as you want, and it's not until you start
to have tau. We're understanding more that tau... Whereas amyloid is sort of widespread,
kind of from the beginning, and builds up all these years beforehand. And so the
tracking amyloid doesn't correlate to symptoms. Tau, on the other hand, is very different and has
a very specific pattern in which it spreads that does indeed correlate with symptoms. So some
people feel like it's really the tau that kind of stages where things are, whether you're going to be
symptomatic or not. So to answer your question, I think there are a lot of people who start to
build up amyloid maybe in their 70s or whatever, and then die of something else.
So a way to think about it is it's sort of like saying, and this is a bad example,
but I think it's the best one I can think of on the spot, it's like coronary calcification,
where if somebody dies of cancer and you see calcification in their coronary arteries,
you knew they have atherosclerosis, but it may have never clinically manifested itself. And
if they had not died of cancer, they may have died of an MI 10 years later.
That's exactly right. And that's frankly the analogy we most often like to use.
So before 2011, the FDA, the definition of Alzheimer's was dementia. So there was no place
in research for these prodromal patients or testing these interventions in people before
they had full-blown dementia. And that was very much like waiting until someone had a heart attack
to say that they had coronary artery disease. Well, it's like, no, you knew that because they
have high cholesterol and they're building up and you could see on an angioplasty or whatever
this was happening. And so in 2011, with the advent of amyloid imaging,
Pittsburgh compound was the first thing that came out that allowed us to see that,
although its half-life is so terribly short that it really is not clinically
useful because it has to be made and used within minutes. But that really allowed us to redefine
what Alzheimer's is so that we could see this amyloid building up in patients before they
started to have symptoms. And it allowed some redefinition and there were white papers that
came out kind of dividing. And I know on a previous podcast, Richard Isaacson did go into
this in some detail, but the preclinical phase of Alzheimer's, then mild cognitive impairment,
and then dementia. So it really has allowed us to then kind of take a step back and see if we can
intervene before people have these symptoms that we may not be able to reverse. Yeah, to me, Amanda,
that is probably the most exciting part of this field, which is effectively taking from the
playbook of the chronic disease we understand most. I talk about this with patients, which is
like there's basically these three main chronic diseases, which is Alzheimer's disease, cancer,
even though of course that's not one disease, and the atherosclerotic diseases, both cerebrovascular
and cardiovascular. And those three legs stand on a platform, which is metabolic disease,
which is then basically the distribution from hyperinsulinemia to insulin resistance,
naphyl D, and type 2 diabetes. So that becomes the table and you have these legs that stand on it.
Of these, I think we have the best understanding of atherosclerosis, where lesion by lesion,
we can stage them. We understand what a fatty streak is, we understand what a foam cell is,
we understand what leads to calcification, how we go from soft plaque to vulnerable plaque to a
ruptured plaque to an MI. And we clearly understand, as your point is made, to sit there
and wait until someone has a major adverse cardiac event to say, oh, this guy's got heart disease,
is nonsensical. I would go one step further and say, waiting until a person's 10-year risk exceeds
5% to intervene is equally nonsensical, yet that is still largely the standard.
Because we know from autopsy studies of teenagers, that the process begins then. I mean, it probably
begins even younger, but we don't have too many autopsies of people below the teen years. But
certainly autopsies of people in their late teens and early 20s who have died for other reasons
already show foam cells, fatty streaks in some cases. So if I'm understanding you correctly,
by definition now, based on everything we understand, anyone who clinically classifies
as having dementia with amyloid has Alzheimer's disease. Is tau necessarily preceded by amyloid,
or are there scenarios in which tau arrives with minimal to no amyloid beta?
So the answer to that question is yes, but I want to kind of go back for a second.
So anyone that has dementia and has amyloid does have Alzheimer's, but they may also have
other pathology too, right? So you could have a mixed dementia where you have Alzheimer's and
vascular disease, or you could have a mixed Lewy body in Alzheimer's. And we know from
the autopsy studies certainly that are done by Dennis Dixon up in Mayo and Jacksonville,
most pathology is actually mixed. I don't have the numbers, and I don't remember them quite
frankly offhand, but I know that the number of pure Alzheimer's is actually lower than the number
of mixed cases. So most people have something else too. And is vascular the most common
additional diagnosis? Yes. And so what does that mean? Let's think about that for a second.
You may recall I interviewed Francesco Gonzalez Lima probably two or three years ago.
He's here actually in UT Austin, works with Jack De La Torre and they really have a strong point
of view that says, look, it's this microvascular disease that is really a big driver here. And
there's a very compelling rationale for that. You mentioned it earlier. It's very hard to make it
into your seventh, eighth, ninth decade without unbelievable amounts of microvascular damage.
And to your point, if a critical mass of that is reached, it's quite likely that that's going to
result in the cognitive impairment and ultimately even higher levels of impairment beyond memory,
such as executive function. And if, as you said, amyloid is accumulating along the way, it makes
sense that you could have this mixed picture where you have the clinical side. So you meet the
criteria for dementia, you have amyloid beta and you have a heavy enough burden of vascular disease.
I guess it begs the question, if you had a time machine and you could go back in time
for that particular patient and you correct the vascular insult. So let's just say in one patient,
they were aggressively, you aggressively manage their hypertension. In another patient, you
kick the smoking cessation in 20 years sooner. In another patient, you manage the dyslipidemia.
You're going to impact the vascular stuff. Do you think that has an impact on the amyloid side of
the equation? And more importantly, does it impact clinically their development of dementia?
I think definitely, yes. I mean, I know, again, when you had your conversation with Richard
Isaacson, he stressed the importance of those cardiovascular risk factors and the development
of Alzheimer's. The other thing that we know is, and again, it's not exactly the same
protein, but it's so closely related, amyloid is a component of blood vessel walls.
So to what extent, I think there's still room for more understanding in that and what the
exact relationship is between normal amyloid and pathologic amyloid. So it's important to say in
Alzheimer's, the buildup of amyloid is this abnormal length amyloid that's not the usual
thing that we find in our bodies. So it's changed a little bit. But there is normally amyloid that's
part of our being. And so because it is part and parcel of blood vessel walls, it's only natural
to assume there must be this interplay between the vasculature and the Alzheimer's side of things.
I would be lying if I said I knew what that was. I think that still needs to be elucidated.
That's why we have floors of people smarter than me upstairs doing experiments.
Does amyloid beta exist outside of the blood-brain barrier? Does it exist on the other
side of the blood-brain barrier? Honestly, I don't know.
That's interesting. I never actually thought of what, until you said what you said
about the relationship to the endothelium. I never thought about that. I'm guessing somebody
has looked into that. And the answer is probably not enough to matter or else we would simply be
doing a blood test to look for enough amyloid, right? Right. Well, that's coming though. Yeah.
So there are some really exciting, I don't want to forget about your tau question.
Yeah. Yeah. We'll come back to that. So I have that over here.
There are some really exciting developments in terms of looking at blood biomarkers,
including plasma amyloid, in terms of potentially having a blood-based test for Alzheimer's.
So there has been progress there. And I think that as time goes on, we're going to be able to
do these less invasive tests and really have a better sense of both risk for people who aren't
maybe symptomatic yet, as well as diagnosis. One blood-based test. Oh, okay. Yeah. Yeah.
Let's go back to tau. And then I want to ask another blood-based question.
Okay. So you had asked about whether you could have other things like tau without amyloid. And
the answer is definitely yes. So frontotemporal dementias, some of them are characterized by
abnormal tau buildup in the absence of amyloid. There are some familial genetic
frontotemporal brain diseases that are characterized by tau burden, chronic traumatic encephalopathy
that we see in football and other boxing. And things also have abnormal tau often in the
absence of amyloid. So yes, that definitely has a role in the development of dementia
in other types of dementia too. We sort of glossed over it, but maybe it is worth
explaining what it is that amyloid beta is doing to neurons and what it is that tau
is doing to neurons to actually injure them. Do you want to spend just a second
kind of outlining those things? To the extent that my blonde self can, I will.
To a first order approximation. No, but I mean, I focus on the patient part of things. I let the
scientists do their, the neuroscientists do their part. But it is this sort of cascade of damage.
There is activation of glial cells, which sort of help protect our brain against intruders.
They can release toxins. They can sort of eat, it's called autophagy, eating up our own tissue.
And so there is damage both inside the neurons and then outside, plaques and tangles. And
it creates a cascade that eventually leads to cell death.
And so is it more the death of the neuron itself or would the injury to the glial cells alone be
sufficient to lead to these symptoms? Because the glial cells, of course, when I was in medical
school, which was not that long after you, I don't remember that we talked that much about
glial cells in our neuroscience classes. I feel like we talked more about the neurons,
but I know that in more recent discussions I've had with neuroscientists, they really place almost
an equal emphasis on the glial cells. So I'm curious as to whether or not injuring the glial
cells in this particular pathology is equally responsible or at least to a first-order
approximation equally responsible for the damage. I think they're more responsible for the damage.
I think that they're part of the cascade that leads to the death of the neurons because they're
trying to protect the neurons and in doing so injure them. I want to go back to a biomarker
question. We're going to talk about the ApoE genotype at some point, but of course one can
actually measure ApoE in the plasma. Just like you can measure Apo lipoprotein B,
which we use obviously extensively in cardiovascular risk stratification. To my
knowledge, there's not a commercial assay for measuring ApoE though it can be done.
Do you are you aware of any utility to that? Would looking at ApoE levels, I read a paper
seven or eight years ago, I think suggesting that the lower the level of ApoE, the higher the risk,
but I could entirely have that backwards and I could entirely be wrong. Is that something
you're aware of at all? Not really. I mean it's really more about the genotyping than the
quantification of it. Obviously, and again you've talked about it on prior podcasts,
the risk that E4 genotype carries compared to the others and the fact that E4 homozygotes
have higher risk and also different responses to cardiovascular meds, different
risks for other diseases besides dementia. It is typically not something that we check for in the
routine day-to-day clinical care for a couple of reasons. One is it's not diagnostic, right? So you
can have E4, E4 not have Alzheimer's or you can have E2, E3 which might be protective and still
have Alzheimer's. So it really just makes people worry. It does have a lot more utility in the
research setting in terms of looking at how carriers versus non-carriers respond to certain
treatments and helping us understand that carriers may respond differently to different lifestyle
interventions, may have an earlier onset compared to people who don't have it but ultimately end up
with the same disease. Yeah. So when people come to see you in clinic, there's not a lot of utility
added by looking at it. I mean my view is APO E4 is great to help people identify risk early on,
but at the same time nobody gets off the hook and you used a great example. The 2-3 shows up a lot
and I tell my patients with the 2-3, they're not off the hook. You've got about a 10 percent risk
reduction relative to the 3-3 but the 3-3 is clearly not at risk and on the flip side, the 3-4
patients or even the 4-4 patients, I say look it's certainly not a fait accompli but I would take this
a lot more seriously than maybe you otherwise would in terms of preventative measures. So
let's go back to the patient that shows up in clinic. Oh actually there's one other thing I
wanted to clarify. I'm sorry. Let's go back to Lewy body dementia. Most people have heard of this.
There have been some notable examples in the public sphere about folks that have
died from this. Is it still the case that that's a diagnosis that can be made only post-mortem?
I mean again, yes, but there's this sort of classic clinical picture that is so compelling
that it can be made fairly accurately in the clinic without diagnostic testing.
And so the clinical distinction between, I hate to use this term, the clinical distinction between
classic Alzheimer's dementia and classic Lewy body, so let's exclude the mixed variants of that.
How would you differentiate those patients? So classic Alzheimer's would begin with
short-term memory loss and slowly but surely over time progress to having difficulty paying
bills and then eventually needing supervision, needing assistance with activities of daily living,
cooking, bathing, the classic sort of decline. May or may not have behavior issues.
May or may not have some changes in walking. Lewy body disease on the other hand presents with a
fairly classic triad of symptoms that occur within two years of one another. One is
an Alzheimer's-like cognitive impairment that can notably fluctuate so that some days people seem
really good and some days they seem really, really bad. There is a Parkinsonism component
where they will often be stiff, have trouble rising from a chair, shuffle. They may decrease
arm swing when they walk so that they walk and, you know, normally when we walk our arms move,
but their arms don't move. They may have more or I should say less expression on their face.
They don't necessarily have a tremor. So true Parkinson's disease proper often begins with a
tremor, a slow writhing kind of tremor at rest on one side. And often we don't see that in Lewy body
disease, but they have these other elements of Parkinsonism. And so we've got the cognitive
impairment, the Parkinsonism, and very often prominent visual hallucinations.
Seeing things that aren't there, fairly elaborate, often delusions that go along with it.
You know, there's this family living in my house. There's people and bears living in the trees.
You know, people will close their blinds because they don't want these people seeing them and all
that kind of stuff. So that classic triad of symptoms with some additional supportive features,
including restless leg syndrome, even many years leading up to it, as well as REM sleep behavior
disturbances. So people who often act out in their dreams or a spouse who says, I have to sleep in the
other room because he punches me. You know, that's sort of a classic Lewy body picture. And
furthermore, they fluctuate. Both the motor and the cognitive symptoms fluctuate. So today we
might be able to go to the mall and walk all around and tomorrow they might have trouble
walking across the room. And from the time of diagnosis, Amanda, until those patients are
either in hospice or incapacitated or dead is typically how long? Is that a quicker disease?
Sometimes. I mean, it's usually about eight years. But for some, you know, my experience,
I've had a lot of Lewy body patients who have sort of this precipitous decline and then kind of hit
a plateau for a while and then really drop off. You know, this is not this is anecdotal. This is
not based on any data. But it's just my experience with them and having seen enough of them to see
that that's frequently kind of how it goes. But it's usually about an eight to 10 year process.
And there it's less often as protracted as Alzheimer's can be, even though the average
for Alzheimer's is still also eight to 10 years. It can be significantly longer.
How hereditary is Lewy body dementia either with respect to Lewy body itself or being
predictive of the next generation's risk for Alzheimer's disease or Parkinson's for that matter?
I honestly don't know. I don't think it's terribly genetic. You know, we don't have well established,
you know, as with early onset Alzheimer's, which does have some specific mutations that cause it.
I don't know that we know of specific mutations for Lewy body disease, but I may be just not
informed. I mean, that makes in some ways, Lewy body a bit more of a mystery because, as you said,
for Alzheimer's disease on the very early onset side, we have the PSEN1 to APP mutations, which
are about as close to deterministic as you get. And then you have the APO-E4 gene, which is not
deterministic, but is highly suggestive for the more typical variant. And we also have known risk
factors, diabetes, you know, microvascular disease, dyslipidemia. I mean, these things are
absolutely known risk factors. We seem to have none of that on the side of Lewy body, correct?
As far as I know, yeah.
What's the relative incidence of Alzheimer's versus Lewy body dementia?
Is it like eight, 10 to one, or how much more prominent is Alzheimer's?
Well, it depends, I guess, if you're looking at, you know, the autopsy confirmed versus
sort of what we see in the clinic. You know, I think that I honestly don't have the numbers
specifically for you, but I do know that, you know, it's diagnosed less, but found more on autopsy,
that people do have Lewy bodies that we may not have expected.
I got it. And just in your experience in your clinic, what's the approximate distribution of those?
The, it's about, I would say, you know, 50 to 60 plus percent Alzheimer's, about 20 percent
true vascular, about 20 percent Lewy body. And then the rest is FTD and some of these Parkinson's
plus syndromes, progressive supranuclear palsy, and some of these other less common things that
we only see once in a while.
So back to kind of the way your practice works,
presumably people are coming to you at the referral of a neurologist, correct?
Not necessarily, no. We get people referred from their primary doctors. We get people that are
self-referred. We get people that are referred by neurology. It varies widely.
That in and of itself is actually quite interesting, right? If you think about the different paths
that a person gets to you, they can say, hey, there's something wrong with me. Oh, Dr. Smith,
that's a so-and-so psychiatrist specializing in geriatrics. I'm going to go see her. And then
the primary care doctor can say, look, I have a high enough degree of suspicion that my patient
has Alzheimer's. They're going to come to you, presumably when the neurologist is sending to you.
It's not to make the diagnosis. They've made it. I assume it's then to treat some of the
behavioral components. Sometimes, yes. I mean, well, first let me say that I would say
fully half of my patients think I'm a neurologist. They don't even sort of differentiate or they'll
refer to me as their neurologist and it just is what it is. They assume and it's fine. Or maybe
they don't want to say they're going to a psychiatrist. I don't know. Sometimes
I think it varies from place to place. There are a few neurologists here in town that do
specialize in Alzheimer's and treating dementia and focus on that, but a lot of them don't.
A lot of them prefer specializing in stroke or headache or MS or seizures. And so
when it turns out to be dementia, they just say, well, go to the Alzheimer's Center.
So I don't think it's a question of necessarily psychiatry versus neurology. It's just go to the
memory place. But yes, there are definitely a subset of
referring providers who do so specifically so that we can manage the behavioral aspect of things.
How long have you been in your current practice in Tampa?
Yeah, since 2002. In this building since 2008. So what happened is I came down to USF in 1997
as an intern to do my residency here. So I did my residency in psychiatry and then
a fellowship in geriatric psychiatry. And part of my fellowship time was spent with the Suncoast
Gerontology Center working under Eric Pfeiffer, who had founded that here in 1980 and really was
a leader in the field of geriatric psychiatry and Alzheimer's disease. He was the first president,
I think, of the American Association for Geriatric Psychiatry. And it was actually one of the reasons
I chose USF because I knew Suncoast was here and I was interested in geriatrics and Alzheimer's
at that point. So when I finished my fellowship on a Friday, I started working for him on the
following Monday. And that was in 2002. And then in 2008, he retired and I kind of stepped in and
took on his role as principal investigator for a lot of the clinical trials he had been doing and
kind of directing the center. So I'm curious as to how your practice has evolved in nearly 20 years.
What is different and what is the same about people showing up with dementia today? Are they
older? Are they younger? Are they more metabolically ill? Are they on a faster track? Are
they progressing quicker? I mean, what are all the differences that you see?
So that's a really great question. And the thing that's the same, I would say, is the fear.
People are terrified of losing their minds and losing their memories. And so that continues
to be sort of the biggest motivator in terms of people seeking help. I will say that we are seeing
people that are both older and younger. I think that there's more of an awareness of Alzheimer's
as a disease, as well as an awareness of the fact that there are things that we can do about it.
Because when I first started, there wasn't a whole lot that we could do. And furthermore,
there was sort of this assumption that it was a normal consequence of aging. There has been a lot
of effort put into really educating the public that this is a disease and that this is not
something that you have to live with. And this is not a normal consequence of getting older.
And because of that, I think there's been success in kind of getting that message across and getting
people into the clinic. I think that there's definitely more of a shift towards people seeking
baseline, people looking at prevention, people wanting an evaluation and tips on brain health.
And I know, again, you spoke with Richard Isaacson because he runs a prevention clinic at Cornell
in terms of the lifestyle modifications and things that people can do earlier. We often see people
who have a parent who have Alzheimer's and want to come in and have an evaluation for themselves
or get involved in prevention research so that they don't go down the same path. So I think
that's the biggest area where things have shifted. I think there's also a better understanding that
people realize that there's more that we can do and that early intervention is key. People often
used to be embarrassed by this problem or isolated by it or not want to tell family members or
neighbors. And now they understand that if they come and they seek help and we start them on
medication, even though our medications are not miracle drugs by any stretch, the ones that are
FDA approved, but they can slow down decline. And then in some people, they can even subjectively
and objectively help for a period of time. And so knowing that you can preserve your function and
stay better longer or stay at home longer, there was one old study way back with denepazil showing
that it delayed nursing home placement by an average of 24 months. That's huge. If you're
someone that wants to be at home versus being in a skilled nursing facility, or if you're a spouse
who wants to keep your loved one home, that makes a difference, even though the drugs not...
people are still going to get worse on the medication. So anyway, that was a lot of big
mouthful just to say that. I think there is this better awareness of the things that we are able
to do and the help that we're able to provide so that people seek help sooner. We talked about it
at the very outset that so many of the things that the patients are experiencing when they show up
are, quote unquote, the garden variety things that a psychiatrist would see anxiety and depression,
for example. What percentage of the patients that you're taking care of are you prescribing
antidepressants and anxiolytics? And is that standard of care? Is that something that you
have the ability to be more bespoke in because you have a greater understanding of how those
drugs work and how effective are they? So the answer is quite a few. I would say the majority
of our patients do have some mood or behavioral issue that does require treatment.
90% of people will have some behavioral issue at some point in their illness. It may not be a
terribly problematic psychotic type behavior issue. It may be something simple, but nevertheless,
they're very common in all types of dementia. The key is understanding that they are equally
treatable. Depression in a dependent person is just as treatable as depression in a healthy 25-year-old.
So there are obviously some adjustments that have to be made for age and renal function and other
medications and drug interactions, but we very frequently prescribe the SSRIs,
the type of antidepressants, because they treat anxiety very well in this population. They're
pretty well tolerated. They generally don't make people fall, which is a big issue in this group
as well. We try to stay away from the benzodiazepine type drugs, Alprazolam and Lorazepam and
all the PAMs, particularly diazepam and the longer-acting ones, because they can really
increase confusion and have a dramatically high incidence of hip fracture with those drugs
and be used chronically. So a lot of it is identifying the specific problem, treating with
the least sort of offensive drug that's going to cause the least amount of collateral damage.
Stopping them at times when they may no longer be necessary. Old people sort of,
they collect meds like they collect other things. And sometimes you'll see someone who's on 15,
17, 18 meds, and you're like, why are you even on this? People who had hypertension when they
were 50 and needed three meds to manage it, but now are 90 and they're falling all the time
because their blood pressure is so low, but nobody bothered to say, hey, you don't need three
meds for your blood pressure anymore. So we do have to be vigilant and really target symptoms
with the safest, lowest dose, and the shortest treatment period that we can. But in doing so,
can be very effective in treating these symptoms. You might not know the answer to this, but
do you have a sense of how many patients in the United States or what fraction of patients in the
US with Alzheimer's disease are getting that type of complimentary care for the psychiatric component,
specifically the depression and the anxiety? Do you think it's the majority or the minority?
I would probably say it's the majority. I mean, a lot of them do get treated by their primary
doctors for depression. I see a lot of people who come to me already on medication for that.
I think doctors are prescribing and people are sharing those. And certainly from the standpoint
of some of the more problematic behaviors, people don't want to live with them. They're
difficult. They're difficult for the patient and they can also be problematic and troublesome for
the caregivers. So they often will seek help for that more acutely than they will for
the underlying condition. How much are you providing? I mean, you're not necessarily treating
the family members medically, but after all, you are a psychiatrist, which means you have more tools
in your toolkit than simply your prescription pad. How much are you treating the spouse,
for example, as you are the patient, the spouse without dementia?
Well, in a way, I think we all sort of give free therapy, if you want to call it that.
I do occasionally medicate caregivers if they register as a patient. I'll say, hey,
you really have a severe depression. We need to treat this, but I won't do it under the patients.
You know, once we're dealing with meds, it's a whole other story. But
obviously, there is a lot of support and education. Sometimes, I mean, especially with the pandemic,
sometimes I'm the only other person that they will see or talk to, even if it's on telehealth like
this. Oftentimes, it's just that opportunity to vent, to talk to somebody who can understand
what they're going through. Although I have had some experience with family members having
dementia lead in life, I was not a primary caregiver. Most of what I know comes from
the village of patients and caregivers that have shared very personal things with me. So
I have the opportunity to share their insights with others. But I would say quite a lot of,
if you want to call it free therapy or whatever, just that opportunity to listen, to
make them understand that what they're going through is valid and real,
and give them pointers and tools and things that they may not have thought of in terms of handling
a certain behavior. Just that one little pearl that might make their day easier. The other day,
I was talking to someone who just simply cannot get their loved ones to take a shower. And I'm
like, well, what's their favorite snack? And they kind of looked at me funny. And I said,
they're like Cheetos. So I'm like, okay, tell them after they get out of the shower,
you'll give them some Cheetos. You'll go to the store, you'll get some Cheetos. And they're like,
they don't think of it that way because they're just sort of trying and fighting. Like, you need
to take a bath, you need to take a bath, get in the shower. And I want to take a shower. And there's
not that sort of stepping back and like, okay, how can I do this differently? So sometimes just
kind of giving them a little reality check and a break from the constant stress cycle that they're
in to kind of look at things through different eyes really can make a big difference, I think,
in their the way that they approach things. You know, the other thing that's sometimes really
difficult for caregivers is, you know, a lot of times they'll think that some of these behaviors
that their loved ones are showing are intentional, you know, or he's just doing it to annoy me.
It's like, well, no, he's not. He's really not. If he knew the answer, he wouldn't ask you again.
So instead of saying, don't you remember, just say, answer the question like it's the first time,
you know, and take out that sort of personal attack side of it, you know, and not look at it as
they're intentionally trying to irritate you, but, you know, they have a disease that's making them
do this. And often, you know, that is something that people really need to hear, and it really
makes their days better. I mean, it's easy for me to sit here at my desk and tell them it's a lot
harder to do, but at least kind of having that reality check can change the way that they
approach caregiving.
I'm sure people listening are familiar with Elizabeth Kubler-Ross and how she goes through
these sort of five stages of grief and how people go through, you know, denial and anger, etc. on
their way to acceptance. And that model has always sort of been helpful when thinking about
something like cancer. And I got to see that a lot firsthand. Is it similar here with Alzheimer's
disease, both for the patient and the caregiver that they that there's this, you know, in some
combination or in some order they go through those?
Oh, absolutely. I mean, you know, other, you know, I can't take credit for the phrase,
but it's, you know, it's like grieving for someone while they're still alive. You know, it's the,
you know, this can't really be happening and then being angry that it's happening. And, you know,
sort of, well, maybe if we do this and maybe do that. In fact, I re listened to your podcast with
Lauren Miller Rogan and Richard Isaacson last evening, just kind of in preparation for today.
And just to make sure we didn't sort of duplicate everything that we talked about. But, you know,
Lauren in that podcast really gives a very compelling journey right through those stages,
you know, in terms of dealing with her mother who was my patient, which is how I got to know them in
the first place. But, you know, it's really a very distinct journey while her mother was
was still very alive and, you know, going through those stages of grief in losing her hopes for what
her relationship with her mother would be like as she got older. You know, and it's really
terribly sad. And it's also something that naturally happens as we grieve. You know,
I think those stages of grief apply to almost everything. You know, they're sort of part and
parcel of our, you know, existence as human beings is that's kind of going to happen. We don't always
go through all of them or we don't always resolve all of them or make it through all of them.
But it's a very, very real and major part of dealing with this diagnosis.
In my experience with oncology patients, once they've progressed through denial and anger and
bargaining, etc., and they sort of get to acceptance, the usually the biggest concern,
the residual concern is the amount of suffering at the end. So it actually becomes,
at least one of the concerns becomes around the mechanism of death. And that's not something a lot
of people think about. Most people walking around, if they're level-headed, know that they're going
to die at some point. There aren't too many people walking around believing that they're immortal.
So most people understand in an abstract way, I'm not going to be able to do that. But I think
I'm not going to be alive at a point in time. But it's kind of a vague, fuzzy, foggy thing,
which is, I'll have a heart attack at some point, then I won't be alive. But to the patient with
metastatic cancer, who's again accepted that and understands that they've progressed through all
standard treatments. So even now we can even take a subset of patients with stage four cancer who
are in hospice care. All of a sudden, a big priority is the actual mechanism of death.
And certainly for the palliative care physician, and in my opinion, also for the good oncologist,
the one who doesn't just sort of abandon the patient when there's no more oncologic care.
I think a big part of that is explaining, no, actually, we might not be able to save your life,
but we can absolutely prevent discomfort. What is that discussion like for you,
once the patient and their family have progressed through all the stages and really understand
that this is an irreversible disease, and it will result in the end of their life? How do you
address the specific fears that remain? That's a great question. I do get asked about it fairly
frequently, but yet at the same time, we often don't get into it too much because what I try to
do is really help people focus on the now. That being said, what I share with them is that a lot
of times, as they progress, they're going to have more difficulty doing more simple things and more
basic things. They will have trouble swallowing. They will need assistance. They will perhaps
aspirate on food and get pneumonia. They may lose mobility and be bedridden. We go through
that conversation when they ask, well, how do you die of Alzheimer's? But the truth is,
a lot of people don't ever get to that stage. Many people die of something else. They die of
old age. They die of their heart disease. They die because they fell in a parking lot
before they ever reach such a terminal stage of dementia. We have the conversation, but we also
try not to focus on the end game because that's just miserable. I know a little bit later,
we're going to be talking about healthy aging and stuff like that. That's one of the biggest
things that I see is not focusing on the end, but focusing on the now. The truth is, with Alzheimer's,
that's all people have. They have today. They have because they may not remember tomorrow what
happened today. They're really living in the moment. We try not to spend too much time dwelling
on ... I'm obviously extremely honest in terms of what can and will happen if they inquire,
and also in terms of letting them know that support is there through hospice and other things
when the time comes, that they don't have to go through that alone.
We try to reroute that thought process into focusing on making each day better.
Let's shift gears a little bit and talk about the clinical trial landscape because that's a very big
part of what you do. You're a clinical psychiatrist who deals with patients on an individual basis,
as we've discussed, but you also are heavily involved in another part of this, which is
how to do clinical trials. This is obviously a very important part of this work.
Alzheimer's disease and drugs don't have a great marriage. They don't have a great track record the
way cardiovascular disease does. Even though oncology is not great, far from perfect,
oncology even has a better track record than Alzheimer's disease. I think you could make the
case without being hyperbolic that there is no disease that has a worse track record relative
to the inputs on the output side. In other words, there are orphan diseases for which we have no
drugs, but there have been few shots on goal. The ratio of shots on goal to goals is lower in
Alzheimer's disease than unquestionably any other disease. On the one level that undoubtedly speaks
to the complexity of the disease, some might argue that on another level that speaks to
the wrong goal or shooting too late in the game, shooting from too bad an angle at the wrong goal.
You could take this metaphor 10 different ways. As it stands today, there are about 120 drugs
in the pipeline. If my number crunching has it right, about 27 of them, if we extracted this
correctly off clinicaltrials.gov, are in phase one. For the listener, meaning these are drugs
that are really just being evaluated for safety at this point. We have some animal data that
suggests this is a good idea. We have no idea if it works in humans, but in a very small way with
dose escalation, we want to make sure it's safe. About 65 are in phase two, so that means they've
passed that bar of being safe or at least safe enough to proceed to phase two, where now we're
looking for some efficacy and will of course continue to monitor safety. Then 29 are in phase
three, which means at a small scale, they've shown efficacy typically against a placebo. Now we want
to see if there's efficacy again, either versus a placebo or ideally against a current standard in
a larger trial where again, we're always going to continue to monitor safety, but it's really this
third stage that is required for FDA approval. Another way to slice the data is to look at it
by category of drug. I found this to be the most interesting. 12 of these are in the space of
cognitive enhancement, 12 are in the space of neuropsychiatric and behavioral improvement,
and 97 are in the space of disease modification. Can you explain a little bit what the differences
of those three categories mean? Knowing that the next question I'm going to ask you is,
how has that evolved over the last 20 years? That to me has been the biggest, that was the thing I
was most surprised by. The symptomatic treatments are ones that can help slow cognitive decline
or help improve memory and thinking, but are not targeting the underlying disease process.
All the drugs that we currently have on the market are ones that are symptomatic treatments,
because they're just helping those neurons communicate in the case of dinephazil and
galantamine and ribostigmine, they're colonasterase inhibitors, and then there's
memantine, which is an NMDA receptor antagonist that normalizes levels of glutamate. They're
helping with neurotransmitters and they're not targeting the underlying pathology of amyloid and
tau. Then obviously the behavioral drugs are ones that are being targeted for specific behavior
problems in Alzheimer's and other dementia patients, things like apathy, agitation,
psychosis, sometimes sleep issues, sometimes even appetite and eating problems. So those all kind
of fall under the behavioral umbrella. And then these disease modifying treatments are ones that
actually target the underlying pathology in the case of sort of the biggest group of those that
are in trials right now are really monoclonal antibodies against primarily amyloid, but also
if you look targeting tau and removing them from the brain in the hopes that then there will be
cognitive improvement or at least halting cognitive decline. Can I interject for a second
mechanistically? Is it known exactly where amyloid beta is made? Is it understood
where the transcription takes place or is this all post-translational modification?
Well so there's a whole science dedicated to that, and it actually is different points
along the cascade. So there's the amyloid precursor protein which is on chromosome 21,
which is why people with Down syndrome who have three copies of chromosome 21 almost inevitably
will get Alzheimer's if they live long enough because they're making a third more amyloid than
the rest of us. So anywhere from the very beginning of our DNA all the way through some of the enzymes
that cleave amyloid, so part of the problem is that the amyloid gets cleaved at a length of 40
or 42 amino acids rather than whatever it's supposed to be, which I don't remember.
Then the abnormal amyloid kind of folds and there's fibrils and there's
plaque. The plaque itself is a conglomeration of a series of folds in the protein,
and so there are even differences among the antibodies as to what part of that cascade
they target. Amyloid is not necessary. In other words, if you could wave a magic wand
and pull amyloid out of a person, is there any ill consequence? Well like I said it is
part of blood vessel walls normally, so this pathologic amyloid, these abnormal lengths of
A beta 40 and 42, yeah I mean those could be pulled out without consequence because they
shouldn't be there in the first place. So if you wanted to target the system you would not target
the creation of amyloid, you would probably target the enzymes that abnormally cleave.
Well that is one area that has been studied. The gamma secretase inhibitors for example
are ones that have been studied. There's the base inhibitors, these are things that are being
looked at because these are responsible for cleaving, but a lot of times those have had
side effects that we didn't really want. Yeah I wonder if has anybody looked at
something like an antisense oligonucleotide that goes straight after the enzyme in a laser
precision basically says you can't make this enzyme and you don't have to carpet bomb the
enzyme and everything around it, you're literally going after the transcription of the enzyme.
Yeah I honestly don't know, that's for the scientists.
I mean I'm sure somebody has thought of it and declined, I'm sure there's a reason that hasn't
been there. Yeah I mean the thing is sometimes they have thought of it or they've tried it but
then they don't realize what the downstream effects of doing so may be. And that's been a problem
with several of these medications, you know, where it's a great idea, you know, they've identified a
target, they've identified compounds that seek out that target but they cause liver toxicity
or they cause, you know, some other significant medical issue or they cause cardiac arrhythmias or
things that medically are not safe to continue. So the thing that surprised me Amanda when I
looked at the distribution of drugs, just again this is available on clinicaltrials.gov, is that
80% of the drugs are disease modifying drugs, which is a good sign of course because the other 20%,
as you said, are symptomatic. Now that's not the way the drugs are currently represented,
are there how many drugs, six approved drugs for Alzheimer's disease right now?
Well there's technically five, well yes there's six but one of them is a combination of two.
Two existing, right, right, okay. All of these are symptomatic drugs, right? We don't have a disease
modifying agent out there, we're going to obviously talk about Biogen in a moment
which is an important almost watershed moment in the field. So I assume that it's from your
standpoint a great sign that 80% of the pipeline is actually focusing on the underlying cause as
opposed to just the symptoms. Right and a lot of that has to do with what I mentioned earlier
with regard to that 2011 sort of major moment where we were allowed to redefine what Alzheimer's
is and our understanding that the amyloid pathology building up for many years is was
a key factor, you know I'm not saying it's a B factor, but it's a key factor in the development
of Alzheimer's disease symptoms. Now some of the disease modifying drugs that were initially tested
were tested in people with mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease and were negative, you know,
they did not seem to work or help and it may have been because targeting amyloid at that stage of
the disease may be too late to help people who already are significantly impaired. But that 2011
shift into understanding that there's MCI and that even before that preclinical Alzheimer's
allowed us to then design trials that are currently ongoing looking at both prevention
by amyloid removal before cognitive symptoms start and then also treating people with mild
cognitive impairment who do have some symptoms of memory loss but are not yet demented because
they're still functional on their day to day. What was the typical duration of those failed
studies? So if you look at the earlier studies that were trying to remove amyloid late in the
game that failed, do you recall on average with the duration, are these like four year studies,
three year, five year studies? No, they were usually about 18 months. Wow, so really short. So
yeah, you could definitely make the case that that's again, just going back to the disease I
understand best. That's like saying we're going to take patients who, you know, have the most
aggressive form of cardiovascular disease. They've got multi vessel disease, huge stenosis,
you know, vulnerable plaque everywhere. And for 18 months, let's see what happens if we
employ lipid lowering therapy and we see that it has kind of a minor impact and you can make the
case. Well, you probably should have done it earlier and for longer. Right. And well, I mean,
the earlier is definitely key. I mean, I don't know that. So well, yes, for longer,
but not in that particular group, you know, there would not have been any
benefit, I don't think, to doing a three or four year study of that moderate, you know,
moderately demented group with these therapies because they were just going to keep getting worse.
You know, that's the thing they kept getting. They were their disease had was progressing. The
train had left the station and it was going to do what it was going to do. So, you know, traditionally
18 months has been a standard length for Alzheimer's trials because it's the amount of time,
you know, you have to remember these trials cost lots of money. You know, people often complain
and rightfully so that certain drugs are extremely expensive. And, you know, obviously you coming from
Canada have a whole different perspective on that than, you know, the American side of it,
you know, where it's just all about money all the time. That being said, you know,
there is some validity to the price of some of these drugs because of the vast amount of resources
that have been spent. You know, it takes on average, I read a statistic that, you know,
10 to 15 years and a billion dollars for any one drug to get from development and discovery to
FDA approval. That's right. It's probably it's probably higher today. Actually, it's probably
higher today. Actually, it's probably closer to about 1.3, 1.4 billion. And you're absolutely
correct. So if you look at that pipeline of 120 odd drugs, again, it's not going to be 120 billion
because some of them will get, you know, weeded out in phase one. But there's no question that
the United States subsidizes the rest of the world in drug pricing. So what if there's basically
an understanding quid pro quo in my mind that says, look, in exchange for having the best drugs
available first, you will pay a premium for the development of the drug. That's effectively what's
happening in the U.S. Yeah. And then it's also important to point out, though, that for every
one drug that makes it all the way through, there's literally four or five thousand that don't,
you know, some get squashed in the very beginning and some make it to animal models, you know, but,
you know, so so it's a very, very, very expensive process for the drug companies. And so
by going back to my point, you know, they have to find that sweet spot in terms of length of a trial
that will sort of be worth their investment, but at the same time not spend extra resources,
but also give the information that they need. And so knowing how Alzheimer's progresses,
particularly in that group, you know, 18 months is a spot where you're going to see, OK, so in 18
months, if they're better, well, that's crazy because that doesn't happen. If they're stable,
well, that's good because it's usually there's some drop off in that period of time. And if
they're worse, then clearly it's not working. Yeah. And if you if you look at the oncology
playbook here, you understand the challenge of this space, which is you have the same economics,
right, which is a billion to a billion and a half to get a drug from inception into a clinic.
And truthfully, you have kind of a gray area of utility, right? There are drugs that are
getting approved that make very little sense. So they extend median survival by two months
without extending overall survival. And they're going to cost one hundred thousand dollars and
we can debate the merits of that. And that's where you'll see differences between the U.S.,
the U.K., Canada, et cetera. Right. But you see, one of the issues here that I find most interesting
and I'm not familiar, I'm not as familiar with it in Alzheimer's disease, but I'm intimately
familiar with it in cardiovascular disease and in oncology is the importance of patient
selection and study design. It's everything. Right. So to me, let's use cardiovascular disease
in an example. I always found the Fourier trial and the Odyssey trial, which were the two major
trials used to test the PCSK9 inhibitors. I found them to be very elegant and very complimentary.
So the Fourier trial took patients who were maximally statinized. These are patients that
had an LDL cholesterol that was typically south of 70 milligrams per deciliter or in about that
neighborhood. So these are people at the fifth percentile of LDL cholesterol and then added a
PCSK9 inhibitor to them. The study was stopped after two to three years. I believe it was
intended for four or five and it demonstrated an improvement. And again, in cardiovascular disease,
what are your outcomes? It's usually MACE, a major adverse cardiac event. So heart attack,
stroke, revascularization, death. So you have heart outcomes. That's an important thing,
right? They're not tracking. Nobody cares how much it lowers your cholesterol. The biomarker
means nothing anymore. It's only, does it prevent an outcome? You had a complimentary study in
Odyssey, which did not take heavily statinized patients, but patients who were, if I recall,
equally at risk. And again, it was major adverse cardiac event. And there's all, they usually
include all cause mortality. This is a challenge that I see in Alzheimer's diseases. And I'm, I'm
saying this not as an absolute challenge, just as a challenge to me as an outsider, I struggle to
understand these endpoints sometimes. And I just don't understand how valid they are. Not because
I think that the people measuring them are nefarious, but because they just seem very soft
and squishy at times, like, well, did the person cognitively get better? Maybe yes, no, I'm not sure.
And yeah, we use this test and it has a five point scoring system and we square the boxes and such and
such. But in the end, it's a harder disease to measure definitive outcomes in the, to your point,
at the duration of time we want to study them. So that's a lot to unpack. And, and I guess where
I'm going with that is how do you think about, let's start with one element. How do you think
about patient selection? Who is the right patient to be studying? Where on that progress from
preclinical to MCI to disease? I think we've ruled out bucket three, right? I think we're,
if I've heard you earlier, it's we don't want to be studying patients for disease modification
that already have significant dementia. So are you, would you say the same is true of MCI and we
should be looking at the preclinical or what the, which means we by definition are making
an imaging diagnosis or is it early MCI? So I think, you know, the jury's still out with regard
to MCI. There still are a lot of trials and I think there may be opportunity for mild cognitive
impairment as well as mild dementia to benefit from these disease modifying therapies.
You know, if we're looking at a cure, because that's what everybody wants, right? A cure.
I think the prevention trials are really going to be the way to go because then you're
stopping it before it starts. You know, we know that these anti-amyloid drugs
remove amyloid. We know this. They successfully reduce amyloid to a point where
people go from having positive amyloid pet to negative amyloid pet.
In fact, we had an occasion once where we had a patient who was in a trial, an anti-amyloid
trial for some time and then that study stopped and then she wanted to enroll in another study
and it was actually an anti-tau antibody and they did allow people with previous exposure to
anti-amyloid drugs after a certain window of time. Sometimes they don't.
So when she had her new amyloid pet for that study, she screen failed because she was amyloid
negative. And so, you know, that's been shown in numerous trials with more than one compound that
it definitely removes amyloid. So if you look at the pet outcomes for these drugs, they're great.
What are the clinical outcomes?
Yeah. Just like you said, nobody cares about a marker or cholesterol. You care about the
clinical outcomes and symptoms. And so none of that matters if you're removing amyloid,
if the people aren't any better or if they're continuing to get worse. You know, that's what
was happening with the mild to moderate group, you know, the original solenazumab trials.
You know, people just kept getting worse because they already had enough neurodegeneration and
other pathology now going on in the brain that whether the amyloid was there anymore didn't
matter. I do think in MCI that there's opportunity for these drugs to work and, you know, the
FDA is considering the adjucanumab data right now. There was just last or actually at the beginning
of this week data for Donanumab, which is a Lilly study that came out at the ADPD meeting showing
that it met endpoints on almost all of the primary and secondary outcome measures that they had set
forth. So, yeah, I wouldn't rule out the MCI group at this point. But in terms of sort of the ideal,
I think prevention ultimately is going to be the way to go as far as disease modification. And,
you know, just like you'll go to the doctor and see you have high cholesterol and intervene then
before you get to these, you know, bad cardiac or stroke outcomes, you know, you'll go to the doctor
and perhaps have a test that shows you have amyloid and then intervene then so that you don't then
develop cognitive impairment. That's our hope and our goal. Yeah, that makes hands down the most
sense. And again, I'm obviously stating the obvious, but the more we can model this after a disease
where we've had unbelievable success like cardiovascular disease, rather than a disease
where we've had very little success, which is cancer, because we have to wait until you have
cancer. Now, of course, I think liquid biopsies are going to change that. And we are really on
the cusp of that. In fact, that's going to be a super exciting discussion we're going to have on
the podcast in the next, you know, couple of months. So the goal, of course, is to turn cancer
into cardiovascular disease instead to turn Alzheimer's disease into the same. So one of the
most promising versions of these monoclonal antibodies to amyloid is Atacanumab, which is
a drug manufactured by a company called Biogen. And it's been in the news a lot lately.
I think for several reasons. One is it's a drug that made it to phase three.
And it was running two parallel studies, Emerge and what was the other one called? Engage. Yeah.
And to my understanding, very little difference between them, obviously different sites and maybe
a slight difference in some dosing, but effectively the same trial, which is not uncommon for how a
drug like this would be tested in phase three because of the size that you need to have of the
number of participants you need, where I think it got interesting was how the results were
interpreted for the two arms and then what a reevaluation looked like. So do you want to
explain the story of, I guess let's start with the beginning. This was a well done study in that
it had, you know, pre-specified endpoints. And that's very important for people when they're
evaluating clinical trials. You have to pre-specify your primary endpoint. You got to call your shot
before you, you know, go to bat. Right. What was the endpoint in this study and how did they go
about evaluating? Honestly, I don't remember what the specific primary outcome measure was.
It was cognitive, but it wasn't like, it wasn't an imaging study. It was a cognitive study, right?
I don't remember if it was the 8S cog or not, to be perfectly honest. The story of
the Embark and Engage studies is, I'm sorry, the Emergent Engage. We're doing Embark now,
which is the follow-up for the people that had previously been in Emergent Engage.
So the bottom line is that the study was going along and at some point they do what's called
a futility analysis to see if it's worthwhile to continue spending their resources on
the drug or to abandon it. And when they did the futility analysis, they were not meeting
their primary endpoints. But after further analysis and looking at sort of a cohort of people who had
dose-escalated kind of in the interim, they realized that the people in the high-dose group
actually were meeting those endpoints. And so they went back and looked at all the data
and in a very unusual turn of events, they were like, actually, we were wrong and this is helping.
And so they ended up going back and putting people back in the study who had previously been on it
in this new Embark study, as well as submitting to the FDA for approval.
And the numbers aren't necessarily relevant, but the highest dose, if I recall, was like 10
milligrams per kilogram. And there was also a stratification for APOE and non-APOE,
which I didn't understand because they were giving a lower dose to the APOE-4 carriers than
a higher dose. And are they currently just giving everybody the highest dose in the revisit trial?
I don't know if I'm allowed to talk about the current protocol.
Okay.
That's confidential or not.
But what's interesting is that there's something that's going to happen on June 7th. What is that?
What are we waiting for on June 7th?
Well, I just want to go back and touch on a point that you mentioned. One of the reasons that they
give the APOE-4 carriers a lower dose is because of the risk of ARIA or amyloid-related imaging
abnormalities. So we know that with these amyloid drugs that remove amyloid, we often will see
changes in MRI, either edema or swelling or microhemorrhages. So RE for edema,
REH for hemorrhages, often asymptomatic. But certainly, we're very significant in some of the
earlier iterations of anti-amyloid drugs and drug trials that were going on. And there was a distinct
difference between the risk of ARIA and E4 carriers versus not. So that would have been the reason at
the beginning that they would have been on a lower dose. I believe, and I don't want to speak
incorrectly, but I do believe that subsequently they did fine with this trial. And I think that
they did fine with this drug that that was not happening. So they may have allowed the E4 carriers
to go to the higher dose. Yeah, there was a protocol amendment. They did amend the protocol
for E4 to go to 10 mgs per KIG. So June 7th. Yeah, what's going to happen? What are we waiting
for on June 7th? Everybody's anticipating. Yeah, so the FDA is supposed to render a decision about
whether they're going to approve this or not. And what did the advisory board say earlier in
the year? There were two different things. So there was one group that recommended approval,
and then there was another panel that was like, yeah, the data is not so compelling
and recommended not. So we really do not know which way the FDA is going to go.
There is a very large push on the part of families and patients who have gone without
any new treatment for this disease for almost 20 years to say, it's better than nothing. Please
approve it. I know, you know, from an advocacy standpoint, there's a lot of that going on.
Then there's some very strict science people who are saying, if the data doesn't support it,
don't do it. So we really have no idea which way they're going to go.
Let's assume the FDA concludes that there's insufficient data and they do not approve it.
Does anything prevent biogen from, aside from the destruction of shareholder value,
is anything preventing biogen from running another clinical trial at phase three to try to seek
approval with a better protocol that might be able to yield a better outcome?
No, there's nothing preventing that. Obviously, it's just a question of having the funds and
inclination to do so. But that's, I think you touched on a little bit earlier, part of the
problem that we have is that the outcomes, the primary outcome measures for these trials
aren't that great. These are sort of long standing, well established cognitive tests,
but how much they move in the right period of time may not be as good as we hope. The ones that
focus on the CDR, the clinical dementia rating, there is a subjective component to that because
that's not just a test, that is an interview and a rating that a rater makes based on
what both the patient says and what an informant says.
The CDR is the primary endpoint for this drug.
Okay, so and that's the thing. I mean, the CDR has...
I think it has six dimensions to it, but it's subjective, as you said.
It is subjective and prone to bias from, let's say, a depressed caregiver who sees everything
worse than it is. There have been studies looking at that kind of thing and a lot of times,
a caregiver who is highly stressed and depressed will over report symptoms
leading to higher scores on the sum of boxes. So the CDR looks at memory, it looks at judgment,
it looks at home and hobbies and some other things. A rater will interview the subject,
well they'll interview the informant and then they'll interview the subject and
then they'll ask about recent events, tell me something you did last week, tell me something
you did in the last month. And then part of the rating is based on what the patient remembers
compared to what the informant said. And there is that sort of intangible part where if you're
kind of on the fence, you could go either way, even though there are very well-established
scoring parameters and hours of training videos and things on how to do the CDR,
there still is that sort of, eh, it feels like a one or it feels like a 0.5 that plays into it,
that's not just an objective measure like an LDL level.
That to me is the biggest challenge here is cancer progresses quickly enough and at least
currently we study it in a very clear sense. I mean, we can debate that there are actually
some limitations in how we study cancer progression and that's been, I think, gamified a little too
much. Cardiovascular disease we've already discussed. It seems that the best hope for
a disease in which subjective evaluation is so important is to have biomarkers that are
so predictive of clinical outcome that you can rely on those in combination potentially with
a clinical evaluation. I don't think we're, you're not gonna, you can't do a long enough study to get
hard outcomes. So, I mean, there's really two enormous challenges in drug development for
Alzheimer's disease. There's the technical challenge of how do you develop a good enough drug
and then there's the operational challenge of how do you actually study it.
And, you know, so going back to your question, you know, Biogen could very well go back and do
another study and use a different primary outcome measure, whether it's the ADAS-CoG or there is a
cognitive composite score that was recently used by ESI for a different trial. You know, they got
a lot of flack for it because people accuse them of kind of cherry picking things that
worked, but at the same time, as you also mentioned earlier, these were things that were
predefined. You know, it's not like they went and just chose the best things or the things that
showed change. They defined in the beginning that these are the measures that we're going to look
at and made this cognitive composite based on years and thousands of patients worth of data
showing what specific cognitive tests may be better predictors or may change more during a
certain period than those that won't. So, you know, I personally didn't have a problem with that
cognitive composite because I thought that it was a thoughtful way of kind of rethinking
and getting good data that might be useful. You know, the ADAS-CoG is just so ingrained in this
field and although it certainly has a lot of utility, it also has limitations. And so,
finding some of these better objective primary outcome measures from a cognitive standpoint,
in addition to the biomarkers, I think certainly will be useful for drugs moving forward.
So, I want to kind of close our discussion, Amanda, with something you alluded to earlier, which is
what does it mean to undergo healthy aging? It's inevitable. We're all aging. We're all
going to die. And unfortunately, many of us are going to die with some form of cognitive
impairment, even if it is not dementia. So, in your 20 years of practice, what wisdom have you
gleaned and what might someone who is, you know, seemingly far from that learn?
So, you know, it's interesting and I knew we were going to talk about this, so I've actually been,
you know, more contemplative in the last few days kind of thinking about it. You know, there are a
lot of different frameworks for aging, you know, the stuff that we learned in psychology class and,
you know, some of these classic structured approaches to aging, both psychological and
sociological. But, you know, I've never wanted to kind of fit into one neat category. I like to kind
of be eclectic and take a little bit of this and a little bit of that, you know. But at the end of
the day, you know, it really has to do with, you know, how people see themselves, how people
interact with the world, what kind of relationships they have, how able they are to let go of things
that they've lost, and, you know, how able they are to focus on the positive. I think that's where I
see people struggle the most as a psychiatrist and people develop the most depression is when
they spend so much time looking down the road at what's going to happen or what might happen
that they can't enjoy now. And, you know, it's very interesting. I can have two patients,
you know, maybe both of whom were marathon runners and now both have Parkinson's disease.
And while they both have disability, one of them sort of centers their whole identity around this
new disability and focuses on the fact, well, I used to be able to do this, I used to be able to do
that. Now I can't do this, I can't do that. Whereas the other one is like, well, okay, so I can't run
anymore, or I might fall if I go to the beach, but I can still enjoy the sunset in a special
wheelchair, or, you know, focusing on what I still can do and trying to make the most of each day.
And those are the people that I think age successfully even in the face of having illness.
You know, we all will age, we all have
changes in our physical strength and our, you know, mental alertness and, you know, acuity,
but it doesn't necessarily disable us. And even if it does, the key for me really is how
that shapes our attitude or how much we let it affect our attitude.
I want to run an idea by you and I'm curious as to your thoughts. I describe health span or quality
of life as having broadly three dimensions, a physical one, a cognitive one and an emotional one.
And I think it's safe to say that as sure as God made little green apples, the first two decline
with age. Now, if you're really lucky, they don't decline too, too much, assuming you live a long
life, right? So if you talk about someone who's going to live into their nineties, there's a
physical decline that is undeniable. Even if you are fortunate to be spared dementia, there is a
cognitive decline, but not it doesn't have to be that sharp. And for the lucky ones you do here,
you know, you got the Charlie Munger's of the world who are literally in their nineties and appear to
be just as sharp as ever. But the one that doesn't appear to have an age component to it is the
emotional one. And so the question I've been pondering is are the most miserable people going
to be the people whose identity is wrapped up in the things that inevitably decline? And therefore,
should we be putting more of our identity in the one thing that really has no tie to age, which is
basically our emotional health, which I believe is most a function of the quality of our relationship.
So a person who has wonderful quality relationships is generally an emotionally healthy person.
And that doesn't mean it's a person who doesn't get sad and a person who doesn't get angry and a
person that doesn't struggle, but, you know, they have an emotional strength to them that I think
comes from this tethering to other people. So does that framework make sense?
Absolutely. I think it's spot on and exactly true. You know, that is so important in terms of,
you know, well-being is having people feeling loved, feeling that there are people you can rely on,
feeling that there are people who can share experiences with you. You know, social isolation
is a huge problem for some people and a definite determinant of quality of life versus not.
I definitely see that people that struggle the most are the ones that are constantly
comparing themselves to their former selves. You know, I used to be able to do this. I used to be
able to do that. I used to, you know, if I did that, I would just be, you know, hiding under my
covers. I mean, I didn't used to need these, but I do. So it's like, well, I might as well buy
cute ones because you got to have them, you know. And so it's so hard though, Amanda. Like I,
you know, I think about it like we're about the same age and it's true. We've already experienced
a decline, but it's going to get steeper, right? Like it's when you look at what it means to be
90 for most people, at least it's going to be a far greater loss over the previous two decades
than maybe we've experienced in the previous two decades. There's a real non-linearity to it, but
I guess it's as good a time as any to begin rehearsing that. And I've been very deliberate
about this for the past two to three years in anticipation of hopefully a long life,
which, because, you know, look, I think there was a day when all of my identity was wrapped up
in these things that are inevitably going to decline and none of it was wrapped up in the other.
And I'm undergoing an asset reallocation, which I guess the point is we should be doing this when
we still have a chance to. No, you're absolutely right. And that actually is a great point,
not just doing the asset reallocation, but just doing things when you still have a chance. You
know, one of the things I, you know, I, as we were talking earlier, another big thing that I think
contributes to quality of life and you sort of, whether people age well or not is regret and how
much regret they live with. And so very often I see people who come in and, you know, have worked
really hard throughout their lives and put off this and put off that. And we're just about to
retire and do XYZ. And then now, well, now I have this devastating disease. And so, you know, part of
what I do is educating them. Well, you can still do XYZ. You just might have to do it a little bit
differently. But it also, I mean, personally has affected me. You know, my happy place is the beach.
I love the beach. I have dreamed my whole life of being able to see, you know, the horizon from my bed.
And so, you know, as soon as we were able to afford it, we got, you know, a condo at the beach. It was
old, built in 1972 and, you know, quite frankly hideous at the time when we got hit. But
it meant that I could wake up and see the Gulf of Mexico. And, you know, we, especially through
the pandemic, we've gone there almost every weekend just because what else are you going to do?
And, you know, but that's something I learned from my patients. You know, don't wait. Don't wait until
I retire to get that beach condo because I might not be able to use it. You know, I'm living now,
so do it now. And that's, you know, A, something I've learned and B, something I really try to
impart to these people that are coming in that sort of feel like that's a hard stop. Like, oh,
I can't do this now because of this diagnosis. And it's like, well, no, you still can. You just
have to be a little more careful or you can still take that cruise, but just where, you know, I
actually, anytime I go to a meeting, I haven't been to a meeting in, you know, a year and a half, but,
you know, I save all of my name tag, you know, lanyard things and I give them out to people.
I say, here, take this on your cruise and just put your room number or cabin number or whatever in it
and your cell phone number. So if, you know, your loved one wanders off on a ship,
at least they can call you or they can find out what cabin you're in. And so it's making those
adjustments, but still, you know, doing the things that you enjoy with the people you enjoy doing it
with. I think that's incredibly well said, Amanda. You know, I've really enjoyed our discussion today.
And I know that everyone listening to this has as well, because I just think people are becoming
more and more aware of this condition. And as you said, it's less taboo. It's something that
people are talking about. And I do believe that people are cautiously optimistic that the next
decade looks better than the last decade in terms of actual medical treatments we have.
I'm still firmly in the camp of Richard, which is not to say that you're not saying that,
that says, look, prevention is the best medicine for chronic disease, be it cardiovascular disease,
cancer or Alzheimer's disease. But inevitably, a number of us are going to slip through the
fingers and the grasp of prevention and are going to need treatments. And I'm hopeful that these
monoclonal antibodies that can target amyloid beta or tau can be a step in the right direction.
So thanks very much for all of your insights today.
Oh, my pleasure. And of course, exercise.
You don't need to tell this audience.
No, I know. That's what I'm saying. Even if you've passed the point of prevention,
you know, and I know you've gotten into this in other podcasts, but, you know, the data,
the growing body of data shows that even in people who have cognitive impairment or have
full-blown dementia, aerobic activity can actually improve scores on cognitive testing.
You know, some of the research that some of our colleagues do through all of these prevention
trials and then through these intervention trials in MCI and AD, Silver Sneakers Program at the YMCA,
Laura Baker at Wake Forest is doing a lot of great stuff with this and showing that even if you have
dementia, your scores will go up if you do aerobic exercise. So I'm glad you said that's what gets me
going in the afternoon. All right, Amanda. Well, thanks so much. And I hope you get to see the
sunset this weekend. Thank you. I really appreciate it. It was great talking with you.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper,
person thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday
through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not
getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head
over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.