Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Pat. Thanks so much for sitting down with me today. I've been wanting to sit down with you
for quite some time. And I know we've been rescheduled and rescheduled on several occasions,
and between one thing or another, it took a while, but I am pretty confident it's going to be worth
the wait. How are you? I'm good. Thank you. I'm very happy to be here. That's something that I have
a lot of pleasure talking about oral health with MDs. That's my life is trying to do this connection.
So I'm very excited to be here. It's going to be interesting because I don't know much about what
to do. And I think I can bring something new about dentistry and oral health and things,
which is so important. Yeah. Well, I think it is important, and that's certainly why I've wanted
to talk about this for a while. And I've been trying to figure out who would be the right person
to speak with. And you came very highly recommended because I think it's actually a very
underappreciated part of health. I think it's easy to think of the mouth as this sort of thing. And
we go to the dentist and hopefully we don't have cavities. And obviously we have a whole bunch of
cosmetic concerns with the spacing of our teeth and the whiteness of our teeth, et cetera. But
I'd like to sort of tie that all together. But I want to kind of start with a little bit of your
background. So obviously you grew up in Brazil, I shouldn't say obviously, but I recognize your
accent and I know your history a little bit. When did you leave Brazil? Well, so it was a long time,
over 20 years ago. So I had my dental degree in Brazil, and then I had my specialty in
periodontics and implant dentistry, which is one of the fields that is more connected with
systemic health. I always wanted that. And then I went, I came to US mostly for personal reasons.
And I want to, and I, and my passion for research because I, that's what I do my whole life. And I
never went back because I got fascinated by the opportunities and everything that I could have
near that. Unfortunately, we don't have the resources in Brazil to do. And I'm still doing
research up to today, many years. So this is a bit off topic, but tomorrow is a very sad anniversary.
Do you remember where you were 27 years ago tomorrow? No, remind me. Sunday, May 1st,
1994 was the day I Artan Senna died. Oh, wow. I remember that day really clear. Yeah. Wow.
Where were you that morning? Were you like everybody watching the race on TV? Yes, yes.
I was still there in Brazil. Yeah. Yeah. I have so many Brazilian friends and we're just fortunate.
So many people in our life are Brazilian, our nanny is Brazilian. And I've never met a person
from Brazil who was, who was, you know, anything over about four or five years old on that day,
it's etched in their minds forever. Yeah. Well, yeah. He's a big legend. And I think in a time
that made Brazil so visible for the world and all those things. So everybody was always very proud
of him. Yeah. Well, he's my personal hero. And so for you today, I wore one of my Senna bracelets.
So let's start a little bit with tooth anatomy. Unfortunately, I have teeth that my wife refers
to as a Tia teeth, which she jokingly means like I just have genetically horrible teeth. Like I
always seem to be at the dentist for something. Something's always going wrong. So I'd like to
think she's exaggerating a little bit, but, you know, there was a period in my life, unfortunately,
of maybe 10 years when I didn't go to the dentist once. And I think I'm, I sort of ended up paying
a bit of a price for that going on, which sounds like a stupid thing to say, imagine somebody not
going to the dentist for 10 years, but that's sort of what happened for largely much of my medical
school and residency. I just never made the commitment to go still brushed my teeth and did
all that stuff, but obviously wasn't getting regular checkups. And now that I find myself
taking dental care so seriously, the first thing I realized is I had to understand the anatomy,
you know, I had to understand what they meant by pulp and dentin and all of these things.
But I think it might make sense to give people a decent overview over the semantics of the tooth
at the individual level, and then sort of at the level of how all of the teeth fit into the mouth.
Can we start with something like that? Yeah, yeah, yeah. Of course, I think which is strictly
important, they all have a reason to be. So you have 32 teeth in your mouth. All of them, of course,
they have very specific functions. So if you think about the anatomy of the tooth, you can
think about one unique tooth only, which is the anatomy of you have the root caries. You have,
if you think about between what you see in the oral cavity and what you don't see is like the
crown and the roots, as you see in this figure. And then you have all the parts that surrounded
the tooth, they call the supports where the seat sits on top, which is the periodontum, which is
another very complex system as well. So, and then if you think about this whole system together,
and you have multiplied that by 32, then you have this amount of very unique set of different,
think about individuals inside your mouth and they all have very specific functions.
Can you pull that slide up again of the individual tooth? I have some questions about that.
Yeah, the first thing that jumps out to me is that there's a vascular supply
that is quite high in the tooth. If I didn't know better, I would assume that when I look
in my mouth and I see that white crown, that everything inside it is a bone. In other words,
I would assume the entire tooth is an avascular amorphous thing that serves one purpose and one
purpose alone, which is just to basically break down food. So why is it that this tooth is so
much more complex than just having enamel? Why does it have this dentin and this pulp?
Yeah, it's a very complex structure and it's for a reason. So the enamel, it's minerals,
so it's a very hard surface. It's actually the hardest surface on the human body. It's the enamel.
And then under the enamel, you have the cement and then the dentin, sorry, the dentin and then
I have the pulp and the cement is everything part of the pitot don't turn. But there's three
layers of the tooth itself. The enamel protects the underneath layers. The second one that you see
is just like cushion and has a lot of tubules as well. So it's hypersensitive. And then the heart
of the tooth is actually the pulp. So it's high. You see a lot of nerves and they all connect to
the body. That's why you have a lot of tooth pain is one of the most detrimental type of pains that
we have because you have all those nerves connecting everywhere. And then you have the
bone as well. And the ligaments around the roots, they protect, it's that cushion that protects
against the impact and it gives you all that biological symbiotic so you can chill and you
can function. But why is it that we need a nervous connection to the tooth? Because
I understand that like if you had a dental implant, obviously you've given up the nerve and vascular
supply to the tooth, correct? So we can still carry out the function of breakdown without that or?
Well, so the first signs when you have a tooth loss, right, for example, you start with the decay
and then if decay takes the pulp, then you have to excise the pulp and you can still preserve the
boot. So the main thing that we think, the way we want to think in dentistry is that you want to
preserve health as much as you want because you want to preserve function. So you don't want to
extract teeth because teeth, they have a very precise reason because they need to hold this face,
you need to chill. There's just a lot of things that that's part of the mouth. So you need to
have the teeth. So you can do a root canal or if you don't have any more of the crown because you
lost to the decay, you can take it out the crown, you can put some metals and then you can put it
in a trick with your crown. The moment that you lose is infected and you have to extract the whole
tooth, then you need to put the implants on. But not that the implants is better, it will never be
better than your natural function in your teeth because it's a metal and it has many other issues
and we still have periodontitis which is an infection of the implant. It doesn't mean that,
oh, I'm going to take my teeth out and I'm never going to get inflammation, periodontal disease.
It's not true. You still have that. I think my question is more that if you have an implant
and therefore you have a denervated tooth, it seems to still be able to carry out the function
of breaking down food. I think the thing I'm trying to understand is you pointed out something
that unfortunately most people listening to this can relate to, which is dental pain is some of the
worst pain in the world. And it speaks to, I think, that highly, highly innervated pulp that
you showed. I'm trying to understand what the function is of having something so highly innervated.
Like for example, our fingers are highly innervated because they serve such an important function.
Our ability to have fine motor control with our fingers is why we have so much innervation here.
So why is it that we have so much innervation in a surface beneath this enamel, which as you said,
is the hardest surface in the body? What is the purpose that that innervation serves?
That's an interesting question. It's the viral part of the tooth that preserves blood flow and
keeps the tooth alive. And it's a connection, now that I'm thinking through, it's how you protect.
So it's a connection with your immune response if you have, let's say, if you have a
caries infection. So probably that's how the body tries to be able to respond and fight against
infection information. So the moment you don't have that anymore, so it's just a dent.
I see. I see. That's a good point. So you're saying-
That's what I think now that we're talking.
So maybe it serves as such an early warning indicator as a breach of a barrier, basically,
an important barrier. Okay. That's interesting. I just have to tell you, having been through so many
miserable dental experiences, I've often cursed our evolutionary gods for giving us so much
innervation in that tooth. So you've already started to talk a little bit about the pathology
that can go wrong here. Before we do that, I want to get a little bit more an understanding of the
function. Can you show me again that slide that has all of the teeth and maybe explain-
Yeah, sure.
How different teeth serve a different purpose in the mouth?
So technically you have the incisors. So you have four of them in each part of your jaw,
in the maxilla and the mandible. Then you have the canines. There are another four. So the incisors
is mostly in your mouth where you can cut your food in any animal. That's how you bite and how
you separate pieces of fruit. And then you have the canine that is a very strong, that's the
longer root that you have in your mouth that's chewier so you can see animals when they are eating
meat and all of that. You tend to go to the side because it's a very strong anatomy that they have.
And then you have four, we call premolars or bicuspids. So that's where you start to break
down the food that you eat to tear them apart. And then the molars, they do the whole
through duration. That's where you have to chew. And when I always talk about chew is because
when the digest process starts in the mouth, so it's very important that people chew their food
and in contact with the saliva and all the nutrients that we have. But it's a completely
different subject talking about saliva, but it's mainly to chew your food, to start the digestive
product so then you can get most of the nutrients out of your food. Now, looking at the lower part
of this figure, it seems that the different teeth have different numbers of roots. Is that correct?
Yes, that's correct. So incisors and laterals and cream molars, the one in front,
they have single group. Then if you go to premolars, they will have two and some premolars
itself, they might have three or four depending on how big the chew is. So it's a much more complex
because they are much more strong and they have to get much more pressure and to function. So they
need to have much more sustainability so they can chew and treat our food.
I see. So that actually probably explains another reason why these things are innervated,
which is the harder they have to oppose other teeth, so the molars would have the greatest
opposition to another tooth. Then they need greater sensory input to understand the relative
spacing and force. Would that be part of the difference as well?
As well, you think in your mouth it's like a bridge. It has to be very well balanced. The
occlusion needs to be perfect because then you're going to hurt all your ligaments and cause
inflammation in your mouth. So it's a very elaborated system. If you think about the occlusion,
they connect. They have to be very perfect aligned. If you start having issues like your teeth,
they don't have a perfect occlusion. You start losing your vertical occlusion, then you have
a lot of other issues like pain on your face and headaches. There are many other issues that can
happen if you don't have a good function in your mouth.
Okay. By the way, I learned the hard way that I have four roots in my molars, not three,
because I've had two root canals and the first one, they missed one of their roots. They only
went after three roots and I still had endless persistent pain until they figured out I went to
finally then see an endodontist who realized I had a very hidden fourth root. But we'll get to
root canals later, my least favorite procedure in the world. So let's talk about what a healthy
mouth looks like. You alluded to saliva. I assume that that plays a very important role in oral
health and I assume it does something beyond lubricating food. Does it play another role?
It's true. So the oral cavity is a very complex system. So if you think that you have teeth,
you have the gums, you have the gingido cravutua fluid that is open and allows the bacteria to go
in and out. You have the tongue, which is a completely different texture structure. You
have the throat, which is entrance to your body. So all this whole complex system, they need to
live in a very organized way. And on top of that, you have the saliva. Saliva is, again, we could
have a completely other podcast just about saliva, but in the context where they preserve health,
because we know today that people with dry mouth, if you have, I treat patients with radiation,
they're going through radiation ecology. We're going to talk, we can talk about that later, but
the moment you dry your mouth for any reason, systemic conditions, medication,
who causes dry mouth, and many of them, the causes or toxicities, your cancer care,
radiation drives mouth. It's a completely shift of the oral microbiome in your mouth
because saliva protects. It's that bio-food that's constant washing and flushing your mouth and
maintaining a very omniostasis on the microbiome as well. It prevents GDRs on the
oral microbiome. So this whole complex needs to be balanced on every single aspect that we look.
You need to have the teeth, you need to brush, you need to have a lot of saliva, and you need
to eat well. So it's a combination of a lot of factors that makes people say to be in health
when you look at oral health, but the primary is so simple. It's actually oral hygiene.
If you brush your teeth, you're going to be technically, you preserve a little bit more
of health than people who don't. I want to go back to what you said about the dysbiosis and
the microbiome of the mouth. So my recollection is that the mouth actually has a significant amount
of anaerobic bacteria. Is that correct? Well, they're both. You have anaerobic, you have
facutative bacteria. They can play both roles because it's so strong, they can change,
but we have over 700 different bacteria than these in a perfect symbiotic
habitat in our kingdom. And they can live really well with the host without causing disease
if you can maintain the state of health. Because in the past, people think that
what causes disease or disease is this specific bacteria, but it's not true.
We all have all those bacteria in your mouth. It's indigenous to you. It's not that it's from
something external. You have that. Their normal habitat is your mouth. But for some reason,
you don't stop rushing or you start taking medication and your mouth becomes dry. You have
a health condition that allows inflammation to be more prevalent. All those things might change the
cognitive environment. And that allows some bad bacteria to grow and supersede the good ones.
And then that's what happens with the dysbiotic. So we talk about two things, abundance,
changes in abundance and diversity, which is allowing bad bacteria to flourish and suppress
the good ones that helps us preserving health. So that's mainly what's going on.
Of course, there are the co-polarities.
So in an ideal state, directionally, what amount of bacteria are aerobic, anaerobic, and facutative?
What's the approximate distribution in a relatively healthy mouth?
It's probably half and a half between aerobic and anaerobic and another maybe 30 to 40 percent of
them. They can play both roles. But those, let's say, a clear example, and we can talk about that
in a completely different section, but even children. When I did my studies with the twins,
and then we asked them to stop brushing for two weeks, all the periodontal pathogens,
pitin jubile, chidintrachol for cytos, that we only see in adults with periodontal disease,
in two weeks, they became abundant in their mouth. So they were there that I couldn't see
a baseline. The more that they stopped flossing, they became abundant. So they are there, but they
never cause disease unless you have a shift on their own microbiome.
Let's talk about that study. How old were these twins?
So let me go back. It was a long time ago. That's when I first started my research,
because I always had an interest in dental care. There were between 12 and maybe 16 years old. I
wanted to have adolescence because they have, that's where they don't like to brush the floss.
You know, it's a very hard population to do that. So what we did, we got, so when you do
studies, and I'm going to talk a little bit about the twins. So I understand why we use the twins.
So they're the perfect model to do clinical trials. That's my passion is clinical trials,
because they share, especially on that age, the same households, the same, there is no confounders,
right? We don't need to adjust for age. The identity between do they even need to adjust for
gender because they share the same sex and they share 100% of the genes. So when you look at
Mona's, I got it and guys are got it twins. The Mona's I got it twins, they share 100% of their
genes. It's almost a perfect clones of each other. Right. And to your point, as adolescents,
they're still in the same house. It would be different if you did this with 30 year old
monozygotic twins, because at least there might be some environmental differences, right?
And the environment takes place and then a lot of no epigenetics might change even mutations.
And then when you look at the dizygotic twins, they're 50, 50, they share 50% of their genes.
It's the same as two siblings. So there's two ways that you can do studies with twins. You either
get the twin set, and then you do treatment A and B to see response to treatment because they're
very similar or the way I like when you want to see traits and how a trait can modify by genetics
or environmental factors, you get the same set of twin and you give the same drug medication or
treatment. Because then when you look before and after, if you don't see, if you see that the
identical twins, they behave in the same way, you're going to say, well, genetics modulate that trait.
But then if you look at both of them and say they're all over the place, they behave in the same
way as the identical and the fraternal twins, they say, well, here the environment is playing
a big role because genetics are not holding anymore, right? So when we do this flossing in twins,
that's how we did the study. We got, we didn't want to give separate treatments for the twins
because they're going to the same house. So, and I did very controlled. So for two weeks,
we asked the twins to come every day to the center and I'd have the hygienists and my clinical people
trained and they do brushing and or flossing because they're two groups. One group, we wanted
them just to brush. The other group, we wanted them to brush and floss stitch. And then, so the
hygienists would floss and watch them doing, it was very supervised and controlled. And when they
go home, I asked them to do at night at home. But if you think about, that's a very hard
kungka trial to do because we had to bring the kids every single day with their parents
to the center so we could actually watch them doing the intervention. So when we finished the
study, what happens that we saw is that the children that stopped brushing the teeth,
they, we saw a changeable bleeding, not brushing, sorry, both of them were brushing. The children
that did not floss, we saw elevated levels of changeable inflammation, which was represented by
changeable bleeding. We measured changeable bleeding. And what was striking was all those
periodontal bacteria. They just came in abundance. Which ones in particular
overexpressed in the non-flossing group? It's the three big guys we call P. gingivalis,
T. denticola, A. actinomycin. They're very complicated names, but it's the top bacteria
that causes periodontal disease and change of virus we found in a very young population.
Are those all faculty of anaerobes or any of those?
Yeah, anaerobic species. Most of the bacteria, so caries and periodontal disease,
they're very similar in the way they behave and they respect us. But they can be separated. That
caries is most aerobic species because they live in the presence of the oxygen. So they're free on
the oxygen because of the aurocab
to just grow and cause inflammation and to cross, which is the end.
Just to be clear, the periodontal pocket is inside the tooth and the gingival
pocket is between the gum and the tooth? It's all the same thing. So the way
periodontal disease manifests is that first it starts with inflammation around the gums.
The way the periodontal works is that it's very serious by the periodontal ligament attaches.
If you were in health, your periodontal ligament is very healthy. It's like a muscle.
It's very tied to your tooth. If you stop brushing, which is the primary cause that
your gums get inflamed, you stop flossing or you relapse, you're going to immediately,
if you floss, you're going to see some bleeding. That's the initial stage of periodontal disease,
but it's highly modifiable. If you have only gingivitis, you can't refer to health.
So if you keep going and you continue with the traits of the disease, the ligament
is going to get inflamed and they're going to be attached from the tooth. The bacteria is going to
come in and then that whole process of inflammation, bacteria, and the deterioration of the ligaments,
that's where we form the pocket. That formulative harm to the periodontal culminates in bone loss.
So the initial, the acute periodontal disease, you're going to see someone is that they come
to your office. If they take radiographs, the gums are still somehow attached to the tooth,
very inflamed, it bleeds a lot. You touch it bleeds. But if you go and look at the
radiograph, you're going to see a big gap. The bone is all done. And then that's the pocket.
It's when the bone goes down and then if you put a probe, you're going to see three millimeters,
five millimeters, seven millimeters. It keeps going down. Now, how does that relate to the
carry? Because the carry typically occurs on the sort of top surface of the tooth typically, correct?
And everything you're describing is often actually below the gum line, yes?
Well, that's the next stage. So once the pocket gets influenced, the chronic periodontal is what
happens is that the actual of the gums. So the gums, they're going to recede and they're going
to keep going down. So it's very typical that you look, if I look at someone, I know they have
periodontal disease just by looking at their gums because we're going to see the teeth, they become
bigger. And then you're going to see the gap that you're going to expose the root. So usually the
roots of your teeth, they're not meant to be exposed because once they expose, the bacteria
can colonize and you can have root carries as well. So you can add the corona carries, which is just
on the crown of your tooth. But when the root get exposed due to periodontal disease or the forms of
trauma, malocclusion and things like that, then you can get carries to take over the root of your teeth as well.
So in children, the typical carries that we see are on the occlusive surface, correct?
Mostly, but one of the most common carries we call early childhood carries, which is
caused by baby bottle, children that breast, not the breastfeeding, but the bottle overnight and
many times a day. So it's mostly on the antineuptive. I don't know if you have a chance to see it,
but they carry the belly very rapid because the milk accumulates in that area and it's extremely
painful. It's actually one of the most common, then the disease is the most common
disease worldwide due to that carries. Everybody has dental carries.
Why did you say it doesn't happen with breast milk?
Because the breast milk, we have studies showing that it causes much less decay than
formula because every formula has sugar.
So what is it about sugar? We all grew up knowing that sugar was the worst thing for your teeth.
I've never understood or heard a, I don't want to say compelling reason that suggests I don't
believe it. I do believe it empirically, but what is it about sugar? Is it the fructose? Is it the
glucose? Is it the combination of them that leads to a rapid overgrowth of the carry causing bacteria?
It's all of them. It's
fructose, sucrose, lactose, more complex starch. They are even worse. All the drinks today,
they have added sugar, you name it. Everything has sugar, right? But the main mechanism is very
simple actually. The cardiogenic bacteria, they love sugar. They metabolize the sugar. It's actually
energy for them. Every time that they see it, so the way they have a very, they have the capability
of attaching the tooth surface, all this bacteria. So they get together, they stick to each other,
and they have the ability to secrete that extra cellular matrix that is like a glue.
We call biofilm, and that attached to the tooth. So every time that you put sugar,
they take that sugar, they metabolize that sugar as energy source, and they multiply, and they grow
with other foods that we put it on the other cavity as well. But what happens is that when
they might metabolize sugar, they secrete acids, and that acid is the one who destroyed the
normal future. So that's the cycle. That suggests that they're metabolizing
sugar anaerobically to produce lactate. If they're increasing the acidity of the environment,
presumably hydrogen ion is coming out with lactate, they're doing this not in mitochondria.
They're doing this outside of mitochondria. This is almost like the Warburg effect,
where whether oxygen is present or not, they always choose anaerobic metabolism. Do we know
if that's been looked at? Probably yes, but I don't know. I don't remember, Peter.
And also, you say sugar, but I just want to be clear. Do these bacteria have a preference for
glucose over fructose? Obviously, sucrose is both. It's an equal mix of them, but I want to get very
specific on this point. Is fructose specifically more harmful? Because if that's true, then
sucrose would be more damaging than, say, starch, which would just be pure glucose.
I think the glucose is the worst, especially when they do syrup, when they intensify and do
with higher concentrations of sugar on that. But technically, all of them
can be metabolized, even the fructose from fruits and vegetables. They can metabolize that as well.
Do you have a sense of how our species survived before we brushed our teeth?
How they survived?
Yeah. I mean, when you think about it today, if after two weeks of twins not flossing their teeth,
never mind not brushing, just two weeks of not flossing, you're able to induce significant
periodontal disease where you actually had gingival disease that would induce bleeding
in the gums. Now, let's go back in time 300 years, which our species looked the exact same
as we do 300 years ago. It's not like we're talking Neanderthals, but presumably 300 years
ago, we didn't have toothbrushes and dental floss, did we? Do we know what oral care consisted of
300 or 400 years ago?
Well, we know that 400 years ago, we see from research that people have
don't have toothbrush, they have dental care, it is not new. But if I look at populations
from developing countries, for example, I go to Africa and I do a lot of research there.
They have like some plants, they have like a stick that they use and they clean their teeth
with that three is a three that they find. So I'm assuming that people just use different devices
to clean their teeth. Because if you think about the removal of flaps is mechanical to brighten it,
you need to just drop the biofilm. What we do with brushing, we're just trying to just drop
that matrix of the biofilm, but they form again. Research shows that you clean, you can have the
mouth with zero plaque in two hours, you have them all formed again, they colonize back.
But what we're trying to do with the brushing is just instructing that we don't let that
colonize and be like overwhelmed in the other capacity.
Yeah, I just, I mean, I would assume that the food consumed somehow, even though obviously
people hundreds of years ago still consumed glucose and fructose, maybe the form in which
they consumed it was less concentrated and refined, which I suppose we know it was.
And so they had less of an insult to the tooth. But every time I've had a bad dental pain,
I've said to myself, how would I be functioning right now if this was hundreds of years ago and
I didn't have modern medicine with lidocaine and a very good dentist who could take care of this?
Like as you, again, I want to go back to this point earlier, it is the single most uncomfortable pain
imaginable. It's horrible to have pulpitus or any of these things, you can't function.
Highly preventable.
Well, yes. Yeah. We'll certainly get to that. But again, I'm just constantly amazed that our
species would have had to presumably suffer quite a bit until we figured out this ability to clean
these things. Because it's counterintuitive, I think. Now it seems obvious, but if you're
sitting in a cave 10,000 years ago, I don't know that it would have been the most obvious thing,
that you need to remove this thin film bilayer on your teeth, right?
Yeah. But I think the diet, fibers, everything was very different back there. So they with the
modernization and the amount of sugar everywhere that it looked, sometimes you can't even buy
anything because everything has sugar. I think it's a big change on the culture and what we eat,
how we do things today, I think is much worse.
So let's talk about the brushing. I once heard somebody say
that the toothpaste is far less important than the toothbrush. In other words, you could almost
brush your teeth without toothpaste, but if you did a good enough job just using a wet brush
to brush, you were getting most of the benefit. Is that true?
I tend to disagree. I think both are equally important and I'll tell why because the toothpaste
is the main source of fluoride. So the fluid protects your teeth and harden the nimbal and
protects against cavity, especially in children. It's extremely important that you look at that
exposed to fluoride. If they have high risk of care, there is other sources you can paint,
you can have varnish, you have a bunch of approaches that you can preserve oral health
in children just by brushing and fluoride. It's all about education. So in the flossing,
it's a combination. You have to clean in between your teeth, you have to clean the surface of your
teeth and I needed to put fluoride. And I'll tell you more. Now on my new clinical trial, I'm
actually brushing the oral mucosa to decontaminate against bacteria. So I still think that is another
neglected surface of the arachab which is all the oral mucosa, the tongue. Most people don't brush
the tongue and there's a lot of bacteria that accumulates in the tongue. So I think you need
to clean every single surface and just the brush itself is not going to do the job.
When you say brushing the tongue, is the purpose to remove bacteria or?
Yeah.
Okay. And what about the rest of the oral mucosa? Do you mean brushing the gums as well?
Well, technically, that's not standard of care, right? So the way research has done and proved
that you can maintain optimal oral health just by brushing teeth, by flossing really well and
having good nutrition and all those things. Of course, there are phases in your life where,
like in the specific case of my population, they're undergoing radiation ecology, they have a lot of
ulcers in their mouth and they can drink, they can eat and or they cannot brush their teeth because
it's so painful because of all the ulcers. And then there is a whole just the ozy that are
pores in the oral cavity because on top of this has radiation and a bunch of things. So on that
specific population, they need a more intense oral care program where we clean the period
down to, we clean the teeth and we contaminating and brushing the oral mucosa. So it depends on the
risks, it depends on the population that we're treating, it depends on their ability to brush.
Every oral hygiene program, I think needs to be personalized to the person, to the age, to the
risks that they have, if they have dry mouth, if they have different diseases that affect
your body. So it's a very, it's a holistic approach that not one regime would fit.
Is the importance of flossing the mechanical removal of food particles between the teeth
or is it the actual transient irritation of the gum that actually provides the benefit? Because
you can imagine a thought experiment where a person subsided on an all liquid diet, so there
would never be food particles that are between the teeth, but where they might still benefit
from flossing or more directly, they might still experience a harm from not flossing.
At least that's my hypothesis, which would suggest that the benefit of flossing
is not just the actual removal of the gross large particle, but it's the transient irritation
that's created at the gum surface. Do you have a point of view on that?
Yeah, there have been research on that. Some people on the opposite direction that my,
if you floss, for example, a mild, someone who is immune compromised, you might see nurses
and doctors saying, don't floss. Yeah, what about non-immune compromised people?
I don't think that is any harm on flossing. It might give you more resistance to those
constant exposure to bacteria, but mainly it's to clean that anaerobic bacteria that is really
hiding in between your teeth. So that's the main function of flossing. And the brushing,
if you think about brushing, it also stimulates the gum. The gum is not driven from any other
muscle or in your body because it needs to be really strong and attached around your teeth. So
the brushing as well, it helps a lot with that dynamic constant, because it massages
all your gums, your periodontum. And I believe that is a good benefit as well.
Is there a benefit or a rationale to flossing before brushing, which for some reason is the
way I've always done it. I don't know why. Yes, I love that. Because that's usually how we
recommend. Actually, I asked them, you've brushed your floss and your brush again,
if you want to be perfect. Because when you brush, you remove all the biofilm of the bacteria and
your surface of the teeth and you need to rinse your mouth well, to just get everything out. And
then you floss. But imagine if you floss and then throwing all that bacteria back in the autocavity,
that might populate and recolonize again. So that's why I say you just brush your floss.
We either rinse your mouth really well after that, or you just quick brush again. That would be the
most, the way if you want to be obsessed. And then you need to brush your tongue because bacteria,
even the ones that are flossing and throwing inside their mouth, they might just colonize
the tongue as well. Some people have fissures on their tongue and then allows them to get in.
When we do studies and I collect bacteria, for example, swabs from different parts of the mouth,
every study that we do, we collect that. Buckle left, buckle right, tongue, floor of mouth, throat,
every surface of your mouth, you find different bacteria. So your tongue has a different
colonization from your buckle, from the floor of mouth, from the throat, throat we know colonized
by bacteria and virus, the HVV virus. It's highly associated with autopharyngeal cancer. So all those
variations, they do different things, right? But you don't recommend also brushing the
buckle surfaces or other surfaces if they're also a great source of bacteria?
I don't think I can recommend because it's not a standard of care. So everything that you recommend,
for example, the trial that I'm doing right now, I'm implementing an oral care that doesn't exist.
So no one tells people, patients who are undergoing radiation treatment that they need to see a
periodontist and do a periodontal treatment every week. That's how intense it is. They come, we do,
they hold the bridesman of the periodont, we clean the oral course, we clean the teeth, that doesn't
exist. And if you ask a dentist, they're going to say, ah, why I need to do that. And that type of
procedure as well is not insured. So if you've got a patient who is undergoing radiation treatment,
they can get speech pathology. They go to see their oncologist, they go to see their nutrition.
This is all part of the healthcare system. And this is all they can charge to the insurance or
Medicaid, Medicaid. Oral health is not part of that. And I want that to be part of a magically
compromised patient that the same way that they need to see a nutrition, they need to see our
health specialists, because that's going to help them respond to the cancer treatment. They're not
going to have the burden of infection information in their mouth. And of course, they're going to
perform better. They're going to eat better because if they have ulcers, they're not going to be able
to eat. So there's a whole benefit around that. But there is no insurance would pay. And that is
not a standard of care procedure. So I'm doing the research. I'm collecting all those biomarkers.
And I want to prove the benefit of that. And once I prove the benefit of that, because now I do the
clinical trial, I might be able to push and get all the centers and other people to do it. And
that might become a standard of care for this specific population. Now, is there evidence that
cancer patients, because of two things, their immune compromise through treatment, coupled with
the increased susceptibility and the loss of immune barrier in the mouth, are actually at
greater risk of systemic infections that arise from the mouth? Yes, yes. There's a lot of research on
that. And that's what I believe as well. And when they're going on top of everything that is going
on with them, they have horrible dry mouth. Week two of radiation, they cannot, two or three,
they, some patients cannot produce saliva anymore because the radiation damage they salivate grants.
And that's changed the whole auto-microbiome allows opportunists, organisms to prevail. So they have
a lot of fungal infection because of the issue that they have with dry mouth. And that escalates
a lot of local infection and inflammation burden on the oral cavity and affects them systemically,
because I don't have data from the trial that I'm doing right now. But the reason I'm doing is that
on my small pilot that I did to lead to this large trial that I'm doing now, I saw that main
inflammatory markers. I look at saliva, inflammatory markers and microbiome before
they started the trial and three months after they completed the last dose of radiation.
And then when I look at cytokines, I sampled several cytokines in saliva, most of them,
they're completely suppressed on the oral cavity. They're all cancer patients, but the group that I
didn't do the periodontal disease, they all had even increased on those. But the ones that I did,
this very comprehensive, they all gone suppressed on the negative. So it's clearly showing that
that's something going on systemically on those patients that is just because I'm brushing your
teeth. And the way my studying started, that's why I always say that it makes me so happy when
I'm discussing oral health with MG, like you, smart that understands a lot about those things,
is that I started my life when I was at NYU and I used to work with all the radiation college and
all the surgeons that were doing surgeries on the patients. So they had diagnosed the cancer.
And because I was doing research, I would go to the OR, collect the samples and take over the
patients throughout the whole research when they're looking for oral cancers and all those things.
And I started looking at those patients' mouth and said, I can't believe that that is not a single
doctor who's looking at their mouth. They have horrible oral hygiene. They got the cancer,
they're depressed. They start radiation right after surgery, which they already can't brush
their teeth because sometimes they lose half of their jaw, they take their tongue. So they
hide their ability data, so they stop brushing and they go into radiation. When they get into
radiation, then comes with R2. Radiation also changes the microbiome and they develop horrible
ulcers in their mouth and then they become immune compromised. So it's a whole cascade of things
that happen in those patients. And then I started, one of them, I came to the oral surgery and I said,
do you mind if I start cleaning your patient's mouth? And I said, why do you want to clean?
And I said, well, I know he's going to go into radiation. Let me do a dental cleaning. I can't
look at any more the way this. I said, Pat, do it, whatever you want to do it. So I start doing my
cleaning, periodontal disease, and after I treat it, and they were going through radiation.
Some of them I'd say, well, I'm going to clean your mouth twice a week. Radiation is usually
six to eight weeks. So if I clean your mouth every two weeks, at least you're going to get a baseline
middle radiation and end. And others will say, well, if he's not responding really well, I will
just start training, say, what can I do to get a good oral help. Others I start every week,
and then after I treated like 10 patients, I got a call in my office with the, he was a
head, his name is Nico Sanfilippo. He was the head of the head and neck group. And I said,
Pat, I never had never talked to him, but he was the referrals from our patients because you have
the cancer, you have the surgery or not, and then you're radiation oncologist like a referral. So you
need to find a radiation oncologist that can see your patients. So he called me and said, Pat,
can you tell me what you're doing with my patients? And I was like scared because I knew that wasn't
like a perfect like stand of care. And then he said, well, I have maybe eight patients that you
treated and they don't develop mucocytes. And they're sitting on my waiting area and they're
talking to each other. Well, I went to see Pat, Pat is doing that, Pat is doing that. And then
he said, can you tell me what you're doing? And I said, Nick, you're gonna laugh, but I'm brushing
your teeth. Of course it wasn't that brushing, but it's oral hygiene. And he was going to say,
Pat, can you do a pilot? I'm fascinated by that. And then we did, we saw 16 patients, that's the
pilot that I submitted and we got the grant. But that was how everything started was him
call you and say, what's going on? Now, how in depth was the oral care you delivered to these
patients? Is it the type of thing that they could do for themselves if taught, or did it have to be
done while they're sitting in a dental chair and by someone who was highly trained? It's a
combination. Actually on the current trial, I'm trying both approaches. If I can just give a
baseline to me, because if they have a lot of, if someone has a lot of plaque in it for a long
period of time and you haven't brushed for six months, for example, the plaque becomes harder
and becomes tougher. No one can remove that unless we have a very specific ultrasound that vibrates
an instrumentation. That's what we do every six months when we go and get our dental cleaning.
They either scrape your teeth with very sharp instruments or they use the electronic one to
disrupt and they get blood. So at a minimum, you have to do once in a dental office. But in my trial,
I'm doing both because I don't know which one is better. Nobody ever did before. So one group,
I'm doing mechanical debridement as a period dentist. It's the same, even I go sub-gentle.
I'm trying to flush every toxins that I have sitting on the oremulcosa inside their gums,
on the gums, on the tongue. I brush and cross. It's, there is not a single surface on the other
cap that we don't clean. How long does that take? Takes one hour on the chair. Okay. The other group,
we give them a dental hygienist come every week to reinforce the importance of brushing,
flossing. And she flosses the patient's mouth, tell them how to properly do that. So it's just
to blind the study. They both come to the clinic. They didn't have to come because it's just a brush.
But we want to blind so both groups come to the chair and the hygienist does a light cleaning,
flossing only and brushing, or she does this holistic, comprehensive approach that I put
together. So, which is something that is striking going on right now on my patients in iron group,
they're not the following the disease. Now, just to make sure I understand, how many of these
patients are patients with head and neck cancer where they're developing, they're either directly
receiving radiation to the mouth or this area, which is resulting in the deterioration of the
environment versus patients with other cancers whose chemotherapies are rendering them susceptible
due to the mouth sores that are pretty common with chemotherapy coupled with the anticholinergics
that can dry the mouth out. Well, on my population, because I wanted to do a more controlled clinical
trial, they all had an eye cancer, scheduled to undergo radiation. The head and neck cancer
can be different areas of the head and neck, but I have a very strict inclusion criteria that at a
minimum 50 grains of radiation needs to be delivered to the other cavity due to the cancer.
Because I know that in this particular condition, 90% of them will develop mucocytes.
And this is male and female?
Male, female, and we have RT only and we have combined treatment. RT plus chemo,
100% get mucocytes. It's not a single patient. If you have a combined program,
regimen like that, it's very aggressive. And then on top of that, they get immune compromised.
But these are mostly squamous cell, not lymphomas and head and neck lymphomas, correct? This is
mostly squamous cell. And how many of these patients are HPV positive?
Probably 90% of them. Oral cancer, it's very low incidence.
Which is known by research as only the oropharyngeal cancer that has been linked to the HPV.
Most of them have HPV positive.
This is an interesting epidemic that's getting very little attention. And I don't know why, but
I think these HPV driven squamous cell carcinomas of the oropharyngeal region really frighten me
because we don't have really adequate ways to screen for them the way we can screen for HPV
cancers of the pelvis in women. Unless people are doing very advanced imaging like MRIs,
they're often caught quite late. What do you think accounts for the rise in incidence we're
seeing of this cancer? I mean, it's obvious that it's the HPV, but yeah.
Is it just sexual transmission? Like why are we seeing?
Yeah, it is sexual transmission. So we were in condoms. It's oral sex. We know today that
is sexual transmission. Of course, combined with poor oral health, they might cause disease or not
because we know there are like several predominant bacteria. They have a very symbiotic relationship.
They allow virus to grow. Like the pigeon gee values, there's several studies that show that
they can allow other virus to grow. Immune system deficiency as well. We know that every time that
you have your immune system is not strong, allows virus and bacteria, full infection to grow. So
you might charge over abundance as well. But it is, it's just, you need to modify habits so you
can prevent. I want to go deeper into this, but before we do, I want to actually go back to some
of the more mundane stuff, the real, you know, the blocking and tackling of dentistry and talk about
carries again and what, like what the stages of carries look like, when the tooth can be preserved.
All right. So when you're just replacing a little bit of enamel and then what that next layer of
damage looks like that ultimately leads to a root canal, presumably once the pulp is irreversibly
damaged. And then ultimately when even that can't be reserved and a crown is no longer sufficient
and you have to replace the whole tooth. Can you, I know you have some nice figures on that. Can we,
can we kind of go through those different stages of, of dental care? Because I think it is important
to see these images. It certainly helps me understand what's going on. So technically,
the first initial stage of dental decay is the one that breaks through the enamel.
The very incipient decays, they haven't got to the second layer of the tooth.
And they're, those are the ones, some of them, even like if we call white spot vision, you start
the decalcification, they can be reversed. If you have a child, you can have a very intense flow,
right? Furnished application, they are in reverse. So most of those very significant
solutions we shouldn't be touching or treating. And to be clear, is this the type of thing where
the dentist will use a little probe and say it's a little bit soft there, but I think it's okay,
or it's a shadow on the tooth, but they're confident that it's. Yeah, there are like some
controversy on that. In the past, they would have that very pointed probe and they would poke and
do inspection. Today, most people they would clean and they look with air because you don't want to
break the enamel more yet, right? Because if the enamel is already with loss of minerals, you don't
want to be poking. So you need to be very careful when it's a very superficial case like that,
because you might want to restore in a different way. But this is not painful. The enamel carries
have come nowhere near the pulp, so no one feels anything. There's no cold insensitivity or heat
insensitivity. Very, very minimal. Most people, they just don't even know it's there. And then
when it gets close, the more it gets close to the pulp, because it has so many nerves, the more
painful it's going to be. The dentin now is very soft. So it's more like a sponge that it's there
with very rich inside. So the moment it hits the dentin, it's painful. So that's when you're going
to start feeling like you get something cold and say, something's different in my tooth.
Hot is more signs of inflammation if you feel the hot surfaces, things that you put in your mouth.
Or when it gets infected, the bacteria can come to that hole and start colonizing. Then it starts
the inflammation and is that pulsation that you feel. And the pain now doesn't stop.
And before you get to full-blown pain, when you're just dealing with temperature and
sensitivity, is there anything that can be gleaned clinically between the cold versus the hot
insensitivity versus both? Yeah, most, I'm not an endodontist, an expert, but most tests that they do
to look for inflammation and infection when you have more of that hot sensation that is painful,
you know that you most likely might need to do the root canal because it's highly infected,
inflamed. The cold, it's a little bit better because it's not in more advanced stage.
And then when you go, if the decay progresses, that's when you see on the other two figures is
that it hits the pulp. The moment it hits the pulp, there is no way you can not do the root canal
because now everything's already infected. And most root canals are done when the pulp is still
alive. They just excise the pulp and clean it just in fact, so it's not from a dead tissue that has
been there for a long time because it's hard to keep up with the pain. But just to be clear,
the dentin carry can be fixed without a root canal. Yes, yes. If it is not as close to the pulp
that got to the point that is infected and it broke through, you can resort. So this is my
own personal misery. Both root canals I've had were from what I now believe were dentin carries.
The first one was actually a dentist that wanted to change an old filling that I had from when I
was a child. So I had an old mercury filling from when I was a kid and fast forward 20 years,
he said, your insurance will cover the changing of this to a white filling. We should just change
this out. Keep in mind for 20 years, I had no complaint of this filling whatsoever. And the
moment he changed that mercury filling over to a white one in the process of mucking around,
that tooth started really hurting. And over the next couple of weeks, the pain got worse and worse
and worse. And ultimately I needed a root canal on that tooth. So needless to say, I was
very unhappy about that. Let sleeping dogs lie. The next one I had was the same thing,
was another filling that the dentist thought in this case, hey, I think there's another little
carry next to it. It should be an easy fix. And it actually was on a wisdom tooth. But my teeth,
my mouth seems to be big enough that I'm able to tolerate having all my wisdom teeth. So he said,
look, we can do a root canal on a... Or sorry, this was before we needed the root canal. This was just,
hey, we'll just replace or fix the carry there. But same thing, it ended up hurting and hurting
and hurting. So they ended up doing the root canal. I still have that tooth with a... I didn't
even put a crown on that one actually, which is amazing on a wisdom tooth not to have a crown,
I assume. So you said something very interesting that's counterintuitive, I suppose, which is most
times you do a root canal, the pulp is actually alive, but you still have to remove it all.
Once they anesthetize you, they kill all that pulp, right? So the process is remarkably crude.
They're using these little fine... I don't know what you want to call them. They're almost like
needles, but they're a bit bigger. They're sort of serrated. I remember wanting to play with these
things after I had my root canal, but it's like these little... You wind these little serrated,
jagged tools into the end of the root. It's basically a very mechanical procedure.
It is, but today they're very sophisticated. They do all microscopically. I think in the past,
they had a lot of the issues from 100 years ago is because we're not sophisticated enough.
So they would put those fine things and they would break through the roots because they couldn't see
well and they cause immediately like the inflammation, the reaction, because you're just
perforating everything. But today, if you look today, how they treat periodontal disease,
it's a microscopic surgery. So they just put the tooth under the microscope. They're a completely
aseptic environment because they put those rubber bands into to isolate, to not let the bacteria
from the arachavia to get inside. And they do the whole excision of the pulp. They disinfect
everything and they fill in with special materials to just fill the hole. It becomes
like just a cast, the truth, because there is no more vitality on that tooth, but yet
preserves function, which is extremely important. That's why you shouldn't be extracting all your
teeth unless you really need it because it's not even the influence is better than your,
even without having a root canal is not better than your natural tooth.
Yeah. I mean, I think that's probably one takeaway here, which is, and I want to talk about the
concerns that people have around root canals because it seems to be one of these very
controversial topics in some small circles. But if you're going to have a root canal, it seems to
me that you have to have this done under a microscope by an endodontist. I just think
the days of freewheeling root canals where a dentist is looking through his or her glasses,
regular glasses and ramming these things through just doesn't make any sense. And I know that both
of my root canals were done initially in that way. Ultimately, both of them needed to be corrected by
endodontists who did it with microscopes in a much more aseptic fashion. Ultimately, one of them
ended up developing an abscess many years later. That tooth needed to be extracted.
So, which by the way, after that tooth was extracted, I was relieved of so much pain that
I decided in a temporary moment of insanity, I wanted to in that moment have all of my teeth
extracted and replaced by implants so I could never deal with this again. Of course, that's idiotic.
No. Yeah. So let's talk about the controversy around root canals. Basically, the controversies
are root canals are a dangerous procedure and they lead to kind of fill in the blank. And fill in the
blank is I've heard everything. I've heard people say, oh, root canals cause cancer, they cause
Alzheimer's disease, they cause sore toes, you name it. What is the state of evidence
about the safety of root canals or frankly, the state of evidence that root canals are indeed
potentially hazardous? It's hard to say in a nice way, but I think it's a total nonsense.
It's been, it's 100 years ago that all those focal theories that they said that would exist,
there is zero evidence, Anik, there is no research, there is nothing that can
prove that this is true. If you think about, I was even the other day talking to one of my faculty
because I said I'm not an endodontist, so I don't know. I've done root canal, but it was a long time
ago, but I was asking him, what do you think about this? And he said the same thing to Pat,
that there's no common sense on what's going on, is that focal point of infection. But what he said
is that if you think about the most root canals, the way they start, it's through the crowns and
the same bacteria that colonizer tube goes inside the pulp and then comes and goes inside the root,
and that's the infection that we're saying, right? That it's causing all those infections. But this
is all in your body already. And if that's the case, every time that you have a dental case,
you need to extract the tube because it's all the same route of infection. So when I think about all
those things and talking to them, I said, this makes no sense. There's no way we can explain that.
And again, I still think if it is well done, of course, there are a lot of root canals out there
that people don't know what they're doing. They don't clean well. They leave things behind or they
perforate. And we see how many regographs we take and we see a focal infection on the throat.
But that's because it's small cracks or someone, or not even they couldn't see well to do a proper
way, right? But as an end today, most root canals, if you walk in their clinic today,
they all under a microscope and I can guarantee it's really well done, the process. And people
don't have issues after that if it is well done. Yeah. I mean, I guess the question is,
even in the cases of root canals, which were not done ideally, such as mine,
beyond the local complication, which is the need for subsequent root canals,
ultimately the need for even an extraction, does that pose a systemic risk even when it's done
poorly? I don't believe so. Most have localized, there are few surgeries that they do and they
open through the gum and they clean that area and you see that improve. I don't believe that.
They're like with this root canal, for example, there are another paper who's saying that
people with root canal have breast cancer, for example. But then they look at a hundred of women
that didn't have root canal and also had breast cancer. So, it's not clear evidence.
These epidemiologic, I call them bottom of the birdcage papers, because that's about what they're
good for. They're the papers that say, well, if you look at the number of women who have had a root
canal on the same side that they get breast cancer, it demonstrates the relationship. But these papers
always fail to look at the numerator, which is all the women who develop breast cancer who did
not have root canals. They don't have root canals. Yeah. Yeah. So, it's true, true and unrelated.
And it's unfortunate because I think what bothers me the most about this type of pseudoscience is
when a woman gets breast cancer, it's already upsetting enough. I think the last thing she
needs to be told is this is because you had a root canal five years ago. And that's been
probably the biggest issue I take with this nonsensical science. And unfortunately, it tends
to aggregate from the same group of people who tend to have other beliefs that are very unsubstantiated,
such as vaccines causing autism and things like that. So, there tends to be a core group of
beliefs like that. So, let's go back a bit to the kind of broader theme of these systemic diseases.
When you think about major chronic diseases, is it safe to say that the greatest causal relationship
we have between poor oral health and poor systemic health would be with cardiovascular disease?
Or do you think there are... And so, I guess, first of all, how strong do you think that
relationship is causally and how does it compare to others? There is a lot of research showing
association. We don't know what comes first. So, they show the relationship that's proven with
periodontal disease and diabetes. Periodontal disease in low birth weight. Periodontal disease
and heart. That is the hypothesis, of course, is all based on the insult of the bacteria causing
inflammation and systemic health. We know that. And other things, Alzheimer's, for example,
amyloid in the brain. And a few studies that we did showed markers as well. Periodontal disease
and markers of Alzheimer's. So, they're all associations. But the only way you can say
causality is if you do a clinical trial. You need to treat those patients and see changes on those
markers. And then you say, see, I changed their behavior. They're brushing their teeth. Now,
look how better they became. So, we need to do those things. We have a group of people that I
work with from NYU since I was at NYU. Monique de Leon is his name. And Dr. Kamer. She's been for
over 10 years trying to make the point. She has all those papers. She saw, for example, children
with, that have motor skills or I think her study was in, I just blinked here now, the name of the
disease. But we found in children that they have amyloid better, amyloid in their brains,
accumulation. And we know this population has very poor oral health. They have cold on tidings
and six years old, it's Down syndrome. So, the first study that she looked, it was Down syndrome.
So, we know because they have motor skills, they have cognition issues and it's a very hard to brush.
So, that's interesting. So, because we know that children with Down syndrome
are very susceptible to Alzheimer's disease and cardiovascular disease, in fact,
people with Down syndrome usually do not live a normal lifespan and they usually succumb to
these chronic conditions much sooner, as early as in their 40s or 50s. So, you're saying that,
well, again, it's hard to know if the increase that she sees in amyloid is an independent process
that's being driven by the chromosomal abnormalities that are found in Down syndrome versus
related to the poor oral care, which could be true and unrelated. It could be that they have
poor oral care because they don't have the life skills developed to provide oral care. So,
an interesting experiment would be a longitudinal study of two groups of peers with Down syndrome,
one that are provided intensive support for oral care and one that are sort of standard of care.
But again, those are very difficult studies to do because they're very time consuming.
Well, they are. It's all about prevention, right? How about if you intensify a very intense
preventive approach so you don't let that child be with carries and predile disease and pain and
inflammation and all of that. It's not only that disease, it's any people with disability.
Like we just opened at Penn right now because the dean's visionary, he's really focused on
prevention. He opens a center for people with disabilities. So, any person who has any
motor skills or has any disease that impacts cognition, we're going to create this program
that we can do a lot of research. How is the best way of cleaning toothpaste, toothbrushes,
what can intensify this population? We reach through caregivers. It's a whole educational
process because it's not them. We need to educate people who are taking care of those
injured needles to do an optimal oral hygiene. It's simple as that. Can we just brush, brush,
brush, fluoride, intensify because you can prevent all those things are highly preventable.
But I was looking for say, what are we going to measure? There is no outcome assessment that you
can use for this specific population because they're so neglected.
But going back to your earlier point, just to make sure I understood,
did you say that if you took two groups of people and one group received excellent oral care and
the other group did not, and this is not in cancer patients. Let's just say patients who are not
immune compromised and whose oral mucosa is not compromised. So, if this hasn't been done,
consider it a thought experiment. One group receives best in class oral care, which I want
to come back and define. The other group receives horrible oral care or mediocre at best. Would you
expect to see a difference in inflammatory markers, including cytokines and inflammatory cells,
macrophage monocyte derived lineage cells across those two groups? Because if that's true, that
alone could explain the increase in systemic disease. In other words, that could be a causal
factor. It's undeniably well established the relationship between inflammation and
cardiovascular disease. You could take two people that have virtually an identical profile of
lipoproteins, but in one group, the high amount of inflammation will lead to a greater burden
of disease than in the other. Inflammation plays an important role in cancer and certainly
inflammation plays an important role in Alzheimer's disease. So, that to me seems,
I guess the easiest hypothesis, that's the Occam's razor approach here, which is poor oral health
leads to poor or substandard amounts of inflammatory environment, and that's the
driver of these diseases. That would be my guess. Yeah, it's very simple, Nick. But think about,
Peter, when did you ever go to a doctor? You are MG, that the doctors ask you,
how's your mouth? Do you have periodontal disease? How do you brush your teeth? Think about when.
Sure. It's not at all part of the doctor's toolkit.
Ever. So, look what's going on with COVID. COVID is an infectious disease. What is the
transmission of COVID saliva? It's the mouth. Now, there are papers coming up because the
AC2 receptors, which is the COVID bind to enter the body, they are highly expressed in your
country. Look at the literature. They're in the tongue, the floor of mouth,
gingebo, curvicular food, they're everywhere in your mouth. So, a patient gets COVID.
The two things that I'm very surprised and saying why people are not doing anything.
So, people get COVID, they go to the hospital. The first thing that they do, they put them on a mask.
They never brush their teeth. They don't look if they have periodontal disease. How is the quality
of the oral cavity? They put on the subpoena position because they need to free up the lungs.
That patient spends a month, some people, more than that, in a very critical condition. They
think this is going to lead to pulmonary infection. Of course, we are. If someone has periodontal
disease and already have a lot of bacteria and pockets, all the periodontal pockets, it's a
perfect reservoir for the virus to thrive. Even like the new, if you saw, there is a publication
that just came out, only hypothesis because nobody ever tested it. That it might be, if you look at the
characteristics or actual risk of COVID, the way it manifests, the upper respiratory tract,
in terms of secretion, how congested you have is very minimal. You might have a stuffed nose,
but from the mouth goes directly to the lungs. So, there is a huge connection there. No one is
doing anything to tell people, can you brush your teeth? Do a mouthwash. Clean your mouth. If you
have COVID, you have to have an excellent, in the hospitals. Give the nurses, you have to ask this
patient to brush because no one is doing that. Look at the committee. So, of course, now,
science is going back because our new president, they have, they're very, they're fostering all
those prevention maps and everything. Look at the committee that we have that has been put to
support COVID. Is there any, one of them is an oral expert?
I'm guessing not.
An oral epidemiologist, an oral periodontist. Is there anyone there, if there are anyone there that
understands a little bit about the mouth, if you connect the mouth with the body, I can guarantee
that you can present. Look what's going on in Brazil, China. It's just ridiculous because there's
no prevention. The only prevention is the mask, which we could do something better, right?
Some argued that last year we saw a great increase in the rise of dental carees. Some
suggest that it had to do with mask wearing. To me, it seems the most obvious explanation would
be simply that people sought less dental care last year. Do you have a point of view on, first
of all, is it true that dental carees went up last year?
Well, so what happened, that we're still dealing with that, is that when COVID hit,
dentists was considered not essential. So they shut down everything that wasn't essential,
which health care and places that you can buy food and things like that. So dentists was left
behind. So dental clinics, I know because I had to suspend my clinical trial for
three or four months. I came back immediately the moment they allowed me to open the clinic. But
dental clinics, they were closed, completely closed for about almost a year. And on top of that,
they suspended every single type of procedure that produces a result because they thought that
was a way of infecting people. So people couldn't go to the dentist. You saw horrible things on the
internet. We left our emergency clinic open only. And we saw really detrimental things because
people couldn't get access to care. So combined with, of course, putting masks. And if you're
wearing a mask at work a whole day, you forget to brush because you can't drink too much because
you need to hide because you have to drink water or eat. So everything is detrimental. You might
breathe more through your mouth because the mask, people don't know how to breathe well through the
mask. So it dries your mouth. You have dry mouth because you're breathing. So this combination of
poor or hygiene, you have dry mouth, you have a mask. So it's not the mask that is causing anything,
but it's just a cumulative effect of everything that is going on.
Yeah, that makes a ton of sense. You mentioned thrush earlier, so oral candida. And you mentioned
it in the obvious context of people who are immune compromised. But from time to time,
I've seen people with a totally normal immune system develop oral thrush. Now, I will say
there's usually something going on, like they're usually on an inhaled steroid for asthma or
something like that. So maybe that's partially explaining it. But do you have any other
explanations for how a person with a normal immune system could develop oral candida or thrush?
It's highly associated with candida infection. And it can be through, I think the primary reason
is lack of saliva, because your mouth is dry. So that's why MDs, they show up at their patients and
how much in which picture they have. And ask the question, you have dry mouth. They might have in
other complications and don't even know why. But primarily, I think it's poor oral hygiene,
because if you have no donor disease and poor oral hygiene, you're going to allow those
opportunistic species to grow. And medication, they don't have a specific cause, but mainly,
I would say medication and poor oral health would allow virus to grow. We see it a lot in HIV.
You mean fungus.
Fungal. Yeah. Fungal. Yeah.
I said virus, because virus and fungal, they work really well together. Like people with HIV,
they have episodes constant of fungal infection in their mouth.
So there are lots of reasons why people could have dry mouth. Certainly one of the most popular
classes of drugs that would do it are anticholinergics. It's also interesting, by the way,
that there's some strong associations between anticholinergics and Alzheimer's disease.
It hasn't been demonstrated whether that's causal, but if indeed anticholinergics, which lead to a
very dry mouth, would decrease the resistance of the bacteria in the mouth to the systemic system.
And that could play a role. So it becomes very interesting. But for an individual who has dry
mouth, is there a downside in using sugarless chewing gum or lozenges or having something in
the mouth to induce saliva? Is there a downside to that? Is that considered one of the effective
methods that someone can use to keep their mouth lubricated?
Yeah. Yeah. I don't see any wrong doing that, but never use anything that is sugar
content. There are a lot of sugar substitutes that you can do because you can stimulate
the salivary lens and you're constantly moving your tongue and your mouth. And I will say
hydration, it's extremely important as well. If you don't like to drink, just get a sip water
all day long. You're always washing the oil cavity, the gastrointestinal tract, because it's all one
system. It starts in the mouth and go to the bacteria they are all together. So always
hydration and drinking water, I think it's very important for oral health as well.
Now, have you looked into xylitol specifically? I've seen some literature to suggest that xylitol
may actually not only not be harmful, because I think there are lots of things out there that
are not harmful, aspartame or any other things that might be thrown into gum that are sugar
substitutes, but that xylitol specifically could be beneficial. And so my practice has been to have
some xylitol-based chewing gum that if I'm out and I eat, I can chew it for a while to serve two
purposes. One is get saliva there, but two also clean the food out of teeth. Do you recommend
anything like that? Because a person can't brush their teeth four times a day, presumably. At some
point, it becomes counterproductive. Yeah, that's the one that I like the most. I actually did some
research a long time ago where we are looking for mothers to child transmission of dental care.
We know that as mutants can be highly transmissible from mothers to child. For different things like
the mom who proved the food and put in the child's mouth. It's proven that it transmits
the struck mutants of the child. They've done some research about kissing in the mouth. They didn't
find a hinge correlation that they know that proving and tasting their food, which is you
should take a look at nannies and people who are watching children. But I really like xylitol
and we found that we prevented the transmission because we gave the xylitol to the moms.
During the gestation time, we asked them to chew on xylitol just to prevent that
vertical transmission of the mutants that struck mutants. It prevents the K2
because the bacteria does not metabolize that. That's great. I'll plug my favorite brand of it.
I use one called Pure. You can buy it on Amazon and I like the Pure gum and the Pure mints.
Let's talk about teeth whitening. Generally, the two things people notice about somebody's teeth
when they smile is how straight are they and how white are they? Let's talk a little bit about the
latter. Is the color of a person's tooth genetically determined?
Somehow, yes. We can see that different races, they might have more white, but it's relative as well
because let's say if this person with the darker skin, the teeth are going to become much more
whiter. It's almost blend with someone who has a very white skin. Most of the changes on tooth
color can either be done by some genetic factors that people who might have a lot of very yellow
and that will never change but since they're born or sometimes they're like in few countries, they
have fluid in the water so excess of fluoride might have some stains on your teeth but mostly
the color of the teeth is highly environmentally determined because we talk about my study with the
twins where we gave the same product for the two twins, they behave completely different.
Even they were identical 100% of their genes. The kid who had like drink a lot of tea,
coffee and things, they had much more stain in your teeth and of course the whitening wasn't
efficient of another one who had less. The environment takes place and it's highly
can modify just with those whitening products, brushing, things like that.
Yeah, I have found that for me, the two worst actors by far in terms of darkening my teeth are
black tea and red wine. We're going to talk about whitening in a second because I want to ask you
about it. I don't whiten my teeth due to sheer laziness. My approach has been to just try to
minimize how dark they get by always rinsing my mouth out with water or chewing gum or something
like that after I consume those things. Is whitening a safe procedure? Is it something that
harms the tooth in an effort to produce this aesthetic? Does it bleach the enamel away or
do something that's dangerous? Yeah, it's bleach and it's of course in excess, which most people do
because they want to always have meaty wine. It's detrimental because somehow it has loss of
minerals because of the product is very strong. Also, if you're allowed to touch the gums,
it's very aggressive because you're bleaching and it cannot be for a long time. So what I tell people
is that if you want to do at home because it's less expensive, ideally you should do at the dentist.
If you care about your teeth, do at the dentist. They're going to protect your gum. They're not
going to apply the product if you have a disease, if you have root case and all those things. They
will know exactly what is the population who can have that but people just go and buy out of the
counter and they don't know what they're doing. Sometimes they place that and they watch TV,
they spend hours or every time they have a party, oh, I want my teeth, why? They put again and then
becomes that constant demetrization. Of course, you're going to have to stop with your teeth.
You're going to harm your gums and things like that. So if you want to do, talk to your dentist,
ask them, am I attending date for that? And do at the dentist, do at the correct timeline,
look at the prescription. Don't do cheap or products that are not FDA approved. So all
those considerations, if you do the right way, it's okay. It's just when they go outside to do
things that they should do. But it still seems that prevention is worth a lot here. If you
minimize the things that really discolor your teeth, it would at least reduce the need to
do those other things. I alluded to it earlier that one of my most miserable,
not one of my hands down, my most miserable dental experience of my life went as follows.
Mercury filling placed when I was whatever, 10, 30 years later, someone comes along and says,
you really ought to have that removed because your insurance company will now cover the replacement
of these and you can have something white instead of something silver. And that damaged
the dentin and or pulp enough that I needed a root canal, that root canal. I eventually,
that's the one where they missed the root. I had to go back and back and back and back and ultimately
led to an injury that required the tooth coming up. Okay, let's go back to the jugular question.
Should we remove mercury fillings? No. If they're highly functioning, there is no decay
under there are several statements and research that has been done and that's the minimal,
they're afraid about the mercury that gets in there. It's proven that there is no harm with that.
So if it's working fine, if you ain't functioning and it doesn't affect the appearance, the status
of the tooth, just leave it there. I don't think you should. Okay, you also talked about fluoride
earlier. This might sound like a naive question, but does all toothpaste have fluoride in it?
No, you have to look for and not all of them have the correct amount. You want to like
1000 ppm to 1500 ppm of fluor. So that's very important. So you have to, and the ADA, the
American Mental Association, if you go to their website, they have all the toothpaste that they
endorsed, not for political reasons or anything, because we've done research and we know they work,
they have the correct amount of fluoride that prevents decay. So you just need to get from a
good source and it's extremely important to have fluoride in any toothpaste. Usually children,
before one year, they recommend not to put it on because they swallow all the time,
but as long as they have the first tooth in their mouth, you can start putting very small amounts
and start the dredging to brush the child gets used to. But other than that, everybody should
use fluoride. And is there fluoride at all in any small amount in drinking water?
It depends. I know that the US is very particular with fluoride in many regions that people don't
like to have. Most countries, the drinking water is fluoride, but there are additional
sources of fluoride that pediatrician, they can do like drops that you, even when you're breastfeeding,
you can just put drops on the child and or varnish, which I think is extremely, extremely
preventative for children. It's so simple. It's like a varnish that you paint in your teeth every
six months. And guess what? We don't have the decay because it's just protecting more and more.
So I do that myself also. Yes, for any. I have discovered that I have one area in my mouth
where my gum has receded just a little bit. And as opposed to putting a filling there, I just use
every three to six months, a little bit of what you said, like sort of a fluoride varnish. Yeah.
And it reduces any sensitivity. And my goal is obviously just to prevent any decay there.
Yeah, the fluoride varnish, if someone is highly susceptible to decay, we have a,
it's a prescription base. You have to ask the doctor or the dentist to call. It's one of the
ones that we have in the market is prevalent. I give to my cancer patients, but they are highly
concentrated fluoride. And we recommend that they use once every night and for people who are high
risk of care, which is people undergoing radiation. And then you do a regular oral hygiene with the
regular fluoride toothpaste, your floss and everything. And then you put that toothpaste
on a toothbrush and then you brush and don't rinse with water. You want the product to just
treat the cavities and everything overnight. So that's very efficient as well. And mainly,
and it's a very fun story to ask my son because I have two kids and none of them have never had
decay. How old are they? Today they are 30, 34. So, but they never had decay. But if you think
Francis, which my youngest, he, because I was tell the stories about microbial that they're going to
eat your teeth. If you have food, they're going to eat the food that they're going to just go down
and make holes in your teeth. So I would tell them those stories overnight. And how many times
that kid in the middle of the night, cause he would fall asleep and I'll put him on like three
years old in the bed. And I would watch him in the middle of the night, brush the bathroom and brush
the teeth because you're afraid. I always told them because the most important time of the day
is actually the night rush and never give your child baby bottles and things overnight. Because
when you're sleeping, you have a suppress your saliva production.
And that's the perfect environment to the bacteria to grow. That's why child have baby
bottle decay because when they're sleeping and they put the bottle in their mouth,
the milk concentrates all on the anterior teeth and they get severe decay. So brushing before you
go to bed and you floss, you'd like to do that. You have me a optimal optimal or hygiene is really
high and you're going to prevent, right? It's a very important brushing time.
What are the implications of children having carries in their baby teeth? I mean, for example,
I assume we would never do a root canal in a child. You just yank the tooth out because you
know that the adult tooth is coming right behind it. Do people put fillings into children's teeth?
It's highly complicated to treat those kids. First, because you traumatize them, you cannot do local
anesthesia. They will never come back to the dentist to try to do that in a regular way because
they don't understand. They're very young. It's one, two, three years old that will start with
decay appear. So they do in the hospital under sedation. The teeth that they can't treat, they
treat, they will extract the ones that causing a lot of pain. Some of them just treat the pulp,
put some medication there and wait until the tooth is 48 just to preserve function because otherwise
they're not going to be able to chew. So every case they need to approach, there is another type
of fluoride as well. It's highly concentrated that they put it with a marrow together, but the
teeth becomes black. That's another resource that they have because they cannot open, put a hole,
and restoration because the child will never allow us to do. So excessive fluoride darkens teeth?
Just this specific time. It's mixed with a metal that the moment it gets in contact with this soft
denture, it hardens and becomes that very hard layer.
Okay. So it doesn't affect their adult teeth. It's just a temporary barrier until the tooth falls out.
Yeah, I rest the decay in a very nice way, but you need to tell the mom and say, I know it's going to
take the pain away. It's going to rest the decay, but the teeth is going to become black. So it's a
trait because we know that a couple years later the tooth is going to exfoliate. It's not going
to be black forever. So it's an approach that we can do for this age of children.
There's an entire cottage industry of products out there like oil for pulling through the teeth
and tongue scraping things. Are you aware of any research that supports the use of such devices?
You've obviously talked about brushing the tongue, but any research that suggests scraping the tongue
is efficacious or I don't even understand what oil pulling is, although I've seen the oils and
I don't think I fully understand what the claim is about why oil pulling is beneficial. Are you aware?
No, honestly, I've seen, I have no idea. There is no clinical or research evidence that shows that
it's good or bad. I've seen a few studies on the tongue scraping, which is similar with whatever
the brush is doing, but I really like much better the brush because I asked the patients to put a
little bit of toothpaste because toothpaste is also anti-bacteria and then you just brush.
It doesn't harm the cells or anything. You just brush the surface. If I had to choose between
this toothbrush brushing the tongue without scraping, I would say just brush. It's simple and easy.
Okay. Is there a difference between the types of dental flosses out there? The two most common
that I see, actually, let's say three. One is the ribbon. It's a very soft, almost looks like a
gortex-like ribbon. The other is a rope, a miniature rope. Then the third one would be a
miniature rope that's coated in wax. Are they all basically the same and you just pick the one
that is the most comfortable to you or do you have a preference for which type of floss a person uses?
Well, what I tell my patients, I have like 10 different ones. What I tell them, the true one,
you're more comfortable using. It's a mechanical, the bright one. It's disruption of the biofilm
and taking the food away from in between your teeth. There are people who have perfect teeth,
very close together. They might need to use the one that has the wax because they're going to go
in and out very quick and you don't want to harm your gums trying to pull in something very strong
and then it's going to cut through the ground. It has to be done very carefully. There are people
who have prosthetics or big holes. They are like little brushes that they can put inside.
There are people who have teeth that are connected to each other and they have another type of
device that they can go inside the bridge and clean. It doesn't really matter. You just need
to clean and you can clean. Most people don't floss. Really? Most people do. What does the
literature suggest? What percentage of the US adult population does floss once a day?
If I tell something, I might not be right, but I know by the whole population that I treated,
it's like half of the people floss or they floss twice a week or something gets stuck,
they go and floss, but if you ask people do you floss every day, most people don't floss every day
and another consideration is that floss costs money. So you need to keep buying all those
supplies and you might not have the funds might be used for different things.
But if you think about flossing and brushing, I still think the floss is even more important than
brushing because it's all the research that I did. People can stop brushing and you recover health
easily. People stop flossing as the change of items, inflammation comes so quick because the plaque
that is in between your teeth, you can never change or clean if you don't have a device.
The plaque that is on top of the surface of your teeth, you're eating, you get an apple,
things that have fibers, somehow you just clean, you drink water, the saliva is constant cleaning
your mouth. The flossing is where the one thing is a bad bacteria because they love the anaerobic
bacteria that causes most of the systemic health, such cardiovascular disease, diabetes, they all
anaerobic and they are the ones that hide in the tongue, they hide in between your teeth,
they can hide back in your throat as well because they like those niche that the oxygen don't go.
Is a water pick an additional benefit to flossing? Is it at all a substitute? I mean, obviously,
there are some cases where it's very valuable, kids that have braces, things like that,
but how do you incorporate the water pick into your oral care regimen?
I like it, but I would say it's only if you're not able to use the traditional, the brushing is the
best because the water is more if you brush, then do the water pick. Don't do just the water pick
without brushing because the water pick is that flushing of all the toxins that are in between
your teeth and between your gums and all of that, but it cannot be just water pick. It's a benefit,
but don't do alone. Any harm or benefit to using toothpicks? This is just a personal obsession of
mine. I love toothpicks. It sounds crazy, but when I find toothpicks I like, I buy them in massive
quantities and there's this one toothpick I got at a steakhouse 10 years ago and I became so enamored
by it that I had to find out where they got it from and I found the company that made it, but the
minimum order was something like 20,000 packages. I had to buy 20,000 packages of this toothpick,
which I still have to this day. I love them. Point is, I always have a toothpick in my mouth
am I hurting myself? Am I helping myself? What am I doing? I don't think you've heard of yourself.
They even had research in the past that they say that stimulates your gums and things like that.
Well, honestly, that's part of what it is. There's a use case, which is anytime I have food in my
teeth, I love doing it, but what I've also realized is I find myself massaging my gums with the side
of the pick. I put the toothpick in and I'm grinding it on my gum surface and it just feels
so good to me. I still floss every day, so it's not a substitute for flossing.
That's what I was going to say.
Yes, not a substitute.
Yes, I still floss every day.
It doesn't do the same job because the floss goes around too, then go up and down, but it's benign.
There's nothing that I don't think any wrong of doing.
That's good because I have enough to last me, my children, my children's children, and their
children for the rest of our lives. People talk about generational wealth. I don't have
generational wealth, but I have generational toothpicks.
Talking about that, the electric toothbrush, I like it a lot.
I was going to ask you about that. I'm an Oral-B guy. I've tried the Braun and I've tried the Oral-B.
Something about the Braun one bothered me. I don't know if the frequency that it vibrated at
resonated too much with my head, but it didn't feel good.
Yes.
But I love the Oral-B.
I had the same.
Okay. Is one superior?
I actually did clinical trials with both.
Okay.
They equally good. The difference is the technology. One is sonic. When you're doing
that, it's almost a few vibrations in your head.
Right?
Oral-B is much more like...
It's mechanical.
...the vibrations much more natural.
Yeah.
Mechanical. I love the mechanical because it simulates your gums.
There are people who loves doing the other one. It's very fast and cleans very quick.
I like the Oral-B a lot. That's the one that I have.
So bottom line is they're both efficacious if you can use them both
and use the one that you enjoy more.
Yes. It is just whatever you're comfortable and whatever you know,
you're going to clean your mouth. That's what I say.
I've done anything, all types of floss, all types of toothpaste, and it's a device
that is there for you to do your oral hygiene.
So let's now talk about the ideal reasonable regimen of oral care.
Let's start with what I do and use me as an example of how I could do it better.
When I wake up in the morning, I do nothing.
And the reason is I don't usually eat in the morning, but I drink coffee.
So I don't know why. For some reason, I think it's a waste of time to brush my teeth first
thing in the morning because all I'm going to go to do is drink coffee.
So let's say I get up and I drink my coffee. Oh, by the way, I used to scrape my tongue.
I have one of those tongue scrapers. I used to do that.
And then my wife got so mad at me because she said,
that's so disgusting. It makes me sick.
Get rid of that stupid tongue scraping piece of expletive.
So I still have it. Don't tell her, but I don't use it anymore.
So I go and I drink my coffee and I kind of do all my, I usually exercise in the morning
and I usually don't eat my first thing until maybe 11 o'clock in the morning.
At that point, I then go and I get my oral bee toothbrush and I brush my teeth.
And as you probably know, the oral bee toothbrush has like this little 30 second timer
that it does, allows you to go two minutes. So I'm very, very robotic about this.
I 30 seconds on the top, 30 seconds on the top, 30 seconds on the bottom inside, 30 seconds on
the bottom. And then I'm done. And then I don't do anything again, except use my toothpick all day
until dinner after dinner. I then floss. And I, I like that. I like both. I like any floss,
actually. I just love flossing. So I'll use the little ropey floss and I'll use the tape floss,
whatever I've got. And then I do the same thing with the oral bee toothbrush. By the way, I'm
using a xylitol based toothpaste for what it's worth, if that matters. And that's it.
That's it has for it has fluoride. That's that's my only oral care regimen.
I don't use mouthwash. I don't use a water pick. I used to, but then I gave it to my daughter
because she got braces. I figured she needed it more than I do. That's all I'm doing. So
what could I do to be, am I getting 80% of the benefit a person can have? Am I at 60% benefit?
And what should I, what else should I be doing? So one little adjustment. So usually back to near
the biofilm, it takes like overnight. That's where you have the most suspicious bacteria.
They start growing in your mouth. All those reasons that I said your mouth is closed,
no oxygen, reduce saliva flow, sorry, by flow is almost zero because you sleep and things like so
people, when you wake up, you feel, if you stop and thinking, you're going to see, yes,
my mouth is dry. If you cross your tongue on the surface of your teeth, you're going to feel the
biofilm. That's the only, that biofilm is invisible to your eyes, but you can feel with your tongue.
That's the morning that you're going to see. So there's nothing wrong of you. I do that as well.
I like to take my coffee in my bed. I just read a little bit and I take my coffee without brushing.
Brazilian coffee, I hope.
Exactly. Espresso. Espresso. So then you get out of the bed and you brush your teeth.
You have to wash out from your night.
Okay. So what, so the change you're suggesting is before I begin my day, do a first brush. So I'm
going to be now brushing my teeth three times a day. I'm going to do the first, the morning.
That's the idea.
Okay. And is it okay if that, should they all be done with the Oral-B toothbrush or is there a time
and a place to just use a regular toothbrush? You can use any toothbrush if you're out. If you're
in a place where you can brush, you can use any. If you have that, because the mechanical toothbrush,
they do such a good job. Although I have to be honest with you, I've never been able to
brush my teeth, sorry, brush my tongue with the mechanical toothbrush. Because I, the, no.
Yeah. I have to use the, okay. All right. I got it.
You have, find a, I usually write, I like a children toothbrush.
Yeah. So you want a soft, a versatile toothbrush, right?
Soft, soft with the tongue. Yeah. Just get a separate one. And I tell people that every time
that you use a toothbrush, which most people don't do as well, you rinse your toothbrush.
You can even rinse with soap. Like put water, soap, you decontaminate. You need to clean your toothbrush.
Oh, I never thought of that. So I, you're saying like, this is, you're really adding,
you're, you're literally going to add another four minutes to my day. You realize that?
Four minutes to my day, 28 minutes to my week. You know how many hours you're adding to my year?
This is ridiculous. Well, look, it's worth it though. So, so I'm going to be healthy.
So I'm going to now be rinsing my toothbrush with soap and water.
If you don't want to put the soap, just rinse with water.
Well, I always do that, but now I'm committed to doing this. Maybe salt. Would salt water be
beneficial? You don't need, you don't need, no. Just even hand soap, just rinse with water and
soap and dry. You have to dry because my tear loves the moisture in butter.
I hate the taste of soap because as a child, my mom would often wash my mouth out with soap
because of how foul a mouth I had. So I'm still traumatized by the taste of soap.
It's an awful taste. Rinse with like hot, hot water. It is very hot. So that is soapy toothpaste
because soap disrupts my COVID. Like the COVID can be disrupted by soap. You know that, right?
So every toothpaste has soap because of that. Because most bacteria have the lipid protein in
their surface. So that's why we have, but they put all the flavors. They put the fluoride. So that's
why they don't feel that soap taste, but that is soap and antibacterial. But, and that's all.
Any role for mouthwash, which I don't, I don't, my wife loves it. I don't, I just,
it's one more dumb thing that I don't do. The thing that I just like with mouthwash is that
it kills every single, it just wipes out all your microbiome, including the good ones,
because they're all antibacterial. So I am in favor, if you like, in a situation that you're
not going to be able to brush much, like for short periods of time, let your body do normal,
like recolonize with the good, without any interference. The same thing about antibiotics.
If you take too much antibiotics, you're going to be resistant to bugs and bacteria. So if you use
every day, in one point, you're going to have a virus in your cavity, but that's going to be
very resistant compared to someone else. That's very interesting. Is there any evidence that
excessive use of mouthwash, for example, leads to candidaal overgrowth or fungal overgrowth? I mean,
that would certainly be one hypothesis worth testing. I don't remember, Peter.
So I don't want to say anything that I don't remember, but I can go back and look. But the
studies that I did, it changes the microflora. So that's why I'm very concerned about changing
an oral environment that is healthy. So if you're healthy, why are you going to use the mouthwash?
You don't need that. Okay. Anything else that we would consider best practices for the average
person who is looking to preserve the quality function of their teeth and by extension,
their overall health, besides what we've discussed? Well, I think everything that we discussed,
and we talked so many times about prevention. So dental care is a chronic non-communicable
disease, and then it's through life. People have dental care their whole life. The only way
to control is preventing. So preventing means every six months, you need to go to a dentist,
and you need to do a clean at a minute. At that time, they're going to look if you have any
cavities because the cavities is a niche for the bacteria to grow as well. By the way, is six
months a magic number? I mean, the only reason most of us go every six months is because that's what
insurance covers for free. But if you decided you were willing to pay out of pocket, would it be
better to go every three months or every four months to do an overall cleaning? Well, there
is a lot of research about if you maintain a good oral health, you don't need to do more often.
Someone who is at high risk, you have a systemic health, you have diabetes, you can
do three times a year, for example. But the six months is how dentists recommend it, and it's
through research that shows cause for the dental disease, it's a very slow progression. I see.
It's not a disease that you have today. In three months, you're going to have two
millimeters of bone loss, unless you have something else in your body that combined with the
inflammation that is triggering systemically, then your bone is going to go away very quick.
But I think because for the dental disease, it's a slow progression. And I know we did a study
three years ago that we looked at people and we measured the dental disease every two months.
We held the treatment, we didn't do the treatment, and we watched how people would progress. And it's
crazy. There are people who progress very quick. There are people who never progress, and there
people would take two years to progress. Wow. So- What do you think explain those differences?
Systemic, because periodontal disease is a highly
common case with your body. If you have a systemic issue, it's going to exacerbate inflammation.
So- Wait, so you could predict the extent of disease a person has if you knew how systemically
healthy or sick they were? Yeah, you can. If you have a lot of infections,
you have diabetes, we know you're more susceptible to help with the dental disease. So there are
groups of risk that those particular group, they need to see a dentist more often, they need to do
more cleanings and they need to prevent. But there was a huge study that was done five years ago,
but was not conclusive. It's all, they'll never know this. When they finish, they say they don't
know which way it's coming. If it is the diabetes, that triggers or if it is the burden and the
orocavity that is treating the diabetes, they couldn't dissect that. I think the good news is
they're both preventable diseases. So that again, goes back to the point of prevention.
Well, Pat, this has been super interesting. Just on a purely selfish basis, I learned a lot. So
that will immediately go into practice effective, I guess, tonight and tomorrow morning. So thank
you very much for the insights you've shared. And I think people will take a lot of practical
information from this. Very welcome. It was my pleasure.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail
every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's
show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple
Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.