Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hugh, it's so awesome to have you here today. Although I do wish we were doing this in person.
We've been talking about...
Me too.
Yeah. We've been saying, well, let's wait and do this in person. Let's wait and do this
in person. But between all that's going on, I think this is the next best thing.
Yeah. I mean, the best part of in-person, I know the conversation is great, but the cooking
is off the charts. You're cooking, you and Jill combined to like a crazy good dinner.
There's another whole avenue there for you.
I don't know. I still think some of the meals I've had at your place have blown my mind
even more. And including the meals I haven't had. Do you remember the day I came over to
your place? I think I was on day six out of seven on a fast.
Yes. Yes.
And you and Deb really, really thought you were going to get me to cave and instead I
just walked around the kitchen smelling it and regretting.
I respected that. But I can't really take any credit for the meals of my house. You
can take the credit, the ones that are yours. I mean, right down to sourcing the food. I'm
impressed.
Yes. I know you appreciated that. Actually, I want to come back to that because there's
an interesting story about some of those meals. But this is kind of a different podcast for
us. We've talked about this a lot and we thought that what would be fun today is not just that
I'm interviewing you, but in some ways that you're interviewing me. And I think that's
in part because you're the most curious person I know. And that's evident any time you are
sitting down with anyone. I've watched you interact with so many different people, even
just in the few minutes before we were getting this podcast recording, when you were talking
to Nick, you're just immediately obsessed with and interested in every detail of what
another person knows and how they've come to know it and stuff like that.
And so I think in the past couple of months as we were thinking about this, it became
clear there was no way I was going to be able to get away with just interviewing you because
you were going to end up asking me a bunch of questions anyway. So we said, well, why
don't we just acknowledge that this is going to be a discussion and not an interview?
Yeah, no, it's my favorite way to do it anyway. I often in interviews, no matter what, and
I've done a lot, I always try to ask questions because I get bored of talking about myself
anyway. And if you think about my job, my job is human nature, like observing it. If
you're an actor and you're not curious about people, it's going to be a real struggle.
So I do want to start with this idea of, because it's actually something Olivia asked me yesterday.
I said, hey, Olivia, I'm talking to Hugh tomorrow, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. And she's
because she's very interested in music. And she said, will you ask him a question from
a researcher? She said, when did he know he was good enough that he could make it in
his chosen profession? And I said, I don't know. Let me, let me ask him that.
I think when, when I got cast and I got the job at the Royal National Theater in London,
so I'm, I'm now 28. I've studied for four years at college. You certainly don't know
that. I mean, the stats on college, and I went to probably one of the top two colleges
in Australia, three year full time program, the stats are maybe 5% actually make a living
from that. So there's 18 people chosen in a year. So I certainly didn't have it there.
And then I came out of the gate and got quite a bit of work straight off the bat, which
was I was super lucky. Don't let's not forget, I was 26. So I needed to work. And but when
Trevann Nunn, I auditioned for Trevann Nunn for Sunset Boulevard in sorry, I should I
just give you some context. Sir Trevann Nunn is one of the great theater directors of all
time. And I was a huge fan from his work at the Royal Shakespeare Company, but also Les
Miserables, Nicholas Nickleby, you name it, he was just one of the greats. And, and so
when he came to Australia doing Sunset Boulevard, I actually didn't want to do the musical.
I wanted to go I was an actor who weirdly got into musicals. And I thought I'm going
to get out because I was getting pigeonholed into that world. And I, I said to the casting
director, listen, I don't want to be in the show. And this is the like the most presumptuous
thing I'm ever going to ask of you, but I would love to audition for Trevor. Like he's
my hero. But I don't want to do it. So I totally understand if you tell me to, you know, get
stuffed. And she said, All right, I'm just gonna put you in. So I went along and I auditioned.
And Trevor, I could tell it went well, it was like an amazing hour that I spent with
him. And unusually, it was in a theater. So I was there, I had this feeling of what it
was going to be like working with him. And I remember thinking if he offers me this,
I'm gonna do it, because I need to work with this guy. It was just so clear. And really,
that was the turning point when someone like Trevor, none kind of and then he took me to
London to do Oklahoma. That's when I thought, all right, that was the turning point for
me. And he was the one who gave me that confidence to see, okay, so you're getting work in Sydney
and Australia, can you make it overseas? And he was the one who gave me that.
It's interesting. Is it sort of like being an athlete where you, with obviously a different
life cycle, but where, you know, you show these glimmers of greatness early on, but you're still
constantly evolving in the craft. So for example, consider like a Tom Brady, right? You know,
everybody loves to talk about, oh my God, you look at him and his combine, you would have never
predicted what he could have done. Of course, he's the backup to Drew Bledsoe. And if Bledsoe
hadn't have gone injured in the 2001 season, who knows how long he would have sat on the bench.
But then once he got his chance, all of this preparation he'd done in advance, he was sort
of ready to unleash it on the NFL. Did you sort of feel that you were in this constant state of
pent up potential and you just needed an opportunity to demonstrate it or was it much more
incremental than that? Still is incremental. I still, I marvel at those people who have the,
I know what I have to offer. Give me a shot. Give me the ball. Give me the ball. Like,
come on, coach. I marvel at that kind of confidence. I've always had the courage to say,
give me the ball, whether I felt like getting it or not. And I realized that that was essential.
At some point you get it. In fact, I was pretty scared of drama school. And I just had a rule.
I just put my hand up when they said, all right, we need someone to do the scene or we do it,
put my hand up. Because mainly because I didn't want to sit around for an hour and a half being
scared whilst watching everyone else. I just wanted to go. So if you and I were bungee jumping,
and I was scared, I'd be like, Peter, I'm going first. So I, but really, and I think some people
saw that as courage, but or confidence, but it wasn't, it was more. I just wanted to make sure
that I didn't miss an opportunity to try and to grow. And I think for me, what happened with
something like Trevor Nunn, it wasn't like, ah, yeah, I'm going to be great in this or this. I
just felt like a thoroughbred running in the paddock like, ah, this just feels so good. And
by the way, part of my head's going, this is Trevor Nunn who's worked with
Judy Dench, Patrick, you got you name it, Ian McKellen, like the greats. And we were having
this kind of great sort of repartee. I could just it felt like a match. And that feeling of a match
just made me go, all right, yeah, I deserve to be galloping in this paddock. And hopefully that'll
continue. What about you? You are one of the most, this is, I'd written down some questions,
this is not one of them. But you're obviously one of the most successful doctors in the world.
And listen to podcasts, you know, when was the moment where you knew that you could look after
some of the most demanding, high achieving people on the planet?
You know, that's tough. I don't probably the same way that you would say it's not entirely clear.
I don't, I don't think that I, I don't feel like I've got to some point where yes, I can do this
and everything. I think there's a, there's a constant sense of am I doing enough? Am I learning
enough? What am I missing? What am I forgetting? What could I be doing better? How can we make this
process better? But what I think I can say is it was probably in the, it was probably about a
year ago that I stopped feeling like an imposter. So that was a big transition, right? That was a
big step forward, which is there was this sort of lingering feeling of what if you're, what if
you're just nowhere near as good as people think you are. And I think I'm over that now, which is
only a year ago. Yeah. Only a year ago to get to the point of it's okay. Nobody is perfect.
And don't, you know, you're not representing yourself to be all knowing. And you're not an
imposter. Was that the drip, drip, drip of achievement? Or was there a crystallizing moment?
Yeah, that was, that was a lot of therapy actually. Right. Yeah. That was learned on the couch.
Not, not it. So that actually became, that was a big challenge to my identity, I think. That was
also recognizing like how much of identity is wrapped up in what you do versus who you are.
And I think so part of it was like kind of releasing my identity being involved in my work.
Wow. Which is an ongoing struggle, right? How do you remind yourself of that? Do you have a way of
reminding yourself? Yeah. I think honestly like kids are probably the best part of, kids are a
great reminder of that, which I know we're going to talk about a lot, but I think a lot of the
things I do are, have the potential to warp my head around my identity. So exercise, you know,
driving a race car, shooting my bow and arrow, medicine, all of those things have the potential
if I'm not diligent to consume me in a way that also sort of determines my self-worth.
Right. But if I anchor to my eulogy and not my resume, which is sort of my, I think I've shared
this with you, but that's, that's kind of like my mission statement in life is make your eulogy
better than your resume. Then I just say, look, these people here, these little people, these,
these kids are the ones that are going to matter at my eulogy. So sometimes I'll come in the house
after shooting really poorly and I'll see my little boys running around and it's just much easier to
now dismiss the thoughts of how frustrating it is that I can't shoot that well today when I sort of
see them playing and realize, well, if I play with them, they don't even know the difference.
And I think that's true of medicine as well. Right. So brilliantly articulated. I just need
to drill down on you said, am I doing enough? I completely relate to this. I'm, I'm an overworker.
The job for me is what do I really want to achieve and how can I do it with less? Because I think
insecurity has led me to overwork and that I guess I'm asking you that question. The, am I doing
enough, which certainly helped get you and I to where we are today, right? Because we probably
did work harder than other people. We never stopped, but it's clearly not actually not a
disciplined recipe for wellness or happiness or being a good husband or good father. Right.
Um, how have you made that transition? Very, very slowly. Do you worry that you won't be good enough
if you don't worry about being good enough? You know, this is something I, I've spoken at length
with Esther Perel, who's someone you know well and come to respect greatly. Um, yeah. When I wrote out
my recovery contract a year ago, a little over a year ago, um, this was a very important part of
that recovery contract, which was, um, being able to on a daily basis journal about the trade-off
that you describe, which is if you start to prioritize your eulogy over your resume, you will
make deliberate trade-offs that may sacrifice your performance in the short run. And you have to be
able to accept that and you have to be able to write about that in a sort of dialectical way,
which is it is okay to say goodbye to an opportunity today in exchange for something
that you value more in the long run. Um, and it's, and it's okay to acknowledge that I think
was her point, right? In other words, don't just, don't just just sort of shove it under the rug and
say, well, I'm just, you know, I'm going to be much more focused on my family and less focused on my
craft and act like that doesn't matter. No, that's a very deliberate trade-off and it's okay to
acknowledge that that's a trade-off and it's okay to acknowledge that you might pay a price for that
in the short run. So how specific is the journaling? I'm not a journaler. Give me, can you give me an
example? What would it look like? I actually enjoy journaling a lot. I think it's one of my
favorite activities that augments my mental health. Um, I, you know, you and I have spoken about it,
but I, you know, for me, therapy is a very important part of this. I'm, I have a number
of therapists actually, and I, I'm involved in, you know, sort of, I do sort of regular psychotherapy.
I do something called dialectical behavioral therapy, which is something I'm really interested
in and I've become more and more fond of as a tool to help me change behaviors. Um, but in that
journal is sort of where a lot of thoughts go in an unprocessed way. And then in fact, one of the
chapters of my book, which you've read, you're one of maybe six people who's read it actually,
that chapter basically wrote itself because it was simply extractions from the journal. I basically
just went back to two volumes of my journals and literally just sat down one day. This was actually
at Esther's recommendation and put sticky pads in piece in pages that meant, you know, that sort of
took me back through the story. And then the next day literally just wrote 26,000 words basically
into that chapter out of, out of those journals. So, um, I recommend it for a lot of people. I,
I do think that it's a, it's a, it's a great way to process info and, um, you know, it's private.
I've never shared it with anybody. Um, so no one's read it directly. Um, but it's a, it's a place
where I can be as honest as I can be anywhere. It's a great, can I talk to you about that chapter?
I won't mention, I mean, it was a great privilege to read. You were the first person to read it.
Wow. I remember being incredibly moved by it. It was so articulate and honest,
a vulnerable, smart, and you could tell it was years of synthesizing everything. And I remember,
I think the first thing I told you after reading it, I think it was chapter, it said chapter 15.
I think it was chapter 15. That's right. I said, dude, for me, that's gotta be chapter one. I said,
because if I'm going to you, if I'm picking up your book, because I want to improve my life,
whether it be my longevity, my health, my, this, my body, yeah, I might think I want to improve
my blood pressure results or whatever, but actually in the end, we all just want to
be better humans, right? We want that eulogy to be stronger than our resume. And that was one of
the greatest examples of teaching that I ever heard, which came from your ability to go, I've
failed here, here, I've learned this, I've learned that. And I don't think I've ever heard that from
a doctor before, to be honest. And it made all the other chapters go, sure, tell me what to do about
blood pressure, tell me how to train, tell me how to, I'm in, because I could see where I was going.
And I just, yeah, I can't wait for people to actually read it. Even if they only read that
first chapter, you'll get a lot from it. Yeah. And it's so interesting to know how
it's going to shake out. Just now, that book is being, it's in the process of undergoing a major
revision. It's far too long. So that book, when it's submitted was 180,000 words. It needs to be
chopped down by a full third. So, but I've said a couple of things to the editor. And one of them is,
I feel strongly about this chapter staying in the book, because there was even some discussion about
just discarding that whole chapter, because it's so different from the rest of the book.
And as much as I'm afraid to put that chapter out there, because in some levels, it's all my mistakes,
right? It reflects so poorly. But I also think what you say is true, and what we'll talk about,
I think more is true, which is living long without living well in terms of mental health.
It's a form of torture in a way. And I want to obviously talk about the fountain,
which is one of my favorite movies that you are in. And I want to explore some of those themes
when we get there. Yeah. Well, I imagine, like I was thinking, when I was asking, I said, we have
stuff in common, but it is different for actors. I mean, in some ways, every time I do a job,
you're open to criticism from critics or people or bloggers, whatever, but I actually feel the
internal pressure from your industry, other doctors, academics is more brutal. In fact,
I like if I do a job, Leonardo DiCaprio doesn't write an op ed and go, you know, this guy is
the worst. He's like your fellow actors, my bitch about you, I'm closed doors, but you,
your fellow actors are not getting out there trashing you. Whereas I think that's a real thing.
Tell me if I'm wrong, but in the medical industry, there is, but I'm sure I think it's tougher for
you. I think it's tougher for you. No, you're on a much bigger stage. You're on a much bigger stage.
And you, I don't think in the history of, what do you, what's, what performance are you most proud
of on the screen? There's elements of the fountain. It's, I'm going to say elements. I'm super proud of
Les Mis. There was some really frightening stuff for me and elemental stuff. Logan,
because I knew that was a 17 year journey to get to that. There are moments in prisoners in,
moments in the prestige, the first movie I ever did, which no one has ever seen called
Erskineville Kings, which we shot in three weeks. First time I did a movie. I actually
proud of a lot of stuff in the front runner, which, you know, it didn't come and go, but
in quite land in the way, I guess we all hoped. It's sort of, it's moments are very rarely
kind of come away from a film without criticism, personal criticism.
That's my point, right? Is, is there's no matter how great a job you do, there's always someone
given the stage you're on, that's going to say something that is, represents a total lack of
understanding of what's, what actually took place. And so, in that sense, I think that,
I think the criticism that a, that a, that an actor or an athlete, a professional athlete or
a politician, and look in our culture today, politician's a dirty word, but I got to believe
there are some of them that are still good. And so, you know, think about a job where a 60%
approval rating is amazing. Like that, if you're a politician, a 60% approval rating means you're
exceptional and that means 40% of people can't stand you. Speaking of approval ratings, I love
this statistic. You know, these Q ratings, right? Do you know that you have the highest Q rating in
Australia? Your Q rating, which is a measure of popularity and likability is 99%. And I think the
next person after you is 67%. Yeah. It's a, I, I, a friend of mine who runs Foxtel, which is like a
big sort of cable network in Australia. And he did come from marketing originally in PR, but
anyway, he rang me and he, he told me this. Why did he tell me, I think I was going to do something
like a commercial for something. He goes, and so the Q rating is more around if you're going to
endorse a product. Yeah. How much do you trust this person? Exactly. Yeah. And he rang me and he said,
for the last eight years, you've been the number one guy by such a long way. And he said, but here's
the thing. I know you're going to hear that. And all you're going to think is what, there's 1% who
don't like me. What do I have to do to get the 1%? That's exhausting. That's probably the, and I
laughed my head off and there's certainly an element of truth to that. Well, that's why you
absolutely could never go into politics. The worst. When I did the front run and people said,
Oh, you want to go to buy certain? No. In fact, when I, when, when I did you meet, did you spend
time with Gary Hart, by the way, in prep for that movie? Yeah. Yeah. I went and spent time with him.
And let me just, before I forget, when I asked, told my dad, I was going to go and study acting
and I sort of wanted his blessing. Very, my dad never gave advice about, there was, you know,
he always thought it's your choice. And then after I make a decision, he let me know what he thought,
which was super frustrating at the time. But now I think incredibly wise and disciplined.
But I said, I'm getting into acting. He goes, I definitely think you have the talent, but I think
you're too thin skinned. That was his comment to me. So I've always kept that. And actually it was
helpful to me. I don't read reviews. I'll get a, I'll get the temperature of the while. Someone
say, what's, what's the temperature here? What's the basic idea? But once I start reading,
particularly when you're doing stage, it gets into your head. And actually a compliment is
sometimes worse than a negative. The negative can fire you up. Oh yeah, I'll show them. Oh yeah,
really. You know, but a positive like it can, can kill you. But, but that's, so there's sort
of different, right? There's the review for on screen where you can't do anything about it.
The work is done. It's out there. Then there's the review on stage where you're going out night
after night after night. So do you, do you think about those types of reviews differently?
Totally. So I really don't look at the reviews for on, on stage. Again, I'll just try and find
that the thing, because I like, for example, I did a show called The Boy From Oz. It was back in 2003.
We did not get well reviewed. I did not read any reviews, but my feeling on opening night,
being on stage was like, man, this is landing. Like this connects with people. This is, I can feel,
it's great. So I remember we got together on the next night we were back on and we were in a circle
and our producers came and they did one of those, don't worry, we committed to the show. And I
remember looking around and going, what's going on? How bad was it? And it turned out it was not great.
And so in theater, particularly New York back, particularly back then, if you didn't get a review
from the New York Times, it could kill your show. Because a lot of the other reviewers followed
that. Most people look at the New York Times and it depends, ticket sales depend on that. So
movies, it's not always dependent on that. So anyway, we ended up, but I could just, I was like,
no, I feel this connects. I really feel it connects. And we ended up being kind of a massive hit. And
it did actually, I could feel people came back and back and back. One woman saw it 200 times
out of 400 shows that I did. It was people just, I could feel them by the end, we were like, you
couldn't get a ticket. So in that way, I'm kind of glad I didn't read those reviews, because I knew
no one knows better than me and all those other actors, not even the director. I know when it's
landing a bit like a comedian on stage. And you know, something is landing or not. And someone
could write a review and it will, but film is different. Film, you're removed from it. You're
not in the editing process, unless you're part of that or directing it. And you never really know
how it's going to land. And I do actually now think I've sort of grown up a little bit and think
it's worthwhile reading really good reviewers to see what their take is on it. But I think I was
always basically scared to read what the hell is this guy doing on the screen? Like he's not that
good. I don't understand it. And that something like that would just bring me to my knees. That's
what always scared me, I think. So does Deb have the same sort of relationship? Like when you
are doing something or when she is doing something, can you not read for each other? I mean, is it
harder to see your spouse going through something that you deem unfair? And then do you have sort
of an agreement that says, look, you can read these reviews, but I don't want you to share with me
the nitty gritty of it. You can give me the Gestalt if it's productive for me. Like how do
you navigate that? Yeah, that's exactly how it works. So I remember I did my one man show here
on Broadway and Deb came down to me. She goes, I've read them all and they're amazing. And I know
you don't want to read them, but you have to read this. It's in the New York Times and you need to
read it. So I read it and I was like, Deb, I don't think this is a great review. She goes,
what are you talking about? It's amazing. And I said, I don't think so. There was a line in there
that I remembered to this day. All Hugh Jackman asks of his audience is that you love him,
loving you, loving him. And I kind of went, what? But in my heart, I knew that was like,
this is kind of bullshit. He's really, he wants you to think that he's really there for you. But
I'm not sure he is. It stuck with me to say I'm ever going bright red reading it going,
is that am I am I anyway, and Deb was like, Oh my God, I'll never get to you again. But I kind of,
in a way what I didn't want to hear, I kind of, it might've been a throwaway line from the review.
I don't know, but it's certainly, but ultimately, I think it helped me because it made me go.
All right. Really look at yourself. Is that the real me? Because I'm doing a one man show. It's
elements of my life. How much am I manipulating that to show you what the version of me I want
you to see? Which is, I guess what that line is about and how much of it is actually me.
And that's a work in progress for all of us. If I do that show now, I would say I'm more authentic
than I was 10 years ago. But it's a good question. And Deb is like a lioness. She'll just want to
lop someone's head off if they give me a bad review. She's very, very protective. I'm sure
Jill is the same for you, right? Yeah. I mean, Jill, well, this is funny. So Jill really has
enormous disdain for social media, which is really the place where people are going to attack you the
most. For example, recently I put out a number of podcasts that dealt with vaccines, vaccine science,
and a lot of the misinformation around this. And not surprisingly, you're going to get a very small
vocal minority of people who are just going to attack you over this kind of stuff and do so in
a very personal way. It's almost impossible for these people to say, this is your interesting
take on the science, but have you ever considered such and such? No, no, no. It's usually like,
you're in the pockets of pharma. You're an idiot. Literally, I had one person compare me to Adolph
Hitler and say that what you're doing is propagating so much lies that are going to hurt so many people
that this is like Hitler killing Jews. So when you have this type of vitriol coming at you,
Jill's view is, why do you even do this? Why in the world do you do this? Why would you ever
have a single account on social media that even gives people an opportunity to comment?
What's your answer? It's that, look, I don't really look at these things that much. Frankly,
it's very rare that I look at them and it's even rare that I would respond. Maybe once every
six months I have a lapse in judgment and I'll actually respond to someone like that trying to
clarify something. I'm O for 20 on ever changing anybody's mind who's in that stage. So you'd think
after the first 10 I would have learned when someone comes at you with that, that you can't talk
rationally with them. Joe Rogan gave me really, really great advice a few months ago after a
particularly awful attack. He said, because I said, Joe, how do you cope with this? How in the world,
because you're such a polarizing figure and he just said, post and ghost, post and ghost.
Whenever he puts something up, he never, ever, ever looks at a single comment.
In some ways that's our analog, I think. Yeah. But in the end, I guess you're doing it because,
I can't imagine, do you care about those people who are saying you're right off the table?
No. I mean, when someone says something so ridiculous, it doesn't phase me. I think what
does bother me though, truthfully, is that I know that a lot of the people who have really warped
views about science will suffer for those views. Science is a hard topic and I think scientists
have not always done a good job explaining it. I think that people do sometimes pay a price
for this. I think in some ways I have empathy for people who are, I think, being misled.
Obviously, I have incredible empathy for parents of kids with autism who think, this vaccine did
this to my child, even though there's not a shred of evidence to suggest that. But I understand,
of course, you want to have someone to blame for this. I think if anything, I just want to be able
to offer those people some hope that says, hey, you didn't do this to your child.
So that's part of what I think makes me a bit sad. I think that's why your book is a bit of a
game changer for me in that it's incredibly humanizing. I think a lot of people feel,
with medical stuff or with doctors, they want confidence. They want to feel like what they're
getting is the right answer because I don't know. I don't know. I haven't done any science. I don't
know. Should I take this pill or that pill? So you want the confidence. Sometimes that can come across
as arrogance, I guess, from some doctors. And then people want to question it and lump it in with some
kind of government conspiracy. I don't really understand that. But your book, I think, will go
a long way to just humanizing it and saying, hey, I can be wrong, by the way. And I've been wrong.
And here's how I've been wrong. And here's what I've learned from it. But I've done a lot of work
on this. And this is the way forward. I want to kind of ask you something about, I've never asked
you this before, but you live in a world of data in many ways, right? And you clearly kind of love
data. I think you love the puzzle of it and that. And you know, you've helped me out some things
where I can, you love solving. I want to do it this way, which has amazed me. Have you ever gone
against the data with your gut? Like your guts just said, he really should stand on his left foot
and turn around four times and there's zero data on it. Or the data might say, this is ridiculous.
Have you ever gone with your gut instead of the data? I'm sure I have at times.
This is a ridiculous example, but probably the best example of my life, choosing to marry Jill.
Right? Like if I remember, we were dating when I was in residency and
it was, I just didn't think I was, I just at the time was so focused on my work. And I just wanted
to be the best surgeon in the world. I mean, I was so maniacally driven Hugh and how she even put up
with me. I'll never understand like every, you know, so we're already working 110 to 120 hours
a week in this hospital. And when I would get out of the hospital, I only had two priorities,
exercise and more practicing and reading. So I would have to read, I made a commitment to read.
I don't remember exactly what it was, but you know, something like 15 pages a day out of surgical
textbooks. I ended up spending a few years summarizing the top shelf of my bookcase,
which was, I forget, I think it was like 17,000 words of surgical text into 150 pages. And then
I also would practice doing these very delicate anastomoses every night with my surgical instruments
in these models that I had built. And so when we were dating, like even before we would go out for
dinner, I would have to do these things and she'd be sitting there twiddling her thumbs,
sitting on my bed while I'd be doing these things. And then I'd even make her come over and inspect
that. I'd be like, you know, put the magnifying loops on and look at that. Do you think that's
perfect? Is that, you know, could that, and we, it became a joke. But, but really I was like,
and even she had sort of like this thought of like, you know, this is a guy who will never put
me first, right? He will always put his work first. And- Did she articulate that to you?
Not then, but later on. Right. This is actually a very personal story, but which I guess I'm
sharing now, but we, the week before our wedding, we really collectively had second thoughts.
And we sat outside. I remember exactly where we were and thought, maybe we shouldn't do this.
You know, maybe I'm just not the kind of guy who's ever going to want to be married and,
and that's that. And, and I guess you could argue that was sort of the data talking to me. The data
was saying, Hey, you know, surgeons have a divorce rate of, you know, X and-
Did you initiate this talk? Yes, I did. No, it was a hundred percent me.
And then something in my gut just overrode that. And by the end of that day, I decided that, no,
there's something here that I don't yet understand and it's going to be more important. And I will
say, and you know, you now know how my life has turned out. It turned out to be the most important
decision I've ever made because I don't think I'd be doing what I'm doing without Jill. In other
words, when I think of all of my, all of the, all of the, the, the difficult things that have come in
my life, having her as the base of my support has been the most important thing. And it's,
she is a unique person. Everybody would say that about their spouse, I suspect,
but so it's, it's, it's that she's the right person for me, right? She, she is the right person
for me. And that would not have been apparent from any amount of data. But I do think my gut probably
sensed that, sensed an ability for an unconditional love that probably even transcends what most
spouses could provide. Yeah. I mean, it's clear from the outside that you and me to be together.
Again, that's a gut feeling you get. I actually, I have a little bit of a similar story at the
beginning of my relationship with Deb, who is down there. Deb, are you okay if I tell the story about
you at the restaurant? Remember the story of you in the restaurant early on talking to someone else
and I'm like, Oh, she wants to break up with me. Remember that story? Okay. You okay with that?
All right. So early, it's two or three weeks in, but I, I just had this feeling
two weeks in and now Deb and I met on a television series. She's the star and it is my first job. So
we started dating two or three months into it. But both of us, it's an unlike, you never date
your co-star. That's the biggest cliche. It kills the series. The whole series was about this kind
of sexual tension between, in the prison, between the psych, psychologists played by Deb and the
prisoner, me. So everything was wrong about it. Anyway, getting through that, we get together,
we're there and so happy and I'm falling in love. And I'm just like, this, I've never felt like this
before. This, I didn't really know. It could be like, I didn't know that there were human beings
like Deb on the planet. I didn't know. And I was super happy being single. First job out of drama
school, 26 happy days. And we go out two or three weeks in, never spent a night apart. We go out to
dinner. I want to say there's 14 people at the dinner. I sit down sort of on one corner and Deb
sits in the literal opposite corner on the other side. And I'm like, fine, you know, whatever. Like,
that's okay. And at one point I was telling a story and the whole table was listening to my
story or I can't remember what it was. But I remember looking down and Deb had her back turned
to me talking to someone next to her. So apart from Deb and that person, everyone's listened to me.
And the thought just came into my head or more in my gut. Oh, she's trying to rake up. She's trying
to rake up with me. And that stayed with me for the dinner. When we get in the car, I just knew it.
And I said, and this is not me at all. The me up until that point was, if I'm getting the data
that someone wants to break up with me, I'm out first. I'm out. Like, I'm not waiting there to
get dumped. I'm going to like, see ya. Like, so I'm there and I'm in the car. And I turned to Deb
and I said, you're trying to work out reasons to break up with me, aren't you? And she, I remember
she goes, yeah, yeah. I said, I get it. I said, listen, I know you're scared. Remember, it was my
first job. There was a star at the time. Her New Year's resolution was, I'm not going to date any
more actors and definitely none under the age of 30. Right. And I'm 26 year old actor in his first
job. Like I was her worst nightmare. And I remember these words came out of my mouth. I still to this
day doesn't, didn't feel like me. I just said, well, I understand you're scared. I get it. I guess
I would be too, but don't worry. I know we're going to be together for the rest of our lives. I can
feel it. So you better just get over it. And she just laughed and that was kind of it. That was
sort of the moment. Like, and you there Deb? She's not, no, I thought I heard her. Anyway, so that,
I'm forever grateful. I mean, I knew and I'm the most, you know me, I'm very indecisive. I can't
whatever lunch, have this or that or super indecisive. And somehow with Deb is one of those
moments where she just went, oh, this is absolutely clear. And it is the greatest relief. And when you
get that, I always say to people, just if you get that moment, just go with it because it's turned
out, obviously be one of the greatest blessings in my life. We just celebrated 25 years together
and it just gets better and better and better. And there's no way I would be here or as happy or who
I am today without it. Can you think we've got that in common for sure. Yeah. Do you, do you have
any other moments like that? I, when I grew up in Canada, there was this sports network called TSN,
the sports network. And every night they would show a highlight called the TSN turning point where
they would pick one game and there was one play and one game that totally changed the game.
And so I've always had in my back of my mind, this idea of like you're at the TSN turning points of
your life. And that was obviously one of them for you, right? That's a very important decision. Had
you fallen into your default state, which is to run totally different life. What are some other
moments that you've made enormous, maybe at the time they didn't feel like enormous decisions,
but they totally changed the arc of your life, whether it be personally or professionally.
Yeah. I'll tell you a little one, which is, I just want to tell you this because it's a little freaky.
And I think it goes back to, I was brought up in a very religious household. My father was converted
to Christianity by Billy Graham. So we lived that sort of life very much. Every holiday was church.
There's, and I remember praying every single night for most of my childhood through till 1516.
The God just tell me, make it clear to me what you want me to do. That's all I ask. I actually do
not care what it is. It could be anything, but I want to know that I'm on that path. The idea
that is in Christianity that I was taught was there is God's will. It's a narrow path. It's
easy to go off it. And most of the world would distract you from it, but stick with it. So
I went and auditioned for a drama school after I'd done a degree, majored in journalism. And
before I went off to do that career, I thought I'm going to audition for this drama school because
long story better. I'd spent time doing a play and just loved it. And it was clear to me. I
loved it more than I did my degree. So I went auditioned when I got in. And that's a long story.
I just got in. Had you acted before? Had you done any acting before?
Amateur. I'm only amateur. So I did amateur all through school, even a college. I was in
local community plays and I did a play at college in my last semester, which made me
realize I was spending way more time on the play than my thesis and everything. So I thought
someone's off here. I might just spend a year while I'm waiting. I'll do this course. And I found this
course that was in Sydney. I wanted to do a course in England, but I couldn't afford it.
So I want to do this one in Sydney and I got in and I opened up the, I remember opening up the
letter and it said, you're accepted. And I was so happy. And at the bottom, it said,
please make payable your check for the tuition of three and a half thousand dollars. Now, that's
not going to sound like a lot of money, but in Australia, when I was growing up, you didn't pay
for tertiary education. So university was free. It's now not quite like that. But I was like,
I hadn't even thought of it. And I just finished a degree. My dad had helped me and I was like,
three and a half grand. I don't have three and a half. Whatever. I screwed it up. I put it in
the trash. And so I thought, oh, well, there goes that. They're not meant to be. And it's going to
sound like an exaggeration. I swear to you, it's not. My grandmother had died three months before
and the bequest came to me the following day and a check for three and a half thousand dollars.
And I'm literally fishing through my trash can, which of course I never emptied anyway,
so it was there. And at that time, I wasn't as as sort of maniacally into Christianity that way,
but I was like, oh, that's just super clear. So that's that's sort of a TSM moment, but not
really of my own doing in a way. But then I at the end of that year, I was offered,
I got an audition for Neighbours, which is a soap opera, but it was like a seven o'clock at night.
Beverly Hills, 90210. Yeah. Melrose Place. It was a massive show in Australia. Huge in England. I mean,
the amount of people who come from it is as actors that you would know is extraordinary. I got offered
a role. It was it sort of came out of the blue. I auditioned. I got it. And all of a sudden I'm
like, oh my God, I've got a role. And I remember the contract is two thousand dollars a week. I'm
like two thousand. What am I going to do with two thousand dollars? This is unbelievable.
Two year contract. This is crazy. But I was in the middle of auditioning for a major drama school.
I auditioned. It went well. I got a call back. I went again. The contract hadn't come through
for Neighbours. So I just kept sort of auditioning and long story short, I got offered a spot. And I
had a weekend where I had to decide. And I remember I had an agent back then who was begging
me like, what are you doing or thinking you must what are you talking about? This is Neighbours.
This is a job. You must do it. And I went to my dad, who I as I told you before, he wasn't really
in the business of giving advice. And I said, Dad, I just don't know what to do. I see both sides.
I don't know what I should do. Like my agent saying, go into the thing. And I said, I don't know
go into the thing. And money, go off and study. You'll have money and you'll have experience.
You've been trying to be camera and then keep studying. And I said, but dad, I just don't trust
myself. Once I start working, then I'm going to do the training. And I don't feel I deserve an
audition at the Royal Shakespeare Company, which is where I want to work or the National Theatre.
And I don't think working on it. Anyway, I'm doing all this. And I remember he said to me,
he goes, Hugh, I can't answer that for you. That's the decision you have to make. You're 22.
And this is your choice. Right. Thanks, dad. I was like, I went off. I just put it away. Don't
think about it. By the next day, it was just clear to me that idea of I want to work at the Royal
Shakespeare Company. When am I going to get the training that makes me feel I deserve to audition
for that? A bit like you. You want to be a great surgeon. You didn't want to just, I'm going to
work in that little place down there. I've got the job. At least I can do that kind of work.
No, I wanted to have the opportunity to do everything. So in the end, I decided, I went
to my dad and I said, dad, I've decided to go and go to drama school and not do the job. And he goes,
oh, thank God. Oh, I'm so happy. I said, what? I said, you knew all the time. He goes, yes,
but I just, if I made the choice for you, then I would have denied you that moment of maturing
and growing. And it would have forever been dad told me. And I remember that to this day,
but that was one of those great TSN moments for me at turning points.
Your relationship with your dad is kind of amazing. How old were you when your mom left?
I was eight. So I was eight when mom left, but she had been unwell. First year and a half of my life,
I'd spent with my godparents. So I think mom went into hospital when I was about,
we postnatal depression major, when I was about three months old, she went into hospital. So I
was with my godparents for that period. Then I came back and I remember periods where mom would
be just going away for a week, which I guess was some kind of reset. Or maybe I actually don't
know if it was like an official sort of facility or rehab or just getting away. By the way, five kids.
Yes. And you're the fifth. You're the youngest. Yeah, I'm the youngest. So,
yeah, so when I was eight, she left, I don't think she ever planned. In fact, I know she didn't. She
told me she didn't plan to leave for good. And it just sort of did. And she wasn't in a great place.
And her mom was not well. So she went back to look after a mom in England. And so I did.
So my dad, from when I was eight, my oldest sister, I think was 15 or 16. So he brought up,
you know, from those ages, he brought up all of us. He's sort of an amazing man in that way.
It's like, if you think about what that decade must have been like,
I don't think he had a moment to himself for 10 years. I don't ever remember. Like,
there was sometimes he used to, he was an accountant at Price Waterhouse and he used to travel
for work. And I actually remember, now I know we travel when I had young kids, like,
just the first two days when you travel, when you have young kids is the greatest thing. When
you go somewhere, you want to go out and go, shut up. No, I want to go to bed at eight o'clock.
I want to sleep and then I want to wake up and I want to read the entire newspaper
from front to back or the other way around. And I want to drink coffee. I don't want to talk to
anybody. But he had an incredible, incredible time. But that decade, I in many ways, I learned many of
my, I guess, ethics, hard work from him for sure. How much do you think that your mom's departure
impacted this perfectionism and this insatiable, probable desire to sort of please people?
Do you feel that that was either conscious or subconscious?
Subconscious for sure. It certainly rocked my world. As you can imagine, I was eight, but
I remember people thinking, oh, you don't really, I remember them saying it doesn't, I'm like,
I totally understand. Like, I think we underestimate eight year olds and also I have older brothers
and sisters. So I certainly have learned after that more about the dynamics of the relationship. But
I was never, and I can't say this for all my siblings. I don't want to speak for them, but
I don't ever remember being super angry with mom. And I, on some level, I always had a kind of
connection to her and a sort of understanding that she loved me, that she had done her best.
Like on some level, I think I always felt that, but it was certainly a whole for sure. And I had a
lot of fear that got exacerbated from that. So I guess you'd call that anxiety now. I didn't,
at the time, just scared of lots of things. And I guess that unknowing, I can rationalize it now,
that that perfectionism in me is you got to work really hard to make sure people don't leave,
right? You've got to be your best. And it's interesting. I just finished watching that
great documentary by Ken Burns and Lynn, is it Novik? I always get her last name.
It's called College Behind Bars, and it's about the Bard Prison Initiative. Anyway, it's an
amazing doco. If you haven't seen it, I highly recommend it. And I actually, not lost a minute,
my first job was in a prison, playing a prisoner. It just feels to me very similar dynamic. Like
when you have some kind of abandonment or a hole, my way of cutting that was I'm going to make sure
that I please every, that no one's going to want to leave me behind. Like,
that's not going to be, I'll work, whatever you want me to do, I'll work hard, I'll do this.
In that way, I think it's really, I think it's sort of the opposite in some ways of people who
end up being rebellious. By the way, my next brother up was really rebellious and all of that.
And I was the opposite. I would do all the things my brother did, but I never wanted anyone to find
out. I just wanted to stay in the good graces of everybody. And that's how it impacted me.
That is such an amazing topic to explore. As you know, our mutual friend, Paul Conti,
who's really one of the most thoughtful people when it comes to understanding trauma.
And certainly your mom leaving when you're eight, if that's not trauma, I'm not sure what is.
But one of the things that's so interesting in talking with Paul is kind of the ways that
two people in the same household even could have different adaptations to the same trauma.
And so one could move one way and your brother could move another way. And yet those were both
serving very important needs to each of you. They were both adaptations that were serving you
and usually more productively than unproductively, which of course brings us back to kind of how we
open the discussion. At some point, those adaptations generally become counterproductive.
At some point, those adaptations catch up with you and they start to become maladaptive instead
of purely adaptive. And I think that's the thing that people struggle with is understanding,
which again is another form of dialectical synthesis, which is, hey, there was a day when
this was a really good adaptation and it sort of got me to a certain place, but now it's a little
counterproductive and that doesn't mean that I can't embrace what it's helped me do, what it's
protected me from. And yet there's still a rationale to be made for changing things and improving.
Well, I couldn't agree more. I actually want to ask this
to you because knowing your history in particular, I didn't know that you had that desire to be the
best surgeon in the world, but it doesn't surprise me when you did athletics or you did swims.
It wasn't a three mile swim. It was a 50 mile swim. It was like you would push yourself through
crazy limits, physical, mental, spiritual, emotional. There was that need to push, am I right?
Sure. Yeah.
So I've only recently read as a man think of, it's like written in 1904. It's like this big.
It's a great book and James Allen writes in that, that the growth is part of nature. It's very
natural growth and it is uncomfortable, but it is the natural state. So I think both you and I
went beyond that natural state in our need to be successful or to achieve or to grow.
We would go through unusual amounts of pain or sacrifice. You've done it, I would say more than
me. I think your capacity is one of almost everyone I know has been so huge. Well, now
I know you're more sort of measured about it, but what is that line? How would you coach your kids
about what is the line where it's actually destructive and not productive?
This is such an important topic that I struggle with a lot and I talk about a lot with my wife
because I don't know the answer, right? There are times I look back at my upbringing and my
childhood and I think, boy, I look back at the child and I feel sorry for certain things that
the child endured, but then I think, but look at what came out of that, right? Look at the resilience
that came out of that. But then I think I don't want my kids to experience some of the things I
experienced as a kid, but I also want them to have the internal drive to do things that I wonder,
how can that be created from a positive place? Because I do think most of my drive came from
a negative place. It's important, at least for me, to separate the part that is above the surface,
that which one sees the striving, the achievement, all of those things from that which is beneath
the surface, which is, is it coming from a place of self-love or is it coming from a place of
self-flogging? I think in my case, pretty much everything I did came from a place of self-flogging
and therefore I think there's really no scenario under which that's the right thing.
Right. So if the answer is, could you be sort of, so first of all, I don't think that's uniformly
the case. I think there are lots of people who achieve, who are doing well in whatever it is
they choose to do, who can do it in a way where they're not sort of flogging themselves to get
there. Right. And what I want to understand better, and one of the things I'm really interested
in exploring as a parent is how do you encourage your kids to achieve the best that they can do,
but not from this place of beating themselves up to do it?
Totally. I remember asking my dad, Oscar, who's now 21, was maybe four or five or six, I think I
even was born, and I remember saying to dad, I said, dad, give me some advice. You've had five kids.
Like you'd watch him. We were on vacation. What am I doing? No, no, no, no, you're doing great. No,
that's fine. I said, come on, dad. I had to really push him. And he said, you praise the kids too much.
I'm like, oh, he goes, you know, when Oscar takes his plate off the table and puts in the dishwasher
and thank him for that. That's expected. And I, in that minute, I was like, oh, yeah,
all of us, my siblings have this sort of need to do more to please. And, you know,
but sometimes I go, what sort of work, you know, in some way it works. But what is that balance?
I don't, for my dad, I do praise him too much because I guess I want to focus them on,
I like following like the Seth Godin approach. Like I read a lot of Seth and I know you like Seth,
that way of following your fear, the thing that scares you, that there's some illumination in that
and having something to say and doing it for other people. And in that way, it takes care of a lot of
stuff. So there is a responsibility for every single person on the planet to be part of this
community. And I try to say that to kids, like what, what are you offering? What is it you've
got to offer? And it's, even if it's something you love, there's going to be days you don't want to do it.
But I want them to do it from a place exactly as you say of self-love.
Ava just went off today to do a pre-ACT test. I was just, I texted her this morning, I was mad
with myself, I didn't say it to her before she left. And I wrote this, have fun today. No test
is a reflection of you, who you really are. Just be curious and open, love you. And I'm sure she's
rolling her eyes when she read it, right? But I guess that's what I'm trying to be curious.
I try to say to her when she goes to school, I was like, ask challenging questions today. And she
was like, roll her eyes. I'm like, don't just do the good girl. I got my grade. And at the end of
that, I said, the world doesn't need those people. I was one of those. I was school captain of my
school and this and like that. And I always spend my homework and blah, blah, blah. But that's not
what the world needs. And all these people who are going to do what they love know when enough is
enough. More is not always better in terms of consuming or just achievement. Be disciplined
about doing less. All those things are what I'm trying to teach him. Speaking of kids, how much
have your kids struggled with being the son of, you know, famous people? You told me a story once
that I thought was very touching about how devastated Oscar was when he learned obviously
retrospectively that John Lennon had been killed. And I mean, first of all, it's just amazing to me
how much that troubled him. It really troubled. I would say he was eight or nine when he found it out.
And there were tears for, I'm going to say on and off for three months, three to six months.
There was a period where I genuinely said to Deb, I've got to step away. I think I've got to step
away. It's too much for him because he was genuinely frightened. We would go to Central
Park all the time. We would go to the story that is past the John Lennon Memorial. And he just saw
me as a famous person. And I did try to explain to him that there's different levels of fame. There
is a mania with some people, Tiger at his height or Bieber or, you know, that's never really happened
to me. John Lennon and the Beatles. That was a whole different thing. But to an eight, nine-year-old
for him, he just found it really difficult. He hated the paparazzi. He hated the attention when
he was a little kid. Like I remember he was about two. People would come up to us at a table.
They want to talk to me. And you know what people, they want to talk to you. So what they do is they
come up and go, oh, hi to the kid. Hey, look at that. You look so cute. And it's like his way in.
And people would come up and Oscar would just go, he would look at him and go,
and I thought that's the most honest response at this table right now. I just wanted to be, but
of course, you know, I never want to be like that with people. And sometimes people overstep. They
don't mean to. They don't know. Or sometimes as kids, but for Oscar, it was always brutal. And so
it was on and off. And when he was a little older, it never really left in a way until he was like 16.
He would, if I said Oscar, I need you to, why am I going to clean your room? You got to clean your
room. You know, why don't you clean your room? He goes, well, why would I listen to you when you
won't listen to me? And I would say, what do you mean? He goes, well, you won't stop acting.
So why am I going to clean the room? You know how that important is to me. And so we really
sat down and had a conversation about it. And I said, I said, you don't understand. Like I didn't
ever expect to be famous. Like no one ever does. I don't think none of the actors I know, you got
a drama school of all he is and you hope you can pay your rent. And if you don't, you're going to
do something else. But it's a really rare thing, let alone be really sort of successful. That's
just a crazy thing that just sort of happened. And I said, well, he said, well, why don't you
just do theater? Like when you were just doing theater before the movie came, I understood
people in the theater were, you know, they would clap you and then you would have your normal life.
I said, you know, well, I really loved the films as well. And I said to him, it's not what I set
out to do. I didn't set out to be famous. I'm not trying to hurt you. You know, I understand
I want to be there for you. And he looked me straight in the face and he said, so if you had
your time again, would you do it differently? I was like, wow, I said, that's a really confronting
question. If I knew what was coming and what how it might impact you. I said, I would find it really
difficult. I might have done things in a different way. But I said, I probably honestly still do it,
Oscar, and not for the fame or the money. But because the people I get to work with, I pinch
myself every day, like I'm having the most amazing time. I'm working with incredible people.
So imagine there's something you love to do. And all of a sudden you get to work with other people
who you just can't believe every single day. I said, it's so fulfilling to me. I never really
got it. You just but I remember thinking that's a really brilliant question for a 12, 13 year old
to ask. It was a really difficult time. And I remember there was a period where I thought,
if I was truly loving, you know, I should just drop it. For whatever reason, it's just too much
for him to bear. Even now the hand has always been really balanced about it. And I'll tell you a
funny story about that. We arrived in Australia after a 24 hour flight from New York. And once
we got through customs, there were a lot of photographers. So the way we would handle that is
I would separate myself, the family would go ahead, it would, you know, split them up. And ultimately
they needed me in the photograph. So and in Australia in particular, the kids are famous because
Deb, Deb is very famous too. So they want the family shot. So I would just separate myself. And
a neighbor just came back and started to walk with me. I said, Oh, babe, you don't have to do that.
That's fine. I guess it's okay. I said, we're walking along and they're taking photos of us.
And I said, How is this for you? Like, would you prefer that it was just an account like my dad and
you never had to go through this. And she said that we just got off a first class flight on Qantas
from New York to Sydney. I can put up with this for like 40 seconds.
And I thought, you know, let's she's just sort of super, super balanced about it and kind of gets it.
She's just always seen the, all right, there's a bit of a trade off here. But no, I'd still
prefer to fly first class for 24 hours and put up with two minutes here, you know. Yeah. And then,
and then I've been lucky in the paparazzi thing just to follow up. Now, I remember we came straight
from the airport. I was super worried and we were going down there to shoot a movie. So I was there
for 12 months. They all followed us. I'd rented a place and I'm like, Oh, they know where I live.
Of course, they're going to know where I was renting. And we pulled in and I could see behind
me 15 photographers. And I thought, and Oscar was dark. He was dark. And I thought, I don't know,
we're back home. We've got a year here with my family, with his cousins, with everything.
So I just said, everyone go, okay, you guys go inside. And I said, I'm going to unpack.
I wasn't going to unpack. I went out of the garage and I went out onto the street and I
started walking towards him. You can see the cameras come up like, Oh, this is great. He's
going to confront us. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
He's going to, this is like gold for them. That's what I want. Right. And I, one guy, Shane, I said,
Hey Shane, and he puts his camera, he's sort of like the most senior guy. I said, can I have a word?
He comes over. They all put their cameras down. They didn't quite know. I said, dude,
we're here for a year. I said, you could see the airport. I get, this really, really bothers
my son, which means it really, really bothers Deb and I. And I don't want to get in a situation
where we're hiding inside a house in Australia. And I said, so, but I understand you need
something. So what do you need? And he goes, we need you at the beach with your shirt off.
I said, I'll see you there Bondi tomorrow morning, 8.15. So I literally had just made a deal. I felt
I've made a deal with the devil, but I thought in the second I thought, okay, this is the lesser of
two evils, I guess. So I went down the next day and I trained with my mate Mike and I said, Mike,
I'm sorry, but I have a feeling there's going to be some photographers when we get into that.
And he was hilarious. He goes, awesome. Cause I've never looked better. Like
he's the same age as me completely ripped. And so he's like, bring it on. So we go out there.
It was the most uncomfortable 20 minutes of my life because there were 15 of them and they were
in the water up to their waist. Like it wasn't like we're on the beach. I'd given them this
permission and I was like, what have I done? What have I done? This is so embarrassing. So I have a
swim. I catch a couple of waves. I come back in, Shane just nods at me and I said, we're good. And
he goes, we're good to their word. Never saw him again for 12 months. Wow. Not with my family. Like
that would take me occasionally. Like if I was somewhere, I get that. That's fine. I can live
with that. And other, yeah. So that was my little deal with the devil, which worked out well. There
was, I thought some honor amongst them. And I was pretty impressed that they kept that for
12 months and it would end up being a great year for us. You know,
there's so many things I want to, I want to pull on that. One of them is just the amount of energy
it takes to perform and then the amount of energy it takes to not perform. Right. So, so there's,
there's a clear, you know, so to me, the stage and the screen are very different and I want to
explore them both in separate ways, but let's go back to the greatest showmen, the stage production.
Right. So when you came and stayed with us in San Diego, I guess that was two years ago, right?
Yeah. When you and Irv came and one of the things that amazed me was the whole purpose of having you
come and spend a day and a night with us was to give you a break. Right. It was like, I don't know
how many weeks or months you were into that, but it was a grueling schedule. It was hotel,
hotel, hotel, hotel, Deb and the kids are back home. It's just you and Irv, you know, I, it's
like, you can't even leave your room. You're having meals in your room. I mean, it's this,
it just, it just struck me as, you know, a very difficult experience. And we were like, look,
we want you to have a totally normal day where we're going to work out in the gym. We're going
to do nothing. We're going to have a home cooked meal and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. But, you
know, it just happened that like my, my sister-in-law and her husband are in town, the kids are in town.
So there's like all of my kids, all of their kids, everybody's there. And like they worship you like
no other because they don't understand you're not the greatest showman. Like they actually think you
were the greatest showman. Right. And what amazed me is actually that's a movie I should have mentioned
too. Yeah. Well, I don't know why I didn't. So I couldn't believe, cause, cause our thinking was,
okay, Hugh, let's just make this, we're going to go to the gym, go have a shower, go relax. We'll
call you when dinner's ready. But you couldn't wait to jump in the pool with the kids. You played
with them for like an hour and a half while I got dinner ready. And I, and I just remember thinking,
Hugh, this is your chance to turn it off. Like you don't have to perform here. You don't have to
please these kids. This is, this is your window to not please anybody, but just relax. And yet it,
I just, I was amazed at how much, first of all, it didn't look like it was an obligation to you.
You genuinely looked like you were having fun, but I was just, I didn't know where the energy came
from. That that's really my question. Where does that energy come from? Well, it, it kind of energized
me and it surprised, it did surprise me because I was very tired. It's a game of exhaustion. I guess
the same for like during the NBA season, you're traveling in this and it's, it's managing recovery
and, and, and like you, you're really just doing your best and it's a bit monk-like. And when you
get a day off, cause that was a day off for me. It was a rare thing to be in the city without
traveling in a day off. You think, okay, this is the time to recharge. And when I was there,
we jumped in the pool. Like, look, if I, I definitely would have jumped in the pool with a
I love your kids and the kids were there and I would have done it for five minutes. You know what
I mean? If, and done enough to, you know, okay, the kids have spent time with me. They got to know
me a little bit. It just was energizing. It was somehow genuinely fun. First of all, the kids
forgot within five minutes, I was a greater show. I mean, we were just playing a game and they got
competitive and I sort of felt like a kid again. And you realize sometimes, particularly in a
creative field, actually, I don't know if it's creative or not, you've got to go outside your
zone a little bit. And it becomes an inspiration. I, I learned this when I was at drama school,
like my teacher goes, if you're an actor, and you didn't say yes, when someone offers you a ticket
to the ballet, then you're not a real actor. And I'll be like, the ballet, but I'm interacting,
he goes, it's another creative art form, you've got to, you don't know where the inspiration is
going to come from. If you're just gonna listen to the songs that you think you like and go to
the movies that you like, you're just gonna stay in that lane as an actor, like you need to mix it
up. Right. So I didn't mean to do it, but in a way, it was like, I have been on my own. Like,
well, I've been with the group and then you get to the stage and you've got 20,000 people and you're
leading the group and tell you when you get home, you just want to sleep and read. And I was just
missing my kids, my family just being silly and playing in the afternoon where you don't care about
whether you're overusing your voice or, you know, and again, great food, wine,
those berries. I remember awesome. What was it that you put it was a month?
You brought the wine though. That was the finest. That was a, that was, that was a,
it was a Penrose, right? It was a Penfolds Grains.
A Penfolds, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Penfolds Grains, which I'm happy to give them a plug because it's probably one of the finest wines.
I have since been procuring it, not to the level of the bottle you bought. That was one of the
finest. Yeah. Penfolds. That's right. But anyway, so that was that. It was a joy. It was a real joy.
And by the way, couldn't you see it in it? Irv has been my, like, when I first knocked on the door
to Deb's house, Irv was over there helping a change of clocks. Like, Irv's known Deb since
November 11th. So, and it's become one of my closest friends and he ended up working with me
and still does occasionally on things. But we both went away that night just going,
I didn't realize how much I needed that. We're good friends, family barbecue, like a Sunday
afternoon, just where you let loose. You have a couple of beers, a glass of wine, good conversation.
And it was totally energizing. Yeah. It was, it was great. And of course the next night
when we came to the show, I simply couldn't have imagined what that was going to be like
because I had deliberately not read any reviews also. So I knew nothing about this. And it sounds
funny, but going into it, I literally assumed it was going to be a stage version of the movie,
not realizing that it was actually more of a stage version of your life, which included the movie.
And the opening tribute to your family immediately makes that clear. Right.
And it's so, it's so moving. It's so touching that at the end, I mean, I don't know if you remember
the email I sent you that night when we got home, but I mean, I was, I was really kind of,
it was very hard for me to all take in and how gracious you are with an audience, right. And how
much energy you give. And that's the part that again, of all the things that an actor can do,
it's that ability to be on stage night after night and put out that type of a performance.
Because how many times did you do the greatest showman on stage performance wise? 92, 92. Right.
So on average, let's assume that each person is only seeing it once. So they're not going to go
to multiple shows. So you can, you know, you can largely figure out how many people have seen that.
But for each of them, it's the only time they see it. So you're the type of person who goes out there
and every night you're making sure that they see the best version possible. Like you have to do
that 92 times. Right. Very few people live in a world where that's the case. I mean, I think
great athletes will often say that, right. This Muhammad Ali used to say that all the time, right.
Right. You know, you may never see me fight again. I want to make sure every person knows
on this night they got to see the best version of Muhammad Ali. I don't know where that energy
comes from actually. Because it's both, there's a physical piece to it that I can sort of understand.
Like you could be well enough conditioned and obviously you are, but there's actually an
emotional piece to that that I can't relate to. Well, first of all, thanks for saying those nice
things. And there's, I think for me, the stage in particular, whether it's an arena or the theater
is as close to the spiritual, I think my job gets. I've had moments on a soundstage where
you're filming something and it feels incredibly intimate and powerful and things are happening.
But you rarely get that feeling of this is a sacred space. I get it almost all the time. And
I make sure that I do everything I can every night to do that. So there's a few things,
for example, triggers for me. I never really wear aftershave, right. I just, you know, occasionally
I do it, but I usually do it on a special occasion. So for me, I always wear aftershave when I'm on
stage because just that smell makes me go, oh, oh, special night tonight. This, it's a visceral thing
to waiting in the wings before I don't look through the thing. I want to hear that sound
of the audience gathering. I actually had an idea, which I got talked out of on that tour of
warming up on stage as people were entering. I'm like, why do we have to have this feeling of,
oh, we're waiting for Hugh and we're in and we're waiting and the show's going and there he is.
I was like, everyone does that. What if they saw me on my foam roller and I'm out there and I just
say, hey, what if it was more like in my living room and then we're still going to do the big
opening and the lights are going to go out. But what if we just dropped all this pretense? Oh,
my God, you came to see, you know, like anyway, I got talked out of that, I think for security
reasons in the end. Did you still get, would you get nervous before each show? Yeah, yeah.
Which, you know, you mentally just go into excitement and there's definitely a buzz.
There always is for me and it comes out of that. I want this to be a special night. And for me,
when I go to the theater or to a show, like I've been to lots of concerts and doesn't matter how
good they sound or how big the production is. If I feel like this is the exact show they did in
Portland, Oregon, like I'm pretty sure this is the exact same show except Hello, Melbourne. Hello,
Sydney. That's it. I just go, oh, we're just sort of churning out the same show. It just feels,
doesn't feel sold for me. I always want an audience member to go. I was there on the night when,
you know, that feeling of something happened that night, because it is a special thing. And I know
what it takes. And I love going to the reason I stand in the wings is because when I'm sitting
in my seat, I'm reading my playbill and I hear the hubbub and I literally get tinged. Like,
I'm so excited. I've always been like that since I was a kid. So clearly is where I'm meant to be.
But it certainly is important to me. And I'm actually an introvert by nature, not an extrovert,
but somehow I can feel on a stage, even like in San Diego that night, more relaxed. I would stare,
say my heartbeat is even lower apart from when I'm dancing than when I'm just on stage. I can feel
very calm and myself. I don't know where that comes from. I think that's, I don't know where
that comes from. That's just maybe that's more not made, but that I certainly had that feeling.
And did you have to train yourself to do that? Because to be an introvert and yet to be able to
be so energized by that type of an experience seems counterintuitive to me.
Yeah. Well, the reason I got into acting, why I wanted to do it, I had, I told you I was brought
up in a very religious sort of upbringing. I certainly, that idea that there is a spiritual
element to life, there is a higher purpose to life, to everything you do. The activity in the end is
not as important as fulfilling that. And my definition of that is far broader than what it
was growing up. I certainly don't believe there is a literal heaven and hell and only those people
who believe this set of beliefs are going to the heaven, everyone else. But that's what I was
told growing up. I don't believe that. I don't think it's as linear in any way. But I wanted
to get into acting for that Socrates idea of know thyself. Like in, you know, on the Delphic Oracle,
there's just two words, know thyself, that's it. Understand who you are, why you're here. And
acting for me was the way to do that. For you, it was medicine, like, and that was your path,
you know, meant to be clearly meant to be on, right? For me, it was acting. So I was always more
interested in that. I can tell you now the most spiritual moments I've had in my life have all
been on stage. It's like the moment in which everything stops, things are floating in that
feeling of timelessness, where things will be happening, you can be singing a song, but somehow
you can be acting, you feel a connection with 2000 strangers, 20,000 strangers, we're just all
of a sudden together, that feeling of consciousness, whatever that is. I've only I've had those
always on stage. In a different way, obviously, with family and close friends, you can get that
moment. But that certainly, that out of body experience that people talk about, that spiritual
experience, for me, has only ever happened on stage. And that's why I always go back to it. That's
always my goal. Why I was embarrassed by that line in that review, he just wants you to love
him, loving you, loving him. I'm like, no, no, that's not why I'm trying to use that. Jeez,
okay, that's not my higher self. That's my lower self. If it's true, I really want something deeper.
And so that's why we really on stage, and I don't think I've learned it. I think that's somehow a
mass of everything I'm trying to do in being this world of feeling completely at home and connected
on stage. It's where I have that spiritual meaning, I guess.
Is it different if Deb, Oscar and Eva are in the crowd?
Yes. Yes and no. Like, I really am trying to be, it's actually wonderful to me. Like when you guys
were there in San Diego, I really love it. Because I know in a way that you were seeing a different
side to me, and a real side of me. If you ever see me on stage and I walk out and I do this,
I did it at the Oscars, I did it at everything. So my, everything I do first off is I try to find
their eyes. Now my kids look down because they're just terrified I'm gonna call them out or put a
spotlight on them. I always do this to Deb, because this is where they're one of the greatest gifts
for someone who is sensitive to have a marriage with someone where you know that no matter what
happens, if I completely suck, if I die, if the career is over, if whatever happens is over,
she's there for me no matter what. So when we were together that that night of San Sebulabar,
she always says it was a real, we were already married but
she said you could feel I'd become a star. That night, like there was a hubbub and talk
and she's there at interval and then after, and all I remember was coming backstage, it was
excitement, it was a big thing for me, big, my big lead role I guess in a way. And I said I just
needed to see Deb. I said a bunch of people came backstage, I said I just want to see Deb first.
And I remembered, I just held her and I said no matter what happens, you're the most important
thing to me, like anything else. And so now to sort of remind myself of that, I always put my hand
over my heart just as a signal to her to say you're the most important thing to me. And it
gives, it just really calms me down. So in that way it's different. At the Oscars it really helped
when you go out, and this is when I was hosting the Oscars, if you see Meryl Streep, Brad Pitt,
Angela, like they were all front row, front three rows, just every star that ever lived,
they're all looking at you like what were you thinking man, like why did you say yes it is.
Just to see Deb, it somehow puts that perfectionist in me, just quines it down.
No matter what happens, everything's going to be okay.
I feel like you've asked me a bunch of questions. I think it's my turn. Can I ask you a real tough
one? Can I ask you a tough one? Sure. And I actually don't ask this of anyone, but I remember
I was very moved, you asking or just explaining in your book and you said it on this, the eulogy
qualities as opposed to resume qualities. And of course as a doctor you've seen a lot of death,
you've experienced it, you I'm sure you have patients who are facing it or faced it.
Are you scared of death? Yourself.
So it's really funny. You haven't read the epilogue of my book, which I only wrote
maybe a couple months ago. And in the epilogue, I actually answer this question for the first time.
Oh, wow.
Because I don't think I understood it until very recently. I would say
I had always been afraid of death, not afraid of dying. And they're obviously different,
right? Dying is the mechanical process of going away. I think I probably have the same level of
trepidation about that. There's the uncertainty, am I going to die in a car accident? Am I going
to die this way or that way? But that's actually a far distant concern to me. I think my greatest
fear was my fear of not being here. And I think that fear took a dramatic step forward when I
became a father. And I think the reason for that is the constant tension between what I'm doing
and what I should be doing. And therefore, I think my initial kind of obsession with this
topic of longevity, which started about 10 years ago, in some ways, although I didn't know it at
the time, was really trying to delay this thing I didn't want as much as possible, which was leaving
this planet without having done what I was supposed to do. Because deep down, I kind of
knew I was doing a bad job of it, which was not being a good enough dad, not being a good enough
husband, not being a good enough fill in the blank. So I think that through everything that
I've gone through in the last year and so I've got more confidence in the stuff that I'm doing
that I actually don't feel afraid of dying in the way I used to. Right. Yeah. In that you-
I'm coming to grips with the fact that- You can answer those questions in the affirmative.
Yeah. I'm doing- I'm a good dad, a good husband. Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, that's pretty awesome. That's a great place to be. I mean, I think if-
I was just talking to my mate yesterday about that, the idea of coming to terms with, you know,
I've done enough. There's more I want to do, but we've done enough. It takes a huge weight off.
I think for people like us, that idea of having to do more-
Let's talk about this in the context of The Fountain, right? Which is, I think,
one of the most amazing movies. I mean, obviously you and I are both just such fans of Darren.
Yeah. And I just, I think he's literally just one of the most gifted people imaginable.
Yeah. And what I like about that movie, oh, there's so many things I like about it, but
is that it's open to so many interpretations. And I actually want to hear yours because I'll share
with you mine. And I've never heard Darren's. I don't know if Darren's actually spoken about
what he intended it to be, and maybe he didn't. He has.
Has he? He has. He has.
Okay. Well, before you tell me, I want to tell you what I think. But obviously the theme of this
movie is immortality, right? This is a big part of it. How did you get inside that character of
Tomass, Tom, Tommy? How did that challenge you and how did it make you think about your
own mortality, if at all? Hugely. It was a, so we, 17 years ago now, Darren came to see me do The Boy
From Oz, a musical. I was playing Peter Allen and he just, he said, I've got a script for you. And I
read the script. And I was like, I read it that night because I was such a huge fan. I thought,
I don't fully understand this, but I think this is about the meaning of life. Like this is,
this is as close as I've read to, this is what it's all about. And I just said, I'd love to do it.
We spent a year working on it. Before we rolled one foot of film. I did Year of Tai Chi. We did
yoga. I had to be in this. There's a position you have to sit in. Yeah. Yeah. Took me a year to get
my hips, you know, flexible enough to be able to do the Lotus position. And also just understanding
the history of it and the mentality of it and the obsession of a man who, I'm now literally,
as I'm speaking it, I'm seeing some of the parallels with your chapter in your book, right?
He's loved for his wife who is sick and dying and he's raised to, to heal her and cure death.
And he's obsession with that and the absolute need to cure death. When I spent a lot of time
talking to doctors, there's a lot of doctors who believe that's in some ways, theoretically possible
that we could cure every disease, which is interesting. Probably another question I want
to ask you, but I had to go further inside deeper into my own emotional reservoirs, journey.
And in many ways, it was the most lost I've ever got in a character. I'm not an obsessive person
by nature. I'm quite. I'm balanced. Even when I was partying with my mates, I'd be the guy at
three in the morning going, you know, guys diminishing returns from here. I'm out and
there, there'll be dead or be dead or midday the next day. And I was just naturally that's,
that was my thing. Or maybe I was too scared to kind of just fully go down the rabbit hole. But
I spent, and I'm so glad you called that out, Darren, because he also became a great friend.
And this was actually in film, the closest I got to a spiritual experience, where the rolling camera
and stopping your camera, just the blur and that feeling of living, particularly when I was in the
spaceship in that bubble. There were moments where it touched on emotions for me, where an hour later
I was still crying, like everyone's gone to lunch and I'm
racked with sobs, like it was touching on things. And that was totally because of Darren and his
belief in the sacredness of the creative space. He's just a pure artist. And, you know, funnily
enough, all that stuff, you know, Tim was talking about the I wasca and all of that, which
I'm not sure how much I should say, but this sort of came out a lot of that. But this is way back
when, you know, Darren's always been a searcher in the
in consciousness, in the broader sense of consciousness and meaning of life, the eternal
immortality. And he's not afraid to ask those questions. I feel like I've gone off track a little
bit. Like the found out, like I feel that it was certainly the most is the only time I came home
from a movie where Deb said it took you three or four days to get your feedback on the ground.
It took me a while to get grounded again. And I remember, by the way, with Darren, I've never
really had this before, but I formed such a creative bond with him that there was all that time in the
spaceship where I was on my own and imagining in this where he's gone on to live, you know, forever.
Darren would be right next to the camera, the camera's here, and he would just be right there.
And I would ask for him. So I said, Darren, can I have you close? And just him coming there would
open literally with my heart open. He just created a feeling on stage. And he would just
he just created a feeling on space in the space that was sacred. And in terms of what it's about,
I used to ask him all the time, I like to explain this and he goes, what do you think? So I think
expose and he goes, yeah, I said, right. But what's it about? He goes, no, I'm not going to tell you
like it doesn't matter. It's it's whatever it is for you as it is for the audience. I go, yeah,
got it. But come on. So I remember I kind of I would bug him about it all the time. And when we
went on the I would be at press conferences and a panel and he'd get asked a question and he would
start explaining the move. And I'd be like, looking down, I'm like, that's what that was about.
I was completely wrong. Like I'm literally, I'm on the complete wrong page there. And he would look
down at me and just sort of smile at me like it's okay. Because it was true for you. It is true.
I actually don't I wish I could remember exactly, but I had the whole timeline. Like everyone asks,
which is the present? So yeah, and I don't know why for me, it resonates that the present is the
present. That's the way I find it. That's the way it spoke to me was that the present was the present
and that the past and the future were sort of metaphors and were sort of spaces of sort of
emotional travel. But that what was really happening between Tommy and Isabel was actually
her physically dying in front of him and him not being able to save her and him struggling with
this loss of control and this fact that we're mortal. Yeah. I could be entirely wrong. I could
be entirely wrong. That's what I thought. That's what I thought. And I think from memory,
Darren at the conference was saying the future is the present. But I'm actually not very
confident about it. I have to I know I'll just bug him. Yeah. He's one of the most genius
filmmakers. And by the way, so much fun. Like he's really, really fun. And a good, funny guy,
super smart, super interesting. Yeah, I love him. We catch up all the time now. And he's great.
It's so bizarre that I forgotten again, what the whole meaning is. But to me,
I sort of love the mystery of that movie. Yeah. Like the it's sort of the mystery of life. It is
whatever you, whatever we want to believe it to be. It is actually this is a question I want to ask
you. Manifestation, right? You hear all about it. Are you buying into it? Do you believe it?
I don't know. I mean, you know, I think I'm still in many ways sort of grounded to
my science, my reality. What about you? I'm a recent convert to it. You're evolving. Yeah.
I actually, my dad was always about it. Always this. And in my head, I'm like,
it just sounds nice. And I get the placebo effect if you believe something is probably going to come
true. And certainly with fears like don't hit the tree, don't hit the tree. Oh my God, the tree.
You're thinking about obsessing your head in that way. But I used to think, no, and actually
my life is a good example. He said, I used to say to people like if I had manifested when I was 23,
I wouldn't have thought up half the stuff that I've done or has happened to me. Not even a
quarter of it. I would have had far less sort of scope to imagine what could be. So maybe I would
have eliminated my life if that was true. You know, so that's not what it's about. So it's like,
Devin, I played backgammon. We played backgammon a lot, like probably 15, 20 games a day,
really for 500 a month. Yeah. It's like our little backgammon is such a great game because
it's five minutes. Like chess is like a commitment. It's minimum 30 to an hour. You just don't really
often find that time, right? Backgammon, you can just go play one game, three games. Anyway,
I will, when I was first introduced the idea, I wanted to believe it because I was hearing it
from a life coach that I still see to this day. And I thought, you know what, I'm going to test
this out. I'm going to test this out and back him. And it worked. It literally worked. This whole,
I was losing my for the month by and there was no way I was going to win. I was like, all right,
this doesn't make any sense that I'm going to win this month. I have to win like 20 games to three
or something like that to win. Okay. I'm practical. Close my eyes. Believe it. Feel it. Imagine it.
Okay. Imagine your senses around it. If anyone dies is rolling into double six, the fact,
the frustration of Deb that I'm winning, winning, winning. And I won. And I'm like,
I almost didn't want to test it again because I was anyway, I'm a recent convert, but I imagine
like even if you publicly said, yeah, I'm kind of into it, you would probably get completely
destroyed. You would be professionally destroyed. But anyway, I'm just sort of,
that's why it's a very unfair question, but I do find it fascinating. And maybe for me goes back to
my biblical religious sort of upbringing, all that stuff in the Bible of you can move mountains.
And if you believe it, if you know what is prayer, what is prayer to imagination,
then you hear coach K famous letter to self. Have you heard that?
I haven't let it to self. No, I think it was on CBS Sunday morning. He used to do this
thing where let it to myself. So you write a letter to your eight year old self. Listen to coach
case and coach K would have all the players do it or no, he did. He did it. Okay. He did it for
himself. A letter to himself when he was eight and you can Google it. Yeah. No, when he was,
I mean, he did. Yeah, yeah. But a letter to his eight year old. So, yeah.
And he talked about, he didn't say the word manifestation, but the power of imagination.
He said, if there's one thing I could tell you, all those hours spent imagining that you're
hitting the game time buzzer when you're really on your driveway out the back and you're going past
six defenders and there you are lay up and you win the championship. And he goes, that those
hours you spend are preparing you for the future in ways you do not yet understand.
But I actually think to me, that's very plausible, right? I think that that's entirely plausible
because I think that is rehearsing a set of skills and literally my relating a set of
channels in the body that do come into play. Right.
Where I can't come up with a plausible explanation is where it impacts randomness
that's out of your hands. Right. In other words, I can absolutely see how it can actually material
alter the course of something you have control over. But I don't understand the mechanism by
which it would go otherwise, which of course is exactly the great conundrum of how one
reconciles religion and science. Right. Like, you know, religion makes sense to me in the sense of
why it exists. It exists because we had no tool to explain the natural universe until 400 years ago.
Right. Right. Until the 17th century, there was no tool to codify
nature. Right. So if you think about how many thousands of years our species existed
without a framework or a tool to explain what we saw, why is it bright out? Why is it dark?
Why are there stars? Why does anything happen? Well, if we don't have a tool that can say, well,
there are gravitational forces and this planet is rotating this way, well, then you have to come up
with something plausible and that something plausible becomes stories and those stories
become the basis of religions. And that's why going back to a question you asked me a long time ago,
I think that's why science is very difficult for people to understand. It is not remotely innate.
Evolution has not at all prepared us for it. We have not been selected for it. It's, you know,
the scientific method is literally only 400 years old. The idea of controlled experiments,
like this is a fraction of time in evolution's history, right? This is less than one, one
thousandth of 1%. Yeah. So the likelihood that this would be innate to any of us is preposterous,
right? Yeah. And I'm sure there are some people for whom these ideas come more naturally than
others, but just as there are probably some people for whom acting comes more naturally than others,
but the reality of it is if you want to be good at your craft, you've got to practice it. And
similarly, learning to think critically is very difficult and very unnatural. We're wired to
pattern recognize and come up with stories. Right. Absolutely. Evolution actually prepared
us very well to do that because you were rewarded for that evolutionarily, right? Right. You know,
if you saw, you know, Billy in your tribe. What story do you tell your kids?
I actually love to, I love to try to explain science to them. I really do. But if they say,
if they say, dad, is God real? Yeah, this is where my wife and I struggle a little bit. I think my
wife likes to demure a bit more and say, well, you know, I mean, I think that's, you know, she'll say
more like that's a bit of a mystery. I'll just say, look, there's no evidence of that, you know?
You know, and that's, you know, I'll just, and again, that really, amazingly, I haven't been
asked that question directly, but what I like to be able to do is kind of not get dogmatic with them
and say, of course not, that's a stupid question, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, but instead say, well,
you know, it's an unanswerable question. Let's be honest. It's an unanswerable question. So
maybe you'll find yourself being an agnostic more than an atheist.
But let's think through how would one even go about answering that question and how would you
test some of the claims that would come along with that question? You know, things like that.
So this goes back to kind of what you said. Don't read your social media tomorrow. There's
going to be a lot of evidence just plowing in. Yeah, exactly. So on this thought of immortality,
let's talk a little bit about Logan because how much affection do you have for Logan? Like you've,
he's been such a part of your life for so long. It's like, I can't imagine how you must feel for
him because my affection for him is unbelievable, right? Like he's not even real. And yet I feel an
affection for him the way I feel an affection for you. Now explain how that's possible, right? Like
you're a real person. You are my friend. I have affection for you. Logan is a character and yet
I feel for him. I weep for him. How is that possible? That's a really, that's a great question.
I think there's something archetypal about the character. I'll go back to my personal connection
with it, but it's a very archetypal character. It's been the basis of many, the outsider,
the reluctant hero. He's a mixture of where we want to be. While most of us want to be,
like that's why he's so cool and I wish I was Wolverine and marches to the beat of his own drum.
And yet he's imperfect too, which is so important.
Completely imperfect so we can relate in that way. I have such a, when you're acting, you have
to fall in love with the character. You've probably heard that before. It's, but you sort of do. You
have to, even if you're playing, you know, Macbeth, if you're playing someone who murders the king
because he wants to become king on any level, you have this guy's a monster, right? But that's where
Shakespeare's brilliant. You get inside his head, his ambition, and you can see it coming. You see
failings. It goes without saying every character I've played, there's some level of love or affection,
but with Wolverine, I've, I've felt at the beginning, like he was teaching me, it's going to sound
weird because I'm a people pleaser and he's the opposite, right? He, he almost to his own detriment
is an outsider. I'm desperate to be an insider. I will do whatever I need to be to be on the inside.
And so playing someone who was the opposite was so great for me. So kind of believing and fun.
And it was difficult. It was not a particularly happy set. I didn't feel comfortable for quite a
long time. I didn't feel I really had the support on set.
In, in just the very first one?
Just the first one.
Okay. Which was what year? Was that 2000?
99. We were filming. And I was, you know, someone else was playing the role.
Doo Gro Scott had the part and he got injured on another film and that film went over. So
they had to recast. So I was sort of like, I got cast, they were shooting, it was their third day
of shooting. And I was coming to do an audition on set. So I was a bit of a last minute thing.
I could just feel a bunch of people like, we had the guy like, who's this guy? And then I just
don't think I found my feet for a while. I was trying to, I was came from the theater. We rehearsed.
Let's work it out together. And it just wasn't that. And, and I felt very much on the outside.
And I actually thought I was going to get fired.
Pretty reliably, I felt that I was close to getting fired. And, and the humiliation of that,
I remember spending a weekend talking to Deb. And I was just pitching to her about this person,
that person, you know, this situation. And she actually said to me, she goes,
I don't think you've done enough work. I said, what? She goes, I can, I understand why you're
angry and probably been embarrassed and scared. But it sounds to me like you actually, you haven't
done the work. Like, and a really, I spent all that weekend and I went, Oh, that was, that's
another TSN moment. That's right. Yep. That's great. Great spouse from your wife. Great spouse
to kind of hold your hand. I know. Yeah. Tell terrible you poor thing. And they shouldn't have
done this and more there, but you got to pull your finger out and get to work.
Yeah. And I did it. And on that Monday morning I went in and I, instead of trying to make scenes
work, I just add like the first thing I did that day, I ad libbed everything. I ad libbed, I rewrote
it. I did everything. I said, I'm not doing any of the dial. I was like, I just sort of took over
in a way like I was forced to, because I felt like I was fighting for my life.
By the way, that's something I've got. I'm a pretty nice guy. But if you back me into a corner,
you're going to see the Wolverine in me. I definitely have that and it's appeared.
I've sort of got off track of it, but I just felt like I owed you a bit of an explanation
of that first one. So I felt in a way even closer to the character because of that situation.
Then it was clear to me that people, it was clear to me, I was getting calls from the street. You
could just feel when things are turning around, when you're in a position, you're on set and
they're not loving what you're doing. It's like you've got a bad smell. People just away, you're
not getting invited to the drink after thing. You can just feel there's a jockeying for,
don't get close. So he's a nice guy, that guy, and then you feel them coming towards you.
And I'm getting calls. So I knew that things were turning around. I had no idea what would
happen to the film at all. The success of it, no one knew that. That was a bit of a shock to
everybody, I think. But over the years, my affection just got deeper and deeper. And by the way,
people, I remember people saying to me like, oh, you're doing another one. Like, does it get boring?
All I wanted to say was like, this character couldn't be further from me. And it's like,
imagine you went to the gym, you got yourself into a greater shape, and then you didn't go to that
gym for two years. And then all of a sudden said, right, we're back in the gym again. And you're
like, oh, how do you do it again? It was always like that. And I always had this feeling from the
first one, I was reading the Japanese saga. The first one, I'm like, this is the story we're going
to tell. And, you know, I just didn't really have a say in it. And so by the time we got to the last
one, where I had to say I was really adamant about what we were going to do. And I'd always felt
like I'd let the character down a little bit, if that makes sense. There was more to the character.
And I could easily rationalize that in an X-Men movie because you're one of, I mean, he's one of
the more popular characters, but you're still one of 12 characters. And on any level, if you're the
writer, you've got 120 minutes, you have 12 characters. You just don't, you may have three
scenes for your character. And was prior to Logan, was Origins probably the one that most featured you?
Would that be? Right. Because you were in Origins. Yeah, Origins was what, 09 Origins? Yeah, yeah. Which
was unbelievable. Like, I mean, I've probably only seen it 51 or 52 times, but I mean, it's
just unbelievable. I still then felt frustrated that we hadn't got to the core of who this character.
I just really felt there was a deeper story to tell. And there was resistance for sure. Not amongst
the key people at Fox, to be honest, you know, the key people were like, let's go for it. But then
it was like, if we go R rated, it's probably 100 million from leaving on the table. You know,
we've spent all these years building it. And then I said, got to call it Logan, because this is
actually about more the human being. No, like we've spent 17 years building a brand. Yeah,
Harley Davidson's Harley Davidson. You don't all of a sudden call the Harley Davidson Terry. Like,
that's a Harley. So that we need Wolverine on the post. And I said, me and Jim were like, no. And
again, they went with it. There's a lot of bold steps. And I guess that's why I was super proud
of it because I knew it was going to be my last one. I had. I know that and it just kills me to
hear you say it still. I know that's true. And it upsets me so much. I didn't want to have any
regrets about it. I didn't want to have any sort of, because then I would be doing another one.
Probably. Because I wouldn't have to lose myself. You know, so I just came back to your original
question. I just still pinch myself that I got to play such a great role, that I feel at peace with
it, that I got to do it in nine different movies. That anyone who knows me from any thing just knows
that if they knew me before I went for the audition for and I wasn't getting the part like
it's not so it was felt in every way. It just felt like a great when Patrick
dies. I mean, when Professor dies, of course. I mean, first of all, that is to me one of the
most startling scenes in the movie that you just don't expect. And what's so heartbreaking about
it is how he doesn't realize it's he thinks it's Logan. Right. And, you know, I don't
know. How deliberate was that?
Very. That was very deliberate. And that's where like the writers and Jim Mangold, they
made so many decisions. I was just immediately so proud of when I watched. First of all,
Patrick was incredible. That scene, prior to him dying, he does that monologue, which is
admitting his failures and faults and his regrets and
live. It's not too late for you. Live. I know. You can live like it's so beautiful,
beautifully written, his affection for your daughter is is unbelievable. And he's basically
trying to give you this one last chance to make it all right. And then, you know, I remember sitting
next to Patrick Stewart and Jim Mangold, the director who I've done three movies with is one
of my closest friends in Berlin. So we get to the Berlin Film Festival, which I wrote down on a
sheet of papers. This is the type of movie that will premiere in Berlin, like film film. This is
going to be seen as a film, not a superhero movie, but a film about a real character. So we're sitting
there in that scene where Jim just directed this. So, well, obviously it wasn't there because
my character is in the grave spoiler, all of it, if you haven't seen, but where she walks up,
all the other kids walk off, they've done the funeral. She walks up to the ex, the two sticks
that have been put in the thing. She just takes it out, tips it over onto its side into an ex.
I could get emotional, I could cry now just thinking about it,
weeping. It was so, because in many ways, going back to telling you about my upbringing, that idea of
this is how you were taught, I was taught when I was a kid, this is religion. And at some point,
you have to become your own man. And Wolverine was always his own man. But actually,
he wasn't really an insider. In the end, he was an X-Men. Like he really was the epitome of what
I thought the poetry in that moment, and we didn't know if we were going to kill Wolverine or not.
When we started it, of course it was a discussion. And we all said, unless we earn that moment,
then it's a stunt. It's just like, oh, it's one in and we'll piss people off. If we get a ride,
it was that feeling that I had in that cinema, we were just, and I remembered just grabbing Jim's,
like put my hands on their legs and I turned to Patrick and he was just crying. And you know,
we realized it was 17 years and such a gift in our business where you go in, you meet people,
you become super close three months later. See you later. It's a really odd kind of business in that
way. I don't know if you remember this, actually it was at Darren's birthday, Darren's 50th birthday,
you and I were sitting next to each other and we were talking about the last scene of Logan because
I had recently rewatched it. And I sheepishly admitted, I was like, you're not going to believe
this brother. But the first time I watched this, when Logan says, this is what it feels like,
I thought he was talking about death. Right. And then of course the second time I actually
understood what he meant. Has anyone else ever said that to you? Has anyone ever?
Oh, all the time. Really? All the time. That's Jim wrote that line. I think it was Jim. I don't
think it was Scott, but I think it was, I'm pretty sure it was Jim. When I read that, I was just like,
I thought the same thing because the ultimate, when I first read it, I thought, oh, the person
who's immortal, effectively immortal, and yet unhappy with life, like,
this must speak to you as someone who deals with longevity. What's the point of being around
forever if you've got so much pain and lack of understanding where it comes from? That moment,
oh, this is what it feels like. In the whole movie, you get a feeling of someone who almost
wants it to come like, please take me out of my misery, please, please, please. But then
it wasn't until we were doing it and playing the scene. Oh, no, it was before that. When we
talked about it, I realized there's such a dual meaning to this. People are going to take it in
different ways. Again, that's what Jim Mangle always says to me. He goes, don't, in a movie,
don't tell me one plus one equals two. That's science. Tell me one, in science, I want to know
one plus one equals two. But in art, tell me one plus one equals three, and then spend the
movie proving it to me. It's like, make me go, and an end line like that is just such a great example
of one plus one equals three. It can work on both things. I think Aronofsky had knows that fully.
That was a great birthday party, by the way, wasn't it?
I think it's literally the best birthday party I've ever been to in my life.
I'm with you. Can I ask you something? I feel weird. I do want to ask you this.
It's more trivial than some of the subjects we've been talking about. But when I was training for
Wolverine, at one point, my trainer said, hey, we need to mix it up. I'm going to bring in this guy,
Scott, who's a professional bodybuilder and natural, but natural bodybuilder. And we're just
going to train with him for a week. And we might just pick up some tips. So training with him at
the gym. This was when I did actually was X-Men origins. I was in Sydney. Someone comes up to him
every 10 minutes at the gym and wants advice. Right. No matter what he's doing. And I never
forget the first like he was on the lap pull down and he's doing it. By the way, a great thing I
learned from him that I've used to this day. I seem to be in his shape. You have to just smash it.
He starts super light on everything like it's fun and builds up. He doesn't do one warm-up set
and three smashing it. Like I said, by the time you're doing your third, fourth set, you want it.
You actually really want to lift. Your body's got used to it. It was such a great tip.
Go light. Like it shouldn't feel like a chore all the time. Like, oh yeah, I can do this pull.
This is easy. A little more, no problem. And then you just want to go in and rip it. So he's on the
lap pull down and he could feel someone walking up asking about to ask him, hey, dude, how do I get
in the shape? Right? His whole life. That's what he is. And without turning yours, don't eat carbs
after three in the afternoon. The guy goes, oh, he didn't even ask his question. He walked away.
I said, dude, how often do you guys literally in tons of work, someone was going to ask me that. So
you in your job as a longevity doctor must get asked every five seconds, what's the one thing,
what's the thing you say on the lap pull down to that is the most important thing to change your
life? Oh, no, he said one more thing. He goes, donate carbs after three, you'll lose three to
five kilos in the first month. That was it. Oh gosh. Look, I think there are glib answers to
that question and I think there are serious answers to that question. I think, and by glib,
I just mean universal. Right. So what's the universal truth in longevity? Gosh.
If you're willing to exercise nearly every day, like you're going to end up in a good place.
You know, exercise is a very potent,
zero protective agent, right? That's a very non sexy way to describe exercise, but it's potent,
right? So it's, it's, it really has a strong impact. It's diffuse. It acts in many different
parts of the body and it's very zero protective, right? It really slows down aging. And, you know,
if you want evidence of this, just examine the opposite. Just look at what happens to people
when they are sedentary. Um, you know, you look at someone who, especially someone who's, you know,
our age, who gets laid up in a hospital bed for a week and you look at how far it sets them back,
you know, if you, if you're laid up for a week in the hospital, it could take you six months to
recover from that physically. So, so you very quickly understand the potency of exercise. And,
and so I would just say, don't underestimate the power of exercise, which of course then gets into
all the technicalities. Well, how much of it should be zone two, how much of it should be zone five,
how much strength, how much stability, and of course the devils and the details there. And then
I think the other thing I would say is something we've been talking about all along, which is
don't underestimate the power of relationships because ultimately they are probably going to
play a greater role in the quality of your life than the length of your life. But that matters more.
What's, what's the long, you know, the, the definition of, I think the definition of hell
would be infinite length and misery. Right. So, you know, what can you do?
I love that. I love that you said that about relationships. I, I, I, my best mate started a
charity Gus, he started a charity based on a doco he did on male suicide. And it was incredibly
successful, but his idea in this charity, it's called Gotcha for Life, the number four, but it's
gotcha is the idea that never worry alone, like make sure that you have someone and hopefully
more than one where you can say anything, everything. And he goes, and by the way, like I have that in
my marriage, you have that in your marriage. A lot of people don't, but as long as you've got someone,
a mate that you can, that actually that loneliness and the inability to unload stuff, you need to
we as humans need to unload it. I think that's really vital from my medical standpoint.
Look, this is an example of things that things where my thinking has evolved so much, right? I,
I think that, you know, 10 years ago when I thought about this, I just didn't find this to be this,
this meaning the sort of emotional side of this to be a particularly relevant piece of the puzzle.
And, and I've evolved obviously, as you know, to the complete opposite end of that spectrum.
And now, you know, it's one of those things that's often the case. Once you get to the other island,
you look back and you think, what was I thinking on that other island? You know, because you just,
you can't appreciate what you didn't know at the time. And I think that
there's something about giving to someone else that, and sacrificing that, I think David Foster
Wallace spoke about so eloquently in his commencement address. Yeah, this is water. And,
and the way he, the way he talks about these, the myriad petty ways in which we can sacrifice for
other people. And that's, you know, that's, that's a big part of what it's about. And I think that
any parent recognizes that that on, you know, on some days it can be really tough to be a parent,
but, you know, you're making these sacrifices for your kids, you know, it's not always fun to be a
parent, right? It's not always fun to be married. It's not always fun to do all of these things,
but I think somehow finding the beauty in those difficult moments, you know, when your kids having
a meltdown or when your spouse is really pissed at you and you think it's unjustified, but you bite
your tongue, like there is value in that. Totally. And I think there is joy in that.
Yeah. My brother, my oldest brother, Ian, when my, when my, he's had four kids, when my,
when Oscar was born, he rang me and he said, I'd, hey man, everyone's going to tell you this is the
greatest thing that ever happened, send your life. You're going to be amazing. And it's the best time
your life. And he goes, here's the truth. Some of that is true, but it's also, you're going to be so
tired and angry and frustrated. And a lot of it's going to be really annoying at times. And it's
going to be inconvenient. He goes, it's okay, man. When those moments happened, just give me a call.
It's okay. It was so relieving because of course you get three hours sleep at night,
four hours sleep at night. You're going to be shitty, you know, at times. And of course it is
great too, but parenting is, I tell you, I've learned some, the mirror gets, you know,
shown up to you about who you are so quickly as a parent. Yeah. Very nakedly.
So how do you handle aging in your field, right? You're in a field where you are forever going to
be judged by your appearance. I think the field is harsher on your female counterparts than you.
For sure. For sure.
But nevertheless, how do you think about this process and how do you balance, because, you know,
you're becoming better and better in your craft and you're getting older. And at some point,
I mean, there are, you know, there's, there's the Clint Eastwoods of the world where, I mean,
they just seem to never be able, they seem to transition into that age, like as they go.
Totally. Yeah. I embrace it. Like I embrace it. Certainly 95%. You know, sometimes you go, wow,
or you'll see a photo of had, you know, where you looked and you go, wow, those bags. Wow. Like,
you look like shit and all that. But in general, I embrace it. I, he'll kill me for saying this, but
the guy who did my skin cancer, my basal cell, I had a bunch on my nose. So every time I go in
over the years to do something on my nose and they're doing corrective surgeries, like,
you know, I could just do a little, this bag, it's easy. I could just fix that. Or we can do that.
I'm like, no, I did. And or, or there's, he goes, I could take some fat from somewhere and I can
pump it into, into here. And then you won't get that scar that did it. Because when you look from
the side, I said, no. And he goes, it's my wall. And I said, it's my nose. I don't have that. I,
I kind of have that feeling of embracing it. And I actually enjoy it.
If I'm really honest, part of that, I wanted to stay a movie star. I've got to do that. I've got to
be, is exhausting to me. It feels pointless to me. And I'm happy not to embrace it. You know what
I mean? It's like, I've never really loved that side of it. And it's exhausting, relieving. My
real North star, I look to is Newman. Paul Newman. Everything the way he did his career,
the Newman zone, the way he just kept his passions going. And he did a lot for the actors union
behind the scenes. He did a lot on nuclear disarmament behind the scenes. Like, yeah,
that's, that's the way you're doing. Did you ever get to meet him?
Once, once it was awesome. I was, it was awesome. He was, he was fading at the time.
He was super skinny and clearly not well, but yeah, he's my hero. So thanks for today, man.
You're a hero to many. And you've played many heroes. And I thank you so much for your openness.
I know it's, it's a hard thing for an actor to do because you have this contract with us that says,
as long as we don't know you, we can believe you. Right. It's true. But, but as you can tell from
me, I'm, I want to answer the questions. That's why I'm doing it. So you're right. It's, it's a bit
of a tightrope, but you helped me walk out better than, better than almost anyone else. And I, you
know, I listen, we're friends, but I also listen to your podcast. And I think what you're doing is
really helping. It's helped me a lot. Thank you for that. I love you, man. Give my love to the kids.
Give my love to Jill. And thanks to the two Knicks behind the scenes. They're doing all the work.
Love you, man. I love you too. And please give my best to dev and the kids and look forward to
seeing you in person, hopefully in the next three months. Awesome, man. All right. See you.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes
only, does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.