Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Welcome to this episode of the Peter Attia drive.
This was a really fun one for me to do.
I mean, it was done relatively without much preparation or prompting.
So in this episode, I interview one of my really, really close friends, Mike Trevino.
Mike and I have been friends from the moment we met, which was about five years ago.
And there are just a number of things about Mike that are really interesting and you'll
learn a lot of them in this episode.
Starting with the fact that Mike is arguably the most accomplished amateur endurance athlete,
certainly that I've ever known, but you'd have a hard time making a case for any other
amateur endurance athlete period.
His accomplishments are beyond legendary.
And we go through many of them here, though not all of them.
And that's sort of why I wanted to have this discussion with him.
I was like, Mike and I see each other every week.
We somehow figure out a way to time our travel such that there's one day a week, at least
three weeks out of the month when we're not traveling and we can go out and do a ride.
And it's a relatively short ride.
We ride about 40 kilometers, but it's just kind of this amazing time when we get to catch
up on life and all of the things that we think about together.
And so Mike shares a lot of that stuff today.
He gets into, again, I think you could listen to this and easily come away overwhelmed and
thinking, wow.
There's nothing about that guy's experience that I can relate to because he's basically
setting world records in running, in cycling.
He's doing these things like the race across America that I think it's almost impossible
for a normal person to fathom what that means.
It's impossible for me to fathom what that means.
And I have some experience in these sort of ultra distance world.
But I think he also is able to make the case that the lessons that he learns in doing these
things are applicable to life and they're applicable to specifically things that you
might want to do for your own endurance.
If you're currently able to run a 5K and wondering what does it take to get to the 10K or the
half marathon or you're running the half marathon and you want to run the marathon, what does
it take?
Well, in many ways, it's sort of taking a page out of Mike's playbook.
Mike's a really special guy to me.
Mike and his wife Nada, who are very close friends, have been there for me during arguably
one of the most difficult periods of my life.
And they were the first people to basically show up when I needed to be picked up.
And so I'm forever grateful to Mike and his family.
And I just find that our weekly bike rides on Sunday mornings, which are usually when
we do them, are among kind of the most cherished things that I do outdoors anymore.
So much of what I do is now alone.
I lift weights alone.
I ride my Peloton or my Wahoo Kickr alone.
And this is kind of the one time a week when I get to go and be with somebody else for
an hour, 75 minutes, an hour and a half.
And I value it greatly.
One anecdote that I'll tell before we jump into this episode, just to put in perspective
for anybody who is themselves a cyclist or a reasonably serious athlete, just to put
in context Mike's accomplishments and just his ability.
So about four years ago when I was training very hard as a time trialist, and at this
point Mike was, you know, he was running, but he was kind of done with his ultra distance
career and had not been on a bike in probably a year.
And he was like, you know, I'm going to come out and join you one day for one of your workouts.
I said, that'd be great.
You know, and I couldn't expect that he could even come close to keeping up with me because
at the end of the day, just conditioning seems to matter and how much preparedness you have
matters.
And so we went out to Fiesta Island where we train and there's, you know, a loop that
you do that's part of the training.
So we did this workout together and it was a very tough workout, lots of sort of three
minute, four minute all out intervals.
And at the end of the workout, we decided to do two hot laps.
So that's two laps of the big loop of Fiesta Island.
That would be about almost 14 kilometers for those two laps.
And you know, I was fit, like I was training for races and I guess, as I said, Mike hadn't
been on a bike in about a year and we went out and did these two hot laps and I couldn't
believe it when I crossed the line for the second lap.
I mean, I expected Mike to be three or four minutes behind and I look back and he's all
of 15 seconds behind me and I was like, wow, I'm about as fit as I'm going to be at this
stage of my life.
There's not a lot I'm going to do to take my game to the next level.
And he's pretty much right where I am just out of the gate.
And that was kind of an interesting, you know, wake up of like, there are guys that
are just at a different level and these guys train and they're forget about it.
They're in another world.
So I hope you enjoy this episode.
It's really geared towards people who have some sort of interest in physical performance,
but I really think there are enough sort of life lessons placed within here that I think
anybody even someone who has no desire to run a marathon or do anything crazy like that,
I still going to find something in it.
And finally, at the very end, if you just don't want to hear anything else and just
want to skip to the very end, we do disclose what we consider the second best beer of all
time.
Again, we do not disclose the best beer because, you know, I've got my reasons for that, but
I'm at the very least, those of you that are interested in great beer, we'll get a little
tip at the end.
So anyway, I hope you enjoy.
Mike, I'm super excited to sit down and talk about all this stuff with you.
You know, we've known each other for such a long time now, but you're such a sort of
mild mannered understated guy that if someone Googled your name, they wouldn't realize a
fraction of what you've accomplished.
And I think there are a lot of people who are going to listen to this who are going
to be, I think we'll learn a lot from this and be able to apply it to what they're doing.
I doubt many people who listen to this are ever going to want to go and do Ram or try
to set 24 hour world records in cycling and running.
But I think the principles that you've learned over the years are applicable to someone who's
going on to try to run their first 10 K or whatever.
But let's start with a funny story, which is what'd you do for your birthday this year?
I ran.
So how old did you turn?
43 in December.
And what is your shtick on your birthday?
Starting at 40, the new goal became run my miles and years, years and miles.
So this year was 43 miles.
So I remember when you called me later that day after you did your 43 mile run, which
in and of itself was crazy.
The part that I found most impressive was your nutritional strategy.
Yeah, this year was a new experiment.
I thought it was in good shape and decided to try the run, no calories.
So self supported, but no calories just to see if I could pull it off.
So I left with a couple of crystal light packets for flavor on hydration and 20 bucks to buy,
worst case by a banana at a 7-Eleven or something like that.
And I pulled it off.
Yeah.
I had dinner the night before.
Yeah, I started fasting at five the night before.
Had a beer.
By the way, I just want to state for the record, the beer that we drink, we never mentioned
by name.
Never.
Ever.
Okay.
Just yet.
So don't let that ever slip out in case that was the beer you had.
So you had a beer at 5pm.
Had a beer at five and went to bed 9 or 10, up at four and out the door by five.
No breakfast.
And that was it.
Started running.
And you ran about eight minute miles for 43 miles.
Yeah, just over eight with some hills.
Went south.
I went left North County, San Diego, went to the coast, ran up Torrey Pines.
Gorgeous morning and just kept going down the coast of La Jolla and Pacific Beach and
down to Point Loma and then turned around and stopped at Pacific Beach at the pier where
I met my family noonish and we had brunch.
And you said you weren't even really hungry when you were done.
I wasn't.
I expected to.
You know, we were ready to have a big brunch and Bloody Mary's and celebrate.
You know, my wife brought the kids and balloons and we ate at our favorite restaurant and
now it was great.
It was a wonderful day.
Yeah.
So in the parlance, that's what we call fat adaptation because, you know, if you do the
math, the extent to which you're expending energy, you're probably expending somewhere
in the neighborhood of six to seven hundred kilojoules per hour.
And you know, if you were trying to get access to that just from glycogen, I mean, you'd
be done in probably two, three hours.
Two or three.
Yeah, two or three at most.
And that was fairly aggressive pace.
Right.
So, you know, there's a series of energy stores that you tap into depending on your output
and duration, you know, that well.
So now I try to keep an even pace and stay hydrated.
I didn't really stop.
It was actually nice because in prior runs, I'd, you know, you have to stop at a seven
eleven and wait in line or stop at a gas station and get something to drink and buy a banana
or granola bar or something.
And then you get tight.
So I was able to just keep moving.
How did you drink?
How did you stop the game?
So I had I had 20 ounce handhelds and fortunately was able to refill.
There's a little drinking fountain at Toy Pine State Beach and there's one in low way
shores and I didn't kind of know where all the stops are.
So I just planned it and a little 30 second diversions.
And by the end I was just doing, you know, straight water, which felt and tasted better.
I turned around Point Loma OB and then went back up north and one last water stop in South
Mission Beach and ended in Pacific Beach.
So I remember one of the first times we hung out, we were introduced by a mutual friend.
This is probably in 2013.
And this is back when I was cycling pretty seriously.
You were running pretty seriously, but you weren't cycling much at the time.
But I was telling you about this shake that I make this generation.
You can I call it the Peter Kaufman where I take the generation you can and I mix it
with heavy cream and almond milk.
And it's like it's like the best meal you can have in a shake.
Right.
And I was like, hey, you know what?
Why don't you come over after your workout on Sunday?
And I'll fire this up for you.
And you said, sure, I'll be there.
And you came over.
But the part that blew my mind is you ran over and it was a 50 mile run.
You know, even though we only lived like you lived in La Jolla at the time.
So we only lived maybe 12 miles away from each other.
But you had turned it into a 50 mile run to end at my place.
I forgot about that.
Yeah, of course.
Because for you, that's nothing.
Well, no, it was it was actually one of my longer runs training for so that was that
was 13 and that Sunday Saturday or Sunday was one of my long runs training for a supposed
to be a 300 mile run down the coast.
And so I think I peaked around 50 or 60 in terms of I was doing 130 mile weeks getting
ready for that.
170 you hit one week, didn't you?
No, the week of the run, I hit 315, 313, 315.
Ended up being about 275 miles.
The run itself, which was Gaviota State Beach to San Diego to raise money for the Navy Seal
Foundation.
So that 50 mile I was training for that, which was five, six weeks after your shake.
I remember your wife and daughter saw me standing in the driveway and she kind of looked at
me out of the corner of her eye and just ran in the house.
The pool of sweat.
It was incredible.
Yeah, a lot of sweat.
But yeah, you came in and fired up the shake.
So I'm really glad to have microscopically contributed to that recovery that there.
Yeah, it's all about that shake.
So where'd you grow up?
I grew up in Iowa.
And were you like a cross country star in high school or something?
No, no, I was actually a football player wrestler in Iowa.
I started riding my bike at four and was out the door independently by six and then doing
50 and 100 mile rides by the time I was 10 or 12.
Did Greg Bry, which is a bike ride across Iowa.
First one was in 87 when I was 12.
I was 400 miles across the state.
So I mean, I always liked the endurance stuff, but most of my time was spent.
My dream was to play Notre Dame football.
Your dad went to Notre Dame, right?
Dad went to Notre Dame.
My grandfather did.
My mom went to St. Mary's, which is the sister college there.
So my dream was to Notre Dame football.
So that was big too.
Weighed about 200 pounds in high school and wrestled heavy weights.
I didn't want to lose weight.
Offensive lineman, offensive tackle in high school and then went and played football in
college inside linebacker in college.
And I remember the first time you told me that I was like, how were you a football
player? Like you just you don't have an ounce of extra weight on you at this point.
And so what was that metamorphosis like to transition from being kind of a power athlete
to an ultra endurance athlete?
It wasn't planned.
You know, it was college became about college and I played a year and a half of football
and I wanted to finish college early.
I just didn't want to go the whole four years.
So I just loaded up on classes and realized I was there to study and work and not
necessarily play football.
So I quit football, played rugby.
And my first job out of college was actually a startup in Europe.
And the interesting byproduct of that whole transition was I was learning
German, living in Heidelberg, Germany.
I was running sales and marketing for this tiny little startup there.
And the family teaching me German, one of the daughters was dating a rugby player that
played for the local semi pro rugby club.
And when he found out I had played rugby, he said, come practice with us.
And their practices at the time were runs in the mountains in Bavaria in southern Germany.
So I just fell in love with the trail running.
So it just and I ended up playing rugby with that team, which was fantastic.
It was a blast.
But I also ended up losing weight and that's just sort of fed on itself.
So by the time I got back to New York, you know, I'd lost 15 pounds and just kept
training, kept running.
It didn't lift as much and it just fell off.
I mean, I was at my peak 218.
I'm 170 now when I was racing.
I was 155, 160.
I lost five, 60 ish pounds over the course of five, 10 years.
But the amazing thing, because I've seen so many pictures of you back, like the picture,
there's a great picture of you that hopefully we'll figure out a way to sort of link to
it in the show notes.
But at the beginning of the 2000, I think 2004 Ram maybe.
And it's like, I'm looking at you and I'm like, I know you're 155 pounds, but you
don't look at, you look like a beast.
Yeah, it was never about looks.
No, but it's just you're, you know, you become purpose built.
We've talked about this, you know, being an engineer, I've always just looked at my
body's just a utility to achieve an outcome.
Right.
So how do you engineer the outcome that you want?
I made a transition from running to cycling.
In hindsight, it was a fairly short transition.
I was riding a lot cross training when I was competing in ultra is running 2001,
two, three, but I knew I wanted to do race cross America.
And so I was always, I mean, I was still riding 150 miles a week when I was
running 100 miles a week.
So I was still riding quite a bit.
But then as soon as I stopped running and started writing, my body just changed.
I, my massage therapist, who's still my massage therapist today, couldn't believe
the transformations, your body just changed overnight.
But that's all I was doing.
All I was doing was training.
You have that sort of unique ability where you can go out and run a sub three
hour marathon, which that's a very fast marathon.
But at the same time, you're setting 24 hour world records on a track and running.
I mean, you ran almost 150 miles in 24 hours, right?
Yeah.
I didn't set any world records on the track running.
I did set some course records on a track 24 hour run in a one, which was the San
Diego one day, and I swore I would never run on a track again.
It was probably the hardest ultra, single day ultra I ever did.
Cause it's just so monotonous.
You're on a quarter mile track.
Quarter mile track.
Kiamaka college in, you know, South San Diego running 24 hours just going, you
know, you looked forward to every four hours or every six hours, they'd change
direction, they blow whistle and you crossed the chip tracking was, and then
you'd change direction and you'd run the other direction for four hours.
That's what you look forward to.
And at the time, this is a one, I mean, I was running with the handheld Sony
Walkman and I had tapes.
Oh my God.
Back then the CDs were still skipping a little too much.
CDs didn't work.
And shortly after that, you know, MP3s, you started playing with mini discs
and other things, but so that in hindsight, you know, I'm running with a
water bottle on one hand and a Sony Walkman in the other hand carrying it for
24 hours.
And did you have like a big support staff for something like that?
I did not have anyone there at that event.
In fact, I had a cooler that I brought, you know, I backed my truck up to the,
you know, back of the track and threw a cooler in the back and left the hatch
open and I just crude myself for that.
I didn't want to bother anyone.
I mean, couldn't ask anyone to stay out there.
This was sort of your opening, uh, like this, this was the event that kind of
put you on the map of like, cause again, you didn't, a lot of these ultra distance
guys had been sort of doing that stuff for longer, but you just sort of showed
up and wasn't that like your first big win?
That run was actually at the end of what had been my first big year.
So I, in 2000, I ran my first 50.
You know, Trent made the transition from marathons and you know, the question was
just, can I do a 50?
And I did the, it was, we call it PCT 50, the Pacific Crest Trail 50 molar, um,
hot August, and I then did a hundred molar called the Angeles Crest 100 starts
in the right wood ends at the Rose Bowl, Pasadena, about six weeks after that.
And I was doing the hundred because my goal is to qualify for what was, and
still is the super bowl of ultra is the Western States 100.
Uh, I didn't get into the Western States.
This was in 2000, but I submitted for the bad water.
So that was my goal.
So in 2000 applied to get into bad water.
I did for 2001, the July 2001 running to the bad water.
And so 2001 was, I stacked a bunch of races.
I did a bunch of 50 molars actually to the Boston marathon, you know, in there
and between two fifties and so the track run was actually at the end of that season.
So I did 50 you've been doing a lot of water.
And then I actually on September 11th of 2001, I was scheduled to fly to
Colorado to try to beg a bunch of 14ers set a record of 14ers and had to postpone
that a week and did it a week or two after that.
And that was in September of 01.
And then I did the track run in November of 01.
And that was the end of my year.
So tell people what bad water is.
Cause that out here means a lot.
Cause anyone in Southern California knows what that is, but yeah.
So bad water is a running race that is starts in Death Valley, California.
So it's nice and cool.
Nice and cool.
You know, it's a cool one 25 at the peak around four o'clock.
You know, it's so hot.
If you run the white line, it's, you know, 10 degrees cooler.
The surface gets really hot.
So the air temperature is 125.
The surface to me can fry an egg.
People can fry an egg on a hood of a car.
So I did the bad water and how long is it?
It's 135 miles and you start in Death Valley at a hundred or so feet below sea
level, I don't remember exactly.
And it now finishes in Whitney portals, which is 8,500 feet.
So it's a beautiful, let me go through all these.
Ecosystems you start in a desert and you journey over to three 95.
You roll into lone pine, which is sort of a cool little mountain town in
California, the base of the Sierras.
And then you start get on this portals road, Whitney portals road, which is
about a half marathon pure, you know, all climbing.
So you have 13 or so miles of climbing up to the Whitney's portal.
It used to actually go all the way up to the top of Whitney for safety
reasons, they stopped doing that.
And funny side note is I had, I was doing a lot of climbing, a lot of
mountaineering stuff in 2001.
So my crew, I did have a crew for bad water.
You have to have one.
So I had two crews.
I actually had a running crew and a climbing crew and my climbing
partner was waiting for me at the portals.
I don't think I've ever talked about this with you.
So I did the race, you know, 10 a.m.
Start.
I finished, I forget my time, but I finished the next day around noon or one.
And my climbing partner was there.
We were going to go climb.
So we're going to hike up to the base of Mount Whitney.
And we were going to climb, I think the East face of Mount Whitney.
And he had all the climbing gear ready to go.
And I finished 135 miles and I said, Hey, buddy, you don't want me on the other
side of playing you, you don't want me on the other side of the road.
And so we ended up going down to Lone Pine and having pizza.
Yeah, they all, they all down the climb.
I have a much smaller story than that, meaning like it's a fraction of that.
But, uh, in 2007, I was, I wanted to swim across Lake Tahoe as a training swim
for a longer swim I was doing later that summer and trans Tahoe.
I mean, you can do it 10 different ways to Sunday, but I wanted to do the
longest possible crossing, but I didn't do a good job picking a boat captain.
I left it till the last minute.
I didn't know how to get someone really good.
So I just kind of went to, you know, some local and said, Hey man, can you
pilot me across this thing?
And it turned out he was clearly drunk.
And we only know this because I left accidentally, I left my GPS device on
in the boat the whole time we were on the boat, but he didn't realize that the
purpose of the guy in the boat is to set the direction, the swimmer sets the speed.
The boat sets the direction he followed me.
So we asked our way across Lake Tahoe and I mean, it was a total shit show.
I ended up like running out of food.
Because of course I only budgeted this to be so many hours and it ended up being
like two and a half hours longer.
It turned out to be probably the hardest one in my life mentally.
But I remember that day I was like, Oh, you know, we start at night.
So I'm like, I'll be done by 2 PM.
I told my brother, I was like, dude, have the bikes down at Lake Tahoe.
As soon as I get off, we're going to ride around the lake, you know, which is
like a 80 mile ride or something.
And I swear when I finished that swim, I was, I could barely walk
to the car, just, you know, the sun beating down on you, like the mental fatigue.
I was like, yeah, I don't know how I thought that I was going to ride around
this lake at this point.
That's a great, I mean, the training, the training for these things is what
prepares you and not just the miles, not just the time on your feet, but it's
stuff like that, that mentally is demoralizing, right?
It completely humbles you.
And I think if I look back on the stories, you know, very few stories come from races.
A lot of my stories come from the training and we all have great stories.
I mean, I've gotten stuck in the desert, sand storms, learned to bring goggles
with me to ride my bike and goggles to deal with sandstorms.
I had my beam.
I used to ride a soft ride and my beam delaminated.
It was so hot in the desert.
So the carbons sat in this, this carbon beam sat in an aluminum sleeve and it was
so hot it delaminated.
So essentially what happened is, is the, my seat lowered about six inches.
And so I was on my way out east to the Salton sea and I think somewhere around
Westmoreland and Brawley, I found a machine shop and I went to the guys and none of
them spoke English.
And I said, do you guys, do you have any screws?
Some cheap metal screws.
And so they had a bunch of power tools and they, three of us, they pulled up on the
sea, got it to a relatively close spot where I needed to be.
And we started drilling sheet metal screws through the aluminum and carbon.
Cause I was 200 miles from San Diego, 150 miles from San Diego.
And it just wouldn't occur to you to call a friend and come pick you up.
No, I mean, yeah, you're, you're on your own as part of the journey.
And this is this, I had a flip phone that I turned off because you had no reception
out there, so I don't think I probably even could have called a friend at the time.
Great.
You know, the stories are endless on, you know, stuff like that.
Another, you know, Whitney story, we tried to rock climb Whitney in May and it was
still all snow and ice and what should have been a six or eight hour climb turned
into a 22 hour climb.
No food, no water and brutal.
Same deal.
We had planned to meet some people afterward and, but those, you know, those
are the most memorable stories.
It provided you get out alive.
Provided you get out alive.
Yeah.
That's the caveat.
So you very, very briefly a moment ago alluded to Ram, which again, anybody in
the cycling world, especially in the ultra world will understand what Ram is.
It would generally be regarded as the single most challenging cycling event.
I, again, I don't even know how you can pair it to the Tour de France, obviously
the Tour de France or one of the grand tours like the Giro or the Vuelta.
Those are remarkable feats that only the best professionals in the world are going
to do it was Ram, you know, it's an amateur event, although some pros have done it,
but I don't even remember when I learned about Ram, like it was always something I
knew about and couldn't fathom that people could do it.
So you obviously decided to do it, but tell us what Ram actually is.
Ram is the race across America.
It's a bike race across America.
It started in the, I think it's the early eighties and my first exposure to Ram was
actually when I was a kid, there was a guy named Bob Breedlove, who was a surgeon in
Des Moines, Iowa, who was doing this crazy race across America.
So I learned about Ram and I was already riding my bike.
And it's just, holy cow, these guys can go 3000 miles across the country nonstop.
So it's the same length as the Tour de France, but it's not in stages unless you
decide to make it in stages, you just go nonstop.
So the whistle blows and first person to these coast wins.
And to put that in perspective, the Tour de France, which is ridiculously grueling,
is about 22 days.
It's about 22 days.
Yeah.
And the winner is going to do Ram in how many days?
Eight.
And depending on the route in the year, it's over a hundred thousand feet of
climbing and you're going through the desert of California, the Hills of West
Virginia, of course, to the Rockies and Kansas and the flats that are windy.
And the year I did it, it was very windy, crazy rains.
So the thing about Ram is it's not just the person riding the bike.
It's the logistics.
It's the crew.
You're dealing with rules, crazy race rules.
And so it's a really multifaceted, I mean, you have to really engineer
the race to do well, right?
So of course you have to prepare for it, but you know, your bike equipment,
you have the vehicle equipment, you have race food, racer food, you have crew food.
And then you think about everything from batteries to, we were rigging the
car to get power, extra power.
We had speakers on the vans and I mean, it's just crazy logistics, getting
ready for something like that, which is part of the fun, it's part of that.
You know, all the different variables you have to control for.
I've seen world-class racers bail before they even hit Arizona.
Cause they just, their crew blows up.
My crew in 2004, when I did it, only one was a cyclist.
You know, it was kind of like building a company, you know, you, you, you,
problem solving comes best from people that represent different functional areas.
Right.
So I had massage therapists.
I had a doc.
I had a one cyclist at a software engineer, my sister, you know, I had a
really mixed team, none of them, except for one knew how to change a tire on a
bike and I figured we could teach them that.
Yeah.
And the crew dynamics is the biggest part of pulling that thing off.
It's all about the crew.
You know, when you're talking about eight, nine days, that's unbelievable.
I always felt the highest compliment that I ever felt or the greatest sense of
pride I probably ever felt during my marathon swimming days was when I got
asked to crew chief for one of my fellow swimmers.
So when I was doing the swims, you don't have to have a crew chief.
And that person basically is the one that is designated in charge.
There is one and only one boss on that ship and everybody does what they say,
no matter what the fuck is going on.
That's right.
So you have to trust that person with your life.
They're the ones that make the decision on when you have to change
feeding, if things are going wrong, they're the ones who pull you out of the
water, if they think you're failing, that's like the guy in the corner who
can throw the white towel.
And when you're getting the crap beat out of you, so, cause you know, as
athletes, when they're doing these ultra distance things, like they can
become delirious and then you have to think about their safety.
So, you know, a number of occasions I got to crew chief for friends of mine who
were doing some of the most ridiculous swims I've ever seen.
Like Forrest Nelson is a friend of mine who again, outside of the swimming
community, nobody would know him, but he's the guy's ridiculous.
I mean, he's soloed around Catalina Island.
That's a 50 mile swim.
He's done a double crossing of Catalina in the winter, which is, I mean,
just from another planet and yeah, you realize like, you know, the
responsibility that's on you when you are responsible for making sure the
other 10 people on the boat aren't screwing up their jobs and you are a
hundred percent responsible for everything that swimmer is doing, counting
their stroke, right?
All those things.
And, and again, the longest I've ever had to crew is, you know, be a chief
is maybe 36 to 48 hours.
I can't even imagine what a crew is going through for nine days, eight days.
It's nine days.
It's nine days of the most intense and you know, these are first world problems.
This is an invented challenge.
We should keep that in perspective.
So, but when you're in the moment, when you're in the race and there's other
crew out there and there's other racers out there, and especially as you get more
and more sleep deprived and vested in the outcome, it's as real as it gets.
So that's exactly right.
In fact, my crew chief, the first year was the only cyclist he had brought his
brother, I think his brother was a math professor at MIT or Columbia, and they
ended up getting into a fist fight in the parking lot of a grocery store in the
Midwest.
And I heard screaming out, I was down for a sleep.
I heard screaming outside the RV.
What's going on by her and Jerry or in a fight?
What it's come to blows and they didn't speak for the rest of the, I mean, that
was the, I mean, that this is, these are brothers.
So that was one of many things that happened that year, but I broke my crew
in the first 45 hours.
I didn't, I didn't get off the bike for 28 hours.
I didn't sleep for 45 ish hours.
And when I was supposed to go down for my first plan sleep, the goal was to sleep
two hours a day after the first night.
So I'd ride through the first night and then sleep into the second.
But it's a funny story.
I came off the bike 44 hours, but just outside of Mexican hat, Utah in second
place, tell folks where the race starts.
The race started in Oh, for the race started in downtown San Diego.
So star of India, we're starting San Diego and you start heading east.
You know, go through.
It's not just that you're crossing the country.
You're diagonally crossing the country.
You're going from the bottom left corner of the United States to the
top right corner, right?
Cause that's right.
It's not Northeast.
It finished that year in Atlantic city.
And so we, you know, I don't remember how many miles, but you know, call it 800
miles into the event.
I went down from my first sleep and I'm naked, getting massaged and my massage
therapist is just trying to put me to sleep.
And just as I'm falling asleep, I feel this rocking and the whole RV is rocking.
And I like, for whatever reason, something fires and like, wait, that's the wind.
And so I jump up completely naked, run outside the RV.
And I'm standing on the highway.
Like, which way is the wind blowing?
Which way am I going?
I didn't even know which direction I was going.
And the crew had just slept, you know, just everyone's asleep.
And I, it's probably a half hour after I had gone down.
I hadn't slept yet.
And they realized like, I wanted it.
If that's a tailwind, put me back on the bike.
And it was, and it was.
And so they put me back on the bike.
So they got me all dressed and getting me dressed.
You know, it was a process.
Cause at that point I was sunburned and pretty beat and sore and shaved.
You got me dressed, got me back on the bike and I started riding and I saw
the guy in first place.
I passed the guy in first place who was just coming out of his first lead
slept for an hour.
So this was for Robic.
Robic.
Yeah.
So your aerobic was had just slept.
I passed him and I was then in the lead wasn't by design, but then he, what
happened is he and I then rode for four or five hours and pushed into Utah.
You guys gap the field.
We gap the field.
And what happened is that wind was a storm.
And so if I had stayed, I would have gotten caught in the storm.
And so what happened is we gap the storm.
There was one guy behind me named Wolfgang fashion.
It's a world-class endurance athlete and seven summit sky, Austrian guy,
greatest guy, he was behind me, but a few hours behind me had blown up in the
desert, just a lot of the European guys struggle with the heat.
Cause they just can't train in the heat over there.
So your aerobic and I ended up pushing 10, 12 hours ahead of everybody else.
And everybody else got caught up in this storm.
So I ended up being a really very good strategic move to get back on the bike.
I ended up sleeping around the 48 50 hour mark.
I did get my, you know, hour and a half.
And at that point we were ahead of everybody else and everybody else was
just playing catch up for the next six days.
It's unbelievable.
I mean, we'll come back to talking about Robic who would go on to become probably
the most storied writer in Ram history, correct?
Yeah, he is.
Five time champion.
Yeah, I think four or five time.
Yeah.
There's a book that talks about Ram and I've read it and I'm blank on the title.
Now we'll definitely link to it in the show notes.
Do you remember the book I'm talking about?
I don't.
Well, you're in it, but barely because I remember talking about it with you a few
years ago and I was like, Mike, this is the year you were second in Ram.
And you're like, yeah, I didn't want to talk to the reporter, but, uh, I, I,
anyway, we'll, we'll figure out what the name of the book.
It's a great book because, you know, if anybody's listening to this and thinks
what the hell I want to understand a little bit more about this, you go into
it and the book, because I mean, Robic must have been able to speak with the,
with the author, you know, you just get a great picture of this crazy dude.
What he's Serbian, right?
He's Sylvanian.
It's Sylvanian.
Okay.
So he was riding for the Sylvanian army.
He was a soldier and his full time job was to be an endurance athlete.
And he was just a beast strong, you know, just in his mental
patience was just phenomenal.
Although that year, if I recall, first of all, you're a rookie.
So a rookie is not supposed to be, I was not supposed to, you're not supposed
to be riding next to him.
In fact, that year was the race directors couldn't figure me out.
I was a runner.
Who is this guy?
And I just didn't know any, but I was young, you know, I didn't know any better.
I just hammered and just I all along was part of my plan.
I was actually off my pace to my, you know, I'm all about looking at my
expected pace over 55 time stations and altitude gain and loss and, you know,
planning it all out, I was off my projected pace.
So, you know, I was a little bit disappointed with where I was, but that's
eight days of 3000 miles.
So, you know, things get out of whack pretty quickly.
So, you know, it's all about just being a, it's adaptation right in real time.
Now, was this the year or was it the following year when Robik's team
basically accused you guys of cheating?
That was that year.
So that year Robik thought he was going to win it.
He had been preparing.
He should have won by a day.
Yeah.
He expected to.
And so his crew, all, you know, armed forces guys, about halfway through
the country when I was still in it and they, for whatever reason, they just,
I just wasn't sleeping for that year.
I just didn't, I could not sleep.
I, you know, over the eight and a half days, slept 10 and a half hours.
Oh my God.
I just couldn't sleep.
And, you know, we can talk later about the mental effects of not sleep.
I mean, sleep I've found is more important than food and hydration when it comes to
thermoregulation and muscle glycogen restoration and synapse repair and
formation, I mean, literally when I was clinically insane by the end of that race,
fully delusional by the end of that race.
But I just kept hammering.
And so the Robik team, what, who is this guy?
What is he doing?
He has to be cheating and it's legal to spot people.
So they sent a van back and they just attached him to my team.
And apparently this is sort of race tactics.
The Ram is famous for other racers playing mental games and the race
directors kind of encouraged it.
And that was all new to me.
I mean, I'm kind of a pure clean, just go and hammer and let the best man win.
And they love that those antics, right?
The mental games.
And so the accusations of cheating were chalked up as all.
They're just mental games, but it did become more than that for me because the
race director, you know, at first of all, I had the press, which is why I wouldn't
talk to the press after that.
I had the press asking me, what do you think about the accusations?
My team hadn't told me yet.
And Robik's crew just accused me of cheating so that officials would scrutinize me.
And they intend, eventually they withdrew their accusations and, you know,
it was all fine.
The damage had been done.
I had one really, really bad night.
I think it was in Kansas or a little bit past that.
And it came after I, Robik told me flat out, you're going to win.
And he said, you just don't need to sleep.
You're going to win.
And I said, we've got a thousand miles to go.
So you and Robik would actually be riding together at some point.
Is that even legal?
You're allowed to ride together for 20 minutes every 24 hour period.
And so we rode together and we taught his wife was pregnant at the
time and, and oh, for when we were riding, you know, he's, we were talking about
his, I think he knew it was going to be a boy.
So, you know, he's talking about his, his soon to be born kid and, you know, he
asked me where I was from.
And, and so we talked a little bit, you know, he, his English was okay and
actually had a great time.
And then I told him to go ahead and he said, no, you go ahead.
And so I ended up riding ahead and got ahead of him a bit.
And he was hurting at that point.
Cause I think he was just like, what?
And I was, I did my best to look fresh and was smiling and joking.
And, you know, acting like, oh, this is just a little stroll, you know, in the park.
So mental games.
But shortly after that, his team accused me of cheating and, you know, it all
played out over a day or so.
What's interesting is one of the race officials, I almost, I don't think we've
ever talked about this, but I quit, I quit the Ram.
I think we were in Indiana, we were outside of Indianapolis and it all came to a head.
And the race official, his name is Johnny Boswell.
And Johnny came up to me and he said, we're so sorry about everything that's
happened. I heard you, you're withdrawn from the race.
Is there anything we can do to keep you in the race?
And I said, this isn't why I came out here at, you know, this is crazy.
And mind you, I've, you know, 2000 miles into it.
Yeah. With no sleep, you're not even able to think straight.
I just got off the bike.
Robic at that point was four or five hours ahead of me.
It was completely demoralized, right?
And my team's having to answer questions about why they pulled me off the road to
sleep in the RV. Just crazy stuff, right?
All within race rules.
And so I told John, I said, the only way I'm going to stay in this is if no one
speaks to me for the rest of the event, I don't want, because there were crew or
press vans cruising up alongside me, trying to take pictures, trying to interview
me. And I said, I want everyone to leave me alone.
The only way I stay in this.
And at that point I'd felt like, you know, the race is lost.
I'm not going to win this race.
Grobix too far ahead.
So four or five hours with how many miles to go is insurmountable.
Around 800, I think it was around 800 miles.
I'd have to go back and look.
And believe it or not, I went for a run.
I went.
I would say I don't believe it, but you went for a run before we rode our bikes
today. I did.
You just decided at 5 30 in the morning you needed to go for a run just to, you
know, get a little workout in before we got on our bikes.
So I asked myself, what's the one thing that'll center me?
And for me, running has always been my call it meditation, but it's just, I get
centered, right? So I asked my crew, I said, you get, find my running shoes.
And I, you know, what?
And I went for a run and I found a park bench and a little town in the Midwest.
And I ran, you know, a mile or two and I just sat under a park bench and I checked
myself and it was, you know, you could say I was sleepy, but I was of probably
the clearest mental, I knew exactly why I was there and what I was doing.
And I asked myself, do I want to do this to my crew?
They were demoralized.
I was hurting and I ran back and I said, all right, I will do it under these
conditions. I will get back in the race and do it under these conditions.
And I did.
And the official stayed with me and kind of protected us the rest of the race.
And it was fantastic.
They gave us space, but they just kept an eye on us the rest of the race.
And I've, you know, since I still exchanged Christmas cards with Johnny Boswell.
And we'll always think of him as a friend because he, he saw what we were trying to
do. And I think a lot of people are like, what's this guy doing?
What's, what's his angle?
What was the strategy that normally people took to Ram as far as how much time on the
bike versus how much sleep time?
What would, what would be considered the sort of best practice?
20 to 22 hours on the bike, two to four hours of sleep.
You know, so you want to sleep if you're at a minimum 18 to 20 hours over the course
of a week.
So did anybody ever experiment with I'm going to ride 18 hours and sleep a full six?
A lot of guys have talked about time trial and it, right?
So yeah, you ride 300, you hammer and you go off, you know, so you ride for, call it
18 hours and then you get off the bike and you sleep six.
And I think there's something to be said for that.
I mean, that's the ultimate, you know, if you can do that and sustain it and still put
the same performance in on your sixth or seventh, 300 mile or then that may be there.
You know, it's just math if, you know, cumulative time elapsed is less than just
hammering the whole time.
It's tough though.
I'll tell you, it's tough to get off the bike.
It takes a lot of patience, especially early in the race when the other guys are, you're
going to see like, Jesus, I'm going to sleep for six hours when some dude's sleeping for
two. Like I'm going to wake up, you know, given the difference in speed, three hours
behind a guy.
That's right. And there's a guy here in San Diego that his name is Pete Pinsiras and he
held the transcontinental speed record for a long time.
He was 15.4 miles an hour for eight and a half days.
That includes off the time.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's ridiculous.
So his on bike speed is 20 miles an hour.
He's flying and he didn't stop much, but he said there's really two and I eventually
experienced this.
There's two things that will determine whether or not you can win Ram.
One is what is your Ram speed and really what is your speed?
What speed can you maintain on the bike after you've depleted your muscle glycogen and
you're just cruising?
Because that's ultimately going to determine how fast you can really go.
We used to call that your all day speed in the water.
This is we're well beyond thresholds.
We're just talking about something totally different.
That's right.
You're no longer trying to stay 5% of threshold.
You're you're just you're done, right?
That's that's one.
And the other is what's your REM cycle?
And he taught me this and his wife used to do it for him is she would watch him sleep and
then watch when he would come out of Ram and she would chart it and they would do this
before the Ram because obviously it changes over time.
And so right up before the Ram, his wife would watch him sleep, time it, and then she
would wake him up.
And the whole point being don't wake yourself up in the middle of Ram because you're going
to be sleepy and not be able to perform.
So she'd look at his eyes until because theoretically you go from Ram you if it's late
enough, you might go up to stage one to which is a perfect time to wake somebody up.
That's right.
So she would wait till his eyes stop moving.
She would wait till his eyes stop moving, bring him out.
He would feel rested even though it was two hours.
And he said, look, if your Ram is 90 minutes instead of 220, two and a half hours, you're
going to win.
Yeah.
Wow.
That is freaking incredible.
Sleep engineering, engineering the sleep and then he, you know, we've talked a lot about,
you know, staying liquid because it's, you know, you don't want to move blood to your
gut while you're riding because then obviously you're taking blood away from your
legs.
So stay liquid, try to let your body do as little work digesting, but you want nutrient
dense calories, right?
And nutrition, nutrition and hydration should be one of the same to the extent that you
can tolerate that.
So yeah, you're engineering your sleep.
You're engineering your intake.
Of course, you're engineering your training and race strategy.
And then people engineer the shit out of their bikes too.
I mean, people are doing all kinds of crazy things to get their bikes dialed.
Now you got to know Panzaris pretty well and you got to ride with him.
You told me a story about him once and I couldn't believe it.
Like how old was he and how fit he still was?
Yeah.
In 04, I was introduced to him in 04 and went out and rode with a group of guys that
still ride.
And he invited me to ride with them.
So I rode up there in North County, San Diego, and I rode up, did 60 or 70 miles to meet
them.
And we rode and we were, we rode up a hill that was a 26% grade, probably a hundred or
so miles into our ride.
I was about 140 or so for me.
And we rode up the hill.
We were leading this crew and I looked over to him at the end of the hill, 26% grade in
North County.
I think it was up near Fallbrook or Vista where he was former nuclear engineer at San
Onofre.
And he said, what's your heart rate right now?
And I said, I think it's like 188.
And I said, what's yours?
And he said, it's 181.
So he's 60.
I don't know how old he was.
He was mid sixties then.
And his heart rate was like 180.
And I said, what's the highest your heart rate has ever gotten?
And he said, I just hit the highest heart rate I've ever seen.
So here he is in his mid sixties and I asked him, I said, you said, I've never gone up
this hill this fast and I've never seen that heart rate.
So here's someone in their mid sixties.
And if you do the math, right, 220 less your age and that's your max heart rate.
That's, that's, so, you know, he should have been around, let's call it 160.
Maybe max heart rate for highly trained, adapted semi professional athlete, world
class athlete, transcontinental speed record holder at the time.
And here he is hitting 180 and he just did.
I'm still reeling in the 26%.
I mean, admittedly I've never been able to climb particularly well on a bike, but
I don't actually think I could pedal a bike up 26% grade unless I had like a
mountain bike or something.
Like if I took my road bike now, which probably, I can't even remember if I have
a compact crank, I probably do.
So I'm riding like a 34 23.
I don't think I could get up 20.
Like that hill when we're coming around like Hodges, as we're, you know, when you
come to the light before you get to Del Dios, that's maybe 18%.
Maybe.
And it's a, and it's only like 600 mile.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
It's nothing.
In fact, he told me most guys will, what they call paper boy.
So they weave back and forth to get up that.
So they'll paper boy.
And then the rule used to be they would go, there's an avocado grove.
It gets to the top of the hill.
And when they were kids or younger, they would go grab avocados and they would
start just, it's all you have to do is lay it on the road and the avocados would
roll down and start, start bouncing down the hill and they'd try to nail guys on
their bikes and avocados.
So if you're slow, you're going to get beamed by avocados.
Oh my God.
So Pete came up to me before, right before the race and said, good luck.
You know, that record needs to go and I wish you the best.
And he, he taught me so much.
I mean, very early on, I haven't talked to him in a few years, but he taught me a
lot and just this whole notion of engineering, the sleep, the nutrition,
the training plan, the race strategy, of course, all the crew stuff.
And that's a lot has to come together.
There's so much more I want to talk about on that front.
I want to come back to Robic because I don't want to forget this.
There are a lot of people listening to this who do, they just can't relate
to what you're talking about.
Let's call this beta spade.
I doubt there's anybody listening to this who's ever going to go out and ride Ram,
let alone, you know, do any of the other crazy ultra endurance stuff.
But I get, I am sure there are a lot of people here who are thinking, I really
want to run a marathon one day, or I really want to do an Ironman.
You know, I want to take that leap from Olympic distance to Ironman.
What can they learn from you to make that transition, which, you know, for many
people running a marathon is as crazy as doing a 24 hour run.
And for many people doing an Ironman for them is as big a stretch
as it was for you to do Ram.
I think we all have the physical ability.
We all natural born athletes, right?
Everyone.
Some people may have, you really believe that.
I believe that.
I firmly believe that.
Now some people may have better genetics or better biomechanics, but look, I was
heavy and a jock football player, and I'm not the best endurance athlete in the
world. I mean, I was able to engineer myself, kind of hack my way to positive
outcomes. And if I can do it, I think anybody can.
Now people may have different goals.
So I think the biggest thing is just assume that you have in you somewhere
the ability to do great things.
The other piece of it is change your mindset, right?
Whatever your goal might be, whether it's running a half marathon instead of a 5k,
if that's what you want to push yourself is there should be no sacred cows, right?
We have these constructs in our mind about limits.
And I'd say that's the biggest thing I've talked to people about this before is
just change your perspective on what you think you can do.
Just throw it out the window.
It's the classic, you know, if someone gets electrocuted and they get thrown up
across the room, it's not the electricity throwing them across the room.
It's their body.
They have the innate ability to do amazing things.
Most people haven't figured out how to tap into that.
So that's my only piece of advice is just check your assumptions at the door,
right? And just open your mind up a little bit.
We talked about all these things you've done and what's missing from the story is
you were working 60 hours a week as an engineer at Qualcomm during this period
of time. Yeah. In the early 2000s,
I was running a software company and you know,
we had test engineers and programmers, et cetera,
working at Qualcomm and lots of other places. That's right.
So I actually, but it fit very nicely with my routine.
So I would get up at three ish run that ride into,
just to be clear, that's 3am, 3am run and run.
How far, what would be giving a day in the life of training?
1212 was sort of my staple run 12, jump on the, you know, no shower,
jump on the bike, ride in to work, shower,
ask and seat by 630. And I was a programmer at the time. I met,
even though I had people, I loved the architect and build stuff, right?
So somewhere in there and prepping from my run,
I would make a smoothie with whey protein isolate and L-glutamine and
glucosamine and flaxseed oil and all the stuff I needed to recover.
So I'd have that in the freezer, come back from my run, grab that,
throw it in my pack, throw my computer in my pack, jump on the bike,
and then I'll put my feet up. And so from 630 to noon,
I would sip on a smoothie that was super cold and eat over time.
You know, that, that, those would be my,
that was 2000 calorie shake essentially. Right.
And so that was my routine,
but it worked because that was my recovery time and occasionally I would go out
and run or when I was training for bad water, I learned bad, you know,
bad water was all about just becoming like a human water filter because you have
to push so much fluid in bad water just cause you sweat so much that
I would go and do sauna time.
So I would run over to a fitness facility that had a nice sauna and jacuzzi
and I would just focus on raising my, my body temp. So I'd sit in a sauna,
then I would go sit in the jacuzzi and I would just pound waters and I would go
back and work for a few hours and jump on my bike.
So you trained yourself to be hot and to basically process as much water as
possible. Did you have to pay attention to your minerals and electrolytes?
Because you know, at that level,
you can start getting into concern around hyponatremia and things like that.
Exactly. Yeah. In fact, I learned to love salt.
So I would actually find it kind of became a salt geek.
So I would find different salts with trace minerals and elements.
I fell in love with this Celtic sea salt that I found and it just,
it felt like electricity. You put it in your mouth and I would actually just do,
you know, teaspoons of that. So I would do grams of salt. I mean,
of course other things, magnesium and potassium, et cetera.
So without a doubt, salt was a big part of it.
And then of course fat in, you know,
whether it be a tablespoon of coconut oil or something else,
I would do that throughout. Yeah. You were kind of far ahead. I mean,
I think today most people, if they're going to be objective,
so let's dismiss all the sort of zealots on all sides of the equation,
but if you're going to be objective,
there's no doubt that if you want to be an ultra distance athlete,
you have to be fat adapted. Now that doesn't mean you have to be a nutritional
ketosis, but you must be fat adapted.
You do not want to do these things with an RQ above about 0.75 to 0.8.
But I feel like you sort of backed into that because there wasn't anyone to
look to 15 years ago.
There weren't people doing this stuff or talking about it the way there are
today. When did you figure that out? And what made that so clear to you?
There were a couple of things and you're right. It was, it was accidental.
I backed into it and it was through experimentation. Again,
just checking all your assumptions at the door. There was this, first of all,
back then there was this idea you shouldn't run more than a marathon or two a
year, which at one point I was doing one a day.
And just as part of my training regime.
So what about this whole idea of carb loading? Really?
Cause I always felt bloated and it didn't, you know,
my performance the next day, my heart rate and you know,
blood was still in my gut. And so I'll metric for me often when I woke up the
next day about whether or not I was going to run a train was my heart rate.
And my resting heart rate used to be 37, 38. And if it was ever above 40,
I would just stand back. I wasn't adapted.
And there was no point in stressing myself further because I would break into
overtraining. Well, that in and of itself is pretty impressive.
Cause I'm guessing many people listening to this are thinking this guy's just a
hammerhead. He's just a robot. But that takes, I remember from my days,
the hardest decisions were the days when I pulled back on training. That's right.
Cause that was like, you're struggling with your own demons. Am I good enough?
Am I, I'm going to stay in and not train today, but my opponents out there
training, Oh my God, what am I doing? But you,
this is almost where it helps to have a trainer. That's right.
Who you can outsource that decision to, but you had the discipline to do that.
But after a lot of research, so, you know, a couple of things, you know,
I want to come back to fat adaptation and, you know, carb loading,
I learned, so I had some fairly objective indicators that I would use to make
decisions. Cause a big part of doing this consistently over time is just to be
objective with yourself. Am I really in course record shape,
or am I just fooling myself? And so what are the metrics?
What are your times? Time doesn't lie, right? Time is objective.
Your heart rate it's objective. It's a great metric to use force power.
If you're on the bike is the absolute. And if you know you're at altitude,
there's some other things you can do in Mountaineering to keep yourself in check
and Mountaineers are the same way. They're very disciplined.
If I'm not where I need to be by 2PM, I turn around. It's not summit day.
So it's not going to work.
That is impressive. When I talk to those guys that have summited Everest,
especially those I've talked to a few guys have done it repeatedly.
That actually impresses the hell out of live the climb another day.
It's that simple. So I borrowed from Mountaineering.
I'll get back to the fat thing in a second. Cause there were indicators,
early indicators in terms of just being in ketosis and what your body does over
time to optimize endurance.
So Mountaineering is actually where I learned about fat and I'll get back to
that in a second. So the carb thing didn't work for me, right?
And I learned accidentally that you can actually fast and do better.
And feel better and feel cleaner.
And so I just started phasing things out, right?
So I started phasing carbs out, drank very little alcohol and very monastic
lifestyle for a long time there.
I had no girlfriend lived in a little condo by the beach and just worked my
tail off and trained and loved it. It was a very simple life.
No drama outside of just not, maybe not feeling good about my run that day.
It was a very simple life engineered intentionally to be that way.
So I did learn that the traditional thinking was wrong.
And I also learned that the assumptions around what a human body could do were
wrong. And I learned that through experimentation.
So back to the Mountaineering thing. So there's a great book called,
I think it's called fast and lighter moving fast and light.
There's a Mountaineer named Mark Twit who's a batshit crazy Mountaineer who was
doing all kinds of stuff in the nineties.
And I've always been intrigued by doing endurance stuff and in the mountains.
And there's guys not doing what I knew would eventually happen.
I came to it late and of course had a family decided risking my life wasn't worth
it anymore. But we knew that metabolizing your body is very different at altitude
and actually taking a shot of oil at altitude was better than eating a bowl of
spaghetti. And it's written about and that's where I learned sometimes it's
better just to take a shot of olive oil and never forget reading about this.
And I'm like, well, I'm going to experiment with that.
If they're doing this at altitude and it's working and it's actually helping
them, right? First of all,
a little Nalgene vial of olive oil or flaxseed oil to take in your pack if you're
doing it on summit day to not have to carry a bunch of food.
Yeah. From an energy density standpoint,
it's the most energy dense way and your fat adapted and your body has a hard time
metabolizing the fat and anything else at altitude and it's hard to cook stuff at
altitude, which is another story.
So I learned that fat, fat's actually not bad.
And also learned, you know, sugar is not good when you're doing long events because
you know, insulin response and you bonk and you know, so sugar is great.
It's like a drug though, right?
It's chasing the Drake.
And once you have your Twix at mile 20, you're going to want another one at mile 25.
You're hosed.
You have now committed to a pure glycolytic strategy and you better have it timed
perfectly to the finish line.
And it is part of the strategy and you know, and I would argue in terms of optimizing
performance should be part of your strategy, but you, you only get one shot at it.
So if you're doing a hundred, you better, you know, if it comes before a mile 80,
you better know what you're doing because after that, I'll be, you know, if you're
going to take a mountain do don't do it a mile 20 because it is at that point, all
bets are off.
Your body is now shifted into a completely different world and it's going to want to
stay in that world and you know that well.
So I came back from the Himalayas in 02.
I spent a couple months over there in Tibet on Everest and we were eating yak meat,
which you can't cook at 25,000 feet.
And I was like, Oh, I'm going to eat this.
I'm going to cook at 25,000 feet.
And so I came back with just crazy parasites, which I later learned in 03.
And so the other part of this, to answer your question about sort of backing into it is
the only way I was going to get rid of the parasites was to essentially go nuclear on
my own body, which meant like a 10 day fast.
So I did the Eastern Western thing.
So I went to, you know, infectious diseases guy at, you know, San Diego or UCSD.
And I said, well, how do we get rid of this stuff?
How do we, he's like, Hey, I'm going to give you some stuff and it's going to be really
hard on your body.
I need you to take it.
And I said, what have the people been doing for thousands of years?
Because you know, tapearms and other stuff has been a problem for a long time.
You starve yourself, just starve it, you starve it eventually, you know, get rid of it.
So I did both.
So I said, give me the meds.
And I did the meds and I didn't eat for 10 days.
So I just drank warm water every day, didn't really train and did other crazy stuff to
just completely cleanse myself.
And by day three, day one and two was brutal.
By day three, I just it's like my whatever, 170 degree vision went to I could see around
myself, right?
I could feel stuff.
I could smell stuff.
And it just turned into this journey was of course, fix the problem, get rid of it.
And I was, I was developing exercise induced asthma.
I became allergic to certain foods.
And I was allergic to myself.
I was actually, of course, fighting these parasites, but I didn't know it at the time.
All that went away in 03 by fasting.
And I felt better.
And so I backed in.
So I was obviously in ketosis, because I started training again by day seven, I wasn't eating,
but I started training again.
And I felt fantastic.
And that's when I realized like, holy cow, like it was accidental.
But between the fat and understanding that that's a component of performance, and then
the fasting, which was again, just to get rid of parasites, I realized like, heck, and
actually perform even better, throwing everything else out the window.
It is amazing.
I actually didn't know that story about you.
I didn't know that you had to do this tend to I didn't even know about the whole parasite
thing.
And those things are really interesting, because I, I know a lot of people who have had that
experience, right?
They go off and they climb Kilimanjaro, and they come back and they're never the same.
You know, one of the people who was actually helping me and that trans Tahoe swim had just
come back from Kilimanjaro.
And this person's kayaking, one of my kayakers, and I mean, had to literally hop out of the
kayak and take a shit in the water about every, I don't know, hour.
I mean, devastated by these parasites.
But it's really interesting.
I mean, I can, it certainly strikes me as relatively low downside to at least give a
trial attempt of fasting coupled with the medical therapy.
I mean, certainly there's evidence to suggest that fasting coupled with chemotherapy can
increase the efficacy of chemotherapy.
I mean, this has been now actually demonstrated.
Valtra Longo has talked about this quite a bit, but you know, Dom Degasino has been
talking about this for at least five years now.
So I didn't know that about you.
I love that.
I feel like I know everything about you and yet I've already learned like six things about
you in the last hour that I didn't know.
Let's close out the Ram story just because I, again, I'm, to me, your Ram exploits might
be your second most impressive story.
We're going to come to the most impressive feat of them all in a moment.
But there was a really sad ending to Robic, wasn't there?
Yeah.
In fact, there was a sad ending to Robic and Bob Breedlove.
So Bob Breedlove died in oh five on the Ram.
I was a few hours ahead of him.
These aren't, I think at the time I did Everest, it was one in eight people would die.
So you're not talking about people are asking me about finished rates.
There's death rates to some of these races.
So one in eight die on Everest.
I don't know what the stats are today.
K2 is even worse.
K2 is like one in three or something crazy.
There's a few that are just, and that's, you know, it's why with young family, I'm not,
you helped me a few weeks ago, pull a tree down and I had my climbing gear out for the
first time in 15 years, rapping slings around a tree.
I walk over and I see you with a chainsaw and a fricking 80 foot tree.
And I'm like, Hey, Mike, you need a hand?
It's the first time I climbing gear has been out in a while.
So yeah.
I think unfortunately I had a fantastic performance a number of years after we raised against
each other and he died on a bike in Sylvania.
Gosh, it's been, it's been a few years.
He was riding down a hill or something.
He was riding down a, as I understand it, riding down a gravel road, a fire road or
something in Sylvania and crossed the center line and ran into a car coming up and went
over the top.
I mean, I've, I've been there.
I mean, I've crashed several times and I just, there are so many people I know that
have died on bikes, which is why I just don't ride as much anymore.
Eventually.
It's just law of large numbers, right?
You're out there enough.
Something's going to happen.
Yeah.
I had that wake up call in, um, maybe 2010.
There's a guy named Nick Venuto.
I don't know if you knew Nick, but he was the CFO at our company.
This was back when I was working at a biotech company and a amazing cyclist.
He actually won the Mount Palomar time trial a couple of times.
So for people who are around here and understand what Mount Palomar is, it's basically Alpe
d'Huez in terms of rise grade and even including the same number of switchbacks.
So it's a serious climb and every year there's a time trial and Venuto would win it.
And I remember on one afternoon I was leaving, this was back when I was, could call myself
a cyclist and I was like buggering out earlier.
It was like five o'clock cause I wanted to go home and I had intervals to do that day.
And on that day I remember I had the luxury of calling an audible, which was I could either
do repeats on Torrey Pines, which would be Hill repeats, or I could go out to 56 on the
bike path and do VO two max repeats.
Cause it's not as steep.
You know, you're only climbing like sort of 4% as you ride from Carmel Valley out the
Poway.
And I just decided, you know, I'm going to go ride Torrey Pines today.
So I did.
And I remember walking out my door cause Nick and I opposed each other and I said, and he
was like, he, you know, I know everybody says this about everybody, but he literally
was the nicest dude on the planet.
And I remember saying, all right, Nick, see you later, man.
And Nick used to ride to and from work every day.
He was such a devoted family guy that he just didn't want to waste time training outside
of his commute.
And he lived far away.
So you know, he'd get in like 40 miles a day training just on his commute.
He's riding home on the 56 bike path, the same road I was going to do.
I could have been doing my intervals on.
And if I showed you where it happened, it's the last place you think this could ever happen.
But a woman driving, her SUV decides at that moment, she's just got to check her cell phone
and she drives up the embankment through the fence and hits Nick and kills him.
And I couldn't believe it.
I mean, I just, you know, to think like I was just with this guy two hours before.
And unfortunately that's just not an uncommon story.
Like, you know, obviously since then have known of other cyclists that have died, but
I didn't know any as well as him.
And yet, you know, given what you've done, you really know a lot of people who have met
this horrible fate on a bicycle.
And a lot of times actually the cyclist is 100% not at fault.
You know, in the case of Nick's case, I mean, he's on a bike path, nothing he could have
done to prevent that.
That is a lightning strike.
You know, to be hit from behind when someone veers off a freeway going 75 miles an hour
and hits you.
I mean, like you're done.
You're done.
And on a bike path, that's protected.
You think that, you know, the worst you can do is make a mistake and go down or someone
else on the bike will hit you, which is probably not lethal.
You know, my brother, who's a really good mountain biker, the reason he's just so obsessed
with being on a mountain bike, he goes, look, here's the difference.
When I used to ride on the road, if something bad was going to happen statistically, it was
the driver's fault.
On a mountain bike, when something bad happens, it is always my fault.
That's right.
And it's a broken collarbone or, you know, broken arm.
It's not, it's usually not lethal.
It's part of the reason why I don't ride as much as I did.
And I was hit actually similar driver.
I thought she saw me.
She looked right at me.
I don't know if it's sunlight, sun was setting, but I was also bike commuting, leaving work,
and she accelerated right through me.
She had a stop sign.
She just rolled through it.
I was doing about 35, just rolling down a hill and I was slow motion.
And you know, I've had other accidents, but that was probably the most mentally.
I mean, that's when I bought my CompuTrainer.
Actually, my wife got it for me because she just, I just wouldn't get on the bike because
I really thought she saw me and I couldn't hit my head and I couldn't move the right
side of my body.
And I apparently was making this crazy noise sound, just moaning on the pavement.
This was in oh, I think it was oh six, oh seven.
And that's was when I, I mean, it took me, she was absolutely sweetheart about it.
I mean, she was just devastated.
I mean, I went over the hood and the back of her car and the bike went one way and I
went the other and we were both, by then doing 40 and just, you know, hit the pavement and
rolled.
And fortunately, my wife was a mile away and call her and come get me.
And I tried to walk it off.
I was going to try to ride home and I just literally was, it shook me up.
It shook me up.
And after that, I just said, you know, it's, and after, you know, many deaths, friends
and guys like Robic and others just said, you know, it's going to happen.
Eventually, it's going to happen.
Yeah.
By the way, going back to the CompuTrainer, you're probably one of the only people that's
broken a CompuTrainer.
Twice.
Yeah, the CompuTrainer at this point is a resistance trainer and I've stopped replacing
them and I just get on at this old Slocum stand, which I've had powder coated a couple
times from the sweat and the rust.
And I used the actual.
First time I saw your CompuTrainer, I was like, dude, what have you done to this thing?
Well, I have my contraption I've engineered for the PVC.
You know, at the time it was a blackberry and computer stand and other stuff.
It's now an iPad holder.
And so my contraption strapped to the front of it bracketed to the front of it for my screens.
So of all the incredible things you've done and as I, you know, as we become closer over
the past five years, I've gotten to know all of these things.
But you're so unassuming that I have to like pry them out of you.
But I don't know what it is about Trans Iowa.
But when you finally told me about that, I was blown away.
I think Trans Iowa might be the most ridiculous feat in the history of cycling, certainly
as far as a one day event goes.
So explain the motivation for that.
What the hell you did, how fast you went.
Like, well, talk to me about Trans Iowa.
Well, you know, growing up in Iowa and having done the bike ride across Iowa, Ragbri, the
registered annual great bike ride across Iowa many years.
I always asked myself, how fast could you do this in one go?
Even when I was a kid, like, why are they stopping?
You know, I get people drink at night and party and it's a fun time.
But why isn't anybody doing this in one push?
It's possible.
And so it's been on bucket list thing, right?
A lot like hearing about Bob Breedlove in the 80s about Ram that was became a bucket
list thing.
Ram became a bucket list.
Trans Iowa became a bucket list.
And so no, did Ram in 04 and lots of other stuff and decided that I could work at my
own sort of attempt at trying to set a speed record across Iowa.
It's where I'm from.
And it was a bucket list.
And so I got, actually my Ram crew chief was the official because they're, you know, to
be a true record, the UMC has, you have to have an official and he was a UMC official
and my uncle, best friend from high school.
And you know, some, a couple other people crew me for it.
And it's a, you know, depending on your route, you can pick your route and you know, there's
UMC recognizes record attempts.
Looking at it, just a few simple criteria.
So I picked my route, set my date and pick my official.
And the distance was what?
270.
So the 270 mile.
270 and change, actually more climbing than you'd think.
Most people think Iowa is flat, but it's not.
How many feet vertical?
I'd have to go back and look at the stats, but several thousand feet of vertical.
So you start at one river and end at the other, right?
One east to west and, uh, was able to do, I didn't have to unclip.
It was pretty cool.
I, I, there was halfway through some guys from construction on the road and the guy
had a stop sign, you know, one line open at a stop up and I waved to him.
I just let me through, forget the car behind me.
This was my, my crew vehicle.
Um, but let me through and he flipped it around and you know, so I didn't have to unclip for
the entire state and managed to do in about 10 hours and 40 ish minutes.
I can give you all the stats if you want, but I did about 25.7 miles an hour average,
a little tailwind to start across wind.
It was beautiful day conditions were perfect.
You know, in fact, there were storm chasers out the night before there were tornadoes
all over the place.
It was a may.
And so this was the lead up to Ram Oh five.
So this was an Oh five.
So it was, it was a great day.
I start with a bit of a tailwind and you got a crosswind in the middle and then you
ended with about a tailwind with a headwind.
Ended with a headwind and I felt fantastic.
In fact, I thought about continuing on and well, let's go do the next state.
But you know, it was, it was, it was a fun day.
I'll never forget looking down at my polar heart rate monitor at the time and I just
couldn't believe the numbers because I, you know, I've done coastal stuff training here,
right?
Like Newport or whatever and do one days or one push rides with two water bottles.
Don't stop.
Don't unclip if you, unless you have to.
But I looked down and I just covered my home state in 10 and a half hours and it was fun.
Yeah.
I mean, you didn't have a power meter at the time, but I remember when I was time trialing,
I used to have so many models that I could basically estimate power by CDA, wind speed,
velocity, et cetera.
And I remember calculating you were probably doing about 310 Watts to 320 Watts for 10
hours and 40 minutes.
That would have been your average power.
Obviously you would have ebbed and flowed.
And I remember thinking, wow, we're in a different league here.
People like, you know, like, you know, you're really a professional cyclist at that point.
You're not really amongst the amateurs anymore.
Well, the metric in professional cycling is Watts per kilo.
Right.
So, and you weighed what at that point?
Ah, 160.
So that's what, 72 kilos.
Yeah.
I mean, so you have to figure that if you were averaging 310 to 320 Watts for 10 and
a half hours, your FTP was probably very close to 380 ish, maybe 400 Watts.
I mean, that's a professional level, at least a non-EPO professional level FTP.
EPO certainly probably gives you about a 10 to 15% boost on that.
But, you know, like the best guys in the tour during the sort of more EPO driven
eras were putting out, I used to know this stuff so well.
I think they were putting out about 6.3 to 6.4 Watts per kilo.
Anything over five is five sort of the, well, five for, I mean, if you can do five
with us, if you can do five without drugs, that's incredible.
And I, and I, that's kind of where I try unintentionally because I, you know, I had
no, for me, it was, this has always been sort of a sacred endeavor, right?
I knew how to make money.
I didn't, you know, to the extent that I needed to for Ram, I had sponsors, but for
me, I love the product side of getting into clothing and other gear production and
design, but for me, it's never been about monetizing it, right?
So I, you know, been invited to join professional cycling teams and train with
them and teams come out here or Arizona.
And it's never interested me.
It just was never something that I wanted to do.
That wasn't part of the deal for me.
It's always how good could I be?
And I knew the drug side of it as well.
And that's something that had no interest in.
Was there a lot of drug use in Ram and in these sort of?
We were drug tested throughout.
I don't know.
I don't know if anyone else was.
It's one of those things where I think that so it's such an epic event.
I don't know what you would do because there's so many components
to an optimal performance, right?
So I don't know what drug you would do.
I mean, stimulants would eventually blow you up.
Yeah.
I mean, modafinil, I mean, I think modafinil is banned on Wada and
Usada, but modafinil would certainly help.
What is that?
It's a drug that's approved.
It's only FDA indication is for narcolepsy, but it's a non stimulant
that keeps you awake.
It's actually a pretty interesting drug.
This was our drug of choice in residency.
We abused the shit out of this drug.
I was during residency taking two to 600 milligrams daily.
The maximum it was ever been tested at is 600 milligrams, but
in the air force, they had done a study, which is the study that I clung to,
which was they put a bunch of pilots into a simulator flight simulator.
And so the placebo group has nothing and predictably over the course of 24
hours, their performance declined.
So, you know, but not surprisingly.
And then you had like a caffeine group and their performance got a little bit
better initially, but then sort of petered out, if not outright crashed by 24 hours.
And of course I could be completely mistaking some of the details on this,
but this was the gist of it.
At 200 milligrams of Medafinil, which is the standard dose performance was
maintained for a very long period of time, but at the end of the 24 hours, it fell
off, but the thing that I always clung to was at 600 milligrams.
I think performance actually just got better monotonically over 24 hours.
And so I found this to be the most amazing drug in the world because basically
in residency, you're sort of sleeping about four hours a night on average, but
it never works out to that.
So it's like, you'll have zero and then you'll have six, and then you'll have
seven, and then you'll have zero and then you'll have three and then, you know what
I mean?
And so being able to take Medafinil was huge and you know, Medafinil has a number
of interesting properties.
I don't really use it more than a few times a year these days.
I only really used around jet lag, significant jet lag, but it strikes me as
being a pretty impressive drug.
Again, not withstanding the fact that I'm pretty sure it's Wada and you saw it.
It probably is, but that goes back to the point that I had no desire to be
professional because I didn't mean for me, it was very simple, which is natural
performance.
And if you're augmenting with things like that, it's just, you're not answering your
question, right?
You throw into these other variables that are called unnatural and where do you stop?
IVs have always been sort of a disputed territory for ultra athletes.
I've never, if you go into Vinnius, you're done in my opinion, right?
You should not need an RV.
That's not natural to me.
Even if it's just sailing, doesn't matter.
A lot of people disagree with me and that's just my personal opinion.
There are a lot of guys that design their whole plan around being able to go into
Vinnius and get, you know, all change.
And, and I haven't.
I mean, that's just me.
It's just my own standard.
There are very few things I think drug wise that would you.
Yeah. Ram is a tough one.
Ram's a tough one.
Because it's not clear to me that EPO would help you that much in Ram.
It's not even clear to me that anabolic steroids would help as much as they do in
the tour.
I mean, I think EPO is a much more important factor in grand tours than even
the anabolic steroids or the glucocorticoids or corticosteroids.
Yeah.
And the stimulants, I mean, that used to be the drug of choice up until the,
about the eighties in professional cycling.
But as you pointed out, I mean, stimulants, you better know when you're using them
and for how long because it's, you can fall off a cliff pretty quick.
Yeah.
And I've seen guys do that.
I've seen guys do that.
And I've been part of a few studies that have tested down it, which not
Liberty station and I think it was the NTC down in Point Loma, the Naval
hospital, I participated in a few studies with Navy SEALs and they were testing
different things and the SEALs and special forces there on a whole cocktail,
right, depending on what they're doing.
They're in transit.
They're taking one thing.
If they're getting ready, they take something else and they should.
And my Daphanil is a great drug in that setting because when you consider that
the alternative is stimulants with their horrible cycle, you know,
well, not to mention the psychological stimulants, throw you, right?
Throw your judgment and do other things.
So I agree.
I agree.
You know, I've never tried Adderall even once.
All of them.
The time I've taken the Daphanil, I've never once tried Adderall.
And yet the talks with a lot of people who swear by low dose Adderall for, you
know, mental clarity, like 10 milligrams or something like that.
But I don't know.
I just, I don't feel like stimulants would sit well with my system.
Yeah.
I didn't even know what Adderall was.
And some of the guys that software programmers on my team were trading
Adderall a few years ago, like, what are you guys doing?
And we're going to go outside and we'll be back and, you know, total hours
later, they're still heads down.
It clearly, I've seen it clearly.
I mean, it's certain tasks.
It's works.
Yeah.
I've seen, I think that this low dose Adderall strategy for the right person
can be remarkable.
Again, the question becomes frequency at what point does it become too much?
You know, today when we were on the bike, we were kind of talking
about this a little bit, but I remember when I was swimming a lot, it's a very
tight knit community, you know, the weirdos who want to do really long
swims or really long rides or really long runs or whatever, but it became
clear to me a few years into my swimming endeavors that most of the people
I swam with were addicts were recovering addicts.
So they had, they were former alcoholics.
Um, they, you know, you know, recovering drug addicts or things like that.
And I remember thinking, God, this is so interesting.
Like I'm the only non addict who does this amongst my peer group, but I've come
back and revisited that assumption and now realize that of course I am an addict.
And just because it's not alcohol or drugs, doesn't mean I'm not.
And so it makes me wonder like, what kind of person does this stuff?
What motivates them?
What are they numbing?
Where is this coming from?
And have you, and it's a philosophical question, but have you ever sort of
stopped and said, what the hell drove you to do all of this stuff?
Cause at the risk of just being a little blunt, like it ain't normal, man.
Like it ain't normal to do any of the shit we just spent the last hour talking about.
It's normal to me.
It's my normal.
No, it's not.
It's not.
And I learned this on Ram and I've never, I haven't experienced it since, but there's
a sequence of mental states that I think you go through in these things and call
it normal homeostasis.
And then you move to with sleep, DAP and extreme output, you move to illusions,
hallucinations, people talk about that and laugh about it.
They're funny, but you're still with it.
And then you get truly delusional.
This is when you're mentally insane.
There's a time on Ram toward the later part of 04 where I literally didn't know why this
van was following me.
And I somehow concocted this whole story about being chased and somehow crafted that we
were going by a power plant.
And I thought they were spies and I was truly delusional and I was paranoid and I would try
to get away from them and I kept racing away from them and they're still following me and
they're turning where I'm turning.
I'm like, what the hell is going on?
And finally I decided to get off the highway.
Well, I get off the highway and I'm in a cemetery in the middle of nowhere and I put my
bike.
It's all I had to protect myself in between me and my crew.
And they followed me and this van is here and they get out and I'm like, what are you
doing?
And they're like, so you didn't recognize them even once they got out of the van.
I didn't recognize them.
I was confused.
This is after six, seven days and maybe an hour and a half, two hours of sleep.
I slept up of my 10 ish hours the whole race.
One of the three hour block is very end where I just shut down.
So I had very little sleep over six or seven days.
I was just, I was losing it.
So it's not normal, right?
And eventually came back and the next day in daylight, like a holy cow.
And I remember everything.
I remember the whole episode and they're like, we picked a frickin cemetery of all places to
like peel off the road.
It was a cemetery and it was, they were scared.
Like, who is this guy?
What is he doing?
And then, you know, finally we got to New Jersey and 60 miles from the finish and I
had completely lost it and threatened a dear friend of mine, Howard, who's massive
college swimmer, former college swimmer.
And I decided I was going to get in a fight with him and he just, he stuck his hand out
and I thought I was going to get into a fist fight with Howard and I was 160 and he was
220 and twice my size.
Now you lose it.
Yeah.
What's the, but more deep seated.
And I think that's your question, right?
What motivates this?
I started the marathon.
I was living in New York city, actually living in Stanford, Connecticut in 97, 98.
And I moved back from Europe and came to New York, was working for Pricewaterhouse and
was living with guys I went to school with, you know, their Goldman Sachs and
et cetera, et cetera.
And they were bringing home a case of beer every night and I was sleeping on a couch
because I was tired in New York city.
I just wanted to get out of New York.
And so I crashed on their couch in Stanford.
I was always on the road.
And after a week of those guys bringing beer home every night, I'm like, this
isn't what I want to do.
So I needed an excuse.
So believe it or not for me, and by the way, when you're on the couch, you can't get
away.
So these guys would sit and watch TV and drink beer and five guys sitting around,
you know, living like they were in college, taking the train into New York, you know,
every morning at five thirty and just doing the drill.
So it was actually an escape for me.
So I started training for the 98 New York Marathon in the spring of 98.
And that was my excuse.
Sorry, I can't drink.
I'm got to get up and run in the morning.
And that's what I did.
So that's how it all that's how it all started.
They right around the same time was going through a brutal breakup with my college
sweetheart. And I think that was the second component of it.
Right. I had no desire to socialize and just wanted to get back to some foundation that
I could find for myself.
So a lot of transition.
So I'd say, you know, running away from stuff is where it started.
And then, of course, it evolved to, you know, once I did my move to Chicago, did the
Chicago Marathon, then did New York, which was my goal, did New York as Batman in 98.
It blast, frickin blast.
You know, run it.
Just didn't know.
Didn't worry about time.
Just had a good time.
But then realize that, you know, I could actually pull off some decent times.
It's not that hard.
I've hardly trained for this.
And I did well by my standards.
And so that's when I moved to San Diego in 99.
As I said, you know, I'm going to get serious about this and really focus on it.
Obviously, what what do you think about?
Big question I get.
What do you think about when you're out there for so long and I've you get bored and I've
never gotten bored.
And for me, you know, you and I have, I think, similar backgrounds, right?
We working class families who care deeply for us.
But we've also had a lot of stuff happen to us over time, right?
And for me, it's always been a time to work through stuff and just think about things
both past and present.
And so it's been very meditative for me.
And unfortunately, and I've learned over time to somewhat mitigate this, but it's where I
found my happy place.
Right.
I'll never forget.
I saw this a couple of years ago in my application for bad water in 2000 for the 2001
bad water.
Why do you want to do bad water?
And I said, I love ultra running.
And you know, the follow up question is, is why?
And you know, it's the only time I feel normal and I like to feel normal.
I feel normal when I'm out there doing that stuff.
It's just it feels right, right or wrong.
That was my comfortable spot.
Now, at least going back to that time, what felt abnormal when you weren't running?
Probably the biggest thing that felt unnatural, maybe not abnormal, is I just I've never
been terribly social.
I never when I moved to San Diego, I you know, I I like to build stuff.
I like to challenge myself.
And I just didn't fit in in New York.
I didn't fit in out here.
And I liked just pushing myself.
And that was abnormal.
That was unusual.
And I would have people ask me all the time about this sacrifice that I was making to
do what I do.
And my response has been it's a privilege to do what I do.
I love doing what I do.
It's fantastic.
It's not a sacrifice.
If it was a sacrifice, I wouldn't be doing it.
So that's, in my mind, abnormal.
And this is an I don't judge people, right?
I mean, I don't judge people for not doing this, but it's just I don't choose a path of
accepting that I have certain limitations and certain things are impossible.
I think that's bullshit.
I just refuse to accept that certain things are not possible because most of the time
it they're wrong.
It's amazing.
I mean, you know, people listening to this who obviously don't know you won't
necessarily appreciate some of the nuance in this.
But and obviously I won't mention names, but one of my favorite stories is there's a
piece that came out about you in Vogue, Men's Vogue.
I don't know.
God, it's got to be 12, 13 years ago.
And it's an amazing piece.
We'll make sure we link to it in the show notes here.
And it's amazing.
Like it's a really great piece that gets into it.
And one of my favorite stories is how on the day of the Oscars that year, you get a call
from someone basically saying, hey, so-and-so wants to invite you up to be her guest at the
Oscars tonight.
And it turned out to be like one of the biggest A-list actresses of our generation.
And you just decided, nah, I don't want to go.
And I'm thinking, you remember when you told me this story, I was like, oh my God, I would
have freaking walked to L.A. backwards or on my hands and knees just to have had a chance
to have met her, let alone have been on her arm all night.
But you just don't care.
I love it.
Yeah, I don't care.
I wish I could say I didn't care.
Believe it or not, I out of everything that I considered in that.
And I think I mentioned this to you when I first I just told you this story recently,
although it was written about years ago, someone that knew my mom knew how to get to me.
That's how the introduction came.
And talking through it, I just don't want to go to L.A.
I do not want to go to L.A.
I don't want to do the drive to L.A.
That is I don't if it were here.
Sure.
I no big deal.
I'm not doing anything today, but it might be fun.
But I don't want to deal with that.
But I think a big part of the mindset, my mindset at the time was I was really good at saying no.
I'm not so good at that now.
I say yes to a lot of things and at a detriment to time with my family or kids.
But at the time, I was very disciplined about saying no.
If it wasn't on the critical path, I wouldn't do it.
And I was very focused and I was just great at saying no.
In fact, there was a time there for months where I just told my family I'm busy.
I don't want to talk to you.
I don't want to communicate with you.
I'm going to be laser focused and I want to eliminate every potential distraction I can.
And at the time that for me would fell into that category.
It was just a distraction.
When do you think you made that transition to, you know, today your priorities are clearly split between mostly two things.
Your family first, your company second.
You obviously still exercise much more than the average individual could ever fathom.
But you know, you're not trying to set world records anymore.
What led to that transition?
Was it simply meeting your wife?
It was my wife.
Yeah.
I mean, there's a funny story here.
I met or didn't meet but saw my wife two years before I formally met her.
And I thought she was an angel.
Right.
I saw her and like, Oh my gosh, this is the woman of my dreams.
But I was trending for Ram.
That was the end of that.
Didn't even talk to her.
May have walked by her office once or twice.
And that was the end.
She was also an engineer.
Yeah.
She was a, she's electrical engineer and at the time was at Qualcomm.
And so, Sarr love at first I didn't talk to her and I'm relatively shy.
I'm not a big fan of hitting on that.
It wasn't my deal.
So a couple of years went by and we were both in the spin room a couple of years
after that I had a cast.
I had shattered my elbow training in 06 training for Ram and had reconstructive
surgery and had a cast that had drilled holes in.
So it was from my arm head all the way down to my wrist and I was drilling holes
in it so I could shower with this cast.
And I had pins and wire and crap in my left elbow.
And she came in and I had a pool of sweat.
I had gone in.
I was doing 12 hour.
I couldn't ride outside with my cast.
It was too dangerous.
But I was doing 12 hour sessions on a spin bike in the Qualcomm training room.
And I had gallons of water there, towels, of course, and carrots and celery.
That was my nutrition for the fiber.
And so, and a stack of DVDs.
I was there at three.
She rolls in at six or seven.
And at that point, I think I had taken my shirt off and was just hammering.
Right.
I was not expecting anyone to come in on a Saturday.
And so I throw my shirt back on and she gets on a spin bike and it was a, it's a
fun story, but I won't tell it now, but I, she was, it was her, right?
So I met her and we eventually went on a date and she and her dad, the Furnace
Creek 508 were my crew on the Furnace Creek 508 later that year.
She got me.
I mean, I, I went, we went to Hawaii shortly after we met and I ran
up polyacala, so I ran from paella at the beach up to the top of
polyacala on the last day of our stay.
And this is six weeks after we met and like, she gets me, she crude me in the
middle of the night, running whatever, 40 miles up to top of, you know, this
volcano, I, all right, she's the one we decided to get married after our third day.
So she changed.
I mean, it was, I'm done.
I, you know, I had answered the questions, most of the big questions.
I still had some bucket list things, but you know, where do you draw the line?
Right?
So I, it really comes down to the tree.
I found myself asking the question, what am I doing?
So I'd be out in East County doing my 300 miles training for a, I did the
UMC a 24 hour race that fall and in training for that, for the first time,
I had never asked myself that question.
What am I doing out here?
It's kind of like Forrest Gump when he's running back and forth across the country
and he sort of stops and realizes he's done.
Yeah.
Like that's, it was that.
And I, that was my last ride in East County that, you know, 10, 12 years ago,
like I asked myself that question and I knew I was done because I wanted to be
with her and so it was that simple.
So I want to let you get back to your day.
I know you got a hundred things to do today.
You got three great kids.
You are a man that I admire greatly.
You've created a tribe where you don't have to leave.
I mean, you can, you know, get to work from here.
You get to play with the kids.
You get to be with the kids most nights.
Obviously you have to still have to travel because you're still
running a startup company, but what do you take from all that stuff you learned
about being at the, you know, right at that level of being among the world's
elites, ultra distance athletes?
How do you bring that?
How do you bring what you learned from that to your, your ability to be a dad?
Or maybe asked another way, what do you take from those experiences that you
want to impart on your kids?
That's a tough one because I, I only learn what I learned because I figured
it out on my own and so I want to expose the kids to stuff and let them take to
whatever they take to.
I want them to know, I want them to be proud of their dad and their mom.
You know, we liked my wife played college basketball and still holds records here
in San Diego for shooting percentage, et cetera.
So I want the kids to be proud of their parents, but at the same time, like I
don't want them to feel like they're living our shadow.
I try not to go to the pool.
I know a lot of the coaches from my prior life, so I don't want the kids to get
special treatment because they're the, the spawn of me.
And so I try to actually coach them right now.
They're eight, my twins are eight.
My son's three.
Have fun.
It's really pretty simple.
I hated, I hated wrestling and then I grew to love it when I was in high school.
I hated it when I was their age.
But did your, did your parents make you go through to get you through that
transition of not like me, but it was more pure, right?
In Iowa, if you're not wrestling, something's wrong with you.
I mean, I started wrestling when I was five.
I thought it was ridiculous.
Why are these guys crawling all?
I mean, this is just crazy.
Like, why are you wrestling?
You know, it's smelly and I just didn't, you know, it didn't wasn't into it.
And then, and then I grew to love it when I got stronger and I saw the
strategy in it and loved wrestling in high school, but I grew to love it at my
own pace.
And so for me right now at the kids, I don't take a lot other than just,
Hey guys, you may not, you know, when a lot of it's just nutrition and lifestyle.
That's the biggest thing that I try to bring to them is this whole notion.
You don't need a car bloat.
You know, I'll make them this morning before my son went to his swim meet, you
know, I gave him some dry nuts and some cherries and my daughter's off for the
rest of the day.
And so a lot of us comes to nutrition in terms of the things that I've learned.
It really comes down to adversity and hard work.
I mean, like you said, we live in Nirvana.
I've really tried hard to create an environment for my family that is they can
feel safe, secure, they can explore, but I want them to see you saw me out with a
chainsaw for a reason.
First of all, I love chainsaw.
You're the only friend I have who chops more wood than me because I thought I was
the wood chopping, so Cal, like no one in San Diego could be chopping more wood than
me.
But I will say this in the last four weeks, you have broken me.
You've taken it to a new level.
And until four weeks ago, I had no idea you even chopped wood.
Yeah, we need to take a picture of my pile right now.
Yes, I want the kids for me.
I really want the kids to see that hard war comes in many forms.
It's physical, it's mental, etc.
And I want them to see the perseverance lead by example.
And we live in this society where everything gets outsourced and it seems to be like I
let other people do the work for you.
Look, like you mentioned, I, you know, we run a small company.
There's 15 of us now, but I take out the garbage and I run the company and I'll do
that until the day I die.
And I want my kids to see that too.
I don't think there's, you know, whether it's Iowa background or, you know, I think
we were cut from the same cloth that way.
Nothing is beneath me.
Well, you know, I fully believe in scaling through people and all that great stuff when
it comes to running a company.
But at the same time, when it comes to my kids, I want them to see that dad will roll
up his sleeves and whether it's cutting down a tree, taking care of the yard or taking
care of the house, whatever it might be.
I'm just putting a new faucet in yesterday because like, why are you down there?
I'm fixing the faucet.
Yeah.
You're so far.
I mean, I wish I had that desire, discipline, whatever.
Like, you know, I've just taken this opposite approach and I do worry deep down that it's
in the long run.
It's not the right thing for my kids because I grew up around a dad who did everything.
Yeah.
My dad didn't do any of that.
I so interesting.
My dad, my dad was the handiest dude that ever lived.
My dad, my dad, he couldn't fix anything.
It was a joke.
It's still a joke with our family.
And he, it's funny.
He comes out here now and he's clearing brush with me.
So, and he loves it.
And I love it.
But the kids will make their own decision.
And of course we could hire someone to put a new faucet in, but I want them.
I want them.
First of all, I enjoy the accomplishment, sense of pride.
If I just did that and enjoy tinkering around the house, but it's good for the kids to see.
The biggest thing for me with the software company has been in terms of taking the lessons
from endurance.
And so my family and my company are like my two families, right?
And never give up.
It's that simple, right?
And we've taken a lot of different paths to get to success for my training and my endurance
accomplishments, our family.
We've done a lot of different things to try to architect the best situation for our family.
And we've done the same thing with my company.
And you know, and I sit on the board of a few companies as well.
And my only advice is don't give up.
It's that simple.
When training, don't give up.
A lot of it, you get a lot of adversity, but don't give up.
It's usually the person that keeps moving.
If you don't win the race, you'll finish the race.
So just keep moving.
But there's something more to it, right?
There's this intelligence like you knew the days that you needed to back off.
And I suspect that your greatest asset outside of your mental toughness, which I just there's
just no way to displace that or there's there's no substitute for just the raw mental
toughness.
But I think it's that you've been, for example, very fortunate in your career to not have
many significant injuries.
You've had one arthroscopic knee operation.
I mean, there's nothing they like yank the little tiny sliver of meniscus off it for a guy
who's run tens of thousands of miles and has done all you've done.
You know, you've got a broken collarbone from a bike crash.
You've got a broken elbow from a bike crash.
You got a little meniscal nubbin that got cleared pretty quickly.
I think part of that is just the intelligence with which you've been able to approach this,
which is like you sort of know what are the days to push?
What are the days to back down?
And to me, that's the thing that like if that if that knowledge can be codified, that's
probably the thing that people would benefit from greatly.
Right. If you're listening to this and you're thinking, how am I going to run a marathon
while I'm, you know, the VP of operations at whatever company I'm at or I'm the single mom
who's trying to figure out how to get two kids off to school and back while working 40
hours a week.
But I still want to set these physical goals.
Like you got to be able to train smart.
Everything you do has to be purpose driven.
Yeah, I'm going to read you a text I got late last night.
Hey, Mike, quick question.
Today was meant to be 20 per Higdon.
That's how Higdon who fantastic marathon coach puts together training plans.
Didn't realize that I'd be climbing a lot.
Super awesome.
Although after loop, I only got 12.5.
And should I go pound more flat?
Eff it.
I'm also running out of time.
And my response to him is the general rules to stick to plan, even if you didn't get all
miles as scheduled.
In other words, don't try to make it up.
And he's the guy training for his first marathon.
He's up in San Francisco.
Good friend of mine.
So I've learned through mistakes.
If I push too hard, if I try to make up miles, for example, I'll blow up.
How do you codify that?
I mean, a lot of it's just it's just a voracious appetite for information and research.
It's the literature is there.
The information is there.
It may not be in context, right?
So I've learned a lot about running and fat adaptation, etc., through mountaineering and
cycling through other.
So it's there.
It just needs to be translated.
I mean, you and I are huge fans of Richard Feynman.
And if you look at what Feynman did with the whole Challenger investigation, bringing
together a cross-functional team of engineers and physicists, etc., in terms of problem
solving and scientific reasoning, the best approach is a cross-functional world-class
expert team because you think outside the box and you bring other ideas from other domains.
So I think codifying it comes down to don't limit yourself to just thinking about a marathon
or whatever.
Think, you know, look at yourself and be objective and figure out what it's going to
take to achieve whatever you define as success.
If you're a VP of ops of whatever company and you want a marathon, you want a 5K, look
around you, the information is there, the resources are there.
I mean, it's so much, that's the thing, right?
We talked about this.
When I used to ride out east in the desert, I would print out maps scanned from an Atlas
and then I put them in a Ziploc bag to keep them dry from my sweat.
And I would literally, that was my navigation.
I would chart out my 300 mollers, my 400 mollers.
It's so easy now to get information, perhaps too easy because when you have to work for
it, sometimes I think you're more vested.
So in terms of translating some sort of general rules, don't be afraid to ask questions.
My friends ask me, I coach a lot of people informally today and it's generally, you
don't overthink it.
I mean, while I definitely think there's something to be said for looking at the data
and analyzing, et cetera, unless you're looking to break a world record, don't be too
hard on yourself and just get out there and have fun.
I mean, that's sustainable.
You are very data light these days.
We were out riding this morning and lamenting the heat and how slowly we were riding
relative to what we would like to.
And I was like, God, these power meters, they never lie to you.
Just once I want this thing to lie to me and tell me I'm better than I am today.
And you're like, dude, I don't know how to power meter.
I don't have a heart rate monitor.
I'm just out here having fun.
And I was like, you know, why the hell do I have a power meter?
I don't compete anymore.
I don't do this anymore.
Yeah.
Why do I have this data?
It's like, yeah, artifacts of the past.
I don't even have a speedometer on my bike.
I mean, I have my phone in my pocket for emergency.
He's better.
It's not even tracking me.
Yeah.
Next, we're going to ride Saturday.
So you and I ride once a week.
This has been kind of an amazing tradition.
You've got me back on the bike.
I took a three year hiatus and I've really enjoyed our Sunday morning rides.
We only ride 40K.
We ride 40K and you listen to me rant the entire time.
I love every...
But the only reason is if I were ranting, I couldn't keep up with you.
So it's like I have to let you do the talking so that, you know, it can normalize
us a little bit so I can keep up.
No, but it's awesome.
The last thing I'll say is, and this is going to be disappointing to the listeners
because I'm not going to let the cat out of the bag.
But you are the guy who has introduced me to the greatest beer in the history of beer.
And this was probably four years ago.
I came over to your place one day and you gave me one of these things.
And I was like, yeah, yeah, I don't really like beer.
Then you're like, yeah, just try this.
I mean, that was the moment the rat hit the lever and got the cocaine.
I was like, this is from another planet.
This this isn't beer.
This is all that shit I thought I hated.
You know, Coors Light and Budweiser and every IPA on the planet like that.
I just find disgusting.
This was a different animal.
And to this day, even though I don't drink much, I might have one bottle a month,
including right now, I just finished one as we were sitting here talking.
It's hard to put in words how good this stuff is.
And I don't know if you know this, but you probably do know this.
So once you introduced me to said beer, I don't do anything in moderation.
So I wanted to make sure I could get enough of it for us.
So I had one of my analysts start looking around the country to find it,
because at the time you were only getting it in Belgium, right?
Yeah, I would.
I was bringing this into the country as yeast samples.
I was ordering it online and the first shipment came as a box of yeast samples,
which is, I guess, what they did.
I I just ordered it online, right?
And it was like 10 euro a bottle.
It was not cheap.
Yeah, it's not cheap.
And you've since you know, I've traveled to Belgium to experience this firsthand.
It's a great beer.
And so I had Nick Stenson, who was at the time and still and still actually is working for me.
And I was like, and Nick can figure out anything like he's just like a savant
of figuring stuff out.
And I was like, Nick, can you figure out if we can get this beer in the United States?
Two days later, he calls me, he goes, all right, 13 bottles up at this liquor store
in Alameda, California, 42 bottles in this place in New Jersey.
He rattles off the whole country.
And he's like, so how many do you want?
I was like, I'm not trying to stand the question.
He's like, well, which of these ones do you want?
And I was like, all of them, every single one, 260 bottles of this stuff arrive.
And, you know, that lasted us for a couple of years.
It did.
And I've been fortunate.
I have stockpiled.
Because the last shipment I got for you was about what, six months ago, we got you.
It was about six months ago.
So the seller is full of this beer and every other beer this brewer makes.
And they're all fantastic.
Are there any, can we give the listener a bone?
I can't, I don't want to name this beer because honest, I mean, not to sound like a dick,
but I just, I'm not going to be happy if we can't get this beer anymore.
And I'm worried that it's such a limited beer that if I say what it is, I'm never
going to get to drink it again.
So I'm just going to have to be a selfish jerk.
Can we name the brewery and not screw ourselves or what people figured out?
No, no, we can't name it.
What I love about the brewer, the brewery in Belgium, they're truly authentic.
They just don't give a shit, right?
So they're just low volume.
They're low volume.
They do all these crazy runs.
They experiment.
They try different things.
They have some of their, they do like 300 bottle runs.
They just, they tinker and it's fantastic.
I mean, it's all so bad.
Everything share anything.
Some of it's, some of it's not all of it's great.
They have a couple of sours that I just don't care for.
I'm not a fan of those, but yeah, from strong Belgian nails to quads and
everyone I've introduced it to has just been blown away.
You don't have to be a beer drinker.
You know, you don't have to be a guy who even likes alcohol.
Like there's just something about this that's so good.
So, so here's the bone.
I think we can throw people in one of our droughts a couple of years ago,
when we were between like being able to find more of this stuff, you introduced
me to a beer that I think we can share with the general population that I
honestly is 80% as good.
It's close.
It's not special, but it's fantastic.
It's a great mass production beer.
I agree with you.
And that would be judgment day.
Judgment day.
Lost Abbey is a San San Marcos, California brewery.
Judgment day is up there.
So it's a strong Belgian quad, as they call it.
There are a few others, Shemais Grand Reserve and others, but the
judgment day is, it's a local brewery.
It's the closest thing I've ever tried to this beer.
There are a few, and I've come at it from a few different directions to try to
find something similar to our favorite judgment days and judgment.
There's a few other, you know, Cask aged judgment day equivalents that the
Lost Abbey put out that are fantastic, but it'll a little too smokey or a little
too oaky or et cetera.
The judgment day is just the right taste.
Judgment days.
It is.
It's dense.
It's a dense, strong 10 plus percent alcohol.
All you need is one.
Yep.
You know, and I find it to be the best beer when there are a lot of people over
because a, I'm not going to drink any other beer.
It's so gross.
And B, I'm not sharing our special one.
Cause that's just, yeah, that's.
I've made the mistake.
It's funny.
I shared this beer with one other friend and he's not a beer drinker either.
And he, he said, no, no, no, I drink wine.
And I gave him this beer and he had two.
And you're thinking, Oh my God, that's two of my beers gone.
Well, and now he's going to go and get more.
Yeah, I didn't go.
I have stuff dating back dating back to the early 2000s.
So I actually have a stockpile of age, really good stuff.
So I, you know, I'm completely out by the way.
I have you none.
I gave you my last batch because I was so grateful for all the help you'd given me.
Yeah.
You can have one.
I got my one for the month today.
So they went and bought up everything they could find.
And I've learned if I want to share it, I take off the label, put it into a glass.
Yeah.
It's other, the world's supposed to be the world's best beer.
And I forget the name of it in Belgium.
It's easier to get to this now.
All right.
So for the listener, Oh, and then here's another little point.
I was at BevMo this week, totally opportunistic.
I pulled in, I was looking for like a credit union that I needed to go open
an accountant, blah, blah, blah.
And I was like, Oh, there's a BevMo here.
I'm going to go get some more lost Abby.
Cause that's where I used to get the judgment day.
And I go in and they don't have it.
And they're like, yeah, we're not carrying it anymore.
It's not profitable enough.
I'm like, what the hell is wrong with you people?
Who cares how profitable it is?
It's the greatest fricking mass produced beer in the history of civilization.
So now I'm sweating it.
Are we going to be able to struggle to get judgment day?
So what we need to do is go up to the brewery.
That's what we need to do.
And we'll just fix that.
Maybe if enough people are listening to this and they can
repique the demand, we're not going to BevMo.
We might start stocking it again.
And it's relatively cheap.
I mean, it's, it's 10 bucks for a Magnum basically.
Yeah.
Pine or whatever, whatever that size is.
It's cheap.
Well, Mike, we've talked about what I consider some of the most ridiculous
feats of human endurance, along with probably the most ridiculous
feat of beer engineering in the same discussion.
If people want to learn more about you, unfortunately, you are a hard guy to
learn about a Google search of your name yields almost nothing.
Is there anything you want people to know about you read about?
I mean, we're going to figure out a way to find that Vogue article,
which I think is great.
We'll link to a page that you have that talk, you know, that kind of lists
out some of these things that you've done.
Is there anything else people can do to learn about you?
No, I'm just go to Peter's website.
Very well.
No, I used to have a race website years ago.
We've tweaked that to just be a landing page, but I, at this point,
go to Peter's website.
Well, maybe one day when you sell indigenous, your current company, you
know, after you take a little hiatus and really relax, maybe you'll
reconsider this idea of forming a coaching company, because I think in
many ways you actually have the perfect skill set, right?
Which is you're a software engineer who knows how to build huge products
that can be scaled and more importantly, you bring an expertise to this
field that nobody has.
And I don't know, I get the sense that there are people out there who would
really value being able to access your brain to help them accomplish their goals.
So maybe we'll plant that seed here today.
Maybe.
All right, man.
Thank you very much.
And I wish you the best on the remainder of this smoking hot day.
It's been a blast.
Thank you.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
podcast, there you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this
episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com.
What's a nerd safari you ask?
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a
week email, where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting
papers I've read and all things related to longevity, science, performance,
sleep, et cetera.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the
ID Peter Attia MD, but usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your
questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the
practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the
user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnoses, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical
condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare
professionals for any such conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously
for all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.