Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Bob, that's a lot of books behind you, man. Have you read all of them or most of
them?
Well, thanks for noticing, Peter. I'm a voracious reader. Sometimes my appetite is too big,
so I have to admit, I haven't read all of them, maybe 90% I think at this point.
That's impressive. Everything, the classics, literature, science.
Mostly the classics, you can probably tell by the book binding on some of those. Yeah.
Hard to get them out of the shelf, to be honest, to pull those things out. They're in there
so tight.
Yeah. And it's good, too. Your kids can do little projects flattening leaves and stuff
like that.
Yes.
We've got more of those going on.
It's fun for the whole family.
All right. Well, what do we have on the docket today for AMA number 20 something, 25?
Yeah, 25. So in a similar vein as some of the previous AMAs, I consolidated a bunch
of questions around a particular topic, and this one is cancer screening. We've gotten
a bunch of different questions related to cancer and cancer screening. So you've got,
I'll give you a flavor of some of the questions that we've received. How do you think about
cancer screening? Why and or when should I be screened? Which ones or which tests are
worth getting? What do you think of liquid biopsies? How do you interpret sensitivity
and specificity of tests? What do those actually mean? What are some screening tools for cancer
you use in your practice? There's another one. I don't know if this was a question from
someone, but I found this very interesting. And this is this question is, can you discuss
how you categorize cancers and how you screen for each? So I remember you told me this,
too, and it was it's pretty interesting. I don't know if everybody would suspect this
answer, but cancers outside the body versus cancers inside the body. So we'll get into
that a little bit. But I think it probably makes sense to start off with sort of in general,
I know you're a you're a strategy person. I know you love tactics, too. But I think
that just to be clear, Bob, do we have three or four hours set aside for this podcast?
Hopefully it's the hopefully it's the latter. Yeah, I think this could be a lot. This could
be a long one. All right. Well, where would you like to begin? I think we should begin
from the top. The first question was, how do you think about cancer screening? Yeah.
So again, I guess putting this in the context of what we're interested in clinically probably
sounds repetitive, but longevity has these two components and they're not independent.
But sometimes it's helpful to think about them in isolation. So lifespan, health span,
how do you live longer and then how do you live better? And in many ways, cancer versus
the other major chronic diseases that rob a person of lifespan, namely the atherosclerotic
diseases and the diseases of dementia and neurocognitive decline. The latter two tend
to go more hand in hand with the reduction in health span. In other words, by definition,
when a person has Alzheimer's disease, their quality of life, i.e. their cognition is also
deteriorating. So they're experiencing both the slide in quality of life and eventually
length of life. And similarly in people that have advanced atherosclerosis, while of course
it's true that people die suddenly of heart attacks who are otherwise totally healthy,
a lot of times the reduction in the ability to carry out activities of daily living kind
of moves more hand in hand with that. I would say that's a little less the case with cancer.
Obviously cancer is still a disease whose primary risk factor is age. So age is the
greatest risk factor for cancer just as it is for the other two diseases. But it's also
in some ways a little bit easier to think of cancer in isolation from the health span
stuff, the decline in physical and mental and emotional state. So if you're trying to imagine
a world in which you can live longer, as we've discussed many times previously, that means living
in a world where we delay the onset of chronic disease and or have better tools to live longer
with chronic disease. But you know that I much favor the former option because we basically
spent most of the history of modern medicine working on the latter option with very, very
limited success. So, okay, so let's now pause it for a moment that one of the pillars of longevity
is minimizing mortality from cancer. So where does screening fit into this? Well screening is one of
three pieces that you would envision, right? The first piece would be how do you prevent cancer?
The second thing would be how do you screen for cancer and detect it early? And I'll explain why
I think that's necessary. And the third is how do you treat it when you have it? So we can talk a
lot about the former, how do you prevent cancer? We've had many podcasts and we have many podcasts
coming up where we're going to get into the treatments of cancer. But I want to focus this
one on the prevention piece. So why do I believe that? Well, this is a controversial topic I want
to say first. So not all people believe that screening matters. But I think the simplest
explanation for why screening matters is the evidence that suggests that a cancer that is
caught earlier is easier to treat than a cancer that is caught later. In other words, if you catch
a breast cancer or a colon cancer when there are tens of millions or hundreds of millions of cancer
cells, your odds of treating that successfully are better than if you catch the same cancer years
later when there are billions of cells. And the evidence for that basically comes from examining
how patients respond to the exact same drugs in the adjuvant setting versus in the metastatic
setting. So what does that mean? So the adjuvant setting is when a drug is given to a patient who
has no visible cancer. So these are patients that may have had the visible cancer removed. You believe
that they have microscopic disease that remains and you give them a drug like Herceptin for a
HER2-neu positive breast cancer. And if you compare the outcomes of those patients to the
outcomes of patients who are given the exact same drug for the exact same phenotype and genotype of
the cancer, but in the metastatic setting, there's no comparison in the outcomes. And one explanation
for that may be that the more mature cancers, the ones that have been around longer, have developed
more mutations, they are more difficult to treat. So it is therefore my belief that the more we can
do to screen for cancer and catch it earlier, the better we will be. But we do pay a price for that.
We pay a financial price for that. In other words, it costs money to screen early. And we pay
potentially an emotional price from that because as we'll get to, and you alluded to, we have to now
get into false positives and false negatives. But at a high level, Bob, that's how I think about
this cancer or this topic around cancer screening. Yeah, I think it's telling too, if you look at
statistics on that, they call it five-year survival. So what are the odds of you surviving a
cancer? And then if you look at specific cancers like breast cancer, you're talking about, you catch
it early and it's a local cancer, it hasn't metastasized. And the statistics on that is the
five-year survival rates are about 99%. And then you go to a distant cancer, so a metastatic breast
cancer, and it's closer to about 25% in terms of the five-year survival. And also what you alluded
to as well, the false positives, false negatives. I said I alluded to that. So that gets into
sensitivity, specificity. And I didn't mention this, but positive predictive value, negative predictive
value. And I think it probably would be helpful to go into that. And I think pictures are probably
worth a thousand words in this case, in terms of looking at how good a screening tool is and
determining that stuff, sensitivity, specificity, et cetera. So do you want to start with just,
we want to just start explaining those things? Sure. So I think it makes sense to pull up a second.
Yeah, we've got some slides that we use with our patients. So go ahead and pull these up and we'll
walk through that. Because I think if you want to take ownership over your own understanding of
cancer screening, you'll definitely want to get to a point where you're really facile with these terms.
Thank you for listening to today's sneak peek AMA episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in hearing the complete version of this AMA, you'll want to become a member. We created a
membership program to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
Membership benefits are many and beyond the complete episodes of the AMA each month,
they include the following ridiculously comprehensive podcast show notes that detail
every topic, paper, person, and thing we discuss on each episode of The Drive. Access to our private
podcast feed, the qualities, which were a super short podcast, typically less than five minutes,
released every Tuesday through Friday, which highlight the best questions, topics, and tactics
discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is particularly important for those of you who
haven't heard all of the back episodes, becomes a great way to go back and filter and decide which
ones you want to listen to in detail. Really steep discount codes for products I use and believe in,
but for which I don't get paid to endorse, and benefits that we continue to add over time. If
you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward
slash subscribe. Lastly, if you're already a member, but you're hearing this, it means you
haven't downloaded our member-only podcast feed where you can get the full access to the AMA,
and you don't have to listen to this. You can download that at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
members. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You
can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast player you listen on. This
podcast is for general informational purposes only, and does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to
this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay
in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the
assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts
of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or
advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list
of such companies.