Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey Steve, as we were just talking about a minute ago, this has been a long time coming.
I am so excited about this discussion today.
Good.
I'm looking forward to it myself.
You're one of those people and they're a handful of people like you where anytime we sit down,
if it's over a coffee, a meal or a short phone call, I feel like my learning increases at
a geometric rate.
To now be able to do a very long discussion and then share it with so many people is going
to be awesome.
Frankly, any discussion about longevity, I think, needs to begin with your background.
I think people need to understand the curious character that you are.
Your journey to where you are today is not common, but yet I think it speaks to the unique
lens that you've brought to this space.
Give folks a sense of what you did growing up.
When you were in high school, what were you interested in?
It was interesting.
In high school, I was a math nerd and everybody assumed that I was going to be a mathematician,
including myself.
In fact, I was a math major when I first went to college.
What I really did in my spare time in high school when I wasn't playing sports is I liked
to kick around in the woods.
This was in Southern California and I would actually go out into the desert.
I actually had a high school biology teacher who would take students out in the desert
to catch rattlesnakes.
I'm still not sure why he was doing that.
I think he was milking them and getting money for the venom or something.
Anyway, I had a great time doing that.
At that time, I think I was in 10th grade, he said, you're going to be a biologist.
I thought that's the most ridiculous thing I've ever heard of.
I know I'm going to be a mathematician.
After I got to college, I suddenly discovered after the first year, I didn't really like
math all that much.
I wasn't about to spend four years doing something I didn't like.
What I really liked to do was read.
I switched to an English major and I actually ended up with an English degree.
My goal at that point was to write the great American novel and become the Ernest Hemingway
of the latter 20th century.
You went to UCLA for undergrad?
You're in SoCo.
Yes, I did.
That was really my job.
The one thing I did is I thought, well, to write novels, I've had a pretty traditional
upbringing, middle class upbringing, except for the fact that my family traveled all over.
I went to 20 different grade schools, at least.
I'm not sure how many, really.
We would live two months.
My dad sold our house and bought a house trailer that we put behind the car.
About six years, we would spend three months in this town, four months in that town.
This wasn't because one of your parents was in the military?
No.
No, my dad was a newspaper pressman.
His union had something called a traveling card, which meant that if you were a union
member, you could go to any big city newspaper and be hired for some short amount of time.
He must have just had a travel bug.
I really regret that I never asked him, what were you thinking, Dad, when you did this?
That's where we went.
El Paso, Dallas, Atlanta, Miami, Virginia, New York, Detroit.
That was my schooling, except in doing all this traveling every year, I missed probably
two months of school.
When we were traveling, my parents just threw these books at me in the back seat of the
car and said, there, it's your study time.
I learned a lot on my own and that probably influenced somewhat who I am because that's
a pretty unusual upbringing, probably.
Well, I mean, I can't imagine most kids could thrive in that setting because it's so disruptive.
I actually had a patient once who went to 11 different schools between first and 12th
grade.
I averaged about a year per school, so at least they didn't have to move during the
school year.
I always thought that that was just the social aspect of that, not to mention just the continuity.
When you move from one state to the next, they may have different standards for what
you're going to learn in English, math, or science.
What you described takes that to a whole new level.
Were you ever behind in school?
Did you ever show up at the school that you were in and feel like you're out to lunch
or was it the opposite?
Did you generally feel like you were more than making up for it in the backseat?
I felt like I was more than making up for it, but I also think the school systems in
Southern California were particularly good at that time.
I usually had had in school a lot of the stuff that I would come across, particularly in
the South, which is the first part of this journey where we travel through.
In fact, it was probably made easier for me because I was an only child and I was used
to being thrown on my own resources.
One of the things that I quickly figured out, because I was always the smallest kid in class,
even when I graduated from high school, I was still 105 pounds and about 5 feet 4.
I quickly learned though that I could avoid being beaten up by the bigger kids if I helped
them with their homework.
I quickly fell into that in every school I went to.
I was the guy that would help you figure out what was going on in math or history or
whatever.
You're a normal sized person.
It's not like you're 5 foot 7 today.
What do you attribute such a late growth spurt to?
Well, it's kind of interesting given the topic we're going to be talking about.
When I was a sophomore in high school, I was still way behind.
I was a wrestler.
I was wrestling in the 98 pound division, which is the lowest weight class, but I only
weighed 79 pounds.
At some point, my parents took me to the doctor because they were concerned about delayed
puberty and me being so small.
I got some sort of injections then.
I don't know if it was growth hormone, I don't know if it was testosterone, but almost immediately
after that, I started going through puberty.
My real growth spurt was after I got into college.
It was very unusual and I still think of myself as being little.
Even though I know I'm normal size, I still think of myself as being small.
Well, that's interesting.
That probably speaks to the psychology of our formative years, right?
Right, exactly.
I really would be curious to know if I got growth hormone when I got those injections
or not.
All good aspiring authors you somehow lined up in New York.
Right.
Yeah, I figured that was a place to be if you were going to be a great novelist because
that's where all the publishing was.
The other thing that I figured was that if I'm going to write a great novel, I don't
have anything but a typical middle class experience because at the time, I didn't realize how
unusual my background was.
I went there, but I decided I needed to start accumulating experiences.
I started having adventures.
I would hop a train from Southern California to San Francisco and back.
I got to New York by hitchhiking to New York.
Later on, I hitchhiked back to California again.
When I was in New York, I thought, well, where am I going to get experiences here?
I ended up driving a taxi there because I thought, wow, this looks like you could really
accumulate a lot of experiences in a hurry here, which was true.
How long did it take you to learn the city?
New York is in some ways a pretty straightforward city to learn because it's on a beautiful
grid, but there's some nuance to it given the one-way streets and you've got Broadway
is diagonal.
It's not a trivial city to learn, especially given its size.
How long did it take you to be a competent cabbie?
Well, I was pretty competent right off because of the logical structure of it, but there
are these parts of the city below 14th Street, for instance, that were amazed.
Usually what I would do to hide my ignorance is I would just ask the passenger, which way
would you like me to take?
Then they would direct me.
I never really felt like I was lost there.
Then, of course, if you got to the outer boroughs, it was a whole different ballgame, but I didn't
go to the outer boroughs very much.
When I did, I had to have help getting back because it was challenging.
But it was a really unique experience.
I drove at night, so I would go to work about four in the afternoon and come home about
somewhere between midnight and 2 a.m., depending on what the fares were like.
The experiences I had, I had people who, one person I remember well, wanted me to stop
in every bar along the street.
We did this for a while.
He said, go in the bar, and he said, wait for me, and he'd come out, and we'd go to
the next one.
I finally said, if you don't mind my asking, because I was afraid he was going to go into
the bar and never come back, and I would be in debt for the taxi fare.
He said, oh, I'm looking for my wife, and when I find her, I'm going to shoot her.
That's the point at which I said, okay, well, you can pay your fare now.
That's a type of thing that happened to me more than a few times.
What years were this?
These were in the mid-1970s.
In New York, a totally different city from what it is today.
Yes, yes.
No, in those days, you could get robbed in daylight in Central Park.
Now Central Park is just a wonderful place to go.
It was, in retrospect, really quite the interesting time.
What was the dodgiest part of the city south of 96th?
Probably the extreme west side, 9th and 10th, because there was a lot of abandoned buildings
over there.
The lighting wasn't good.
And then, of course, Harlem was not a great place then.
That's why I said south of 96th.
I took that as a given.
I figured it was.
The interesting thing is a lot of cab drivers would not take fares to Harlem, and I would.
I would take somebody any place they wanted to go.
But I did have some dicey experiences there, I have to say.
I never was robbed, but I, when the only taxi driver in this garage that I knew that was
never robbed during that time.
Do you attribute that to pure luck or something else?
Yeah, I do.
The one time I was certain I was going to be robbed, a police car turned a corner and
pulled up behind me and couldn't get by because it was a narrow street.
So the guys that I could just tell from the vibe, this is not going to be good, they just
paid and got out and left.
So that was the closest that I had.
Although I did pick up two taxi drivers who had been robbed and their cab had been hijacked.
And they were on the street and they waved me down.
So yeah, it was a pretty adventurous time.
So where was it in here, Steve, that you also began a little side hustle training animals?
Well that was after my taxi driving years.
What happened is that I moved back to Portland, Oregon.
After all of the travel that my family did, we ended up in Portland, Oregon where we
kind of settled down.
So I'd spent my first year, sort of sixth through tenth grades there.
I really liked it.
And after I got out of college, I went to Portland for a short time before I went to
New York.
So I went back to Portland and there I was taking karate.
And my karate teacher had some African lions at his ranch out in the country.
I used to go out and visit him and if he was cleaning the cages, I would, you know, he'd
say, come on in, let's talk while I'm working.
And so I'd do that.
And I guess I wasn't too obviously terrified because he got an offer to use the lions in
a movie in Hollywood and he needed someone to help him drive the lions to Hollywood.
So he asked me if I'd do that.
I had a job as a newspaper reporter at the time, so I thought, well, this is going to
be a long weekend.
So I said, yeah, I'll help you do it.
And I went out to his house and I assumed there was going to be something like a horse
trailer that was modified for lions.
And what he said was, help me get the back seat out of the car here, Steve, and we're
going to put Churza, which is one of his lions, in the back.
So we did.
We took out the car seat.
We put the lion in the back seat and we took off for L.A.
And there was nothing between, no screen, no window, nothing between the front and the
back seat.
But in my naiveté.
This is when you're wishing for the New York taxi with the plexiglass.
Yeah, no kidding.
Well, actually, I wasn't worried at first because I thought, it's his pet.
He must know what he's doing later on after I knew more.
But you weren't worried about the fact that the pet's more familiar with him than you
and if...
No, I should have been.
I should have been.
But here's the weird thing is that he was driving initially and the way he controlled
this lion was with a cattle electric prod.
And so he handed me this prod and it was if you push the button, it buzzes.
And he said, the lion's afraid of that.
So if he gets restless, just stick that in his face.
Don't touch him with it.
Just stick it in his face and buzz it.
And so that worked once.
And then the battery ran out.
So then I said, what am I going to do now?
He goes, well, just hold it in his face and go, buzz with your mouth like that.
And I thought again, I thought, it's his lion.
He must know that his lion's that stupid.
And it turned out his lion wasn't that stupid.
That worked once.
And then the lion started to get really quite active.
And then I realized my friend was scared.
And that's when I got scared because I thought he knows what.
So we ended up pulling off on a side road in the middle of the night now, getting his
lion out on a long leash and walking it down this rural country road for several miles
to try to get it tired out.
And I was driving the car so that he could be in the headlights and see where he was
leading the lion.
And every time we would go around a corner and the lion would lose sight of the car,
we'd come around the corner and the lion would attack the car.
We'd jump up on the hood.
So I was expecting a catastrophe.
I thought there's going to be a farm and there's going to be a dog.
And the dog's going to run out.
But none of that happened.
So we put the lion in the back of the car.
It was tired.
It slept all the way until we got to the Bay Area when we had switched drivers.
And suddenly the police lights came on behind me.
And so the policeman pulled us over and I jumped out quickly to try to pretend this
was just normal.
But you know how in the middle of the night they'll shine their lights into the car ahead
of them so they can see what's going on.
The lion is now getting up and it's pacing back and forth.
And I'm saying, oh, just bringing the lion down from Disney Studios in Washington.
Very routine.
Was I speeding?
Sorry about that.
And in the meantime, my friend who owns the lion is in the front seat and he's trying
to keep it from coming in the front seat.
So you can see him trying to hit it with his elbow and then the lion goes over and steps
on the car horn.
And so the car horn just starts shrieking.
So at this point the policeman said, just get out of my jurisdiction.
He didn't know how to deal with it.
So we had a rather uneventful trip down to LA.
At some point did you at least get a new battery for the Taser?
We didn't.
Once we got to LA we did.
But by the time it was light we were close enough that the lion was asleep still.
So we never did.
It was really pretty interesting.
My intention was as soon as we delivered the lion to fly back to Portland and continue
on with my life.
But it turned out the movie producer offered me a job on the spot.
And he said, we're doing this movie.
We're going to have 25 lions in it.
We need lots of lion trainers.
I said, you don't understand.
I have a job as a reporter.
This is the first time I've ever been in close contact with a lion.
And frankly it scared me to death.
So he said, don't worry about that.
He says, I've got lots of professional training.
You're the only one dumb enough to do this job.
I can't find anybody in my union willing to do this.
But yes, carry on.
Exactly.
So I was still pretty dubious.
I have to sell you.
But here was the key.
He said, well, the way you're going to start is I'm raising some lions at my house.
And so I'd like you to live at my house for the next few months and take care of the lions.
And the only people that you'll have to deal with is my wife and my daughter, my wife,
Tippi.
And I had this crush on this actress named Tippi Hedren since I'd seen her in the birds
when I was a kid.
And as soon as he said Tippi, I thought, gee, that's an unusual name.
And it turns out he was married to Tippi Hedren.
So suddenly I'm thinking of going and living in a house with an actress that I had a crush
on since I was 11 years old.
So that changed my attitude entirely.
So I said, OK, when do I start?
I mean, at this point, Steve, you have more than enough substrate to write a fantastic
novel, right?
Yeah, but by that time I realized that that's not where my talent lay.
So I really wasn't thinking anymore of writing a novel.
I was trying to think I loved animals so much.
I thought, gosh, this is great.
I get to spend my entire day around these animals.
And actually for the first year I worked there, I never took a day off on Saturday and Sunday
because I just enjoyed it so much.
So I'd almost feel like I'd been given this gift of something that I was always meant
to do, but by luck I had just stumbled into it.
So what finally got you to go back to graduate school?
Probably a bad encounter with a lion.
I was fairly significantly injured by a lion.
And I spent a couple of weeks in the hospital and a couple of more months laid up.
What happened?
I jumped to me.
A lion attacked me under a very bizarre set of circumstances.
And there was no one around when this happened.
So I was completely helpless, pinned to the ground by this lion, expecting that it would
start eating me at any point.
And again, it's one of these lucky things.
The only thing that saved me is that it grabbed me and it sunk its teeth into my leg.
But it was getting possessive over my leg because they get that way over food.
If you've ever seen a group of lions eating, they'll just get their food in front of them
and grab onto it very tightly.
And that's what it was doing.
And so I was just trying to stay conscious and not pass out because I thought then he's
going to let go of my leg and start to eat me.
And the only reason I'm here today is there were some people that were driving by on the
road above the compound.
And this was kind of a well-known place that people could pull off the road and they could
look down and they might see lions running around or tigers.
Where was this, Steve?
This is in Acton, California, which is just north of Los Angeles, out in the desert near
Palmdale.
And so they saw me with this lion on top of me.
So they drove up to the front office and said, there's a guy in the back with a lion on top
of him.
We don't know if that's supposed to be that way or not.
And so they came and rescued me, the other trainers that were in the office.
So that gave me a lot of time to think about my future.
And I really, by that time, was kind of disinterested in the Hollywood part of it.
I still love the animals.
But I really got bored with the movie aspect of it because there's a stereotype that movie
people only talk about movies and making movies and movie deals and movie sequels and movie
reruns.
And I didn't find that very interesting.
And so I'd really gotten bored with that part of it.
So I thought, I've accumulated all this knowledge about animals that's applied.
Maybe I should go to graduate school and study it in a formal sort of sense.
So I actually went to graduate school with the intention of studying lions in East Africa.
And I went to East Africa at that point.
There was a long-running Serengeti lion project that had just ended.
The people that were doing it had just quit.
I went to graduate school.
My advisor did research in East Africa on monkeys.
And he told me, if you get over there, you might be able to take over this project.
But I didn't.
By the time I got there, someone else had come and taken it over.
So it didn't work out.
So I ended up doing a PhD that was a very combining my math and my interest in animal
behavior.
And I did a PhD on sort of theoretical models of animal combat and why animals very seldom
fight to the death.
And under what circumstances they might do that.
So I had nothing really to do with lions.
So at that point, I didn't really know.
I thought, well, I've got a PhD.
I guess I should be a professor somewhere.
But I had no interest in aging.
It never even occurred to me.
But I did a postdoc in South America at a biological station.
Again, unrelated to aging, I was studying these social birds.
But a friend of mine there was studying another group of animals.
But he kept catching opossums in his traps.
And at one point I said, you know, you're not able to catch the foxes that you want
to.
You're catching the opossums.
You're studying the wrong thing.
You should be studying the opossums.
So he said, well, what of interest could we do to the opossums?
And we put our heads together and came up with something.
It still had nothing to do with aging.
But in the course of that project, I would capture opossums once a month.
And I would weigh them and measure them and look in the pouch.
These were all females that were radio collared.
And one of the things I discovered was they aged incredibly quickly.
So this is an animal.
The South American ones that we were studying looked very much like the North American opossums.
Most people would not be able to tell the difference.
So they're about the size of a small cat.
And I expected they would live 10 or 20 years like cats do.
And here at 18 months, they would get cataracts.
They would lose muscle.
They would be able to parasitize.
They would just look terrible.
Even the same animal that I caught three months earlier.
And I just became incredibly intrigued with why they would age so much more quickly than
a cat.
And that really started my interest in aging.
In fact, the project that he and I were working on eventually was published in one of the
most prestigious scientific journals.
And by the time it came out, I completely lost interest.
I was interested in aging.
And I've been interested in it ever since.
So that's kind of the long story about how I got into this.
So after you finished your postdoc, where did you come back to?
My first faculty position was at Harvard.
And it was great because that was the point where I was switching over from what I had
done before, which was behavioral evolution to aging.
And at Harvard, junior professors, they don't care what you do really.
So I had some time to really gear up and switch fields.
It wasn't like I had to get six grants the first year or something.
And so it was great.
So I basically spent some time developing my first aging study, which was a field study
of opossums.
And these were North American opossums.
But I was comparing the way they aged on an island compared to the mainland.
And I was interested in that because there were some theories of aging that suggested
animals that had evolved in environments that were low risk and this island had no predators
on it will evolve slow aging at the same time.
So I ended up doing this project where I had a population of opossums on the mainland and
another population on the island.
And I would track them from birth to death because one of the nice things about opossums
is that because the babies are born in a pouch, if you catch a mother that's got babies
in the pouch, pouchung, you can mark them at that point.
And then if you later catch them, you can put a radio collar on them.
So you know the exact birth date, basically, of every animal in a population fairly quickly,
which is pretty unusual for wild animals.
So that was really how my aging career got started at Harvard.
It was a great experience.
It was a wonderful place to be.
Unfortunately, my wife hated Boston.
And so she was really wanting us to go somewhere else.
What did you find out about the opossums and what explained the difference?
How much of a difference was there between the groups that grew up in a low-stress environment
versus the high-stress predatory environment?
There was about a 20% difference.
Okay, so pretty substantial difference.
And the next phase to figure this out was to try to work on the mechanism.
What is it?
And was it cortisol-related?
Right, exactly.
This was in, you know, this by now was in about 1990.
And we didn't have genomics, really, at that point.
If we did, the first thing I would have done is sequence the genome of the opossums
on the island of the mainland.
But the only thing I could think of to do next was to, two things.
One, I was interested, is this some genetic thing?
In other words, did you take the island version and just let them breed?
Because in one generation, you'd pretty much get your answer, right?
That's exactly right.
And I submitted a proposal to do that, and it didn't get funded.
There was a problem.
I could only really do it in one direction.
I could take the island of opossums and release them on the mainland and see how they did.
I didn't want to do the reverse because I thought,
if this is really a unique genetic population, now I'm not.
Right, you don't want to contaminate it.
Yeah.
So I never did that.
It was the obvious thing to do, and I thought about it, but I never ended up doing it.
And I'm sort of disappointed.
What I did, though, is I got a population of opossums that I brought into the laboratory.
And my plan was to start off with just some regular opossums.
And then once I knew how to manipulate opossums in the laboratory to go get some from the island.
But opossums are really not easy to keep in the laboratory environment.
And my colony ended up getting some flesh-eating infection.
And so I basically had to abandon that project.
I thought about going back to it subsequently.
You know, and in fact, I went back to the island,
which is called Sapelo Island, which is off the coast of Georgia,
about 10 years later with the film crew to do a film about them.
And in the interim, a new species had been introduced to the island.
Armadillos had never been there before, and now they were there before.
So I suddenly got worried that my population of opossums had also been contaminated.
So that discouraged me from going back and working on the genomics of those opossums.
So at what point did you begin to come in?
Did you start to get interested in the difference between animals in the wild
and animals in the lab as far as longevity differences?
And of course, where I'm going to go with this, Steve, is two directions,
just to give you a heads up.
Obviously, I want to have a really deep discussion on the largest longevity experiment ever done in
animals, which is the Wisconsin NIA experiment, obviously, animals in captivity.
And I also want to talk about the distinction between
mice in the wild and mice in the lab when it comes to all of the literature on CR and DR.
Right.
So it's really, I mean, and these are discussions you and I have had,
and every time we have it, it gets richer and richer.
So I guess what I'm really asking at the outset is,
when did this subject matter become of great interest to you?
Okay.
So my background is entirely in field biology at the point when I start doing laboratory biology.
So I'm coming from it from a way different perspective than most people.
And when I started to learn about the, not just the mice, but the other laboratory animals,
and how much different they were than the same species in the wild,
I started to get very interested in what I call laboratory evolution.
How have these things changed in the hundred years or so since they were brought into the laboratory?
Because, you know, when I was in the field, I'm always thinking about,
well, how is evolution shaping these animals to do whatever?
And in the laboratory, I'm thinking, well, the way that we breed them,
and the way that we inadvertently select them,
there's very strong evolutionary pressure on laboratory animals.
It's just that most people aren't aware of that.
So I started thinking, well, what can we learn? Is there anything to learn?
And one of the things that right off the bat was this dietary restriction experiment.
Now, before we even get to it, Steve, maybe we should explain to people
what a laboratory mouse looks like.
When you think about the B6 mouse, which is sort of the workhorse of so much of the research that
goes into cancer biology, I've had guests on this show before who have made a very compelling case
that we simply should never use that mouse model for anything that comes down to cancer therapeutics,
because whatever you learn in it almost assuredly is not going to apply later on.
But notwithstanding that, help folks understand what a mouse in captivity has been through.
What does it mean, for example, to be homozygous at each loci?
What is it that we're trying to accomplish?
What's the price we potentially pay for that?
Yeah, so let me describe the history of the laboratory mouse.
So the laboratory mice came from what were called fancy mice.
And these were mice that were bred for bizarre coat colors and coat textures, kinky coats,
straight coats, silver coats.
And people used to have mouse beauty contests, just like the Westminster Dog Show.
There used to be mouse equivalents.
And for all that, there probably still are mouse equivalents.
So at some point, this is early in the 20th century when they just rediscovered the laws
of genetics from Mendel.
Some geneticists got looking at all these bizarre coat colors and said,
this could be a nice model to see if mammal rules of inheritance are the same as plant
rules of inheritance.
So they started working with the mice for genetics.
And then for reasons of trying to understand the genetics, they started inbreeding them.
And when I say inbreeding, I'm not talking about cousin breeding.
I'm talking about brother-sister mating.
And they did that for now hundreds and hundreds of generations.
So the mouse that we currently have in the lab, the typical mice,
come from mice that were selected for bizarre coat colors and sizes,
mice that were then inbred for hundreds of generations so that they're
absolutely genetically identical to one another.
And then over the generations, of course, as we're raising these mice, once they started
being commercially valuable, the companies that produced them would always...
The ones that left the most young were the ones that formed the next generation.
So you're always getting this selection for bigger and bigger litters and faster growth
and more rapid reproduction.
So by now, you have what a friend of mine calls a mouse-like object.
Something that looks like a mouse, but it's not only genetically identical to all of
the other ones.
It's now called a strain.
So B6 is a strain.
It's now called...
It's not only genetically identical, but again, because of the inbreeding,
it's homozygous at every locus.
That is, it has exactly the same two genetic variants at every single place in the genome.
So that makes it very, very different from any kind of...
From humans, certainly, but from any animal in the wild.
And I got very interested in how does that affect all of the experiments,
not just in aging, but in cancer, in Alzheimer's disease.
I mean, we use that one mouse.
And I used to say to people, this is like if we only tested drugs in the same set of twins
time after time after time after time, rather than ever going out.
So I agree with the people you've had on your show that said,
we need to really avoid this kind of reliance on such a bizarre creature.
I mean, it's about as bizarre of a creature from a zoological perspective,
as you can imagine.
They're twice as big as a wild mouse, at least twice as big.
They reach sexual maturity about twice as fast.
They have much larger litters.
They have a bunch of bizarre mutations and some strains become blind in a few months of age,
some become deaf.
Some, if they hear a loud noise, start having convulsions.
And this is the fundamental basis of our biomedical research enterprise as it applies to mammals.
So there's 4,500 species of mammals.
The fact that we've had one species and a very bizarre species at that be the substitute for
all of the others, including ourselves, is just a very weird approach.
And to me, it just shows that the culture of evolutionary biology is never really soaked in
to the laboratory biology.
And I've kind of made it my goal to try to help with that over my career.
Now, some people, of course, have gone to great lengths to avoid this.
So I recently had Rich Miller on the podcast and we talked about the investigation,
the intervention testing program, the ITP.
What is it that they do that raises the bar on rigor?
Right.
So Rich Miller is a good friend of mine and we've done a bunch of projects together on mice,
on different kinds of mice.
And what the ITP does is that they create what are called genetically heterogeneous mice.
That is, every single mouse is genetically unique, but they're all brothers and sisters.
So that you can recreate that population at any time, not the specific individual,
but the population.
Now, the interesting thing about those mice is that their ancestors are all these inbred mice.
So they've been selected for strange genetic alleles that only work
seemingly when they're together with themselves.
So I'm a very big fan of that mouse model, I have to say,
because I think it's a huge step in the right direction.
It's the least bad option, basically.
Yeah, exactly.
And there's one kind of weakness that I'd like to see them work on, and maybe they will.
And that's this, because of the breeding scheme that they use,
all of the mice have the same mitochondria.
No matter how genetically diverse they are, they all have the same mitochondria.
And we now know that the mitochondrial genotype,
because it interacts so closely with the nuclear genotype, can have a huge impact.
And in fact, someone here at my university, Scott Ballinger,
has created these mice that have different mitochondria in the same nuclear background.
And they have very different characteristics.
So the other thing is that because all of the current laboratory mouse came from a relatively
small number of these fancy mouse ancestors, they all have pretty much the same mitochondria.
The only differences are differences that have evolved slowly by drift over the last hundred years.
So for instance, my friend that's got the nuclear mitochondrial exchange mice,
his two mitochondria, which are very different by mouse standards,
only differ at five individual nucleotides in the whole 16,500 nucleotide mitochondria.
How many genes is that again? Is that about 20 genes?
Yeah, it's about 17 typical genes, but we're finding new genes.
It's interesting, we're finding new genes in the mitochondria.
So it's around 20 or 25 genes.
So we may be missing out on a huge amount of variability that's due to mitochondria.
And humans, of course, have incredibly variable mitochondrial genomes.
Now, is it too late, Steve, to sort of say, look, we're going to go into the wild,
get a whole bunch of completely wild mice that are so genetically heterogeneous,
and we're going to start letting them breed, and we're not going to force them to be inbred,
we're just going to let them breed naturally. Is that just too expensive?
Or like, why has no one gone about trying to address this?
Because it's such an obvious limitation.
Right. Well, I think one of the reasons is the lack of genetic control that you would have
in that situation. There has been some attempt to do that.
That is, people have been working on a diverse, a genetically diverse population of mice,
where they took a whole number of the laboratory mouse strains and mixed in a couple of recent
introductions from the wild and mixed them all together to create something.
The problem isn't talking to those people. The wild backgrounds don't seem to breed as well
in captivity. So gradually, those genes are lost. But I think there are some reasonable
alternatives that are out there that are being developed and have been recently developed.
It's just that it's going to take a big change in the culture of the way we do laboratory medicine,
I think, before people will accept that. It probably comes back to a point you made
earlier, which is for many people who work in the lab using laboratory mice, that's all they've
known. And it might not be as apparent to them how genetically far removed they are
from their predecessors, whereas because you came at this from being a field biologist,
and also with a much greater lens for comparative gerontology, right, you're looking at this
opossum and that opossum, and these are both wild, and yet they have some differences, but they're
totally different. It may simply be a blind spot, right?
Yeah, I think it is. And I think that even the best mouse is still a mouse. It's still one species,
and it's a very different species than we are. And so even the best mouse model is not going to be
enough. We need to know more about general mammalian biology if we're going to understand
our own biology better. Well, before we leave the mouse, let's talk a little bit about Clive
McKay and kind of the history of caloric restriction. I think most people today
are generally well aware of the reported efficacy of caloric restriction in life extension.
There are no shortage of people that are now looking at ways to mimic caloric restriction,
be it pharmacologically with molecules, or be it using dietary interventions that sort of act
like transient periods of caloric restriction, all in search of what we believe CR does. But let's
maybe have you explain to people what this history looks like.
Sure. Well, the first person to really do this in a formal way was, as you mentioned,
Clive McKay, who was a nutritionist at Cornell at the time. And he wasn't interested in aging
either. He was interested in growth and how to make animals grow faster because that has all
kinds of agricultural implications. And so in studying growth, he was looking at the effect of
restricting the diet on growth rate. And when he did that, he noticed that his animals seemed to
be staying healthy longer and living longer when he fed them less. And he did this in fish,
he did some stuff in dogs, although he didn't look all the way through their lifespan. And then he
finally did this experiment in rats. In that one, he let them live their entire lives and documented
very convincingly how dietary restriction made, in this case, only females, not males, live longer.
And the interesting thing about McKay is that about a decade ago, I was a visiting scholar
at Ithaca, New York for a week. And I went to the Cornell libraries and I looked through all of his
old papers. And I don't think he ever really appreciated the significance of what he'd done,
because he didn't really follow up on that. This was in the 1930s, if I recall. Yeah,
this was in the 1930s. And he was active until the 1960s. But he got into producing high protein
bread and making nutritional food for the military during World War II. And he really kind of dropped
this whole thing. So even though he made what in retrospect was really, I think, a landmark
discovery, I don't think he really appreciated that, because he was never focused really on longevity.
So what are the ways in which this got validated and repeated throughout time? Who was the next
person to pick up that baton? You know, I'm not exactly sure who the next person was. There were
a whole bunch of people starting really after World War II that started looking at it more closely
in rats and more closely in mice. And there were actually a whole bunch of people working on
invertebrates that did this experiment by accident. And I'm one of them, actually. The first paper I
published on this topic was some stuff that I did during my PhD. So my PhD was testing all these
mathematical models about combat. But I was testing it in a small spider. And as part of that
experiment, I had groups of spiders that I was feeding various amounts. And I would keep them
until they died. But I wasn't paying any attention to that. Once I discovered all of this work,
I went back to my data and I said, well, I wonder what happened when I fed them less.
And it turned out the less I fed them, the longer they lived. And so after World War II,
people really started getting interested in this. And there were a number of people. There were mouse
studies now, rat studies. There was really, I think the next big advance was when Roy Walford
got into it, who was very interested not just in how mice age, but how that might tell him
something about human aging. And Ed Masero, another researcher who followed up on rats,
and those two, I think, really took it to the next, jumped it to the next level, which is,
can we understand why this is happening? There was really very little investigation of that
previously. But Walford, who was an immunologist, was very convinced that was doing something to
the immune system, and that was at the base of it. And Masero didn't really have his own hypotheses,
but he thought that it was a great way to test hypotheses about how aging worked.
The other big difference between these really fascinating characters, I mean, Walford,
was probably one of the most interesting and colorful personalities.
You must have known him because he only died, what, maybe 20 years ago, 25 years ago?
Oh, yeah. In fact, my first paper, he published the figure out of my spider paper before it was
published in a real journal because he had heard about my work. And he asked that,
I'm writing a book. Can I put this figure in my book? So yeah, I knew Roy quite well.
Of course, he's famous for the biodome, right? That was the...
Yeah, yeah. The biosphere too.
A biosphere, right.
Yeah. And it's pretty interesting when I was writing my book on, so the biosphere too was
this inadvertent experiment on dietary restriction because these people were sealed in this dome,
and they couldn't grow as much food as they thought. And Roy was the doctor in there. And
so this is a great opportunity. He wanted to know how dietary restriction worked in people,
and here he had all of these people that couldn't make enough... Anyway...
How long were they in the biosphere?
Two years. Two years.
And when you look at pictures of him when he came out, I mean, he looked pretty emaciated.
Oh, he looked horrible. He looked absolutely horrible. In fact,
they have this famous picture of them all standing on the rafters in the biosphere when they went in
naked, and they had the same picture that Roy showed at a meeting when they came out.
And you've seen pictures of him. He looks like he just emerged from a concentration camp, right?
Yeah.
Well, I wanted to use... They all look like that. I wanted to use that picture before and after in
my book on aging, and so I asked Roy about that. And he said, I'd love to give you that picture, but
everything's tied up in litigation. It turned out that the people in that experiment have become
enemies, and everybody was suing everybody else over everything having to do with the biosphere.
So psychologically, that wasn't such a great success. People would disagree about whether
it was a success scientifically or not. Roy thought it... He looked at it in one way,
thought it proved everything that he had seen in mice was true in people. Other people were looking
at it and say, oh my gosh, I don't know how you felt, but you just looked terrible. And then he
died.
Yeah, he died young, right?
I mean...
Not... Yeah, well, he wasn't that... I think he was 79 or something.
Oh, okay. I thought he was younger.
But he was always one of these people that if you knew his age,
you'd say, man, that guy looks 20 years younger.
Than he is. But after he came out of the biosphere, he didn't look like that anymore.
Now, the other thing, to be fair, that happened in the biosphere is that the atmosphere got really
out of whack. And they ended up without realizing it, they had so little oxygen, they were living at
the equivalent of about 17,000 feet. And so, yeah, and they'd been doing that for they didn't know how
long. Eventually, so they had to refresh the air and the environment. And he attributed his later
health problems to that, not to the dietary district.
Which is certainly plausible. I mean, we'll never know, but you have to spend some portion of two
years at Everest Base Camp if you haven't grown up there. It's one thing if you're a Sherpa,
right? But it's another thing if you've spent your whole life at sea level.
So going back to the sort of CR insights, which was the, oh, by the way, sorry, before I do that,
what can you tell us about rats versus mice in terms of the genetic diversity and the ability
to glean insights that are perhaps more or less interesting?
Rats are a lot different to the extent that, as I say, almost all of the traditional laboratory
mice strains came from this small handful of weird ancestors. Rats have a different history.
They were used earlier in biomedical research, actually, but they've been domesticated multiple
times in multiple parts of the world. So if you look at all the genetic diversity and the
mitochondrial diversity that you have in rats, it's far greater than you have in mice. And so
I'm actually working with some other people now trying to bring the rat back more into aging
research because we discovered how to manipulate the genes of mice a lot earlier than we discovered
anything else. And so they kind of took over. That's really why almost all the focus is now on
that one species. We now can do these genetic manipulations in other species just as easily.
And I'd like to see something like the rats. For instance, we're working on a rat, which the two
mitochondria we're interested in, instead of different only at five of these nucleotides or
DNA letters, differ at 100 of them. So that's much more similar to the kind of genetic diversity
that you find in people's mitochondrial genomes rather than rats. So I'm hoping in the next few
years we can really... I would like to see something like like Brit Miller's interventions
testing program in rats as well, because I think I'd have a lot more confidence that something we
found in mice might have relevance to people if we found the same thing in rats. It's not the
ideal comparison, but considering because rats and mice are reasonably closely related, they're
kind of like we are to a rhesus macaque about that degree of divergence. But still, they're very
different. We also can do a lot more sophisticated cognitive studies with rats than we can with mice.
They're trainable. And so I'm hoping that over the next few years we can make an impact and bring
the rats back because we might learn something differently. Right now, one of the most robust
findings in mice is that if you somehow disable growth hormone activity, the mice stay healthy and
live a lot longer. There's only been one experiment doing that in rats, and it came to a very
different conclusion. It's kind of like the two primate calorie restriction studies. But again,
it's one study against the gazillion studies over here, but I'd like to really look at,
are we getting a biased picture of something like growth hormone? Because we only really know a lot
about its mechanism in mice. What is your best explanation for why the rats, given growth hormone,
fared better? They fared worse. They didn't live any longer. I don't know.
No, but they fared better than the mice, didn't they?
Oh, so we're talking about two different things here. So if you compare dozens and dozens of
mouse studies and you look at how much life extension there was with dietary restriction,
you look at a whole bunch of rat studies, you're right. The effect is bigger in rats. And growth
hormone is suppressed by dietary restriction. The experiment I was talking about was one where they
had taken a natural genetic mutation that disabled growth hormone in the rats, and that didn't live
longer, like the same natural mutations occurred in mice. Now, why is the effect bigger in rats
than mice? That's a good question. I don't think we know why. And I also don't know how far to push
that comparison because there's been a lot fewer rat studies done. We've done mouse studies with a
much greater diversity of mice. And so if you look at the biggest effect that we've ever seen in a
mouse and the biggest effect we've ever seen in a rat, those are not that different. So I think
it's a little bit premature to conclude that dietary restriction works better in rats generally
than it does in mice. That may be true, but I just don't think we know enough yet.
So speaking, of course, about big experiments with DR and CR, we have to look no further than,
I mean, they have to be the largest experiments done, the Wisconsin NIA experiment, correct?
Yes. Certainly the most expensive aging experiments that haven't been done in people.
Yeah. So, gosh, this experiment was probably kicked off in the late 80s?
Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
Tell folks about the experimental design.
Yeah. So it was almost serendipitous that they had started at the same... So two groups,
one at the National Institute of Aging, one at the University of Wisconsin, and one person,
Rick Windrick, actually was involved in both. He was at the NIA when that project got started,
then he moved to the University of Wisconsin. And the idea was to see whether the results that we
saw in these laboratory rodents could be replicated in something that was a lot closer
related to humans. And also something that hadn't gone through these bizarre laboratory inbreeding
selection and all that stuff, closer to a real animal, in other words. And of course,
these things live up to 40 years. Actually, many people don't know, but there was another study
started at the same time on squirrel monkeys because they were only supposed to live 25 years
and they thought they could do that quicker. But it turned out squirrel monkeys were unusual. You
could restrict their diet, but they didn't lose weight. So they ended up abandoning that study.
So anyway, because monkeys live so long and it takes so long to see results, these things
went on for years and years. And they would publish occasional studies about their blood glucose,
how it affects their blood glucose, their body fat and all these. Eventually, when enough died
over the next few years, they came to very different conclusions. Now, I've got a lot of
friends and been involved in both of these studies. And so at the risk of irritating my friends,
I'll have to say that I think we learned something, but we learned something very different from each
of the studies. So let's explain some of these differences because I do think there were some
interesting differences. And by the way, it's an interesting footnote to just by total coincidence
that when the first of these papers was published in 2011, I believe it was the same day. So I
should say not published as in the scientific publication, but on the day that the New York
Times ran the story of the results of the first of them, which I think was Wisconsin.
Yeah.
On that same day, they ran the Rapa Mison ITP result, the first Rapa ITP result.
In 2009.
Yeah, 2009, in 2011, you're right.
What's interesting is, of course, the monkey study was front page news, the Rapa study was
buried in the back, barely good.
Really?
Yeah.
See, I didn't remember that at all. That's interesting.
What was different? Let's talk about what was different between these experiments.
First of all, let's talk about wild monkeys versus laboratory monkeys. So they haven't been in the
laboratory long enough to really have had the kind of genetic alterations that mice have.
But again, this comes from my, I had a long history with studying
lions and tigers and other big cats and bears and elephants in captivity,
and then seeing them also in the wild. And one of the things that we know is that
virtually all captive animals are obese relative to their wild cousins.
Kind of like us captive humans.
Exactly.
Yeah, exactly.
And one of the things that I did in the late 80s, early 90s, that I did some research in Papua New
Guinea, where we're basically studying people who are still hunting with spears and arrows.
And it's very similar to wild primates versus captive primates.
All captive animals are obese to a degree. Now there are some that are just frankly obese,
and there are some that look okay to us because we've only seen animals like that,
but they still have a lot more body fat. So what the Wisconsin study did is they took animals,
the control animals that were eating ad libitum, so they had food available pretty much all the
time, and they restricted each individual animal by 30%. So they tracked individual animals,
how much does it eat over a certain amount of time, and they said okay, its diet for the rest
of its life is going to be 30% less than that. And they did that for the next 35 years.
And this was one to one randomization, Steve?
Yes.
So just to be clear, they follow all the animals, get a baseline intake for them,
then they divide them in half randomly. One group gets to continue consuming that amount,
or gets to continue consuming ad libitum.
It gets what it wants to eat, ad libitum.
Okay, so that's an important distinction. The CR group gets pegged to 70% of what they were eating
during the run-in.
Right.
Okay.
Right. And so, you know, 35 years later, they report that the animals that are eating less
are living longer, substantially longer, and by all kinds of disease metrics, are healthier.
So pretty much replicating the laboratory experiments. Now I have to say that up to this
time, I really hadn't thought too much about how you would translate the laboratory rodent
experiments into human experiments. But suddenly, because I was asked to write something up on
these two experiments, I started thinking about, yeah, what are we? I mean, you think about it,
a rat or a mouse spends its life in a cage that's no bigger than a jail cell. Usually,
has very little except other animals in the cage. So has zero opportunity for much physical activity.
And needless to say, because they have food available all the time, because they've been
selected to reproduce as much as possible, they're going to get really quite big.
And I think that that was a perfect replication, the Wisconsin study, of what goes on in most
laboratory rodent experiments, which I think is what they'd intended. I think the philosophy of
the National Institute of Aging study was different. I think they were trying to say,
what is the relevance for people? And not for people who are sedentary and obese, but for people
generally. So what they did differently, well, I'll get to the diets.
Yeah, I was going to save the diets for the end. Because that to me is, I think,
the most important thing.
Let's just talk about the way they did the experiment. What they did is they said,
we want our control animals to be at what we consider to be a healthy body weight.
So we're not going to feed them ad libitum. We're going to feed them a couple of times a day,
and we're only going to feed them enough to keep them at what we think is a healthy body weight.
And we're going to restrict our other animals, our restricted animals, 30% from that. So now we're
talking the restricted ones are going to be much leaner than the Wisconsin restricted ones. And the
controls are also going to be much leaner.
So it's a form of pair feeding, but it's a CR pair feed, basically.
Yeah, exactly. And what they really were saying is, look, if you take a healthy human,
and you restrict a healthy human, what kind of effect are you likely to see?
So almost inadvertently, because I don't really think they had this philosophical difference
worked out at the time. But that's really the way I think it ended up happening.
And in this case, the animals didn't live any longer. And it was very clear. It wasn't like,
well, it's a little bit longer, but not quite enough to be statistically significant. So it was
there's no difference whatsoever. But their controls were also living longer
than the Wisconsin controls, which again, not surprising, because they're kept at a healthy
body weight. And these others are, you know, gotten to be frankly obese.
And then we get to the difference in the diets.
Right.
Which is really stark. I mean, that's, that's not a subtle distinction.
No, no. So so the difference in the diets is critical. So if you look at the gross
macronutrients, the carbohydrates, the fats, the protein, they're not that different.
But here's the critical difference is that they use natural ingredients in the NIA study.
In the Wisconsin study, they wanted to use what they call purified ingredients,
because you're complete control of this, you know, you might get a different source of
cornmeal, and it might differ slightly in nutrients. But if you're just doing specific,
if you're just doing albumin, you know, you're always getting the same protein.
The trouble is that that wasn't a very palatable diet. And to make it more palatable, to do the
carbohydrates, they were adding sucrose. And by the end of it, well, I think by the time they
figured out the diet, it was a, they were 28%, 28.5% sucrose diet in Wisconsin, and, you know,
very low sucrose, you know, all these natural ingredients.
I think it was about 3% sucrose in the Bethesda mice, right?
Versus, as you said, 28, 29% sucrose there.
Um, Bob Kaplan did an analysis for me. We write about, you know, we've written about this,
I think, in a, in a weekly newsletter or something. But the, the Wisconsin monkeys
were effectively eating the equivalent. If they were humans, they were effectively eating
three Big Macs, two large fries, and two jumbo cokes a day. That was the equivalent of their diet.
Um, and then you were, so you were basically getting a control animal that's eating like
three Big Macs, two monster fries, and two jumbo cokes a day. And then the controls were getting,
or sorry, the CR group was getting 70% of that. In Bethesda, it was basically like a whole foods
pescatarian diet, right? With 3% sugar in it. Um, and you know, it's a bit of a shame because it
doesn't allow us, in my opinion, to appreciate the effect of the weight difference. Because as
you said, the controls in each group, there's no comparison, right? The, the control group in
Bethesda was the longest lived animal. Uh, pardon me, the CR group in Bethesda and the control
group were the longest lived animals. And they actually lived longer than the CR groups in
Wisconsin. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, this isn't, this isn't a surprise when I said they started off
with these squirrel monkeys as well. One of the reasons they abandoned that was they soon realized
the squirrel monkeys were living longer than any squirrel monkeys that ever been reported to live
before as well. And now they're racist Macaques have been reported to live longer than any Macaques
have been before. It's interesting because as, as often happens in science of two groups do what
seems to be the same experiment, although with the, I agree with you, this wasn't really the same
experiment, but if they seem to do what's superficially the same experiment, they come to different
conclusions. They're not happy about it. And so in one of the attempts to reconcile the data,
they looked at the weights of the control animals in Wisconsin versus Bethesda, but compared to all
of the racist monkeys in the country and all of the research facilities in the country and the
Wisconsin ones were about 10% heavier and the controls now and the Bethesda ones were about 10%
lighter. So, um, you know, like I say, I think they're telling us something differently. Someone
might want to know if instead of eating two big Macs and two helping some fries and two giant
cokes a day, what if I only ate 70% of that? Would I be healthier? Then you as a physician would
probably say, yeah, yeah, eating less of really toxic food is good for you. That's exactly my
conclusion from that study is in a still somewhat contrived way. I think what we learned is the worse
the diet, the more beneficial the caloric restriction, the better the diet, the less
of an impact caloric restriction has. And what that says to me is dietary restriction might be as
important if not more important than caloric restriction. By dietary restriction, I mean
manipulating or reducing, uh, components of the, uh, macro or micronutrient. And in this case,
the sucrose was head and shoulders. I mean, to me, this was basically an experiment demonstrating
the harm of sucrose. Yeah. Yeah. Because if you looked at, uh, what they call, uh,
glucoregulatory problems and the controls that were massive and there were zero of those in the
restricted animals. And I'm glad you brought that up because it reminds me the control animals in
Bethesda, I either fully fed animals in Bethesda had less diabetes than the calorie restricted
animals in Wisconsin. I don't know that that's correct. I don't, I don't remember Wisconsin
reporting any. No, I think it was, I think it, I think it was, I think this was an after publication.
I'm pretty sure. Yeah. Okay. We'll, we'll confirm that for the show notes, but I think this is
something that came out much later, but I actually think that the, that the group eating 70% of the
high sugar diet had had a higher incidence of diabetes than the control in Bethesda,
which again, just speaks to dramatic differences in, um, what you're feeding.
Yeah. And, and I have to say, I don't think we've ever really gone back and worked out the best
diets for mice or rats. I think there's a lot still to be done in those, you know, we, most
of those standards were really just developed for keeping them healthy so they could breed.
And, uh, I think that if we really wanted to understand more about nutrition in those animals,
we'd have to go back and do that with modern techniques. If we really wanted to understand
nutrition of rats and mice, I don't think we understand it very well.
And there's no way to really study monkeys in captivity without limiting their exercise. Right.
I mean, there's, there's, is it, is it possible? Well, I think it is. I mean, it's, it's possible.
I think there are two problems. One is that because you need to control the diet,
the animals were kept individually housed. And this is a very social species, just like we are.
Right. And so cognitively, psychologically, these had to be extremely unusual animals on top of that,
because of the size of the cages that they had. Yeah. There was virtually no, uh, opportunity for
physical activity. That's very similar to the rat and mouth studies. Right. But I think for primates,
it's probably worse. I think it's, yeah, I think it's much worse cognitively. I'd have to think
it's terrible. Um, I mean, they were in a room where they could see each other, they could hear
each other, they could smell each other, but they couldn't touch each other. And I think if you,
So they didn't even get to mingle outside of feeding times?
No, no. Why?
Probably had to do with the, with the, with captive setup that they had in those two places.
Um, it's not easy to get strange monkeys to interact with one another. He might end up with a lot of
fighting. And at least one of the other differences between the two studies was the Wisconsin animals,
were all monkeys from India that were born in captivity. And so they knew the precise age.
In the Bethesda study, they, they sort of added animals of different ages as they got them.
Some of them came from the wild and some of them, they kind of guessed the age at the start.
And some of them came from China. So some genetic differences as well. So, um, so yeah, your, your,
your basic conclusion that nutrients seem to count, I think is, is very valid. And I think that,
I think it's also something, you know, I always say that humans are the worst
animal study that you could imagine because they don't do what you tell them to do,
you know, and they'll lie about what they do. But on the other hand, there's certain kinds of
studies that I think you have to do in humans. And I think that the idea that the nutrition
that works best for a mouse, even if we knew what it was, might not tell us anything. I mean, mouse,
mice eat seeds and insect larvae in the wild and we're very different. So I think for these
kinds of nutritional studies, I think you really do have to study humans because humans have their
own unique characteristics. Which is a point I'm going to absolutely want to bring us back to as
we look to one of the great challenges of studying humans is not only the timescale and the difficulty
with interventions, but frankly, the lack of biomarkers that could really help us assess
geoprotection. But I want to go back to kind of what you think would happen to animals
calorically restricted in the wild. Do you think that if we could, and imagine this as a thought
experiment, although I believe this experiment has also been done in some form or another, where you
calorie restrict wild mice. What do we know about that? Yeah, so I actually did an experiment like
this. So I didn't calorie restrict wild mice in the wild, I calorie restricted wild mice in the lab.
So I brought them into the lab because one of the ideas that I had, which turned out not to be
correct, was that we have selected, well partially correct, we have selected these animals to grow as
fast and reproduce as fast as possible. So we may have created gluttonous mice just by laboratory
selection over dozens and dozens of generations. Mice after my own heart basically.
So wild mice of course don't have that. So I went out and I caught a bunch of wild mice
and I brought them into the lab and I let them have babies for a couple of generations to get
rid of all the contaminants of being in the wild. And then I restricted their diet. And what I found
was that there was no difference whatsoever in how long they lived. Now I have to say,
I'm watching the animals die and they're right on top of one another almost. And I'm just ready to
say there's no way that dietary restriction works in wild mice. But then the last few, the last 20%
lived longer. The restricted ones were living longer and longer and longer. So all of the
longest lived ones were in the restricted group. So what I concluded from that is that these are
wild animals. They're genetically diverse. So I thought, well maybe, because the other part of
this I didn't imagine, is very early on when I restricted them, a number of the restricted ones
died early in the experiment. So maybe depending on your genes, dietary restriction would be good
for you, can have very little impact on your health, or can be bad for you. The ones that died early,
Steve, what did you, when you examined them after death, what were you seeing? You know, I don't
think that we did enough necropsies on the early ones that died to know that. It's not very easy to
to get good necropsy material on mice because their bodies cool off so quickly and their
tissues start to degenerate so quickly. So almost all of what we know about mice
pathology is from mice that were euthanized. And I don't think we euthanized any because we didn't
expect them to die when they were young like that. So maybe they had some nutritional requirement
that we weren't meeting. Like I say, we were using standard laboratory chow and that's,
you know, we don't really know how good that was. Which I mean, standard mouse chow is total garbage.
That's probably a good reason to be concerned. At the upper end, Steve, did you see a, I mean,
I guess if you didn't euthanize them, you wouldn't know, but you'd expect to see cancer being the
biggest difference. Although do wild mice suffer cancer to a fraction of the extent that in bred
mice do? They do to a fraction, but they don't. Yeah, we did for the ones that lived longer,
most of those we were watching much more carefully because they were getting to the
point where we were expecting them to die. So we have quite a bit, we probably have
necropsies on about at least 20 mice in each group. And yeah, they still get mice. They still
get a lot of cancer because let's face it, mice in the laboratory live on average about
two and a half years. And the longest live ones live about three years. In the wild, they live on
average about three or four months and the longest live ones live maybe a year or a little longer.
So we're talking about incredibly long live mice. So yes, about half of them
had cancer when they died. I don't know if that's what killed them, but they had cancer when they
died. But if you bring lower, that's a lot lower than live mice. If you bring wild mice into the
lab, how long do they live when you take away their predators and you insure them food?
They live, they live a little bit longer than, uh, than your laboratory mice,
maybe 20% longer. Okay. So they are a healthier mouse.
They're pretty healthy. Despite, despite not being bred for being in a lab. Well, I mean,
if I gave a handful of these mice to people that were only familiar with laboratory mice,
they wouldn't have any idea. They're looking at the same species that first of all, they bite.
Secondly, they can jump. You know, when we change mice from cage to cage, we set the cage down,
we take the top off, we pick the mice up, we put them in the new cage. You take my wild mice,
you take the top off and you got popcorn, you know, they're, they're all over the place. And
there's a common test that we do in laboratory mice for sort of coordination and balance,
which is called a rotorod, which is kind of like log rolling for mice. Right. And the idea is that
this is probably 18 inches off the ground. So they're afraid to fall. So we'll sit there and
try to stay on the circulating rod. Try that on a wild mouse and just immediately leap off the
thing and leap off to your desk and leap onto the floor and they're gone. There's another one that
we call, called the raw, the wire hang, which is just what it sounds. Take mice and you hang them
from a wire like they're dangling a pushup. And you say, how long can they stay before they fall
off? It's like kind of a grip strength test. Yeah. Yeah. And you do this to a wild mouse and
it does a pull up, it pulls itself up onto the wire and it runs off the wire and that's the end
of your test. So when I say there's no comparison between them, I'm really meaning that you could
take the most sedentary overweight person you could imagine and say, okay, I'm going to compare you
to this trained athlete, you know, and that's the kind of comparison you get.
Cognitively, it would be really interesting to see as well. The trouble is wild mice are not
used to being around people. So, you know, they're freaked out when you touch them. And so you can't
do the same kinds of cognitive tests, which is unfortunate. But on the other hand, this is what
you have with the other thing is if a domestic mouse wants to get away from you, it jumps back
in his cage and sits there. You know, if wild mice wants to get away from you, bites you and then it
jumps off the table and onto the floor and it's gone. So if you had to do the thought experiment,
which is you're going to take a group of wild mice in their environment, remove the predators.
So assume that they can live a little bit longer. One group gets 100% of their necessary nutrition.
The other group gets 70% of that. Do you believe that the CR group would live longer?
No. No, I don't. Do you think they would live shorter? Quite possible. I think probably yes.
And I'll tell you why. So this experiment has not been done because it's hard to do.
But the reverse has been done. So there have been a lot of studies where people have
supplemented the food of animals in the wild. So they don't have to go out and forage as much,
because I'm going to give them as much as they need to eat every day. So you would expect, okay,
now I'm going to get obese mice that are going to be short-lived. But that's not what you get.
You get mice that live longer. And they live longer because they're foraging less. They're
exposing themselves to less predation. The reason I think that if you restricted animals in the wild,
they would live shorter, is that the first thing is they would have to forage longer.
They would have to take chances to go after food. They don't normally go after.
They would possibly eat things that they normally don't eat that might be toxic. So my thought
experiment is that the animals, if you did this in the wild, if you could somehow control
the available food for them, that they would be shorter-lived. The other thing is that there's
a couple of things that calorie restriction does that don't seem compatible with the long life in
the wild. One of these is that it slows wound healing. The other thing is that it makes animals
more susceptible to certain kinds of pathogens. And those two things in the laboratory are not
a big deal because they don't get wounded. And we spend a great deal of time and effort to keep
pathogens out of the colonies. But in the wild, those are very important causes of pathology and
things that you need to work well. So that would be my guess is that they would probably be
shorter-lived. Are there any other studies in the animal literature that you think can shed light on
this very important question as it pertains to an extrapolation into humans?
Well, I mean, there's the human studies. Yeah, of course. Before we get to calorie and
cronies and stuff like that. No, I don't think so. I mean, you know, when I first came into this and
people told me about this phenomenon, the first question I asked, well, if this is so healthy,
why don't animals in the wild not eat less? And of course, the answer is that the animals that
have the genes that have survived for millions of generations out there are the animals are the best
at reproducing. Right. They're not optimizing for the longest life. They're optimizing for the most
reproduction. That's right. And so I said, well, of course. So they probably eat more than is
perfectly healthy because that helps them reproduce faster. It made perfect sense. And so
I don't find it particularly surprising that you get this kind of health because that's
not what nature has designed any of us to live as long as possible. That's kind of up to us to figure
out how to stay healthy long. Nature was fine with us when we were living 35 years. Yeah.
So I know I can't think of any other experiments that I would there. Yeah. There's one experiment
that was done that where they took mice that had been genetically altered so that they lived longer
in the laboratory and they put those in a field. Exposure with some normal mice and just came back
18 months later. And the ones that live longer in the lab were shorter life. They're almost all
gone in the real world. So there's a slight complication to that experiment, which is a
follow up experiment showed that, well, that same mutation, they don't necessarily live longer in
the lab. It was one of these, you know, unfortunate false results that couldn't be replicated.
But that's the way science works sometimes. So let's turn to the human studies then,
which obviously don't have the luxury of the same duration relative to the lifespan of the animal.
But what have we learned there? Right. So there's I think you have four human studies,
five maybe. So the first one I think was the Biosphere 2 study. But we don't know much about
what happened. Most of the people in that study were pretty young. Roy was a real outlier. Roy
Walford was I think 66 at the start of that experiment, 68 when he came out. But certainly
from their blood analysis, they had very good cardiovascular risk factors. Their blood pressure
was extremely low. Their blood glucose was extremely, of course, those were all exceptionally
healthy people when they went in. So this was not a random group. The calorie studies are the two
best controlled studies in humans. And there was two of them. There was one that was very short
term, six months. And then there was another was slightly longer term, which was two years.
How many institutions were a part of these two studies?
Three institutions.
Go to Pennington, there's one, right?
Pennington, Washington University, and then Tufts. And Tufts didn't publish anything out of the first
phase of the study, I don't believe. But in the second one, they did. So to me, I'll just give you
my bottom line on those studies is that people can't do calorie restriction in that traditional
sense. I mean, in all cases, the goal was to reduce calorie intake or energy imbalance by about 25%.
And they never came anywhere close to actually getting that. In the longer study, I think,
ultimately, the amount of restriction was about 11 to 12% that people were able to achieve over
two years. Because these people were in charge of their own nutrition. It's not like the study
could afford to actually give everybody all of their food every single day, which would at least
give you some hope of doing that if participants could limit themselves to eating the provided
food.
Yeah, as I recall, I think they provided meals initially for a short term. But they didn't
monitor whether the people wouldn't eat anything else as well. And then they were on their own.
And so it's quite clear that people can't, normal people, there are people that can,
but certainly your average person cannot. So in none of those that they achieve
anywhere close to the dietary restriction, they had hoped to do.
So what did they find with what they did achieve? Cardiovascular risk factors, all improved,
certainly. You know, blood pressure was better, lower insulin, lower glucose.
But there were some things, lower bone mineral density as well. So it's a mixed bag. And the
main thing is, if you look at a dietary restricted mouse, it's got almost no body fat.
Both of these experiments, the thing we struggle with is that most people are
overweight or obese in the US, where these were both done, right? So your control group
is not going to be like the Bethesda monkeys. So what that means is if they can only achieve
10% dietary restriction, you're going to get people that are on the verge of being overweight
or obese and getting them down to a healthy body weight. And I don't think it's surprising anybody
that that's good for your health. And that's pretty much what they found. They never got people
to that extreme leanness that Roy Walford and the people in the biosphere had, or that the subsequent
the cronies have. So I think you could generally say from the calorie studies that, yes, reducing
your food intake had lots of benefits, had some possible negative effects in terms of bone mineral
density, had some negative effects in strength loss, although not if corrected for body weight.
But yeah, generally beneficial. But again, take somebody that's on borderline overweight,
reduce them to a healthy body weight. I don't think any physician, it wouldn't have to be a
specialist like yourself, any physician, I think, would say, yeah, okay, what's the news?
So that's what I take away from that. Now the other study is the study of the cronies.
And these are people that belong to a society called the calorie restriction society
that have taken the rodent work and assumed that is going to make us healthy longer. And they really
have restricted themselves like we really do to mice. And they also have good, very good
cardiovascular risk factors, less inflammation, they're probably going to get less cancer,
but they have low bone mineral density, negligible sex hormones, you know, whole suite of things,
no muscle mass to speak of. I've spoken at a couple of their conferences, and they're always
exhorting one another to exercise more, because they have trouble with this degree of restriction,
keeping any muscle mass at all. But it's a struggle because they don't really have the
energy. Yeah, yeah. So, so these people typically have what how much of a BMI, Steve, these are
people that are 1718 BMI at this point. Yes, I'd say 17 to 20. Yeah, the interesting thing is in
that society, if you look around the room, I would say probably 30% of the people are actually
doing it like that. The others are maybe aspiring to do it, but not quite making it they look more
like an average person would look. But yeah, that that's that's the problem. And I'm not sure,
now that all these other diets are starting to come out, how many people are still sticking with
that? Because I haven't I've kind of lost track over the last few years of what's going on with
those people. The other thing is, they're all they they have very low thyroid hormone. So they're,
they're cold all the time. So one of the things I noticed at a comfortable room, everybody would
be wearing a jacket that was really BMI of 18. So and we don't actually know the impact of this on
long term cognition, do we? I think the on cardiovascular and cancer, it's pretty clear
that they will have a benefit. Not clear with respect to dementia, not clear with respect to
immune function, and certainly not clear with respect to the diseases of frailty. In fact,
I should say it is clear with respect to the diseases of frailty, they're much, much more
susceptible. Yeah, I think that's true. The cognitive part. I mean, in the calorie study,
they did a little bit of cognitive research. But again, I, you know, these were people that
weren't being restricted to the same extent. And, you know, the people in that society are very
eager to be studied. The problem is, this is an uncontrolled experiment. Yeah, my guess is before
they started calorie restriction, they were not your average person. No, of course, this is this
health habits. Yeah, this is the poster child example for healthy user bias and epidemiology,
we can learn virtually nothing from that without randomization. In terms of the immune system,
though, I will have to say that I did ask a lot of people at the conference, how often do you get
colds or the flu? And they say they don't. And I tend to believe them because I've never met a
group of people that are fanatically attentive to their own health. Like if I said, what's your BMI,
they could tell me to three decimal points and then say, well, do you mean in the morning or in
the afternoon? You know, so when they tell me they haven't gotten a cold in five years, I believe them.
Fair enough. I mean, this highlights an important point, right? Which is, one, it's a very, very,
very rare subset of the population that is going to be able to adhere to 30%
caloric restriction every minute of every day. And I would argue that even if you could,
the quality of life might be not justified the trade off. Isn't there a joke that says caloric
restriction will lengthen your life and it will feel like it or something to that? Like the,
yeah, what is it? But I think, you know, for these people, I don't think they perceive it.
I don't think they miss it. No, no, no. My point is you couldn't extend, they are the subset who
can do that. Yeah. To try to make that the solution for the rest of us who are interested
in some form of zero protection. Yeah. It's a non-starter. Right. Yeah. Sort of, you know,
constant caloric restriction isn't the answer. Right. So we now look to other things and you
maybe heard me talk about this, but I kind of have this framework, right? That says on the one hand,
we have this thing called the standard American diet, which is sort of the cesspool of nutrition
we all live in. So that's the environment where food is infinitely abundant, infinitely cheap,
infinitely palatable, and infinitely transportable. So meaning it's so processed that
you can actually take it with you anywhere. Right. And it's hard to escape the gravitational pull
of that. So we're all sort of in this orbit around the standard American diet. And there's basically
a handful of ways out. So I think one avenue out of that is time restricted feeding, where you start
to say, well, look, I'm not going to restrict what I'm eating. I'm not going to engage in any
form of dietary restriction. I'm just going to limit the window in which I expose myself to this
toxicity. So I'll not eat for 16 hours, but I will eat for eight hours. And you can obviously make
that window narrow and narrow. And then there's the, then there's what I call dietary restriction.
You and I use these terms a little differently, although I know what you're meaning when you say
when I refer to dietary restriction, I mean, no attempt at reducing the content, but rather
changing the mixture or quality. So dietary restriction, which is probably what most people
think of when they think of a diet, like a paleo diet, a vegan diet, a keto diet, a low carb diet,
they're not explicitly telling you to eat less. They're just telling you to not eat certain things.
And so those two become, I think the mainstay of how most people are trying to escape the
gravitational pull of the standard American diet. And then you can actually talk about intermittent
forms of fasting. And that can be complete, such as, Hey, I'm not going to eat anything. I'm just
going to have water for three days every month or every quarter. And they can be partial sort of
like the fast mimicking diet where for five days you consume, you know, 750 calories. When you
think about that entire landscape, where do you think we have the best insight about the health
benefits? Well, first of all, these are all pretty new ideas. And I don't think they've had a lot of
empirical testing at this point. And the empirical and testing that they have had is mostly been in
people that already had some health issues that were diabetic or pre-diabetic or something like
that. However, the logic of it is pretty compelling. And this is something we have learned from the
mice. You know, from the mice, in the Rapamycin studies, we've learned how suppressing this gene
called mTOR can have multiple health benefits. And now we know that it doesn't take that much
fasting to also suppress mTOR. So we now kind of have an idea. So, you know, one of the things we
should probably mention is that the people that were studying mice and rats, you know, years later
started noticing, well, wait a second. And I noticed this one. We will go to feed these animals.
They're right there. They're doing pull ups on the cage waiting for you to get the food. And,
you know, literally within half an hour, all their food is gone. And what we never really
thought about until recently is, wait a second, maybe it's the timing that's the important thing,
the fact that they're fasting for 23 hours a day or 23 and a half hours a day, maybe that more than
the total consumption or as much as the total consumption is doing it. And now we kind of have
a molecular mechanism for understanding how a period of fasting might have benefits and might
have short-term benefits. I mean, I think that's one of the really interesting things is that these
short-term fasts, whether they're a mice or humans seem to have multiple benefits. I mean, one of the,
I think one of the most groundbreaking studies was by Jay Mitchell, unfortunately.
Who just passed away a year. I mean, yeah. Yeah. Terrible, terrible. Bicycle, but he showed that
if you fasted a mouse for two or three days, they recovered from surgery so much faster than.
Well, actually, Steve, I mean, we should double click on that a little bit because it's not just
that they recovered from surgery. They recovered from a lethal injury, right? There's one experiment
where I think if I'm thinking of the right experiment, they took a group of mice that were
constitutively calorically restricted their entire lives. They took another group that were fed ad-lib
their whole lives. And then they took another group that were ad-lib fed, but I think three days
prior to the surgery were severely calorically restricted. So each of them then had the same
procedure, which was a laparotomy with a ligation of the femoral arteries for a period of time and
then a reperfusion. So what, you know, for the folks listening, what that means is you clamp off
all the blood supply to the lower part of the leg. And then, you know, basically just before the
animal is about to die, you let it, you let the blood flow again. But because of all of the
ischemic damage to the tissue, all the tissue damage due to no oxygen, you create such an
injury to the animal that I believe all of the ad-lib animals died from that. But yet the two
groups that were calorically restricted, one its entire life and one just for three days survived,
suggesting that just that period of caloric restriction could produce a similar benefit.
Now I could be a little wrong on the numbers, but that was sort of the gist of my memory. Is that
correct? Yeah. Well, what he did, it actually cut off blood supply of the kidneys. Was it the kidneys?
Okay. Yeah. Another one that they did the liver. Okay. Same result though. And you're exactly
right. They did these ones that have been calorically restricted their whole lives, the ones
that had been, that were ad-lib and then the ones that have been fasted for, they did some that have
been fast restricted for a few weeks and then some that had been just fasted water only fast for a
day or three days for two or three days. That's a big fast per a mouse. It is a big fast. That's
absolutely right. And they did much better. You're right. I don't remember if all of the controls
died, but if not, almost all of them did. And the ones that were restricted lifetime or for two
or three days, I think none of them died. So you're right. It's yeah. When I said a surgery, I guess I
was thinking about it from a mouseologist standpoint where a lot of our surgeries don't turn out so
well, but yeah, this wasn't a minor surgery that you expected everybody to recover from it.
They really were expecting most of the mice were going to die and they did. So yeah, I mean,
that kind of, I think it changed my thinking entirely about dietary restriction. And you're
right. We use these in different terms. Initially it was called dietary restriction because they
just restricted the amount of diet. But then after they decided it was calories that counted,
then they started being called calorie restriction. And now probably not exactly calorie. So I don't
know food restriction. Maybe we should call what they do to the mice at this point.
Well, what's your take on the role of the macronutrients here? And I'll pass it to
candidates to consider the first being a subset of amino acids, whether it be methionine,
tryptophan, leucine would be candidates to consider. And then other things such as sugar.
Again, the Wisconsin half of the monkey experiment certainly suggested that a reduction in sucrose,
perhaps independent of calories, could have played a role, but it's difficult because we can't
disentangle it from the weight loss and other things. But what do we know about amino acids
and their role? We certainly know that mTOR, which you brought up a moment ago, is an amino acid
sensor. So how do you think that fits in? Independent of calories, perhaps?
Yeah, well, I think we need to work that out. Because there are these diets around and there
are diets that say, Oh, what you want to do is you want to eat as many carbs as you can, and as
little protein and fat as you can. And there are others that say the opposite. And I don't think
the animal work is going to tell us a lot about that. I think we have to try to figure out
how to do the experiments in people. We have to do it in healthy people. Because I think if we want
to make sick people less sick, that's great, we should be doing that. But a lot of people that
are healthy want to know how to stay healthy. And I think that we can't do these things long term,
because what if you're in one that's turning out to be really bad for your health? What we need is
we need some biomarkers, which you mentioned before. We need something so we can do an experiment
of a few weeks or a few months and have the answer long term. And we need to do it in people
of different ages as well. The thing that we didn't talk about, the calorie strategy,
so those were done on people who were basically in their late 30s. And what's good for them is not
necessarily good for what people in their 60s might want to do. You know, one of the things I think
that the intervention testing program has demonstrated that shocking is how late in life
you can start some kind of intervention and still have a dramatic improvement in health.
And that to me has really major implications for people, right? Just because you're 50 years old
and you've never done any exercise and you've eaten a terrible diet doesn't mean you can't improve
your health a lot. So, because I think a lot of people feel that. I've done this my whole life, so
what's the point in doing it now? You know, I'm curious for you, you know, I get to ask you a
question occasionally here. What is the average age of people that come to your clinic? Are they
people in their 30s or 40s or 70s or 80s? I think the median age in our practice
is high 30s. Yeah. Would be median. And mean is probably a little bit higher. But range is 29 to
79. 29 to 82 maybe is the range. Right. So that makes sense. So that's about the time in life where
people start realizing they may not live forever, right? And start making some changes potentially
in the way they live their life. You know, I have a dramatic memory of when I first detected aging
in myself. What was that? And that was, I probably was 32 maybe, but it was during a basketball game.
And I was always the quickest person on the floor. And I was used to blowing by people.
And suddenly this person blew by me who was much bigger than me. And I was used to if anybody was
going to be as quick as me, it was going to be somebody as small as me. And I thought, gosh,
that had to be an accident. And then he did it again. And then he did it again. And I realized
I lost a step. This is what they mean by aging. I have lost a step. There's, you know, and if you're
a professional athlete, of course, you're tested much more often and you probably notice this much
earlier than I did in a casual neighborhood basketball game. But it was a shocking moment
to me because before then never entered my mind that my body was going to change in a way that
would make it less good at things that used to do. Well, speaking of human longevity,
Steve, what do you think is the best explanation for the sex difference between men and women?
In the United States today and much of the developed world, it probably accounts for
about two years of difference, doesn't it? More like five. Is it that much? Wow. Yeah.
Okay. What's our best attribution? Well, it's a really interesting problem. And
let's sort of talk about, I think, some myths about that difference. It's not that women
survive better in an old age. They do, but they also survive better when they're infants and they
also survive better when they're in their 20s and in their 30s and their 40s. So they survive better
at every age and they survive better when times are good and during epidemics and during
famines. And so there's something about their biology that allows them to survive better. And
it doesn't seem to depend on conditions. That's very different from a lot of animals where
it depends on the diet, it depends on the circumstances. We don't know any circumstances
in which men survive better than women, even prematurely born infants. Being a male infant
is a risk factor for dying if you're a preemie. So there's some robust feature of human biology
at play here. And unfortunately, we don't really know what it is. We don't know, is it sex hormones?
Is it something that happens before birth that we can't do anything about later? There's a little
bit of weak, but I think maybe provocative evidence. There's at least two studies showing
a major increase in longevity for men who were castrated for one reason or another.
These were unique populations and maybe that has no relevance whatsoever. But that would
kind of put the onus on sex hormone. On the other hand, there's the hormone replacement
work in human females, which suggests that, well, maybe replacing those hormones isn't
such a great idea. So I don't think we know. So I'll tell you the three.
I think we now don't find that to be the case. I think basically every conclusion of the
original women's health initiative has been turned over, right?
No, I would say that's not the case. But the key factor for the women's health initiative
is the women didn't start doing it until 10 years after menopause, on average. And so there have been
shorter term for women that start replacement therapy earlier and then stop it, that there may
be this window in which it's benefited. But of course it depends on your family history.
But my point is there was no increase in mortality. I think if you really scrutinize
the WHI data correctly, even the most headline grabbing finding, which was that the women in the
progesterone and conjugated equine estrogen group had a greater, 25% greater risk of breast cancer.
I mean, I think we now understand that that was a very misleading finding.
Yeah, I mean, there were several things that they were more likely to have a stroke. But you're
right, the overall mortality rate at the time that they stopped the study because of the blood clots
and the strokes, there was no difference. You're absolutely right about that. There was no difference
in mortality and you could have made the case that they shouldn't have stopped it at that point.
And it's interesting on the castrated study, on the castrated literature,
the obvious one, the first or Occam's razor view of that would be, well, there's something about
testosterone, right? Because it's not so much that the men who are castrated are getting estrogen and
progesterone. If you castrate them, they're actually going to have no estradiol versus the
estradiol they would have if they could keep their testosterone. But of course, that kind of flies in
the face of the testosterone replacement data, which say, well, actually it doesn't seem to impact
mortality either way, at least outside of two or three years. But then that comes to a point you
made earlier, maybe it's something that happens early in life with high exposure.
And yeah, I mean, to me, the telling
data points are that the women survive better from ages zero to five. You know, that suggests to me
that there's something already in place and it probably may not have anything to do. I mean,
let me point out the two testosterone studies are very weak. They were not
done with this in mind. They were done post hoc. There's a lot of complications. So I don't put a
great deal of stock in those. It's just provocative. And also, I mean, the difference in longevity was
something like 20 years and both of them. So it wasn't a trivial difference. But I can certainly
understand why men would have a lower all-cause mortality or higher all-cause mortality when you
factor in a couple of things. One is behaviors. I mean, if I compare my sons to my daughter,
it's literally like they wake up every day trying to figure out how to hurt each other and hurt
themselves. And I'm actually very fascinated by that, Steve, because I don't understand
where that is in their genes. Like you would think, well, that has to be sex linked, right?
But when you look at men who are double Ys, so there are some men who don't get an X chromosome,
they get two Ys. They turn out to be no more aggressive than a standard XY. So it's not
something as just as simple as like, well, that Y chromosome, it's going to be a little bit more
nuanced than that. And I think about the dumb things I did growing up. There were literally
times I was engaging in such stupid behavior, like into my late teens that it's a miracle I'm
sitting here, at least when you almost died. Well, I guess we could argue that was kind of,
maybe not the wisest behavior, but. Oh, you don't have any clue as to what the really dumbest stuff
that I did. We used to, I used to be in a group of friends that hunted with bows and arrows,
rabbits, when I lived in Florida. And we would take our bows and arrows and go into a vacant
lot in the middle of the night when it was dark and shoot them straight up in the air and then
stand around to see where they would come down. So they could have come down straight through the top
of our heads. And you look back and you go, yeah, what was going on? It's a miracle. Yeah, I say that
I call this testosterone dementia. And I think probably most men go through it at some point,
you know, in their, probably in their adolescent years, right? Yeah. When I was in high school,
one of the things we used to do, there's this huge train in Toronto called the GO train.
And it was the above ground transit train. And we used to play this game. As soon as you got off it,
you would dive underneath it and see who could lay the most coins on the track and then get out such
that when it started rolling, you'd get whoever had the most flattened coins would win. Can you
believe that for a moment? Like it's just not hard to believe that that a subset of our species could
be so stupid to do something like that. Yeah, we would also shoot arrows at one another on purpose
and dodge them. And that ended because I was the first one that didn't dodge well enough when I got
an arrow stuck in my leg, at which point our parents investigated what we'd been up to. And
that was the end of that. Yeah. And like, do you think in the history of the, how many billion
people have lived? Like eight billion? Oh, there's almost eight billion alive now. There's probably
probably 800 billion. Yeah. So when you think of all the people that have lived, half of them being
women, do you think there is one example of a woman doing something so stupid? I can't imagine.
Hard to imagine. Yeah. But to get back to it. But that's not all of it, right? That doesn't
explain the infant mortality in the NICU, right? Right. And it doesn't explain the lower influenza
deaths. It doesn't explain the lower, I mean, COVID was, if you look at the COVID, so women are
dying at about 45%, men about 55%. That's pretty much what it looks like for the flu. And I mean,
if you look at all the major causes of death, women die at a lower rate, even if you adjust for age,
so you take age out of the equation, then men for all of them, with the exception of Alzheimer's
disease, which is really interesting to me. And it makes me actually, my private hypothesis that
I don't think I've ever said publicly before is I think Alzheimer's disease is going to turn out to
have an autoimmune component, because that's the kind of thing that women seem to be more prone to
than men is some of the autoimmune diseases. So I mean, there's a few possibilities here. There's
one idea that it has to do with the fact that women have a redundant set of genes on their
second X chromosome. So if they have a defective gene or genes on one of the X chromosomes,
the other one can compensate for it to a certain extent.
If that's true, I don't know if we have enough men with Kline filters out there, but
that would be an interesting comparative analysis, right? Just for folks listening,
men with Kline filters, instead of having XY have XXY. So they would also have that same
redundancy of genes. Right. But some of those redundancies might be bad because Kline filters,
those people don't live long for certain. I don't know how short live they might be,
but they're not longer. I didn't realize their lifespan. I mean, they certainly have a unique
phenotype, but I didn't realize they lived shorter. Certainly. Yeah. But that's interesting because
women with turners, right, which is X, which is aneuploidy of X only, one X, they definitely live
shorter, don't they? Right. Right. So that's one idea. And a little bit of support for it is if you
look at, so one of the X chromosomes typically gets inactivated in each cell and it tends to be random.
As people get older, as women get older, there tends to be a bias in one or the other X chromosome.
So one is inactivated more than the other. Early in life seems to be random. Half of the cells,
your paternal X is inactivated. Half of it is your maternal X. But over time, you get a
kind of a selection for one or the other. Maybe that might be it. The other thing is that there
might be an issue of compatibility of the mitochondrial genome and the nuclear genome,
because mitochondrial genomes only get passed from female to female through generations, right?
So you'd expect there would be a lot of selection for excellent compatibility. Now, the mitochondria
that end up in males are at a dead end. So they don't, you know, it may be that the male
nuclear genome is just not as compatible with the mitochondrial genome as the female genome.
So that's the other possibility that I find kind of, I find both of those really interesting and
what we really need to know about is we need to know a lot more about this in X inactivation,
because it's not total. Not every gene on the second X is inactivated, only some of them.
But the other thing is the Y chromosome is, this has got to be the first time in the history of
medicine that men get less attention for anything than women. But we've always assumed the Y
chromosome is about sexual characteristics. But we now know there are at least nine genes on the Y
chromosome that are expressed in every tissue. We have no idea what they're doing in all those
tissues, but maybe they're doing something that's not so good for us in some of those tissues.
I find both of those ideas, Steve, incredibly fascinating. I'd never,
I'd never thought of either. The mitochondrial incompatibility is a brilliant one. I'll have
to think for a moment about how, what experiments one could do to test that. But on the other one,
on the dominant X, it would be interesting to follow women and identify ones who partition
more into a dominant maternal X and then a dominant paternal X in the women who have a
dominant paternal X. Presumably, that X is better than the other X. And then I would like to see if
there's a difference in the longevity of that father versus, and it's not a random experiment,
so it sort of sucks, but is that a better surviving male than another male that's otherwise
comparable? That's one way I would try to get at that. Yeah. I mean, I think this is a really
intriguing area of research and something that we could do now that we couldn't do a long time ago.
The limitation, of course, because it's humans, is that we're kind of stuck with doing that in blood
and we don't know if the same thing might be going on in the brain or the liver.
Although again, I guess from autopsy studies, we could probably figure that out now. But we do have
the tools now to do a lot of this. We could do muscle biopsies. Is it the same in the blood and
the muscle? That's a possibility. So, you know, my feeling is that we have yet to really explore
these sex differences in any depth and that we may end up having somewhat different therapeutics
in women and men once we start looking into exactly how these things work out between the sexes.
Now, the ITP vary consistently, even whether you talk about its home run drugs like rapamycin
and other drugs like recently 17 alpha estradiol,
they disproportionately favor the male mice over the female mice. Do you believe that that is
simply the result of the fact that they have a higher bar to clear with the females?
Possibly, because in the ITP the female mice live longer. So, it's the longer life sex that's
having no effect and shorter life sex is having the bigger effect. A really interesting one is
rapamycin because you know in rapamycin the sex bias is very, in longevity at least, is very dose
dependent. At the lowest dose they've done, the females live substantially longer than the, or
put it this way, the effect of substantially bigger in females than in males. And that difference
gradually goes away as you get it to a higher and higher dose. And in the highest dose that
anybody has used, which is not in the ITP, but in another study, males had a big effect and females
had no effect. So, the idea is maybe you've overdosed the females at that stage. Now, do you
recall that in the ITP the females had a much higher plasma level than the males despite
consuming the same amount? And I don't remember if Rich had an explanation for why that was the case.
Do you? No, I don't think that they have an explanation. But that could explain the difference,
right? It could be that it wasn't that at a lower dose females are living longer because it's a
lower dose. It's because they have a higher plasma concentration. And maybe that's the gap that
vanishes at a high enough dose. I don't know because I don't know what the kinetics were
in the other study. And what they've published, it wasn't related to blood levels of rapamycin or
metabolites. There was something else is going on. But those things get metabolized very quickly
and there's lots of downstream things that could be. But again, I think that mice are a particularly
bad place to look for these sex differences. And that's because, as I said in the ITP, the
females live longer. But if you look at all the mice studies together, there's mice studies in
which males live longer, mouse studies in which there's no difference, mouse studies in which
females live longer. And they're all over the place. And it's not a genotype thing. Because I
once looked at 30 black six mouse studies and you found the same range from males living 25% longer
to females living 25% longer. And we don't know what that's a result of. Is it something in the
diet? Is it something in the bedding? Or who knows? But the other thing is that mouse sex chromosomes
are quite a bit different than human sex chromosomes. Just to give you an example,
some genes on the X chromosome do not get inactivated on the inactive X. About 15%.
You know, you get expression in both sexes. In mice, that's about 3% to 4% of the genes on the
X chromosome get inactivated. There are also genes on the Y chromosome in humans that are not on the
Y chromosome in mice and vice versa. So I'm not, this again is one of these things where I think
of this as looking at the world through one eye. We have one comparison with humans. Now it's mice.
And just like you don't have much perspective when you close one eye, I don't think you have
much perspective when you have one comparison. And that's kind of what we have now.
Why do you think it's been, I don't want to say so difficult because I don't know that we've tried,
frankly. But why do you think there hasn't been a greater effort in identifying better biomarkers
of aging? Or do you think that there has been an enormous effort and it's just been too difficult?
But for example, we don't know how long one as a human needs too fast to achieve a significant
inhibition of rapamycin to extract the benefits that we think are there. Why is that?
Well, I would say that of your two alternatives that we haven't tried hard enough or maybe we've
tried hard enough and haven't found anything, I would say it's the latter. Because in the 1990s,
the NIA put I think $100 million into developing biomarkers of aging and it came out with nothing.
But that may have been that we just didn't have the right tools at that point. I think
we're really on the verge of something big here so that we can have biomarkers that will tell us
exactly this kind of thing. And do you think these biomarkers will be in the metabolome,
in the proteome, in the epigenome, all of the above? I think they're, yeah, I think they're
likely to be all of the above. And right now, the hottest one is in the epigenome
because that's looking better and better and it seems to...
Are you optimistic? I mean, I've seen how easy it is to manipulate those and I find it completely
uninteresting. And that's going to alienate a lot of people that are listening to this because I'm
the naysayer on that. But Steve, when I look at those data, I'm not remotely impressed. And by
the way, I've done the experiments on some of my patients. You measure their epigenetic age on day
zero. They do a three-day fast. You measure their epigenetic age. It goes down by 10% or more,
frankly. Have you really learned anything? And then a week later, it's back to normal.
I don't know what that's telling me. Well, it may be... So I'm actually fairly
impressed by the epigenetic data, but maybe it's not going to work in the short term like that.
This may be something that tells you something over the course of years, but not over the course of
weeks or months. I think my only point there is that it's very sensitive to what's happening in
the moment. And so when I look at a lot of these aging clocks and I look at the inputs,
I think to myself, these are very easy to manipulate. What was your vitamin D level on
this day? What was your glucose level at the moment of that blood test? I mean, these things
are so easy to manipulate and they have so much volatility over time that I don't find them to be
clinically quite useful. Well, they may never turn out to be clinically useful because it may be that
they're integrating things over a time scale that's not clinically meaningful. I think the
likelihood that we're going to find something in the proteome and the metabolome is higher. I mean,
something that's therapeutically useful just because those things really change rapidly.
Yeah. And if we want to know, if you do X for the... If you fast six hours, you fast 12 hours,
I think what you're going to look for there is changes in gene activity.
And that's going to be in the proteome or in the metabolome. The thing is, it's going to be
computationally complex. Now we have all these tools for doing computationally complex things,
but they're not cheap tools. And so I don't know how long before they'll be in the clinic where
we can afford to do this in people amass. If I were, you know, Czar for a day and could
marshal the resources for the Manhattan Project on longevity, this would be one of the departments.
Right? Like this would be, you know, if you had a billion dollars to put towards a Manhattan
Project of longevity, I feel like a quarter of it would go into this problem. Yeah. Because it,
again, if we're interested in longevity, presumably we're interested in human longevity.
And if we're interested in human longevity, we don't have a hundred years to come up with the
answer. So we have to come up with markers that are better. Well, and now we have the tools to do
that. Yeah. You know, every year the tools, the computational tools, the analytic tools, you know,
if you can detect, you know, 3000 different proteins in your blood, then you're much more
likely to detect something that's really, really meaningful. And so those things are all happening.
Of course, they could happen more if there were more money invested in them.
I think that's the big issue, Steve, personally. I think this is not commercially interesting enough.
And I think that that's why it hasn't gotten the attention. I mean, I think the diagnostics space
is a lousy space, right? Like if you're a venture capitalist and someone comes up to you and says,
I've got a new diagnostic test. I mean, that's nowhere near as interesting as I have a new
therapeutic model. Right. And that's why I feel like this could only really occur in kind of a
Manhattan project or a heavily funded government project. But I just don't. And I use the term
Manhattan project, meaning an entity that is so large commercially that they understand that this
is an important tool that needs to be developed in our research to foster the development of,
you know, molecules down the line. Yeah, it's an interesting, you know, I mean, Craig Venter tried
to do that, right? And that corporation company, we know why I have thoughts on that. I can't share
publicly, but but you're right. I mean, I think the key the keys got to be there. This is not magic.
You know, there's stuff going on in the body. I think the blood, because it courses through
everything in the body, is going to have clues to what's going on everywhere. Once we've learned how
to read those clues. And I think part of the problem is that we're not, you know, there's a
very small group of people that are interested in making other people live longer. But most of the
time, it's trying to prevent them from getting a specific disease. There's a lot more money that
goes into obesity, I think, than that goes into longevity. And it's hard to say that it's not
well spent money because obesity is the huge problem. Right. So you you you made a very famous
bet with Jay Ashonsky 20 years ago, right? 21 years ago. Yeah. What was that bet?
The bet was about when the first when we would have the first 150 year old human. Which side of
that bet did you fall on? I was on this. So my part of the bet was I think that person was born
in the 20, already was born by the year 2000. The person is already alive, who would ultimately
become the first 150 year old person. And Jay bet the opposite. And the critical thing was the person
had to be mentally competent enough to carry on a sensible conversation about something.
Yeah, so that was 20 years ago. And nobody's lived as long as the longest live person had lived at
that point since then. Which was about 122. Yeah, 122 and a half, roughly. Nobody's even reached
120 since then. And so yeah, I'm asked quite awfully if I still think I'm right. And I do
because I never thought this was going to happen because we got better at treating cancer, or we
got better at preventing heart disease. I always thought it was going to happen because we would
develop something or some things that would fundamentally change the rate of aging. And we
haven't developed that yet. We've got a lot of clues. And I think we're getting closer and closer
and closer. But the other reason I'm still confident that I'm going to win that bet is that one of the
things that's come out of the interventions testing program is that things can have this big effect
started late in life. So it may be that this doesn't happen until the person that was born in 2001
is 50 years old. But if it happens, then that doesn't mean that they still couldn't live 150
years. Now it's important to note because this wager gets mischaracterized something. I'm not
saying that I think the life expectancy. That's right. You're talking about 150. Yeah, yeah,
I'm talking about a single person, probably a Japanese woman. It would be my guess if I
had to guess right now. I don't think that 150 year life expectancy is in our future. What do
you think is the limit of human life expectancy as we currently exist? Maybe 100 years. I think
that's reasonable. Now if that happens, some people will live 150 years. Yeah. Right. It's
like the average is around 80 now and this one person lived 122 years. So I think if we get to 100,
that seems conceivable to me. And also something that could be reached by getting better at what
we do now. The key thing is getting people to do what we know is better for them. Now,
do you understand the math behind Jay's models that say if we completely eradicated cancer,
we would increase life expectancy by X years. If we completely eradicated disease Y, we would
increase. And the numbers are very small in his estimates, but I've never actually taken the time
to look at the models to see where those numbers come from. Yeah, those models rely on a number of
assumptions. One of the assumptions of each of these is independent of the other. Which is
completely untrue. Metabolic syndrome tells us that's untrue. Right. So eliminating a single cause
of death is not the same as delaying 20 causes of death. Yeah. Right. So I think they're kind of
artificial in that respect. So those give me no pause for possibly winning my bet. So when you
think about existing molecules, i.e. molecules that are either FDA approved or like 17 alpha
estradiol is not an FDA approved molecule, but it's been tested and it's had unbelievable success
in male mice in the ITP. When you think about kinagaflozin, acarbose, of course rapamycin, metformin.
What molecule do you think of the molecules we know about today has the most potential
for giro protection? Certainly, if we go by the mouse date, it would have to be rapamycin.
If we go by the human date, it would have to be metformin. Both of those are weak statement.
In my qualifications for each of those is a pretty major qualifications. I actually think that
what might turn out to be the most helpful is combinations of these things. So rapamycin plus
metformin. What I like about metformin is that the most compelling data come from human studies,
not from mouse studies. The mouse data on metformin are weak. It didn't succeed in the
ITP, were you surprised by that? No. I wasn't surprised by that at all.
I wouldn't be surprised if it didn't work out in humans. Just because most clinical trials don't,
I mean the existing data, which is voluminous and all pretty much points in one direction, which is
that it's going to be beneficial. Again, it all comes from people that are taking metformin because
they're diabetic. This could be a lot like the Wisconsin experiment again, where it's not going
to work if you do it on people who are healthy. Right. Now, Nier would argue against that, right?
Nier would say that there are many benefits that we see in metformin that go far beyond its
glucose regulatory benefits. They're the obvious benefit that the diabetic patients get.
Yeah. No, no. Nier would be quite emphatic about disagreeing with me on this.
I'd love to be wrong about that, but if I had to put my money, it's just because most clinical
trials fail. Most clinical trials fail because they were based on mouse data to start off with,
at least. Maybe this is something ... It's certainly worth figuring out, just because the
effects are so manifold. It's dementia and cancer and heart disease, and we don't know what else.
We don't know, for instance, what it might do to muscle function. The best data on that,
it's not good for muscle function, but again, that comes from early work, and I think we have
a long ways to go. Because it's so safe, that's the big thing about metformin, is that we know
it's extremely safe. It's been taken by millions of people. We don't know that about rapamycin yet,
but I think it ought to be a high priority to find out what low dose rapamycin does.
The trouble is, giving drugs of any sort to completely healthy people is something that
the FDA is not going to go for. We're almost going to have to work these things out on people that
have some sort of illnesses to start off with. How would you dose rapamycin in a longevity trial,
just as a thought experiment, given two pieces of evidence that seem
to be at dialectical odds with each other? They are as follows. In the mice studies,
in all of the ITP studies, the animals were fed rapamycin in their chow, meaning they received
rapamycin every day. They were always eating rapamycin. Based on our mechanistic understanding
of rapamycin, we believe that the benefits come not from global inhibition of mTOR, but from the
inhibition of mTOR complex one, and not the inhibition of mTOR complex two. In fact, the
inhibition of mTOR complex two might actually have some negative consequences. If you were to take
constitutively rapamycin, as patients do with organ transplants, you were suppressing both.
How do you reconcile those two, and how would you design a clinical trial to address this if your
stated purpose was increasing longevity? Well, the first thing I would do is I would start off
with a dose that's already been tested in human for its effects and enhancing vaccine response
to influenza, because they did multiple doses. That wasn't rapamycin, that was a rapalog.
So five milligrams of everolimus and 20 milligrams of everolimus given once a week did just that.
Right. And the lower dose was just effective at boosting immune response, as the higher dose,
and had fewer side effects. So I would start off with that episodically, like they did, because I
think there's some evidence that you're getting just as big a boost from that. Without the side
effects. Without the side effects. And also, I think you can imagine how much the drug companies
are working to find a rapablog that doesn't inhibit complex two. I mean, that's going to be
huge if they can come up with something that works really differentially on complex one.
That's really where I would start. I think those vaccine studies were a great start. And if they
would, because they were, those were healthy people, right? They just were older people,
they were people, I think 65 and older. I would like to see those things continued.
Now it's interesting, a number of years ago, we tried to get funding for what I thought was
a really good rapamycin study, but we were unsuccessful, which is that there was an NIH
clinical trial to look at rapamycin as preventative for the reoccurrence of kidney cancer.
Those are people that already had a kidney removed, but were seemingly cured. But they
have a higher than average rate of relapse. They were giving one year of rapamycin to see
if it reduced that. And I said, wait a second, why don't we jump in and measure inflammation,
muscle strength, you name it, all these things in this experiment that was already ongoing.
But unfortunately, that didn't get funded. But on the other hand, it may have been too high a dose,
because this is a therapeutic dose for immunosuppressive purposes, right? So it
may not have been the right dose anyway. So we might have come to a conclusion
that was misleading. I thought that that vaccination study was a great avenue for starting
a longer term study. And I know they're doing some of that in a private company,
spin off from-
Yeah. Are you excited about the SGLT2 inhibitors?
I think it's a little early to tell. That and the NAD, various NAD precursors,
I think it's a little too early. So scientists are often, by temperament and training,
extremely skeptical. And I think that's why we make boring interviews so often.
We don't ever come down and make a clean statement. But I really need to see the data
before I start to get excited. And I never get excited by a single mouse study. I get intrigued,
but I don't get excited.
Although the human data on the SGLT2 inhibitors is also remarkable. I think that's-
Yeah.
That's the theme here, is you have a great ITP outcome. And of course, the human data are not
for longevity, but they're-
Right.
Again, they suffer the limitations of all human studies, namely that they're being used in a
subset of the population that might not be the subset of interest. But the impact on kidney
failure, all-cause mortality, heart failure is pretty impressive. And I think what's interesting
about what the ITPs show us with both kinagaflozin and acarbos is that the benefits might not have
to do anything with reducing caloric intake, which was the proposed reason for acarbos,
but rather has to do with glucose kinetics. And I find that very fascinating, actually.
I do too. And I have to say, I'm disappointed in the ITP that they dropped their parafed arm of
that. When they started off, there was going to be a parafed arm and they dropped that. And I'm a bit
disappointed because we don't know now, we only have body weight. We don't have food consumption.
So we don't know how much of these effects might be due to food consumption and how many might not
be. Or changes in the temporal pattern of food consumption. Maybe if it makes your stomach feel
a little bit queasy, you don't want to eat again for 20 hours. So the human data, I mean, we're
going to make real progress when we have human biomarkers. And we can do a five-year study and
we can say, we know this is going to decrease dementia, heart disease, cancer, preserve muscle
strength, boost immune response. Not just immune system, because we have to be careful of that. I
think people think, oh yeah, we want to boost the immune system. Well, we don't want autoimmune
diseases. We don't want our immune system to go haywire because it mischaracterized something as
an invasion. But we want to boost immune responsiveness, certainly. Yeah, I think the
limiting factor right now is biomarkers. Well, yeah, you know my feelings on that. So I think
we end on the same page there, Steve. This has been a lot of fun and we're long overdue to share
a dinner and continue these discussions. So hopefully the next time it'll be in person.
That's great. Next time in New York, Austin, wherever.
Perfect. All right. Well, thanks so much, Steve. I'm sure everybody enjoyed this as much as I did.
Well, great talking to you, Peter. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership
program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now,
to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass,
comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person,
thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiels like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every
Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without
having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I
believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that
we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only
benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on
Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on
Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only, and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.