Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Hello Peter. Hey Bob, how are you man?
I'm doing well, how are you? I'm great. Okay, you ready for an AMA?
I am. I saw the agenda. It's very aggressive. Yeah. Yeah. Ambicious.
Oh I like it. Yes. Yeah, to say the least. I don't know if we'll get through everything,
but we did get a lot of follow-up questions on CGM based on our previous, actually I think
it was the previous AMA where we talked about glucose. We talked about mean glucose, glucose
variability and glucose spikes. And then we also had that Sunday email on CGM and non diabetics.
It was related to a JAMA perspective talking about it. So there's a bunch of questions on that.
Okay. We also have a couple of questions on Aura, the sleep wearable, the Aura ring. We've got some
exercise related questions and we may work in one or two additional questions if we have time.
How's that sound? I think it sounds like a good, good list. Okay. So Peter, since we have a lot of
CGM related questions, one of the things that I've heard you talk about is you have a framework for
interventions that I think will be really helpful in laying the foundation for how you think about
CGM and their use in different populations. So can you start off by telling us a little bit
about that framework? Yeah. So again, it doesn't pertain to CGM specifically. It pertains to
anything that comes across my plate. And the first time I actually contemplated this was
really when I started kind of trying to look critically at the data around meditation. So
this was probably about maybe eight to 10 years ago. But anyway, it basically asks a series of
questions. So the first question is what is the risk of harm from doing this thing? So that's a
direct question. So if you do X, how high is the probability of harm? The second question is
obviously the contrapositive of that. If you do X, what is the probability of benefit? And then
the third question, and by the way, before I go to the third question, those first two questions
are so obvious that they're almost not worth stating. And of course, that's mirrored in the
way the FDA organizes drug trials, right? So a drug trial is organized first by, well, after you
get through the preclinical data, the animal work, after the IND has been filed, your first trial in
humans, which is called a phase one trial, is looking at harm. I mean, it's typically a small
trial with dose escalation that is only trying to understand if as you escalate the dose, do you see
an increase in side effects? Very occasionally, you see some benefits in a phase one trial. And if
you do, that's interesting, but you generally can't take it to the bank because the study is
so small. And generally, it's quite homogeneous. So that's when you move on to phase two studies,
which are geared towards efficacy, i.e. is this thing doing good? And of course, if the phase two
trial is positive, you move to a much larger trial called a phase three trial, which really doubles
down on efficacy. Of course, both of these trials will continue to be able to pick up any signal of
harm. So you're always in the spirit of trying to capture that. But the real point here is you're
raising the bar, so to speak, for what you're demanding of this. So again, what's the risk of
harm? What's the probability of benefit are two obvious questions. I think the third question then
is what's the opportunity cost of this intervention? And I feel like I've talked about this on a
previous podcast before, and maybe it was even one of ours. But there was this device that you
would listen to, and it would supposedly put you in a trance. And the company that was proposing
this thing had all sorts of theoretical benefits from using it. If you listen to this device,
you are less likely to get breast cancer and all of these other things. So was there any
harm in this device? As far as I could tell, no. I really didn't think that listening to this
device was harmful in any way. Was there any benefit of this device? Certainly not to the extent that
they made claims. That said, I had tried the device because a friend of mine bought it for me. And I
have to admit, it was the most relaxing thing I'd ever done. In fact, virtually every time I tried
it, I fell asleep. So maybe there was some good in that, maybe there was some bad in that. If it
was a daytime nap and you could speak to the disadvantages of daytime napping. But there was
an opportunity cost to it. And I don't just mean financial. So the device was pretty expensive. I
want to say it was like a thousand bucks if you were going to buy the thing. A thousand bucks is
no trivial sum of money for anyone. So that's obviously something that has to be weighed
against what else could be done with an opportunity cost. But the other thing you have to keep in
mind is their prescription for use was two 20 minute sessions a day, much along the lines of
like transcendental meditation, which is similar, but has much better data. And that's where I kind
of thought, well, there's a problem because for most people who are super busy, 40 minutes a day
for very questionable benefit didn't make a lot of sense. If it came at the expense of other things
that undoubtedly had benefit, such as could that be 40 minutes a day of actual meditation? Could
that be 40 additional minutes a day of sleep? Could that be 40 minutes a day of exercise? All things
that I would point to as having far greater evidence in favor of. So I think anytime you're
thinking about doing something, you want to kind of go through that. And those are especially
important questions to be asking when the answer is not readily apparent from RCTs that have
generally already answered one and two. Now remember, many RCTs are the easiest RCTs to do
or the ones that are based on pharmacology. And they're generally addressing one and two,
but they're not really addressing three because there really isn't much of an opportunity cost
of taking a pill outside of the economic cost, but the time cost of it is relatively low. Of
course, when it comes to RCTs that are more intervention based, such as exercise, yes,
you want to be able to think about this. But as you look to something like CGM in the case
of non-diabetics, this framework to me is very helpful because at this time we don't have great
RCTs to point to that say in people who are not yet diabetic, there is a benefit to using CGM.
So again, as you go through that, you ask yourself the question, what is the risk of harm? And again,
when we talk about CGM specifically, I think the risk of harm is very low. If we were going to
sort of speculate what could be harmful about it, well, I think the most obvious thing that comes to
my mind is anxiety that it can stoke, right? It can create obsession in someone. And certainly I
can speak to that personally. I don't think personally I've found it harmful, but I could
absolutely understand it. And I frankly think we have some patients in whom I've never recommended
it. So for example, we have some patients who have a history of eating disorders. These are
patients I would not in any way, shape or form advocate the use of CGM. I think it's yet another
tool that can create a negative cycle around obsession. Is there any chance of it doing good?
Well, I mean, I think I've already made the case for that. I think there's ample chance for it
doing good on two fronts, right? The first front is what I call insight-based good, which is
teaching you what your carbohydrate tolerance is. That's what the tool is for. And then secondly,
what I would call behavioral good or behavior modification, which is effectively a strapped
on version of the Hawthorne effect. So when you're wearing a CGM, you're basically utilizing a tool
that is monitoring you. And there is no shortage of data to support the idea that when people are
asked to monitor food intake, they make changes in the right direction. So if I said to you, Bob,
I want you to record everything you eat for the next month and track it in a food diary,
are you going to make better food choices than you are making now? And the answer is unequivocally
yes. You are going to do that. Which is also, not to pile on, I guess this is the first time
I'm mentioning observational epidemiology so far, at least for this episode, but that's one of the
challenges right there with food frequency questionnaires is that they start asking them
to ask them what foods they're eating or they ask them what foods they ate. And oftentimes,
just that by asking, they're changing their behavior. And so you're not really getting
an accurate representation of what they ate previously.
Right. So that's a problem that plagues epidemiology, but you can use that to your
advantage, right? And we do that stuff clinically, right? This is how you create accountability for
patients. You say, look, we're going to check in once a day and I just want you to tell me what
you ate. And even if you provide no other instruction, which is, oh, I want you to have
this many grams of protein and this many grams of carbs and this many grams of fat. No, no, even if
you don't go to that level, if you just say, I just want you to tell me what you ate, that level of
accountability immediately changes a person's behavior. And that's an example of how you can
use that to your benefit. So is that sort of a, I guess I'll get to the third point, which is
opportunity costs. So what's the opportunity cost of one of these devices? Well, I think hands down
the biggest opportunity cost is the economic cost. These things are not cheap. And if you are not
diabetic, you are not going to have your insurance company cover one of these devices. So there are
no shortage of companies out there that are repurposing and repackaging CGM. So there are
really three companies that make CGM's in the clinical grade. So there's Medtronic, Abbott and
Dexcom. And again, by way of full disclosure, I consult with Dexcom, not on their CGM business,
but actually on a part of their business that deals with other analytes. So other things that
you could measure. So actually don't really interact much on the CGM side. But those three
companies make CGM's. And then there are lots of companies like Levels and Super Sapiens that
people have heard of who are plugging in those CGM's into their apps to help users with their
goals, be it weight loss or otherwise. Well, they're not cheap. I'm trying to remember what
the cost is the monthly. I mean, I feel like the daily cost of CGM is about 10 bucks. And there's
probably cheaper ways to get it if you're buying your CGM on eBay or if it's a little bit expired,
but directionally speaking, it's about a $10 a day habit. And that adds up, right? Call it
$3,500 a year. That's a huge expense, assuming you need it every minute of every day. And I don't
think you do. I think you can gain a lot of insight using these things periodically. I don't
think this is something you need to be tethered to every minute of every day. There are some people
like me who enjoy that, not going to lie. I've been wearing CGM for almost six years. It never
gets old to me. I continue to find insights that just provide value. And more than anything else,
it's really the behavioral tool. And that might make me a mental midget. I might just be a guy
that is such a simple plebe that having that little CGM on my arm is what keeps me away from
the ice cream in the freezer and the cookies in the pantry. But if you saw my freezer and you saw
my pantry, you would certainly understand why I stand to benefit from using CGM.
Well, I think you mentioned this in the article or the Sunday post about how the percentages change
with when you talk about how much insight you're getting, say, in the first 30 days versus long
term, whether it's a motivational or behavioral tool and how those can shift. But I also want
to mention that when I was at UVM, I was getting my undergrad and I was studying nutrition that,
to your point about ice cream in the freezer, I remember for one of our courses that we were
taking, we started doing a food log or food diary. And I remember at the time I was eating,
I don't know why I got into this, but actually you probably will know why. I was eating a pint
of Ben and Jerry's chocolate chip cookie dough just religiously. Like I would just-
Is a pint the one that's this big? Like the little one? Is that a pint?
Yeah, that's the 16 answer. Yeah. But I think that's the only thing that Ben and Jerry's comes in.
Okay. And you were eating one of those a day?
I was eating one of those a day after dinner and it was just like a, yeah, whatever kind of habit.
Then I was doing the food log and I had to keep a food log. And that's how I kicked that,
if you want to call it a habit, that's how I kicked the Ben and Jerry's habit. I said,
okay, I'm going to have to write for the, I think it's two days during the week and one
day during the weekend that I had to do it. And that's typically what they do for food diaries.
And you just log everything you eat, real time, over 24 hours for like a Monday and a Thursday
and a Saturday. And I remember I kicked that habit, but it reminds me of the stuff that
some of these things are behavioral tools may be in disguise. But I think you mentioned something
like 90, 10. Yeah, yeah. And that's sort of what I tell patients. Because look, a lot of our patients
are like, Hey, Peter, what do you think? I mean, do you think I should do this? And my answer for
most of them is, yeah, I think you should. I think everybody deserves a three month trial of CGM,
again, notwithstanding a handful of patients who I think have contraindications. And I typically
say, look, it's going to start out as about 90, 10, 90% of this is going to be insight. Like you're
going to be going, holy cow, I can't believe, fill in the blank. And only 10% of it is going to be
changing your behavior through this Hawthorne effect. I said, by the end of that 90 days,
that's going to flip. Again, it depends on how much insight you look to extract. But directionally,
within about three months, you're going to be like, you know what, I've sort of figured out the
effect of grapes. And the difference between like, you know, a grapefruit and a banana, like I've
kind of got that dialed. And I've also figured out that, you know, I can eat a ton of carbs after I
work out. But if I eat a ton of carbs before bed, totally different effect on my blood glucose
and overnight in the morning. But the shift is you start to gamify it a little bit. So yeah,
again, I guess that's sort of what I would say on my framework for how to think about these things.
Okay. So the related questions to CGM, I've got actually just mentioned grapes. So this person
says my glucose spikes when I eat some fruits, but not others. Do you know why this happens? And
does it mean that I should avoid fruits that spike my glucose? Thank you for listening to today's
sneak peek AMA episode of The Drive. If you're interested in hearing the complete version of
this AMA, you'll want to become a member. We created a membership program to bring you more
in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. Membership benefits are many and beyond
the complete episodes of the AMA each month. They include the following ridiculously
comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, and thing we discuss
on each episode of The Drive. Access to our private podcast feed, the Qualies, which were a super short
podcast, typically less than five minutes, released every Tuesday through Friday, which highlight the
best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is particularly
important for those of you who haven't heard all of the back episodes. It becomes a great way to
go back and filter and decide which ones you want to listen to in detail. Really steep discount
codes for products I use and believe in, but for which I don't get paid to endorse, and benefits
that we continue to add over time. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Lastly, if you're already a member,
but you're hearing this, it means you haven't downloaded our member-only podcast feed where
you can get the full access to the AMA and you don't have to listen to this. You can download
that at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash members. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.