Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Lawrence, thank you so much for coming over. I love being able to interview people in person.
So to have somebody that's from Austin and to be able to sit down with you is really exciting
today. Well, it's a pleasure to be out and about even under the constrained circumstances that we
find ourselves. This is a topic that I think many of my listeners are going to kind of wonder
what does this have to do with longevity because that tends to be what I speak about. But as we sit
here basically minutes away from effectively the 20th anniversary of certainly the most
pivotal moment for many of us in our lifetimes, of course, you were also alive
during some of the other pivotal moments in our history. I think for many of us, we just sort of
can't believe how fast 20 years has gone by. So I kind of want to just start with maybe a silly
question, but what do you remember of that morning, that Tuesday morning? Where were you?
Back then I had breakfast with a bunch of colleagues that were learning Spanish. And so
we would speak Spanish at breakfast and every Tuesday. And after breakfast, I got in the car
and NPR was on and they had reported one plane had hit the World Trade Center. And by the time I
got home, the second plane had hit. And I hadn't had written about terrorism already. So I was
aware that this was probably a terrorist attack. It wasn't a surprise to me that it was a terror
attack. Of course, it was an immense surprise that it was such a dramatic strike.
Had you heard much about Al Qaeda before this? Were they familiar to you?
Yeah, I had written a movie called The Siege with Denzel Washington, Bruce Willis, and
Annette Bening. And it was about what would happen if terrorism came to America. That was
the question I asked myself. And it already happened in London and Paris, of course,
Tel Aviv. So I suppose it happened in New York. And this movie came out in 1998.
And in August of 98, a couple of months before the movie actually opened,
there was the first big strike by Al Qaeda against American embassies in East Africa.
And 224 people were killed. And that was scarcely remarked. And I don't even think that
during the elections, the terrorism was mentioned. Campaigning had already begun for the... Well,
the midterms were underway. So it wasn't a central issue. It happened over there.
We still had this sense of invulnerability in America. And I think that's why it was
unnoticed. But there was another bombing that same month in Cape Town, South Africa,
at a Planet Hollywood restaurant. And two people were killed, two British tourists,
and a little girl lost her leg. And an Islamic group called... I've forgotten what the name was.
An Islamic group claimed credit saying that they were protesting the trailers that had appeared
in movie theaters for the siege. The movie hadn't even come out yet and people are already dead.
And that was a scarring experience for me. I didn't feel that my movie was responsible
for people getting killed. But had the movie not happened, they'd probably be alive.
And so terrorism touched me right off. And it's three years before 9-11,
there was a lot of anger in the Muslim community about being depicted as terrorists because it was
a... having spent a lot of time in Egypt and so on, I sensed that if you're going to make a
plausible terrorist action, that would be the source of it. But there were pickets outside the
movie theaters. I mean, and people don't like to go to the movie when there are pickets. So
you know, there's always another show. So it didn't do well. It was a bomb. And then after 9-11,
it was the most rented movie in America. And I think it was because in the movie,
yes, there is terrorism. Yes, it happens in New York and it presages so much of what actually
did happen, but it had an ending. And it turned out all right. And I think after 9-11,
people were desperate for something that would give them a little hope.
Yeah, I was talking to my wife this morning. She was so bummed she couldn't be here to meet you
because she's such a fan. So we'll have to figure out a way to do something another time. So,
because she was really bummed to not be here. But I was talking about how it's not clear to me,
because I've never really talked about it with anybody else, what the impact is like collectively
for the average person, right? So, you know, my story is like everybody else's, which is I can
remember in crystal clarity, every detail of that morning, I was a surgical resident at Hopkins.
I was down in the pediatric trauma bay. A kid had just been hit by a car. So I was tending to this
kid, you know, getting x-rays, doing all the things. He turned out to be totally okay, but
just making sure he didn't have broken bones. And I remember a person, I remember who they were
walking in and saying, a plane just hit the world trade center. And I assumed it was like a Cessna
that had hit the trade center in the fog. So it was sort of like, my only thought was, oh,
it must be a foggy day up in New York today or something. Didn't think anything of it,
kind of went right back to work. And then of course, you know, some odd 40 minutes later,
second plane hits, all of a sudden now the TV's on in the ER and we're all seeing what's going on.
And then, you know, for the next 48 hours, none of us left the hospital because we were sort of
waiting. Would there be survivors coming? Obviously there were none. But the part I never
really understood is how much of a lasting impact it had on me for reasons I can't explain. I didn't
know anybody who died that day. I didn't even know any of the first responders or people who were
traumatized as survivors. And yet for at least 10 years, I had horrible dreams about being on,
was it United 93, the flight that crashed in Pennsylvania. I had dreams of being in the
cockpit as it was nose diving in the ground. You've spent time talking about this with people.
Is that an experience that you've seen in the normal person who's not,
who wasn't physically or directly touched by this?
In some ways it's a generational divide. You know, we're old enough for it to have deeply
affected us personally. And I think every American was profoundly affected in one way or another.
For one thing, there was this sense of invulnerability. It was a smug feeling about
we exist in the world, but apart from it, you know, things that happen out there in the rest
of the world don't really touch us. We meddle in wars and so on, but it never comes to the homeland.
And that was so punctured. It was so disillusioning. And that we're a regular country and we're
vulnerable. And that was shattering. And I don't think anybody who was cognizant at that age
I don't think anybody walked away feeling the same. Now it's interesting to me because,
you know, the culture changed around that event and young people don't know what America was
before 9-11. They only know, you know, the country that we've become. And I reflect on,
you know, when I was like in high school,
I remember I took a date to the airport in Dallas. It's called Love Field, but not for that reason.
But back then, when you didn't have any money and you wanted to entertain your date, it was,
you know, a plausible place to go. And so we went, walked out on the tarmac where an American
Airlines plane had flown in. We decided he'd just come from Paris. So we sat in the first
class compartment and a stewardess, as we call them then, served us a snack. And then we went up
in the FAA tower and, you know, come on in kids. And so we sat down and watched them, you know,
landing planes. And that was America. There was a sense of freedom and, you know, we talk a lot
about freedom, but that was really freedom that you could, teenagers, you know, just wander in
and see things and this unguarded feeling that Americans had, that we were not threatened.
And now the airport experience, if you can just compare that,
nobody, you know, young people, even people in their, you know, mid 20s now, or even 30,
don't really know America beforehand. They don't know that you could go into an office
building without having your picture taken, or you could go visit the Liberty Bell in
Philadelphia without having to take off your belt in your shoes. You know, we've built up a security
state and we've been so deeply involved with the rest of the world in an antagonistic manner
since then. And that has become normal, but it's an aberration in our history. And, you know, I
think that, you know, I would like for us to try to remember the country we were and aim to steer
towards that. Because if you forget the memory, if you lose the memory of the country that we were,
then I don't think we can ever get back to port. It's funny you mentioned that story about being
at Lovefield. One of the memories I have is anytime my dad would travel, and I'm sure my parents will
come up during this discussion because they're immigrants from Egypt, which plays such a central
role in the story we're about to discuss. But it was not uncommon for my dad during flights,
you know, if he was going somewhere and he was returning to Toronto, which is where we live,
he would spend most of the flight in the cockpit just playing patty cakes with the crew because he
was such an outgoing guy. And I'm not making this up. There were times when he would bring the entire
crew home and prepare a meal for them because he was, you know, he cooked, you know, in a restaurant.
So there were times when he would show up with eight random people from Air Canada who were coming
to our house because they had, you know, a night layover in Toronto and they'd be coming over for
dinner. I mean, like think about how bizarre that is in the context of the world we live in today.
In the context of the world we live in today. Yeah. We're not unique in that, but other
countries have been putting up with this kind of defensiveness for a long time. And so it's a bigger
challenge in America. And, you know, there's no doubt that we needed to be on guard and protect
ourselves and ramp up our defenses. And, you know, but the truth is, you know, we've in trying to
create security for us. We've created a security state that is such an abridgement of our freedom
that we are doing to ourselves. You know, we're doing it to protect ourselves, but at the same
time we're the ones that are holding the handcuffs. And it's an abridgement of our freedom in a profound
way that I think that people who talk a lot about freedom don't really appreciate. So how long after
9-11 did the idea come to you that you were going to put in the type of profound research
that ultimately led to the looming tower, which I think came out in 06? That's right. It was immediate.
You know, I knew this was the story of our lifetime. It was not clear that day that it was Al-Qaeda
but it was pretty clear to me. I mean, I had in my movie, The Siege, I depicted something like that
kind of organization. And if you remember, the phones were out in Manhattan that morning
because the cell tower had been destroyed. I do remember that because I had at the time my
girlfriend, who was an architect, lived in Manhattan and I couldn't get a hold of her for a day and a
half. And I had a couple of friends from medical school who were residents there, couldn't get a
hold of her. Very strange situation. Yeah, it was unnerving. And so I sent an email to my editor at
The New Yorker, David Remnick, and I said, put me to work. I've been kind of straying from the
reservation, working on movies and things like that. So that afternoon, the phones came back on,
at least for The New Yorker. And we had a conference call with, I guess, about a dozen
New Yorker writers. And like me, scattered around, Jeff Toobin, I think, was in the Bay Area.
Jeff Goldberg and Jane Mayer were both in Washington. And we're all checking in.
And what do you want us to do? And what David asked us to do was to find stories,
human stories that can form part of a narrative that he would weave together. And I felt that
a handicap in Austin. But somehow I found this young man named Kurt Yeltsin. He was a reporter.
He was supposed to have been on the top floor of the World Trade Center at the Windows on the
World restaurant, on the 101st floor, before a conference that his magazine, which was called
Waters, was an investment magazine. He had an appointment there at nine o'clock. And he slept
through the subway stop for the first time in his whole life. And so he turned around,
got off on the Chamber Street exit, ran into the World Trade Center. The Trade Center's elevators
were up a flight of escalators. So he ran up the escalators and into an elevator. And there were
like 200 elevators in the two towers. And you had to change floors. So he ran into the elevator. And
an elevator operator was holding the door for this woman who was taking her time, walking across the
lobby. And Kurt was very anxious because he was late. And as she stepped into the elevator,
he noticed that she had a rose tattoo on her ankle. And he thought to himself, oh, wow.
And then the plane hit. And in the doors to the elevator accordion, and nobody knew
what had happened. Was it an earthquake? The building had been bombed before by a precursor
of Al-Qaeda. So there was that. But Kurt stepped out of the elevator. And he looked around in the
lobby. And there were objects lying there, concrete objects. He said the size of an alarm clock and
some like the size of an office chair and just lying on the ground of the lobby. And it was eerie.
Remember, he had to go up a flight, but he was confused. And he saw daylight. And he went towards
that. And it was a door that led to a patio. And he walked outside and there were hundreds of shoes
on the ground and something else that he thought was luggage, but turned out to be human torsos.
And then something landed right beside him. And so he went back in. And his story of
escaping the Trade Center and making it home to Queens became the
bookend of the New Yorker's black issue. And that's what got me started. It was, I gotta say,
incredibly wrenching to hear his story and pasted it together over a number of interviews. And I
would interview him. And then my wife would type up the notes and a lot of weeping going on. But
I knew from then that I was on the case and that whatever portion of my life was already
spoken for. A couple of months later, I signed a contract February for a book that was supposed
to be turned in a year later. And I scratched out February and wrote March or something April. I had
no idea. I turned it in five years later. So I had no idea what I was getting into, but I just knew
that I was going to go all the way to the end of this.
Yeah. Those stories, by the way, are so interesting to me. I only know one,
which is a friend of mine's ex-wife was supposed to be on one of the four flights. I don't remember
which one, but she missed the flight. So she overslept, she got to the airport, but didn't get
through security and time. So by the time she got to the gate, they had already shut the doors.
I think the plane was even pulling away. And so you have this moment where you're so upset,
in that moment, can't imagine a greater tragedy, right? Whatever it is she was going to do,
what an inconvenience to, because it was a cross country flight. And then of course,
to realize that that saved your life. Those stories are, there's hard to process.
And what you're doing here is that somebody else may have gotten that seat.
And so there's another side of those coincidences.
Right. The person who would have only made that flight by standby or something.
Well, your book is really two stories. It's really a book of two parallel stories that are
each one very difficult to get through. If I'm going to be honest, I've read your book
two and a half, three times basically. And it gets more frustrating the more you get through it,
because you pick up new things in it that just seem so difficult to swallow. But at least the
way I sort of read the book is it's basically the history of Al Qaeda. How did this organization
come to be? Because most people, when they think of Al Qaeda, they of course think of Osama bin Laden.
But there are more actors to it. And there's a long history that goes back to Egypt. And as you
and I were speaking a little bit before we sat down, so much of what you wrote about resonates
with things I knew about my childhood, because we used to go to Egypt every year. And then there's
this parallel story that's perhaps the most upsetting part of the book, if that's possible,
which is the story about the intelligence. I remembered shortly after 9-11, Thomas Friedman
wrote an article in the New York Times that said, this was not a failure of intelligence. It was a
failure of imagination, implying that it's not that our intelligence community failed us. It's
that we could have never imagined this. But I don't know that I can agree with that after
reading your book. One bit, I think this was a catastrophic failure of intelligence. So maybe
we'll start with the former. And it seems that a good enough place to start would be Saeed Qatub.
So who is this character and why is he an important figure in the creation of Al Qaeda?
Saeed Qatub was an educator in Egypt and very cosmopolitan in his way. And he was religious,
but he wasn't at the beginning fanatical. But he was a member of the Muslim brothers,
which was outlawed in Egypt. And Nasser came into power in 1952 and the officers revolt. And
looking around for partners, he decided that maybe the Muslim brothers could be co-opted.
And so he tried to enlist Saeed Qatub in his governance. And Qatub signed on for a little
bit. But the truth is, the Muslim brothers had a goal, which was not to have a military
dictatorship, but an Islamic one. And they never really came to an agreement.
And Saeed Qatub actually wasn't thrown out of the country. Some friends arranged for him to get out
of Egypt at a time when it was really difficult for him. And he got a job teaching in Greeley,
Colorado at this little college. And I visited Greeley, and I don't know how different it was
in 1940s when he first went there. But I think it's a town that reminds you of America as it used
to be. Lots of green lawns, innumerable churches, just a scrubbed up Norman Rockwell type of town.
And Qatub hated it. He just thought it was the worst excesses of America. I mean,
if only he knew. But he was shocked by the behavior of the women. He was very threatened by them.
And he was-
I mean, imagine he'd gone to Vegas or something, right?
He did spend a little bit of time in New York, which was interesting for him because his brother,
who was in Mecca, came out of Mecca to allow me to interview him, said that he had never met a Jew
until he got to America. And yet he hated them. There was the unseen enemy. And then suddenly,
he's in Manhattan, and he's encountering Jews all over the place. And then he goes to Greeley.
It was a turning point for him. He came back and wrote a very influential article about how
dangerous America was. And this was at a time when America was seen as the one non-colonial power
by the developing world. And it was held in very high esteem. And yet that was an opening shot.
Then came the revolution. And Nasser reached out to see if he could bring him into the government.
And that didn't work out at all. They had totally different aims for the country. Nasser,
not obviously a secularist, but probably, but he saw the powerful trend of Islam in the country.
And he wanted to tame it in some way. And he thought by co-opting site, Qutb might be able to.
And Qutb had written every Friday in the newspapers, not just in Egypt, but all over the
Arab world, they would publish his commentaries on Islam and the Quran. So he was a figure of note.
And at the time Egypt was mostly Sunni? Egypt is divided into almost entirely Sunni
Muslims and Christians. The Shiite minorities, insignificant. But there is about a 10%.
Nobody really knows, but there's a smaller population of Christians. And like a lot of
Islamic countries, there's little to choose from on the religious banquet. And the option is to be
more or less religious. And piety is how you advance in a deeply religious society as
Egypt was and actually became much more so. When I lived there in 69 to 71,
my female students were not covered. Even at Cairo University, it was rare to see women with
head coverings. And I was teaching at the American university at the same time, I'm in Elza water.
He was a medical student at Cairo University. And he was part of an effort to get women to cover
and to become more obviously religious. So it was a country in transition.
It's interesting. So you were there. My mom left Egypt when she was 22. And the day she flew out,
it was her first time leaving the country was September 28th, 1970. And so when she departed
from Cairo, Nasser was the president and a young president. He was in his fifties. When she landed
in Copenhagen on the news, Nasser was dead. And she was in such shock because Nasser was like kind
of a God to her generation. And he seemed indomitable. It just seemed like this is a person
who will be president of Egypt forever. So you were there exactly in the middle of that transition
from Nasser to Sadat. What did it strike you as the implication of that was in terms of
either the secularization of Egypt or the move towards this more religious state?
You have to understand what Nasser stood for. In Egypt, he was the first Egyptian
to rule over Egypt since- 2500 years.
Yeah, at least 2500 before Cleopatra and all the Greeks who took over as a pharaonic figures,
even King that they overthrew was Turkish. So suddenly you have an Egyptian,
not just an Egyptian, this glamorous, very handsome, compelling figure.
Extremely charismatic and an unusual figure in the Arab world. In fact, his appeal was so broad.
Egypt essentially annexed Syria. It was the United Arab Republic, but the Syrians had very little.
They just wanted to throw in their lot with the most powerful figure in the Arab world.
So his sway was unbelievable. It was so powerful that even the hideously mismanaged war against
Israel in 1967, which the six day war, you might have well called it the six hour war because it
was over as soon as the Israelis bombed the Egyptian airplanes. It was a catastrophe.
And yet he survived that. So the idea that there would be a day without Nasser was just not
something that occurred to Egyptians. And I remember when it happened, he was actually
moderating a peace conference with the Palestinians at the time. And he had a heart attack.
And I had a cook who came to my apartment that morning and he said,
the people are like sand in the street. Remember the night that the news came out.
I had not heard the news before hearing the eulolating all over. It was eerie.
And because it wasn't a singular sound, it was like a vast sound. And so as Americans, we were
counseled not to go out. I don't think that anything would have happened to us, but the
streets were weirdly empty. And Cairo always had a problem with pollution and noise. Suddenly it
was dead quiet. The atmosphere clarified. It was beautiful, but unsettling. And for three days,
you just didn't see anybody. And then they had the funeral. And we went up on the roof.
We lived in Zimalik, which was an island in the middle of the Nile. We were right across from
the Russian news agency Novosti. And so we were up on top of the roof and you could see the
parade forming. It started at the end of Zimalik. There was a revolutionary tower.
There's a story on that. The CIA tried to bribe Nasser with $10 million. And he used it to build
this tower, the revolutionary tower on the island directly across from the Hilton so that
Americans could see where their money went. So that's where the parade started, the funeral
cortage. And they were going to cross the Khasser El-Nil bridge. And there were all the
dignitaries around the world. And what we could see was just a mass of uniforms and suits and
stuff like that. But we could also see this immense crowd of people on the other side of the
bridge. And they rushed in towards the cortage. And in the middle of the bridge, they met the
mourning chirines and the dignitaries. And in the front of the cortage, there were police with
batons beating a path through people. And the turmoil was so great that from where we were,
which was a mile away maybe, we could see the bridge trembling. And I've often thought about
how soldiers have to break ranks when they cross a bridge because of- Right. Otherwise,
you get the Tacoma Narrows effect. Yes. So I worried that the bridge might actually crack,
but they beat their way all the way through the mobs in the streets. And I thought,
this country will never be the same. And it really has never been. I will qualify that by saying,
it has never been, although it has always been ruled by military forces, military figures,
with the brief exception of the Muslim Brotherhood president. And then who becomes
president is Anwar Sadat, who was regarded as a joke in Egypt. He had been in the officers'
coup, but he missed the revolution. He was at a movie. It was a double feature, but he missed
the revolution. And that was a story that hung around Anwar Sadat. And people thought he was a
fool and he wouldn't last. And he turned out to be a significant figure because of him,
Egypt and Israel are at peace to this day. Everybody underestimated him, but he had been
in Nasser's shadow all that time. So it marked a turning point. And it was Sadat who expelled the
Soviets. Up until that point, Egypt had been a kind of Soviet military base and the US and
Egypt didn't have diplomatic relations. There were only a handful of Americans actually there
when I was living there. Now, four years prior to Nasser's death, he had Qutb executed. But you
get the sense that he was, that was reluctant. I think he understood that that execution would
make a martyr of him. And there's probably nothing worse that you could have done than have made a
martyr of this man. Didn't he have Sadat then as either prime minister or vice president,
almost try to get Qutb to just ask for some sort of forgiveness so he could save face and not
execute him? Qutb was a hard case. He would rather die than renounce his stance. And he told Sadat
that. And he called their bluff. It cost him his life, but it also gave birth to this movement
because once Qutb was dead, he became a symbol of the oppressiveness of the Arab regimes.
The dictatorships that spanned the entire of North Africa all the way to Turkey.
And what was the alternative? The only alternative that people could see was the Muslim Brotherhood
or some other form of Islamism. So it was Qutb's death that inspired, for instance,
Ayman al-Zawahri. Ayman al-Zawahri, his uncle, was Qutb's lawyer and had been his teacher.
He was a dear friend of Qutb. And just before Qutb was hanged, he gave Zawahri's uncle his
Quran, which was incredibly treasured. And so when Ayman al-Zawahri was 15, he started a cell
to overthrow the Egyptian government. That'll show you the level of commitment that Al-Qaeda
was born in. And there's something else that's very interesting that I remember,
as I mentioned to you, so much of reading your book put into context so many stories that I had
heard growing up that seemed at the time disjointed because they sort of lacked the clarity of the
full arc. But one of them was how Sadat upon immediately becoming president basically freed
many of the prisoners that Nasser had put away. So it seemed that Nasser had a much clearer
understanding of the threat of Islamic fundamentalism. And I guess the question is,
what is it that Sadat hoped to gain by freeing these individuals?
Sadat, unlike Nasser, was very pious and he thought nobody was more pious than he. He called himself
the first man of Islam. How about that? And he thought because he was religious that he would
have standing with people in the Muslim Brotherhood. He totally underestimated
the fanaticism that had grown up in those prisons. And not just because of Said Qutb, but
one of the things that radicalized Qutb was when he was in prison, soldiers came in and shot
prisoners in their cells. And his question to himself was, what kind of Muslim would do this
to another Muslim? And his answer was, they are not Muslims. And so essentially,
there's a phrase in Arabic called takfir, which is to expel someone for their disbelief.
And so he created the precedent that unless you believe as I, we do, you're not a real Muslim.
And once that door was opened, it led to the idea of terrorism. And that's where Zawahiri and
bin Laden got permission to become the terrorists that they became.
How far back does that precedent go? If you go back to Muhammad, where is the first sign
that it's okay to kill someone if they don't believe what you believe?
Well, the question of killing someone, there was a lot of tribal warfare before Islam. And
Islam was really in part an effort by Muhammad to unify Muslims, to stop fighting each other.
And Islam, one of the meanings is submission, submit, accept your place.
But that didn't stop a lot of the infighting in Saudi Arabia, in particular, the Iqwan,
were wildly fanatic tribesmen that the first king of Saudi Arabia enlisted in his battle. But then
in order to subdue them, he had to bring in British warplanes and machine guns to shoot his
own soldiers of the cross, so to speak. In modern era, it was bin Laden who looked out at
in the Takfiri universe. There was a kind of doctrine that came from some of the discourse
that first of all, you have to attack the near enemy, and then the far enemy. And the far enemy
being the West and the United States, but the near enemy being dictators like Mubarak and so on,
the royal family in Saudi Arabia. So the heretics, the heretics, the Shia, the Jews, the West,
those would be the four stated enemies. Absolutely. In basically in proximity.
Yes. But first of all, tend your own house. Well, it was bin Laden who looked out and said,
the far enemy is not far. America is right off our shores. There are bases in Saudi Arabia.
You cannot call them the far enemy anymore. So using the permission that he had been given
to wreak havoc and kill people at will, bin Laden turned on America.
So going back to the early 70s, so Zawahiri is in school. He's going through medical school.
Sadat sort of saves face during the 1973, the Yom Kippur War. Sadat is sort of romanticized in
the West. But what was the view inside Egypt of Sadat in the sort of mid to late 70s? Was he
basically ostracized in the Middle East for creating peace with Israel? I mean, that can't
have been popular with the other Middle Eastern nations, correct?
It wasn't popular in Egypt either. Well, let me qualify that. There were people that were tired
of strife and wanted to make peace. But the rhetoric in the Middle East, the rhetoric in
the Middle East at that point was that Israel had to be destroyed. And here was Amor Sadat saying,
no, we're going to make peace with Israel. First, he had to demonstrate that he was willing to go to
war because the Israelis were so complacent they didn't see a threat. And actually, I don't think
here, Sadat doesn't get enough credit for the daring. There was a kind of maginot line that
the Israelis had built. They'd taken all of Sinai. Sinai, yeah.
And along the Suez Canal, they built this sand fortress that extended a whole length,
cliffs of sand topped by artillery and little caves inside with machine gun emplacements and
stuff like that. It looked really formidable. And Sadat managed secretly to create this army
and invasion force. And how do they bring down that castle of sand with fire hoses?
It was amazing how the sand just melted away, but they had these high pressure fire hoses they'd
gotten from Germany. And within a few hours, they had managed to cross the Suez Canal,
which the Israelis thought was totally impossible. And it was in kind of a mirror of the 67 war.
Egypt was essentially defeated by Ariel Sharon's army, which surrounded them. But
they had made the point. And at that point, Sadat was a real hero.
He gave pride to the Egyptian people who felt so humiliated. And one of the things that
he had to counter was the lessons that the Egyptians had drawn from the 67 war and the
Israelis. The Israelis thought, well, we really are God's people. Look at this. Just before the
war, we were digging trenches for mass graves in the public parks. And now we've conquered
all of our Arab neighbors within six days. Just unbelievably thrilling.
And so what lesson did the Arabs, and particularly the Egyptians, take, which is we're not God's
people. Why would he let this happen to us? And the answer was, we are not religious enough.
And so that answer resonated with so many people. And the 67 war was a huge
influence in driving people into radicalism. And that was something that Sadat
didn't fully take into account. And of course, eventually that radicalism would focus on him.
And so what did you describe him as? I thought that was just hilarious. He described himself
as the first man of Islam. Yeah. The funniest concept ever. Because the reality of it is,
he would, at the end of his, as we drew close to the end of his life, he would completely turn
around and say, no religion in politics, no politics in religion. He saw the damage that
this religion was causing and said, we must separate this church and state. And is that
ultimately what led to the fatwa being brought against him? Well, peace with Israel was a part
of it. There was also, he was chiding. He was really pharaonic in his behavior, which is not
unusual in people that rule over Egypt. But he derided women who were covered as saying that they
were wearing tents on their head. And that really offended a lot of Islamists. And his wife, I
believe had pushed for the right for a woman to have a divorce. So they were really trying to
bring modernity to Egypt. And it was ultimately the nail in his coffin. It was a similar path
that the Shah of Iran had gone through. Yeah. I was going to ask you about that because the Shah
was basically overthrown in 79 or was it 78? It was 79. And that year was a catastrophic one
for Islam and for Muslim countries. It's the year that the Soviets invaded Afghanistan. It's
the year the Shah was overthrown. And it was the year that Camp David peace accords were signed.
And I should also say it was the year of the attack in Mecca where radical Islamists took over
the holiest place in Islam. And Saudi Arabia needed the French to come and help. Yeah. They
don't like to admit this and there's still no toll. We don't know how many people died, hundreds
or thousands. We don't know. But there were snipers up in the minarets and so on. And
underneath the plaza, there's a warren of rooms and they had stored weapons and food in there.
And so there were plans maybe to flood them out. But they were holding hostages. And
we don't really know what happened. But what we understand, when I was researching this as
carefully as I could, they bore holes in the plaza and dropped grenades down. So a lot of
innocent people were killed and then dozens were arrested and executed. But it was a trauma
on the scale of 9-11 in Saudi Arabia. And out of that came a bargain between the royal family and
the clerics, which was the royal family needed permission to attack the mosque.
In Islam, it's so holy that you're not even supposed to mow the grass. Every living thing
should be untouched. And here was a situation where totally out of control,
thousands maybe of people would be killed. And the royal family did not feel they could do this
without a fatwa from the leading clerics. And in return, the royal family agreed to allow
religious figures greater standing and more power within the society.
So upon that, Saudi Arabia immediately became far more conservative. And the clerics took control.
And you began to see the religious police in the streets and so on. And Saudi Arabia
had been on a path not to liberalism, but a more stable society that was somewhat moderate.
But not fanatic. But there were people... Once the religious authorities acquired power,
they used it, but they also became far more fanatical themselves.
So the name of the organization that ultimately assassinated Sadat was Al-Jihad, correct? This was
the one half of what would become al-Qaeda. Right. The American intelligence called it
Egyptian Islamic Jihad, but in Egypt, it's just called al-Jihad.
How much of a role did al-Zawahri play in that?
In the assassination? He was a small role. He transferred some guns. He was still a...
He was still a practicing physician.
Yeah. He was still a young man, but he had been able to organize police officers and
soldiers and stuff like that into his cell. But he wasn't central to the assassination itself.
That's one of my... Of all the turmoil that we've discussed so far in the Middle East,
the first one that really... That is sort of ingrained in me is when Sadat was killed.
So I remember that day very clearly. I was eight years old and I remember it so well.
One of my uncles was one of the generals standing with him when he was shot. As you recall,
everybody but Sadat realized what was happening and they all hit the deck. And Sadat actually
thought it was part of the parade and he actually stood to greet these soldiers who of course were...
I interpret that differently.
I know you did. In the book, you thought he was standing to receive his execution.
Yeah.
My uncle always said that he felt that Sadat actually thought it was part of the parade.
Well, who knows what thoughts were going through his mind, but it was chaotic.
These guys jumped off the truck and it began firing and throwing grenades.
Most of which didn't go off, which was sort of a miracle. A lot more people would have died.
A lot of people would have been killed.
I don't know why everybody on that reviewing platform wasn't dead, but they came for Sadat.
When I looked at the news footage and the stills of that, it looked to me...
The stills are harrowing.
Yeah.
Yeah. He's standing in attention as he's being shot.
It looked to me like he was going to go out unintimidated.
And maybe you might be right.
That would have been part of his character. And of course, he was so vain. He had his new
Italian-made uniform and he didn't want to ruffle the lines of the uniform with a bulletproof vest.
With a bulletproof vest.
He was unprotected in that way.
You talk about how the men that were charged and even not charged, basically the men that were
imprisoned following that were tortured. And that out of that torture came a lot of the
humiliation that ultimately fed what would become the terrorism we all learned about 20 years ago,
for the first time, many of us. What happened to those men? And what did your research uncover
about what that period was like following the assassination of Sadat? It wasn't long after.
I mean, Mubarak would have been immediately instated as president.
I think we don't understand clearly the role of humiliation in human affairs,
but it's very powerful. And going back to the 67 war, the humiliation, I think, gave birth to this
rise in radicalism in Egypt and elsewhere. And torture is deliberate humiliation. And we don't
really know what happened to Zawahiri, although he was probably electrocuted and stripped naked and
humiliated in every possible way that you can imagine. And you can emerge from that totally
broken, or you can emerge full of rage and willing to do anything to exact revenge. And I think that
prison population was divided along those lines. There weren't people that weren't affected by it.
There were people that were either broken or turned into something else. And that something
else became the seeds of Al-Qaeda. Al-Qaeda really began as Zawahiri's organization. It was al-Jahad.
And when they got out, they were on a rampage. And they were killing people as fast as they
could. And they tried to kill the prime minister. They did kill some people. They accidentally
killed this little schoolgirl named Shaima. This is a characteristic
jihad action. So carelessly did they plan this assassination of the prime minister. They just
put the bomb outside a girl's school. And the only person killed was a schoolgirl. It could have been
dozens of them. But the city, Cairo, was infuriated. And there were marches in the street,
and protests. And Zawahiri actually complained because he felt offended that they were subject
to so much abuse. And yet it was pretty clear that Shaima was a step too far for jihad. And
actually, one of the killers lives now in London. He got political asylum because of the fact that
Egypt had a death penalty. And the British would take in anybody who was under a death penalty. So
Shaima's killer is living in London. Still? Last I talked to him, he was still there.
Something else that you point out in the book that I thought was so fascinating,
because it's so obvious once you stated it, but I'd never really understood it, which was,
why couldn't the real resistance take place in Egypt? But you point out that
the topography is not amenable to it. You can't really live away from the Nile.
The moment you get too far off the Nile, you're in the middle of the desert. It's not amenable
to guerrilla warfare. And the military had too strong a hold over the Nile from upper Egypt,
all the way to the Delta and into the Mediterranean Sea. So basically, if they were going to create
an army, they needed to do it outside of Egypt. And it seems that Zawahiri realized that
in the mid 80s, if they're not the early 80s, correct? And is that about the time that he left?
Yeah. He went to Afghanistan first as a medical doctor, answering a call that many heeded. And
then he came back and he affected some Afghan outfits and so on. But I think he was very
stirred by that. When the Soviets invaded, it was an electric alarm in the Muslim world,
an Islamic country was being occupied by a secular government.
And... What was Russia's intention? I guess the Soviet Union's intention.
It's a really good question because you could say that they were trying to beat a path to
the Mediterranean. But it's a long way. It doesn't go directly there. So they might have
done better going through Pakistan. And Pakistan was nominally allied with the United States,
so that might've been problematic. But the Soviet Union was an expansionist power.
It was crazy. If you remember that period, there was a lot of turnover in the leadership.
I think that there was confusion about who's in charge. It didn't make any sense at all.
And the Carter administration, Brzezinski was a national security advisor. And
he saw that as a huge opportunity to give the Soviets their own Vietnam. And essentially,
that's what we did. We supplied the Mujahideen with weapons and then finally with stingers,
which brought down the helicopters. And the Soviets didn't want to go
mano a mano on the ground. And so once they lost that air cover, they were essentially defeated.
Which now brings us to the other half of the Al-Qaeda duo, Osama bin Laden. I think it's
well known by many people who have paid attention to the stories of Al-Qaeda that he came from
unbelievable wealth, unbelievable privilege. But maybe for folks who aren't quite familiar with
his lineage, who was Mohammed bin Laden and why did he have such an empire? What were the
circumstances of Osama bin Laden's upbringing? Mohammed bin Laden came from Yemen. And there
are stories about how he got there. But essentially, I think the most credible is he kind of hitched a
ride on a boat that took him up to Jeddah. And he was a laborer. He was blind in one eye. He was
illiterate. And he put himself to work as a handyman and then did some work for the Americans at that
time working on a Ramco building up the Saudi oil reserves. And there were American companies in
Saudi Arabia who were essentially beginning to build the kingdom itself, the roads, the hotels,
and so on. So it was a good time to be in that business. And Mohammed bin Laden, the king didn't
really trust the Americans. Who was king then? Was it Faisal? No, this was before Faisal.
Did it was Abdul Aziz? Well, I think it was Abdul Aziz when Mohammed bin Laden first got there.
It was the first king of that lineage. And he built a... I don't know if he built the whole
palace, but the king was infirm. And if you remember, in the meeting between
Roosevelt, President Roosevelt and King Abdul Aziz in the Suez Canal, Roosevelt gave him a
wheelchair. And so the king liked having the wheelchair, but he lived upstairs. So he got
Mohammed bin Laden to build him a ramp so the car could drive him upstairs. And so that was
a display of the genius that Mohammed bin Laden had. And then there was a goal that
had been from the very beginning of the kingdom to try to unify the two sides of Saudi Arabia.
The western portion was divided by a mountain range. And on the other side of it
was the Holy Lands, Mecca and Medina and Jeddah, one of the major cities.
But it was cut off by the Sarawat mountain range. And when Faisal became king, he was trying to get
a contractor who would build a road that would unify the kingdom. And the main contractors
looked at this steep cliff face and just, it was daunting. How would you do that? And so
Mohammed bin Laden, this one-eyed illiterate Yemeni laborer, gave a bid to the king. It didn't turn
out to be accurate. And the king accepted. And so the legend is that he pushed a goat over the edge
of the cliff and followed him down this cliff face, marking the path. And that's the path that
this road, I drove down it, I drove up and down it, but it's very windy. And oddly enough,
beset with chimpanzees. So there are a lot of animals along the way, you have to be careful.
But it's a two lane road that goes down, but that was one of the most important roads in history,
because it unified the kingdom and it made Mohammed bin Laden the most famous non-royal
figure in the kingdom, a real hero. And he took advantage of his celebrity, he had a lot of wives.
How about 45 children?
Well, 52, I think. I think bin Laden had 52 brothers and sisters, so maybe 53 total. And
some of the wives he would marry on Friday and divorce on Sunday. So there was that kind of
arrangement. But typically in Saudi Arabia, under Islamic rules, you're awarded four wives.
And the fourth wife is always a little bit of a threat to be discarded. And it was the fourth
wife that was the mother of Osama. And she was Syrian. And she was an Alawite, which is the
sect that Assad, the ruler of Syria, is a part of some minority sect that is thought to be heretical
inside Sunni Islam. So that was by itself a mark against Osama. And his father divorced her.
But he arranged marriage for her and one of his trusted employees, who actually Osama became close
to. And they lived in a little house in Jeddah, off a street that's called Makaroni Street,
because there's a pasta factory nearby. And that's where he grew up. He was always pious. It wasn't a
conversion. He would play soccer and he would wear long pants. But he must have had some influence
on these other kids, because eventually they adopted his long pants strategy. And
even when he was fasting, which he'd fasted two days a week, emulating what he thought the prophet
did. And we're talking about bin Laden as a teenager. Absolutely. He would make sandwiches
for his soccer mates, even though he wasn't eating them. And then they serve cakes and then play
Islamic games, guess the names of the prophet's companions and that sort of thing.
Even though music is frowned upon, instrumental music is frowned upon in Saudi Arabia.
He led this acapella singing and I tried to get, he taped some of them and I tried to find some
tapes of bin Laden singing, but I never could lay my hands on anything like that.
Did you have an insight as to why he was so pious?
Well, I think that if you want to stand out in a very religious society like Saudi Arabia,
you can become less religious or more. And in his environment,
he was not going to become less religious. So I think he always had the idea that there was an
achievement by becoming more of an authority. I mean, you have to bear in mind, his father was
an exceptional figure. He died in an air crash and bin Laden was young when that happened. But
very few people in Saudi Arabia in all of history have achieved the kind of status that Muhammad
bin Laden did, someone who is not in the royal family. I mean, that was exceptional. And I think
that Osama being the son of the fourth wife and then cast out of the inner circle
when the father divorced his mother, he always wanted to distinguish himself. And there was a
hoard of other children around to compete against. And Osama was adventurous.
Some of the other sons were adventurous, but I think one of them died nearby here in Central
Texas. He crashed an ultralight plane in a power line. So it wasn't just Osama that was
an adventurous type. But early on, he was racing horses. He was
he drove very fast, not professionally, but he liked to drive and he was careless. He had wrecks
a lot. But he had his kind of impunity around him. And he liked to go out and camp in the desert by
himself. He was forging an independent identity, even as a very young man. He was drawn more deeply
into Islam in his school. Apparently, there was a I think it was a gym teacher who was in the Muslim
brothers. And he impressed Osama. And so that probably drew him more into Islamic politics.
And he met other people that would be important to him inside what was a secret cell of his Muslim
brothers in Saudi Arabia. Do we know if he was influenced by Saeed Qutb's writings? Oh, yeah.
There's no one who wasn't. You have to start with that. But Saeed Qutb was a big figure. And when
he was in the university, there were lots of discussions about Qutb. And there was another
head of the Muslim brothers in Egypt who had a bit of a contrary view. And sometimes Osama would take
one perspective and sometimes the other, but they were essentially arguing over Qutb. And so he was
a huge figure. He might have met, no, I guess not. Because I would have asked Qutb's brother,
Muhammad, if he had ever met Osama, but I don't think so. So when did Osama first go to Afghanistan?
Well, he... Early 80s, mid 80s? Yeah. Well, the invasion...
invasion 79. So Osama went to Afghanistan. He said he went as soon as he could. There's no
evidence he went there in the first year or two, but he might have been, but there's just no evidence
of it. And he was inspired. He didn't stay long. He came back, but he became a conduit for money.
He was a bundler. And Abdullah Azam was the sort of godfather of the Arab participation in the war
against the Soviets. And bin Laden hooked up with him. And Azam just saw this tall, enigmatic
Saudi with a lot of money and a lot of prestige and just saw him as a cash machine, which he was.
I mean, he played a huge role in raising money for the war against the Soviets.
And that was his main task for the most part until he actually moved to Afghanistan and
decided to form an Arab wing of the war. And it was totally feckless. I mean,
it was worse than feckless. It got in the way. Arab, Afghan warlords complained about it.
They didn't know what they were doing. Essentially, they were just putting young men without any
training at great risk and affecting no real change in the war. But from the perspective of
Saudi Arabia, here was a Saudi, not a prince, but Prince Ling in the sense that he was the son of
the famed Mohammed bin Laden. And the idea that Saudis would actually go out and fight
was really titillating. They weren't allowed to fight. There was a nominal army, but essentially
there was no military tradition. What was the scale of this? So how many Mujahideen fighters
were there? Well, I don't remember the exact number. There were fewer than a hundred, I would
say. But you also have to bear in mind that young Saudi men would sometimes fly up from Saudi
Arabia for a few days. They would be given a gun. They would go out and they'd be not facing the
enemy probably, but they'd go out and shoot up a tree or something. And then they would go home
and say that they'd been fighting in Afghanistan. So it's sort of hard to-
And the US had no forces there, but the CIA was providing weapons to the Mujahideen, correct?
Right. And they were also supplying money. Unfortunately, we landed on this guy named
Hamet Ghul, who was a general in touch with the Afghan warlords. And he would parcel out the money
among the seven warlords, the CIA to call them the seven dwarfs, but he picked the most radical
of them. So the money that came from American taxpayers went to empower people that would later
become allies of the Taliban. Now the Taliban didn't exist yet, correct? The Taliban were kids
in school. The Taliban, the word means students in Arabic and I guess in Urdu. And especially for a
young Afghan boys, and Pakistanis as well, parents didn't have any money. They would be sent off to
these madrasas, many of them on the border between Pakistan and Afghanistan. And especially after the
Soviet invasion, there were a lot of orphans and there were a lot of families that were unable to
provide for their kids. So they send the boys to these madrasas where their main task was to
memorize a Quran in a language Arabic that they didn't speak. And oftentimes these boys would be
abused, especially, you know, warlords and so on would take advantage of them. And really the
Taliban came to power when there was a battle, a personal duel between these two Afghan commanders
over a boy. And that was when Mullah Omar, who had come to be the leader, who was a minor cleric,
got on his motorcycle and began to organize. And that's where the Taliban arose. It's an odd culture
because there's some pictures of these boys, you know, it's beginning as they begin to form into
a military force, but they put on cosmetics. They look very feminine, you know, with eyeshadow and
lipstick and so on. And so there was a... It's hard to characterize it because I can't say that I
understand it, but you know, there was, I think in terms of absenting women so much from society
that these boys were sexualized. And once again, I think humiliation played a role and hard to
quantify, but I think impossible to ignore. And then the Northern Alliance at this point,
as part of the Afghan government? Oh, I don't really know. I mean, the government went through
several iterations and coalitions, but the Northern Alliance would have been opposed to...
The Northern Alliance was a Pashto organization, so they would have been inside the tent of government.
So when did Zawahiri and Bin Laden meet? Nobody knows. You know, I wish I tried really hard to
find that out. And I asked many of Zawahiri's colleagues.
Most people think that they met somewhere along the line in Jeddah where Bin Laden lived, and he
was raising money for the Majjah Dine. And Zawahiri went there ostensibly to practice medicine at this
Muslim Brothers' coalition of doctors and so on. So it's totally plausible. It could have been
shortly after that in Peshawar in Pakistan, where Bin Laden set up shop. So it's one of my great
frustrations that I was never able to chronicle the moment when these two guys ran into each other
and what they thought about each other. So as the Soviets ultimately withdraw, which is what,
89-ish? Yeah. On some level, I think, though probably not justified, Bin Laden feels like a
bit of a hero. Oh, yeah. He glorified himself. Although by all accounts, he really hadn't done
much. He mucked it up, really, is what he did and got a lot of kids killed and just young men.
But in terms of victories, no, he had none. But what he did accomplish was to create a legend
around himself and around the era of Majjah Dine. And it's fascinating to me as a person that's
always been intrigued by religious beliefs, how these legends spread and how they fortified his
image. There was the idea that if you fell in battle, your body wouldn't putrefy. And
the green birds would come circle your corpse. And I remember I asked Jamal Khalifa, who had been
Bin Laden's best friend for much of his life and his brother-in-law and had been in Afghanistan
with Bin Laden. Really? Do you really believe? Oh, absolutely. I saw it with my own eyes.
It can't be true, but it's hard to deny someone who speaks with such conviction. And so that was
the kind of thing that young people, not just in Saudi Arabia, but throughout the Muslim world,
would be hearing the stories of these fighters and their mighty men. And they live in caves and
they fight these technological powers and they win. And they are our Muslim brothers and we
should be doing the same thing. And not only we have to contribute however we can. So in the mosque
and even in shopping centers, there would be cans for contributing to the effort. And so people did.
It was a very popular effort and Bin Laden was very central in his name and his identity became
central to that cause. I call him Saudi's first celebrity because there wasn't a category for
Bin Laden. He wasn't royal. In Saudi Arabia, there is a true of other Muslim countries to
some extent, but there's a prohibition on human forms. You're not supposed to have pictures of
people or animals for that matter. But there are pictures of the king and princes all over the place.
And I remember when I was there, there was a legal battle going on over the Starbucks image.
Because it's like a human form.
Yes. But finally in the courts they decided she's a mermaid. And so she's neither animal nor human.
She's a mythological creature. So Starbucks was allowed to keep their logo. But that's how
seriously it's taken. But here's Bin Laden. He's not nobody. He's Mohammed Bin Laden's son,
but that's not an unusual category. He has 20 something brothers, but there's nobody like him.
He can go to the mosque and make a speech and people would pour out to hear him.
He wasn't charismatic in the traditional sense, but he had a kind of an ethereal air about him.
He was an enigmatic, intriguing, very handsome, very tall, just had a kind of elegance about him.
And that turned out to be a real pain in the ass for the royal family because they weren't used to
having a rival power. Someone who had a voice of authority and Bin Laden even at a very young age
was that person. Now, I guess it would have been the summer of 1990 when Saddam Hussein
invades Kuwait. Right. And although I guess we wouldn't know it at the time, you could argue that
was certainly one of the greatest factors that would ultimately lead to 9 11 though it wasn't,
you can only know that in retrospect. Right. And it's peripheral in that, I mean,
we wouldn't understand it from our point of view because America and other allies rushed in to save
Saudi Arabia. Bin Laden was trying to keep that from happening. And so he went to the minister
of defense and said, I'll take care of this. I'll bring my al Qaeda guys, which were
several dozen maybe. And together with my father's earth moving equipment, we will
enlist the people and we will repel the million man Iraqi army. And the minister of defense just
didn't laugh him out of the office. It wouldn't be polite, but he was not taken seriously.
The first time I heard this story, by the way, was I had the privilege of meeting Prince Turkey,
spending a week with him actually. Really? And he told this story, which was how Bin Laden
was adamant that he based on his victory in Afghanistan, which again, means he believed his
own hype. I think so. Right. Like he, he actually thought that he moved the needle in Afghanistan.
Well, he defeated the Soviet. So what would the Iraqis be by comparison? That was what was going
on in his mind. Right. And the disconnect from reality, but how humiliated he was when
not only was he not the one that was going to defend his country, but these filthy Americans
were going to come in and do this, which included women, Jews, Christians, you know,
and they were going to spend quite a bit of time there. Right. This was, even though it didn't
take long to get Saddam Hussein to retreat, you still had to maintain no fly zones. You still had
to maintain a military presence there. I'll stop you a bit on that because
we didn't need to stay in Saudi Arabia. There were other bases in, you know, Qatar and UAE,
you know, we could have gotten away, but the Saudis had very nice bases. And, but it was
the lingering, I mean, we promised we were going to leave when the war was over.
Yeah. So that's a good point. It was promised that the US would leave. Why did they not?
They were comfortable. You know, and I think probably the royal family felt happier having
an American presence there because the Saudis have always been insecure about their, you know,
they're sitting on this golden egg and, you know, everybody around the world wants a piece of it. So
the Saudis, suddenly they've got the American military there. And that's not the worst thing
in the world in their opinion, but for Bin Laden and for other people, you know, there's a, you
know, there's a saying attributed to the prophet, which was there shall be no two religions in
Saudi Arabia. Well, you know, there are more than two religions and there were at the time of the
prophet, but Bin Laden took this to mean only Sunnis of his particular stripe should live in
the kingdom and everybody else has to be expelled. And it was such a huge thing to have half a
million Americans and other nationalities, most of them not Muslim, living in their country,
protecting how humiliating once again, you know, is it that you have to turn to these other powers?
We're not strong enough to do it ourselves. That, you know, for Bin Laden, that was, you know,
big motivating force. That's when he really sort of turned his attention to America.
And this is where as he and Zawahiri are getting closer, there's a bit of a difference between
them, right? Which is at this point, Zawahiri is still really focused on overthrowing Egypt,
overthrowing what he views as these horribly immoral, corrupt Arab leaders. But Bin Laden
is thinking far beyond that already. Yeah. It wasn't just Zawahiri. I mean,
there were a lot of nationalist groups in the Arab world focused on changing their countries.
And what Bin Laden did was to create a coalition and then redirect them to become an international
terrorist group rather than just be stuck in their nationalist orbits. And Zawahiri was one of those
people. You know, given his druthers, he would have just spent time trying to overthrow the
Egyptian tyrants. And as you characterize, you know, the corrupt, ruthless leader, that was true.
He was right about the nature of the rule, but he was wrong about the solution.
It's funny, I always talk to my parents about this stuff, you know, when Mubarak was like entering
his 573rd term as president, right? And I always said, you know, why, and I would ask naively as
sort of a youngster, I was like, why can't Egypt have an actual democracy? Like, why do these
elections have to be rigged? And my parents for right or wrong, and you have to remember,
my parents have a very different view of Egypt, right? So my mom views Egypt fondly, right? Left
reluctantly, loved Nasser. My father on the other hand couldn't wait to get out, despised Egypt,
never looked back, hates everything about it, and is the classic immigrant who wants to come to the
West and, you know, just hates the corruption, hates the socialism of Nasser, right? Nasser wanted
to take every, wanted to socialize the country. But they both agreed full stop that a country like
Egypt had to be ruled by a strong man. Like their view, again, I don't know if this is true, but
their view was you could never take democratic principles and just lop them into an Egyptian
society. Like it needs an iron fist to rule it, and Mubarak was the least bad option. That was
basically the way they thought of him. What's your view of an autocratic leader of that era? I mean,
do you think that my parents in their assessment were correct of Egypt?
You know, I was wrong about Egypt. I thought it was ready for democracy. And
they had a parliament back during the era of the king, you know, so there was, even though
it was somewhat forgotten, but there had been, you know, deliberation laws were passed, you know,
it had the appearance of being a constitutional monarchy because the king was so indolent
that he couldn't stir himself to do anything. But my analysis was this is a sophisticated country.
People have, it's a country that is never going to dissolve. Like, you know, Iraq may fall apart.
That's not going to happen to Egypt. It thinks of itself as eternal. And so it's always going to be
one thing. It's always going to be the most significant Arab country and they know it. So I
thought, well, yeah, this is, I was all for the- You were very optimistic in 2011. I was.
I wrote a lot of, I read a lot of what you wrote. And I had been affected. I went back to Egypt to
make a speech or a couple of speeches. I spoke at the American university in Cairo, where I used to
teach. And I spoke at the Cairo university where Barack Obama went to make his famous outreach
speech to the Muslim world. And I remember, this was back during the election. This was before the
Arab Spring started. But, and during the primary season when Barack Obama and Hillary Clinton and,
you know, were running for office. And I was asking the kids, if you were an American,
who would you vote for? How many here for Hillary Clinton? All the girls in his job raised their
hand. And how many for Barack Obama? A lot of other people. How many for John McCain, one guy
from the embassy? And so, but they were totally into the idea of democracy. They were excited
by what they were seeing and that there could be revolutionary non-violent change was on their
mind. And one young woman said in this very plaintive voice, what happened to us? I mean,
every Egyptian lives with the weight of history on the shoulders. You look at the pyramids and,
you know, Egypt was the center of civilization. Absolutely. And it really was, you know, I mean,
China, you know, but it was so powerful and so much art and, you know, just, and then a long slide
into, you know, being just a tourist kingdom. So what happened to us? And also such an important
pillar of science too. I remember as a student, as a youngster, I hated school, despised school,
didn't do well in school or anything like that. And ultimately I turned that around, but a lot of
it had to do with something my mom would say to me repeatedly growing up, which is she would say,
because we're Coptic, right? So she would say, you know, we're defendants, we're descendants of
the pharaohs. Like, you know, you are a pharaoh. Science and engineering is in your blood. Your
ancestors built pyramids, you know, and she would just say these things, which when you're a kid,
you kind of start to believe it after a while. It's like, well, you know, maybe mom's right.
Maybe I am smarter than I think I am. But it's also a society that does have a very scientifically
literate population. Like you would think this shouldn't be hard to do. Well, when I was thinking
about that question that she posed to me, that young woman, I thought when I was teaching in
Cairo, Egypt was a part of what we call the developing world. You know, these were countries
like India, South Korea, Singapore, you know, just so many of what these countries that became
the Asian Tigers, you know, they roared past Egypt. And I thought the answer I gave her was
her question made me think of my father and his generation. He had come out of the dust bowl in
Kansas, you know, broken farms, you know, just really poor. And he went on to become a banker
in Dallas, small bank, but he spent seven years in wartime in World War II and Korea. And he and
his generation built the most powerful country and economy in the history of the world. And I said,
it takes a generation. And there are generations like that right now in South Korea, in India,
in places like China that are making their country great. But it can't be done by an individual. And
I think that's my argument against tyranny. It takes a generational commitment. And they have
to have influence. They have to know that they are a part of an enterprise and they can't be
suddenly ruled out. And that is the failure of tyranny, I think, is essentially those kinds of
people that would be transformative for a country or not given the chance to be the kind of leaders
that they could be. What role does religion play in this? And specifically, what role does Islam
play in this? Is there something about Islam in its current level of maturity, which maybe is akin
to Christianity a thousand years ago, that is standing in the way of the progress you speak of?
Well, Islam has many manifestations. And so it's different in Indonesia, for instance,
the largest Muslim country, a far more successful country than Egypt or Saudi Arabia, Turkey also.
But there are manifestations of Islam that are really, really harmful. And
people are encouraged to adopt a kind of submissive attitude. And of course, Islam means
submission. So there's a literalism about it. And then if you don't believe in it,
you have tyrants who will beat you into submission. So there are two very powerful forces. You have
dictatorships that are ruthless, justifying themselves on the basis of religion.
And then you have actual religious texts that urge you to be compliant. And tyrants are
quite adept at using those kinds of instructions. I don't think it's true that you can't have a
modern country or a democracy in an Islamic country. I think Tunisia has been struggling to
do that. And they've had some turmoil recently. But you see that people in Tunisia want to have a
democracy. And they feel like they can be trusted with one. But it's a blight on the Islamic world.
And you have tyrants from Morocco all the way to southern China. And it's something that I hope
that that religion outgrows at some point. Yeah, I sometimes just wonder if it's really a
time scale problem. And we can't think about this in decades. Well, I certainly think that's true
because I've already spent decades hoping for change and just not seeing it blossom.
Egypt is, when I was there, was far more secular, far more accommodating. When I was there,
the Soviets were essentially an occupying force. And the Egyptians really longed for a relationship
with the West. They liked Americans, even though we were essentially persona non grata.
They liked the fact that we horsed around with people. We would talk to the help. We were
Democrats in person as in spirit. We liked being around people, whereas the Russians in the
news agency across the street, they were incredibly insular. And I remember it was odd
because I used to play doubles with one of these Soviet guys. I called us the big powers.
But they would have these parties on Saturday night and you could hear them playing Teresa
Brewer records. Put another nickel in. And they would be sitting on couch with their drinks,
just sitting around glumly. And then around one in the morning, they would spill out into the
street all drunk and singing. It looked awful, but the Egyptians just hated them. And it was a great
time to be an American in Egypt. Whereas after 9-11, it was entirely different. The governments
were friendly, but the people were very upset with America. And it seemed odd to me because, I mean,
you attacked us. A strong motivation for me was to go back to Egypt and find out what happened.
Because I remember it so fondly. I just had a great time living in Egypt and teaching these
young Egyptians and also Palestinians and Jordanians and some Africans. And what's the answer you have?
You talked a little bit about your mom and how she believed in conspiracies and things like that.
I asked this one Egyptian woman who was saying that the Americans did 9-11 to themselves.
I heard that a lot. I said, how can you believe something for which there's absolutely no evidence?
You say that, but there's nothing you can point to that shows that there's any evidence or
motivation. And she said, well, in Egypt, nobody's ever told us the truth. And so we have to try to
imagine for ourselves what it is. So the question we always ask is, who benefits? And in this case,
we think America has been waiting for the opportunity to attack the Arab world. And so
you created this excuse for yourselves. Well, that was her thinking. And that's how conspiracies
nurture themselves on these kinds of rationalizations that float above the world of
truth and evidence. By the same logic, obviously, the CIA killed Kennedy because
had to figure out a way to get into Vietnam. So let's go back to our good friend,
it's the early 90s now. He's been humiliated by his own government who have said thanks,
but no thanks. We're going to have the Americans help us out here. He goes to Sudan of all places.
What happens in Sudan? Why doesn't he end up just settling down in Sudan and
living the rest of his years there? Oh, I wish he had. At 92 to 96,
Al-Qaeda became essentially an agricultural organization in Sudan. Ben Laden in Sudan
probably was the largest landowner. He owned a considerable amount of property. And he would
do jobs for the Sudanese government, build highways and stuff like that. And they would
pay him with land. Whenever I think about Sudan, I went there to try to understand that period in
his life. And I was trying to penetrate Sudanese intelligence. And so I was recruiting some names
of people that I'd been given. And I finally got made some relationships and they took me around
and showed me Ben Laden's house and so on. And this was a time when I had been traveling a lot
and I had injured my back. And it was very painful to take those long airplane flights.
And I took one of those big exercise balls where you had to blow up and you'd have to un-blow it
when you left the country. But in order to ease the pain. And so one day, one of my Sudanese
contacts knocked on my door at a hotel that called itself the Hilton. And Ahmed was the intelligence
agent. And he had this guy with him who was kind of plump. And he had one of those conical Indonesian
hats that Muslims wear. And so come on in and Ahmed was very tired. And he sat on the edge of
my bed and his eyes were bobbing. And I said, Ahmed, just lie down. So he falls asleep and he
leaves me with this al-Qaeda guy. And I got my ball and I give him the office chair that's in the
room. And so, who are you? And he said, well, you can call me Loay. And that was frustrating. But
I started asking him about Ben Laden. He seemed to know everything. And he especially in Sudan,
he knew all about Ben Laden's enterprises. He started raising seeds. He had for a while
a bicycle importing company. Bikes are usually used in Sudan because the roads are all sand.
But he had all these different enterprises and this guy knew everything. But he also knew all
about fighting the Arabs, Mujahideen in Afghanistan. And yet I was at sea. I didn't really know who he
was. And so I went back to the US and started triangulating and I found Mohammed Loay
by Azid whose al-Qaeda name was Abu Rida al-Suri. And he was the guy who took the
notes at the founding of al-Qaeda in May of 1988. It's his handwriting. I thought,
oh, God, I didn't have any idea who I had. And so I flew back to Sudan and he wouldn't see me.
And that was, you know, so then I began to court him, you know, and finally he agreed. And I flew
back and I said, Loay, why didn't you see me last time? It means a lot of trouble to come to
court to him. And he said, well, I didn't know how seriously to take you. The first time we met,
you were sitting on a balloon. That was my first al-Qaeda interview. It was a real triumph.
But those years in Sudan, at least according to Loay, you know, they were kind of wonderful
years for al-Qaeda because they weren't fighting anybody. Bin Laden still had money and he was
generous in handing it out. They would have celebratory dinners and they had soccer teams.
They played, you know, they had their own little league and, you know, people had dormitories and
stuff like that. People got money to get married. They were settling down. It was the US State
Department that decided this can't stand. And so they put pressure on Sudanese government to
expel Bin Laden and the Sudanese government did that. Based on what? He was a potential
terrorist, a funder of terror anyway. What hard evidence did the State Department have at that
time? Really none. There were suspicions. About that time, the CIA had opened up an office on
Bin Laden or a file in any case. This was before the creation of Alec Station? That's where Alec
Station came from, which was really the first sort of off campus in the US station. But it was
off campus and ignored by the CIA. They called the people that worked there the people on the
island of lost toys. You know, there were people that were kind of pushed out of their own
departments and, you know, that was the team, the original team. That team was led by Shore.
Michael Shore. And what is it about him that brought him to lead Alec Station? What was his
conviction? Well, Shore is a loose cannon to put it. Well, certainly today he's about as off the
rails as they come. He wants to shoot Democrats. Yeah. But at the time, what was his conviction
about Al Qaeda? Well, he was right about it. Yeah. You know, he was right that it was,
you know, it was a terrorist organization that could strike America and intended to.
He was right that they had reasons. And I mean, you think you have to give Michael Shore your
credit for seeing into the mind of Bin Laden and his followers and seeing how they looked at the
world. It's so foreign. I mean, when 9-11 happened, the idea that a man in a cave in
Afghanistan would attack America was comical and Shore didn't think so. So he was, you know, he was
not a prophet, but he was an analyst that could look at the tea leaves and see what could actually
happen. And nobody took him seriously. That's another beautiful parallel in your book, right?
We've gone through kind of the history of the Muslim Brotherhood, Al Jihad, Al Qaeda. We haven't
quite got to the point where Al Qaeda and Al Jihad become one entity, which will happen in the late
90s. But as we move to the intelligence side, which is the harder part, I think, to wrap one's
head around. You also have these two parallels between I-49 and Alex Station and these two
personalities between Michael Shoyer and John O'Neill, which are both right, but because of their
remarkable disdain for each other, tragically both let this thing slip. So maybe let's now
shift for a moment and talk a little bit about Alex Station and I-49, the CIA and the FBI,
which by around this point in time, the mid 90s, are starting to kind of pay attention to this
threat. Yeah. You know, when you're talking about it, I reflect on the fact that the siege
was built on this same premise. That, you know, my mission was to write a movie about a woman in
the CIA. That was the assignment. Annette Bening became the woman in the CIA. And then what was the
Soviet Union had fallen? What was the problem? You know, and I realized the CIA had a real life
enemy. It was the FBI. And so that's what the movie's about. So maybe I was already primed to
see it that way, but I'd heard about the antagonism. But as an American, I can't tell
you how disappointed I am in our intelligence agencies and their failure to protect our country.
That's their mission. But they got so caught up in their institutional and personal antagonisms
that they allowed 9-11 to happen. And John O'Neill lived a big life. You know, he was a
flamboyant. You would never think of an FBI agent. I mean, to me, FBI agents were kind of like
Mormons in terms of their dress and their sober demeanor and so on. At least the stereotypes.
John O'Neill wore these Gucci suits and he had these transparent black socks and
kind of almost ballet slippers. And he had an office that he had personally decorated. Most
FBI offices or the furniture is all made in prisons. So all of that goes out. And in comes
this luxurious office. And he always has fresh flowers and he has on his coffee table this book,
Tulips, the flower that drives men wild. I mean, this is not your typical FBI agent. And he set
out when he was assigned to New York station to conquer the city. He wanted to meet everybody of
any importance. And he did. He gave his new secretary a Rolodex with all the names of the
people that he wanted to meet in the next six months. And he went down that list. So he had
tentacles in every part of the city. And he thought of himself as a sheriff. And he,
you know, when the embassy bombings happened, the FBI was given the task of trying to find out,
you know, if it was a crime against America. Yeah. We should probably take a moment to make sure
people understand the difference in the mission of the organizations, right? So the FBI is law
enforcement. Right. So think police, right? They're the top police force. The CIA is intelligence.
Right. And it's easy to see, I suppose, how they can have different priorities. Yeah. So let's use
this example that you're going to talk about, which is the bombing of the American embassy in
Kenya, which was 98. Yeah. Okay. Now 224 people were killed. Yeah. A number of them Americans.
And more than a hundred people were blinded by the flying glass. I mean, it was a horrible,
horrible tragedy. When Americans are killed on foreign soil, is that clearly in the purview of
the FBI? Yes. That is law enforcement. They have to get permission from the country.
Yeah. That they're going into. But in a country like Kenya, which is an ally. Right. This is a
relatively straightforward request that the United States FBI would be able to go in there,
conduct a criminal investigation. Right. And bring to justice people to stand trial in the
United States. Yeah. That is completely within the law. And so that's the way it's supposed to work.
The FBI being the world's premier policing organization, it's supposed to be on the case.
And so as it turned out, there were only six agents in the 50,000 member FBI who spoke Arabic.
And one of them was Ali Sufan, born in Lebanon. And it was during this period of time that
Sufan began reading Al-Qaeda literature and piecing together what was actually going on.
And he's the one who wrote a memo that got to, he got O'Neill's attention that,
you know, that this was probably the mover behind that. And O'Neill had an eye for talent.
And he reached out and just grabbed this young man and brought him in, put him on I-49 squad.
Somebody who would be his eyes and ears in the Arab world.
When did I-49 get formed? I don't know. I'm not sure exactly when it was.
And was it specifically anti-terror? Yeah. That was his goal. But I-49 squad was made up of a
lot of people. At the end of the Soviet Union caused a lot of disruption in our intelligence
agencies because they've been, you know, guys on the I-49 squad, some of them spoke
Russian, some spoke Eastern European languages, Polish and so on. And their mission was to
recruit people that were in the embassies in New York and so on to try to, you know,
and then suddenly all that fell apart. And so there was then the rubble of the absence of the
Soviet Union. I-49 squad was built up of enlisting a lot of people who had no experience in dealing
with the Arab world. There's a very interesting parallel between the transition in both human
capital and military capital. We're going to talk about the USS Cole, but you're very deliberate in
the way that you write about it, the way you write about the bombing, which is you describe
in excruciating detail the strength and might of that ship. And you're deliberately vague about
the skiff that blows it up to demonstrate, I think, the enormous asymmetry that took place.
The point being this USS Cole was an unbelievable warship for traditional warfare. Right.
And yet was defenseless against guerrilla warfare. Right. And that basically means there was kind of
this decade lag after the Cold War where the military industrial complex had not adopted
to what the new warfare was. But I think what you're saying, which is you got six people that
speak Arabic and the entire FBI and the CIA, you know, also has their, you know, tentacles back in
the Cold War. Well, that's basically the same thing, right? It's the human and intellectual
skill set that's for the wrong war. And it seemed like it just took a while to catch up. Unfortunately,
it didn't catch up. Right. I mean, I think that's part of the story. It never did. And the the Cole
bombing was a very telling moment. You know, October 20th, I think. Two weeks before the election.
Yeah. And this is not really bemarked upon in the campaigns, but 19 sailors died.
And the ship, you know, it was a stealth vessel, you know, but there was no hiding it. It was in
the middle of Aiden Harbor in Yemen, which had no business being. I mean, Yemen is far from an ally.
And, you know, the whole area was riddled with, you know, jihadis and, you know, people that were
intent on doing harm to the U.S. And there was this very appealing target. And there was a failed
attempt to bomb it. The little skiff was overloaded with the with explosives and sank. But then then
they pulled it off. And in some ways, it prefigured 9-11. You know, that kind of imbalance of forces
that you were talking about, you know, the, you know, the coming out of the blue, who would who
would ever have expected it, you know, that was common. It's always been common. And, you know,
ports that, you know, little boats would come out and try to sell trinkets and stuff like that,
or deliver food. And so the sailors were used to seeing boats coming toward them. But they had no
idea, you know, they were waving at the people that were about to kill them. What was involved
operationally for Al Qaeda to pull off the embassy bombing in Kenya and then the USS Cole? Because
obviously they were they were prologue to 9-11. They were practice runs. They were never the end
goal. Well, I mean, I guess you could argue Bin Laden. Bin Laden's objective was to draw the US into.
Yeah, I think he thought after the embassy bombings that he that would do the trick. And,
you know, it was infuriating to him that we ignored it. So and then the coal bombing,
same thing. It had to be something more spectacular to get America interested in him.
And the embassy bombing took place after Al Jihad and Al Qaeda had merged.
Yeah. You know, they and some of the operatives, some of the main operatives in the embassy bombings
were the watery's men. So the it was, you know, both of these were, you know, catastrophic events
that for whatever reason, America was not prepared to pay any attention to.
Why do you think that is with all the benefits of 21 years of hindsight? Why is it that
neither George W. Bush nor Al Gore during their entire campaigns, including, right, you know,
including a campaign that included the explosion on the USS Cole? No. Why was this? Why was this
not a priority? If it had happened here would have been a different story, but it happened elsewhere.
And I think that's what, you know, that's one of the reasons Americans were so vulnerable,
is our own hubris and in the sense of isolation that we have historically always felt.
But why wasn't it enough that it had happened abroad? They were still U.S. lives.
Yes, they were. And they should have been counted more dearly, but they weren't. And I, you know,
it's similar with our wars, don't you think? You know, I mean, we have wars, people die.
Sometimes there is a tribute to them in the paper and you see their pictures, but not often.
And so it's the cost of doing business. You know, we are not as...
There's a gap between our role in the world and the people we think we are. And I think this was
especially true before 9-11. The reason Bin Laden attacked us is, you know, he felt surrounded.
He felt America was encircling the Islamic world and they were under threat. And why would we do
that? Well, obviously our goal would be to destroy Islam. And then there was at the same time, this
mandate he had in his mind that Islam has to rise again once it was the superpower. It went all the
way into middle Europe and to southern China. It was an expansionist power and that it should
resume that role. So there was the sense of being threatened by the superpower and the feeling that
Islam should replace it. And that was, I think, the dynamic that was driving him. And nobody in...
I can't say nobody in America, but very few people in America would have imagined that such
preposterous dreams would motivate somebody like Bin Laden and actually be able to put into effect
an attack on this nation that was seemingly invulnerable, that was so distant, how could you
even reach it? And how could you touch it in a way that would make it suffer? Yes, Bin Laden wanted
America to suffer. And he also wanted to humiliate America because I think he understood the power
of humiliation. Now, going back to O'Neill and Scheuer, they agreed on one thing, which was
Osama Bin Laden was a really bad actor and needed to be taken seriously. In fact, you could argue
that no two people believed it more than these two. I think that's fair. One who headed the CIA's
Alak station, which was in charge of anti-terrorism, and the other I-49, which was the FBI's response
to that. But beyond that, they didn't see anything eye to eye. Fundamentally, O'Neill believed that
Bin Laden and other operatives of Al Qaeda should be brought to justice in the court of law in the
United States. Scheuer and colleagues believed these people should be assassinated. An attempt
was made to assassinate Bin Laden in 1998 after the bombing in Kenya. It was a bit of a debacle.
It didn't amount to anything. Why is that? Was it failed intelligence? Well,
one thing, here's the thinking that was going on inside at that time, Clinton White House.
They hit us twice. Well, we should hit them back twice. This is the kind of thing you do
with nation states, parallel responses. We'll bomb training camps in Afghanistan, and we'll hit
this factory in Khartoum that we think is manufacturing poison chemicals for Al Qaeda.
Actually, it was making veterinary medicines, and it was one of the main factories in the whole
country, a very poor country. We killed a night watchman. It just had nothing to do with any of it.
We bombed the camps in Afghanistan. Fingers crossed Bin Laden would be there. Well, he wasn't.
He was on the road to go there and then changed his mind, and they went somewhere else. So,
it might have happened, but it didn't. But the point was, look what we can do. You hit us,
we'll hit you back. Well, that's exactly what Bin Laden wanted. The failure of imagination that
you referenced, there was a failure of imagination, but it was coupled with
prejudicial ideas about who we're dealing with and a tremendous absence of knowledge about the
cultures that our adversaries came from. So, we just didn't understand, and we couldn't understand
their language. We didn't know what was going on. And so, yeah, it is not a surprise that our
imaginations didn't rise to the task because we didn't know who we're dealing with, and we could
not figure them out, nor did we really spend very much time worrying about it. Let's just deal with
them as if it was Russia that did this, and we'll strike them back proportionally. And
Clinton did have the idea, he spoke to one of his military commanders about sending in ninjas,
dropped, rappelled down from Cobra helicopters, and that sure surprised Bin Laden. And
on balance, it wasn't a bad idea. That was probably the right thing to do, go directly in there.
But we were still in the remote control phase of our imperial rule. And
I think that that's partly why we didn't take the embassy bombings seriously.
That's not the way we do things. We send drones over, or we send F-16s, or we send bombers over,
and we do it remotely, and we don't dirty our hands, we don't bloody our hands.
And so I think people just thought it would be a nuisance, and that we would take care of it.
So as the coal, as the planning for the coal bombing is underway, the planning for 9-11 is
also underway. These were parallel, not serial operations. Two men come to the United States,
January 15, 2000. Who are they? These men are Khalil al-Midhar and Nawaf al-Hazmi.
Saudis. There's two Saudi guys. They scarcely speak any English at all.
They had been in a meeting in Kuala Lumpur with the coal bombers. And so the coal bombers went off to
do their thing, and then they fly, first of all, to Thailand, and then they fly into LA.
And so how can they do anything? You know, they're in a country they don't understand.
They don't speak English. You know, their mission is to go train as pilots, but they would not
qualify because they couldn't even speak enough English to go into a class. So this is the first
mystery. What are they doing here? And as it happens, that very day that they arrive, there is a
Saudi figure named Bayoumi, Omar Bayoumi, who happens to be at the Saudi consulate in LA,
talking to the Minister of Religious Affairs. That's kind of significant because, you know,
they are the, as a result of the Mecca catastrophe, Saudi put, Saudis put
these imams and consulates all over the place, and they had a lot of authority. So anyway,
Omar Bayoumi leaves the Saudi consulate, and he goes to a Middle Eastern restaurant,
where he happens to overhear these two guys speaking in a Saudi accent. It's, according to him,
and the Saudi government, a total coincidence. Do you believe that? No, not at all. No, I think,
in, you know, the families of the victims of 9-11 are suing the Saudi government, trying to get
more information about the people that are involved in that. And Bayoumi is one of the
people that they have on their list of people to talk to. But Bayoumi is such a generous fellow
that he offers to help them find a housing in San Diego, where he has a place. And so he fronts
them some money. He sets them up in San Diego. Bayoumi and other people in his circle begin
receiving money from the wife of the Saudi ambassador in Washington, DC, ostensibly for
an operation for the wife or, you know, these, you know, but it's significant thousands and
thousands of dollars. And Bayoumi takes these two guys, Nawaf al-Hazmi and Midhar, to meet a cleric
in this Saudi mosque in San Diego, who is Anwar al-Alaki, who later becomes, you know,
the voice of radical Islam. We finally killed him in Yemen. But whether he was an al-Qaeda connection
has never been established, but wouldn't it make sense, you know, in any case.
And what is your thought on the money that was coming directly from the wife of the Saudi
ambassador? The ambassador Bandar was very close to the, you know, the Bush White House. He was,
he was sort of the dean of the diplomatic establishment. So there was a plausibility
thing. How, you know, would you really see such a thing happening from the ambassador himself?
But it stands that, you know, these Saudis were getting money sent to them in San Diego by Bandar's wife.
And now his daughter is the ambassador of the U.S. So, you know, that has never been, I think,
satisfactorily accounted for. Another thing that's going on, you know, they arrived in January 15th,
and in March the CIA finds out that they're in the U.S. Probably, you know, Prince Turkey, you know,
Prince Turkey told me that he had informed the chief of station in Riyadh, the CIA man in Riyadh
about that. So that's probably where it came from. So in March, this is 21 months before 9-11,
almost two years. The CIA knows that Al Qaeda is in America. And this is at a time when they're,
they say their hair's on fire about, you know, about Al Qaeda, that we're under threat,
they're going to the White House. And yet they know that Al Qaeda is in San Diego. And moreover,
Midhar's wife is in Yemen. She comes from a very Al Qaeda, jihadi family. Her name is
Hoda Al Hada. And the Al Hada household, because it's such a hotspot, we've got wires on the phone.
We've got the phone. Yeah. So I think it's on-
The CIA is listening to the phone calls.
14 occasions the NSA is getting calls to this Al Qaeda house in Yemen from San Diego.
Do you have to draw a picture? You know. What's more disturbing than this
is that in October, after the coal bombing, when Ali Sufan is questioning
Cuso and the other suspects, he asks specifically, well, he kind of, I think through that questioning
comes to learn of the meeting that took place in Malaysia. And asks explicitly on at least
three occasions for information from the CIA about these two guys in the US. And he is stonewalled.
It's not casual either. A request like that goes to the director of the FBI who sends
a letter to his counterpart, the director of the CIA, formally requesting information
about, in this case, this meeting in Kuala Lumpur. Do you know anything about it? No,
is the answer. No information. In fact, the CIA actually covered the meeting. They
recruited the Malaysian police to take photographs and stuff like that. So they got pictures of the
participants and they hide this information from the FBI. And going back to the mission
of each of these agencies, the story about the siege was who was fighting. They were fighting
over who had control over terrorism in the United States. And in real life, the FBI won that battle.
So they have the authority. The CIA is not supposed to operate in our country, but the FBI
has the authority, has a warrant on Al-Qaeda and bin Laden and all his followers.
So how is this not, in the clearest legal sense, obstruction of justice?
It is obstruction of justice. The CIA obstructed justice when Ali Safan was investigating the
coal bombing. They hid information about the planning and they hid information about the
Kuala Lumpur meeting. This is a murder investigation. 19 sailors.
So at this point, Michael Shurer is gone, correct? He has been relieved of his duties at
Alex station. What led to that? Well, he was relentless in pressing
the agency and trying to get rid of bin Laden. There was a moment where he thought bin Laden
might be at one of the camps in Afghanistan. And he said, and the reason that he might be there
is that a lot of the royal family from the UAE was coming to do a buster hunting,
this endangered bird that is popular. And so let's bomb the camp and we'll kill all the princes,
but we might get bin Laden. Well, that was the kind of thinking that Michael Shurer was capable of.
Yeah, which again, the UAE is an ally. I mean, it would be hard to fathom that.
Yeah. And we were just at that moment selling them a whole fleet of F-16s. So there was a
financial investment in not doing that as well in addition to the absurdity of the scene. But
that's the kind of thing that Shurer would propose. So who took over Alex station when Shurer was
terminated? The woman that took over the station
is an FBI view, a villain, but she and Shurer later married. And so it was an office romance.
It was an extension of Shurer anyway. Now, one of the things that's interesting about
Alex station is it had a number of I-49 agents that sat within it physically. So these are
FBI agents that are sitting inside Alex station, but they were kind of handcuffed because they were
privy to the information that the CIA had, but they weren't permitted to share it with their
colleagues at FBI. One of the things that struck me as odd is that none of them broke rank, right?
Like you see in Edward Snowden, you know, a decade later, who, you know, goes completely rogue and
decides for right or wrong, this is his conviction. This is what he's going to do about it. This is in
the life. This isn't the best interest of American lives. And yet amazingly, none of the FBI agents
sitting inside of Alex station who presumably saw what was happening, didn't think I'm willing to
jeopardize my job here and maybe face criminal charges to get information because they saw the
wires coming in. They saw the requests repeatedly from the FBI, from Sufan saying, who are these
people? What happened in Malaysia? Why is money leaving to go to these people? Why is this money
coming to the United States? I mean, did you ever get an insight into why the FBI people inside
Alex station were, were, were muzzled? You know, there was a, it was more of a legal
conceit. They called the wall. And the idea was that information should not travel from the
intelligence world into the criminal one and vice versa. There was really no law. There was,
people thought it was a law, but there was a, it was a custom and an FBI had its own intelligence
division. And so it was part of the, just is like grand jury testimony. You know, it's not supposed,
it's supposed to be sealed, you know, it's kept, kept pure and secret. But
when you're faced with something like that, the only alternative, you know, is to break the law.
And there can be very serious consequences and it's a lonely thing to do. But that's really the
only thing you can do. What I can tell you is how broken those people are by what happened.
They knew what was going to, they knew what was underway and they lost their boss. You know,
John O'Neill died as a consequence of their reticence to say anything. I'm not holding them
responsible for 9-11, but I do hold the CIA responsible for it. If they had been transparent
with the FBI, if they had said, we have these Aikaida members in America, the FBI had the authority,
they had the warrant, they had everything. They could follow them. They could tape them. They could,
you know, clone their computers and they could arrest them. There were all these things that
they could do, but they were kept in the dark. And of course, the question is why? And I've asked,
you know, I- How many people in the CIA were you able to interview?
Uh, they were actually working in the CIA. There was a moment where I think it's
time has passed enough that I can say this. I wrote an article about Iman Elzawari for The
New Yorker and the CIA asked to talk to me. And so I was picked up by an FBI agent who worked at
the CIA and driven to CIA headquarters and gone up the seventh floor and there was a conference
room and I met with Alex Station. They were about 20 something people there. And the meeting started
off in Arabic. And I said, Kula hah dah hai na bakadam aarvi? You know, everybody here speaks
Arabic and they had learned it in the last couple of years. I was impressed by that. But I was not
impressed with their intelligence. You know, I was a reporter on the ground, you know, going
around talking to people and I wasn't trying to hide information from the CIA. I published it.
You know, it's not what I find out. I want people to know. So I didn't feel like I was betraying
sources or anything like that by talking to the CIA. What I did want was a little bit of information
from them in return. And what they confided was that Bin Laden was alive. At that time, there was
a lot of talk. What year was that? I'm guessing it was 2003. It might have been earlier than that
because I went to Egypt in, I guess in the fall. It must have been 2002. Bin Laden was keeping his
head down. And so, you know, there was a lot of talk that maybe we got him or that he was sick,
you know. But, you know, the intelligence agencies, at least my experience with American
intelligence agencies, is that they tend to trust information that has been stolen. In other words,
you know, wiretaps, you know, stuff that people are saying not knowing supposedly that they're
being listened to. Reporters have a different posture. We go out and talk to people and ask
them what they're up to and why and, you know, where'd you come from. And, you know, those
sorts of things you don't normally get on transcripts. And so they apparently taped my
phone. You know, one of my sources said he read a conversation I had, came in on his laptop at the
agency. It was a conversation I'd had with Zawahiri's cousin. And so the legal authority they had to
tap your phone was because of who you were speaking to? You're not supposed to tap Americans.
So that was, if that had been a tap on my line, then, you know, if I were talking to, you know,
as I had been to Zawahiri's cousin, they should say individual A, you know. And so I'm not
identified. But, you know, obviously I was. And I thought at the time, oh, those Egyptians, you
know, they're on top of, you know, Zawahiri's cousin. They sent this as a gift to the CIA.
And the, but then I, you know, then I a couple of years later learned, you know, that
we had been, you know, they had, the American intelligence had been taping Americans and some
reporters. And I obviously, I had had a visit from, there's a terrorism squad, even in Austin.
And they, you know, a couple of guys came over, they wanted to talk to me. And I thought they
wanted advice because I had talked to FBI agents before and give them a little background on
Al Qaeda. And I thought that's what this was. And one of them was from the FDA, but he was on the
terrorism squad and he walked into my office and there are all these books on Al Qaeda and there's,
you know, a whiteboard full of Arabic names. And, you know, he was terrified. His hands were
trembling. And what they wanted to know was about a call that I had made to England. And
it was a 44201 number, you know, and it just sounded like business number in London.
And I said, surely you know who it is. But I looked on my rolodex and it was a barrister
who represented some jihadis. And it turned out, you know, then they said, did you know a person
named Caroline Wright, who's my daughter, she was in college. And they thought it was Caroline
calling this barrister to get to these jihadis. And I thought, this is our intelligence. You know,
it was, you know, and then as I started thinking about it, it was like, wait a minute,
how do you know it's my line? How do you know that, you know, that Caroline would, how do you
know about Caroline at all? You know, and so you wouldn't have gotten that if you hadn't been
listening to the call. And I was really outraged as an American citizen, but also shocked by the
level of incompetence that I mean, I was grateful they came to clear it up. I have to say they at
least did that. But the presumptions that they had were so absurd that I could see how we got
ourselves into this fix. The two hijackers, the future hijackers in San Diego, the FBI,
their line on what was going on is the CIA knew they couldn't operate in America,
but the Saudis could. And so they struck a deal with the Saudis to try to follow these
guys and turn them. Here they are in our clutches, we have an opportunity to penetrate Al Qaeda,
which is not something the CIA had been able to do. And all the young men from all over the world
were simply walking into the camps and becoming Al Qaeda members. But they thought that the Saudis
would do them that favor. And then the two hijackers disappeared and the CIA lost them.
And it was then in August of 2001, just a couple of weeks before 9-11, that the CIA went to the FBI
to ask them to find these guys that they had lost. And it was too late. The FBI never did find them.
So Muhammad Ata is an interesting character.
Of all the 9-11 hijackers, obviously he was the senior figure, but he was also
such an interesting and unusual character. It's hard to make sense of his motivation,
an educated man, a pious man. But one of the things I've always struggled with is,
what is it that these guys believed was going to happen? You go back to the story about the
birds circling and the flesh not rotting. Do you believe every one of those 19 men believed they
would be greeted in paradise by virgins? Do you think they literally believe that?
I think so. It may have not been the preponderant motive for them.
Although martyrdom seems to be the highest motivation, right?
Martyrdom, even if you're not going to paradise and getting the virgins and all of that,
Martyrdom has its appeal, especially for young men who have really little opportunity to make a
dent in the world. And here you can go off and change history. All you have to do is sacrifice
your life. So the martyrdom might be the carrot, but it might not be. It might just be that they
wanted to prove a point and they wanted to go down in history and they have.
You talk about how terrorist organizations were allowed to legally operate inside of Germany,
provided that they were foreign and not domestic terrorist organizations.
It's almost an unfathomable statement. Can you help make sense of that?
Well, Germany has a tortured history and its problems with fanaticism on German soil have
historically been a corrective. So you cannot very easily be a fascist in Germany now.
There are fascists in Germany, but it's sort of an underground thing.
Other countries, there's this sense in Germany of implicit neutrality. We don't take positions on
things like that. And so if you're opposed to your government and you flee to Germany for asylum,
what you do in relation to your home country is your business, not ours. Just don't screw
around with our country. It's not just Germany. Europe was slow to awaken to the threat to their
own countries, in part because in England, terrorists were actually brought into England
because they were escaping the death penalty in Egypt and they still live with subsidized rent
and such a thing. In London, one of my sources is a driving instructor in London and he killed this
little girl, Shema, in Egypt in his attempt to kill the prime minister. That kind of mentality
came about because people just didn't feel threatened. And I think to some extent that
explains why these terror groups were allowed to grow up inside the borders, especially of England
and Germany and Spain as well. When did Ata come to the United States? I don't remember the exact
month. His cohorts had begun to assemble. And so I think he was one of the last to arrive. He was in
Spain coordinating with some of the Spanish Al-Qaeda guys. To what end, we're not really sure.
But then he flew into America. Of course, unlike the other guys, his English was pretty good.
So his English is good. He's one of the four pilots.
How were they coordinating inside the US? What did they communicate by? Did they speak on cell
phones? Did they use email? How did these 19 guys organized in four groups communicate?
Well, they did use email and cell phones. And what you have to understand,
they weren't really hiding. The CIA knew that Al-Qaeda was present. And the Al-Qaeda guys didn't
know the CIA knew that. So ostensibly, they just lived openly. They had driver's licenses and
stuff in their own names. Eventually, the FBI would find that they were listed in the San Diego
phone directory. So they weren't in hiding. They didn't feel threatened. And they took
advantage of that freedom. So after the election,
Richard Clark, who's also a very important figure in your book, gets a demotion.
Why is that? That was not clear to me in the book.
Well, he had been under Clinton, the terrorism czar. And when the Bush administration came in,
they didn't see the need for that. And their view was about the big picture. We're talking about
China and Russia. And so the people in their NSA and Secretary of State and Condi Rice and so on,
they came from the old school. Clark told me that when he talked to Condi Rice to try to
alert her to the danger of Al-Qaeda, he had the feeling she'd never heard of the organization.
And it's hard to imagine that she didn't hear of it at all, but she clearly didn't take it
seriously enough to take his counsel. And so he was pushed down the ranks. And Bush was,
you know, I don't think he took it seriously until the Saudis threatened to break off relations with
the US because of Israel. And that woke him up. He was very concerned about that. But then there was
a CIA memo. I think it was dated August 6, 2001. This is the presidential daily brief. Yeah.
That was titled, Al-Qaeda set to attack in the US. Right. And so it couldn't have been clearer.
And this was about the same time the CIA lost those guys in San Diego. So
suddenly things are moving and they're out of the CIA's control.
Now during the 9-11 commission, when Condi Rice was asked about that memo, August 6th,
right? So five weeks before 9-11, the president of the United States gets a briefing
that says Al-Qaeda is going to strike on US soil. And of course, when Congress questioned her,
it was sort of, why was this not taken seriously? Her response was, if I recall, something akin to
this was dated. There was nothing new in here. This was speculative. There was no real intelligence.
Am I remembering that correctly? Yeah. Such dodges were characteristic of a lot of the
people involved in this massive intelligence failure. You know, I've asked people in the CIA,
you know, people in high authority about those hijackers, for instance. And no, we didn't really
know. I mean, it was just incompetence, actually. There were memos that we didn't read and, you
know, it was in, yes, it was in the memos, but it never really came to the attention of people in
authority. And in other words, there's a fog, pixie dust thrown in your eyes, whereas nothing could
be more incendiary to very same people that are ringing the alarm bell saying Al-Qaeda is on the
warpath and is coming our way. And then they say, well, you know, we didn't, we weren't really paying
attention to that. And the memo never came to our attention. Bullshit. You know, this was, you know,
CIA was well aware by this time, you know, there was the embassy bombers, there was a coal bombing.
There was, and then, you know, they become aware that Al-Qaeda is in America now. So
they're moving onto our soil. And that's the origin of that particular memo is that
CIA knows they're here. And so they're obviously they're going to do an attack here.
Now, O'Neill said this to Condoleezza Rice before he was fired, forced to resign. And
she seemed to indicate that this was not a high priority because it, I think in the, in the words
at least used in the, in the dramatized version of this, this was swatting flies, right? This was
what? We've got a couple of Al-Qaeda guys in this country. That's not strategic. That's not relevant.
One of the things that's just so mind boggling to me about this story is how,
is how, yeah, incompetence is, I mean, this is obviously a big part of this, but it's the
personality conflicts that got in the way. I mean, another character in this story,
whose role is really quite sad is Barbara Bodine, then ambassador in Yemen, who did not get along
with John O'Neill, which I guess you can't fault her for that. I can, John O'Neill struck me just
from everything I've read about him. And I know you did not have the ability to interview him,
but you're doing, your reporting is based on interviews with everyone who knew him.
He struck me as a love or hate guy. Is that a safe, a safe, polarizing thing? Yeah. You either
absolutely loved this guy or you absolutely hated this guy, but I never got the impression that
anybody wouldn't think he was competent. Yeah. Barbara Bodine seemed to have a thing about
men and guns. And she was offended that the FBI came to Yemen with a bunch of armaments. And
of course it was dangerous. And, and O'Neill was trying to take care of his people and they were
authorized to carry weapons, but she was offended and made them give up their long guns.
And she kicked him out of Yemen. She did. Which is another real setback in the investigation
at the time. It could be, I mean, taking her side, I'm sure she perceived O'Neill as a swaggering
misogynist and, you know, and she wasn't going to have any of that. And she felt that she had a
role as the ambassador cultivate a better relationship with the Yemenis. And here he was
coming in, kicking up all this dust, alienating everybody with his American big footing.
And so enough of this, you know, I can do without him. And it was a terrible blow for O'Neill. And I
think, you know, that in some ways led to his sort of disgrace at the end where he had to go to a
retirement conference and he took some papers out of the office he shouldn't have taken, but he was
doing work in Florida at this retirement conference and then left his briefcase in the
conference room and somebody took it. He got it back. And, you know, the only thing it was taken
was like a silver cigar cutter. And the papers were still in there, but, you know, he turned
himself in and he had a lot of enemies inside the FBI and they were not going to miss the opportunity
to use this to get rid of him. Now, he had many job opportunities after he left the FBI.
One of them was a job in the government, again, in the White House, correct? Or at least that
was something that Dick Clark hoped he would take. It's not clear that he would have been on it.
Yeah. Dick wanted him to replace him. He couldn't think of a better person. And
O'Neill had lived above his means for many years. I don't know how he got away with it.
But he was deeply in debt. And I think he was also deeply wounded by his experience with
government. And so he wanted to get out and make some money. And there was money to be made for
him. With his experience, the job that he settled on was head of security at the World Trade Center.
And I know that. And listen, when this whole adventure started for me by reading obituaries
that were streaming online right after 9-11, I was trying to find a way into the story,
something that would humanize it. And I thought I was looking for people who died in 9-11 and see if
I could find a narrative. And on the Washington Post site, about six days after 9-11, I think,
was this obituary of John O'Neill, FBI head of counterterrorism.
Recently retired, been on the job for a month.
It was more than that. It's spelled out that he had taken classified information out of the office.
And I thought I didn't know if he was a hero or a goat, but his life could tell us something about
why we failed. He was the head of counterterrorism in New York. He's the guy that had the warrant on
Bin Laden. But instead of getting Bin Laden, Bin Laden got him. That was the way I looked at it.
It's one of those things, Lawrence, where if this weren't a true story,
if you had written The Looming Tower as a fiction, I don't know that the editors would have let you
end it the way you did. I don't think they would have let you have John O'Neill actually die inside
the World Trade Center a month after being forced to resign from the FBI because he was
kicked out at the shins and not able to do his job.
I thought when I read that, Obed, that it was a supreme irony, but I don't see it that way. Now,
he told his colleagues, some of them said to him, John, you'll be safe now because they already hit
the Trade Center because they've been a bombing. And he said, no, they'll come back to finish the
job. So I think he instinctively put himself at ground zero. In that sense, I see it as a Greek
tragedy. He in some ways anticipated his fate and went to meet it. He actually
left the tower that day and went back inside to rescue people.
Yeah, yeah, that's the thing. He walked back into the building, as many heroes did.
Yeah.
If September 11th took place on December 11th, if the mission were postponed two months,
do you think that would have been enough time for the FBI to figure it out? How close was the FBI
to doing this despite the incompetence of the CIA, if not the outright negligence of the CIA?
Well, it's hard to calculate how much they could have done, but there's no reason to think that
they couldn't have once alerted in August and given three or four months to work it out,
no reason to think that they couldn't have tracked down the communications if the American intelligence
community had been helpful to them.
Because remember, the other thing that I always feel like they were so close to cracking was
once they had the list, the CIA list of suspected Al-Qaeda operatives and the list of Arabs in
flight schools and they crossed that list, that was just a matter of time.
It seems like, and there were several cases, like you mentioned, the flight schools in Arizona and
Minnesota, there were these weird things where these Arab would-be pilots who wanted to learn
how to fly but not how to land. Those were really puzzling things. Now, of course, nothing like this
had ever happened before. It seems crazy, but on the other hand, it had been envisioned.
But you'd think all it would have taken would have been a handful of these guys show up on a
cross list and that manifest gets sent to TSA or whatever. Was TSA TSA back then? I don't know
what it was called. But there would have been a watch list that said, because as you said,
these guys are getting on airplanes with their real names. They had real ID.
Well, also, one of the FBI agents in Phoenix actually wrote, I think this was a guy that did
that. They could envision crashing into buildings. That's spookily prescient. And then there was
secret. The 9-11 families had sued to get the 28 pages that had been suppressed in the 9-11 report,
and we finally got them, although there's still some redaction in it. And in there, you see
Saudis on airplanes doing trial runs, getting the ticket in the first class compartment
and walking into the cockpit. And oh, I thought this was a bathroom. And then one of them was
so provocative in his actions that they actually landed the plane to stop the flight, put down to
nearest airport, and had somebody come out and interrogate two, I think, Saudis. And they said,
no, we're going to a party at the Saudi embassy. And they gave them a number in the Saudi embassy
in Washington. Well, that's damning. And no wonder it was suppressed if you're trying to
protect your relationship with Saudi Arabia. But it hasn't been explained. But these were clearly
trial runs. And the CIA knew about them. That's why that was in the 9-11 report. This is intelligence
that had been surfaced. So there was intelligence around that something was cooking. And even the
CIA, George Tenet was telling the White House, they're going to attack us. They're coming for us.
That's the thing with Tenet. I can't understand from your book. I got to be honest with you. I'm
really conflicted and confused. On the one hand, he seems to be in lockstep with Richard Clark
in saying this is a big deal. And he seems incredibly frustrated with the Bush administration
that they're not taking this more seriously. And he seems to believe that this is almost something
they're doing out of spite. Whatever the previous president did, we're absolutely going to do the
opposite. But at the same time, I think, how is it then that under your watch, your organization
was so derelict? He's never really been able to produce an incredible answer. And I've tried to
imagine what was going through his mind. If it's the case that he did seriously believe that Al
Qaeda was a threat and that he had been striking a deal with the Saudis, it was a risky deal,
but one that had the potential for a huge payoff. And then it gets out of control. And just as it's
getting out of control, he is dramatically shouting, pay attention, Al Qaeda is on the war path.
So it's sort of like the arsonist who, as the house catches on fire, is actually the one that
calls the firefighter. Yeah, I think that's a fair comparison. I don't know what's going through. I
want to be fair to him. But he were not able to interview him? He wouldn't talk to me. And he's
never really dealt seriously with this subject. It's not just George Tenet, but he's responsible.
He was the person who oversaw the American intelligence community in one of his greatest
catastrophes in our history. And not that it's been so sterling since then, but it was
an unbelievable failure. And there are so many points. Yes, it's true Monday morning
quarterbacking and all of that. But I think I'm being fair enough to say the CIA knew what was
going on. They hid the information from the FBI. Had the CIA been transparent and worked in tandem
with the FBI, the 9-11 would not have happened. I think the facts support that. And so there's
never been accountability for this, not any. And in fact, George Tenet got the Medal of Freedom and
all these other things, accolades. I'm not saying that he belongs in prison, although
I can understand why people might say that. But he should be held accountable, as should everybody
in authority at that agency. So I wanted to ask you about that, which is given all that we know
today, has anyone inside the CIA been charged with a criminal offense for obstruction of justice?
No, no, they were promoted. People that knew about this were given plum assignments. And
I asked one of the directors about, has anybody been held accountable? And he said, well, yes.
I've held people accountable. Well, who? For what? And he wouldn't specify, but there was no evidence
of it. And I asked about, it was a question about torture and the two hijackers in San Diego,
and maybe one other thing. And I said, this is a history of the CIA, not all under your reign,
but partly, has anybody been held accountable? And he quarreled with some of my facts
without actually saying that they were wrong. And then I said, so in other words, nobody's been
held accountable. And then he said, no, that's not true. I've held people accountable myself.
But I don't know how to credit that. The most conspicuous people got promotions.
Yeah. I mean, let's just think about it through the lens of the family members of 9-11. So we had
a 9-11 commission. What came of that for the family members?
Well, it was frustrating for the family members. It was presented as being the whole truth and
nothing but the truth. And then it came out that there were parts of the 9-11 commission that were
suppressed at the 28 pages, most notably. And of course, a lot of pages were redacted.
And the 28 pages that were suppressed dealt primarily with the Saudis.
The Saudis.
Because again, I remember even at the time, one of the things that was odd was the Saudis
being given air clearance to leave. How do you make sense of this? This is one that I have a hard
time wrapping my head around, which is why would the Saudis have, why would anybody inside of Saudi
Arabia had wanted this? I'm talking about not obviously Al-Qaeda, but I'm talking about anyone
within the royal family, anyone within the Saudi intelligence community. I mean, there's no doubt
to me that Prince Turkey was a good guy. This is a guy who I can't imagine there was any part of
him that would want to see bin Laden and his organization succeed. So what's the explanation
for how any of the quote unquote Saudi good guys could have stood by and knowingly watched this
happen or worse supported it financially or otherwise?
If we think about these things as an intelligence analyst, just imagine, here are the facts.
So where are the Saudis in this and why are they behaving like this? I think that the Saudis thought,
for one thing, they gave us the information that Al-Qaeda is in America. Perhaps if this FBI's
scenario is correct, that the CIA thought that they could turn these guys, they work out a deal
with the Saudis where they're going to run these people. They'll use them as potential recruits.
And they fund the bayoumis and other people that are sort of their supervisors. So they give them
money to keep the operation going. And there is a certain ambition on the part of the Saudis to
show what a great job they can do. And also, these are Saudis that are in America. And so they want
to try to keep control of them. So I can envision that. But does that explain how they would actually
how the ambassador's wife would send money to know? It would explain if Bayoumi, for instance,
is a Saudi intelligence operative and his job is to oversee these guys.
Oversee them to prevent them from attacking on US soil?
Oversee to penetrate their cell and understand what's going on.
I see. And I don't know if the Saudis knew that they were planning to fly planes into buildings,
but they were up to something. So what could it be?
I see. So that's a more plausible explanation, which is that, again, their failure of imagination
was they had no idea that these Saudi kids could accomplish something as grand.
Especially given that pair. It's hard to imagine that they would take them that seriously.
On the other hand, there they were.
I see. This makes a bit more sense. So going back to my analogy,
they're not really acting as an arsonist. They're somebody who accidentally sets the house on fire,
but then realizes, oh, I just set the house on fire. I better call. But I also better make sure
I'm nowhere near this fire to get here. I'm not going to stick around to say I was doing this and
that. One always hopes for whistleblowers and somebody to come clear of the air and their
documents to surface that, and none of that has happened. So far, I may be wrong about all this.
It could be simply incompetence, which explains so many things. But there were people like those
FBI guys. They knew something was going on and they were alarmed. They were also shut down when
they tried to air their concern. So obviously, it was important enough. Dozens of people in the CIA,
at high levels, read these memos. So I long for the day when somebody comes up and says,
this is what actually happened. But it hadn't happened so far in 20 years. And I think that
the longing of the CIA is to bury it in institutional memory and have it never surface.
Richard Clark apologized to the family members of the 9-11 victims. How many other government
officials apologized publicly? I don't know of any. There was an awful lot of scolding going on.
But what made Dick Clark's statement so cathartic is he took responsibility. Nobody else did that.
I always found it amazing that he became sort of a target of partisan hit jobs. Yeah, I know.
Which is, I mean, I've read quite a bit about him. I obviously never had the privilege of meeting him,
but never came across to me as a partisan guy, actually. I actually served presidents of both
administrations. Yeah, I served George H.W. Bush before Clinton. I mean, I was on Sean Hannity's
show one time and it seemed like one of the main things he wanted to do is attack Dick Clark.
I wasn't prepared for it at all. And I mentioned that incident where he said that
Condi had dismissed Al Qaeda and Hannity went off on Dick Clark. And I said, but
he's been a wonderful public servant. I mean, you may think ill of him, but he's a master bureaucrat.
And he was one of the ones that was ringing the alarm about Al Qaeda. I don't know.
We live in a culture that's just full of people that like to attack others. But Dick Clark,
you can be puzzled over some of his actions, like he was the one who authorized the flights for the
Saudis to leave the U.S. And I'm sure that he envisioned retaliatory attacks on members of the
Saudi royal family or Bin Laden's family who were present here. And that's totally plausible. But
was it a wise thing to do? I don't know. What were the days after 9-11 like for Ali Sufon?
Oh, God.
It's hard not to think about who he was. You know, this young guy,
an earnest immigrant who is probably the most valuable person in the FBI at that point.
He's in his 20s. He's been given, I think he was 26 when he became the lead agent for the coal
bombing, a huge responsibility. And he is deeply intelligent. And he is also totally conversant
with Islam and with the politics of the Middle East, such that, you know, when he would interrogate
al-Qaeda guys and they would bring up stuff about Islam, he pulled out the Quran and said,
show me where, show me that in the Quran. And he could recite the Quran himself.
Yeah. In fact, during his interrogation of Abu Jindal, I mean, he basically won him over
with his knowledge of the religion. He knew how to interrogate people without torturing them.
And in fact, during Guantanamo, when they started waterboarding, he called the director
and said, I'm either going to arrest these people or I have to leave. And the director said,
leave, we don't want to, we're not going to be a part of that. He's a seminal figure in our
history in some ways. He's the guy that identified through his interrogations who the al-Qaeda people
were. You know, he got the names, you know, through his skilled interrogation techniques.
And all the time, the CIA was hiding something from him, which was the meeting in Kuala Lumpur,
where the coal bombers had been present and photographed. And, you know, those photographs
were... Tons of cash had been transferred. Ali knew about the transfers, but didn't know why.
And, you know, and who, who were they? And he was beginning to get some names from his
interrogations. And so that was some of the stuff that was flowing up in his request to
the CIA for more information. And, you know, he's flatly denied. And then 9-11 happens.
And all he can think about is he has to get back to America. And of course...
He's lost his mentor.
He lost John.
So he gets on the plane and then he's told by a CIA representative, no, you have to go back.
Go back into, you know, your office in Yemen. And they give him a Manila envelope.
And in there are the pictures of the people that were at the Kuala Lumpur meeting.
And suddenly he knows... And there was one picture that he knew. And he knew that, you know,
there's an Al-Qaeda operative. And this has been withheld from him. You know, had they given him
that just those photographs that he had asked for back when he was doing his, you know,
starting his investigation of the coal and began to piece together what had happened,
the FBI would have been able to break open the case right there. And
he went to the bathroom and threw up. And then he went to work.
And that's when he got the names of the Al-Qaeda guys. And, you know, he essentially
solved the crime from that office in Yemen. One man.
And history could have been so different if the CIA had, you know,
exceeded to his request. And there was nobody better prepared to take advantage of it than Ali
Sivan. Lawrence, it's hard to believe this has been 20 years. Yeah. I want to thank you for
an unbelievable, unbelievable investigation. Just an amazing amount of research.
It's hard to imagine what you had to do to write this book, how many trips you had to take to take
into the lion's den. And at the same time, how infuriating it must have been to learn
the set of events. I can't think of anything I've ever done in my life that would be so upsetting.
Right? Like I think of anything I've ever done that's upset me that in terms of like learning
that something happened or didn't happen, or this person wasn't competent and it led to this,
you know, like the dietary guidelines in the 1970s, like none of that compares in some ways to this.
But I also think that, you know, you've created a place in history for a lot of people who
wouldn't otherwise be recognized. And I think the Ali Sufans of the world are probably people who
would, you know, not become household names. And look, I hope that as we sit here at the
20th anniversary of, you know, one of the most consequential dates for most of us,
that people will take time to go back and reflect on the history of that
and reflect on the people who were trying to make a difference.
I guess I'll close with one last question, which is
what do you think the future holds with respect to this type of asymmetric warfare,
be it Al Qaeda or fill in the blank, you know, pick your favorite organization that operates
in the same mindset. Is this something that is going to be part of our world for the next century?
I think so. You know, just, I mean, there are innumerable terrorist groups around the world
and in our own country, you know, the white supremacist and most notably. But Al Qaeda set
a template, you know, a small group highly empowered by kind of judo moves of, you know,
using technology against the countries that developed the technology. But now we have,
you know, Al Qaeda, you know, which was on 9 11, three or 400 guys. Now the estimates 30 to 40,000
members of Al Qaeda and its affiliates, you know, from Morocco through the Sahel up through Saudi
Arabia to India to Southern China, you know, there were Al Qaeda groups all over the place.
Their intentions haven't changed. They haven't been able to pull off the highly successful attack
in America that would equal 9 11, but many smaller attacks and not just in America,
but other countries, many other countries with technology, I especially worry about drones.
You know, small groups can have a tremendous, you know, far greater influence and power.
And then, you know, I've been writing about the pandemic.
I worry that, you know, these kinds of episodes can be suggestive. There are groups like
Omshin Riki, oh, was a Japanese cult that really wanted to destroy much of the world with diseases
or atomic bombs. You know, they're in a lot of very capable scientists were members of it.
Adam Waffen division, one of the white supremacist groups, they have a philosophy of, you know,
wanting to eliminate much of the population and so that it narrows down only to white people.
And biological warfare is part of the, you know, the goal of some of those groups.
It's dismayingly easy to create diseases. And, you know, I was talking to,
who's the guy in James Bond that creates all the weapons? Is it him? Is that the?
Not sure.
All right. I think it's him. Anyway, I talked to this American version of that.
And he didn't show me the good stuff, but I asked him, this was several years ago,
what worries you? And he said, what really worries me is those high school kids that are now
creating computer viruses will one day soon be able to manufacture biological viruses just as
easily. And that day is on us now. So I worry about that a lot. And, you know, I think, you know,
we live in a hazardous world. A world is constrained by a lot of loss of freedom because of that.
And, you know, it's, you know, we have to keep in mind the idea of freedom and country that we used
to be and hope that one day we can return to it. We also have to be sober minded about the
challenges. And I don't think our children are going to live in a world without terrorism or
our children's children. I think that, you know, terrorism is going to be a factor for a long time
to come. And I don't, I don't finally know, given the proliferation of terror, how we're going to
put breaks on it. I mean, you can think of it from two standpoints, right? You can think one of it is
you reduce the drive for it, right? So what are the factors that are contributing to terrorism?
What is the humiliation? What is the disenfranchisement of the individuals who go on to
perpetrate these things? So what are all those things? What are the forces to reduce them?
At the other end of the spectrum, right? That's is the kind of offensive strategy, which is how
much better can our intelligence agencies be? Look, every person who has run for president
since 9 11 has said, look at the success. We have not had another attack of this magnitude on US
soil. Is there something to that? Is that, is that, I mean, that's presumably that's not been
through a lack of effort on the part of Al Qaeda or others, correct? Well, we always tend to look
over our shoulder at what happened in the past and we have to keep in mind what's happening
right now. The terrorists proliferate, they move around, they adopt new ideologies. There's a
fluidity about this and we're going to see eruptions of terror. Some will be of small magnitude,
but I've just been writing about the massacre in El Paso in 2019, 23 Mexican Americans killed.
This is the largest attack on Latinos in our history. And it wasn't Al Qaeda,
but it was terrorism. And that idea is so seeded into our culture now that
things can, no doubt, things change over time. You had school shootings, for instance,
that's diminished, but the whole mass shooting thing started here in Austin with the UT tower
shootings in 1966. So in a way, there was a wave that was created and emulators came along. And
then, currently, it seems like school shootings have diminished, they have drive by shooting.
These memes get into our society. And I don't know how other than being displaced by a new meme,
they get removed from the consciousness of people that want to do harm.
But I do think that we are doing a better job of containing terrorism. And we're far more alert to
it. But I do think that our intelligence agencies have to improve. The pandemic was a catastrophic
intelligence failure. This was a national security threat. We've lost more than 600,000 Americans.
If a nation had attacked us and killed half a million of our citizens, we'd been totally on
a different track. But we have to take new things into account. And when we're talking about our
safety and security, it's not just terrorism, public health, the natural environment, global
warming, all of these things, we have real challenges ahead of us. And so far to date,
we are not performing adequately to put them at rest. I know I said that was my last question.
I guess I have one more. In all of your research, have you come to believe that these relatively
small terrorist organizations would have the capacity to acquire and actually utilize nuclear
weapons? I think nuclear weapons are kind of hard. When the Soviet Union collapsed, there were
a lot of loose nukes. And Al-Qaeda tried to get hold of a nuclear bomb and it turned out to be a
fraud. But nuclear weapons tend to be beyond the capacity of the people that we've dealt with in
the past. That doesn't mean that there couldn't be people in the future who have that capacity
and would be willing to. But you would say biological weapons would be a far greater concern
in terms of massive, we're talking about on the scale of hundreds of thousands of lives.
And some toxins. Anthrax is a good candidate. I think we have to be really, really careful.
Anthrax has come out of our own Fort Detrick. So we have to be always cautious. We can't live
our lives in fear all the time, but you'd be nuts not to pay attention to the fact that there are
dangers out there and there are people that want to cause harm. And I think we have to,
it's the absence of unity in our community that threatens us the most now because we're not
together on this. And there are people that would cheer on such actions. And
what kind of country have we become in that case?
Well, I seem to keep coming to a real down conclusion.
I was about to say, I'm looking for an optimistic way to close this out. And I guess the only thing
I would say is I hope that this week people can basically pause for a moment and reflect on
people who lost their lives, people who made sacrifices as a result of that. And if nothing
else, just to remember that, I mean, I'm not sure that there's something actionable I can do with
that other than just be grateful and at the same time be sad. So simultaneously, I think,
experience these two extreme emotions. It occurs to me though that tragedies often have
surprisingly good consequences or let's say benefits for society. And if you look at
our recent history in this country with 1918 flu, I would not say that we took advantage of that.
We tended to forget about it, but then came the depression and in the middle of the depression,
we made ourselves into a different country, stronger, more compassionate, more resilient.
We could do that. And then World War II once again, took a challenge and transformed our country.
And since then, we had 9-11 and we invaded Iraq and tortured people in Guantanamo. So
tragedy is an opportunity. And- Do you think we squandered this one?
I thought we squandered 9-11 terribly. And the consequences of what we did to ourselves
after 9-11 are greater than what was done to us. Unquestionably.
The invasion of Iraq, the trillions of dollars we spent in Afghanistan, just all of that
inconsequential in terms of lives lost. But we made huge mistakes, but we're capable.
We've shown ourselves to be capable of triumphing and we've got another opportunity now.
And I hope that we take the lessons that 9-11 have given us and pandemic and try to make
ourselves into that country that we once were and want to be again.
Lawrence, thank you so much for making a lot of time to talk about this. I know this is a book
you wrote 15 years ago, so I'm sure sometimes it's not even top of mind. It's back of mind,
given all the things you've written about since. But I appreciate you taking a trip down memory
lane and pulling some of the cobwebs off. What I think is one of the most remarkable things
written. Well, thank you. And I appreciate having the opportunity to talk to you and your listeners.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of
medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this
podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in
obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of
their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest
very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise,
please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.