Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Matt. Awesome to have you back on the show. It's been a while because you were one of the
very, very initial and original guests on this podcast. So I've been looking forward to having
you back from almost the moment we finished our first discussion.
Yeah, thanks, Peter. It's great to be back. Unfortunately, we can't see each other in person,
but this is the next best thing. Yeah, I know. I mean, we certainly will get together in person
soon, I'm sure. There are so many things I wanted to talk about. And I think last time we spoke,
we focused mostly on our mutual favorite drug, rapamycin, and our favorite pathway,
the mTOR pathway. And certainly for those listening, I don't want them to think we're
not going to touch on that today. We absolutely are. But I want to start even broader than that
because so often you and I are having these discussions about all things that pertain to
aging. And I find you to be one of the most thoughtful people across the topic. So I sort
of want to start with these broader questions about aging. A lot of people have different
definitions of aging. And truthfully, I'm not sure I even know how to define aging sometimes.
It depends, I guess, on the context in which I'm asked. I think if my five-year-old asks me about
aging, I would come up with one answer. And if I'm giving a keynote talk and somebody asks me
about aging, I'd have to give a different one. So what are some of the ways that you really
describe aging? Yeah, so that's a really good question. And I think I would probably
say the same thing that you just said, which is that I'm not sure I have a great answer and it
changes depending on the situation. I think in the past, I often gravitated towards sort of a
molecular definition of aging. So what are the types of damage that occur during aging? What are
the consequences of that damage? Sort of in some ways a hallmarks of aging framework view, right?
Where we know that things like mitochondrial dysfunction, telomere shortening, cellular
senescence, things like that happen during aging at the cellular and molecular level and contribute
to many of the functional declines in diseases that go along with aging. And so given my training
in biochemistry and molecular biology, that sort of is the natural place where I go when I think
about what is aging. I would say over the last several years, I have developed, I think, a great
appreciation for a functional definition of aging. And so as I start to think more and more about
translation of interventions that seem to affect the biological aging process in laboratory animals
outside of the laboratory and to the clinic, I spend a lot of time thinking about, well, what
are some of the functional changes that go along with aging? And we know that across every organ
system in the body, we see functional declines that go along with aging. And so I've started to
think more about things like frailty as an important component of defining aging from a biological
perspective when we're talking about having an impact on health and longevity. So I think it
really depends on the context. I guess the other thing I would say is both of those definitions
and the way I almost exclusively think about aging, unless somebody sort of forces me out of
my box, is from a biological perspective. There are other aspects of aging that intersect with
biological aging that are probably as important as what I think of as fundamental biology of aging to
quality of life. So social aspects of aging, for example, are extremely important in people,
especially for quality of life as you get older. I don't tend to gravitate towards that kind of a
definition of aging, but I do recognize that it's important. So I think I'm naturally always
thinking about the biology of aging. And as I already said, I tend to focus on the molecular
mechanisms that drive the biological changes that go along with aging. So let's look at the sort of
two extreme views within the biologic and then kind of try to figure out where disease fits in.
So on the one hand, you referred to the hallmarks of aging, and there's a very famous set of papers
that have laid these out. And if the day comes that I can actually recite all of them, I'll be
very impressed. I always have to look it up, right? I think I can probably get seven. Yeah,
it's like so you mentioned a bunch. Who can name the most hallmarks of aging? Adder Peter. DNA
damage is one of them. Cellular senescence is another. Stem cell fatigue is another.
Protein misfolding is another. Telomere shortening is another.
Mitochondrial dysfunction is another. My favorite. Yeah.
Let's see. Did I mention nutrient sensing issues? Now, dysregulated nutrient sensing.
Yeah. So that's my seven. What am I forgetting?
There's intracellular communication. Bingo. And what are we missing here? I'm going to be really
ashamed if it's something that I study. Yeah. But yeah. So we got eight out of nine. That's not bad.
You've got those. And then at the other side, you talked about, okay, let's talk phenotype. Let's
talk about the outward expression within the organism and frailties, I think, a fantastic
example. Where does disease fit into this, right? Because with aging comes more cancer. With aging
comes more cardiovascular disease. With aging comes more dementia. And you could argue that
those are functional. Maybe less so cancer, but certainly cardiovascular disease and dementia are
very functional forms of decline. But of course, at their root, they have a very cellular component
and a very strong set of cellular contributions. Do you think of disease as basically the bridge
or the link between these fundamental cellular declines and the ultimate phenotypic declines?
No, I would not say they're a bridge. So I think that I actually, I actually personally tend to
think almost the other way around where I think that the functional declines that often proceed
overt disease or clinical diagnosis of disease are probably as important or more important from
a quality of life perspective as we get older. And this may simply reflect the fact that I'm
getting older. And I've noticed some of these functional declines in myself. And I think that
I think these functional declines happen, as I already said, in every organ, every tissue,
we don't always recognize them as such, unless we sit down and think about and try to list out all
of the ways that we have changed as we get older. And those often happen far before you get diagnosed
with any age-related disease. So I'm pretty fortunate. I turned 50 in February. I don't have
any age-related disease, at least that I've been diagnosed with. Yet I have a multitude of
functional declines, which fortunately don't impact me severely, but that I recognize I'm
functionally impaired to where I was 25 years ago. I think we, you know, it's just a fact,
any 50-year-old is. And so I kind of think of those as the first sort of things that you can
observe that happen during aging, often way before you get an age-related disease. The other thing I
would say about disease, so there's actually two things, two points I want to make. One is, I think
it depends on the disease, but we really don't have a good understanding of when the pathology
of the disease is no longer normative aging. And what I mean by that is, you know, we've got some
understanding of the molecular cellular mechanisms that drive biological aging that contribute in
some way to our risk of developing Alzheimer's disease, cardiovascular disease, you know,
sort of all of the age-related diseases that are major causes of death and disability.
But in most of those cases, you know, there comes a point where the pathology of the disease is not
necessarily at a molecular mechanistic level an extension of aging biology. It becomes something
different. And I think that's really important to recognize because one of the implications of that
is that an intervention that affects biological aging, let's just say rapamycin, we can discuss
whether rapamycin really affects biological aging in people. I think that's still a little bit of an
open question. Let's just say for the sake of argument that it does, it's not clear that that
same intervention is going to be effective once a pathology, you know, progresses to the point that
it's not the same mechanism anymore. So I think that that's a really important point that sometimes
gets lost in this discussion of aging and disease. So let's actually double click on that using
a disease. So you want to pick one of the big three, atherosclerosis, cancer, dementia.
I think cancer is a really good example, right? So we know mTOR, which I'll go back to rapamycin in
part because, you know, it's again, something I think a lot about, but it actually it's a really
good, I think, example in this specific case, because we know that mTOR, which is the target
of rapamycin, right, the protein that rapamycin inhibits, plays this fundamental role in regulating
cell division and cell cycle, right? So if you inhibit in a non-cancerous cell, if you inhibit
mTOR enough, you will stop the cell cycle. The cell will stop dividing, right? But there are mutations
that can happen that lead to cancer that cause the cell to no longer pay attention to the mTOR break,
right? And so once that's happened, if that's the type of cancer you have that no longer responds
to mTOR inhibition, rapamycin won't do anything to cell cycle in that case. So that's a really,
I think, specific example that you can point to. There are, you know, sort of an infinite number
of other examples that we could use, but that's a really nice one because there rapamycin will be
quite effective at preventing cancer before that mutation happens. But after that mutation happens
and the cell's not responding to rapamycin anymore because it doesn't sense the mTOR break,
it's completely ineffective, right? So that, I think, is a case where the mechanisms have
changed, right? The mechanisms that are important for preventing cancer before that mutation
occurred are different from the mechanisms that might deal with that cancer after that mutation
has occurred. Yeah, it's funny. This is a little off topic, but I've often contemplated this
question in the context of nutrition because in as much as there's an optimal nutrition to prevent
a condition, it might not be the same as the optimal nutritional strategy to treat the disease
once it's present. Yeah. And, you know, an example of that in an extreme sense might be a ketogenic
diet. I happen to believe a ketogenic diet is probably the best treatment for someone with
type 2 diabetes because of course type 2 diabetes by its very definition is a carbohydrate
intolerance disorder. So once a person has it, you pull out the carbohydrates completely and you let
them heal, right? You basically let them recover and regain their ability, you know, and again,
we've seen that people who have been on a ketogenic diet for a long enough period of time
can resume some amount of carbohydrate consumption provided their other factors are changing such as
exercise. Does that mean one needs to be on a ketogenic diet to prevent diabetes? No, I don't
think so. So it's a little bit of the same idea though it's still something that's unclear. You
know, one thing I want to go back to on the disease front is, and I believe it was Cynthia
Kenyon who spoke about this once. I think I read it in a paper, something to the effect of, you
know, using a disease-based definition for aging is she didn't use the word tautology, but she
effectively said it is a bit of a tautology because at what point is a disease a disease? It's only a
disease when some people have it and some people don't, right? If everybody has cancer by a certain
age, then it's normative aging to your point. It's no longer a disease. And then we get into,
well, what does it mean? Like why do, you know, 0.0004% of the population live to be 100?
They've managed to not succumb to a disease by the age of 100. And what does that tell us about
their normative aging versus everybody else? All of this is to say I literally still don't think
I understand what aging is, which is unfortunate given my line of work. Well, I mean, I think we
have to just accept that it's extremely complicated, right? And so you're never, I shouldn't say never.
I don't think I will ever understand aging fully. And I don't think the field will, at least, you
know, in any timeframe that I can expect to experience, right? But I also believe that we
don't have to understand it fully to be able to have an impact on the biology of aging through
interventions. And so I think that, and that's kind of where I'm at. I feel like I've got a
conceptual flavor for what aging is. And I have some information about what the molecular
mechanisms are. And it's enough information that I can come up with rational approaches to target
those mechanisms with the prediction that those approaches should have an impact on health and
longevity as animals and people get older. And then we have to test those predictions, right?
That I think is, that's kind of the way I think about it. I do want to come back to one point,
though, which I also think is often underappreciated in this relationship between disease
and the biology of aging. I think, you know, sometimes people get into this debate about
whether or not the biology of aging causes diseases of aging, right? So does the biology
of aging cause Alzheimer's disease, cancer, cardiovascular disease, right? People get in
debates about that. And I personally think the data are pretty good that these, that what I think
of is the biology of aging, the molecular mechanisms, the hallmarks, whatever you want to
call them, contribute in a causal way to your risk of developing diseases. But I also think it doesn't
matter. It does. And this, I think is really important from the perspective of what is the
best strategy to keep people healthy or longer. It just doesn't matter whether aging causes disease,
or it creates a permissive physiological state for disease. You can't argue that biological age
is the single greatest risk factor for every major cause of death and disability in developed
countries. That is just a fact. And whether or not biological age causes those diseases or
creates a physiological state that allows those diseases to manifest themselves doesn't matter
from the perspective of how, what is the most effective way to prevent those diseases. And I
think that's where this debate is counterproductive, right? Should we call aging a disease? Does aging
cause disease? I think that those are not the right questions to be asking in my view.
Yeah. Let me see if you would agree with my assessment. I think you would, but I'll tell
you how I think about this problem clinically, right? So let's use atherosclerosis as an example.
And I want to highlight what you just said in case the person watching this or listening to this
missed it in any way, shape, or form. This is one of the questions when I used to give talks.
I'd always lead with a question like this. What is the greatest risk factor for atherosclerosis?
Hand will go up. Yes. Smoking. No. Hand will go up. High blood pressure. Nope.
Hand will go up if it's an especially erudite audience. Apo B or LDLC. Nope. And they'll just
keep rattling on inflammation. Nope. Nope. Nope. Nope. Nope. Nope. Nope. The number one thing is age.
Hands down, right? You take a 70 year old person who has everything perfect about them and you
compare them to a 20 year old train wreck who has not a single thing that is in their favor.
There is no comparison about their 10 year mortality prediction. But the 70 year old is
in hands down or worse shape. So yeah, you can't undo that. Now, here's how I think about this
problem clinically. Atherosclerosis is a great example because it's the disease that we understand
the most of the big three, right? Which is not to say we understand it completely, but we have a far
better understanding of what its drivers are and how to prevent it than we do cancer and Alzheimer's
disease. Lowering Apo B pharmacologically, nutritionally, et cetera, is arguably the most
important strategy you have to reduce it along with probably improving metabolic health. So those
two things, right? So regulating glucose, insulin, lowering Apo B, all of these things can be done
through lifestyle, through drugs, et cetera, can dramatically reduce a person's risk of atherosclerosis.
None of those things are necessarily directly targeting the nine hallmarks of aging. I think
indirectly they certainly do. But when you give somebody a PCSK9 inhibitor, which specifically
targets a protein that allows the body to clear more Apo B particles out of circulation, it is by
no means targeting one of those nine pillars, but it's having a measurable impact on reducing their
risk of disease. And in the end, that's the part that I think is hard for some people to understand
within the aging community, is that you can still target metrics of a disease specifically without
going after a hallmark. Sure. And I mean, I think I don't disagree with you that I think that is a
concept that sometimes is underappreciated, right? Especially within the aging community. I also
think it makes sense, right? So even if the hallmarks... We focus so much on the hallmarks
because it's easy, right? I think there are some reasons why the hallmarks are incomplete, but let's
just keep using that term sort of as a surrogate for the molecular mechanisms of aging, right?
If we accept that the hallmarks are at some level preceding the damage, whatever that is that's
causing the disease, it makes sense that you could intervene sort of, if we think about it in an
upstream downstream perspective, right? The hallmarks being upstream, the disease being ultimately
downstream. It makes sense that you could intervene at the level of the hallmarks. It also makes sense
that you could intervene, you know, in whatever the bridge is that's connecting the hallmarks to
the disease, you wouldn't necessarily impact the biology of aging at all. And this gets back to
what I was talking about before, which for many diseases of aging, there comes a point where the
pathology of the disease is not normative aging anymore. And so you can quite successfully treat
or cure a disease of aging in an individual without impacting the biology of aging. In fact,
I would argue that's almost exclusively what is done clinically, right? Is to try to either
alleviate the symptoms of the disease or cure the disease. They're starting to be more on the
preventative side, but I still think that lags far behind, you know, waiting until people are sick
and then trying to do something about their disease. But you don't have to impact the biology
of aging to be successful at any of those things. I would just argue that impacting the biology of
aging is going to be a much more effective and efficient approach from sort of the overall health
perspective. I think the other point that's obvious but is important to make is if you don't target
the biology of aging, that you're really only impacting that one disease. Say it's cancer, you
can cure somebody's cancer, you can take the tumor out, right? And they can go on and live a normal
life. But you haven't done anything to the biology of aging. If you don't confront the biology of
aging, right, you still have all of these other functional declines and diseases of aging that
are increasing, you know, essentially exponentially as you're getting older. And so the effect on
health and longevity is quite small. In fact, I think J.L. Shansky was the person who originally
kind of did the math here, right? And it's really very striking. So if you consider a typical 50
year old woman in the United States and you say, you know, what would happen if we had a cure to
all cancers, right? Every type of cancer, we had a cure today and we implemented that. Life expectancy
for a typical 50 year old woman in the United States would go up about three years. That's it.
So we've won the war on cancer. We get a plus three on life expectancy. It's about the same for
curing heart disease. If you cure both of those diseases, it's roughly additive. It's I think
about seven years. So the impact on life expectancy is actually from curing disease is actually quite
small. If you compare that to the impact of targeting biological aging, which again, I think
we have to be honest, right? This is hypothetical in humans at this point. So all we can really do
is extrapolate from what is done in laboratory animals. But it's pretty routine now. There are,
I don't know, maybe a dozen, 15 different interventions that can increase lifespan
slow aging in mice by between 15 and 30%. If we just extrapolate that to the human condition,
the impact on life expectancy is about 20 years with the added value that because you've sort of
slowed all of the functional declines of aging simultaneously, those extra couple of decades
are spent in relatively good health. So I think it's just important to appreciate the potential
difference in health and life expectancy from targeting aging as opposed to what we do right
now, which is trying to cure individual diseases. And I've sort of adopted the term, I think of that
as 20th century medicine, the disease first approach, or I would even say 19th century
medicine. We've been doing this for a long time. And I contrast that to what I think of as 21st
century medicine, which is approaching health and longevity from the perspective
of the biology of aging. And we're not there yet, but I do believe that this is happening. There is a
transition occurring, a slow appreciation among the broader clinical community of the potential
of this kind of approach. And I do believe that we will get there in this century. So it is my hope
and expectation that 21st century medicine will really become targeting the biology of aging to
enhance health and longevity, hopefully by much, much greater amount than we're currently able to do.
Yeah. So I agree with a lot of that. The one thing I would throw a little bit of a question at is,
and I'd love to have Jay on the podcast because I don't know that I fully agree with his analysis.
I agree with the spirit of his analysis. So I completely agree that disease-based whack-a-mole
is not going to be nearly as effective as targeting the basic biology of aging. So completely
agree with your points. I don't know that I agree with the magnitude, the de minimis magnitude
of it, because I really think that Jay's analysis is focused on an independent look at each disease.
Whereas in reality, if you eliminated cardiovascular disease, by definition, you have reduced
inflammation significantly. You've reduced the burden of microvascular disease significantly.
Those are going to play into other diseases. So his analysis is very actuarial, but it's not
actually very biological. That's my opinion. Now, again, I should have-
I think that's fair. Yeah. I think that's fair. I think you could make the case, at least for
cancer, that it may be closer to-
I agree.
... just what the straight math would suggest.
Yeah.
Now, with all of that said, I couldn't agree more with the macro point here, which is
delaying chronic disease is probably not going to be as effective as targeting something at the
foundation. Now, that said, let's take a look at NIRS data. So when you look at NIR Barzilai's
work with centenarians, the overwhelming statement here is they get chronic diseases later. They
don't live longer with them. And I remember really being struck by that. That would not
have been my null hypothesis going into NIRS, a study of NIRS work, and Tom Pearls as well.
Between NIR and Tom, you really have the greatest assessment of the centenarians and their siblings.
Yeah.
And you realize that they don't seem to have magical protection from a disease once they get it. When
they get cancer, they're just as hosed as the rest of us. When they get heart disease, they're just
as bad off as the rest of us. But they get a phase shift. They get a 20-year, 20, sometimes
30-year phase shift in when they're going to get the disease. And so how does that factor into my
thinking clinically? My factoring to that clinically is the sooner you begin prevention,
the more you can mimic the centenarian. What we don't fully understand is molecularly,
why is that the case? We've identified some of their genes. We know that they're going to be
more likely to have ApoE2 versus ApoE3 or ApoE4. They're going to be less likely to have ApoC3,
high regulation versus low. You have a lot of genes that produce phenotypes that are favorable.
But when you bring it back to our nine hallmarks, by the way, the ninth hallmark is epigenetic
modu- Of course. Yes, it's the epigenetic modulation.
Now, the other point I guess that we're both well aware of, but maybe for the listener, is
how difficult it is to study aging in humans targeting the basic biology because you don't
get to do what our clinical trials apparatus is set up to do, which is pick a disease,
a very clear endpoint, and target it. If your endpoint is nutrient sensing, that's a tough
clinical trial. Yeah. So I agree. And I think we should definitely come back to that point because
it's clearly a major focus of the field right now is how do we start to test some
of these interventions that we know work in laboratory animals in the clinic. That's a
challenge. I want to come back to your comment about centenarians though, because I think this
again is a conceptual area where there's a lot of, I think, misunderstanding both among people in
the field and also lay people who pay attention to the field. So you're right, I think, that the
bulk of the evidence supports the idea that centenarians do not live longer with multiple
age-related diseases, but they have genetic risk factors or genetic variants that put them at lower
risk, at least for the major killers. So there is a genetic component to being a centenarian. It's
not huge, but it's significant, probably somewhere I think around 25, 30%. And they tend to not have
the high risk genetic variants for Alzheimer's disease, certain types of cancer, heart disease,
things like that. And then there's a luck or environment or something else we don't understand
that comes into play. But people often look at that observation and make the assumption that we
don't see variants in things like mTOR or sirtuins, not that there aren't variants that haven't been
talked about, but that have strong effects. So I think the question becomes, why don't we see
variants in sirt6 or mTOR or pick your favorite longevity gene, foxo, that cause people to live
to be 180 years old? Because we can do that magnitude of lifespan extension in a mouse or
a C. elegans. And so they go from that. So that's an observation. We haven't found those variants yet.
Although foxo is one of the genes, foxo 3A, no, it's not, it's a very weak effect, but it's clearly
a higher amount. As is 36. Right. And as is mTOR, there's evidence for all of those things.
You can find genetic evidence, but the effects are relatively small. So then the interpretation
that people make is the reason we don't see those variants is because humans are fundamentally
different from mice or whatever your favorite laboratory organism is. And none of those things
will work the same way in people. Now I can't prove that they will work the same way yet
for aging in people, but that's a, that's an ill, that's not a logical sort of interpretation,
right? I would argue the reason you don't see strong effect variants in mTOR, for example,
in people is because we know that strong effect variants in mTOR are incompatible with life and
development, even in mice, right? You make a mTOR knockout mouse, it's dead. So, so I think the
reason why you don't see these strong effect variants in people is because there is such a
strong selective pressure. Either, either they don't make it through gestation, they don't make
it through development, or they're sterile, right? All of those are incompatible with, with evolutionary
success. And, and that's my hypothesis for why we don't see these very strong effect genetic
variants in people that lead to 160, 170 year lifespans. Again, it's a hypothesis, right? It's
hard to, it's hard to know what the explanation is, but it certainly fits with what we see in
laboratory animals. Any of these, any of these mutants in mice that have, you know, 30, 40%
lifespan extension, I mean, they are all significantly defective in, in, from a, from
an evolutionary perspective, right? They would not be selectively advantageous mutations. And so
I think that's, that's at least a consistent explanation for why we don't see these, these,
these, what we would think of as slower aging variants pop up in, in people. The other point
that's, that's important to make as well though, is that that doesn't mean that we can't intervene
in these pathways to have an impact on health and longevity. And for me, this has been, you know,
probably the most exciting aspect and development in the field over the last probably 15 years.
You know, if you asked me 15 years ago, whether I thought that, that it would be easy to slow aging
in an old mouse, I would have said no, I would have said, you probably have to start, you know,
at six months of age and treat them all the way through life to get, to get the benefits. And that
was honestly, largely based on caloric restriction, right? Which that seems to be the case for caloric
restriction. You know, what has emerged now is there are five or six or seven, or maybe even more
different interventions that can be initiated in middle age or even in late age in mice.
And you actually go, it's not only that you slow down the declines, you actually reverse the
declines, right? And again, I come back to rapamycin because in pretty much every tissue where this
has been looked at, you take an old mouse, you give it rapamycin functionally, it's younger in
that tissue or that organ and lifespan is extended. And by the way, to your point, Matt, I was having
dinner with a friend last night who asked me, why don't we start giving rapamycin to children?
And I said, look, I think, I think rapamycin is the most important, you know,
giroprotective agent out there today, but you wouldn't want to give it to a developing
child, right? He said, if you had to guess when would be the right age to start, I said,
I have no honest clue, but it wouldn't be before 25, right? It just wouldn't be before about the
age of 25, which speaks to your point, any genetic manipulation or in this case, naturally acquired
genetic variation that mimicked rapamycin would probably not be selective because you wouldn't
be able to turn it on and off the way you would need to with the drug. That's right. Yeah, that's
right. And I mean, I think that's a really interesting question about rapamycin and other
interventions as more and more interventions start to, you know, get to the same sort of level of
confidence that we have about rapamycin. When is the optimal sort of treatment period, right? To
get the biggest benefits. And I think, again, this is a, it's not something that often gets,
I think, talked about in that conversation, but it's really a, it's a balancing act, right? Any
intervention is going to have some risk associated with it, right? The risk can be low, the risk can
be high, but there's always some risk of side effects. And so the question of optimal treatment,
right, is a balance between the beneficial effects that you get and the risk of detrimental
effects, side effects. And so I think we still don't, even with rapamycin, we still don't have
a great feel for what that risk looks like, right? And that's in part because, you know, we haven't
had long-term controlled clinical trials at multiple doses, multiple strategies of, you know,
intermittent versus continuous treatment, things like that. So we just don't know, right? And it's
interesting in the case of rapamycin because my impression is that, you know, there are a group of
people, I think you and I both know some of them, we might even be among them, who, you know, have
self-experimented, right? And my impression is that there has been a movement towards the idea that,
you know, once a week dosing with rapamycin is probably better than daily dosing with rapamycin
for aging effects in people and that, you know, you might want to do it for three months and then
you stop for six months and you do it again for three months, right? I think that's where people
are starting to coalesce around this idea. There's not a lot of data to support that, right? It's a
guess. And so it's just interesting to sort of see how that, you know, is evolving in the absence of
long-term, large-scale controlled clinical trials. And this is getting to the point that you raised
earlier, which is it's really hard and expensive to do long-term controlled clinical trials
for aging in people. We really, I think, still as a field don't have a great strategy for how to
address that challenge of actually trying to answer some of these questions in the way that,
you know, at least traditionally we would want to see them answered in a clinical setting.
I mean, I think there's an even bigger problem, Matt, which is I don't think there's a regulatory
appetite to even do what would be necessary because we have the regulatory appetite to say
you take an individual who is either at very high risk for a disease or already has said disease
and we will go ahead and accept the risk of a clinical trial to assess it.
But by definition, if you truly want to understand how giroprotective metformin or rapamycin or
canagaflasm or pick your favorite molecule is, you really need to be testing it in people before
they have a disease. So even if you, so there's really two fundamental problems. This is one,
we do not have a regulatory environment that accepts that risk. So I would love to see the
IRB submission that says we're going to test rapamycin in healthy 50 year olds who are,
you know, whose 10 year risk of death is less than 1%. And then secondly, because we can't
logistically follow those people for the next 50 years, which is what would be necessary to
understand its true magnitude of giroprotection, we would need really good biomarkers of aging,
of which I will posit and you may disagree. We have somewhere between zero and epsilon of those.
We don't have diddly squat in the way of meaningful biomarkers of aging. By the way,
I want to go back to your point on rapa. So, you know, as you do know, and I'm very happy to talk
about, I mean, I've been taking rapamycin for two and a half years now, and I am one of those people
who has coalesced around once weekly dosing. I have fiddled a little bit with my dose. I've
varied it from as little as five to as many as eight milligrams once a week. I've also done the
cycling on and the cycling off, but I am completely flying blind. Most of my dosing
and frequency data comes from Joan Manick and Lloyd Klikstein's 2014 paper with Evrolimus,
which of course is not the same as rapamycin, but it's a pretty reasonable hand-drawn facsimile of
it. And it was from that study that I concluded that, you know, 20 milligrams versus five
milligrams versus one milligram, your sweet spot was at about five from a side effect standpoint
and an efficacy standpoint. And the daily dose of one milligram didn't seem to produce as good an
effect as the five milligrams once a week. But how does that stand in comparison to what we
learned from all of the ITP studies where it's continuous administration of rapamycin? And to
your point, because we'll come back to these and talk about them, remarkable results, regardless of
when it's initiated. Right. I don't know what to make of that. Yeah. And I kind of agree with
everything you said about why, you know, if you're going to pick one regimen for rapamycin,
that makes sense. And like you said, it's really based on two clinical trials, right? I mean,
really. And so it's a limited data set, but at least for immune function in people,
you know, it seemed to work. And that's actually, I mean, you know, we could, we could spend hours
talking about this because that's a whole nother, I think, interesting and informative sort of
experience was the failure of the phase three clinical trial at Restorbio, right? And what
happened there? And I don't think we actually, it's at least not in the, it's not published yet.
Well, let's talk about this because it is really interesting. So let's back up for a moment and
give people the context. So when Joan was at Novartis in, and both Joan and Lloyd were at
Novartis in 2014, the Everalymis study was done. And do you want to just tell people really briefly
what that study looked at? Right. So that study, so Everalymis is a derivative of rapamycin and
biochemically, it has exactly the same mechanism. So it's, I, at least I conceptually think about
them as essentially the same molecule. So anything that we see with Everalymis, we would expect to
see with rapamycin. And so that was a phase two clinical trial in healthy older adults to look
at whether or not a six week treatment with Everalymis could boost vaccine response. So,
so the ability of older adults to respond to an influenza vaccine. And that actually was based on
one of my favorite papers from Panjang's lab at the University of Michigan, who showed that in mice,
I think it was, I think it was four weeks of rapamycin. It was either four weeks or six weeks
of rapamycin and old mice boosted the ability of a flu vaccine to protect those mice against a lethal
dose of influenza. That if anybody hasn't, hasn't looked at that paper, I would just encourage you
to go check it out. I think it was a 2009 science signaling paper from Panjang's lab, something of
the title has something about hematopoietic stem cells and rapamycin. We'll look to it in the show
notes for sure. Okay, yeah, it's an amazing study. But but my favorite experiment there was this
experiment where they took young and old mice, and they gave them influenza vaccine. And then they
waited two weeks and then they gave them a leaf, what would be a lethal dose of influenza if they
hadn't got the vaccine. And in the old group, half the mice either got rapamycin or they got a
control, right? So the first thing that struck me about that experiment was if you look at just the
difference between young and old mice who got the vaccine, all of the young mice were protected 100%
vaccine response, I think it was about 65%. So two thirds of the old mice did not have a
sufficient response to the vaccine, that they were protected against influenza, right? And I don't
know if the numbers are, I don't think the numbers are exactly the same in people. But there is
definitely that same trend where older adults tend to not respond to vaccines as robustly as
younger adults. Unless those old mice got rapamycin, if they got six weeks of rapamycin,
they were 100% effective at responding to the vaccine. So at least for that measure of immune
function, rapamycin fully restored the immune system back to that of a youthful immune system.
So that was the mouse data that sort of served as support for testing this in humans in this
clinical trial that we're about to get to. And by the way, Matt, do you recall if the immune response
in question, i.e. the immune response that was better in the rapa group versus the non-rapa
group of older mice, was this a B cell response, a memory B cell response, or was it a T cell response?
I don't recall the data. I know they have a lot of data in there looking at the antibody titers and
different types of immune cell types and how they responded. As I said, the title of that paper and
the model that they proposed was that rapamycin was acting at the level of hematopoietic stem cells
to rejuvenate hematopoietic stem cell function in some way. I don't recall the details of the
immunology. I've tried multiple times throughout my career to become fluent in immunologist speak
and have failed miserably every time. So that's a weakness of mine that will likely never be
addressed adequately. It's just got such amazing implications for what we're seeing with
COVID vaccination because we are still in such a nascent stage of truly understanding. We're
seeing people who naturally acquired COVID who within six months have no more circulating IgG.
We have no clue if they still have immune function. For example, do they still have
memory B cells in their bone marrow that when challenged will make antibodies? Do they still
produce, do they still have memory T cells that will show up and immediately respond?
And so we're actually involved in a study that's looking at that. But my intuition is
you can probably still have an immune response or an immune response that's ready to go absent
circulating IgG. Yeah. The one thing I will say about rapamycin and everolimus is that it seems
like it's not one simple mechanism at play. So Joan, for example, has published data that one of
the effects of everolimus and another drug called RTB101, which is also an mTOR inhibitor,
is to boost antiviral gene expression. And we know also that rapamycin, at least in mice,
and almost certainly in people, tamps down on the sort of chronic sterile inflammation that goes
along with aging through mechanisms that still are being worked out. So I think it's probably
multiple things that are going on that can impact immune function in different ways, right? When you
treat with rapamycin, especially in the context of an old animal or an old person. So it's probably
not going to be one mechanism is my guess. So based on this study, so Joan and colleagues
take a group of, I believe, 65 year olds, I think they're, you know, 320 of them, so divided into
four groups of 80, you've got a placebo group, one milligram a week group, 20 milligrams once
a week and five milligrams once a week. Yeah. That's right. Yeah. And so they did a six,
I think it was a six week treatment period. And then they also waited, I think two weeks,
and then they gave them a flu vaccine. And what they showed, I mean, obviously it's people,
so you can't do the mouse experiment and then give those people a lethal dose of influenza. So they
were sort of, you know, stuck with looking at things like antibody titers and to try to get
an assessment of, you know, did the people who got everolimus respond better to the vaccine than the
people who got the vehicle control? And it looked like they did. And it was, you know, you can argue
about the strength of the data. I think it was pretty clear that they had at least at the
five MIG once a week. And I think the one MIG daily, I can't remember, maybe it was the 20
MIG once a week, but the five MIG once a week looked pretty convincing that they had a better
response to the vaccine. I think the other thing that's really important about that paper is that
the incidence of side effects was really hardly different at all between the different everolimus
groups and the placebo. And particularly the five MIG once a week, there really was no significant
increase in adverse events in that group, which gets back to how we kind of started on this
this tangent, which is that that's part of the reason why, you know, I think people are moving
towards the idea that you can still get efficacy from once weekly dosing and that the side effects
are reduced at once weekly dosing to essentially zero or close to zero. So that was the first phase
two trial. And then they went on and did a second. Before we leave this trial, Matt, I think it is
important for someone listening to understand why people like you and I and Dave Sabatini and all
the people who live in mTOR land. I'm not putting myself in the same category as you guys, but you
know what I mean? I'm an mTOR fan boy. Why was that such an interesting and landmark paper? Well,
I think it's because up until that point, the only human application for rapamycin was immune
suppression, right? That's right. Rapamycin is a drug I have known about forever because as a
surgical resident, I was giving rapamycin to kidney transplant patients, heart transplant patients,
and liver transplant patients, along with a cocktail of cyclosporine, you know, prednisone,
MMF, all of these other really nasty drugs. And it was one part of that in their ability to suppress
the immune system. So I think prior to that paper, you have the ITP that the first ITP that came out
in 09 suggesting this is a remarkable tool for longevity, at least in the ITP mice. But then on
the other hand, you're saying, wow, but it can't really work in humans because it's going to be
really horrible to the immune system. So you had this sort of dialectical dilemma, which all of a
sudden it became, well, maybe that's not the case. So how do you reconcile the data that we saw in
Joan's paper with the fact that rapamycin is at least in theory an immune suppressor as it
pertains to organ transplantation? Yeah, and I think you know, you're absolutely right. That was
one important aspect of that paper. And I unfortunately think that the old view, which
in my room is the wrong view that rapamycin is an immunosuppressant, still is prevalent in the
clinical community. I think most clinicians still think of rapamycin and rappalogs as immune
suppressants because that's often how they're used clinically to prevent organ transplant rejection.
So I think the simple answer is it's all about dose dummy. I mean, we know every drug has a
dose response, right? And that you can get different effects, different outcomes, different side effects
depending on the dose. And so when you back off on the dose of rapamycin or everolimus,
in the context of an aged physiology. So there's multiple things going on here in that study.
They used lower doses, they tested once weekly dosing, and these are old people who show a
functional decline. You're not going to see a functional improvement in vaccine response if
you did this experiment in young people, right? You're only going to see it in the context of
older people where they already have a functional deficit. And that's, again, it's an important
conceptual point that I think often gets lost in these discussions. The other thing to appreciate
about how rapamycin has been used traditionally and how it was first approved is these are
people who had an organ transplant, right? Taking high doses of the drug and also, I think always,
I'm not an organ transplant physician, but my impression is these people are always taking other
immune suppressants in combination with mTOR inhibitors. So in that context, yes, it does seem
to be the case that mTOR inhibitors can help reduce the chance of organ rejection in transplant
patients. I could be wrong. I think there's preclinical data. I don't know of any
strong clinical data that by itself, rapamycin, even at higher doses, has substantial immune
suppressing effects. It might, it wouldn't shock me if it does at high doses, but I don't know that
that's really ever been shown clearly in healthy people taking higher doses of the drug.
Yeah, that's interesting. I don't think I've ever gone back and looked at the FDA approval process
in 99 because obviously it was approved for that use. And I think that's the only use that it's
been approved for. So I wonder what trials led to that approval, whatever trials would have taken
in the mid-90s. Yeah, I don't recall. Another point that I think is worth making is, and I'm
as guilty of this as anybody else, we use broad terms when we're talking about the immune system,
suppression, lower function. We say the immune system doesn't function as well in older people
as compared to younger people, which is true. But I think when we say it doesn't function as well,
we tend to think of as it's functioning at a lower level. There's just less activation,
which actually isn't necessarily the case. In old mice, in old people, there's a lot of immune
activation that shouldn't be happening. There's a lot of sterile inflammation that's occurring.
So it's not necessarily that the immune system is functioning less, it's functioning inappropriately.
And I think there's a ton of evidence that many of the benefits that we see in mice
from rapamycin occur because it tamps down on that sterile inflammation that goes along with
aging, the inappropriate activation of the immune system. So in that sense, you could think of it as
an immune suppressant. But through mechanisms that I don't understand at all, and I don't think
anybody really understands, it seems to be more effective at targeting the bad part of the
aberrant immune response in an aged physiology, which might be the reason why you're able to then
have more of the good part. And here I'm clearly showing my ignorance of immunology because I'm
referring to it as bad and good. But I think in some ways it's useful to think about it at that
level because it's easier to appreciate that immune function isn't intrinsically good or bad.
And there are different types of immune responses. And if you get the
wrong type of the immune response at the wrong time, that's bad. If you get the right type of
immune response when you need it, that's good. And I think in the context of aging, we just see
a lot more of the bad and probably a decline in function of the good. And I don't know if
rapamycin is affecting both of those, but I think it's definitely affecting the bad and bringing
it back down, which might just be enough to allow the good to come back up where it's supposed to.
Yeah, which look, I think that's a great point to make. And it's very similar with reactive oxygen
species, right? I mean, you have to have them. They are vital signaling molecules. And yet if
they run amok, they cause damage. And so, yeah, a lot of biology is in the Goldilocks framework of
not too much, not too little. Yeah. Can I just throw one more thing out there as well,
which is, and this is, again, I'll admit, if you'd asked me 15 years ago, like how important did I
think that, you know, chronic inflammation and immune function would be in aging, I probably
would have said, you know, I don't know, but my guess is it's not going to be the major player,
right? Because, you know, my background came from working in yeast and worms, which, you know,
worms sort of have an immune system, but not really, right? I would have pointed to things like
translation and autophagy and mitochondria, all of which are clearly important for affecting
inflammation and immune function. But I wasn't really bullish on inflammaging at that point.
And I have become very bullish on inflammaging as, you know, critically important for many of the
functional declines and diseases of aging that we see in people. The point that I want to make here
is that maybe I shouldn't say every, all of the interventions that I know about that I'm
enthusiastic about translationally seem to hit inflammation in mice and they seem to tamp down
on, you know, the chronic sterile inflammatory signaling that we see go along with aging, which
makes sense. It's encouraging, right? That they all seem to have this shared mechanism.
But the flip side of that is people talk a lot about, people are very excited now about,
you know, senolytics or reprogramming now is the new, the new senolytics, right? It's the
thing everybody's excited about. I'm not sure that those are fundamentally different from
rapamycin in terms of the way that they're working. And I think we obviously we need to find out
because, you know, it would be nice to know whether combinations of these interventions
are going to do better than one alone. But to me, the underlying theme that seems to be similar
about all of these things that work in mice is if you look in tissues of aged mice at, you know,
inflammatory cytokines, P16, P21, markers of senescence, they seem to be tamped down by all
of these, these interventions, which might explain the functional improvements that we see from,
from using these interventions in age mice. Yeah, I think that's actually a really interesting
point. And I would kind of say I'm in the same boat. I have become probably more convinced at
the importance of inflammation, certainly in Alzheimer's disease and certainly in atherosclerosis
because I've seen enough people who either develop these conditions without otherwise clear
reasons for it and vice versa, right? People who do have other risk factors and don't go on to
develop, but have, you know, at least have a demonstrably low measured amount of inflammation.
Again, the question becomes, do you target, is there a direct target of inflammation or do you
simply reduce inflammation by targeting these other mechanisms, which we'll get to. Let's go
back to the everolomous progression. You were just about to talk about RTB101. So what is that
and how is that the next stage in the evolution of this Rapalogue? Right. So there was the first
phase two trial was done. They hit their endpoint. It looked like it worked and they didn't see any,
I mean, this was a phase two trial. So the important thing was they didn't really see any
substantial adverse effects as well. Right. So then for the next trial, they added in another
drug called RTB101, which is one of these drugs that hits multiple kinases in the cell. So mTOR
is a kinase, which, you know, means it's biochemical activity is to put phosphate groups on other
proteins, but you can think of it as a signaling sort of activity, right? So it, mTOR
senses the environment and regulates the output based on this signaling function of being a kinase.
This drug, RTB101, inhibits mTOR, the catalytic activity of mTOR. It also inhibits other kinases.
So it's talked about as sort of a dual kinase inhibitor, but in reality it hits multiple
kinases. So it's a dirtier drug. That's maybe the way that the point to make it. It's a dirtier drug
than rapamycin, which has a very specific biochemical effect on mTOR and mTORC1 specifically,
which we haven't, we haven't dove into the mTORC1 versus mTORC2 situation. And was the rationale
for using a dirtier drug simply to create a new drug to have a molecule that is novel and therefore
protectable by IP? Or was it designed to be dirtier without thinking of it as being dirtier,
but thinking of it as being sort of a pluripotent across several kinases? Yeah. So I wasn't, I
obviously wasn't involved in designing this trial. So I can't, I can't answer that question as to what
the, what exactly their thought process was. I think it is true that RTB101 has a, had had and has
a longer existing patent life than ever Aligna. So there is that component certainly to, to,
to moving a drug through the approval process. And if you talk to Joan, she will tell you that
they had unpublished data that RTB101, if the doses that they were using in this trial appears
to be specific for mTORC1 like rapamycin. So I think their thought process, I mean, in reality,
it was probably twofold, right? The IP life was greater and, and there's a biological rationale
for testing RTB101 either alone or in combination with ever Aligna. And so that was really the
design of the phase two trial was one, it was, it was structurally very similar to the, to the first
phase two trial, right? So you have older adults, same sort of age range. I think they had to be 65.
They couldn't have a pre-existing age-related condition, significant age-related condition.
They had a control placebo arm, ever Aligna alone, RTB101 alone, and both. And, and I'll be honest
with you, I don't remember the dosing on the RTB101. And so they looked at vaccine response.
And then they also looked at, in this study, upper respiratory tract infections over the next season
to look beyond just, you know, if there's an impact of the mTOR inhibitor on immune function,
is it specific to vaccines or does it look like it's broadly boosting immune function? And again,
I think you can, you know, you can look at the data and, and not be completely convinced,
but certainly for the ever Aligna's plus RTB101 and the RTB101 alone group,
I think the ever Aligna's alone group in this case didn't reach statistical significance,
but for the combination and the RTB101 alone group, they saw improved vaccine response. And I think
what was really striking was a lower risk of upper respiratory tract infection in the people
who'd gotten the mTOR inhibitor over the next season. So that suggested that not only is it
boosting vaccine response, but it's also broadly conferring protection against a variety of, of
immune challenges in this, this older population. And again, very, very little in the way of adverse
events, which, which gets back to the point, you know, you hear people talk about how mTOR inhibitors,
you know, you could never use them for aging and people, because the side effects are so bad.
And it, you know, it just gets frustrating over and over and over again to say,
go read the data, you know, go look at the data, right? That's just not true at the doses that,
that, you know, have been tested so far. It's just, that's just blatantly false, right? There's
no evidence actually for significant side effects from rapamycin monotherapy, ever Aligna's monotherapy,
or RTB 101, at the doses that people are talking about using in this context.
Yeah. I mean, statins have far, far greater side effects than rapamycin. I know.
I mean, it's not even close. And, you know, I think statins are a very important type of drug,
but, you know, I mean, to think that, to think how ubiquitous they are and that we accept, hey,
10% of people, I mean, I think the literature says 5%, but really clinically 10% of people
have debilitating muscle aches from statins that, you know, render it impossible to take them.
People, some people have elevated liver function tests that are otherwise unexplained. I mean,
yeah, it is, it is really frustrating for me to hear this, especially when people talk about
how, well, we could never really study rapamycin because, you know, it's just too
unsafe. It's like, I, I'm not sure what data you're pointing to, but when, when you have it,
let me know. Yeah. Yeah. I agree. So anyways, so that, so that was the second phase two trial,
which was successful. So then they went on to a phase three trial to, to hopefully get FDA
approval for improving vaccine response and immune function in elderly people. And in that phase
three trial, I'm trying to remember what they called that. They think they called it. I don't,
I don't remember the trial, but now what was rad 001? What was that agent? That's ever a limus.
That's the same. That's what they were calling ever a limus. Okay. Yes. Okay. Yeah. And they had
a name for the, all clinical trials have names. They had a name. I don't remember what it was,
but, but in that phase three clinical trial, they only tested RTB 101. So they, they took out
the rapalogue ever a limus and only tested RTB 101. So there was no rad 001 plus RTB 101. Okay.
That's right. No combination, no individual, a rapalogue. That's right. And that clinical trial
failed to hit the end point and it was, it was terminated halfway through. So they,
this is my understanding. They, they were going to do one group in the fall season and one group
in the spring season or something like that. And they got halfway through, they weren't hitting
their end point. So they terminated the trial early and, and then RTB 101 or sorry, Restore
Bio was the company that was doing this clinical trial to try to, to move RTB 101 through to
approval. They, the board basically merged them with a, with a CAR T cell therapy cancer company.
And they gave up on RTB 101 because of the failed clinical trial. So, you know, why that clinical
trial failed, I think still the data has not seen the light of day yet. I don't think there,
yeah, I don't think it's come out yet. So, so we don't know for sure what happened. I think,
you know, we can observe that the Rapalog wasn't in there anymore, right? That is one difference
between the two successful trials and the one that failed. And I believe Joan has talked about this
publicly that, that, that they also in conversations with the FDA were required to change the end point
from laboratory confirmed infections, right? That, that was the prior, that was the,
that was the end point. One of the end points in the phase two trial to something else, which
involved owner reported, or not owner, sorry, thinking about dog trials here, patient reported
symptoms as the end point and they didn't hit it. And so I think that, I think my understanding
from talking to Joan is that data will come out at some point and, you know, we'll be able to really
take a look and, and see, you know, what the drug was doing and what it, what it wasn't doing in that
third clinical trial. My intuition is that it probably worked and they probably got screwed
by being forced to change the end point of that clinical trial. And if that's the case,
then I think, you know, we really do need to have a conversation around the way that FDA, I mean,
we need to have this conversation anyway, but the way that FDA is approaching clinical trials
in the, the aging space, right? What, what needs to be shown for an appropriate end point
and what is the acceptable level of risk when the, the goal of the trial is to test whether or not
an intervention is affecting a functional decline that goes along with aging or aging itself,
right? And that's a, that's a bigger question. I certainly have plenty of thoughts around that. I
know there are lots of people in the field who are thinking about this and working on it. And some
have talked to FDA. It's a, it's a real challenge. And I think, I think that, and I don't want to
blame anything on FDA, right? I think that they are, the people at FDA want to do their jobs to
the best of their ability. I think there are constraints around the way that FDA is required
to work and the culture that does not in my view appropriately evaluate risk reward, right? I think
that there is a culture of, you know, the risk has to be extremely low in people who are of normal
health status for their age. I actually am trying very hard. I still slip, but I'm trying very hard
not to use the word healthy when we talk about aging or older people. I'm relatively healthy
for my age. I would say I'm probably in the top 10% health-wise for my age group. I am not as
healthy as I was 20 years ago. We already talked about this, right? So I'm a, you know, normal to
upper health status for my age, but I would not call a 65 year old, a typical 65 or 70 year old
healthy. They're not, they're functionally impaired. And we really need, we being, you know,
the regulators, society, policymakers, you know, really need, I think, to start taking a realistic
look at what normal aging is, right? It is a progressive, chronic decline in function
that at some point will lead to overt disease and with 100% probability will lead to death,
right? And so if we can intervene in that process to slow it down or reverse it,
there should be some level of risk that is acceptable for that potential outcome. And I
think that because we tend to think of 65, 70 year olds as healthy as opposed to functionally
impaired, it makes it really hard to have a rational discussion around what the appropriate
level of risk is. Matt, I think that is so astonishingly well said. And I've had so many
discussions with NIR and to a lesser extent, Steve Osted about the choice of metformin over
rapamycin in tame. And it always comes back to this point, which is the regulators will absolutely
positively not consider rapamycin, which of course comes back to this question, which is what are we
claiming to be studying and in whom? The other thing is the studies are being designed around
disease, progression of disease or outcomes of disease. So this really comes back to a broader
theme, which is where are we on the spectrum of understanding aging in the way that you're
defining it and getting it further away from the discrete definition that involves a disease?
Because until we really get people to center around that, your very eloquent explanation
of there being no such thing as a healthy 70 year old, until we realize that at the regulatory level,
right? At the policy level, even at the scientific level, it's going to be very difficult to study
the things that will have an opportunity to give step function changes in longevity.
Yeah. So let me start by pushing back on what you said about tame and metformin versus rapamycin,
because I think that's a myth that regulators would not allow you to do a clinical trial with
rapamycin, right? We just talked about three clinical trials that were done with mTOR inhibitors,
two of which were with everilimus, right? Which is essentially rapamycin. So I think that is
talked about as to why metformin was chosen for tame. I don't think that is true. And I don't
actually think that is the reason at all. I think that the FDA regulators- I push. I needle near
constantly about it. Well, I mean, honestly, I think there are good reasons why metformin
makes sense to test in that context, and there's data in people that support that. So I'm not
trying to say they should have used rapamycin. I think that people with expertise in the field
can come to differing opinions as to what the best shot on goal is, I guess is the way I would put it.
You're just saying, let's say we picked rapamycin. Let's just say we picked metformin because of
these reasons, but not because we thought that rapa wouldn't be safe enough, or the regulators
themselves would decline it. Yeah, I think they'd let you do the trial. Obviously, they would pay
attention to adverse events, and there would be concerns around adverse events, but they would
certainly let you do the trial, and that's been proven, right? I mean, Rest for Bio did the trial,
right? And it wasn't because of adverse events that it got shut down. I think that's the other
important point to make. I think the regulators at FDA are doing the best job that they can within
the constraints of how they are required to regulate drugs. I have a real problem with the
way we regulate drugs in this country, but I don't necessarily blame it on the people at FDA.
And I do think if you came to them with a clinical trial where you had an end point
that was quantitative and functional and related to quality of life in people,
they would let you do that clinical trial with rapamycin. I'm 100% certain of that.
The challenge is, I think the reason why this hasn't happened, one, rapamycin's off patent,
nobody's going to make money off of it. And two, there is a misplaced concern about side effects,
which we've already talked about. It's just not reality that the risk is significant at doses of
rapamycin that would be tested. So I think the real challenge though is identifying the right
end points for a clinical trial in aging. You're not going to do lifespan in people. We can do
it in dogs. You're not going to do it in people. I think we just have to accept that.
So what is the right approach? I don't even want to say the right approach because I don't think
there's one, but what are some approaches that one might consider if your goal is to move FDA
towards approving a drug in people of normal health status to prevent age-related functional
declines in disease, to target aging. That's what I mean when I say prevent age-related
functional declines in disease to target aging. So if your goal is to get there,
so what does that clinical trial look like? So the TAME trial is a specific example of one strategy,
which is to take people who already have one age-related disease and ask whether your intervention,
metformin in this case, can delay the onset of the second age-related disease. It's a comorbidity
trial. That makes a lot of sense because we know with pretty good precision how long that time
frame is on average from the first age-related disease to the second age-related disease. And so
you can quantitatively assess does your intervention increase that length of time. That's the rationale
behind TAME. In my personal view, the limitation of that approach is it's not a true healthy aging
study, right? It's not taking people who are who are of normal health status for their age and asking
whether the intervention can improve or extend the healthy period of life, right? So it's a
different design, but I totally get why that's TAME was designed that way. And I like the design. I
think there's a reasonable chance it'll work, but it's different from the way I would think about
a clinical trial in this space. What I would do is I would try to identify the best single endpoint
or set of endpoints that correspond to a significant functional deficit that impacts
quality of life in older people and assess whether or not my intervention improves that. And optimally
that endpoint would have quantitative markers that you could measure, right? To show that you've
improved it. So RestorBio went with immune function and they went with vaccine response initially and
then ultimately I think in the phase three trial they were also looking at respiratory tract
infections over the next season. That was their endpoint. It's quantitative. The problem is it's
really hard, right? It's a really noisy endpoint and I'm not at all criticizing them. In fact, I
think as you know, Joan Manick is one of my favorite people. She's a good friend. I have
an amazing amount of respect for her. I think they went for it and for reasons that were probably
beyond their control, that clinical trial failed. But I have so much respect for what they tried to
do. I'm just saying it's a tough clinical trial. It's a tough endpoint. It's noisy. I think there
are other endpoints that you could consider that might not be as noisy, right? That you could
consider doing a clinical trial for. So one of my favorites at this moment is periodontal disease.
And that's because my lab has published that aged mice get periodontal disease, that
eight weeks of treatment with rapamycin reverses the clinically defining features of periodontal
disease in mice. We know that something like two-thirds of older adults have periodontal disease
or will get it. And those who have periodontal disease are at higher risk for dementia,
cardiovascular disease, diabetes. So it's connected in some way to other age-related diseases.
And by the way, a recent podcast of mine explored this topic and it may in fact be causally related
through that inflammatory axis, right? I mean, I think that's probably the strongest line of
evidence connecting oral disease with systemic disease. It's through this immune inflammatory
pathway. So I think that's actually an elegant approach. So the reason why I like periodontal
disease, right, is the endpoints are extremely quantitative, right? So what we looked at in the
mice are gingival inflammation, bone around the teeth, which can be measured, you know,
crudely by pocket depth, more quantitatively by x-ray, and microbiome. That's really the,
at least in my understanding, I'm not a dentist, but I've learned a lot about oral health over the
last few years. That's my understanding of, you know, if you have gingival inflammation, you've
lost enough bone around the teeth, you don't even have to have the dysregulation of the oral
microbiome, but it always goes along with it. You've got periodontal disease, right? So there
are nice quantitative endpoints that can be looked at in people and it's extremely non-invasive,
right? The way that you do this clinical trial is you have people come in for a dental exam,
right, before and after treatment. So you've got a shot at seeing changes in quantitative endpoints
that we can not just delay, but actually reverse the declines in mice in people, you know, in a
reasonable timeframe. So you could easily imagine something similar to the structure of the Restore
Bio trial with Rapamycin or Everolimus or RTB101 or, you know, pick your favorite intervention,
where you treat people for eight weeks, three months, you know, they have a dental exam before,
a dental exam after, a dental exam six months later, and you just look and see what was the
impact of the intervention. So it's a pretty straightforward clinical trial. And, you know,
I think we're going to, I hope we will get this off the ground. We're actually trying to get some
funding to do a clinical trial now. This is, I should say, in humans or in dogs? In people,
yeah, in people. And this is really, the person who deserves all the credit for this crystallizing,
in my mind, is a gentleman named Jonathan Ahn, who was a DDS PhD student. So he had already got his
dental degree. He did his PhD with me. And he, you know, before he came to my lab, he came to me
one, one day, vividly remember this conversation because I had never thought about oral health.
And he goes, you know, people get periodontal disease when they get older in much the same
way that people get Alzheimer's disease or heart disease. If you look at the risk profile as a
function of age, it looks strikingly similar to these other age-related diseases. You know, what
do you think maybe the biology of aging is contributing? And, you know, in hindsight,
it's like, oh yeah, that makes a lot of sense. But I had never thought about that before.
And so he came to my lab and showed that we could do this in mice. We could see age-related
periodontal disease. We could see bone loss around the teeth. We could see inflammation of the gums.
And that we could reverse that with rapamycin. And so he's actually now a faculty member
at the University of Washington. And he's really the one who's trying to push this clinical trial
forward. So I'm sort of peripherally involved, but John is really the guy in this space. He's
going to be a rock star. And this would be a phase two? Yes, right. What's the approximate
budget for this study? I mean, we're just submitting the grant now. So I don't know,
you know, it's very early, right? What would be the budget for this study?
So it's going to be a three-year grant. You know, I don't know. I think it's R01 size,
couple hundred thousand a year over three years. Okay. If money were no object,
what secondary endpoints would you add to that study? In other words, if you could power this
study to hit that as your primary, but also go after multiple secondaries, let's just throw in
immune function. There'd be no reason not to repeat what was done with RAD 001. What else would you
add to that? Right. So if you look at the mouse data, I mean, I think the mouse data is,
it's a reasonable place to start. Again, obviously mice aren't people, but it's a reasonable place to
start. So where does rapamycin reverse functional declines associated with aging?
Hearing, right? Wasn't there that study that just came out? Yeah, just came out two weeks ago.
Absolutely. It reversed age-related hearing loss, which I, that was, that got me very excited.
Yeah, I agree. So that, and that's again, a very easy and quantitative endpoint, right? Wouldn't
it be amazing if you could improve age-related hearing loss with rapamycin? And so that's a
no-brainer immune function. I mean, I agree if money was no option, sure. But, but even in the
context of a, you know, let's say the periodontal disease clinical trial that I talked about,
if you could also measure hearing in that clinical trial, right? It's a big bang for the buck, right?
It costs you almost nothing. And you get potentially another endpoint that you could hit on.
Where else? So muscle function, there's pretty good evidence that at least rapamycin can prevent
sarcopenia. I don't think there's a lot of data yet on improvements in muscle function, but you
could do things like, you know, grip strength, walk speed, things like that. Cognitive function,
that's hard. Again, that's, I put that in the sort of the same category as immune function as an
endpoint. It's a tough endpoint, but it would certainly be interesting to look at cognitive
function in this elderly population of normal health status. So some of these people are going
to be on the road to dementia. They won't have dementia yet because that's an entrance criteria
to get into the trial. Heart function, it's another place where we see reversal of age-related
declines. This would be hard. So this is a different clinical trial, but also potentially
cool. Reproductive function, you wouldn't do that in that same patient population, probably.
But in mice, there's pretty good evidence that you can reverse, at least in females,
reproductive declines that go along with aging or at least delay them. Let's just pause on that
for a second, Matt. That is staggering when you consider where we are today from a standpoint of
reproductive medicine, right? Yeah. Women are having children later and later. And I can't tell
you the number of just patients in my practice, either male or female, for whom this isn't a top
of mind priority. It's simply unbelievable. And to think that there would be a... I never really
had thought of this, honestly, because I don't think I've paid attention to that subset of the
Rapa mice in literature. If you were to... And again, this is guessing, but how much of an impact
do you think you could have? So if you had a woman who was 40 years old, who's been... She's obviously
still pre-menopausal, but her AMH is low and or it's reasonable, but she's got significant
aneuploidy for the listener, meaning whenever her eggs are produced, they don't evenly divide
into the right number of chromosomes. So they don't show up with one of each chromosome. And
that's an enormous cause of infertility as a woman ages is this aneuploidy. So they either omit
a chromosome or include two and those almost universally lead to an early miscarriage. Some
of them like try some 13 or 21 will make it. Do you have a sense of what type of magnitude
of an effect this could have? I think the honest answer is no. So I think there's a couple of
things to say on this. One is there's not a lot. There've been, I think, two or three studies in
mice looking at this, right? And so there's not a lot of data on magnitude of effect,
even in mice. So my guess is that in people... So I don't even want to comment on magnitude of
effects. I really don't know. I think the way that you would design a clinical trial though
would be very similar to what we've talked about with rapid mycin already with the immune function
or periodontal disease. You would take a woman premenopausal, let's say early 40s,
a group of women and do eight weeks of treatment, right? And then a washout. And then you could
look at your endpoints or if they are going through IVF, for example, right? Look and see
whether or not you get an improvement in outcome using that functional measure.
I would... I think that's the way I would say...
Do we really believe that that would be a sufficient amount of time? I mean,
are we just coming up with eight weeks because that's where we saw the vaccine response
in the Evrolimus trial? If you were shooting for the moon and cost were not an issue,
what would be the downside of longer treatment?
Well, a couple of things, right? So one is increased risk of side effects, right? I mean,
I think that's one... The longer you go with any treatment, the more risk there is for an
adverse event, even though I think the risks are pretty low. And the other is, I think...
Here's a really interesting piece of data that we don't have with the immune function studies in
mice or people. In all of those studies, the treatment was stopped.
That's right.
And then there was a two week or so period before the vaccine was given.
So what was the rationale for that washout?
I think it's because people think and thought about rapamycin as an immune suppressant,
right? So that you might... And this is where I was going with that. What we don't know is if
they were still taking the drug, would you have gotten the same effects for immune function?
I don't know. So it's an important question that I think we just don't know the answer to.
But the other risk is that at least for some of your functional measures, if it requires,
let's say, hyperactivation of mTOR to get the response, you might impair that by doing
continued treatment with rapamycin. And at least all of the data that I've seen,
limited in people, extensive in mice, eight weeks is enough to give you essentially that
full benefit for whatever the functional output is that you're looking at.
Maybe not for lifespan, right? Maybe multiple eight week transient interventions would be
better than one. The only thing that I know of for data there is our study where we did three
months of rapamycin treatment between 20 and 23 months of age, and then let them go to the end of
life. The magnitude of effect was pretty similar to what the ITP saw. So it was reasonably close
to continuing treatment, but we don't know. But eight weeks in mice is... What would that be
in humans, right? Yeah, I know where you're going with that. If you were to linearly extrapolate
that, that would be a few years, right? And I agree with that. I think that the immune trials
that we've talked about suggest that that might be long enough. But I agree. We don't know is the
answer. I'll just say, so I haven't talked about my experience with rapamycin, and I really don't
talk about this publicly, but I'll do it here. So I've tried eight to 10 week courses of rapamycin
a couple of times. The most recent time, it was because this was probably spring of 2019. So I'm
pretty active. I play softball in the spring, and I noticed I had a lot of shoulder pain. And by
the end of the season, it was to the point where I couldn't throw a football. I couldn't go play
catch with my son. Actually, that's one of the hardest personal aging experiences I had,
was when we went across the street to the park and I was going to play catch with my son, and I
couldn't do it because my shoulder hurts so much. It was my right shoulder. And I thought I must have
a rotator cuff tear. I went in to see the specialist. Finally got diagnosed with frozen
shoulder, which is inflammation of the shoulder capsule, which happens to some people as they get
older. Extremely painful, completely limited my range of motion. And the doctor was like, well,
I could give you a shot of cortisol, but I don't really recommend it. That can degrade the cartilage.
Really, there's not a lot you can do. Some people, it goes away after a year. Some people just, you
just learn to live with it. And I was pretty depressed by that diagnosis, right? I was like,
at least if it was a rotator cuff tear, I could get surgery, get it fixed. So I go home and I'm
sitting there and I'm thinking, so I'm looking on the internet and I see, okay, it's an inflammation
of the shoulder capsule. I'm thinking to myself, what do I know that has anti-inflammatory effects,
you know, in the context of aging, right? Rapamycin. So I got some rapamycin and I did
eight weeks. And I mean, again, placebo effect is real, but this was so painful.
I don't believe it was placebo effect. Within two weeks, I had probably half my range of motion back.
Within eight weeks, I was back 95%. And were you just taking, were you just dosing once a week?
Once a week, eight migs once a week. Yeah. I mean, I couldn't do this two years ago, right? Because
it hurts so much, right? And now it doesn't hurt at all. Within eight weeks, and I want to be careful
because I want to say I'm not encouraging other people to go do this, but I am a true believer
after that experience, right? I don't think it's placebo effect. I don't see how it could be with
how painful it was, how real the limitations were on range of motion. So that goes to this
eight week question, at least for that indication, which I believe this was a real effect, eight weeks
was plenty and it hasn't come back, right? Which actually kind of makes sense with frozen shoulder.
I think when people recover from it, it doesn't always come back. So I think that again, a lot of
these age related conditions that are inflammatory driven, you can kind of reset that with an eight
week treatment and rapamycin. I suspect senolytics, if we had good senolytics, would do pretty much
the same thing. Do you think that rapamycin is itself a senolytic? I don't think it's a senolytic
in the sense that at least the classical way people have thought about senolytics where it
kills the senescent cell. I absolutely think it turns down the chronic inflammatory signaling
that is driven by P16, P21, NF-kappa-B. Yes, we see that in mice, multiple tissues, no question
about it. I also, I still think the senescence field is a little bit messy in the terminology.
I think a lot of what people call senescence isn't truly being derived from senescent cells,
the way that we think about them. It's P16, P21 mediated inflammatory cytokines, right?
Doesn't necessarily have to come from senescent cells. No question. Rapamycin shuts that off and
it shuts it off within eight weeks, at least in mice in a lot of tissues. And do you think it's
doing that independent of what it's doing at the mTOR or do you think that it's doing that through
mTOR? I would be shocked if it's not doing that through mTOR. I don't know of any good evidence
that rapamycin has off-target effects that aren't through mTOR. Yeah. Okay. And so really it's these
sasps getting whacked. That is how it would act through via the senescent pathway as opposed to
targeting a senescent cell directly. That's by the way, that's been my reading of the literature.
Would you agree with that? Yeah, it's really, I think that's right. I think in some way it shuts
off those chronic inflammatory signals. The secretories. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And maybe other
stuff, right? I mean, we always look at the sass because that's what we know. I mean, I think
this is natural in science. We look under the lamp post. We measure what we know to measure,
right? It would not shock me at all if there are other things that go along with the canonical
sass that senolytics or rapamycin or caloric restriction. I think that's a big part of
fasting. Fasting does the same thing, right? Tamps down on that chronic inflammatory signaling,
maybe through mTOR, maybe through other mechanisms. So I think that what we know about is part of it.
It wouldn't shock me if there were things we don't know about yet that also are contributing. Yeah.
But getting back to this eight week, right? That's how we got started. So I tend to think based on my
personal experience and the little bit of data from these two clinical trials, that that's probably
long enough for at least some endpoints that are driven primarily by immune dysregulation
and chronic inflammation. Yeah. I think two and a half years ago when I started, I was very strict
about eight on six off, eight on six off, eight on six off. And I don't know, a little while ago,
I just sort of said, yeah, I'm just not coming off. And I wish I had a biomarker to point to.
I wish I had some way of measuring whether this is the right thing to do or if eight four, eight
four, eight four. There's a symmetry to eight five because you'll get through exactly four cycles a
year. Maybe I do eight five, eight five, eight five, eight five. But it really frustrates me that
we don't have a biomarker for this. Yeah. Or aging in general. Yeah. For aging in general. So let's
talk a little bit about that. So what does that look like? I mean, when I had Eileen White on the
podcast, gosh, it's been maybe a year and a half now, we had a really interesting discussion about
why we don't even have biomarkers for autophagy. I mean, something that is so important and we
can't measure it. And this was important in the context of people who choose to calorically
restrict or fast, is fasting for a day long enough to generate a meaningful amount of autophagy in
a human, in a mouse it clearly is, but in a human is it? No idea. It's two days, three days, seven
days. Seven days is almost assuredly enough. It's a big difference between fasting for a day and
fasting for seven days. Why don't we have biomarkers for that? Why don't we have a biomarker that can
assess nutrient sensing better? Why don't we have a, I mean, you could argue we have some biomarkers,
we can measure telomere length, but you know my feelings on this, Matt, I'm in the camp that
thinks measuring telomere length is not helpful at all for aging. And I think there's plenty of
data to suggest that while telomere length is a very important marker of cellular division,
it really speaks very little about the organisms state of aging. Despite the popularity of that
biomarker, even the epigenetic clocks I don't find to be helpful. I find them to be far too,
and I'd like you to push back on this if you feel as much, but I've seen how easily they can be
manipulated by short-term interventions that don't seem biologically relevant.
Yeah, so I think I'll start with the epigenetic clock because everybody, that's a big, you know,
let's explain to people what that is. Let's start from the beginning. Assume people don't know what
an epigenetic clock is. Right, so the epigenetic clock refers to typically chemical marks on DNA
that regulate gene expression, whether or not, you know, the gene that is located at specific points
in your genome gets turned on or off. And what has been observed is that those marks change
with age in pretty much every organism where it's been studied, and that you can identify
patterns of change at specific locations in the genome. So specific changes in these chemical
marks with age that correlate very strongly with chronological age. And so that has led to the
idea that you can create clocks that look at specific changes in chemical marks in the
DNA, the genome, that are telling you something about how long that organism has been alive.
And then what sort of has emerged from that is that there may be, there are two things that have
emerged from that. One is you may be able to use that chronological aging clock to find individuals
whose marks don't fall on the line that you would expect it to fall on based on their chronological
age. In other words, you know, they have marks that make them look older or younger than their
chronological age says that they are. And so you might, you would hypothesize that those individuals
biologically, if those marks are really reflecting biological age, might be aging more slowly or more
quickly. And what's been shown is that indeed those individuals who tend to be off the line,
depending on whether they seem to be aging more slowly or more quickly, are at lower or higher
risk for specific diseases. So that adds some level of confidence that this epigenetic clock,
chronological epigenetic aging clock, is actually reflecting biological age. And so the idea is maybe
we can use that information to develop epigenetic clocks that will, in a predictive way, tell you
how old you are biologically, right? So you can get tests now, there are plenty of companies now
that are selling these things, where you can go buy your epigenetic blood test. Mostly this has
been done in blood cells. That's one limitation to think about is almost all of the literature in
humans is developed on epigenetic clocks from blood. And it's still, I think, a little bit of
a question, you know, what if the, even if this is reflecting biological age, it's the biological age
of your blood, which may or may not reflect the biological age of your entire body. But you can
buy tests now that based on your, you give them some of your blood, they will tell you your
epigenetic biological age or some number. So they're looking at PBMC, I assume?
I don't know. Honestly, I'm not involved in any of this stuff. So I don't know exactly what, yes,
most of the studies that have been published are PBMCs. They may even have saliva tests now. I don't
know, honestly, how these commercial companies are doing it. I mean, some of the clocks I've seen
where I've just immediately discounted them is when some of their inputs are things like glucose
level, vitamin D level, which are things that vary so much from day to day. And by the way,
are so easy to manipulate. Like you can take a vitamin D supplement or not take a vitamin D
supplement. You can, you know, have a high cortisol spike one morning and your glucose is
110 versus have a good sleep the night before and your glucose is 95. So something that's that
malleable, I just don't think makes sense as an ironclad marker of true biologic age.
Yeah. So let me take a step back. So the epigenetic clocks are probably the one that
people talk about the most and have gotten the most traction in the field. And I'm not,
I guess I'm a little bit of a skeptic, but I mean, I believe these clocks,
I believe the data and I believe that the correlations are extremely strong. I'm a
little bit worried still that there are so many data points in the epigenome that you can find
a pattern that will fit anything you go looking for. And that, so I'm a little bit worried about
the dimensionality of the data and whether or not, you know, it's pattern matching in some cases
rather than it's really truly going to be a robust predictor of biological age.
That probably reflects what is admittedly, you know, my limited understanding of the
mathematics behind a lot of the epigenetic clocks that have been built. So I don't view that as a
strong criticism. It's just a personal sort of concern that I have. So you're basically saying
without doing the complex mathematics to correct for so many, the multiple looks that you can take
at the data, you could be tricked. And I have not spent enough time looking at that either.
I would like to have Steve Horvath on the podcast at some point, because I think Steve could speak
to that probably better than anyone else. He's the expert. Yeah. So that's, but the other, the other
point I wanted to make is what you alluded to is now what people are doing is going beyond the
epigenetic clocks to try to look at every possible thing you could measure, sometimes combining that
with the epigenetic clock to build these super clocks or multi-clocks or multi-omic clocks.
Right. And I think there's huge power in that. But it also increases that dimensionality problem.
I just mentioned, because, you know, all of a sudden now you've got, if you're doing omics
stuff, you've got tens of thousands of additional data points that you can measure and you can fit
a pattern where a lot of this, and I think, I think even Steve and other people who are in the
epigenetic clock field would agree with this, where a lot of this has yet to really mature is in
getting us to biological explanations for what the patterns are telling us, right? What genes
are they that these, these marks are located at and are those in any way causal for, you know,
biological aging. So I think if you get to the point where you can understand mechanism,
it's going to be much more powerful. I also think though, this gets to the fundamental
challenge with biomarkers. And I think this is where you're dissatisfied. We have a lot of
biomarkers of aging. We just don't have any validated biomarkers of aging, right? And it's,
and it's a, it's a real, this has been a problem, you know, since I was a graduate student,
everybody's wanted biomarkers of aging. The, the NIA had a huge program where they, they did all
this funding to identify biomarkers of aging. I think it was back in the eighties, maybe before
my time nineties, maybe you can identify all sorts of things that correlate with age. How do you get
to the point of convincing yourself first and other people second, that these things are actually
telling you something about biological aging that can then be used to understand whether an
intervention is working first of all at the population level, but ultimately where we want
to get to is at the individual level, right? So what we all want is a test that you can take
and you can fast, you can do your fasting regimen. You can do your rapamycin, you can take metformin,
whatever. And you can come back and find out, is it working from this set of biomarkers? And,
and that's where we want to get to. And, and we're not there yet. I think everyone would agree.
I'm not sure when we're going to get there. So who's the natural owner of getting there? Because,
you know, I had this discussion with Steve Osted recently and he, he made the same point you did,
which is, look, the NIA tried to do this a long time ago and, and, and tried, you know,
validly, right? They put a lot of money into it. You could make the case that the technology
simply wasn't mature enough to do this. 30, 30 years later, we have a lot more tools at our
disposal, right? It's, it's, you've got, you've got the entire world of omics at your disposable.
Plus you've got machine learning plus, plus, plus. Is there any reason this couldn't be done today?
And if so, is this, this strikes me as a project that's almost too big for, for academics, right?
Cause it's too disjointed, but at the same time, it's not a particularly interesting, um, commercial
problem to solve because it's far too big an investment before you could get to why you would
care about it, right? A commercial problem is give me a drug. Yeah. But I'm arguing you can't
develop a drug really well without this. So who's like, there's a bit of a cart and a horse thing,
which is someone's got to pony up a lot of money to develop the foundation of a pyramid that will
ultimately become a great tool for drug discovery and, um, a much more streamlined manner in which
we could do clinical trials around this. Yeah. So, so I think it, I think the answer to your question
is it depends on whether you're talking about doing this pre-clinically or clinically, right?
I actually think this is a problem that is. Don't you think it has to be done both?
Well, eventually yes. It's, it's, it's a problem that can be solved today pre-clinically. Like
there is no real barrier to doing what you just said. So multi-omic analysis of aging in mice
with interventions, applying machine learning to identify patterns that predict the effect of
interventions and individual outcomes for longevity. You obviously have to think a little
bit about, you know, what, what can you measure? Um, if you want to do this longitudinally,
right? You can't kill them, the animals, right? Uh, um, so you could, you're sort of restricted
to blood, but so there are some practical aspects, but there's no, there's no technical barrier to,
to doing that now. Who should do it? Who might be doing it? Right? Um, I mean, I think this would
fall maybe in the realm of what Calico could do, right? They've got the resources, they've got the
expertise. Is there any evidence that Calico is interested in this type of a problem? Um, I think
so. I, I don't, I don't know. I don't honestly don't know anything about the inner workings of,
of Calico these days. Um, I think conceptually they are interested in, in multi-omic signatures
of different aging processes. I don't know if they've done this particular experiment. They
certainly have the resources and expertise to do it. Um, they're not the only ones, but they're the
first ones who come to mind and they sort of fit this space between true academia and industry,
right? Where they're kind of, they're kind of this interesting beast in the middle. Um, so I think
it could be done pre-clinically and you could actually then once you, let's just say you have
this test, right? You get to the end of day, you say, okay, these are the most predictive,
I don't know, whatever, 24 things that, that give you, you know, 95% confidence on remaining life,
right? Or whatever, whatever your end point is. Um, then you, you get that test and then you show
whether it works or not in an independent study. And if it does, I'd be pretty convinced, right? If
you can show me that you create this test and then you go do a separate experiment and you can predict
when the mice are six months old, how long they're going to live at an individual level, I'm impressed.
And if you can show that this intervention, when you treat them, makes the signature go in the way
that you think it should go and you can predict they're going to live 30% longer, I'm even more
impressed. I'll believe it at that point. That's not easy, but I think it's doable. I think we know
enough now and we've got enough things that we could measure that you could certainly, you could
certainly build the test and then whether it would work in the validation step or not, I don't know,
but I wouldn't, I think you could probably get it to work. Um, you can't take exactly that same
approach to people. And this gets back to that, that they know the same issue that we talked about
with clinical trials, right? It takes a long time to do the validation step and know that you have
actually changed somebody's biological state so that as they get older, they are at lower risk
for disease and are likely to live some X% longer. So you're almost obligated to have some level, you
have to have some level of faith in the test at that point, right? And I don't know, it's going to
be different for everybody. And I honestly don't know what the regulatory step has to be, right?
Before you could convince regulators that you can actually, you know, go out and tell the general
public that this test works. Although I will say there are already people doing that and the
regulators aren't doing anything about it as far as I can tell. So, you know, there you are.
Let's come back to your dogs. We spoke about them at length, um, three years ago when we sat down to,
to talk about rapamycin. But again, let's assume a clean slate and folks might not be familiar with
some of your work specifically around dogs and how working with companion dogs, uh, offers many
advantages over working in mice, beginning with some of the obvious, like they're far more
genetically similar to us. They live in our environment. Um, and you know, they also seem
to, to die of things that more closely replicate how we die. They die of heart failure. They die of
cancer, but not the same type of cancer that a mouse gets. That's almost genetically predetermined.
Yeah. So, um, so just to start from ground zero, uh, we, um, at the University of Washington and
Texas A&M and at several other institutions have a large project called the Dog Aging Project.
And so the goal of the Dog Aging Project, um, is really to understand the biology of aging in
companion dogs or pet dogs. Some people, when I say companion, some people think I mean,
you know, like, like seeing eye dogs or things like that. Yeah, no, pet dogs. Um,
and there are really two aspects of this project. One is a large scale longitudinal study of aging,
completely observational. The goal there is really just to understand what are the most important
genetic and environmental factors that influence healthy aging in dogs. And part of that, this is
getting back to the conversation we just had, is to measure as much as we can about those dogs
every year as they go through their lives, um, in order to be able to identify patterns,
right, that are associated with health outcomes during aging, lifespan, disease incidents. Um,
so in some respects, it's a similar approach as to what you would do if you wanted to create
biomarkers of aging, right? Um, so that's the longitudinal study of aging. The second goal,
and that, so one way to think about that is that's to try to understand aging in dogs.
The second goal, and this is really where I'm, you know, focused, uh, uh, largely is to do
something about it. So can we slow or reverse biological aging in pet dogs to increase healthy
lifespan? And so that, um, ultimately I hope will be a series of veterinary clinical trials
to test interventions to figure out can we slow aging, reduce disease, and increase lifespan
in pet dogs. The first clinical trial is with rapamycin. Um, and so that's our first shot on
goal, uh, but I hope it won't be the only one. Um, and so you talked about, so why, why dogs,
why pet dogs in particular? And I think you hit on, I think most of them, the most important,
um, reasons, right? So they've got this really interesting and powerful genetic architecture.
We have a couple hundred purebred breeds of dogs, which you can almost think of as inbred strains,
right? And then on top of that, we have this mixed breed population. Um, and that's coupled with,
with phenotypic diversity. So for almost any trait that you think about, dogs are more diverse
than people are even. Body size is a really easy one. Everybody can just think about the difference
between a great Dane and a Chihuahua. Um, so that combination of, of unique genetic architecture with,
with phenotypic diversity is really powerful for mapping genotype onto specific traits. And
lifespan is another case where you have this strong diversity, right? A great Dane will grow
old and die, you know, maybe in eight to 10 years. Uh, whereas a Chihuahua often will live to be 16,
17 years old. So, you know, we're talking a hundred percent difference in lifespan. Um,
so that, so, so that's really powerful for mapping genotype onto lifespan. Uh,
dogs share the human environment is, is another big one, right? And that's, that's for me, one of
the most important because we cannot model that in the laboratory. In fact, we do exactly the
opposite. We really try to limit variation in environment to extreme measures. Dogs share our
environment with the exception of diet, share almost all aspects of the, of the human environment.
And so that's a, a bridge in some ways between laboratory studies and, and human studies. And
as I've already alluded to, they age more rapidly than we do. Their lifespan is substantially
shorter. We all are familiar with the idea of one human year is about seven dog years, right?
That's just another way of saying dogs age about seven times faster than people do. Um, that's,
and we can talk about that. It's interesting. If you actually look at the epigenetic clock,
it's not a linear seven time rate, but, but they, but I think it's close enough, right? It's close
enough. Uh, and as you suggested, they age very similarly to the way that people do. They get
essentially all of the same age related diseases and they're all age related and they show the
same functional declines that people do. So dogs get arthritis as they get older, right? Uh, you,
you know, an arthritis is, I guess it's a disease, but it's also starts as a functional decline,
right? Anybody who's ever had an old dog, you will notice that your old dog doesn't move around as
much. Doesn't walk as fast, right? So, so, so they are going through the same changes with aging at
the functional level that we are. Again, it just happens seven to 10 times more quickly. So they're
very powerful animal in which to understand aging and test interventions for that reason.
And you can do it in a timeframe that's, that's, you know, feasible. That's again, I think, you
know, we've talked about the challenges with doing a clinical trial for lifespan in people, even if
we believe metformin is going to extend lifespan in people, you're not going to do a clinical trial
to prove that you can do that clinical trial in dogs. And so we've designed the, the rapamycin,
the test of rapamycin in aging dogs or triad. That's, that's what we call our clinical trial.
We've designed triad so that we'll be able, we'll be powered statistically powered to detect a 15%
change in, in lifespan within a three year window, right? So we can do a three year clinical trial,
reasonable cohort sizes to see an effect on lifespan that's comparable to what rapamycin
does in mice. That's a pretty high bar, Matt. That's are you at all worried you've underpowered
that given that you only have, and they're being administered the drug for the entire three years?
No. So, so yes. Yes, I'm worried that the study is underpowered. I will say from my experience now
we've done two safety clinical trials and this is our big clinical trial. So this is my third
veterinary clinical trial. I've learned that there are many reasons to be concerned
when you do a clinical trial. Clinical trials are a lot of guesswork. You have to take an educated
guess about a lot of different things. You can't test every dose. You can't test every duration.
You're, you know, you can't test, you know, an infinite number of study subjects. So I'm,
I'm worried about this clinical trial for many reasons. I think we've done the best that we can,
you know, given what we know and given the constraints that we have to work under
to give ourselves a reasonable shot. 15% might be a high bar, but it, you know, it's,
it's consistent with the lower end of what people see in mice. So the first study at the lower,
low dose of rapamycin in mice from the ITP had a 14% effect, I think in females and a 9% effect in
males. Subsequent studies at higher doses had larger effects. So do you expect to see a sex
difference in dogs? I don't know. I don't know. So people still don't completely understand
why female mice seems to respond to a given dose of rapamycin better than male mice. So it's
correlated with blood levels. So I think the simple idea is that, that male mice either take up
rapamycin less effectively or break it down more quickly. There's no evidence for that in dogs. We
will be measuring rapamycin levels in the dogs. So we will see if there is a difference in blood
concentration in females versus males from the limited data that we've got so far. We don't have
any evidence that that's the case in dogs. And I don't know of any evidence in people that that's
the case either. So that might be a mouse specific thing. I think there's this misperception that
rapamycin works better in female mice than in male mice. That's not true. At a given dose,
at a given plasma dose, we don't know if it's true, right? No, no. At a given dose in the food,
at lower doses, females show a bigger lifespan extension. When you go to higher doses,
the males catch up. And if you push it too far, you can actually find a dose where female mice,
the lifespan extension starts to go back the other direction and male mice actually get a
bigger lifespan extension. So I think it's more about effective concentration than it is a male
versus female, truly sex specific response. And in the dogs, you give it daily in their food?
No, no. So it's once a week. So this is a now, now, you know, guesswork, right? What's the best
way to do it? Now we're back into the alchemy. Yeah. So we've tested three times a week and once
a week, and we decided to go with once a week for triad. And, you know, it's a guess.
And how many migs per Kig are they getting? Is it one dose?
0.15 migs per Kig once a week. And that was based on our observations from 0.05 migs per Kig,
three times a week. Yeah. That's how we get, you know, 0.05 times three.
So let's talk about what might be going on in the ITPs, which I've had Rich Miller on.
Let me just come back first to the dog study. Because I want to make another point, which is
that you asked if I was concerned about being underpowered for a 15% lifespan effect. So lifespan
is our primary endpoint, right? Which is important because I think this is the first clinical trial
that has lifespan, you know, in a healthy or normal health status population as the endpoint.
I will say also, it's funny, because I get pushback from clinical people, you can't call
this a clinical trial. It's just in dogs. It's not in people. And I just simply respond that
a veterinary clinic is a clinic. It's a veterinary clinical trial. But it is a clinical trial. And I
think this is the first clinical trial with lifespan as the endpoint. I don't know if you can
hear my dog. I can. I can actually stop sparking. No, no, it's funny. It's totally appropriate that
as we're talking about dogs, we can hear the environment. So the point I want to make though
is that lifespan is our primary endpoint, but we are tracking multiple secondary endpoints to
give us a picture of is rapamycin broadly impacting the aging process. So we're looking
every six months, the dogs get echocardiograms to look at heart function. The dogs will be fitted
with activity monitors periodically to look at spontaneous activity. Every six months, the dogs
will get cognitive assessments to look at cognitive function. We're getting blood chemistry, serum
metabolome, fecal microbiome, and of course, we'll be tracking disease incidence as these dogs get
older. So, you know, over this three year window, I hope that even if we don't see that magnitude of
lifespan extension, and we don't reach statistical significance, if there is a broad effect on
multiple age related outcomes that we will be able to detect changes in other secondary endpoints.
What's the sample size? You're going to have two groups, placebo versus dose.
Right. Half placebo, half treatment. The goal, the intention is to randomize 350 dogs equally split
between the two groups. So 175 of each. And do you know roughly if you had gone with a 10%
effect size, how many that would have required? How many more?
I don't recall off top of my head. I think probably around 500. Yeah.
In your previous work, you had already got a sense of what was happening in animals with heart
failure. Remind people a little bit about that if they don't remember the first episode.
Sure. So there's really good data. Three, at least three, maybe four now,
studies from different labs in mice showing that if you look at age related declines in heart
function, particularly left ventricular function, so several measures of left ventricular function,
decline with age, that eight to 10 weeks of rapamycin is enough to reverse those changes
and make the young heart by echocardiography look functionally like a, make the old heart look like
a young heart. There's also data in mouse models of a few different types of heart failure. So
dilated cardiomyopathy is work that we've done in particular, where you can reverse dilated
cardiomyopathy in mice with rapamycin treatment. So I think there's really strong evidence in mice.
In our first clinical trial, which was, it was designed to really only be a safety trial. There
were 24 dogs. 16 got rapamycin, eight got the placebo, but we had the dogs also get echocardiograms
before and after the treatment period. And in that study, there were statistically significant
improvements in two measures, two of the three measures of left ventricular function by
echocardiography in the dogs that got rapamycin compared to the placebo. What was, I think,
to me most interesting in that data was that the improvements that we saw were exclusively found
in the dogs that came in with lower function. Now, one thing to note is none of these dogs
had functioned so low that it would be clinically diagnosed as heart failure. So,
it was normal age-related declines in function, and it was exclusively the dogs with the lowest
function that showed the improvements from rapamycin. That is an interesting observation,
which my gut feeling is real. Again, a small cohort, so I don't want to make it out to be
stronger than it is, but it also is intuitive. We know that individuals have individual
trajectories of aging and develop a unique spectrum of functional declines. It makes sense
that some of these interventions that are restoring function would primarily be effective
in people who've lost function. That's just intuitive. So, I think that's probably what we'll
see in our long-term study in triad, where we follow the dogs for three years,
is that there's going to be variation at baseline, and it might be the case that those
individuals that have the lowest function at baseline are the ones that are going to see the
biggest benefit, if there is a benefit at all. Now, in triad, will you be trying to create
somewhat of a homogeneous sample in size? By that, I mean the size of the dogs, or are you going to
be completely heterogeneous with respect to the size of the animal? And also, what is the age of
the animal? What are the exclusion criteria around the age on either end, lower high?
Age, they have to be at least seven years old to come into the study, so that'd be middle-aged.
We do have a size range, so the dogs have to be between 40 and 100 pounds to be randomized into
the study. So, it's not for little dogs? That's right. And the reason for that is not because we
have any reason to think rapamycin will work differently, or better, or worse than little dogs.
It's because big dogs age faster than small dogs. Let me come back to that in a minute, because that
might not be an oversimplification. But they certainly live shorter than small dogs and develop
many age-related diseases and functional declines at an accelerated rate compared to small dogs. So,
we need a population that's already middle-aged and that will be aging rapidly to be able to
see potential benefits from rapamycin in the time frame of this study. And that was all factored
into the power calculations, the demography of dogs in that age and weight range. I said that
it may not be completely accurate to say that big dogs age more rapidly than small dogs, because
there's a growing body of evidence, which we have some preliminary data in support of as well,
that for brain aging and cognitive function, that might not be the case. That the rate of
cognitive decline in big dogs looks, from a chronological sense, very, very similar to small
dogs. Even though the big dogs are dying at an earlier age, they don't seem to show accelerated
cognitive decline, which is interesting. And I think there's a little bit of data
in people, although obviously people don't show the same diversity in body size that dogs do,
so that's harder to see. It doesn't really seem to be the case that accelerated aging due to
increased body size is reflected in brain aging. And the mechanisms there might turn out to be
really interesting. So, just an observation that I've noticed recently and I think might be important.
You're using once a week dosing. Explain to people, because we just mentioned it briefly and then said
we'd come back to it now, we're going to bifurcate mTOR into mTOR complex 1, mTOR complex 2, give
people a sense of how those function and why it, on the one hand, is leading you to do what you're
doing, me to do what I'm doing, and why in some ways it makes it a little bit interesting why the
ITP found what it did with daily dosing. Let's tie all of that together, but first with an explanation
of how mTOR works. Sure. So, mTOR of course is a protein, it's a kinase, we already talked about
that, but it acts in a complex with other partner proteins. And so the mTOR protein acts in at least
two, I think there's only two that we know of, two different complexes called mTOR complex 1 or mTORC1
and mTOR complex 2 or mTORC2. And the difference between those complexes is that they have different
partner proteins for mTOR. So there are a couple of things that are the same across both complexes,
and then there are a set of partner proteins that are unique. And the two complexes do functionally
different things in the cell. So mTOR complex 1 is largely thought of as the mTOR complex that
is most responsive to nutrient levels. So when nutrient signals are low, that leads to lower
mTOR complex 1 activity, and mTOR complex 1 downstream is known to regulate things like autophagy,
mRNA translation, effects on metabolism. And mTOR complex 2 does different things. And I think we
know a lot about what mTOR complex 1 does. We know much less about what mTOR complex 2 does, although
people are studying that and learning more and more about what mTOR complex 2 does. From the
perspective of aging biology, people have focused almost exclusively on mTOR complex 1. There's a
little bit of data on C. elegans on mTOR complex 2 affecting lifespan. But outside of C. elegans,
almost all of the data for rapamycin or mTOR as a regulator of aging is thought to be mediated by
inhibition or reduced signaling through mTOR complex 1. So that's what people almost always
think about when they think about effects of mTOR on aging. And rapamycin as a drug, biochemically,
is a specific inhibitor of mTOR complex 1. So the way rapamycin works is it actually,
it's a small molecule that binds to another protein called FKBP12 or FPR1 in yeast. And once
rapamycin binds to FKBP12, that complex of rapamycin with FKBP12 goes to mTOR complex 1,
and you can think of it as sort of just messing it up, breaks it apart. So it inhibits mTOR complex 1
when rapamycin is bind to FKBP12. So biochemically, rapamycin is an extremely clean drug,
and that as far as I know, and I haven't really seen any good data otherwise, there's no direct
inhibitory effect of rapamycin on anything other than mTOR complex 1. What people have observed
is that chronic long-term inhibition of mTOR complex 1 can have feedback effects on mTOR complex 2.
And it's kind of confusing because there's actually some data both directions that chronic
inhibition of mTOR complex 1 can lead to activation of mTOR complex 2 in some context. Mostly, I think
the data supports the idea that chronic inhibition of mTOR complex 1 with rapamycin can lead to
inhibition of mTOR complex 2 in the long term. And that's definitely true in mice at higher doses of
rapamycin. At lower doses of rapamycin, it's not completely clear to me how much effect on mTOR
complex 2 there is. So the reason why that's interesting from the perspective of aging is
I just said that almost all of the data for lifespan at least is that it's inhibition of
mTOR complex 1 that leads to lifespan extension. Work from David Sabatini and Dudley Lamming when
he was in David's lab led to the development of a model which I think is still the sort of preferred
model. I will say up front, I think it's at least partly wrong, but it's the preferred model which
is that the side effects associated with rapamycin, particularly the metabolic side effects associated
with rapamycin, are due to this chronic effect of inhibiting mTOR complex 2. So people will talk
about rapamycin as if it induces something like diabetes, a pseudo-diabetes. And this is true in
mice. There's evidence for it in humans as well that chronic long-term treatment with rapamycin
leads to glucose intolerance. So if you give a mouse who's been on rapamycin for a year,
glucose tolerance test, they will not clear that glucose as rapidly as a mouse that never saw
rapamycin. And the model is that that's due to the chronic effects of rapamycin on mTOR complex 2.
Most of the evidence in support of that model comes from genetic experiments with mTOR complex
2 deficient mice. So I have yet to see a really clean experiment showing that that's what accounts
for the rapamycin effects on glucose tolerance. I think it's a reasonable model. In other words,
that evidence comes from creating genetic mice where you manipulate mTOR quantum mTOR2
rather than experiments where you give them mice rapamycin. I didn't ask Rich Miller this question
because I'm pretty sure the answer is they didn't do it. But in all of the ITPs where the animals
are getting rapamycin every single day, did they see impaired glucose tolerance despite longer life?
Yeah, my recollection is they did not look, but there have been other studies,
I think mostly in the C57 Black 6J mouse strain. So that's a different strain than the ITP,
we don't need to get into it, but it's a different genetic background. But in the C57
background, you do see the same changes in glucose tolerance test at the 42 part per million for sure
rapamycin dose. So the higher ITP dose in older mice. So I think it's a real effect. I think you
see that effect with rapamycin. And like I said, there's evidence in organ transplant patients
for impaired glucose homeostasis as well. So I think it's a real effect. There's a couple of
things that I actually, my intuition is it probably is due to mTORC2. I don't have any
reason to doubt that. I just don't think it's been shown cleanly that that's the mechanism.
Where I differ a little bit, certainly from Dudley, I'm not sure what David's view on this
is right now. Where I differ from Dudley's interpretation is that I am less convinced
that these effects that we see for glucose homeostasis are bad. I think there's at least
as much likelihood that what this really reflects is an underlying change in metabolism
that might actually account for part of the beneficial effects of rapamycin, where they
shift away from primarily relying on glucose as the preferred carbon source and switch over to
fat metabolism and maybe even ketogenesis to some extent. And in that context, so it's a different
physiological metabolic state. In that context, when you challenge them with a non-physiological
amount of glucose, they don't respond the same way. So I don't know that it's actually a defect
in glucose homeostasis. I think it may reflect the test that's done. And in some ways it's an
artifact of that test that you get a different response, which is in the context of diabetes
would be interpreted as a bad response. It might just reflect a different underlying physiological
state. And I haven't seen anybody really try to address that. And what makes me believe that
might be the case is we and others have seen that rapamycin treatment has pretty profound effects on
fat mobilization, fat metabolism, adipogenesis, and at higher doses, ketogenesis. And so it would
not surprise me at all if that metabolic adaptation accounts for some of the beneficial
effects of rapamycin and is also leading to this apparent, aberrant response to a glucose tolerance
test. Yeah, it's interesting. I've spoken with one other physician who uses rapamycin, although he
uses it very liberally in many of his patients. I think his patients are coming in much older and
much more metabolically deranged. And the results that he's seeing in an uncontrolled manner,
meaning you simply have no idea what the performance effect of rapamycin is. So when
you give it to somebody who's expecting to get better, they may go and change many other behaviors.
But he's shared with me some of his data and it's quite profound, right? So triglycerides falling
from unhealthy levels of 200 milligrams per deciliter to 70 milligrams per deciliter. And
actually they're seeing the opposite, right? They're seeing improved glucose homeostasis.
Again, these are people starting who are prediabetic and in some cases diabetic.
And I think your point's a fair one about oral glucose tolerance tests are very unnatural.
And you can see a physiologic insulin resistance when you do them on people who are either calorie
restricted or carbohydrate restricted because that initial form of muscle insulin resistance is
actually a protective element there. So all of that said, you've decided to go with once a week
rather than daily, despite all of the other animal models that have shown great success with
daily dosing. Is that a hedge? Yeah, so there's a couple... I don't know if I would define it as a
hedge. I mean, I think that... So the rationale there is both based on the human data, which
again is limited, right? But we've talked about the daily versus weekly dosing for immune function.
And again, we've also talked about why I think that readouts of immune function
are probably telling us about the underlying inflammatory state, which I think is a big part
of what rapamycin is doing. So that is suggestive that weekly dosing is at least as good as daily
dosing. And it's also suggestive that weekly dosing has fewer side effects. And because this
is a challenge with human clinical trials, as we've already talked about, it's also something
you have to be absolutely aware of when you're talking about doing a clinical trial in
companion dogs, right? These are people's pets. There is an extremely, rightly so, an extremely
low tolerance for significant side effects when we're talking about people's pets, right? I love
my dog and I would be devastated if I hurt anybody else's dog in this clinical trial.
So you want to do everything you can to reduce the likelihood of side effects. And there's reason to
believe that once weekly dosing is likely to have fewer side effects. And there's also the pragmatic
aspect of, we're asking owners to give this medication to their dog in the context of a
clinical trial. We expect that there will be better compliance and fewer mistakes with once a week
dosing versus daily dosing or three times a week. So let's pivot a bit from Rapa to Torin 2. You
recently, you and I have shared a couple of emails on this topic. Tell people a little
bit about what that is and why you're excited. Right. So Torin 2 is a different version of an
mTOR inhibitor. So we just talked about mTOR complex 1 and mTOR complex 2 and how Rapamycin,
at least biochemically, is a specific inhibitor of mTOR complex 1. Torin 2 is what's called a
catalytic inhibitor or an ATP competitive inhibitor of mTOR, which at least in theory-
Versus what we call allosteric.
Allosteric inhibitor, which is Rapamycin, meaning it interacts not through the catalytic site. Yes.
At least in theory, Torin 2 and Torin 1 and other catalytic inhibitors will equally inhibit both
mTOR complex 1 and mTOR complex 2. And for reasons that I still am not sure about,
as far as I know, nobody has tested Torin 2, Torin 1, other catalytic inhibitors
for effects on aging in mice. It seems like an obvious-
Why is this not-
Yeah, this seems like something that needs to be submitted to ITP tomorrow, right? Or at
least for the next cycle.
Yeah. I don't know. I don't know why it hasn't been done, to be honest with you. And maybe it has
and I just haven't seen the data. That certainly is possible. But I don't know of any data, not
just for lifespan, but for other functional measures of aging. I don't know of any data.
So I don't know that I would say I'm- I can tell you why I think there's additional reason to test
it beyond the rationale that seems obvious. But I don't know that I would say I'm excited about
Torin 2. It seems like an obvious gap in knowledge and would be actually a nice way to test the
question we were talking about previously of Torque 1 versus Torque 2, good, bad, right? All of that
stuff. It seems like an important set of experiments to do. And as far as I know, nobody's done it.
So part of the reason, additional reason why I think it's an interesting set of experiments to do
is, in addition to studying aging, my lab also works on mitochondrial dysfunction and mitochondrial
disease. And we have worked for many years in a mouse model of a childhood mitochondrial disease
called Lee syndrome. So this mouse is defective in complex one of the electron transport chain
of the mitochondria. And it is very short-lived. It lives about 55, 60 days. And it develops
many of the same molecular phenotypes and neurological phenotypes as kids who have
Lee syndrome, this childhood mitochondrial disease. And these children typically live how long?
It's variable onset, but it's anywhere from infants to eight, nine years old. Typically,
kids with Lee syndrome don't make it to be teenagers. It's a horrible, horrible disorder.
So we found out many years ago that rapamycin could roughly double or triple the survival of
these mice and basically prevent the neurodegeneration and brain lesions that
are thought to limit lifespan in both the mice and the kids with Lee syndrome.
And presumably, Matt, that's because when you knock out complex one, you're destroying oxidative
phosphorylation. And presumably, the neurons are going to be the most sensitive to that.
Yeah.
Is that the thinking?
It's an interesting question. We don't really know. I mean, I'll tell you the sort of current
thinking in the field. So first thing is to recognize is this particular component of complex
one is an accessory stabilizing factor. So the mice are not 100% deficient in complex one. They
have a low level of complex one. I think you'd probably be dead if you didn't have any complex
one. And the same thing is true in the patients. So it's a deficiency in complex one. And you're
right. So one idea, there are actually several reasons why being deficient in complex one
could be a problem. One could be you just can't generate enough ATP and neurons or a subset of
neurons are particularly sensitive. Another could be that you're generating high levels of reactive
oxygen species. We know subsets of neurons are especially sensitive to that. And you could come
up. There's also an inflammatory component to this disease where we see a lot of neuroinflammation in
the brain regions where the lesions occur. So we don't quite understand what's causing that
inflammation. So there are multiple ways that this could be causing the symptoms of the disease.
An interesting body of work from Vamsee Mutha's lab and Isha Jane, who was in his lab and now has
her own lab, shows that hypoxia can also rescue these mice. And hypoxia actually rescues these
mice to a greater extent than rapamycin. So that at least is consistent with an oxidative stress
model. So one idea would be that when you're deficient in complex one, those neurons are not
using as much oxygen because they've switched over to non-oxidative glycolytic metabolism
and fermentation. So you have higher oxygen levels in the brain that leads to higher oxidative
damage. When you reduce oxygen through hypoxia, you've suppressed that. By the way, have you ever
tried the experiment where you give them excessive amounts of lactate, which neurons like lactate,
and if you gave them lactate in theory, you would also come up with a way to bypass the ETC. I mean,
it would be an interesting control or way to test that hypothesis. We've never tried that. So what I
can tell you is they have higher levels of lactate in their blood. That's common in mitochondrial
disease because they switch over to fermentation. But that doesn't mean that your experiment
wouldn't work. It's just an observation. And rapamycin suppresses that high level of lactate,
interestingly, as well as the accumulation of all the glycolytic intermediates upstream of lactate.
So anyways, oxidative stress is that there's at least some reason to believe that oxidative stress
is important. Another phenotype that these mice get is a dramatic loss of fat. So they are extremely
lean and rapamycin suppresses that. So we think that there is some... we know there's something
going on with fat mobilization, adipogenesis, when we treat with rapamycin that spares those mice
from presumably using up all their fat. Presumably they're trying to burn the fat in some way.
And that's why they become so lean. So that's another observation. So how do we get to mTORC2
and Torin2? So we did a phosphoproteomic study with Judith Villan, who's at the University of
Washington in Genome Sciences, to try to just take a sort of a global picture and ask,
what is the effect of rapamycin on the proteome and the phosphoproteome in the knockout mice
compared to wild type and then with rapamycin treatment? There was a lot of interesting stuff
in there. This work is published. It was published in Nature Metabolism, I don't know, several months
ago. So if people are interested, they can look at that paper. There's a lot of interesting stuff
in that proteomic data set. But one of the striking things that we saw was that mTORC2 components were
at the protein level decreased, which actually fits with the idea that high-dose rapamycin
chronically leads to inhibition of mTORC2. And associated with that was an inhibition of
protein kinase C, which is another kinase that's regulated by mTORC2. So that led us to hypothesize
that... and protein kinase C is known to regulate some aspects of inflammation. So that led us to
hypothesize that maybe some of the effects of rapamycin, at least in this mouse model, are through
protein kinase C and mTORC2, as opposed to what we had assumed was all mTORC1 related effects
of rapamycin. So we tested a few drugs that are known inhibitors of protein kinase C,
and they rescued part of the lifespan of the mitochondrial disease mice. So it weren't as
good as rapamycin, but they did give significant increases in survival and delayed some of the
neurological symptoms that the mice experience. So that is consistent with the idea that this
inhibition of mTORC2, inhibition of protein kinase C, is part of the effect of rapamycin.
So now we've gone back and we've tested Torin-2 in this mitochondrial disease model,
seems to work, you know, as well as rapamycin, which is interesting. No negative side effects
that we can see from inhibiting Torc2 in that context. And then we're also working in another
mouse model of a severe metabolic disease. And I think I'm not going to talk about it because this
is a collaboration and it's not published yet. And so I don't want to give away, you know, what the
initial observation was, really the observation of our collaborators. But let me just say in another
childhood metabolic disease, which is on the surface, completely unrelated to complex one of
the mitochondria, we see dramatic rescue from rapamycin and Torin-2. So this makes me wonder,
first of all, I thought for a long time that mitochondrial disease might be a good model for
normal aging in some respects. We know that, I mean, we talked about mitochondrial dysfunction
as one of the hallmarks of aging. So severe mitochondrial dysfunction, I would not argue,
is accelerated aging. But I think interventions that are effective in a model of severe mitochondrial
disease might also be effective in the context of normative aging. Everything we've seen so far
is consistent with that. And it makes me wonder if Torin-2 or other catalytic inhibitors of mTOR
might be as effective as rapamycin in the context of aging and maybe even more effective in the
context of some age-related indications. So to me, it just seems like a gaping hole in the literature
that, you know, really needs to be explored and, you know, we'll learn from doing that sort of
exploration. The other point that's interesting to make is RTB101, the drug we talked about previously
in the Restorbio Phase III clinical trial, is a catalytic inhibitor of mTOR as well as other
kinases. So it would fall, at least biochemically, into the Torin-2 class as opposed to the
rapamycin class. How is Torin-2 discovered or synthesized? Was it synthesized directly to be
a catalytic inhibitor? Was it discovered and modified? You know, David Sabatini would be
the person to ask. I should know the answer to that. So rapamycin is interesting, right?
Of course, we found that. It was found on Rapa Nui, made by bacteria. I think Torin-2 came out of a
more traditional sort of chemical screening as a mTOR inhibitor and then was modified to be a more
potent catalytic mTOR inhibitor. But I honestly don't know that literature. And does it already
have an IND? Is there already a molecule that's in a pipeline than an FDA pipeline? That's a good
question. I have looked a little bit, and I don't know of anybody who's developing Torin-2 or Torin-1,
which is another catalytic inhibitor for FDA approval. And I've wondered about this, and
honestly, I just haven't had the bandwidth to really dig into it. Is it because people
tried and there were side effects? I don't know. But I don't know of anybody who's actively
developing the Torins, at least, for FDA approval. RTB101, again, we talked about that's being
developed or has attempted to be developed for FDA approval. There are other dual kinase
inhibitors that are used clinically that hit mTOR in addition to other like a PI3 kinase,
a different class of kinase. So there are molecules that have similar types of activity,
but I don't know of anybody who's really trying hard to develop the more specific
mTOR catalytic inhibitors. And again, I'm not sure why.
Let's change gears for a second and talk about NAD, NR, NMN, all these things.
I've had David Sinclair on the podcast a couple of times. He's very eloquently explained what
Sirtuins are, how they work, why they require NAD. So for folks who want to get up to speed on that,
you can do so in great depth. Do you want to give the 30-second answer as to why Sirtuins matter
and why they need NAD? Sure. But I would start by saying that I'm not sure that Sirtuins are
the only or most important reason why NAD is important.
Sure.
So Sirtuins are a class of NAD dependent, mostly deacetylases. They also can do some other
activities. But basically one way to think about it is that Sirtuins
take acetyl groups off of other proteins, that's their activity, and that requires NAD. And it
actually consumes NAD. So NAD is a cofactor for many metabolic reactions where it gets converted
between NAD, which is the oxidized form of the coenzyme, and NADH, which is the reduced form.
Many, many different metabolic reactions use NAD in that way.
Including the electron transport chain.
Including the electron transport chain and glycolysis and fermentation, yes.
Sirtuins are fundamentally different in that they use up NAD. And so NAD is required for
their activity. NADH, the reduced form of NAD, is actually an inhibitor of Sirtuins.
So the NAD to NADH ratio can be used as a proxy of likely Sirtuin activity.
So Sirtuins are important in the aging field. This really goes back to my work as a graduate
student in yeast when I was a grad student with Lenny Grenti. When we first showed that you could
over express the yeast Sirtuin, which is called Sirtu, that's where Sirtuin comes from. So the
yeast protein is called Sirtu. If you over express Sirtu, you increase lifespan in yeast. And since
then other people have shown that activation or over expression of Sirtuins in worms or flies
or mice can have interesting effects on aging. You and David must have overlapped, right?
You guys must have both been in Lenny's lab at the same time.
David and I overlapped in Lenny's lab. He was a postdoc when I was a grad student. And I
got to give David, I mean, David and I have had our scientific disagreements over the years,
but I got to give David a ton of credit as a postdoc. He mentored me in important ways and I
think actually guided me to the project looking at Sirtu, which is what I just talked about when
we over expressed Sirtu. So David was a very important early influence on my scientific
career. And the Grenti lab at that time was full of really smart, I'm sure it's still full of really
smart people, but it was just a really great environment. It was a powerhouse. Yeah, with
lots of really fantastic scientists. So that was the first, and it was really Lenny's lab that
established Sirtuins as important in aging in multiple model systems. So in mice, I mean,
I think, you know, David might disagree with this a little bit, but I think if you're being honest,
right, the evidence that Sirtuins are potent regulators of lifespan in mice is mixed. It's not
strong. There are a couple of studies out of probably, you know, a dozen that have been
published, and there's probably two dozen that are unpublished where people saw no effects on lifespan
from manipulator or activating Sirtuins. There are a couple of studies that show in one case of a
brain specific activation of one of the Sirtuins called Sirti-1 could slightly extend lifespan.
And another that overexpression of a different Sirtuin, Sirti-6, could slightly extend lifespan,
I think, only in males, but nowhere near the reproducibility or magnitude of effect of other
things, including rapamycin. So the data on Sirtuins is broad, but the absolute effects on
lifespan at least are, in my personal view, unconvincing. Like it hasn't been broadly
replicated like rapamycin has, and they're not big. What we do see with Sirtuins is abundant
evidence that metabolic markers of health can be improved by activating Sirtuins. And in a few
other disease specific models, pretty good evidence, heart disease in particular, some evidence for
cognitive function as well, improvements in age related outcomes. So there's a lot of smoke there,
but I think there's a lot of confusion in the field about the relative strength of data for
different interventions. And at least in my view, there's really no comparison between the effects
you get from inhibiting mTOR and the effects at least so far that people have reported from
activating Sirtuins. It's like mTOR is head and shoulders above Sirtuins when it comes to
the magnitude of effect. Yeah, I think it would be impossible to dispute that. I don't think there
could be any dispute of that. What's interesting is if I were to tally up the number of questions
I get per month about NR and NMN versus rapalogs, the ratio is the exact opposite to the magnitude.
So if the effect size of rapamycin and the importance of mTOR is 10X that of Sirtuins,
it's flipped in the number of questions I get about it and just the pop culture awareness
of that. So let's put the marketing of that aside and talk about the chemistry of it for a moment.
Sure. So Sirtuins are NAD dependent enzymes. So they need NAD to do their action. And we've
already talked about in general, the model is that turning up Sirtuins is a good thing, that you're
going to get... if you're going to get benefits in the context of aging, that's going to happen from
activating Sirtuins. Again, that's probably a pretty massive oversimplification because there
are seven Sirtuins and they do different things and different things in different tissues, but
that's kind of where the field has gotten stuck. The idea is that activating Sirtuins is good.
And so if you accept that and NAD is an activator of Sirtuins, then more NAD is good. And there's
good evidence that NAD homeostasis becomes impaired with aging, that the ratio of NAD to NADH,
the oxidized to reduced form of NAD, in many tissues at least, shifts towards more NADH and
less NAD. And so that with age. And so the prediction would be that you would have declining
Sirtuin activity due to that metabolic shift. And I will also note, because I think this is important,
that in mitochondrial disease, you see the same shift. It's just much, much more pronounced.
You see a shift towards NADH and less NAD. And that's exactly what you see when mitochondria
are less functional because the cells will switch over to glycolysis and fermentation,
fermentation to lactate. And the whole reason why we ferment to lactate is to restore NAD levels.
Fermentation to lactate takes NADH and turns it back into NAD. So this probably reflects an
underlying metabolic defect, which could be mitochondrial in origin, that leads to this
shift towards the reduced form of NAD with age. So those two observations, less NAD, bad,
Sirtuins good, the prediction is that if we could boost NAD, that would be good. Because that would
then restore Sirtuin activity and have effects on aging. And so this led to the development and
popularization of these molecules called NAD precursors or NAD boosters. The two of which get
talked about the most are nicotinamide riboside, NR, that was kind of the first to gain popularity.
And then nicotinamide mononucleotide, NMN, both of those are precursors of NAD that within cells
can be converted into NAD. And so there's a large body of literature in a variety of model
organisms showing that treatment with NR or NMN sometimes leads to benefits that are associated
with healthy aging. And in one study, Lifespan Extension in MICE, I say sometimes because there's
also a large body of literature that doesn't reproduce those results. Including the ITP.
Including the ITP, that's right. Which is what I think has to be considered the gold standard for
at least MICE data. I think that's true. Although, as we talked about before, it's a different genetic
background than C57 Black 6. And I would argue it's a much better genetic background. I think
you can make that argument and there are good reasons to believe that argument. Nonetheless,
I think it's important to note that that could be why it worked in one context and it wasn't working
in another context. And we've struggled with this as well in my lab. So it's been reported in this
mitochondrial disease mouse by a collaborator of ours who I trust their data. That NMN could
increase lifespan in that mouse model. We've tried multiple times with both NR and NMN in that mouse
model and been unable to get these effects. So I think these drugs are tricky from a biological
efficacy perspective. There's something we don't understand about delivery or uptake.
Do you think they're temperature stable?
Probably, well, I don't know. I'm sure there are people who know the answer to that.
I've read conflicting things. I've read that, and I need to go back to the sources on it,
but I've read that at least through the lens in which they're provided as supplements,
the likelihood that by the time that thing arrives at your door, it still has the biologic activity
that it would have had in a refrigerated manner is low. Now, I don't know that the companies that
sell them recommend refrigerating them, but they might not recommend refrigerating them because
then it would imply that they're being shipped in an unrefrigerated manner, which nullifies the
whole benefit. But I don't know if you've looked at any of that.
We haven't. So definitely in our mouse studies, we are careful to keep the food in the refrigerator
until we put it in the mouse cage. I suspect that there certainly might be some truth to the idea
that the biological activity goes off over time at room temperature. But I think that reflects a
bigger problem with the NAD precursor field, which is that there's a lot of controversy even
among the two camps. So I mean, it's sort of funny, right? Because there's an NR camp of researchers
who really think NR is the tool that we should use. And then there's an NMN camp, and they both
say that the other camp, that their molecule doesn't work, right? Because it's not biologically
available or all sorts of reasons, right? So there's a lot of lack of clarity around
biological availability and efficacy with these molecules in the preclinical literature, right?
Where in theory, people should be able to exactly reproduce the way that other people do the work
and get the same results, right? There are lots of reasons why scientific results don't get replicated.
It's my impression that in the NAD precursor field, that's a bigger problem than in some other areas.
And I don't know the reasons for that. But all I can say is we've experienced that in my lab as well.
So I've tried to stay on the fence here because I think there's a ton of smoke, right? There's a ton
of smoke with sirtuins. There's a ton of smoke with NAD precursors that they can, if you do the
experiment the right way, have positive effects that look a lot like what we would expect for
something that's impacting the aging process. And as I said, I mean, it's funny because people who
are in the field, I think sometimes think of me as this anti-sirtuin guy, which is absolutely not
the truth. I'm the guy who first showed that you could overexpress a sirtuin and increase lifespan.
If anybody's going to be pro sirtuin, it's me. I think the problem is that I've seen a lot of
data that people have struggled to reproduce, right? And I just honestly don't know how to
interpret that. Whereas with rapamycin, it works for everybody, right? It's robust and everybody
gets the same result over and over and over again. So I'm less enthusiastic, I would say, about
sirtuins and NAD precursors as opposed to some other interventions, right, in the field. But I
think there's a lot of data that suggests that these molecules and that sirtuins are important
for aging. I think what we haven't done yet is figured out how to tweak the system in exactly
the right way to get robust and reproducible experimental results that I personally would
feel comfortable moving forward with clinically. And it might be that the answer is you have to
hit this system with two prongs. You have to provide more of the precursor and you have to
activate the sirtuin in the way that resveratrol attempted to do but wasn't doing, right? So maybe
the answer is it's both. Again, that's literally just- Yeah, right, sure. That's a possibility.
Yeah. The other thing that I find weird about the NAD precursor literature and the limited
work that's been done clinically is often, I mean, in principle, it should be trivial to determine
whether or not you have boosted NAD levels, right? If you treat somebody with an NAD precursor, we
know how to measure NAD. That's not hard. Okay? So we know what the biomarker is at least that far
in this case. And oftentimes that's not done. So, you know, if you're treating somebody with NR
or NMN and you're not increasing NAD levels in the blood or in your target tissue,
that should tell you something important, I would think.
Well, and the other question is, is increasing it in the blood sufficient?
That's a different question, but it is an important question. I agree. That's why I said
target tissue and we can't biopsy certain tissues, but we can biopsy some tissues. Yeah.
No, it's super messy. Look, I get asked about it at least once a week by patients and I usually
point them to something I've written on the subject matter. But in the end, I say, look,
I will say, I think it's very safe. I really don't see a downside other than to your pocketbook
of taking NR or NMN. So they check the first box of any intervention, which is,
is the downside sufficiently low? And I think the answer is yes. I'm just having a hard time
seeing upside. So yeah. And I'll tell you, honestly, I would love to test NR or NMN or both
in dogs for exactly that reason, right? Because there is essentially no risk and we could
actually find out, does it work? Three years from now, five years from now, I could tell you,
do NAD precursor slow aging, at least in pet dogs. And I think if I saw NR slow aging,
increased lifespan and or improved multiple functional measures of aging in dogs, I'd be
much more bullish on taking NR myself. Wouldn't prove it's going to work in people, but it
gets you a part way there and a pretty big part of the way there. And I would put that on the
shortlist of things I would like to test. The fact is nobody's going to do the definitive clinical
trial in people because they don't have to, because they can sell that stuff to people now,
right? They aren't required to do the clinical trial to show that it works.
Yeah. Matt, you probably don't remember this, but there was one night, oh, four,
four or five years ago. Are you making comments about my cognitive decline with aging?
I just don't think you'd remember some random night of us having dinner in New York, but
it was about four years ago. Is this with you, Shin?
Yes. Okay. Wow. You do have the cognitive function. So the three of us were having dinner
at my favorite, not my favorite, but a decent Persian place on the Upper East Side. And I don't
know if I said so at the time, but I might've told you after, it was after that dinner that I decided
I got to do a podcast because the three of us had such an enjoyable, she's at Einstein, isn't she?
She was, yeah. She's actually moved to Columbia. So now she's running a reproductive aging center
at Columbia now. Apropos with our discussion today. Right. But we just had such an amazing
discussion, which really means me asking the two of you guys nonstop questions. And I remember
thinking after that, goddamn, why didn't I record this dinner? Why didn't I have my phone sitting
on the table to record it? And it was literally that moment that made me realize this happens
the same time. Every time I go out with Sabatini, I have the same feeling. Every time I go out with
so-and-so, I have the same feeling, I got to just do this podcast thing. So for anybody listening
to this who is appreciative of the podcast, they owe you personally a great debt of gratitude
for always providing. I got to say, I'm sure it was you Shin who made most of the really
insightful comments at that dinner. I think it was both of you guys. But it is always such
an awesome time to be able to sit down with you. I think as the listener appreciates here,
the breadth of topics within the space of longevity that you can cover is broad. So you're
one of the few people who can go very wide and very deep. And I think today's discussion
demonstrated that. So thank you very much, Matt. Really, as always, enjoy this discussion.
Sure. Yeah. Anytime. I enjoy the discussion as much as you do, I think. So it's been a lot of fun.
All right. And best of luck with the triad study. I know a lot of people are probably more interested
in that than any of the human stuff because the dog owners I know care far more about what
Rapamycin can do for their dogs than they care about what it can do for them. So
hopefully we'll have those results by the next time we speak.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper,
person thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday
through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not
getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head
over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.