Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
All right, Bob, we got a pretty fun AMA today here. But before we do, I don't think I realized
until looking at your background that the Boston Bruins had a 30-year drought in which
they did not win their division. 1940 to 1970.
Oh, I'm glad I missed that drought. Was that when there were fewer teams?
Oh, yeah, there was only 16.
Really embarrassing.
Yeah, yeah. Well, it's not as embarrassing as the Maple Leafs, who haven't won the Stanley
Cup since, I think, 1967.
Oh, my goodness.
Well, if any team deserves a Stanley Cup, it's Toronto.
I enjoyed it. I think I sent you a video of a guy talking about, you know, that's bad enough,
but was it a year ago or a couple of years ago? They lost to a backup goaltender who was a Zamboni
driver for their-
Yeah, at the ACC.
... from Toronto Maple Leafs. Yeah.
That's a beautiful story, though.
Yeah.
All right, so we've got a pretty fun topic, an important topic on the docket today, which is
effectively kind of scratching the exercise itch as it pertains to longevity, but at a probably a
deeper level than folks are used to. So where should we start?
I think we should start with, well, aerobic fitness or cardio- respiratory fitness,
because I think we've got a few things that these questions have come in. I think a bunch of
questions related to this, which is studies that look at how much lean mass you have and whether
that is a predictor of longevity. And then there's also studies that talk about muscle strength,
not just muscle mass and whether that predicts longevity and whether one of those is better than
the other. But I think a good place to start is with cardio- respiratory fitness, with similar
question. You know, does better lead to less mortality and does lower cardio- respiratory
fitness lead to higher mortality or is it at least associated?
Okay, so let's start by kind of explaining to folks the metrics that we're going to talk
about through this. So the most common thing I think we see in the literature is either
METS-metabolic Equivalence or VO2MAX. And I think part of that is it's quite objective.
So if anybody's had a VO2MAX test, they'll understand how objective and unpleasant it is.
I think we've talked about this before, so you are hooked up to an indirect calorimeter. So it's a
device that provides complete occlusion around your mouth and your nose. Typically this device
also sort of plugs your nose so you're only breathing through your mouth. And the important
thing is that the device has two sensors on it. One sensor measures the concentration of oxygen
that is being expelled. And for the purpose of this discussion, that's the more important of the
sensors. But for what it's worth, the other one is also measuring the concentration of carbon
dioxide that's expelled. So because we know the concentration of oxygen and CO2 on the way in,
by knowing what comes out, and obviously oxygen will be lower, CO2 will be higher,
we know how much carbon dioxide was produced and how much oxygen was consumed. And knowing those
two things gives you a flow rate of VO2 and a VCO2. Those two pieces of information alone tell you
how much energy you're utilizing via something called the Fick equation, if I'm not mistaken.
So total energy consumption is 3.94 times VO2 plus I think it's 1.11 times VCO2 at any point
in time. So if you have for this minute, VO2 was this, VCO2 was that, you apply it to that equation
and it will tell you, you were utilizing 10 kilocalories per minute, which would be 600
kilocalories per hour. Which is, I do this sometimes when I'm doing my zone two. My zone two
tends to be about 780 kilocalories per hour. So interesting, but again, that's not how I test
zone two, I'm using lactate for zone two. But now what we're talking about is something different,
which is what is the maximum utilization of oxygen? So if you make somebody work harder and harder and
harder, so if they're on a bike and you keep adding wattage to the bike and they have to pedal against
more and more resistance, or if they're on a treadmill and you make them run faster and faster
and up at higher and higher incline, at some point they will reach a maximum, at which point they can
no longer utilize more oxygen. Now we're not going to go into the why right now, but I believe that
Alex Hutchinson and I covered that in some depth in our podcast, you may recall. And we talked about
some of the alveolar limitations, how much of that is being limited at the gas exchange surface,
versus how much is being exchanged in the actual, pardon, how much of that is being limited in the
muscle. But regardless of which of those it is, and it's possible it's a combination, or it's
possible that at low levels of fitness it's more in the muscle, and at high levels of fitness it
might be more in the lung. But that number is the VO2 max. When you're doing the test, it's
measured typically in liters per minute, but then we normalize it by body weight. So we normalize it
as liters per, well we do it actually as milliliters per kilogram per minute. So when you start to hear
the numbers that people kick around, the fittest of the fit are going to be north of 80. But what
does that mean? It means they're north of 80 milliliters of oxygen per kilogram per minute. And
I think actually Alex and I talked about that on the podcast, right? The highest ever recorded
person was probably about 96 or so. And any sort of elite athlete, elite cardiac type athlete,
so runner, cyclist, rower, those sorts of athletes, they're generally going to be above 70.
So what does that number tell us about mortality? I think that's a question. And I think we've got
some data to talk about that. So do you want to pull out one of these slides here? Yeah, let's
pull it up. All right, I've got to slide up now. Okay, so this took a group of people. Do you recall
how old they were? I don't, but I'm looking right here. Let's see, about 53 on average.
Okay. All right, mean age. So and it ran them through a VO2 max test and then it ranked them.
And low were people who scored, I believe in the bottom 25th percentile. These are non-equally
weighted groups if my memory serves me correctly. But I think that low were the people in the bottom
25th percentile. Check me on that. Below average, I think was 25th to 50 percentile and then 50 to
75th percentile was above average. And high was like 75th to maybe 95th. And elite was just that
top 5%. I'm probably off by a little bit, but directionally, that's true. I just want to make
sure people don't look at these and think that each of them represents 20% of the population.
Yeah, I think that's directionally accurate. I'm looking at the table one,
their patient demographics. It's interesting. So it's a total of 122,000 patients. And if you look
at the low, below average and above average and high, they're all about 30,000 participants in
each one of those groups. And then you've got the elite and there's a little over 3,500 versus the
30,000 that's split amongst those other groups. Got it. Yeah. Okay. So that's about what we just
said there. Okay. And we're looking at all-cause mortality here and you can see a pretty clear
trend. So two things stand out, right? The two things that stand out are there's kind of a
monotonic relationship between fitness and mortality. But the second thing that stands out is by far
the biggest gap is between the people in the bottom 25%, which are categorized as low fitness
and basically everyone above them. So if you go to the next figure, Bob, I think we get to see
this in a little bit more detail. Yes. Yeah. I like this figure frankly more because it allows
us to see a bit more interesting stuff. So here we can see both for all patients, so lumping
everyone in together, male and female, if you have low fitness and then comparing it to everybody
else, what's the risk reduction? So if you go from low to below average to above average to high to
elite, you can see what is the hazard ratio. So it's interesting, going from just being low to
being below average is a 50% reduction in mortality over a decade if you're starting in your fifties.
We're going to come back to that, but that is so important, right?
It is. It seems like a weird message to give to somebody that, I want you to be below average,
but that is definitely a step up from low in terms of how they categorize these.
That's right. If you then go from low to above average, it's about a 60% or 70% reduction in
mortality. And it just continues monotonically to increase. Again, the lowest improvement
is going from high to elite. That doesn't buy you a whole heck of a lot.
It is still statistically significant. And to see that, you have to look at
figure C. Again, this is going to be one of those podcasts where it's really going to be better to
watch this over video because the data just speak for themselves. And of course, the show notes are
going to include all of these. So make sure you're looking at this. But remember the hazard
ratio for mortality is the reciprocal of the hazard ratio of risk reduction. So tables A and
C are basically showing you similar things in the group comparison. So again, when I said that going
from high to elite didn't have as much of a benefit, you can see it has the smallest hazard ratio of
improvement in benefit or the reduction going from elite to... Sorry, going from high to elite.
It's 29%. But notice that the confidence interval does not cross one and therefore the p value is
less than 0.05. Now, here's what's interesting. What they've done, and you can see all of these
listed, right? So if you compare someone of low fitness to elite, it is a five fold difference
in mortality over a decade, which is pretty remarkable. And that's what they show you above.
They give you context. They put this in the context of other things that we commonly understand
as being problematic for mortality, namely smoking, coronary artery disease, type 2 diabetes,
hypertension, and end stage renal disease. So look at these differences, right? And I believe, Bob,
this is not just for someone who's currently smoking. This is if you've ever smoked, right?
Yes. I think it was previously used or used tobacco. So they're really looking at
the difference between never smokers. So you've never smoked in your lifetime to if you've ever
smoked. Okay. And that's a 41% increase in mortality over the decade. Coronary artery disease,
29%. Diabetes, 40%. High blood pressure, 21%. And the most of all of these things,
end stage renal disease, about 280% increase in mortality. Now we all understand what that means,
but now when you compare that to these, the differences in these fitness levels, it gives you,
at least in my opinion, a greater appreciation for how much improvement in mortality comes
from improving your fitness. So if you look at the biggest driver of mortality,
which would be end stage renal disease in this cohort, it's the same as going from low
cardio respiratory fitness to above average cardio respiratory fitness. So going from the
bottom 25th percentile to being in the 50th to 75th percentile, which is a totally achievable
feat as you'll see in a moment. Anything else you want to say about this, Bob,
aside from the fact that it's sort of stunning? It is. It's really striking. So one little pro
tip or amateur tip is when Peter was talking about the Peter was talking about the reciprocals
is that if you look at figure two, a, and then you look at figure two, C, and you look at the
group comparisons, if you want to see those, that plotted point, for example, on the way on the
right hand side of figure two, a elite versus low, you can take that you can look at figure two,
C, where it says low versus elite and the hazard ratio is five. You just take the mean, the
reciprocal is just take one divided by five and you get, but you get point two. And then if you
look at that, so then when you look at the chart, it seems it, it makes sense. And then high versus
low, for example, it's 3.9 for hazard ratio, which is about four. So one divided by four is about
0.25 that checks out. So just a little pro tip for the fans out there. And that's, that's helpful
because these graphs have a log linear axis. So it's not intuitive to look at these things,
you know, going from low to below average gives you half of the benefit, but you'll never get the
remaining half ever because that would imply immortality, which obviously isn't happening.
Okay. So now let's put some numbers to this because this is one of those things that we use
a lot with our patients because we want most of our patients, we want all of them doing this, but
not all of them are willing to do it, but we certainly want everybody to have a VO two max
test so that we can kind of benchmark them on their way to their centenarian Olympics. So let's
actually see what these numbers look like. I think there's another graph here, right?
Thank you for listening to today's sneak peek AMA episode of the drive. If you're interested
in hearing the complete version of this AMA, you'll want to become a member. We created a membership
program to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. Membership
benefits are many and beyond the complete episodes of the AMA each month, they include
the following ridiculously comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person,
and thing we discuss on each episode of the drive access to our private podcast feed. The
qualities, which were a super short podcast, typically less than five minutes released every
Tuesday through Friday, which highlight the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of the drive. This is particularly important for those of you who haven't heard all
of the back episodes, becomes a great way to go back and filter and decide which ones you want to
listen to in detail. Really steep discount codes for products I use and believe in, but for which
I don't get paid to endorse and benefits that we continue to add over time. If you want to learn
more and access these member only benefits, head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe.
Lastly, if you're already a member, but you're hearing this, it means you haven't downloaded our
member only podcast feed where you can get the full access to the AMA and you don't have to listen to
this. You can download that at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash members. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward
slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.