Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Dr. Rosenberg, thank you so much for making time. I know how busy you are. I know as much
as anybody how busy you are because I've sat next to you and watched how hard you work and
how tirelessly you work. So it really means a lot that you would make any amount of time
to sit and talk about what we're going to talk about today. I almost don't know where
to begin, but I can't help but want to begin chronologically with your life story because
you're probably one of the most focused people I've ever met, if not the most focused person
I've ever met. And that focus seems to have started at a very young age. Let's talk a
little bit about your childhood. You grew up in the Bronx, if I'm not mistaken, correct?
That's correct. I was born in the Bronx. If I recall, we're coming up to your 81st
birthday. So you were born, I think it's August 1st, 1940.
August 2nd, 1940.
Yeah. So what are your earliest memories of childhood as they pertain both to your love
of science and perhaps more importantly, your obsession with cancer?
So up until about the age of five or six, I wanted to be a cowboy. I have an older brother,
and we would talk about going out West together and riding on horses and doing all kinds of
exciting things. But the first things I remember, other than wanting to be a cowboy, occurred
when I was about five or six years old. And I've given a lot of thought to how that came
to pass. When I was about five or six, living at home, right at the end of the Second World War,
when all of the remarkable tragedies of the Holocaust sort of came home as my parents got
one postcard after another. I remember this, and they're suffering as they got word of relatives
that died in the death camps during the war. And I remember being so horrified by that
in terms of how evil people could be towards one another. And somewhere around that time,
I developed an almost spiritual desire to become a doctor, to do research and make progress in
helping people in alleviating suffering rather than causing suffering. And that persisted.
As I began to keep scrapbooks about anything I could find about medicine or research,
and I think it was in response to the horrors of that particular time that inspired me to not only
become a doctor, but to become a doctor who not only helped alleviate suffering now, but alleviate
potential suffering in the future by doing research. And I stuck with that right through
my education. Now, you did very well in high school because, or at least we've never spoken
about it, but I can only assume you did because you were accepted to the best medical school. And
not only that, but you did the combined bachelor's MD degree, which I assume would have been very
difficult to go straight into medical school from high school. But you somehow managed to
get into this six-year program. And so just talking about Hopkins for a moment,
what was the impression that that place left on you in what would have been, I guess, the late
fifties and early sixties? So I went into this six-year program. It was three years of college
and three years of medical school, knowing that I would want to get further education,
that I would take additional time. And I knew from the very beginning that I would go on to
get a PhD in one of the sciences. It turned out to be biophysics. And Hopkins was a very
nurturing environment with respect to that. As soon as I got to Hopkins, I started working
in a biology laboratory in the afternoons and evenings doing some very simple projects
in the biology lab. But I knew from the very beginning that I wasn't just going to try to
practice today's science, practice today's medicine, but rather try to create the medicine
of tomorrow. And that stuck with me for these last 60 or 70 years or so.
Who was the chief of surgery when you were there? Was Blalock still the chief of surgery?
Alfred Blalock, yes. And the medical school was not necessarily a terribly nurturing environment.
You were thrown in there and at rounds there seemed to be a spirit of
calling people to task in front of others. It wasn't the way that I thought education should
happen, but there were brilliant people around. And that's what I think is the most, probably one
of the single most important components of a good education. And that is being surrounded by people
who know a lot, know more than you, can inspire you. And that kind of person was at Hopkins.
Now, I remember when I was in medical school, when I was spending time with you and we got talking
one night and you explained that the reason you chose to do your PhD at Harvard in biophysics,
and this is as close to my remember as a direct quote as possible is,
you never wanted to be intimidated by a differential equation, which presumably was
a bit of a shortcut for you wanted the biggest or the broadest education possible. But what led to
that choice? I mean, at that point in time, for example, did you know you had an interest
in immunology? Have that piqued your curiosity yet? Or were you still thinking just more broadly?
I knew I was somehow interested in the mysteries of cancer through high school biology and in my
college, in my college classes. I got a PhD because I wanted more formal learning. I never wanted to
be intimidated by what I did not know. I wanted to be able to grasp any area of science and use
it to answer questions. And maybe differential equations were in the source of that. I ended up
doing a lot of math in graduate school, but it was more than that. I wanted to have the feeling
that I had a good enough broad background in the sciences because when I got that PhD in biophysics,
I was doing physical chemistry, quantum mechanics, thermodynamics. It was a lot of nonbiology in
biophysics. I wanted to have a background in the sciences such that if I encountered a problem,
I could get a good book, read some papers and understand it. And it was that base of knowledge
that I tried to acquire. So when you were doing your PhD, had you already applied to residency
or did you take time out between medical school and the application to residency?
So I went immediately into the surgical residency at the Peter Ben Brigham Hospital right out of
medical school and then took off four years to get a PhD in biophysics. So it was a year of
internship, took off four years and then went back to the residency and then came down to the NIH
for several years to join the immunology branch here. This was during the Vietnam War before
going back to actually finish the residency in 1974. Now was Franny Moore sort of the most
significant figure in your life at that point in time as a mentor? Franny Moore was the chief of
surgery and an incredibly smart person. There are an awful lot of smart people in that
educational system, but Franny stood out in that discussing a problem, discussing a patient,
it wouldn't be at all surprising for him to come up with an idea or an outlook or a perspective on
a problem that most people had not considered. So in that sense, he was an important figure. He was
not so much loved as respected, which is a feature that I think can be very inspiring to young people.
And was it unusual for someone to leave their internship or leave after their internship and
go into a PhD program at that time? Well, it was as a matter of fact. Brigham encouraged you to take
off a year or sometimes two years in the middle of the residency program, generally after two or
three years. But I knew at that point, I was just itching to learn more. I was just not satisfied
after medical school, the college and medical school, that I really knew enough to do
creditable, meaningful, impactful research. And so again, this was a real program. For two years,
I did nothing but study, nothing but take classes and study and learn. And then the latter two years
I spent in the research laboratory doing basically physical chemistry and protein
chemistry research of cell membranes. And Franny was supportive of this.
He was to an extent. To take that time off after internship required a few meetings. And I
ultimately, I remember sending him a note saying, look, I'm 23 years old. I've just finished the
residency. I need to do what I'm excited about. And he gave in and I have enormous respect for him
for that. And he was quite patient because I came back for a year and then I went down to the NIH to
was part of the Vietnam draft obligation. And he kept taking me back each time, which is very,
very nice. But turns out I set some kind of record at the Brigham. It took me 11 years from the time
that I started my internship to the time I actually finished the residency, which was some sort of
record at the record at the time. So you would have been a hold for a chief resident at that time.
I guess. Yes, I was what? I was 33, 34 by the time I had my first job.
But of course you made up for it because you sort of progressed so early at the outset.
As you know well, the book that you wrote with John Barry in 1992, The Transformed Cell, is a book.
I may have the record for most times reading it. I may also possess the record for most copies
owned, which I know you get a kick out of that. Every time I say something to that effect,
you basically say I'm one of the few people who's read it, which I know is not true.
But I still remember the first time I read it. And it's a remarkable story. I suspect many people
will go on to read it after this interview because it is in many ways one of the best books about
science, which I think was your motivation for writing it. And we'll come back to that. But in
it you talk about an important moment in your training, which occurred in 1968 with a patient
who you met in the ER one day. Can you tell us a little bit about that story and why it
altered the course of your career? Well, there were actually two patients that I saw early on,
or was familiar with early on, that influenced my thinking about cancer. The first was a patient I
saw when I was a junior resident at the West Roxbury VA Hospital. We rotated through there
three or four months at a time during the residency. And it was a 68-year-old fellow who
came in complaining of right up a quadrant pain. It looked like a typical gallbladder attack, and
I got pretty excited about it because it might be a patient that I might be able to perform one of
the first operations I was allowed to do. And so I looked into his chart, and a remarkable story
was encountered. I looked into the chart, and it turned out that 11 or 12 years earlier,
that patient had been seen at the West Roxbury VA Hospital. He had had a gastric cancer,
a stomach cancer. He had undergone a laparotomy, and I looked at the surgeon's note, saying that
he opened the belly. He saw a tumor that was encompassing about three-quarters of the stomach.
There were multiple liver metastases, deposits that were biopsied, shown to be the gastric cancer
that had spread, multiple enlarged, hardened nodes. And he took out part of the stomach,
I guess, as a palliative measure, left the rest of the disease in place, and the patient recovered,
and about a week later went home. Well, as I turned the page of the chart, the patient comes
back three months later. Nobody had expected to see him. And he was doing fine. He was gaining
weight. Six months later, he was back working. And here he was 12 years later, having lived the
past 10 or 11 years completely normally. And so I took part in removing his gallbladder under
supervision, of course. And his belly was completely clean of cancer. There was no evidence of cancer
of any kind. And we went back and looked at his, be sure it was the same patient, re-reviewed the
pathology. Sure enough, it was a cancer that had spontaneously disappeared over time in the absence
of any therapy. One of the rarest events in medicine, and that is to have the spontaneous
regression of cancer without any treatments being given. Somehow, his body had rejected the cancer.
And I then did what turned out, of course, to be a very naive experiment. But I was wondering
whether or not this patient who had somehow cured his own cancer could be somehow taken advantage of
to treat other patients. And it turned out we had another patient in the hospital with a gastric
cancer, a veteran, who happened to have the same blood type. And so I called up the head of the
surgery department, Brownie Wheeler, and said, hey, I want to take a blood transfusion from this
patient who spontaneously was cured and give it to this other patient. And he said, okay, that was
the IRB as existed at that time. And so we actually got blood from this one patient and infused it into
the other veteran. But of course, it didn't do anything. And the other patient ended up dying of
his gastric cancer. But at least planted the seed that, in fact, maybe there was something
in the immune system that caused the rejection of that cancer, much as you would a foreign transplant.
And the body's major defense mechanism, of course, against foreign invaders is the immune system.
It got me thinking about potential immune manipulations. But there was a second patient
that also influenced me a great deal. And that was a patient that had been seen about a year before
I came to the Brigham as an intern. And this was a patient who had received one of the early kidney
transplants that were developed and innovated at the Brigham Hospital. He had received a kidney
from a young individual who died in a motorcycle accident. And that kidney was transplanted into
the recipient. And the recipient developed widespread renal cell cancer. And it turned out,
after study, that the kidney that had been transplanted inadvertently had contained a renal
cancer. That then, in this other patient, under the influence of immunosuppressive medications,
had spread widely through his body. So in an attempt to control this, the immunosuppressive
medications were stopped. Of course, the kidney rejected and had to be removed.
But the patient's cancer then went away as well, because it, too, was allogeneic. It, too, came from
the genome of the original donor. So what did that teach one? Well, it showed that a large,
invasive, vascularized cancer could be caused to reject completely by the immune system. If you
had a strong enough stimulus, that could mediate that rejection. And so it was that spontaneous
regression. Maybe this demonstration that the immune system, more directly by removing
immunosuppressive medications, could result in tumor collapse and regression that tended to
put me on the path towards cancer. But I was already pretty much there because of what I had
seen as a doctor in cancer patients. Now, in the late 1960s, what was understood about the
human immune system as it pertained to even viruses, let alone cancer? I mean,
had MHC class one and class two been identified yet? I don't think they were identified until the
mid-70s, right? Class one in the 70s and the early 80s, class two. But when I started in 1974,
the idea of immunotherapy was a dream. There were anecdotes way back to the late 80s of
tumors going away when people got an infection, but really nothing stable. There was no ability
to measure an immune reaction against any cancer. There was no such thing as a cancer antigen that
had ever been found. There were no manipulations you could give that might work. So it was
a sort of a dark period when it came to knowledge about the immune system against cancer. It's a
little hard to understand just how frequent immunologic information developed. In the 1957
issue of the Journal of Immunology, the word lymphocyte was not in the index. We did not
understand what small lymphocytes did, what they were doing and circulating in the 1950s.
And so that information only came to pass in the early 60s when it was clear that
you could transfer immunity by transferring lymphocytes in a way that you could not do by
transferring blood or serum. And even in experimental animals, there was no manipulation
that could cause an existing cancer to disappear. You could immunize a mouse against a tumor by
letting it grow and then removing it and cause that mouse to resist an implantation of the same
tumor again. But once the tumor was growing, there was no maneuver that could keep it from
growing, no immunologic maneuver that could keep it from growing. So the field was desperately in
need of more information. So before we get to how you arrived at the NCI, well, actually let's talk
about that. It's a very unusual first job. How did it come about and what did you assume you would do
at the completion of this otherwise very long residency? So as you're indicating, I
finished my residency June 30th, 1974. And the next day I was appointed Chief of Surgery
at the National Cancer Institute, a position that I still hold. I'm still Chief of the Surgery
Branch now, what, 47 years later, 46 years later. The NIH, when I came here, I knew it was a
remarkable place. It had resources and a commitment, a mandate to make progress. It's a state-of-the-art
hospital that provides outstanding care to patients, but it exists again, not only to practice the best
of today's medicine, but to create the medicine of tomorrow. And that always intrigued me from my
first knowledge of the NIH when I came here in the midst of the residency during the Vietnam War.
Now you did have an offer to stay at Harvard, correct? Was Dana Farber still, was it in
existence at the time? Dana Farber was just being built, the hospital that was just being built.
Franny Moore, who was Chief of Surgery, offered me a position as the head of surgery in that new Dana
Farber institution. Emil Fry was the director of it and head of medical oncology, and he too offered
me the position. And I attentively accepted it, although we're in the midst of some negotiations
about whether there would be individual and independent operating rooms in the hospital
and so on. But in the course of that, I heard from one of the division directors here at the NIH,
who I had gotten to know when I was a fellow, who came to the Brigham to interview me.
He was wondering whether I would be interested in the position. And so he interviewed me, and
I was expecting to stay at the Brigham at Harvard, but one day I got a phone call from him saying
that the Chief of Surgery offered Ketchum was, had decided to retire, and the position was open July 1.
Was I interested? And I knew I was, but I had a call. My wife, Alice, told her about it. She said,
just pack, let's go, and off we went. Was Franny disappointed? Oh, it was a, it was a really shocking
encounter that I had with him, and that I went in to tell him I decided to go to the NIH. I thought
it was a place where I could best utilize my interests and knowledge, and he said no.
And I said, look, I've decided to do it. He said, you have to stay here. It's too great an opportunity
to turn down. And I said no, and he wasn't an easy guy to say no to, but I knew I wanted to
come back to the, to the NIH. And finally, after almost an hour, I finally said, Dr. Moore, I'm
not, I'm going down to Bethesda, Maryland. And I offered my hand, my hand to shake his hand
as I was going to leave, and he refused to shake my hand, which was a little shocking. But he got
over it finally. I left, and we became good friends, and he said all kinds of nice things about me when
he needed to. So it worked out well. You see, at that point, I knew I wanted to study cancer. I had
already made that absolute, absolute commitment, and the National Cancer Institute seemed like the
right way to, to do it. And in some sense, it was a logical decision from me, given my childhood
experience that got me interested in medicine and science. Cancer is such a devastating disease. It
attacks innocent people through no fault of their own. It makes them and their families watch
impotently as they progress and then die of cancer as a holocaust. And just seemed like the
kind of thing I wanted to study. So it was around this time, I guess, a little bit before this time
that Richard Nixon and that administration had declared a war on cancer. I believe it was just
a year prior to that. How did that resonate with you? Did you view that with great optimism?
Or did you think that it was naive that, you know, in a matter of years, cancer would be eradicated
in the same way that man had gone to the moon? Well, I had great hopes for making, for making
progress, perhaps naively, even at that point, not fully understanding all of the complexities.
The National Cancer Act mainly influenced funding outside of the NIH. The NIH was already, I thought,
well funded. Had a building that had been built in 1953, one of the largest buildings in this area,
dedicated to doing research. It had hospital beds. And so that National Cancer Act didn't have much
impact on the intramural NIH that I could see. But again, remember, I'm a worker bee. I became chief
of the surgery branch and have never advanced in the hierarchy. I was where I wanted to be. Turn
down a fair number of physicians. And so when it came to the influence of the National Cancer Act
on the country as a whole, I really wasn't involved with that very much at all. I focused
on the work that I wanted to do intramurally at the NIH. So how did you lay out a research agenda
when you arrived in 1974? You're now finally able to, not only with the resources of money,
but perhaps more importantly with the resources of time, lay out an agenda for hypotheses that
you want to test to build effectively a program to systematically narrow down the set of questions.
So what was the process by which you went about doing that? So when I came to the NIH,
knowing I wanted to study cancer, I started reading everything I possibly could about
therapeutic approaches, which at that point were simply surgery, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy,
most used alone. And it was clear to me at that point that although incremental advances had been
made over the years, surgery 3,000 years old, radiation therapy began immediately after
Renkin discovered x-rays in 1895, and chemotherapy arose in biological and chemical warfare
laboratories here at Fort Detrick in Dietrich, Maryland to attempt to develop these agents.
And it was in laboratory accidents in 1942 when nitrogen mustard was inadvertently exposed to
laboratory technicians and found to develop a lymphopenia throughout their body with their
lymph nodes shrinking down that led a Yale physician to attempt to use nitrogen mustard,
now known as melphalan, as a chemotherapy agent. And that was the birth of chemotherapy
in 1942, and that started chemicals to treat, search for chemicals to treat cancer.
But the advances that were being made were slowly and tiny incremental. I wanted something that big
that would make a big difference. And as I began to read about the immune system,
how little was known about it, but with the examples that I had, the intuition that I had
developed, which is so important in science, that this might be something valuable that I decided
to study immunology. I looked at everything I could read about, and it seemed to me that
the immune cells that were then being recognized as the mediators of organ rejection were the
agents that one needed to stimulate. And why not use an immune cell as a drug that has taken
advantage of a patient's own immune reactions to try to treat the disease, immunotherapy. And I
started with some unbelievably naive experiments. There was no way at that point to keep lymphocytes
alive outside the body. We're talking about 1974. You could take them out, and they would die in a
day or two. And you had no way to keep them alive. You could mix them with other cells,
and they would stimulate for a few days, but then they would die after about a week.
And yet I was desperate to try to use lymphocytes with immune reactivity to treat patients.
And so I began implanting human tumors into the mesentery of mini pigs. A good friend of mine,
David Sacks, here had developed a mini pig colony that was partially inbred at MHC Losai.
And so I would embed a tumor in the mesentery of these mini pigs, wait about two weeks, operate
and remove the inflamed lymph nodes that were draining that tumor, and gave those lymphocytes
to six patients. That is, we take out their tumor, generate lymphocytes,
react them against that tissue, and then harvest lymphocytes from that pig and administer them
intravenously to patients. And of course, nothing happened. But it's just a sign of how desperate I
was at that point to have some impact to be doing something. I have over the door of my lab,
you probably remember it, when you were in the lab, it said, it's a modification of a Louis Pasteur
saying that said, chance favors the prepared mind. And what I added to it was,
chance favors the prepared mind only if the mind is at work. And so I was trying things. And it was
only with the discovery of T cell growth factor in 1976 by Morgan, Rossetti and Gallo that opened
the door to be able to manipulate lymphocytes outside the body by putting them in a growth
factor called interleukin-2. And that was something I began to study quite intensively
to see if one couldn't then grow lymphocytes that had anti-tumor activity and would retain it as they
grew. None of that was known, but those were the first experiments I was doing along those lines.
Now, before we go further, I think it's worth making sure people understand some of the
semantics because obviously you and I can take so much of this for granted. But
let's start with some basics about cancer. How does one define cancer? What separates
a cancer cell from a non-cancer cell? Well, if you look at the broadest properties,
there are two properties that separate cancer from other cells in the body. The first is
uncontrolled growth. Virtually all of the tissues we have, either fingernails or eyebrows or you
name it, they'll grow to a given amount and then they'll stop. Well, cancers don't have that
signal to stop. They'll keep growing. And the second is it's the only cell that can arise in
one part of the body and spread and live and divide and grow in another part of the body.
And that's not true of virtually any other kind of cell. So cells with uncontrolled growth
that can spread and grow elsewhere are the biologic properties. Now, we can dig down layer
by layer by layer and get to the point of, well, why does a normal cell ultimately become a cancer
cell? And we now understand that that's due to the accumulation of mutations in DNA of these cells
divide, which explains why it's the common organs of the body, all of which have ducts. The lining
of those ducts are constantly turning over. And as that DNA is turning over, mistakes are made
called mutations. And it's that accumulation of mutations that results in the cancer itself. So
we can take it all the way from the biology of uncontrolled growth, but down to the very
molecules that are involved. We can describe it. It doesn't mean we really understand it all,
but we can describe it. And let's also explain to people the difference between the epithelial
tumors, the hematologic tumors, and even let's frame it as it was in 1974 in terms of what was
a person's odds of surviving. So maybe tell folks what the common epithelial tumors are and explain
a little bit about the, we're not going to go into staging in great detail, but what's the difference
between local tumor versus metastatic tumor and what's the impact that has on a person's survival
at the time you arrived at NCI? So the hematologic cancers, of course, are the blood cancers and they
start from progenitors in the hematopoietic system, because after all, the hematopoietic system starts
from an individual stem cell that then divides into multiple different characteristics, much as
we all grow from a single fertilized egg from one cell that makes us what we are.
So even back then, and a little more so now, if you developed a cancer of the bloodstream,
which were about 10% of all cancer deaths are due to those, 90% of cancer deaths are due to
the epithelial cancer. So these start in the solid organs of the body, and that goes all the way from
the rectum up through the GI tract, through the stomach, through the esophagus, the pancreas,
the GU organs, the testis, the ovary, the prostate. All of these solid organs have ducts,
and as I've mentioned, it's the epithelial lining of the ducts that are turning over that
become the cancer. In blood cancers, it's the more primordial cells that develop into neutrophils and
lymphocytes and other types of cells. So let's talk about the solid tumors, which are 90% of all
cancer deaths. Last year in the United States, there were about 600,000 deaths due to cancer,
550,000 were due to the solid epithelial cancers. If you operate on a patient who develops a cancer
to remove that cancer, then well over half the time that patient will be cured. That is, go on
and live their normal lifespan. But the half, a little less than half of patients that cannot
be cured result in this enormous tragedy of 600,000 innocent people dying of cancer every year.
Once the cancer spreads, however, and this in my view is a dirty little secret of oncology,
and that is that if a cancer spreads from its local site and cannot be surgically removed,
then the death rate in that patient is 100%. That is, we have virtually no
treatments that can cure, systemic treatments that can cure a patient with a metastatic solid
cancer that is one that has spread to a different site that can't be surgically resected. Now,
there are a couple of exceptions to that. There are two solid tumor exceptions that have existed
for several decades. One is choriocarcinoma. These are cancers that start in the placenta of pregnant
women that then spread, and you can have 90% of the lung replaced by that tumor, receive methotrexate,
a chemotherapy drug, and it will all disappear. Still don't understand exactly how. Germ cell
tumors in the male, tumors of the testis like Lance Armstrong, who had brain mets and lung mets,
no matter how much they've spread, if you give patients platinum-derived chemotherapy
regimens, you can cause complete, durable regression of that metastatic disease.
Up until 1985, those were the only cancers that could be cured. We can now add to that list,
solid cancers. We can now add to that list melanoma and renal cancer because Interleukin-2
administered the patients back in the mid-80s cause complete regressions of widely metastatic
cancer in patients that are still alive today. But that's it. Choriocarcinoma,
germ cell tumors, melanoma, renal cancer, other than those for everyone who develops
a spread cancer will die of it despite all the best treatments that we have. We read in the paper
that this celebrity has cancer and they're going to fight it and they're going to beat it, but
nobody beats it. We're in such desperate need of better treatments for patients with metastatic
cancers because we just, we can beat them back a little bit. We can improve survival by months
and for some cancers, maybe a few years like breast cancer and colon cancer, but everybody
ultimately will succumb to the disease. Well, and that's what I was actually going to ask you about,
which is if you think about the past 50 years in cancer and what you just said, I really,
I still starkly remember having those discussions as a medical student with you.
And the main point was we've basically just extended median survival of metastatic cancer,
but we haven't increased overall survival. And what would be the extent to which even median
survival has changed if we are just talking about stage four of the common cancers, breast,
colorectal, lung, pancreatic? How much has the needle been moved with respect to median
survival, notwithstanding the fact that overall survival hasn't changed?
Well, if you look at current papers and advertisements, most regimens that
ultimately get approved by the Food and Drug Administration prolong survival by
months. Probably the best example in modern oncology is treatment of metastatic colorectal
cancer. When I started median survival would have been maybe eight to 10 months. Now it's
two and a half years. So there's an example where life has been extended by years. Breast
cancer patients can go from one regimen to another, each one causing some temporary
regression of the cancer or limitation of its growth, but the cancer will ultimately grow and
the patient will have to move on to something else. And that's why cancer care is so remarkably
expensive because people just move from one treatment that can prolong life by a few weeks,
like a lot live in pancreatic cancer, six week improvement in survival. For $40,000, right?
For enormous toxicity and huge, huge life altering expense. The most frequently prescribed drug in
oncology today is a vastin, Bevacizumab, which can impact on blood vessels and tumors.
And the trials of that regimen in combination with others will prolong survival in patients
with colorectal cancer by about four and a half months. But those are the tiny increments,
which can provide substantial, some can provide substantial benefit to patients, but
not a curative and people are always living under the cloud of that cancer that is going to,
is going to regrow. So we need something more dramatic than the application of surgery,
radiation and chemotherapy barring some enormous advances in those fields.
And I think one other point worth making for folks with respect to chemotherapy,
I was actually just on the phone yesterday with one of my patients whose
wife is currently recovering from surgery, from a cancer. And he asked a question about the
efficacy of chemotherapy and how good is chemotherapy at killing cancer cells,
which I thought was an interesting question. And it led to a discussion where I said,
you know, the challenge with chemotherapy is not finding chemotherapeutic agents that can kill
cancer cells. You know, I made a point that he probably had 20 chemicals in his home and in his
garage that could kill every cancer cell remaining in his wife. The issue is how can you do that
selectively? How could you do that and not at the same time kill the normal cells? And I think
therein lies the arbitrage that needs to be exploited with chemotherapy and ultimately
what we're going to talk about, which is immunotherapy. But I think that's an important
point that many people don't understand, which is how difficult it is to thread the needle of
chemotherapy. It's not the killing of cancer that's hard. It's the killing of cancer and not
killing the non-cancer. No, the point you make is incredibly important because it's the selective
killing of cancer without killing normal cells, which is not the case for virtually any chemotherapy
or radiation therapy. Even in surgery, you have to remove some normal tissue. And so it's that
selectivity against the cancer that's so important. And in fact, that's almost the perfect
explanation for another reason that I think immunotherapy has potential importance because
of its immense selectivity and sensitivity of recognition. Can recognize single amino acid
changes in a protein and develop an immune response against it. Trivial differences that
can distinguish normal from tumor or if you get a viral infection, destroy the virus
in the respiratory system without destroying the respiratory epithelium. It's the exquisite
sensitivity and specificity of the immune reaction that I think makes it such a seductively
interesting approach to trying to develop new cancer treatments. Well, let's take a moment and
have people get a little bit deeper on how the immune system works. I remember for me personally
in medical school, it was one of the most interesting sets of courses we took where the
courses in immunology, in particular how T cells worked was fascinating. It seemed to lend itself
to a story almost and with generals and soldiers and all of these things. So explain to people,
let's maybe start with a virus as the example because obviously in the era of coronavirus,
that's on everybody's mind and we can talk about how the body defeats a virus, but then pivot to
then how in the case of cancer, that exact same immune system can accomplish what you just said.
So let's take viral infection as an example, whether it's a common cold or coronavirus.
The virus comes into the body and infects the respiratory epithelium in the
pharynx and the bronchi and the lung. And as that virus then infects those respiratory epithelium,
the virus replicates and the infected cells then express the viral proteins.
The immune system has evolved to detect proteins or other molecules that are not part of the normal
self of the body. As the immune system evolves, cells that can recognize foreign invaders get
spared, whereas cells that can attack normal tissue get eliminated in the thymus. And so
except for autoimmune diseases, we don't have cells that can recognize normal tissues. They've
been eliminated in the evolution of our immune systems. So you have lymphocytes, B cells that
make antibodies, T cells that act directly by interacting with other tissues. And so
the immune system via antibodies or T cells recognizes viral protein that's now being expressed
by the respiratory cell. The lymphocytes are constantly patrolling the body. Every 14 or 15
seconds, your heart's pumping out these lymphocytes that are circulating through the vascular system,
sometimes extravasating into tissues, coming back into the lymphoid system and returning to the
heart via the thoracic duct. Well, when the lymphocyte encounters a foreign antigen to which
it can have reactivity that's not cells. And define an antigen for folks to tell people what an
antigen is. How long is it? What's it made of? So an antigen is a molecule in the body that is not
normally being expressed in the body by tissues. They're generally proteins, but they can be
carbohydrates. And what makes that molecule an antigen is its ability to be recognized by a
T lymphocyte or a B lymphocyte. That is a T lymphocyte that can directly recognize an infected cell
or a B lymphocyte that can make antibodies against it plasma cells. And so if a molecule is recognized
as foreign, the immune system can recognize that antigen. Well, lymphocytes are patrolling the body.
Lymphocytes are patrolling the body. They encounter this viral antigen in the respiratory
epithelium. They stop at that location and you can visualize this in mouth ears with something
called two-photon microscopy. They stop at that location and you can see them extravasate
into the tissue. When they're there, they then begin to divide. As they divide, the dividing
cells can further recognize the viral protein and starts making molecules that can destroy
the infected cells, but also call other cells into that arena, macrophages, neutrophils, and so on.
And that's what an immune reaction is. As the antigen is eliminated by these mechanisms,
lymphocytes, other cells, there's no reason for those cells to stay around anymore. They're not
stimulated. They enter the circulation, but now you have patrolling the body for the rest of your
life. Long live lymphocytes that can recognize those foreign molecules. And that's why when you
get immunized against smallpox, you have that immunization for the rest of your life and
hopefully for coronavirus, although we don't know that. We don't know the extent to which those cells
survive. Now, at the outset, you said there are two things about cancer that make it different
from self. It has these two properties that individually wouldn't be the end of the world,
but when you combine them, they're devastating. It's this failure to respond to cell cycle
signaling, which results in unregulated growth. And it's this capacity to leave the site of origin
and grow in an unregulated manner elsewhere. And you also mentioned that this is the result of,
although you didn't use the word, somatic mutations, which we can clarify for people,
these aren't typically mutations that people are born with, although in diseases like Lynch
syndrome, that might be the case that it leads to that. But these are acquired mutations.
So the natural question would be, why is it that a cell that has these acquired mutations that
clearly produce a phenotype that is different from self, why wouldn't that be foreign enough
for the immune system to act? In other words, why does cancer even exist in the first place?
Why doesn't it get squashed out in its infancy? So these mutations, these changes in DNA that
are random events as the cell is dividing can produce proteins that can be recognized or other
molecules recognized by the immune system. And they do it in complex ways by breaking down
small molecule peptides and putting it on the cell surface. But the immune system can recognize
these mutations. And it's only been in the last, I'd say, three or four years that we now recognize
these mutations as commonly recognized by the immune system. And about 80% of patients with
the common epithelial cancers, it turns out as a result of the research done in recent years,
do exist. It can recognize the products of the mutations. But the immune system against them
is too small, is not vigorous enough. What does that mean? Create enough cells, create receptors
that have a high enough validity for recognition to the tumor. The immune reaction is not very
strong. And the growth of the tumor can overcome the small impact that an immune reaction might
have in killing some tumor cells. Plus for a tumor cell to survive and grow, it develops certain
properties that can suppress the local immune reaction. It can make molecules like transforming
growth factor beta, TGF beta. It can make cytokines like interleukin 10. It can cause the
development of cells lymphocytes that inhibit immune reactions. I mean virtually every
physiologic system in the body has stimulatory elements and inhibitory elements. You have
hormones that can increase gastric secretion, some that can decrease it. You have a sympathetic
nervous system, a parasympathetic nervous system. Well the immune system is the same.
It has effector cells that can be very aggressive and recognize antigens. And it has regulatory T
cells that deliberately suppress immune reactions. And that's one of the things that keeps us from
developing autoimmune disease. But there are many of these regulatory elements. Recently described
myeloid derived suppressor cells can suppress immune reactions. And so it's the balance of the
aggressive immune reaction against the inhibitory molecules that can prevent that immune reaction
that is the holy grail of trying to find effective treatments. And effective treatments
come in both directions. Interleukin 2 stimulates immune reactions. And we now have checkpoint
modulators like Ipilumimab or PD-1 inhibitors that can inhibit these inhibitory factors and
thereby stimulate the immune reaction by taking away the breaks on the immune system. So the more
we understand the more we can take advantage of the biology. So let's go back to the first of those
because that seems to have been the first big break you got at NCI after Gallo's discovery
was Interleukin 2. So now you had both a cytokine that could allow you to grow lymphocytes
in vitro but also something that could be given to patients in vivo to stimulate the immune system.
So how did that sort of propel your work? Well with the advent of Interleukin 2,
what had been shown was that there were some bone marrow cells could make a substance which
would keep lymphocytes alive outside the body. But the minute I heard about that,
there were a series of questions that arose. Well if it kept lymphocytes alive,
would it keep lymphocytes alive and dividing in a format that enabled them to have all of their
immune recognition? That is as they grew would they just lose that property? And so we try to
demonstrate that by developing cells that could recognize what we call alloantigens that is very
strong antigens that are present in one person that inhibit the ability to transplant organs
for example. And so our initial studies were to see whether or not we could develop
lymphocytes, grow them in culture, and cause experimental skin grafts in mice to disappear
faster. We're not talking about tumor, that's normal tissue. And we showed that in fact we
could grow lymphocytes that retain their function in the laboratory and then retain their function
in vivo. Well with that knowledge, we didn't want to cause skin grafts to disappear more quickly.
With that knowledge, we had to try to develop cells that could react against the cancer.
And very early on when we grew cells in interleukin-2, we found that in fact they could destroy
tissue-cultured cancer cells, have some impact on normal cultured cells as well,
just by virtue of exposure to interleukin-2. And we call them lac cells, lymphoclin-activated killer
cells. And we studied them for three or four years. It turned out to be a false alarm because
they could impact on tiny little tumors in mice before they became vascularized, but by the time
they were vascularized they would not work in mice at all. But interleukin-2 seemed like a molecule
that might be able to stimulate those rare cells in the body that could recognize the cancer as
foreign, or develop cells in the laboratory that could do that recognition. And that then led us
to many years of experiments in the laboratory, but also clinical trials trying to see whether
or not either interleukin-2 administration alone or cells that you could devise in vitro that could
recognize a tumor and administer those. And that was a very frustrating time. It wasn't until 1984
that we finally figured out a way to use interleukin-2 to mediate regression. We treated
over 70 patients with either interleukin-2 or cells that we grew and interleukin-2 and administered
to patients without seeing a response until we modified the schedule of interleukin-2 administration,
knowing it's pharmacokinetics that is only after half-life inside the body of about seven minutes.
And so we had to alter the schedule. We had to give higher and higher doses, which mediated
toxicity, until finally a patient that we treated in 1984, we had widespread melanoma,
was administered interleukin-2, and was the first patient finally after over 70 other patients to
show us a tumor regression, the first time that a deliberate immunologic maneuver could reproducibly
cause cancer regression. It was one of the few eureka moments that I've had in doing research,
but the realization finally that after all of those patient deaths,
everybody had advanced cancer, all would go on the die of their cancer,
survived, and that patient now alive over 35 years later, free of disease.
You know, it reminds me a lot of Thomas Starzell's work in the 1960s with liver
transplantation, where the number of patients who died was, it was hard to keep track of
before finally achieving the technical success that was necessary, both the perioperative
care and the post-operative care and the technical skill necessary, plus the immunosuppressive
regimen. All of those four things had to be firing on all cylinders for patients to finally
undergo liver transplantation. And this patient in 1984, if I recall, was the 67th patient treated,
meaning 67 consecutive patients died of metastatic cancer and were unresponsive to interleukin-2.
The first question is really just a logistics question. How many different histologies were
in that group? How many different types of cancers were you treating at that time?
We were treating all cancers, metastatic cancers, with the idea that although they each arose from
different organs, had somewhat different properties and methods of spread, there would be commonalities
that could be attacked. And so we were treating all kinds of histologies. It was
the first patient that we treated with this revised regimen happened to have a melanoma.
The third and fourth patients had renal cancer. And as we continued to use interleukin-2, we found
that those two histologies, patients with those two histologic types of cancer, could respond and
ultimately response rates in those two diseases turned out to be about 15 to 20 percent of patients
with about a third of those patients having complete durable regressions.
But it was a little different than the liver transplant situation. Because in that situation,
there were technical problems that had to be overcome. And it was a genius of Tom Starville
to stick with it and to figure out those technical problems. When it came to immunotherapy for cancer,
it was a little different. We didn't know that it would ever work. We didn't know that there
was ever going to be an immune system that could cause a cancer to disappear.
In contrast to if you could work the technical problems out of so the vessels together,
you could get this thing to work. And so that first patient had an enormous impact on me and
on the field because it showed that it was possible. And until you know it's possible,
you never know that it's ever going to occur. And so that changed everything because it showed
that simply administering this one molecule, a T cell growth factor, could cause a cancer
regression in a patient. And that then led us to studies to understand how that was occurring.
And that then led to a lot of different directions, cell transfer, gene modification, and so on.
How did you keep going in the face of all of those failures up until this patient's
miraculous remission in 1984? How did you, because again, let's, if you were working as a surgical
oncologist at the time, you would not have been exposed to that death. The surgical oncologist's
work would have been done after the primary resection. Typically the medical oncologist
would be the one that would be at that patient's bedside as they progress through treatment. But
you were seeing something that you would not have seen had you chose a different arc to your
surgical career. And I just, I wonder how you coped with that. What were those drives home?
What were the drive, you know, what was it like to be alone in your thoughts?
Well, you know, as I look back on it, it seems remarkable that there were so many patients,
one after another, everyone died eventually of their cancer because we did not have any
impact in the manipulations that we were, that we're applying. And, you know, you're a doctor
and you know that it's not the patients that do well that you remember, it's the patients that you
you fail to help that you remember. And there was just a remarkable number of tragedies,
young people dying of cancer, people of all ages. But I had this intuition
based on everything I knew about biology and everything I had studied in biophysics. I had
an intuition and also influenced by these inklings of the first two patients I mentioned
that this would, this would work. You know, I recently saw a quote by Abraham Lincoln
that said success consists of moving from failure to failure without loss of enthusiasm.
And that actually happened to me. I actually just saw that quote a few months ago. But
I always felt it was going to work. And it did eventually. And a small number of patients,
still a long way to go. But at least now we have effective immunotherapies for a variety of
diseases that can be effective. And when that first patient responded,
they, it all exploded in my brain. It does work. This can work. And we'll figure out now ways to
make it better. And I imagine Alice was a big part of that support for you. Again, I know I have the
privilege of knowing her and knowing how important she is. Do you think you could have got through
this alone without the support of your family? I mean, you had to do this very difficult thing,
which was basically, you know, have this remarkable obligation to your family,
which every father does. And at the same time, you felt like you were carrying the weight of
your world, the weight of the world on your shoulders, trying to take care of these patients
who were otherwise really left with no hope. Do you see that as sort of a synergy between those two?
They were probably, and I'm not exaggerating, 40 days in the first 40 years of my work here,
that I was in town, not traveling, that I was not in this hospital.
I would come in every day, of course. I would come in every Saturday. Sundays, I would come in to go
over research with some of the fellows. You probably remember that or see some patients.
And that kind of life requires support of some kind. And there are not a lot of wives who I think
would tolerate that kind of commitment outside the home. And Alice was such a person.
She never hassled me about it, always understood that. I remember once she said,
look, I know what you're doing is important. And so what I'm going to do as much as I can
is relieve you of the burdens that we commonly face as part of daily living. She handles,
I haven't written a check in 20 years. Alice pays our bills and really takes care of so much that
enabled me to work at that level. But it was a family thing. I have three daughters who were
growing up as all of this was happening. And I remember when my oldest daughter applied,
my first daughter applied to college, Beth, she opened her college essay with it,
setting somewhat along the lines of, at our dinner table at home, we're much more likely to be
talking about cancer and AIDS than the Washington Redskins. And made me understand how much the
kids had been affected by all of this talk of death and suffering from these diseases. So
it takes a family. And I doubt I could have done it without that kind of support.
So once you identified this patient, patient number 67, did you have an inkling what it was
about melanoma and renal cell cancer that made them particularly immunogenic relative to
this whole host of other epithelial cancers that were less reactive?
The answer is no. But the answer would be yes, 35 years later. But I think now we do understand
what's different about melanoma. But we didn't at the time. We were seeing responses to interleukin
two in patients with melanoma and kidney cancer, but no other diseases would respond to interleukin
two. And we learned that the hard way, treating over 600 patients with interleukin two here at
the clinical center, it turns out those two diseases were uniquely responsive. And we now
know, at least for melanoma, why that's the case. And that is the immune system is recognizing the
products of mutations. And melanoma, if one looks at the number of the frequency of mutations among
different cancer types, melanoma has more mutations than any other cancer type with the exception of
lung cancer. They're about equivalent, about 400 mutations per tumor as a median. And that's very
likely because melanoma induced by a carcinogen, ultraviolet light, lung cancer by the carcinogens
largely in cigarette smoke or the environment, that leads to an increased number of mutations.
And that at least is part of the answer. And that is the more mutations you have in the cancer,
the more likelihood that you'll develop a particular protein, foreign protein, that can be recognized
by the immune system. Did you ever see patients with Lynch syndrome response? They would typically
have many mutations as well, wouldn't they? You're exactly right. So there are some situations like
the microsatellite unstable cancers, colon cancer, other kinds of cancer types, Lynch syndrome.
But we didn't understand that with mutations that were involved at that point, and I don't remember
ever treating a patient with Lynch syndrome. You're right. They would have a very large number of
mutations. So for comparison, if we talk about a standard, you can't even use the word standard
you can't even use the word standard. There's no such thing as a standard cancer. Right now,
we know so much about cancer that every cancer is different. But what would be the median number
of mutations in a metastatic breast cancer, colon cancer or pancreatic cancer?
You would probably encompass 80% of these common cancers. If you considered mutation frequency
between 60 to 70 and 150, that would be the major the median would probably be somewhere
about 110. But it would vary from cancer type to a cancer type. Some pediatric cancers have
very few mutations. Some cancers have more. But about I'd say the median would very likely to be
about 110. How many of those mutations would be driver mutations? So they are oncogenes,
tumor suppressor genes. They are playing a functional role in the cancer versus what we
might call passenger mutations that can still produce antigens. They would still generate a
peptide that could be recognized by MHC, but they're not playing a functional role in those
two properties of cancer that we spoke about. So about six years ago, we described an assay
that would enable us to actually identify the exact molecular nature of these antigens that
are recognized by T cells. And that came from, again, the understanding that it was the products
of these unique cancer mutations that were being recognized by the immune system. Well,
it turns out that some of these antigens that are recognized by T cells are recognizing the
proteins that derive from driver mutations, that is, that caused the cancer in the first place,
like P53, present in half of all cancers. But only about 2% of patients develop immune reactions
against it. KRAS, about 90% of pancreatic cancers, will have that as a driver mutation.
But what's stunning to me about oncology and the biology of cancer, and that is how few
of these shared cancer mutations exist. There's P53, there's KRAS. To some extent, pick 3CA in
breast cancer, maybe BRAF mutations in melanoma. Other than that, the incidence of driver mutations
as a cause of cancer is low single digits. You'd think there would be many mutations that would
change the cell so dramatically. But it turns out it's not only those few driver mutations,
but the accumulation of mutations, each with its own property, that in and of itself
appears unlikely to cause cancer. But in concert with the action of other genes,
other mutations does cause a cancer. And we've more recently shown in a breast cancer patient
that we published a few years ago that we could mediate complete durable regression,
now over six years later, by targeting for what appeared to be random somatic mutations,
none of which had a driver function. But in concert, cause the cancer and by attacking them,
you could cause cancers to disappear. Now, I mean, I still am struggling to understand why it is
that a P53 mutation or a KRAS mutation is not immunogenic. Is that simply due to the evolution
of cancer, that because of the ubiquity of these mutations in cancer, cancer has come up with
enough evolutionary tricks to evade detection of those mutations? I mean, that's a teleologic
question, but I mean, do we have any biologic insight into this?
So you have to get a, have to dig a little deeper into the biology. For a mutation gives rise to a
molecule, a protein, right? It's DNA, RNA transcribed, translated into a protein. For that protein,
even though it has now a mutation, a string of amino acids that are not seen as normal by the body,
that mutation, that abnormal amino acid called a non-synonymous mutation is only recognized by
the immune system. If the molecule in which it occurs is broken down inside the cell into small
peptides, that is small sequences of amino acids, or the tumor cell or the antigen presenting cell
takes an antigen, a protein from the outside of the cell into the cell and breaks it into small
peptides, strings of amino acids. Well, that has to happen. And then one of those strings of amino
acids has to fit onto the surface of the patient's own HLA molecule, that is the kind of molecules
that we call transplantation molecules. And so for a mutation to be recognized by the immune
system, it has to be broken into these 9 to 11 amino acid peptides and fit on that patient's own
transplantation molecule. And that transplantation molecule is highly polymorphic. There are hundreds
of them. And so if you had a mutation and your cells made small peptides, but it didn't fit on
your HLA molecule, it wouldn't be recognized by the immune system. And so as we've learned more
in the last 5 to 6 years about what cancer antigens are, it's these mutations that are broken down
and put on the surface of a patient's presenting cells or tumor cells. And that turns out to be
between 1.5 and 2% of all mutations. And when you look at melanoma, it's 1.3%. When you look at the
gastrointestinal cancers, 1.6%, breast cancer, 2.1% of mutations are immunogenic because they happen
to fit into that individual patient's HLA molecule. And the most stunning finding of recent years,
in my view, in this field is that virtually every patient recognizes a unique antigen. And so we're
in the process of writing a paper now on 195 consecutive patients that we've identified the
exact antigenic nature of what the T cell can recognize, and it can recognize in about 80% of
all histologies. And that turned out to be 363 individual antigens that were recognized in these
195 patients. And no two patients shared the exact same antigen with the exception of two
patients that had a K-RAS mutation that was recognized on a very rare Class 1 molecule,
CWA-802 HLA molecule. So just to make sure I understand that, you're saying that in this
series of nearly 200 patients, the first interesting finding is each of them produces
at least one neoantigen that is immunogenic. 80% of patients will, yes. Okay, 80%. We haven't found.
And secondly, outside of the K-RAS overlap, they were novel across the board.
That's right. Of those 393 antigens, 392 of them were unique, not shared by any patients with the
exception of K-RAS. That's not to say that P53 or other driver genes can't recognize it, but they
don't naturally recognize it. You might be able to raise those very rare cells, but that's correct.
It's good news and it's bad news. Explain why that is to people, because I was just about to say
that's really good and creates a huge problem for scale. You got it. That's exactly right.
It's good news because we finally understand after all of these decades what a cancer antigen is. Back
in 1985, I knew one existed. I didn't know what it was, whether it would be shared, and we spent an
enormous amount of time trying to identify shared antigens, especially in melanoma, these melanocyte
antigens shared by normal pigment-producing cells. But now that we understand what an antigen is,
and we understand that most cancers contain multiple mutations, which give rise to the
antigens. Well, since almost all cancers have mutations, if we can find, figure out ways to
target these mutations that are foreign, we potentially have a treatment applicable to
all cancer histologies. Since almost all cancers have mutations, let's recognize them, and now
you don't have to worry whether it's a breast cancer or a colon cancer or a brain tumor.
The T cells are there. So the possibilities of developing broadly applicable treatments exist.
The bad news is, as you point out, it's going to have to be, as you target these mutations,
highly individualized treatments. Unless you can fully unleash the immune system against even the
most minor amnigants, which we can't do now, checkpoint modulators have virtually no impact
on the overwhelming majority of the solid epithelial cancers. It means that if you're going
to stimulate immune reactions via a vaccine or a T cell as a drug, it has to be individualized
to target that cancer, because that antigen is present only in that patient, but not in any other
patient. And that's going to make it very complex to develop. But when we develop this other form
of T cells, CAR T cells, a whole other story, people said that it could never be applied. But in fact,
if you have something that works and can cure people, the genius of modern industry will figure
out ways to make it available. Well, I wanted to go back to 1985 to pick up the story with both
Ronald Reagan and Tittle, unrelated but temporally related. But before we do, because you brought up
CAR T cells, let's tell the story about the diffuse B cell lymphomas that
ultimately led to KITE, because it's a great way to... I think most people listening to this will
have heard of a CAR T, but I think it's an important... This is an illustrative case to
explain how they came about, how they differ, of course, from a regular T cell receptor. And
as you said, how industry basically came in to solve a problem that at the outset looked pretty
daunting. So pick it up wherever it makes sense with respect to the T cell.
It makes sense with respect to lymphoma. So again, you have to understand the biology,
you have to go back to the biology, that normal T cells have receptors that can recognize
antigens on the surface of a cancer cell, right? These tiny peptides that are put on the surface.
Those alpha beta chains are expressed by a lymphocyte, and that's how the immune system
recognizes antigens. Well, there's a way to create an alternate way for a lymphocyte to
manage it, and it was created by some scientists at the Weizmann Institute about 10 or 12 years
ago, Zeligashar and Gideon Gross. They took advantage of antibody recognition. Now,
antibody recognition is very different than that of T cell recognition. Antibodies recognize the
three-dimensional structure of a molecule on the surface of a cancer cell or of any cell.
Not a processed peptide brought to the surface, but an actual molecule on the surface and that
antibody, like a lock and a key, will latch on to that antigen and recognize it. Well, T cells
can't do that, but by creating a chimeric T cell, you put antibody recognition domains into a
lymphocyte that converts the lymphocyte from its normal recognition from its own receptor into the
recognition of this antibody that you've put into the lymphocyte, and that expands the number of
molecules that can be recognized by T cells. And so it's this chimeric antigen receptor,
which is part receptor, normal receptor, but with antibodies attached to it that enables the
lymphocyte to recognize now molecules that it never was able to recognize in the course of evolution
based on antibody recognition. And it turns out that there are very few molecules on the cell
surface, very few, like I could name the few I know of and then the fingers on one hand,
that are unique to a cancer that are not on normal cells. And we learn the hard way
that the immune system will destroy a normal cell just as quickly as it will a cancer cell,
and we've mediated cancer deaths by targeting antigens that are present even in very low levels
on normal cells. Well, it turns out there's a molecule on B lymphocytes called CD19. We don't
exactly know what its function is, but when B cells turn into lymphomas and leukemias, they
continue to express CD19. And so with this understanding, and as soon as I heard about
these chimeric T cells, I invited Zellig Eshar to come to a sabbatical in my lab. He came the next
year and spent three years working in the surgery branch. And we worked out ways to use CAR T cells
to attack cancers, but we could never get them to disappear because the molecules that we were
giving could not be used in large enough numbers because of their ability to recognize normal.
Well, CD19 expressed by leukemias and lymphomas, they developed from normal B cells,
expressed CD19, and we developed a technique to introduce these anti-CD19 CAR molecules, chimeric
antigen receptors into T cells to create a CAR T cell that when we administered to patients would
kill every cell in the body that expressed CD19. So all the normal B cells were eliminated,
but so too were lymphomas and leukemias. And that became the first actual cell in gene therapy
ever approved by the FDA. So how did that happen? Well, we studied the ability of these anti-CD19
CAR T cells to kill cells and experimental animals, and they did. They wiped out normal B cells, but
you can live without normal B cells because you can give antibodies to the cell.
Because you can give antibodies by giving antibody infusions. We used these CAR T cells
to treat the first patient ever to receive a CAR T cell. This was in 2009. This was a patient that
had a lymphoma that had spread throughout its chest, had been through four different chemotherapy
regimens, had enormous to kilogram tumor burdens in its body. We treated with CAR T cells that could
recognize a CD19 molecule on the surface of normal B cells and tumor, and all this tumor disappeared.
And he's, well, we treated him in 2009. He's 12 years later and completely disease-free.
We published a series of those over the course of the next two years, and we had seven or eight
patients who had a complete disappearance of all of their lymphoma. Diffused large B cell lymphoma
is the most aggressive form of and lethal form of lymphomas that people develop. And they developed
complete regressions that were ongoing for at least seemed like several years.
Well, once we did this, and incidentally all the patients' normal B cells disappeared,
but again you can live without B cells.
And so in 2011, two years later after we had published several of these papers, and a year
after we published that work, Carl June at the University of Pennsylvania used these CD19 CAR T
cells to treat leukemia patients. And so two years after our description of multiple lymphoma patients
undergoing a complete regression, I was contacted by a former fellow named Ari Beldyren who had
worked in my lab 25 years earlier. He was, just finished his urology training, became a professor
of urology at UCLA. And he, we had become friends, and he came to see me in 2011 saying,
hey you're treating patients with these T cells, these chimeric T cells, these CAR T cells, and
successfully treating lymphoma patients. I want to commercialize this. I want to start a company
to do this. And we had had several companies come through like Johnson and Johnson brought in 12
people, examined everything we had done, said hey if we have a lymphoma we'll come back and
get treated by you, but we don't see how we can make any money doing this at Johnson and Johnson.
Well Ari Beldyren had a different vision. He said we can figure out a way to make this available.
And in 2012, we formed what's called a CRATE, a Cooperative Research and Development Agreement,
that enabled us in the lab to work with this company, this biotech company, started Kite Farmer.
They were able to give us funds to help support the research. And so we started that in 2012.
We signed the CRATA. We worked together. We treated over 50 patients, showed that this
could happen, and over half of patients will undergo durable regressions.
He then did a multi-institutional study, and Novartis was doing this in leukemia patients
almost simultaneously. His multi-institutional study reproduced the results exactly,
about a 70 percent objective response rate with 50 percent durable complete regressions.
And in 2017, five years after Kite started working with us on this, Kite was sold to Gilead
for 11.9 billion dollars. That all happened in the course of those five years, and that treatment is
now available thanks to Kite and Novartis, available for use in patients in the United
States and Europe and parts of Asia that can effectively treat these B-cell lymphomas
at leukemias. So really a pretty incredible story that evolved so rapidly.
Yeah, it is. I mean, do you think that CAR T-cells can have efficacy against
non-hematologic cancers? Right now the answer is no.
We have no way to use them against solid cancers, again, because the solid cancer is to be treated
with a CAR T-cell. You have to have a molecule on the cell surface that's unique to cancer.
We originally didn't fully realize quite how sensitive they could be, and when we targeted
molecules that were on normal cells, patients died, devastating events in the development of the
treatment. But monoclonal antibodies were first described about 45 years ago, and no one has found
unique monoclonal antibodies against molecules uniquely on cancer cells and not normal cells.
And that's what you need to make a chimeric T-cell receptor. You need an antibody that you can put
into a lymphocyte that has specificity. And antibodies just have not evolved to recognize
individual cell surface molecules on cancer, which are shared by normal cells, whereas
conventional T-cells do, because internal proteins then get digested and brought onto
the surface. So right now there's very little prospect for CAR T-cells being useful for the
treatment of solid tumors, but that's not to say that some brilliant ideas will come forth in the
years to come that will make them available. Right now they're not useful.
Now, what about for organs that are not essential? So where you could waive the need to recognize or
differentiate between cancer and non-cancer. So for example, breast or even pancreas. If a person
had metastatic pancreatic cancer and you were willing to completely lose both normal and non-
normal pancreatic cells and render that person a type 1 diabetic, it would still be worth it.
So are there any antigens that are present on exclusively pancreas or exclusively breast or colon?
Obviously, this wouldn't work for liver and lung, but is that a slightly easier problem
to solve or is it just as hard? Well, it's just as hard because for the past 45 years,
some of the best immunologists in the world have tried to develop these monoclonal antibodies
that can uniquely recognize cancer and they have not found any. Either of course they haven't done
it right or there just aren't these molecules on the cell surface. And even very recently,
last several months, you probably heard about this T-immunity, these two deaths for patients
that were targeting what was thought to be a prostate specific molecule, BSMA, but it's not,
it was present on normal cells and that can result in death of patients. And so, yes,
if you could find a molecule unique to prostate cancer, breast cancer, that is expendable organs,
you could develop more effective cell-based therapies against them.
But right now, none of those molecules have been identified.
So let's now go back in time to post the IL-2 insight. You have this other amazing realization,
which is there are certain types of lymphocytes that manage to track to tumors,
these T-cells that infiltrate the tumor and they're called TIL.
So after we describe, I'm sorry, go ahead.
Yeah, no, no. So how did you come to understand these and understand
the efficiency with which they could identify tumors?
So things seemed to move very slowly, although we had an explosion of ideas. But looking back
on it, when it comes to scientific advance, it actually moved along pretty quickly.
Because IL-2 as a T-cell growth factor was mediating reproducible regressions,
it seemed reasonable that is being mediated by the ability of interleukin-2 to stimulate
lymphocytes in vivo. And so in melanoma patients, we looked for T-cells that could recognize the
tumor deposit itself. We didn't know what it was recognizing. And what better place intuitively
to look for a cell doing battle against the cancer than within the cancer stroma itself.
And so we grew those cells, one out of peripheral blood, but we also grew cells invading into tumor
called tumor infiltrating lymphocytes or TIL cells. We grew them in vitro and in animal and
then very quickly in human experiments, grew those lymphocytes to large numbers in vitro
and administered them to patients with metastatic melanoma. And now instead of the 15%
response rate that we got from giving interleukin-2 alone, by giving lymphocytes that we grew in
interleukin-2, these TIL cells, we got response rates 30, 35% in melanoma patients. And so it
represented a substantial improvement, but they were pretty short durations. They were real, but
they did not appear to be durable. But it was the first demonstration that lymphocyte transfer as a
sole modality could cause tumor regression in patients with melanoma. And to some lesser extent,
kidney cancer was mediated by lymphocytes. So that intuition then became a reality of a
biologic finding and that is lymphocytes were the cause of these regressions or could be the
cause of regressions. And then things moved along fairly, well, slowly and quickly, depending on your
point of view. It immediately became apparent that if we had these lymphocytes naturally,
maybe we could genetically modify them to be more potent. That is, they were making factors that
drew other cells in. Well, let's introduce that gene into them. But no one had ever introduced a
gene into human cells. And so I teamed up with the two scientists at the NIH, French Anderson
and Mike Blais, who were trying to develop gene therapies to replace adenosine deaminase
deficiencies, a lethal deficiency in young and young children to see if they couldn't introduce
those genes. But of course, no genes had ever been introduced into people. We decided to see
if we could break the ice about putting foreign genes into humans by putting a marker gene into
the lymphocytes we were administering to patients. We picked a bacterial gene called neomycin
phosphotrazferase, inserted that gene into a patient's normal lymphocytes. And our plan was
to administer them so we could track where these lymphocytes were going inside the body,
because they would have this unique bacterial gene they were being expressed.
And so we proposed that to investigational review boards. At that point, the government had
established what's called the Recombinant DNA Advisory Committee, the RAC, adequately named,
who had a review, any clinical proposals. We went through, we tabulated, won 17 different review
groups, having to go back and forth as they made changes until the RAC finally voted. It was a
painful time, 13 to 4, to allow us to do it. But the director of the NIH, James Weingarten,
insisted that before we would start tampering with the human genome, we needed a unanimous consent,
back and forth, making changes. Finally, there was a vote of the RAC, 13 to nothing,
0 with 1 abstention, which was unanimous. And so we got permission to proceed
with the clinical trial, biotechnology activists and filed lawsuits against the NIH, saying we
shouldn't be tampering with the human genome. It was immoral. It was ungodly. But we finally got
permission to do it and inserted these lymphocytes that were genetically modified with this bacterial
gene that did enable us to track the cells inside the body. When we did biopsies, it was a paper we
published in the New England Journal of Medicine. And that then led to the gene modifications of
lymphocytes that we attempted to use to improve them. We put in the gene for Interleukin 2. That
didn't improve them because we couldn't regulate it. But it just started our endeavors to
genetically modified cells that finally came to their fruition in the CAR T cells.
By inserting the genes that would insert these new receptors that could recognize
molecules on lymphomas and leukemias. So that started us on the track of trying to improve the
cells. And then there were a variety of advances. We learned that you had to first wipe out all of
these inhibitory T cells, regulatory cells, before you gave the administered cells. And that then
jumped the response rates up to 55% in melanoma patients with about 25% being durable, complete
remissions. We then started developing ways to use T cells to do cancer treatment. And
2013, finally realizing that it was unique mutations, we developed techniques that
enabled us to develop T cells specifically targeting mutations. And published the first
paper on that in 2014. It was a patient with a bile duct cancer, a calangiocarcinoma
that was widespread in the lungs and liver. We gave her bulk T cells did not work. We gave
cells that were uniquely directed against her mutations. And she's undergone a dramatic
regression is now disease free. But those were till that were not genetically modified? Those
were? Those were not genetic? Those are the natural. So our work went in two directions,
genetically modifying till or figuring out ways to use natural to them. And these were natural till
that were selected for mutation reactivity and given to a patient and whose natural immune
system was temporarily eliminated. And she's living disease free now eight years later,
all of her liver and lung disease is gone. And we subsequently now have published on these
T cells that recognize unique mutations in their ability to cause regression in
cervical cancer induced by human papilloma virus, by colon cancer, that patient recognized
k-RAS, breast cancer recognized for random somatic mutations. We're now struggling to figure out ways
to more efficiently target the products of unique mutations that cause the cancer. Sort of ironic
that the Achilles heel of the cancer is going to be the very abnormalities that caused it in the
first place. And so that brings us up to 2021. Can we now take advantage of all this new
biologic information about the role of mutations and T cells that target them about the ability to
genetically modify cells in large numbers using retroviruses? Can we take advantage of that
technology, that biologic information to develop more effective immunotherapies in the years to come?
And that's what we're working on today. That's what we're working on in the lab as we speak.
Well, I want to go back a little bit and talk about a few other things, both for
posterity, I suppose, and also because I think there were some other things we've glossed over
quickly. But in 1985, you had this opportunity to operate on the then President of the United
States who had developed colon cancer. Why is it that you were a part of the team that would take
care of the president? Why is it that the chair of the National Cancer Institute would be involved
in the president's care? Is that something that sort of mandated at the federal level?
No, it's part of the aberrancy involved in treating high government officials. It turns out
that there is a set of modules in Walter Reed or Bethesda Naval Hospital that are set aside for
the treatment of the president. It's an isolated set of rooms. I learned this as it happened. I
didn't know it ahead of time. Where the kinds of equipment and availability of technology
was available so the president could actually run the country from his hospital bed. But it turned
out that it was the physicians in this particular case at Bethesda Naval Hospital, and they have
marvelous doctors there, that would be treating the president. And it turned out that the chief
of surgery at Bethesda Naval Hospital had just rotated off an AFFcraft carrier to be the chief
of surgery at Bethesda Naval. It would change very commonly if officers in the Navy had different
assignments. And he happened to be an expert in vascular surgery, not oncology. And he was the
one responsible for calling the shots about the patient's cancer. And it turned out he was an
excellent doctor, an excellent vascular surgeon, but not an oncologist. Never really was operating
on cancer patients in any volumes. And so they needed an expert in oncology to take part.
And just out of the blue on one Friday evening, I got a call saying, will you come over to Bethesda
Naval Hospital? We have a patient we need your help with. And it turned out to be President
President Reagan. And it was simply because I was nearby. I had previously gotten a
security clearance because I had tentatively been assigned to be part of a medical team that would
take care of high government officials in the case of calamitous nuclear emergencies.
So it was because the vascular surgeon was in charge, and I was across the street that I got
that I got called and took part in that, took part in that surgery.
And if I recall, at the press conference following the surgery, you explained point
blank that the president had colorectal cancer. And if I recall, Nancy Reagan wasn't too pleased
about that, right? No. And I'm not telling stories out of school here about a patient because
Larry speaks. It was public. Yeah, it was public information. And he later wrote a memoir that
described some of this. But Nancy Reagan, when we had to have a press conference and there were
little concerns about having a vascular surgeon handle the questions, and I had been an operating
surgeon as part of the operating team, she, before I went on to hold the press conference,
I remember standing backstage and she said, you cannot use the word cancer
in describing this because if foreign officials know,
think the patient has cancer, the president has cancer, they won't pay any attention to him anymore,
thinking he would not be around. And I said, I'm sorry, I can't do that. You know, if I have to,
I go out, I have to just tell the truth. And it was Don Reagan, who was the chief of staff,
who finally talked her off that ledge and said, look, we've just got to let him
do what he wants to do. So we went out and the surgeon who led the discussion just basically
read off the PATH report, there's an adenocarcinoma, the disproportionate of the colon and so on,
and nobody understood what he said. And so they asked me to explain it. So I said,
the president has cancer, which got me into all kinds of trouble. I later learned that when
Vince DeVita, who is the director of the NCI resigned to become chief at Memorial Sloan
Kettering, I was on a shortlist to become the director of the NCI, not a position I would
have thought of accepting. And I was told at that point when I actually wrote this book in 1992,
that my name get taken off the list as someone who would become the director of the NCI,
which was very upset that I used the word has cancer, and not had cancer, that is past tense.
But we got over it. And the president did very well and recovered and never recovered,
never recovered from his early colon cancer. You mentioned it in passing earlier that,
although you've been in the post you're in now for 47 years, along the way you've had a few
job offers that have tempted you. I'm sure you've had many job offers. What are some of the other
ones that that tempted you, at least where you thought you could even do better work or
continue your work? Because obviously you're so mission focused. It would be a special
opportunity that I would imagine would get you to leave NCI. But what were some of those other
opportunities that you even contemplated? There were only three that I looked at once.
One was here at Georgetown because of a relationship I had with a surgeon in terms
of collaborating things, and it was sort of a favor to him to look at the job. I was also
invited to look at the job as chief of surgery at Hopkins. And ultimately I was told it got boiled
down to John Cameron and me on the short list, but I went back a second time but refused to go back
a third time because I knew I would not go to Johns Hopkins and leave the NIH. I was also asked
to look at the job at the Brigham. Remari Brennan, a friend of mine, and I were again
being pursued to accept that position. But again, I backed out. I knew that I didn't want
to take an administrative job. I wanted to be in the lab. I wanted to be mentoring fellows. I
wanted to be trying to make progress. I didn't want to guide other people making it. I wanted
to be there. I wanted to be doing it. I wanted to be guiding it because I thought I could do it
well. And so I actually refused any of those offers. Never looked at another job
and actually turned down opportunities to advance in the hierarchy here at the NCI
because I wanted to remain at the level that I'm at, the control of resources that enabled me to
pursue the kinds of research that I thought needed to be done in an environment of enormous
resources. So let's talk a little bit about checkpoint inhibitors. They've come up now a
couple of times in this discussion. You've mentioned anti-CTLA-4 and anti-PD-1. Certainly
my time at the NCI, my second stint, got me very familiar with anti-CTLA-4. It was an exciting time.
And of course, James Allison would go on to receive the Nobel Prize a couple of years ago
for his work in the discovery of this. Maybe go back and explain how that system works,
how the removal of breaks works. And of course, as part of the undercurrent of this,
it only works if there's a tumor antigen to be recognized. In other words, taking the breaks off
when there's no stimuli doesn't do anything. But how does that system work and how is it a two-edged
sword? So again, there are stimulants and there are inhibitors of virtually every physiologic
system that we have. And one of the inhibitors are molecules on the cell surface, on the surface of
a lymphocyte, that when engaged by a receptor will inhibit a lymphocyte from developing an
immune reaction. And surprisingly, there are two molecules that have been found on the cell surface,
now many more, that when targeted by an antibody will not kill the cell but actually turn off
the breaks that are keeping that cell's activity from exhibiting itself. So it's releasing the
breaks and it turns out to have a very important function in the body because there are some cells
that can react against normal tissues that do not react because they're being inhibited by these
breaks. And when you release those breaks, now the T cell can be very active. And it turns out that
cancer has manipulated those and by taking the breaks off, you can attack certain cancers and
explains why melanoma is one of the more common cancers to be attacked because it has so many
antigens, so many mutations. And it was a startling discovery that simply attacking a
molecule, a single molecule on the cell surface could take the breaks off a lymphocyte and let
it attack cancer. And when it comes to melanoma, kidney cancer, cancers that have large numbers
of mutations because they have a mismatch repair gene mutations, Lynch syndrome, the
MSI, the microsatellite unstable tumors, they can very strongly react against cancer. But the
common epithelial cancers that result in 90% of deaths in patients have very little reactivity
against the checkpoint modulator. So although they can be life-saving and very likely, although
it's been too soon, curable for some cancer patients, the overwhelming majority of cancer
patients just do not respond to taking off the breaks because when you take off the breaks,
there's not a strong enough reaction to take advantage of. But hopefully combinations of
treatments using checkpoint modulators will be more effective in the future. But it was a major,
a major step forward. And the beauty of it, easy to apply because all that required was the injection
of an antibody. So when you think about these amazing conceptual advances in the field,
the ability of CAR T cells to recognize CD19 on B cells and eradicate any lymphoma originating
from that lineage, the checkpoint modulators, NTCTLA4, NTPD1, and the durable effect that they can
have on patients in whom you have enough mutagenic burden that relieving the checkpoint is enough to
initiate it. Obviously what you've alluded to earlier with IL2, high dose IL2,
I don't want to at all sound disparaging, but just for the lack of,
let's just call that the low hanging fruit of immunotherapy, which is of course completely
ridiculous given that that's 50 years of work and countless lives. But if for the sake of being
cheeky, the low hanging fruit of immunotherapy are those pillars, do you believe that the final
frontier to go from where we are in 2021 until the point where all of those six, let's just call
the 550,000 patients with solid organ metastatic cancer who have neoantigens or 80% of them have
neoantigens that are unique to them, but not occurring in high enough frequencies that they
will respond to a checkpoint inhibitor in isolation and or in combination with cytokines.
Do you believe that there is a path for these people to be cured using adoptive cell therapy,
either genetically or naturally occurring in some sort of a customized format? Do you think that
that is the path forward from here? My intuition is very strong that the answer to that is yes,
for a variety of reasons. One, we know it can work from multiple tumor types. And as I mentioned,
we've described it and published treatment of liver tumors, bile duct cancers, breast cancer,
colon cancer, cervical cancer. We have responses in ovarian cancer that we've published. And so
it's no longer a question of can it work in these other cancers. The answer is yes, it can work.
And that's a world of difference. Like before IL-2, we never knew that immunotherapy would work,
but once it did, we knew the immune system could do it. Now we know that antigens recognized by
T cells are present on 80% of the common cancers. And if you can develop unique reactivities,
lymphocytes select reactivities against them and administer them, they can cause those regressions.
And in fact, now, because we know the exact T cell receptor sequences that we've cloned
and isolated, it's almost an engineering problem because since we know the receptors,
we've now isolated libraries of receptors against P53, KRAS, that we can now use to genetically
modify lymphocytes to turn a normal lymphocyte into a lymphocyte that can attack the cancer.
And we have our first example of that now that we've submitted for publication targeting P53 by
genetically altering a lymphocyte by giving it a receptor that could recognize
some of these driver antigens. So we know it can work. And
tell you the truth, I finally feel like I have the hang of this kind of research.
And that by sufficient work, creativity, this is going to be a problem that is solvable. We know
the antigens are there, we know the T cells are there, it should work, and it can work, and I
believe it will work as the years go on. And that's 100% of what I'm working on today, and that is how
to utilize these unique mutational reactivities to cause the solid common epithelial cancers that
result in 90% of all cancer deaths, how to get them to respond to immunotherapy.
I mean, of all the eureka moments in your career, of which you've had several,
this one seems to be the most promising, which of course, maybe they always seem that way when
you're glowing in them. But do you see it that way? That every one of these milestones that
came before this was vital, but this has the greatest potential, this recognition that
virtually every solid tumor out there has novel peptides that can be recognized by a patient's
own immune system. Right. Now realize how current this is. We published a lot of these individual
cases that can respond. We published the first 40 or so colorectal cancers showing that mutations
were all unique, but we haven't published much of what I've told you. So for example, none of the
breast cancer work has been published. We now have looked at these 195 individual cancers and found,
regardless of histology, they're there. And so it's very recent, this realization that mutations
are the antigens and now that T cells can recognize these mutations. It's really a new world,
but that happens every time you make an advance. You find the immune system can be stimulated.
Okay, well, let's get to work on figuring out how. You know, cells can do it. Let's figure out how.
And science works that way by incremental advances. We know this can work and I have
every confidence that scientists around the world will figure out ways to make it work.
That kind of reminds me of some of the important lessons that those of us who've been privileged
enough to work alongside you have learned along the way. And I don't think you never sort of
pounded the table to make these lessons, but it was abundantly clear. And one of them was no
secrecy. There was never any secrecy. I remember working on my experiments and before data were
published, you know, people from other labs, I don't mean other labs at NIH. I mean other labs in
different parts of the country would, you know, you would encourage me to reach out to them and
share my results with them, even running the risk that they would quote unquote scoop me.
But none of that mattered to you. Your goal was what is the fastest path to the accumulation of
collective knowledge in the field? Am I accurately representing that? I don't think I'm overstating
that. No, I've always been horrified by the secrecy that exists in medicine. And it's an ongoing
problem. The need for biotech companies, pharmacologic pharmaceutical companies, to protect
their intellectual property, given current patent laws, prevents them, will often prevent them from
sharing information, from sharing reagents, and this is holding back progress. If we could somehow
overcome this secrecy that results from either people's own personal jealousies about wanting
to be the one who does it, or intellectual property that companies have to protect to preserve
themselves and raise funds to continue to do their work, we need kinds of regulations that will bring
lawyers and doctors together to figure out ways to prevent that kind of secrecy from being a part of
modern science. It's not like we're trying to create a better air conditioner. We're trying to
save the life of another human being. And I think when you take care of cancer patients, it puts a
lot of things in perspective. And the idea of having a policy or a rule that you live by that
inhibits your ability to help people who could potentially be helped is abhorrent to me. I wrote,
as you know, a perspective in New England Journal of Medicine trying to change things, but they
haven't changed. They're every bit as common today as they were back then. And as you know, the first
thing a fellow hears in my lab when they start the first day is, look, anything you know, you share.
Any experimental result you have, you can tell somebody. Any experiment you plan to do tomorrow,
you can tell somebody about. I mean, our goal is to help people that are involved in the suffering
of cancer. And there's no excuse for not doing everything you can to try to help. And that means
sharing what you know. On the other side of your office, right? If one side of your office is the
lab, the other side of your office is the clinic. The other lesson, I think, that you've infused
into the literally hundreds. You might even be into the thousands now of people who have come
through and trained with you. How would I say it? Basically, this idea that one never retreats from
the bedside. One of the things that struck me, actually, especially in medical school when I was
there because I spent the entire time on the clinic. I lived in the clinical ward. You may recall,
I had rented an apartment in Bethesda, which I never went to except on Sundays to get new clothes,
but I slept in the clinic. I remember that. You're quite a legend at the NIH with respect to that,
incidentally. I mean, people thought I never left, but you never left. So it was really quite
an experience to see you in operation there. But the thing that was hard to believe and hard
to process until you experienced it was nine out of 10 people that walked in the door died.
Eight or nine out of 10 of the people who walked. Because again, I think most people don't maybe
understand because it's implicit, but it should be stated. The patients who are coming to NIH have
progressed through every standard therapy. People aren't coming here for whom there are
standard options elsewhere. By definition, these are patients who have the most advanced,
the most aggressive, the most recalcitrant cancers imaginable. These are people who would
probably be expected to live no more than six months without a miracle. They come to the NCI
for those Hail Marys. If 20% of them are saved, that's remarkable, but it means 80% of them don't.
And I think what I remember most was the way in which you described taking care of those 80%
and fighting the urge to retreat from them because of the failure we saw in ourselves.
How did you develop that? I mean, I assume it came naturally to you, but how deliberate has it been
in how you teach those of us that came through? I have enormous respect for practicing oncologists
who face this every day in their practice. It's difficult if you point out, especially when you
get treatments that not only don't work, but actually cause some harm, which has happened
in the course of the development of these treatments as we try to figure out exactly
what we were doing and the right ways to do it. But I always had the feeling that I was working
and working hard to try to improve the situation, to try to somehow repair this Holocaust.
And that kept me going. I don't know what it must be like to be taking care of cancer patients,
knowing you have limited tools at your disposal that are not good enough, and yet that's all you
have and that's what you do day in and day out. I mean, that must be even more trying.
And so I think one of the things that keeps me going, at least, is the fact that I'm doing
everything I possibly can within reason to improve the situation. Without that, I think it would be
much, much more difficult. Yeah, there are so many patients that I still remember from more than 20
years ago who were those ones that didn't make it. And I can't imagine how haunting it is
for you sometimes because I can see their faces, I remember their names, I remember their voices,
and I remember their stories. The newlywed girl who came to clinic one day, and I mean,
she had literally been married for maybe three months, a beautiful 25-year-old woman
with metastatic melanoma, and she was not one of the survivors. A young man whose name and face I
remember every detail of single guy metastatic melanoma, and what was most tragic in his case
was I remember everybody kind of abandoned him at the end of his life. I've said this before,
I feel like cancer takes families that are close and brings them closer and takes families that are
fractured and fractures them more. And I got the sense that his was fractured to begin with, and
he was maybe 26 years old. So I certainly understand the motivation. There's no
lack of motivation for how you do what you do. I guess I'm amazed that you talked about how cancer
has both these stimulants, or the immune system has the stimulatory and the inhibitory components.
Well, it's similar that taking care of patients like this, there's the motivation that comes from
it to do more, but at some level there's the depression of the death toll. I'm not sure
everybody could do that. You seem to have found that balance.
Well, you know when I lie awake at night it's not the successes that I think about,
it's the tragedies patients that you're remembering even now that I'm sure are impacting on you. And
it gets even worse because there are patients that we've killed by doing the wrong thing
to them, not understanding some of the underlying biology. That's the hardest thing to deal with.
But again, given the fact that I'm doing everything that I can reasonably do to help them,
it certainly eases the burdensome. And if you know being a doctor what an unbelievable
privilege it is to have the opportunity to help people like that, given the skills that you've
developed. One of the first lines of the prayer of Maimonides goes, you have been given the wisdom to
alleviate the suffering of your brothers. And that's true in medicine because we spend a lot
of time just learning how to help people. It's a unique opportunity in the world and in life in
general. So there are the satisfactions that you're trying hard, even if most often things
don't work out. But there clearly are sleepless nights involved in all of that process.
You know, the good news is you have wonderful longevity in your family. So despite being 81,
I have every confidence that you're going to be doing this for many more years.
I know you don't like golf enough to hang up what you're doing for the golf course.
I pulled this off the wall today. I wasn't sure if you still recognize these guys here.
This is us from, I think this is 16 years ago. We both look quite a bit younger. And this is
the only picture of me in my office, is this picture. And it speaks to what an influence
you've been in my life. I think the list of people who have had a greater impact on the course of my
life than you is somewhere between zero and Epsilon. It's a decidedly small list. So I feel
forever in your debt. And though I have not been able to follow in your footsteps,
your impact is greater than you could ever recognize.
Well, thank you for saying that. That means a lot to me knowing that someone of your
incredible intellect and perseverance feels that way. So thank you.
I know again what a sacrifice it was for you to take time today to speak. And I know that every
minute you spent talking with me was literally a moment you were not working on this problem.
So I'm beyond grateful. And I know that the people watching this or listening to this are equally
grateful. So thank you so much, Dr. Rosenberg, for everything. Well, you're very welcome.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday
through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head
over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.