Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Alright Lance, thank you for making time today to come by.
Absolutely.
How does it feel to be back in Austin?
It is, it's pretty surreal. I mean, having been here or having lived here for 30 years,
the, the, you know, I've seen the city change and I saw it change as a cyclist.
So I think cyclists see more stuff than most people.
And you're always, you know, you're covering ground, you're finding back roads, you're, you're, you get a sense for a town growing.
You see, you know, obviously the roads get more crowded, but you see more construction trucks and you figure you're like, wait, this is, this place is getting built out.
And so, and then if you go down the rabbit hole of hearing these offers in the real estate market, it's just, this is a different city.
Well, before we get into the great city though.
Yeah, no, look, I, the only thing my wife and I could say after moving here is what took us so long.
Before we get into kind of the details of, of all the stuff I want to talk about, I think it's just sometimes easier if we can get into some hard yes and no questions just so that there's no ambiguity about some of the really important stuff.
Okay. So I've been here before.
Yeah, I think this is going to be familiar to you, but I, I want you to really limit yourself to a yes or no only Lance.
This is, these are important questions.
Is Dura Ace better than campy super record?
Yes.
Is the greatest innovation in time trialing the aerodynamic water bottle?
No.
Is Edgar Allan Poe, the greatest poet of the 19th century?
Sure.
Are today's clinchers as high performing as tubulars?
Yes.
Is Alberto Contador, the greatest cyclist of all time?
Absolutely not.
Can you still ride up Alpe d'Huez in under 45 minutes?
Probably not.
Is the 1985 Oakley Pilot Big Ass Sunglass the greatest shades of all time?
Um, no, but.
Just yes or no.
No.
Thank you.
Is Pinarello the best bike on the market?
No.
Is George Hincappi the best lieutenant you've ever had?
Absolutely.
Was your grandfather the first man to ride his bike on the moon in 1969?
No.
All right.
Now that we've got that out of the way, talk to me about Plano, north east suburb of Dallas.
Pretty much straight north.
Plano is, um, you know, it is, uh, it lives up to its name, right?
Plano is, is Spanish for flat Plano.
Uh, very flat, very windy, um, growing, you know, that's another community like Austin, uh, that's drastically changed when I was a kid growing up in Plano.
You know, I would, you know, leave the house and be out in the, in the fields and I would head up into Allen and go around Lake Levan or I would, um, out to Frisco.
I mean, now Frisco is one of the fastest growing communities in America.
Um, there was only one building out there and that was the global headquarters for EDS.
People thought Ross Pro was nuts to build, you know, the EDS headquarters there.
And, and now it's, you know, mom's still there.
So I just going back is crazy.
A lot of times I'll, when I visit my mom, I always take my bike everywhere, but I'll, I'll just kind of ride around and, you know, go past Duly Elementary where I went to middle school and I'll go to, I actually went to,
sorry, elementary school and middle school was Armstrong.
I'll just go by these places and just, and look at them through a 50 year old's eyes.
It's crazy.
So it's, uh, um, is it bittersweet by the way?
Because like, I hate seeing where I grew up.
I hate it with a passion.
I, the last time I went back to look at my elementary school, I mean, it just upset me so much.
I don't know.
I mean, I could no, no, no, no, no.
I mean, I think, I think most people have a.
Some, uh, level of that in their lives.
You're allowed to sort of hate where you grew up.
Uh, I think, um, I don't want to live there, but you know, it's, it's, it's, it's fine to go back.
See mom.
So your birth father is, is Eddie Gunderson, right?
He left you guys when you were two.
Did you ever see him again after that?
Never saw him again.
Do you ever want to?
Well, he's now passed away.
Yeah.
He passed away in 2012.
No, that's a good, maybe around there.
Um, and from what I hear, he died of a spider bite.
Maybe that led to some other complications, but, um, I never had a desire, um, to sort of reconnect with him.
Um, for most of my life and even, you know, of course now it would be too late, but I might have a different view.
Of that now.
Did he ever reach out to you?
He, uh, not directly.
You know, when, when, after the first tour, when in 99, um, people reached out to him.
So a lot of the press and journalists, they wanted this story.
Um, and his, I mean, his interviews are just, yeah.
They were totally inappropriate.
You know, the comments about my mom that, you know, that far down the road.
Um, but that community, they were, meaning he had disparaging things to say about your mom or.
Yeah.
And so, uh, you know, but I mean, I don't think Eddie was, uh, I was a road scholar.
So how long after, or how old were you when she met and or married Terry Armstrong?
So I would have been three or four.
Yeah.
Right.
And so that's where the name comes from, right?
That's, I wasn't born Lance Armstrong.
Um, funny thing is my initials would have been leg if I would have stayed Lance Edward Gunderson.
But yeah, she became obviously blend Armstrong and I became Lance Armstrong.
You've told me stories in the past and I know you've spoken a bit publicly about Terry and kind of how strict he was.
And did you ever think of him as a father?
Did he feel that way to you in any way, shape or form?
Oh, sure.
Yeah.
I didn't, uh, you know, as a five, six, seven year old kid, you don't know, you know, you're, you, you have your mother and I knew he wasn't my biological father, but, you know, we had a roof over our heads and, and my mom seemed happy.
And so, yeah, at a young age.
Um, and he wasn't, uh, when you say violent, I mean, he, he was just strict.
I mean, it was every little thing got you in trouble.
And I mean, if I did, if I look at my kids' lives and, you know, if they leave their drawer open, I walk by and I'm like, first of all, I don't care if they leave their drawer open.
That would have been a big deal to him.
Um, so I know you've told the story before about, hey, you know, playing every Texas sport, every kid does, you didn't shine in any of those things.
And you're 12 years old, mom throws you into swimming, which you didn't really know how to do, but you obviously picked it up super fast, huh?
Yeah.
I mean, I caught it early.
You're right.
I didn't know how to swim.
And, uh, and she didn't necessarily suggest swimming.
She just, she knew that she had a high energy kid that if that wasn't applied somewhere, directed somewhere, it was going to go somewhere toxic.
And so she was right about that.
But, uh, and I sucked.
I mean, I, at, at, at sort of mainstream sports, um, I've had an issue with balls my whole life.
But you didn't have an issue with your phone a second ago.
That phone came falling out and you, that was one of the most impressive one-handed catches I've seen in a long catch.
I was, I was, yeah.
Um, but, uh, I had a few friends on the swim team.
So I thought, well, I'll try that.
And, um, problem is I was, you know, they, I was 12, they were all 12.
And was this an age group team?
This was an age group team.
So very different.
Um, you know enough about swimming to be dangerous.
And so it's, it's, uh, swimming is really kinda.
There's different categories, so to speak, right?
The most serious is age group swimming.
That's where everybody, that's where Michael Phelps grew up swimming.
That's where everybody grips.
Um, then you have sort of country club setups where it's a summer league and you swim some laps and you have some meets and all the parents are there.
Um, and then you have kind of high school, right?
Which most of the time, at least for us age group was the, the serious training for high school swimming.
Um, but yeah, I was, I was 12 and, and I didn't know how to swim.
And, uh, I certainly didn't know how to swim.
I mean, I could have faked freestyle, but I couldn't have, I didn't know any strokes.
So, you know, I showed up and man, the coach that kind of watch you for a while.
And they, I mean, they stuck me in the six year old lane, six, seven year old lane.
And I still don't, when I think back and I never even questioned it, I just stayed, I stayed swimming with these little, little kids.
Meanwhile, all my buddies are over at the other end of the pool, you know, doing 3100s on whatever.
And I'm like, but I just hung in there and I, and I swam the kids.
And then after, you know, a month of that, then I moved over a lane and I was with the eight year olds.
And then a month later, I was, I just kind of kept going across the pool until, you know,
probably, you know, less than a year later, I was, uh, I was a legit swimmer.
Still, still one of my great loves.
So by the time you get into high school, you're swimming both for the high school team and the age group league.
Yes. Yes and no, because I turned pro in triathlon when I was 15.
So I was, I was already my swim coach at the time who was just a total hard ass, but an amazing coach and Chris McCurdy.
Wonderful coach.
One of the best coaches I've ever had, but man, he was tough and it was, I mean, you don't, you did not miss a workout.
You didn't skip a workout.
There were no excuses.
I mean holidays, family, it doesn't matter.
Like, and we were, our age group team was called Cops, city of Plano swimmers, which was at the time, one of the best age group teams in the country.
And that was because McCurdy and, you know, I started traveling to triathlons and, and, and skipping workouts.
Cause I was on a ride or a run and he was just, he wasn't having it at all.
So you gravitated to the mile and swimming, right?
Well, yeah, I mean that was, I mean, I'm an endurance guy.
So, you know, my, I have no other than catching that phone.
I don't have great fast, which muscle, you know, my hundred free.
I mean, I could, I could have, you know, whereas the, you know, the miles 16 and a half of those.
You know, my, what was your best mile?
I'd have to go back and look, it was decent.
I mean, at state championships one year, I got third.
It's decent, but not, I wasn't going to the Olympics.
Do you think if you'd stayed with swimming and that was the only thing you could have pursued, you would have at least, you know, you would have swim in college, presumably.
I would have swam in college.
And if you asked McCurdy, he thinks I could have gone far, but I did, you know, I was 15.
There was prize money. There was travel. I was like, Hey, this is way cooler.
When did you realize you also had an act to run and bike?
I actually was running right around the same time.
So at the same time I was swimming, I was running track and cross country in high school.
So I was, and I was a decent, you know, in Plano, I was city champ in the, um, it wouldn't have been the, I was, I was young enough that we ran the 1200 city champ in that.
And I remember, you know, back then the timing was primitive.
You got these timers per athlete and you had stopwatches and you come across the line.
It's a funny story.
And they'd ask you, uh, your name.
And so I came across the line and the timer says, what's your name?
And I was going to Armstrong middle school and I said, Armstrong.
And he said, I didn't ask you what, what school you went to.
I said, what's your name? And I said, I finally, I was like, after three or four go rounds, I was like, I'm Armstrong from Armstrong.
But as, you know, it was a decent runner.
How much did you enjoy training at that age?
Uh, I love, I loved, you know, I loved it.
I mean, the most structured thing I had was swimming.
I mean, McCurdy was, I mean, you should have seen the board.
I mean, this dude, I don't know.
I mean, he must have laid awake every night and dreamed up these workouts.
It was so detailed and like, I, I loved that.
Um, and that was the most structure I had running.
I would train a little with the, with the cross country team that had structure.
Uh, we had another great coach in, in, um, track and cross country named James.
So James Mays was a world-class 800 meter runner.
Uh, he was actually the rabbit for, uh, for the dream mile.
And this guy ended up being our high school track and cross country coach.
And he was awesome.
He'd run with us and he like drove a Porsche and we're like, holy shit, our teacher was his dude.
Um, he was awesome.
And then cycling was more, yeah, I just go pedal around.
No structure group rides.
When did it become clear to you that you had a knack for this at the level of, I mean, was it that one race that everybody talks about where you were right at the front with Mark Allen and you're 15 years old.
And at the time, you know, Mark Allen must've been one of the top three professional triathletes in the world.
Well, that was my first pro race.
That was the president's triathlon in Dallas.
That was 80.
That would have been 87, 87, because I did the best I could.
87 87.
87.
Cause I did the presidents in 86, which is out at Lake Le Bon.
It was a longer format or longer distance.
And then they moved it over to Las Collinas where the old Cowboys facility was in 87 and they made it an Olympic distance.
And I was trained with some guys and they said, well, you should just turn pro and go try it.
I was 15 years old.
And so, but I was swimming my ass.
I mean, I was a great swimmer.
I knew I was going to come out of the water with the leaders.
So this is Olympic distance.
So you're coming out of the water under 20 minutes.
Oh, easy. Yeah.
And then you hop on the bike.
Hop on the bike.
You're going under an hour.
You're going what?
55 minutes.
Well, this is pre-Aero bars.
Although actually that might've been the year Andrew McNaughton flew away on the bike.
He had the bars, the original Scott Aero bars.
And then I rode with Allen the whole time on the bike.
And I'm sure he was, you know, those, they all race each other every week.
And they know.
Was Dave Scott there too?
I don't know if Dave was there.
Mike Pig would have been there.
Pig might've been there.
The big Kiwi.
Anyways, it was, it was like, I rode with Allen, but I'm sure he's looking at me going.
Who the fuck is this person, this guy, this kid?
And then, uh, you know, got like Mark Allen get off and run 32.
And you would run what?
36 after that?
No, no, probably more.
Right.
38 or 39.
And so I think I ended up fifth or sixth and, uh, that was, I was like, okay, I can do this.
Was the bike different compared to swimming and running for you?
Like, was there a gear that you felt you had there that you didn't have in the other two?
I don't know about a gear, but it was the experience was certainly different.
I mean, how so?
I mean, I know it is, but what did you feel that was different?
Well, it's, it's just like I said at the top, you know, being outside, I mean, think about the life of a, of a full time, essentially professional swimmer you, you spend and I don't think people really appreciate how much time swimmers devote to their sport and how much distance they cover.
I mean, when we were 13, 14, 15, we were swimming.
Um, you know, there'd be days we do swim 10 miles a day.
Like if somebody said they run 10 miles a day, I would say, you're a fucking badass swimming.
That's two days.
So 5 30 a.m.
Morning practice for an hour and two hours in the afternoon.
You're covering some ground and you're staring at a black line the whole time.
That's why swimmers are crazy.
Well, and the funny thing is most people don't appreciate that the swim to run ratio is about four to one.
So when you say somebody swims 10 miles a day, that's comparable metabolically to running 40 miles a day.
I mean, it's the no impact.
Yeah, without the impact.
What makes it a great sport for, you know, as you get to be my age or even older.
I mean, the thing I love about swimming is you can swim your whole life.
You can't necessarily ride your whole life.
You certainly can't run your whole life.
Like swimming, if you put a gun in my head and said, okay, dude, you got one sport to choose for the rest of your life.
There is no question it would be swimming.
No question.
So I've heard you say in a previous interview that triathlons were awesome, but at some point you got this desire to go to the Olympics.
And you realize that what kid doesn't want to go to the Olympics?
Yeah. Well, at some point you realize, look, my quickest path there is probably going to be on the bike.
Yep.
And I'm guessing that was the late eighties.
You kind of had that realization.
Well, I, yeah, I started to transition to full time cycling in 89, still doing trias.
I did them also in 89 and 90, went to the junior world championships in Moscow in 1989.
But in my mind, I just assumed triathlon would be an Olympic sport.
It is the ultimate.
I mean, the best sports in the Olympics are swimming and cycling and running.
Like, why wouldn't we combine them and make this an Olympic sport?
Well, this is in the late eighties, early nineties.
Right. It wouldn't be till 2000.
2000 in Sydney was the first time.
Nobody knew that.
But, um, yeah, so I switched over basically full time in, uh, in, uh, 1991, 1990 or 91.
Which is kind of amazing to now fast forward to 93.
Um, what expectations did you have going into Oslo into that road race for the world championship?
Well, the one thing that did happen is I, I.
You went to the Olympics.
Actually, you did go to Barcelona.
You fulfilled that dream, going to the Barcelona games.
You did road race or time trial?
What did you do?
Nope. They didn't have the time trial back then.
They had, uh, and I want to say, I think we had team time trial.
I did the road race.
I don't think I did the TTT.
How many cyclists went for the U S boy?
You're making me think a lot.
I mean, this is a long time ago, Peter.
This is 30 years ago.
So I don't know.
Three or four.
But this was back in the day when you couldn't, you didn't have pros there, right?
No pros.
Yeah.
They added the pros in 96.
You have pro and that was the, so who were the best amateurs then Bobby Julek, you.
Yeah.
And then, um, you know, the international guy, the Italians were amazing.
Casa Tully, uh, who we lost a 95.
He won.
He won the games.
David, uh, Debbie de Rabeline was on the Italian team, but you know,
a lot of Eric Decker was on the Dutch teams.
I was on the German team.
So what was that like there competing against the best amateur cyclists in
the world?
Um, it was, I mean, it was great.
I didn't, I didn't race very well.
I didn't, um, tactically, tactically, I was still not, I was still trying to
figure out cycling.
Um, I didn't know how to move through the Peloton and, and, and sort of gauge
and judge the Peloton and the tactics and the flow of the race.
Uh, then like,
that's very hard for people who watch cycling to understand.
It's funny.
I mean, I, you take it for granted now.
You could throw me in any bike race and I could absolutely find my way around.
But that's not, I don't, nobody's born with that skill, right?
I mean, that strikes me as fair.
I mean, I'm sure there are some people who'd have a better feel for it than others.
When they start young, I mean, you get, you know, Galli George, he started,
he was racing in central park against adult men when he was 12 years old.
I mean,
but to go from, because in triathlon, you can't even, could you draft at the
time in 90, 91?
All right.
So, so you go from a sport where bike should never be able to draft.
Yeah.
This pisses off all the, uh, yeah.
All the purists.
Well, no, all the, you know, the, the, uh, sort of the ITU guys,
the, the Olympic guys, cause they, that's, you know, I got in a bunch of, uh,
a bunch of grief once because I called, you know, the, that kind, or that part of
triathlon, uh, a shampoo, a blow dry and a 10 K.
And I mean, it was, it was people.
But anyways, I just, it's an individual sport.
But that's amazing that you basically,
your cycling career as a cyclist begins two years or a year,
two years before the Olympics,
because all of the stuff you're doing as a triathlete is preparing your
cardiovascular system and your fitness, but not your bike handling skills,
not your tactics, not any of those other things.
No, the handling I had down, I mean, it was,
I wrote enough that I was comfortable in the peloton,
but just understanding the movements of the race and, uh,
positioning and, you know, just the, the, the, you know, the peloton, it's a,
it's just a big organism and you've got to be at the right place at the right
time. And yeah, it took me a few years.
What metrics were you guys looking at then?
Were you mostly just relying on heart rate?
Not even, I mean, going back then we heart rate monitors and we were,
when I got on Motorola, we were sponsored by polar.
And so we had some of the earliest heart rate monitors. These things were as,
I mean, I'm sure you could still find them. I mean, they were massive.
These things, they look like bricks legitimately component.
And that was it. I mean, and that was sort of the first, yeah, obviously no power
meters, no, uh, no testing. I mean, we just, yeah,
he just looked at the heart rate.
So did you have any metrics or insights into your physiology being unique at the
time? I mean, did you figure out what your maximum heart rate was? I mean,
we'll get to it later, but I remember you telling me during,
I don't remember which time trial it was.
You were telling me about in one of the,
one of your tours that you were able to hold a heart rate of 200 beats per
minute for the entire TT.
Yeah, that was, that was later. Um, I think the first time I really,
um, thought I had an engine,
so to speak and maybe because they told me that as I, I,
they were doing a study at the Cooper clinic in Dallas. And of course I was
living in Plano. So I,
and it was a treadmill test and they wanted me to, and they were,
I forget what the original study was, but it's got a funny ending to the story.
It was all about core temp.
And so I went down and did a running VO two tests and the guy was like, Oh,
I mean, it was, I killed this thing. And then, then they, and, uh,
do you remember what your VO two max was now? No, no, but the guy was like, okay,
this, this kid's special. And, and then they said, well, look,
we'd like you to come back next week because we're doing this whole core temp
study. And this time you're going to have to do it with some sort of probe in the
exactly. And I'm 15.
And this guy says he's going to shove something up my ass and I am
terrified. I'm like, uh, I never went back.
So to that, uh, research to this day,
we have no idea what your core temperature response would have been under that
aerobic load. Well, you want to do that test. We can do it again.
You know, I know enough to know that I run hot, so that I'm going to leave it at
that. Um, so, so Motorola was 93.
I went, I went to Motorola in, uh, actually in 92.
I was the only amateur on the team. Steve Bauer was on that team.
Bauer was there Phil Anderson, Andy Hampson. So, so by the way,
Steve Bauer is why a kid growing up in Canada like me was obsessed with cycling
growing up. Right.
So I was one of like 12 people in North America that loved cycling followed it
because Bauer won a silver in 84 at the Olympics. So basically I'm 10,
11 years old that puts cycling on the map is something that's like awesome.
And, and then of course, LeMond was, I mean, forget about it.
Like the most exciting thing in all of sports in 1989 was the,
the 89 company is unbelievable. Uh,
some would argue the greatest ending to a tour.
You could argue maybe second greatest after what happened last year,
that let the scholars debate that. Um,
but I want to talk about the 93 season because you've got a
guy named Miguel Indran who's come along and dethroned. Um,
Greg who's dethroned Greg, right? And at this point,
Indran is now won three consecutive tours. He,
there's no sign he's going to slow down, right? He wins 91 92 93.
He looks like an absolute machine.
This is one of the guys you're now racing against for the world championship in
the road race. What's your thought going into that race?
Um,
well the w the way the season was structured then, and I,
and I actually much preferred it. The worlds was much earlier was, you know,
four or five weeks after the tours, the guys, the Vuelta. Yep. Yep.
Well, no, the back then the Vuelta was in, uh, early in the season.
Wait, wait, the, the Vuelta was for the Giro. Yeah. Okay.
So you had, and the Vuelta was, was minimized, uh, which it should have been,
because it's, it's, it just anyways. Uh,
but we had a true world cup. So you had all of the monuments,
all the big spring classics. And then every week after the tour,
we went to St. Sebastian, we went Zurich, we went Leeds in England, but you know,
it was like boom, boom, boom. And so it was just this,
I loved the rhythm of that calendar. And I was after the tour, 93,
which you won a stage. I won a stage, uh, into Verdun, um,
in the national champions Jersey. And then, uh,
they pulled me out because I was young and,
but my form just kept coming up and up and up. And,
um, and all the world cups, and I was, I was, I was right there.
All the prep races I was, I knew I was going to be in the front group, but,
and I was, shit, I didn't care. I mean, I looked around in that group. I mean,
you had, you had Olaf Ludwig, you had Indira, you had Kia Pucci,
you had Schmeel, you had Museu, you had Reese. I mean,
I was looking around going, yeah, of course I'm here. And then of course,
it was absolutely pissing.
Worst day of ever. And people crashing. I mean, I crashed twice. Uh,
people crashing everywhere. How cold was it? Uh, it was, it's funny.
I never really felt that cold. It was, but it was cold.
It looked cold. Yeah. Yeah. It was, it was, it was probably in the fifties.
I mean, Northern Europe with weather like that, it's going to be cold.
No matter what time you're here.
Explain to people what it means to win that race, to be the world champion.
What you know,
you get to wear a special Jersey that nobody else gets to wear for a year.
Yup. You wear the rainbow Jersey for a year. And then for the rest of your
career, you, you have some representation on your jerseys or shorts.
So rainbows on the sleeves, the collar. Uh, it's a, it's a cool one to win.
Thinking back to that year in the tour, we're going to talk a lot about,
obviously performance enhancing drugs. You've in the past said, you know,
that was in the era where you and your team were still in the low octane phase
of things, right? The, the cortisones, things like that.
But it was the pre EPO era, even though EPO was around, it was around. Yeah.
This was, but this was before the real shootout.
What were you aware of in that year's tour?
I mean, there was buzz of, of EPO, but it was not, um,
you know, it wasn't a dinner table conversation like it became. There was,
I mean, there was obviously speculation,
but there was scientific articles about it.
People knew that that, that substance, um,
as great as it is to treat certain disorders or issues.
It could also be hugely beneficial for endurance sport. Um,
but in, in 92 93, it was, it was not, it wasn't an obsession.
You know, at the time, obviously when I was just a kid following cycling,
I was always surprised in the 91 tour, how quickly Greg fell off. Um,
and years later, of course we would all speculate, was that the,
was that not just the passing of the torch between two great cyclists,
Lamond and Induran, but was it also the passing of the torch of an era? Right?
Was it, do you believe that that was when high octane products became the
mainstay in 91? Or do you think that no,
it would not be probably until either the end of Induran or because clearly by
the time Reese came along in 96, I mean, that might've been the most, um,
yeah, people, people most that really have a deep understanding will tell you
that it, I mean, it was in the Peloton in the late eighties. Um,
but that's really going far back and, and, and,
and nobody from back then is talking for sure. Um,
but honestly, yeah, Pedro Delgado, I think there, there were definitely rumors
that, that, um, cause he won in what didn't he win the year that Lamond was out,
which was 87.
You know way too much about the sport. Yeah. This is, you know, a lot more than me,
but I peg it to the jerseys I had as a kid and Greg, I had the PDK.
And honestly, Greg, Greg still could have,
he towards the end of his career and it was well documented. I'm not,
I'm not saying this as a, as a, uh, as a knock on him, but he's,
he was starting to let himself go in the off season. I mean,
he would show up to the earth season races and I mean, you could see it.
You're like, dude, is this guy been training or not? And, and,
and Indorine was a machine. Indorine was a beast. I mean,
this guy trained 365 days a year. So, um,
so it's not clear what that transition was. Yeah,
but Indorine was, he could do it all.
So I think another thing that most people don't understand about cycling is,
or certainly about the, about the tour is that because of how
grueling it is, which again, I can't tell you,
I understand because I've never done it,
but as much as somebody who's never understood it or has never done it,
I feel like I at least have some appreciation for it because I understand
physiology. There's nothing about it that's reasonable, right?
Like there's nothing about doing that, that is physiologically appropriate,
or in any way, shape or form promotes a person's health, right? Like a rider at
the end of the tour is probably the least healthy they could ever be. Um,
and as a result of that,
there's no era in the history of this bike race where cyclists haven't turned to
substances. Um, and,
and whether they're banned or not banned is really a semantic point, right?
But you know, in the earliest renditions of this race,
riders were using alcohol to numb pain or traditional painkillers, cocaine,
more sophisticated amphetamines, war hopping on trains.
Exactly. Grabbing cars, literally just getting yanked up mountains. Um,
what was the environment like? Not that you were there, but you wrote,
you overlapped with the guys that were there in the eighties.
Was there an environment of testing of anything?
Like were people looking at himatic rate to see if people like actually blood
doped, let alone using EPO,
were they testing for cortisone or testosterone or other hormones?
Um, I don't have to go back. And I mean, like, for example,
in 93 when I won a stage in the tour, I won the world's, I was tested.
You were tested. Okay. Um, but that's not, you know,
you acknowledge that back then you were using things like cortisone.
Were you worried that those things would show up or were you just making sure
that they were out of your system by the time you were racing? Well, you know,
the, the, um, what the, what the, um,
the way to go about that in the day was just a TUE.
So a therapeutic use exemption and, and, you know,
a lot of these compounds come in different forms and different form factors and
different administrations. And so you, you know, you could say, well, you know,
I've got tendonitis in the knee. And so they, that's how they,
the TUE was sort of the, which I think they've cut back on a lot of that. Um,
but in competition testing for certainly for something like EPO,
which has a five hour half life. No way. Not going to work. Yeah. That's where,
that's where they, you know,
they started doing the out of competition testing and the whereabouts and the,
but you know, the,
the biggest hammers that have dropped in cycling in and around drugs like that
were not through testing. They were through the police. Like look at,
yeah, nobody got, nobody tested positive, positive in the Festina fair. Right.
Do the police shut up and raid them?
A dumbass one year across on a border gets pulled over low and behold a car full
of stuff. That's how that happened. Like the agencies had nothing to do with
that.
So coming into the 94 season, you've got to be optimistic, right? You've just won.
You're the world champion. Um, what,
do you remember what your expectations and your goals were for that season with
respect to either single day classics or grand tours?
Yeah. I mean, I thought, um, that,
that was an interesting period in time though, because that is when,
yeah, no, and I know you basically got your ass kicked out here,
but I want to know what you thought coming in.
Well, I thought I would, I mean, I thought I'd be, yeah,
competitive and every one day race I started.
And did you think like I'm going to be on the podium in the tour in the next
three years? No, no. At that time I was fully resigned or,
or committed to the fact that I was, I was a classic rider. I was one day,
right? What did you weigh at that point?
I probably weighed, I was big, you know, I was,
I was my whole career. I was big just cause I was as a swimmer, you, you never,
a swimmer never loses a swimmer's body. Uh, the back, the chest,
shoulders, I mean, you can lean it out, but you're going to be big.
So I was probably one 75. Yeah.
Which is tough to be a climber at one 75. But I was one,
when in the tours I was, you know, between one 61 65.
Still big. Yeah. I mean, race in Pantani was one 25.
So when do you realize in 94, like something's wrong?
Well, I, I, I think we realized that something had changed. Um,
and I mean, it was, it was overnight. I mean that, but that between 93 and 94,
even though I'm sure 93, there was, um,
and that's the great thing about a one day race is it is in a way,
a race, a chance you can play your cards, you can play tactics. You can,
you obviously have to be fitting up to be in the front group.
But when I made my move in 93, I mean, that was a, that was a bit of a hail Mary.
I went early. I got a gap. They were disorganized behind and,
and you stay away. So, you know, the big tours were, you know,
the race of truth in the time trial or the hardest climbs. Like there was no,
those are individual competitions. And so,
but there was a tectonic shift from 93 to 94.
And how long did it take you to understand this is exactly what's happening.
This is not about more cortisone. This is not about more testosterone.
It was all over. It was all over the press. I mean, you know, you had,
in 1994 you had in flesh for loan,
you had three go with riders go up the road and then the,
the press went crazy after that because you're having an Italian team.
Um, Ferrari's the trainer,
you know, the, the press also back then was more, uh,
they were more sort of beat riders. So they were friends with the riders.
They were, uh, they were beat right.
Ters and they were friends with the riders. They were friends with the directors.
So they were all kind of buddies and,
but they wouldn't write about what they would hear. Um,
until then, and then they started and then they got on it. And so,
uh, and then people got to Ferrari and, and he made, you know, of course,
the famous quote about trying to compare E-boat to orange juice.
And at least that's the way that it was printed. But after that,
every, yeah, it was everywhere in the press and in the belt.
Did you remind me what happened in the 94 tour for you?
94, I got sick halfway through and dropped out. Okay.
And then in the 95 tour finished,
you finished and that's a tragic tour, right? Yeah.
So Fabio is killed. Yep. Yep.
He was on our team. He was on your team.
The same guy that won the Olympics. He won the Olympics in 92. Is that,
is that a wake up call to you in any way?
Do you realize how dangerous your sport is when you watch your teammates head
smashed open on the side of the road? Yep. Yeah. That was, uh,
um, you know, of course the helmets were
not certainly not required and very few people wore them. Um,
I'm not sure what it helped Fabio. He hit really hit his face.
Um, and basically died right there, but, um,
and just surreal to, you know, it was a tough mountain day and,
and we were in the group petto and I mean, we were out there forever.
And we actually got news of his death, um, in the race.
And so it was just, you know,
that's so rare, but to have, so to have it happen to us on our team,
you know, you have breakfast with the guy, but he's not at the dinner table,
you know, and the whole, the, the, the, the, the, the,
the whole story is tragic, right? Young wife, new baby boy. I mean,
it, and he was, you know, Fabio was interesting.
He wasn't your normal Italian. He was, uh,
they were all super serious, not really jokesters.
He was a jokester like, and he came to our, uh,
he obviously had huge talent and potential won the Olympic gold. Um,
but he didn't, he wasn't adjusting to pro cycling.
And so we picked him up in 95. Um,
and ironically the, uh, the, the, the, the, for that last,
or for the ninth spot, it was down, uh, it was down to him and George.
And George was actually there at the start cause we would always take 10 guys.
And then literally the day before the team would decide who the ninth guy was and
they decide George was young, but they decided to take Casa Telly.
Um, you know, yeah, I was, it was, it was bad.
It was the 18th stage that you won in his honor. Three days later,
when did you realize you were going to win that race that stage rather?
Well, you know, that's those, those stages at the end of the tour,
they're, they're, they're just custom made for breakaways, right?
The GC is set. It's, it's,
those days are for the opportunist and I went away in a group and it was a huge,
ironically, Johann Berniel was in that group too,
but it was a huge group and, and that group stays away.
They never get caught. And then, you know,
they basically race amongst ourselves and, and, and, uh, you know,
I just took a huge flyer. I think it was 30, 40 K to go. Just,
just went away and, and, you know, they'll let you go. Um, but you, you're playing,
you're betting that they, you know, like a lot of times they can't get organized.
And, but when I went, man, I was fucking,
flying moves. It was, I knew I was. I mean, in fact,
our director at the time, Henny Kiper, who was a legendary Dutch cyclist,
he kept coming up, you know, this is, uh,
he kept coming up and giving me time splits.
And you were gapping, you were gaining on the gap.
Yeah. And finally I said, Henny, don't come up here anymore.
I said, I'm not getting caught. Just stay back there. And I was,
I knew it and I was just, just flying.
And you, did you feel a sense of like this was for Fabio,
you felt a little extra strength that day. I mean, I've heard,
I've heard so many athletes talk about that when they're Damon Hill talking about
racing after Senna died later in that season, feeling like he, he couldn't do,
he couldn't just make that cargo fast enough.
And it's almost like he looked up to the skies and just asked for some bit of help
from him.
And just floating and, and, and, you know,
I don't want to oversell our relationship or our friendship because we,
I didn't really know Fabio. We were on our team together.
He didn't speak English. I didn't speak Italian. Um,
but it's nonetheless, I mean, he died in our colors and, and, uh,
you know, it's, it's, it just, it just doesn't happen. So for, I mean,
it's extraordinary that it, that it happened to us. And I mean,
at that day, I mean, I was just possessed.
So going into the 96 season,
that's the year you decided it was time to, to,
to start moving into the high octane world. Correct.
Actually, no, we, we, we, we made that decision. 95. Oh, you did. Yeah. Okay.
96. I was, I joined Ferrari. So that was,
so you, so in 95 you were sort of doing freestyle EPO,
managing it on your own.
Yeah. I mean the, the, we had, you know, there was,
there was medical care. There was guidance. I mean, this isn't, you know,
I think that would be a bad idea to just go off and do that on your own,
but there were, there was some oversight.
And would you manage it to a certain himatic, right?
Is that effectively what was being done? They weren't testing,
they didn't start testing for himatic, right? Until I want to say 98 or 90,
they started testing,
doing the sort of morning himatic tests while I was out of the sport.
So, but in 95 and 96, they didn't know, no,
I don't mean the race organizers.
I mean where the doctor is using himatic, right? Oh yeah.
As we got get a guide, your EPO level and your, your.
And hemoglobin. Yeah. Yeah. So what is your normal hemoglobin? Like,
like what is it today? Low? Well, that's a good question.
Yeah. Uh, since we live in Aspen now, I'm sure it's, it's,
it's probably 45 or 46, but you know,
if I lived here in Austin, it would be in the low forties.
And so do you remember when you started doing EPO in 95,
presumably they gave you enough EPO to bring your himatic rate up to 50,
I would guess is where they kind of wanted you. Well, there was,
50 was not, um,
I know that there was no ceiling, right?
Did they have concern about blood clotting and things like that? Um,
not at 50 and maybe not even at 60.
And there are people on Everest that you know, you know,
better than me that have a himatic rate of 70.
So do you know how high they were pushing your crit back in 95?
Not specifically, not that it was, uh, the answer is no,
but I mean, it would, I would remember if it had been 60, you know,
sort of the stories you hear from, from some folks, but,
and, and also just, um, you know, enough is enough, right?
At some point you're, you're, you're competitive. You're at the front of the,
you know, you need to do more.
Did you feel a difference? Did you notice a difference from 94? Oh yeah.
I mean, let's not get ourselves. That's,
it's a very effective substance.
And do you have the sense that it was being used as
often in the one day races as it was in the grand tours? Absolutely. Yeah.
Again, there's no reason it wouldn't help you in Perry,
Roubaix just as much as it helps you on.
Absolutely. Watts or Watts. I mean,
if you're getting 10% more hemoglobin or hematocrit, whatever you want,
however you want to describe it, you are also getting at threshold,
10% more power. Do you, were you using a power meter yet at that point?
My, no, I didn't. I,
I 98 was when I first started using the SRM.
The SRM. Yeah. It was so good. Yeah. Well, I,
do you remember off the top of your head,
what your functional threshold power was in 98?
Um, I remember what it was in 99. What was it? I mean, in 99,
I could before the tour in 99, I tested on, uh, on the Madone.
And which was your go-to test. Yeah. It was, well, it was,
I wasn't the first to use it. Tony Romager used it. He,
he had the fastest time and you know, how many kilometers is Madone? It's, uh,
what's about 30 minutes,
30 minutes. And what's the grade? It's about 7, 8%.
So it's a straight in the saddle pound away for 30 minutes.
And what did you average for 30 minutes in 99? 500 Watts.
Are you freaking kidding me?
500 Watts for 30 minutes.
And at that point you were 165 pounds. Yep.
Yeah. Seven Watts kilo.
All right. We got it.
We got a few things to cover before we get the seven Watts per kilo. Um,
96, you should be in top form and you're sick as hell in the tour.
You pull out. Yep.
I thought I was just sick. Um, and I was certain,
and I was definitely sick of being there. It was just,
it was shit weather that year and I wasn't riding that well and I was ready to
go home.
When did you notice that testicular pain?
Certainly then. Um, but I just, you know, soreness, uh,
that was the first symptom, right? Just, just enlarged testicle sore.
Um, but on every level, sore to the touch, sore to sit on a seat.
You know, if you crossed your legs in an awkward way, it would hurt.
And I just thought, I thought I'd had to do was sitting on a bike seat all the
time, which is, you know, I've heard you say that before.
And I've always thought it's kind of funny because you've been sitting on a bike
for 10 years at that point. I know. But then you also, I mean,
you're rationalizing it, right? And, and I, you know, nobody, I was growing up.
And just to even to this day, I just rarely get sick. Like I, you know, I,
I just didn't have,
and I certainly didn't think that I would ever be in that position, but, um,
and I just, it was ignore after ignore,
even as the symptoms sort of became more and more drastically significant.
I just, I just kept going. I had an excuse for all of,
did you have any headaches? I had one big episode, uh,
that was right before diagnosis. Yeah.
Massive headache, massive headache, massive. Any visual changes?
The next day. Yeah. So the visual, um, so I, I,
I was here in Austin actually. I used to have a venue, um,
South of town. Uh, what's it called?
I forget, but I went to a Jimmy Buffett concert and I got a huge headache at the
concert and, uh, next day woke up blurry vision.
And even then I'm pushing through it. I'm like, okay.
Headache cause I was at a concert and maybe I had a couple of beers. Now,
you're not supposed to have the headache while you're having the beers.
It's supposed to be the next day and the blurry vision. Well, I'm, you know,
I might need to get some glasses. Uh,
and then probably a week after that was the, you know,
it was the one that sent me to the doc.
Just coughing up blood everywhere. Everywhere.
That's October 2nd. That was, um, uh, no,
no, because the, the, um, I mean, it would have been,
maybe October 1st because the blood episode happened and you know,
coughing up the blood,
spitting it out and, and, um, called my buddy. He was a neighbor.
He's a doctor said, I don't know. We were coughing up blood.
Can you come look at it? And you know, um, cosmetic surgeon, not a,
I'm an oncologist, not a, you know,
sort of looked in my nose and my down my throat and you know,
he thought, and I had rinsed out the sink.
So he didn't see how much was in there.
He didn't see how much blood there was there. Did it scare you? Oh yeah.
Yeah.
And I obviously didn't do a good enough job telling him how much blood was in
the sink. Um, so he thought it was a sinus thing.
You're a sinus, you dry the crack, you cough up a little bit.
And you weren't putting two and two together. Of course,
this thing in my testes, the headache, the blood, there's no way in your mind.
These are all related.
Nope. And then, and then the next day, which was October 2nd,
I called him back because this pain at this point was so bad and the testicle
was so swollen. I said, listen,
there's just one other thing that that, you know, I just embarrassed or I just,
you know, I haven't talked about that this is going on.
And that's when he said, okay, this, we gotta get that checked out.
And then that's when I drove to Jim Reeves's office on the second.
What do you remember people talk often about when a diagnosis like this is
levied on them, they're not even able to process what's being said. Like,
you hear some things, but you don't hear other things. Like I,
I remember experiencing this as the one delivering this news where you sort of
try to talk as slowly as possible. You pause as much as possible,
but you realize at the end of that, they probably heard a 10th of what you said.
What is your recollection of the very first time this news was,
because by this point they probably had a chest X-ray.
Well, it was one of the first things Jim Reeves did.
They also did another little shot. I'll never forget this. They did, they,
they gave me a little shot under the skin where they were going to test a
reaction or so. So what's that? What are you doing? What's, what's this for?
And they said, Oh, we want to, um, we just want to rule out tuberculosis.
And I remember thinking, God, please give me tuberculosis.
And then he wanted a chest X-ray and I'm like, well, why are you,
what do you need a chest X-ray for?
And then they sent me to the ultrasound. Uh, and it took,
that they had a young lady in there. It was the text. She just took forever.
And I thought, does she not know what she's doing?
Then the actual doctor came in and repeated the test. Um,
this was an ultrasound of your testes and your abdomen. I'm guessing.
Yeah. And, um, and then, and then they walked in and they,
they handed me the, uh, the file, which, uh, had the chest X-ray,
they had the scan report and they said, you know,
go back to Dr. Reeves office. He's waiting for you. And at this point,
it's like, I dunno, six or 7 PM. I'm like, this is not good.
And so that's what, I mean, he didn't,
I can remember most of what he said cause he didn't say very much. I mean,
he just straight in.
Now at the time did they know that it was not seminomatous?
So they, there was still a window of opportunity that this was going to be a
very curable form of testicular cancer.
I think with the chest, I mean the chest X-ray was, was riddled. I mean,
it was, it was more white than it was gray.
So you had pretty good indication.
How long until you had the orchiectomy? How many days?
Nice morning. Yeah. Cause that's what I said to Reeves. I said,
I feel like I should get a second opinion. And he said,
you have surgery at seven AM tomorrow morning.
And you know, keep in mind, this is in 1996.
So this, the way people would process this news today, they would,
they would say, okay, I'm going to go home. I'm going to open my computer.
I'm going to, I'm going to Google everything I can about whatever my doctor just
told me.
And I'm going to start to learn and get a bunch of information and figure out
options. And none of that existed.
We did not have the internet in 1996.
When did you call your mom?
Oh, right away. Yeah. Right when I got home. How was she?
My mom's always, uh, you know, on this,
and this is, you know, I think what makes her great and strong,
if she would never show weakness. So it,
although I know she had moments where, um,
she would be sad and upset and worried, um,
on the surface, she just, she just had this shield. Like, let's,
let's fucking go. We got this. You could do this. Um,
so she, yeah, she would for anything that I ever saw,
she was totally confident.
Did you understand what the prognosis was at that time?
Um, not really. Uh,
and who does right? I mean, it's, it's, uh, I mean,
I know it was, it was as advanced as it was.
Well, it wasn't just that it was advanced, right? It was the histology of it.
It was not a seminomatous tumor, which is at that point,
really the only testicular cancer that's curable, right? You had,
you had a much more histologically advanced cancer that choreocarcinoma,
which was, which was wildly metastatic. What was your alpha-theta protein level?
Well, that was, that was elevated. The one we monitored, um,
the closest was, uh, beta-HGG.
How high was that?
A hundred thousand.
So you were pregnant.
I know. Well, anything, you know, it was very pregnant. Um,
yeah, that was, uh, you know, I mean,
if you come in with 500, you got a problem.
Anything above two, you have a problem.
So you had the orchiectomy. They also took out lymph nodes.
They didn't know. We didn't do any, no, didn't touch the lymph nodes.
Didn't touch the lungs.
When did you know you had brain meds? When did they do the CTs?
When I got to Indiana.
So you mean you went through all of this and they still didn't know you had
right? Metastatic disease.
I originally was treated, I did my first cycle of chemotherapy here in Austin.
What was the chemo you did here?
That was traditional BEP. So I did, I did do one. We were talking about it.
One with bleo.
Yeah. I did one cycle with bleo.
Could have won eight if I didn't do that one cycle.
Yeah. So bleomycin is a really, really toxic chemo.
And we'll talk about it in a second when we get to Indiana,
why they decided to have a little faith and play the long game.
What led you to Indiana? Because again, in a pre-internet era,
it wouldn't have been as clear that, um,
that that was a place that was really on the cusp of doing something.
Yeah. But even, even, I mean, they had done the work, right? Like the, the local,
my local oncologist knew, I mean, I may, maybe even, even pre-internet,
they, they still knew where the centers of excellence.
In other words, it came from the docs here.
You didn't have to go and make that decision.
Well, he, he had mentioned that,
that Dr. Larry Einhorn in Indianapolis was, uh, you know,
it was sort of the, um, the king when he came to testicular cancer. In fact,
a lot of his work really led to, um,
platinum based therapies really being as effective as they are. So I immediately,
and he was in Australia at the time, he was lecturing in Australia. And I, you know,
when I heard his name, I said, I gotta find this guy.
And then we tried to call him and he was off in Australia. Um,
but I did do that one that, that, you know, I did four cycles in total.
The first cycle was done here in Austin. Um, and then I had started, you go one
week on two weeks off, one week on two weeks. So I had two weeks.
And that's when I first went to Houston to visit MD Anderson.
And then I ended up,
did MD Anderson also recommend, uh, recommend Leo?
Well, they had a whole different approach and was a much more,
um,
it was, it was not traditional therapy, which is interesting. I mean, they,
they much more chemotherapy, a lot more compounds.
Um, I didn't, I did, it just didn't,
it didn't feel right. I left.
So when you got to Indiana, did they do the CT scan first?
They figure out you've got brain meds as well. Yeah.
Is that another, what the hell is going on here?
How much worse can this get moment?
Well, it was kind of a, I mean, yes, the answer is yes,
but also a bit of a relief. You're like, okay, that's,
this has got to be the worst part of it. So like now that this is my line in the
sand, I'm not, it's not getting worse.
It's really, really bad, but it's not going to get worse. Right.
So I'm just trying to understand Lance. Like at what point were you thinking I
might not live here?
Um,
God, I didn't, I didn't have,
I mean, certainly crossed my mind,
but I didn't have days where I would sit there and go, I am going to,
like I just kept, and we were doing so much, you know, with, with, with the blood
work on it, like we were measuring the HGG, it was coming down.
They, they expected, you know, I said, look, what, what do you want to see?
Like what's what's, what's this is the scoreboard. What's my metric? Yeah.
What is my metric that says I'm ahead in this game and they said a log drop off
every, every cycle and man, we were hitting it. Bam, bam.
It just kept coming down and I was like, I, I'm kicking this thing's ass.
Like yeah, I can turn around and the body can,
and the cancer can pivot and the chemo doesn't work. Whatever work,
whatever happens, but I just,
I just felt like I got on top of it and I didn't sit around with this other
protocol, right? They went with, they went with what? Yeah. Instead of, well,
that was first thing they asked me. They said, okay, you're a professional
cyclist. I said, do you ever want to race bikes again? I said, I mean,
if I can live, yeah, they prefer to live, but that's, that would be cool. Um,
and they said, well, you, we can't, you can't keep doing bleo. And so,
it's so pulmonary toxic. It's so cardio.
And people ask like, why,
why wouldn't everybody be treated the way you were treated with the protocol
called VIP, which is doesn't indicate that you're a VIP. It's just the,
yeah, it's been Christine and so spot and then and blah, blah, blah.
But the downside to being treated with VIP is you have to stay as an inpatient.
So bleo, you can go home,
like you go into the chemo clinic for three or four hours,
get your chemo and you go home. Uh, VIP, one of those, and I don't,
I forget which one is so toxic, not on the lungs,
but on the body that you have to have 24 seven hydration.
So you have to be in the hospital. And so they just, you know,
I just don't, people want to go home.
Kima was bad for you.
Kimo was bad at the end. Kimo is a,
and I still talk to people about this cause they, if they're going to be about to
start chemo, they asked me and you know, cycle one, I was like,
you sure you did this right? Like I don't feel anything.
Cycle two gets sick a few times. Like, Ooh, okay.
I think they got it right this time. Cycle three, just sick as shit.
Cycle four, you just, you just want to sleep. Like you just, it,
it just compounds and compounds. It got, it got much, much worse.
What was the recovery like from the neurosurgery?
Um, you know, that was, those were,
those were big cuts. I mean, they were, you know, they're probably,
you know, tennis ball size. Um, uh,
the easiest way to describe it for people listening or have never been there is
it's, it's, it's like, you know,
doing the pumpkin for Halloween. Like you literally just cut the hole,
pull off the thing,
dig out the seeds and put the thing back on it. Like that's what,
and there were two of them. There was one on the top, one on the back, um,
right on the surface. So Dr. Shapiro was my neurosurgeon.
He saw him and he pulled that skull off and right there.
And they were dead.
Oh, this was done after most of the chemo. Uh, no,
it was done before halfway. Wow. But you know,
the response was amazing. I don't know how, you know, the,
the blood brain barrier, you know,
this barrier that prevents super toxic stuff from getting into the brain.
They should not have been dead.
That's why they go in there and take them out and sit, you know, they,
and I'm not a surgeon or a scientist,
but they take them out and they walk them over and you know,
look at them immediately in the microscope and they were dead.
At that point in time,
is there anybody you remember meeting in the hospital that kind of made you feel
like you were having a shared experience with another patient?
Was there any patient that sticks out to you?
No, I was kept pretty, uh, isolated. I did.
I never shared a room. Um, I did chemo in my room. I didn't, you know,
a lot of hospitals or, or centers, you know, it's like a,
a big room with nice boys everywhere. And you sit beside the, you know,
I'm Lance with testicular cancer and you're, you know,
the Gina with breast cancer and Joe with colon and you're all just kind of
talking, watching. I never, I was always alone in my room.
Which is interesting because it seems like very early on you,
you, you, you sort of latched onto an important idea, right? Which was, um,
people need help navigating this system.
And you obviously felt moved at a very early point in your disease and recovery
to create a foundation that you ultimately would,
what do you think was part of the impetus for that in your experience?
It just, it just, you know,
even as modest as the expectations were, it was like, let's just do like,
and you can think about it a lot of different ways.
It wasn't so much about navigation at the time. It was more about here.
You have a disease or a type of cancer with a huge stigma around it.
You have young men that like, you know, like me that are,
if they have swelling or pain,
they're not going to go out and like advertise that and seek,
most likely not seek help until it's a problem. Um,
so just trying to bring awareness to that. And you know, we thought we,
we'd started a bike ride here in Austin.
We thought we'd maybe get a few people out there, donate some money.
We had no plan. I mean, it was,
but it just felt like the time to do something.
Was it sort of a pay it forward thing?
Like you were just so happy to be alive that you were like,
I just have to share some of this. Well, we start, yeah, well,
we started it before and then we started, or I should say we started it during.
So that wasn't entirely sure that there was going to be a forward, but
it's interesting. Obviously the foundation would grow to over half a billion
dollar in, um, in, in, in money raised.
And I think what a lot of people don't appreciate, um,
but I always appreciated was that that money was very specific and that it
wasn't directed towards research. And you might say, well, God,
that doesn't make sense. Shouldn't all money in cancer be towards research?
But I always thought it was a really great thing that the money wasn't directed
towards research because there are a lot of dollars directed towards research.
And there are not a lot of dollars directed towards the other things.
Research is imperative. It must be,
and it should be by far the largest allocation of resources within a portfolio
that's trying to address cancer. But it's this other stuff,
this softer stuff of how do you help a family that can't afford the travel for,
you know, the child with cancer? How do you provide the resources for somebody?
And then of course there are, you know,
you inspired a lot of other people like fertility hope and other people to come
along and address other problems that, um,
just probably didn't get enough attention.
And on the advocacy side, I mean, on my answer to,
I agree with everything you said. Uh, you have to raise,
you know, billions and billions, maybe even trillions to, to properly,
I mean, there's only one person that can fund that. And that's, you know,
those are federal governments. And, um, and so,
but on the advocacy side, because we ended up gaining so much power, uh,
just with the story and the brand of Livestrong, I mean,
we advocated here in the state of Texas for, for, uh, uh, uh,
a bond initiative that, that created the, what we called Seaprot,
the cancer prevention research Institute of Texas.
It's a $3 billion bond initiative. We at the time,
Livestrong spent about
600 grand on that initiative. So picking the best lobbyists,
you know, all the strategy, right? Well, you know, I,
I see the 600, but I view that as we just funded.
That's an Archimedes lever, right? Like,
we funded $3 billion in, in, in research and prevention. So,
otherwise you could never go out and you can't sell enough yellow bands to,
to do that.
So when did you decide? Yeah. Like not only am I well enough to,
to come back, but, um, and remind me where, did you already,
did you already have the contract with COFIDES prior to getting sick?
Motorola had already. Motorola folded. Okay. So you're already,
you're already officially on, on COFIDES and then you come back and
what are they thinking? Well, they, they, they were, I mean,
before the even, there was no company. I mean, they, they sent a representative
over and it's crazy that they're still in the sport. Um,
they sent somebody to, uh, to the U S to basically say, listen,
this is probably best. He just,
they sent somebody to evaluate you to come in, lay eyes on you,
lay eyes on me, but then have a conversation with my agent and say, look,
you know, we, we feel like we should probably just part ways.
And your contract was a big contract, right? I mean,
it was just like a million dollar contract. Yep. Yep. Yeah.
We didn't let them part ways.
So you, you, you were officially with, with that team for a year
for, yeah. Yeah. So nine 97.
Did you ride? Nope. Okay.
So they don't renew your contract obviously at the end of 97. So,
and I had the other interesting thing, which I don't think has been talked about
much. I had a disability policy, which typically is for, you know, injuries,
crashes, anything that makes you disabled enough.
You can't turn the crank and, but cancer, you know,
you know, in a way fell under that. So I,
I took the disability policy or started to take it.
And the deal was if you go back and race again, then it's not. Yeah.
And so, and I think it was a three year payout and I thought, God,
this might be a good off ramp, right? I'll just, and so, uh,
until it wasn't until it wasn't, then I decided to stay on the highway. But,
but it wasn't easy, right? Because it wasn't like anyone was clamoring at your
door in 98. No, no, nobody was. Yeah. I mean, that,
when we went back out to, uh, to sort of shop me to teams,
um, zero, zero interest, right?
Even not even, I mean, postal was really not that interested.
What do you think changed their mind? Well, the only reason, I mean, I was,
you have to go, you know, have to go back, follow it backwards. But I mean,
postal, the team postal,
which was owned by Tom Weisel had been around.
I was on Weisel's team before Motorola. So I had history there.
I had relationships. I had obviously a relationship with him. Um,
so maybe it was that, but it wasn't, it wasn't a cold call.
Like I was essentially going back to Weisel's team.
Cause I left Subaru Montgomery to go to Motorola.
No, you're you're, they gave you 200 K or something like that as a base.
Yeah. I think that's, and then a bunch of performance bonuses, right? Well, I,
uh, yeah, I negotiated like, uh,
like a thousand bucks back then again, I loved the, and I really did.
I loved the way the sport was structured, the world cups, UCI points,
you had a number one ranked rider in the world. Like that's a fucking cool deal.
Like when I watch golf or tennis or, you know, who's the best? Yeah. Wait,
Djokovic is the number one player. Well, yeah, duh, you should have,
who is the number, Lewis Hamilton is the number one driver in F1 because he has
all the most points and wins it. No shit. We had that in cycle.
They don't have that anymore. Um, so I, I, I, I, I, I pinned it to a thousand bucks
per point and, and realistically back then,
how many points would the top rider have thousands? Okay. So it's a million,
millions of dollars potentially. And that's what I went out and did. Yeah.
In 98 and 98 because you did perinies, right? Then I, then I quit,
came home, said, fuck this. I'm out of here. I'm not cut out for this. I'm not.
Yeah. I want to talk about that race. Yeah. Why? What went wrong? Oh, just,
Terry, you know, the weather and, and I,
and I sort of had this idea in my mind that if, okay, if I,
I did the Olympics in 1996, I was, and I was,
but you were, you didn't know it at the time, but you were riddled with tumors.
One flesh for loan. And then looking back on, I was like, wait,
if I was that good then and I was that sick,
like all this shit's gone. Now I'm going to be like 10 times as strong,
which I, of course I wasn't.
I was strong and it was good to have it out of my body, but, um,
you know, it just, and it just caught me on a day, man. It was fucking crosswind.
It was freezing. I was, I got, I was in the back of the Peloton,
Peloton split and I'm just like, I'm going home.
Literally pulled over, got in the car, went to the hotel, called Kristen.
I say, we're going home. What did she say?
She, you know, she, she was supportive.
Um, she, she didn't support it. She, she didn't necessarily agree,
but she was supportive. It's, it's been so long since I read your book. I mean,
I read it when it came out. It's not about the bike,
which probably came out in 2000. So I vaguely remember in that era,
you kind of vacillated back and forth between I want to ride. I don't want to
ride. I want to sit around and eat tacos all day and text. And yet somewhere in
there, didn't you, didn't you come in fourth in the Vuelta that year?
Well, that was at the end of the year.
So, so was the Tex-Mex beer drinking in the spring?
That was, that would have been, you know, Perinises in March, um,
April, that was probably, you know,
those six weeks around the April timeframe. Uh, and then, and then, and you know,
it wasn't, it was almost like a, an intervention group of friends that were like,
look, man, like I get it. Like you don't want to do it anymore, but just,
just go back and finish the season. Like just start riding, start training.
Just, just don't, don't go out like that. I just finished the season.
I said, okay, I'll, uh, I'll do that. So I just started riding,
but no, no, no, no structure. Just ride. I'd go out here in Austin. I just,
and I rode a lot, like four or five, six hours every day. Just,
just ride. No, this is the season. So what are your teammates doing at this point?
They're out racing. They're racing. Yeah, they're racing.
And the team doesn't care that you're not there because they're not paying you
anything anyway, basically. Yeah. Yeah. And I, and I, I believe I went to,
I went to the U S pro, uh, the core States and Philly.
And then, uh, and then I flew to Europe and did my first race back was a tour
Luxembourg. You win that one that now went to Germany,
did another race and won that. These are stage races, short stage races.
You've reintroduced EPO at this point. Yep. Do you, by the way,
I forgot to ask you this post-orchectomy wouldn't you have needed a,
wouldn't you have had a medical exemption for testosterone at that point?
I don't think you can in any sport. Could you get that?
Yeah, but I never, I never,
but didn't you have to start taking more testosterone after you had your test
school removed? Um, not necessarily.
Do you know if you were producing normal amounts?
Always, always on the lower end, but nothing that was,
you know, problematic or something. And you said, listen,
this is going to cause further issues down the line, but not certain. Yeah,
obviously not on that. And the other thing I meant to ask you, Lance,
did you at some point during the period of your cancer recovery,
think, man, did that growth hormone amplify this in any way,
shape or form or any of the other anabolic agents, particularly?
There's no way EPO would have, but,
but what was your thought on some of the other drugs you'd used? Um,
well, you know, that certainly crosses your mind.
And, and, uh, HGH, you know, there was just very,
pre-diagnosis. There was very little of that anyways, only in 96,
which is of course the year that I got sick, but.
By the way, it seems to me the least performance enhancing drug for a site.
We never went, we, and by the way, we never went back. I mean,
Ferrari was like, don't need it. Yeah. Yeah. Never, never went back.
So really the mainstay of drug when you came back was EPO. Yep. Um,
and it's amazing that cortisone helped that much, huh? Um,
yeah, you know, I'm surprised you haven't,
it's, it's, it's how would you guys administer it? Intramuscularly?
Yeah. It's helpful to shed weight primarily. And especially as a,
as a, as a bulkier guy, um,
trying to shed upper body muscle. Yeah. Very helpful.
Unbelievable. Um,
so 98 comes to an end. You, you finish unbelievably right.
Fourth in the world. Fourth in everything. Fourth at the world,
the fourth at the world's TT fourth at the world's road race.
I just was like, shit, I'm fourth in everything.
But I got a thousand plus UCI points that Tom Weisel had to pay. Well,
not only that, but you've done it kind of not at your best, right?
Like you're only, you know, you, you,
you really only came back into shape for nine months.
So you decide at the end of 98, no, I'm coming back in 99. Like now it's,
I'm all in. Yep. At that point.
I have Bernille. Okay. The big, that was, that was the big, you know,
the team was, uh, who was the, uh, director of sport.
Johnny Welch was the director of sport chief in 98. And this Peter,
when I say this team was unorganized, like you cannot,
you cannot believe it. It was such a shit show.
We remember 98. So I remember cause I was in my second year of medical school
and I just remember there was a group of guys,
we would go riding every Saturday and Sunday morning and we would, first of all,
I was so excited that you were back,
but we would joke about like go postal having the two meanings like you're
cheering for postal team and you're going crazy cause it's just so disheveled.
And yeah, well we had, and I'll never forget this. I mean,
Johnny was so disorganized and he would like, you know,
they wouldn't pay the swan years and then that,
that Welter that I ended up getting forth and I'll walk down one day,
a breakfast table and everybody's good. There's no, no swan years. I said,
where's, I said, where's the fucking swan years? And I said, they walked out.
I said, wait a minute. We were in the middle of a grand tour.
We have to have mechanics. Swan years. Like what the fuck is going on?
They just walked out cause we're getting paid so sketchy and I,
and I'm sitting there going, okay, I think I'm back. I said,
but I'm not going to put up with this shit. Like this is, this is ridiculous.
This is just amateur hour and Johan was retiring and uh,
I got his number. Uh, Marshall,
Marcel Wustel German guy gave me his number.
He wore the yellow Jersey for a day back in those trainers.
They went in the early stages. They get the Jersey, but uh, I just called him.
I said, what do you, it's funny. We, you know,
we didn't really like each other when we raced. He was,
we always just sort of butted heads and, but he was always at the front of the
race. Like he fucking took going back to what I was saying earlier about knowing
the race, like knowing where to be knowing, uh,
just the energy of this thing. He knew it and he spoke all these languages and I
thought that would be good. I just called him and I said, what do you,
what are you going to do now? Now that you're retiring.
And he was actually either wanting to start or somebody asked him to,
to be a part of a cycling union, which he would have been,
that would have been a great use of his time. And I said, listen, you know,
I got an idea. Like, why don't you come be the director?
He was like, are you kidding me? No. And I said,
because the travel, like it's basically, it's not retiring.
I mean, that's just not what he thought he would be doing. Um,
but I convinced him.
So people, this is a topic that gets, it's such a controversial topic,
but I just, I really want to understand this, right? People consistently say,
look, yes, we know everybody doped during that era,
but us postal was different because they did it at an industrial level.
It was much more systemic. Um, so let's,
let's kind of unpack what that means. So this,
so you had already been working with Ferrari and I've,
I've never met Ferrari.
He's actually a guy I would always want to meet because I think despite how much
he's been demonized, I just think he's probably a very smart physiologic wizard.
He's incredibly smart.
And um, like how much of your training was he actually guiding?
All of it.
So did Carmichael who gained fame being associated with you and being your
coach, did he do anything?
He not, not at that stage. He was, you know, as an amateur, I mean,
he was the Olympic coach in 92 and, and, but, but, but once I went to, you know,
start seeing Ferrari, you know, Chris was just a, um, you know,
advisor friend. Uh, no,
but we are talking about two very different skill sets here. Yeah.
And I'm not talking about doping. I mean, just in term, I mean,
Michaela for, you can say what you want and you,
you and I calling him intelligent or bright or smart or even
genius, you know, just drives people crazy. No, but I,
but I've heard him in interviews talk about the nuanced level of
physiology. I mean, he's, he's top three of all time.
And so, so we're talking about two different types of, yeah. Um,
so you said earlier, look, you had no aspiration of winning the tour, right?
Did that change when you placed fourth in the course? Was that the first aha
moment that says I could win this thing?
Yep. And that, and, and when Yohan finally decided to come,
you know, take, take me up on my offer, he said it, he said, you're gonna,
he, he, and I'll never forget, he said, you are going to finish on the podium.
In 99 and 99.
I said, if you are crazy, there's no way,
you didn't think so with your confidence.
Nah, I mean, that's the, first of all, the Welter is not the tour. I understand,
but so getting forward to the Welter, yeah, to me,
that that sort of equates to maybe top 10,
which by the way would have been a great result. Um,
but he was a hundred percent sure. He said, you're gonna,
at that point in time. So in 98,
Pantani had won in 97. Ulrich had won.
How much time had you spent riding alongside those two?
Well, in the grand scheme, not much.
So did you have a sense of how you'd stack up against them?
Um,
no, because I didn't, uh, uh, I mean,
I had never been in a grand tour at my peak form, their peak form.
I mean, I was, you know, just guessing.
And I don't remember why were they not there in 99?
Well, Pantani had the thing that the Giro got,
yeah, that's right.
The dramatic retest. And, and I want to say Jan,
he also had, of course, you and I offline have talked a lot about, uh,
Jan Ulrich, but I think he had another thing, right?
Maybe you tested positive for him. Something happened. Like he just,
he wasn't there.
So you show up at 99 and the two best tour riders are not there.
That's right. The previous two winners.
The previous two winners. I,
I still remember my couch where I sat and watched the prologue.
Yup.
That July day.
And explain to people why the prologue matters. Like it's not a long stage.
Let's get an eight and a half kilometer time.
Yeah, but you can, what's the, what's the importance of it?
Well, it's a, it's, it's first and foremost it, it, and,
and they don't always do it anymore, which I completely disagree with.
I think it's the baddest thing in the world. Of course.
It's the only way to start a tour. It allows the rider, especially the,
the, the GC guys to really test their condition, not just their own,
but against the other guys. And you can, you know, if it's,
you put 30 seconds in a climber, 30 seconds to 30 seconds.
So it's, it's, uh, and that was a tough one. I mean, that was,
that was a not, uh, it had a, uh, a serious climb sort of halfway through.
It was enough that you could make some separation. So, um,
but it it's, there's,
there's certain things that the Twitter France should always have.
It should always have a prologue. It should always have a team time trial.
It shows. And they really gone away from that for some reason, but
thankfully not then you win the prologue, win the prologue.
Your first yellow Jersey. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
never even, I mean, it was just, uh, I mean, we,
we thought we were in a dream. Now remind me in that tour,
you were not using blood transfusions. It was all EPO. Right.
And it was, you didn't micro dose. You were just giving straight regular doses.
You didn't, this is before they had a test for EPO. Yep. Starting to, yeah.
The only thing they had was the hematocrit test.
And do you remember where you kept your hematocrit at that tour? Was that,
this is when you were having to stay at about 50. No, 50'd be too close.
Cause you had to stay around 46, 47. Cause if you don't,
you know this, I mean, you get dehydrated,
hydrated and, and, and, or you, or you get sick or,
and they show up like you're, you're done. I don't think,
so something people don't realize is in 1996,
Reese won the tour. So finally unseeds Induran.
His hematocrit was somewhere between 60 and 66 during that race.
That's what they say. I mean, we weren't, we weren't there with the spinner,
but, um, yeah, the nickname, Mr. 60%. Yeah. His nickname is Mr. 60.
So what changed so much? Was it Festina in 98?
Basically brought the hammer down and said,
we're done with these guys walking around with hematocrits in the sixties. Yep.
So is it that much of a difference if you're walking,
if you're walking around him out of crit is 42 44 and you're racing 46 47 or is
it cause this has always been my take on it.
It's not so much how you're functioning on the beginning of the tour.
It's that at the end of the tour, you could keep your hematocrit there when
ordinarily it would really start to dwindle as you break down. Yeah.
But when, when the test came around, then yeah, you,
you just knew that you would, you would drop.
But obviously ever, ever, you know, the, the, the GC guys at least found ways
around that and that's where, you know, the transfusions came in and which is
effectively the same thing. Yeah. Right. Um,
was there anybody on the postal team that year that was not doing EPO?
Not that I'm aware of. And how,
how much were you guys co-mingling information?
So you were seeing Ferrari, but I assume everyone was seeing it.
No, a lot of them were, a lot of them were. Um,
but the team also had trainers and doctors and had its own set up.
Was that the year moto man was going around? Yeah, it was 99. It was 99. Yeah.
I thought that was a great idea. It's uh, and do you think it's back on it?
It's like, it's just like, well, it's a movie. I mean, it's fucking crazy.
Like what? Oh God.
Yeah. That was 99.
I don't know if this is still the case, but I believe at the time you won in 99,
you were the only person to not only win the tour,
but when each of the three individual time trial time trials as well. Yep.
Well, you had the prologue and two log and then we had long time trials.
Yeah. 60 K at least. Right. 55. Yeah. Yeah.
And so if you're the best and it's that long, you're going to win.
You win that year, you win that.
That's that long. You're going to win. You win that year. Do you think to yourself?
You know, Ulrich wasn't here. Pantani wasn't here. Can I win this thing when they're
both there? And not to mention, I mean, it, it, it, um,
you know, would that big crash, uh, early in the race, I mean,
Zula lost seven minutes. I mean, Zula was close in the race.
If you, if you, if you back out that accident or the huge crash,
he was within about a minute, right? Yeah, it would have been close. And he was a,
I mean Zula's, I mean, even if by saying Pantani and Ulrich aren't there,
I mean, you still had Zula, Escartin, Olano, uh, I mean,
you had, you know, I can't minimize those guys.
What was the, we almost take it for granted now, but at the time,
how much scrutiny was there over your performance that year? A lot. Yeah.
That was the year of the cortisone. Yep. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It started.
And it was the year after Festina. I mean,
so this was could have won the tour and they were to, they would have questioned
it. Yeah. So what,
you know, prior to this, you've never really been on the hot seat, right?
So you'd been using the drug, but nobody really cared because you weren't winning
the race. So now you're winning the race. I wasn't in the crosshairs.
So where do you think the posture came of this is how my denial is going to be?
And, and what in retrospect, was there another way to deny,
without attacking? Cause I gotta be honest with you.
I don't really remember what the attack mode was like in 99 versus Oh five.
Like that's a, there's a spectrum of attack.
You would have to be in the, you'd had to be in the, in the press conferences,
you know, that you'd have questions about the race and questions about whatever.
And then somebody in the corner would holler one of the interested, you know,
they were just asking a question felt like an attack at the time,
felt like an attack on me. I said,
I said, excuse me, what the fuck are you talking about?
I mean, literally like that. Like just let's go.
Um, you know, if I had your teammates say, did anybody pull you aside and say,
Lance, you gotta back this down, man. No, no, but they wouldn't have done that.
It would, there, there are others and man, you know, maybe you know,
Johan. No, no, but Johan's a he, he, we are, we are like brothers.
I mean, he would answer, he would do the same thing. You know,
it might've been better. Somebody, you know,
here locally where my whole operation was run out of to go, you know what?
It feels like we may want to back this down a little bit. Just,
just let it go. And
how many other people in your life knew at the time,
obviously your wife must have known.
Oh, I think, yeah, I think, uh, uh,
that's a good question. I mean, it wasn't something that I offered up,
but I mean, did your mom know? Nope. Did she ever ask? Nope.
And what did, what did your wife say? Um, very little.
I mean, I think she just assumed, I mean, look, it was,
it that level of the sport and that level of, of doping,
you, you cannot keep that. If you live with a person,
that is not going to be a secret.
But did she ever say something like Lance, is this worth it? You know,
like if you're playing the long game, I've never had this conversation with her,
but, um, I, I, and this is my point is that if you have
no ability to keep this a secret from your spouse or whoever you're living with,
um, we're in Europe. There's, I have my teammates,
they have the wives clubs. I think, I think the wives,
the conversation was like, this is just part of the job.
Cause they certainly all knew.
So in 2000, you come back. I want to ask you about Vantu.
What was going on between you and Pentani there? Were you guys talking?
What was, I was trying to tell him that he, yeah, I thought I was going to give
him the win, which is one of the biggest regrets in my career. Why?
Because you don't, uh, and it's, you know, not on the Vantu. And that's why,
I mean, Merck's called me when I was on the car ride down, he said,
you don't ever gift the Vantu ever.
Why did you want to gift it to him?
I was just, I mean, I was going to win the tour.
I knew I was going to win the tour. I was just, you know,
I was actually trying to be gracious and be sort of the,
the Patron of the Peloton. Like, look, you know,
I don't need to win everything here. You go win the Vantu and you go.
And, but in hindsight, God, and may he rest in peace.
I mean, I'm just not, I'm not talking about Pantani.
I'm just talking about, um, I'm talking about the Vantu, right?
Which is just, you just don't give that one away.
And Merck's called you on the car ride down. Don't ever, you never,
it's a huge mistake. You never gift the Vantu.
Is Merck's the greatest cyclist of all time? Of course.
If Merck's, different sport, different sport, different sport, but
if Merck's were riding today with the sport being so much more specialized,
where would he choose to focus his energy? Would he be on the grand tours? Yeah,
for sure. Yeah. Very different sport now though. I mean,
Half Man Half Bike is a biography of Merck's that I love. And you,
you gave me one of the most amazing gifts ever,
which is that book that's on my coffee table. I was psyched. I saw it.
And I was like, oh, Peter has one of those too. And I was like, wait,
you dumb ass, you, you gave it to him. Yeah, that's a cool book. It's,
it's unbelievable. Um,
I would recommend anybody who's interested in cycling reading Half Man Half Bike
because you can't really understand what he did. Like,
what does it mean to win five geros, five tours,
every single day classic, the one hour record,
like it just doesn't make any sense. And to, and yeah.
So, um, now in that, who was, um,
who was second that year? Was that Poloki was he, or was that Ulrich that year?
No, in 2000, Jan, Jan got second, I believe.
Is that when you guys began, you've said before that of all the guys you've ever
raced, you've never respected anyone more than Jan.
Obviously we're going to talk about Jan a little later.
Your, your respect and your love for Jan post-cycling is he's a brother to you.
Did it begin in that tour in 2000?
It was more intense. I mean, he was, I didn't, you know, uh,
I viewed him as a real enemy and a rival and, and fuck this guy. And I'm like,
you know, but, and when I say, I mean,
when I talk about Jan and what he, uh, drove in me was just,
I had, um,
I was fully convinced that he was the most talented,
that he was the biggest fear that like, if,
if anything, every morning got you up and it's pissing rain outside and you had
five hours on the schedule, like you better get out there.
It was Jan Orogtikami. None of these other guys, they're all good.
They're all, I'm sure nice guys, but none of them inspired me like him.
Yeah. You probably didn't know it at the time,
but how much you guys had in common, right? In terms of your upbringing.
Yeah. Yeah. Jan's had a complicated upbringing.
What's your biggest memory from 01 and 02?
Which was the year you began having suffered a broken collarbone, um, in,
um, didn't you, didn't you fall in break?
No, in Dolphini that was to 03. So going into 03,
01 was, you know, 01 was probably physically my best tour. I mean, 01,
it was, you know, that's, everybody refers to it as the look and, and, you know,
what was your, um, what was your time or what was your wattage up Madone in 01?
All those years were 500 Watts.
500 Watts for 30 minutes.
Yeah. And loving it.
And what do you think your wattage would have been without EPO?
Oh, it would have been 450. It's telling you it is 10%.
You think it's a full 10%? Yeah. Yeah. 10%.
Seven Watts per kilo.
450 is still pretty good by the way.
Yeah. I mean, look, Bradley Wiggins probably put out 450,
440 to 450 during his one hour record, which that's more important. That's flat.
Yeah. And you're kinked. Yeah.
So it's really hard because you're bent over. Um,
the look, yeah. How deliberate was that?
I wasn't looking at young. What were you looking at?
I was looking, I knew I was about to send it.
And I thought, man, I feel good,
but if this doesn't work, I'm going to need somebody to bail me out.
So I'm going to need a teammate and Chechu was the last guy with me.
And so I was looking back just to make sure that Chechu,
and it was just the angle of the photo,
but I was looking back to make sure that he was,
that he was going to come with you. Well, that he was close. Yeah.
That I could still, it still had him in sight. And so,
but just the way the photo was captured,
it looked like I was looking directly at Jan, which I wasn't.
Um, oh three,
you've got to be a little worried going into that, right? Cause you're,
you're pretty depleted on red blood cells. Aren't you?
Oh three was,
that's when I had a pretty big crash in the dolphin right before.
Huge crash actually.
And that's when you couldn't just give yourself EPO willy nilly. Um,
I think by then we had an EPO test, right? Yeah, but not, I mean,
out of competition. You could,
yes. But I think what was your himatic rate at the beginning of O three?
Didn't you come in at like a 42 or something? 38.
The start. So you came in, 38, 38.
How many bags do we didn't do just, just, just so you know. And so we're clear.
We didn't do after 99, we never did equal on the tour.
NC. You mean you did it out of season. I mean, you did it out of competition.
Still. And then just, and then we, then, you know,
Ferrari had to switch to transfusion. Oh, I didn't realize that.
I thought that happened in O two. So you're saying by from 2000 on,
it was two bags during the race. No, 2000.
First year was 2000. We did one bag, one bag at what stage?
So that halfway through. So that first day at Hautacom were,
that was with nothing. That was before the bag.
How are they not catching the jump in himatic rate that comes?
I don't know. You were not worried about, Hey, one day,
my himatic rates 41 and the next day it's 47.
Right. Yeah. Um,
how close were you to understanding the UCI's algorithm for testing? I mean,
at this point you're becoming, I mean,
one of the things that people have always said is, Hey,
Lance had the UCI in his pocket. But
yeah, that's not, listen, we can go down all these rabbit holes,
all the stuff that's, I mean, and I'm not, uh, uh,
I'm sort of done with that part of my life where I have to contest every,
it's like, but in, in its totality, if I, if,
if we just put them all on a whiteboard and said they said this and this,
and I mean, you cannot believe, and I'm not, and I,
this is where I just don't need to go one by one.
But if you look at it in total, you cannot believe how much bullshit was out
there. I mean, yes, the, the, the pillars are true,
but most of it is just total
bullshit. I mean, I think the point is,
by the way, it's turning a blind eye.
By the way, Peter, a month ago,
they had a 30 minute program on French TV convincing
themselves that they had figured out that I had an engine in
my bike and that they figured out this is, I'm not kidding.
They figured out where the switch was. Are you joking?
I'm not joking. I'm, I am dead serious. I'm like, what are you people,
what are you doing? Like, and I don't know if you ever noticed this,
but I would always sort of grab my chamois.
Okay. Like I would always like kind of adjust it, adjust my chamois.
I had this whole theory that, you know, the,
that the ass and the chamois and the seat have to line up. That's peak power.
Like it's perfect, perfect balance and all this shit. And so I would always,
and I am, this is a network television.
This was the, this, there's the switch.
The switch was in the shorts. Of course. I mean, this is,
but this is a really dumb example, although it's a true story that they,
that they aired this. Um, but most of it just, I'm just like,
and fortunately I've gotten myself to a point in life where it's like,
so going into that last time trial in oh three,
you and Jan were really close. Well, yeah. I mean, it was,
you were not that far ahead of him, right? You were inside a minute, maybe.
Yeah, inside a minute. Talk to me about that time truck. I've heard you talk
about it less, but that wasn't the, the, the, the,
the fear or the stress around it was not so much. No, it was the checkpoint,
right? It was, he gained, how much did he take out of you? Well, but the bigger,
the bigger stressor was how much he took out of me in the first time trial.
I think he took two minutes out of me. So you're going, you're thinking, okay,
you got 45 seconds. What stage was that? That was, uh, the first one. Yeah.
I don't know. It was early. Captain Kuvera too. Right.
So that's when you're himatic rates 38. Yeah. So you're, you're, you're, you're,
you're going, well, you're got 45 second lead.
He took two minutes out of you in the first, I mean, everybody said it's over.
He's gonna, he's gonna catch him. I remember that like it was yesterday.
And he put rain, he put six seconds on me in the first kilometer.
How many K was the time trial? Long 50, 50 ish.
So what went through your mind at that point? Yoan didn't tell me that.
He didn't tell you how much, okay. Six seconds in one kilometer.
Unbelievable. If I can get off the bike. Yeah. Like I'm done.
He made you feel you were redlined. Oh yeah, that's terrible.
And were you using your power meter at that point or mostly heart rate?
But most of the, we didn't race with power meters train, you know,
a hundred percent of the time with them, but not in the races. So it wasn't just
heart rate. Yeah. Um, when did they tell you that he fell?
Right away. I mean, Yoan's watching the race on TV in the car as he's driving.
Um, yeah, right away. And then I knew,
and it was over. The other thing about O three was, uh, was below key, right?
Below key. I still don't, I still don't understand how you avoided that.
Well, of all the things that ever happened to me in the tour,
I get asked about that. I mean, it's, it's not even close. I mean, that,
that the ride through the field, that's the one,
I think every, even people that don't follow it, like, man,
I remember that one time I keep fucking road across that field. I was like, yeah,
I do remember, but you know, incredibly lucky. I mean,
he very unlucky for, uh, Joseva, but, um, you know,
if you go back and rewatch and it's of course there's a hundred versions of it
on YouTube, but if you go back and rewatch exactly what happened, right?
So he's leading flying downhill. It's a hundred degree day. It's a, you know,
these, these bad roads with the, they would, you know,
patch the whatever with tar. The tar was literally boiling and he just, you know,
his tire caught some hot tar and just,
he just high sided him and ruined his career and did his career. And I had,
I mean, I had a choice. I said, I either lay this thing down, right?
Or go left. How many miles an hour were you going? Oh,
we were going 40 miles an hour.
And I said, I'm going to go left. Well now, you know, keep in mind,
the, the, the story ends with me not just riding through the field,
but having to get off my bike and jump down on the road. Well,
that whole field was, you can go back and watch it on YouTube.
So there are massive ditches all this,
the split second that I said, I'm going left. There was a path.
What are the chances there was a path into the field where the farmer,
would go in and out with his tractor? What are the chances? I mean,
five feet to the right, five feet to the left at 40 miles an hour is like that.
Yeah. And I go straight into the side of the ditch.
So I mean, what are the chances that that path is there?
And I get in this field and it just is dry. I don't know.
I'm no farmer, but it was like dry crop, sharp. And I get,
I was like, I was like, man, this shit is sharp. Like,
I better not get a flat. And I'm just like looking down and going, come on, man.
And I got to the other side and I could see that it was way down. I was like,
I was like, I better get off this thing. And just,
I was just, what are the chances?
Well, the other one that you must get asked about a lot,
and I don't remember which year it was, was when your handlebar got caught.
Same year. Was that also 03? Yeah. Comedy of errors. I know.
And by that point,
clearly you and Jan had established an amazing respect because that's when he
waited. Yep. Yep. Yeah. Yeah. Jan is,
you listen, Jan is a, he's a total gentleman.
So yeah, that was, yeah. I hit the,
you know, hit the guy, I hit the kids bag
and just straight down bike was broken, which we didn't know at the time,
but that's the whole
chain stay was snapped. But yeah, Jan waited up.
So let's fast forward to the end of 05, right? You've won seven. You,
at the time said, look, I want to spend more time on the foundation.
I want to spend more time with the family.
I assume those were the real reasons you wanted to retire. I think that's right.
Yeah. I mean, when you came back,
the, was it LeBlanc wrote an open letter basically telling you not to, right?
What was that about? He, uh, you know,
um, Jean-Marie LeBlanc was, was an icon. I mean, he was, he was the,
the, you know, the director, director general of the tour, all of the,
you know, he was, I think, and, and,
and he'll go down as being viewed as one of the greatest directors.
Um, ever. And, and a very, very tough guy, you know,
it was his way or the highway and you just, you just didn't cross Jean-Marie.
And, and, but the sport had started to, uh, you know, I retire,
Landis wins, Landis test positive.
So it was a Festina esque moment in time and cycling and,
and yet another shift to like guys looking around and going, wait a minute.
All right. We might be extinct here if we don't fucking clean this up.
And so the sport was, was shifting to a better place.
Yeah. And Jan's, uh, Jean-Marie's point was, um, look,
you, you are a bridge to the past, right?
So the sport has evolved.
You are part of the old culture and it's not good for this.
And you know what? He's exactly right.
So I remember, uh,
I remember when he wrote it and I think they printed it and, uh,
it was too big political papers or Le Monde de la Figaro.
I think it was in a Figaro. And I just thought,
and it was interesting cause I was in,
I was in West Texas with Anna on a Marfa, one of my favorite places.
And, uh,
where you just went recently.
Yep. And we had just gotten together.
She had just gotten, or she just got pregnant. We'd, you know, but she didn't,
she wasn't with me when I raised before.
And we were out there and we went to this car. This is so crazy.
We were in Fort Davis outside of Marfa and went to this, uh, lunch spot.
And I said, this is a mistake coming back. Yep. I said, I can't,
I shouldn't do this. By the way,
did Le Bonc actually call you as well to follow up? Not that I remember.
Do you think he would have been more persuasive? No.
So why did you, why did you do it?
Well, it was, uh, you know, I mean it,
it, the wheels were in motion. Like it was all,
I felt a ton of, um,
responsibility or, you know, to the foundation. Yeah. All of it. I mean,
all the, all the sponsors were excited. The foundation was excited. The,
that, that, that, and, you know, it would have been so easy to,
and it felt like quitting. Like you can call me a lot of things.
You cannot call me a quitter. I don't quit at anything. And, and,
but it would have been easy to say, you know,
the routine, he chatted on some bullshit and just got out and you would have been
three days of press where it's like, Oh, what happened?
And your view at that point is the sports clean. So yeah,
there's no risk to me because I don't need to use anything because no one else
is using anything. Was that kind of your view? Um, that, that was,
uh, the best I could tell. Yeah. I mean, I knew I wasn't that.
So that sort of phase two or phase, whatever the comeback years was clean.
Absolutely. And ironically Ferrari was the one who was adamant.
He's like, they are coming for you. And so he was, you know,
we just didn't cross the line.
So Oh nine is kind of close, right? Your third and then 10,
it wasn't close. I mean, it wasn't even, it wasn't close at all,
but third is, I mean, meaning you're on the podium. Yeah. Yeah.
I remember reading an article in the fall of 2009 and I think it was like an ESPN
magazine that was comparing your Oh nine tour to Jordan's come back.
His second comeback, the year they didn't win, right?
Cause remember he came back for the last part of the season in 95 and then
they're like, well wait till you see Lance in 10,
cause that's going to be the, like,
that's going to be Jordan's 96 or whatever it was when they went. Um,
so what did you think after 2009, do you ever think, you know what,
I gave this a great go. It would be totally respectable to just retire right now.
You know, to be off the sport for three years, four years, come back,
be on the podium. Now I can retire. What made you come back in?
What made you stay back, especially when it meant building a new team? Yeah.
Well that was a, that was a big part of it. I mean,
being able to not be on a team from Kazakhstan, literally team Borat.
Yeah. And, and build a whole new team. I mean, that was,
but at this point, Lance, you're 30. Yeah. I'm old.
I mean, I was old in your 30s. That was 34 years old when I won.
Yeah. Like wasn't it getting a bit old in terms of training? But again,
this machine was, was rolling. Like I wasn't going to be the guy to say,
I'm getting off the wave here. Like I just,
but what part of the machine at this point,
because from a personal wealth standpoint at that point, you,
you're going to get those sponsors even if you're not riding, aren't you?
I don't know. I mean, it, it, it seems it's like how much of this,
what I'm trying to get at is how much of this was filling a void that said,
I don't like sitting around and not being an athlete. Right. But, but that's,
that's not the point. The point is, I mean, every day of that comeback,
I was like, what the fuck am I doing? Like it wasn't, I had,
I had, and I had this conversation the other night. I was like,
some, somebody asked or came up and I was like, God, it's like,
I'm never in my life.
I am never going back to that place where you're looking around going,
what are you doing? Like, what are you doing?
You're not going to win the tour and you're not like,
what the fuck are you doing? And then as of course, as it led, you know,
down all the investigations started and you're trying to do both,
you're trying to defend your reputation, defend your livelihood,
defend everything and having to do one of the hardest sports in the world.
It was, I was just like, get me out of here.
When did you realize that you had to tell the truth?
Um, I think when I knew that, that they,
they either interviewed George or George went to the grand jury.
I knew that was so fall of 12, basically.
It might've been earlier. Yeah. You know, it's funny. I,
this is going to sound incredibly naive.
I actually believed you guys were not on PEDs at the time.
So my view was either you all are or you are not right. Like, you know,
meaning the GC contenders, I don't necessarily mean everybody in the race,
but my view was either all the GC contenders are or they are not.
And I truly believed that post 98 that you guys were off.
Right. Um, well you were wrong. I was absolutely wrong,
but the moment I realized how wrong I was was not with Landis.
It was actually with Tyler.
Landis didn't come across as very believable. Tyler did.
And so when did I'm trying, I've lost track of time,
but Tyler's book that he wrote with Dan Coyle,
did that come out in like 2011? Does that sound about right?
I feel it's something, yeah, maybe 2010. Yeah. Yeah.
It was when I read Tyler's book that I was like,
this guy's way too freaking believable. Um,
and if he's saying this and he's saying that this is what they were all doing,
like I believe it now. Um, and then it was kind of a question.
He had a different version in his deposition in the postal case, but,
Oh, see, I don't, I don't know what his deposition said. Yeah. I mean, it was,
it was, you know, when anybody's deposed and they've written a book, I mean,
that they're just going to read you the book and go, did you say this?
And did, is this true? Just read, they go page by page. Yeah. Yeah. I'm sure.
And, uh, you know, some of it was,
he agreed. He said, he said, but then if he did, if it was in any way,
sort of contradictory towards him or his,
somebody cared about, and then he would blame Dan. I will never forget.
Oh, that's right. Because you have to co-author. Yeah.
He said that's a Danism. I was like, wait a minute.
Anyways. So it's late. Yeah. It's late 11 or whatever.
And you're basically like, I gotta come clean. Uh, yeah. 12, 11, 12.
Or 12, 12. Yeah. Um,
you've talked about your reasons for doing the interview with Oprah,
which I think make a lot of sense, right?
Which is if you're going to give a deposition, you might as well do it on your
terms. Right. Yeah.
And even that, I mean, looking back,
well, you can look back all you want. Right. I did what I did.
I was convinced that it was the right thing to do. The lawyers hated it. Um,
you know, whether it was Oprah or, or,
or Tom Brokaw, who was my other option,
it wasn't gonna, wasn't gonna help.
What was that period like when you went to think you went to Hawaii right after?
Right. I went to, we still traveled a lot, um,
just to kind of get away and.
Did any of the sponsors call you to quietly thank you for what you had done
over the past 15 years? No, I know they can't publicly, but did, you know,
someone at Trek say, Hey, Lance, I hope you understand.
We've got to dump you like a hot potato,
but you did turn us into a billion dollar company. No.
No, none of that. No sponsor in any one of your relationships ever thanked you
for the, for what you'd done. Um, no.
I mean, I mean, I think there is a, uh, a general, I mean, ironically,
I mean, use tracks as an example. So the answer is no.
But if you asked Mike Senniard from specialized, he would say, thank you.
Cause you, you raise the time. All the ships rose.
Um, Luke was obviously old enough to know what was going on with the twins.
They were, yeah, they were, yeah. I mean, they were young, but they were,
yeah. So what was the discussion like with them?
Um, you know, I, I just took a, uh,
my conversation was, I know, um,
basically just an open door policy. If you ever, if it's certainly,
if anything comes up at school,
but if you ever have any questions about my life and the decisions I've made and
are you hear something like the, we're not going to have one conversation about
this. We're going to have as many as you want to have. Like it is just totally
open door. And what have they asked you about?
Not very much. Yeah. I mean,
but they also, they're like, what are they going to ask? Like, uh,
they're going to ask questions like you're asking,
cause you'd know the sport so well and you're, you're, you know, the,
the good, the bad, the ugly, right? They, they, they, you know,
and, and, and I feel like, um, we stayed all of us and,
and, you know, certainly, um, a lot of credit to Kristen as well.
I mean, we've stayed very close as a family. When I say family, I mean, you know,
myself, my kids, Anna and Kristen, and now Anna and I as kids,
like it's, it is, if you can imagine that Brady Bunch set up,
we are a very close family.
So after the Oprah interview, which I guess is early 2013,
who was the first person you reached out to apologize to?
Well, there was some, well, I mean, I, actually before the interview was,
you know, I reached out cause I knew that it would, it would, you know,
they would see it, you know, so the Andreas Lamon and Kathy and Greg wouldn't,
wouldn't take my call. Have they to this day? We did meet up,
met with Greg and Kathy. Yep. How long ago? Oh God, it's been years.
How did that, how was that meeting?
I thought the meeting went, um,
uh, I went better than I thought it would, would, uh, would go there.
Their version of the, of the media. I mean, it's,
we don't have enough time in this data. It was, you know,
I was sincere. I said, but I, I, I felt like I needed to say,
they accepted the apology, but
what about Emma? Emma, Emma,
Emma and I met up in Florida. Emma's great, man.
She's, you know, Emma's,
Emma's mission all along was not to get me,
her mission was to try to fix, to talk about the sport, fix the sport.
Maybe not everybody listening knows who Emma is. Emma was our Swan year,
was my Swan year 99, um,
and left the team and, and, uh, you know, you know,
was a person that I went after. Um,
and she got mixed up in this because of the LA confidential book.
She was quoted in it. As you said,
it ended up being really about you, but the only reason I,
my understanding is the reason she agreed to talk with David Walsh was really to
make a broader statement about how corrupt the sport was.
Yeah. And I tell you, we've, that's, that's, uh,
I've enjoyed sort of reforming that friendship and
I wrote the forward for her book and, uh, she's, she's a,
she's a cool lady.
What about any of your former teammates? Have you reconnected with Tyler?
I know you have strong feelings about Floyd.
No, no, I mean, it's, those are the two names that stick out.
The reality is, uh,
95% of that former, what was known as the blue train,
we'd still all go. I mean, we'd go all jump back into war together.
Like we fucking we're like, like brothers, um, Floyd and Tyler,
they, they, they were never, they were never our brothers. Um,
and so yeah, there won't be any, won't be any future,
uh, dinners.
You know, I remember a while ago,
your Twitter bio was different than it is now. Do you remember what it used to say?
No, what it's, I don't even know what it says now.
Today it says like, I don't know, something boring, like everybody else's,
but it used to say, um,
there's a reason the, uh, the windshield's bigger than the rear view.
Yeah. Um, I'll tell you, I've always found that,
I don't know who that quote is attributed to. I'm sure it,
I'm sure it appears in many formats,
but I always found it to be very poignant because it's not saying you should
only have a windshield and no rear view mirror. Right. Right.
And it's not saying you should have no windshield and only a rear view mirror.
It's saying you need both, but one's bigger than the other. Yeah.
But in my own life, I've always felt like I have to have a rear view mirror.
Yeah. Like I, I never want to lose sight of my sins. Right.
Cause they kind of ground me. Of course. Um,
when I think of all of the, again, you've lived, you've,
you've had the both the luxury and the inconvenience
of living all of your sins on the world's most public stage.
So most of us make all of our mistakes behind closed doors and nobody really
gets to see the horrible things we've done.
I remember when I hit the one year anniversary of doing something so awful,
I couldn't stand my existence for it.
And I remember talking to my therapist about it and she said,
I actually don't want you to ever forget this. Like I want you to remember what
you did because this is,
you have to remember that the monster that did that thing,
he's never going to die. He'll sit in the corner. He'll be small,
but he's never going to die. If you have the tools in place to keep him in the
corner. Right. Are there moments that you look back at,
like you look at that SCA deposition in October of a Oh five and think like,
I need that video playing over and over again, just quietly.
Yeah. It's totally embarrassing. I mean, a lot of that shit.
And I was forced to rewatch a ton of that. Not, not, not,
cause I wanted to, or I thought it would be a good idea, but I mean,
in legal settings and depositions and trials and like,
they just hammer you with this, but it's yeah,
you look at that and you're like, that is, that is a pathetic person. Like that,
I ain't never going back there. And, um,
I mean those sort of things is unfortunate and as embarrassing and as tough as
they are to watch. Actually for me, they're,
those are, those are good. I mean, I don't want to do it every day,
but it's like that guy needed to die. Right.
And then, and a new guy needed to come around and, um,
yeah, that's where you get stuck. You know, you say, uh,
wouldn't change a thing and all these things that, that I would,
I would say that would, yeah, actually, I mean, you would change things, right?
I mean, you wouldn't,
I mean, I love the spot that I've been able to get to.
So you sort of think in your mind like, well,
these were all events that shaped the person sitting here today, but
there would have been a better way to go about it.
Yeah, it's funny. I was watching a video of an interview you did a while ago and
I normally don't read comments on YouTube because they're so incredibly
uninteresting and ridiculous. And I don't know why, but for some reason,
I read a couple and, and,
and I came across one that I thought was so interesting.
I actually copied it down. I want to read it to you.
So it was an interview. I don't even remember what interview it was,
but not surprisingly, a lot of the comments were like,
this guy's a horrible human being like, you know, what a,
what a ridiculous person. Oh, I know.
It must've been the interview where you said,
and you tried to offer a nuanced explanation for why
you wish you didn't have to hurt people,
but you also wouldn't have done it different in the sense that you needed to
learn the lessons you learned. Do you remember this interview?
This thing was on NBC.
These were all the ones that.
Yeah. So not surprisingly, every commenter is like ripping you apart.
And this one guy writes something, I'm just going to read to you verbatim.
And I was, I was, I was really moved by it. He says,
I was not a good person and it took losing everything to realize it.
I'm not yet at the point where I would not change a thing,
but I do get the, I can't change a thing.
So it's useless to feel as much regret and shame as I do.
I really believe him when he says that he values the lessons he learned because I
do too. I might not be a good person yet. I'm learning,
but I'm no longer a bad one.
Yeah. You know, those are few and far between. I mean,
it takes a lot of, you know, most, yeah, I mean, it's amazing, but,
you know, comment. I mean, I don't read comments.
Yeah. I just can't mean it. And it's, and it's, you know,
I used to read comments, but I don't.
Something about the last line of this.
I might not be a good person yet, but I'm no longer a bad one. I mean,
I remember feeling like when I went through that transition of, okay,
like you're not the worst human in the world. You're not perfect.
And you're never going to be, but, um,
I still don't understand a couple of things about the sport. Now we could,
we could explain all day long why,
why you ended up where you ended up, right? Everybody will say, well,
it's not, you know, it went from, once it became clear how widespread EPO use
was in the Peloton and blood transfusing and all that stuff,
it became very difficult to say, well,
Lance is a bad guy because he did these performance enhancing drugs because to a
first order, you did them no more or no less than anybody else.
So then it turned into, well,
he treated people so badly and that's why Lance is the worst person.
But that doesn't explain to me why, you know,
oh,
Yvonne Basso who did everything that Pantani did is loved and Pantani was
completely vilified and I mean, effectively killed himself.
It doesn't explain why, well,
pick your favorite German rider who's loved and, and Ulrich was rejected.
Um, why Vauders is loved and you know,
Tyler gets rejected or whomever, right? So,
so if we're did you take Lance out of it for a moment, right? Cause you're,
you know, you're radioactive.
What explains that difference between those other guys?
Cause Jan wasn't beating anybody up. Pantani wasn't screaming at anybody.
But these, yeah, I mean they're, they're, they're, um,
yeah. And say, and same in Spain with him in us, right? So you, you,
you have a handful of examples here with, with,
with characters who were, uh,
had problems so they could not handle, you know, the, the, the, you know,
this is, and I speak, I've talked about this before, but this, nothing,
looking at the whole situation, nothing infuriates me more than that, right?
If you've, and it's, it's,
it has more to do with society and the press and just in,
in the organizers and the politicians in the sport, how they will embrace,
you know, Jan Ulrich is not welcome at the start of the tour. Meanwhile,
Eric's Abba was up there shaking hands with the, the guy in the yellow chair.
You know, it's like, wait a minute, like this is fucking stupid. I, I,
I don't understand.
Do you have any idea why that hypocrisy exists?
Um,
I mean, only then, you know, the ones,
the ones who rose the highest, I mean, obviously, I mean,
Pantani was the biggest athlete in Italy at the time. No soccer,
whatever sport F1 Pantani was the biggest athlete in Italy.
Jan was the biggest athlete in Germany. I was the biggest athlete here and,
and you know, on and on. And so, you know,
maybe it has to do with those heights and the only,
the only place you can end up is,
is the complete opposite, like just at the bottom of the pool. Um,
but it doesn't, I don't think it excuses it. I thought that just, and,
and we're talking about, we're not talking about me again, but with these
stories, I mean, Pantani dead,
Hemenez dead, uh, you know, Vanden Broek dead Belgium,
um, Gomont dead in France. I mean,
all guys that were at the top of the game and they just could,
they couldn't handle this perp with their own demons.
They couldn't handle that fall from grace. So they turned to other things.
And, but nobody reached out, you know, you know, in many ways,
the press just sort of chased that story. I mean, they'll get Vanden Broek.
I mean, Frank Vanden Broek was arguably one of the most talented of all time.
He was the next Mercs. He was the next, that, that, that, that.
And the press just,
just let it go and just hammered this guy and he died in the hotel room in
Senegal. Pantani dies at a dirty hotel room in Milan.
Jan almost dies. I mean, it's like, you know,
when did you realize Jan was in trouble? I know it was,
I remember you and I talking about this in the summer of 18.
You sent me a picture and I'll never forget it. I was like, that can't be on.
Well, you know, Jan was always,
Jan was always like to have fun. I mean, we talked about it.
Yeah, but this didn't look like having fun.
No, no, no, this is, but you know, it, it, um, you know, I guess, uh, you know,
cause the other interesting thing is, is, you know, one of Jan's closest
lieutenants when, when we were competing head to head was, was Andreas Cloden.
Yes.
Who ended up being on Astana with us and Radio Shack. And, and so I,
ended up getting to know Cloden and really, really getting to love him. Um,
so I had heard that a lot of these guys, so Cloden, Sable, Daniel Hondo,
they had tried to reach out to him and you know,
and it was in the press. He got in a fight with his neighbor.
Like these are no secrets. This shit was out there. Um,
and then, uh, you know, he has, he has, uh, and he,
but he, he turned everybody away and not just turned them away, but just,
just flat out erased them from his life because he didn't want to hear it.
But he had two guys, uh, Frank and Mike Baldinger. So the,
the German brothers from, from where he's from, they're normal guys.
Like they're not professional cyclists. They're not rich. They're not famous.
They're just regular dudes. They're good dudes. And, uh,
they contacted me and they said, we, we,
he's told everybody else to just leave him alone. And then he's turned on.
They said, you're our last call. Like you, and so,
and I didn't know these guys. And so that's when I made the trip, um,
to, uh, was it Switzerland or Germany place? And that was,
you know, it was a mess.
Yeah. What was that like to see him like that?
Unrecognizable. It was like an alien had entered his body. It was,
it was, I've never, I have never, I've seen some crazy shit.
I have never seen anything like this. Um,
but you know, Jan, two years sober,
he's got his kids back in his life. It's on the bike.
If I can love that guy.
It is amazing to me how our society summit we, we, again,
I can't understand it.
Why we sometimes lift people up and then find such joy in watching them crash.
Yeah. We're not going to figure that out, you know,
and I don't, I don't spend any time. I mean,
I get very frustrated and straight up mad when I see,
you know, the, the, the,
the differences between Ulrich and Zabel and Pantani and Basso and on and on
and on. But, you know,
and, and guys that were just not equipped to handle that downfall,
like it, I was the one, the man, I was the one thing I said to myself,
I said, just whatever you do, just do not, I mean,
you can go have fun and do some crazy,
but don't you ever lose, lose contact with your health,
your wellness, your fitness, your family. Like,
don't ever lose sight of that.
Did you go through a period in 2013 where you were pretty reclusive?
And so this is meeting right after kind of the whole confession. Um,
cause you didn't try to think like, when did you start your podcast in 16,
17?
I'd have to go back and look, it's been, uh,
like there was a period of time when you were really off the radar.
Yeah. I mean, you had, you know, no choice.
Radar didn't pick you up either. I mean, there was no, nothing to do.
What was it like when you walked into a restaurant? Did people, um,
I mean, you've told one story a number of times about, you know,
you walking across the street and a bunch of people in bars.
Yeah. What was, what was the normal reaction like perfectly fine?
Indifference. Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, I, I people, people are, and again,
he goes to this comment thing. Like I just think about,
that's why I don't read comments because I walked through my day. You know,
I see guys on the golf course. I see people on bike rides.
I see people in restaurants. I see, you know, I go to meeting. Like it's,
it's that is not a, a, a, a,
an accurate snapshot of what my life is like
at all. You know, even in 13. So because remember it,
the other thing that was going on at that point in time is the foundation is
crumbling and you're getting kicked out. Yep. And you know,
you've told me before that that hurt as much as anything else. Yeah. I mean,
it was, it was surreal and, and just sad.
And what did the people to foundation tell you unofficially, not the,
not the board, but the people who worked there,
the people who were doing the actual heavy lifting? Well, I mean,
now those folks, I have a ton of, um,
regret about because they, they, they were doing the Lord's work and they were
not privy.
Yeah. They weren't decision makers. Yeah.
But the, and they believed the dream, they believed the story. And so that's,
and as a byproduct of that, you know, they in many ways felt, uh,
complicit in, in the scheme. And so for that,
it that's, that's tough for me to hear and to,
and I'll spend the rest of my days trying to make that okay for them. Um,
you know, at the, at the top, you know, and I wasn't part of these discussions,
so I don't know what the board room discussions were like or, or,
or who, which consultants were hired or I don't know how it all went down,
but, um,
and I just knew it was the wrong thing. I knew it.
I knew that that, that, that timeout, yes.
Space, but some agreement here that we will both reemerge.
That was the right thing to do. I mean,
and I don't need somebody to sit here and say, well, you're right. Like,
but if I look at where Livestrong has ultimately ended up and I look at,
you know, you've brought up a pie. I mean, if I look at my audience now,
well, they're very different.
And one of them is, is not doing very well. And the other one's is back,
so to speak.
What interaction do you have these days with a cancer community?
Very little, just one, just one on one just would, and by the way,
that's fine. Like I don't, you know,
I don't need to be asked to speak at a gala or get some award or all the stuff I
did in the past. Somebody's got a friend that's just been diagnosed and Hey,
Lance, can you reach out to him? A hundred percent. Let's go right now. Um,
and that's, that's enough for me.
I don't know if you've been asked this question before.
I'm sure you have. Um, and so I apologize in advance,
but, um, when the story's done, what do you think your legacy is going to be?
Well, you don't,
there's, um, well,
yeah, that that's, that's, that's harder to,
what do I think it will be or what do I want it to be?
Because you don't get to write your own.
What do you think it's, um,
too early to say too early. I mean, if, if,
I know what it would have said in January of 2013, yeah.
But you know, I don't, I don't, I don't like to brag about myself,
but I gotta say I'm really fucking proud.
What are you most proud of? Well, I'm, I'm,
I am proud of the fact that I didn't quit.
Which time? Because you had a number of times to do this.
Just do this whole, do the whole thing that, that,
that I was able to keep it together and, uh, you know,
without really any support and thank God we live in 2021,
2020, whatever, where you can, people can re,
that you can re reinvent yourself on your own.
You don't need network television. You don't need, you know, uh,
the New York times. You don't need any of that.
Like what we're doing right here right now, you did this on your own.
You bought the cameras, you got the mics, you're asking the questions.
You're the smart guy. All the millions of people are listening.
You did that on your own. You couldn't have done that 10 years ago,
20 years ago. Right? So that's,
I've chosen to go that path and, and, and, and I'm proud of that.
Honestly. Um, so who knows what, what to, to,
to your original question. Like I, I, um,
I'm 50 years old. I think I'll have another
40 or 50 years. So there's, uh,
there's a lot left to be told.
That's the amazing part here, right? Yeah. And I don't, I don't need, um,
I don't, I don't, I don't need, uh, um,
any more puff pieces in my life. Like, you know, I, I'm, I'm,
I'm really beholden to a few things. One, my family.
So that's my, that's my first checkpoint.
And that's amazing. Right. And then I really feel,
uh, beholden and loyal to the audience of our podcasts.
And then as a byproduct of the success of the podcast, the fund, right?
So the LP base, the people that have entrusted me, right?
That the guy that the whole world thought could never be trusted again,
have trusted me with their hard earned money. Um,
I'm beholden to them. And so those are all, and that's all I care about. Right?
So that's, and if, uh, and you know, but I, again,
I don't need a, I don't need to be on the cover of Forbes because our, you know,
it's just, uh, I'm totally cool to keep that private. Um,
but look, I mean, at the, also at the end of the day,
it is going to contain a lot of the, of the rear view mirror.
That's just, that's just the way that I'm okay with that.
That's the way society is. That's the way legacies are mine, especially.
It will, it will mostly be that.
If you can go back in time to
15 year old Lance, you've got, you've got a, you've got a week with him.
Yeah. What kind of lessons would you try to impart on him?
Um, you know, that's because 15 was a, uh, an interesting age.
So, uh, there were, there would have been a lot. I mean, that was a very,
yeah, you're good enough that you, you know, I, I picked 15 because you're a pro
traffic.
Well, I was a pro athlete and it was when my mom kicked out Terry Armstrong.
Okay. So I didn't know that was 15. Yeah, that was 15. So that was,
that was a point in time where it was her and I against the world.
Like fuck everybody else. We're going to, we're going to get these people.
Like he's gone. We're together. Like let's go.
And so that was a very important, um,
so the chip on your shoulder, which I'm guessing exists subconsciously now became
pretty conscious. Yeah, absolutely.
And that chip on your shoulder fit a lot of good for you and obviously a lot of
bad for you. Yeah. So do you think that again, in this thought experiment,
right, if you had a week to coach that kid,
could you have figured out a way to extract the value from that complex and
soften some of the damage that it was going to ultimately cause you via the
damage it would cause to others?
Yeah. I mean, I, I didn't really, you know, but maybe 15 year olds don't realize
that, but, but the amount of trauma that, that I had already had in my life,
which, you know, just got actually worse and worse and worse. I mean,
cancer was hugely dramatic and then the fall was traumatic. Like there is,
there is, there's a lot to unpack there. And so, and then, you know,
never meeting your father and having this way around, it was just,
and never having that, that, that figure in your life.
And the, and the figure that was there was wildly defective. You know,
you, you, you, it would have been in and around that, you know,
whether that was through even therapy at the time, then, you know, I mean,
it's always by the way, if, if somebody would have come up to me when I was 15
and said, you know, I feel like you've had some crazy shit in your 15 years,
you should just do a little bit at once a month, I would've said, you know what,
why don't you go fuck yourself? I'm doing therapy for nothing.
Like I embrace that stuff now, but, um,
there would have been a lot of work to do even then.
What could you have told him though? Like, again, if he's not willing to go to
therapy, which I can understand, that's a pretty hard sell to a really,
really cocky 15 year old, you know, what else can you tell him? I'm, I'm,
I'm just, or was he too far gone at that point? Like, you know, I,
it's one of the things I've learned about myself over time is that so many of the
character traits that were both positive and negative, and they tend to go,
they tend to cluster like right on top of each other, right? It's like,
that it's like two genes that sit right next to each other in the chromosome.
One good, one bad. Um,
a lot of those traits come about long before we're consciously aware of what
led to them. Yeah. And, um,
I think your, your case is really obvious sometimes.
Like some of those traumas are so obvious, right? Like the dad, the step dad,
the growing up without this, the growing up in a place that like,
and then of course that says nothing about cancer, which I don't know,
like do you feel you've gone back and unpacked that PTSD through all of those
layers now as an adult?
Well, I don't know that we can ever, any of us can ever unpack it all,
but I've in the last year,
I've certainly done more unpacking than in the previous 49.
Yeah. Yeah. Like way more, you know, and that's,
but, uh, you know, and I should have done,
I should have started that process a lot earlier. Um,
but you know, I guess going back to the question though, on the, uh, you know,
I was just every, you know, even then at 15, everything was, you know,
I had drove a fast car and every, every green light was a competition and every,
everything was like slow down kid. Like it was just, everything was,
um, everything was a fight, not even a competition. It was a fight.
I didn't just,
but you said it, I mean, it would have been impossible to get through just like
that 15 year old, the 25 year old, the 35 year old, even the 45 phone,
you would not have gotten through.
I think that's something that very few people can understand.
I can relate to it Lance because I've had my own total,
total destruction and I've, I've, I've played the game in my head a hundred
times. God, I just wish I could take that all back.
I wish I could undo all of that stuff,
but I realize if I were to undo all of that stuff,
I wouldn't have fallen down. And if I didn't fall down and lose it all,
but this is, we talked, this is when you say, well,
I wouldn't change a thing because these series of events happened and boom,
it caused, you know,
whether it's deep work or introspection or, or realignment,
whatever you want to call it, then that wouldn't happen. Like that, that,
that's that's just hard to, that's a hard answer. I mean,
that, that, that answer has never worked for me, but because you know, people,
well, but what, but they, they analyze so much of the stuff,
but I mean, in many ways it's true.
Yeah. So how do you keep fit these days? I mean, you talked about swimming.
Is that the mainstay of your training?
No, I, I, I, well now we're in the summer.
So now I get to Aspen is completely thought out.
The mountain bike trails are open. What's your fastest time at Mount Evans?
I've only done Mount Evans once like an 80,
no, in 90. I did it in 1990. That's at your doorstep. No, no, that's,
that's not that close. It's close to Aspen. Isn't it? It's like a couple hours away.
Well, that's, that's not close. I brought, I,
I don't get in a car to ride my bike. That's kind of a rule.
All right. What was your fastest time at Palomar? Don't know.
That was a long time ago. Do you care anymore?
Do you still care how fast you can ride up the mountain? No, I,
I find myself being happier and happier just
riding. Do you use a power meter still? Nope. No heart rate, no power meter.
None of that bullshit. Do you have any idea what you're,
what you would ride up a Madone in today?
How many Watts you could average if we stuck a power meter on you?
I have no idea. Like 350? No, I doubt I could do that.
I bet you could. You give me, you give me a week or two to train. I could,
I could, I don't know, but it's, I find myself just when I'm out,
it's like I ride easier as opposed to harder. I mean, I,
do you enjoy a group ride or do you still enjoy just kind of going out on your
own, doing a four hour ride? I like it. I like being all alone.
How much on the mountain bike versus road bike? Mostly mountain bike.
Just cause of the risk of cars or cars. I like Stan. And it's where we live.
You get out in the mountains on a mountain bike all by yourself. Come on.
You're running much.
I haven't run. I keep getting hurt. Run. I think I'm too old to run.
I don't, I don't do at this age, you know, if,
if I did yoga three days a week or was serious about stretching and pliability
and things that I should be thinking about at 50, I could run,
but my dumb ass is just like, put the shoes on,
don't stretch a bit. Let's go. Like that,
that doesn't work when you're 50.
And I mean, if, if I were to give you,
what's the tightest interval you'd swim 10, 100 zone,
what would be your touch and go interval for 10, 100?
Uh, uh, C level. Like if I went right now.
Yeah. Would you do, would you be 105 touch and go? No, I couldn't do that right
now. I could do one to one 10 to one 10. I'd be,
I'd be really touching and going at the end, but.
So one 15, you could, you could bring a minute one 10. No problem. Yeah.
So you're still a fit guy.
I'm fitter than most 50. What's your, what's your biggest,
what's the biggest liability to your fitness? What's your biggest vice food,
alcohol, what gets in the way of, cause what do you weigh right now?
180. Okay. So you're 15 pounds above your tour weight,
which is actually not a lot given the most retired cyclists. So is that,
is that a struggle to maintain your weight? No, I don't try. I mean, I, I,
I seem to have a balance between consumption and we,
we, you go where whether you're consuming food or alcohol or, or whatever,
that's consumption and, and, and exercise. I, I never,
I have to exercise not, not because I want to stay a certain weight or I work in
book. It's just, you need it for your mental health.
It is my own sanity. Like it's the only reason. Um,
that's interesting by the way, isn't it?
There are a lot of former pro athletes that I know who once it's no longer
their job, they just do not want to do it anymore.
I will, I will ride for as long as this body will allow it to ride.
Absolutely. Yeah.
Well man, it has been, it has been great sitting down. Yeah. Um,
been a long time coming. I know.
And I've got an amazing salmon and okra dish waiting. Oh God.
You gotta tell that story right quick. You can't tease them out with that.
This is, I'll tell the story. I'll tell the story. So there's, there,
and every people that like Anna who cooks from you all the time,
she knows that I just, I don't like salmon and like growing up,
we would eat okra and I just don't like okra. So I come over, this has been six,
six, seven months ago and I walk in and I'm like,
that smells like salmon. I'm like, Hey, what's for dinner? Peter? He's like,
Oh, I got some grilling this amazing salmon. I was like,
I was on the Traeger, my special marinade. I was like, Oh, okay.
And then I was like, what do we have in with it? And you're like, Oh,
I got some fresh okra. And I was like, this is not,
this isn't happening. This is a fucking joke. Like somebody's,
I'm getting punked. It's like Anna called me to tell me this before.
And I was like sitting there just like getting to the meal and we were,
we had a wonderful time. And then I, when I don't know why I was,
when I was stepping out, I was like, I was like,
I have to be honest with you guys.
Like there are two things in this world that I just really can't stand to eat.
Salmon and okra. It was,
but you had a brave face, man. I wouldn't have known you. You put it down.
As far as salmon and okra go, I hope it was good salmon and good okra.
We had the Japanese whiskey too. Ah,
that, that definitely lubricated it. All right, my friend.
You ready to go get your butt kicked in the Sim? Yeah. Well,
I wouldn't, you don't, you, you don't know that I'm going to get my butt kicked.
So it's not fair for you to say that, but I'm ready to, uh,
I'm ready to go see what happens. Okay. Very well.
I can drive. I'm sure you can, but I just think,
I'm excited to see this. Okay, good. Let's do it. Let's do it.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss,
we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in depth,
exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the
subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things.
One totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person thing we discuss on each episode.
The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or
ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely access to our
private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The qualities,
which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday,
highlighting the best questions,
topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive.
This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back
and necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other
benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on.
If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to Peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe.
You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, all with the ID Peteratiamd.
You can also leave us a review on Apple podcasts or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only.
It does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing,
or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the
user's own risk.
The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have,
and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any
such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise,
please visit Peteratiamd.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and
active list of such companies.