Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Jeremy. Thanks so much for making time. I've been looking forward to this one for
quite a while, both personally and professionally. This is a topic I've wanted to learn a lot
more about, something I've been playing with a lot myself, including this morning, particularly
painful session this morning of blood flow restriction, which I might be doing wrong.
So I'm looking forward to maybe the end of our discussion when we can get into the practical
aspects of it. But I want to take a step back and get a sense about how you became interested
in exercise in general. Obviously, you've devoted your career to it. So when did that
become a passion great enough that you decided it was worth all of your study?
Yeah. Thanks for having me on, Peter. I wrestled early on in my life. So I wrestled from probably
the age of five through high school. But I wasn't really into training that much. I
was into wrestling, but not really lifting weights or any of the conditioning. And my
coaches would always tell me that you need to try to get in the gym. You just stay in
the gym, get stronger, get stronger, get stronger. And I didn't really listen up until towards
the end of high school. And then I started one of my friends was really into bodybuilding,
powerlifting. So I started training with him. And I do feel like it probably helped
me a little bit in wrestling. And then I kind of got interested in just trying to see how
to make a muscle get as big as possible. And I started reading, you know, muscle magazines,
which is kind of the, you know, the common story, training in a little bit. Then I kind
of focused on exercise science early on in my undergrad. Again, with a focus on how do
I make every lecture was I was just trying to learn how to make a muscle bigger and how
to make a muscle stronger. That's all I was trying to get out of every lecture towards
the middle of, I guess, my undergrad, you have to make a decision about, you know, obviously,
what do you want to try and do with your career? And I was dead set on working with athletes.
But then I did that and quickly realized that's not what I wanted to do. So they suggested
that I instead maybe you're really interested in research, why don't you try and do an internship
related to that. So I landed at the University of Illinois. And that's where I met Lane and a couple
other people. And that's where I really came across blood flow restriction. And that's where
I started to really read a lot about it and then came back and started to really focus all of my
times. That was around 2007, 2008. So just about, you know, reading blood flow restriction and how
I might be able to do that. So I started off with wrestling and then kind of got interested in body
building, powerlifting, and then came across blood flow restriction when I was up at Illinois.
Now, you mentioned briefly that you did a little bit of work with athletes, which was obviously
kind of a logical, at least place to look, but it sounds like you didn't find that to be what you
wanted. Why is that? You know, I, I think I'm a pretty mediocre athlete. And I think I, but I
mediocre athlete, but I always trained extremely hard. And I think I had this mindset that, you
know, everybody was going to train what I thought training was, and how everybody was going to train
as hard as I thought they should train. And when I was doing a little practicum work with some of
these athletes, I mean, they weren't world-class elite athletes, but they were fairly good
collegiate athletes. I didn't get the same vibe that everybody was into training. Like I was in
the training at the time. It doesn't mean they weren't great athletes. They obviously were. It
doesn't mean they didn't train hard, but I, my perception of how they should have been training
was, was not what I thought it was going to be. So I knew I wanted to be in the exercise world, but
I quickly realized that that's, that's not for me. I really kind of want to maybe do research. And
that's when I went to Illinois and I was doing animal research, but I didn't really like that
either. I knew I was, when I was there, I quickly learned that I want to do research, but definitely
not with animals. I wanted, so I came back and that's when I got into human research.
So where did you do your PhD?
University of Oklahoma.
And what was the focus of your dissertation?
Looking at different methods of applying blood flow restriction. So looking at, you know, different
exercise loads of 20%, 30% different pressures. In other words, we were trying to get at this idea
of, do you actually need higher pressures? So in my dissertation, we were doing a lot of acute work,
which has obviously a lot of limitations with applying it to adaptation, but we were trying to
really see kind of a short term characteristic of what that response would give acutely. What does
this response give? What does this response give? And then try and kind of pick out two of the more
promising ones and then study them head to head a little bit later on, which is kind of what we did
once I took a job at Ole Miss.
I can't wait to talk more about that. And there's no shortage of questions I have for you,
but I was thinking about this last night, that before we jump into a lot of the questions I have,
I think it will be important for people to really understand the ins and outs of muscle, what's the
muscle, the structure of a muscle, not the gross anatomy of a muscle, but obviously the micro
structure, the physiology of a muscle. So without worrying about going too deep, I think it's okay to
do that. Let's talk about a muscle because I don't think we can get into what we're about to talk
about if people don't know what a sarcomere is and what actin and myosin are and what the different
types of fibers are. So if I were to sort of take a knife and cut down on my bicep and yank it off
the tendon and throw it out there as a muscle, how would you explain to somebody what's actually
going on inside that thing? Yeah, that's a good question. I think when we talk about a muscle, so
like just your the whole thing, so it's like a box within a box within a box. So the smallest unit of
that is, as you said, a sarcomere, which is actin and myosin. And that's the kind of the proteins
that we're ultimately synthesizing when we exercise. So we're making more of those. And if you make
more of those than you break down, then obviously the muscle will get bigger. So when we actually
exercise those actin and myosin interact, and that's how we make a muscle contract. And that's
important because when actin and myosin interact and you have muscle contraction, that's where you
get a lot of this signaling for ultimate muscle adaptation. So I think the characteristics of
muscle, we have kind of two broad types is how we typically teach it. We have type one, which is
more endurance based type two, which is more force based. But in reality, those are probably on a
continuum. So when we exercise, we can shift them, we can shift the continuum one way or another.
Depending upon the type of exercise that you're doing. But in general, when we become more
physically active, the overall fiber types shift slower. So they become more oxidative, they become
more efficient. That's the general kind of response. So those are the different types of
fibers, the actin actin and myosin, that's the functional unit, they interact to make the muscle
contract. Let's explain to people how that works, Jeremy. So you pull out this sort of sarcomere,
and inside you have these fibers, and you've got these Z lines. Explain to people how the actin
and myosin actually interact with each other relative to the Z line, what the contraction
looks like. And frankly, even one of the more interesting things that I think is a bit counter
intuitive the first time people learn it is which part of the interaction between actin and myosin
requires ATP. Yeah, it's sort of it's a bit counterintuitive when you're first presented with it.
Right. So when we decide to exercise, we have a signal that goes from the nerve to the muscle,
basically, we have a release of calcium. And that calcium is going to expose the binding site. So
basically, we have these filaments, they slide past each other. That's the that's the general dogma,
at least with concentric actions, eccentric is a little bit more complex. I think they're still
trying to figure that out with Titan. But just in general, when a muscle contracts, so the myosin
is interacting with the actin and it's causing it to pull in. Now, ATP is required to break that
bond. So the ATP comes in, it breaks it off, it gets hydrolyzed, which recox it and allows it to
be able to reattach assuming there's more calcium on board. So that's the the general basic
physiology of muscle contraction. So as long as calcium is there, or as long as the signals
being sent, those sarcomeres, those actin and myosin will keep interacting. So they don't all
interact at the same time. Otherwise, you couldn't really sustain exercise. But you have them, you
know, in a textbook, we talk about we have kind of like an image and we have myosin head, but those
myosin heads are on all the way around that myosin and they're all interacting at different times.
So that's how we're able to actually move through kind of a fluid motion. And what's interesting,
as you said, is that the ATP is required to actually release the actin myosin complex,
which is we learned in medical school explains why a corpse is experiencing rigor mortis, right? When
a person is dead, and they're no longer able to produce ATP, they don't have the ability to
release the actin myosin filaments. That's why a body gets stiff, sort of a morbid thought,
but it explains physiologically what's happening. So let's not talk a little bit about this difference
in fibers, because again, I think most people have probably heard of the idea of a type one and a type
two fiber. But as you said, it's probably more complex than that. And there's more of a continuum.
I think even by the time I was in med school, the teaching was really it's a type one, and then a
two A and a two B, and then it became a two A, a two A B, a two B, you could argue it's even more
complex now. Let's start with the term fast versus slow twitch. I've read conflicting things. So I'm
hoping you can clarify this for me. I've read that there's no difference in the twitch speed.
They all twitch at the same speed. It's the force of contraction and the speed to fatigue that's
being referred to. So the faster twitch muscle has a higher contractile force, but it also fatigues
quickly, hence fast twitch. Is there actually a difference in the neurologic signal that's
happening there? Or the speed of contraction for that matter? Yeah, that's a good question. I think
this is not work that I actually do. I have a lot of confusion surrounding this myself.
And a lot of it reading some of the work by Andy Galpin, and some others, a lot of it comes from
the old methods are still being used. And the limitations of those is that we can't do hybrids.
And some people say we should be using these new methods. And I think it all depends on how you're
actually identifying the fibers. What are you doing to call it a fast or a slow? How are you
ultimately deciding that with your methodology? So I don't honestly know the ins and outs of all of
those. The general idea, I think, as you said, the type two fibers. So for example, type 2X,
those typically are bigger, they're typically stronger, but they fatigue much faster. The type
2A, it's a little bit more oxidative, they're pretty forceful, and they can sustain it for
quite some time. So in general, when we exercise, it's thought that type 2X usually transitions to
type 2A. And you don't have a whole lot of type 2X left over. That's my general understanding.
Type 1 fibers generally a little bit slower. And they're not as forceful, but they don't fatigue,
it takes a lot to fatigue those fibers. So I think that's the general characteristics. I think
how you go about identifying that, you might get a little bit of different things, but that was the
general idea, as I understand it at least. And what accounts for the difference in contractile
strength between a type 1 fiber and say a type 2X, take two opposite ends of the spectrum.
So it's, I mean, sometimes using the extremes is helpful, right? So the type 1 fiber has lots of
mitochondria surrounding the fibrils within the sarcomere. As you said, it is readily able to
access glucose and fatty acid oxidative conversely the type 2X fiber. I don't even think it has
mitochondria surrounding it. It's purely a glycolytic tool, meaning it's going to basically have to go
glycogen to glucose to lactate. What accounts mechanically for the difference?
I think most people would say that perhaps the overall just size difference, whether or not there
are other things, whether or how it may interact and the speed of it, that might be different as
well. But I think the big characteristic difference, at least in young people, is that the size of the
fiber is just distinctly different. And I think when you look at fiber mechanics outside of the
body and you test a type 1 or test a type 2, they will be different. How those interact within the
body as a whole, I think, is quite a bit different. And that's always been an interest of mine with
respect to dynamic strength, moving the whole person, not necessarily saying, well, their fiber
is still nice and strong. But what about when the fiber is in the person? What's going on then?
So I think both of those are very important. I don't want to come across like I'm talking down
to that type of work. I think it's very important work, but I think they're just different.
How genetically set is this? It seems that there's clearly a difference in individuals' capacity for
work, meaning aerobic work versus explosive strength and aerobic work. But do you have a sense
of how genetically diverse the fiber distribution is? That's a good question. That's kind of a
question I always put forth to my class as well. I think you can look at papers and get some
percentages, but I don't feel super confident doing that, mostly because we have a lot. I mean,
not that those scientists don't know that, but those are mass extrapolations from small bits
of fibers. And one of the things that I'm always interested in is the athlete that's thought to
have some of the greatest endurance capacities or cross-country spheres. And if you were to look
at their fiber types, many of them may have a predominance of type one fibers. So the question
is, were they mostly born like that? And then they gravitated towards sports that they're good at,
or was there some sort of shift with training? If I had to pick one, it's probably both. But if I
had to pick one, I think there's a big genetic component there, probably at baseline and then
your response to exercise as well. But it seems to me that most people gravitate towards events
that they're pretty good at, and they don't do the things that they're not good at. So I think that
makes it difficult to study this anyway, but I do think that there's a big genetic component to it.
It doesn't mean, again, that they don't train hard. That's always the thing that I get when I
have a lot of athletes in my class. It's like, well, we train, it's like there's no there's no
question that you guys train extremely hard. But it's also possible that there's something
different about you already. So that would be my my guess. And you sort of already touched on it a
bit, but do we have data to suggest how malleable that is? We all know the extremes, right? We know
these sort of mesomorphic specimens that kind of look at weights and get bigger and stronger.
And then conversely, we know that sort of wiry person who can't put on muscle no matter what
they seemingly do, but boy, like, you get them out there on a bike and you can never catch them.
But when you take someone maybe who's not quite at the extremes,
how much can training over and over what time period impact fiber type?
Yeah, I think certainly some. I don't think we're going to take someone like myself,
who's athletically quite average. I don't think any amount of training was going to make me a
lead in anything. But I do think that I could improve certain aspects of that, for sure. But I
don't think it's going to myself move me to, you know, up a couple notches. Now there could be
some people who certainly can. I think that this is where there's quite a bit of confusion with
kind of individual response data and things like that. I think, you know, we've published a little
bit on this topic about, you know, the measurements that we have aren't typically good enough to say,
not only did this group increase muscle size more than this group, but this individual increased
more than this person, but not quite as much as this person and not quite as much as this person.
That would require a very, very good instrument. So I think people often take that to mean,
so you're saying that there aren't individual responders. I'm not saying that at all. I'm
saying that we may not have the ability to appropriately determine who's who. We can say,
overall, on average, doing this will increase this or that. But I think that just looking around,
it seems at least pretty clear to me that there are some people who you give them a certain
response and, man, do they look like world beaters a couple months later. So that does tell me
something is different about them. But I don't know that we could detect that with a lot of the
measurements that we have. Okay. I think the other thing that would be helpful for us to understand
before we get into the science of blood flow restriction is to understand what strength is
and to understand what hypertrophy is. Do you have a preference with which one we start with?
Either one. Okay. So if we measure the size of my bicep today, we could do it crudely with a tape
measure. We could do it more accurately with an MRI or an ultrasound. And you were to prescribe
exercises that we'll talk about. Whether with or without blood flow restriction, we can get into
load, we can get into reps, et cetera. We come back and measure. And again, let's just use the
gold standard. We'll use an MRI. We'll come back and measure me in six months. And demonstrably,
my muscle has gotten bigger. What does that mean? Did I grow more muscle fibers? Did each fiber get
bigger? How would you explain to somebody what happened in that cycle of hypertrophy?
So there's a couple of different ways that it could happen. You could have an increase in fiber size,
which is hypertrophy. So all the muscle cells that you have, maybe not all, but the muscle cell
itself has gotten bigger. The other, so that's hypertrophy. The other component would be you
have an increase in the number of cells. That's hyperplasia. In general, we don't think that
hyperplasia is playing a big role, at least in adults. And I wouldn't necessarily rule it out,
but it doesn't seem like we have a lot of evidence for that. So we always just look at
growth changes and assume that it's probably hypertrophy. So what that, when your muscle
was to get bigger following exercise, what that would mean is, is that the individual cells
inside that bicep have increased in size. And we typically assume that that's due to increases
in overall protein, actinomycin and things of that sort. You're obviously going to also have
an increase in other components to help support the cell. But that's generally what we mean,
an increase in cell size. And, you know, when you think about like an epithelial cell or something
like that, we don't really pay much attention to the size of those cells, right? Like, I don't know
that anybody, I don't know if the dermatologist is looking at somebody's moles when they biopsy
them and looking at the individual cells and talking about the size of them. There we would
concern ourselves much more with hyperplasia and certainly metoplasia or dysplasia. Those are the
things that really get people concerned. But in this sense, muscles are kind of unique in that
they can have not just a non-pathologic, but a healthy change in size. So is it, as you said,
do you think it's primarily due to an increase in the amount of actinomycin within the cell
or some other characteristic? Is it, does the actinomycin complex actually change in size or
do you just have more of it? That's a good question. I think that most people would say that
because they usually connect it to short-term measures of protein synthesis. So myofibrillar,
which is actinomycin, so synthesizing more and more of those, I think is the general
is the general thought that you have more overall actinomycin, along with other things, of course.
And let's talk about strength now. So we can talk about sort of, we can kind of break it down right
into kind of mechanical strength and neurologic strength. How do you think about that? So again,
let's use the same example of you measure my ability to do a bicep curl. And let's just assume
there'll be two measurements. You'll measure my single rep max, so the most that I can do.
And then you'll also do a separate test for the most that I can do 10 times or 15 times or
something. So you'll measure kind of two different components of strength, maybe absolute, extreme,
and sort of more of a muscular endurance test. And then you'll have me do a set of prescribed
exercises for six months, and we'll come back and we'll do that whole thing again. And my one rep
max went up by 20% and the amount of weight that I could move 10 times went up 15%.
What happened to me mechanically, structurally, neurologically? What explains that change in
strength? It's a good question. And that's something that it's a question that I'm extremely
interested in. And I don't know why people get stronger. I think the general thought or how we
teach people is the initial change in strength is due to neurological changes. So
and that's what that means. What does neurologic mean, I think is also up to some debate. But we
can think about a signal being sent from the brain through the spinal cord to the alpha motor neuron.
So the alpha motor neuron is the nerve that communicates with the muscle. So there could be
changes anywhere in between that. So you have more excitatory input, you have less inhibition,
you have lowering of thresholds that makes it easier to fire the type two fibers. There's a
lot of different things that that could be playing a role there for why someone might
get stronger with neural adaptations. So most people are okay with that part. Then the next part
is people will say after about three to four weeks, when the muscle is also getting bigger,
that that change in fiber size will also be contributing to a change in string.
And that's something that we have recently taken some exception to.
And there's been a lot of really good discussions about that part of it. But yes,
I do come back to that, Jeremy, because I've read the studies that you're referring to.
They're super fascinating. And I was actually surprised at how little evidence there was in
favor of the dogmatic view. So I look forward to diving into that a little bit more. And you can
see why intuitively one would say, well, size must produce strength if size comes from more
active in myosin, which basically means more contractile units. But but as we'll see, I think
when we talk about some of your more recent work, that's not necessarily settled, is it?
Not in my opinion, no. And I and to be fair, it's not settled one way or the other.
But I do think that there's a probably a neural component. But I think that there can also be
some changes at the local level that might explain some of those changes in strength.
And I think we can discuss that a little bit later as well. But there could be some, some, you know,
changes at the myosin head, or changes in calcium release and things of that sort. So
I don't have any good evidence that that is actually happening. But just some ideas behind
why someone might get stronger following exercise. All right, I think that's a pretty solid primer
for where we're about to go. So I'll start with the story. I used to swim a lot. And
oh, God, this might be circa 2010. So call it 1011 years ago. I have a friend, Steve Munet,
Munet onus, who's himself a remarkable swimmer, like truly a world class marathon swimmer.
And he was visiting San Diego from where he lived in LA. And he came to join me for a workout at the
master's club I swam at. And after the workout, he brought out these bands. They were called
catsu bands, which we're going to talk about. And he said, Okay, Peter, I want you I'm going to put
these bands on your thighs, upper thighs, and I'm going to put them on your arms, the upper arm.
And I'm going to, you know, compress to a certain level. And he had what looked like a blood pressure
cuff there that he could sort of calibrate the the the the occlusive pressure. And I want you to swim
a 50 yard butterfly all out. Now keep in mind, swimming a 50 yard butterfly all out under any
circumstance is quite challenging. But totally doable, right? I mean, you you would do a set of
1050s of butterfly at 90%, you know, with 45 seconds in between and be totally fine.
And I remember pushing off the wall. And before I got to the other wall, which is 25 yards away to
begin turning around to come back. I was like, this is the hardest thing I've ever done. This
feels harder than swimming 200 yards of butterfly, which is really hard. So butterfly is one of those
strokes where the longest distance it's ever swum is 200 yards. And even people who train to swim
the race at 200 yards almost never swim that distance in practice, you're swimming shorter
distances perfectly, because your form tends to fall apart so badly at 200. And here I
was at 25 yards thinking, I'm going to die. And by the end of that 50, my body felt like it would
normally feel at the end of a 200 yard individual medley, or 200 breaststroke, which would be kind
of two of the most miserable things you could ever do to yourself. And, you know, that began my kind
of curiosity with this technique. I read a couple of books about it. And, you know, unfortunately,
I kind of just forgot about it. I, you know, once Steve went back up to LA, and I didn't have access
to the fancy devices, I kind of sort of forgot about it. But, you know, recently, it's now become
sort of curious to me. So what's the story of, of Yoshiaka? So what was the name of the gentleman who
came up with this system? Sato. Sato, yeah. So tell me about this guy and then how he came up with
the with this idea. Yeah, so some of this is, I'll say is a legend. But I think the story that he's
told is that he was at a Buddhist ceremony was kind of kneeling. And Sato was also, from what I
understand, interested in bodybuilding, especially in his younger days. So he felt kind of a little
bit of numbness about or a little bit of sensation that he felt when he was doing heavy squats. So he
kind of thought that there could be some connection there. Because he was kneeling and he was
restricting blood flow. Okay. Right. And I think that that led him to start kind of experimenting
with different ways to try and restrict blood flow, you know, in his lower body, upper body, etc.
I think that there's been some stories that his initial kind of ideas, he actually harmed himself
a little bit because he was maybe applying it too tightly. But I think then he actually had a skiing
accident and then applied it to himself and actually rehabbed himself with blood flow restriction and
saw some what he thought was some pretty good kind of gains. And I think that he really did
probably develop a lot of the methods for at least the initial way we were doing blood flow restriction
and kind of made it, you know, very popular with studying and research and things of that nature.
But yeah, I think he's probably the one who made it more popular, at least initially,
because they started doing research on that in the late 90s, early 2000s, at least in the published
literature. So yeah, I think the idea is is that it mimics something that he had felt before in
the gym. And he wanted to see how you could try and do that. And ultimately found that you can use
very light weights, low loads, but make it feel like you're lifting very, very heavy weights,
which is obviously useful, you know, if you have a ski in accident or you don't want to lift heavy
weights, you'd have some sort of injury. Yeah, I had a patient the last year who was playing with
his kids and tore his bicep had a complete tear. So he underwent a surgical repair of that.
But we decided to have him use blood flow restriction during the rehab phase so that
he could get back to training sooner, obviously under a far less load. And although it's anecdotal,
I mean, it was a remarkable recovery that he made, which further kind of piqued my curiosity around
this. So this this term catsu is kind of synonymous with blood flow restriction. Is it I mean, I think
it's Japanese for like training with pressure or training with added pressure or something to that
effect. Correct. Yeah, it means increasing pressure. So it's just a brand. Okay, yeah. It's the one
that's, I think it's fair to say is one of the first, but it's just a brand. So we started using,
I think a lot of people will use the catsu as just kind of a generic name, but it probably
shouldn't be done unless you're using the catsu apparatus. But yeah, it's a form of blood flow
restriction. So I want to come back to the different types of apparatus, but let's kind
of talk through it now maybe chronologically in terms of the most insights. Like if I was to go
back in time to the 1970s and I'm Sato and I'm trying to think about how to test this hypothesis,
it seems like hands down the easiest way to do this would be to use individuals as their own controls
and isolate and compress one side and not do for the other and have them do the same things
or do different things and try to isolate the variable. So was that the first experiment that
was done? Yeah, the first experiment done on blood flow restriction, at least to my knowledge,
on how we think of blood flow restriction. So I always add a lot of caveats
because some people will say, well, if you look in the 30s, there were studies done where they
applied a cuff, but it wasn't done for the purposes of increasing muscle function. So
to my knowledge, with blood flow restriction, how we use it, Shina Hara published the first
paper in 1998, where they had individuals that all they were looking at was strength, but they had
one leg do a certain exercise with blood flow restriction. The opposite leg did the same
exercise without blood flow restriction and they saw a treatment effect, meaning the limb that
underwent blood flow restriction saw a greater change. So that's the first study was looking
at a change in actual function with blood flow restriction. It's kind of amazing that that didn't
happen until 1998, which is 30 years after Sato began writing about this stuff, or at least
experimenting with it, right? Yes. The other question for me that's been very difficult to
wrap my head around is what is the definition of blood flow restriction? If I were to wrap a cuff
around my arm and apply no pressure, clearly that's no restriction. If I were to create an
occlusive pressure that was twice my systolic blood pressure, almost certainly it would imply
not a drop of blood is making its way past. So there's no arterial flow and no venous return.
That would obviously blood flow restriction. That would be blood flow restriction,
but like everything else, you have a continuum. So how do you think about this? And maybe that's
the wrong question. Maybe the better question is in the genesis of kind of the study of this,
how was restriction defined? What methods were used and how much variability existed in the studies?
So the idea of blood flow restriction is to reduce blood flow going into the limb,
but not completely occlude blood flow. So in other words, we always want blood flow to be going in.
So there is a tremendous amount of variability in how the pressure was applied early on. That's
improved substantially at improvement, in my opinion, at least the early studies would take a cuff
and apply the same pressure to every single person independent of their blood pressure,
independent of blood pressure, independent of limb size, independent of the cuff size that you're
using. So all of these things are important factors that you can account for by doing this
one measurement. That's how we do it now. But obviously it's easy to look in the past and
throw stones, but there are certainly a lot of variability. So given that the idea is to
restrict blood flow, but not occlude it completely during exercise, what we started to do and others
have started to do as well is before we do exercise, let's just take the cuff up to the lowest
pressure of which there is no flow at all. So if that's a hundred millimeters of mercury means that
you no longer have flow going into your limb at all. Let's take a percentage of that. So we know
that you always have flow during the exercise. So now do you determine that with Doppler at
some distal point to the occlusion? Yes, you can use ultrasound. We use just a handheld Doppler
probe that's essentially detecting the pulse. So we can look at it here, we look at it at the ankle.
So before we have anybody do any exercise, we just lie them down. We slowly inflate whatever cuff
we're going to use because the cuff size matters. It's going to totally change the pressure applied.
So we slowly inflate it until we don't hear any more flow. And then we take a percentage of that.
So if the arterial occlusion pressure, which is the lowest pressure of which there is no flow,
if that's a hundred millimeters of mercury, then we'll typically apply anywhere between
40 and 80 millimeters of mercury in our lab at least. Yeah. So two points I want to make and
or 1.1 question. The point I want to make that is a very important one that you just
made is that this idea of cuff size matters, right? Because the pressure and the force are
related by the area that that cuff takes up. So is it safe to say that the wider the cuff,
the lower pressure you need to reach occlusion? Yes, that's definitely true.
And I think some people interpret that to mean that does that mean that a wider cuff is better
because the pressure is lower? I would say no, because it's pretty much relative. Some would
argue that the wider the cuff is, you might actually attenuate some of the growth beneath the cuff,
but certainly the size of the cuff will change the pressure. So as you said, the wider it is,
the lower the pressure that you need. But again, as long as you apply whatever cuff that you're
going to use to whatever limb you're looking to exercise, taking one measurement can account for
everything. So then my question is, when you say 40 to 80 percent, that is a very wide range, right?
That's like the difference between 40 millimeters of mercury and 80 millimeters of mercury. When
100 millimeters of mercury is the occlusive pressure could be the difference between comfort
and discomfort as an example, right? Yes. So typically we use 40 percent.
40, 40. Yeah, that's the pressure that we use when all we care about is muscle adaptations. In
other words, increasing muscle size and strength. Now you can see the same adaptation at 80 percent
with a little bit less work because you're going to fail sooner.
But the discomfort is going to be much higher. Now, I think the other component of that is that's
muscle adaptation. Now we have some data. It's very preliminary, but some data that suggests that
some of the vascular changes might actually require a higher pressure. So vascular changes,
meaning kind of a change in form, limb blood flow or form conductance. So that's a gross
measurement of basically the vascular network. So there's some indication that maybe you do
need higher pressure for that. But that's one study. We did observe it in both the upper and
lower body, which gives me a little bit of confidence, but it's one study. So but with
muscle, I feel pretty confident saying you can use a moderate pressure, 40 percent or a high
pressure, 80 to 90 percent. And the adaptation is going to be pretty much the same with respect to
muscle size and strength. The discomfort might be or will be quite different, will be much higher
with a higher pressure. How much variability is there between an individual's tolerance for
discomfort at a fixed occlusive pressure? So I love the idea of using 80 percent of
occlusive pressure because now it's not a given number. It's 80 percent for that individual.
So in theory, everybody is experiencing the same amount of relative occlusion. But if you took a
hundred people and let's even make it more homogeneous. If you took a hundred fit people
and you simultaneously applied 80 percent of occlusive pressure to bilateral upper extremities
and just had them sit there. So we'll do the first experiment where nobody does anything.
What is the what would the bell curve look like? How tight would it be for the time at which a
person cries uncle? And the pressure is 50 percent. You pick a number. I said 80, but but I.
Okay. 80. I mean, I don't know the the minute we have done some discomfort studies applying 40
percent and just having people sit. Yeah. So at 40 percent, what's the answer? It's pretty low.
You know, we stopped at four minutes. We didn't have anybody who couldn't do it.
But you are going to have some people who who do experience that as more discomforting than other
people. And but it becomes much greater when you obviously combine it with muscle contraction.
But yeah, you're right. So when we say 40 percent AOP, that doesn't necessarily mean a 40 percent
reduction in blood flow either. That's right. So those are those are two separate things. So
somebody when we apply 40 percent of AOP, the reduction in blood flow might be different
depending on how big the muscle is, a variety of other things. And the discomfort associated with
that will also vary depending on the person. There's some people who we have who, you know,
they perceive almost everything as extreme discomfort, whereas we have people on the
opposite side as well. But in general, we see I can't think of the actual numerical value,
but we have 40 percent is right here. And then with 80 percent, it shifts, meaning that the
average is certainly higher. But there are certain people who, you know, the discomfort they feel at
40 is not different than it is 80 because they already rated it so high. So I mean, that's the
limitation of the scale. But what is the what what is the approximate blood flow restriction that
occurs at 40 percent AOP? How much of the blood flow arterial flow is being limited and how much
Venus pooling is occurring? Yeah, I don't know the actual the percent drop off the top of my head.
It isn't 40 percent. It's on average is a little bit less than that,
depending upon the position, depending on what you're doing. But yeah, in general, I think during
the rest period, you probably do have Venus occlusion because it doesn't take it's not thought
to take a lot of pressure to collapse the vein. So during the exercise, you're obviously pumping
it back out with the muscle pump. But I would say at most of the pressures that we apply, at least at
rest, there is Venus point occurring. Yeah, today, I finished my workout with a set of leg press.
So did 30 reps, rest 30 seconds, 15 reps, rest 30 seconds, 15, rest 30 seconds, 15.
And I'm not sure what hurt worse, just the 30 seconds in between or the actual last two sets,
the 15 reps in the last two sets. I mean, the whole thing was just so wildly uncomfortable.
Again, I'm flying by the seat of my pants, not doing this based on occlusive pressure.
So I don't know how far off I am. It's something I'm looking forward to diving deeper into.
I think you've already convinced me I should be more scientific in my approach because I'm
sort of white knuckling it and putting these things on and screaming for dear life. So I'm
in pain kind of before the I'm sort of I'm very uncomfortable before I start. And even after that
first set of 30, I'm questioning my sanity. Sure. So who knows, maybe I'm going to do a
break. So who knows, maybe I'm applying too much. It would seem that
the directionally, would you have a nomogram of occlusive pressure versus expected number of reps
at a percentage of one rep max? Yeah, that's also tough. I think
most of the loading that we use is 30%. And to be honest, if we have somebody who's stronger,
they're not getting 30, 15, 15, 15. There's no there's no question they're going to be at failure.
Most of the time when we actually do experiments, we just have people exercise four sets to as many
as repetitions as you can. That way we can at least hold that constant so we can control for effort.
But yeah, I do think that you can use the number of repetitions as a as a as a weak
surrogate of blood flow restriction. So I would say that if you're using 20 or 30%,
you should be getting close to 30 repetitions each set. No, no, for the first set. So and then close
to 15, you may get 12. But if you can't get 30 on the first one or get close to that, the load is
probably too high or the wraps are too tight. I would say that if you're in pain before you're
starting, it's too tight. And you know, we've we've done a lot of work on practical restriction as
well. I would say that practical meaning, we don't really know how much pressure is being applied,
we're applying a knee wrap. That's what I refer to as practical blood flow restriction.
I think if you are rehabbing, or you're in a clinical setting, are you working in that,
I think you really need to know the pressure that you're applying. Yeah, I think if you're
a healthy person in the gym who wants to use blood flow restriction, I don't think it's all
that important to know the pressure. Assuming you have the discussion that we're having now where
I know the load is low, I apply the wraps, I'm in pain, well, then the wraps are too tight.
So I loosen them up. And then I can get close to 30 reps, and then close to 15 on the last three
sets. Now on the last one, depending on how strong you are, you might fail pretty quick in that fourth
set. That's okay. So but I do agree with you that I think that you can use goal repetitions as a way
to have some idea at the level of restriction that's being applied. So when you're at 40%
occlusive pressure, what would be the kind of maximum period of time you would let a subject
stay under that pressure, both in terms of the combined lift recovery period? Yeah, I think if
they're just starting out, I think it one, it depends on are they resistance training or are
they doing kind of low intensity aerobic exercise? If it's low intensity aerobic exercise, you can
probably keep it on for 30 or 40 minutes, because it doesn't feel that discomforting, because you're
exercising at a low intensity, the cuffs are not all that tight, you're not building up a tremendous
amount of metabolites, probably why you're not also getting a tremendous amount of adaptation.
But with resistance exercise, I think if you're just starting out, I think it's hard to have a
minute, I think maybe seven, eight, nine minutes, 10 minutes or so. I would say one exercise is a
good place to start. We've done it early on, we did multiple exercises for people who are untrained,
and that's pretty tough. But I would say, you know, start off with four sets of an exercise and then
take the cuffs off or take the wrap off. And then you might be able to eventually work up to a couple.
But I wouldn't with resistance training, I don't think that, you know, you should leave it on
continuously for probably more than a few exercises. But if you've never done it, I wouldn't go beyond
one, just so you can start to kind of see what it feels like. And so if 40 to 80% of occlusive
pressure is the technical way to do it. What other metric do you, would people use if they don't
have access to a Doppler? Yeah, I think, for example, if somebody knew their blood pressure,
I can see why that would not necessarily be, I can see why systolic blood pressure would not
be the same as occlusive pressure. Is it a reasonable proxy? Not always. It really depends
upon if the size of the cuff that you're using is very similar in size, then you could you could do
that and base the pressure as a percentage of your systolic pressure. I think the average gymgoer,
I think one of the things that you could do is, you know, apply the wrap as a percentage of your
resting limb size. So there's some data that's done that's used that one of the ways that we've
tried to work with is condition people to feel what 40% supposed to feel like. So you would have
to have the device one day. So we're doing this because there are some places that are applying
this to clinical populations, where they have only a small amount of time with the patient,
and then they send them home to do exercises. So the idea being is that you could be with the
patient, have them feel what 40% supposed to feel like, and then say when you get home, try to mimic
this pressure. So we've had some success with that. We are able to get people to on average rate
around 40%, but the individual level is anywhere between 20% and 60% of AOP. So it's not terrible,
but it's not very good yet. One of the things that led us to that is that initially,
I was on a paper a long time ago that said you should rate the pressure based on 7 out of 10,
because that can make sure that the pressure will be sub-inclusive. And that's overall pretty much
true. The issue is, is that you have a tremendously wide range, and it's not reliable, meaning that
on day one, you might say 7 out of 10 is 90% AOP. The next day, it might be 10%. So we don't really
recommend that scale anymore. We're interested in this idea of conditioning and or using a percentage
of a resting circumference, and or what we talked about earlier, we use repetitions as kind of a goal.
Yeah, that's, I mean, the cups I have are super cheapo cups, I feel like I want to invest in
sort of nice ones. But the one thing they have on them is numbers. So I've got a sense of like,
on arms, I need to be between 7 and 8, and on legs between 11 and 12.
And sometimes I just overcook it. And after the first set, I have to loosen them if I want to
have any hope of completing the exercises. And then going back to weight, 20 to 40% of One Rep Max
is about the place you like people to be. Yeah, I generally prefer lower, meaning around 20 or 30%.
There are some people who creep up to 40. And so I just think that the real utility of using
blood flow restriction is the fact that you can use it with very low loads. So I think that's the
benefit. We have we've tried to combine it with high loads and different aspects. And other people
have run training studies with it, but it's not additive. So it doesn't add anything more to
high load training. And it's probably because, you know, high load normal exercise is a maximal
stimulus. So it's hard to maximize something that's probably already pretty much maximal.
In a given training session. So that's why I'm like, if you want to lift with heavy weights,
then just do that. I think the utility of using blood flow restriction is with that you can use
lower loads. Any playing with the speed, either concentrically or eccentrically? And does that
matter? I think if the slower you go, the less repetitions you're obviously going to be able to
do. I don't think that it probably matters overall too much, especially for growth. The pace that we
typically use is about one second up, one second down. So relatively quick pace. Some people use a
second and a half. So if you use a second to a second and a half, it's usually a nice controlled
movement. So we haven't messed with too much in the lab. But I don't think it would matter too
much. I think it would alter how much work you were able to do and a load that you would be able
to use more than anything. And do you think that ultimately time under tension is all that's going
to matter? So if you do it slower, but you get fewer reps, it's still okay if you have the same
time under tension? Yeah, for the most part. Yeah, I think because when we think about muscle growing,
at least when I think about a muscle growing where it requires a muscle to be activated for a
sufficient duration of time for all those signaling pathways to be turned on. So from my
perspective, there's a lot of different ways for that to occur. You know, you can use really,
really heavy weights, you know, repeatedly, and that will do it. Or you can use low loads,
or you can use very slow pace as well. I think all of those are kind of doing similar things. You're
recruiting these more and more and more fibers, activating them and signaling them to grow. So
yeah, I think it would be very similar. Then how much rest are you prescribing?
I did 30 seconds today. Sometimes I do like a super set where I'll do, you know, one muscle,
another muscle, another muscle, and just go back and forth with two different muscles
and not take an act or take a passive rest. What do you what do you think about those approaches?
Yeah, I think in general, we use about 30 seconds. That's the standard one that we use in our lab.
I think when I've experimented in the gym, I think that super setting works really well,
especially if you are working out of muscle that's not necessarily directly under blood flow
restriction. So for example, the chest, you know, there is some idea that just doing a standard
bench press exercise with blood flow restriction around the around the arms would augment the size
of the chest. There's some data that indicates that to me, I think a lot of that is driven by
the fact that the muscles distal to the cuff, the triceps are fatiguing, and the chest is picking
up the load. So in the gym, I like to experiment with that. So do is do some chest and then super
set with some tricep extension or something like that. But we haven't studied that in the lab,
but that's those are things that I've messed around with in the past. That's interesting. You
know, I've never thought to do something like a bench press with it, frankly, mostly out of fear
is this. But I guess if you adjust the weight low enough, it shouldn't really be that much of an
issue. What about is I mean, once I did deadlifts restricted, and I wasn't sure if it was a great
idea, I mean, I was it was very lightweight. It was probably like 135 pounds. So it was not,
you know, the type of weight I felt like I could ever hurt myself with. But I was like,
okay, well, let's do 30 reps here of 135 pound deadlift under restriction. Truthfully, I thought
it was pretty freaking cool. I think in the end, I didn't keep doing it because I was like, well,
look, I don't want to develop bad habits deadlifting under such fatigue. Is there what's your thought
on doing complex, you know, multi joint movements? There is data looking at bench press squat.
And they have seen some benefits. I generally agree with you. I think that you can do those,
assuming that you're using lightweight, I tend to prefer kind of isolation movements, especially if
the goal is growth. But you could you could do them. I think that you'd have varying success
depending on the movement, the deadlift. I mean, if it's a Romanian type deadlift, maybe I could
see that having maybe some sort of benefit. But I think I'd have a similar thought as you it's like,
am I going to change my mechanics somehow and then put myself at risk and then really require
blood flow restriction in order to train because I'm hurt. So yeah, you can do compounds that
there's certainly evidence that suggests that it can help with the squat, help with the barbell
bench press. We tend to use isolation movements and for research purposes, obviously. But I tend
to feel that a little bit better. And I feel a little bit safer doing those types of exercises.
Well, let's talk about risks because I know that when people think about blood flow restriction,
I've had people ask me, you know, are you worried about RABDO? Are you worried about nerve damage?
You know, are you basically what are the risks of this? And what's what's the safety profile?
Sure. So I think that's a completely reasonable kind of response when you're telling people that,
hey, I'm restricting blood flow. And I think you should might consider it. I think the first
response that I would hope a person would say is, what's the safety of that? I think a couple things.
One, it helps to understand that this is a very acute response. In other words,
we're restricting blood flow for minutes, not for hours. So I think that that's important. I think
the safety profile overall is comparable to that of high load exercise or traditional exercise.
There are two concerns that people generally bring up. First is blood clotting. Second is muscle
damage. In other words, does it increase the risk of blood clots? Does it increase the risk
of muscle damage? And I think those are the way I stated that is how it should probably be stated.
So any time we exercise or any time we wake up and live, as you know, there's a risk. There's
always a risk for something to occur. In my mind, the question, the important question is,
not is there a risk, but when we add blood flow restriction, does it increase the risk?
And it doesn't appear to at least at the group level and mostly healthy individuals.
So it doesn't increase the risk of blood clots. And that has been looked at in some clinical
populations as well, which is good. It doesn't increase the risk of muscle damage. You will get
sore, but when we look at the fiber, it appears to be intact. So it doesn't appear to be some
structural damages at all. And have there been studies where they've measured CK levels and
contrast them with and without restriction? And does there appear to be more breakdown,
at least measured by CK? Now, generally when they look at most of those, there's not a whole lot of
difference between the same exercise without blood flow restriction. There's certainly soreness
that I feel confident about, but not necessarily structural damage.
Another one that's been kind of brought up is the blood pressure response to this exercise.
So it's true. So proximal to the cuff, is blood pressure going up centrally in the heart,
the aorta, the brain? Yeah. And compared to the same exercise without it, it usually is higher.
But it's usually comparable to that. It's not a little bit lower than high load exercise.
So I think the key component of that is, of course, it's probably going to be higher. You're
restricting blood flow, but how high does it get and how quickly does it return back to baseline?
So I think that those are kind of two important components. Now, when we've compared it to high
load exercise, it's usually pretty similar. And it usually comes back down to baseline within five
minutes, that those are healthy individuals. Now, there was a paper written on it suggesting that
that's great, but there are certain populations where they may hyper respond to that. And
I think that's a good point. So I do think that it might be something to consider if you have
some sort of clinical element you might want to, you know, if you might be hypersensitive
to that reflex, that might be something to really think about. In myself, I would, when I think about
doing unrestricted heavy movements, so, you know, five to eight reps of deadlifts or, you know,
something where I'm really going for it, that feels like I have a much higher blood pressure
than the blood pressure I feel like I'm under doing blood flow restriction, even though
there's a much greater discomfort with the blood flow restriction.
I never really get the feeling like my head's going to pop off my shoulders, which I
commonly feel when I'm doing a heavy deadlift. Right. Yeah, I agree. And I think that's,
you know, a lot of the intramuscular pressure all over, you know, a systemic restriction.
Well, yeah, because I think when you're really lifting heavily, the intra-abdominal pressure
is what allows you to do it. And, you know, that's actually compressing the aorta. So it'd be
interesting if you really think about where the pressure matters the most. But I would say that
overall, it does appear to be very safe. You know, that's something that we're, we've been interested
in for a long time. I do think that, you know, as you, as with anything, when you give a drug and a
large, you know, clinical trial, you start to see, you know, some side effects that you've never
seen before. So my guess is, is that it, when it becomes more and more and more popular, we will
find there will be certain rare events that we've never seen before. But I think in the actual
studies that have been done, we see it to be overall relatively safe. It doesn't increase
the risk at least, assuming it's done appropriately.
Has the following experiment ever been done where you take, well, in an ideal world, I guess you
take the same subject, right? So you have them do the exact same exercises for the same number of
reps. So you take, let's say 30% of one rep max and do the 30, 15, 15, 15. But one of the arms is
occluded, the other is not. So the one that's not is not hurting at all. That should be pretty easy
to do that in the un-occluded side, correct? Correct. So you're exercising one arm under
blood flow restriction, the other arm is not? Correct. But you're using the same weight,
the same reps, the same rest, everything. Yes. I think, yes, that the
Shinohara, for example, same workload, one had blood flow restriction, the other one didn't,
that was within subject. I think that those studies have been done. I think the criticism
on within subject studies is with respect to strength, not necessarily muscle growth,
because some people think that, not some people, I mean, it is an observable fact that when you
train one side, but not the other, the other arm oftentimes can increase in strength. But I'm not
sure that that happens when both limbs train. I think the limb actually responds to the local,
what it's been trained to do. So I don't know that it's that big of a limitation with strength,
but yeah, those studies have been done. And what are they finding typically when they're
under the same load, one side is restricted, one side is not, is the restricted side still making
gains in strength and or size? Yeah, generally the blood flow restriction will be better
than a work-matched control, even if it's the same person with the caveat that it's not to failure.
And that's the difficult thing if you're using 30%, because 30% for some people,
you know, that you'll be reaching failure almost on four sets in the non-included arm. So I think
that should be stated. I think when we have one limb trained to failure, the other limb
trained with blood flow restriction to failure, we've done those studies lots.
The adaptation is usually pretty similar, but the volume, the exercise volume needed
is much lower with the blood flow restriction limb.
Yeah, that's what I was sort of going to get at, which is,
is blood flow restriction mostly just a tool to increase or decrease the time to failure
and therefore act as a more efficient means to fatigue the various fibers.
I think that's fair to say with a couple of potential things to consider. I think
blood flow restriction by itself, so just the application of restriction and deflation
and some ACL reconstruction, post-surgery environment has shown to have some sort of
benefit. So that suggests to me that there could be something to the restriction of blood flow.
Same thing when we have people walk very slowly. In other words, they're not really walking to
failure or even close to failure, but there does appear to be some adaptation. It's not close to
what you see with resistance exercise, but there's something that's a little bit more there.
So I think with resistance exercise, that might be a very fair statement to say that you're just
causing the muscle to have to activate more of the muscle sooner and fatigue sooner than a
non-included condition. I think that's fair, but to say that that's the only thing, the only benefit
of blood flow restriction, I don't know that we can say, especially considering the vascular
response I talked about earlier, that the vascular network, the blood flow, the resting blood flow
to the forearm or calf, it does appear to respond with a higher pressure, but not a lower pressure,
despite that both of them are doing a tremendous amount of work. So I think it might be fair to
say with muscle, with respect to resistance exercise, but I have some remaining questions
before I would go all in. So let's get back to something that we touched on earlier, but we'll
get to it in more depth, which is the relationship between strength and hypertrophy. It's very clear
that they're correlated. It's not clear which way the arrow of causation runs, if it necessarily,
if there is a causal relationship between them. What's the conventional thinking on this?
The conventional wisdom or the conventional thinking is that once muscle growth is there,
that it's probably contributing to changes in strength. And I think that's the textbook
definition. Neural first, followed by large contributions from muscle hypertrophy.
And I think doing a lot of research in the low load realm, as we've done, I started to really see that
maybe that's actually not the case, because we almost always see muscle growth, which is similar
to or equivalent to that of high load exercise. But the strength, assuming that we're not
practicing the test repeatedly, is almost always less. And in my mind, I had a hard time
coming up with a lot of excuses. I did for several years. But at some point, I just,
you know, talk and talking with my students, we just started to ask the question about,
well, where did this story come from about muscle growth, playing a role? And why do we even think
it in the first place? Because I'm trying really, really hard to make excuses for why we aren't
seeing it. But maybe we should go back to the beginning and see why do we ever think it in the
first place. And that's where I think it really becomes difficult for people to have this
conversation, because everybody has learned the same thing that I learned. It's neural,
then hypertrophy, neural, then hypertrophy. And they have a hard time kind of going, you know,
taking a step back and going, okay, but were those studies ever able to actually make that claim?
Yeah. So what where did that hypothesis come from? What is the evidence in support of the
null hypothesis? I think if you were to get a bunch of people together, so and we measured
muscle size, and we measured strength, on average, people who are bigger will be stronger. People who
are smaller will be weaker. And that's, that's true. And we've seen that we've documented that
ourselves. But that's not an effective exercise, because we see the same relationships and people
who have never exercised in their life. So the question that sorry, just to make sure understand
that, Jeremy, you're saying that the correlation or association between strength and size is equally
strong in the untrained as it is the trained? Correct. Yeah. So the question that's being
asked by or the question that we're discussing is when a person begins to exercise,
and then they get stronger, is that due to changes in muscle size? And that's where I have the
question. I don't question whether or not they're related. I completely agree that they are.
But when we exercise, does a change in one result in a change in the other? So I think
people I think it obviously makes a lot of sense that it could, for all the reasons that we said
earlier, we're increasing actinimized, we're increasing this protein, why would they not then
produce greater strength? But there's numerous times in the literature where we have shown
greater changes in muscle size, but strength doesn't even change. So that leads me to believe
that there could be quite a bit of disconnect with respect to muscle growth and the change in string.
Now you wrote a paper basically trying to go back to the root of this dogma. And I think you
basically found that there were sort of three papers that formulated this viewpoint. Two of them,
I think, were from the 70s. And then one was kind of a review paper of one of those papers. Am I
remembering this correctly? Yeah. So the one that's commonly cited as more tiny and diverse or
derived. And they had five individuals, one arm lifted weights, the other arm did not lift weights.
And they were basically inferring muscle growth of changes in service EMG. So they did measure
arm circumference, but that wasn't the variable they were using to quantify growth.
They were looking at changes in the slope of this integrated EMG. So if they saw a change in the
slope, they inferred that to mean muscle growth. If they didn't see a change in that slope,
then they said that was neural. So that's where this can you explain to me how that were. I don't
I don't know enough about EMG to understand that inference. One, I think, at least in my opinion,
you cannot infer growth off the change in EMG. But what they were doing is is that, let's say,
let's pick a variety of weights. So let's say 10 pounds, 20 pounds, 30 pounds and up. So what is the
EMG amplitude? So but EMG amplitude is essentially an estimate of muscle action potential. So how
much signal do you get when you lift 10 pounds at baseline versus 20, 30, 40, then they would do that
every couple of weeks. So if they lifted 10 pounds and the and the basically the amplitude
was a little bit less, they would infer that that was being picked up by muscle growth.
That's kind of the idea. So the amplitude they're using to assess the neurologic signal.
And over time, they're saying if the neurologic signal is going down, and the and the effort is
the same hypertrophy makes up the difference. Or, for example, yeah, I got it. And I think one of the
the points that we're always trying to make is that guarantees that at some point hypertrophy
is going to be a mechanism. You're not actually testing a mechanism. You're just assuming that
at some point, it will be a mechanism. So that was the same thing with the kai and Fukunaga,
which is the other the other study. So they actually did measure muscle size. And to my
knowledge, that's actually the first study to actually document changes in muscle size
in response to resistance exercise. So what I would call a landmark paper, I really enjoy the paper.
But what they infer is is that if muscle growth changes, then it must be playing a role.
And if it doesn't change, and they got stronger, then it must be neural. And that's kind of the
where we've been at for, you know, ever since. In other words, that when we run a training study,
if you get stronger, but we don't document a change in muscle size, it's neural. If you get
stronger, and we measure changes in muscle size, well, then it was neural and hypertrophy. So to me,
I don't think we can make that claim. Because you're just assuming that the ability to document
it means it's actually doing something with respect to strength, I, I would like to see a little bit
more kind of rigor in that I understand why people would think it, I get all of that and make that
makes sense to me as well. But my question is, is that does it actually and we've approached this
through a variety of different ways, but I think it does help to think about this historically,
where did this come from, and it really does seemingly come from those two studies. And then
Digby sale had a very really great paper reviewing kind of all the work that had been done,
where he suggested that most training studies are only documenting a certain aspect of an actual
person's training age. So they're never going to be able to actually answer this question,
because the studies are too short. But I don't know that that's fair to say, because more time
degrees is eight weeks, which is the same duration as a lot of other studies that have basically
contradicted it. So kind of rambled there a little bit. But yeah, you're right. Those are the three
papers that are commonly cited for this neural first, followed by hypertrophy.
Even outside of BFR, which seems to provide a very elegant tool to test the hypothesis,
as you've explained, and we'll get into in a little bit more detail.
It seems that you could do other experiments to test this even without blood flow restriction.
For example, couldn't you have somebody do workouts where they only do one to five reps
of exercises, and they're basically always functioning, and each of those is to failure.
If you're doing one rep, it's a one rep max. If you're doing two reps, it's 95% of one rep max.
If it's three reps, it's probably 90%. If it's five reps, it's probably 85% of one rep max.
And so you cycle through those workouts where you increase strength. In fact,
put a very practical example to this. I know specifically athletes who train this way,
and they train with a trap bar, and they do not do the eccentric motion. So they lift the weight
up and drop it, lift the weight up and drop it, and they're never going above five reps.
So they're really trying to maximize strength, which comes more from the concentric movement,
and they're trying to minimize any hypertrophy because they're athletes for whom strength to
weight is the most important ratio. So it's very typical workout for runners.
So they'll dramatically increase their strength without adding size. And then you could compare
that to the opposite type of workout where you do more of a bodybuilding workout. You're probably
never going below eight reps, and you'll get bigger. And I could imagine a scenario where you
don't even get as strong as that other person. I mean, wouldn't that demonstrate how uncoupled
these two metrics can be? Yes, I agree with you. And we've done this several times now.
We've tried to address this question via study design, doing something very similar to what you
said, where we have one group that's training just doing the one RM test. That's it. They come in,
they work up to about five total reps, and then they go home because we're trying to maximize
the strength signal that not get growth. Because essentially, to answer this question, we have to
know if the muscle did get bigger and stronger, what would strength look like if muscle growth
had not occurred? So when we look at the traditional training group, we have them doing
about eight to 12 reps. And this is a very simple movement, the bicep curl. In that group, we see
muscle growth, and we see a change in strength. Now, what previous or what a majority of articles
would do is say, given that muscle growth is there, that muscle growth must be contributing
to strength. In our mind, we have to say, well, what would strength look like if growth
hadn't been there? And when we look at the other group that was just doing one RM,
the strength is the same. Now, it's not greater, but it is the same. I do think that the more
complex the movement becomes, the greater that separation starts to happen. So we were doing
a barbell bench press. My guess is that the group doing one RM or close to a one RM would be far
better than an eight to 12. But it's just the fact that the movement is very, very simple. So
similar to what you said, in our mind, this does provide some method of trying to address this,
because we see a group with no growth compared to a group with growth, but the strength is the same,
suggesting that that change in muscle size is not necessary for a change in strength,
nor does it appear to be contributing given that the strength is the same. Now,
there are limitations with that. One of the big ones is that in order to get that differential
in growth, we had to apply slightly different exercise patterns. So one group was doing eight
to 12. Still a high load, but not 100 percent where we had another group training at 100 percent.
So some suggested that, well, that's not really that fair of a comparison. There's more things
that are different than just the muscle growth. And that's that's true. And they suggested that
instead that we should follow that up with some mediation analysis where we look at how much of
this change relative to a control is driven by muscle size within each group individually.
And when we did that, we did not see any mediation, meaning that none of the change in strength could
be explained by that change in muscle size in either one of the groups. Explain that more for
me. I'm not sure I follow how you would determine that. So there are some statistical kind of a
approach is where you can do some causal mediation. In other words, you can look at the
relationship between let's say we have these two exercise groups. So instead of looking at them
head to head, let's look at them individually compared to a group that's not doing any exercise
at all. That way we can kind of really control for the random error across time. So measurement
noise, random biological variability, etc. Essentially, what mediation is doing is saying,
okay, we have this group here. How much strength did they gain? So they got stronger. So that's a
direct relationship. So when this group exercises, they got stronger. Now mediation says, okay, let's
add in a variable here to see if we can remove this relationship either partially or completely.
So if we add in muscle growth to the model, and then this group no longer correlates with
strength, then we'll know that that relationship is completely driven by this, this other variable.
Now we wouldn't expect for it to be completely right, but if you respect for it partially,
but that's we didn't see that in either one of the groups is the contra positive then that it's not
at all coupled. Because if you were to ask me what my intuition is, which is worth maybe a warm
bucket of hamster vomit, my intuition would be there is an association, but it's not a, it's not,
it's not a hundred percent causal. So, you know, like the R squared might be 0.5, not 0.99.
So in other words, I would not guess that there is no association. I certainly wouldn't guess a
negative association, but I wouldn't guess that it's one to one causal. Can the mediation tease
that out? Yes, because it would be a partial mediation and that's, and you did not see a partial
mediation. No, we didn't see any effect at all. Now there are other potential reasons. I mean,
we have to think about random error across time with our measurement and things of that. I don't
think that any of the work that we have done so far can conclusively say that it plays no role.
But I do think that we're having an accumulating amount of evidence that's suggesting that
if it does play a role, it is so small that we aren't able to ever detect it. So
I am not sure that muscle growth in response to exercise is a mechanism. I've seen no experimental
evidence that suggests that that's the case. Now for a practical pragmatic person, what would that
mean for them? Well, I think what it can mean is, is that if you are interested in maximal strength
and getting as strong as possible, you probably don't care whether it's a mechanism or not. You
just want to know how do I get strong? I think we can learn a couple of things from some of these
experiments. One, that there's a huge specificity component, meaning that if you want to be a very
good squatter, a very good deadlifter, and being very good squatter or being a very good deadlifter
means you're able to lift as heavy as possible one time, then that means you should be training
at least a good portion of the time at or close to that one RM. Now, if you really believe that
growth might be playing some role, what that might mean for you is to say, well, if it is playing a
role, it might be pretty small. So maybe I can allocate less overall time to it, which would be
good for most strength athletes, because that's typically what requires a lot of recovery. Because
you're doing a lot of volume to see to make a muscle grow. So I become more skeptical of muscle
growth as a mechanism every year that goes by. We're still doing more experiments to try and
address this. But there certainly is no evidence right now that suggests that it is a mechanism.
We have a lot of evidence that suggests that it isn't. But I do think it'd be premature to say,
well, we've completely ruled it out. I don't think that's fair to say at all.
So what are some other explanations? I mean, I guess nobody's disputing the neurologic component
to this. Is one hypothesis that that is the entirety of it? Or do you think that there is
another mechanism that isn't fully clear? Yes, I think some people would say that
some people are of the opinion that the exercise induced changes are probably predominantly neural.
I'm not there yet. I think that there could be some local changes at the muscle.
And that might be able to explain why some groups get stronger. That's not just neural. In other
words, maybe the muscle at the local level is actually getting better at responding to
forceful contractions. So maybe it's how it deals with calcium or how the myosin head binds.
Maybe there's some alterations there qualitatively that aren't due to muscle size.
But I don't know what those would be necessarily. I can only offer potential reasons. And I think
that's usually the argument that's brought up mostly against our point is, well, if muscle
growth is not a mechanism, then what exactly is it? And I don't think that that's a fair argument,
honestly, because I don't know that you have to know for sure what something is to say,
we don't have a lot of evidence for this. And there's a lot of evidence against this.
But that's just my kind of thinking. But I do think that there probably is a huge neural component.
But I don't know that there there isn't something going on at the local level
that is independent of a change in muscle size. But but it is still muscular, perhaps.
So how common is BFR with athletes today?
I think it's becoming more and more common. I know at Ole Miss, for example, as well as a lot
of other Division One schools in the athletic department, I would say a large portion of them
do have blood flow restriction devices. So they are using it for rehab. And I know that I've seen,
you know, players on ESPN, and the NBA NFL using blood flow restriction as well. So I do think it's
rehab, exclusively, or do you see them using it when they're not injured as well?
I think there's a couple NBA players just looking at some of the stories where they were using it,
not for rehab, but just as an everyday kind of way to train where they were able to recover just a
little bit faster. And they don't have to have a as they've aged, you know, they want to make sure
that they're ready to play on the actual court instead of just spending all their time recovering
from their workout. So I think that they they perceive this as one option to use, where they're
able to get some kind of workout in but maybe recover quite a bit faster than they might doing
normal exercise. Is the is the speed of the recovery a function of less trauma to the muscle
during the workout? Or why is their recovery quicker? That's a good question. I think I don't
know that we know that. But I it does appear that when they're able to when they when they are
injured, and they're working out with blood flow restriction, they're able to usually to get a
little bit more out of that compared to high load exercise, or at least very similar to that, but
they have less pain during the movement. So maybe they're able to get a little bit more out of the
rehabilitation than they normally are. Because maybe they're before they're inhibited to a greater
degree with by pain that's reduced a little bit through the application of blood flow restriction.
But I don't I don't really know, to be honest. If let's take an extreme bodybuilder, right,
where they're not being judged at all on strength. I mean, I've yet to see a bodybuilder who's not
very strong, but presumably due to that just the overwhelming amount of volume in their training.
But you know, I even talked about this with Lane on the podcast. And he was explaining how, look,
at the end of the day, the volume is what's going to matter. And you know, you can do that with
isolated movements, you can do that with compound movements, but you just need to get lots and lots
and lots of volume across these kind of ranges. So if the goal is purely hypertrophy, which at
least during part of the bodybuilder, but the bodybuilder cycle is the case, how would how would
they utilize BFR? First of all, would it be a valuable tool above traditional training? And if
so, what would be the optimal way to use it? Yeah, I think it could be. It could be a tool if that's
how they choose to use it. I think for muscle growth, I think I agree with Lane that it really
comes down to personal preference, because even without blood flow restriction, we've seen from 30%
up to 80% or even higher can produce the same amount of muscle growth. So I think that allows
you to have some level of preference on based on how you feel that day or what you enjoy.
I think that there are days where if you have a heavy day, for example,
and you're going to the gym, but you don't feel good, or you're not psychologically have it.
And it could be potentially dangerous for you to use a heavy weight, because you're not focused,
then maybe that's a time where you might be able to implement some blood flow restriction.
Because you can use light weights, it doesn't require as much focus.
And you could probably see a lot of the same response, at least with growth.
So another component could be is that it just helps with some variety. You know, I don't think
that variety is necessary, per se, for muscle growth to be optimal. But I think if you're
training for an extended period of time across your life, things can get pretty boring if you're
just doing the same thing all the time. So it could be a way to try and spice it up a little bit.
And then obviously, if you're hurt, it could be a great tool to use, because there is a lot of,
or becoming to be more and more evidence that it's helpful in the rehabilitation world.
So I think there's a variety of ways that it can be used. But I do think that it's probably
important to note that if a person is not comfortable with it, they don't have to do
blood flow restriction in order to optimize how much muscle that they can grow. But it is a tool
that could be potentially quite effective for them. Yeah, actually, the example you gave
is exactly what happened today, which was today's main set for me was a five by five deadlift. So
obviously, that's, you know, a heavy day. And I took five sets to warm up to get to the starting
weight. That first set of five, I was like, Yeah, this I just I'm struggling. Second set,
still struggling. Third set struggled more. Fourth set, I was like, boy,
and I'm supposed to be escalating the weight. And on the fifth set, two reps in, I thought,
this is the day you hurt yourself, because I'm going to break my form to get number three,
four and five. So I actually just stopped. And that's why I went and did the leg press
with blood flow restriction, which was a very lightweight. I mean, I don't even remember how
many pounds it was, but it was the type of weight that if I wasn't restricted would have, you know,
I could have done 100 reps, I'm sure. So but it was a great way to mix up the training. And
then that's the kind of stuff I'm interested in exploring. I also kind of think of this as a tool
for people who maybe don't have some of the the technique to do heavier lifts, much in the same
way I've sort of thought of the super slow lifting protocols as reasonable protocols for people who
just don't have either the, you know, desire to train at higher volume and frequency and or
don't have the technical chops. Now, that said, I've always felt that the problem with super slow
training is unless it's done to failure, which is upsettingly painful if you've tried those workouts,
it's probably not nearly as beneficial as traditional training. You know, the sort of super
slow advocates will say it's on par with traditional training, right? You could do 20 minutes once or
twice a week and have the benefits of six hours per week. I'm not sure that that's true, even from
a hypertrophy standpoint. But if it is true, it's probably limited to the few people who truly can
fail. And I don't know if you've ever tried these super slow workouts, but it's it's very difficult
to truly fail. I think, you know, it's very hard for I think most people. Yeah, a long time ago,
but I never did much with it. There was somebody in my that I worked with in my PhD who was very
interested in it for a while. But yeah, I was never really a fan for sure. How come for the same reason
or it just I never felt like I was going to get very strong from doing something like that.
I'm just moving so slow and the weight is usually, you know, so light that I don't know how much that
would be transferring over to something that I was interested in at the time, which was, you know,
to to get as strong as possible. But it's definitely hard. There's no question. But
yeah, I didn't enjoy that form of training. So it's safe to say that the one place I think you
really talked about this already, but I just want to make sure we we put a dot on it. The one place
where it's unambiguous that you need to be doing a traditional lift without restriction is if you're
training for maximum strength of that lift, which again, I don't think most people are doing maximum
strength bicep curls. I don't think that's but but when you start to talk about a bench press,
a squat, a deadlift, a leg press for that matter, if you're if you care so much,
there's probably no substitute for being in that 80 percent to 100 percent one RM.
Is that kind of a safe takeaway? Yeah. And, you know, if you do blood flow shifted exercise with
low loads, assuming it's not extremely low, if you're around 20 or 30 percent, you will get
stronger that it will be much to a much lighter to a much smaller degree than you would with
traditional exercise. I completely agree. Now, now sometimes and I'll just add to that we get this
a lot where it's like, well, you're doing, you know, bicep curls in your study because we're using
bicep curl. It's a it's a it's a research model to answer a particular question. We're not training.
We're not personally training people. So I think sometimes people lose the the reason why certain
things are done. But sometimes people will look at low load literature with blood flow restriction
or even low load literature without blood flow restriction and say, yeah, but look at this study.
They found very similar changes in the strength of high load exercise. And some of those studies
do exist. But the majority of those that that do find that effect, if you look at the methods,
what they're doing is the low load BFR group is doing the one RM every two weeks or every three
weeks. And they're doing it in an effect to try and reset the load so they can assume that they're
progressing. But what they end up doing is practicing lifting a heavy weight. So you're
not actually studying low loads of BFR. You're studying low loads with BFR plus one RM training.
And I think that that's a very important point. And we actually reviewed this.
We published a paper on this topic where we show that when you only look at the studies with low
loads that don't practice doing the one RM test repeatedly, almost all of them lose the high load
exercise. Just again, illustrating the point that it's about lifting heavy weight is the best way
to get better at lifting heavy weight. It doesn't mean that you won't get stronger lifting lighter
weight, but you won't be as strong as you were. So how do we think? Well, let's let me summarize
what you just said, because I think in terms of big picture, there are really two areas where
BFR shines. One of them is in an individual who for some reason can't lift heavy weight,
but still needs to get stronger and potentially bigger. And the obvious example is the person
who's recovering from an injury and then potentially the person who just, you know,
has a concern about lifting heavy weight, either from a technical standpoint or injury avoidance
or things like that. The second place where BFR seems to really stand out is in hypertrophy.
Most of these studies are demonstrating slightly superior hypertrophy response
despite less total volume and certainly lower load. Is that it's at least as good in hypertrophy
and in some cases better is my reading of the literature. When it's compared to,
if you have a low load with BFR compared to a work matched low load group without BFR,
hypertrophy is better almost always. And to make them equal, you will just have to go more on the
you'll have to go to a greater degree of reps on the unrestricted side to failure, basically.
Correct. Yep. And therefore it takes more time to get the same effect. So it's a more efficient
way potentially to generate hypertrophy is probably more accurate than what I said. Right.
And correct. Now the vascular adaptations, again, I keep putting that caveat in because it's always
in my mind because I really expected that to be kind of the same across the board as well,
meaning that as long as you're doing a lot of repetitions, it shouldn't matter whether there's
BFR or not. That's not what we found. Now, whether or not that can be repeated, I'm not sure.
Hopefully we can do that in the future. But because my thinking for a long time was similar
to what you were saying earlier, doesn't really matter whether there's BFR or not. If you do
enough, it'll be very similar. The workload would just be less. And I think that again,
it's true for muscle, but I don't know if that's true for every single variable.
Yeah. So let's let's talk about the mechanism by which this is happening. My assumption,
which I don't know if it's right or wrong, is that at least one of the reasons that BFR can produce
so much hypertrophy at such low load is in response to the metabolic challenge that's posed.
And so one of the things I was doing quite a bit was testing lactate levels with and without BFR.
And it's very easy to demonstrate that when you occlude your arm, for example,
will distal to that occlusion lactate is going through the roof because you're exercising that
arm and you're not letting the lactate clear out of circulation. So I'm pinpricking my finger and
getting very, very high lactate levels. And so that's obviously a metabolic byproduct of
any time you're exercising and then especially when you're doing this type of exercise.
And so, yeah, I could demonstrate that I had a higher level of lactate doing blood flow restriction
than not, even when I was lifting slightly more weight and doing something traditional.
Do we think that that matters in this equation? Do we think that that's partially driving this?
Or what? And that's just one of the metabolites that we can measure easily. There's plenty that
we can't. Yes, I would agree. I think that there's kind of two schools of thought. One is that the
pooling of these metabolites in and of themselves is turning on some of these anabolic signaling
pathways, meaning just the fact that you're pooling lactate around the fibers, that that's able to
activate growth. I used to be interested in that idea. We tried to test this using a different,
a couple of different ways. We didn't find an advantage to doing that. So we kind of started
to say, well, maybe there's nothing to metabolize in and of themselves, but maybe it's what they're
causing the muscle to do. So in other words, maybe the way we think about it now is, is that, as you
said, you're exercising with blood flow restriction, the metabolites are being trapped. What we think
is, is that they're augmenting muscle activation. So they're causing the muscle to have to work
a lot harder than it normally would because you're pulling this lactate around it. And, you know,
you might fatigue some of these cross bridges. So we have to recruit more and more and more and more
fibers. So that's where we think the benefit of metabolites is, is that they're basically
inducing fatigue, which then leads to further muscle activation. And muscle activation for
a sufficient duration of time is the name of the game, at least in my opinion, for making a muscle
grow. So one of the big kind of questions always is, are the mechanisms themselves different?
From traditional exercise. If I do high load exercise, is that going to be a different
mechanism than when I do low load exercise with blood flow restriction? And I don't think so. And
I'll tell you why. I think that the mechanism involved in activation is different.
But once the fiber is activated, all the signaling pathways, from what I understand,
are going to be very similar. So when we lift a heavy weight, it requires a tremendous and muscle
activation to even lift one rep. If you are trying to do a bicep curl, and you're only activating a
small portion of your fibers, and you're trying to lift 70 pounds if your one or m is 100 pounds.
Right. That's an enormous bias. I was about to say I really feel pretty pathetic here. Yep.
Go ahead. So choose choose any left. Right. In order to lift that heavy weight, you need to
activate a large portion of your musculature. Otherwise, the weight isn't going to move.
Compared to low loads, where you don't need to activate the same amount of muscle fibers
initially, because the weight is extremely low. So when we exercise with low lows in BFR,
we're activating only a small amount initially. But those metabolize, as you discussed,
start to become trapped. And we activate more fibers, more fibers, more fibers, and more fibers.
And then by the end, we've activated a similar amount of fibers as we did with high load exercise.
By the way, is there an order in that? So if you're one RM bicep curl is 100 pounds,
and then without. So with no blood flow restriction, you pick up 80 pounds and bang out,
I don't know, 10 reps, eight reps. Compare that with if you picked up 40 pounds and banged out
40 reps. What is happening from a fiber fatigue standpoint under those two scenarios?
In general, we have what we call the Henneman size principle, where you recruit type one motor units
first. And then as you as you require, based on the exercise, you recruit type two in addition
to type one. So when you lift a heavy weight, you're getting to the type two is very quickly,
because you need them. Whereas with lower weight, you probably are taking a little bit of time,
but then you are eventually getting to those type two motor units.
So if the person in my example fails at eight reps with 80 pounds and 40 reps with 40 pounds,
it's just that the 40 reps took a lot longer to burn through the type one fibers and then the
type two A's and the two A B's. And then finally at the very end, the two X failed. Whereas the
when he did the same exercise, you know, 20 minutes later at 80 pounds and failed at eight reps,
he just got he did the same sequence, but he just got to the two X much sooner. Is that
what you're saying? Yeah. And I and the reason why I say that is if you look at if you pull out
fibers following training, type one and type two fibers have both been shown to grow in both high
load exercise as well as low load exercise with and without blood flow. So they both respond.
Some people have suggested that type one might grow a little bit more with low low training,
but I'm not I'm not convinced on that yet. I think that it's probably very similar to
high load exercise, although I see the thinking, but but yeah, both of them will grow in response
to both types of exercise in general at the extreme level is a bodybuilder's hypertrophy
more explained by type one or type two fibers, or are they both massive relative to anybody else?
Yeah, I would say probably the increase in both, although I don't I'm not there's not one thing I
can point to that would suggest that for me. But I I think that
in response to training, my guess is that both of them would increase.
I think you might be able to make an argument that people who might again go back to our argument
earlier, who start lifting weights and realize, man, I'm actually able to grow quite a bit.
Maybe they already had, you know, more type two fibers to begin with, which is
some think that is more responsive to to loading. So maybe you can make that argument. But I think
in response to extra when a bodybuilder exercises, I would probably guess that both of them are going
to grow both types of fibers. You mentioned very briefly passive BFR. What's the application for
that? Is that in a highly injured person? Yeah, I. And again, there's only a small number of studies
that have shown this. And that could be for a variety of reasons. One, it could be because
those are hard to do, where you have somebody who had ACL surgery, and then we apply blood
flow restriction to their limb. We inflate and then we deflate for a period of time a couple
times a day. And that's been shown to slow muscle loss. But there's only a few studies that have
shown that now the again, you don't see growth. You only see a slowing attenuation of loss, which
is a big, big deal when people undergo surgery. Now that that's my kind of I'm very interested
in whether or not that's true. One of the things that gives me a little bit of pause
is that there's not more of those studies. So in my mind, I always wonder, is that because
those are again hard to do? Or is it because those studies do exist, but they didn't see
anything? They didn't publish it. So I'm cautiously optimistic that that could be useful. But I do
think that as soon as a person can exercise, you know, and we kind of published a paper on this
idea a long time ago, kind of what we view as a progression of blood flow restriction. In other
words, someone who wants to who can't do anything, how do we give them back to doing something?
So we start off with if they can't even walk, we apply this restriction to slow down muscle loss.
Once they can maybe walk on a treadmill or walk very slowly, but they can't lift weights,
we start to transition them to that phase where they're able to increase muscle size
and strength just a little bit, and if nothing else, maintain what they have.
But then once they can transition to resistance exercise, I think that's where
they're going to see the biggest bang for their buck, and then they can go to high
level exercise if they choose. But I do feel like that's a very potential useful progression to this
technique. I mean, this is such an important question. It's a real shame this isn't being studied.
Like again, if I were Czar for a day and I was in charge of where research dollars would be spent,
because I don't think it would take that much money, by the way, but I would
absolutely prioritize this question when you consider the extent of muscle loss that occurs
in sedentary individuals following elective surgery, emergent surgery, and injuries.
So those are three very big buckets of people, disproportionately, by the way, affected
in the elderly, where the effects are devastating. I'm sure you're familiar with the literature of
you take somebody in their seventh decade of life, and you train them very hard for a year,
they'll put on expounds of muscle and then put them in a hospital bed for 10 days. They will lose
all of it. They will lose every ounce that they spent a year diligently gaining to think that
there could be a tool that could slow that. And we don't know the answer definitively,
strikes me as just an unbelievable unwise decision that's been made. So I would hope somebody
who has the authority over where those dollars go is listening to this and realizing that the
morbidity and mortality associated with muscle loss, especially in the elderly, is so significant.
And one of the things we talk about a lot with our patients is, once you get to be 70 and certainly
80 years old, you're kind of one fall away from the end of your life, even if you don't die
directly. So there's the catastrophic fall where you hit your head, you have a cerebral
hemorrhage, and you die. That's not the majority of them. The real fall you are away from the end
of your life is the injury that basically never permits you to get back on your feet. Because
even when you recover from the direct injury, maybe a broken hip, which is common, you never
get back the strength and stamina you once had. And again, I just think BFR should be
explored much more in this population. That should be standard of care if indeed it is effective in
both the passive and then the, as you described, the progression, right? So passive, low end aerobic,
you know, low load resistance. And ultimately, if you can get back to high load resistance, great.
Right. So if you had unlimited resources right now, what experiment would you want to do? What's
the, what are the burning questions that if, you know, Francis Collins called you tomorrow and said,
Jeremy, I've got this extra hundred million bucks. We just, we've got to get rid of it. What can you do?
Huh? That's a good question. I think, you know, I would do something with blood flow restriction,
of course. But, you know, if I had to, kind of my interest right now is related to trying to figure
out why people get stronger. And I think I can always tie that back into, you know, blood flow
restriction and be able to, to, to do things of that sort. But I'm interested in what that means
and what a change in strength from resistance training, what that means for overall function
of a person. So when I get stronger with resistance training, does that actually carry over to
improvements in my walking ability and things of that sort? So those are some things that I'm
interested in. With blood flow restriction, I'd obviously do kind of what you just stated. I'd
have to, you know, probably connect with our med school in order to do a study like that. But I
would be interested in the application of blood flow restriction by itself. I think that that
is something that I've been interested in for a long time. Again, I think it'd have to be not
something we could do right out of my lab. We'd have to work with a hospital, of course,
but I'd be interested in that. And I'd be interested in doing it on a large scale
because all of those studies that currently exist are extremely small sample size. So for, of course,
for a variety of reasons, but I'd want to see it. I want, I'd want to start answering a lot of these
questions with large sample sizes. That would be kind of my dream studies, you know, whatever it
would be, whether it's strength, whether it's this, bigger studies, longer studies. And I think that
a hundred million dollars I could do a lot for sure. Well, amazingly, that's a fraction of a penny
compared to the amount of research that goes into the fact the fraction of dollars that goes into
biomedical research, but that's not necessarily always allocated wisely. Nevertheless, this has
been, this has been a super interesting discussion. Again, you can tell personally, I just want to
understand this for myself, for my patients. And ultimately I think this is a very important topic
for, for anybody who's interested in any aspect of that continuum we discussed. So Jeremy, thank
you very much. And I'm really so glad that Lane connected us. I'm sorry. I didn't have a little
extra alcohol. I know Lane mentioned you always like to have a drink when we start a talk and I
should have thought to have sent out a nice bottle of tequila for you. Or is it Scotch? What
did Lane say is your favorite? It's Scotch, 100%. So, you know, I'll forgive you. You know, maybe we
can do it again and we can maybe have scotch next time. Perfect. A single malt, I assume. Of course.
Yeah. Do you add, do you drink it neat or do you add like the one spoon of water to it?
I drink it neat generally. Okay. I have a friend from residency. So I don't, I'm personally not a
huge Scotch guy. I love tequila and Japanese whiskey. But I love talking to people who love,
who love scotch and can walk me through the ins and outs of it. But this friend of mine,
obviously a single malt guy, would import water from Scotland from a very specific lake. And
he explained to me why you could, the scotch would get a little better and it would open up a little
bit more and be a little less anesthetizing to the tongue. If you would add just this one spoon
of lukewarm water to it. I don't remember the exact reason, but it somehow had to do with
diluting it just a little bit to prevent some of the anesthetic effect. But you're a neat guy,
which I like tequila neat and Japanese whiskey neat as well. So I can, yeah, I'm not quite on
that level of drinking where I'm importing specific water, but I do appreciate a good drink
for sure. I find it interesting, by the way, you know, on the topic of sort of genetics,
I really do think people just genetically can like the taste of scotch or not. And I don't possess
the gene, I think, because I've, I've sampled very fancy scotches and I've never found it palatable.
But I don't doubt for a moment that you or someone who does finds just as much enjoyment in the
actual taste of it that I would, for example, in some of these other things I like. It's interesting
because my students make fun of me for this, but I can't, I can't drink beer unless it's like a
fruity type of beer. So they obviously mock me for that. But I can't drink beer, but I can drink
hard liquor for sure all day. But the beer stuff I can't do unless it tastes like
apple pie or something else. Then I'm all about, I'm on board, but just standard beer can't do it.
I'm with you. I think standard beer is about on par with urine in terms of palatability. So
I've never understood how Budweiser stays in business, but yeah, I can't do really any of that.
All right, gentlemen. Well, thanks so much. This was a super interesting discussion. I
really appreciate it. Thanks for having me on through there.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on.
If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to
peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram,
and Facebook, all with the ID Peteratiamd. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or
whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only,
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare
services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use
of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The
content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any
medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures
and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.