Hey, David, thank you so much for making time in your evening, my afternoon here today.
Very much looking forward to speaking with you about a topic that I think is on a lot
of people's minds lately.
Well, thanks for the invite.
I'm looking forward to it too.
Let's start a little bit with your background.
It sounds like based on what I've read, going back to your early teen years, you've always
had an interest in the brain, whether it be through the lens of neuroscience or psychiatry.
What do you think sparked that interest?
Well, thinking about things.
Yeah, I guess it was understanding that, I don't know, I think when I was probably four
or five, I suddenly kind of realized that actually thinking was what actually made things
make sense.
And then I realized that thinking came out of the brain and I've always been fascinated
by the brain.
And actually I went to university, to Cambridge to do brain science.
I wanted to be a physiologist, like Hodgkin and Huxley to do physiology.
And then I kind of realized actually that that was, single cells are interesting, but
you've got to put the 200 billion together and make sense of those.
And actually that's where, then I did neurology and that got a little bit boring because it's
mostly people kind of dying slowly from diseases like amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.
So then I moved to psychiatry and then it became really wonderful because you see every
aspect of the brain in psychiatry.
Well, it's so funny you say that because I'm not making this up, but this morning, my six
year old son was in my office and we were sort of fumbling around and I have a whole
bunch of racing helmets in my office.
And so he's putting them on and that got him talking about why we're wearing helmets to
protect the brain and blah, blah, blah.
And then I said, well, you want to see what, well, he said, what does a brain look like?
So I pulled up, you know, on Google, I pulled up some images of brains, but actual anatomic
images.
And again, he's only six, but he's looking at this and he's thinking like that's very
unimpressive.
And he sort of says, it just looks like a slimy thing.
And I said, yep, that's true.
That's what it looks like.
And he says, but is this where my thoughts come from?
And I said, yes, that's where your thoughts are rich.
And he said, well, how?
And I got to tell you, it was very difficult for me to explain how electrical impulses
work.
And of course, I'm not going to get into action potentials and neurotransmitters.
But what's funny is it then took me down a rabbit hole of spending 30 minutes on YouTube
trying to find good videos of this for kids.
And if anybody can find one, please send it.
But I couldn't find great videos because the videos that I found were more anatomic, like
this is the part of your brain that controls movement.
This is where memories are stored.
But he was asking a deeper question, which was how does this blob make me think?
Which it sounds like you were asking that same question as a four or five year old.
Exactly.
But what's amusing, even more amusing is my new book, which is coming out later this year,
is called Brain and Mind made simple.
It won't be simple enough for a six year old, unless he's very precocious.
But I have written a book for the general public to try to explain that peculiar phenomenon,
how lots and lots of single nerves can actually turn into all the complexity of the different
forms of consciousness and the different experiences that humans have.
And at some point, and I think the point you raised is a really good one, it'd be really
nice to then migrate that down for children, maybe as a series of sort of comics or graphics.
I mean, it is the most wonderful thing in the universe, the human brain, there's no argument
about it.
So let's get communicating as soon as we can.
Yeah.
And I do think that, like for me personally, it's not a question I ever contemplated early.
So it made me very happy that he was asking this question at the age of six in a deep
enough way.
And look, even if the book is not written for a six year old, I'm sure it will help
me do a better job explaining it to a six year old.
So coming back to your career, so now you've migrated into psychiatry, which of course,
on some levels is really about understanding pathology of the mind, which is effectively
what all parts of medicine are, whether it be neurology or otherwise.
What were some of the first things that stuck out to you about the pathology of the mind
through the lens of a psychiatrist?
Well the first patient I saw who I was dropped into, there was a doctor who didn't turn up,
I'm a medical student.
So I said, oh, please go and interview, go and Clark this new patient.
So I'm sitting there and talking to this person who's not making any sense whatsoever and
kept talking about there being a smell of fish in the room and rambling on about the
smell.
And after about an hour of trying to get some sense, I say, well, thank you.
I'll just have to go.
I'll be back in a minute.
And I go out and I talk to the consultant and he says, oh, wow, he's clearly psychotic.
Oh, that makes a lot of sense.
That's why he doesn't make sense.
And that's why I didn't understand what was going on.
So what was very interesting about that is that the relationship between temporal lobe
disorders, those parts of the brain, which are intimately involved in aspects of consciousness
and also smell.
And there was this peculiar overlap between temporal lobe disorders where you can be
psychotic, but you also have these olfactory hallucinations.
And that's what he had.
So he was hallucinating rather than in his ears, which most people with schizophrenia
do.
He was hallucinating in terms of smell.
So yeah, I've never forgotten that because it was just such a kind of completely bizarre
experience and it made me realize I got a lot to learn.
Now for most people, when they go into psychiatry, and I'm sure this was the case with you, you
spend a lot of time learning the neuropharmacology of the agents that are going to be used to
help treat patients with psychiatric illness.
And for many people, that's sort of where it stops.
But you've also generated or developed this other interest, which is in the neuropharmacology
of these regulated substances, you know, call them illegal or recreational drugs and otherwise.
Where did that interest stem from?
Wow.
Well, so yes, I am a professor of neuropsychopharmacology at Imperial College London.
Neuropsychopharmacology is really the use of drugs to study the brain and to study the
effects of treatments for brain disorders, particularly in the case of psychiatry, psychotropic
drugs.
My PhD was on the GABA system, on drugs manipulating the GABA system.
As an undergraduate, I think, you know, the big influence on me, I was extraordinarily
fortunate.
I'm at university in Cambridge in the early 1970s when people are discovering that the
brain is a chemical organ.
Up to that point, it was thought the brain was an electrical organ.
It was like a very complicated computer or, you know, like some kind of complex telephone
exchange.
But then the concept of chemical transmission came along.
And now we know that there are at least 80 different chemicals, neurotransmitters, hormones,
neurohormones.
And seeing that transformation from electricity to chemistry made me realise, you know, the
way you study the brain now is through drugs which affect the chemistry of the brain.
And then there are these therapeutic agents which are obviously very important, antidepressants,
antipsychotics, anticonvulsants.
But then it raises the next question, you know, but people use other drugs to change
the brain.
And they use them recreationally for, you know, like drugs like cocaine or crystal meth,
or they use them to deaden pain or to get insights like psychedelics.
And after a while, because I've done so much research on drugs, I was asked by the British
government to help them think through drug policy.
Well, actually, that was not true.
They asked me to help them justify drug policy.
But when I started working for them, I realised that the drug policy wasn't in any way evidence
based.
And when I tried to bring evidence to bear on drug policy, they sacked me because it's
much more convenient to have a political decision making about drugs than it is to have an evidence
based one.
What year was that that you got involved in that?
Well, I started working on the principles of assessing drug harms really back in the
1990s.
And it actually came with the rise of ecstasy and people supposedly were seemingly getting
harm from ecstasy.
And I was one of the experts who was asked by the government to come up with a policy
which would reduce the harms from ecstasy.
And it became very clear when we were researching those that the harms of ecstasy aren't from
the drug at all.
They're actually from the what you do when you're on the drug.
They're either from the fact you dehydrate because you dance all night or you get hypothermic
because you're in an environment where you can't cool down.
And so we said and actually we brought in what in legislation in Britain which said
any club which is serving drinks, which is where most people were going to have their
ecstasy, they're going to clubs, they must serve free water.
Because what the clubs were doing were actually forcing people to drink alcohol or pay for
water in order to get hydrated after using ecstasy.
And in fact, they were doing worse.
They were turning off the taps in the they were even turning off the toilet so people
couldn't drink water.
So we've made it law that people had to get access to water.
And we also recommended a good policy would be to have chill out rooms.
And of course, a lot of clubs do have chill out rooms.
And those just those two simple environmental approaches effectively, you know, the very,
very few deaths from ecstasy since then until we got to the modern day when a variety of
international policies have now made ecstasy considerably more harmful than it used to
be.
How much did this coincide with or following lockstep with drug policy in that it states
which really seemed to get a get a real boost in the arm in the early 80s?
Was the UK leading or following?
Oh, every country in the world follows you.
The United Nations United Nations is probably still is paid for by the US.
And it does what the US tells them.
Every single British drug law until 2016 was made at the behest of the Americans.
So you know, America basically, you know, you know, they say America sneezes, the world
catches cold.
America defined drug policy.
It started in 1934 with the the attack on you know, the liberalization of drinking and
the attack on cannabis.
And it continued.
And I mean, of course, the big inflection was when Nixon decided that the war on drugs
was actually a better vote getter than the war in Vietnam.
So he switched people's attention to drugs.
And the world has been fighting a war on drugs, largely funded, but certainly politically
driven by America since then.
So let's talk a little bit about the framework through which one can think about drugs.
I'm a framework junkie.
Everything I think about whether it's, you know, how to order dinner comes down to sort
of a framework.
So you know, some parameters that people might think of, right, you know, how harmful
is this?
And again, you know, I think the goal of frameworks is to have them be as unemotional as possible
and to have them whenever possible to be objective.
So how harmful is something would be part of it.
How addictive is something?
What's the physiologic dependence?
And then even within harm, you could sort of talk about the harm to the individual and
then the harm to society as that individual acts.
Are there any other things you would include or do those three things largely encompass
what you think of as a good way to think about molecules?
Well, that's yeah, that's that is quite a succinct way.
So I started off with something somewhat similar to that.
But more recently, we've developed what's called multi criteria decision analysis.
And it turns out that there are 16 different ways in which drugs can do harm.
There are nine harms to the user.
And there are seven harms to society.
And the societal harms range from international damage, you know, like the US spraying Agent
Orange in, you know, in Colombia to kill to kill cocoa plants through to economic damage,
through to health costs, through to damage the families, etc.
So there are seven harms to society, and nine harms to the user.
And each of those can you can scale drugs on each of those, those 16 scales of parameters
of harm.
And if you do all that and put it all together, and then do a waiting, because obviously,
not every single one of those scales is equally important.
If you do all that, then you can actually very, very transparently and very reliably
rate the harms of different drugs.
And we've used this procedure in Britain, we've used it in Europe, and most recently
in Australia, and pretty much all the drugs always ranked the same in all those, you know,
there's three sort of groups of Western jurisdictions.
So based on that type of a framework, what are the drugs that consistently come to the
top of the list in terms of harm, aggregate harm?
So the most harmful drug overall in all in Europe, in Britain, in Australia is alcohol.
And alcohol is the most harmful drug, because it has way more social impact, more harms
to others than any other drug.
And that, of course, is because it's much more widely used.
You know, 80% of American adults, British adults drink alcohol, pretty much every family
in your country, in my country, know someone that's been harmed by alcohol, either through
themselves, getting a difficulties having accidents getting addicted, or they've been
harmed by other ones, someone who's drunk, a drunk driver, or someone who's drunk and
violent.
But if you look at the harm to the user, alcohol is not number one, alcohol is about number
four, the drugs that are really harmful to the user are opiates, crack cocaine, and also
crystal meth.
So that's super interesting, right?
Because those drugs have very different scheduling, right?
So heroin would be a Schedule I drug, correct?
Cocaine would be a Schedule II drug.
I guess crystal meth would be Schedule I, or would it be Schedule II in the US?
I'm not sure in the, in Britain it's one, but I think I'm not sure in the US to be
honest.
And then of course, alcohol is not even scheduled in that sense, it's regulated only by the
age at which you can legally consume it.
And also by taxation.
Right.
So what we didn't talk about was tobacco.
Does tobacco fit into this framework?
Yeah, tobacco, yeah.
We always do tobacco because tobacco is, this is an interesting paradox.
When we first did this, tobacco came out at about number six or seventh, and the tobacco,
anti-tobacco brigade got really agitated.
They say it is the most harmful drug because it kills more people.
And we said, yeah, but that's right.
It kills more people, but they often die in their fifties and sixties.
Alcohol is killing people in their twenties.
And that's more important, we think.
Our valuation was that the harms of alcohol is considerably greater than the harms of
tobacco.
And I think most people would agree that, you know, tobacco does in the end kill half
of the people who smoke, but it does it later in life.
And it doesn't, tobacco also causes relatively little damage to other people, unlike alcohol.
This is such an interesting question, and I don't even know how one would think about
it because you could also take the flip side, which is there's probably nobody who's benefited
from tobacco.
I shouldn't say that.
There is a benefit to tobacco, which is that probably it helps some people calm down.
It probably helps cope with nerves.
But there's no moderate use of tobacco.
Like smoking only 10 cigarettes a day is protective, or the harm doesn't really kick in until you're
at a pack a day.
No, that's not really true.
Any amount of tobacco is going to take some toll on your pulmonary system and your cardiovascular
system.
Alcohol conversely, you could say, well, look, a person who drinks responsibly, who has,
you know, three drinks a week, bears no cost of the consumption of alcohol from a relative
standpoint.
I mean, we could debate that.
I would argue that there's no dose of alcohol that's healthy, but there are probably doses
that don't rise to the level of toxicity.
Yet to your point, it's much easier to cross the line into acute toxicity, which also gets
to another challenge here.
Tobacco has no acute toxicity.
It's 100% chronic toxicity.
Alcohol has both acute toxicity and chronic toxicity, and it's that acute toxicity that
results in incredible loss of life, both to the individual and to society.
Does the framework allow you to measure these things?
Yes, it does.
We can give you absolute ratings and rankings on both of those variables, acute toxicity
versus chronic toxicity.
And of course, you know, the drugs which really do badly on both of the opiates, which could
kill you instantly when you take them, but also gradually, quite quickly over time as
well.
But there is another angle, and that's, I think, an important angle which our analysis
doesn't bring in because it's difficult and challenging.
And I'd love to.
And, you know, maybe at some point we can do this.
And that's the benefits.
You pointed out quite clearly that generally tobacco doesn't bring many benefits.
Nicotine is a funny drug, though.
It's the only drug we know of that both calms people but also improves attention.
And so there are people who smoke, you know, generally, although they're addicted, they
do get a benefit, at least when the nicotine's in the brain.
But alcohol has a much broader kind of social.
Alcohol is one of the most social drugs.
I mean, after ecstasy, it probably is the most social drug.
And that's why people use it.
So there are unquestionably psychological or social benefits from alcohol.
And that goes back for sin.
Well, that goes back to pre-Christian times.
millennia.
Yeah, that's right.
You know, you've got, you know, Jesus turning water into wine at the wedding at Canine.
Why?
Because wine was what the Jews used to celebrate weddings.
And it's been used ever since.
We all use it.
We still use it today to celebrate.
So alcohol has a very powerful pro-social effect, which I think is why it's so widely
used and why it's been, apart from that little aberration of American prohibition, why it's
actually been stable in our society for many millennia.
And do you think that that's the fundamental reason why despite the sort of, I mean, hypocrisy
of it, if we're going to be blunt, we would make something like cannabis illegal while
having something like alcohol be legal.
Is it, does it basically come down to our social dependence on alcohol?
Now, that's a great question.
And I think, and it's a very interesting, I haven't thought about those two in that
context before, but I think that's a very interesting point you make because cannabis
is not a particularly social drug.
So people, when they get stoned, they tend to be quieter.
They're not, it's not the party drug cannabis, is it?
And it might, you might be right.
It might be that people are less positive towards cannabis because it isn't so socially
enabling as, as alcohol.
That's a very interesting point.
I take a different view up till now, until you said that I've taken a different viewpoint,
which is that people have been very anti-cannabis because the alcohol industry and the Drug
Enforcement Agency have seen cannabis as the enemy and the disinformation that's been
produced, you know, the hatred of cannabis, which started with Harry Anslinger trying
to keep the DEA functioning after alcohol prohibition was disbanded.
You know, that a hundred years almost, why 90 years of disinformation has actually poisoned
a lot of people's minds to cannabis.
So cannabis has been vilified and alcohol has been celebrated.
I mean, it's been celebrated throughout history in terms of art and culture and music and
television.
You know, one of the staggering things, because of lockdown, I've been watching a lot of Netflix
and I've been seeing these disclaimers at the top saying, this program contains product
placement by which they mean usually this program shows people drinking an awful lot
of wine.
Yeah, we've come a long way.
It's an interesting point you raise.
I guess I hadn't thought of it, that part of the DEA needs a reason to exist and therefore
you need boogeymen, right?
If your business is smashing boogeymen, you need boogeymen.
Don't we have enough boogeymen with other drugs like heroin or methamphetamine or cocaine?
I guess I'm confused as to, and I don't want to, this is not going to be a discussion about
the legalization of cannabis because it seems to me that that train has left the station.
I'm just amazed that there was such a lack of study because I'll tell you where it's
frustrating for me as an outsider.
I have a lot of questions.
My patients ask me questions such as if my 16 year old son is smoking pot, is that going
to have a negative consequence on his or her brain development?
I wish I could answer that question, but I can't really point to rigorous studies one
way or the other.
To me, that's a failure of not having studied this drug the way we should have been studying
it for the past hundred years because you want to talk about a drug that probably has
lots of benefits but also potentially harms.
Cannabis would be a case study in that.
I find it very frustrating as someone who prides himself in caring about data and trying
to not have an emotional discussion about something that I don't have answers to those
questions and it seems like a real missed opportunity.
Well it's worse than that.
The reason that the studies have not been done is because almost all the funding for
that kind of research in America comes through the government, through NIDA.
NIDA has not been funded to study the benefits of cannabis.
Even when, and this is the real missed opportunity, even when California voted to make medical
cannabis legal, what an opportunity.
We know 20 million people using it.
You could have within a couple of years worked out its utility and its harms, but the federal
law because cannabis was illegal under federal law and it still is, they could not fund research.
It's one of the many examples of the perverse negative consequences of this prohibition
approach to drugs.
Let's talk about a few other drugs that we haven't mentioned.
We've talked about basically things that are not particularly harmful.
We've certainly talked about things that rise to the level of harm.
Where do the classic psychedelics, LSD, psilocybin fit in along with some of their more distant
cousins, Ayahuasca, DMT, 5MeO, DMT.
Of course, we've talked around it, but we haven't explicitly asked where does MDMA fit
on this list of harm in the aggregate sense according to this sophisticated model.
That's why I started off talking about MDMA because that was my first introduction to
policy decisions.
When I started working for the government back in 1994, I'd assumed that what they told
me about the harms of drugs was right.
Then I discovered that when I did and my team did the more detailed and sophisticated analysis,
they were completely wrong.
I'd been lied to.
The real paradox of doing this really in-depth multi-criteria decision analysis is it turns
out that the drugs that have been most vilified and which we've been taught are the most dangerous
turn out to be the least dangerous.
The one end of the most harmful drug is alcohol.
The least harmful drugs are magic mushrooms and LSD and MDMA.
It's almost as if the whole law is completely on its head.
Let's now simplify and talk about only harm to the individual.
Purely physiologic risk to self.
If I heard you correctly earlier, heroin and fentanyl and its cousins occupy the top spot,
correct?
I aggregate greatest risk of acute and chronic mortality, yes?
Correct.
Then second, you're putting the cocaine derivatives.
Then third would be the amphetamine derivatives.
If we just look harm to the user, yes.
Crystal meth's probably more harmful than crack because it lasts longer in the body
and the brain.
I would generally, crystal's probably a bit more harmful to the user.
It would be opioids, crystal, crack.
Let's talk a little bit about mechanism of action.
I'm very familiar with how opiates kill, but let's just briefly summarize it.
Is it mostly the respiratory depression?
Is that the fundamental issue in the short term?
Yes.
They kill you in overdose.
You take just too much.
You don't know what you're taking.
Someone spiked your heroin, fentanyl, and you stop breathing and you die.
You want to talk about, you mentioned earlier, almost nobody in America doesn't know somebody
whose life has been destroyed by alcohol.
We're getting pretty close to that with opioids.
I mean, I personally know three people.
Is it four?
Maybe four who have lost a child or relative to an opioid overdose.
Think about that.
I don't know that many people, David.
It is terrifying.
I'm sorry to say, guys, but you kind of got it wrong and then you got it wrong again and
you're still getting it wrong.
Shall I just briefly go through that?
Sure.
So the fentanyl crisis is very much an American problem.
It's not just because there's obviously a lot of you.
The more people there are, the more likely it is that people will die.
But it's a disproportionate number of deaths.
So now I think last year more people died of opioid overdose and died in the whole of
the Vietnam War.
Yeah.
And last year we set here in the United States a record for the most overdose deaths ever.
So it wasn't just the year of the most deaths due to COVID, but the real record, the story
behind the story is the most overdoses.
And the answers are complicated and it's like a perfect storm of things going wrong.
The first perfect storm is the excessive rollout of strong morphine derivative painkillers,
which were heavily promoted by some pharmaceutical companies and you all know they've been sued,
et cetera.
So I think the doctors also, some doctors were to blame.
I mean, some were clearly overprescribing, but there's also the problem that chronic
pain is very common.
Perhaps a quarter of the country have chronic pain.
And doctors are faced with no treatment, no physiotherapy, no occupation.
All they had was prescription pad.
Then they tended to veer towards prescribing opiates, which are not good for chronic pain.
And it's interesting also, you see the states which had the highest prescription levels
of opiates for chronic pain or the ones actually that don't have medical cannabis.
Medical cannabis is the best treatment for chronic pain, better than any other drug.
But if you haven't got that, then you can't have it.
So that was a horrific thing.
Big increase in prescription, you know, partly driven, you know, driven inappropriately,
partly out of just a concern to help chronic pain.
The second thing was then the rise, the dispersion of that into society, you know, parents, kids
were taking it and taking their parents oxycodone and dying.
So you have the crisis, you have the concern, and then you have the reaction.
The reaction then was to stop prescribing.
But when you stop prescribing to someone who is dependent on an opiate, they don't,
unless you provide them with something else like medical cannabis, they are in withdrawal.
And so they go and get an opiate.
And if you're not prescribing it, they go and get it from the black market.
And then you see this complete paradox.
You see this rise of heroin deaths, rise of fentanyl deaths, because that's what the black
market provides.
And then you get into this really, the most damaging cycle, or part of this cycle, is
the rise of fentanyl.
Because until there was a huge increase in black market demand from the people on oxycodone,
fentanyl wasn't a big issue.
But for various international reasons, the United Nations limiting the access of heroin,
the amount of poppies it could be grown in a so-called attempt to prevent heroin misuse.
Fifteen years ago, particularly the Mexican cartels realized if they couldn't make heroin
because they couldn't get enough morphine, then they would make something else.
And they discovered fentanyls.
And fentanyls are so much more potent.
And there's so much more value for money, economic, you know, even the simplest fentanyl,
fentanyl, you know, it's, it's, you know, it's 50 times more potent than heroin and twice
as cheap to make.
So you don't have to be an economist to realize it's better to do that.
And then you get to the super fentanyl, it's like car fentanyl, which is a thousand times
more potent.
They're so potent, no one knows how to measure them.
And so you don't know how much you're giving.
So we've, you know, you see, it's a cycle, a series of mistakes, which has actually just
led to this, this terrible tsunami of deaths.
And, and the only way to deal with it really is to have lots of testing to allow people
to take anything they've got and get it tested so they know what it is, eliminate fentanyls
and start to bring in much safer treatments for people in chronic pain like like medical
cannabis.
I want to talk a little bit about the opiates before we leave it and come talk about a drug
called Ibogaine, a derivative of Iboga.
You know, I have read quite a bit about it and a lot of it's anecdotal, but it seems
that there's something very interesting going on there where you have this alkaloid that
while it comes with its own dangers and it's not clear how over or understated they are
relative to cardiac toxicity, it seems to have quite an efficacious punch when it comes
to relieving people from the throes of opioid addiction.
Do you have experience with it, at least scientifically, if not through experimental collaboration?
Well, we're in the process of trying to do a study.
I would dearly love to understand the nearest science of Ibogaine and we're, but it's been
difficult to do that study because of the cardiac risks.
But we're in the process of working with a company that's developing a derivative of
Ibogaine called Nor Ibogaine, which may be less cardiotoxic.
And we're working with them to do some brain imaging to see whether we can, is it a normal
psychedelic or not?
Because no one's ever studied it yet.
The evidence, as you see, it's used widely in some third world countries as a therapy
for opioid withdrawal.
It's also a licensed medicine, interestingly, in New Zealand, but they've stopped using
New Zealand because of one death.
Now that's probably a bit of an overreaction.
Which strikes me as a little bit odd, right, when you consider...
So based on some of the literature I've read, the risk of a fatal arrhythmia might be one
in a thousand.
And that's, depending on what you're talking about, one in a thousand is an enormous risk.
But if you're weighing it against a person remaining addicted to opioids, what's the
natural history of that?
That might be 300 out of a thousand.
Yes, about that.
Yeah, so do you have a sense of what the true risk of Ibogaine use is?
And how much of that risk could be mitigated if it were administered in a proper setting,
which would be a setting with cardiac monitoring, for example, versus someone's house?
Well, one thing's for sure, we're going to administer cardiac monitoring.
Yeah, of course.
Yeah, exactly.
And there are plenty of other drugs which do have cardiac effects.
Usually they're used by cardiologists.
So the answer, you're right.
I mean, that's why I want to study it, because if we could get more clarity on its mechanism,
that I think would at least then reassure people there was a science behind it.
Because currently it's, well, you go to West Africa, or you go to Vietnam, and you get Ibogaine,
and your brain is shaken up, and you come back cured.
And I think we could probably improve on that.
I think there's also your point you make that doing in a hospital setting, I think makes more sense,
because not just for safety, but also because I'm not sure it should be given during withdrawal.
That's when it is being given.
And I think withdrawal just, we have, you know, there are other treatments which we have given
for opiate users, which have also been toxic in withdrawal.
You know, people, you know, withdrawal is a serious medical problem.
So you know, you know, they're ill, they're physically struggling.
So I think adding a burden to someone who's in withdrawal is not a sensible idea.
To my thinking is that if we can restore a sensible balance with Ibogaine,
we could potentially use it.
But also, I'm very interested in using other psychedelics,
as I think the fundamental principle is likely to be the same between Ibogaine or psilocybin
or DMT in addictions.
You're disrupting these over-learns, these persistent patterns of over-attention
and over increased, you know, enhanced love for drugs.
You can perhaps break down those habit circuits and then allow people to escape.
Meaning things like the default mode network?
Yeah, that's right.
So I mean, our current thinking about how psychedelics might be used in psychiatry
is to is built from this, you know, remarkable finding that, you know,
the psychedelic state is a state which is where you have completely disrupted the default mode
network. This is the network in the brain, which in which your main sense of self,
the core of you is in the default mode network.
And embedded in that, of course, is whether you are, you know, your depressive thoughts
or whether your love objects, you know, your heroin addict, anything that's really related
to you is embedded in the default.
And how innate is that versus how formed is that?
Well, the default mode network, I think, exists in children and babies.
And it is what you are.
It is the part of the brain in which where you encode yourself,
your self-referential memories, your plans, your retrospect, you know,
looking back, looking forward, putting everything.
It is where you are.
We know that if you damage the frontal part of the default mode network,
your personality changes.
You damage the posterior part of the default mode network.
You kind of you become a very strange person who really struggles with coordination and integration.
So the default mode network is a fundamental part of orchestrating what you are.
But in that, of course, are all the things that you have been.
So in the default network coordinates your access to good memories, to bad memories,
to use of drugs, to resisting the use of drugs, etc.
But in a very simplistic way, that sort of current thought thinking is that
some elements of the default mode become misaligned or malignantly over-engaged
with negative thinking and depression or compulsive attitude, the seeking of drugs in drug use.
And if we can disrupt those with psychedelics, then potentially people can kind of restore
a normal balance in that network and have a more rational approach, you know, a less determined.
So the brain is kind of determining things like addiction.
And even though people don't want to use drugs, they often find themselves doing it,
even though they don't want to, because their brain is kind of driving them that way.
And we're going to come back and talk about the impact of psilocybin on the default mode network.
But I guess to your point, this might be one of the ways in which Ibogaine or Iboga
kind of help rewire a brain for an individual who is opioid addicted, which isn't in itself
kind of an interesting thing, isn't it? And that there's got to be a genetic susceptibility
to this, because there are many people who take tons of opioids during, you know, say a post,
you know, post-operative recovery from surgery. And, you know, they take tons of the stuff.
And then when they have to stop it, they stop it. And that's the end of it. And yet there are other
people for whom that's not true. So do we have a sense of what that genetic susceptibility looks
like? And is it more importantly, is it possible to predict that a priori so that we would understand,
hey, this is a person who is at such high risk for opioid dependency that even if they have to
get their wisdom teeth pulled out, we are not giving them this medication. We're going to come
up with a totally different pain management strategy. Yes, theoretically, it is unlikely
to be in the genes. Well, it's probably polygenic, I'm sure. Yeah, yeah, exactly. There's not going
to be a gene. What what do we know about why people become addicted? Well, we know, we know
that social factors are hugely important. You know, I mean, if you've seen The Wire, then you
know that downtown Baltimore. I lived The Wire. Well, I mean, I did my residency in Baltimore. So
I took care of the patients in The Wire. Yeah, it's a frightening place, isn't it?
Unbelievable. The book, The Corner, which The Wire was based on, was the book I,
once I matched to do my residency in Baltimore, a friend of mine who was a year ahead of me
in at medical school who had already now spent a year in Baltimore. I was like, hey, do you have
any advice for what I can do to kind of get ready for it? Because I'm moving from Stanford to
Baltimore. You can't go from the most posh place in the world to the least. And he said,
his only piece of advice was he said, read The Corner, because it's literally what you're going
to be living in. And it will give you a great sense of empathy for the patients that you're
going to be taken care of. And it's a riveting book, which ultimately became a riveting series.
Absolutely. And, you know, a couple of years ago, I was on my way to Philadelphia from
Washington to give a lecture. And as we pulled out of Baltimore, I was looking out the train
window thinking, this is like a war zone. Is this Hiroshima? Because in the downtown,
I hadn't realized quite how destroyed it had been. And if you're living there and you've got no job,
I mean, and the only thing you can do is deal drugs. You take drugs, you deal drugs. So,
a lot of drug use addiction comes because that's the one way people can actually achieve both a
sense, something that takes away the misery of their lives, but also in a way, if they become drug
dealers, become some role. So, so coping with life stress is one reason people use drugs.
But there are some people, you know, very, you know, the rich, successful people and
who still use opiates and get into problems with opiates. And the example, I give two examples of
this to Oscar winners. Tatum O'Neill, youngest ever Oscar winner, marries the best greatest
tennis player at the mic and rare there's maybe ever been, you know, got two wonderful kids, lives
the life in everyone, envy, you know, she's famous, beautiful, everything there. But when she comes
out of heroin treatment, she says, the only time I felt whole was on heroin. And you see that,
I see that with patients, not just heroin patients, I see it with alcoholics. There are
plenty of people for whom alcohol makes them what they want to be. Only when they're drunk,
that they're actually functioning normally. And why that is, we don't know. And actually, one of
the interesting things, you know, that I don't know the reason I want to study psychedelics,
because I'm wondering whether that gap that can only be filled by drugs could actually be kind of
refilled or at least remodeled with psychedelics. So, yeah, so that's another. And then of course,
there are people who use drugs to get high and then they find somehow that their brain becomes
sensitized to the drug use so that they lose control. And that's more classic with people you
use cocaine or crystal. So let's talk about those two drugs, just from a mechanistic standpoint,
and where the risk actually comes from. Take your choice, which one you want to start with.
Well, let's start with the earlier. Let's start with cocaine, because that was the first,
well, there were several cocaine epidemics. But I mean, let's talk about that. Yeah, I mean,
cocaine, I give a lecture sometimes, which is, was Freud right to give up on psychopharmacology?
Because of course, Freud was a great protagonist. Freud used cocaine himself, he thought cocaine
was a very powerful drug for getting people of heroin. He got one of his, his disciples off
heroin, by giving them cocaine. He didn't realize that cocaine also caused dependence. In fact,
Freud and his, his protege both became cocaine dependent. That's another Hopkins, that's another
Hopkins link, by the way, in Baltimore was the, the godfather. Yeah, yeah. So the, basically,
the father of the surgical residency in the United States, and the first chief of surgery at Hopkins,
William Stuart Halstead, himself became addicted to cocaine when he became obsessed with it as a
local anesthetic. And so in the, in the process of experimenting with cocaine as a local anesthetic,
which of course, it became a very potent and remarkable local anesthetic, he and many of his
residents became cocaine addicted. So it's sort of, you know, it's a footnote to the, to this story
of the creation of the great American Surgical Institute. Well, it hasn't stopped. They don't
get addicted to cocaine anymore. They get addicted to remifentanil usually the anesthetist, but that's
another story. Let's get back to cocaine. So I think the reason Freud went into psychology was
because he got them, he became completely terrified of pharmacology because he kind of assumed that
any drug would have that problem. So, you know, you can maybe get, maybe give cocaine credit for
the development of psychoanalysis. But when we get to the modern era, you know, then, you know,
cocaine is the ultimate fun drug. It gives you energy and drive and, you know, an enormous sort
of sense of focus and purpose, and then a terrible crash. And we now, you know, we know that it's
due to the release of dopamine and noradrenaline in the brain. But it's very spiky. And during
the course of a binge over the weekend, you know, the brain gets perturbed, and then people start to
get paranoid and withdraw. And some of them will get sensitized and become addicted. And some of
them will die because of course, there's a cardiac effect. And also there's this problem that if you
mix cocaine and alcohol, you get a drug called cocaethylene, which is a longer acting and more
cardiotoxic version of cocaine. You know, I have patients who, I mean, our patients are always going
to disclose to us what they use. We asked this question point blank, which recreational drugs do
you use? And a number of them will say, hey, you know, two or three times a year I use cocaine,
and they want to know what I think. And again, the goal in that situation is not to come across
as preachy and dogmatic, but it's to sort of have a point of view and have it be grounded. And my
point of view with cocaine has always been, I don't think it's worth the risk. And I don't think
it's the right kind of drug because, you know, just as much as we're now talking about a framework
for drugs, I have a much simpler framework for drugs, which is, it's really only got two levers.
One is what is the physical risk of this drug to me as an individual? So with cocaine, what is the
true risk of cardiac toxicity? What is the risk of deepening physiologic dependence over time, et cetera?
And then the second component to my framework is, is this a drug that only alters your state,
or does it have the potential to alter a trait? I'm borrowing that from the book called Altered
Traits, which gets into this distinction. And so the idea being is, you know, psilocybin for
anybody who's ever taken it is clearly a drug that alters your state. But if it just altered your
state, you probably wouldn't take it because it's really not that pleasurable. But the real
benefit of it is the potential to alter a trait, whether it be depression, smoking cessation, or
something else. And so if a drug can only alter your state, but it has no potential to really
alter your traits, i.e. how you behave off the drug, is it worth it? And so my, the way I explain
this to patients is I say, I don't think cocaine can do that. So therefore it has two strikes,
it's O for two in the Peter framework. It has a physical risk that is non-trivial,
and it's not going to make your life better when you're not taking it. And therefore I think
cocaine makes no sense to take. Do you agree or disagree with that? It's a very interesting
analysis. I like that. I might start using it. So do you agree that basically there isn't a
positive to cocaine that I'm missing? There isn't a benefit to it? I certainly would say
absolutely true for crack. For cocaine, I'm not entirely sure. I mean, I think there aren't people
who can use it just once or twice a year without getting into much difficulty, provided they don't
have serious cardiac problems. So I certainly wouldn't be using it at my age. But then look
at like there's the famous example, which basically accelerated the war on drugs was the case of Len
Bias in 1985. Are you familiar with the story of Len Bias? Oh, he was the probably the most famous
high school, pardon me, college basketball recruit. So he played basketball at the University
of Maryland, a complete superstar, basically on the level of a Michael Jordan. And he was drafted
by the Boston Celtics and probably had he gone on to play for the Boston Celtics would have altered
the course of the NBA for the next 10 years. The day following the NBA draft, he was back in
Baltimore celebrating with friends. They're at a party in their dorm room. He's, you know, they're
using cocaine, he has a sudden cardiac arrest and dies. And this really, really shocked the nation.
This was a really big deal. And, and, and certainly some would argue that that was that only reinforced
and doubled down on sort of the Nancy Reagan esque, just say no mantra, which of course reinforced
the war on drugs. So again, when you can have this totally, you know, the healthiest 21 year old in
the country can die and you don't know what you know, the details, right? How much was he on was
at laced with something, you know, one doesn't know. But you've got to remember that, you know,
sudden death in athletes, I don't know, we just had the European Football Championships. And one of
the star players, Erickson from Denmark had a cardiac arrest on the pitch. So super fit athletes
might be more susceptible. Yeah. Yeah. Particularly if they've got, you know, if they're big and they've
got to develop some kind of cardiomy. So, so yeah, I don't athletes are, are paradoxically more
potentially, you know, at least as vulnerable as other people to these, to these effects.
So, so talk about methamphetamine, crystal meth, these, these drugs, which obviously the,
the amazing Netflix series Breaking Bad brought everyone awareness of what these drugs are, but,
but physiologically, neurochemically, what is it that they're doing? And what is the danger?
Well, they're very similar to KK. I remember as a junior doctor, my very first period as a junior
doctor, giving methyl amphetamine intravenously to a man who had serious status asthmaticus.
Jeez. Amphetamines were developed as a treatment for asthma. They were developed as an alternative
to ephedra. Ephedra is a natural plant product. It was discovered to have this bronco dilating
properties back in the 1800s. There was a huge demand. The plant couldn't supply the demand. So
German pharmaceutical companies went away and made a synthetic ephedra, which they called amphetamine.
And it was used largely for the treatment of, of asthma, really to the second world war,
when people realized it could actually be used to keep soldiers awake. And, and, and, and,
it's another interesting aside, I'm very interested in the, the history of drugs and
war because they tell us quite a lot about the, the consequences of drug use. And what I often
give, I often give a talk when I talk about amphetamines, I compare the, the allies. So the
Brits and Americans, we use amphetamine sulfate. Whereas the Germans and the Japanese thought they
were really clever because they had this super amphetamine called methane amphetamine, which
lasts a lot longer. But what they didn't realize was that longer is not better. And the turning
point of the war was actually the, the North Africa campaign when the Germans were pushed
back when they got to Egypt. So, that's right. Absolutely. By the desert rats, the, the, the
allied troops, the Australians, and the way the desert rats used to work was that they would be
up all night hanging, working around the Germans, harrying them, blowing them up. And then they go
back, they, that would, they'd be up all night on amphetamine sulfate. And then they go back and
they'd sleep all day. But the Germans would take methane amphetamine to stay up to fight, to defend
themselves against the desert rats. But they couldn't sleep in the daytime. And eventually they
became sleep deprived and paranoid. And the same with Japanese, you know, these descriptions of how
the Japanese became, can pull, have these terrible hallucin, sensory somatic hallucinations
from using large doses of crystal meth for long periods. So, crystal meth is, it's longer acting
and probably more neurotoxic than amphetamine sulfate. Talk about the neurotoxicity. What,
what actually happens to the person's brain? Cause we, you certainly have this meme of the crystal
meth user, right? No teeth, bruised, pin skinny, emaciated. But that meme doesn't actually tell me
about their brain. What's, what's actually happening to them? Well, they're certainly pushing
their dopamine system to a point where it's probably depleted. And that seems to then lock
them into a state where they can't really function normally in the world without taking the drug.
There's also a bit less good evidence that it might also damage the dopamine pathways to the
frontal cortex, which impairs their ability to make judgments to executive function, et cetera.
But I have to caution it. I mean, the, the, the big concern about crystal meth actually came
as a result of the Japan after the second world war, there were, you know, factories, crystal meth
factories in Japan, you know, there were barrels of the stuff and there were a lot of Japanese
soldiers had nothing else to do. And they used to use huge doses of crystal meth, often intravenously.
And the evidence for brain damage really comes from that population. There's not so much evidence
from it being, when it's being used as it tends to be used now, orally without, you know, in more
prolonged periods. So I'm not sure that you get a lot of what you might call cortical damage with
crystal meth, but I think it definitely does distort the dopamine pathways in your brain and,
and will affect your motivation and your ability to, to sort of get up and get activated, et cetera.
So now let's talk a little bit about these drugs that unfortunately, or, you know, for,
they seem to have the same scheduling and therefore they're viewed by the DEA as both as dangerous
in terms of harm or risk of, of, of addiction and as medically useless. Cause really that's
the criteria for schedule one, right? Is high, high potential for addiction and no medical use.
And so cocaine does not fit in schedule one because while it is highly addictive, we at
least have one appropriate medical use for it, which is, and it's an, it's a great anesthetic,
especially in the nose. Obviously fentanyl is not schedule one because even though we
acknowledge it's highly addictive, it has this pain blunting effect. Remarkably psilocybin is
schedule one. MDMA is schedule one. So LSD is schedule one. So let's talk about these three,
which are, if you believe the DEA scheduling the worst possible drugs imaginable, because
by definition, they must have a high addiction for potential and they serve no medical benefit
whatsoever. So take them in any order you like. Well, let's take the psychedelics first,
because that's how it all started. I mean, these drugs were banned,
not because they had any negative impact. They were banned in the face of opposition.
Bobby Kennedy confronted the DEA and the FDA when they said we want to ban LSD. And he said,
hang on a second, hang on. We spent billions of dollars researching LSD up till this time.
And we got loads of positive results. In fact, his wife-
Was he still the AG when he was having this discussion with them? Was he still the attorney
general of the United States?
No, no, no, he was, he was secretary of state. He was about to get elected as president.
Yeah, this was, this was, okay, later on.
Yeah. Just before he was assassinated.
Yeah. Okay.
And he's saying to these, come on, guys, we've had 15 years of this remarkable research,
which we've invested. NIH in the States funded over 130 grants to study the therapeutic use
of LSD. And they found it was very therapeutic and very little harms. And then the DEA come,
and the CIA come and say, we've got to ban it. He's saying, what are you talking about?
And of course, what they were talking about was, was the fact that the hippie movement was starting.
And the hippie movement was anti the war in Vietnam. And LSD was seen as fueling the hippie
movement. But also worse than that, it was changing music and people were dressing differently and
putting flowers in their hair. And, and they were sticking flowers down the guns of the soldiers that
were trying to stop them protesting the war. You know, it was changing the whole tenor of,
I suppose, what you might call sort of intellectual debate in America,
particularly among students. And it was seen as a real threat to the American way of,
of doing everything, which was basically having bigger and better bombs and guns.
And so LSD got banned, because it was essentially changing the way people voted,
people didn't want to vote for war. And they had, but they couldn't ban it. In those days,
there were rules which said basically, you had to have to find harms. And those harms can be
physical harms, or they could be social harms. And it's very easy to find social harms, because
you just get a few editors of your National Enquirer or similar rags to just invent stories
about the harms, you know, and the way people have been corrupted by using LSD. And there's these
wonderful, I mean, it's sad, but, you know, but it's amusing now, but of course, very damaging.
It's front covers of these magazines or newspapers, making absurd claims about LSD,
usually with semi naked women. And, and that was enough concern. Editors are socially concerned,
then we can ban the drug and it got banned. And once LSD got banned, all the other serotonergic
hallucinogens that were known about at the time, and actually, in America, you did know about quite
a lot, a lot of countries didn't know there were more than LSD inside of Sydney. So some countries
didn't ban DMT or 5-Methoxy. But you Americans, you just banned it all because you had good
scientists. So LSD was banned for political and social reasons. No, not because of any harm.
If Tim Leary had not been around, would it still have been banned, in your opinion?
Probably not. I think the fact that he was encouraging a fundamental change in the American
way of life through using drugs, I think he certainly compounded the problem. And he certainly
popularized LSD and encouraged people to think differently about society. I think that, I think
there was a genuine fear that Americans would actually cease to want to fight wars and actually
want to have peace. And that was just seen as being extremely bad for the American economy. And of
course, the American presence in Sydney. So prior to the scheduling of LSD, you mentioned over 130
grants had been issued to study it. This was a drug that had been manufactured in the late 1930s
by the pharmaceutical company Sandos. What were some of the things that they had learned about LSD
under that period of time in which it was studied rigorously? So there were 40,000 patients studied,
a thousand papers were published. And there've been analyses of many of these groups of patients.
And they discovered that it actually was very safe. If anything, it reduced suicide rates
compared with non-treatment. And you've got to remember at the time in the 50s and 60s,
there were very few alternatives, particularly antidepressants hadn't been really invented
till the 1960s. It was shown to be effective. And it was shown to be safe and it didn't cause
psychosis. So actually, it was this was the revolution. This was the beginning, the dawning
of real psychiatry. Psychiatry was becoming like the rest of medicine. We had tools that we could
help people with other than talking. And in what context, David, so would that be like a single
dose of LSD combined with a prolonged period of psychotherapy during the period of time under which
the individuals under the influence, or did it require multiple treatments? I mean, do you have
a sense of what was required for that efficacy? But it was used in two different ways. So in the
States, the typical use was how we're using it today, which is give people a bigish dose,
give them a big trip, a few hour trip, and then afterwards help them work out what the trip meant.
So it was always done in the context of psychotherapy, because in those days, all American
psychiatrists were actually effectively, mostly Freudian analysts. So it was always done in the
context of psychotherapy. It was allowed. But in Britain, and we tended to, we often used lower
doses. And we use that repeatedly to try to break down psychological resistance to actually engaging
in psychotherapy. And what was the difference in those doses, David? So the big trip dose would be
how many micrograms? So for LSD would have been 100 or 125. Okay. And then for the, you know, for
opening up the, reducing the resistance, we would say, in psychotherapy, breaking down the resistance,
it would be perhaps 25 micrograms. And is 25 micrograms perceptible, or is that considered a
microdose where the individual? No, no, that's perceptible. Anything over 10 micrograms is
perceptible. Okay. Even 10, a lot of people can discriminate 10, not in the sense, not because
they're psychedelic, but they, they, something's different. Feel that, yeah, feel things. Yes, exactly.
And in the case that you described in the UK, how many treatments at that lower level,
and at what interval were typically necessary to produce the benefits?
Well, they'd be weekly, and they'd be maybe for, you know, 10, 15, 20 treatments.
So it's a, it's a, just an unbelievable loss to the scientific community when LSD becomes scheduled.
Absolutely. Could I just say one other thing? I mean, the, the, the, perhaps the biggest loss of all
is relation to alcoholism. A lot of people don't realize that the founder of Alcoholics Anonymous,
Bill Wilson, he escaped his alcoholism. He broke free from the chains, as he described it. He
escaped the chains of his alcoholism through a psychedelic experience. And then that was before
LSD. And then when LSD came along, and it was legal, he tried it and he said, wow, this drug could help
lots of alcoholics escape from this belief that the only thing that matters to them
is alcohol. It could give them a sense that there is more that it is possible to change.
And he was, he persuaded or was instrumental in six trials of LSD for alcoholism that were conducted
in the state. So one or two doses in people with alcoholism. And a few years ago, a couple of
Norwegians went back and they dug out the old data and they did it, put it through a modern
meta-analysis, collate all the data. You've got an effect size of one, which is twice that of any
subsequent treatment for alcoholism. LSD was a revolution in the treatment of alcoholism.
Now, in the 50 years since LSD has been banned, you know, you can make a rough calculation
worldwide, over 100 million people have died prematurely from alcohol use disorder.
And if LSD helped perhaps just 10% of them, that will be 10 million lives saved.
Now you ask the question, well, how many lives have been saved from the ban? Well,
I'm not sure LSD, maybe let's say let's say globally, maybe, maybe 50, 50 lives a year have
been saved because fewer people took it possibly. So then you say, you know, we got 50 years times
for just two and a half thousand lives saved and 10 million lives lost. So the equation is so
balanced against the decision that was made. It really, I think it's the worst censorship of
research in the history of the world. And what are the typical harms of LSD? Is it basically
self-harm inadvertently through people who are tripping to such an extreme level that they,
you know, you hear these stories, well, this guy thought he could fly and he jumped off a building.
Sure. Well, the CIA were very good at promoting those stories, but they're, they're, okay,
unquestionably people do dangerous things when they're taking LSD in dangerous places.
And we should mitigate against that. And I can promise you when we do psychedelic therapy,
we lock the door so they can't jump. Okay. Here's a statistic in Britain, and I imagine it's even
way worse in the States. Each year in Britain, probably 20 to 30 people die jumping, usually
drunk from piers or breakwaters or even from hotel balconies into the swimming pool. So
probably more people die each year jumping from alcohol. Which says nothing of automotive
accidents and liver toxicity and respiratory depression. But just the jumping. Okay. So LSD,
if you take LSD in a dangerous situation with people who are also tripping and you're not
got someone to look after you, then of course it's, you know, there is a risk. But when LSD was used
in these 40,000 patients in hospitals, there was, there was very little evidence of any harm at all.
Okay. Let's talk about its cousin, psilocybin.
Yes. The psilocybin of course, it's been around a lot longer. Psilocybin is a present in mushrooms.
There are about 200 species of magic mushrooms, different ones in different parts of the world.
It was, it was really the beginnings of the psychedelic revolution where LSD and Hoffman
and Gordon Watson, the American mycologist who discovered a tribe in Mexico that were using
mushrooms for psychedelics experiences and actually went and exposed them and actually
rather destroyed their culture by making it a target for tourism. So psychedelic mushrooms
have been around forever because mushrooms have been around way before humans. One of the
interesting theories about Hinduism, you often wonder, you know, why do Hindu gods have so many
arms? Probably because the first people that became Hindus have been using this, this cocktail
called Soma, which of course was, the term was adopted by Aldous Huxley in Brave New World. But,
but the real Soma was a powerful mixture, probably of magic mushrooms of Ephedra and cannabis. You
mix that a lot together. It's not surprising your elephants have five heads and four arms. So, so
magic mushrooms have been around in many cultures for millennia. The Psi-de-Cybin has been the active
ingredient was also discovered by Hoffman because Watson went to him and said, why is this causing
hallucinations like LSD? And he said, oh, well, because it looks a bit like serotonin, a bit like LSD.
And, and we've been working now with Psi-de-Cybin for a number of reasons. The main one is that it
doesn't have the stigma. LSD, you say LSD to a politician and they immediately turn off.
You know, LSD is a bad thing. Whereas Psi-de-Cybin, they don't know how to say it. They don't have to
spell it. They don't know what you're talking about. And who's, how can you be worried about
magic? That's only a mushroom. The second reason we started using Psi-de-Cybin was because we didn't
have safety, really good safety data on any of these. But we did know that in Britain, magic
mushrooms were legal until 2005. And we knew that about a million young people a year were using
mushrooms. And we persuaded our regulators that they could let us use mushrooms because that body
of evidence of safety was adequate. And they said, okay. What led to the scheduling only 15 years ago?
I mean, what, what was happening that in 2005, they said, we've got to ban this thing.
It's complicated. So the active ingredient Psi-de-Cybin was banned in 71 alongside LSD,
DMT. But the mushrooms weren't banned. Why would you ban the mushrooms? They don't have much of it.
Who cares if people are going to go and lie on the side of a mountain and see pretty pictures
in the sky. But what happened was that a couple of head shops in Camden town, North London,
started selling freeze dried mushrooms. So they would concentrate the dose?
Like you could take more of it? Or was it just the fact that it was being sold commercially in
the head shops? It could be sold in London. And so no one really cares if people go and lie on a
hillside in Devon. That's quite fun. But if someone's selling a dangerous psychedelic drug
to our young people in London, the right wing press just went ape. And we had a new.
These are probably the same shops that sold Doc Martens, by the way, because I know those head
shops. They're very dangerous places. Yeah, absolutely. And it was a classic example
of political expediency. The Tory party had lost the third election in a row to the Labour party,
Tony Blair's Labour Party. And they brought in a new guy called David Cameron.
And David Cameron had spoken previously about, you know, he'd use drugs and, and he was in favour
of drug reform. But as soon as he became leader of the Tory party, he became anti drugs, because
that's what he was told to do. And he saw these newspaper headlines, head shops corrupting our
young people. And he started goading the Labour party that he had soft on drugs, just soft on
drugs. You know, look, they're selling this illegal, the drug wasn't illegal, but the mushrooms
weren't illegal, but they made out they were. And Tony Blair, instead of saying, don't be stupid,
he did what many liberal leaning politicians do, in fact, exemplified in your country by Clinton.
Clinton was the guy that was told the Democrats had to be harder on drugs and the Republicans and
he's the guy with the three strikes and you're in prison forever. And the same with Labour,
they were told if you're not tougher on drugs, or as tough as the Tories, you're going to lose the
election. So he goaded Blair into making the mushrooms illegal. And he did it without consulting
us and without he actually broke the law. But we discovered that actually governments are allowed
to do that. We can if you take even if you take them to court, they can just change the law to
prove it, you know, to allow them to have done what they did. So so yeah, so the mushrooms are
now illegal, as well as the active ingredient. And then MDMA itself is not really a classic
psychedelic, you know, I, there's sort of a framework for these psychedelics where you've
got the kind of the typical the atypical, but sort of if you have sort of psilocybin LSD here,
you've got MDMA here more of an empathogen. And then you've had ketamine is more of a dissociative.
And then these really a typical ones like Ibogaine, which we've already talked about. So correct.
So let's spend just a minute on MDMA, because again, I think it's one that, well, first of all,
people confuse MDMA and ecstasy a little bit. And it's probably worth clarifying the nuances there.
But also talking about the potential that it has, I've had, you know, Rick Doblin on the podcast
before. So we've gone incredibly deep on the benefits of, you know, treatment for PTSD. And
we've talked a lot about maps, we don't need to go that deep. But just for someone who maybe hasn't
heard that, what would be the overview? Well, MDMA is a great American invention. Yep.
Well, your top drug chemist, Sasha Shulgin, was interested in derivatives of amphetamines.
And he, MDMA was made, you know, back in 1904 as a possible agent for blood clotting, but it never
never got used. And Sheldon made it in the in the 60s and said, Wow, this drug is different from
amphetamines. It's not activating. It's not, it's not driving me like amphetamines. It's actually
making, it's giving me a clarity of thought, but also a sense of warmness and empathy. So we gave
it to his wife. And she said, Wow, this is a very, this is empathy. This would be really useful in
psychotherapy and couples counseling, it would help potentially help break down, you know, those
layers of irritation and grits that build up in relationships sometimes, put people back into love.
And it was widely used for about 10 years by therapists, particularly in the west coast of
the states. And it was called empathy, and everything was fine. And then some smart ass
in Texas decided, this is a legal drug, and we could sell this, we can't sell amphetamines,
but we can sell ecstasy because it's legal. But who wants to buy ecstasy? So they changed the name to
ecstasy. So they didn't want to buy empathy, sorry, they changed the name to ecstasy. You got an
amphetamine, which can help keep you active, but also make you much more in love with, with other
people. And it became, you know, widely used. What's, you know, it's the perfect drug for parties,
isn't it? You know, you've got energy, but you're also happy with you're not fighting people like
what you do if you're taking speed. And it became hugely popular, and it spread into Europe. And
then of course, it just riled the right the Puritans, it riled the right wing press, the idea
that young people could have ecstasy, when old when the newspaper owners couldn't even never had
it and couldn't even remember what it meant. They just didn't, you had this moral outrage,
which eventually got the drug banned. But again, you couldn't, in America and Britain in those
days, you couldn't ban a drug just because kids liked it, you had to find evidence of harm. And
some of the worst science has ever been done is the science proving or supposedly proving that
MDMA is harmful. And culminating in that an amazing experiment, it was done by Ricciarti,
which is very embarrassing for Johns Hopkins, you know, when he claimed that taking MDMA and
listening to the poges overnight gave monkeys brain damage. And we all said, well, hang on a second.
None of our kids are coming out of the clubs with brain damage. I think your experiment's wrong,
Ricciarti. He said, no, no, it's right. Exocice cause his brain damage. And he got published in
science, despite the fact the referee said, this is got to be wrong. And of course, eventually,
they went back and they audited what they'd done. And instead of giving the monkeys MDMA,
they given them crystal meth, which is way more toxic. That paper was recall. I mean,
he did have to pull that paper, didn't he? He didn't. No, no, he didn't retract the paper.
He was never retracted. I think you can still find it. If you look in science,
you'll still find it's there. It's not struck out. I think you'll just find there's a,
there's a correction. Sorry, guys. This wasn't MDMA. This was actually methamphetamine.
Wow. So that's, that's, that's our answer to Andrew Wakefield for you.
Indeed. And it's, it's embarrassing really, because, well, for all sorts of reasons, because
so much American science is paid by the government. The, apparently, I don't know,
I heard that the editor of the magazine science was told by senators that the American Academy
of science, which runs a journal, would not get government funding if he didn't put that
paper in and get it published to deter young people from using MDMA. Of course,
all that happens is in the end, young people, young people think this doesn't make sense.
And then they discover they've been lied to. So are they going to listen to anything else
the government tells them? Yeah. Let's talk briefly about ketamine before we come back to,
to psilocybin. Cause I want to, I want to sort of double click more on psilocybin specifically with
with, for the treatment of depression. But let just to round out all of our sort of psychedelics.
Ketamine, of course, is the only drug on this list that is legal. So it's, I believe it's a
schedule three, perhaps a schedule four, used as an anesthetic typically. And it's quite dissociative.
So can you, can you talk, I guess, specifically about the use of ketamine in treatment resistant
depression, which seems to be one of the more promising areas of research? Yes. A wonderful
story. And it goes back to John Crystal, who's a professor up at Yale, and he was using ketamine
to model psychosis. And he was comparing ketamine and THC to model psychosis. And they both produce
altered states of consciousness, which sort of, you know, have some overlap with psychosis.
But he noticed that afterwards, his volunteers often felt better, you know, they actually came
out with the ketamine experience saying, well, that was weird, but they had an improved mood.
Maybe this is mood elevating. So then he and his colleagues went on and he did a study. Yeah,
ketamine elevates mood. And for a couple of days after a ketamine trip, your mood is definitely
improved. And now there've been about 30 studies showing that ketamine can have a value,
particularly if you add it on to other treatments of depression, which have not been very successful.
So if people have partially recovered, give a bit of ketamine, and their mood gets better.
The problem with ketamine, compared with what we're going to talk about in a minute with
psilocybin, is the effect is very short lasting, it lasts only two or three days.
So currently, what you have now is a licensed medicine. Janssen decided to pursue this,
because this was the first real breakthrough in the treatment of depression for really for 50
years. But you couldn't patent ketamine, because ketamine was being used back in the Vietnam War
as the buddy drug when people were being blown up and having it as an analgesic. So they took
the enantiomer, one of the isomers of ketamine, called S-the S-enantiomer, and they called it
S-ketamine. And they formulated it for nasal inhalation, so you don't have to inject it, which
is better and easier for psychiatrists. And now that's sold as a treatment, and it's called S-ketamine
Spravato. And it works, and you take it a couple of times a week, and then gradually over time,
you use less and less as the... So you don't develop a tachyphylaxis to it?
It actually... If you do it twice a week, you don't? No, no. And you are able to get patients
off of it while still preserving the antidepressant benefits? That's less clear, but for certain,
in some that's true. But it does have, there is an advantage of it over ketamine.
Ketamine clinics tend to... They give it intravenously or intramuscularly. They give it
intravenously or intramuscularly. But also the problem there is that ketamine is a
dependence producing drug. It's a drug, a recreational drug, it's relatively popular
in Britain, it's relatively popular in China, probably popular also in the States, I'm not sure
what the stats are. The problem is you do get tolerance, tachyphylaxis, if you use it regularly.
So while it's relatively safe in the doses, you might use maybe 500 milligrams for depression.
If people are using it recreationally and taking more and more, they're getting up to grams a day
and then you get into serious problems. You get bladder problems, you get a... Basically you get
severe chronic cystitis, which can cause bladder atrophy, needing bladder resection.
And you also get a psychological state, you get a kind of... You can get brain damage,
or at least you can get a state of severe cognitive impairment, which actually rather
mimics schizophrenia. So heavy use of ketamine is actually really to be avoided.
And what defines that? I mean, those are very scary things you just described,
obviously the psychiatric component much more than the urologic. What is too much? I mean,
because I'll tell you, this is something I get asked a lot. Hey, I'm going to this ketamine
clinic once a month, it's changing my life. And at what point does that become too much?
Yeah, well certainly daily use is too much. So I mean, people who are addicted to ketamine are
using it four or five times a day, they might be using five grams a day. And that's when you get
into the serious brain damage. So I think twice a week, oh, I think we know from S-ketamine,
twice a week seems to be without, doesn't have any enduring... But if you're not using the
enantiomer twice a week, we'll probably still produce a tachyflaxis and a diminishing return
at some point. Yes, but this one of the really interesting questions, and we don't understand
this. Why is it that when people use ketamine, and they get tachyflaxis, they can overcome it by
taking more? By the way, I should explain to people what tachyflaxis is, because we're using
the term without me defining it. It's of course, when the same amount of a medication produces a
lesser and lesser effect, or when you require more and more of a medication to produce the same
effect. So for example, we don't generally get tachyflactic to Tylenol, right? You have acetaminophen,
if you take 500 milligrams and your headache goes away, the next time you take 500 milligrams,
it does about the same thing. So to your point, you can push the dose a little bit and stay ahead
of it with ketamine? Correct, you can, like heroin, like fentanyl, you can overcome the tolerance.
But with psychedelics, you can't. And that's an interesting phenomenon. And it's probably to do
with subtle changes in the downstream mechanisms in the cells, that you get almost complete absence
of effects of psychedelics after two or three doses. And do you know who told us that?
The US government. So the US government were very interested in, or fearful actually,
when psychedelics came around in the 50s. They thought, well, maybe the Russians will be spraying
LSD on our troops. So how can we protect our troops from LSD? So they started giving troops
LSD to find out what the effects would be to see how they could abort them. And they discovered by
the third day of giving the troops LSD, LSD had no effect anymore. I didn't realize that was the
case. So if you're talking 250 micrograms of LSD, at some point people are going to stop responding
to that. Yeah, but the second dose will be less than the first. If you take it every day,
the second dose is way less than the second. But what if you're taking it once a month,
for example, or? No, no, no, it takes about a week to recover. The effect disappears between
about one and two weeks. I see. So it's not a lifelong tachyphylaxis. It's very temporal.
Now, although some people do say, well, a lot of people say that for all drugs,
that the first one's always the best. But you can't overcome the tachyphylaxis with psychedelics,
whereas you can with heroin and you can with ketamine. And why that is, we're not so clear
as to why that is. All right. Well, there's so many more questions I have about this, David,
but I know we have a very hard stop today. So I want to make sure we have some time to talk about
your most recent work with psilocybin and depression. About three months ago, a study was published in
the New England Journal of Medicine. You were the senior author on that paper. I've written about
it at length, which compared psilocybin to Lexapro, a very, very popular, commonly used, reasonably
well tolerated SSRI. Do you want to just give people a quick overview of the study design and
what you set out to test? I'd be pleased to. Yes. So previously we had done a study, an open trial,
we'd taken 20 people with resistant depression. We'd given them a single psilocybin trip and found
very good outcome. But effect didn't last very long. It lasted, you know, one to two months.
But for many of them, the depression came back. Based on that, and also some theoretical work I'd
done with Robin Carhart Harris, who was with me at the time, he's now moved to UCSF. We came to the
conclusion that psychedelics treat depression in a different way to antidepressants. And the paper
is published in Journal of Psychopharmacology. It's called A Tale of Two Receptors. It's a free download.
Feel free to read it because it conceptualizes that there are two ways you can lift depression.
One way is with with Lexapro or other similar drugs that enhance serotonin in the limbic system.
And there they basically block the stress response. And we know that stress is a major cause of
depression. You block stress induced depressive changes in that system. And that allows the limbic
system to recover. So that it's a bit like if you have a broken leg, you set the leg in plaster so
that the bone can heal itself. SSRIs set the limbic system in plaster. So over a period of six to eight
weeks, they can heal and get you over your depression. And that's through a particular
subtype of serotonin receptors called the serotonin 1a receptor, which is in the very expressed in the
limbic system. But we think psychedelics, we know psychedelics work in the cortex, and they disrupt
cortical processing and disrupt, we think, the deep, persistent ruminations and negative thoughts
of depression. So we said, let's do a study where we take depressed people, we scan them with fMRI
before and after. And then we see if we can look at the if the brain changes are different with the
acetalopram compared with the cytosine. We're predicting that we would see cortical differences
that the cortex would be changed by the cytosine bin, and the subcortical regions will be changed
by the acetalopram. So the primary aim of the study was to see if there were differences in
brain mechanisms. But of course, we have to know whether there are differences in outcome.
So we compared the mood changing effects of these two drugs. But you couldn't just say,
here, you're on Lexoprow, here, you're on cytosine bin, we had to blind it. And that's quite difficult
with psychedelics. So the way we got we did that was to tell everyone that we're going to get
cytosine bin. But half the group got a low dose, a placebo dose, a one milligram dose, and a half got
a high dose, a 25 milligram dose. But they all went through the same psychotherapy, depending,
it didn't matter what dose they got, they all got all the same preparation and the psychotherapy
that goes with a high dose of cytosine bin. And then they all got pills. But the acetalopram group
got acetalopram and the cytosine bin group got placebo.
So they're both getting two pills. One is getting a placebo plus the high dose of psilocybin.
And the point of that is what's called clinical equipoise. People have to believe
that they're getting the best they can. And then and we gave them two doses of cytosine bin,
whether high or low, one at the start and one after three weeks to see how long the effect would
last. And then we measured changes in mood and we measured side effects. And we also looked at other
aspects of depression rather than just looking at depression scores. We also looked at things like
well being, which is a different way of looking at how people are feeling. And in the end, on the
primary measure, there was no difference that cytosine bin at six weeks was as good as or equal
to as acetalopram on that particular measure, which was a particular self-report measure called
the quid self-report, which has been used quite extensively in research in the states,
particularly in the stardew study. But when we looked at all the other measures,
actually cytosine bin did rather well. Yeah. So I want to pause on that for a sec because
I think that the paper was undersold a little bit. I think it was, it read as a negative study
as opposed to a non-inferiority study. Why do you think that happened? Do you think that there was
a mistake in the way that either the journal treated that or even the way you treated that
as the authors? Yeah, that's a great question, a very perceptive question. That's a question
I think you should ask the editors of the New England Journal. So the reality was, the truth
was it wasn't powered for non-inferiority. If you want a proper non-inferiority study in psychiatry
takes 150 patients in each arm, we could never afford to do that. There's very few of them have
ever been done except by companies. Well, probably none have been done except by companies. We could
not statistically do a non-inferiority study. So we had to just do a kind of comparison.
And the answer was that, well, we had to pre-specify, we pre-specified two outcomes,
the quids and the well-being. And it did brilliantly on the well-being, but because that's kind of not,
well, that's sort of soft wishy-washy psychiatry, they insisted that we use the quids as the primary.
Now, if you don't meet, this is a bit statistical sort of jargon really, but if you don't meet your
primary, you're not allowed to report the second trees. It's kind of, it's absolute, it's, it's,
it's purism, it's puristic statistics. But as you, as you say, it's kind of not very intuitive,
because when you look at it, actually it was very clear that the overall, many, well,
there was not a single measure that favored Esitala Fray. Well, that's, that's sort of the thing is,
you know, I read the paper in great detail and my takeaway was this is very promising because
I'm very familiar with, with Lexapro and I'm very familiar with its efficacy, but I'm also very
familiar with its side effects and the baggage that comes with it. Most people, you know, for,
for the listener, Lexapro is typically given at two doses, 10 milligrams or 20 milligrams.
Going from 10 to 20, there is a so sizable increase in the efficacy, but there's also
a sizable increase in the side effects, many of them sexual. And when we're talking about treating
young people, old people, middle-aged people, you fix their depression, but you destroy their libido,
you're, you're, you're trading one problem for another often. And the, the, the list of patients
I've, you know, taken care of who can't tolerate these drugs, despite the benefit that they're
receiving from an anti-depressive or anti-angiolytic standpoint is significant. So, so to me, I read
that study with enormous optimism, right? Which is if there is a way to give somebody 25 milligrams
of psilocybin and get the same anti-depressive benefits, but without these other side effects,
this is very exciting. This needs to be explored a heck of a lot further. Do you think that the
study at least accomplished that as, as, as an outcome? Yeah. So people have said, well,
why didn't you fight back with a journal? Why didn't you demand, you know, that they were more
positive? And, and the answer is, from my perspective, being the first ever psychedelic
study in the New England Journal of Medicine tells the world that psilocybin is a medicine.
And it's as good as Lexapro. And if anyone who reads the paper can see that it does
do better on sexual dysfunction, and it does do better on many of the other issues that Lexapro
has a problem with. And that it fits with the theory that one of the things it's very,
the reason Lexapro and other SSRIs dampen down sexual activity is because they dampen down the
limbic system, which is the part of the brain which drives those behaviors. And also people on
these drugs often say, yes, I don't feel depressed anymore. I don't, I don't, I don't cry. I, I don't
have the distress that comes from seeing sad things on the TV. But they also say, but also I
don't enjoy life as much because I kind of, my pleasures are blunted. Right. And that all fits
with that theory. It's blunting the top and the bottom. Exactly. Exactly. Whereas psilocybin is
stopping the thinking and allowing the rest of your brain to work normally.
A word on microdosing, David, you know, people, it even, I even had to go back and do the conversion.
So when I was reading the study, I was going, wait a minute, what is 25 milligrams of psilocybin mean?
Because typically when people are taking psilocybin, we're giving it to them in the whole
mushroom. And that's typically like five grams. So of course, then I had to get really deep in
the weeds and figure out which species of mushroom and what the conversion is. But the point is
25 milligrams of pure psilocybin is on par with about four to five grams of magic mushrooms.
And therefore it is truly a psychedelic experience. What is known about the imperceptible dose?
You know, like a hundred milligrams of magic mushroom or, you know, one to two milligrams
of pure psilocybin and its potential for antidepressant benefits.
Well, loads of people use it. Loads of people, you know, they go pick the mushrooms, they dry the
mushrooms and they, they take them. I'll give you a, I was talking at a festival a couple of years ago
in Wales. It's, it's, you know, it's got how the light gets in and it's a big intellectual music
and music festival. And after my talk, a lady came up to me and she said, yeah, I got a cherry with
the, you know, I'm a, I'm a nurse. She says, I got a kid. It's difficult. I mean, I'm not married.
She says, but I get up every morning, you know, and I get the kid to school and I come back. She
says, I have a cigarette, a cup of coffee and a mushroom. And I've been really good for the last
few years. And, and, and there's anecdotally, there's large numbers of people who are using mushrooms.
Do they work or not? We don't know because it's almost, the rules around these drugs,
the Schedule 1 status means that a single mushroom is just as illegal as a bunch of mushrooms or as
pure cytoside. Four years ago, we got ethical permission to do a microdosing study with LSD.
But they said, this is an illegal drug, a dangerous drug. Every microdose had to be given in hospital.
And then we costed up what it would take to buy all that time in hospitals to do six weeks of
microdosing. We couldn't afford it. And so there has never been a proper controlled microdosing
study of any, repeatedly, of any psychedelic. But from a mechanism of action standpoint, David, do you,
do you see a plausible path to it, to microdosing being effective given what you now know about
macrodosing? Well, it won't be as good. Obviously not a single microdose won't be remotely as good.
But say repeatedly, because I believe in your study, they were given this macrodose every two weeks,
correct? Twice. Every two, three weeks apart. Oh, twice. Yeah, that's right. So, but if we
were talking about microdosing three or four times a week at, you know, one to two milligrams,
and we're talking about this type of a treatment over the course of a year, so apples to apples
time wise. Is there a plausibility here that you can see from a mechanism standpoint?
Well, it'd be a great experiment to do. I mean, I think it is, I mean, I think, and I think it's
ethical to do that, because I think it is plausible that microdosing over a long period
might do two things. I would be slightly surprised if it really elevated mood and depressed people,
but it might protect people about people against a lowering of mood. And so one of the interesting
questions, in fact, in many ways, the fundamental question we have now, as a result of our two
depression studies is not that we can get back people better, there's no question with cytosybing,
how can we keep them well. And one of the great things we know about the SSRIs is if you take
them continuously, they do protect against depression, they do protect against the
stresses of life causing depression at the cost of blunting. So the question is, how, what could
we do other than give them an SSRI after the psychedelic treatment and maybe microdosing would
work. But until we get it liberated, until we get it out of schedule one and get it available,
it's impossible to do those studies. Where do you think will be the thin end of the wedge to make
that happen? Obviously, Roland Griffiths has done great work at Johns Hopkins, someone I'd like to
have on the podcast as well, looking at psilocybin in end of life depression. Though I don't know
where things are from a pathway perspective, there's obviously efficacy with smoking cessation
and alcohol cessation and now your work with depression. Which of these will be the first
domino that falls in your opinion, to look to change the scheduling of psilocybin?
I think depression, because a multi-centre study is going on in Europe, in the US,
but there's a company called Compass Pathways and they're doing a dose finding study. They finished,
they've recruited the last subject, they would get the results hopefully by Christmas or the new year
and that's a high dose, 25 milligram dose, a placebo dose, a one milligram dose like we did
and a 10 milligram dose in between. I think if that's positive, then the floodgates will open
to their second study and also to funding of that research. Now Compass has come under great
scrutiny from some in their effort to basically do a land grab of intellectual property on a molecule
that basically should be in the public domain. How do you think about that in terms of balancing
the need to make something as widely available as possible to the public, while at the same time
needing to create an economic incentive to do so? Yes, well of course I have to express and I've
been helping them for a lot, I mean their Compass Pathways exists because of our first depression
study. You know they basically took our data and went and tried to do research with it and they
started off being a bit like maps, they started off trying to raise money by being a not-for-profit.
Now Rick Doblin is a phenomenon but it has taken him 25 years to raise enough money
to do the maps phase three and after a year or so Compass Pathways realized that they didn't have
the resources or the skill or the personalities. Yeah Rick's a force of nature. He is and they
realized that they couldn't be a not-for-profit, they had to get the money for this to happen,
they had to go down the more conventional route and so you know much as I would like it not to be
the case you know reality is I think if we want to see cytosybing with enough evidence in my lifetime
to make it a medicine then I think that they're the people that are most likely to deliver that.
But on the other side you've got Oregon, you've got Oregon which voted in November last year
to make mushrooms a medicine in two years time. So it's actually a bit of a race now to see who's
going to win. I don't know how Oregon are going to do it, I just hope they do it carefully and
sensibly but it might be that the mushroom ends up being the medicine rather than the cytosybing.
It's exciting times. David I promised you that at 6pm I would draw to an end and we are at 559pm
so I'm going to stick to my word despite the fact that we are only halfway through what I wanted to
talk about. So I think the only logical conclusion here is that we will have to sit down and do this
again if you're willing. I'd be delighted it's been a wonderful conversation. Thank you so much.
Thank you David. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested
in diving deeper into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies which are a super short podcast that we release every
Tuesday through Friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in but
for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to
trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram,
Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever
podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not
constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have and
they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally,
I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.