Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Hey James, thanks so much for making time to sit down today. It's been a while. I've
wanted to sit down and chat with you.
Yeah, of course. Thank you so much for thinking of me. I'm excited to talk more.
So I'm trying to think when I first read your book, because I read it twice, and like all
good books, you get more out of it I think the second time. In part because I think the deeper
you get down the rabbit hole of trying to create habits, whether it's in yourself or helping others
form habits, the more you realize how challenging it can be. But maybe for folks who haven't read
it, because I suspect there's going to be a bunch of people listening to this who have read it, and I
want to be able to go deeper for them, and then I think there's going to be some people who haven't
read it. Maybe give us a bit of the history as to why this even appealed to you.
Yeah, well first thank you for saying that. I feel like that's the ultimate measure of whether
a book is good or not is it worth rereading. And that's a high bar. There are many books I've
reread, but yeah, I really appreciate you taking the time to do it twice.
So what excited me about habits? I think there are a few things. The first is you're building
habits all the time, whether you're thinking about them or not. So you know, depending on
which study you look at somewhere between 40 and 50% of our behaviors seem to be automatic and
habitual. But most of the time, those studies are looking at things that are like, you know, more or
less automatic brushing your teeth, tying your shoes, unplugging the toaster after each use.
But I think the true influence of your habits is even greater than that. Because a lot of the time,
the behaviors that you're taking are shaped or influenced by the habits that preceded them.
So you can imagine standing in line at, you know, the grocery store or having three or four minutes
free in your kitchen, and you habitually pull your phone out of your pocket. Well, you know,
the next five or 10 minutes might be spent thinking carefully about what email you're responding to,
or the video game you're playing or scrolling social media. But that conscious, you know,
maybe non habitual behavior was shaped or set by the habit of pulling your phone out. So the the
reach of our habits is very wide, and it's influencing our behavior all the time. So that's
one reason why it's important. And I think that if you're going to be building habits anyway,
you might as well understand like, what they are and how they work and how to shape them.
So that you can be the architect of your habits and not the victim of them.
A lot of people feel like their habits are happening to them, like they don't get a whole
lot of influence on it. And partially, I think it's just because you know, it's this process,
your brain is going through all the time, to try to automate and make behaviors more efficient.
But if you don't really know what's happening, or where to adjust it, then it kind of feels like
it's happening to you rather than happening for you. And then I would say the second thing that
kind of really got me diving in deeper and thinking about it more carefully is just the
realization that most of us in life want some kind of results, you know, we want to get better
at a skill, or we want to lose weight, or to make more money or reduce stress and gain peace of mind.
And whatever the results are that you're looking for, most of the time, your results are a lagging
measure of the habits that preceded them. So, you know, your bank account is a lagging measure of
your financial habits, your weight is a lagging measure of your nutrition and training habits,
your knowledge is a lagging measure of your reading and learning habits, even like the
clutter on your desk at work or in your garage is a lagging measure of your cleaning habits. And so,
you know, habits are not the only thing that influence outcomes in life, you know, you have
luck and randomness, you've got misfortune, but by definition, randomness is not under your control.
And I think the only reasonable approach is to focus on what's in your control.
And over long time horizons, your results tend to bend in the direction of your habits. And so I
think, because your brain is building habits all the time anyway, and because your results are
heavily influenced by the habits that you repeat, those are two primary reasons that I feel like
got me interested in the topic, but also just good reasons for anybody to be fascinated with habits.
I'm guessing there's a lot of sort of, well, probably evolutionary rationale for why we're
creatures of habits, right? I mean, I think the presumably the less energy we had to devote to
things that would help us survive and procreate the better. And obviously, that's why we have an
autonomic nervous system that allows us to function, you know, things like breathing and having your
heart go from, you know, beating fast or beating slow to be completely out of your voluntary
control. I'm curious as to whether or not we have a sense of, you know,
ancestrally, what types of habits were people ever trying to deliberately change?
Maybe it's not an answerable question. I don't know if you ever contemplated that. Like,
when did this idea of being proactive in either breaking a habit or creating a new habit? Do you
get the sense that that is a recent luxury of our species? Yeah, I kind of, so I don't know the
answer to the question, but I do have some thoughts on it. And I feel like it probably does skew
somewhat recent for one particular reason, which is, generally speaking, our ancestors lived in
what was primarily an immediate return environment. The majority of the decisions that you would make
that meaningfully impacted your survival were ones that were relatively immediate in nature. So
taking shelter from a storm or avoiding a lion on the savannah or foraging for the next meal in
a berry bush. These are things that like had a pretty quick payoff in your life. If you fast
forward to modern society, though, and we could define that however you want, but probably say the
last 500 years or something like that, certainly the last hundred years, modern society seems to
have created quite a few structures that favor not an immediate return environment, but a delayed
return environment. So you go to work today so that you can get a paycheck in two weeks,
or you study at school today so that you can graduate in four years, or you save for retirement
today so that you can, you know, not have to work a couple decades from now. And there are a lot of
structures that are like that in modern society that that tend to reward delayed gratification.
And so I think in a sense, we're kind of walking through this modern society that rewards ourselves
for patients. And we still have this like paleolithic hardware, where we prioritize instant
gratification and immediate returns in a lot of ways in some kind of evolutionary sense.
And you can see how there's a little bit of a mismatch there. And I wonder if it's that
modern mismatch that has led to the desire to, to change our behavior, and to adjust habits,
and perhaps it wasn't something that we thought about as carefully or cared about as much
in, you know, 1000 years ago, or 5000 years ago, or longer.
It is interesting, though, to say that some aspects of modern society are mismatched with that,
with that ancestral wiring. But some of them are not like, why do we care about delaying
gratification to get a PhD or delaying gratification to save more money, primarily because it affords
some form of status, which is very hierarchical and very, we think, you know, evolutionarily wired
in. So there's, there's still connections there. It's just that not all of it is aligned.
Yeah, it seems that the the the vehicles that we would have used to attain status
earlier were much quote unquote simpler. And today, we're looking at other ways to do it.
You know, hearing you talk about habits that way makes me compare two activities I like very much.
And contrast the challenges of learning each of them. So one is riding a bike and the other is
learning to swim. So if you took a 20 year old who had never done both, and admittedly, it's easy
to find a 20 year old that's never swim, it's probably hard to find a 20 year old that's never
ridden a bike, but I would posit that it's really easy to teach a 20 year old to ride a bike,
if they haven't done it. And let's assume for a moment, this isn't someone who had never been
able to do it before. But some, you know, you sort of found somebody who'd never ridden a bike at 20.
And the reason I would argue that is in a bike, the the object is balanced, right? It's really
about balance. And you get your feedback immediately. So you know, the second you're out of
balance on a bike, because you're in the environment of the air, and the air has a density such that
it's not forgiving, you basically are out of balance, you're going to fall. Conversely, although
most people don't think of it this way, swimming is also about balance in the water. You're, you're
trying to balance yourself this way versus this way, most people would naturally sink feet first,
and you're trying to balance yourself this way so that you can breathe. And those things are not
easy to do, because the feedback loop is very long, and it's very hard to make the connection
that you're out of balance, it also doesn't hurt as much when you fail. So when you fall off your
bike, it's very uncomfortable. But when you're out of balance and swimming, you just have to work
harder, but you don't realize why you're working harder. Anyway, that's why I think it's very hard
to learn how to swim, and it's not very hard to learn how to ride a bike. And therefore, it
requires much more deliberate practice to learn to swim than it does to ride a bike, at least at
some basic level. As a fascinating question, it's really good raises a lot of interesting details
about why we form habits and how they form. So first, I'll kind of give a roundabout answer here,
but I'll come back to your question. So what is it that determines whether a habit is good or bad?
You know, we use these phrases a lot of the time in conversation, we say, Oh, it's a bad habit,
it's a good habit. And sometimes people will ask me like, well, why do I repeat this habit? If it's
bad for me, you know, if it's so terrible, then how can I keep coming back to it? And I think we can
divide, you know, in a sense, some, you know, if you want to get really pedantic about or really
academic about it, some researchers don't even like to use the word good or bad, because they're
their habits, and they all serve you in some way. So we could just say basically adaptive or
maladaptive. Right? Yeah. And I think we could make a meaningful division, in the sense of how
we use it in most conversation and say that pretty much all behaviors produce multiple outcomes
across time. And broadly speaking, we could lump it into an immediate bucket, an immediate outcome
and an ultimate outcome. And what you find is that for most bad habits, the immediate outcome is
actually pretty favorable. Like, you know, the classic example, smoking a cigarette, but if you
smoke a cigarette outside the office at 10am with a friend, well, then immediately you get some
socialization. Maybe it curbs your nicotine craving, or just lets you like de stress for a couple
minutes or get a break from work. There are all kinds of things that you might be benefiting from.
It's only two or five or 10 years later, that the ultimate outcome is negative. With the good habits,
especially the first time you perform them, it's often the reverse, like the first week of training
in the gym, your body looks the same in the mirror, you're sore, you don't really have much to show for
the effort that you're putting in. You feel kind of stupid in there, you're wondering if people judge
you, or if you're doing it the wrong way. There are a lot of upfront costs. And it's only two or
five or 10 years later that you get the outcome that you're looking for. And so in a sense, the
cost of your good habits is in the present. The cost of your bad habits is in the future. And that
misalignment between when you feel rewarded and when you feel punished, helps to explain why we
tend to fall pretty easily into a lot of things that we would categorize as bad like eating donuts
or smoking a cigarette or whatever, and fall less easily into things that we categorize as good or
you know, it feels like I have to force myself to write or whatever. Now, that's very similar to
what you just mentioned about this, like the immediacy of the feedback. You know, bad habits
are giving you pretty immediate feedback, kind of like riding a bike, good habits are giving you
pretty delayed feedback, maybe, you know, a little bit analogous to swimming. I think that example of
the medium that you're in air versus water is fascinating to think about water as being like a
feedback dampener. But there is another element to it, which you also mentioned, which is the
strength of the feedback. So you know, falling on the ground off a bike and skinning your knees,
like pretty painful, you learn quite quickly. Technically, making a bad stroke in the water,
you don't really pay too much of a cost if you're being sloppy with your form. And so it's unlikely
that you rectify that quickly. And this is a phenomenon that I think is so critical or so
important to behavior change, I call it the cardinal rule of behavior change in atomic habits,
which is behaviors that get immediately rewarded, get repeated behaviors that get immediately
punished, get avoided. And it's really about the speed and the intensity of that feedback. And
generally speaking, the quicker you can get feedback, and the more too intense is maybe a
bit much. But you know, at some point you need it needs to be high enough to move the needle can't
be so low that, you know, it doesn't register. So you need both meaningful feedback and quick
feedback if you want behavior to change. Yeah. And well, actually, I want to come back to that
topic because I think therein lies one of the themes of your book, right? Which is that
willpower is not a great long term strategy. But before I get to that, I want to kind of talk a
little bit about you personally, at least before you came to these realizations.
Are you someone I didn't mean, I know you're an athlete in your book, you write about
this horrible accident you had when you were playing baseball. I believe that was high school
or was it in college? Yep, sophomore year of high school. During that period of your life,
were you someone that others and your peers would have looked at you and said, Oh God, that James,
that guy is so disciplined. I mean, he just has what it takes to always get the job done. And he,
you know, never sort of indulges in the wrong things and always does the right things. Like,
were you were you one of those guys that was just a beacon of a quote unquote discipline or were
you a normal guy or were you someone who had a hard time doing what was right?
Well, I wasn't someone who had a hard time, but I do think it depends on the context. So,
you know, I let's keep it simple, like homework, sports, kind of those things.
So with school, definitely. I always liked school. I was like the nerdy kid on the sports teams I
was on. But, you know, in the science lab or something, I was like the jock, which is kind
of funny how you change based on the room that you're in. And so I always felt like I kind of
played that middle ground between those two. I think it helped me learn how to get along with
both groups and, you know, it was helpful socially and all that. But earlier in my life, I think I
thrived more in school than I did in sports. I was never, you know, like I barely got to play in
high school. You know, that's one of the punchlines of that early story in the book is I've ended up
playing a total of 11 innings in high school. Now, I kind of blossomed once I got to college and
ended up being an academic All-American by the time I graduated. But that came much later. So
it really sort of depended on the context. But generally speaking, I would say, yeah,
people probably thought that I was disciplined, but I do think it depended on where we were.
If it was just looking at school, then I think people would say that if you're looking somewhere
else, then maybe not. Was there an area that you struggled with, from a behavior standpoint?
To be honest, there were areas that I avoided because I thought I would struggle. So I think
it was I think it was more about me being fearful and avoiding anything I thought I would be bad at
than it was about watching him and being like, oh, look at him floundering around.
And I think I had to kind of overcome that wiring over the course of a decade or two. It took me a
long time to start to take more risks and take on things that I didn't think I would be good at,
rather than just trying to like stack the deck and just do what I thought I would do well.
I don't know how much you've paid attention to the sort of discussion debate around free will.
I have always sort of assumed we have free will. This is one of those things that
is kind of anathema to me to imagine a world under which I'm not completely
under control of my own will and my behavior. But my good friend, Sam Harris, who I don't know if
you were familiar with Sam's work, but he's written and spoken.
Yeah, I did an episode on his podcast as well.
Okay. So you're familiar with the fact that he's written extensively and spoken extensively about
the idea that we actually don't have free will, that this is an illusion. There are examples that
I can conjure up to make that case. For example, he uses a very clever thought experiment, which is,
if I tell you to think of a movie, the first movie that pops into your head,
you have no control over what that's going to be. Conversely, there's a part of me that thinks,
okay, but there were lots of things I have free will over. My desire to, or my ability to go and
do something, whether it be take an action, go and exercise or something like that. But the deeper I
get into this thinking, the more I start to realize, well, wait a minute, that may still be innate.
This ability that I have, using myself as an example, to really have an easy time exercising,
it requires virtually no effort to exercise. In fact, it usually requires a lot of effort to
sometimes not exercise, but requiring a lot of effort to mind what I eat. And I know people for
whom that's not the case, right? I know people for whom they just have an easy time eating what's
healthy, but maybe they don't like to exercise that much. So when you, I guess, before I go any
deeper than my question, let me just pause and ask you for your reaction to that overall line of
inquiry and how do you think about free will as it pertains to what we're going to talk about today?
Yeah. Well, first, I think I'm probably similar to you in the sense like exercise has always been
on the easier side for me. Nutrition has always been on the harder side, which is kind of
interesting there. I don't know exactly what that reveals, but just interesting to think about where
you have certain inclinations and maybe not others. With respect to free will, I understand
the argument like in once you start to walk through, it's like, okay, yeah, there's this
very long chain of atoms that are essentially colliding and leading us inevitably to, you know,
the next action or the next thought or whatever. And if we could map them all out, then perhaps
we could just predict everything that's about to happen. So I get that as a thought experiment.
I tend to, when I'm living my daily life, fall in the same space that sounds like you fall in,
which is, well, I'm going to continue to act as if I have free will. And ultimately, the more that
I think about it, I usually come down on that side where it's like, listen, the truth is nobody knows
the answer one way or another. We have we have good arguments, perhaps for each, but nobody knows
for sure. If it is all predetermined, then it kind of doesn't really matter. I'm going to do this
anyway. And if it isn't predetermined, I might as well choose the thing that, you know, I think
best serves me. So whether I'm making that actually getting to make that choice that best serves me,
or whether it was predetermined that I'm going to make the good choice, it kind of doesn't really
matter to me like I might as well choose to act that way. So I don't know, I would be very curious
to hear what Sam's thought on that is, but I don't from a practical standpoint, I don't see a reason
to not choose the best option that you can. In the event that you do have free will, you'll be
glad that you chose it. In the event that you don't have free will, you didn't get a say anyway.
So who cares? Yeah. And the other the other thing I add, I guess what I did that is
it might be that free will or the absence of free will is what determines a person's
maybe call it genetic propensity to change habits or form habits. There may be some people for whom
that is easier than others, but that's probably a spectrum. And it doesn't imply that a person
who struggles with a given behavior can't learn to master it just as a, you know, so again, using
an example, I'll never be a Michael Phelps, like ever, right? There is no there is no scenario under
which I was going to be as good a swimmer as Michael Phelps. So even if he hadn't started swimming
till he was 15 and my parents threw me in the water at two, I was never going to be that good.
But it doesn't mean I couldn't learn to swim. And similarly, had he never been thrown in the pool,
we would never have heard his name. So I guess that's how I kind of rationalize it, which is
there are going to be people for whom it is easier to go through the exercises that we're going to
talk about. And there are people for whom that's just going to be more difficult. And in the end,
you're sort of you can't change that part of it. That's the part, I guess, that is sort of set.
Yeah. And I a couple thoughts to add on to that. So I thought of this when you first brought this
up a few minutes ago. I don't know if you're familiar with David Epstein, his very much sports
team and range and so on. So David's great and a good friend of mine, a really nice guy and just
very thoughtful with the way he puts arguments together, which I always appreciate.
And I was having a conversation with him about some of this stuff. And he said one of the things
that surprised him when he was researching the sports gene is that characteristics that he
thought would be mostly genetic, like, you know, strength and speed and things like that,
turned out to be heavily influenced by training and choice and a lot of other stuff.
And qualities that he thought would be a choice like grit and perseverance and desire to train
turned out to have a much higher genetic component than he realized. I always love the example.
I think this is in sports gene who talks about Steffi Graff just happened to be in a tennis
study when she was young. She was like 14 or something. And she was part of this cohort of
young Germans that were being studied. And she not only tested the highest for physical abilities,
like strength and speed and quickness and so on, but also tested the highest for competitiveness
and desire to train and all these other things. And you just I just love when combinations like
that come together, like think about how pointless this is to compete against her. Not only is she
better than you, she also wants it more. And so I do think that there's a heavy genetic component
to some of the mental characteristics that would make you more likely to train some of these aspects
or more interested in some things than others. To your point about Phelps and you know, whether
he had ever been dropped in the pool or not, that I think is a on the surface, it seems like something
that would make you less motivated. It would you would say, Oh, well, why even try? I'm never going
to be Michael Phelps. Or if genes play such a large role, what's the point? But I actually think
that's the wrong lesson to take away. The primary lesson I think is that genes don't,
they don't tell you not to work hard, they tell you where to work hard, or they don't tell you
not to have a strategy, they just inform your strategy. This is another line that David told
me in a conversation once we said, I was saying, you know, a lot of people talk about grit and
perseverance and discipline. But what if that is just your natural propensity based on the thing
that you're working on? Like what you know, what if I just happened to look kind of gritty,
in my terms of, you know, weight training, or working at writing a book compared to the
average person, but I just look that way, because I happen to like those things. And he said, Yeah,
there's this whole line of thinking that like grit is fit. And so actually, the way to increase your
perseverance and discipline is to find areas or categories or skills where you're highly
interested in them, you know, it's very hard to beat the person who's having fun, because they're
going to want to keep working longer than the person who's suffering. So grit is fit, I think
is one way in which you can maybe try to stack the deck or stack the odds in your favor and get your
genes aligned with the things that you're working on. And then, you know, there are going to be
things like, you know, Michael Phelps in a pool, where you're like, Listen, this body was just
designed to do this thing, you know, it's very hard to find somebody who's more optimally designed
to move through the water than him. And not all of us are going to have the good fortune of
discovering whatever that thing is for us in our lives at age four or six or whatever. But I don't
think that that means you should stop searching. This is one of the benefits of trial and error,
you know, the person who is curious and willing to explore a lot of things is more likely to come
across an area where they are fascinated or they are interested. And it also is a really good fit
for their natural abilities or propensities or whatever. And that's kind of the primary lesson
that I take away from the genetic side of things is, you know, similar to what you said, anybody
can improve doesn't mean anybody can be Michael Phelps, but you can always improve your ability.
And let's try to find that thing that I'm fascinated with, that I'm interested in,
so where it doesn't feel like I'm suffering in the same way that other people are when they're
trying this thing. And you often be surprised how far you can go and how willing you are to build
habits and improve skills if you find some of those things that you're truly fascinated by.
Yeah, two comments that add to that one completely trite, but amusing, which is,
you know, not only does Phelps have the perfect chassis and engine for what he does, but
just as you described, Steffi Graf, I've seen Phelps race at meets that meant nothing, right? So,
you know, like total throwaway meets, he's not shaved, he's not tapered, he couldn't care less
to be there. And, you know, he's swimming like a 200 IM and he is, it doesn't look like he's going
to win at all. And yet somehow in the last 15 meters, he out touches everybody. And I've seen
this on enough occasions that I just think like this is a guy who hates losing. So even though
he's not necessarily in shape at this moment, even though this meet means nothing for him,
he's training through it and half the people he's competing against, this is their pinnacle.
He hates losing so much. So it is, I have the same take on watching the last dance when, you know,
it's like you see these clips of Michael Jordan, they had that there was that one summer where he
was recording Space Jam and they set up like a tent for him outside the movie studio and all the
NBA players came in like each night to play pickup games. And it was basically just like, you know,
he just got done filming like 12 hours a day, but he just could not handle losing a pickup game. It
would just bother him so much to not get it right to not win. And yeah, I got to think that that is
maybe not exclusively, but at least largely just he can't turn it off. He doesn't know any other
way to be, you know, that's personality or genes or whatever you want to call it. It's just that's
just how he's wired. And I actually love it when I see that that characteristic in any domain.
Maggie Rogers, who's a musician, she had this post she put on Instagram where it was all of her
notes on a particular song that they were working on and like, you know, hey, I think we need to
bring the symbol in, you know, a second earlier here and, you know, a bunch of other stuff. And
then she shared a little clip of her listening to it with her producer and so on. And you could
just tell that she cared so much about the details. It would bother her if the song was not as good as
it could possibly be. And, you know, that's maybe that's the musician's version of hates to lose.
And I love it when I see that characteristic. It just like it kind of lights me up. It makes me
want to be that way about whatever thing I'm working on. You just if you can find that area
where it would bother you for it to not be right. I got to think you're going to get much better
results there than most people because most people get bored or move on or, you know,
get tired or frustrated. And the person who just will not stop unless it's right is going to end
up with better results. It sounds simple to say the way to have great results is to not lower your
standards, but in a lot of ways, it turns out to be more true than you would expect.
Yeah. And I agree with you. I love watching this in the best of the best. And, you know,
Formula One is one of my favorite sports and especially, you know, historically, you know,
my my hero is this guy named by Art Tonsena. And to hear him, I watch that documentary. I'd never
heard of him. I know very little about for one. I it was awesome. After watching that,
I was like completely hooked. This is a fascinating sport. Yeah. Well, and you gather from the from
that documentary. I mean, that his I mean, he was a perfectionist, even amongst his peers.
He took it to a level that exceeded that. It actually cost him his life. I don't think the
documentary fully explains how much that that need to win killed him because the day he died,
he was trying to do something in a car that shouldn't have been done at a time when it
shouldn't have been done. But it's amazing when in a sport like that, where the stakes are so high
for trying to to do something at the expense of, you know, maybe a mechanical limit or a limit of
the car. But yet all drivers will tell you like they're they're going to go for it. If there's a
gap there, they're going to take they're going to go for the gap. And, you know, there was there was
a debate in the 90s in Formula One because that was before, you know, so Senna's death changed the
sport forever because that's really what changed the imposed safety in the sport. But the debate
prior to that was, look, we'll just tell the drivers to drive slower. You know, they don't have
to drive this fast there. You know, they can choose to drive 10 percent slower, which of course was
nonsense. Right. I mean, the head of the F.I.A. at the time who has just recently passed away
made a point which was that that's the dumbest thing you could ever say. They will all choose
to have a less safe car if it goes faster because you're talking about the 20 most competitive
drivers on the planet. Now, there was another point I was going to make that was so you talked
about. Oh, yeah, here is the point. For most of us, we will never know what it's like to be the top
thousand in the world of anything. Right. Like I could if I think about all the things that I love
driving a race car, shooting my bow and arrow, you know, exercising. I mean, I'm multiple orders
of magnitude beneath even the most lowly ranked professional of those things. And this gets into
something else, which is for me, at least the joy is not in the absolute comparison of myself to
others, but the relative comparison of where I was before. Do you think that's a universal thing?
Is it universal that people are mostly engaged by how much they are making progress relative to their
own performance? Or do you think that there are some people who are only capable of finding pleasure
when being compared to others in an absolute basis? The second half of that question, I'm not sure of.
I generally I think both of those things are universal. I think one, it's universal that the
one of the most motivating feelings to the human mind is the feeling of progress.
And I think it's fairly universal that progress feels good. You know, we are in a sense at the
most base level, we are goal directed organisms in the sense that, you know, we have a goal to get
food or water or to procreate or to be safe. And we want to move toward those things and resolve
the tension, the gap between that goal and our current state as much as possible. And, you know,
now with our complex brains and modern society, we come up with many other goals that are outside
of just our basic needs like food and water. We have goals like getting a promotion at work or,
you know, losing 10 pounds or whatever it is. But that same tension between where you are currently
and where you want to be, we want to have that resolved. And the more progress that you feel like
you're making toward one of those things, I think that generally feels good. So I feel like that's
pretty universal. I also do think it seems to be fairly universal that we have some bias toward
status, some bias toward prestige and rank and hierarchy. And it feels good for pretty much
anybody to win the game or to have the best score on the scoreboard or to climb the leaderboard.
And the more that you see yourself occupying a higher run relative to those around you,
whether it's with wealth or money or fame, the better that feels too. And it probably is a
spectrum or maybe each of those is a spectrum. And some people have the dial turned up real high
on the status part and maybe lower on the internal measures. And other people have it,
you know, the reverse. But I generally think we all have them to some degree and you probably
will find yourself feeling good if you happen to succeed on either of those metrics.
And how much of it do you think is, for lack of a better term, journey versus destination focused?
Because if you talk about your example of weight loss, right, that is generally a very
destination based metric. I want to lose 10 pounds. I'm not going to be happy until I lose 10 pounds.
The process of how I go about doing it, changing the way I'm eating, changing my exercise,
accepting the fact that you're not going to lose 10 pounds linearly, it's going to look like this.
You know, those are details that I'm going to will, I'm willing to tolerate, but I want to lose
those 10 pounds or I want to fit into this piece of clothing that I used to fit into. Contrast that
with I want to learn to speak Italian and I'm enjoying this process of learning a few new words
every day and learning how the structure of this grammar works relative to my native tongue. And
I'm never going to be perfectly fluent in Italian, but I know that in some point I'm going to be
completely functional, but it's more that this journey of learning this new language or learning
how to play this instrument, that's what's giving me the pleasure. And I don't know if that distinction
makes sense, but sure. I think, you know, this is first, I should say this is coming from someone
who's been very goal oriented for most of their life. You know, like I would set goals for the
grades I wanted to get in school for the weight I wanted to lift in the gym for the numbers I wanted
my business to hit. And at some point I actually found this sheet that I made my sophomore year
of college for the goals that I wanted to hit by the time I graduated. It was funny looking back
on it like 10 or 11 years later, because, you know, about half of them I hit the other half I didn't.
And I was like, obviously setting the goal was not the thing that made the difference, right? Like
if it did, I would have hit them all. So something else is going on here. And I kind of had to like,
it was like a little remedial training session for myself or something realizing that, you know,
goals are not the primary thing that drives results. And in fact, if you look at the performance
in most domains, the winners and the losers have the same goal. Presumably every Formula One driver
has the goal of winning the race when they take off from the starting line. You know, if you have
a job opening and a hundred candidates apply for the job, presumably every candidate has the goal
of getting the job. So the goal is not the thing that makes the difference in the performance. And
if the winners and the losers have the same goal, then it cannot be the distinguishing factor. Maybe
it's necessary. Perhaps there's an argument necessary for success, but it's not sufficient for it.
And so that got me thinking more like, well, what is it then that drives it? And I, in the book,
the way that I described is the difference between systems and goals. And so, you know,
your, your goal is your desired outcome, your target, the thing you're shooting for,
your system is the collection of daily habits that you follow. You know, it's like all these
little gears in this overall machine. And if there's ever a gap between your desired outcome
and your daily habits, if there's ever a gap between your goal and your system,
your daily habits will always win, right? Almost by definition, your current habits are perfectly
designed for your current results. So whatever system you've been running for the last, you know,
six months or year or whatever, you talked about shooting a bow and arrow, presumably whatever
system of movements you have going on there, pre shot routine, how you draw it back, everything,
it kind of is inevitably carrying you toward the result of where the arrow ends up. And,
you know, sort of the irony of all this is we also badly want better results in life. You know,
we also badly want to make more money or to reduce stress or lose weight or whatever.
But the results are not actually the thing that needs to change. It's kind of like fix the inputs
and the outputs will fix themselves. And there are some areas like shooting a bow where that is the
connection is quite obvious. But there are other areas where for whatever reason, we don't see it
as clearly, but I think that the pattern is still there, which is let's adjust the habits, let's get
this machine running in a more fluid fashion. And you'll find that the results kind of come naturally.
So I think just appreciating that helped rewire my mindset a little bit. I was so focused on
outcomes and goals for a long time. And now realizing that actually the way this is driven
is with the system that helped me shift from, you know, what I would say now is like
goals are for people who care about winning one time, you set a goal to run a half marathon,
and you train for three months and you do it and you complete the race. But then maybe you
stop training after that. But systems are for people who care about winning again and again.
And if you care about sustaining that success, then you're like, you know, I'm a runner, I care
about the system that I'm building for how I train, how many miles I'm getting in, all kinds
of other stuff. And whether I have a half marathon three months in the distance or not, it doesn't
really matter because I like I'm going to be running my system either way. And so making that
mental shift, I think can be useful for sustaining results. So let's talk about habits now, because
I think that's the thing that, as you said, basically shapes the nature of what we're going
to do. There's a saying that many people have said, and I won't even try to paraphrase it because
at the moment it's escaping me, but the gist of it is like you don't rise to the level of your,
what is it? You don't rise to the level of your training, you fall to the level,
or you fall to the level of your training and what would it be?
Right. The original quote, I think it's from Arcilocus, I believe a Greek philosopher,
and said, you don't rise to the level of your expectations, you fall to the level of your
training. And in Atomic Habits, I tweaked that or adjusted that to say, you don't rise to the level
of your goals, you fall to the level of your systems. And so it's actually your habits that
kind of create that baseline. So why is it called Atomic Habits? I think, I remember when I first
saw the title, my assumption was Atomic must be huge explosion, like big habits, which of course
is exactly not what it means. So, so, uh, well, it's, it's good. Actually, it's interesting which
meanings people pull out when they see it. Cause so I chose the phrase Atomic Habits for three
reasons. Um, the first meaning of the word atomic is tiny or small, like an atom. And I do think
habits should be small and fairly easy to do, especially in the beginning. The second meaning
of the word atomic is the fundamental unit in a larger system. And that's the one that people
often overlook, you know, like atom is built into molecules, molecules built into compounds and so
on. And your habits are kind of like that. Each little habit is like a, you know, a little atom
in the overall routine of your day. You put them all together and you end up with your lifestyle or
your daily routine. And then the third and final meaning is the one that you mentioned, you know,
the source of immense energy or power. And I think if you put all three meanings together,
you sort of understand the narrative arc of the book, which is make changes that are small and
easy to do, layer them on top of each other, like units in a larger system or atoms in a molecule.
And collectively you can get some really powerful or remarkable results. And so I feel like the phrase
atomic habits not only encapsulates that kind of small change in the system that you're looking to
build, but also the powerful results that can emanate from that. So you talk about three different
types of change, right? There's sort of the outcome change, the process change. We've touched
on a little bit of those, but the one we haven't really touched on is this identity change. And
that was something that when I read your book really resonated because it provided, I think,
a very decent explanation, at least for why exercise comes naturally to me, which is it's
so hardwired into my identity and why maybe certain other habits I've tried to create over time
don't come easily to me because I haven't fully identified with them yet. So explain a little bit
what, you know, first of all, what, you know, expand on that, but also how you kind of came to realize that.
Yeah. So two things before I unpack the idea a little more fully. First is of all the ideas
in the book, this is probably the least scientific. There are actually some studies,
which I cite in that chapter and it's not like there's no science behind it, but the majority of
the book, I try to be very robust in the way that I was thinking about, like, how do we build habits
and what actually gets in the stick? And there also are just a bazillion, you know, social
psychology and cognitive psychology studies that, you know, illustrate a lot of the examples that I
talk about. But this is more of a mindset, I would say, or a philosophy on how behavior change works.
Second thing is it's maybe the only unique idea that I have. Pretty much everything else that I
share is, you know, stuff that's been widely covered by other people or, you know, things that
we've known for hundreds, if not thousands of years. But I felt like this was something that,
you know, maybe I could contribute to the conversation. And part of the reason I started
thinking about it is I started asking, like, why do habits really matter? You know, why do we
we seem to care about them a lot as a society? It's something a lot of books get written about,
something we talk about a lot. There's clearly some kind of deeper importance to them. So what is it?
And the surface level answer is that we care about habits because they get us these external
things that make us more productive and more fit and so on. And habits can help you do all
that stuff, which is great. But I think the real reason, the deeper reason that habits matter
is that they are a signal internally to ourselves about who we are and what we care about. And,
you know, they're kind of a signal of like the story that we're telling ourselves.
So in a sense, every time that you perform a habit, you are embodying a particular identity.
Like when you make your bed, you embody the identity of someone who is clean and organized.
When you shoot a basketball for 30 minutes, you embody the identity of someone who is a
basketball player. And, you know, you do those things once or twice, it doesn't radically
transform the story you have by yourself. But if you keep showing up and shooting a
basketball every day for six months or two years, or, you know, at some point, you cross this sort
of invisible threshold where you're like, yeah, being a basketball player is like part of who I
am, you know, it's some aspect of my identity. And so your habits provide evidence, they provide
proof of the story that you're telling yourself. And that I think is a very powerful thing, a very
deep personal thing that habits can provide, and perhaps the real reason why they matter.
So to come back to your question about process versus outcome versus identity, and kind of
where how we change, usually when people set out to make some kind of change, they start by thinking
about the results or the outcome that they want. So they say, I want to lose 40 pounds in the next
six months. And then from that outcome, they back into a process or a plan. So they say,
All right, if I want to lose 40 pounds, then I need to follow this nutrition plan, I'm going to
need to work out four days a week. And maybe there are details to those plans and everything.
But that's usually kind of roughly where it stops. And then the assumption is, if I do those things,
and I lose that weight, then I'll be the kind of person that I want to be. And the argument that I
try to unpack in that chapter is what if we worked backwards from this? What if instead we said,
who is the type of person I wish to be? What is the identity that I'd like to have? And in fact,
we could even ask like, the person who has that identity, what kind of habits would they have?
And then we use that identity to inform the process, the habits, and we let the outcomes
come naturally. And there are a variety of examples of this. I one reader of mine, she
lost a bunch of weight, I think it was 110 pounds in total. And she kept, she's kept it off for over
a decade. And the question that she sort of carried around with her as she was starting her
weight loss journey is what would a healthy person do? And that's very much aligned or oriented with
that identity piece. It's like, okay, would a healthy person take a cab? Or would they walk
four blocks the next meeting? Would they order a salad and chicken at lunch? Or would they have a
hamburger and fries? And she could just kind of carry that question around with her to every
context she was in, and make a choice that she felt like aligned with the identity that she wanted to
have, rather than worrying necessarily about, you know, something specific, like the number of
macros she's getting, or, you know, whatever. Now, I should say, I think it can work both ways,
like I count my macros and works really well for me. But I think that's partially because it'll
aligns with the identity that I already have. And if you aren't, if you don't have that shift
in internal story yet, it's hard for the behavior to follow suit, you know, like imagine,
imagine you went up to two people. And you said, Hey, would you like a cigarette? And the first
person says, Oh, no, thanks, I'm trying to quit. And the second person says, Oh, no, thanks, I'm
not a smoker. Now, technically, they've done the same thing, they both turned down the cigarette.
But the second person kind of has signaled a shift in identity change, like they the first
person is trying to be something they're not, no, thanks, I'm trying to quit. And the second person
is saying, I'm not a smoker. It's just not something that I do. And I think once you get to
that stage, that shift in identity, you're in a much more powerful place from a behavior change
standpoint, because you're not even really trying to change anymore. You're just acting in alignment
with the type of person you see yourself to be. So we can talk about ways to do that. But that's
kind of the quick version on identity versus outcome. Tell me what you think the difference
is in identity between the woman you gave the example of and say yourself, so you're both
striving to the same objective, which is a healthy weight. But she accomplished it by
focusing on what would a healthy person do in this situation, you accomplish it again,
just pertaining to nutrition at the moment, presumably by saying, you know, I don't know
what your macro goals are. But these are, you know, these are the aspirations that I have,
and I'm going to stick to these. So tell me a little bit about the difference between those
approaches. And how can a person know which will be better for them outside of just empirically
trying them both? Well, I think in this particular case, the primary difference is I had an internal
story or have an internal story that I am a healthy person already. And so just doing things
that are aligned with that, like counting macros feels totally fine. Whereas for her at that early
stage, she did not feel that way and did not genuinely believe that about herself. This is
also I should say, it's possible to have an epiphany and to change, you know, cold turkey or
to just flip a switch and suddenly start acting in a different way. I do think it's possible. I
think sometimes people have experiences like that. Ironically, I think it rarely happens from some
kind of bolts of lightning inside. I think one of the most common ways it happens is by reading
books. I think people will sometimes read a book that really changes their worldview and they start
to do things completely differently after that. You can imagine a bunch of nutrition examples,
like somebody reads a book that convinces them that, you know, carbs are the devil and the grain is
terrible. And all of a sudden, the next day, like they want to throw out all the bread in the house.
And, you know, like it's very, very quick switch has been flipped. So I do think it's possible.
However, I don't think that changing through an epiphany is a very reliable way to change. And
I don't know that it's a it's something you can bank on or can plan around or strategize for.
Might happen to you a couple of times in your life, but I don't think that it's an efficient
way to try to build a new habit. So if you can't change or hope to change through an epiphany,
then what are your options if you want to change your identity? And I think the the best avenue
that you have is to cast votes with your actions. So in a sense, every action you take is like a
vote for the type of person you wish to become. So no, doing one push up does not radically
transform your body, but it does cast a vote for the type of person who doesn't miss workouts.
And no, writing one sentence may not finish the novel, but it does cast a vote for I'm a writer.
And I think this is like a meaningful difference between my approach or what I recommend. And what
you often hear, like you often hear something like fake it till you make it. And I don't necessarily
have anything wrong with fake it till you make it. It's asking you to believe something positive
about yourself. But it's asking you to believe something positive without having evidence for it.
And we have a word for beliefs that don't have evidence, we call that delusion,
right? Like at some point, your brain doesn't like this mismatch between what you're saying
and what you're actually doing. And so to bring it back to your question about my friend who lost
all this weight, I think you have to genuinely believe that story about yourself in order for
the actions to start to feel aligned. And what do you do if you don't genuinely believe you're a
healthy person or don't genuinely believe that I'm the kind of person who would track my macros or
whatever? Well, I think you have to start with these very small habits, you have to start by
proving it to yourself in some little way. Maybe it's just that you did walk the three blocks to
the meeting and didn't take the taxi, or maybe it's just that you did order a salad for lunch
and not a burger and fries. And none of those things individually are going to change your body,
or even the story right away. But if you keep casting votes for that behavior, and keep casting
votes for that identity, then eventually you get to the point where it's like the basketball example,
you kind of have to admit that you're a basketball player, because you've been shooting hoops for
the last two years. And like, this is just part of who you are now. So I think that that's the
primary difference between the two of us is that I already kind of had that story and early on,
she didn't. Now she does. So who knows, maybe now she could just track her macros just as easily,
or even easier than I can. I don't know. Yeah. I wonder how that process changes in this person
after 10 years. I mean, most people understand that losing weight is actually not that hard,
but keeping weight off is exceptionally hard. So what your friend did, yes, losing 110 pounds is
remarkable, but the fact that she's kept it off for a decade is actually what's remarkable.
And I'm curious as to what the temporal sequence of events is where, hey, for the first year,
it was a daily struggle of what would the healthy person do? What would the healthy person do? What
would the healthy person do? And at some point that transitions into, I'm a healthy person,
this is what I do. I'm a healthy person, this is what I do. And then it becomes so autonomic that
you can even slip, you can slip up for a day and it feels wrong. Like it's like,
God, that cotton candy is horrible. Like I don't ever want to eat that again.
Yeah. Well, you said something similar to that a few minutes ago about how like it bothers you to
not work out sometimes, you know, and near y'all who also has written about habits has kind of a
little measure for that reason. Like his measure for whether it's a habit or not is does it bother
you when you don't do it? And I think that's a signal that it's kind of aligned with your
identity. It's like, I kind of feel like I'm not being me if I if I don't do this. And to your
point about it taking a long time, it can take much longer than you would think. I mean, my friend
told me she had to lose 60 pounds before the first person noticed before she ever heard anything from
somebody else. Wow. And, you know, that's, that's a lot of that's a lot of weight, a long time to be
working in essentially what feels like a vacuum feels like you're just doing it for yourself,
no external feedback from the world. So, you know, this comes back to a lot of things we've
already talked about, about process and falling in love with the system. And, you know, there are
a lot of a lot of things that go into it, but it definitely is an internal journey. And it definitely
will take longer than you would imagine. A lot of cases. One of the most common examples that I
hear of in my practice for the epiphany behavior change that sticks is the person who quit smoking
the day their child is born. And I've always found this interesting, right? Because the day
before their child is born, they clearly know how bad smoking is, right? There's nobody who's
smoking, you know, who doesn't understand the risks of it. And by the same token, who doesn't,
as you pointed out earlier, enjoy the benefits of it in the short run, right? Very rewarding in the
short run, very damaging in the long run. So that's, that's completely understood intellectually.
On day X, they have a child and they decide, I'm done with this. I'm not going to have smoke in
my household because I also know the benefits of secondhand smoke or the harm rather of secondhand
smoke. And I'm not going to expose my child to this. And yet amazingly, I mean, over and over
and over again, I hear these stories from patients saying, yep, you know, my, I grew up in a household
where my parents were incredible smokers. And the second I was born, they stopped, they stopped. And
that was 40 years ago and they've never had a cigarette since. What do you think is going on
in an example like that? Is it, is there a transference process here where because it
involves the life of another person, it's easier to make this change stick? Possibly. I mean, I'm
sure there are a lot of variables that go into it, but it does align with, there's like this whole
category of behaviors that I feel like if you wanted to hack a radical change in your life,
you want to figure out a way to get, like you said, this epiphany to stick.
Massive environment changes or lifestyle changes are a good way to do that. Perhaps the, you know,
one of the strongest ways to do that. So having a kid, getting married, changing jobs,
moving to a different city, even something small like getting a dog can lead to rapid
behavior change. And I think one of the things that is really crucial about it is that most of
those decisions tend to be irreversible or at least very hard to reverse. I had one that I
struggled with for a long time. Sometimes people ask me, you know, what habits have you struggled
with or whatever? And I, I tend to be pretty good about getting enough sleep. I almost always get
eight hours or even nine if I'm training hard and, but I would fall into this pattern where it'd
be like nine or 10 o'clock at night and I would kind of get a second wind and it'd be like, well,
maybe I'll just send a few emails or something. And of course it's never just a few. You turn
around and it's midnight or one and you're like, okay, am I going to sleep for eight hours? Because
if so, that means I'm not getting up till nine. And I know that I prefer to get up early. I know
that I feel better throughout the rest of the next day. So, you know, 10 p.m. James is kind of
ruining things for tomorrow, James, by staying up late. And I tried a bunch of different things.
There's a little device called an outlet timer. You can buy it for like 10 bucks on Amazon and
you plug it into an outlet and you can set the time for when it kills the power from that outlet.
And so like, if you plug your internet into it, then like the internet shuts off at 10 p.m.
or, you know, whatever you set it for. And so I tried different things like that, you know,
but then you could just pick your phone up and, you know, kind of like get around it.
But the thing that finally made it stick was getting a dog because the dog is going to get
up at seven a.m. Whether I whenever I go to sleep, it doesn't matter. And I need to go take it for
a walk. And you can only do that for a few days before you're like, all right, I'm not going to
play this game anymore. I'm going to bed at 10. And it's because it was fairly hard to reverse.
They got it to stick. And I think, you know, in the case of having a kid like they're going to be
there every day now. And so maybe you could rationalize it a bunch of times before that.
But like that change is not going to or that's not going to change. They're going to be around.
And weirdly, because, you know, presumably this person's wife was pregnant, so they obviously
saw that throughout the whole pregnancy. But that didn't get them to change. But once the child is
there, man, it's really immediate, you know, like you're taking a puff and you have those little
eyes looking back at you. And so the feedback loop is even tighter than before. So I would
imagine both of those things probably play a role. But more generally speaking, those kind of
irreversible or hard to reverse lifestyle changes also tend to be big drivers of quick behavior
change. You know, I can only think of one dramatic habit I changed that has stuck. And it is the
silliest thing. But I always bit my nails growing up. I mean, I would bite them nonstop.
And, you know, invariably what happens is you'd get a little infection because you bite too close.
And it was like my mom was always like, God, that is such a disgusting habit. Like you have like,
it's just it looked horrible. And the day I decided to change it was the day I got my first
interview for med school. So, you know, you apply to medical school and then all of a sudden the
envelopes start coming in and you've got these interviews. And just as I got that first
envelope and I realized, oh, I'm actually going to go and be interviewing because you don't at
least for me, I didn't interview to go to college. This was the first time I had to do an interview.
And I don't know, just something came over me. I was like, wait a second, dude, you can't be the
guy that's showing up to an interview with these horrible looking nails. You have to cut this out.
You are going to get a nail clipper and you are going to start clipping your nails like a civilized
human being. And that was, you know, I don't know, 25 years ago. And today I sometimes like when my
nails get long, I'm a guy who likes short nails, so I'm always sort of treating them. But like,
I can't imagine that I once bit them. It just seems so strange to me. That's fascinating.
But it's just it's a silly example. Well, I don't think it is actually because there's, you know,
we all have habits that are like that. And I think there's two things that made me think the
first is it connects to our conversation about identity from a few minutes ago, which is you
started to take pride in it. You know, you cared about how you presented. And the more that we
take pride in certain elements of our identity, or aspects of who we are, certain parts of our story,
the more strongly that behavior starts to stick. You know, like you can imagine
a woman who takes pride in how her hair looks, she probably has all kinds of hair care habits
and products and things that she does. And, you know, she probably doesn't have to convince
herself to do them the same way that we talk about convincing ourselves of a lot of other habits. Oh,
I wish I could write or I wish I would work out or whatever. It's just an element of her identity.
She takes pride in and so she does it like fairly consistently, or the guy who gets complimented on
the size of his biceps. And so he just never skips arm day in the gym because it's an aspect
of his identity that he takes pride in. And so that connection of, you know, when we talk about
identity change, what I'm kind of getting at is like, what parts of your story do you take pride
in? And once you start to take pride in it, man, you'll fight for it pretty hard to keep it. And
in many cases, you'll find yourself doing it somewhat naturally, or at least internally
motivated to continue doing it. So that was the first piece, the second piece, and this is
something that since atomic habits has come out, I think is even more important than I realized
when I was writing the book, which is the influence of the social environment on your habits. So in
your case, the med school interviews, it was actually the image in your mind, the expectation
about what other people might think and how you would present in that interview and so on,
the judgment of others, essentially, that helped drive that change. And if you look at behaviors
that really stick, the ones that tend to stick for, you know, 10 or 20 or 30 years, a long time,
there's often a strong social component involved. So for example, we're all part of multiple tribes,
some of those tribes are large, like what it means to be American, or some of those tribes are small,
like being a member of your CrossFit gym or being a neighbor on your street. And, you know,
like if you take the neighborhood example, you might walk outside and see your neighbor mowing
their grass on, you know, Wednesday night or something, and think, Oh, I need to cut my lawn.
And you'll stick with that habit of mowing your grass for, you know, 20 or 30 years, or however
long you live in that house, like we wish we had that level of consistency with most of our other
habits. And why do you do it? Like partially you do it because it feels good to have a clean lawn.
But mostly you do it because you don't want to be judged by the other people in the neighborhood for
being the sloppy one. And so it's actually that social norm, that expectation for what it means
to be part of this neighborhood and how you act in this group or this tribe, that helps get the
habit to stick. I think the practical takeaway there, if you really want to behavior change to last
is to join groups where your desired behavior is the normal behavior. Because if it's normal in
that group, it's going to seem much more normal and typical for you to do it. I mean, you know,
Peter, I'm sure you're part of multiple groups that do what most people would determine are like
weird habits, like I'm sure there's a group of friends who are really into driving cars.
And there's probably another group who's like really into bow hunting and archery.
And there are all kinds of habits that these little tribes do. And it might seem strange to
the normal person, but it's probably very casual or typical or easy, relatively for you to stick
to those habits, especially when you're part of those groups or talking with those guys,
because it's just part of something that, you know, it's it's part of what they do.
And I think maybe the deeper lesson here is that we don't just do habits because of the results they
get us. We also take behaviors because they are a signal to the people around us that, hey, I get it,
I fit in, I understand how to act in this group. And most people, if they have to choose between
having the habits they want to have, but they kind of go against the grain of the group,
they like don't really fit in well, they get ostracized, or having habits that they don't
really love, but they get to go along with the crowd, they fit in, they get praised for being
part of the group. Most people will choose belonging over loneliness, like the desire to
belong will overpower the desire to improve. And so you want to make sure you get those two things
aligned to join groups where your desired behavior is the normal behavior. Yeah, it's interesting.
I wonder if part of the queue for me was buying a suit and it was the first suit I had. So it was
like, that was sort of a, wait a minute, you're wearing a suit, think of the trouble you're going
to get this thing and then this tie that you're going to wear and blah, blah, blah, all this sort
of stuff. But it's interesting. And then clearly it just became a part of my identity, which is
I'm a person who has nice fingernails. I present well from the fingernail standpoint, at least.
Yeah. Hasn't translated to all of my habits, but okay. So let's talk about the four laws,
because these four laws are kind of the central tenets to what we speak about and they can be
inverted as well, which I think is important as we think about creating, call it adaptive habits
versus breaking maladaptive habits. So what's the first law? Yeah. So real quick, before we get into
these four, I just want to explain the framework a little bit, because in particular for this
episode or this show, because I feel like your audience will appreciate it more than most
audiences. So I like to divide a habit into four stages. And as you said, those four stages kind
of have four different, what I call the four laws of behavior change that come out of it.
But when I was working on atomic habits and researching this framework and trying to
understand like why do behaviors happen and how do they happen, how do habits form?
I had a couple questions that I felt like previous frameworks did not answer that well.
So while researching the book, I was able to find 40 different models of human behavior that
biologists and neuroscientists and psychologists, a bunch of different industries had come up with
over the last, say about 150 years. And broadly speaking, those human models of human behavior
tended to fall into one of two categories. The first category are what I would call like
motivation models. So they explain things like internal drives and motivations and cravings and
kind of like what compels us to act. And then the second category were what I would call
reinforcement models. And so they described like the rewards that we get from behaviors and how
those things kind of reinforce our behavior and essentially what happens like after an action.
And what I wanted to do was try to come up with a model that I felt like accurately described
both the motivation that may come before and the reinforcement that may come after and how those
things influence the actions that we take. And there were a variety of what I thought were
fairly simple questions about human behavior that weren't totally answered by the previous models.
So things like what causes somebody to try have it in the first place, you know, like you haven't
experienced the reward at that point. So why would you take the first bite of a pancake or the first
smoke of a cigarette? Like what what would motivate you to do that? Or, you know, we say that habits
are very common, you know, start with BF Skinner, stimulus, response, reward, and then Charles
Duhiggen, power of habit kind of popularized as Q, routine, reward. But we say, OK, habits are a Q,
and then there's the action, there's some kind of outcome. Well, how come two people respond
differently to the same thing? Like why would one person see a cigarette and feel like, oh,
I have to smoke and another person's like, I've never smoked a day in my life. I'm not interested
at all. Because if it's just the Q that leads to the action, you would think they would do the same
thing. And even why would the same person respond differently to the same Q? How come when I walk in
my kitchen at 7 a.m., I see a loaf of bread and I think, oh, I'm going to make some toast for
breakfast. But then I walk in at 4 p.m. and I see that same Q and I don't think anything of it,
I just move on. So to summarize all of this, I think the one of the meaningful distinctions
about the four stages that I put together and why I feel like it accurately describes human behavior
and sort of the insight that I came across as I was researching, there's a neuroscientist
named Lisa Feldman Barrett, and she has a bunch of studies and, you know, a couple of books on this
topic. One book in particular that was useful for me while I was researching is called How Emotions
Are Made. And the key insight is that we often think that human behavior is reactive in the sense
that somebody does something and I respond or somebody says something and I feel a certain way.
But in fact, human behavior is mostly predictive. You are kind of endlessly going through your
experience in life predicting about what to do next. And it's actually this prediction that I
think was the key thing that was missing from a lot of the previous models of habits and behavior.
So with that as a primer, the four stages are huge.
Sorry, before we do that, James, just I think you wrote about this in the book, which was that
the dopaminergic surge comes more from the anticipation of the reward than the actual
behavior that gives the reward. Is that that I remember that correctly?
Right. So, you know, there's a bazillion studies on dopamine, of course. And also, I should say,
I think if you only talk about dopamine, you're kind of, you know, it's not the full story about
habits. Like there's, you know, there are many neurochemicals that are involved in the process
and dopamine is just one part of the overall picture. But it does play a very important role.
And for a long time, we thought it was about reward and satisfaction and enjoyment. But in fact,
it seems that the crucial role dopamine plays is about prediction and anticipation. And so the
first time that you take a bite of a pancake, you don't know what to expect. And so you take that
bite and then afterwards, you get a surge of dopamine, almost as if to like mark the experience
or to teach you, hey, that was favorable, you should do that again next time. Like if you happen
to see a bit of a pancake again, that was a really great outcome. And so then the next time around,
you know what to expect. And in fact, what we find is that dopamine tends to spike before you take a
bite, not after. And there are a bunch of studies that show this like, you know, gamblers get a
spike before they roll the dice, not after drug addicts get a spike before they take a hit of
cocaine, not after. And so dopamine, I think probably the more accurate way to describe it
in this context is it's a teaching molecule, it's a learning molecule, and it helps you,
it helps mark experiences that are favorable so that you'll remember them next time.
And then when you come across a similar situation, it spikes in anticipation. So after you see the
cue, you get this craving. And it's actually that craving or anticipation or prediction
that motivates you to act and drives the response. And then there's an outcome.
And presumably, again, using your example, there are lots of there's lots of diversity between
individuals, right? So you take 10 people who have never smoked a cigarette. Let's just to make the
math easy, say, well, seven of them have no desire to. So they walk away. Three of them are
like, I'll give it a try. They take a puff. One of them starts hacking and says, that is the most
disgusting thing I've ever done. I never want to do that again. And they never do. One of them says,
you know, I kind of like that. I'm going to do this socially. Like anytime I'm going to have a
drink, I'm going to have a cigarette. And one of them goes on to become a chain smoker. Now,
what explains that distinction? How much of that is neurochemical? Yeah, it's fascinating. And there,
I mean, there are, you know, examples like that for alcohol and drugs and all kinds of things.
And, you know, I'm not an expert on addiction. And I didn't write the book about addiction. So I
don't want to speak out of turn or step out of my lane or anything. But so I don't know that I have
a good answer to it. But from what I understand, and from what I've seen, as I was researching the
book, it does seem to have a strong, basically genetic or neurochemical component, you know,
it seems like, in a sense, drugs kind of hack the system, you know, it's like, you know, this is,
I think, one way to define an addiction, which is the process of learning is actually broken,
you know, addicts know that the behavior does not benefit their lives in a lot of ways, but they
still can't get themselves to stop doing it, even though they know it doesn't benefit them.
And I think part of the reason that happens, or perhaps the primary reason is the drug kind of
hacks the system, it like gives you this spike of dopamine, even though you shouldn't be getting
it, usually your brain would not be doing that, it would not be trying to teach you to repeat that,
but you're artificially spiking it by taking the substance. And so then that, you know,
the process of learning breaks. I also find it interesting that different people
will get that pleasure from different things. When I'm not in a good place, when I'm unhappy
about something, it's never my tendency to have a drink. So alcohol would only be associated with
something I want to do when I feel good to begin with, I would never want to have a drink when I
don't feel good. But when I don't feel good, I would happily binge on junk food, right? Like that
would be the thing that provides comfort. And of course, there are people who would, who when
they're unhappy, they would never want to eat even, let alone have junk food. And again, it's hard to
know. I find it interesting to at least contemplate how much of that is genetic, how much of that is
learned and what else is going on and sort of understanding that because that does sort of
factor into falling to the level of our habits because we fall to these levels when things are
not going well, typically. I think, you know, I do think there's a genetic component. Some people
are more sensitive to certain substances than others, or at least it appears to be so. However,
it does strike me as like very possible that a good chunk of it is learned and that now you have
a story that junk food is the way that I cope or the way that I, you know, soothe myself when I need
that. And you can imagine like, in a sense, your habits are these solutions to like recurring
problems that you face. So say you have somebody who comes home from work and they feel exhausted.
And one person like that's a recurring problem that they feel often. And so one person comes
home and they play video games for 30 minutes. And another person comes home and they go for a run.
And a third person smokes a cigarette. And all of them are solving the same underlying recurring
problem. But they're choosing different methods through which to do that. And I wonder about like,
how the grooves kind of get formed once we learn that a certain method is effective in solving that
problem, we tend to default to it, even if it's not the only way to solve that, even if, yeah,
going for a run would make me feel better, but I'm just used to smoking cigarettes now. And
then we start to develop a story around it, starts to become a little bit of our identity. We start
to, you know, kind of like use it as a crutch. And so I do think there's definitely a learned
component to that as well. All right. Well, I interrupted you before you were just about to
launch into the four laws. Yeah, yeah. Okay. So the four stages are cue, craving, response, and reward.
The cue is something that you notice. So for example, you see a plate of cookies on the counter,
that's a visual cue starts the habit of eating a cookie. The craving is the prediction or the
meaning that you assign to that cue often happens relatively automatically or quickly. So you see the
plate of cookies, and you think, oh, that'll be sweet, sugary, tasty, enjoyable. It's that
favorable meaning that leads to that dopamine spike that we talked about. And that motivates
you to take the third step, which is the response you walk over, you pick the cookie up, you take a
bite. And then finally, there's the reward. Oh, it is in fact, sweet, sugary, tasty, satisfying.
Now, not every behavior in life is rewarding, right? Sometimes things have a cost or a
consequence. Sometimes they're just kind of neutral and don't really mean a whole lot.
But if a behavior is not rewarding, then it's unlikely to become a habit because you don't
have any reason to repeat it again in the future. You need some kind of positive emotional signal
associated with the behavior for you to stick with it, at least as we've already talked about
an immediate signal. Now, is there is there some evidence to suggest if I remember back to like
my psych 101 class, which is obviously pretty elementary, that some of the most addictive
behaviors are variably reinforcing. And I sort of remember this example of why slot machines
are particularly addictive because the pattern with which they produce a win is actually random.
And therefore, you really don't know when it's going to come. You know, it's going to come. You
have to have belief that you'll see other people win and you've won in the past, but that's somehow
even more addictive. Whereas the cookie in theory is not variably reinforcing. It's pretty much
reinforcing the same way every time and presumably only subject to the tastiness of the cookie.
Yeah. So it's even more. There have been tons of studies done on variable rewards. And
the basic answer is yes, you're right. Variable rewards tend to accelerate or intensify behavior.
It can get even more twisted than that in the slot machines example, because what they have found is
that the sweet spot tends to be right around 50 50. And so if you you can imagine getting a reward
at very different schedules, like you could get it 95 percent of the time or you could get it 5
percent of the time. Well, if you only get a 5 percent of the time, then you learn pretty
quickly like, hey, this isn't a very fruitful action. Maybe I should stop doing this.
But if you get it around 50 50 and it works, tends to work out for you a lot, but not every time. And
it still is coming at it like a roughly a random pattern, even if, you know, over 10,000 trials,
it works out to be about 50 percent of the time. Man, you will just keep pressing that slot machine
button over and over and over again. And, you know, there are studies, there have been studies
done on mice where they would get a like a squirt of sugar water when they poke their nose in a box.
And if they did it at a variable reward schedule, they would do it. I can't remember the exact
number. I want to say it was like six thousand times in an hour or something, but it was it was,
you know, many, many times. And, you know, we laugh at it thinking about mice, but we're not that
different. The average slot machine player will press the button like 800 times in an hour. And
we're just basically, you know, doing the same thing. So that that variable reward, getting the
reward, but not knowing exactly when it's going to happen, it gets you to do it more frequently. And
you can think about examples like this in everyday life. Imagine a remote control where the battery
is dying and you press the power button, but it doesn't turn on right away. And you're like,
did that work? And you press it again a little harder than maybe pressing it a third time. Now,
if you do it, you know, eight or nine or 10 times, you're like, OK, the batteries are dead. But if on
the second try, it turns on the like the variable reward got you to do it again or got you to try
the behavior more. So, yeah, that that variable reward schedule is definitely something I can
intensify behavior. You remember Anchorman? I assume you've said, yeah, this might actually
mean that there is truth to the statement that 50 percent of the time it works every time.
Incredible reference. Yes. Fantastic. Little did we know that Will Ferrell was a
cognitive psychology fan. I think that was Paul Rudd's line, wasn't it?
When he was when he used Black Panther, the Cologne. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Amazing.
Some of the time it works every time. I'm going to be honest with you. That smells like pure gasoline.
It's got bits of real panther in it. It's made by Odeon.
That movie. So, OK, so those are the four stages. And what I like to do and what I consider to be
the hallmark of like my work, you know, I am I'm just interpreting the research like, you know,
I'm just pretending to be an academic. I'm not actually an academic. And my I think the value
that I try to provide is to make these ideas actionable and to turn them into something that
we can operationalize or apply to daily life. And the four laws of behavior change are how I have
attempted to do that. So if we understand that a habit has those four steps, and how do we actually
change our behaviors, we can follow these four laws. And there's one for each stage. So the first
law of behavior change is to make it obvious, you want the cues of your good habits to be obvious,
available, visible, easy to see the the easier it is to see, or get your attention, the easier it is
to notice, the more likely you are to act on it. The second law is to make it attractive, the more
attractive or appealing or exciting a habit is, the more likely you are to feel motivated to do it.
Again, this is about anticipating it or something you you anticipate more feel more motivated.
The third law is to make it easy, the more easy, convenient, frictionless, simple a habit is,
the more likely behavior is to be performed. And then the fourth and final law is to make it
satisfying, the more satisfying or enjoyable, pleasurable a habit is, the more likely you are
to repeat it in the future. And so those four laws give you like a high level overview of how to
build a good habit. So make it obvious, make it attractive, make it easy, make it satisfying.
You don't need all four every single time. But the more that you have those four things working for
you, I think the more likely it is that the good behavior will stick or that you'll find a way to
start on it. If you want to break a bad habit, then you just invert those four. So rather than
making it obvious, you want to make the cue invisible, unsubscribe from emails, reduce
exposure to the queue. If you're trying to be on a diet, don't follow food bloggers on Instagram.
So just, you know, like reducing exposure to the thing that starts the process,
rather than making it attractive, make it unattractive, rather than making it easy,
make it difficult. So increase friction, put more steps between you and the behavior.
And rather than making it satisfying, make it unsatisfying, layer on some kind of immediate
consequence or cost to the behavior. And so those four make it invisible, make it unattractive,
make it difficult, make it unsatisfying, give you a high level framework for how to break a bad habit.
Now, how often is a certain behavior, the combination of breaking a habit and creating a
habit? Again, it seems like a lot of the ones we default into talking about are the hard ones like
nutrition. We all eat, we're all going to eat all the time. It's not something you can opt out of
or into. You just, you know, we all eat. So presumably if a person says, again, I hate coming
back to weight because it's such a stupid example relative to say overall health, but let's say
health, actually, I want to be a much healthier person. So I need to change the way I eat.
So those that's two things, right? You have to start eating better and stop eating poorer.
It is two things, but I view them as two sides of the same coin. In many cases, you know, we can come
up with edge cases or examples where, you know, like the behavior start to get more specific. But
you know, generally speaking, I think there are three ways to break a bad habit. You can eliminate
it entirely. So you can just go cold turkey, cut it out, never do it again. You could curtail the
behavior to the desired degree. So you can reduce it a little bit. You still do it sometimes, but,
you know, instead of drinking a beer at dinner every night, you just have it maybe once a week.
And then you could also replace it. So rather than, you know, you know, drinking a beer,
you replace it with water or whatever. Now, when I'm thinking about myself personally,
when I actually am changing behavior, I don't usually think about breaking bad habits that
often. In fact, most of the time I'm focused on building or establishing new good behaviors,
which necessarily displace the old ones. Like, for example, with eating, it is a bit of a zero
sum game. I mean, not entirely. I guess you could just keep eating more and more and more.
But generally, if you say I'm going to eat more good things, it kind of drives down the bad things.
Is that the way it normally works then? I think a lot of the time it does. And that's why I tend to
focus on that for my personal life is that it's kind of like two plants, you know, like one plant,
if it grows a little bit more and, you know, spreads its leaves a little further,
it starts to crowd out the other plant, you know, just soaks up more energy and resources in
sunlight. And your good habits are kind of like that. I mean, we all in some sense, it is zero
sum in the sense that we only have 24 hours in each day. And so, you know, if you have somebody
who says, even if they're unrelated habits, they say, hey, I want to start doing something healthy.
I'd like to start, you know, working out for an hour each day. And I also want to watch less TV.
I just feel like I watch Netflix too much. Well, you know, if you usually watch Netflix for three
hours each evening, and you decide to insert your workout from six to seven p.m. By definition,
you're not watching Netflix while you're doing that. And so, you know, you start to crowd out
the bad behavior just by focusing on building workout habit, even if you don't think about the
TV thing at all. So my sort of general approach is, look, I'm trying to spend my 24 hours in
the highest leverage way possible, the best way possible, the way that is, you know, moving me
toward whatever I'm optimizing for. And so let me just try to continually think about how to upgrade
those behaviors. I also like that mindset more than the breaking the bad habits one, because
it gives me a reason to improve even once I have good habits, you know, like I'm continually
looking for the higher leverage action, even if what I'm doing is already good. Okay, fine. How
can I make it great now? And so I tend to focus on that style rather than thinking about breaking
bad ones. But they definitely are related to answer your question. And I guess like the example that
we come back to is smoking. So it's hard to think of because smoking doesn't really take that much
time. So it's hard to say I'm just going to introduce a new habit that will force smoking out.
Are there other examples, though, of habits where you really do focus on how to break the bad one?
Yeah, so to take the smoking example, I think it's helpful to divide it into the specific
instances in which it happens. So, you know, we kind of lump smoking into a single habit. But the
truth is, it actually might be a collection of like a dozen habits throughout the day, it might be
that you have a habit of smoking when you get in your car for the morning commute. And then you
also have a habit of smoking around 1030 when you take a break with your coworker. And then you also
have a habit of smoking, you know, after dinner on your porch. And all three of those are going to
have their own cue craving, response and reward. And so you in a sense, you kind of have to intervene
in like 12 different places to try to come up with a solution for each one of those. So you might find
that like, for the morning commute, maybe instead of having a cigarette, you know, you come up with
something else that you can do on the morning commute while you're that fulfills that, you know,
that desire, maybe, maybe even just a cup of coffee is what wakes you up instead of a cigarette.
But that may not work for the 1030 session with your friend, maybe there you actually need like
an e-cigarette to start, because you want to have the socialization of feeling like you're smoking
with a friend. So you may need to like kind of take it in different stages and break it down
to a more degree where it's easier to have a line of attack.
The environment seems to be so potent. You know, again, David Foster Wallace writes about
when in his commencement speech, this is water. He talks about the ubiquity of water and also the
fact that you don't even realize it's there. And that's what makes it so profound, right? Is the
referring to certain thoughts. But I think the same is true of these cues, right? I mean, we,
for most of us, we, we're not actually that aware of what it is, you know, it can be pointed out to
you and you can say, Oh yeah, come to think of it. I am a fish swimming in water or yeah,
I come to think of it every time I get in the car, it's the act of getting in the car and driving to
work that signals a change in my where I'm going. And that's what forces me to light up. But, you
know, the example of having the cigarette at 1030 with your coworker is a very powerful one because
of the connection in the environment. And I remember in my residency when people would
come into the hospital with abscesses from IV drug use. So very, you know, in Baltimore,
which is right in my residency, there was, you know, just rampant IV drug use. And you'd be amazed
at how much that habit and that addiction could cause a person to do something that at the surface
doesn't seem that logical, you know, use dirty needles and needles would break in their abscesses.
And so you'd be down there and you'd be sort of draining a huge baseball size pus filled abscess
that's got broken needles in it. And this person is very sick. I mean, this is a person who's now
risking their life due to this and they would be back in a month with the same thing in a month,
in a month later, the same thing over and over again. And tragically, eventually a lot of people
would die. But I remember at some point saying to these folks, this was the best advice I could
offer, which was not very helpful, was I don't think you can go back to the same place you live.
Like, I think you need new friends. Now, that's not a very helpful thing to offer somebody who
probably doesn't have many choices. But the point was like, how could you expect this person to go
back to the same place that they were living in the same environment with all of the same people
doing the same things and say, well, you just got to resist it. It doesn't make sense, right? You,
you know, presumably someone who decides they want to stop drinking alcohol really ought not go into
a bar that much anymore. Despite unless your environment is like a form of gravity. Yeah,
you know, like it just pulls on you and you can resist it for a little bit. But, you know, maybe
a day or week or a month, but at some point, it just starts to drain on you and, you know, sucks
you back in. And to your point about, you know, going back to this environment that prompted the
behavior in the first place. I mean, this is one of the stories I share in Atomic Habits, but it was
the surprise that we saw from the Vietnam War, which is so many soldiers were getting addicted
to heroin and drugs when they were over there. And then they came back and we were like, what are we
going to do with all these addicted soldiers? And it turns out that 90% of them or more
ended up being fine because they didn't go back to the place where they got addicted. They went
home to their friends and family and like they didn't have all the same signals that were
prompting them to pick up the habit. And so they were able to drop it much more easily than we
thought they would and compare that to the typical drug addict who does the reverse. They go into
rehab and that's where they leave all of their cues and influences behind. And then we, you know,
once they get clean and they detox, we send them back to the same place where they got addicted
before. And that is a much, much harder uphill battle. So environment, I think it's kind of like
the invisible hand that drives our behavior. I mean, we, as you said, it's kind of like water,
you know, fish in water, we don't realize it. But we all have these things that we say are important
to us. Oh, I would like to lose weight, or I'd like to build a business, or I want to finish a book.
But then you look around the spaces where we live and work. And the cues of those habits are not a
big part of the environment. And, you know, we all are busy, strapped for time, you know,
minimal energy, we have kids to take care of, or parents to do chores for, or friends to see.
And whenever we have limited capacity, or limited time, or we're low on energy, or exhausted,
what choice do we make? We often choose the thing that is most obvious in the environment,
we choose the thing that is the easy choice or the path of least resistance. And so, you know,
if I'm recommending a place to start for changing behavior, it's usually either the first law or the
third law, it's making it obvious and making it easy. Because, you know, we can talk about making
it easy, but scaling habits down, obviously makes it more likely that you're able to complete the
task. And making it obvious, essentially creates an environment where the good choices are right in
front of you, where the path of least resistance. And individually, I think it's easy to overlook
the importance of this, because individually, one change to the environment does not usually
meaningfully move the needle or change your behavior. But collectively, making a dozen,
or two dozen, or 50 little choices to how your office is laid out, and how your living room is
laid out, and how your kitchen is laid out. Yeah, now all of a sudden, you're working and thriving
in a space that is stacking the odds in your favor. That's making it more likely that you will
just choose the good thing because the healthy food is on the counter. And the TV is behind a
wall unit and a cabinet where you're less likely to see it. And the remote control is inside a
drawer and there's a book in its place. And you have a couple books that are scattered around in
your desk waiting for you to pick them up and open them. You can do it with digital spaces too,
like when I wanted to start reading more, I took audible for audiobooks and I moved it to the
home screen on my phone and took all the other apps and moved them to the second screen. That's
a very small thing and it doesn't guarantee the behavior, but it's another way to stack the odds
in my favor that whenever I open up my phone, I'm reminded to listen to an audiobook for a few
minutes rather than browse Instagram. And the more that you do those kinds of things,
the more likely good behaviors are to arise. So one thing I want to park for later once we
get through the laws is a very specific question around the challenges that some people face and
that they don't control their environment. And again, I come back to food because I think for
most of my patients and for myself, food is such a struggle because again, it's always around us.
You have to do it. It's not a behavior you can just opt out of. And I think those of us that
have kids, not to throw our kids under the bus, but I haven't met too many people who's eating
habits get better once they have kids. If they're generally inclined to be healthy people, because
at some point you sort of start losing the battle of how much non-crap you can have in the house due
to time constraints and the other constraints, which is look, kids are going to eat things that
are probably not so bad for them, but I shouldn't be eating. And, you know, wheat thins, my kids
love wheat thins. I love wheat thins. I think the difference is they can get away with eating a lot
more wheat thins than I can. So I've lost the wheat thin battle. Like we have a pantry that is
full of wheat thins and I'm never, at least for the foreseeable future, going to get those wheat
thins out of there. So now every time I walk in the pantry, I'm staring down the barrel of wheat
thins and I would love to get those wheat thins in the trash. But every time I do, my wife says,
understandably, hey, if you want to be in charge of feeding the kids every meal, knock yourself out,
chef. But if you're not, let me handle food and our kids eat well, but they're going to eat wheat
thins and a few other things that you don't want to eat. Isn't it kind of fascinating? Like, you know,
I mean, you're someone that I think most people would describe as disciplined and high performing
and, you know, talented and skilled. And you like look at yourself with that and you're like, wheat
thins beat me every time. You know, it's like I think about myself. I was doing an interview
with somebody else a couple of weeks ago and he was joking about how the number of cookies he can
eat is either zero or 30 because if they're there, then he's going to eat them all. And I'm exactly
that way. One of the best hacks that we've come up with is I love chocolate chip cookies and my wife
will make them, but she'll like make the balls of dough and then freeze them and put them in the
freezer. And at night after dinner, we'll take them out and just take out two and put them on the
pan and warm up the oven and put them in. And it's actually a better experience because you get to
eat like fresh baked warm chocolate chip cookies, but you'll only eat two because all the rest of
them are frozen. And it's just enough friction to know that this is going to take another 15 minutes
if I want to take two more out and heat them up. And you're like, I don't actually need another
cookie like I just want to. But what limits you from putting five on the on the on the on the tray?
Great question. We just haven't gotten in the habit of doing that. So hopefully this that
question will wreck my psyche and now we'll be doing that every night. But it's part of that,
the accountability though between you that like probably you say I want to at least she's going to
say she'd be like, come on. Yeah, for sure. And I think we've seen that we've seen it's interesting
the ways in which there's a whole discussion we can have about habits and marriage and like
relationships and how that influences things because you soak up each person soaks up a little
bit of the other partner. But we've seen it work in a very positive way for training, which is
there are going to be some days where I just like don't feel like working out after, you know,
full day at work. But she's like, all right, we're going to go to the gym. And, you know, then I'm
like, okay, I'll change, you know, and then other days I'm like, okay, I'm ready. And she's like,
all right, you know, and she didn't feel like it. And that's really helpful for the long term
consistency. But I've talked to other couples who have said, you know, my nutrition habits
actually got worse because like one day I won't feel like cooking. I'll be like, hey, can we just
order out and she'll be like, okay, fine. And then the other day she won't feel like cooking like,
hey, why don't we pick up something from and you're like, okay, fine. And so you can see how
it goes in both directions. And I don't I don't have a good way to describe these kind of upward
and downward spirals that we often get into where the momentum once it's moving in that
direction, you just kind of like it becomes your default behavior and you just sort of keep rolling
with it. But that there's something very powerful about that in life, that if you get on a nice
trajectory, and you got a good spiral working for you, then that momentum just kind of carries you.
And if you start to get in a downward spiral, you really got to find a way to just reverse course
and gain a foothold, even if it's a really small thing, just to get the momentum moving in the
other direction. But anyway, well, there are a lot of that. And that's actually something I feel like
I've, I've also noticed with my patients and myself, which is it seems that the people who are able to
be more self forgiving, when they slip up and get back on course, have an easier time than people
who approach it through a very perfectionistic lens. And once they make a mistake, they get into
the cycle of self judgment, and beating themselves up. And I say them like it's me too, right? We all
do this. Sure. And all of a sudden, a blown meal turns into, well, forget if the day's over, I mean,
I've screwed this day up. So I'm just gonna eat whatever I want. And then you wake up the next day,
and you probably feel like crap, both physically and emotionally. And that reduces your drive to
continue to do what you set out to do. And you sort of you just you have the spirals. And you make a
point about that in the book, right? Which is don't, you know, if you're gonna miss a workout,
miss a workout, but don't miss two. Yeah, yeah, never miss twice is the idea that I try to the
little mantra I try to tell myself, you know, it's like, okay, stuck to the diet for nine days,
binge ate a pizza on the 10th day. Well, wish I hadn't happened, but never miss twice. So let's
make sure the next meal is a healthy one. And, you know, I think we all know this, it kind of
implicitly from going through life, but it's easy to forget in the moment, which is, it's rarely the
first mistake that ruins you, you know, it's like usually the spiral of repeated mistakes that
follows. That's the real problem. It's like letting slipping up become a new habit. That's
the real issue. And if you can cut that off at the source, if you can never miss twice,
then you know, you get to the end of the year, and those mistakes are just like a little blip on the
radar. But it's really about getting back on track quickly. And I think actually you see this with
top performers in many different industries, like, you know, think about any athlete. I mean,
this is something that like Nick Saban's teams at Alabama pride themselves on the screw up a play
or have a bad drive, throw interception for a touchdown or something. But the focus is on the
very next play. And I'm making sure that you don't let that mistake become another mistake.
And the teams and the athletes that are really good at doing that and having a short memory and
getting right back on track, they end up having, you know, really successful careers. And you can
scale that down to your own life. Gretchen Rubin actually has this, I thought was a clever little
idea, which is divide the day into four quarters. So you got like morning, afternoon, dinner and
night or evening and night. And if you make a mistake, keep it contained to that quarter.
So, you know, you don't lose the day, you just lose the quarter. And then the next one,
you get back on track. And if you can, you know, keep your failures small like that,
if you can contain the damage, then I just think it's easier to get back on track quickly and to
maintain the momentum, build consistency, all the other positive benefits that we've talked about.
And to your point about judging yourself or feeling guilty or, you know, turning this into
some kind of like self berating session. Playing the victim never makes it better. You know,
it never it doesn't make any of it easier. You can, I think generally in life, we all have things
that happen to us. Some of them are, you know, some of them are terrible things. And you can be the
victim. But I don't know that it ever benefits you to play the victim to accept that role. You know,
like bad things can happen to you. But that doesn't mean you have to start to identify
as someone who is worthy of them or someone who is, you know, it's inevitable for that to be part
of your story. And so the more that you can like cut the judgment out of it, cut the the guilt out
of it, the story, the narrative piece and take that away and just accept the event for what it is
and move on to the next instance that I think probably the better off you'll be.
Yeah, this is probably an area where a habit that is probably desirable for many people also
becomes a tool to help. And that's mindfulness meditation, which I think is one of the more
powerful tools to help people observe the judgment without judging it, which sounds a bit, you know,
odd to someone who hasn't practiced that. But that becomes very powerful. And it certainly made a
difference as I've kind of released the need to be perfect, which doesn't mean again, that's just
it's really a continuum. And there's there's a there's a spectrum of efficacy here, which is
like on Monday, we traveled the whole day and we got back and I really wanted to work out, you know,
I just hate ever missing a workout. But the reality is once we got home and the kids were exhausted
and my wife was tired and it just felt like sort of a schmucky thing to do to go and work out and
leave her with decompensating kids and a whole bunch of stuff that needed to be unpacked. And
actually part of the judgment was letting go of that, letting go of the fact that I wasn't going
to work out that day and that was okay. Now that's, you know, you can do that on anything, I think,
if you can come to be flexible and say, you know what, you're stuck in the airport with your kids,
the food sucks. It is what it is today and you're not horrible because of it. But I think this idea
of get back on the horse as quickly as possible is is really powerful. Again, anecdotally,
always bring everything back to driving a race car. It is so rare that you make a mistake
and crash in a car because of what you did at that moment and not because of what happened
earlier. So, you know, if you spin at corner four, the mistake usually started at corner two.
And sometimes you don't realize it and sometimes you do realize it, but you
arrogantly think that you don't have to make any adjustment going forward because of it. At least
for me, that's been an incredible, incredibly humbling experience with how, you know,
mistakes compound. Rapid course correction is probably a deep, like deeply applicable
lesson for many areas of life. You know, I mean, the world is complex and situations evolve. Life
is dynamic. It's not static and your preferences also evolve. What you optimize for or want is
different today than it was 10 years ago and probably will be different five years from now
or 10 years from now. And given that many changing dynamics, it's not possible for someone to predict
the optimal course of action. And even if you could, it is very unlikely that it will remain
the optimal course of action. So given that things are going to be changing, you're going to be off
course at some point and the ability to correct for that and to correct for that quickly. I mean,
it might be one of the all optimal life skills, you know, the ability to assess where you are in
the moment, see what the next step is going to be, keep in mind where you ultimately want to go
and then correct as needed is possibly the path to like living a great life. I heard recently this,
I thought it was a great little framework, which is a BZ came from Sean Pury. He's a entrepreneur
and basically said you need to know your ABCs. A is where you are right now. It's like the truth of
the situation, the reality. B is your next step. And Z is where you want to go. Ultimately, it's
where you want to end up. And I think the key, this is me talking now and not him. For me, the
key is working backwards. It's knowing Z first, knowing what you're optimizing for. And then
jumping back to a and being honest about the situation, what is the truth of the situation?
What are the resources I have, the skills I have? What are my strengths? What are my weaknesses?
What's reality say? And then knowing that I want to head towards Z and knowing honestly where I am
today, what's the next step? I actually don't need to know see through why right now. I don't need to
have the whole thing planned out perfectly, but I do need to make sure that my next step is
directionally correct. And if it is, then you can just keep running that ABC process over and over
again until you finally get there. Yeah. Any Duke talks about this in a slightly different way. And
she refers to it as back casting. And I find it to be an incredibly powerful tool again, to be
contrasted with forecasting, right? Forecasting is I'm just going to stand here and I'm going to tell
you I got to do B and then C and then as opposed to saying, no, this is where I am. That's the
desired outcome. Let's start working the steps backwards. This is what you've described is
slightly different, but I think it preserves this idea of taking stock of where you are. And most
importantly, understanding where you need to be and not trying to do what I think stochastically
is really hard, but predict every step going forward. Yeah. The only thing I'll add to that,
which I like Annie's framework and I think working backwards is it's a really powerful thing,
particularly if you can not be your own bottleneck in the process. A lot of people,
the phrase I like is work backwards from magic. So, you know, what would the magical outcome be?
What would the ideal outcome be? And then let me work backwards from that. And a lot of people have
trouble with that brainstorming part of the process because they think, well, if it's unrealistic,
why would I even try? And the point is like, listen, it's way too early for that. You know,
like most people, most people become their own bottleneck long before reality prevents them from
doing it, which is kind of this great irony. We're like, oh, you know, why would I attempt this like
super impossible thing? And it's like, well, the world hasn't even told you it's impossible yet.
You have. So I think work backwards from the magical outcome. But my key is I want to be very
clear about where I'm going, but very flexible about how I get there. So I don't need it to
happen if I work backwards. I don't need it to happen only through that chain of potential,
that potential path, because if you can only have one way to get there, you're actually kind of
brittle and you become hostage to the, you know, things working exactly in that way. But if I know
where I want to get to the very clear vision, I'm flexible in how I get there. Well, now I can start
to spring on opportunities as they arise and just take whatever the most fruitful path seems to be.
But I do think that that whole process starts with working backwards. So it's a, I think,
a more fruitful way to think about where you want to go than just trying to predict.
Before we leave the first law, what advice do you offer for people if they aren't quite clear
what the cues are? Again, in the spirit of trying to even displace, you know,
a habit that's maladaptive and create new ones. Again, is this something that's just empirical,
or is it, is it, are there, are there, I hate to use the word, but are there tricks for
identifying what the cues are? Yeah, no, I think there are exercises or strategies you can use. So
it's a good question. And I think you sort of hinted at this a few minutes ago, and I meant to
say it, but I forgot, which is the process of behavior change, like strategically changing
your behavior, that, you know, we need to make a separation here, a distinction between the types
of behavior change, because people change their behavior all the time. We're always responding
to the situation we're in, or the circumstance or the conversation we're having. This is like one
of the great myths about behavior change, which is behavior change is hard. Actually, it's one of
the easiest things that you do, like your brain is designed to change your behavior to match the
situation that you're in. So you're, you're making adjustments all the time. The question is, can you
reliably change your behavior? Can you design your behavior in a fashion that you want?
And if you want to design it, if you want to be in control of it more, I think it almost always
starts with the process of self-awareness. And that's kind of what this question is getting at.
Hey, I don't even know what the cues are. I don't even know what my habits are. So the two exercises
I recommend the first one I call the habit scorecard, and you just go through your day,
and you list out every habit that you already do, and try to get as detailed as possible. So usually
there's a big lump in the beginning, like, I wake up, I take a shower, I step on the scale, I brush
my teeth, I go to the bathroom, I get dressed, like there's all this stuff that you do to start
your day. And then there's, you know, things for breakfast and starting a workday and on and on and
on. And the more that you have that list, you're again, the goal is not to judge yourself. It's
almost like you're at the zoo looking at animals, and you're, you're one of the animals, it's like,
oh, how interesting that they would do that, you know, like just kind of, you're just trying to get
a lay of the land and see how do I actually spend my time? What habits am I actually doing if I'm
being honest about it? And then the second, so that's just to understand what habits you have.
To figure out what the queue is, there's a just basically, you're just asking like five questions,
who, what, when, where, why, you know, you're essentially just trying to get a lay of, you know,
what's going on. So let's say that you're like, man, I eat a lot of candy bars, but I don't know
why I do it. I don't know what the queue is. Well, each time that you find yourself eating a candy bar,
just pull up a note on your phone or have an index card or a notebook or whatever somewhere
to record it, write down what time is it? Where are you at right now? What's the what's the context?
What's the environment? Who are you around? Are you near the, do you eat these by the same kind of
people? What were you doing just before this? You know, was it a break from writing emails or,
you know, doing something else? And the more that you start to answer those questions about the
context, the better you'll, you'll start to understand, Hey, maybe that was the queue.
And I bet if you do that exercise for whatever the particular habit is that you're working on,
just do that for, you may not even need to do it for a week, but if you do it for five days or
seven days or something, you're going to start to develop a good sense for what it is that's
prompting the behavior. Yeah, that's, that's a great exercise. And I mean, is there any concern
that when a person does that, that the Hawthorne effect kicks in and they basically start
deviating from the natural behavior because of the observation? In other words, is the act of
going through this exercise potentially, uh, making it harder for them to transparently see what's
happening? Um, maybe I think it's, uh, I, I, sir, I'm not going to say it's not a risk. I'm sure it's,
it's a possible risk, but, um, I think what's more likely to happen is rather than not being able to
see what's going on, assuming you're being honest with yourself, I mean, you know, it's, it's,
it can be hard to honestly observe your own behavior. You know, we have a lot of biases
and stories for why we do what we do. So, but assuming you're doing that to the best degree
possible, I think you're probably still going to get a good idea of what the Q is.
What I think is more likely to happen if there is some influence on your behavior
is you may find yourself changing the behavior anyway, uh, just because you're tracking it.
And there are quite a few studies that show this, like with nutrition, for example, there are some
studies about food journaling, people who just keep a food journal. They're not even trying to
stick to a certain calorie level or a certain macro profile or anything. They just are tracking
what they're eating tend to change their eating habits and eat less just because they're tracking
it. Even if they don't have a specific program, they're trying to follow. So the mere act of
observing something or measuring something often changes the behavior associated with it. And you
may find that to be the case here. You're like, well, I keep writing now when I have candy bars.
So I'm like, maybe I'll skip this one. Um, and I think that's probably the more likely outcome,
but, uh, who knows there could be other biases as well. Yeah. I, uh, these devices here,
these continuous glucose monitors, they, they are a remarkable tool for both insight. Cause it,
you know, when you first put them on, you're sort of learning, Oh my God, like I didn't realize eating
that thing would have this response in my glucose. But once you sort of saturate the insight part of
that equation, which can be three months, six months, depending on the complexity of your,
your life, it becomes forever a behavioral tool. You sort of, you know, you don't want to eat a
certain thing if it's going to raise your glucose, because you've at least bought into the thesis
that you don't want to have your glucose skyrocket the way it does when you eat M and M's. So, uh,
it's interesting. It becomes kind of an accountability partner. And I, and I find some of the most
interesting and sticky devices do that, right? The wearables that offer an insight that's not obvious
that, but as objective tend to be the things that we really like coming back to. Whereas the ones
that are kind of obvious, like how many steps you take that doesn't, that's not very sticky because
we sort of have an intuitive sense for what that is. Like everybody, once they've, you know,
spent enough time walking 10,000 steps a day, they don't really need a device to tell them that
anymore. It becomes easier to do on their own. It's interesting. I have this kind of, this is a
side comment, but I have this like theory about technology and innovation. Um, and that the way
in which we, the technologies that most radically change the world or change our behavior
are all just kind of different forms of vision. So like, you know, you have obvious examples like
x-rays, which, you know, allow you to see the broken bone or, um, you know, uh, MRIs or whatever
that allow you to see some tissue in a way that you couldn't see before. And so that gives you
information that then you can act on and make a diagnosis and, you know, uh, make some kind of,
uh, change. But the glucose monitors, like another example, it's just like, now you can see the spike,
you know, see in a very broad sense. Um, and because you can see it, uh, you change your
behavior. Um, and you know, even stuff like the number of email subscribers to my website, you
know, because, uh, my email platform tracks that and I can see how many people are signing up each
day, I make a change to the form and, you know, conversion and so on. And, um, I do think there's
some deeper lesson there about behavior change and about what drives a human behavior, which is if
you can visualize your progress in some way, maybe it's a chart on a screen, maybe it's, you know,
an actual printout, uh, maybe it's something that you actually see like, you know, looking through
lenses or something, but if you can actually visualize it, then the behavior often follows suit.
And that's why even simple strategies like a habit tracker where you just put an X on each day
seems very, um, rudimentary, very basic, but it can still be meaningful because it gives you a way
of visualizing your progress. Yeah. This idea of what gets measured gets managed is, is, is, is a
great tool. Um, about six months ago, I started going to the water meter of our house every Tuesday
and recording it. And then I've got a little spreadsheet that says, okay, this is how many
gallons we've used this week. This is what it would project to for a monthly usage, et cetera, et cetera.
And you just can't believe how much our water usage has come down in six months. Because I mean,
again, in Texas, water is not that expensive actually compared to California, but just
it became something I was obsessed with, which is like, we're not going to waste any water. Like,
I just don't want to waste any water. And it's now become a game for me. It drives my family nuts,
but it is a game. Like we are going to have the lowest water bill ever in Austin. No one is going
to use less water than us. And I, I mean, I'm obsessed with that spreadsheet. It's kind of like
an adult version of I spy, you know, you like walk in, you're like, I spy the red thing and then all
the red stuff in the room lights up. And you're like, right now you're like, I spy water and
everywhere I go is that's what I see. And you know, you find opportunities and you find ways to
to change it. Oh yeah. When I'm giving my kids a shower, like once I'm lathering them up the water,
I got to turn the water off and they're like, daddy, why are you turning the water off? I'm like,
because we're just putting soap on right now. You don't need the water. It's just, it drives
everybody nuts, but what the hell? Okay. So let's talk about the second law.
Yeah. So the second law is making it attractive. And I think there's a simple example I could
give here, which is let's imagine that you wake up tomorrow and you're like, all right,
I listened to this guy talk about habits all day today. So tomorrow's going to be the day I'm going
to wake up and I'm going to go for a run. So you set your alarm for 6am and 6am rolls around,
but your bed is warm and it's cold outside and you're like, well, I'll just press snooze and
sleep in. Like maybe I'll do it tomorrow. But if you rewind the clock and come back to today
and you text a friend and you say, Hey, you want to meet at the park at 615 and go for a run?
Well, now 6am rolls around and your bed is still warm and still cold outside. But if you don't get
up and go for a run, you're a jerk because you leave your friend at the park all alone.
And so you've kind of simultaneously made it more attractive to get up and go for a run
and less attractive to press snooze and sleep in. Now you haven't made the run itself any easier,
like that's still going to be as difficult as it was before. So the habit, the difficulty is kind
of the same, but you have changed the calculus that's going on in your mind about like whether
you should do this or not, or how attractive it seems. So, you know, there are a bunch of examples,
strategies like that and stuff I talked about in the book and that you could use to kind of make
habits seem more attractive than they otherwise are. But that's sort of what it comes down to on
a short term basis for making habits attractive. On a long term basis, I think it's about what
we've already discussed about the social environment and being part of a tribe or your
desired behavior is the normal behavior because those behaviors become very attractive even a year
or two or five from now, if they help signal that you're part of the tribe.
Yeah, you brought up CrossFit earlier, but I always thought that CrossFit was one of the best
examples of this. I never did CrossFit myself, you know, there's lots of criticisms of it, etc.
But the reality of it is it was certainly it was and is something that really creates a community
of people who have a certain belief about who they are and what they do. And again, for all the
people who not CrossFit, I've seen it take a lot of very inactive people and turn them into some
pretty impressive people. Yeah, I think the social side, the community side of it is the strongest
piece of the whole thing. You know, it's the it's the part that's hardest for any other exercise
program to replicate, that's for sure. And it does, it gets people to stick to it. I mean, it becomes,
you know, it sounds extreme to call it a form of a religion, but it becomes kind of like that for
them. I mean, the box is like their church in a lot of ways, you know, they go six days a week
instead of one day a week. And so there, yeah, there are a lot of strong community elements there.
You also see crossers pick up a bunch of habits they didn't even expect, like they thought they
were going to start working out. But then six months later, they all are buying the same
brand of knee sleeves, and they have a certain type of weightlifting shoe, and they're all eating
paleo. And it was like, we didn't even plan on doing that stuff. I just was going to go to a gym
to work out. But all of those are behaviors that signal what it means to be part of that group.
And again, once you start to build friends in that group and start to, you know, become
ingrained in that society here in that tribe, you start to soak up some of those other behaviors as
well. Yeah, it's really a great example. I guess we'll go to the third and fourth law, but I want
to take a step back and ask you where you put nudging into this, right? So Richard Thaler's
book Nudge, which was probably the first book I ever read on this subject matter.
I mean, it seems so obvious, which is what makes it so interesting and insightful, right? Sometimes
the most brilliant things in retrospect seem so entirely obvious. But it was, I think reading
Richard's book circa, I don't know, call it maybe 2012, it's probably nearly 10 years ago,
that this idea of the default food environment sort of came to me. And I use that term with
our patients as, you know, the more you can control your default food environment,
the more healthy you can be, right? So if your default food environment sucks,
you're going to be relying on willpower a lot. And that's really, really hard. If your default
food environment is at one extreme end of the spectrum, you kind of have a perfect default food
environment, and you could be the healthiest person in the world, even if it's not enjoyable.
At some point, like if you were locked in a room and all you had were the best foods to eat,
you're going to end up being healthy. And you're going to be kind of like, oh,
I eat one more macadamia nut and have one more avocado and salad. But, you know, nudging
obviously refers to a cue, but it also refers to this environmental change. It doesn't seem to
really capture the idea of making it attractive or does it? I think it's more about making it obvious.
I would lump it more in the first law, design the environment to make the good habit the obvious one
to make the good habit the path of least resistance. Some other nudges that are, you know,
very popular people talk about is like default choices on, you know, forms or whatever. So,
you know, the very famous example being the 401ks. Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. And 401ks also. Yeah,
you know, so default opting in every employee to a 401k and making them opt out is a nudge. And I
think that's also another example of making it obvious. Or we could also say making it easy.
Yeah, sort of one in the nothing's easier than letting it ride. So all of those are examples to
your point about about default food environment. Daria Rose, who writes a nutrition blog. She's got
a great concept. I just like it. It's kind of sticky home, home court habits and away court habits.
And, you know, the argument is like, try to optimize your home court habits first, you know,
like what's what's the environment where it's your kitchen, it's your apartment, like you're,
you know, you get to set the tone. And let's just try to prime all of that. Whatever happens at a
restaurant or when you're at a hotel traveling or whatever, let's don't worry about that as much
right now. Let's just optimize the home court. And I like that if you can build a home court advantage
for yourself, then you get in a good, you know, situation, you start to build some momentum,
you handle the thing that you're probably going to be doing 70% of the time or 80% of the time.
And then after that, you can move on to the, you know, to the away court stuff. So one of the other
things you talk about is the idea of accountability. It's come up now several times. And I think
everybody would agree that the moment you have somebody else in this thing with you, the better
it gets. Is there any evidence about the type of accountability partner? So an example you gave was
your wife, great accountability partner for you guys to work out. Would that be more or less
effective than if you were matched with a person who you didn't know, but who had similar aspirations
where you'd be less comfortable and perhaps more inclined to hold yourself to a higher standard.
Again, it kind of comes back to this idea of how we're wired to be, you know, seeking the approval
of others and all those sorts of other things. Is there, is there any research to support this idea?
Yeah, you know, I don't know of any studies that like distinguish clearly between those two. It's
quite possible there are plenty out there. I just may not know of them. But man, I can see it working
well on both sides. And I also see complexities on both sides. So a lot of the time when people
talk about accountability partners, they join a Facebook group or they join a course or program
or something and they get matched up the way that you described. But I can actually see that form of
accountability kind of falling apart fairly quickly for a simple reason, which is it's a
stranger and you don't really bear much cost for them, you know, thinking you did a bad job or you
may not really value or care that much about their opinion. Compare that to the example I gave, you
know, earlier, which is you walk outside and your neighbor sees that your lawn is very sloppy and
you haven't mowed the grass in three weeks. That actually you may care pretty deeply about because
you don't want to be judged by the other people in the neighborhood and you don't want to have
friction with your neighbor and so on. And so there's much more of a cost there. And that form
of accountability is a lot stronger because there's, you know, some reason why you really want to fall
through on it. Now, you could say that that same thing is true for, you know, for example, a marriage
or relationship is that, you know, I don't want to let my partner down. I don't want them to think
poorly of me and so on. But you have to remember in that particular case, you're so close that
there are actually a lot of additional complexities there. Like you want to be fairly forgiving of
your partner because you're living with them all the time. Or even if it's not someone you're
married to, say it's, you know, your brother or your parents or whoever, like there's just a lot
going on in those relationships. And so is the other person really going to become like an enemy
just over you skipping your workout routine on Tuesday, because like you guys got to get dinner
together on Wednesday night and you have to babysit their kids over the weekend. And like,
there's a lot of other stuff that's involved there. And so in those cases, I think the
relationships are so tight or so complex that that person may not actually want to be a strict
accountability partner because of the other costs that they may need to bear. So you're kind of in
this weird situation where you don't want there to be other things on the line that would influence
their ability to be to hold you accountable. But you do actually want to care about their opinion,
and to bear some kind of cost if you don't follow through. Perhaps this is the reason why having
like a coach is a good example, because that's somebody that presumably you want to do a good
job because you're going to see them repeatedly. But even if it's not as dicey as the neighbor
situation where like you do bear some social cost for it, you probably bear a financial cost
because you may be paying your nutrition coats, you know, five hundred dollars or a thousand
dollars or whatever. And the more that there's some kind of painful cost associated with it,
probably the more that you're going to be willing to fall through on that accountability.
And speaking of a coach, just more broadly, how does a coach or how do the best coaches,
if you have insight into this, sort of thread the needle of
creating accountability, but also creating encouragement when you fall short?
Boy, that's a big question. And, you know, I'm not a coach. I've had I've been fortunate to have some
good ones. And I've also had a bunch of, you know, mediocre ones, too. And thinking about the
difference between them, there's just, you know, we could have a whole conversation about coaching
and about the art of that, because there is a really fine balance there. And I think
there also is a big difference in the I'm going to use athlete, but of course, you can have a coach
for many things. But there's a big difference also in the intensity that the athlete might have. I
mean, you know, you can imagine I so I was into Olympic weightlifting for a time and it was kind
of the main way I was training. And I had the fortune of training with a really great team.
I was very average, but, you know, Holly Mangold was on that team and she competed at the Olympic
Games in London in 2012. And watching, just watching the interactions between the coaches
and her and what was required for her to make it to the Olympics was interesting to see, you know,
like there's there, there is every element of a tight relationship there. I mean, there's tough
love and there's like, you know, actual love. And there are some days where you have to be really
harsh and some days you have to be really soft. And there's all the dynamics of the athletes
internal mindset. Like, you know, there are days when you go out and you feel like you're a world
killer and like nobody can touch you. And then there are other days where you just feel completely
broken and you're like, can I keep this training up for another six months? And so the the more
intense the objective is that you're trying to achieve, I think the more detailed and balanced
and nuanced all of that becomes, you know, and then you have like just your standard
CrossFit coach who's coaching a 35 year old dad of two who just wants to get in better shape.
And that I think may be, you know, a totally different relationship. So I don't know that I
have a good answer there, but I do think it's a really important thing and that there are
great coaches are incredibly valuable and they're rare by definition. That's why they're great.
And it's probably much more complicated than a lot of us realize.
So you said rule number one and rule number three were probably the most important rule.
Number three is now make it easy. Yeah. So if I could only recommend like one thing, if I had,
if you forced me to say, hey, where's the one place I would start, I would say start with this.
You hate being asked that question, by the way, if you would just, uh, yeah, just because I mean,
you know, like, you know how it is, you know, like if somebody said, what was the one thing
I would do to get healthy? You'd be like, okay, come on. This is like a very big picture. You
know, there's, there's a lot of stuff here. Um, and, uh, same, same story here. Like, you know,
I do think this is a good place to start though. And so if I had to pick, I would say, follow the
two minute rule, which says, take whatever habit you're trying to build and scale it down to
somebody that takes two minutes or less to do. So read 30 books a year becomes read one page or
do yoga four days a week becomes take out my yoga mat. And sometimes people hate that because
they're like, okay, buddy, you know, like, I know I'm not actually just trying to take my yoga mat
out. I know I'm actually trying to do the workout. So if this is some kind of mental trick and I know
it's a trick, then like, why would I fall for it? Basically. And I get where people are coming from,
but I have this reader, his name's Mitch and I mentioned him in atomic habits and, uh,
he lost a ton of weight. Another guy, I think he lost definitely over 80 pounds. I think it was
probably over a hundred and, um, kept it off for a long time. He, uh, he had this interesting rule
for himself though, where when he went to the gym for the first six weeks, they started working out.
He wasn't allowed to stay for longer than five minutes. So he'd get in the car, drive to the
gym, get out, do half an exercise, get back in the car, drive home. And it sounds ridiculous.
You know, it sounds silly. You're like, obviously this is not going to get the guy the results that
he wants, but if you take a step back, what you realize is that he was mastering the art of showing
up, you know, he was becoming the type of person that went to the gym four days a week, even if
it was only for five minutes. And I think this is like a deep truth about habits, something that
we often overlook, which is a habit must be established before it can be improved. You know,
it has to become the standard in your life before you can optimize and scale it up into something
more. If you want, you can come up with a better theory. Like you could come up with a perfect plan,
but unless you're acting on it, it doesn't do you any good. It's just a really good idea. And so,
you know, for whatever reason, we get like really all or nothing about our habits. We tend to have
this, this tendency to be like, well, if I can't do, you know, the full marathon training program,
then why go for a run at all? Or if I can't, you know, follow through on the perfect, like lean
startup business framework, then like, why bother starting a company? But I think, you know, the two
minute rule kind of helps you get over that tendency of perfectionism and just start to master the art
showing up, find a small way to establish the habit, make a part of your new normal. And then
you can gain a little foothold and start to scale up and expand from there. It reminds me of that.
There's that great quote from Ed Latimore, where he says the heaviest weight at the gym is the front
door. And, you know, that's true for a lot of things in life. I mean, the hardest part is getting
started. So let's master that and make it part of your lifestyle. And then once you're the kind of
person who's showing up consistently, we have all kinds of options for how we can improve and optimize.
And so on. I think meditation is another great place where that the two minute rule really helps.
I think it can be really daunting the first time you decide for the first time, let's say you buy
the idea that, hey, you know what, there's probably real value in this. I'd be better served
to go on a silent retreat for seven days or meditate 40 minutes every day. It's like that's a
real big step for someone who's never done it. How about two minutes every single day you meditate
and, you know, maybe in a few weeks, it's three minutes a day. But yeah, you have to sort of lay
down that track to say, A, I'm a person who meditates and B, this is the actual muscle memory
of what it looks like to sit down. It's also surprising how few people actually have two
minutes in their day where they stop and do nothing except breathe. I mean, that that alone
would deliver more value than you might expect. And there are a whole host of other behaviors that
go along with this. You know, like you think meditating for two minutes sounds very small,
but if you start to back out of it, you realize, oh, there's, you know, you got to pick a space.
Where is it going to happen? What time of day is it going to occur? Is this something that you're
going to do before work or after work? Do you do it on your lunch break? Are you going to like,
try to do it with somebody to so you have a little bit of social accountability? Or is this just like
a private thing that you're going to do in the corner? Do you need a pillow to sit on or you
find a sit on the floor? Like what's your flexibility like? Are you going to get interrupted by your
kids? If you do this at 7am, it might be nice to get it done in the morning. But is that when you're
getting them ready for school and getting them dressed, there's like just a lot of little
questions like that that people don't think about. And so finding a very small version of the habit
allows you to get all of that other stuff kind of handled, figure out the logistics of it,
and just to do it for a minute or two. And then once you get all that stuff handled,
and you don't have to decide anymore, you have a little bit more mental capacity and energy
to actually focus into, okay, let me scale this up a bit and do it maybe in the way that I was
hoping I would. So how do you make them satisfying? Because that's the fourth ball.
Yeah, so this is the final piece. And it's really about just making a habit that's pleasurable
enough that you want to return to it, giving you some, you know, some reason, some emotional signal
that hey, this is worth it. And there are a bunch of different ways you can do this, you know, some
of them are short term, some of them are long term, like the short term stuff is mostly about
reinforcement. So, you know, the classic examples are things like, Oh, you can reward yourself with
a bubble bath or with ice cream or, you know, buying, you know, something that you wanted or
whatever. I think the key with those short term reinforcements is you want to make sure that the
reinforcement also aligns with the long term identity that you're trying to build. Right.
Ice cream wouldn't be a great reward for learning, you know, getting in better shape.
Yeah, right. Like you go to the gym and you do a workout and then you eat a bowl of ice cream.
It's like, okay, you're casting boats for two different identities. Or let's say that you're
trying to get your finances in order. And so you're like, Okay, I want to budget,
you know, consistently and save money for retirement. Well, if you reward yourself with
that by, you know, like buying a leather jacket, and it's kind of like, okay, on the one hand,
you're trying to be a saver. On the other hand, you're being a spender. So I like to pick things
that we feel like are aligned. So like in the in the fitness example, you could say, well,
if I don't miss any workouts this week, then I'm going to reward myself with a bubble bath and kind
of like an hour alone of peace and quiet on the weekend. And that's like a vote for taking care
of your body. And so you know, that seems pretty aligned. Or if I if I save consistently for
retirement this month, and I make a contribution each week, then at the end of the month, I'm going
to reward myself with a hike in the woods. And that's like another example of, you know,
a lifestyle of freedom and of controlling your time and you know, like having having financial
control of you know, how you're spending your time. So anything that's that you feel like is
aligned or reinforces that story you're trying to build, I think that can make a great immediate
reinforcement. In the long run, the way to feel rewarded, the kind of ideal form of making it
satisfying is when the behavior starts to feel like it reinforces your desired identity. So if
if you're the kind of person who feels like, yeah, I'm the type of person who doesn't miss workouts,
then in the middle of doing a set of squats, you can feel satisfied because you're being the kind
of person you want to be. And so this comes back to kind of the point you made a little bit ago
about I just don't want to miss a workout, like I kind of feel off, I feel like I'm not being
myself if I miss. And so just getting the reps in that alone is it's satisfying in the moment.
And that's sort of the the ultimate version of making it satisfying, because you don't even
need to wait for the reward. It's just it's happening as you're in the middle of performing
the behavior. So make it obvious, make it attractive, make it easy, make it satisfying,
those kind of those four laws and you know, the various ways to intervene and do that increase
the odds that you're going to fall through on a good habit. Now, let's take a step back from all
this when when someone picks up your book, presumably, there's a selection bias that exists,
which is this is a person who either through luck or, you know, or through some recommendation or
friend or whatever, has made a decision that they at least want to examine the habits in their lives
and or potentially change them. What do we know or what can we extract from this about a scenario
that's different, which is, you know, I'll use my example, like you have a patient who you're trying
to help and that, you know, helping that patient requires some intervention. They're going to have
to make a change. Now, that change can be at one level really simple. I think the simplest change
medicine has to offer is take a pill and there's a time and a place for pills. I kind of I think
it's a bit silly when people assume that everything modern medicine has to offer is bad. Pills are bad.
You know, obviously, that's not the case. So, you know, taking your medicine for your blood pressure,
your cholesterol, these things, if it's warranted, that's a really important thing to do. And we
also know, by the way, that even something as quote unquote simple as taking your medicine is
actually really hard for a lot of people. Most people are I think studies demonstrate, you know,
sort of in the neighborhood of 60 to 70 percent compliant with something as simple as take a pill.
But it only gets harder from there. Right. So getting someone who's not sleeping well to sleep
well, that's a real big set of behavior changes. Getting someone who's not eating well to eat well,
getting someone who's not exercising to exercise, getting someone who's not taking care of their
mental health to take care of their mental health. All of these things require enormous change.
And if a person says on the surface, yes, I want to be better, like I accept that I want
this outcome of being healthier, but they haven't specifically had the need or desire to change the
way they eat or exercise or sleep or whatever. It adds a layer of challenge or friction to this
process. What advice would you offer to me in a situation like that for trying to implement
your insights into us into that scenario to a person who hasn't fully selected into wanting
to change habits? Yeah, it's a great question. The point about people self-selecting by picking up
the book is interesting because, you know, sometimes it's like you sort of only helping
the people who already, you know, want to be helped in that sense. It's kind of like
it's interesting to think that most of the time the people who most need to read the book are not
the people who pick it up to read it. You know, it's like the people who read about habits are
usually the ones who have like fairly decent habits and are pretty interested in it and like
want to optimize it more. The people who need it the most, like they never read a book on habits
and they don't want to read it and, you know, they're not interested. So anyway, there's a whole
something interesting about that. But I think, you know, the points you bring up are very true
and challenging and, you know, changing your own behavior is hard enough. Changing other people's
behavior is like a whole nother level of difficulty, a whole nother order of magnitude of difficulty.
I'll offer maybe three ideas that could apply. So the first one, and we've already talked about
this in various ways, but I do think you have to make it really small, you know. And so you said,
you know, like taking a pill is the smallest version, but it doesn't always have to be that
it could be, you know, if you're trying to get them to exercise, it could literally be doing one
push up or, you know, walking around the block one time or something. And this is that version of
like, can I just go to the gym for five minutes sort of thing? Let's just scale it down, make it
super simple. Along with that, it is very hard for it to be simple if people are being pulled in
multiple directions. And so I think, you know, if you're giving people a plan that has five things
on there for them to do, can we eliminate four of those for now? Can that be state phase two? And
can we just do one right now? Let's take one thing and scale it down and stay focused and just try to
get a little bit of momentum going on that. And then once we've established that and started to
gain a foothold there and get a little bit more consistency with that one thing, we can take that
momentum and transfer it into the next one. So yeah, ideally, probably a lot of patients will be
doing these five things or these 15 things, but it doesn't mean you need to do all of them right
now. Let's pick one and stay focused. So that's the first thing is try to keep it as simple as
possible. Pretty obvious answer, but I still think a useful one. The second thing, again, fairly
obvious, and we've talked about it a bit, but still, I think useful is the environment design
piece, you know, even the laziest person, even the person who has zero interest naturally in
these topics is a product of the environment that they're in. And as you mentioned earlier,
you know, if you were in some imagine this like lab experiment where you're locked in a room that
only has healthy food options, even the laziest person is going to eat healthy there, they have
no other choice. And, you know, that doesn't mean that they need to change everything in their home
so that that it's that kind of like control lab experiment feel. But look, there's a lot of low
hanging fruit that can be done here, that you don't actually need someone. And this, I think,
is one of the reasons why I like environment changes. You don't actually need someone to be
motivated every day to do this, you really just need them to be motivated for like one afternoon,
so that they change the environment a bit. And that can actually serve them in some cases,
a concern for months, but in most cases, even food related cases, it could serve them for the
next three days or five days or seven days, just by getting junk food out of the house that serves
them for the next, you know, couple days. And so you only need little pockets of motivation.
And if you can direct that pocket of motivation toward a high leverage action, like redesigning
the environment, then it can continue to serve even a lazy person for a good chunk of time.
So that's probably the second thing. So make it small, optimize the environment. And then the
third thing, and this is maybe more of like a coaching thing as someone who deals with patients
or, you know, has clients or whatever. The general strategy is easy to say, but very hard to follow,
which is praise the good, ignore the bad. And it goes against the grain of what we want to do,
because they're like, you're telling me, I just want to ignore the mistakes that they're making.
And, you know, certainly there's a place for rectifying mistakes. And I don't mean that every
problem should just go unresolved. But especially early on, the thing that you really want to build
is momentum. And you want to reinforce the good behaviors. And as we talked about a good plant
crowding out another, a way to encourage that is by praising the good and ignoring the bad.
There was a hilarious op-ed that was written, I think it was in the New York Times,
this wife who her husband would never throw his dirty clothes in the laundry hamper. And it was
driving her nuts. And, you know, occasionally he would do it, but it was like pulling teeth all the
time to get him to do this consistently. And she tried everything. She, you know, she tried nagging
him, she tried annoying, you know, whatever, just all kinds of different, put the laundry hamper in
a different place. Don't even have it in the closet, just have it out on the floor in the bedroom,
and he still wouldn't do it. Sometimes you throw the clothes next to the hamper. She's like,
you're already throwing it over there. Just put it in. And eventually what she settled on doing
was that every time that he happened to put it in the hamper, she would make a huge deal about it.
She'd run over, give him a kiss, give him a hug, say thank you, be like, oh, you're making my life
so much easier. Thank you so much. And over the course of about a year, she effectively trained
him to always put the clothes in the hamper because every time that happened, something good
happened, he got praised, it felt good. And, you know, it's almost like training a dog in a sense,
which is all kinds of organisms, dogs and humans love feeling praised, we like feeling good,
we like being rewarded. And so if you praise the good actions and ignore the bad actions,
it's again, almost like a form of gravity, people naturally gravitate toward the things that they
get rewarded for the things they get praised for. And you'd be surprised how often people don't do
something like this, or in fact, do the opposite. Like, you can imagine, you know, the quiet kid in
the household who comes down for dinner with the rest of the family, and it's like, Oh, look who
showed up, or, you know, they decide to share something about their day. And it's like, Oh,
you know, finally, some, you know, a fact about your life. And you can imagine a parent or somebody
saying something sarcastic like that. And all of a sudden, you're punishing the very behavior that
you wanted to see. And so praise the good, ignore the bad, I think it applies in a lot of situations
and can be more powerful than you realize. The tricky part is it requires a lot of patience,
you got to do it for six months or a year or three years. And it's hard, it's hard to stick with that
in the long run. Last example of this is a weightlifting one. I was at the gym on a Friday night
one time. And I was there with a friend, we were doing a quick workout. And it's probably like 20,
25 minutes, we got done, we're putting our shoes on. And this guy who's just kind of a jerk,
went over, was talking to her, was like, quick workout for a Friday night. And, you know,
like, she just kind of moved on. But that's like exactly the opposite of the type of feedback you
want to be getting, especially if you're someone who's like new coming into the gym or feeling
kind of uncomfortable there, you know, what people should be saying is, oh, it's great that
you got in here, even though you know, it's the weekend. And a little cutting comment like that
is all that people need to not show up again the next day. And so the more that you can be
lavish with praise is, you know, maybe stating it even too strongly, but it doesn't really cost you
very much to be kind. And, you know, you may not even remember it, but it's the kind of thing that
might be enough to get that person to show up again the next time. And so in the long run,
praising the good and ignoring the bad can count for a lot. So James, you're working on another book,
right? I am. Yeah. And working is the correct term. So I'm currently kind of slogging and
battling against the manuscript. I seem to find whatever way requires the most suffering to write
books. Atomic habits. The first draft was like 720 pages. And then I cut it down to 250 eventually,
which for the finished version, this manuscript is like 600 and something right now. So I'm in the
in the trimming phase. What's this book about? It's a book about strategy and choices and
decision making and how we direct our attention. I'm still kind of finding it and discovering it
in a lot of ways, but no one question that you could have after finishing atomic habits is,
okay, that's great. I know how to build better habits, but which habits should I be focusing on?
What's the high leverage action? How do I figure out where to direct my energy and attention?
And so those are a lot of the questions that I'm exploring now.
Well, I can't wait to have you back to discuss that after I read it twice, which I will do. I'm sure.
Thanks very much, James. This has been really great to sit down with you. And
again, this is almost like reading the book a third time. And I've picked up a lot of things
that I hope readers or listeners have also. And I look forward to implementing it both
personally and professionally. That's great. Thanks, Peter. Appreciate the opportunity.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear
everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous
episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products
that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other
benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access
these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe.
You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can
also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This
podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute the practice of medicine,
nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice.
No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to
this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in
obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the
assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts
of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in
or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active
list of such companies.