Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Patrick. Thank you so much for making time to sit down. I know you've done a number
of these interviews. One of the things I always like to do is try to go places or at least
deeper than maybe you've gone before. We'll see if that can be accomplished. There's certainly
no shortage of material here to dive into. I guess I want to start with a question that
I know you've probably spoken about before, which is what drew you to this story because
the depths that you've gone to to research your book have been certainly at the upper
desk aisle, I would suppose, of what an investigative journalist would do.
Thanks. It's great to be with you. Happy to talk about how I came to this. I've always
been interested in drugs as a subject, the way in which drugs fit into our society,
how we feel about them, which drugs are illicit, which drugs are illicit. I wrote a big piece
a number of years ago about the legalization of cannabis in Washington state. I was just
very interested in this idea that you have this existing industry, this pot industry
that's been around for decades. Then with the stroke of a pen at midnight, it's legalized.
What does that look like? How do you turn it into a tax and regulated economy?
I had done a lot of writing on Mexican drug cartels. I did a big piece actually before
I was full-time at The New Yorker. I did a cover story for the New York Times magazine
back in 2012 about the Sinaloa drug cartel. To give you a sense of context, I mean, at
the time I had to explain to the editors of The New York Times magazine who Chapo Guzman
was. He was not a household name at all. The idea there was I wanted to do a Harvard Business
School case study of a cartel. I wanted to look at it as a multi-billion dollar transnational
commodities enterprise. I was really interested in how they diversified and how vertically
integrated they were. One of the questions that grew out of that research was you saw
at a certain point a surge in heroin. They had different pro- I mean, Sinaloa, dealt
in cocaine, marijuana, heroin, and methamphetamine. After 2010, you start seeing more Mexican
heroin, huge volumes of it coming across the border in ways that it hadn't been before
into the US. That was kind of a riddle that I started with, was this question of why this
sudden uptick in heroin? The answer was the opioid crisis. It was one of these funny things
where I started out with an inquiry that was kind of solidly grounded in the realm of the
illicit drug trade and found my way into the world of the FDA regulated legal drug trade
with OxyContin and Purdue Pharma. I started looking into the origins of the opioid crisis
and then discovered that this company Purdue was owned by the Sackler family. That kind
of blew my mind, the idea that this family that's quite well known for philanthropy had
made such a huge fortune on this drug with such a controversial legacy. That was kind
of the way in for me.
I kind of drew on a piece of paper a long time ago when I was trying to get my mind
around this, how many actors there were. The paper looked something like this. It started
on the left and it had producers. I was talking about this not through the illicit chains.
You had the pharma companies of which Purdue would be the champion of them. Then you have
the distributors or the intermediaries, the McKesson's and the Cardinals of the world.
I actually knew a lot about McKesson through a previous life, so I was intimately familiar
with what companies like McKesson did and how they were able to distribute products
from the producers to the retail, the pharmacy, the CVSs of the world. That became your third
actor. Your fourth actor then became the FDA in the approval process of a drug and then
the DEA around enforcement. You could even put those two in a bucket. You then have the
regulators that create or the policymakers rather that create the policies that allow
these entities to exist. Then you have the providers, people that write the prescriptions
for these things and ultimately you have the patients. That's maybe a bit of an oversimplification,
but it gives you a sense of just how complicated this web is. Now, we're going to spend a lot
of time talking about one entity within one of those buckets. Why do you think that that is a
place for someone who's maybe listening to this podcast to get a pretty good sense of the magnitude
of this problem? Because I don't think anybody could with a straight face say there isn't a
problem. You'll put some numbers to what that means. But it's interesting that perhaps the
study of Purdue Pharma and the Sacklers, more than any other single entity in that entire
chain that I explained, could provide a greater context of what we're up against. Would you
agree with that? I'm assuming you have a bias, otherwise you wouldn't have studied them so
extensively. Yeah, it's interesting. It's great that you lay it out with that much nuance because
that's the kind of nuance that often gets lost. There's two things I'd say. One is a sort of
observation that I would make as a writer and a journalist and somebody who writes books. I go
where my interests lead me. I write stories that I think are interesting stories, interesting to
me that I think are important, that I think would be interesting to readers. It's very, very often
the case that I'll spend a lot of time on something and the reaction that people have is,
well, why did you pick this? Why didn't you write about this other thing? I think that there's this
other variable that's very important here. I kind of instinctively resist those types of questions,
right? Because on some level, I feel as though it's my prerogative as a writer to kind of pick the
area that interests me and do it and hopefully do it well in a way that has some integrity. But I
make no claim to suggesting like this is the be all and end all. So in this case, if it's the opioid
crisis, there would never be any suggestion that like this is the only book you need to read on the
opioid crisis. And to segue from that into the particulars here. So when we talk about the opioid
crisis, we're talking about an incredibly complex public health crisis that unfolds over the course
of a quarter of a century. Today, the numbers are a little imprecise, but you have at least a half
a million people who've died from opioid overdoses since the mid to late 1990s. By some estimates,
you have two plus million Americans today struggling with an opioid use disorder of one
sort or another. And when we talk about opioids, that's actually a kind of pretty capacious
category, right? So it's regulated drugs like OxyContin, but it's also fentanyl that comes in
from China or Mexico. It's heroin. And in fact, when you talk about the death toll today, I think
the Sacklers certainly would be quick to say today, people are dying in very large numbers from
heroin and fentanyl overdoses, not from OxyContin or indeed from most prescription painkillers.
This problem has kind of transitioned into an illicit drug problem. So why pick OxyContin and
why pick the Sacklers? In my view, in part because it's an interesting story, I'm interested in the
fact that this was a family, family dynamics are interesting to me, in part because of the
philanthropic legacy because there's this kind of disconnect or there was until recent years
between the reputation that the family had and what I would argue is the reality of their business.
But most importantly, because I think that this was a, OxyContin was sort of the, in the words of
somebody who worked on the drug, was the tip of the spear. So I think it's, you know, this is the
kind of nuance that often gets lost, right? But it can be possible to stipulate that today the
opioid crisis is a heroin and fentanyl crisis. And also to keep in your mind the idea that
absent OxyContin, we might not be where we are today, that it was the kind of first mover
in terms of changing prescribing habits in the United States in a way that had really fundamental
consequences and ultimately built up a market for these drugs, a market which eventually migrated
to illicit sources of supply. So that would be the reason I'm sure we can talk about it in more
detail, but I think there's kind of a special role that Purdue and the Sackler's played, which is not
for a second to suggest that there isn't blame with all those different buckets that you mentioned,
because they're absolutely it is. And I think, you know, based on what I've read of your writing,
you also seem very, very well informed about those other buckets. So I definitely want to make sure
we touch on them, but there's no place to start like where we're going to start. So
let's start with the three Sackler brothers. Take your pick of who you want to begin with, Arthur,
Raymond Mortimer. Who were these guys? What got them interested in pharmaceuticals?
Yeah, I mean, you have to start with Arthur, I think you've got these three brothers who,
they were the children of immigrants, their parents had come over from Europe at the turn
of the last century, settled in Brooklyn. They were Jewish, parents didn't speak English really
all that well. Initially, they spoke Yiddish in the home. And they raised their kids to
believe in a few things. I think to believe in education, to believe in meritocracy.
You know, there's this, I think, kind of wonderfully American. There are these kind
of very American mythical contours to the early parts of this story, right? Where there's a family
that kind of came with nothing and had a hope and an expectation that within the span of one
generation, they would build an empire and really kind of make their mark on the country and the
world. And they were right. And so they raised these three brothers. Arthur later said that
from the age of four, he knew he would be a doctor with a sense that, you know, you're all
going to grow up, you're going to get educated, you're going to become physicians. And there was
a sense that there was kind of nothing as prestigious and virtuous as being a doctor.
I think there was a real kind of veneration in this family for the role of the physician
in society. And so the brothers grow up, but they also grow up against the backdrop of the
Great Depression. There's a period where their father loses everything. And so there was an
expectation that you also have to go out there and hustle and make money and have jobs. And so all
three brothers worked multiple jobs. And I'd say in the book of Arthur Sackler, it's like he's a
guy, it's like he squeezed four or five lifetimes into one lifetime in terms of everything that he
did. And they end up eventually in the pharmaceutical business. But the way they get there is through
pharmaceutical advertising and marketing. And that actually starts back in high school. You know,
when Arthur Sackler's in high school, he gets jobs on the student publications. He's at this
huge high school, Erasmus Hall High School. It's something like six or seven thousand students
in Brooklyn, in Flatbush. It's still there today. And he gets jobs, you know, on the student
magazine, the student newspaper, but he becomes the advertising manager. And if you think about it,
you have six or seven thousand students that you can reach. That was a real job. And so that's
where the hustle starts with Arthur. And all three brothers end up training a psychiatrist,
practicing a psychiatrist. But they pretty quickly pivot into commerce.
So what were the types of drugs of that era that were really making a difference in their practice?
It seems that, you know, sedatives were potentially becoming of interest in that era.
Yeah. I mean, you know, you have this kind of early amazing moment where Arthur there's this
pattern that asserts itself with the brothers where Arthur goes and he does something and then
he kind of brings his brothers in with them. That starts in high school with him getting he's got
got more jobs and he can handle. So he starts handing them off to the brothers. And he ends up
at the Creedmoor Psychiatric Hospital, which is a huge asylum, vast kind of industrial asylum
in Queens, New York, public state mental hospital with a staggering capacity. Right. It's something
like six thousand beds. I mean, when I read that, I thought that can't be possible. I don't know what
that would look like, meaning I literally can't picture the infrastructure large enough to have
six thousand inpatient beds. Yeah. I mean, there's a vast facility, but I believe it was a facility
designed for four thousand beds. So I mean, part of this is a reflection of the kind of,
you know, it's interesting because in these years, right, like this is this is pre-thorazine.
It's kind of the the it's like the last kind of maximalist phase of
of big state mental hospitals, right, of people basically being warehoused for life in these
facilities. It's just prior to the deinstitutionalization that happens in the decades that
follow. And so the brothers get there and they're shocked by the conditions. And also, if you think
about it, I mean, Arthur in particular, he was a Freudian. He trained us at Freudian. Right. So
not a lot of talk therapy happening at a six thousand bed hospital. They were looking for.
Were they still doing lobotomies and things like that?
They were. I mean, in fact, lobotomies start up during this time. So it's a lot of electroshock
treatment. And then and then lobotomies. And I should say, I mean, you know,
electroshock has its has its defenders even today. It obviously has, you know,
it is very successful for some people in some circumstances. But the Sackler brothers are there
and they're administering it thousands of times. And I think it just became more and more demoralizing
for them because they just felt as though we have to. How can we as physicians not have
developed some more humane way of administering to our patients? And so they develop, even at that
point, this theory that a lot of the afflictions they're seeing are probably have some some basis
that is fundamentally chemical. And if that's the case, then there's probably some chemical solution.
And the brothers don't have anything to do with Thorazine. But when it comes along,
they see that right. I mean, this is in some ways a kind of glimpse of the future that they had
that they had envisioned. And it was, I think, generally speaking, an exciting time in the
pharma business, right? Because you have you have penicillin, which is a huge game changer in the
Second World War. And then a lot of these, you know, these companies that today we think of as
like big pharma. Prior to the Second World War, they didn't really look like they do now.
They were producing chemicals, but they weren't really producing branded drugs in quite the same
way. And then you just get this go go period where they're all competing, and they're developing new
antibiotics, and they're coming out with new products every few weeks, and suddenly they need
to differentiate themselves. And consumers are, you know, they're no longer going to the pharmacy
and having the pharmacist mix whatever it is that their doctor has prescribed. They're going in and
requesting drugs by their brand name. And so it's in that kind of exciting, I think quite idealistic
whirlwind climate that the Sackler brothers come of age.
Where did Purdue Pharma come from? Was it a company that they founded? Was it something
that they bought and later transformed? It was the latter. It had been its origins date back to the
19th century. It was a little patent medicine company based funnily enough on Christopher
Street in Greenwich Village, which is like, you know, you can go to the building that it once
occupied. It's just funny that the, you know, the what had once been the sort of humble Purdue
Frederick factory is like today, somebody's $18 million townhouse. And in 1952, Arthur Sackler had
already achieved a great deal of financial success, not in the drug business per se, but in
in pharmaceutical advertising. So he kind of, he really makes his name by joining and then
taking over a pharmaceutical advertising firm. And he's a genius for advertising drugs. At this
point, where all these drug companies need to figure out ways to differentiate their products
and reach doctors and persuade them to prescribe. And with some of the money he's made, Arthur
purchases this company, Purdue Frederick, and he basically gives it to his brothers. So he remains
a, you know, he's a stakeholder in the company, he owns a third of it. But he's a silent partner,
basically, and the brothers will run the company. And that's in starting in 52.
And what happens over the next 30 years?
So they, you know, it's funny. Purdue Frederick was a very successful company. I mean,
the brothers get rich, but they're getting rich in a way that is, I think that even Arthur would
probably have sniffed at. Because Arthur, who again, you know, he's one of the owners of the
company, but not involved day to day, he's really focusing on the marketing of pharmaceuticals.
And his big success is, I mean, he had many successes, but his biggest success
is that he designs the marketing and advertising strategy for the minor trinicalizer, Librium,
and then for Valium, both of which Roche develops. And Librium becomes the biggest selling drug in
the history of the pharmaceutical industry. And then it's surpassed only by Valium. And then for
years, the two of them are in the top five drugs nationwide. And Arthur designed all the advertising
and the marketing for that. And he devised this interesting compensation scheme where basically
he said, I'm going to get an escalating series of bonuses depending on how many pills you sell,
and there's no ceiling. So he becomes vastly wealthy on the basis of these drugs.
His brothers, meanwhile, you know, what they're doing is less cutting edge. They basically license
over the counter products and then sell them. And they were really smart about it. So they
had an antiseptic solution, Betadine, which is still out there. And they got the rights to that
just before the Vietnam War. It had kind of battlefield applications in Vietnam. They had
a laxative, Seneca, very successful. These are these kind of cash crop products. They're very
unglamorous, but they're staples, over the counter stuff. But year in, year out, they're
very, very successful. The irony, by the way, of the company that would create
the opioid boom, having a laxative, which is, of course, they already would address one of the
most painful short term consequences of opioid use being constipation.
Well, and the crazy thing is that they eventually it gets to a point where
the sales reps for Purdue would go out and, you know, they'd market the one with the other,
right? It's they would market them together. But it's really only in the 80s.
That the company starts getting more late 70s, early 80s. The company starts getting aggressive
about really investing in R&D and developing its own prescription drugs. And it's at that point
that they move into pain management. Any inclination from your research why they decided to keep this
company private, as opposed to take it public, like many of the large pharma companies?
God, you know, I can only speculate. But the the Sacklers had a real sense, I think for a long
time, that this was a kind of old world enterprise, that it was a family business. It was family owned,
physician owned, they would always say there was a sense that they controlled it. And they thought
of the people who worked for them as family. You know, it's really only with the advent of
OxyContin in the 90s that the that it becomes this, you know, multi billion dollar company up to that
point. It was a pretty modest outfit. The Sackler brothers themselves did really well. They were
very wealthy. But it was a kind of manageable family firm. And I think that there was there
was something to that. I don't know. I don't know what it would have looked like if it went public.
I do know that you've kind of put your finger on something there. Because I think when you when
you get into the later stages, kind of post the introduction of OxyContin, there's a lot of stuff
that happens in this story that would never happen in a public company. Yeah, that's sort of my
that's the revisionist history in me, which is saying like, had they been a public company,
how far would this have gone? Yeah, I mean, I don't mean to suggest that I think in the early
going, and we can sort of get into the into the particulars, but there are these like hinge
moments in this story. And so you have, you know, you've got all the stuff that happens prior to the
introduction of OxyContin. And then you start seeing things go wrong, and then they go more wrong.
And it's like, well, how do you handle it when you see how do you handle it when you start getting
calls saying that the product that you sell is killing people. And I think that probably would
have been a different response in a public company. And then the really crazy thing is eventually
we're getting ahead of ourselves here, but eventually you get a guilty plea in a federal
criminal case in 2007. And I think at a public company, if you had that, I just think heads would
have rolled, you'd have a total change of personnel, you know, big shake up on the board.
And at a privately held family company, what happened was like, no, you're fired. Yeah. Yeah.
So talk a little bit about MS content as the precursor to OxyContin and
maybe the pharmacokinetics of it, but more importantly, what that transition was about.
So, you know, in the 1980s, you saw the beginning, I mean, actually, taking back to the 70s, a kind of
revisionist school of physicians who felt in the UK and in the US and other parts of the world,
who felt that the medical establishment had been not taking pain seriously enough as a problem,
that doctors weren't treating pain aggressively. They were treating it just just merely as a
symptom, not as a problem in and of itself, that there wasn't enough medical education
for physicians in terms of identifying pain and responding to it.
And kind of going along with this was it was a sense that that many physicians had that
there was a resistance to prescribing opioids out of a fear of addiction that
that doctors have been too stingy in prescribing opioids for pain because of
concerns about abuse and addiction. And it's in this context that MS content,
this drug has developed and it's a cancer drug. It's a drug for cancer pain.
And it's basically just morphine. But the real innovation was the content part. So content
short for continuous. And it's essentially this decoding on the pill. And the idea is that this
will regulate the flow of the drug into the bloodstream over a course of hours. And so
MS content was developed in the UK and then rolled out in the US. And it was it was
it was it was kind of a groundbreaking drug in its way, very successful for the company.
I remember exactly what it was generating in terms of revenue at its height, but
three or four hundred million dollars a year, which was a lot for Purdue. And at the time, and
it was a big success. And I think that the family was was proud of it. And there was a sense that
they were doing a good thing, relieving terrible pain for people suffering from cancer
and and doing very well financially. And so they were kind of in this world of doctors who were
thinking about pain and wanting to kind of reevaluate the way in which pain is treated.
They were heroes. And you had this kind of interesting. And I don't think necessarily
altogether cynical confluence of interests, right, in which Purdue starts sponsoring
academic conferences on the treatment of pain and medical conferences and seminars. And they're
sort of out there with an obvious commercial interest. But also, I think a sense that,
you know, we're part of a revolution here. We're going to revolutionize the way in which pain is
treated. So whose idea is OxyContin? I mean, in some sense, it's an obvious leap because if
M.S. content is simply morphine sulfate formulated in a continuous fashion, there are other narcotics
out there. Percocet already existed. It was simply hydrocodone with acetaminophen. Hydrocodone existed
by itself in a non-time released format. So was there great innovation basically saying we're just
going to make a time release version of hydrocodone just as it had been done with morphine? Was that
effectively the aha moment? Yeah, I mean, what happens is that M.S. content is something I mean,
I should say, and this will be this will be not a surprise to you. But but to me coming from the
outside, I was really startled. I knew as a kind of objective analytical matter that that the
lifecycle of a patent is very important to a drug company. I don't think I fully appreciated the
degree to which it is the sun and the stars. And you know, it's everything. And there were so many
points in the course of my reporting for this story where there'd be some some sort of mystery
about motivation. There'd be some weird thing that they did, and I couldn't figure out why.
And I would puzzle over it and puzzle over it and puzzle over it. And then it always turned out to
be something having to do with a patent, you know, that the, for example, the pediatric indication,
the pediatric indication, very good example, right? So the where they they applied to get at a point
where oxycontin was hugely controversial already, causing all kinds of problems they they applied to
for the the pediatric indication for the drug. And I sort of couldn't figure out why. And and
they had all these explanations that turned out to not be true. And then it turned out it was
because they thought they would get an additional six months of patent exclusivity if they got it.
But the there's a bunch of cases like that. And in the case of MS content, the patent is running
out at a certain point, and they realized that it's going to decimate their profits.
It's going to decimate their profits. And so they just start talking about, hey,
what else could we put with, you know, the content system? And some of the family dynamics here are
a little humorous. But there's, according to Kathy Sackler, who's one of the second generation
Sacklers, who's involved in the company and is a medical doctor. She has dinner with Richard
Sackler, her cousin and kind of rival within the company at a certain point. And she suggests what
about oxycodone? And according to her, Richard didn't know what oxycodone was. And she had to
explain. And oxycodone is stronger than both hydrocodone and morphine. It is. And the end,
well, I mean, part of what's interesting about about oxycodone is that the there's this amazing
thing that happens basically where they make their decision. Okay, we're going to use oxycodone.
So we'll develop oxycontin. And there are these conversations that happen, and they happen over
email. And I have the emails where these senior executives at the company and Richard Sackler
are talking about the market and the idea that MS content was a drug for cancer pain.
And the stigma associated with morphine, this notion that, you know,
if you're a regular person, not a doctor, and your doctor tells you that your mother is going on
morphine, that means your mother is going to die. And what they realize is that oxycodone didn't
have those same associations, even though it's stronger than morphine. They did focus groups.
And you have oxycodone in Percocet and in Percodan. And that was the primary way in which
physicians were encountering those drugs. And, you know, that's right. I misspoke earlier.
I said it was hydrocodone. It's actually oxycodone. That's right. It's oxycodone. And when they're cut
with aspirin or acetaminophen, it's you know, it's a relatively small dose. There's only so much
you can take. So what they noticed in these focus groups is that physicians had a sort of a sense of
oxycodone as more benign, you know, less threatening. There was less stigma, but also they saw it as
weaker. And there are these incredible emails where they say, well, listen, there's only so
many people who have cancer pain. You know, we did great with our cancer drug, but there's a
much bigger market out there of people suffering not just from severe pain, but moderate pain,
chronic pain, back pain, sports injuries. There's a funny cartoon you could envision here,
which is another revisionist, which is imagine if instead they just decided to figure out a way to
make more cancer patients. How could we do to increase a number of people dying of cancer
to expand our market? And then someone goes, no, no, no, that's too hard. That's too hard.
I got a better idea. Let's just figure out a way to make everybody who doesn't have cancer
takes this drug. Right. And in fact, to kind of to sort of create the need, which is, you know,
a big part of what the marketing ended up being. Yeah. I mean, the analogy that I come back to,
you know, the first third of the book is devoted to Arthur Sackler in those earlier years. And
that was a very deliberate choice, even though Arthur Sackler dies in 87 before the introduction
of Oxycontin. Because I think there are all of these, I think there are all of these
things that happen earlier that are kind of the seeds for what comes later. So the analogy I
always think of is Thorazine, which the original Sackler brothers see. You know, Thorazine is a
major tranquilizer for people who are psychotic. And it was very successful, you know, emptied out
the the asylums pretty quickly. I mean, there were other things that did as well, but it was
a real game changer. But there's only so many people who are actually required that kind of
heavy duty solution. And then Arthur Sackler makes his fortune on the minor tranquilizers, where,
you know, who among us doesn't feel a little stressed at the end of the day? You know,
who couldn't benefit from something to make them relax a little bit? And that was what turned
Liberty and Valium into these huge blockbusters. It's kind of a similar thing here, where
there's this sense that, you know, MS-Contin is a drug for this subset of people who are
experiencing terrible cancer pain. There's a much bigger community of people
who have moderate pain. But the weirdness of it is that they then take a drug that is stronger,
not weaker, and market it that way. And you see these emails in which these executives say,
in our focus groups, doctors erroneously think that oxycodone is weaker than morphine.
Let's not do anything to make them realize that they're wrong about the product that we're
selling them, because if we did, it could constrain our market. So they developed this new drug.
What's unusual about the process by which it receives its FDA approval?
A handful of things. So they-
We can insert Curtis Wright at any point here, by the way.
Yeah, exactly. So there's a guy named Curtis Wright, who was the medical examiner at FDA,
who was kind of the grand inquisitor. He was the one they had to satisfy
in order to get the drug approved, but also in order to get the marketing claims.
Maybe explain to folks why those two things are very important. Why is it that
if you and I went into business tomorrow to create a drug, the FDA would have to approve it
from a safety and efficacy standpoint. But then they'd also have to basically put guardrails
around what we could actually say it's for. I don't think people fully understand that dual
role there. Well, I mean, it's the strangest thing. Richard Sackler, the second-generation
Sackler, is probably the most intimately acquainted with or involved with OxyContin.
There's a point where he talks about how the package insert in a bottle of pills
is our most potent selling instrument. And it's a strange thing, right? Because I think for the
average consumer, you see the sort of dense wording on that and it feels like the fine print.
It feels like something the doctors read. You may read it as well, but it doesn't feel like a
marketing document. But if you're the drug company, it's all about the indications. It's all about
the claims that you can make for what kinds of ailments this medication might alleviate.
And then also in terms of the kind of competitive positioning. So in the case of OxyContin,
I mean, I'll give you a very extreme example. They didn't do any tests on the
addictiveness of the drug. They didn't do any tests on the abuse liability of the drug.
But there was a kind of hypothesis that they had at Purdue, which was because of the content
system, you wouldn't have the kind of peaks and troughs of a sort of wave of euphoria when a big
dose of the drug hits your bloodstream, followed by a kind of diminution and withdrawal. Instead,
it's the steady, regulated, continuous flow. And their hypothesis was that because of that,
it wouldn't be addictive and it wouldn't be subject to abuse. And that that was a competitive
advantage vis-a-vis other opioid products that were out there on the market. And you have this
kind of crazy stretch where they start working very closely with Curtis Wright on the approval
process. Some strange stuff happens. I mean, the company said, I don't even think this is in the
book, but the company sends Curtis Wright, this is in the 1990s, this is in the 95. The company sends
him a webcam. This is like a very early webcam where he can talk directly with folks in Stanford.
Curtis Wright starts requesting that they send things not to his FDA office, but to his house.
And at a certain point, a team of people from Purdue travel to Maryland and get a hotel room
and they spend three days with Curtis Wright helping him write his reviews of their studies.
Let's just pause there for a second. It's almost impossible to imagine that happening.
I'm not saying it didn't because you've got the email proof that it happened.
I'm just saying from a matter of process, that statement is so difficult to comprehend.
So how do we put that in perspective? What did other people at the FDA know at this point in time?
What do you think emboldened the Sackler leadership to do that without fear of Curtis Wright turning
to them and saying, are you freaking crazy? I mean, how does this unfold?
So it's really hard to say, and I've tried to kind of puzzle through this. And I should say,
I mean, Curtis Wright wouldn't talk about it. I got him on the phone and he very quickly hung up.
He didn't want to talk to me about any of this. I filed a Freedom of Information Act request with
the FDA, which they dragged their feet in the way that federal bureaucracies always do. So I
actually sued them in federal court to compel them to turn over documents to me. And I got a New York
federal judge to order them to do document production to me, thousands and thousands of
pages of documents. And my first request was for all the emails of Curtis Wright. And the FDA came
back and told me that all of his correspondence and emails have either been lost or destroyed.
Yeah, which again, you couldn't make that level of malfeasance up. Like you can't,
you know, it's so ridiculous. How do they even say that with a straight face?
I know. I know. Well, particularly given that the, you know, I could understand if it was a sort of a
document retention thing where after a certain number of years, they eliminate stuff. In his
case, though, this is a guy who had been, you know, he was investigated by Department of Justice
investigators, really starting in like 2002, 2003. I mean, this was somebody who was red flagged
early by other federal agencies, the notion that they would today say, you know, it's the equivalent
of saying like there was a very small warehouse fire. It's just that box, I'm afraid that, you know,
we didn't retain. It's pretty shocking to me. But so I've tried to sort of puzzle this out.
There's an interesting email chain. So some of this email has come out, not through the FDA,
but through federal investigations of Purdue. There's an interesting moment where one of the
Purdue officials says that he happened to bump into Curtis Wright at a conference. This is as
all of this approval stuff is happening. And they talked in a kind of a sidebar way. It was not
formal. And I, you know, my sense is that the generally speaking, the FDA process, at least in
theory, is one that is, it's pretty formalized, right? Because you don't want too much of an
opportunity for improper influence to happen. And there's this interesting memo that the Purdue
guy sends back to headquarters where he says, you know, I got talking with Curtis Wright, it was
great. We talked about the whole Oxycontin thing. And he indicated that he would be open to other
such informal exchanges in the future or something to that effect. So I don't know. I don't know how
to how to make sense. I mean, wouldn't the Occam's razor response be the following given that a year
after leaving the FDA, Curtis Wright is now employed by Purdue Pharma? Isn't the only obvious
explanation here that there was a quid pro quo, a very clear and direct quid pro quo made between
Purdue and Curtis Wright? So it's interesting, the former federal prosecutor, long time federal
prosecutor from the Western District of Virginia who prepared really the, you know, the biggest
case against Purdue and spent years pouring over millions of pages of documents and looked really
hard at Curtis Wright. He told me on the record, this guy is pretty careful about what he says.
And he told me on the record, I think a deal was made. He said, I can't prove it, just my opinion.
But I think a deal was made. When you look at the totality of the evidence, it seems hard for me to
believe any other, I mean, he's saying exactly what you are, you know, any other explanation.
I don't know that I need to go that far. And here's why. I don't think Purdue even needed to say,
hey, make this work for us, and there might be a job for you on the other side.
I think that, and this is where from a policy point of view, this gets really hard to
regulate, right, is that the FDA is full of over educated, really smart people who are making
government salaries. And, you know, they have the unglamorous task of working on these approvals. And
on the other side of the table is this huge multi-billion dollar industry, where, you know,
you can make a lot of money and where there's a great deal of interest in former FDA officials,
you know, both in having them come and work at the firm because it's at the pharmaceutical firm,
because that's useful in a whole bunch of ways. But also, I would argue, I think there's probably
a great deal of interest in having the FDA officials that you're talking to know that someday there
might be a job for them. And that's this hard thing, because it's not corruption in an explicit
quid pro quo sense. It's not corruption in a way that's actually all that easy to please.
Because if you're the FDA, what do you do? I mean, do you say, okay, we're gonna have a cooling off
period, you know, once you leave the agency, how long? A year? Three years? You know, at what point
do you start losing talent? Because people don't want to be locked up after they leave. I think
these are, I don't mean to suggest for a second that these are easy questions. But I also think
there's what I would call a kind of soft corruption that pervades this whole process. I don't think
it's unique to Curtis Wright. He's a very extreme example. But what you get is in his case, as you
said, he goes a year after OxyContin is approved, he goes and works at Purdue for three times his
government salary. But to your point about the marketing claims, there's a line in the original
package insert for OxyContin that says the content seal is believed to reduce the abuse liability of
the drug. And that's a weird thing to have in a package insert. In general, I think I mean, it's a
great marketing claim. But it's like is believed doesn't seem very scientific, necessarily.
What was the basis of that belief, the scientific basis? There was there a study that was cited?
Was there an experiment that was done? I mean, it wouldn't be hard to have studied these things.
There wasn't one. No, in this case, what it was was it was this conjecture that because of the
content system, you're not getting the high highs and the low lows. And therefore it would it would
make it less prone to abuse than other drugs. And the real measure of how compromised this line was
is that to this day, nobody will admit writing that line. So Curtis Wright has been asked about
this and he said, oh, yeah, it was it wasn't the FDA, it was Purdue Pharma, the Purdue Pharma
officials who were there say, oh, wasn't us, it was Curtis Wright. But I mean, to me as a consumer,
right, the idea that the FDA is working so closely with a drug company that literally you don't know
where one ends and the other begins. And there's a line that ends up in the package insert claiming
that this drug is safer than other alternatives. And nobody can tell you who wrote it.
So is it 96 when MS when when OxyContin hits the hits the retail?
Early 96. Yeah. So how long does it take before the unintended consequences?
Because there's really two unintended consequences here, I guess. The first is people who probably
would be better served with another form of pain control or instead using this drug. That would be
one unintended consequence. That's one that Purdue would not be against because that's simply more
market share. And then there's the unintended consequence that everyone, including Purdue,
would presumably not want, which is you start to kill your customers. You know, sort of the tobacco
company problem, right? Like to have an addictive product with no termination of use,
is wonderful if you just could figure out a way to keep the customer alive. So
what are the canaries in the coal mine with respect to these problems and how are they handled?
So, I mean, I think in some ways it's probably
useful to start with what the official story was,
which is that the drugs released in early 96. And according to sworn testimony by
several senior executives at the company and by Richard Sackler, they had no inkling that there
was any kind of a major problem for four years. There were four blissful years where they got
lots of letters from pain patients saying, you know, you've given me my life back. And there was
no real sense at all that there was any kind of a problem. And it's only in early 2000,
when the United States attorney for the state of Maine writes a letter to thousands of physicians
saying this drug OxyContin is really dangerous, actually. It's killing people. People are
overdosing. We've got a real problem here and there's a crime problem associated with it.
And a little bit after this time, the chief medical officer, Paul Goldenheim, the chief medical
officer of Purdue Pharma is brought in front of Congress, right? And he's asked questions about
this. What does he say? Same thing. He says we had no inkling that there was any kind of big problem
until this hinge point, which is when this U.S. attorney writes this letter in 2000. So,
and interestingly, the other thing they say is that they say, oh, we read about it in the press.
They say we read about these problems in the press. And for me as a journalist, this was funny
because I've written about a lot of companies doing bad things and
reporters like to take credit where they can get it. But generally speaking of a company is doing
a bad thing, they don't find out about it because they read about it in your article. They usually
know a long time before the rest of the world does. So there was something about their explanation
that always seemed just on its face seemed a little fishy to me. When I dug into it and got a bunch of
documentation, what I learned is that it was it was a lie. I mean, they, you know, they knew really
early on. How bold a lie was that? Let's use Goldenheim as a specific example. So in 2000,
he's giving sworn testimony that we no clue this was going on. What do his emails from the late 1990s
suggest? That they did. I mean, it's not just, you know, you name it. There's all kinds of back and
forth about these drugs. There's another sort of associated lie that they told, which is that there
had never been a problem with MS content, which also is a lie, a lie that was told under oath,
when in fact, there's all kinds of back and forth about that. But you've got very, very senior
people, including Goldenheim, emailing about the fact that there's an abuse problem. Pharmacies are
getting robbed. You know, there's the kind of people talking about the street value of the drug.
There was a kind of media advisory group that was brought in to do interviews with these
senior officials. There are literally emails in which some of these senior officials who later
claimed that, you know, nothing was said will be emailing about it. And then they'll say,
should we have all this chat on email? You know, it's maybe not a good idea for us to be having
these conversations on email. So you have a very clear awareness that there's a problem. And if
you back up for a second, part of the reason OxyContin did what it did. Part of the reason I
would argue it changed the way in which these drugs are prescribed as a category of drugs
is that they had one of the biggest marketing forces ever. And they sent out hundreds of
say something like 700 sales reps to fan out across the country, meeting with thousands and
thousands of physicians. And that was how they kind of got the message of OxyContin out there.
But those are the canaries in the coal mine, right? Like those are the sales rep who
goes into a local community. There's a story I tell in the book about a guy named Steve May,
who was a Purdue sales rep in Virginia and West Virginia. And he had a, it's 99. So this is like
before, according to Goldenheim, like they didn't know anything at this point. It's 99.
Steve May had this one doctor, the really big prescribers, they would call them whales,
you know, to use the vernacular of a Vegas casino for a big gambler. Because if you had a big
prescriber, that was great for your, for your bonus if you were a sales rep. So Steve May had
this whale and he went to call on her, which he would do from time to time. And she's upset
when he showed up and he asked her what the problem was. And she said she had a young relative,
a young girl who'd just died of an OxyContin overdose. So there you literally have an OxyContin
sales rep going out and meeting with a doctor who's a big prescriber and finding out that her
relative has died from an OxyContin overdose. And all those reps are writing these encounters up
in notes and sending them back to headquarters. So I think what I was able to substantiate in
the book at some length is that it's clear really early on there's a problem. I think, you know,
from as early as 97. So that's just a year after the drug is released. And word is coming back
into the company and those discussions are not just happening at low levels. They're happening
at high levels. I think what happens in 2000 is it just becomes impossible for them to deny it
anymore. Right. It's like at that point, the sort of head in the sand won't work as a strategy. So
then you need to pivot. You need to say, okay, there is a problem. Here's our spin on it.
And that spin, of course, became these are really bad people. Like, you know, we've created
a miracle breakthrough product that helps millions of people. But there are these derelicts who abuse
this product and are jeopardizing it for everybody else. We really need to ramp up
the enforcement of those people or we need to somehow just decide that they're bad. I mean,
what was proposed as the remediation for the problem? It was a bunch of things, all of which
were very much along the lines of what you're talking about. So the suggestion was, you know,
there's nothing intrinsically dangerous about the drug. I should say the level of denial here
is pretty impressive. But I mean, the Sacklers even today argue that instances of iatrogenic
addiction to OxyContin, where it's prescribed to you by a doctor for a legitimate condition and
you take it as instructed by the physician, are vanishingly rare. That's like a block that they
have where they can't really acknowledge even today. Now, do we know what that true number is?
So if we say there are, and I'm being a bit perhaps overly simplistic, but and so feel free
to make this more realistic. But if we say there are three buckets in which a patient came across
OxyContin, bucket one would be, and this excludes the cancer patient. So I want to take the end of
life cancer patient out of the equation for a moment. So you talk about patients who are not
terminally ill, who have become exposed to and or addicted to OxyContin. Entry path number one
is the individual who is recovering from surgery. They are by their actual doctor who is a legitimate
doctor given a prescription for a reasonable quantity of OxyContin that should get them through
the perioperative period. Path number two is the person who, and by the way, you can get to path
number two from path number one. So these are not independent paths, but path number two is
the sham doctor, the doc in the box who's prescribing this stuff from one state when
you're in another state, doing it online or running basically the revolving door clinic where you just
come in, you ask for what you want, you get a prescription, you go out the door provided you
fill it at a pharmacy a couple of hundred miles away. So, you know, they're a doctor only in legal
terms, but they're certainly not a physician in any reasonable sense of the word. And then path
number three is the illicit acquisition of OxyContin through a stolen channel. So in the much in the
same way you would buy any illegal drug, you're simply buying OxyContin. Do we have a sense of
the relative distribution of paths one, two, and three?
No. And I mean, I think it's very hard and in fact impossible to parse it out. And I also think it's
something that's fluctuated a lot over time, but you do get these little data points that I think
are illuminating. And these are honestly like two of the more shocking things I discovered in my
research, but it's hard because it's a little complex. And so sometimes I think from the cheap
seats, it's like hard to appreciate the gravity of this. So Purdue sells OxyContin, they release it in
96. Right away, people realize that that that content seal, you can override that just by
crushing the pills. So you can chew them, you can grind the pill, you can dissolve it in water after
you've grinded and shoot it if you want intravenously. There's actually a warning on the
models telling you not to crush the pills because if you do, you could get a potentially toxic dose
of oxycodone. So in a weird way that functions as a kind of inadvertent how-to. I think that's
significant for at least maybe for all three of the buckets you're talking about, because you get
people who are just kind of opportunistic drug users looking to get high. I certainly have
interviewed a lot of people who say that heroin was scary, you bought it on the street, you shoot
it with a needle, that they were looking to get high. It was like a party drug in high school,
OxyContin was, but that there was something reassuring about the fact that it had been
approved by the FDA, that it is, you know that even if you bought it from a dealer,
at some point this entered the stream of commerce. There was a doctor writing a prescription.
You also have people who are prescribed the drug by a doctor and it doesn't work for as long as
they think it will, or they find themselves just kind of in its grip, they want more, and some of
those people actually convert to the immediate release thing. What they find is they don't want
to wait and so they'll end up chewing the pills because it relieves their pain faster, you know,
is what they'll say. So you get different ways of getting there, but the pill can be crushed.
That's 96. In 2010, Purdue rolls out this reformulated version of OxyContin that they've
worked on for years. It's basically you kind of crush it. It's sort of, it's like a gummy bear,
you know, if you try and break it up, it just kind of goes chewy and gummy on you.
There's an interesting backstory there, questions about why it took so long to roll that out. There's
an interesting aspect of the timing, which is that the original patent on OxyContin were about
to run out. So it kind of just in the nick of time, they have this line extension basically in
the form of the reformulated drug. Well, it goes one better than that, doesn't it Patrick? Because
at the time they even basically declare that their old formulation is probably unsafe,
which is really a great dig at the competition, which is as we're about to roll this thing off
its patent life, we want to make sure that nobody else uses it either as we reignite a new patent
on a new drug, which is infinitely safer in the presence of our old dangerous drug. I mean,
again, that would be the skeptical view of things. Oh, I mean, and I think in this case,
the skeptical view is right on. And in fact, there are emails going back years and years and
years talking about how if they came up with a kind of abuse period, they would have to
kind of abuse proof, tamper proof formulation that would function as a line extension, that
that was the reason they were doing it primarily was to extend the patent life. But yeah, the kind
of the surpassing cynicism of the idea that having for at that point, 14 years said, oh,
it's perfectly safe. It's perfectly safe. It's perfectly safe. The original formulation,
they develop their new formulation, and then they turn around and say, but we wouldn't want to see
any generic versions of the original formulation, because in fact, it's not so safe after all,
is amazing. And it worked. And the FDA obliged. But so here's the statistic that really blows my
mind. 2010, the reformulated version is rolled out. And the old pills are, you know, they kind
of disappear from the shelves and the new ones take their place. And what I discovered was a
study, an internal study that found that in 2010, when this happened for the 80 milligram pills,
which is the biggest and most profitable pills on the market, also the most popular on the black
market, sales nationwide felt 25%. So I can't tell you proportionately who's in what bucket.
What I can tell you is that up to 2010, I think it's safe to intuit 25% of the sales of 80 milligram
OxyContin. We're going to people who were abusing those pills in, you know, in one way or another,
which is astonishing to me, because I mean, that's, that's like a non-trivial
part of the company's profits. So on the one hand, it's, you know, they don't want their patients,
their, their, their customers to die. On the other hand, there is a sense in which even as
they were decrying the black market, like the black market was helping to pay the bills at the company.
Yeah. And the thing that, the thing that I really wish we could have an insight into is
even if you take the most charitable view of things, which is that every person's first interaction
with OxyContin was through path one. That is to say you were legitimately prescribed this for
non-cancer pain by a legitimate caring, understanding physician. But then, you know,
a subset of the people left bucket one for bucket two or bucket three as their appetite for the drug
grew in the absence of an indication, right? That's versus how many people de novo show up in bucket
two and bucket three drug seeking. You know, the fact that we don't know that is, it makes this
very difficult and creates this moral ambiguity around it, which, you know, frankly is a bit of
a distraction from the real, you know, the culpability here. Oh, that's interesting. I mean,
I think it's, it's a very, I think the fact that we don't know it and that it's impossible to know,
combined with the fact that when you look at, you know, this is a favorite of Purdue and the
Sacklers, but like when you look at the toxicity reports on people who die, people who overdose,
it's often not just OxyContin in the bloodstream, right? It's often mixed with other things.
There's this whole kind of exercise of parsing, like moral and legal parsing that they do,
which, you know, I have to say for me, just as a, as someone who's trying to live a righteous life,
it's always amazing to me because I always just think, I can't imagine how do you get there? Like,
how do you, how do you get there? At a certain point, so many people have died from your product.
It's this kind of incredible symphony of rationalization that happens. But on your,
on your, on your point about, you know, everybody, the idea that, you know, ideally you'd have a
situation which everybody sort of enters through bucket one. Let me give you the other statistic,
which is that we'll get to this, but Purdue Pharma is now in bankruptcy. And in the context of the
bankruptcy, there are many, many, many creditors who have a claim that they'd like to exert against
what's left of the company. And one of them is UnitedHealth. And UnitedHealth had this fascinating
filing where they were, they were, you know, talking about the idea that they should have a
piece of the pie, such as it is, and we'll leave aside for a second, whether a big insurer should,
you know, should be there in line along with all these people whose lives have been ruined by the
drug. What was interesting is that they said they ran a study. And I don't remember how many years
it was, but it was, it was over the course of something like seven or eight years. They looked
at people who had UnitedHealth plans and who were prescribed OxyContin or another Purdue opioid
and subsequently diagnosed with an opioid use disorder. So I think that would actually be a
kind of a smaller subset because you, you literally have a diagnosis of an OUD. And they said that,
so for that subset, prescription from a doctor, subsequent diagnosis, just UnitedHealth over seven
or eight years, they said the number was in the hundreds of thousands. And did they say, I mean,
I'm sure it would be in the study, but what percentage of that, what percentage of people
was that who were initially given a prescription? Was that 10%, 20%, 50%? Oh, that I don't know.
That's interesting. I don't know. It probably was in the study, but it's not, it hasn't been,
it was not revealed in the filing to the bankruptcy court.
That would be interesting because that would actually shed great light on this issue.
It would. I mean, I think to me, the thing that's interesting is that it remains a talking point
certainly for the Sacklers and their legal counsel that it's virtually impossible if you're a
paying patient and you're prescribed to drive by a doctor and you take it as directed to become
addicted to put that side by side with this hundreds of thousands number is extraordinary.
Even if you build in a discount where you say, okay, well, some of those people probably did,
you know, some of those were fraudulent docs or fraudulent patients or what have you,
you still end up with a really huge number of people who have become hooked on the drug
in an iatrogenic context. Yeah. So, you know, I have a real personal history with this,
which I'm sure you'll appreciate. I wasn't sure I was going to tell you this story,
but I think it's appropriate here. So in some ways I feel very lucky to be sitting here
having a discussion right now as opposed to being dead. A little over 20 years ago when I was in my
last year of medical school, I had a really bad back injury. Kind of, you know, sort of hurt it
kind of acutely and for two and a half weeks just ignored it. But the pain grew more and more
debilitating. I remember I was doing a rotation, you know, one of my rotations and I couldn't even
sleep. I had to get, you know, the residents to inject tort all into my thighs just to allow me
to have enough, you know, of an inkling to be able to sleep for a while. So finally, at some
point I just agreed to go get an MRI and look and sure enough, there was a really bad herniation
in my lower back and about a five centimeter fragment of disc had broken off on the left side
and it floated down the canal and it was sitting on the S1 nerve root, which is what was causing this
almost comical amount of pain. I say comical now because it's hard to even describe.
There's nothing funny about it. So I underwent surgery the next day,
but surgery didn't go well for a number of reasons. But the surgeon operated on the wrong side.
So I woke up from the surgery in terrible pain, but also with a new complication on the other side.
This resulted in a number of follow-up procedures initially aimed at correcting the first problem.
But before I knew it, you know, even once this, the structural problem had been fixed,
the pain was so bad that I finally relented and agreed to take pain medicine.
I had been horribly petrified of taking anything beyond NSAIDs.
So what was the first drug? This is the year 2000. So what's the first prescription I get?
It's for 20 milligrams of OxyContin to be taken, I believe twice a day. I think you take 20 in the
morning and 20 in the afternoon or evening or something like that. But you can probably
imagine where this story is going, Patrick. How much OxyContin do you think I was taking within
four months? Tell me. Almost 400 milligrams a day. Unreal. So again, maybe for the listener who
doesn't know what that means in context, that would be enough to kill an entire family of drug naive
people. Right. That, you know, 400 milligrams would kill mom, dad, Susie, Bobby, Sally. They'd
just stop breathing. So it didn't take long for me to go from 40 milligrams a day to 400 milligrams a
day. And there are a couple of things about this that are interesting. The first is that was all
prescribed by a legitimate doctor who was not at all an expert in pain management. This was a
surgeon who had already demonstrated gross incompetence, not operating on the right side.
No one was monitoring how much of this drug I needed. The dose just kept going up and up and up.
I was very fortunate at the time to be dating an anesthesiology resident. So she was about three
or four years older than me, actually probably in her last year of anesthesia. And she herself was
actually interested in pain management. So she would go on to do a fellowship in pain management.
And, you know, she was a bit troubled by how much of this drug that I was on.
And that sort of got me thinking, like, how the hell did I get here? Because it happened so quick.
Right. It was, you know, one minute you're like, I never, ever, ever want to take one of these drugs.
And then the next minute you're basically in a day, you're in a constant haze. You're, you know,
there was no moment that I wasn't high. The turning point for me came when I realized
that I couldn't differentiate between the pain relief and the high. In other words,
I realized I was probably taking the drug to avoid the psychological pain, which at the time,
I was pretty convinced I'd never walk again. This was a one year recovery process. But the first
three months I couldn't walk. So that basically shattered all of my dreams. I was no longer going
to be able to be a surgeon, I believed, let alone be an active, healthy person that I'd been all my
life. And so I was actually taking this drug just as much to blunt that grief as I was taking it to
blunt the pain. And finally, in the fall of that year, I just decided this is not, I don't want to
do this anymore. I never imagined I would overdose. That's the other thing, by the way,
it never even crossed my mind that I could get to a point where I would stop breathing.
But I just thought, no, I can't do this anymore. So I said to my girlfriend, I said, I'm going to
stop this cold turkey. And she said, you absolutely can't do that. The withdrawal from this will kill
you just as much as this drug will kill you. You need to be on nortriptyline, morphine. I mean,
she rattled off all the drugs I would need to take to taper off. But I was a stubborn kid and
I just stopped cold turkey. And the next three weeks of my life would be about the most miserable
three weeks of my existence. I certainly hope I don't have another three weeks somewhere down my
life that will be that bad. But here's the thing that is interesting. I'm not telling this story to
for a moment suggest any superiority, like look at me, I was able to come off this drug.
What my point is that what I've learned about addiction since then would suggest that I'm
simply biologically lucky. In other words, I truly believe that the neurotransmitters in my brain
are not wired the way that someone who in that exact situation would have become a lifelong addict.
So that's why I say I'm very lucky. I'm not lucky because I have willpower. I'm lucky because that
chemical didn't put a hook in me the way it would in others. So in other words, I had become
physiologically dependent on it. And that's why I went through withdrawal just as anybody would.
But I'm really lucky that I managed to escape this drug. And it's interesting, I was still
deathly afraid of the drug after the fact. And only seven years later, when I had a really,
really bad dental issue, would I ever touch another Percocet in my life, which of course is
a fraction of the drug. Right. And I remember being really worried like what's going to happen?
Is this going to escalate into massive use? And fortunately, it didn't, you know, I needed
Percocet for like a week until I had a tooth extracted. And then I just stopped it and that
was fine. But, you know, it paradoxically gave me more empathy than self-righteousness over the
people who became addicted. I don't know why. That's not obvious why that would be the case.
But I think I just sort of believed that there are some of us who don't get addicted to these
things even when exposed, but there are enough people who do. And I don't know what that number
is. Right. And to your point, I don't know that we can ever know that number. But I agree with you
that that doesn't remove the moral obligation of the people that were involved in exposing people
like me and people much less fortunate than me. Yeah. I mean, I would imagine that part of the
reason that it gave you a kind of, you know, a sense of compassion for those whose experience has
turned out much worse is that it does sound as though you encountered the,
and I've talked to so many people whose lives have been upended by this drug and other opioids.
And it's often like there's a kind of undertow, right? There's just this sense that
you're suddenly in the grip of something and, you know, you managed to get out of the grip,
but it sounds like even you were in terms of the physiological dependence and the idea that you were
titrating up so fast. That upward speed was unbelievable, Patrick. I mean, unbelievable
how quickly tolerance developed. And by the way, it's total bullshit to say you don't get high from
a time release drug. I mean, maybe I don't know what it's like to take heroin. So I'm sure compared
to heroin, it's blunt, but there is an absolute blast off high that came from those mega doses
of that drug. Yeah. What's so intriguing to me though about your story is actually the doctor,
right? The idea that you have a surgeon who writes you the prescription. And, you know, part of what's
so fascinating is that the drug companies, Purdue and the other companies, argued from the beginning
that doctors don't know enough about pain management. They haven't gotten the training.
And there was some truth to that, but the weirdness of it is they then rush into the vacuum and they
say, we'll provide that training. We'll do that education. And the catchphrase for OxyContin early
on was that it's the drug to start with and to stay with. And so, you know, the first part of
that, right, is it's like, this isn't some nuclear solution you keep on the top shelf where you would
try other courses of therapy and only when those fail do you resort to it. It's the first thing you
should administer. And then it's the one to stay with, meaning you can just keep taking it, you
know, for chronic pain conditions you're in, you're out, even if you have to keep titrating up. And
it was a core belief at the company. Richard Sackler felt very strongly about this, that there
was no, you know, what was what he described as no ceiling effect with OxyContin. That in fact,
you could just keep taking greater and greater doses, which you would need to as your system
accompanies itself to it. And then you have the pharmaceutical reps who are meeting with doctors
like your surgeon and are heavily incentivized to get those docs to titrate up. That's always
the message because, you know, the profits and in fact, even the bonuses for the pharma reps
were all based on the volume of the drug that's sold and prescribed. So it's just funny because
hearing your anecdote from your side, what I see on the other side is this sort of perfect storm
of scenarios where, you know, when you're thinking about like, do I go cold turkey? Do I
taper off? Should I be taking morphine? You're having this conversation with your girlfriend
because the guy who prescribed you the drug probably doesn't know how to explain to people
how to get them off. I mean, you have this kind of crazy situation in which you have a generation
of doctors who learn how to how to like on-ramp their patients with these drugs and never learn
how to off-ramp them and actually kind of don't necessarily have any interest or inclination.
And if you talk to people who've had these experiences, they'll say, I went back to the
surgeon who wrote me the original script and I said, hey, listen, you know, I'm having problems
here. And they say, whoa, whoa, whoa, I'm not an addiction specialist. So when you look at all
those circumstances and you kind of extrapolate from that story you just told, it's not surprising
to me to think that there are many, many, many people who, you know, who had a similar situation
and ended up in very dire straits. Yeah. And I think you, you, you, you made me think of
something else, which I should have mentioned earlier, which is there's another reason I was
very, very fortunate was to have a girlfriend at the time who is not just an anesthesiologist,
but someone who's a year away from doing a pain fellowship. She actually got me in to see a pain
expert at Stanford, who I think really is the guy that saved me because remember,
it's one thing to sort of quit this drug cold Turkey, but I still had pain.
You know, it didn't, it's not like, you know, getting off the drug was one problem,
but addressing the pain was another. And I think only because of this other guy,
whose name was Sean Mackey, I don't even know if he's still at Stanford, but, you know, he was able
to treat me, I think appropriately, right? So that meant doing a lot of injections to begin and sort
of cool things off that had flared up using a drug called Neurontin, which is not addictive,
incredibly benign. It is sedating. So that's a drawback to deal with the neuropathic pain
and then using very strong NSAIDs. So at the time Vioxx was a drug that basically saved me. And,
you know, that allowed me to break the cycle of pain and do enough PT such that a year from when
that whole thing began, I was actually in my surgical residency and free of all pain medication,
meaning free of the Neurontin and free of the Vioxx. So, you know, that part of the story also
speaks to the incredible fortune that I had that many people don't have. And maybe had I not had it,
there still would be a different ending, right? It still might've been that, well,
after three months of going cold Turkey, I had to go back because there was no alternative.
And it's funny, I'll take better. When I was in my residency, I was still amazed at how ignorant
we were as surgical residents of pain management. I mean, completely ignorant. There was absolutely
no teaching of this subject matter. Something that I learned that was very simple was studies
had demonstrated that before you do an incision on a patient, if you inject Markane, which is a long
acting sodium channel blocker, like a, you know, like the type of, you know, like a Novocaine type
thing that the dentist would put in your teeth. So you have Lidocaine, which is short acting,
Markane, which is long acting. If you inject the incision site with Markane before you cut,
wait a moment, you then make the incision and then immediately following surgery, you put the patient
on a pretty aggressive dose of NSAIDs. Many patients can actually avoid narcotics postoperatively
for the incisional pain, which is the dominant source of pain. And I remember thinking,
why aren't we doing this with every patient? And I got into an argument with one of the attendings
because I was about to do an operation and, you know, I went to do this and he said, come on,
come on, come on. That's going to take five minutes. You've got to, you know, put that in and
then we have to sit here and wait five minutes with our dicks in our hands while it sets in
before you cut. No, no, no, no. We don't have the time for that. I remember thinking, really?
We don't have five minutes? You know, it was shocking. Yeah.
Yeah. But listen, I mean, I think in a weird way,
and I say I'm not a doctor, right? I say this, I say this coming from the outside,
but having done a little bit of a kind of anthropological bushwhack through this world
over the last few years, you go back to what we were talking about earlier,
where you have the Sackler brothers in the 1940s and 50s saying, wouldn't it be beautiful
if someday there was just a pill you could take for everything? And particularly Arthur Sackler
kind of trying to sort of intermingle medicine and commerce in ways that I think ended up being
more profound than anybody could have probably recognized at the time. From the outside, I think
that one of the ingredients that gives you the opioid crisis is actually that idea of like,
we want to waste five minutes. You know, we need to get our patients in and out. Time is money.
And there was a, you know, I've interviewed, I've interviewed doctors who talk about the,
how they felt duped. How when the produce sales reps started flogging OxyContin,
you know, if you're a doctor, you encounter patients who are in pain, you want to relieve
that pain. You know, it's often it's kind of in some ways inherent to why you chose to do this
in your life, right? You want to, you want to bring relief to people who are suffering.
And suddenly there's this medical innovation, which you're told is like a panacea. It can
relieve that pain and has virtually no side effects and people can take it forever. And
there's no dosage ceiling. And so, you know, I've talked to people who've said just earnestly,
that was a siren song I was all too ready to listen to, because it filled a need in my,
you know, in my kind of therapeutic arsenal. And of course, it ended up being more complicated.
But I also think that when you think about the way in which American medicine is structured,
the idea that you have a patient who's in pain and you say, I'm going to write your prescription for
20 milligrams of OxyContin, be on your way. I never have to see you again. I'm not really going to
give any thought to how this is working out for you two weeks from now or two months from now or
two years from now. I think that the that notion that, you know, that five minutes is money,
right? Five minutes is, you know, that five minutes is five minutes you're not spending
with the next patient. It's a longer line in the waiting room. I think those kinds of structural
considerations were part of what allowed Purdue and other opioid makers to kind of snow the medical
establishment as effectively as they did. Where if you look at the prescribing levels for these
drugs, with the introduction of OxyContin, they just suddenly start climbing in this really
dramatic way. And you would think that there would have been more skepticism that it would
have been slower growth. But I do think there was a sense in which it sort of it filled a number of
needs. Right. And that was what allowed it to take off the way it did. Well, it also seemed to become
very politically correct in the sense that they somehow managed to infiltrate the AMA. I mean,
one of the other memories I have from, you know, the early days of residency was how all of a sudden
a new vital sign emerged. So vital signs are by definition objective. So they are things that can
be measured for which there is no ambiguity, temperature, pulse, respiratory rate, blood
pressure. But then a fifth vital sign got introduced, which was pain, a subjective measurement on a scale
of one to 10. And there were laminated posters on every corner of the hospital. Don't forget the
fifth vital sign. Don't forget the fifth vital sign. What is the fifth vital sign? What is your
patient's pain? I mean, it was, you know, and this really came from the medical community. This was
some this was a form of self policing. So how involved was Purdue in driving that agenda?
I mean, I want to be careful about how I put this.
Very would be the short answer. But I think you have this tricky thing. It's a little bit like
when I was talking about Curtis Wright and the FDA and how there's a kind of soft corruption
that happens, which is, you know, it's not as glaring as the kind of caricature is corruption
that you would think of. I think there's a similar thing here where you have the American
Medical Association, you have all kinds of groups, you know, groups of doctors, groups representing
patients, patients rights, you know, kind of pain advocacy groups. And and then you have industry
underwriting a lot of this stuff. And there's just quite a good piece in Mother Jones just
recently about the AMA and, you know, the Richard Sackler was on one of these boards, and you have
a lot of money going to sponsor education. Yeah, well, that that's I just read that Mother Jones
piece. And I couldn't believe that the AMA both as an organization and its foundation separately
are receiving money from the Sacklers. Yeah, yeah. And then and then often what happens,
right, is that you get these things where it's there's like an educational pamphlet that they
end up distributing. There's a kind of laundering that happens, a sort of institutional laundering,
right, where where industry comes up with these educational brochures or they sponsor research or
what have you. I mean, the example that I love from from that story, the Mother Jones story was
that there was one kind of handy guide to pain and the fifth vital sign and the idea of how do
you talk to a child about the pain they're feeling. And there was there was a kind of an admonition to
the doctors that you remember, you know, you got to tell the child that no pain is not an acceptable
answer. You know, there's a continuum, but but the end of the continuum where there's no pain,
you know, that's that's that's not not not an option. The yeah, I think it's tricky because I
just think that a lot of the time it's not necessarily that I think it's more a coincidence
of interests in which you have people who earnestly believe these things and then are
underwritten by industry. And that kind of turbo charges the arguments they're making
more than it is a situation of docs being paid off to tell what they know to be lies, right.
And I think there was a kind of like when you when you talk about the idea of the fifth vital
sign, even just that phrase, on the one hand, I think that there was some truth to the critique
that that there hadn't been enough education and pain management and enough consideration given to
how you relieve patients pain. I think as a critique that had some truth to it. On the other
hand, when you say the fifth vital sign, like to me, that sounds more than anything like a great
marketing slogan. I don't know who dreamed that up. But it sounds like something that an
advertiser would come up with, right? It's catchy, it's kind of pithy. And of course,
it's totally subjective. There was a study I couldn't give you the citation, but I remember
reading this reading about this great study, where it was like the scale of one to 10 thing,
right? And they found that it's not just that it varies that you may have, you know, what,
what might be a seven for you could be a nine for me. But that it actually varies regionally,
where they, you know, they found that like people in Northern Europe,
you'd exert some sort of standard amount of pain, and they would say, you know, oh, that's a four,
and then people in Southern Europe, you'd exert the same amount of pain, and they would say,
it's a 10, it's a 10. But you know that you actually get these kind of cultural regional
differences in terms of people's pain threshold. So the it's hard, because I do think it's a
legitimate thing that people should be looking at and inquiring about, but at the same time,
it's totally subjective. And I think that again, and again, you see just the money pollute everything.
You know, you mentioned earlier that Curtis Wright effectively,
whether, you know, in a direct quid pro quo, or more of just a confluence of interests,
not only basically approves this drug single handedly for the FDA, but then ultimately winds
up working for this entity. But, you know, the other story in this one that really blew my mind
was that of Lyndon Barber, the DEA, a guy who on the one hand is seems by all accounts to be one
of the most credible voices within the DEA to standing up to the, you know, unmanaged distribution
of these drugs, and then kind of doesn't about face and becomes one of the most powerful lobbying
entities for the very companies. I believe Cardinal was one of his largest clients,
Cardinal McKesson being two of the largest distributors. Kind of hard to believe,
but at the same time, I guess you, you know, going through the, what you said earlier, it's like,
look, how long can you work for nothing as a government employee? Right. And at some point,
he has a choice, which is he's going to go make a living harnessing his existing skills, but it
just doesn't feel right. You know, I don't know. I don't know how else to put it. It just doesn't,
just doesn't sit well with me. Yeah. You know, I, it's funny. I, it's, it's very, you know,
I don't want to sound like a scold or preachy or somebody who's holier than thou or like a
boy scout. Cause cause I'm not by any stretch, but the, but it has been one of the more dispiriting
things working on this project where, you know, a lot of the time in the past I've written about
crime a fair amount and you, and you, it's just kind of baked in that you're writing about a bad
person doing a bad thing and they kind of know they're bad usually. And there's a sort of moral
clarity there. What was so fascinating to me about this story is that, you know, I think the
Sacklers are, are, are kind of are bad actors. I think they, they did really bad things. And
they're the focus of the story, but then around them are all of these facilitators and it's, it's
former prosecutors who go and work as private defense attorneys for the family or for the
company. It's former DEA officials who go and work as lobbyists for the industry. It's former FDA
officials who go and work at the company. It's, you know, folks at McKinsey, it's this whole kind
of amazing entrenched machine of people who I think in many instances don't think of themselves
as the bad guys. And in some cases, society doesn't think of them as the bad guys, right? You know,
one of the characters in my book is Mary Jo White, this, you know, former U.S. attorney for
the Southern District of New York, former, she was Obama's head of the SEC. She's a hero to lawyers,
many, you know, all over the place of a woman who kind of broke the glass ceiling. And she's
represented Purdue and the Sacklers for years and is totally a handmaiden to them. So it's a thing
that I've kind of wrestled with personally. I'm a lawyer by training. And I know that there is a
sort of it's very fundamental to the ethos of the profession that, you know, the lawyer isn't the
client and that we shouldn't necessarily kind of transpose the moral stink of the client onto
the lawyer. But it's hard for me when, you know, you tell the Linda Barber story,
there's a hundred people like that in the book who play that kind of role. And again and again
and again, you get these people who are supposed to be the cops, basically, they're supposed to be
law and order and they get co-opted by the money. And it's really discouraging. And sometimes I
don't get it because the money isn't even that much. And when you look at Chris Dodd and Marsha
Blackburn and Tom Marino and Orrin Hatch, I mean, it's just hard for me to look at these people and
think of them as reasonable or respectable truthfully. You know, when I look at their involvement in
the bills that they sponsored and the positions that they took in all of this. And when you look
at the dollars that they received from the. They're bought so cheaply. Yeah. That's exactly
the point, Patrick. You know, I expected that it would have taken tens of millions to have
bought those people. They were bought for hundreds of thousands of dollars. U.S. senators for sale
for hundreds of thousands of dollars. I don't understand it. I think, yeah, I mean, I think so.
So I think the thing is, it's some of it is the is the money donations and what have you. But I
think there's this other thing that is more about the revolving door and the kind of this insidious
thing where the it's the lobbyists and the lobbyists are often people they know. Right. And
it's a kind of you know, you see this with the way in which Purdue and the SACRIS would use
lawyers like Mary Jo White is a good example, or they hired Rudy Giuliani for years was kind of
their hatchet man. And it's like if you were a federal prosecutor and you're investigating me,
the real move is to not to sort of fight it out with you on the merits in court the way most
people would. It's for me to go to your boss, but not for me personally to go to your boss, for me to
find somebody who your boss knows and respects. And that's the person I buy off. And I send them
to go and kind of make the overture. And so I think when you look at these people, it's not just that
they're again, it's the sort of soft corruption thing where some of it is the it's not like
campaign contributions. It's that you're you know, it's like the it's the you know, it's that scene
in the godfather where the where the guy is supposed to testify in court. And they sent they
get the old guy from Sicily to come and just sit in the courtroom and it happens to be his uncle or
whatever. And he sees the guy in the courtroom and he he suddenly sort of loses all his moral
conviction and decides he's not going to testify. It's sort of that. It's it's like being really
smart and strategic about who's the right messenger? Who would we send to make the case to
Chris Dodd, you know, about why he shouldn't come after us or why he should help us in this or that.
And man, they're really good, really, really good at that. And it's interesting at how,
if I want to use the word, you might not use the word, but if I want to use the word corruption,
how bipartisan the corruption was. Totally. What was the bill? H.R. 4709.
This is the sleeper bill, right? It's like this three page nothing burger that basically opened
the pipelines to move these drugs and put the DA's hands behind its back. I mean, again,
it's a little detail, but my God, it's amazing how unopposed that bill went.
Yeah, but I mean, this is absolutely. But but but some of that, I think, is the fact that
nobody's really reading the bill. The bill was carefully designed to look like it was sort of
doing the opposite of what it was doing. Right. It's like we're going to fight the opioid crisis.
You know, Obama signed it and who knows how closely he looked at it. I think that there's a
there's enough business that goes on in Washington. And I think particularly when it comes to law
making, you know, you have these members of the House and senators who are they spend all their
time raising money. They if you can make what you're doing look like business as usual,
you can pull it off. It's it's super dispiriting. But again, I mean, listen,
you know, the painkiller, the opioid painkiller industry spends, I think the statistic is like
seven or eight times what the gun lobby spends on lobbying in Washington. Right. So so just imagine
the kind of impact that you can have on the on the legislative picture. And then you see this with,
you know, with a company like Purdue, you have this long period of time where all these states
are trying to respond at a state level to the opioid crisis. And they're there, you know,
they're trying to introduce new legislation to shut down pill mills or, you know, go after bad
docs and what have you. And you have these legislative initiatives at a state level that
gets set up and Purdue finds the right state lobbyists to go to the state capital and help
neuter those bills as best as best they can. And we're very successful at doing that. I mean,
it is a when you have a drug that's generated $35 billion in revenue,
the amount of influence you can buy is just awesome.
So what what happened? What was the first sort of shot across the bow 2007?
It's a little bit of a slap on the wrist. What what led to that?
You had a couple of investigators at a small federal prosecutor's office in the Western
District of Virginia, who their community had been upended by OxyContin specifically. They're
just they started realizing, you know, we're getting all these pharmacy thefts and crime
is going up and you get people ODing. And they started investigating. And and to them,
it was this kind of weird thing where they felt like they felt like a hurricane had just like hit
their town. And they wanted where it came from, and came from Connecticut. So they started
investigating. And they they did this really amazing investigation. They spent five years
investigating Purdue, they subpoenaed millions of documents, they did, you know, huge amounts of
grand jury testimony and wanted to charge three senior executives at the company with felonies.
The idea being that these guys were, you know, we're not going to go to jail. Faced with jail
time, they would flip on the Sacklers. One of those federal prosecutors has said this on the
record. And there's another one who's confirmed for me that the plan was actually to target the
Sacklers if they could flip these guys. And what ended up happening was that the
the company sent Rudy Giuliani and Mary Jo White to kind of go over the heads of those federal
prosecutors to the George W. Bush Justice Department in Washington and say, you can't go
after these guys for felonies. We need to take felonies off the table, take jail time off the
table. And so they got overruled by their own bosses. This was Alice Fisher and Paul McNulty.
This was Alice Fisher and Paul McNulty. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. And which is funny too,
because it's again, there's it's a little bit like that line in the in the package insert where
in 2021, I talked to Alice Fisher and Paul McNulty and said, who made that decision to tell these
prosecutors in the Western District of Virginia? They're each pointing at each other. They're
pointing at each other. Nobody would own it. You would think, you know, all these years on,
it's a pretty consequential decision. You would think that somebody might take responsibility
for it. But what that meant is that because they couldn't charge these guys with felonies,
the guys weren't going to flip. They just they charged, they pled to misdemeanors. So they
couldn't go after the Sacklers. The company paid a six hundred million dollar fine and pled guilty
to felony charges of misbranding. And then it was pretty much business as usual. I mean, they didn't
they did not slow down their marketing a job. So what changed in the last couple of years,
what's led to the bankruptcy and perhaps more importantly, where do we stand on this? What
is it called? This nonconsensual third party third party release? Yes, this this seems to be a very
important granting on the part of a one white Plains bankruptcy judge. Yeah, Robert Drane.
So so 2007, the company pleads guilty. And the official line after that was, oh, you know, we
we kind of cleaned up our act. We had a few bad apples, but everything's OK now. But they didn't
really change a whole lot. And really, all the senior folks, you know, but there were three guys
who pled guilty to misdemeanors had to leave. They couldn't keep working at the company. But other
than that, all the senior folks who were involved in this stuff stayed on. Heads did not roll.
And Purdue kind of kept doing what it was doing. And they were doing a lot of work. And they
um, in 2020, the company pled guilty to a new set of federal criminal charges. And the the conduct
that it pled to dated back 10 years. So if you imagine, right, like the company pleads guilty in
2007. And then in theory, there's like a couple of years of good behavior. But then starting in about
2010, they were back to committing crimes and kept at it through 2020 when they pled guilty again.
And in between those two guilty pleas, what happens is that you get all these lawsuits. So some of
these are private class action lawsuits, lawsuits brought by hospitals, school districts,
cities, states, eventually every state in the union pretty much is suing Purdue over its role
in the opioid crisis. And what's happening in parallel to that, which we didn't know about
until fairly recently, is that the Sackler starting in 2007, after that guilty plea, they
start quietly taking money out of the company. So they're just sort of siphoning money out 100
million here, 100 million there. Over the course of about a decade, they take more than $10 billion
out of the company. And then in 2018, 2019, 2019, you have thousands of lawsuits against the company,
companies kind of on the ropes. And the family kicks the company into bankruptcy, they say the
company doesn't have any money anymore. Which is only the case because they took $10 billion out of
it. But they say the company's bankrupt now. So all those lawsuits against the company have to be
suspended. And they end up in this bankruptcy court in White Plains, New York. Because this is
the way bankruptcy law works, they got to pick their judge, you can decide where you want to
declare bankruptcy, corporate bankruptcy. So they picked this judge who they thought would be
sympathetic. And where it gets really interesting is that by this point, roughly half of the states
were not just suing the company, they were suing individual members of the family who had sat on
the company's board. And there's a move by the company and the family to say, okay, so you
suspended all these lawsuits against the company, because it's in bankruptcy. But we want you to
spend the lawsuits against the family too, even though they haven't declared bankruptcy.
And the judge did that temporarily. Which is pretty controversial. There are states in which
you're not able to do that. You're not able to say to like the attorneys general of
half of the states, no, you cannot bring your lawsuit. A federal bankruptcy judge in New York
says to the state AG of Idaho, like, no, you cannot bring your state based claim. It's pretty
exotic, but he did. And where we are now is we're sort of in the end game, where the Sacklers have
made this bid, which is they want him to make that grant permanent, where he would permanently
immunize them from any litigation. So the phrase for this, and it's a mouthful, is non-consensual
third party releases. And this is happening in real time. Like, as you and I are talking,
there's a bankruptcy trial going on with testimony. But I think everybody knows how it's going to end.
Why are we so pessimistic? Why are we pretty convinced that the ruling is going to hold up?
Because the judge has kind of telegraphed where he's going with it. And because
there are some states that continue to fight, but they effectively don't have the votes. So
basically what you have is a situation in which the Sacklers have made a proposal to,
in one fell swoop, deal with all this litigation kind of once and for all. And they're doing it in
the context of this bankruptcy proceeding, where they say, we will pay $4.5 billion of our money
to remediate the opioid crisis. We'll pay it out over nine years. And we'll make no admission of
wrongdoing. We'll give up our interest in Purdue. And we'll be granted one of these non-consensual
third party releases where basically this judge gets to kind of wave his wand and say,
nobody can ever sue you again. No state prosecutor, no private plaintiff. Nobody can
sue you ever again over anything having to do with OxyContin or the opioid crisis.
And I think there are a lot of states that are desperate and fighting, you know, dealing with
the kind of the trillions of dollars in public costs that this crisis has generated. They're
reeling. They see $4.5 billion and they think, I could use one 50th of that, you know. So they're
inclined to take the deal, even if they don't like it. You know, it's an interesting one, because I
think a lot of people look at it and they feel like this wouldn't be justice.
To put that $4.5 billion number in perspective, the SACRA is still having an $11 billion fortune
and they're going to pay it out, pay out the 4.5 over nine years. And it's actually not linearly
weighted. The majority of that payment comes at the end of time. So in theory, they're technically
going to come out ahead if they reasonably invest well. Yeah. I mean, I, you know, I did some, I had
some conversations with people who advise high network families and invest their fortunes in the,
you know, I think conservatively between interests and a very conservative portfolio,
they can probably expect a, you know, a 5% return on that $11 billion fortune. And if that's the
case, they never have to touch their principal. Yeah. I mean, this will not, again, in absolute
terms, it's a lot of money, but it's, I don't think commensurate to the damage. And I think
ultimately it'll be a pretty good deal for the SACRA's, but I think that's how it's going to shake
out. Now, do you think that this accomplishes anything else? So no amount of money is going
to bring back a loved one. You know, I have several patients whose lives have been directly
impacted by this, whose children have overdosed. So kids that became addicted to prescription
pain pills and, you know, in one situation, one of the kids was clean for a number of
months, if not a year, was at a party. Someone suggested he tried a pill. It turned out to be
laced with fentanyl. And you know how that story ends tragically. So no amount of money
is going to fix that. And so whether the SACRA's have to give four and a half billion or forfeit
every dollar they've ever made and will make in perpetuity that never brings back a life.
So really it's about two things, isn't it? It's sort of about how much can be fixed today with
money, because maybe some things can be fixed with money. Some things can't. I guess three things
is justice being served. And the third thing would be, is this creating a deterrent
for another entity in the future to be a little more careful with what they do? So
let's talk about the latter. Do you think that this will create a sufficient enough deterrent?
And not just this. I mean, if you look at what was that other company, Insys or something like that?
Yeah. Well, Insys was different because people went to jail.
Yeah. So when you look at the totality of these things, do you think that at least for their
foreseeable future, the legal slash illicit drug market is kind of on notice?
I do and I don't. I mean, I think that the... Look, in some ways this kind of, this fits into a
larger trend that we've seen happening over the last 10 or 15 years, sort of since the days of
Enron and WorldCom, which is that there's a pronounced disinclination, this is across
political parties, to bring criminal charges and jail time into the equation when it comes to
corporate executives acting within their role, even if the conduct is criminal. So you have this kind
of bizarre thing with Purdue Pharma, where when the company pled guilty for a second time in 2020,
there were no individual executives even named. So I say in the book, it's like it's a driverless
car. I mean, how is it that the company could commit federal crimes if there's no individuals
who can be identified as having committed crimes? It doesn't make any sense.
But I think it's sort of expressive of or reflective of the general posture of the Justice
Department and our whole sort of system of justice, broadly speaking, which is we don't really...
It's really the exception when a corporate executive ends up doing jail time, as we saw
in Incis. And the Incis case is kind of particularly extreme. Incis is like,
everything you see in the Purdue story, but just like dialed up to 11. I think there were a bunch
of reasons why you saw jail time in the Incis case and you don't in the Purdue.
What was the CEO? Was Kumar, wasn't that his last name?
Something I'm blanking on his name. But yes, I mean, Incis was just such a scam. And there you have
like, kind of strippers working as sales reps and real kind of fairly sort of bald bribery schemes,
not the soft corruption I've been talking about, but like the hardest of hard corruption.
So there you saw jail time. In my view, jail time is the only thing that really
that really is a deterrent. I think otherwise, I don't know. I mean,
people are rational, particularly when it comes to money. And when it comes to money,
and they think about risk, right? They evaluate risk. And if you look at the Sacklers, right?
It's like you take $10 billion out of a company during a period of time when it's committing
crimes, you're going to have to give back 4.5 billion. Do you do it? You know, do you do you
you look at that fact pattern, you take you got a company company commits crimes, you own the
company, you're on the board of the company. You're never going to go to jail, you're never going to
get charged with any crimes, you will have to give back 4.5 billion, but you can do it over nine
years. Do you do it? I mean, I could probably go out on the street and find you some people who
would say, hell yeah, sign me up. For the Sacklers, I think, you know, the real costs are going to be
reputational. And it's hard to measure that. Yeah, that's the thing that I mean, you have to
argue that are they any different from O.J. Simpson? You mean in terms of the notion that
everybody knows. Yeah, like, I mean, O.J. Simpson commits this completely heinous, graphic, premeditated,
violent act in front of the world. And if not for a technicality, effectively, you know,
an eraser cop gets off, right? Right. But I don't think the world's ever really forgiven him,
right? I mean, I my guess is he probably is being basically socially punished for the rest of his
life. And rightfully so. Is justice served? No, presumably not. He should be in jail, but
nevertheless. So the blood of two people is on O.J. Simpson's hands. The blood of how many people
is on the Sacklers hands conservatively. What would be the most conservative estimate? Right.
I mean, it's so hard to say, right? Because the thing is you can you can, you know, do you look
just at people who have O.D. done Oxycontin? And of course, they would say again with that parsing,
they would say, oh, yes, but, you know, there were other drugs in their systems. Yeah. My point is,
of the half a million people who have died in the last two decades, I'm willing to acknowledge that
some subset, maybe a small subset of those people, the blood is on the hands of this family
and work like yours has really brought that to light. And it just I just wonder what the rest
of their lives look like. And will this be basically forgotten about? And will the next
generation of Sacklers carry no shame for this? Or will this be something that forever makes people
in polite company a bit embarrassed to be around them? It's funny. I mean, I think.
I think both of the last two things you said are are going to be the case. I think the I think
people will forever be embarrassed to be around them. I think the name is toxic and it's, you know,
it's it's coming down off of institutions. I think it'll come down off of more institutions.
I think the family isn't happy about that. But I also don't know that any of them feel any shame.
I mean, there's this kind of one of the things that's been so revealing to me is
it's funny. There's an analogy that I don't draw in the book in any explicit way deliberately. But
it was one that I thought about a lot as, you know, I was writing this book in the last years of the
Trump presidency and, you know, one sense in which the Sackler situation I think was a little bit
similar to Trump's and it's a sense in which I'm almost sympathetic in both cases is if you're a
billionaire, you're surrounded by advisors and lawyers and PR people and all these people whose
livelihood depends on keeping you happy. And I feel as though that there is a kind of heightened
danger of delusion of you just getting out of touch with reality. And it probably starts in
small ways, right, that you tell a joke and everybody in the room laughs. But then you can,
you know, so initially, you're just like kind of a millimeter or two off track in terms of the
the fidelity of your perceptions of the world. But then the longer you go, the further off course
you get. And what you saw with Trump, which you also see with the Sacklers, is that there are
people in the mix. I mean, I've talked to people who a decade ago said to the family, what if you
took some of this philanthropic money that you give to art museums and started a foundation
dedicated to the study of addiction, you know, redressing the opioid crisis,
people who were making, you know, frankly, a cynical argument, but saying just purely in terms
of the optics here, you should make some gesture, recognizing that there's a problem and that people
think that you're responsible for it. And those people were always sidelined and fired, right?
And the people who end up in the kind of inner circle are the ones who say, you are just terribly
misunderstood. All these people don't understand you, you know, the press, the public, the people
making jokes on The Late Show, the attorneys general of every single state, you know, all these
members of Congress who keep condemning you, all these studies that are done about OxyContin and
its legacy. It's all just a big misunderstanding. You never did anything wrong. And what's been
astonishing to me is they tend to pretty uniformly feel that way, the family members.
Yeah, that's one of the things that surprised me about your book is
you had to do all of this without actually talking to anyone in that family. And when you
think about how many children the three Sackler brothers had and how many children they had,
and how many spouses they have, like, that's a pretty good list of people who could have
come forth and said something to you even off the record or on background. And yet,
I don't think that happened, did it? No, I mean, I listen, my assumption from the beginning had
been that there must be some apostate, you know, there must be some third generation Sackler who
looks around and, you know, never mind my writing, right? It's like they read the New York Times,
they read the LA Times, they read Sam Kinyones' book, Dreamland, and they say, geez.
Yeah, this is blood money. My trust fund is blood money.
I'm a little uncomfortable with this. Yeah. Right. Let me, you know, I don't need this. I'm
going to turn my back on it. Couldn't find one. And one of the more revealing documents I got my
hands on was this. It's a WhatsApp log. It's like a chat log from the the heirs of Mortimer Sackler.
This came out in the context of the bankruptcy proceeding, where they all talk over the course
of a couple of years, all these different family members, siblings, cousins, and they're talking
about, you know, their problems and how do you deal with it and the litigation and the bad PR and,
and what's the right strategy? And it's this private channel.
And there's nobody, nobody who at any point says, you know, geez, maybe our critics have a point or
like, maybe we should ask some tough questions. Instead, it's this pretty lockstep feeling of
persecution. And in fact, I mean, sometimes when you read their private correspondence,
the way they talk amongst themselves, at times it feels that feels as though in their minds,
like the real victims of the opioid crisis are the Sackler family. That's amazing.
That's more amazing to me than the indignant response that is seen publicly.
It's that even privately, there's no awareness. No. Not a shred of introspection.
None and a profound sense of grievance, you know, a sense that this has been,
that they've been kind of persecuted. I mean, there's this amazing email that I quote in the
book where Jacqueline Sackler married to Mortimer Jr., a second generation member who was, who was
on the board of the company. She's talking about how, you know, with all this press coverage and
the sort of stigma for the family, she's worried about her children applying to elite private
schools in Manhattan in the fall and their chances. And in the context of griping about this,
she says children's lives are being destroyed. And not to pivot from the comic to the tragic,
but like, I get emails every week from people who have lost children to opioids. You know, I mean,
when you hear from as many bereaved parents as I do, it's just amazing to read an email like that
and kind of consider the level of disconnection that it betrays. I know you've spoken about how
you also hear from basically two groups of people, right? So you hear a lot from exactly what you've
just said, the family members or friends of people who themselves have become addicted or who
more tragically have lost those. But you also seem to hear from people saying, you know, your
work is potentially threatening to the supply of pain medication to people like me who genuinely
and legitimately need it, which of course is not your intention. But you seem to be sensitive to
that and you seem to understand that there's a fine line here and an overreaction or an overcorrection
that would limit the supply of or access of patients who do need pain medication to it would
be an unintended consequence of this work. So do you get a sense that that is actually happening?
Yes. I mean, I think that there is a definite sense in which the pendulum has swung back.
And in which a lot of doctors are less likely to prescribe these drugs in the first place,
more likely to prescribe shorter courses at lower doses. I think a lot of that is a good thing
ultimately. There are many chronic pain patients who are very fearful and are, you know,
I certainly get emails from people talking about how they're just fearful that they're
supply of this drug, you know, these drugs, I'm not just talking about OxyContin here, but
prescription opioid painkillers broadly that they count on in order to function in life
is really jeopardized by these kind of changing currents in terms of the way in which
people perceive these drugs. And it's an incredibly difficult thing. I mean,
I am very sympathetic to this. I certainly don't want to see
people who use these drugs stigmatized, whether they use them legally or illegally. I tend to be
to be pretty sympathetic with people. I'm also not a prohibitionist. You know, I don't,
given all my work on illegal drugs, I tend not to think that the drug prohibition is the way to go.
People certainly make arguments that if you cut off pain patients and do kind of rapid force
taper and what have you, that that might actually drive people onto the black market and become,
you know, more unsafe, that that might be part of what's driving the opioid crisis.
Where I balk at that kind of note, and this sort of goes back to the thing I said to you at the
outset is the suggestion that I shouldn't write about the Sacklers and their culpability because
there might be some sort of second or third order consequence of that, or that my kind of focus is
in the wrong place. And there I'm not going to, you know, I'm going to write the books that I
want to write and the articles that I want to write. I find it's very often the case that people
who are sort of telling me that I shouldn't be doing these things, generally speaking,
haven't read the book, you know, haven't really engaged with the particulars all that much.
But yeah, look, I do hear from pain patients quite often, and I think this has been a sort
of an agonizing period for them because from where I sit, the problem was not that a drug like
OxyContin shouldn't have been produced or made available to pain patients. It was all in the
decision to do two things. One was dramatically expand the universe of people who should be taking
it. And the other was, I think, pretty systematically play down the risks so that there's a kind of
dishonesty with the consumer and with physicians about what the dangers are. You know, I don't go
from that to any sense that these drugs should not be available at all. There are some doctors
who do, but I sort of don't feel the need to go there myself. I'm pretty squarely focused on
the origins of the crisis and some pretty unambiguous wrongs perpetrated by Purdue and
the Sacklers. So if the Sacklers represent a cancer, right, that cancer has largely been
excised, right? The Sacklers themselves are no longer going to be a part of this dilemma.
But unfortunately, the cancer metastasized before it was excised. So as you point out,
we still have an opioid crisis. And in fact, it doesn't seem to be showing any signs of abatement.
In fact, last year we saw more people die of opioid overdose than any other cause of
accidental death, which is actually a staggering statistic when you consider how many people die
in car accidents, how many people die of gunshot wounds. So in that sense, your work has been a
success in the work of all the people you've written about who have finally brought a modicum
of justice to at least the initial perpetrators of this. But what does the path forward look like?
Like what will it take to actually address this crisis?
Yeah, I mean, you know,
this will sound like a cop out, but in some ways I'm so overwhelmed by that question. I think anybody
would be. You know, the way in which I've grappled with that is to kind of take this small piece of
it that I can focus on and understand. And for me, in some ways, it's kind of, you know,
looking at the origin story of the crisis really more than where we are now.
The numbers are staggering. As you say, they're getting worse.
The sense in which I feel as though the sacros are not absolved by the fact that this is today a
heroin and fentanyl crisis is the sense in which there are many, many people who I think would
never have taken heroin or fentanyl in the first instance that started on prescription opioids
like OxyContin. But of course, you know, from the vantage point of today, I'd rather people
be abusing OxyContin than abusing fentanyl, right? Or heroin that's laced with who knows what.
But it is a very, very scary situation. I feel as though
we need far more resources than we have. I mean, I think it's a problem that needs to be
resourced. I think treatment is very often not available to people. I think there's still a
huge amount of stigma associated with the abuse of an addiction when it comes to these types of
drugs and anything we can do to diminish that stigma. I think, you know, medically assisted
treatment, which I think there are still some for whom that's a kind of a scary concept. And I
think it's one that should be adopted and embraced and not cause the consternation that it does for
some. But I think it's a huge national crisis. And in a strange way, I feel as though were it not for
Covid. It's not that the problem would have been solved, but I feel as though the
just prior to Covid, there was a sense in which I, you know, it's tricky because it was the Trump
administration. But the but I think there was sort of a recognition that we need a major national
strategy to deal with this. It is out of control and killing people in vast numbers. And we need to
to kind of, you know, have all ideas on the table and be strategic and resource the solution.
And then Covid came along and there just wasn't really the bandwidth, right, or the oxygen in the
room to have that conversation. But when we neglect the problem, as we have during Covid,
just purely in terms of the triage or the last 18 months, you see what happens.
Are you optimistic that 10 years from now things will be different?
I mean, I have to be just because I'm, believe it or not, after this after this grim conversation,
I'm fundamentally an optimist about a lot of things. I have to believe we will learn and
we'll sort of find a way out of this. But it's hard. And I think the hardest thing in a way is,
you know, I've had many of these conversations and it sounds like you have too. You mentioned,
you know, the patient who had a family member who actually managed to stop using and seemed as
though they'd moved on and then went to a party and relapsed as such an issue with these drugs.
When you talk to people who've sort of achieved, you know, they've found their way out of the
woods. Often the thing that's so striking to me is that there's a kind of, there's a sort of fragility
to it, you know. They're always talking in the present tense. There's this sense that kind of
every day is a battle. And that's what worries me, I think, about the idea of us kind of 10 years
from now, right, is that on a kind of very micro level for the individual who is struggling
with addiction, there's that sense in which it's like each tentative step. You just never know when
you're going to get pulled back in. And so on a kind of macro level nationally, I worry that
there may be a similar danger. Yeah, I worry about the sort of impact of what it takes to escape the
gravitational pull of an environment that facilitated the use. I did my residency at Hopkins,
which is in inner city Baltimore, and even 20 years ago was probably a leading indicator for how bad
heroin use could get. And I remember, you know, we would take care of a lot of patients who had
abscesses and all sorts of, you know, infections and cellulitis and things like that from IV drug use.
And sometimes these infections themselves were life threatening. So it wasn't just the overdose
on the drug. It was the repeated use of a dirty needle or a needle that gets broken inside the
arm and gets infected. And, you know, so you would take care of these patients and you always wish
them the best when they left, but you were really in the back of your mind, you knew you were going
to see them again. Because even though for the five days that they were in the hospital, they
were not using any drug and they with the total clarity of the thought that they had realized
how lucky they were to get this second chance, they were still going back into the same environment
that brought them into the hospital in the first place. And we used to sort of say to ourselves,
like, you know, the only way this person's not coming back is if they get a whole new group of
friends. Like, in fact, the best thing you could do for this person is get them out of inner city
Baltimore. Like they can't go back to the row home they came from. Now, that might sound like a very
extreme example, right? Well, come on, inner city Baltimore. I mean, you're talking about a crack
house, but is it really any different for a college kid who's trying to desperately get off
the transition from oxycodone to fentanyl and this is being done in a dorm room or at a party
or something like that. And it's their friends and they decide, you know, they managed to,
you know, again, pull out of the grip of that, but they find themselves at another party in three
months. I mean, it's really difficult. That's the part that concerns me is if it's hard to do this
one person at a time. Yeah. Yeah. And it's again, I mean, I think it's funny. I kind of come back to
the, you know, that idea of undertow and even you telling your own story about your experience with
OxyContin. I think the big thing that comes home to me is just that the, you know, these things are,
these substances are, they have an awesome power and that's compounded by all of the kind of
atmospheric social sort of situational things you're talking about. But just having talked to
a lot of families over the years who've dealt with this and they, you know, they thought they
were out of the woods and then they weren't, I think you're right. Like in any one individual
life and even somebody who actually has a really supportive, you know, they've got a whole support
system there. And in some instances, you know, in many instances there are people who don't have the
resources for the appropriate treatment, but in many instances there are people who do, right?
Who throw resources at the problem and it's not enough. It's not adequate. So I think that the,
I just think we should all be sort of humble and mindful in the face of the
tremendous kind of potency and power that's on the other side of this problem.
Yeah. Well, Patrick, thank you very much for, first and foremost, for your book and your
investigation, which I think has brought to light a lot of things that probably could have easily
gotten ignored or swept away. I mean, it's true that during these proceedings, a lot of documents
are brought into the public light, but that's only half the battle. That's the easy half. The hard
part is actually going through them and extracting what the story is. And you've done a better job
of that with respect to this important part of the story than anybody else. But also thank you
for making time. I know this is, I imagine as an author, you must get tired of having to do
interviews on the same topic, but I really appreciate it. But this one was so, it was really,
really in depth and yeah, I very much enjoyed it. It was a great conversation. Thank you.
Thank you, Patrick. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're
interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that
allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our
goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end,
membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast
show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the
street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear
everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about,
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.