Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Sam. How are you doing today?
I'm doing good. How are you?
Good. Good. Congratulations on the publication of your book very recently. Having never done
that before, I can still only imagine it's akin to giving birth or something like that.
It feels like the weight of the world off your shoulders after how much research you've put into
that.
Yeah, it's a huge relief just to be done. So I'm trying to think about a future project,
but I feel like I need a few years just to relax now.
Oh, yeah, yeah. I imagine there's nothing more annoying than when you publish a book when somebody
says, so what's your next book going to be about? It's like, let me bask in this one.
Yeah, I've done that a few times.
Like many books that go really deep into a topic, be it science or otherwise, they often start out
as articles. And of course, you wrote a piece, was it 2015? When was that piece?
It came out in 2016.
Yeah. And it was the New York Times Magazine piece, correct?
Right.
And I remember that quite well. You and I had spoken quite a bit before then. And I know that
that sort of ultimately led to the work that went into this book. But more broadly speaking,
what attracted you to this topic of Warburg cancer metabolism, the era of Nazi Germany,
and science in that era? What gravitated you to that?
Yeah. I mean, like so many people in this world, I was influenced by Taubes at a fairly early stage
of my interest in metabolism. I read some of his work and that had led me
to other authors and eventually to a lot of your work and your blog, which I learned a lot from.
So I had been interested in metabolism for a number of years. But I had not really thought
of cancer as a metabolic disease or thought about cancers being lumped with obesity and diabetes and
heart disease. And when I start to read more about that and see that they clustered together
and that you see the same pattern that begins in the 19th century of all these metabolic
conditions growing more common, that's what really sort of sparked my curiosities. You know,
cancer isn't supposed to be metabolic like these other diseases. You know, it's bad luck. It's
mutations that are caused by environmental carcinogens or whatnot. So it just stayed in
my mind. But I hadn't planned to write about it until I came across a mention of Warburg. I think
it was just one sentence, you know, 1923, a German scientist makes an important discovery
about the metabolism of cancer cells. And, you know, so I Google Otto Warburg and I start to
read about him and, you know, it was kind of a light bulb moment for me like, oh my gosh,
I have to write about this man. You know, because I'm a journalist, a storyteller by profession. And
so I don't write about science usually unless I feel like I know how to tell a story. If I have
a central character, then I know how to tell a story. So once I had Warburg, I knew I was going
to write about it and I knew I had a way to tell the story. Before we get to that story,
I want to kind of understand a little bit about your work as a writer. You're a prolific writer,
you actually teach a course in science writing at Johns Hopkins now, don't you? Yes, I do. So
when did you realize you were a writer? Well, my father is a writer, so it helped to have that,
you know, for many people grow up, it seems like a, you know, an unusual career choice. But for me,
it was, you know, obviously, you know, potential option, just having seen my father do it. But
truth is, I didn't try to at least not consciously to follow in his footsteps. If anything,
I thought that, you know, I might need to distinguish myself by choosing a different path.
And, you know, I like my father mostly writes fiction, I like to half joke that my big rebellion
was moving into nonfiction. But it really was in college when, you know, I wasn't sure what I was
going to do. And I was getting a lot of praise for my writing. And, you know, the praise felt good.
And I, you know, I wasn't, you know, killing it necessarily in other areas. So, you know,
I saw that it was my strength, I enjoyed doing it. And I sort of, you know, just continued with it
because I was succeeding with it. So do you think a good writer is born or made or how much of your
success do you attribute to some inborn gift versus something you'd been cultivating and nurturing and
practicing? Yeah, it's a tough question. I think about it a lot because I teach science writing and
general creative writing at Johns Hopkins now. And, you know, I certainly think that everybody
can improve a lot as a writer. And, you know, I think clearly every day about how to get better at
teaching it and helping people improve. But, you know, at some level, it's innate. You know,
some people have more natural ability than others with language. But I think it's pretty analogous
to, you know, musical talent where some people can very quickly get very good at an instrument,
sit down on the piano in a matter of weeks, be good and others will struggle for months and
have to practice again and again. But they eventually get there. So, you know, it's not,
I don't think it's correlated that strongly with intelligence. It's a sort of just an ability to,
you know, use language in a certain way that comes naturally to some people and comes to other people
with more practice. But I think everybody can get pretty good with enough practice.
So when you're teaching a class, let's just say there's a hundred students in the class,
what type of an assignment would you give if you wanted to very quickly figure out the
breadth of natural ability or the spectrum of natural ability across the students? How would
you ferret that out quickly? The truth is that you can see it in almost any writing sample. You know,
I'm on the faculty of Johns Hopkins. I'm also involved in the application,
in reviewing applications and selecting students for the science writing program.
And, you know, they submit samples of their writing, but I often look most closely just at
the cover letters because I feel like, you know, within a paragraph or two, I get the feel, you
know, if they have a feel for the language or not. So it really comes across, you know, I think
almost in any three or four sentences, I can start to feel is, you know, are there extra words in
these sentences? Is the logic tight? Does it flow? It really doesn't take very much to figure it out.
That's amazing. And it makes me feel so self-conscious because of how often I write,
you know, every Sunday I'm putting out a newsletter and I enjoy writing a lot, but
it doesn't, I don't feel like it comes naturally to me so I can imagine, you know, how many people
must read that and go, oh my God, like, yeah, what he's saying is interesting, but he's such a horrible
writer. And of course, I know what it's like to read very good writing. You know, you can sort of
spot the extremes or at least I can spot the extremes. I don't think I could rank 100 people
from one to 100, even though obviously there's somewhat, you know, there's a lot of subjective
stuff in there, but, you know, I could certainly say this is exceptional. Like I can read Sid
Mukherjee and say, wow, this is really, really good. And similarly, I can read something that
is absolutely horrible and say, this is really, really bad. I might not be able to tell you why,
though. So how much of it is also being able to in that cover letter, say,
you gave a couple of examples, right? Like this person is using a lot of unnecessary
words or they're presumably repeating themselves or this is illogical. That's a lot to pick up in
just a paragraph. Yeah. I mean, I think it comes down to clarity more than anything. You can read
something and grasp it right away because the language is concise and clear and you can read
other things where it's just a very simple statement, but you actually have to read it two
or three times just to grasp the writer's meaning. So, you know, George Orwell famously wrote about
politics and English language and, you know, how much good writing depends on clear, concise
thinking. And I think that's true. But such a big part of it, you know, everything that I write
comes out pretty poorly in the first draft, even my emails that if I really care about an email,
I'll spend a lot of time just going over and over and over because it's the repetition,
it's correction after correction after correction where the writing starts to improve. So,
you know, I think the difference between a good writer and a less good writer is often,
you know, how many times the good writer goes over the work, whereas the lesser writer will
just say, yeah, doesn't matter that much and send it off. But there's a price to pay. You know,
I waste half my life worrying about sentences and an email. So, you know, it comes at a cost.
And, you know, for the record, I was a big fan of your blog when you were posting more regularly.
So I think you're being too hard on yourself. Thanks. Did you go to journalism school or did
you do something after undergrad to further hone your writing skills? I did. I graduated and then
I took a few years off to work at a magazine and then I spent two years doing a MFA program at
Columbia. It's a creative nonfiction program. So it's not journalism. I thought about going to
the journalism school, but I chose creative nonfiction because I was interested more in long
form and more in sort of, you know, storytelling as opposed to rigorous reporting that, you know,
I do that as well. But I was really more interested in book writing and sort of long form nonfiction.
And how do they teach at that level? I mean, obviously people who show up to do a two year
MFA at Columbia, which is arguably the best school in the United States, at least to study that subject
matter, you're dealing with a bunch of really talented people to begin with. But what are they
doing in two years to take you to the next level? Yeah, it's mostly a writing workshop. So,
you know, every semester you have a group of about 15 students and a professor and you submit,
you know, three, four times during the semester, you submit your own work and everybody in the
class critiques it. And the professor, of course, you know, critiques it and discusses it. And that's
really the heart of most writing education. And it's a grueling process at times. You know, you
have 15 people sitting there telling you everything that's wrong with your work and you can't listen
to all of them. And they often disagree and you can go a little crazy, you know, trying to make
your work sort of fit everybody's expectations. There are some writers in recent years who have
really been pushing back against this workshop approach because they feel it turns every piece
into sort of a formulaic story or essay where you meet a certain set of expectations that everybody
has and you don't do more experimental work. So there are a lot of debates about that. But
I do think it's really important because even the best writers in the world don't know when
their own work is working. You know, you need feedback from other people. So much of it is
trial and error and, you know, writing a short story. I might use the first person, you know,
telling it from my own perspective. And then everybody says it's not working. So I try it
again and I write from the third person not using the I. And then it suddenly works. And you don't
really know what works until you get responses because when you're writing, you know, if you get
on a roll, everything feels good. Everything, you know, if you're in that space for, you know,
a few minutes when you're writing, you think, oh, I'm on a roll. This is great. And then you show it
to your workshop and nobody likes it. So you need that feedback. And, you know, maybe sometimes
you're right and they're wrong, but ultimately you're trying to publish your work for an audience.
So the audience has to be right at some level. Does it amaze you when you see
people like, you know, Atul Gawande and Sid Mukherjee and Azra Raza, people who didn't
necessarily formally train in writing, but who seem to write beautifully?
Yeah. I mean, it's beyond amazing. It's actually really annoying and frustrating.
I, it just, you know, all, you know, I admire all three of the people you mentioned and,
you know, not only are they exceptional writers, but, you know, they're full-time
physicians and doing these incredible things. And it just absolutely blows my mind that
they have the time to do it. And when they do it, they do it, you know, almost,
in a way that's almost unimaginably good. Like I get depressed reading Mukherjee because I think,
you know, what's the point of me even trying when he's writing in this way? So I don't know how they
do it, but, you know, I just have to accept that, you know, very few people reach that level and you
can still do good things that you're not reaching that level. Well, that's definitely a good way to
think about it. So let's get back to the, to the story here. And let's assume that the listener
here doesn't really know anything about Warburg. That name means nothing to them. What's the,
where's the right place to begin this story? We've, you know, he's born into a pretty well-to-do
family in the kind of latter third of the 19th century. Tell us where to pick up this story.
Sure. Yeah, I do think that his childhood is a really important part of the story. You know,
I had a hard time finding a lot of original sources and documents about his childhood, but the
the basic facts are that, you know, his father, Emil Warburg, is a very prominent physicist,
despite coming from a famous Jewish family. He rises to the top of German physics. He's at the
University of Berlin, which is very unusual for somebody of a Jewish background in the late 19th
century. And Einstein really loves his father. He says that he's like his favorite physicist and,
you know, Emil Warburg ends up providing some of the experimental proof for some of Einstein's
theories. So Einstein was a regular in the house when Warburg was a teenager, Max Planck, Emil
Fischer, you know, all these titans of German science. And, you know, the Germans revered their
scientists. The country was at the top of the scientific world at the time. So Warburg's,
you know, vision for himself is, you know, he's going to grow up and be a great scientist, like
the people that hang around in his house. He's going to make a world-changing discovery, just as
his father and Einstein and Emil Fischer have. And the question is where he's going to, you know,
focus his energies. And he moves away from physics, which is a little surprising.
I think that was his rebellion in a way. And he wanted to outdo his father, Emil Warburg.
And so he moves into the realm of biology and physiology. But it's always throughout his life,
through the lens of a physicist and always interested in energy and how, you know,
we can understand biology through an understanding of energy. So he didn't fully move away from his
father so much as take the physics into a new realm. And that extended to a study of photosynthesis as
well. So how old was he at the beginning of World War I? That's a good question. At the beginning of
World War I, he, I'd have to go back and do the math. So it was 1914 and he was born in 1883.
So he was in his early 30s, I guess. And so what was the impact of World War I on German scientists?
It was, you know, pretty remarkable that, you know, given that if you look back from a historical
perspective, I don't think that Germany's position at the time is particularly defensible, but there
was, you know, just this huge surge of nationalism and the scientists were by and large got, you know,
signed on and signed letters in support of the fatherland and were ready to go fight on the
front lines. And, you know, many of them did. In some cases, you know, many of these scientists were
Jewish and because of the politics at the time, they were, you know, their German patriotism was
questioned. So by signing up for the war effort, this was a way to prove they were full Germans.
So that was a big part of it. And many of them went to the battlefield and others,
you know, worked with Fritz Haber, who develops these gas weapons and, you know, all these sort
of new weapons of war that are coming out of German science. You know, it surprises me that
Warburg went to the battlefield rather than working with Fritz Haber, who, you know, he knew
and, you know, was in, you know, ended up working in the same area in Dalam where Warburg worked. So
it's hard to understand why that happened. But, you know, I think Warburg was really wanted to
prove himself and he loved horses and he joined a cavalry regiment. So I think that was a part of
the appeal for him as well. Now, Einstein urged him not to go, correct?
Well, Einstein, Warburg went and then Einstein wrote a letter to him in 1918. So the war was
nearing its end. And by that point, you know, everybody could see everybody who was rational
and paying attention that it was a lost cause. Germans were dying by the tens of thousands.
And, you know, as madness as Warburg's mother put it, and they want their desperate, you know,
for Warburg to come home, his parents are desperate. So they're friends with Einstein and
they can't convince Warburg to come home. So they turned to Einstein and, you know, they know that
Warburg reveres Einstein and they say, you know, will you write him a letter? So, so Einstein does.
And it's really a perfect letter because it, you know, he knew Warburg well enough to know that
he was a narcissist. And so he wrote the letter saying that you're just too important for science.
We can't afford to lose you. And we don't have Warburg's response to that letter, but sure enough,
he comes home shortly thereafter. So I think it was the letter from Einstein that most likely
convinced him and, you know, possibly saved his life. And, you know, five years later, he makes his
great breakthrough about cancer fermentation. So I like to think that, you know, that Einstein may,
you know, have saved his life and therefore deserves credit for this great cancer discovery
as well. And some indirect way. You wrote about Warburg that he was pathologically dedicated to
his science. What did you mean by that? Yeah. I mean, I think it's hard to understand unless
you grew up in 19th century Germany, but, you know, somebody, a friend who knew him,
described it as having a religious devotion, like a prophet who has like this fervor who
just thinks about nothing but science and is passionate about science. You know,
Warburg used to say a scientist has to be prepared to die for the truth,
get a sense of his perspective there. And I think my favorite example, the one that's maybe most
revealing, is that at one point a friend was telling Warburg about somebody, a mutual friend
or somebody she knew who was having mental difficulties and going through various problems.
Warburg's advice for this person was tell him to think about nothing but science. Just think about
science all day. And, you know, the person in question wasn't even a scientist, but that was,
you know, reveals, you know, a lot about Warburg. I think about how he viewed the world and
this devotion to science was partially about narcissism and wanting to be great. But I think
partially, you know, obviously a genuine love of science and curiosity about the truth, but also
a way to avoid looking internally. You know, I think that comment about the other person really
reveals that he was covering something up by focusing on science all the time and, you know,
trying not to look inward. What do you think he was afraid to look at? Well, you know, he was,
he was a great narcissist. And, you know, I think when you see that personality type,
it almost always comes sort of hand in hand with deep insecurity. And he was clearly, you know,
extremely insecure. You had laugh, you know, whenever he was criticized, he would lash out and
start these feuds with other scientists. So, you know, I think that, you know, that that's where
it ultimately came from. But he also had, you know, all these difficult things to deal with, you know,
being Jewish in Germany wasn't easy even before the Nazis. And then he has this other complicated
issue, which is that he's clearly homosexual. He ends up spending his whole life with his male
partner and he couldn't be out at the time in Germany. And his mother was pressuring him to
get married and questioning his lifestyle. And there were all sorts of rumors about him. So
he had a lot of stress and, you know, there are various ways it comes out. Like he can't do
public speaking. You know, he keeps being told, you know, to get your degree, you have to go and
give these talks and he just refuses. And if it was anybody else, they probably would have failed
him. He was so brilliant that they just finally decided to move him along. So, you know, there
were a lot of psychological issues there. Did he for his I mean, was he in the closet his entire
life or did he eventually come out? Well, yeah, I'm not sure I would use the phrase in the closet.
I mean, in a sense, almost everybody was in the closet. So I actually, you know, he didn't fully
come out and say I'm gay or talk about it. But I think he was about as out as one could be
throughout most of his life. You know, he didn't try to hide the fact that he lived with another
man when he was invited to give a talk. His partner, Jacob Heiss, would always come with
him. Warburg was, you know, in some instances say I'm not going to come unless, you know, my partner
comes. So, you know, they would go to the opera together and travel to his vacation house together.
So, you know, he didn't explicitly say, you know, I'm a homosexual, but I think he came
pretty much as close as anybody of that era. And, you know, I really respect him for that.
And he met Hitler. There's no record of them meeting. I think there's a lot of indirect
evidence that Hitler was directly involved in his case and his fate.
I can go into that detail or maybe we can build up to that. But there is no record of a direct
interaction. Well, yeah, I guess before we get there, let's I want to come back to that because
it's the intersection of them is so fascinating to me. But let's go back to post World War I
and pick it up where Warburg moves into his sort of seminal work. So it's 1918.
Einstein's convinced him to come back, potentially saving his life.
His first choice, I suppose, is where is he going to set up shop, right? Is he going to stay in
Berlin or is he going to leave and he elects to stay? Yeah, yeah. He actually, you know,
right before he leaves, he's given this incredible position, his own sort of wing in the Kaiser
Wilhelm Institute for Biology, which is sort of the pinnacle of German science. They create this
Kaiser Wilhelm Society, which is now the Max Planck Society, as supposed to be the Oxford of
Germany. The idea is that they're going to get the best scientists in the world and give them
everything they need. It's actually inspired a lot by the Rockefeller model, the Rockefeller
Institute in the United States, just find the most brilliant people, give them what they need
and let them go. So he returns, you know, right before World War I, he's about to start this
position. His lab was under construction. And when he returns, it's a very different world. You know,
all the wealthy funders of the Kaiser Wilhelm Society are now bankrupt. So he doesn't even have,
you know, much money for his work at this point. There's this famous example. He has to write a
grant proposal for one of the only times in his life. And, you know, he can't bear to do it
because he's so narcissistic. So he finally writes, you know, scribbles on a piece of paper,
I need $10,000, 10,000 marks, and he actually gets the money. But he actually focuses on,
when he comes back from the war, he focuses on photosynthesis rather than cancer first. And
it's actually really interesting. I think that when his father was trying to get him out of the war,
he was making the case that Warburg was needed for photosynthesis research because he was going
to find new ways to grow food, make photosynthesis more efficient and have more crop yields. And,
you know, the Germans had been starving throughout much of the war and there were huge
food shortages. So, you know, he, you know, came back and really, I think, wanted to solve world
hunger. And that remained an interest of his throughout his life. But he was always interested
in cancer as well. At one point, he asked another famous scientist for advice, should I do
photosynthesis or cancer? And the scientist says, do cancer. Photosynthesis is working pretty well.
So he decides to do cancer. And it's because, you know, he wants to make a world changing
discovery and cancer really has become a German obsession by the 1920s. You know, if you look
back into, you know, the early 19th century, you know, there's not much cancer. And obviously,
there's all sorts of discussions and things you have to look at in terms of longevity and
diagnostic techniques. But I think there's overwhelming evidence, which I try to document
in my book, that cancer did really increase and continue to increase well into the 20s and 30s. And
by the 1920s, there's a panic. So many people are getting cancer, you know, it still pales in
comparison to today's rates, but it's a panic at the time. And, you know, the Germans had conquered
so many diseases. Robert Koch and Paul Ehrlich had figured out bacteriology and infectious diseases.
And it just seemed natural that they were going to do the same thing with cancer. And Warburg
worshiped Ehrlich and Koch and, you know, thought he was going to be the next one to make this
great discovery. And so he takes on cancer and pretty quickly finds this remarkable thing,
which is, you know, as you well know, and probably a lot of your listeners know that, you know,
most cancers eat differently than other cells. They ferment glucose rather than,
you know, burning, you know, breaking it down and burning with oxygen, oxidative phosphorylation.
So this cancer cell shift to fermentation is a remarkable discovery and, you know, ends up
occupying his life, his thoughts, and he ends up focusing on that for much of his life.
So let's go back to how that discovery was made and what he was actually seeing in the laboratory
that led him to this observation. Sure. Yeah. So he, you know, the background is that he had been
studying actually sea urchin eggs in the first years of the 20th century when he's still a young
scientist. And he had seen that these eggs, you know, it's just a little complicated and that,
you know, he didn't necessarily get all of this right. But what his early studies showed was that
when the eggs were about to grow and proliferate, they would immediately begin to increase oxygen
consumption. And it made perfect sense because, you know, you need energy to grow and, you know,
using oxygen is the more efficient way to create energy for the cell. So when he turns to cancer
in 1923, he expects to see the same thing, you know, cell needs to grow, it needs more energy,
it's going to use more oxygen and burn more nutrients with oxygen to grow. And so, you know,
the experiments that he does is, you know, he takes, you know, a slice of a tumor from a rat
and, you know, he attaches it to a manometer, which is a device, really a very simple sort of
U-shaped tube, which can just measure changing gas pressures. And, you know, he expects that
these cells will start to take up more and more oxygen and he'll see the pressure change inside
of his U-shaped tube. But he doesn't see it, he doesn't see the oxygen consumption increasing.
Instead, you know, he checks the solution that these cells are in and he finds it's full of
lactic acid. You know, lactic acid is what's made from fermentation, you know, what human
cells make from fermentation. Of course, you know, yeast and other microorganisms will make alcohol
and carbon dioxide. But so he sees that they're clearly fermenting and, you know, it's a strange
phenomenon that is happening. And he, you know, tries to do other experiments. They end up doing,
you know, tests in vivo and people and seeing that they have more, you know, with cancer have
more lactic acid in their blood. And, you know, every test he sort of carries out comes to the
same conclusion that cancer cells are taking up a lot of glucose and fermenting it to lactic acid
and using less oxygen than he would expect. Go a little deeper for folks into that biochemical
pathway. So when a cell is presented with glucose as substrate and it wants to make ATP,
what are the different fates of that glucose molecule? And why is it so absurd that a cell
would in the presence of sufficient oxygen choose to make lactate? Why is that such an unusual thing
to do? Why is he so surprised by this? Sure. You know, he wasn't the first to understand or to see
that a human cell can ferment. It was understood, you know, going back to, you know, the previous
decades that human cells could do this. You know, it was very surprising when it was discovered
because it was thought only microorganisms did it. But, you know, Warburg was very close with another
physiologist, Otto Meyerhoff, who, you know, made a lot of important discoveries and found that
human cells could do much the same thing that microorganisms can do. So Warburg knew a cell
could do this, but what he didn't know was that a cell would ever do this if oxygen was available.
It was always thought to be a compensatory thing that moved to fermentation if you didn't have
enough oxygen or, you know, if there was, you know, as Warburg thought some damage to the mitochondrial
where the oxygen is used to burn nutrients. So the really surprising part of it was not just that
a cell was fermenting, you know, if you do, as you know, intense exercise and oxygen, you know,
your lungs are eating and you don't have enough oxygen to sort of keep up with the needs and,
you know, fermentation will, you know, glycolysis will take place in that setting as well. But the
surprising thing and what we now call the Warburg effect is that the cancer cells had oxygen and
they were still turning to fermentation, you know, what we call aerobic glycolysis. So that was the
really surprising part. Yeah, aerobic meaning in the presence of oxygen, but still undergoing
this inefficient pathway of glycolysis. And it's so inefficient, in fact, that from an energetic
standpoint, it's hard to understand because the total yield of ATP when you take glucose to
lactate, I believe is four units of ATP, two going, and I could be wrong, it could be two.
Whereas in normal aerobic metabolism, which would be oxidative phosphorylation, you would take
glucose, which has six carbons, you would make two molecules of pyruvate, which each have three
carbons, and that pyruvate would be turned into acetyl-CoA into, and then it would enter the
mitochondria and where it would go through all of the steps of the electron transport chain.
The final emissions would be carbon dioxide and water. And that process would yield either 32 or
34 net molecules of ATP. So the difference is so stark, right? It's like a 17x difference in
energy yield, which as you point out, the only reason you would ever make that sacrifice in
favor of lower energy yield is if you have no choice. So if I said, hey, go for a jog and
run your eight minute mile pace, that's great. I'm demanding ATP at a slow enough rate,
and therefore you have enough oxygen that you can do it the efficient way.
But if we make somebody run for their life, the fastest quarter mile ever, all of a sudden the
need for ATP is so great that it can't be matched by enough oxygen intake. So you take this
inefficient pathway, which unfortunately we can't sustain for as long because with lactate comes
hydrogen and hydrogen reduces the pH and that reduction in pH with that hydrogen ion makes it
very difficult for the actin and myosin filaments in the muscle to release. And that's what people
are actually experiencing when they feel that horrible burn that's actually erroneously
attributed to lactate. It's really the hydrogen ion. So yeah, it's like we knew about this,
but I think this was a really interesting discovery. And that's why I think the term
aerobic fermentation is a paradox, right?
Yeah, I mean, the aerobic glycolysis or aerobic fermentation,
from Warburg's perspective, it was a paradox. And as we'll maybe talk about more, not everybody
sees it that way, but many scientists continue to see it that way. I think that's the only
explanation that if you're choosing to use glucose in this way to ferment it rather than to do the
much more efficient way of breaking it down and getting much more ATP, then the only way to
explain this paradox is that something is broken and why else would a cell do this?
And we'll certainly get to that because today I think we have other explanations. But going back
to Warburg, how did he then explain the observation? So if science is a process of making an observation
and then coming up with hypothesis, what was his hypothesis in light of that observation?
His hypothesis was that the mitochondria, he didn't have full understanding of mitochondria
at this time, but he felt that there had to be some sort of defect in the mitochondria,
the structure that was burning nutrients with oxygen because it made no sense otherwise. And
the only way to really understand it is that Warburg idolized Pasteur and he had his library set
up so that he was gazing at a portrait of Pasteur at all times. One side was Robert Koff,
the other side Paul Ehrlich, but Pasteur was in the center. And it was Pasteur who had discovered
that microbes could ferment, that they didn't need oxygen. It was this shocking thing to him.
Life without air. And Pasteur himself had explained it by the fact that if they were cells were
fermenting and not using oxygen, it must be because there's some kind of problem because
why wouldn't anybody, any cell use oxygen if it could? And it's called the Pasteur effect,
the seesaw-like relationship, respiration with oxygen goes down, fermentation goes up.
So that was how, and that's what other scientists had found when they were studying frogs and
I mentioned Meyerhoff. So that's how everybody understood this relationship. So
that was Warburg's lens. I think a seesaw is a good way to think about it. Respiration goes
down, fermentation goes up. In my book, I talk about it as a backup generator clicking on.
And what's interesting about it to me is that both Pasteur and Warburg were sort of
aristocratic personalities. And I think they really thought of fermentation as lower and less noble
than respiration. Warburg actually literally used those type of terms when talking about it. So
for him, it was just almost shocking, almost unbelievable that a cell could use oxygen and
they would do this lowly thing that microorganisms do. It's impossible.
So how did Warburg attempt to actually test the hypothesis? So if the hypothesis, if the observation
is cancer cells are undergoing aerobic glycolysis to fermentation and the hypothesis is they're
doing this because their mitochondria are defective, how would he test that hypothesis to
increase the confidence that he would have in that hypothesis?
He didn't really have a great way to test it. Certainly not at the time in the 1920s. I mean,
the test that he did was just to see the effect over and over, but he couldn't
prove that it was a problem with defective mitochondria.
Did he recognize that, by the way, as a limitation?
I don't think he did. The most surprising part really is that in the early 20s, his first test
actually showed that respiration was continuing. And then later in his career,
he does additional experiments and insists that respiration is not continuing or if it is,
can be explained in various ways that there's uncoupling, which causes the electrons to leak
out, et cetera. But his early tests showed that fermentation was increasing while respiration
continued to just sort of hum along. And he just sort of denied that or came up with various
explanations for it. But it was really in the post-war period where he starts to make more
and more extreme statements. He finds these cancer cells in the abdominal fluid. I think
they're called ascites. Is that correct? And he sees that in his test of these cells, he sees
very little respiration and just very high fermentation rates. So he becomes more and
more convinced. And he called these pure cancer cells. He thought it was the best test of it,
but he never really had any concrete evidence that there was some sort of structural defect
or in the mitochondria. He felt it was almost tautological that the job of respiration is to
keep fermentation repressed. And if that relationship is not working, then it's necessarily
broken. At one point when critics were charging him with asking for more proof, he said it was
a semantic debate. It's necessarily true because it's not supposed to work that way.
Which really is ironic, right? Based on his observation, there is absolutely no way to know
if his observation is the cause or the effect of cancer. So I was struck by, I think in his case,
you could almost use the word, the arrogance with which he would treat it as tautological
as opposed to acknowledging that, hey, absent additional tools, laboratory tools, it's
difficult to know for sure if this is cause or effect. Which actually brings to the forefront
of this discussion this overlap between him and Hitler, right? Which is this view of cause and
effect that Hitler even writes about, right? Oh, I think you're referring to Warburg's
thinking about causation and cancer. Correct. Yeah. One of the interesting things that I found is that
Warburg and Hitler, Hitler was one of history's greatest monsters. I always had the chance to
compare anybody to him, let alone Warburg, who's somebody I admire greatly despite his flaws. But
I couldn't help because I was writing about both men, I couldn't help but see some parallels in
their story. First and foremost, they grew up in Germany or at the same time, Warburg's born in
1883, Hitler in 1889. And at the time, the hero of the day is Robert Kuff, the German scientist who
makes, discovers the causal relationship between microorganisms and infectious diseases. It starts
with anthrax, then he has his great breakthrough with tuberculosis. So it's hard to, from our
perspective today, it's hard to, I think, appreciate how much Germans revered Kuff. They were like
parades and flags with his face on it because he was conquering disease. And so Hitler and Warburg
are both narcissists, both want to be the greatest men of their generation. And the model for that
is Robert Kuff, first and foremost, in their childhood. And what's amazing, I think, is that
Kuff is most famous in a way for his postulates, which talk about how you can know one thing causes
another thing and what conditions you have to have to show that a microorganism actually causes
the disease. Which are, let's see if we can rattle these off, right? So one is the healthy individual
can never contain the microorganism that is reported to be caused, right? Right. I think that
another one is the corollary is that anyone with the microorganism must have the disease.
And then I think anytime you take a healthy person and insert the microorganism, you must be able to
cause the disease. I think that's the third one. What's the fourth? It's been a year since I...
But that's the gist of the logic. It's a very rigorous logic that, again, I think we all take
for granted today. But at the time it was remarkable and it demonstrated the causal
relationship between these various microorganisms and the diseases they caused.
Yeah. And a key breakthrough, if I'm remembering correctly, is that they had already known that
you could take blood or whatnot from one organism to another and transfer the disease. But Kuff
understood that he first had to get the micro and grow it outside the body. So
he wasn't transferring anything else. He had to prove that it was the microbe itself by growing
it independently and then taking some of those microbes and injecting them. But in any case,
if you listen to Hitler's speeches, some of his speeches in the 40s and read some of Warburg's
papers, they actually... It's almost like they're quoting Robert Kuff. You can hear the same phrases
and talking about causality. And one of the most chilling things that I... And they both refer to
Kuff directly, but the most chilling thing I found, I think, is that Hitler, multiple occasions,
referred to himself as the Robert Kuff of politics. And he said that Kuff had saved the world through
science by eliminating the microbes, the microorganisms that caused disease. And I've done the
same thing with the Jew. So he saw his effort in some ways as a scientific project and that killing
Jews in his twisted mind was like eliminating microbes. And of course, it wasn't just Warburg
and Hitler, but I was just struck that they were both using this language of causality.
And so how did Warburg describe that in terms of primary and secondary causality of cancer? How did
he really start to sharpen his thinking on that? So Warburg says that every disease has a prime
cause and a secondary cause, and he uses the analogy of Robert Kuff that the prime cause of the disease
is the microbe, and then there are all these secondary causes, the unsanitary conditions
that cause the microbe to get onto a person and make them sick, various plagues and anything
that causes a microbe to transfer and get into someone's blood is a secondary cause, and the
microbe itself is the primary cause. So Warburg tries to extend this to cancer. He says the most
fundamental thing about cancer is the shift to fermentation. And so that is the primary cause.
Although there was never proof for this, he insisted that it existed in 100% of all cancers.
I think today people say 70% or more, but not 100%, but Warburg thought it was 100% of all
cancers. I should modify that by saying probably all cancers at some point start to ferment as they
have reduced access to oxygen if they become advanced cancers, but at the most fundamental
level, I don't think you can say 100%, but Warburg said it was 100% of all cancers ferment. This is
the primary cause, and anything that causes the fermentation can be thought of as a secondary
cause. So you might have a dangerous chemical, and that injures the mitochondria, and therefore you
have fermentation. So that's the secondary cause is the chemical or anything you can think of,
a virus that causes cancer would damage the mitochondria. It's always viewed through the
lens of causing a structural problem, which causes respiration to be damaged and fermentation to
increase in a C cell-like relationship. What did Warburg believe accounted for the
significant increase in the prevalence of cancer leading up into the 1920s and 1930s?
As a secondary cause by his definition.
At the time, in the 20s and 30s, he doesn't say much about it. But I think it's clear looking back
that he was from an early time very worried about environmental carcinogens, but in the post-war
period, he becomes very outspoken about environmental carcinogens. And I think his
influence is much wider than many people realize. In Germany, he starts campaigning against smog from
automobiles and buses and food dyes used in the German food supply and all sorts of chemicals.
He becomes basically an organic farmer, one of the first organic farmers I've heard about. He has
his own garden, and he has his partner, Jacob Heiss, is the only person who's allowed to cook
for him. And he even has a well where he gets his own water. So his hypothesis was that the chemicals
in our food, first and foremost, were poisoning ourselves, poisoning the mitochondria and causing
the shift to fermentation. But what's really interesting, I think, is that if you read
Rachel Carson's Silent Spring, which is a hugely influential book and really changed American
environmental policy, Warburg is actually the first cancer scientist mentioned in the book. And
it's clear that that's exactly how she viewed cancer and saw all these environmental chemicals
as causing cancer via the damage to respiration that Warburg cited. So I think he ended up
having a massive influence on American life, just nobody knows about it.
He was awarded the Nobel Prize in 1931. What was the seminal work for which he was awarded?
Sure. Yeah, a lot of people think that he got the award for cancer, but that's not true. He was
nominated in 1926 and should have won for his cancer research. But it was apparently a tie,
and they gave it to the other guy. And no one really knows why Warburg didn't get it in 1926.
In 1931, he gets it really for figuring out the final step. He believes it's the only
step at the time, but really the final step of a respiration, understanding how the electron
passes down the electron transport chain and is able to react with oxygen. So he sort of
elucidates this process and wins the Nobel Prize for that. So what happens during World War II?
As you point out, obviously he's Jewish, he's gay. I'm guessing that both of those things
make him an enormous target for Nazis. Why does he stay in Germany?
Yeah, it's one of the most fascinating parts of his story. 1933 comes along and only two years
earlier, the Rockefeller Foundation has built this beautiful institute for him. He has designed the
institute himself after a country manner that he admires. And he's on top of the scientific world,
he's just won the Nobel Prize. And all his colleagues start to flee, his Jewish colleagues,
they see what's coming. And Warburg refuses to see it. He's not going to give up his kingdom
in Dallum in southwestern Berlin. He says, I was here before Hitler. And like a lot of Germans,
he believed that the Nazi phenomenon would be short-lived. His cousin Max Warburg had said,
we just need to give Hitler enough rope to hang himself. So Warburg had said, maybe six months a
year, he thought they'd be gone. But I think that part of it was, he was so arrogant and so
narcissistic that he couldn't fathom anybody telling him what to do, let alone, he called him
Bavarian noisemakers. These Nazi thugs were going to kick him out of his institute. No way.
I mean, that was his perspective. And I think the most shocking thing about his story is,
he has a famous Jewish name, his father's Jewish, so he's Jewish by the Nazi standards. He lives with
his male partner. He should have been as vulnerable as anybody in Nazi Germany. And yet he not only
staves, but he provokes the Nazis. He screams at them when they come to his institute demanding
Aryan descent forms. At one point he says, he'll burn down his institute if they come again.
He won't do the Hitler salute. He won't put up the Nazi flag. So he really was in a very
dangerous situation in 1936. The New York Times ran an article saying Warburg, maybe in jeopardy.
He was famous enough at the time that they were writing about him in the Times. And he was also
tremendously stubborn. He said to his sister at one point that it's going to be either me or them,
I'm not budging. And his sister's understanding of it was that the more pressure he got,
the more he insisted on staying because he couldn't stand to think that he would lose that battle.
And it's very hard to understand this. When we look back, we see these Jewish scientists clean
and we think, oh, what wise, moral people, they saw what was coming and they left. They didn't
want to be a part of it. But at the time, it was really considered a shameful thing that to leave
was to accept that you were somehow a lesser German. And Warburg, that was the antithesis of
everything Warburg stood for, to do anything that would cause him shame would be unimaginable. So
there was really no way he was leaving. He didn't think about it, but I think he correctly understood
that he would never be the same if he left. Did he journal? I mean, what type of sources
were you able to, if any, get into his head during that period of time?
It was honestly one of my most important, I didn't find it myself, but it already existed in German.
But one of his sisters, Lotte, kept a diary and she was a writer and she wrote a great deal about
him and recorded their conversations. So that ended up being really my key source for a lot of this.
Warburg didn't keep a diary, but because he was famous and he wrote a lot of letters, I had a lot
of letters that he wrote. And whenever somebody encountered him, they would often write down their
impressions because he was such a character and he was already world famous. But at the very end of
the war, he actually did scribble out some notes. A few years ago, a historian, Karin Nicholson in
Germany, actually discovered in the back of his notebooks these notes, which were really
fascinating. He was dealing, we haven't really talked about that part of the story, but he was
dealing with some guilt that he faced by not protecting certain people who worked for him
from being forced into the military. So he started to scribble out these defenses and just,
it's only a few sentences here and there, but it gives you a window into how persecuted he felt
at the end and how guilty in some ways I think he felt as well. How many people did he know that
died in concentration camps? Fewer than you would think, partially because most of the Jewish people
that he associated with left, in the Kaiser Wilhelm Society, I think there were like 2,500
Jews at various institutions and Warburg was the only one who stayed until the very end. So
most of them left and a lot of people don't realize that German Jews,
in many cases, were more likely to survive the Holocaust than other European Jews.
So he didn't, some of his Warburg cousins actually were murdered in the camps. He wasn't
particularly close with them, but he didn't lose a lot of people who were close to him, but
he certainly knew people. I don't have a good answer to that question, but it would be impossible
for him to have not known a lot of people who died, but I don't know that there were people who
were closest to him. He certainly knew hundreds or thousands of people who fled for their lives.
In countries like Poland, there was clearly a moment in time when you could no longer leave.
Was that true in Germany as well? Was there basically a time beyond which if you had not
left, you were not going to leave? Yeah, I mean, certainly for Warburg there was because
he was famous and the Nazis saw propaganda value in having him there. For others, it really
changed a lot after the war started and by that point if you hadn't left,
you were in grave danger if you were Jewish or homosexual or various other persecuted categories
in Nazi Germany. But in the early 30s, you had an opportunity to leave Germany at least, but
it was extraordinarily difficult because they would take all your wealth. You basically had to
give up everything and leave with nothing and find a new career. This is in Germany. The other
countries didn't have the advance warning and the Jews of Eastern Europe were much less wealthy.
These are in many cases more people who lived in much less wealth than the German Jews and never
really had a real opportunity to escape when the Germans rolled in. So it was very different for
Eastern Europe where the Holocaust really begins. So what do you attribute the fact that he
survived the war to? Is it simply that the Germans benefited more by him staying there and being alive
as a showcase of their scientific prowess? Or do you think there was an explicit directive
from Hitler or someone else saying, despite the fact that he's everything we despise,
he's everything we despise, there's value in the work he'll do?
Yeah. So by the mid 30s, it's clear that he serves propaganda value for them. The Berlin Olympics in
1936, they're able to show that this guy who has Jewish ancestors is still here working in Germany.
But by the late 30s, that propaganda value drifts away and certainly is useless once the
war starts. So he's increasingly sort of grave danger as things progress throughout the late 30s.
Meyerhoff, a lot of people stayed until 1938. Meyerhoff, who's also a Nobel Prize winner, escapes
in 1938 and flees to France. And from that point on, that's when Germans roll into Austria and all
the Austrian Jews who can escape escape in 38. But the fascinating thing really, it comes to
a head in 1941, where, you know, by that point, you know, the war is in full swing and, you know,
there's no value to keeping Warburg alive, really, you know, for propaganda means at that point.
So Warburg is called to Nazi headquarters in 1941, June 21. And he meets with Victor Braque,
who is one of the worst Nazis, a guy who designs the euthanasia killing program that sort of starts
the mass killing. And it looks like it's going to be the end for him. He's already received an
eviction notice from his institute. He has a lot of enemies in German science. I mean, you have to
keep in mind, he had a lot of enemies in German science before all this started. So you can imagine
that how many people hated him and wanted to get rid of him. You know, all the other institutes
were full of Nazis. It was the only one that wasn't. So, you know, they finally succeed in,
you know, getting rid of him. And he's called to Nazi headquarters. And he sits down with Victor
Braque. And he's told that he's actually going to be allowed to live on one condition that he
focused on cancer research. And, you know, it's extraordinary in itself. But the part that
surprised me most, you know, and other German historians had recorded this meeting on June 21st,
1941. But what I realized, nobody had yet realized that this was an extremely important moment in
German history. The very at dawn, the next morning, the German tanks rolled into Soviet territory was
the launch of Operation Barbarossa, which is, you know, the biggest at the time, the biggest
military invasion in history. It was, you know, the most significant moment in the Nazi project
in a lot of ways. And that very day, they're sitting around, you know, worrying about Warburg.
And it wasn't just Victor Braque. You see in Himmler's Daily Planner that he has a meeting
about Warburg that day. And then later that night, Goebbels kept a diary. And he records in his diary
that later that night, just hours before Operation Barbarossa, he and Hitler are talking about cancer
research. The diary, that diary doesn't say Warburg's name, but given that everything else that went on
that day and that Warburg was in the building, it certainly seems, you know, that Hitler knew what
was going on. And at Warburg, there's more evidence of Hitler's direct involvement, because
Warburg has applied for something that they called a German blood certificate. This just
shows you what a, you know, twisted, horrific world it was at the time that, you know, for
Judah to survive in Nazi Germany, at that point, if you had managed to stick around that long,
you could apply to have yourself upgraded to be more Aryan. So Warburg goes through this
application process at this point, I think it's defensible, because, you know, it's really to
save his life in a way. But Hitler would actually review these applications himself. And certainly
for a Nobel Prize winner, Hitler would have reviewed this application. So, you know, as you
had to talk about all your ancestors and submit photos, you know, just sick stuff where, you know,
the kid would, you know, look at the noses of the people and decide if he would upgrade them or not,
so that they, they never actually formally Aryan eyes, Warburg, but it's clear that Hitler would
have been involved in that review. And that probably decided on that day, June 21 1941,
to let him continue to focus on cancer. Was Hitler personally obsessed or touched by cancer? What
was this? I mean, was it simply just the epidemiology of the time?
Yeah, he, you know, was very personally touched by it. When he was a teenager,
he lost his mother to breast cancer. And his mother was really the, you know,
historians say the only person he was capable of loving. And he had already just sort of failed to
get into art school and was depressed. He comes back to Austria, or comes back to his hometown in
Austria, and sees his mother dying of breast cancer. And it's just distraught. It's actually
a Jewish doctor who's caring for his mother. And he left a little reflection on the experience.
He said in his entire life, he's never seen anybody look as dejected as Hitler. And, you know, Hitler
sort of okayed these experimental treatments on his mother, which left her riding in pain. And he
was there at the bedside. And for the rest of his life, he was obsessed with cancer and talked
about it constantly in his speeches as a metaphor, but was also a hypochondriac who constantly had
stomach problems and thought it was stomach cancer. And, you know, it became a huge part of
the Nazi project is trying to eliminate cancer. And, you know, one of the very uncomfortable
things about this is that, you know, as monstrous as the Nazis were in every way, they actually did
make some advances in cancer prevention, you know, for all the wrong reasons. But, you know,
they inherited, you know, a great scientific establishment and it makes sense that they
would actually make some progress on cancer. It's very interesting to imagine a world without
the Nazis, given the prominence of German science into going into, you know, the Second World War,
and how much of a balance and how much of a shift in power that was scientifically post-World War
II, right? How effectively that was the change from Germany being the epicenter of science,
not just biological sciences, but physics, and then that shifting. In fact, so many of the
journals, right, shifted from being published in German to being published in English post-World
War II. Yeah. I mean, early 20th century, you had to speak German to be a scientist or be able to
read German. You know, it's incredible how the extent to which, you know, all the early Nobel
Prize winners were Germans, not all, but, you know, shocking percentage. It's rumored. I don't,
I've never actually been able to confirm if this is true or not because I've read various accounts
that Warburg could have won a second Nobel Prize during the Second World War. What was your finding
on that? Yeah. I think that he, you know, certainly deserved a Nobel Prize for his cancer work, which
he didn't get in 1926. I don't think there's really proof of the, you know, Warburg said that
he didn't get the Nobel Prize in the 40s because the Nazis wouldn't allow it. He certainly was
considered for it. I found evidence that he was considered for it, but I didn't find any evidence
that they were going to sort of give him the award, but couldn't because of the Nazis. And what work
was that in the 40s that they would have been potentially considering him for? Yeah.
Warburg, you know, his Nobel Prize, as we talked about before, was, you know, for understanding the
last stage of respiration, this, you know, enzyme that we now call cytochrome oxidase. But, you know,
at the whole time he had been saying in the 20s that this is the only thing you need to know for
respiration. It's kind of analogous to what he said about cancer. But then he finally accepted
that no respiration is actually a multi-stage process and you actually need, you know, not just
to react directly with oxygen, but to rip hydrogen off these nutrients and to pass the electrons down
the transport chain. So he became interested in these hydrogen transfers and understanding, you
know, how the reaction took place. And he actually, you know, a lot of people think this is the best
science he ever did. He actually made huge advances in understanding the role of coenzymes
and how they react with hydrogen and allow for these transfers. You know, it was really innovative
work, really kind of set the stage for decades of enzyme research. So, you know, that led to
the discovery of the components of NAD among other things. So he did deserve a Nobel Prize for that,
but I didn't find any evidence that they were going to give it to him. But I think he fairly
deserved three Nobel Prizes. Say a little bit more about his work on NAD. That was actually
new to me. I until recently was not aware of his contributions there. It's not surprising,
I suppose, when you consider his involvement with the electron transport chain. And as you point out,
the electron transport chain transports its electrons using hydrogen back and forth,
transporting between NAD and NADH. But it's actually kind of an interesting story, right,
about how he made these discoveries. Yeah. So, Warburg is trying to do a chemical analysis to
figure out the reactive component of what we now call NAD. He called the in-between ferment.
And he can isolate a very small amount, but he can't get enough of it to really understand and
do the chemical analysis of what it is. And he's using horse blood to study it. And he says at one
point to figure this out, I'm going to need to kill all the horses in Germany. And he was a great
lover of horses, so that was not a good option for Warburg. But he knows, he has enough of the stuff
to figure out the molecular weight and a few basic facts about it. So he has a friend who works in the
chemistry industry and in the chemical industry. It's just a big part of German industry. And he
asked him to look it up, see if he can find anything similar. And based on what he looks up,
he finds an exact match, which is nicotinic acid. And so Warburg is the one that figures out that
this key component that makes this reaction possible is actually a chemical that everybody
knew about that was being used in photography for decades. Warburg said a day ago, I couldn't
buy it for all the money in the world. And now I can get it for two marks. And it actually turned
out to be hugely important, not only for understanding respiration, but for understanding
the disease, pellagra, which was only solved after Warburg made that discovery. And someone thought,
let's give this chemical to people who suffer from this disease and see if it cures them. And sure
enough, it did. And it's one of the ironies of Warburg story that he always wanted to make a
great discovery and save lives. And he actually did, but he never even really recognized it or
saw it that way. So he stays in Germany after the war ends. He could obviously at this point have
gone anywhere. He could have come to the United States, which is what many of his peers had done
before the war. What was his reason for staying? In terms of staying in the years after the war?
Correct. Yeah. Yeah. I think that for a few years after the war, I think he was prepared to go
elsewhere. I mean, I found letters of him searching for places and he comes to America in the late
40s and he stays in one lab for six months and another lab for six months. But it's clear that
there's no future for him in America that a lot of the Rockefeller's no longer want anything to do
with them because it looks suspicious that he had stayed. The truth is he despised the Nazis as much
as anyone, but anybody who stayed when they could have left is under suspicion. And he's making more
and more extreme statements about cancer. So he's alienating a lot of people. And meanwhile, in 1950,
the Americans give him back his Institute. They had taken it over when they had their
military occupation of Berlin. So he gets to go back to his beautiful Institute. And he has,
again, some propaganda value for the Germans. We can say, look, we've given this person of
Jewish descent, his Institute back, and he's living here and thriving in Germany. So I think,
you know, if he had gotten the right offer, I think he would have gone to America, but he ended
up sort of returning and reestablishing his old life in a lot of ways. In some ways, it's
shocking and upsetting. But, you know, by 1955, you know, from his perspective,
it was like nothing had happened. You know, he's continuing with all the same stuff.
Now, forgive my ignorance. How is it that was it a is it was it an easy choice for him to end up
in West Berlin as opposed to East Berlin following the war and what determined
that was it simply a function of where he was prior to the war and therefore it was somewhat
fortuitous? Yeah, it is actually interesting and a little bit complicated. His Institute ended up in
the American sector. But another extraordinary thing about his story is in 1943, bombs are
falling near his Institute. And he's actually moved to a new Institute and the Nazis built him,
you know, sort of they sort of refurbished this beautiful sea house for Warburg in the middle
of the worst part of the war for them when, you know, there's no gasoline for anything.
It's forbidden to build anything if it's not for the war effort. And they take time out
to build, you know, sign for Warburg to continue his cancer research in a safer place.
But in that that Institute was actually ended up in Soviet territory. So he was sort of caught
between these two different worlds. And he had a vacation house, which is in Soviet territory. So
when the war ends, he is actually under Soviet rule and he has to escape back to the West.
But the Soviets were trying to recruit him much more so than Americans. Interestingly, you know,
both a lot of the great German scientists and, you know, unfortunately, a lot of Nazis ended up,
you know, being smuggled into America, you know, for the purposes of American science. But the
Germans, I mean, the Soviets were going after them as well. So he is sort of caught between
these different worlds, but ends up, you know, because his Institute is in West Berlin,
is able to stay in the American side, ultimately.
So interesting to me, because you have to wonder if people in Berlin at that time understood how
stark that contrast would be. You know, you could argue that, well, gosh, it's just it's wonderful
that the war is over and the Nazis are gone. And, you know, you might end up on this American side
or, you know, what the time was American occupied, or you might end up on this what will be a Soviet
side. But it probably couldn't have been clear just how different those two would end up being
over the coming, you know, four or five decades. Yeah, I don't think it was clear, but it was clear
that the Soviets, you know, with good reason were much more feared. So, you know, in the last days
of the war in 1945, you have a lot of people fleeing westward, not so much because they could
imagine what the Cold War was like for decades, but because they were worried about being murdered
and raped, you know, because the Soviets were, you know, with good reason, you know, furious
at the Germans and out for revenge. And they certainly took that revenge. So it was understood
that you had a better chance of surviving if you made it westward. But I don't think anybody could
foresee what happened in the following decades.
Warburg has a really interesting tit for tat with with with Sidney Winehouse in in science,
about a decade later, I actually was able to pull up the article and and read it. They both wrote
letters. And and Winehouse was really kind of a mild mannered guy, wasn't he?
Yeah, he was, you know, most of the people Warburg had these, you know, vicious, you know,
scientific feuds with I would look them up and they seem, you know, much more reasonable and calm
than than Warburg himself. Winehouse, I mean, the Philadelphia suburbs, he actually worked at a
hospital just a mile away. He died in what, the early 90s, I think. And he he was at he was at
Penn, wasn't he? Or no, he was at Jefferson, if I recall. He may have been, I think he was at
Lincoln Hospital, but maybe maybe at Jefferson as well. I'm not sure. But he was around here.
I actually found some people that knew him and talked them a little bit.
But he but he publicly called Warburg out. He basically said, don't agree with this observation.
I mean, agree with the observation. Don't agree with the interpretation is what he said.
Yeah, I think if you look at the quotes from him, he was relatively calm about it. But, you know,
as a journalist, I have to laugh. I'm sure it was the headline writer. You know, the headline under
one of the articles was cancer theory overthrown. You know, I don't think that Winehouse would have
put it that way. But, you know, some editor like me just wanted to, you know, make it a little more
sensational. So well, and he was deferential to Warburg in the article. I mean, he did say something
to the effect of I don't remember exactly, but the gist of it was in we owe a great debt to
to Warburg for his amazing contributions to the field, et cetera, et cetera. But, you know,
cellular respiration is basically there. He said, look, there's no difference in oxygen consumption
between these cells and there's no evidence that the mitochondria are damaged.
Warburg's rebuttal was far less kind. Yeah, he was. Yeah. You might be thinking of the papers
in science in 1956. Yes, exactly. Yeah. They had a back and forth. I believe it's August 1956,
where first, you know, Warburg writes a piece in early 56 and then Winehouse responds in Warburg.
That's right. Response to his response. And, you know, Warburg, you know, comes off. I mean,
it's a really elegant paper that he writes. He was a great writer. And we should have talked
about Warburg's writing at the beginning because, you know, I really admire his writing. And
but, you know, he makes much bolder statements and denounces his opponents in a way that
that Winehouse doesn't. Winehouse is a more humble scientist. But that is, yeah, I encourage all
listeners to look up Warburg's paper from 56. It's pretty remarkable. We'll link to it in the
show notes for sure. I love reading that stuff. I mean, I just absolutely fancy reading that stuff,
which actually an example of one of my favorite scientific papers to read is the next logical
place to go in this story, which is the paper by Watson and Crick describing the helical structure
of DNA. So that's relevant to the story for reasons you will tell us. But it's also a funny paper in
that the I think it's the last line either in the abstract or the paper makes some very, very,
very understated remark that this this thing, what they're referring to as DNA, you know, may prove
to be of interest at some point or something to that effect. I used to be able to quote it verbatim.
But what is it about the discovery of DNA that would ultimately put a
change the course of Warburg's discovery and this entire field of cancer metabolism for decades to
come? Yeah. So, you know, by the fifties and sixties, Warburg is already fading away for some of the
reasons we've talked about, you know, Winehouse challenges his beliefs that, you know, cancer
cells have defective mitochondria. He sees respirations running fine. So there's more
skepticism of Warburg and people suspect him because of the Nazi years. But I think the single
biggest factor was sort of the changing wind in science and, you know, more than anything,
you know, the discovery of oncogenes beginning really in the mid-1970s when they're first
able to identify specific genes that in their mutated, activated form cause cancer. So
this unleashes the whole new world of molecular biology and Warburg's study of enzymes and cancer
metabolism starts to seem like, you know, old world biochemistry stuff. And, you know, if you want to
really understand cancer, you got to look at the DNA and these signal transduction pathways and all
the new molecular biology. And, you know, there's literally stories of like, you know, people seeing
manometers thrown in the trash, you know, Warburg's signature tool. And it's just amazing to me how
quickly Warburg gets relegated to the old world and, you know, nobody's interested in, you know,
by, you know, by the 90s, you know, students don't know his name. And then...
And by the way, he died in what, 1970?
1970. But, you know, there's all these remarkable examples in the year 2000, Robert Weinberg,
co-authors, you know, the Hallmarks of Cancer paper, which sort of, you know, is, I'm sure you
know better than I do, the sixth, you know, fundamental traits of cancer and doesn't include
the Warburg effect or mention Warburg or metabolism. He later, you know, they later do a revised
edition and do mention it 10 years later, I believe. So Warburg is just gone from cancer
science, gone from textbooks. You know, Weinberg's famous textbook in 2006 doesn't mention him,
you know, Mukherjee, who, you know, I think his book is absolutely brilliant, but also doesn't
mention Warburg just because nobody was mentioning it. You know, it's just not something that people
were interested in. They talked, you know, the enzymes that Warburg's today were referred to as
housekeeping enzymes, you know, seems, you know, cancer needs to divide and therefore it needs
energy, it needs nutrients, but it's sort of, you know, just not fundamental to the process,
just something that's needed to supply cancer as it progresses. And it's really shocking to me
that something so fundamental could just get lost. But I think, you know, to some extent,
that's how science works. You know, there's an exciting new thing and it's hard to focus on two
things at once. And look, I mean, I think it is a very remarkable discovery in the 1970s that there
are oncogenes. And Harold Varmus and Michael Bishop are awarded the Nobel Prize in 1989
for that discovery. It holds a lot of great promise. Certainly by the time I got to medical
school in the late 90s, that was, I mean, my God, if I could go back and figure out how many
oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes I had memorized and all the pathways and such,
I mean, that was really what, that's the only thing that mattered in cancer biology.
So what do you think led to the Renaissance? I mean, for me personally, the first thing that
came on the radar screen was a science paper in 2009 written by Matthew Vanderheiden and
co-authored by Luke Antley and Craig Thompson. Was that sort of the first thing that showed up on
the radar? I mean, obviously those three had been doing a lot of work leading up to that. I've had
Lou on the podcast and we've talked at great length about his work and the discovery of PI3 kinase.
So clearly this idea that metabolism mattered was on the radar of others, even though it was not
necessarily on the forefront of the field. I think that that paper was in the moment,
it was 2009 or 2010 that it sort of reached the mainstream. But as you mentioned, they had been
working on this stuff for some time. So it was really in the late 90s that the revival starts
mid to late 90s in the two key labs, I think, at the early stages. One is Craig Thompson, who you
mentioned, who is now the president CEO of Memorial Sloan Kettering. And the other lab was
Chi Ban Dang, who is at the time at Johns Hopkins. And they both were sort of working on
understanding cancer and molecular biology and both sort of tracing these signaling pathways
to the cell and sort of working their way back to metabolic enzymes. In Chi's case, he found that the
transcription factor, MIC, was actually activating lactose dehydrogen, LDH.
And he was really quite shocked to find that this pathway leading back to this basic fermentation
reaction. So he became very curious about Warburg and reading the old papers on enzymes and
really helped launch a lot of the metabolism revival. And then Craig Thompson and Vander Heiden
was a student in his lab. They had also sort of independently rediscovered metabolism and ended
up focusing on AKT, which is, you know, was already known as an oncogene that caused cells to
proliferate. So the surprising part of their work wasn't that they had found an oncogene,
but that this oncogene was actually a metabolic gene. And what its role was basically to allow
glucose into the cell and that, you know, Thompson, I think correctly states that this is the most
fundamental thing that it does and that the proliferation is downstream of this glucose uptake.
Yeah, it's a very pro-growth factor. So what I think is most interesting about the 2009 paper
in Science is that it acknowledges the Warburg effect but comes up with a different explanation.
Right.
And what was that explanation?
So, you know, prior to this point, you know, the accepted view or that Warburg's view, which,
you know, again, some people still support is that all fermentation is a response to
defective mitochondria. It's compensatory. The cell can't create energy in one way. So it's using
the backup generator. It's revving up fermentation. But, you know, what Thompson and Vander Heiden
can't really argue in that paper is that, you know, we actually don't have, you know, as we
talked about with Winehouse, we don't actually have the evidence that respiration is completely
defective. So the mitochondria still seem to be functional and intact. And there are other
reasons that a cell might need to take up a lot of glucose. And, you know, first and foremost,
they're bioenergetically need the building blocks to create, you know, new nucleotides and lipids
for the daughter cells. So it makes sense that, you know, glucose uptake would increase rapidly.
But the cells, they actually, you know, they're getting some energy, some ATP from respiration,
some from fermentation, but they have enough to continue to function. What they really need are
the building blocks for growth. And so that is a sort of new way to understand the Warburg effect.
And I think that, you know, that's now what most scientists, but not all sort of view is the main
explanation. What's your view? You know, it's tough as a science writer.
At a reporter, you know, I am not trained as a scientist. And I interview one person,
you know, famously, Thomas Seyfried, who is very much a Warburgian who thinks that Warburg got it
exactly right, and that it is a problem of defective mitochondria. And he cites the research of,
I believe, Peterson at Johns Hopkins, who also believes this. So there are a lot of very smart,
accomplished scientists who think Warburg got it exactly right. And, you know, it would have been
easier for me to write in this book to conclude that Warburg was right about everything. You know,
that's a story that would have been easier to tell and made my narrative tighter. But,
you know, I interviewed many more people who felt that Warburg was wrong about this, that
it was not ultimately a problem of defective mitochondria. And, you know, I look at papers
from both sides and don't ultimately feel that, you know, I have a good way of resolving this
debate. But ultimately, I cited much more so with Cantley and Thompson and Vanderheide and
others like now, Chandel, who also takes this position. And, you know, it's partially just
a number saying like many more people believe this and their evidence is compelling and I can
see that they're brilliant. And it's partially also sort of an intuitive feel for the science.
And I say that because, you know, one of the things that really struck me is when Craig
Thompson was giving a demonstration for students about what cancer is. He puts up this slide, I
don't know if you've ever seen this talk and he shows a mold growing on a piece of bread. And he
said everybody's first cancer experiment and then he shows the mold growing. And, you know, it really
goes back to Pasteur in understanding, proliferative metabolism is not something that happens in
microorganisms only in response to defective respiration. That's what Pasteur thought, but
he was wrong. You know, proliferative metabolism happens when a cell can get all the nutrients it
wants. You know, you put, I mean, when I say a cell, I mean the microorganisms, you know, you put
the yeast on grain and they don't care how much oxygen is available. They take up the grain and
they grow and they grow and they multiply. And that I think is a fundamental program that
ourselves know how to do as well. And I think that's really the key to the story is what causes,
you know, this proliferative program to, you know, to take off. And I think it's, you know,
in single-celled organisms, it's the nutrients. And I think in, you know, when you look at advanced
organisms and animals, we have to think not just about the nutrients, but the hormonal
involvement as well. It's much more complicated, but the fundamental, you know, program is running
and it's the nutrients and the growth factors. I mean, I think if you just step back from it
and you say, you know, what is cancer? It's a problem of growth. Okay. Well, what causes things
to grow, you know, nutrients and hormones, that's where you start the conversation. And I think that
if science had progressed in a different way, then that always would have been the focus, but,
you know, it was only in, you know, the late 1960s where we could even measure insulin in the blood,
you know, so cancer, all this stuff about the Warburg effect as a response to, you know,
damaged respiration made sense before we knew anything about, you know, insulin and growth
factors. But, you know, the science has progressed and I tend to view it in much more of the way of
Thompson and Cantley, but I do think that Seafree deserves a ton of credit for sort of bringing
metabolism back into the conversation. And it is, as I said before, you know, I think everybody agrees
that as a cancer progresses, you know, the blood vessels no longer are getting oxygen in the same
way. And that's clearly playing a role in terms of revving up fermentation. So it's not necessarily
either or, but at the sort of core origin of cancer, I don't see that the respiration damage
is being sort of conclusive. Yeah. And I don't either. I mean, I just think on first principles,
it doesn't actually make sense, right? So if you follow the logic of Warburg,
if the primary insult or the prime cause to use his language is damage to the mitochondria,
that's an insult to a cell. That's a deficit to a cell. That's an inhibition of a cell's ability
to respire and frankly acquire energy. So the fact that the cell has the ability to do something
outside of the mitochondria in a compensatory fashion is great. But in and of itself, that
doesn't explain why it would take up more nutrient. It simply explains why it would metabolize
nutrient in a different way. And to, for me at least to focus just on the availability of
nutrients and hormones doesn't explain to me why if we're, let's just talk about colon cancer,
right? Or pancreatic cancer, you pick your cancer, you have a normal cell and you have an abnormal
cell. The normal cell, presumably then is the one that is not going to become cancer. The abnormal
cell is the one that is going to seed the cancer. They're both exposed to the same amount of
nutrient. They're both exposed to the same hormonal milieu. So why is only one of them going down that
cancerous pathway? Why is one turning into a polyp? And why is only that polyp becoming
dysplastic and ultimately, you know, or metoplastic and ultimately dysplastic and ultimately
becoming metastatic. I think that the hormones and the nutrients are simply the fuel that allow
the thing to happen, but they're not the spark. And to me, the spark is what matters. And that's
why I don't agree that Warburg was correct. I don't agree that the initial insult is the
mitochondrial insult. I think that the event that is driving this, I think the oncogenic effect is
the driver. And I think the metabolism allows the cancer to be even more adaptable to the scenarios
that you describe. And I've spent perhaps not as long as you, but I've certainly spent a lot of time
talking with people on both sides of this, going to conferences.
But in the end, it somewhat matters because it comes down to what's the implication of this from
a treatment and prevention standpoint. And I would say in the opposite order, right? What's
the implication of this from a prevention standpoint? What's the implication of this
from a treatment standpoint? And that's what I think about because in the end, that's the part
that I think is a kind of a bedside doctor, that's the part you have control over is what can you do
to prevent cancer or reduce the probability of cancer? I don't think one can truly ever prevent
it. And then in the presence of it, what can you do? So how did this work impact your thinking on
that question? Sure. Yeah. In my mind, that's really the key to my whole story is, there's
sort of two components to it. One is what's going on inside the cancer cell. And that's all this
discussion we've had about the Warburg effect, but there's another part to the story, which is
150 years, 200 years of cancer epidemiology and seeing various environmental causes of cancer or
various theories about what causes cancer. And what really struck me, and I don't think,
you know, as a journalist, I can't understand the science sometimes in the same way that
probably you can and a lot of the people I interview can, but what I try to do is connect
dots. You know, that's one thing I can do as a journalist is look at one scientific field and
another scientific field that aren't necessarily talking to each other and try to put stories
together. And the thing that really struck me was that in the late 90s, at the very same time that
Thompson's lab and Chivan Dang's lab are returning to Warburg metabolism,
we have these new epidemiology papers coming out showing both that insulin is correlated,
elevated insulin, hyperinsulinemia is correlated with cancer and obesity is correlated with cancer.
So it happens at the same moment. And that in a lot of ways, that was my project for the end of
the book is trying to understand, you know, is the obesity story related to the overeating of glucose
in the cancer cell. And I think those two stories are related. And that's why, you know,
the last part of my book is really a focus on hyperinsulinemia, because I think it's
a piece that puts it all together. It could explain the obesity, it could explain the cancer,
and it could explain why cancer was once a rare disease, and then in step with diabetes and
obesity and other, you know, quote unquote, diseases of civilization became much more common. So
in my book, insulin is sort of the explanation which ties it all together, which obviously not
all cancers are caused by insulin. And, you know, insulin's role, according to some scientists,
is only indirect, it causes the obesity and the obesity causes other hormonal changes in
inflammation. But one way or another, I think it's a big part of the cancer story. And the part that,
you know, if we're going to really make progress on prevention, we have to focus,
I think, on hyperinsulinemia. To me, you know, this is now exactly 50 years since the war on
cancer begun. And, you know, we've made so little progress in many ways, certainly with respect to
prevention, you know, there's been remarkable cures and therapies. And, you know, I review the
scientists who make this work, but certainly in terms of prevention, you know, we're just not
making progress. And I think it probably comes back to the hyperinsulinemia.
And, again, I do kind of like the way Warburg positioned a prime cause and secondary causes. So
when you think of the ravenous diarrhea that was ripping through London in the 1800s,
the prime cause was cholera. But the secondary cause was the lack of sanitation, right? It was
that which permitted the cholera to travel so freely from sewage to drinking water.
So now let's think about cancer through the lens of the two most readily identified epidemiologic
factors on scale, not necessarily with the clarity of evidence, but just in terms of breadth of
numbers impacted. First and foremost is smoking. And second, as you point out, is obesity,
at least in the developed world. So with smoking, would we put it in the prime or secondary cause?
I think we'd put it in the prime cause, right? I think we would argue that the evidence for the
causal relationship between cigarette smoking and cancer is likely related to the carcinogenic
effect of the tobacco on presumably the DNA structure of the cells that leads to mutations
that drive unresponsive or unregulated growth. Would you agree with that?
Yeah, I mean, it does come down to semantics at some level. You could argue that the prime cause
is the mutation in the DNA that's driving the cancer. Or you could say that cigarette
smoke is the prime cause. I personally find it more logically compelling to talk about the prime
cause as the very first thing in the step and the very first step in the process. So I think you can
say cigarette smoking is the prime cause. But by Warburg's definition, he would say that if you
accept that paradigm, then you would say the mutation is the prime cause, the chromosomal
damage, whatever it is. Another way to think about this is that the accepted paradigm is that all the
problems, one way or another, go through the DNA and that the safe read and paradigm is that all the
problems go through the mitochondria. So those are the two causal centers. But I think logically,
prime cause should be the very first thing. So smoking and the case of cancer makes sense to me.
Yeah, no, I agree with you. I think that makes sense. So now the question is, how do we apply
that thinking to the second one? So if we posit that indeed, obesity plays a causal role in cancer,
there's no dispute that the correlation is quite strong. That I mean, you don't need to be an
epidemiologist to understand that. The question is, is that correlation causative? Now with tobacco,
the correlation is so strong that it's very hard to find somebody who doesn't appreciate that
there's a causal relationship there. I did see somebody on Twitter the other day try to argue
that tobacco has no relationship to cancer. But let's put that guy aside for a moment.
With obesity, it's a little harder because the hazard ratio isn't nearly as large as it is with
tobacco. And obesity is actually harder to disentangle from its other multivariate parameters.
It comes with so much else. So the person who is obese eats a different way, sleeps a different
way, exercises a different way. The list goes on and on and on of other things that could potentially
play a role. But again, for the purpose of the discussion, if we posit that obesity is causally
related to cancer, then the next step is, is it one of the growth factors associated with obesity,
of which insulin is one? Is it other changes that are prominent with obesity, such as inflammation?
How do you then arrive at, for example, insulin being the prime candidate, to use the word prime
again within the obesity paradigm that's driving this? And that says nothing, by the way, of where
we're going to then have to go, which is, is it the enabler or is it the primary cause?
I mean, my argument is that ultimately, as you said, these are very complicated.
There's many different factors that play out. But my ultimate argument is that the obesity
is not causal, that it's actually the hyperinsulinemia that is simultaneously
driving the obesity and the cancer cell proliferation. So I think part of the evidence
for that is that there are people who are, quote unquote, metabolically healthy obese that
they store more nutrients in their subcutaneous fat, more energy in their subcutaneous fat and
not the visceral fat. And they tend to be metabolically healthy and do not have insulin
resistance. And they seem to be no more likely to get cancer. Whereas when you look at the insulin
resistance and people who are thinner, but clearly, I think it's most people actually do have insulin
resistance. And when you see that metabolic disruption, people who aren't obese, that also
tends to correlate with cancer. So I think you can, to some extent, dissociate the obesity,
but then you still have to, the insulin cancer correlation isn't as strong as smoking either.
So you still have a lot to work with. And then there's the question that you brought up is,
I think this is what you're referring to, is the insulin actually the first prime step in the
process, the hyperinsulinemia, or is it a mutation that occurs for some other reason and allows the
cancer cell to take advantage of that hyperinsulinemia? Yeah, is the model basically that if you take
a two by two matrix where you have
chromosomal insult, yes or no, hyperinsulinemia, yes, no. So which one gets cancer? Is it only the
double positive? I mean, we would agree that the double negative almost assuredly does not,
and we would probably agree that the double positive does. The question is, what's happening
on the other corners? What's happening in the individual who has the chromosomal insult in the
absence of hyperinsulinemia and what's happening to the person without the chromosomal insult,
who is hyperinsulinemia? To me, those are the questions that matter a lot, and they matter a
lot for the sake of prevention. Now, the obviously, and this is the approach that I take
clinically, which is let's be overly aggressive and assume that both of those are sufficient.
Then you would say, well, you have to put yourself in the double negative box, which is avoid
hyperinsulinemia and any sign of metabolic ill health and do every single thing imaginable
to reduce the burden of DNA insult. You try to narrow yourself and confine yourself into this
very narrow box, and then you layer on a whole bunch of other things like really aggressive
screening and all this other stuff. That's what you would do if you don't have a choice.
If you're absent perfect information, you have to probably act more aggressively.
But I still think this question of which of the two positive, negative, negative,
positive squares, at least for me, I don't have a great understanding of those.
Both, I think there are examples and counter examples for both.
Yeah. No, I mean, I don't think anybody has a great answer for it at this point, but I do find,
you know, this is speculative, but one hypothesis is sort of that these
chromosomal insults occur by chance or for whatever reason. Eventually, you get one in this
PI3K pathway and the cell is now able to take advantage of that hyperinsulinemia.
But another speculative idea is that if you have hyperinsulinemia and sort of excessive glucose
metabolism, that it's actually going to be driving the chromosomal insult through creation
of reactive oxygen species in the mitochondria and that the hypermetabolism, as Craig Thompson
puts it, actually creates a way for the cell to mutagenize. So, I think that's probably part
of the story. And there's new research coming about how nutrients are actually, play a huge
role in epigenetics as well. So, it may be that there's just bad luck and mutation comes along
and then if the insulin is there, a cell takes advantage. And if it's not, maybe that microscopic
tumor never takes off. You know, a lot of people die with cancer rather than from cancer, as they
say. Maybe the immune system can kill these microscopic tumors if not for the insulin,
keeping the insulin really tells the cell to stay alive. And so, I don't think we have great answers
to these questions, but I think that if you just step back and look at the epidemiology, like
something has to be going on with nutrition because the cancer was so much more rare
prior to the shift to the Western diet. And it could be many different things, but
it all points to hyperinsulinemia. And it's a growth factor and cancer cells are covered
in insulin receptors. It just makes a lot of sense that this is really fundamental in one way
or another. I'll just say that the counterpoint is, you know, maybe that you just have bad luck
and get an AKT mutation, then the cell, you know, no longer needs insulin and can just get all the
glucose at once. And that's, you know, maybe true in some cancers, but as I understand it,
that even when you have these mutations in this PI3K, KTM, TARP pathway, that they're still insulin
dependent, just less dependent. So, you can imagine a scenario at least where keeping insulin
really low will help even if that chromosomal insult takes place and it makes the cell more
susceptible. You know, what about non-insulin requiring nutrients such as fructose? Rick
Johnson and Lou Cantley have both spoken about this. What, if anything, did you uncover about
the potential role of fructose in cancer? Yeah. That was one of the more surprising
parts of the story for me and humbling in a way as well. You know, a reminder to me, you know,
I was writing about Warburg who always believed too strongly in his own ideas and couldn't,
you know, accept that they may be wrong. And, you know, it's anytime you're writing a book that has
any kind of argument in it, you sort of fall into that trap and have to remember that, you know,
science changes and not everything's proven. So, I had decided, you know, early in my writing
process that I thought sugar, sucrose was a big part of this story. But my assumption was that
it was all by way of driving, you know, liver fat and insulin resistance and hyperinsulinemia.
And then in recent years, this work out of Cantley's lab and Richard Johnson's and has shown
that, you know, even independent of the effects on insulin, that fructose seems to drive, you know,
certain cancers that, you know, particularly in the colon that are able to get the fructose
and actually, you know, turns on, you know, through sort of a, an odd metabolism actually turns on the
Warburg effect and allows sort of ATP to go down and then glucose to flow in. But the surprising
part for me was that, you know, that could be disassociated with insulin. I had to step back
and say that, you know, maybe sugar is even worse than we thought and is sort of causing cancer in
two different ways in some cases. Yeah, that to me is the most interesting question. Still somewhat
unresolved, frankly, although I think Rick Johnson's work is among the most compelling I've
seen to disentangle that relationship of fructose independent of its caloric contribution.
And as you said, this is a mechanism that has an indirect effect on insulin, right? So fructose
metabolism when consumed in excess does in fact lead to insulin resistance, which by its very
definition leads to hyperinsulinemia. But the work you allude to in colonic cancer by Lou Cantley
actually posits that, you know, that it's the energetic issue in the cell that you alluded to
of the trans and Johnson as well. It's this lowering of ATP in the process of metabolizing
fructose. And it's that that ADP ATP sort of switch that can drive the hyper influx of glucose.
And that's not necessarily an insulin driven phenomenon. Yeah. Yeah. Now that, you know,
it's kind of odd for me in a way, it supported my hypothesis that sugar is at the center of the
story, but it sort of upended my idea of what the mechanism was. So, you know, there's still
a lot to learn, but I found, you know, Rick Johnson's whole discussion of this
absolutely fascinating. I listened to the podcast and when he was talking to you,
you know, part of it, you know, all the stuff we were talking about, you know, the turn to fermentation
of low oxygen environments, which, you know, again, I think you and I agree that that's maybe
not the whole story of some people think, but that it, the seesaw like relationship does exist. But
his example, which really fascinated me was that these naked mole rats, I don't know if you remember
this, but the end, they live in this low oxygen environment and they run a lot of Warburg
metabolism by converting glucose to fructose and then using the fructose to drive the Warburg
effect. It was really fascinating to me. What did you learn in this project that
you absolutely positively could have never predicted? I mean, you sort of alluded to the
fructose more than glucose issue here. Was there anything else that either historically or
scientifically completely caught you off guard and challenged what you thought you knew about
yourself or this body of work? Yeah. It's a good question. I think one of the things that really
struck me, and I think a lot of people who spend years researching and writing about Nazis end up
with a similar insight, but you sort of have to go through it to maybe realize it, is, you know,
I grew up Jewish and learning about the Holocaust and Nazis and in my mind, you know, they were
evil monsters and they were, but I never humanized them. And now I had to sort of look
at the personal stories of all these Nazis and not think of them as in an abstract,
you know, evil monstrous way, but understanding as human beings, how they went down this path and
how it happened progressively throughout the 30s and how it could be that somebody who, you know,
might in one context be a nice neighbor and friend and then, you know, go into the office and,
you know, work on documents that, you know, that need to, you know, millions of people ultimately
getting murdered, you know, just getting into the lives of these people and seeing that progression
and it really was chilling and eye-opening in a way to make me think that this wasn't an anomaly,
that this in theory, you know, it has happened elsewhere and in various forms and could happen
elsewhere. So it made me sort of much more politically attuned to certain extremist politics.
So that was part of it on a political level and, you know, on a personal level in terms of the
writing. It was such a daunting project for me. How many words is the book, Sam? I actually don't
even know. I think it's about 120,000 some words, but, you know, I didn't have the training in
biochemistry. I didn't speak German fluently and I really, you know, I didn't plan to write the
book. The publisher came to me and said, I saw your New York Times article. Do you want to do this?
And I hesitated and say yes right away because such a big project. But, you know, I think that
over the years, I sort of learned a lot about myself as a writer and sort of was able to
gradually, you know, trust myself more as a historian. And, you know, I think that I feel
more confident as a writer having completed this project. We'll see, you know, if I still feel that
way after somebody crashes the book. But for me, I felt like I was taking a big risk and that I made
it to the end of that project, you know, is very rewarding. It makes me feel confident about taking
on other stuff. As a writer, do you pay attention to what people say about your work or do you go
out of your way to avoid reviews and things like that? I go out of my way to avoid reviews. What's
fascinating to me is that even positive reviews, which, you know, I'm very grateful for,
but they also make me uncomfortable. Just the thought of anybody sort of passing judgment,
you know, on something that, you know, you work on so hard for so many years, it's just too much
to get a reaction to it in some ways. I'm incredibly grateful for the positive reviews and
it's been really rewarding to get some nice responses to the book on Twitter. But, you know,
I think there's going to be a New York Times review out soon. I'm not even sure I can read it, you know,
just I have the same thing with my student, you know, I teach and students provide, you know,
assessments of my teaching at the end of each semester. And I read them because I need to know
how to become a better professor, but it makes me deeply uncomfortable.
You know, I don't write book reviews anymore because it's just, you know, when somebody works
on something so hard for so many years, it's terrible to have to pass judgment on it.
You know, I'm kind of a softy, I guess. But how do you learn that? I mean, I can be totally
sympathetic to that. But is there a model where you let somebody else read the reviews and pass
on just the objective, you know, this is working, this is not working feedback? I'm asking,
honestly, for personal reasons, as I sort of think about how to digest
feedback in a forum that is actually very harsh. No, I mean, no, it's certainly I think it's
certainly true that if you don't read your views, you're not going to learn as much. But in a way,
it's too late at that point. You know, what I do is for, you know, before I finish the project,
I sent, you know, first and foremost, my editor who is wonderful, live right Dan Gerstle,
to give a shout out. But, you know, I also have a handful of trusted friends who
I send the manuscript to and get their feedback on. And, you know, certainly, that doesn't make
me uncomfortable because it's a different dynamic. It's not in public, it's in private. And there
are people that I trust. And I don't feel publicly shamed if they tell me it's awful. And, you know,
I can't get better unless I get their feedback. And, you know, I got tremendously valuable
feedback from those early readers. So, you know, I don't think there's a writer. I mean,
every writer I know does some form of that. And I think everybody should.
So, Sam, tell folks again, the name of the book.
The book is Ravenous, Otto Warburg, the Nazis and the search for the cancer diet connection.
All right. Well, Sam, thank you very much for taking the time,
so much time to sit down with me today and talk about this and share these insights with all the
folks that are everybody's interested in cancer. So, I think there was a lot here both in the
history of it and also the implication, which is potentially that metabolism plays a very important
role in cancer. It might not be entirely clear if it's the trigger, you know, if it's the spark,
if it's the oxygen, if it's the fuel, but it's in that mix. So, the more we can do reduce
hyperinsulinemia, improve our metabolism, reduce reactive oxygen species, all these things that
you've spoken about, presumably the better odds we have against the disease to which we've made
very little progress as you pointed out in the last few years. So, thank you, Sam.
Yeah, thank you so much. It was an honor to be on the show.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now, to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is,
nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes,
hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to
hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short
podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics,
and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up
on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only, does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about,
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
you