Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Bob. How are you, man? Looking pretty studious there in the library today.
Hey, Peter. Thanks very much. Yeah, just getting some reading in before the podcast.
Well, this is going to be a pretty good one because as you may recall about, I don't know,
four or five months ago, maybe longer, I was on a podcast with Tim Ferriss and I don't know how it
came up, but I do remember somehow it came up that we had spent a lot of time writing this series,
studying studies and God, that's been four years ago, I think. Yeah. But we didn't really have
something more digestible for folks on how to make sense of the ever-changing landscape of
scientific literature and in some ways how to distinguish between the signal and the noise of
the research news cycle. And I remember after that, Tim and I went out for dinner and he kept
pressing me on, well, what can I do to get better at this process? Are there newsletters I should be
subscribing to and things like that? And while I'm sure that there are, I didn't know what they were
off the top of my head. And so I think what we've done here, when I say we, I mean you,
what you have done here is aggregate all the questions that have come in over the past year,
basically, that pertain to understanding the structure of science. And I really, I don't know,
I looked through the questions last week and I was pretty excited. I think it's going to be a
sweet discussion and I hope this serves as an amazing primer for people to really understand
the process of scientific experiments and everything from how studies are published and
obviously what some of the limitations are. So anything else you want to add to that, Bob,
before we jump in? I agree. I think it's a fun topic. We get so many of these questions that we
end up, or at least I do, or to the website where we'll point readers to one of the parts
of the studying studies. But I think sometimes just talking about it and explaining it can help
a lot. So I think this will be really useful as far as like a question and answer session rather
than just reading a blog. Yeah. And I don't think this displaces that other stuff. I think we go
into probably more detail on some things there, but I also think we're going to cover things here
that aren't covered there. So depending on how you like to get your info, this could be fun. So
where do you want to start? So I think that we have, again, a lot of questions, but I think this
question gets to the core of I think what we're trying to do here, which is how can a user or a
person who has no scientific background better understand studies that they read in the news
or in the publications to know if the findings are solid or not, especially in today's age,
where you can easily see two studies that contradict each other. Coffee's good, coffee's bad. Eggs are
good, eggs are bad. So I thought we could run through a bunch of questions with the first one
that we got here is what is the process for a study to go from an idea to design and execution?
Yeah, it is a great question. I mean, in theory, it should start with a hypothesis. Good science
is generally hypothesis driven. So I think the cleanest way to think about that is to take the
position that there is no relationship between two phenomena. So we would call this sort of a null
hypothesis. So my hypothesis might be that drinking coffee makes your eyes turn darker. So I would have
to state that hypothesis and then I would have to frame it in a way that says my null hypothesis is
that when you drink coffee, your eyes do not change in color in any way, shape, or form. And that would
imply that the alternative hypothesis is that when you drink coffee, your eyes do change color. You can
already see, by the way, that there's nuance to this because am I specifying what color it changes
to? Does it get darker? Does it get lighter? Does it change to blue, green? Does it just get the darker
shade of whatever it is? But let's put that aside for a moment and just say that you will have this
null hypothesis and you will have this alternative hypothesis. And to be able to formulate that cleanly
is sort of the first step here. The second thing, of course, is to conduct an experimental design. How
are you going to test that hypothesis as we're going to talk about? A really, really elegant way
to test this is using a randomized controlled experiment. If it's possible to blind it, we'll
talk about what that means. But you'll have to decide, well, how long should we make people drink
coffee? How frequently should they drink coffee? How are we going to measure eye color? These are
the questions that come down to experimental design. You then have to determine a very important
variable, which is how many subjects will you have? And of course, that will depend on a number of
things, including how many arms you will have in this study. But it comes down to doing something
that's called a power analysis. And this is so important that we're going to spend some time
talking about it today, although I won't talk about it right now. If this study involves human
subjects or animal subjects, you will have to get something called an institutional review board to
approve the ethics of the study. So you'll have to get that IRB approval. You'll have to determine
what your primary and secondary outcomes are, get the protocol approved, develop a plan for
statistics, and then pre-register the study. All of these things happen before you do the study. And
of course, in parallel to this, you have to have funding. So those are kind of the steps that go
into doing an experimental study. And what we're going to talk about, I think, in a minute is that
there are some studies that are not experimental where some of these steps are obviously skipped.
Yeah. One of the questions we got was, what are the different types of studies out there? And
what do they mean? For example, an observational study versus a randomized controlled study. What
are the different types of studies? Yeah. So I mean, I think broadly speaking, you can break
studies into three categories. One would be observational studies, and we'll bifurcate those
or trifurcate those in a minute. Then you can have experimental studies, and then you can have
basically summations of and or reviews of and or analyses of studies of any type.
So let's kind of start at the bottom of that pyramid. And I think you actually have a figure
that I don't like very much, but I know it's- I was going to say, that was one of your favorites.
Yeah, I can't stand it. I'll tell you what I like about the figure. I like the color schema, because
my boys are so obsessed with rainbows that if I show them this figure, they're going to be really
happy. So let's pull up said rainbow figure. Okay, got it. Okay, so you can sort of see these
buckets here. And again, at the level of kind of talking about them, I think this makes sense. What
I don't agree with the pyramid for Bob is that it puts a hierarchy in place that suggests a meta
analysis is better than a randomized control trial, which is not necessarily true. But let's
just kind of go through what each of these things mean. So looking at the observational studies,
an individual case report is, look, I think the first or second paper I ever wrote in my life when
I was in medical school was an individual case report. It was a patient who had come into
clinic. This was when I was at the NIH, and this was a patient with metastatic melanoma, and their
calcium was sky high, dangerously high in fact. And obviously our first assumption was that this
patient had metastatic disease to their bone and that they were lysing bone and calcium was
leeching into their bloodstream. Turned out that wasn't the case at all. It turned out they had
something that had not been previously reported in patients with melanoma, which was they had
developed this parathyroid hormone related like hormone in response to their melanoma.
So this is a hormone that exists normally, but it doesn't exist in this format. And so their cancer
was causing them to have more of this hormone that was causing them to raise their calcium level.
It was interesting because it had never been reported before in the literature. And so I wrote
this up. This was an individual case report. Is there any value in that? Sure. There's some value
in that. The next time a patient with melanoma shows up to clinic and their calcium is sky high
and someone goes to the literature to search for it, they'll see that report and it will hopefully
save them time in getting to the diagnosis. So your mentor and friend, Steve Rosenberg,
I think of him when I think of individual case reports where I think if you listen to the podcast,
he talks about this, but a lot of what motivated him early on, I think we're just a couple of
cases in it. I think it gets back to that first question too about the process for a study to go
to an idea to design to execution, which is to have a hypothesis, you need to make an observation.
So you make an observation, you say, hmm, that's strange. And I think that that's what individual
case reports can represent sometimes is this is an interesting observation. It's hypothesis
generating for the most part, but it really, it might kickstart a larger trial or it might
kickstart a career. You never know. Yeah, exactly. Now, of course, it's not going to be
generalizable, right? I can't make any statement about the frequency of this in the broader subset
of patients. And obviously, I can't make any comment about any intervention that may or may not
change the outcome of this. So that gets us to our next thing, which is a case series
or set of studies. So here you're basically doing the same sort of thing, but in plural, effectively.
So you wouldn't just look at one patient, you would say, well, I've now been looking back at my
clinical practice and I've had 27 patients over the last 40 years that have demonstrated this very
unusual finding. And another example of this going back to the Steve Rosenberg case would be
one could write a paper that looks at all spontaneous regressions of cancer.
Well, there's obviously been a number of them. They're infrequent. In fact, they're exceedingly
rare, but there are certainly enough of them that one could write a case series. So now let's
consider cohort studies. So cohort studies are larger studies and they can be retrospective or
they can be prospective. So I'll give you an example of both. So a retrospective observational
cohort study would be like, let's go back and look at all the people who have used saunas for the last
10 years and look at how they're doing today relative to people who didn't use saunas over
the last 10 years. So it's retrospective. We're looking backwards. It's observational. We're not
doing anything, right? We're not telling these people to do this or telling those people to do
that. And the hope when you do this is that you're going to see some sort of pattern. Undoubtedly,
you will see a pattern. Of course, the question is, will you be able to establish causality in
that pattern? Cohort studies can just as easily, although more time-consumingly, be prospective.
So you could say, I want to follow people over the next five years, 10 years who use saunas and
compare them to a similar number of people who don't. And now in a forward-looking fashion,
we're going to be examining the other behaviors of these people and ultimately what their outcomes
are. Do they have different rates of death, heart disease, cancer, Alzheimer's disease,
other metrics of health that we might be interested in? Again, we're not intervening.
There's not an experiment per se. We're just observing, but now we're doing it as we march
forward through time. Okay. So this brings us to the next layer of this pyramid, which are the
experimental studies. And again, we divide these into randomized versus non-randomized. And of
course, this idea of randomization is going to be a very important one as we go through this.
So a non-randomized trial sometimes gets referred to as an open label trial where you take two groups
of people and you give one of them a treatment and you give the other one either a placebo or
a different treatment, but you don't randomize them. There's a reason that they're in that group.
So you might say, we want to study the effect of a certain antibiotic on a person that comes in the
ER and we're going to take all the people that come in who look a certain way, maybe they have
a fever of a certain level or a white blood cell count of a certain level, and we're going to give
them the antibiotic and the people who come in, but they don't have those exact signs or symptoms,
we're going to not give an antibiotic to and we're going to follow them. That's kind of a lame example.
You could do the same sort of thing with surgical interventions. We're going to try to ask the
question, is surgery better than antibiotics for appendicitis or suspected appendicitis?
But we don't randomize the people to the choice. There's some other factor that is going to
determine whether or not we do that. And as you can see, that's going to have a lot of limitations
because presumably there's a reason you're making that decision and that reason will undoubtedly
introduce bias. So of course, the gold standard that we always talk about is a randomized control
trial where whatever question you want to study, you study it, but you attempt to take all bias
out of it by randomly assigning people into the treatment groups, the two or more treatment groups.
We'll talk about things like blinding later because you can obviously get into more and more
rigor when you do this. But before we leave the kind of experimental side, anything you want to
add to that, Bob? I would add some non-randomized controlled trials, maybe another example. I'm trying
to think of another example, which is you have patients maybe making a decision beforehand,
which we'll get into selection bias. But people might want to go on a statin, let's say, and then
you give them a choice. And the other ones might want to go on some other drug like azetimibe.
And they're basically selecting themselves into two groups, but you could compare those two groups
and see how they do, but it hasn't been randomized. There's a lot of bias that can go into that. There
could be a lot of reasons why one group is selecting a particular treatment over the other.
And so that's what I think when we get to randomized trials that it shows the power
of randomization. Yeah, exactly. We don't need to go back to the figure, but people might recall
that at the top of that pyramid was systemic reviews and meta-analyses. Let's just talk about
meta-analyses since they are probably the most powerful. So this is a statistical technique
where you can combine data from multiple studies that are attempting to look at the same question,
basically. So each study gets a relative weighting. And the weighting of a study is
sort of a function of its precision. It depends a little bit on sample size,
other events in the study. Larger studies, which have smaller standard errors, are given more weight
than smaller studies with larger standard errors, for example. A very common way that these...
You'll know you're looking at a meta-analysis. We should have had a figure for this, but
I'll describe it the best I can. They usually have a figure somewhere in there that will show
across rows all of the studies. So let's say there's 10 studies included in the meta-analysis.
And then they'll have the hazard ratios for each of the studies. So they'll represent them usually
as little triangles. So the triangle will represent the 95 percent confidence interval
of what the hazard ratio is, which we'll talk about a hazard ratio, but it's
basically a marker of the risk. And you'll see all 10 studies, and then they'll show you the final
summation of them at the bottom, which of course you wouldn't be able to deduce looking at the
figure, but it takes into account that mathematical weighting. So on the surface, meta-analyses seem
really, really great, right? Because if one randomized trial is good, 10 must be better.
But again, and I know I've said this before probably three or four times over the past few
years on the podcast, but as James Yang, one of the smartest people I ever met when I was
both a student and fellow at NCI, once said during a journal club about a meta-analysis
that was being presented, he said something to the effect of a thousand sows ears makes not a
pearl necklace. And that's just an eloquent way to say that garbage in, garbage out, right? So
if you do a meta-analysis of a bunch of garbage studies, you get a garbage meta-analysis. So
it can't clean garbage. It simply can aggregate it. So a meta-analysis of great randomized control
trials will produce a great meta-analysis. So I'm sure they try to control for garbage,
the researchers and the investigators, but I think to your point with the pearl necklace,
imagine if you had say 10 trials and nine of them are garbage. One of them is really good,
really rigorous randomized controlled trial. And you're looking at the top of the pyramid and
you're saying, well, meta-analysis is the best. We should be looking at this meta-analysis.
Meanwhile, you've got that one randomized controlled trial that actually is worth its
salt. It's rigorous, et cetera, that I would say if you had the option, I think you probably would
rely more on that one randomized controlled trial, which is lower on the pyramid. So I think that's
probably, I think you've told me one of your hang ups with the pyramid because it's not
necessarily top of the pyramid is going to be some meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials.
That's right. Yeah. And so I don't want to suggest meta-analyses are not great. What I want to suggest
is you can't just take a meta-analysis as gospel without actually looking at each study. You don't
get a pass at examining each of the constitutive studies within a meta-analysis is really the point
I think we want to make here. Yeah. There's one thing in here that isn't represented, but we had
a few questions about it, I think a couple. People were asking about what's the difference between a
phase three and a phase two or a phase one clinical trial? Do you know what's going on there?
Yes. And these are great questions. So here we're talking about human clinical trials and this
phraseology is used by the FDA here in the United States. And typically, the world does
tend to follow and lock step, but not always with kind of the FDA's process. So if you go way, way,
way back, you have an interesting idea. You have a drug that you think is or a molecule that you
think will have some benefit. Let's think of it as a cancer therapeutic. And you've done some
interesting experiments in animals and you maybe started with some mice and you went up to some
rats and maybe even you've done something in primates. And now you're really sort of committed
to this as the success of this and the safety of this in animals looks good. So it's both safe
and efficacious in animals and you now decide you want to foray into the human space. Well,
the first thing you have to do is file for something called an IND, an investigational
new drug application. So after you do all of this preclinical work, you have to file this IND with
the FDA and that basically sets your intention of testing this as a drug in humans. And the first
phase of that, which is called phase one is geared specifically to dose escalate this drug
from a very, very low level to determine what the toxicity is across a range of doses that
will hopefully have efficacy. So these are typically very small studies, usually less
than a hundred people and they're typically done in cohorts. So you might say, well, the first,
you know, 12 people are going to be at 0.1 milligrams per kilogram. And assuming we see no
adverse effects there, we'll go up to 0.15 milligrams per kilogram for the next 12 people.
And if we have no issues there, we'll escalate it to 0.25. Now you'll notice, Bob, I said nothing
in there about does the drug work, right? So these are going to be patients with cancer. If this is
a drug that's being sought as a treatment for colon cancer, these are going to be patients that
all have colon cancer. They're often going to be patients who have metastatic colon cancer,
right? So these are going to be patients who have progressed through all other standard treatments
and who are basically saying, look, sign me up for this clinical trial. I realize that this first
phase is not going to be necessarily giving me a high enough dose that I could experience a benefit
and that you're really only looking to make sure that this drug doesn't hurt me,
but nevertheless, I want to participate in this trial. So if the drug gets through phase one
safely, then it goes to phase two. And the goal of phase two is to continue to evaluate for safety,
but also to start to look for efficacy. But this is done in an open label fashion. What that means
is they're not randomizing patients to one drug versus the other typically. They can, but usually
it's now we think we know one or two doses that are going to produce efficacy. They were deemed
safe in the phase one. We're now going to take patients and give them this drug and look for an
effect. And a lot of times if there's no control arm in the study, you're going to compare to the
natural history. So let's assume that we know that patients with metastatic colon cancer have,
on standard of care, have, you know, immediate survival of X months. Well, we're going to give
these patients this drug and see if that extends it anymore. And of course you could do this with
a control arm, but now it adds the number of patients to the study. So again, typically very
small studies can be, you know, in the 20, 30, 40, 50 range, maybe up to a few hundred people.
And that one Peter, I think is a probably a good example of if you have the non-randomization,
this might be a case where say it's an immunotherapy and people know about the
immunotherapy and it's been really effective for a particular gets approved for a particular cancer,
let's say. And there are a lot of people that know about it and there are cancer patients that
know about it and they want to get that treatment, but it's not approved. If they're talking to their
doctor, they, or maybe they're online, they might enroll in one of these trials because they really
want to try the drug and maybe they, you know, they might believe in it more than some other
treatment. Yeah. Yeah. There are lots of things that can introduce bias to a phase two if it does
not have randomization. Again, the goal would be to still randomize in phase two because you really
do want to tease out efficacy. So if a study, if a compound succeeds in phase two, which means
it continues to show no significant adverse safety effects, which by the way, it doesn't mean it
doesn't have side effects, right? Every treatment has side effects. It's just that it doesn't have
side effects that are deemed unacceptable for the risk profile of the patient and it shows
efficacy. So really you have to have these two things. You then proceed to phase three
and here a phase three is a really rigorous trial. This is a huge step up. It's typically a
log step up in the number of patients. So you'd, you know, you're talking potentially thousands
of patients here. Um, and this is absolutely a placebo controlled trial or not necessarily
placebo, but it can be sort of standard of care versus standard of care plus this new agent,
but it is randomized whenever possible. It is blinded and with drugs, that's always possible.
And these are typically longer studies. Uh, so, so now because you have so much more sample size,
you're going to potentially pick up side effects that weren't there in the first place. And of
course now you really have that gold standard for measuring efficacy. And it's on the basis of the
phase one phase two and mostly phase three data that a drug will get approved or not approved
for broad use, which leads to a fourth phase, which is a post-marketing study. So phase four
studies take place after the drug has been approved and they're used to basically get
additional information because once a drug is approved, you now have more people taking it.
And they may also be using this to look at other indications for the drug. So we talked about this
recently, right? A phase four trial, um, with semaglutide being used to look at obesity, uh,
versus its original phase three trials, which were looking at diabetes. So kind of, that's a,
the drug's already been approved. This study isn't being done to ask the questions. Should
semaglutide be on the market? No, it's on the market. It's basically expanding the indication
for semaglutide in this case, so that insurance companies would actually pay for it for a new
indication. But given the size and the number of these studies, you're also looking for, hey,
is there another side effect here that we've missed in the phase three? Right. And it might be the,
the particular population that might have a different risk profile so that you might,
you might have a different threshold. That's right. Because you're not doing this in patients
with type two diabetes. You're doing this in patients who explicitly don't have diabetes,
but have obesity. Ah, you know, different patients. Kind of, we're going to see something
different here. So yeah. So, um, anyway, that's, that's the, that's the long and short of phases
one, two, three, and four. Okay. So going back to observational studies, are there any things that
you look for in particular that, that will increase or decrease your confidence in it,
whether the bits of pearl necklace or, or garbage. Thank you for listening to today's sneak peek
AMA episode of the drive. If you're interested in hearing the complete version of this AMA,
you'll want to become a member. We created the membership program to bring you more in-depth
exclusive content without relying on paid ads. Membership benefits are many and beyond the
complete episodes of the AMA each month, they include the following ridiculously comprehensive
podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, and thing we discuss on each episode of
the drive access to our private podcast feed, the quality is which were a super short podcast,
typically less than five minutes released every Tuesday through Friday, which highlight the best
questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of the drive. This is particularly
important for those of you who haven't heard all of the back episodes, it becomes a great way to go
back and filter and decide which ones you want to listen to in detail, really steep discount codes
for products I use and believe in, but for which I don't get paid to endorse and benefits that we
continue to add over time. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Lastly, if you're already a member,
but you're hearing this, it means you haven't downloaded our member only podcast feed where
you can get the full access to the AMA and you don't have to listen to this. You can download
that at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash members. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.