Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Paul, amazing to be back here in person with you. It's been way too long. And the only thing I miss,
well not the only thing, but one of the things I miss the most about going to New York frequently
was that we got to see each other constantly. And now that we don't really travel that much.
It's mostly phone calls, but we got to spend so much time together and I do miss that too. And
it's just really wonderful to see you. And I so appreciate you having me here and spending
time with you and family. It's wonderful. Well, I'm going to start to talk about your book,
of course. But I think even though a lot of people have heard you on the podcast before,
because we did, we sat down probably three years ago, I'd probably take the assumption here that
a lot of people are also coming to you and hearing about you here for the first time. So let's tell
people a little bit about who you are. What's your day job? What is it you do?
Sure. I'm trained as a psychiatrist and a big part of my day job is being a clinical psychiatrist.
I also do some consulting work along the lines of understanding brain function and how brain
function can impact us in personal or professional settings. But by and large, my work is really
grounded in the clinical. And I do have a clinic, about 15 really great people I work side by side
with in trying to meet the needs of people who bring us whatever mental health question there
may be, which sometimes is clinical care and sometimes is just trying to understand themselves
and the world around them better. And when is it in your journey of medical school and prior
that you sort of had this inkling that you were interested in mental health?
Yeah, I think around the time in the clinical rotation part of medical school, probably into
the last year when I realized that you could really be a doctor and understand medical things
and how they impact people and really kind of be grounded in that aspect of practicing medicine,
but also trying to understand people's experiences of life. What people think and feel as they're
going through their day and that you could combine these two things and then be grounded
to all the things one learns about life, just going through it and really help people in that
way. And that just had such tremendous appeal as a sort of widely encompassing way of approaching,
trying to be of help. You of course didn't come to medical school in a typical way. You were not
a pre-med, you had been out and working for four years or so before medical school if not more.
So what were you doing first of all before you made this decision to go to medical school?
I worked for a consulting firm in New York and really enjoyed a lot of aspects of the work,
the business and the financial aspects of it. But there was just something I kind of wanted
more. I wanted to know more and learn more and be more directly involved with people. And it was
kind of a nebulous sort of theoretical set of thoughts, but it led to medical school to try
and learn more and explore like what might that be able to bring.
So we've spoken about this obviously before, you write about it in the book. There are a
handful of events that occurred during your upbringing, your adolescence that I think
ultimately shaped how you now think about this thing called trauma. You want to talk about some
of those things? Sure. I had a really interesting course of life in the sense that in kind of the
first half of my life, there weren't major traumas. So I was fortunate to have a stable
family system around me and to develop a pretty stable sense of self, which is much easier to
do if there aren't big traumas. And then in the second half of my life, there started to be some
very major traumas. And to experience the traumas after having developed an orientation to myself
and to the world that had been free of them was very, very striking. I think it put me in a place
to see, even though I didn't completely understand them, but like what was going on in me and what
was changing in me and what were the impacts of the trauma on me in a way that was distressing and
surprising. And I think that's also part of what led me towards mental health. We're seeing like,
wow, these things are happening in me. And then there's a set of thoughts that come from that of
like, well, what happens if you experience these traumas and you don't have the fortune to have a
good fortune ever stable family system around you and have developed a strong sense of self? Because
my sense of self was really thrown off by the traumas that happened, even though I had gotten
through those formative stages without that. How old were you when your brother committed
suicide? So I would be 24, 24 at the time that he committed suicide. And at the risk of asking
an obvious or maybe not so obvious question, how shocked were you at that time? Because you hear
these tragedies of someone commit suicide and everybody around says, well, it was just a matter
of time. This almost seemed inevitable. And then you hear these other stories where everybody around
is in such disbelief. So they're really coping with not just the loss, but the feeling blindsided
and guilty and how do we see this? And so where on that spectrum were you and I guess by extension,
your family? In the disbelief, in the shock and disbelief side of the spectrum, which I think
a lot of families that go through this, if one stood from the outside and looked at the development
of events, and what was really going on and what was changing in my brother, he had had a huge trauma
a few years before where he had a very significant medical issue that had come out of the blue and
was life threatening and really shook his sense of self. And he was very different after that in
ways that I could see in some sense, but not fully understand. So I think from the outside,
one probably could have seen that there were these changes in him that would have meant it
was not necessarily that shocking. But from the inside, we often don't see that or we have our
mechanisms of denial or of rationalization that tell us like, no, things are pretty okay when
really they weren't. And then the shock of it happening and then of realizing, oh, like,
what could I have seen? Would I have seen? I think it contributes to a lot of the guilt and the shame
that people feel. It's a bad combination, an immense amount of shock. And then immediately
thereafter, a sense of guilt and responsibility and also a sense that if there haven't been big
traumas that, oh, like they don't happen, right? Like, that's not something that happens to me or
happens to us. And I think we can get into that mindset because it sort of psychologically
protects us a little bit, but it can make the shock of a trauma like that in a sense all the
more difficult because we start to feel cursed or unworthy or like there's some mark of stigma
that I think is just very, very frightening. How did your other brother, your parents cope
with this and how did you talk about it with them or what was discussed and how did you all
move on in the immediate aftermath of that? I think my other brother and I were sort of built
in somewhat the same way of like kind of continuing to persevere and trying to find
something new that can make life feel better, which often means working toward achievements,
applying ourselves, right? Which can be quite a good defense against trauma. I think in my
parents, it was a little different. My father is a morse of outgoing, gregarious person and was able
to fall into a social network that was really supportive of him. Whereas my mother who has
passed away was more of a private person, less socially connected and I think ultimately
suffered from a lot of depression without her or us really understanding it. And I think that's
part of what pushes so strongly towards my interest in trauma is the realization of like
all the things we didn't understand or understood enough to know weren't good but didn't have the
words or the understanding to really talk about it and to talk about like what it happened and
what it meant and the changes to all of us that we don't have a ready lexicon, right? Or a ready
environment to be able to talk about things and then people at times sort of retreat into themselves
and then the trauma stays very, very immediate even though that immediacy can play out over years
and years. So I think we were very ill-equipped like I think most people, we were ill-equipped
to handle a massive trauma and its impact upon all of us individually let alone the greater
complexity of all of us as a family. Is it more common that in a situation like that where a child
commits suicide and the parents and siblings are left picking up the pieces that very little is
spoken explicitly? I mean, I think about the stories in my life of people I grew up with for
whom suicide was an issue. So I had a girlfriend in college whose mom committed suicide, had a very
close friend in high school whose dad committed suicide, had another girlfriend in high school
whose dad committed suicide. And one of these had a very tragic outcome. The one there was a friend
whose dad committed suicide, he later committed suicide. And that was an example of where I
thought to myself and it's something I felt very guilty about because I was in college and my mom
called me to tell me he wasn't doing well. And it was in April and it was during finals and she said,
and his dad had committed suicide two years earlier and she said, look, he's really,
just doesn't seem like he's doing well. And I said, well, to this day, I just feel so ashamed over
this. I said, I'm going to be home in like three weeks. I'll connect with him then. But at that
moment in my life, nothing seemed more important than graduating first in my class and anything
that was going to stand in the way of that was, I couldn't go home for a weekend at my mom's
request. And of course, by the time I got home, it was too late. He was dead. And I just wondered,
like, it's so obvious and yet I did nothing. What was talked about? What else was being done?
So not to dwell on this too much, but I'm just curious how much you remember in the months after
your brother's death, was there a time where you sat around the kitchen table and said, boy,
it would really be great if we had a therapist here that could help us process what's going on?
Or after the funeral, was it sort of like, nope, we're all kind of going to do our own mechanism
of coping? I mean, there was some discussion about it and I think partly because maybe the
generation, right? I mean, I hadn't been to medical school yet, so I had no knowledge of anything,
but I'm maybe a little more inclined to want to talk about things. I could tell, like, we all
seem not to be doing well, but I didn't know the words to put to it. I mean, we don't in a sense
give ourselves permission to have words of immensity, right? Of impact, of, oh, my whole
existence feels different, right? Like, we don't quite know or feel a sense of permission to say
those things. And then often the reflexive nature of shame, right, causes us to go inside.
And I think that's a primary point that I wish to make about trauma is that there is a reflexive
shame that comes of being traumatized, right? The same shame we see if someone is assaulted and
then presents talking about the assault through the lens of their shame that it happened, right?
These powerful stories that reinforce the reflexive nature of a sense of shame that drives us
inward. So we don't have the words for it, and we feel very, very bad about it. Even your own,
you know, even the trauma that you felt as a result of not going home. Like you say,
oh, it's so obvious, but it's obvious only in retrospect, right? At the time, it was not
obvious, right? Because those words of desperation and of immensity were not being used, right? And
we sit within a social context around us that in a sense normalizes not really talking about it in
those big words or the words of like, everything has changed and I don't know what to do about
that or what that means. And, you know, then we kind of move forward as best we can, but we're sort
of limping forward without really talking about the things that matter, which really starts with
how differently we feel about ourselves. That I think we all felt a sense of shame and a sense
of responsibility of what should I have seen? What should I have done? And, you know, he was
living at home at the time. So for my parents, the thought of, you know, their thought of how
they could have, would have, should have, right? Seen something, known something, right? That sense
of shame drives everyone inside. And now we're trying to communicate and we don't have the words
anyway, but we're like a muffle. They're trying to communicate, you know, while being sort of
glogged or all of it. And we don't know, like, I don't know the words to say, and I'm driven inside
too. And then I think the things that we do often fail to give us what we need. And then you do see
that cascade of trauma where one suicide, you know, follows upon the initial suicide or the
people around the person feel so guilty and ashamed that they, their lives had in different
directions. You know, I think my mother became depressed and more isolative and it really changed
the course of her subsequent life in a way they think was very negative without any of us really
knowing how do we understand this and what do we do about it? And I think that's among the biggest
aspects I'm fighting against of saying, like, look, we need to be able to talk about these things.
Like what's more important and what's more worth the time and effort to put the right words of
understanding to, then what happens inside of us after trauma. So you were living in New York,
obviously at the time, I'm guessing this was probably a very significant factor in your decision
to kind of take an orthogonal turn in your career towards medicine. Yes. But it's interesting that
it turned you to medicine, but not necessarily to psychiatry immediately. That it was, you know,
it would take a few years within medical school to realize that psychiatry became the vehicle
through which you wanted to help someone. I mean, everybody goes to medicine for the same reason.
Generally speaking, everybody has some desire to help in one way or another. And then of
course the purpose of medical school is to figure out the avenue in which you want to do that. What
other thoughts did you have as you went to medicine as it pertained to your brother or
were there other factors that shaped that as well? Yeah. I see in retrospect in myself what I often
have seen in my clinical work over these past 20 years, which is, there's a sort of bifurcation
often after big trauma. And, you know, I had wanted to serve other things in my life before
my brother's death. I wasn't completely happy with my career and I thought, well, maybe I want more
education. And I had a lot of thoughts about that. And the idea of doing those things was really
based on some sense of faith and confidence in myself. They're like, Hey, I could go do that. I
could apply myself. I could learn new things. I could take a different path and figure it out.
Right. But after Jonathan's death, there was a bifurcation where I start to feel very differently
about myself, to feel incompetent, right? To feel incapable. I mean, how could I even hope to take
care of myself if I couldn't be a brother to my own brother, right? And my thoughts about myself
changed in this way that I now I write about in the book and I think about and talk about a lot,
which was sort of forgetting that I had a sense of confidence in myself, right? And, you know,
I was going in a negative direction of becoming less healthy and drinking too much and just
wallowing in my own unhappiness through a sense of guilt and shame over what had happened. And
and it really came to a point of realizing like this is not going well, right? And I'm sort of
forgetting who I have always thought I was, right? And I got a little bit of therapy, which was a very
a kind of wild thing to do. Like, you know, no one went to therapy, right? And there was a sense
of stigma even around needing mental health help after my brother's suicide, right? But even in
that little bit of therapy, it helped me ground again to like, like, no, I don't actually feel
differently about myself. And if anything, then I felt more of a drive. Like I want to go do this
good thing. And yes, it was a drive to help people, but it was really based in a drive of self that
am I going to take care of myself in a way that says, if you're not happy and you want more of
your life, right? In the way that you see it, are you going to go do that, right? And that's where I
think helping ourselves and helping others kind of comes together. I mean, if I had no confidence
in myself, that I could guide my own life or be worth having in anyone else's life, right? How
would I go off and do something to help other people? And I think that's often what we see after
tragedy is, you know, in a very seductive and evil way, the consequences of trauma beckon us
to limit our horizons, to see ourselves in a different and very negative way, which leads to
bad things, right? It leads to depression, at least to panic attacks, it leads to substance abuse.
It just, it leads to not being who we want to be, right? And often juxtaposed to that is,
is seeing the trauma through a lens that makes us redoubled in wanting to be who we can be.
And our understanding of trauma, whether it gets the best of us and the guilt and shame wins the
day and the changes to our memories of who we think we are, is it going to be that or are we
going to be lodged into life in a way that lets us move forward? And I was very fortunate to have
to have gone the good path, right? Instead of where it could have led me. And going to medical
school was, although, yes, I wanted to help people, you know, it was about me and my sense of
confidence in myself that ultimately wasn't taken away by my brother's suicide, but man really
could have been. So when you think back to your residency, you stayed at Stanford after med school
for the first part of your residency before going to Harvard. You think back to those first couple
of years, what stands out in terms of what you learned and how one teaches psychiatry? Because
in some ways it strikes me as a more difficult discipline to teach than say surgery. You know,
in many ways, if I think back to my residency, it was, you know, there's a knowledge base you have
to glean and then there's a technical set of things you have to be able to do and they're
relatively easy to mirror. But at least from my vantage point, teaching somebody how to
make a psychiatric diagnosis might be less challenging than teaching somebody how to
talk to someone and elicit information that would allow you to make that diagnosis or more
importantly, communicate with a person in a way to help them. In other words, using words
seems harder than using a needle and suture. So what is the process of education in a psychiatric
residency program? There's lots of learning of facts, right? Of course, around neurobiology
and around medicines and around different modalities of therapy. So I think in that way
it's probably similar to other fields of endeavor. But then there are the less tangible aspects
that are the most important, right? Like how do you establish rapport, right? How do you really be
present with someone? And I think that's where the training in the field, I think across the board,
often fails us. And I think part of that is sort of the world, the society we live in in the world
of modern medicine. I was very, very struck and I can continue to be over these past 20 years,
so much of what I learned, say as a second year psychiatry resident, I think we should be teaching
people in elementary school, right? And I really do mean that about like just how we respond to
the world around us, right? Even the idea that bullying comes from a sense of shame in the person
doing the bullying and then creates a sense of shame and inadequacy in the person on the receiving
end, right? And how does this all work in our brains, right? And how the logic and emotion clash
in our brains and emotion wins over logic, yet we're taught that we're logical creatures, right?
Things like that, I was in some sense actually quite incensed at a whole education process
that doesn't prepare us to like live life by telling us the basics of what goes on
in our brains, right? So I was very struck by that and also struck that as I was learning it,
it wasn't necessarily being directly applied in the field as mental health has tried to kind of
fit itself in with the rest of medicine, it wants to have very clear diagnostic paradigm. So this
trend away from describing someone in a narrative, you say, well, how would you diagnose that person?
Right? You know, years ago, it would be in a narrative, you know, you would talk about who
that person was and in at least a couple of paragraphs, right? And that's by and large
gotten reduced to a number, right? And in trying to regiment itself in a way that I think is
overly rigid and serves the field's interest and desire to integrate with the rest of medicine,
we start losing the truth of really sitting with people and being present with people.
And a lot of what I learned about how to be a psychiatrist was about boundaries with other
people, right? Which do in many cases make sense, but the boundaries were put forth in a way that
was often about eliminating the realness of presence with someone. And I think that's the
part that maybe is the intangible or the harder aspect of the field that I think doesn't really
have to be that way, right? If we realize that we're going to help people through understanding,
through really being with someone and trying to understand their experience. And of course,
having it be about the other person, but being a real person with them, right? That I did find in
my training process, but I didn't find in the field, which is largely moving towards these
brief appointments and just giving people medicines instead of trying to understand what's going on
with them. A lot of what I often describe as polishing the hood, when it's very clear there's
something going on in the engine, right? And while I learned a great deal and I learned from
some wonderful people who role modeled for me how to be with people you were trying to help,
there was also a great deal of disappointment with a field that often in its training and its
interaction with patients ignored the crucial point of realness of the experience of the other person.
I want to think about kind of the differences between these two programs you trained in,
because you did half of your training at Stanford and half at Harvard, which are
generally regarded as two of the finest psychiatry training programs in the country,
but they have a very different method of training. So what did you find as you moved across the
country for the second half of your training and how did that impact the way you practice today?
Because in some ways you have a luxury of having seen two very different approaches to psychiatry,
more sort of biologic and a more clinical, more of a sort of Freudian view versus a more,
I don't know how the way you would describe the one at Stanford, but it seems to me more of a
neurobiology view. Yes. Both of which strike me as having huge benefits if they can be integrated.
Yes. Was it received that way by you? I think I didn't understand,
it's certainly not at the beginning because Stanford is so neurobiology based. So the medical
and neurobiological approach to psychiatry is just really among the finest points of that program.
And I was lucky to learn a lot of neurobiology, neurochemistry, function of medicines,
aspects of the different parts of our brain and how they communicate amongst one another
to generate our perception of reality. And at times the problems that can afflict us,
I learned a lot about that. But I think I didn't realize how little I was learning of the psychology
of being a psychiatrist, of the unconscious motivations in us, of this rich history of
understanding human beings that is so tremendously important to being able to help people.
And it was only when I got to Harvard and Dr. Marian Batarac
was a very good person. And I think that's a lot of what I really needed to know. And then the way
how do you put the rubber to the road of that is by being a real person with the person that you're
trying to help, which I think is the way I approach the field and then the people that I work with,
we approach the field the same way. But we're really the instrument through which all of that
comes and hopefully helps somebody. So that maybe is in one's personality or where you just
realize that when I'm being more rigid in a certain way, I'm less helpful. And if I'm less
that way in a more existential therapy approach to realness with a person, then I can use all of
what I've learned, the neurobiological and the psychological, to really make a difference to
someone. And I think that I figured out through practice and through learning what really helps
one, just like I found my way to trauma. I didn't decide, I'm going to be a trauma person. I'm going
to write a trauma book. I saw it was undergirding a very, very high percentage of everything that
I was trying to treat. So the things like that, I think we learned by trying to apply what we know.
And I ended up being very fortunate to have had the brain biology knowledge and the psychological
knowledge, although it was a little bit distressing to realize when I got to Harvard, how little I
knew. And I probably wouldn't have known how little I knew, right? Unless I had had that experience
that really exposed that. So when was the first edition of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual
published? I don't know where this fits in the evolution and history of psychiatry.
1948, somewhere in the late 1940s, I think 1948, but in that range.
And as you alluded to earlier, the DSM as it's abbreviated is really, at least in part,
a way to catalog and create crisp diagnoses around psychiatric illness, correct?
That's what it has evolved to. In the initial versions of the DSM, it was describing in a sense,
the phenomenology of like, what is this particular diagnosis like? What are the aspects of it? What's
felt or experienced by the person and what's seen from the outside? And then there were sort
of clusters of symptoms that would then lead one to think that that diagnosis fits, right?
Which acknowledges, it says the unique aspects of human beings, that if we get too rigid about that,
right, we start serving in a sense, the manual, right? Instead of the person. And in many ways,
the DSM evolved as a way of allowing for research criteria to say, okay, we want to be
calling a diagnosis sort of the same thing if we're going to communicate among clinicians and do
research. But in my very strong opinion, that has come to a place that now is so overly rigid that
you now you have this very, very thick book that could give everyone multiple diagnoses, right?
Because it's kind of designed to do that. And then come up with a number that justifies the 15-minute
appointment, right? In which the person has no hope of actually being understood in any way,
because you can't do that in 15 minutes, right? And we're at the DSM-5 right now, correct? We're
in the fifth generation of this manual, which seems to get updated about every 15 or 20 years.
Yes, it's the fifth generation, there are technical revisions in between, but it's really
evolved to something that I think is so rigid that it in many ways works against the clinical
care that we're trying to achieve. And again, I'm all for criteria and being able to have
descriptive language and research criteria. But we've gotten to the point where it often gets
called like a Bible, right? Which I think is like a very unfortunate word to use in many
ways. It implies that there's something in that book that actually tells you what mental health
problems are and what they are not. And some of the criteria really make no sense. So for example,
someone who has sort of vicarious trauma that they're experiencing, but not in an occupational
framework, doesn't meet criteria for a PTSD diagnosis, which has come to mean like everything
trauma. So if you have trauma that's real or legitimate, you have PTSD. And if not, you don't,
right? Like this clue makes no sense, but the field often views it that way and then applies
criteria that are not the be-all and end-all of the human experience, and then becomes very,
very rigid in a way that I think trivializes often what's going on with someone and trend
towards that symbolism of capturing everything in a number as opposed to in a human experience.
And I think we've gone so far away from the realness of human experience and how to sit
with a person and be helpful that the field has in many, many ways let itself very, very far
astray. And I think that the evolution of the DSM is both a driving cause of that and also
a resultant symptom of that too. So outside of post-traumatic stress disorder, PTSD,
how often does the word trauma appear in the DSM-5? Well, it appears in other places, but it
doesn't appear in a foundational way, right? Because if the book is descriptive, then the book
is looking to take an inventory of signs and symptoms, right? It's not looking at causality,
right? And that is a problem, right? Because so much of the depression that I see,
so much of the anxiety spectrum disorders, obsessive compulsive disorder, for example,
abuse of substances and addiction or alcoholism, right, is undergirded by trauma, right? And trauma
changes that person's experience of life to a place of fear and vulnerability, right? And then
that drives the subsequent problems. But if we're not looking at what's at the root of the things
that we're describing, then we're just taking a descriptive inventory and that's how we end up
polishing the hood, right? I can't tell you how many people I've seen with very severe substance
disorders that haven't been helped by three, four, five, six courses of treatment, right? And they're
then often labeled as quote unquote failing, right? The treatment. And very often the treatment is
never taken to trauma inventory. And it is trauma that is driving the substance use, right? It's
trauma that's changed that person's internal dialogue towards something that's extremely
negative that tells them that they're not worthwhile and they'll never get anywhere in life. And why
try for a new job or a new relationship, right? Because nothing ever works out for you. And,
and, you know, this wasn't that person's belief in themselves before trauma. It's undergirding
everything and then it's spinning off these symptoms. And then we take inventory of the
symptoms as if they are the be all and end all. And then somehow we're surprised when the treatments
don't work, right? So, so the fact that we're not looking to etiology, right? And, and I think that,
I think that's a huge problem and it fits with not actually paying attention to people that,
you know, I would get handoffs that would describe a person in a number like, Oh,
who's the patient I'm taking over? That's a two nine, six point four, four with a three
or nine point eight one. And they're like, Oh my goodness, right? We're talking about
human beings here, right? But we've somehow reduced that to numbers that indicate a set of
symptoms. And it's hard for me to see how one could argue the field hasn't been led astray.
If that's become the standard. So let's define trauma as broadly as we can, because
there's probably somebody listening to this right now who's thinking,
okay, trauma could be an injury. And if they can extrapolate from that and say, well,
psychological trauma, we talked about PTSD. I can see how a soldier coming back from Fallujah,
having watched people getting blown up, both civilians and soldiers. I can see how that would
be traumatic. Obviously the story with your brother. Yep. I can see how that's traumatic,
but trauma includes much more than that. So how do you define for somebody who's really hearing
about this for the first time, what trauma means? Yeah. Trauma is anything that pushes our coping
skills to and beyond their limits. And then results in a set of feelings inside that could
be acute terror, or it could be, for example, a chronic sense of denigration, right? But it
creates these feelings inside that then change the functioning of our brain, the communication
within our brain among the various parts, right? In a way that shifts the lens through which we
see ourselves in the world around us. So it pushes our coping skills beyond the limits,
and then it changes the ways that our brains function. And that's identifiable in modern
science. We can see the changes in space-aged neuroimaging, right? That shows how the connectivity
in the brain shifts, or even the fact that trauma changes the expression of genetically
determined characteristics in us, because genes are either on or not on, and that changes as a
result of trauma and can be passed down to children even years after the trauma occurs. So someone can
have the trauma occur, change the brain, and then have a child years later, and the child is impacted
by the trauma that occurred years before. So these are real changes inside of us,
identifiable by modern science, that happen when our coping skills are pushed beyond the limits.
And our view of trauma comes through this history of seeing trauma through the lens of combat,
right? Because it's sort of the most obvious way to see it, right? Like that person went off to war,
and they experienced terrible things in war, and they came back, and it's so clear that they are
different, right? So that's how we look to acute trauma, because it's the most obvious, right? And
as you said, if, okay, there's a suicide, and gosh, the family members are traumatized, again,
we can see that, right? But what we pay less attention to and less heed to are two different
factors. One, the variables inside of us that determine what pushes our coping skills over the
limits differ, right? It differs by genetic characteristics, it differs by early life
experience, it differs by, for example, how finely tuned one's emotional compass is. It differs by
the chronicity of trauma. So the sort of multiple hit hypothesis, which we've seen that if there
are multiple traumas, it might be, oh, it's the fifth trauma that now pushes that person into a
post trauma syndrome where the brain is different, even though the fifth trauma might seem less
traumatic than the first four, but the weight of the first four are there, right? So we tend then
to paint with this broad brush that ignores, right, the richness of human diversity, right? And how we
are impacted differently by different things, right? And then it also ignores that not all trauma
is chronic, sorry, is acute, right? That there are traumas that are chronic. So you think of the
trauma of neglect, right? The neglect of a child is not defined by an acute incident, right? It's
defined by the impact upon that child of the neglect over time, right? The same thing with
with the aspect, for example, of systemic racism, right? Of a person who gets messages over time
that they're less than, right? That they look different, they dress different, they worship
different, whatever is going on in them is less than. And that's inculcated into the person over
time. And that can have exactly the same effects on the brain. And the same is true with vicarious
trauma. I mean, we are fortunate, of course, as a species that we can be empathic with one another,
right? We can experience the emotions of another person, right? In a way that's connected as if
they're our own, right? But the other side of that coin is we can be traumatized by what happens
to other people, right? And sometimes that might be someone we're very close to, right? Or it might
be a person who develops such a strong interest because they're sort of horrified by things they
see going on around the world. And then are paying very, very close attention in a way that overwhelms
that person's brain's ability to cope with that. And then, for example, a person who was so deeply
impacted by the crisis in Syria, right? That then it develops post trauma symptoms, right? And that
person never left their home in the United States, but was so appalled and so distraught by what was
going on and didn't know to divert their attention. There was too much attention to something coming
from a good place in their heart, but that ultimately leaves that person manifesting the
same post trauma signs and symptoms as people who suffer from an acute assault. And whether the DSM
likes that or not, it is true. It's true and it's identifiable in human experience, right? So the
truth of human experience reflects the diversity of how we can be traumatized in acute, chronic,
and vicarious ways. And that how traumatic things impact us and whether they push our coping skills
over the limits is also unique to each human being, which doesn't mean we don't follow patterns. And
of course, the discipline of psychiatry following patterns and identifying patterns is very, very
important, but we also need to acknowledge that we're different and we can't understand what's
going on inside of a person without paying attention to that actual person.
Using that example, it seems that at the risk of oversimplifying, there are at least two
variables at play. There's the individual's susceptibility, and then there's the event or
events, which again can be acute, chronic, or experienced by others that you witness.
Maybe circumstances. I would think of that as circumstances, right? Because events still in
my mind implies something more acute, right? As opposed to circumstances, which could be an
acute event or something chronic or vicarious. So using that extreme example of a person who
witnessing events in the news rises to the level of the definition of trauma, those events,
which are not being experienced by this individual over a prolonged period of time, produce the state
you described, which is to say they are pushed beyond their manners of coping and they themselves
begin to internalize shame and these feelings we're talking about. So when you, I mean, does the DSM
look at that and say that's not trauma or it says there's something wrong with that person because
they shouldn't be feeling that way based on that event? I think it just excludes them because they
just don't meet the criteria for what validates the trauma, right? Which is interesting. So the
book has to validate the trauma, right? And like that doesn't really make sense, right? I mean,
we should be looking at people and saying, do you present with the signs and symptoms of trauma that
has pushed your coping skills over the limits, right? Is your mood chronically lower? Is your
anxiety chronically higher? Are you having panic attacks you didn't have before? Is your sleep
disturbed? Are you more hypervigilant? Do you feel less safe in the world about maybe yourself
or people that you love? Like these are clearly identifiable things, right? And if we're taking
stock, like what is your human experience, right? And has something changed in you? Then the idea
is we would honor that, right? And I wouldn't say, well, oh, wait a second that that happened to you,
but you were vicariously traumatized in the course of something occupational. So now, okay, so you get,
I'm going to put the stamp of approval on you. Wait, would that happen to you? But you were just
so horrified by what was going on, say in Syria, that you couldn't take your attention away from
it. And it woke you up in the middle of the night and you went on the computer for two more hours.
And now all of a sudden you really can't sleep well. And you're fearful about your children in
ways you weren't, wait a second, that wasn't occupational. Now we're not, now you don't get
the stamp of approval, right? I mean, the idea is we have to anchor to the truth of human experience
because it's not that extreme that people are traumatized by vicarious things. I mean,
and I absolutely see this. I mean, I've written many more times than I can count on a prescription
pad. Like I'm going to write your prescription and the prescription I'm writing is no more news,
right? Because I see that that person's health or maybe that person I've known for years,
their health has really deteriorated over a couple months of paying attention to something
so intensely distressing. And we've had more, you know, that we can shake a stick at, right? In
recent years that you could pay attention, you know, to the point of like utter despair, right?
And then who is that person? Like is that person someone who's had three or four really acute
traumas, but they don't have a post trauma syndrome, but boy, they're really a setup for it.
So they start paying intense attention to traumatic things they're seeing in, you know,
in the world around them. And now they have a syndrome, right? So we're not doing justice to
that. If we're making a set of criteria that try and treat us like robots or machines instead of,
Hey, like these are human beings. And we have to know like, what's come before in your life,
right? Where were you at when you experienced an acute or chronic or vicarious trauma? And if we,
if we look at the manifestations, what's going on in a person and how do we help them understand it,
then we can help people. I mean, part of the message of the book is this is not rocket science.
There's a lot about this. That's very simple and very grounded to common sense,
which is pay attention to what's going on in people and help them understand it. And if we
have an entire paradigm of helping that's around symptom inventory and putting a label or not
putting a label and then schlepping some medicines at someone without really trying to understand,
then we often, even the first step we take down helping pathways is misguided. And then it is a
really a surprise that the mental health treatment system is not serving well the majority of people
that it is supposed to serve. And I think it's very clearly true. I don't think this is a
overly strong or exaggerated statement that accessing mental health help often leaves
someone feeling worse. And I'm not trying to be over critical of the people working in the system.
There's so many good people that are trying to help other people, but the system often doesn't
let them do it. I mean, you have panels of more patients and you can count in 15 minute appointments.
How are you supposed to understand and help someone? So I think the entire system is misguided
towards this, how little money can we spend in the short term? How can we get human beings out
of the equation? Because human beings cost more money to deploy than medicines. We are misguiding
ourselves in a way that's away from common sense. And we do often leave people worse than when
we found them. A classic example being going to a hospital and trying to get help,
where maybe 15 or 20 years ago, when a person I was taking care of might be in crisis, I would
think if I don't send that person to an emergency room, that would be malpractice. They're in crisis,
they need help. Now I have to stop. And the vast majority of times I do not do that because I worry
or I know for sure if they show up at a hospital, they're going to wait 36 hours, 40 something hours
before they see someone. They're going to be put in a place that's going to feel very shameful and
very stigmatizing. There's a locked room and people are watching that person in a way that makes them
feel like they're being treated like they're crazy when they're in distress. And when they
finally get help, there's some short term stabilization, give them a little medicine,
they fall asleep, they wake up, they feel a little better because they slept, now send them home.
And we're not serving people well with this short term view of how we're supposed to help them.
I mean, there are not enough beds in emergency rooms in mental health units. There's not enough
time with practitioners. I mean, the fact that the system is broken is to me as obvious as one
plus one is two. I mean, I just see it in front of me day after day. Where in the last 20 years
did the sort of matrix come together for you with respect to trauma? I mean, the first time you and
I ever spoke about this was four years ago, 2017. And not surprisingly at that time, I didn't really
know what you were talking about. I only thought about it in the most literal sense, which is
something that is so obviously physically harmful that that could be traumatic. But it was clear you
had been thinking a lot about this because you had a lot to say on it and you had already
been sending patients to inpatient facilities, residential care facilities that specialized in
trauma care. So when did this occur for you? When did you start to integrate these other
modalities? When was the first time you sent a patient to a residential program that specialized
in trauma such as the bridge to recovery or a place like that? I would have been sending patients
to residential facilities for trauma since very early on in my career, but not having the
understanding. When you do anything for a long time, you internalize aspects of doing it that
become reflexive and then it frees up parts of your brain to learn more. And as I got,
I think just learned more and got more experience and more ability to spend more time with people
and try and just always have a venue where I could try and understand that person. It led me to
realize that I'm doing the same things all the time. If you present to me with panic attacks,
you present to me with obsessive compulsive disorder, you present to me with depression,
you present to me with addiction. What I'm ultimately doing is the same thing. I'm trying
to help you understand why, because that's what's going to make the difference. And maybe along the
way we can treat symptoms. Maybe I have you on a couple of antidepressants or even someone who has
psychosis, something so dramatic that we're trying to decrease that with medicines, but ultimately,
how to really help that person is to try and understand what their experience is of it and
their sense of vulnerability is of it. And I realized I'm doing this all the time, is trying
to help people understand where the problems are coming from, because that's how they get better.
Which is the same as what I saw in myself. There was anger, frustration, resentment,
underlying depression. All of these problems were in me and a very negative and oppressive
internal dialogue. And in my own psychotherapy of exploring this, we weren't trying to treat
like, what symptom is it spinning off now? We're trying to understand what's going on inside of
you, that you're doing this. And so I saw in my own, the process was to help me, my own psychotherapy,
and what I was doing with others, that it was all about the same thing, which were the roots of what
ails us. And those roots are the seeds of trauma falling into a soil that lets those seeds grow and
trying to understand what is that soil inside of you? How is it unique to you? How does it follow
patterns that impact all of us? What was that seed? How has it grown? I at some point realized,
oh, that's what I do. That's what I'm doing. And I stopped thinking, oh, like how many depression
cases do I have? Or how many? Think about that. I said, oh, I kind of have all trauma cases.
And that was such a revelation. And then in the practicality of starting to do my work more
intentionally that way, I could see that it was more effective. It was very, very clear that it
was more effective. And then I started working with really great like-minded people and their
knowledge and experience with what I was learning really came together in a way that this lens of
trauma seemed not like, oh, some esoteric discovery, but just rooted back to the obvious.
Right? It rooted back to the obvious, which it's really some of the older literature and describing
human behavior that we knew all the time, right? But just wasn't at the forefront of the discipline
in terms of its education and training. If you had to hazard a guess, what fraction of mental
health providers, psychologists, psychiatrists, counselors, et cetera, have never referred one
of their patients to a residential trauma facility? What would be your guess? It's an unknowable thing.
Probably a pretty high percentage, right? Because trauma gets defined as does that person have PTSD,
right? And people aren't going to even say all the things that would leave them to be diagnosed,
right? Because they're ashamed of the symptoms, right? I mean, the role of shame is so huge.
When you go to one of these facilities, and I've been to two of them,
the word PTSD almost never comes up, right? It's usually, hey, you have this addiction,
you have this maladaptive coping strategy, you're angry, you're depressed. Let's find out why,
let's find out what's underneath the surface. So given that the facilities themselves don't
position themselves as PTSD treatment centers necessarily, although there are people there with
PTSD, but it's just another group. It's interesting to me that practitioners aren't
more aware of this tool, but let's take something like an eating disorder, right? You take care of
many patients with eating disorders. What fraction of those patients would you say have an underlying
trauma as a significant contributory factor in their illness? Approaches 100%. Even if you look
at trauma through that appropriately broad lens, right? Because we're looking at what causes the
outcome. So I'm not trying to look at what factors do I want to be part of it. I'm looking at the
actual truth of what causes the outcome. So the chronic trauma of immensely high expectations of
self, right? Often placed upon self by self, but often that process being aided and abetted by
external forces, right? Which sometimes are the expectations of the people around that person or
just the expectations of society of how you're supposed to look and how you're supposed to act
and how you're supposed to present yourself to the world and what you're supposed to achieve
can create immense senses of insecurity and of vulnerability. And people laboring under that for
long periods of time can find an outlet for control. I mean, in many ways, that's often what
the signs and symptoms of so many mental health issues are, right? It's an attempt to find control
and maybe somebody finds control by tapping five times when they think they have a negative thought.
Someone else finds control by restricting what they eat and they can control what goes into their
bodies, right? And what are the roots of that? The roots of that are always trauma. I can't think of
an eating disorder situation. A person suffering from an eating disorder who did not have trauma
as a root of that eating disorder with the trauma being discovered and talked about and addressed at
least to some degree during the treatment. And that's why the facilities understand this. I mean,
it's interesting. The facilities know because when you show up at a trauma facility, right,
they want to understand and treat your trauma, right? They're not concerned. Do you have the
magic card of entry of PTSD, right? But because medicine, you know, how many times this gets said
so often, but it's true, right? If the doctors are treating the computer, the chart, right? The
paperwork, right? That like so much of it is about, because that person have trauma or not
to have trauma. I got to turn with that PTSD. Like, you know, it's, it's so busy around with things
that don't matter that are about establishing a diagnosis. So the insurance company will pay for
the 15 minute appointment or will pay for the medicine that's going to treat the symptom,
but not the problem, right? That there then become a gating mechanism. And like PTSD is some magic
gating mechanism, right? That doesn't get talked about when you're actually treating trauma
because it actually makes no sense as a gating mechanism. And I think what you're pointing out
is very, very powerful that, you know, the, the world we live in says, we have to have PTSD and
meet these criteria where you don't have trauma. But what happens if you get to somebody who's
treating trauma, they never talk about that, right? They talk about the reality and truth of what
you've lived and, and what that has done to you in ways that are then counterproductive to your life,
right? And like that's the truth and the realness of it as opposed to, as opposed to a false
sense of surety that comes from all those guidelines and box checking that is really
divorced from the human experience. It seems to me that part of the problem,
I mean, there's so many problems to the recognition of this, right? The first is there's,
you know, medicine works in the, in the sphere of biomarkers and objective measures of illness or
disease, right? So we can look at a biomarker like a person's APOB or LDL cholesterol or a
hormone level and it's subjective. We can understand what that implies or we can look at a CT scan that
shows an injury here, there, but you know, psychiatry has none of these things, right? Psychiatry,
you know, doing an MRI of a person's brain offers you no more insight into their plight or their
suffering than, you know, rubbing a towel on their head and dumping some hot wax on it. You know,
again, there are exceptions of course, there are exceptions where, you know, certainly, you know,
a nutritional deficiency, like a B12 deficiency or something that can show up in a biomarker can
explain a psychic realist, but for the most part, that's not the case. So that's sort of, I call that
kind of macro problem one. I think macro problem two is the heterogeneity of the soil
that you'd describe, right? You could take 100 individuals and simultaneously expose them to
the same traumatic event, but without knowing what their antecedent history is, right? So what have,
what else has this person experienced? And so in other words, what else has been dropped in the
soil and without knowing the composition of each of their soils, you really have no idea how those
100 people are going to react to an identical stimulus. And that of course is very uncomfortable
for medicine when, you know, it's uncomfortable for science, right? Like you think of Koch's
postulates, like we really love it when we can say, add this microbe, get this disease, subtract
this microbe, subtract this disease. Like, you know, medicine is so good at that type of thinking.
And it's like, we don't have the, and again, I'm not saying this to be critical of medicine or to be
critical of psychiatry. It's just an observation of maybe this might explain to somebody who's
listening to this, who thinks you're out to left field. This is a very hard problem to quantify
because of these, A, again, the obvious, the lack of biomarkers, et cetera, the lack of diagnostic
criteria and the incredible heterogeneity of the individual and their history. And those are
actually not the same thing. Yes. Anything on the one hand, look, we need to acknowledge that
complexity and also that lack of specificity, right? But on the other hand, there are aspects
of that, that I think simplify in ways that are very, very compelling, right? So, you know, in
the book I interview Stephanie von Gutenberg, who's an expert on the prevention of understanding
and prevention of child abuse and Darren Richard, who's a professor at Stanford, who's done a lot
of trauma work around trauma work and trauma research around the impact of trauma on identifiable
markers and what that means, right? So for example, his work draws at times from the field
of epigenetics, which shows that gene expression changes after trauma. And he was, his testimony
was instrumental in jurisprudence on an international level, recognizing that, for example,
rape as a tool of war, right, is not like a one event criminal act, right? Which was how it was
being viewed. Okay. That thing happened on that day, right? In a way that circumscribes it. And
the epigenetic research around trauma shows that not only is it not a one event limited to a day,
right, experience, but that it carries on throughout that person's life, right? It impacts
the society in which that person lives and it gets passed on to the next generation, right?
So now we start having that kind of powerful science that can show that woman who was raped
as a child three years later and the genetics that are expressed in that child are impacted
by the trauma that happened three years, say, before conception. So we do have, in a sense,
the scientific proof to hang our hats on these days. We do have that in a way that tells us,
right, we kind of knew all this was true because we saw it obviously in front of us.
Now we do have what science wants to have to hang our hats on, right? And even though, like,
say, those hundred people have different soil and will be affected in different ways, we can
understand how that may sort of disperse across those hundred people, right? Like, what is the
trauma? You know, a certain number of people, a percentage of people are likely to respond in
certain ways if it's a dramatic trauma. Like, if there's some dramatic acute trauma, it might not
matter so much what the soil is. People are going to be, you know, the majority are going to be very
deeply affected, right? Or there might be other kinds of trauma where you can only understand by
really understanding that person. So, like, we do fit patterns and we can understand how those
patterns unfold just like we can understand the aspects of basic science that we've learned now
in a way that says, yes, this is very, very complicated. That's why it can't be deployed
in some checkbox kind of manner, right? But we can understand it well enough to say, okay,
it's actually not that complicated, right? To try and understand like, what has your experience
been or what's going on inside of you, right? If you present as depressed, like, well, what's your
history, right? And what are you saying to yourself inside, right? And has that shifted over time? Like,
we can understand that in a way that says, do I think that your brain is different because of
trauma? It's like, it's not that hard to do that. And then to say, well, let's try and understand
your trauma so we can help make it better, right? So, there's an aspect of this that's also
kind of simple too that we don't deploy because we're lost in the complexity of all those other
things, all that box checking and, you know, we don't know, we don't understand, and psychiatry
wants to be like the rest of medicine. And then we get lost in the complexity and that complexity
very often prevents a person from being understood, feeling understood, feeling help, getting any help
at all. Are there checklists that provide value? So, for example, the adverse childhood event,
is that what it's called? ACE? It's a series of questions, right? It's 10 questions, 20, how many
questions is it? I don't know. There are different versions that get utilized in different realms
that I'm not, I don't know what the standardized version is now. Yeah, yeah, yeah, but it's in that
ballpark. So, sometimes these tests are really good at catching, they have a high positive
predictive value, but they seem to have a low negative predictive value. In other words,
there's lots of people who don't score highly on the adverse childhood event score, but nevertheless,
they are, there is significant trauma in their lives, but it might only account for one of the
10 checks, but again, for them, it was very instrumental in how their identity was formed.
So, is this something that can be automated or is this something that can only be done by
someone who has the ability to dig and really get deep into it? So, let's take an example, right?
So, let's take a person who grew up in a family where they simply weren't paid attention to,
right? So, they would check the box of neglect, but none of the other boxes would get checked.
Now, let's say there were multiple kids in that family, five children neglected because the
parents are working like crazy or for whatever reason, those five kids could completely
internalize that in different ways, right? Right. Some of those kids could go on to become
the most successful people in the world because, at least externally, because of a drive that gets
instilled in them to prove their worth. Right. One of their siblings could easily go in the
exact opposite direction and turn to a life of substance abuse and addiction. We see this all
the time. Exactly. Let's explore that a little bit more because, again, there's two things I
want to explore there. One, something as innocuous as neglect can produce such vastly different
phenotypes. And secondly, the heterogeneity of the soil problem, which is how is it that
two siblings, and you and I have both seen scenarios like this, two siblings in the exact
same family exposed to the exact same stimulus or environmental factor, in this case, neglect,
can have such vastly different responses. Right. And one of them, society frowns upon,
and the other one, actually, society is pretty impressed with. Right. So, you're getting
questions around the heterogeneity of it or how do we understand it? Well, I think it's both,
right? It's how do we explain the heterogeneity and two, how would both of those people even rise
to the level of coming to the lens of trauma given that, again, I'm using this very specific
example where on an ACE score, neither of them would rise to the level of concern.
Right. We are different even if we are siblings. Right. I mean, the genes are different and their
manifestation can be very different, right, based upon aspects of early childhood experience that
may have nothing to do with trauma. Right. So, I think where it leads us is inventories of signs
and symptoms can be useful, but they're just one element of data. Right. I mean, one aspect of it
is accuracy of reporting. Right. People will often under report because trauma creates
shame in us. Right. I mean, I can't tell you the number of times, say someone comes to care with
me and they're checking or they have depression and panic attacks and say there's some intake form
and they don't check the trauma box. Okay. And maybe I meet with them and maybe there is like a
purely biological depression. It comes out of the blue. Right. And I can't find trauma associated
with like that happens. Right. It's rare, but it happens more often than not. When you start
talking to the person, it's remarkable. Sometimes I've, you have three sessions worth of trauma
history. Right. That's, that's intrinsic to all aspects of that person's life. And they check no
on the trauma box. Well, because they didn't really think this was trauma. And they really think
that, that seems, that was too long ago to be trauma. And like, that's not as bad as what other
people have to deal with. So that can't be trauma. I mean, this happens all the time. Right. So the
what you just described strikes me as the norm. Right. It is. Yes. The majority of people who
come into kind of a trauma diagnostic scenario with, with, with an astute caregiver,
maybe caregiver is the wrong word, a provider, but it's the, the comparisons. Right. I mean,
come on. That's what happened to me is not that bad. Look at what happened to so and so.
That can't be trauma. Right. And it's too long ago. Right. All the time. Absolutely all the time,
because, and this is really a crux of the messaging of the book, because
trauma changes the instrument that we use to understand our trauma, right? Like it's
changing our brain, right? So, so you can combine that with how much shame is evoked, right? And how
hard it can be to discuss that, right? Because if we're ashamed of something, we don't want to
reveal it to somebody else. And we often don't know just because it's a professional, is that
person going to feel okay about me? Or are they going to look at me differently because they see
that shameful thing in me? Like we feel this. And absolutely. I felt this after my brother's death.
I'm going to go see this therapist. I don't even know this person. And you know, what's she going
to think of me? Like, you know, here I, you know, here I wasn't around enough. I only lived two
hours away and I wasn't home enough to see this. And like, you know, I, I thought maybe, you know,
she was going to say, shame on you for what happened. Like I didn't know, right? And I think
that is the norm, which is why like we can't replace humans, right? Like we kind of understand
this, that we can't replace humans in our helping endeavors with like something that's computerized,
right? So we're mechanized in some way. So, so sure. We want to take inventories and like,
if we can leave, it makes sense. Like to take a, an inventory of trauma scientists, but realize
it like you have no idea what that data means until you sit with the person, right? And like,
it's, why should it be strange to say that human beings are a necessary part of this helping
process, right? Because often I may look at all the data I have from someone. And a lot of times
I have data even from other providers or other facilities, right? You know, I have a lot of data
and like, okay, it tells me something, but I really don't know anything really about that person
until they sit in front of me, right? Because once they sit in front of me, I can anchor that data
to something, right? And, and very often what I started seeing over, you know, getting more
experience in the field was when you talk more with a person about what's going on in them,
it is indeed linked to trauma, whether they've checked that box or not. And it's all those
barriers. It was too long ago, or they feel ashamed of it. That lead them not to recognize
that the trauma is driving all of the problems. And I think that the last story in the book about
the woman who is a true story who 10 years later was 10 years younger. And I got her permission
before writing it because I didn't, you know, I didn't, that's not a composite, right? It's this,
this person who just didn't understand like how her life had changed. So she had had a tragedy in
her life and it was years before. And just standing from the outside and hearing the story,
there was such a disjunction of how she felt about herself and felt about her life and was
living her life that changed after the trauma in a way that was so stark. This is the woman whose
daughter died. Yes. Who without realizing it, was living this life that was so changed. And her
thoughts about herself were through such an unfair lens, right? Who really had no, despite being
intelligent and personable and like all these wonderful qualities, couldn't see it, right? And
like that's not the exception. That's the norm, right? And those rationalizations inside of
herself, no, it was too long ago or, or even feeling so badly about it that, that being
unable to let it to the surface enough to see what it was doing, right? What had driven all of this
change in her. So despite attesting to not having trauma, it was 100% of the cause.
How did she come into your care?
There's three other things to treat some of the symptoms that had spun off, which is often the
case, like, oh, this person is depressed or, you know, there's so many things. I'm like, okay,
that's, that's just the card of entry. Like maybe that I will find there a pure biological
depression, right? But I've ceased to believe that that is what I will find because 20 years of doing
this intensively has taught me differently. So then the place case, the person comes in and I see
whatever the presenting, I don't remember, right? Because like, that's not where the money was at,
so to speak, right? Where the money was at was in trauma, right? And is this that leaf at the end
of the tree that caught the person's attention? I want that leaf to be a little healthier that,
that a little bit better, right? That then brings her in where we look at what's going on in the
roots that's affecting all of the leaves, right? And it then gives us a chance of actually getting
at it and developing an understanding of trauma and of reflexive shame and what that does to us
and what a change in internal dialogue from, from feeling a sense of pride in oneself as someone
who works hard and does good things for other people in the world around her to someone who
didn't, couldn't see her own worth anymore. And you want to see an absolute disjunction of oneself
from a before and after that will do it. And by understanding it, it could get better, right? Does
it take away the grief? No, in fact, it lets her begin, it let her begin to process the grief,
right? Because if we're blaming ourselves, we can't grieve. That's why it can be 50 years later
and be just as immediate as when it happened. Because if the grief gets walled off, right,
under this layer of shame, like an abscess medically would be in the body, then it can spin
off symptoms for years and years and years without anything ever getting any better. And in fact,
with things getting worse, because the trauma then brings new trauma, right? It brings the shame of
like losing jobs and losing family and, and, you know, all the ways in which feeling bad about
ourselves makes us feel worse about ourselves, right? So the, it's a great example, but it's not,
oh, that's one in a million. It's just a great example of something that I see all the time,
which is like, let's get to the truth of what's going on in the person, help them understand it
and things get better. And it's not that hard and complicated, but it requires an approach that
actually wants to understand what's going on. Actually, I've always found the analogy of the
abscess to be quite helpful, especially for folks who understand what an abscess is, how it's formed,
and what the implications are of it, right? So for maybe folks who aren't familiar,
an abscess is a walled off infection. So a great example of how one might get an abscess is if they
had a ruptured appendicitis. And, you know, a ruptured appendicitis carries with it a very
high mortality, but there are some ways to survive it without antibiotics, without anything. And this
was even known hundreds of years ago when people were making long haul journeys across the ocean.
If you had a ruptured appendix in the middle of the Atlantic Ocean, when you're halfway between
Spain and the Americas, kind of SOL. But what they realized was if you put the person on their
right side down, tilted slightly head up, all of the pus that was coming out of that ruptured
appendix would at least wall off in the lower part of the right abdomen, as opposed to spread
throughout the entire abdomen. And there was at least you'd increase the odds that it would form
this fibrous capsule around it that would wall off. So you'd have all the pus and all the nastiness
inside there, but it was sort of walled off. And if you could get this right, that person might just
might survive. Now, they weren't going to be perfectly healthy, but they'd survive. Now,
today we still see people that show up with abscesses from a ruptured diverticulum or something
like that. And they're not well. They're not dead though, but they're just not well.
Well, the first thing that has to happen is they have to come into the medical system for treatment,
which I guess the analog would be here. They have to at least present for help in some way. The
second thing is they have to be willing to get help. They have to acknowledge, I have an abscess.
Now, it's a lot easier with an abscess because we have a CT scan that is stark. I mean, an abscess
is an unmistakable thing that you don't even need to be a radiologist or even a medical student to
spot the abscess on a CT scan. It's the easiest thing to see. Literally, there's nothing easier
to see on a CT scan than an abscess. But nevertheless, there's got to be some component
of convincing the person that you have this abscess. But what's interesting is the treatment,
you often get a little worse before you get better because when you open that abscess and you
release all of the bacteria, even though you're doing it in a manner to clean it up, the patient
will initially have an inflammatory response to that that is probably worse than the condition
that brought them in. Now, of course, you have the luxury of doing this in the hospital. You're
giving them antibiotics. You're giving them IV fluids. You're monitoring them. So this is rarely
a fatal event, but it's nevertheless uncomfortable. And in many ways, that just strikes me as a great
analogy for what has to happen here, except it's harder in the case of trauma because one,
they might be less likely to come in and seek help. Two, you have a really big hurdle to
actually convincing the person that you have this abscess. And three, the treatment is much harder.
In many ways, the treatment of the abscess is really quite simple. You're going to be under
anesthesia for the next couple of hours, and we're going to do all this stuff, and we're going to
give you a bunch of antibiotics. Well, it's a lot harder to do what you did with that woman
than what I would have done with that patient. Yeah. And I think as I'm listening to what it
makes me want to focus on is the really big hurdle. Because I think the abscess, it's a remarkably
good analogy. Because the re-sledges- It saved you. Your response to the trauma
saved your life. Right. We're built to recoil and protect ourselves from dangerous things,
which is why if you think about trauma leading to avoidance and hypervigilance, and people become
more afraid of the world and less likely to engage and less likely to take chances, even if it's the
chance of a job that seems better or the chance of dating someone who seems like they could be a
great partner, taking chances in good ways, that a person becomes much less likely to do that.
Right. And if you think about how these systems grew in us, that trauma raises a lot of negative
emotion in us, and then we recoil to protect ourselves. And it may be that even a depressed
mood or panic attacks and disturbed sleep, this may all go hand in hand with hypervigilance and
avoidance to say, look, that is better than death. Right. And when these systems grew in us,
where a lot of the trauma that happened did tell you to stay close to home. Right. And human
development, right. And we're in small groups. And if you eat something that makes you sick,
like never, never, never eat that again. Or if you go over that hill and someone from another
tribe attacks you, like don't go there again, right, to stay closer to home. They're there for
a reason, right. They're part of the evolution of human beings psychologically, right, over time in
order to stay alive. Right. But then in the modern world, those things don't always make sense
anymore. Right. And that walled off, say, psychological abscess, right, that is indeed
better than death is spinning off symptom after symptom, right. It's making that tendency towards
a little too much alcohol soothing that that person, you know, does a couple of times a year.
Well, now they want to do a little more because there's a desperation in them,
right, to not feel so terrified or have panic attacks when they're falling asleep. And
now they're drinking three, four, five, six, seven days a week, right. Or that that tendency
towards avoidance is now they can't get out of bed or leave the house. Like these are things I see
all the time. And, and often what brings a person to care is a symptom, right. Just like the person
with the abscess might come to care because. They don't know they have an abscess. Exactly.
They just don't feel well. So, so the parallel is so strong there, right. And I think the difference
is in the hurdle, right. That even though I might say, okay, wait, I'm going to feel a little worse
before I feel better. But like, Oh, I see that bright thing on the CT scan. And you're telling
me you're going to go in and take it out. And I'm going to feel a lot better, not just this thing
that brought me in, but 50 more things I didn't know about. I'm much more likely to say yes to
that, right. And the problem I think is in how high the hurdle is for trauma. And I guess actually,
I think the problem is twofold. It actually is, and it's not as easy to recognize as the abscess,
but I think that it should be, right. That our mental health methods of coping, of helping,
sorry, should look for this. In looking for abscesses, we have 256 bit CT scanners that
can produce a resolution of one by one by one millimeter. And the analog of what you have in
psychiatry to do this is pre-CT scan era when you have to just palpate somebody's belly and surmise
that they have an abscess. I mean, there's a huge, I mean, I don't want to use the word technology to
imply that you will need technology to do this, but it is effectively the difference between a
catapult and a cannon. But I think maybe the beautiful answer to this is in this example,
we're setting forth psychiatry is choosing to use the, let's palpate the abdomen instead of the CT
scan, right? I completely agree. Yes, yes, yes.
Because the human brain has more sophistication than even that finest CT scan, right? That's right.
So if we apply the trained human brain to say, look, I want to try and understand what's actually
going on in you instead of saying, oh, oh, you're depressed. You checked all the depression boxes.
Let me give you an antidepressant and I'll see you again in two months and we won't make eye contact.
I mean, like that's not helping. That's not understanding, right? But if we apply the
human brain, like we apply the CT scanner, right? Then we will identify way more trauma and say,
look, how many times I tell a person, like here's the great news is you do not have five problems,
right? Because people will present saying, you can't help me. There's no way you're going to
help me, right? There's been going on me for years and I have four different problems, right?
How are you going to help me? Right? So here's the great news. We've been going on for years because
it's never been looked at, right? So it's not surprising it goes on for years.
And you don't have four problems. You have one, right? You don't have depression and sleep
disturbance and panic attacks and alcohol abuse, right? As entirely different problems, right?
They're arising from trauma. And I may be, why would I be saying that? Because we've had a couple
of conversations where the person told me how none of those things were present before the trauma
and all of those things are present after the trauma, right? And then that's not rocket science,
right? So we could stop palpating the abdomen and bring in the equivalent of the CT scanner,
even better, right? The human brain, right? And then we can identify what's going on
and we can also decrease the hurdle. Like why is it so daunting to get help for trauma, right?
I mean, in many ways it is scary, right? Because the person often has been keeping it inside and
then I hear this all the time too. Like, I can't talk about that because then they realize and
often they knew all along, not always, but often they knew all along that that's what was going on
because they get told the whole world inside of me is different now. But look at what it's doing
to me and I'm not even talking about it, right? They don't realize, look at what it's doing to
you because you're not talking about it, right? But when you can get someone to understand that
and often that comes already, that's right there waiting because you're talking at least enough
about it that the person has disclosed that there's been some trauma. They put words to something.
They maybe never put words before and guess what? The world didn't end, right? And I didn't lean
across the table and say, what? Like get out of my office. Things that people are afraid of,
like I was afraid after my brother's death, right? Already there's an excuse. People,
this happens all the time. I'm saying, I feel better now, right? I already feel better because
literally after just 40 minutes say of talking about like, yeah, you know, I really have felt
different since that car accident or even since that thing happened to my friend's child, right?
They know, right? They know, but because of the shame and the idea of what are you going to do
with that, right? They don't know that there's helping resources. So we don't put it out there
that there's helping resources, right? And people have way too many experiences of going to get help.
And then they come out with a prescription for an antidepressant from somebody who didn't really
talk to them. And they know that's not going to help or they've already done it four times and
it hasn't helped, right? So we create these barriers by like so many things in modern medicine
by stepping away from common sense. Like let's use the right helping mechanism. Let's use the
equivalent of the CT scan to find the abscess and let's make the barrier lower so the person
doesn't have to feel that it's utterly terrifying to go through this helping process. Once people
start doing it, even though it's difficult, people feel good about it, right? They feel good about
it. Like you feel good about doing something that's hard for you. Like, you know, like working out
is really hard, right? But like, you know, you're getting healthier so you don't mind going and
doing it. And that's often how the experience is. It's not miserable. And it often surprises people
that like the clinic that, you know, the whole group of us have together, like it's not a
miserable place to come, right? And people are often surprised by that, that, you know, this is
supposed to be miserable. It's supposed to make them feel bad. And if you come to a place that's
like just reasonably nice and you meet people who are like, hey, I'm in the soup with you too,
right? Like I know things I'm trained, that's why I can help you. But, you know, I have the same
problems. In the short term, it can be quite distressing to go back and revisit these things.
I mean, I think that's been more my experience than not, both personally and with others, that
it can, it really does feel a little bit like that abscess where in the days after that surgery,
in that case, the patient actually looks worse. Yeah, absolutely. Like, absolutely yes. But
because you know why and you know that it's helping you, it's much more tolerable, right?
This happens in my own therapy. I'll think, gosh, I've got to talk about something from the past
that is now being triggered, right? Like something happens in my present and it links me to a trauma
of the past that like really shook my confidence and like now my anxiety level is higher. And I
know it's going to be hard to go in and talk about that. I know it. I know it's going to be painful,
but I'm not afraid of it, right? Because I know that it's helping me just the way that
people perceive pain differently in medical settings if they know why, right? And I saw
a study you probably have seen around like gunshot wounds, right? And like people's pain
being so different if they see that there's something, that there was some reason, right?
Like they're trying to help somebody, right? And now they know that like, even though like this is
terrifying, like they're going to survive it, right? And their level of pain goes down, right?
So yes, it's painful, but the perception of the pain is this pain that threatens me,
menaces me with destruction, right? Or is this pain that although painful is in the service of
like doing right by myself, right? And that's often what we'll anchor to of like, look, I don't see a
reason for you to have a dialogue running in your head where 500 times a day you tell yourself that
you're worthless. Really, that doesn't seem fair or right to me. You know, not even sometimes you
joke, I don't know if you've been kidnapping buses of school children I don't know about, right?
Like, is this it? That this, you know, there's something to feel ashamed about here, but it's
the person who did that thing to you, right? Maybe there's nothing to be ashamed about here because
like something just happened in life, right? And it's that change inside the person that gives us
all the bravery to go and do difficult things because we see that it's aligned with truth.
And I think often people see psychotherapy as like, oh, we're trying to shift towards something
that feels better. Like that's not the purpose of it, right? The purpose is to shift towards
something that's true. Oh, and by the way, that true thing feels better. What do you think are the
impediments to a person once they're presented with a plausible explanation for their symptoms
in the roots of trauma? What are the impediments to them doing the work that's necessary? Because
again, here's the second huge difference from the abscess. The abscess, you get to basically
put an IV in your arm, take some propofol and wake up and have it be over. When you're confronted with
these events of your childhood, though seemingly completely disconnected from the problems you're
having today as an adult are probably causally linked. And we need to go back and talk about
them and we need to go back and process them. And we need to go back and disconnect your shame
from those things. There's a lot of resistance that's met there. I mean, last night over dinner,
you and I were talking about common patients whom you get the feeling that they might not
take treatment. Right. I mean, I think the biggest problem, because he says, what are the problems?
The biggest problem is presenting to a system that is not looking to throughput and minimal
short-term cost as the primary metric of success. That brings the frustration of not finding what's
needed. And what's needed, of course, are skills that are learned through education and training,
their neurobiological knowledge and pharmacological knowledge and psychotherapeutic modality knowledge.
But most importantly, it's presenting in a setting where there can be what's called a
holding environment. The reason that we can do these things that are very, very frightening
is because we establish rapport with someone who we feel and believe wants to help us,
is capable of helping us, doesn't want to look down on us and can help us hold the distress of it.
Right. And that's the commonality. Psychotherapeutic modalities are so very, very different. But if you
look at primary predictors of success, it lies in the rapport because of the rapport, the trust,
the mutuality that's generated is what creates that, again, that thing that's called the holding
environment, which is like, I'm really scared of this and it's intimidating, but like, I'm going
to come here and this is a safe environment and you're a safe person and you want to help me.
Right. And I don't feel bad when I'm sitting across from you, which is why me and most of the
people I work with, if not all, acknowledge our own trauma. I mean, we're not talking about it in
a way that serves ourselves when we're supposed to be serving someone else, but I'm not pretending
that I'm not a person for whom trauma isn't deeply ingrained in my life. Right. And that sense of
mutuality leads a person to feel the trust and to be able to tolerate the distress because they're
not tolerating it alone. And when I pack up my trauma at the end of my psychotherapy sessions,
I'm going to carry that until the next time I'm going to go back in part because the person I go
to for therapy makes me feel helped and understood. And I know that he's going to carry it with him
and he wants to help me. And he feels a sense of respectful camaraderie in the work that we're
doing. And then I can bear the distress of it. I can take it home with me, even if it causes me
some symptoms thereafter, right? And know that I'm going to come back next week and I'm going
to make more progress. But our helping systems have to be set up to do that for people. Otherwise-
Let's assume those are in place. Okay.
Let's assume- Big assumption though, right? Big assumption.
Big assumption. But let's assume that that is in place. Why is it that 10 people who have
childhood trauma or early life trauma that is producing very maladaptive responses in their
lives, either with respect to self-care, care of others, any of the other manifestations of trauma,
what are the things that stand in the way of them accepting that information and moving forward?
First three answers are shame, shame, and more shame, right? That trauma makes a reflexive shame
in us. And that's what tells us to make the abscess, right? What's interesting is in the appendix
example, the abscess happens because a biological process happens and now the appendix bursts,
right? And then maybe the body can figure out a way, especially if the person is leaning on
the right side, it can figure out a way. So like that walls off. But the difference here is like
the creation of that abscess occurs inside of us, right? Through our defense mechanisms, right?
That's I've got to wall this off, right? I can't think about this. I can't talk about this. I
didn't want to go to therapy after my brother's death because I was ashamed to go to therapy
on top of the shame I felt about his death, right? So we do it to ourselves because that's what seems
like the course of action that's safest, right? And that's very, very powerful when we're promoting
that process. And then because things aren't going well, we sort of wall off that abscess more
and more and more, right? Because other shameful things happen. Like after my brother's death,
when I was functioning super well and I didn't feel like I was taking good care of myself,
I felt ashamed of that too, right? Which then makes it harder to get help, right? So shame,
which is like the primary henchman of trauma, right? In my view comes along with all these other
accomplices. Like shame loves alcohol excess, right? Shame loves an internal dialogue that
tells you that you're not worth anything. You're not going to get anywhere, right? There are all
these things that shame loves that we then cultivate in ourselves and we apply to further
walling off, further pushing that problem down. And that's why the best route is not just,
okay, let's shift how we're handling the care. So if you go to see someone about whatever your
symptom is, that person is actually thinking about you. But we do need in my very strong belief
to change the sociological aspects of this, right? To look and say like, look, many, many, many of us
have really significant trauma that has overwhelmed our coping skills, changes how we view about
ourselves and the safety of the world around us. And it really behooves us to look at this.
And there's no shame in this, right? I remember this was a bunch of years ago, but I was talking
to a group of about 300 physicians, right? From mixed backgrounds, mixed disciplines.
And I said this, right? I said that I've had really significant trauma in my life and psychiatric
care and psychiatric medicines have really helped me, right? And I could see out in the audience,
like probably about a third or so is a rough estimate of people like, look, shock, like that
I had said something that was so shameful, right? As if the next thing that was going to happen is
someone's going to fly through the air and tackle me, right? And pull my medical license out of my
pocket and put me someplace where people go who need those things. And I said, look, this is a
problem, right? Because I can see, and I hadn't planned on this, right? I said, it's a problem
because I see a lot of you really recoiling from this, right? And I'm saying something that I don't
think takes away from my ability to be a competent physician or a competent person in the world,
right? And I think in fact, being able to say it is what helps me navigate the world, right? But
if we recoil from like, oh, you might need help, right? Or you might need medicines, like what is
going on inside of us? That means how likely are any of those doctors to get themselves help,
right? And how likely are their patients to feel comfortable if they broach something traumatic,
right? To hear something back that even if the person is not in mental health, right? But just
say, wow, okay. Look, we know that way more than 50% of complaints to general medical providers come
from mental health conditions, right? I mean, the studies show, you know, a bottom of 50% and a
ceiling that's significantly higher than that. So non-mental health providers have to be aware and
not respond in this way. And again, I'm not trying to be critical, but you see that response even in
mental health, like some of those people who were coyered were almost certainly in mental health,
right? And we have to change the so to speak, the soup we're swimming in toward the soup that says
like, what do we have? Why should we be ashamed of this, right? Like, don't we have to acknowledge
this? Otherwise, the negatives inside of us, including the anger and frustration that I think
promotes all the dysfunction in our political discourse, for example, like all of this comes
to the fore in sociological ways. So if we don't look at this, how likely are we to help people get
help? And then if we don't do that, do we make everything worse in our inability to come to even
a decision about like, what's factual and what's not factual, as we all as a society try and navigate
things like racial issues or discrimination based upon gender or sexuality or the climate crisis?
Like, how are we going to look at that if we don't look at what's going on inside of us that often
involves the anger and frustration that make people just say need to be right? And like I'm
not saying this is always where it goes. A lot of the dysfunction and the misery, most of it gets
turned inward in people, but some of it does get turned outward. And I think we see the manifestations
of that in the real degeneration of our discourse as a society. What is the antidote to shame?
The antidote to shame is understanding. And I view the lancing of that aspect,
sorry, the lancing of the abscess or the surgical excision of the abscess, that's the equivalent
of shining a light on shame. That shame is so powerful. It's like the old, it kind of gets
told a lot, but it actually happened when I was a kid. There was a clothes tree in the room where
my brother slept. And if you turn the lights off, it could look like a monster. And I know it was a
clothes tree, but as a little kid, it gets scary. And is that really a clothes tree? It looks like a
monster. It gets scarier and scarier and scarier. And then if I start screaming and crying, my
parents come in and turn the light on, oh, I see that it's just, it's not a monster. And that's
shame. If we turn our eyes away from it, which is exactly what it tells us to do, you can't share
that even with yourself, let alone with someone you love, let alone someone professional. It's
your fault that that happened to you. You should have dressed differently. You should have not
been in that place. You should have been better and someone wouldn't have hurt you. You should
have been different and people wouldn't have treated you so poorly when you were way back when in
school. These are the things that shame tells us, like the devil on the shoulder telling us why we
have to hide it away. And then it gets scarier and scarier. And when we go and shed light on it,
we have never worked with one person. I cannot call to mind a single case where shedding light
on shame and all around it, looking at all the dark corners of it and really bringing it to light
in a process that has its moments of fear and misery, but also has its moments of levity. And
also has its moment of bringing good memories to the fore. Being able to shed the light on that has
never been anything but extremely helpful to the person doing it. But all the impact of shame
tells us not to do that. And society really kind of goes along with that. And the health systems
that want to shuttle us through with a prescription for Prozac, we collude in that, right? So society
colludes with shame in preventing way too many of us from ever getting a handle on our trauma
when it's actually not rocket science to do so. So if you shine that light on shame
and the person now realizes why they feel a certain way, right? The reason I feel so inadequate
is because of these events or this event. And because of this inadequacy, I go and do this
other thing. How do you change the feeling? So step one is understanding why, but then step two
has to be, you have to actually change that feeling, don't you? Yes. The answer to that is you work on
it across time, right? We live in a society that so wants rapid results, right? And it's why we
throw medicines at so, so many things and throughout the whole field of medicine that we should
infrow medicines at, right? Or you're not healthy. Well, take this medicine, this medicine, this
medicine, we don't say like, how to change your diet, exercise, I mean, things that you, you know,
you understand as well as anyone on the planet, right? We don't do that. So we look to short-term
fixes, right? And we all, well, we know for our just even basic education in brain biology, right?
That the neurons that fire together wire together, right? So if you and I picked a word out of the
blue and we decide, let's say it over 500 times, right? Then of course, like we'll each be saying
like tonight, right? It'll be in our heads tomorrow morning, right? What if we say that word
5,000 times, right? It'll be in your head next week, right? So, so if we say things to ourselves
and we have a way of conceptualizing ourselves that we've overly reinforced, it will not go away
overnight, right? But we don't tell people that, right? So when a person comes to it, like a really
say an understanding milestone, like, oh my God, right? The shame is it mine? Like I was six years
old. The shame is that person who hurt me, right? That part of how I make sure we end that session
is all those thoughts and the feelings attached to those thoughts and it's the feelings that make the
difference, right? Are not going to go away, right? They will still be there with you because the only
way they go away is they attenuate over time, right? And you've scored a victory today that
disempowers them, right? That when those thoughts come like, oh, you're worth nothing and that was
your fault. And if you'd been better, that wouldn't have happened to you. Like, okay, you say, wait a
second. I don't actually believe that, right? I can't keep it out of my head, but I'm going to put
you back thought. I'm going to direct my thoughts away from you more quickly. And there's a whole
bunch of strategies around that. And then I'm going to put you back a little bit less powerful
than how you came. And we don't, as a rule, we do not talk to people in that way. And then people
feel terrible and they feel ashamed. And often their practitioners think they failed the treatment
and like everyone now looks at this negatively because, oh, two, three, four weeks later,
they're not better. There's no way on God's earth they were going to be better after two,
three, four weeks. Like something that's developed over years doesn't go away that quickly, right?
But if we engage in that process and we take away what? The fear, right? Because otherwise,
if the person feels better, they have this aha moment, right? And then they go home and they're
getting in bed and the same thought goes, you know, tomorrow's not going to be better than today
because you're not worth anything. No, now they feel awful that that thing that happened today
doesn't mean anything, right? So you have to prepare that person and like, absolutely,
you can be better, but it's going to take place over time. You don't have to be afraid when those
thoughts are still in your, in your minds. I've had people I've worked with who say started their
treatment even before I met them, right? And they had among the most severe repeated negative
thoughts and feelings inside of them. And they may have been doing really well for 10, 20 years,
right? But you put them under enough stress and enough triggering and it'll still come in
that, oh, you're nothing and you should kill yourself still comes into their mind, right?
But now they know well enough. They'd be like, wow, that stuff dies hard. There's one person said
that stuff dies hard, not afraid of it. One little bit, because that person understands that he said
that to think to himself a hundred thousand times. And guess what? It's still going to come back
every now and then. It doesn't mean anything. Because if anything to say to that person doesn't
carry one little bit of information, right? And now that person isn't afraid of it. Not saying,
oh my gosh, am I going to hurt my, they don't, they, they know, but you, we have to educate
people and the mental health field doesn't, doesn't put very much value in what's called psycho
education. Let's help, let's help you understand yourself. And I think that's also a lot of what I
do psycho education through the lens of understanding trauma. I think if you told me I could only do one
thing, I can't, maybe I can't prescribe medicines anymore. I can't do depth psychotherapy. I can't
use multiple modalities. I can only do one thing and I got to choose. I think I would choose psycho
education about trauma because then man, you arm people with knowledge they didn't have before and
they can go help themselves. They can get help from people who are close to them. They can maybe get
professional help, but it's that knowledge that helps us even if there's no professional help to
be had, which is also a point of the book that I want anyone who picks that book up to be able to
read their way through it and to end up on the, on the end of it with knowledge and education. They
didn't have before because that I think is what is most impactful and whatever a person does with
that, which may be limited by time, circumstances, resources, all sorts of other things, they're,
they're now equipped to do something good with it and the field generally does not do that.
You know, when I think about our practice, I think about all of the dimensions of health span. So
when I use the word longevity, I'm referring to two things, lifespan, how long you live and
health span, how well you live. And within health span, there's really three dimensions. There's a
cognitive dimension, which I think most people kind of understand, right? How sharp is their
brain? And most people can understand what the extreme loss of that looks like in the form of
dementia. Then there's a physical dimension, the structural dimension, you know, your ability to
be free of pain, your ability to carry out activities of daily living and your ability
to do the things that you enjoy doing physically. And then there's an emotional component to this,
right? So even though some people would touchy feely, call this mind, body, spirit, I really like
to think of it as cognitive physical slash exoskeleton and emotional. I think this is the,
I think it's that emotional bucket that is the hardest one for us in our practice to help
patients with because one, we don't have a great set of screening tools. We have really good
screening tools for these other ones. And by the way, on the whole lifespan side, we have lots of
great screening tools. We have biomarkers and MRI scanners and liquid biopsies and colonoscopies. I
mean, we're very good at trying to identify the things that will end your life in a binary
fashion from a cardio respiratory standpoint. We're not very good at identifying the things
that are going to end your life emotionally. You know, I'm working on a book that's a day late,
a dollar short. It'll be out there eventually. But in it, I talk about four types of death.
The first one being the one that people think of cardio respiratory pulmonary death, like the,
what I call death certificate death. But then I talk about these three other deaths,
cognitive death. So the really the death of the ability of the brain, the decline of the
ability of the brain with respect to processing speed, short-term memory, long-term memory,
executive function, the physical or exoskeleton death or demise, which is basically that which
leaves a person in pain and unable to carry out these activities of daily living. And then this
emotional death and these three types of other death, types two, three, and four often precede
one. In some ways, the perfect life would be a long life that just goes straight to type one death
without detouring through type two, type three, and type four. But tragically, that's almost never
the case. And so we think so much about how to identify and treat type two, type three, and type
four, but by far the one in which we are the most limited is this identification of type four.
And part of it is, I think shame, there's no question, right? Part of it is inadequacy of
tools. So for example, when it comes to identifying type two or type three, let's use the physical one,
we have so many ways that we assess people for movement and strength and balance and stability
and stamina and all of these things. And usually once people are confronted with how
bad they are, because almost always relative to our standards for where we want people to be,
most people fall woefully short, but they can see, oh, this is where I should be. If I subscribe to
your ethos that to be a really kick-ass 100-year-old, I need to be a doubly kick-ass 50-year-old.
And here are the steps that we're going to take to train to get you there.
But for years now, I wanted to think how could we do that same sort of screening around emotional
health? And how would it be received? And how would we then implement therapy? Because really,
a person who's doing very well on the type one, type two, and type three, meaning they have no
chronic diseases, they have no acute diseases, their mind is sharp, their body is great,
but they're a slave to some shame that's rooted in trauma. They can often have the most miserable
life. And really, how long they live becomes completely irrelevant. In fact, it almost becomes
paradoxically a curse. It's just more time to suffer. A lot of these people, of course,
are not obviously suffering. So it's very easy to see a person living in a crack house
with needle tracks in their arm and say, are you suffering? Yes. That's not a huge cognitive
leap for that person. There are enough external markers that we can make that conclusion with
a high degree of... Sure. And they're probably self-aware enough. But when you take somebody
who's actually quite successful by all the metrics of the external world, they're successful
financially, they have a wonderful family, all these other things, it usually takes a bit of
prodding for them to acknowledge. And you have to be astute enough to prod and realize that actually
all is not well. So I'm not a psychiatrist. How do I bring our evaluation of what I call type four
death or demise up to the level of our ability to evaluate the other three?
So the first thing I have to say is you've been kind enough to share with me some excerpts from
the book. And when your book comes out, it will be anything but a daylight and a dollar short. And
I think you're talking about these aspects of life that are just so, so important in ways that
we can understand. Like, am I taking care of myself in the way I want to? Am I paying attention to my
life in the way that I want to? And yes, that emotional aspect of it is the hardest to identify.
As you said, there aren't serological markers for it. And often the truth of what may be going on
is underneath the surface. And I would say that actually, you already do the things there are to
do. And we could talk about how might it be formalized. But I think of when you may refer
someone to me, right? And like, why is that, right? And when you tell me if this seems right,
but my thoughts. I guess I would say this, I think we do a better job than most.
I guess what I'm really getting at is, why can't we be doing better? Why is it that there are some
patients whom I suspect there's an issue, but as I broach it, there's complete denial.
Or there's other patients who on the surface will accept it, but then we can't get them to
engage in it. Right. See, I think the processes that you're going through, so again, what do I
think you're doing? And you tell me, does this make sense? I think that you're looking for people
whose actual behavioral choices are running counter current to what they're presenting for.
And people are presenting to you because they want to be the healthiest they can be.
So it's a little bit maybe the health systems are less like that. People are presenting us with
problems. So you will see if someone presents to you, say, the reason I'm here is I want to be as
healthy as I can be. And then you see that they're not actually behaving that way, right? Or they're
behaving in a way that affords that. And then that will trigger like, ah, something is going on here.
Because otherwise, why would those vectors not all be heading in the same direction?
Good mental health is always consistent with simplicity in all of us. Right. So if I would
like to be healthy and I come to a healthy health assisting resource, one would presume I'm going to
act in ways that assist that resource and assisting me pretty straightforward. Right.
If we're not acting that way, then it points like there's something going on that's not consistent
with that sort of simple, almost common sense understanding of how to make our lives better.
And that will point towards something in the mental health spectrum, right? Which,
the vast majority of times has its roots in trauma. So if you see people running countercurrent to
their stated goals, right? Or the second, I think there are kind of two occasions on which we see
people coming from your practice, right? The other might be if on discussion, the person is sharing
something about their inner world that's not consistent with what you're necessarily seeing
on the outside, right? And then their sharing of that dissonance, right? Then leads to, ah, there's
something going on here that it's affecting them emotionally, right? Even if they are still trying
to be healthy, right? But there's some toll that's taking them under the surface that you want to
understand better and guide in the right direction. And the thought would be we could deploy that in
sort of formalized manners in our medical health settings, right? So the person who really wants to
stay alive because they love their grandkids, but they have diabetes and this is their third hospital
admission in two years, right? And you say, okay, like that person doesn't want this to happen. Like
they like through life and they're grounded to these reasons of like being healthy and staying
alive, but they can't act that way, right? And to look at that and say like maybe there are logistical
barriers, right? Like maybe there are non trauma related barriers to them, like getting to care,
taking medicines, like we can look very hard at that. And then very often I think where that
process can arrive at is there's something that's preventing that person from taking care of
themselves, right? And then there's the light bulb that says, ah, there's something here for the
mental health, for the mental health aspect of helping, right? Or if, and actually talking to
someone whose life appears to be going well on the outside, but like is your inner world consistent
with your outer world, right? And there are ways of formalizing this potentially in your own practice
setting, right? But then in the broader settings of sort of non-mental health helping, right? So
look for vectors that run counter current to the person's stated and healthy intentions, right? And
try and get some assessment of what's going on in the person's inner world, right? Because even if
things are going well in the outer world, but these problems are there in the inner world, they
represent risks for the future, right? And again, I come back to like, it's not that hard to do. And
I think that you're just reflexively doing this, right? Because you're in a sense applying common
sense of, you know, in the practice is if there's something here that seems outside of the fold I'm
operating in, that seems mental health, then you make a referral, right? But the health systems in
our society as a whole can be doing this to help people because it's not that hard to take stock of
someone's interstate. If you, if, you know, if you sit down and talk with them and you establish the
right rapport, or to call out when they're acting counter current with their stated intentions. And
a lot of times the general medical systems kind of push that under the rug because they don't know
what to do about it, right? So they keep trying to treat the diabetes as best they can with some
knowledge in their head that like, you know, this, this lovely person who wants to be healthy isn't
really on board with this, right? But if you don't know what to do about that, or the last 10 referrals
you've made to mental health, haven't yielded anything because three months down the road,
the person got a Prozac prescription and they're no better, right? Then there's a sense of futility
to it. And again, I think if we come back to well-grounded common sense approaches, it does,
it's not all that complicated and it doesn't have to be that esoteric.
Do you, do you think there will be a day when shame is out in the open, right? Because I mean,
that's really what this comes down to, right? You have the stigma of trauma and then you have the,
the, the vector of shame that works so effectively at keeping it in the dark.
Right. And what does a world look like in which the light switch gets turned on and shame has to
retreat to the corner and cower as opposed to let its cape sit over that, which needs to be exposed?
I mean, I think a big part of that is an education process in our societies, right? That I think you
should start with. And when you say education, what do you mean? Does this, is this something
that occurs in schools? Is this something that occurs in medical schools? Is this something
that is for doctors only? I mean, where, you know, should police be aware of this? I mean, like,
how, how broad a net do you cast? Sure. I think you cast a very broad net and I think it's not
that hard to do that. So I think it starts in early education, right? When you, when you talk
about what goes on in people, when they feel bad, right? When something makes them feel good,
what happens inside of you? What do you do with that feeling? Right? Help the bully understand
why he or she is bullying, right? When we're, when we're in first or second grade, it goes,
let's help that person understand and look at that person. How would that be done? I mean,
that would require teachers now understanding this, right? Yeah. I think we, we do educate
the professionals. Like we educate the doctors, we educate the teachers. I mean, there's so much
that we do in the education processes that I don't think I'm saying, well, let's bolt on some
process that tries to turn everyone into a therapist, right? But, but there's so many
things that are done. Think about in medicine, like how many checklists, how much paperwork,
who's done this utterly and completely non-contributory and everybody knows it, right?
Why not an approach that's not paperwork intensive or time intensive, right? That just looks at,
look at part of trying to understand somebody is thinking about them through this framing,
right? And, and structuring the mental health resources so that there is a place to send
someone, right? There's a place where we're going to have basic conversations about what's going on
inside of them that then gates the care, right? There are ways we can do this that involve pretty
basic education that can change again, this idea of the whole soup that we're swimming in,
right? Where we start with early education, right? And we run that through educating
professionals, right? Educating police, educating legal systems, right? There are mental health
courts now. I mean, they're, they're not nearly as widespread as they should be, but we are trying
to educate doctors in the legal process and the education process, but we're not prioritizing it
with a sense of urgency, right? It can be different, but we've got to look at it and we've got to say,
yeah, this is worth paying attention to, right? Is this what's in large part or in very significant
part, driving that we have now over 100,000 drug deaths in this country over the course of a year,
like why do we not feel a sense of urgency and want to look at our, the way that we provide help,
right? And to say, do what we're doing, does what we're doing that drives doctors to burnout,
right? Which is a term that I can't stand. I mean, when I grew up, burnout was a negative term to say
about somebody. Oh, they couldn't handle it, right? And now they're just in a corner smoking cigarettes
doing their own thing. Like that was an insult to someone. And now we level that at doctors
who are often traumatized by the health systems that they work in and the unreasonable expectations
and that they're treating charts and computers all the time and don't have enough time with their
patients. Like why do we not look at this and say, has this gone mad, right? That we spend more money
than any developed country on healthcare, yet we have the worst outcomes. And we're the worst
about things that involve direct contact with humans, preventive aspects of healthcare,
treatment over time. Like why can't we look at this with a sense of urgency that says, oh,
this isn't working, right? And then I think at the other end, people who other people look to and
have a sense of respect for that will talk about their own trauma, right? As, you know, in some
very small way, like I'm trying to do, right? And you do, right? And Tim Ferriss has done and even
Stephanie Germanata, so Lady Gaga, who is kind to write the forward for the book, that she talks
about her humanness, right? That we all, no matter who we are, are susceptible to this. So from the
one end, people who have any power whatsoever and authority need to not shrink away from this. So if
I'm giving a talk to a bunch of doctors, right, I'm not going to pretend that I don't have any trauma,
right? So yes, we need, I think have a responsibility to be open and honest about the
things that have impacted us if we have any public presence whatsoever, right? Let alone if a person
has a big public presence, if that can be done safely and reasonably for the person, of course.
So that's one aspect of it. And the other aspect is the most important is on this grassroots level
of changing how we frame mental health in the world around us and starting to get us curious
about it at very early stages of life. When that bully tells you that you're lousy because of what
you look like or where you come from, right? Then what does that make you feel? Let's start looking
at that reflexive sense of shame, right? Okay, can you stop and think about that, right? Like you
feel bad, right? When that happens and what happens next? Well, you feel bad about yourself,
right? Okay, let's put a full stop there, right? Like that person's hurting you because he feels
bad about himself, right? Like, and you don't, so then you start to put a barrier, right? Between
the reflexive shame, right? And the person feeling bad about themselves. Because how many people
don't actually logically feel bad about themselves, right? But they do actually feel bad about
themselves and it's the feeling that matters, not the facts, right? And we've got to start looking
at that because that is the plain and obvious truth that pervades the society around us. And
we are doing a very poor job of developing understanding in us as individuals at any stage
of life and as a society. And I can't believe that we're not seeing the dysfunction in the social
rifts that we're having in the ineffectiveness of the whole of our medical system, right? These are
big all-encompassing aspects of our society and we see, hey, these things are not going well,
right? And if we look at the roots of it, I think it's clear where a lot of it is coming from and
also what we can do about it. Which is why I feel the book is ultimately uplifting. I mean, I'm
pointing out problems, but I'm not pointing them out in some way of like pointing them out and then
we'll, we don't want to do about it, right? I mean, I'm pointing out solutions that I think
are quite simple and well-grounded. And if we just follow them through, that's resonating with
people because I think it does resonate with common sense. A moment ago, you alluded to a
statistic that I think for many people is just almost impossible to fathom, which is the United
States has just for the first time ever surpassed a 100,000 person mortality for a 12 month period.
So 100,000 people have overdosed in the United States for the first time in 12 months. Do you
see this as an epidemic of trauma and shame, or do you see this as really just a new escape valve
for it based on the availability of cheap and unfortunately highly potent opioids?
Yeah, I think it's a combination of both. And I think the data tells us that more and more people
are feeling desperate and disenfranchised, right? Are feeling like, look, I can't make my way in the
world, right? Whatever my chosen route of endeavor is, I can't make a living in that, right? I can't
support a family in that. I can't get ahead. I can't feel good about myself, right? And we see that in
aspects like almost the entire service industry, right? Which has changed to a place where people
can't have careers that then support their lives and support a family, like was the case even 20
something years ago, right? We see that even people who have good jobs, right? Who feel like,
okay, I finally got my way for work on if I have a good job. That often that job is running them
ragged in a way that they can't take care of themselves and they can't take care of their
families. And they feel the same desperation as a person who doesn't have a job, right? And this
desperation builds anger and frustration and resentment and all these other symptoms, depression
and panic that spin off of it, right? And that makes it much more appealing to soothe in the
short term. Like that's a basic psychological fact of human beings, right? The more pain you're in in
the short term, the more you're going to choose a short term solution without any consideration to
the long term, right? I mean, if I'm absolutely desperately miserable and you've got something
that can make me better right now, I'm not going to ask what that may do to me tomorrow, right?
So we have developed a society that has become more and more and more hardhearted, right? Towards
people's attempts to make their way in the world, right? And I think we see that with the response
to the pandemic of, you know, I'm going to respond in the way that I want and I don't really care
about you, right? And like we've seen enough of that, that, you know, cringe at times at our, like
our inability to even have basic compassion for others, which of course isn't everyone, right? But
like, I think that's present in society in ways that it wasn't before. And I think it's reflected
in the rhetoric and the dialogue that's acceptable, right? That not that long ago, the way people often
behave who have a public presence, right? Would have led to censure by everyone that would say,
Hey, I don't even care that you're advocating for what I want or even for me directly. Like,
I can't support you if you're going to behave that way, talk that way, denigrate people that way.
Like we've moved far away from that, right? And we need to look at what are we doing in the world
around us, right? How are we handling ourselves and are we indirectly promoting this ethic of
not really caring, right? That leads to the desperation that leads people to soothe with
drugs, right? There's a very macabre, it's not even a joke, it's a tragic
atrocity, right? That people will say, Oh, I'm, you know, gosh, I have four people who are drug
addicted in my practice. I'm going to see this afternoon or, you know, or 10 people, right? And
you know, it's not who it used to be, right? Because before it was people who'd sifted down
to places in society where societies really turned their backs on them. Now it's people from all walks
of life, right? And we see that socioeconomic demographic, educational demographic, geographic,
demographic, racial, religious, ethnic concept, we've gone beyond that, right? Where now we're
all menaced by this, right? Because there's often a desperation to soothe that there wasn't that shot
through every demographic we have. And if we continue to turn away from that fact, then we
continue to look at statistics like that and say, Oh my gosh, how horrible. Okay, right? Like we
don't do anything about it, right? Which is a tacit acceptance of it, right? If we don't look at what
are we doing to people that drives them to desperation, right? Then we're not going to
make that statistic better. And how much is going on behind closed doors in the pandemic? How much
violence behind closed doors, neglect behind closed doors, drug and alcohol abuse behind closed doors,
are we going to look more at this or are we going to just pay lip service to looking at it,
right? While we don't actually change anything. And then we'll be going, Oh my gosh, it's so
terrible. It's three years from now that number is 140,000, right? Well, if we don't really care now
as a society, we just want to marvel at the number and say how bad it is and do nothing.
Well, it's exactly where we're going to go. That's why the number has been increasing, right?
I mean, it's not rocket science to say that either. You just extrapolate that line ahead
and that gets worse and not better. Unless we look at it in a way where we accept like,
we got to do something different, right? Because this is staggering in the human misery that it
speaks to not just a hundred thousand people lost, not just, right? I mean, not just a hundred
thousand people. What about all the people who love those hundred thousand people? Like,
what are we doing? Right? Which is why when people would say, Oh, sometimes I'll get approached,
I'm doing something that's very niche, right? Like I'm interested in trauma, right? And I say,
well, this is not a niche, right? You get up to numbers like that, right? There's a cascade
through the population, right? And it doesn't have to be like this that our burdens of trauma just
grow and grow and grow. We should be appalled by that number, appalled enough to do something
about it. Paul, a lot of times we treat people based on the symptom of their trauma or we at
least categorize them that way. And this is even within the lens of helping people and acknowledging
their trauma. So for example, addiction is a very common manifestation of trauma. And
the most obvious of those, or at least the one that probably gets most people's attention would
be substance addiction, right? Alcohol or drugs, but there's work addiction. There's process
addiction. There's gambling addiction. There's sex addiction. There are actually lots of other
types of addictions, but we could bucket those as addictions. There's codependencies. There's anger,
perfectionism, other means of control. We talked about eating disorders.
It seems that one way to think about this is treating people together who have similar end
states. So you go to a 12 step meeting because if it's AA, it's people with alcohol. If it's
Al-Anon, it's family members of people with alcohol. If it's NA, it's narcotics. If it's
essay, et cetera, it's sex. Has anyone ever thought about doing the opposite, which is
rather than take everybody whose issue is alcohol addiction and having them come to a meeting, which
by the way, I'm not advocating against. What if we bundled people together through the common lens
of what the trauma was? Is that something that's ever been thought about? And would that be more
or less efficacious than the current approach? In other words, you have a meeting which has lots
of people in it who have very different manifestations of their trauma. You're going
to have someone who's addicted to alcohol, someone who's a workaholic, someone who's a rageaholic,
someone who's a completely codependent, someone who's got debilitating anxiety, someone who's got
debilitating depression. But what they all have in common is they were completely neglected by their
parents. That's their common thing. Would there be any advantage to doing that or is it better the
way we typically think of doing it? Yeah, I think there's a huge advantage to that. And
at one point I was medical director for a clinic and we had programs running for helping groups.
And it was by and large, it was all around substances, but I wouldn't separate it by
what the substance was. I think we even get that fine. Now we're going to separate by what the
substance is. Alcohol versus narcotics. Right. And even at that level, let alone at the higher
levels of this person is angry, this person is addicted to unhealthy foods. Right. There's so
many ways in which the addictive processes can take hold of our brains in order to provide some
short-term sense of control or short-term relief from the desperation of feeling out of control.
Right. And when we parse that out too much, then again, we're just trying to check
boxes and we're telling that person that what you have, this thing that is in a sense your burden
to carry is so much about you. Right. Well, I'm an alcoholic and I'm a rage-aholic. Right.
And there's just the very language we use about that is often so stigmatizing. That's the thing
that's bad about you. Right. Like that's often the message. Again, not always, but that's often
the message that it sends as opposed to like none of us comes out of the womb. Right. And alcoholic
or rage-aholic or addicted to unhealthy foods. Right. They have like, look, what's happened to
us along the way, right, that leads us to this place. And that's how we make a search for
commonality. Right. So, so we have a set of processes that want to further parse things out.
Right. We're so overly reductionist. Right. That oftentimes we would see where the person who was
an alcoholic would feel like, well, I don't want to sit in a room with it with the person who's
addicted to cocaine. Like we don't, as if there's like nothing in common. Right. As opposed to like,
yeah, what's what is in common? Because I knew the health histories of those people, right?
Because I was the medical director of the clinic. Right. And, and I would say, right, what, what is
80% commonality as a driving force amongst everybody is trauma. Right. And, and, and that's
just here. If you step further back, you see that across the things that we, we get short-term relief
from at the expense of our long-term health. And the over reductionism, I think is a facet of
wanting to just put things in little buckets and then gaining some satisfaction from that.
Right. But now, okay. Now all it is is in a bucket and actually being in that much of a bucket,
right? You know, like a marble that goes down, right? Is like, now you can't get to it. Right.
Or you can't get to what's real about it instead of like, you know, what's going on in a lot of
people say at least is trauma. Can we put those people together and look at trauma, which
ironically is what the real sophisticated helping resources around trauma are doing.
Right. I mean, that's often what say the bridge to recovery is doing. It's looking at like,
Hey, what is your trauma? Right. Okay. Now let's go forward from there. Right. But that's because
they're bringing a sophistication to it. And people who do that work just reflexively know that they
know that that, that that's not different. You can look at people who are addicted to one thing
versus another, and you're not finding massive differences between them. And, you know, the
aspects of art, the science of it all catching up with it shows that, right? It's hijacking the
same machinery in the brain. And you know, you can't tell the difference. Not like one substance
looks different from another in the brain or one thing a person is addicted to for relief of
distress. So it's like, we know all of it, but we have these entrenched ways of looking at it
through the lens of, of how medical care is or how society views it. And we're so far beyond the
science, right? And I will say this that, you know, say this a fair amount that if you're in
a very well-defined field of medicine, let's say cardiology or so, where we kind of know
how to assess people, how to understand people, there's a lot of data behind the interventions.
If you're practicing, like, you know, even just a couple of years ago, like that's not okay. And
one will identify that, right? And, and that's not okay, right? We'll have to change that, right?
But in mental health, the practice within individual practitioners and the systems
can be antiquated by a half a century, right? Or, you know, or a couple thousand years in some
cases. And like, we don't come in and look at that, right? There are programs that are taking care of
people for opiate dependence that don't even talk to them about a medicine that you can get a shot
of that prevents you from overdosing when you leave, right? Like it's somehow okay not to even
talk about that, right? Because we let all of this lag behind. And yes, part of it is, I think,
how the field has handled it and the science isn't as well developed, but it's not like there's no
science and it's not like there's no obviousness to what we could be doing that we're just simply not
doing. And I think a big part of that is the stigma, the shame that we don't want to come in and look
at all of it and say there's an obvious here that we're just not paying attention to. Because if the
shame is shot through humans, then it is also shot through the humans who are making those
decisions around resource allocation and how do we approach the helping process?
Changing gears for a second, Paul. The final thing I want to kind of ask you about is
the role of two substances in particular psilocybin and MDMA, both of which I've talked
about in previous podcasts as they pertain to trauma. I'm curious as to what your experience
is with this and maybe more importantly, what is your optimism around these two molecules,
both of which are really moving quite along a pathway towards a clinical approval, a legalization
for clinical use. In the case of MDMA, it is for in fact PTSD. So kind of curious as to whether you
see that as an amazing adjunct to what we're talking about or a slight adjunct or potentially
less. I see it as among the brightest sort of shining hopes for the future. And I think the data
both from decades ago and the more recent data and the clinical experience in trials and the
firsthand reports tell us things that are so incredibly powerful and that fit with a lot of
what we've thought about and understood about brain biology and about psychology. There's a way
in which it provides so much greater potential for understanding and helping. And of course,
the process is in place so that these very, very powerful tools can be understood and deployed
safely and effectively. And in the context of all of that, I think that the hope is immense.
A story I'll tell sometimes to try to capture that is where I grew up was close to the Delaware
Raritan Canal. In colonial times, it ran between New York and Philadelphia. It was part of a network.
I was always fascinated that artifacts would be found. There's somebody to be fishing and find a
vase or something. And I was amazed. These barges went up and down. I'm like, what's in there?
And people would find things and that was interesting. But then at some point in time,
they drained a whole section of it. And when the section was drained, my goodness,
what they found and what they saw. And it's the same analogy that I think the helping powers of
these substances are so strong that they can get us to places of really seeing what's going on
inside of us and shifting how those brain pathways, which have been so changed. And again,
the science tells us this, this is not esoteric. We have more science that is similar to what
the CAT scans can do for the appendix to see that being able to do that with these helping
modalities allows for understanding and is so predisposes to and is permissive of change
in ways that can let people reorient much, much faster. So I think there's a potential here for
even a revolution within the field, but we have to safely and effectively incorporate those arrows
into the quiver. And then we see, of course, what is often seen, which is many of the people or
organizations wielding that have the magic amulet of like, I am the source of the helping resources,
don't like this. So we see some aspects of traditional psychiatric care that don't like
this. And I think that's through a sense of threat that I think the power of these resources
make a lot of the tools that I wield seem maybe a little bit paltry in comparison. Now, that's not
always the case. And if that is the case, wonderful. There are new powerful tools coming to the fore.
We need to approach it, those of us in Western medicine, through a lens of being respectful of
what that is and wanting to understand the new modalities and approaching it from a lens that
says, look, if I'm going to help people, I'm going to hold myself forth as knowing how to do so,
then I better know what all the arrows in the quiver are and understand them enough that I can
either deploy them or I can understand who can deploy them in a way that does justice to the
person coming in the door, right? If I'm coming in the door for help, I don't care what it is.
I want the person who's going to help me and have all the possible arrows in their quiver. And I
think we can get to a place of incorporating this. But again, society and the helping systems have to
bend a little bit to acknowledge the incredible potential. And then we work towards integrating
instead of splitting. And we're in a societal mode in this country that's very much splitting,
whether it's sociological, it's political, and even medical, right? And I think, again, I come
back to the basic theme of, I think it's trauma that leads us to reject new helping resources
because they may be threatening to our power within a discipline, right? And that by regrounding to
really the first principles of knowledge and of helping, then I think we again come back to an
urgency to ground ourselves to the basic common sense of understanding everything that could be
helpful and having all of those arrows in the quiver of health systems or of, to the extent
possible, individual practitioners. Paul, as always, it's great to sit down with you. And especially
in a case like this where it's not just me you're talking to, but so many other people who I suspect
will really benefit from this. Tell people again the title of your book and other places they can
look to find resources. Sure. So the title of the book is Trauma, The Invisible Epidemic. And you
can find it if you just Google me, Paul Conti, or the clinic I work in, which is Pacific Premier
Group. You'll come up with links that talk a little bit about the book or the principles
contained therein. And there's so many good helping resources around. NAMI is one of them
that across the country has- And sorry, is that NAMI? What's that?
Yeah, so NAMI. Okay, NAMI.
I say so. A great access to resources often on a local level. There's so much help to be
had. And some of that help we can access in our own homes. We can access through people that we
love and who love us. We can access by thinking about what's going on inside of us and others.
And I think that's such a part of the message that I want to deliver that it just isn't esoteric.
And if we ground to what's really going on inside of us and paying attention to it, and
in a sense being brave enough to face it because we see hope in facing it that we can begin a
process of really helping ourselves and others. And I've just seen that unfold so, so many times,
including in myself, that I really believe in it. And I'm so glad that we've had this conversation
that is about some of the real big picture of it and some of the more kind of rarified
medical aspects of it. And I think a real understanding of it runs the whole gamut,
but is ground in that simplicity of what's really needed and what's important to help
ourselves and to help other people. And I so appreciate you having me on and having such a
good friend who's also such a good colleague and helps this discussion unfold in a way that really
helps get the message out there because we all need the message. Thank you, Paul. You're welcome.
Thank you. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in
diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple
Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only, does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.