Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Carl. It is so good to see you today, although admittedly across video,
but it's like a little blast from the past from, I don't know, 20 years ago, right?
Yeah, it's amazing. We had a good group of friends back in the old days at Stanford,
and I haven't kept in touch with them as much as I'd hoped, but it's great to see you.
It really brings back a lot of memories. You look great, unchanged.
Well, yeah, that's funny. You don't look a bit different. It is funny when I think back to that
class of ours in med school, and I really feel like the overwhelming underachiever of our class.
And I remember our first day of our surgical rotation, you, me, and Josh Rabinowitz,
sitting in that room waiting for us to be assigned to which service we would go to.
Of course, you and Josh have gone on to do unbelievable things. I've sort of modeled along.
Now you're the star. And plus, I remember, even though it was the start of our surgery rotation,
you already knew how to do everything, which I was impressed by. You knew all the knots,
and I was like, wait, this is the first day of the rotation. How do you do that?
Well, let's pick it up back there. So you were in the MD-PhD program, so we didn't start at the
same time. We just finished at the same time. You had come in earlier. But I think the reason I knew
you even on our first day of surgery was because you had done your PhD in the same lab as two other
friends of mine, Alex Rabinowitz and Jason Pyle. And all kidding aside, I think that, look, all the
kids that went to med school were pretty bright. But I think the MD-PhD students were sort of in a
class of their own. And I suspect it was even harder to get into that program than it was just
the straight MD program. So thinking back to your time as an undergrad, but what did you major in
again in undergrad? I did biochemical sciences, they call it, at Harvard instead of biochemistry.
They had to do everything different, and they didn't call it a major either. It was a concentration.
So I concentrated in biochemical sciences. So there you go. But I had a lot of other interests.
All my friends were physicists, theoretical physicists, in fact. And so I was exposed to some
pretty unusual stuff for a biochemist. And were they allowed to call it theoretical physics at
Harvard? They were. Okay, that's good. I just want to... Good question, yes. They were allowed to name
it. Good, good. So at what point during your biological science concentration did you know
you wanted to go into medicine? It was pretty early because I was interested in the brain early on,
and I wanted to understand the brain at the level of cells. But I was also interested in the most
high level aspects of brain function. And so I thought I needed to talk to human beings. I needed
some access to the human brain. I found that interesting because I was interested in emotion
and the ability to express feelings through words. And I was torn. I liked writing and literature
and the use of words, and I liked cells and biology. And I wanted to somehow fuse them,
and it seemed that medical school was the way to go because I could work with the human brain.
And obviously you could have just gone to medical school, but you also selected into this very,
very advanced program that was incredibly selected, the MST program, the Medical Science
Training Program. And so that tells me at the outset that you also knew you wanted to do research
beyond, quote unquote, just clinical medicine, yes? Yeah, that's right. And that was the nice
thing about the MSTP is it lets you delay making a commitment. So you keep both threads alive.
And then there's a beautiful synergy that can happen too, and certainly happened with me that
you realize, oh, wait, I don't have to make this decision. It actually is good to keep both threads
alive in my work and my life. And that's what happened. But it's a pretty special thing we have
in the United States. There are efforts along these lines in Europe and other countries,
but it's not nearly as institutionalized as it is here. It's a really special thing.
Well, it really is. And again, I keep saying this, but I feel like there were maybe what,
six or eight MSTPs per class. And I always felt like you guys had the most pressure on you,
right? There was this expectation from both the clinical side that you would go on to be great
doctors, but then you were also, especially at places like Stanford, where you had the opportunity
to do your PhDs with Nobel laureates, would be Nobel laureates, exceptional scientists, that you
would also basically be leading the charge scientifically. And for what it's worth, all of
my friends in the MSTP program, I think you're the only one that ended up doing clinical training as
well. I think most of them didn't end up doing residencies. They either went purely into academic
research tracks or actually went into industry. But before we get into the fact that you also
did clinical training, let's talk a little bit about that transition. You came into medical school
pretty hell bent on neurosurgery. Yeah. That was the goal because, you know, again, how do you,
how do you get access to the, to the human brain and who among the different clinical specialties
has that access? Who can, who can, would most directly interact, study? And it seemed to me
the neurosurgeons had it all. And if one were to build an interface with the brain, if one wanted
to both communicate with a person as they were expressing feelings and emotions and to understand
at the level of cells what was going on, who could do that? But a neurosurgeon was my, was my
reasoning. And, you know, and I, the neurosurgeons that my, that my colleagues and friends that are
amazing people, you know, brilliant. And, and I, I saw no reason not to, to pursue that. And so that
was the first rotation that I, I selected in those second two years of medical school, even before
surgery, I did neurosurgery. And so, which was kind of interesting, just, just coming in there with,
with no general surgical training as well. That's how, how certain I was.
Yeah. It's funny. Well, I had a similar experience whereas the thing I absolutely positively thought
I was going to do, I picked as my first rotation. In my case, I had less of a pleasant experience
than you. I think you had a pleasant experience on neurosurgery. It wasn't that in any way you
didn't like it, but what was your first? Well, I, I planned to do pediatric oncology. So I,
I went out of the gates with two months of pediatrics, which, which actually I didn't enjoy
largely because I just didn't feel like I didn't fit in. I think so much of your medical school
experience in terms of your clinical rotations is a function of how well do you fit in with the
residents of that specialty. And I didn't feel like I fit in with the pediatricians. They didn't
laugh at my jokes. They thought I was probably a little too obnoxious. I probably spent too
much time imitating Dr. Evil and Fat Bastard, pretending to eat the babies, but it just,
the whole thing just didn't go well. It was a disaster. And then my next rotation was general
surgery where we connected. And even though I had no desire whatsoever to go into surgery,
that became a, a kind of overnight love and away we go. But so, so you're doing your neurosurgery
rotation, which again, yes, highly unusual that you would do that so early in your training. That's
usually something one does in the fourth year, not the third year. And I mean, I'll say this,
Carl, when I did general surgery at Hopkins, I did one month of neurosurgery as a rotation,
having never been interested in neurosurgery. So sort of saying, well, fine, I'll do this. I didn't
have a choice. I had to do this month of neurosurgery and I fell in love with it. I couldn't,
and in fact, I spoke to the program director at Hopkins and said,
would it be ridiculous for me to try to transfer into neurosurgery? That's how much I enjoyed it.
And it turned out that he said, I can absolutely get you in, but it won't be at Hopkins. Hopkins
is the most competitive neurosurgery program in the country. We only take three people.
It's already full. You're not going to get in here, but I can get you to another program. And I,
I actually contemplated it for about a month. So I can see the appeal of it. There was something
about cutting open the dura and operating on the brain. And it's a surprisingly simple organ in
that sense. Like at the gross level, it's surprisingly simple. Obviously, much of what
we're going to talk about today, Carl, is not at the gross level where it's anything but simple,
but what was your experience like? I mean, it was, yeah, at the one, at one level, it is an organ.
And, and it's, it would be unfair to say that all that neurosurgeons get to do is think about it as
an organ. They do have to think about that, the blood supply and, and, and the, whether the cells
are receiving enough oxygen and, and, and, and glucose. And they have to think about it in the,
in the context of the physicality of it, perhaps more than the, the, the mentation aspect of it.
And so, but they, they, they do get to think about high level concepts in that rotation. In that
month, there was a patient who had a little bit of a thalamic infarct as a result of the, the
surgery and a little bit of loss of tissue in the thalamus. And the patient had a neglect
syndrome, which I spent a lot of time working with the patient afterward, characterizing exactly
how this worked. You know, I asked the patient to draw a clock and the patient drew, you know,
just half of a clock. And it was an amazing, you know, classical thing, but amazing to see with
your own eyes as you're talking to another person and the person said, oh, the clock looks fine.
It's a, but it was a half a clock. And, and that certainly didn't diminish my interest in neurosurgery
at all. It was, you know, this was at the one level, you know, there were problems, which nearly
clearly needed to be better, you know, aspects of, of neurosurgery as with every clinical specialty
needed to improve, needed to reduce, you know, consequences like that. And yet at the same time,
it was incredibly interesting as well. I loved the operating room. I loved the suturing, although
I wasn't as good as you, I think. And I, I, but I was good enough. And it was particularly because
it was so early. I think the promise was there, it would have worked out. And it was, it still had
a magic about it. You know, when you, when the Dura is exposed, it's a, it's, yes, it's, it's an
organ, but it's a, there's a spirituality to that, to know that, that you're actually looking at the,
the storehouse of human beings, you know, thoughts and feelings and, and everything about them all,
all encapsulated in this collection of cells. It's, it's quite an amazing thing. And so I had no
negativity at all. I did note that neurosurgeons, they, they didn't get a lot of free time. There
was not a lot of, you know, philosophizing. And I noticed, you know, it's a seven year
progression. And I talked to all the neurosurgery residents and I noted a steady decline and
willingness to philosophize as their progression through the residency continued. You could almost
plot that, you know, literally on a, on a graph. And, and with all, you know, due credit to them,
it's the nature of the system they're in that they don't necessarily have all the time. They
would like to think deeply, although they certainly are very bright and thoughtful and
certainly could. And so I did note that I noted that, you know, here, here are people who maybe
don't have the freedom to do everything I would like. And that was in the back of my mind.
Yeah. I think back to the three people in my class. So at the entering class at Hopkins,
three of them were neurosurgery assigned. So they did the internship with us, but then they went
off and I mean, boy, they were, they were three ridiculously smart guys. Yeah. And you would think,
well, they're in neurosurgery. So how interested are they going to be in their year of general
surgery? But they were every bit the exceptional interns that, that the categoricals were the ones
who were going to go into general surgery. But one of the experiences that jumps out at me from my
month of general surgery at in my internship was an awake procedure we did on a patient. So under
local anesthetic, the brain was opened and the patient while wide awake was being probed in an
effort to determine certain symptoms and to see what part of the brain could be lesioned in order
to ameliorate these symptoms. And I think for anybody to see that in real life with their own
eyes even once is it's, it's really hard to believe what you're watching, right? First of all,
the brain is not the same sensory organ. The fact that you can be awake while a surgeon is probing
into your brain and firing an electrical impulse into one area or another to see how it changes
this part of your visual field or this part of your, I mean, that was, that was something that
was a magic that I don't think I could describe otherwise. Yeah. And, and that, I felt that very,
very strongly. And so there was, it was all systems go after that. They, you know, surprisingly,
the neurosurgeons at Stanford liked me okay after that too. I got very positive feedback from them.
And, and, and they said, Hey, you know, come back and do a sub-i sub-entrinship and we'd love to,
to get you down this path. So which, which was a, you know, that, that was a, that was a green light.
And I was, I was happy with that. It was, it was where I was headed. Of course, things changed
after that. Yeah. So the best laid plans, there was another mandatory, there's set of mandatory
rotations we have to do neurosurgery, not being one of them, but pediatrics, general surgery,
internal medicine being the OBGYN. And one of them is psychiatry, kind of this afterthought for,
you know, the medical student, right? Very few people want to go into psychiatry.
And yet amazingly, two of the smartest people in my med school class, you and Paul Conti end up
picking this field ultimately. Just amazing, right? So tell me about your, how did you go into your
psychiatry rotation? Were you looking forward to this or did you view it the way many of us did,
which was just get me through it. I had a get me through it, you know, attitude coming in. And again,
no disrespect to psychiatry, of course, you know, it's a, they have a hard challenge. Still,
we have this challenge that there's not a, a measurable really, you know, we have, we have
effectively, you know, questions we ask patients, it's all with words is how we work. And no biomarker.
No biomarker still. Yeah. I mean, there's efforts along those lines, looking at EEG, you know,
ratios of this to that and there's progress being made, but still clinically, you can't make
diagnoses based on measuring something about the brain and psychiatry. You can, you can notice that
there's something else going on, a neurological or medical problem, but you can't define someone's
psychiatric state with, with a, some biomarker. And that still amazing to this day, still true.
Yeah. So what, tell me about your psych rotation. Cause I remember we kind of had choices. I did an
entirely outpatient month, which I ended up finding quite enjoyable. That's the irony of
these things. You kind of, I did it as one of my last rotations prior to graduation, which meant
there was no chance, even if I'd liked it, I was too late for me to make that choice. I had already
matched, I think in general surgery, but it was an outpatient month. So relatively low acuity.
But, but interesting nevertheless, what, what was your month like?
So my mind was the opposite of that. It was, and this was probably a fortunate thing for me.
It was in the locked unit at the VA at the Veterans Administration Hospital. And this was a,
a unit where patients can't leave. And this is due to, you know, being a danger to themselves
or a danger to others or having a greater disability. And this, you know, these patients
were severely ill. And I walked into that. You know, I'd had typical experiences. Everybody,
you know, has friends or family who've had, you know, depression or anxiety. I'd had,
I'd seen substance abuse and intoxicated states and dementia. And I had a fairly, you know,
I thought decently broad understanding of what can go wrong on the, on the psychiatric side.
But I can tell you nothing, and you, you know this by now, but, but I can, I can tell your,
your viewers and listeners, there is nothing like what you can see when you walk into the,
the locked ward of a psychiatric hospital. There's a, there's the, there's a sort of a purity,
not in a good way, but there's a, because there's not confounding issues like intoxication and so
on, there's a, there's a consistency and a purity to the disorders. And so if you have someone with
acute schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, other things that might confound what's going on
have been removed. And there's this very strong, acute, straightforward expression of the symptoms.
That's just mind boggling to see if you haven't experienced it before. And, and that's, that was,
was my experience and it completely changed my course. There was a, even on the, you know, my
very first day, there was a, a patient with schizoaffective disorder, which is a very severe
combination of mood and psychotic symptoms that are all mixed up together. And this patient
accosted me in the, in the locked unit, started screaming at me and, and, but it was, it was not
necessarily sort of a street encounter that you might have in a, in a city. It was more,
it was more direct and personal and evocative of something going on in the, in the mind of the
patient that was clearly a source of immense suffering, of great disability. And yet at the
same time, it was, it was tantalizing because this was a human being who was physically intact,
but whose reality was so completely different from mine. We were two people with intact bodies and,
and, and brains who were, you know, next to each other. And we inhabited completely different
realities. And to experience that was a utterly transformative moment. And, and I both seen the,
the suffering and realizing I have no idea what's going on here, but it's incredibly
interesting too. How is this possible? How could this be happening to a human being? And,
and without that direct exposure, I don't know what would have happened, but having had it,
it changed my course. Which is interesting. I mean, many people when confronted with that would be
quite frightened, especially when you realize the limitations of the tools that you have,
right? So let's, let's consider another analogy, which is, you know, a patient that comes in with
a gunshot wound to the chest. That's an incredibly frightening experience. There's literally, you know,
a sucking chest wound, blood could be splaying around the room, vital signs are crashing,
the person's on the verge of death. But that can be exciting in a way because we actually have the
tools to do something, right? It might be completely draconian. We might be doing a
thoracotomy in the ER, cross clamping the aorta, but you run that patient to the OR and you know
how to fix them. You're experiencing something that I would argue is much more frightening,
but compounded by the fact that what do you do? I mean, you could temporarily give that person
howdall and, and sort of snow them, but that's not curing them. So was it, which of, was it more the,
we don't have the tools here. This is an unbelievable opportunity to learn or, or,
or, you know, how did that experience, which I think for many people could have been off-putting
do the exact opposite in you? I mean, I had, it's a, it's a great question because I, I,
and I would completely understand that the normal or typical reaction would be sort of an aversive
thing, you know, how this is, this is not something I want to spend my life doing in this,
in this setting. But I had a, I had a different reaction, which surprised me. And it was partly,
it was, it was really, there were two sides to it. One was exactly what you're saying.
The level of mystery here was actually for me, it was a positive rather than an aversive thing. And
maybe this was partly the, my scientific training, you know, at that point I'd completed my, my PhD
and, and, and I spent years trying to figure things out. And we all want to figure things out. That's
a natural human impulse. Not everybody necessarily spends years and years and years trying to figure
out the same thing. And that's, that's the kind of training we get in, in, in, in the PhD program.
And I saw that and I was like, okay, gotta figure this out. This is, this is clearly
a mystery that is something that it's a burden that humanity shares. It's a terrible burden that
this human being is suffering. But what's the solution? We've got to figure it out. We've got
to understand this. And, and it's a mystery that strikes to the heart of, of what it always intrigued
me, which is what is, what is an emotion physically? What is a feeling physically? How does the
collection of cells in our brains, and that's what it is. It's a collection of cells. How,
how is it possible that that creates a feeling and emotion? And I realized at that moment,
this is, this is actually, you know, why I came to medical school. This, and it all made sense in,
in one moment that, that hadn't before. And, and then, you know, of course, as a, as a,
as a physician, as you well know, we, our instinct is to help, is to heal and, and we want to do that.
But as you say, if we don't have the tools, what can we do? It's, it's a problem. And I wasn't
frustrated with the inability to do anything. And I would understand that reaction too.
And the fact is we, we could do a little bit though. So it wasn't quite nothing. And there
are medications back then and still that help somewhat. They don't come with understanding.
They don't help us explain to the patient or the family or to ourselves what's really going on,
but they do help a little bit. And so I was, I knew that I could do something, not much,
but a little bit. And as time went on, hopefully, and as the science progressed,
maybe we could do more. And so that, it fit together in a, in a moment. And I didn't have
another thought for neurosurgery after that, although it was, it was a hard process, you know,
to reshape what my trajectory was going to be. I had one set of plans. My friends and family had a
set of expectations. I can tell you, I think my, my father was pretty disappointed when I told him
on the phone that I was going to do psychiatry. I could hear it in his voice. It was, it was almost,
yeah, it was a quite a, and, you know, again, he, he came around in the end too. And, and I think
he's, he's happy now, but at the time I could, I could sense that this was not what he'd hoped
for me. So yeah, it was, it was an adjustment. It was a, a remapping, but it was a very compelling
experience that, that the process of medical training and the required psychiatry rotation
made possible. So Carl, you, you now make this decision to completely veer into this nearly
orthogonal track. I mean, psychiatry and neurosurgery, of course, have one thing in common, which is the,
the organ of interest is the brain, but at that point they basically, you know, differ.
How did you decide you were going to both pursue the clinical training, the residency for psychiatry,
but also do whatever was necessary to make sure that you could ultimately be running a lab? Because
I, I think throughout this period, you never lost sight unless I'm misremembering of the desire to
be a physician scientist and not just a physician. So, you know, residency, especially 20 years ago
when we did our residencies, they didn't have 80 hour work week requirements and things like that.
So residencies were quite demanding. Was it a little hard for you to say, Hey, I'm going to
actually have to put my research on hold for a little while? It was, it was hard. And this is,
there are a lot of challenges that people in this realm face because things move so quickly.
In the research realm that if you step aside for even a year, forget about four years, you know,
the world you reenter is, is so different and it's very hard to catch up. And this is, you know,
that's to some extent an old problem because that's been faced by everybody who planned
to do a residency. But it's, it's not negligible because it's an old problem. It's that issue,
exactly, that ends up driving people to make this hard choice that you mentioned earlier and saying,
you know, in the end, I'm going to have to do one or the other. If I do the residency,
I'll be a, I'll be a doctor. I'll be a good doctor, maybe a great doctor. I'll be,
I'll be informed by all my scientific training. Maybe I'll read papers better. Maybe I'll be more,
you know, amenable to new ideas, new treatments as a result of that. But ultimately I'll be a
physician or on the other side saying, you know, I'm not going to do the residency. I'm not going to
drop off this, this fast moving train. I'm at this moment, I've just finished my PhD. I'm a
world expert in this. I can do things that nobody else can do. Why lose that momentum? Why not
speed up, add the next tool in the tool belt, launch yourself and make great discoveries. And
that is very, very tempting. I had, you know, very clear opportunities to do that. And so that's the
hard choice that the MD PhD faces at that moment. Now efforts are made to ameliorate that. So
residencies, you know, again, this was the time still where the residencies were extremely
difficult. And I had some, for me, this was compounded by some personal challenges. I was
effectively a single dad at the time. And so I had to also think about this other factor,
very important. Now I've got to think about residency. I've got to think about lab. I've
got to think about family. And it was very, very challenging. And yet there are these research track
residencies and they help a little bit. So there are, and Stanford and other, you know, programs,
both in psychiatry and in other specialties, they have efforts to help people keep their
scientific, you know, mind alive during residency. And it's not great, but it's a little bit, a little
bit of protected time here and there. Never quite enough to get momentum, but at least to keep a
foot in the lab and try to stay connected. And so I did that. It was a research track,
psychiatry residency. And I stayed at Stanford and a big factor in that was that literally at the
same time, and I was very fortunate in this regard, a guy named Rob Malenka, who was a psychiatrist and
a great neuroscientist, was at that moment coming from UCSF to Stanford. He had come and was setting
up his lab at Stanford. And I knew, here's somebody, a psychiatrist, but also a neuroscientist.
He'll understand, you know, what's going on in my residency that I'm, you know, I'm taking call,
I'm up all night. He'll know, he'll understand why I'm never in the lab during expected hours,
why I'm never at lab meeting. And that made it work out. And I worked nights and weekends.
I maybe came to one of his lab meetings over four years and I effectively did a combined
postdoctoral fellowship and psychiatry residency at the same time at Stanford.
Some funny stories. I, you know, because Stanford's very compact, as you know,
I could literally take call from, you know, from the lab. I'd be patch clamping. I'd be up at the
rig, you know, listening in, making measurements on currents flowing across a single cell.
And I'd get paged, go walk over to the ER, admit a patient, come back, you know, patch
clamp the next cell. And it was a pretty special moment when that happened that felt like the
different parts of my life were, like, they could work together. They could be compatible. And that,
with all, you know, so many people have such a hard time understandably making that work,
making the pieces fit together. And I feel fortunate that I was able to make that work.
Now, what year was your son born? Ninety-eight?
He was actually born in 96. So he is 25.
So you're four, he is five years old, basically, when you're in the midst of this.
Yeah, that's right.
So how did you manage that?
You know, it was these, this is actually something that I touch on. I know we may talk about this,
the book I wrote projections later, but it was a turned out to be a theme early in my,
in my life, how my experiences with my son, how they related to all the stressors and the
patient experiences that I was having. And in a way, psychologically, although it was difficult
to make everything work, practically, it also, it helped me a little bit to have a
something that mattered more than anything else in the lab or in the clinic, there was something
that sort of was on a different scale. And it helped me not get too stressed about things
happening in the lab or the clinic. And that's a common feeling and people with kids, for me,
it was, it was extremely important at that time. You know, and it was, there were patchwork solutions
of childcare and so on that made things work, but it was ultimately, I think it was helpful for me
in getting through those times. And by the way, he is now an MSTP student at Baylor. So he's doing
his MD, PhD in Texas. And he's now second year. He's a cool kid. He's good at guitar much better
than I am. And he likes computer science.
Yeah, he's got some big shoes to fill, but I, and I'm positive that none of that pressure comes
from you. So, um, so I remember when you were finishing your residency, um, I just remember
because of our common friends, like how kind of exciting it was when you were now setting up your
own labs. So we're talking about what? Oh, five, Oh six ish. Yeah. The lab started to get set up in
oh four. Okay. Um, and then it really hit full steam. Yeah. Between oh six and oh nine,
but oh four was when we were setting it up. So as you're embarking on this,
what is it that you experienced during that, that transformation of your, your clinical training,
your residency, how did that shape the problems you were interested in solving?
Well, I, you know, having just completed my psychiatry residency, I had seen, I had a pretty
deep understanding of where things were clinically. Uh, I knew what, not just the medications we had,
but also the brain stimulation treatments, the interventions that we had available at the time.
I did, uh, you know, I did electroconvulsive therapy, which, uh, is, you know, it's a,
it's very effective for treatment resistant depression. Uh, it's the treatment of choice
for many people. It's incredibly effective. It's stunning to see it's, it has some problems. Uh,
you don't want to give it too much and there, there can be side effects, but it's incredibly
effective. What's the durability of it? Uh, it depends of some patients need, uh, what we call,
you know, uh, maintenance, uh, electroconvulsive therapy. So after three months or so, uh, the
effect will be diminished and they'll, they'll, uh, require to stay alive effectively patients
who are, for example, just acutely suicidal. Uh, and they'll need every three months or so,
what we call maintenance, uh, or continuation, uh, electroconvulsive therapy or ECT.
So it's not a, it's not a permanent, uh, fix, uh, like so much of medicine and so much of
psychiatry, you know, uh, it's something that moves things back into a healthy range for a time.
But we didn't know how it was working. It definitely helped, but, but it was for a
scientist, it was very, it was satisfying to help the patient to, to take somebody who
was, you know, in just horrific psychological distress, uh, and, and put them into a state
where they could go back and do their work and, and, and, and live with their friends and family
and be happy for some time. That was great, but we had no idea what, and still don't, uh,
what was going on there. Why is this, uh, seizure that we give the patient? And it's,
it's done in a pretty refined way these days. The patient's body is paralyzed, so there's no physical,
you know, seizure. It's, it's all happening in the, in the brain and it's, it's a safe procedure,
but still it's, it's not specific, right? Where you're causing a general pattern of activity
through the brain of the patient and, and this astonishing psychiatric effect is created.
I, I, I, clearly it was a mystery, still is, and I was unsatisfied by that. There were early efforts
at the time of, of other brain stimulation treatments. There was a vagus nerve stimulation.
There's a, as you know, there are the nerves that run, uh, the 10th cranial nerve that comes from,
the brainstem and goes down to innervate the heart and the abdomen also sends fibers back to the
brain and you can put a little cuff around the nerve and, and stimulate the brain through the
neck, which is kind of interesting, a little, little highway to the brain. But the effects,
although it became approved, FDA approved for depression, the effects were very small on the
population level, very inconsistent. Likewise, we had transcranial magnetic stimulation, which was
in its early days then as well, which was a, uh, you know, it's a, it's a treatment where you can
noninvasively stimulate a tiny patch of the brain by putting a rapidly changing magnetic field, uh,
near the, the, the, the scalp of the patient. Effects small on the population level did get FDA
approved, but still not fully understood. So all these, all these treatments, and of course,
none of the medications to this day do we fully understand their mechanisms of action. So there
was a lot of mystery. And so I came from my psychiatry residency fully aware that, that
essentially the entire field was unmoored from scientific understanding, no fault of the
practitioners, no discredit to them. It was just not known and we didn't have the tools and
techniques. We had no specific way of causing something to happen to a particular kind of cell.
All these treatments are non-specific, a seizure all through the brain, uh, you know, a stimulation
of a nerve wherever that nerve may go known, but not specifically related to any psychiatric, uh,
symptom, uh, transcranial magnetic stimulation. Yeah. You can stimulate a little patch of, of the
brain, but we don't know where depression comes from, where anxiety comes from. Is it this patch
or that patch or that patch? No deep level of understanding, uh, was present. And, and of course,
the medications act all through the brain without cell type specificity. So that was the,
that was the setting. And then, you know, to answer your question, then as you know,
clearly, uh, basic science, you know, how could you build an approach to give you some, some kind
of, uh, precise causality. And that was, that was the context. Well, I want to dive really deep into
this because it is essentially, um, the skyscraper of your life. I mean, look, if you, if you retired
tomorrow for medicine and science, Carl, if you tomorrow decided you were going to go surfing for
the rest of your life, you would have already accomplished more than that of a hundred scientists.
Um, so I want to, I want to come to this in detail, but before I do, I want the viewers and the
listeners to get a little bit more of an understanding of the brain structure, because
we're going to be talking about structures of the brain. We're going to be talking about the cells
of the brain. And, um, I wonder what the easiest way to do this is maybe we can start about the
brain and it's three layers and what, you know, we talk about them through our evolution maybe and how
each one added to the next, but, but each one has a subset of functions. I'll really defer to you,
Carl, this is your domain and not mine, but, um, maybe we just take a step back and really give
people a sense of, of some neuro anatomy, some neuro physiology, what neurons are, what axons
are, how chemicals get transmitted. I think investing some time in this now will really
enable people to understand the depth and breadth of your literally world changing discovery.
Well, well, thank you for the, first of all, the gracious, uh, comments. I, we have a long way to
go though, and I'm not, uh, and maybe it's many lifetimes, uh, ahead there, there are very deep
mysteries in the, in the brain that we have much, much work to do exciting fun work, but much work
to do to get to where we want to be. But, uh, it is, it is a, an exciting moment and we've, and,
and what we've been able to accomplish has, has been, uh, thrilling. Um, and, and it's a testament
to all the amazing people that, that we've been able to, to get together to work on this. And,
and indeed the brain is, is something, it's very compelling. Uh, it's so interesting and mysterious.
The cells in the brain are more complex structurally than any other cell. They're
in our brains, there are approximately 90 billion neurons. That's what it'd be.
Each one of them is, it's a self-contained unit. It's covered by a membrane, but it can generate
electricity. It's got little channels, little pores in its surface that can generate little
electrical impulses. And that's how you can have a single neuron that projects from one part of the
brain to another or from one part of the brain to the spinal cord and, or it can send connections
through its axon, its outgoing wire, uh, effectively to many parts of the brain. And it sends that
information in the form of electricity down its axon, down its outgoing, uh, connection. And the
connections are received by the downstream cells through little structures called dendrites. And
the interface from one cell to the next is called a synapse. And in most cases, information gets
across that little gap from one cell to another in the form of chemicals. So the, the electricity
triggers release of a chemical. The chemical drifts across this tiny little gap that's some
tens of nanometers, and then it acts on receptors in the other side, the post-synaptic side, and,
and that creates a new burst of electricity in that downstream cell. So that's the electrochemical
process that, of information flow. Now you've got this going on and 90 billion neurons at the same
time. They're all, maybe they form 10,000 or even a hundred thousand synapses each. Their wiring is
incredibly complex. Uh, um, there's some structure to it. There are collections of axons that may
travel together, but then they also bifurcate and separate in incredibly complex ways. And all of
that's in the brain. And then there's some structure to it, as you alluded to. Uh, and one
way we can think about this is, is indeed evolutionarily. We're vertebrates, okay? That means
we have a backbone and we've got a certain organization to our brain. In my lab, we have
fish and we have mice and we have rats. And then I also do clinical work. These are all vertebrates
from fish to us. We all have the basic vertebrate body plan and brain plan. And, but evolution has
given us, obviously we have much bigger brains than, than fish do. And, uh, a couple of things
have happened over the course of, of, you know, hundreds of millions of years, is that first of
all, we've scaled everything up. We've taken the same structures. We've added many more cells
to them. Uh, and that lets us do more complex things. And we've also added new things on top.
And so in the surface of the brain, there's what we call the cortex, uh, which means literally the,
the surface of, of the, of the brain. It's like the, the rind of a melon. Except in human beings,
it's, it's quite thin. It's just a few millimeters, uh, thick. And within that few millimeters,
there are six separate layers within that cortex or rind. Uh, and those are layers of cells. So
there are six layers of cells in this sort of shawl or, or rind covering the brain. And then all the
wiring coming out from that cortex, uh, goes to deep structures. Uh, and our, our cortex is much
more advanced. The fish don't really have something like that, but they've got the deeper structures.
They've got the interchanges and the movement control and the, the, uh, uh, arousal systems
and the sleep systems and, and there are structures deep in the brain, like the hypothalamus that
govern all the primary needs of, of salt balance and, uh, avoiding danger and mating and sleeping,
thermoregulation. These deep structures are common to every vertebrate. We have a hypothalamus.
The fish has a hypothalamus. These deep structures are shared and ancestral among all vertebrates.
And so you've got this, you've got these deeper structures that are, that are conserved and
ancient. And you've got this, uh, in, in us, we've got this surface structure that is, uh, incredibly
elaborated in, in our lineage and, and, uh, is responsible for some of the most complex and, and,
and mysterious things we do. And, and, but the great thing is, and mice sort of sit somewhere in
between. They have the cortex, uh, that we have, and it's amazingly similar. It's got the same six
layers. It's got the same kinds of neurons that are connected in the same way. It's just much smaller,
than what we have. And so by looking at the fish and the mice and ourselves, uh, we can piece together
a lot by studying the cells and the connections that make things happen. And, and that's the
context that we come to as a neuroscientist. And what about this, this first layer, the brain stem,
this kind of most primordial layer that handles so many of these functions when we're not even
thinking about it, like, like breathing. I mean, what, how conserved is that across all of these
models? Yeah. The brainstem is, is highly, highly conserved the, you know, in the brainstem and in
the midbrain we have clusters of neurons, uh, like the dopamine neurons and the serotonin neurons
and the noradrenaline or norepinephrine neurons. They're all, uh, clustered there in the brainstem
in and around, uh, other cells that govern, uh, the movement of the, uh, muscles of the face and the
neck and that send information down like the vagus nerve that we talked about, send information
down to the rest of the body. These basic structures in the brainstem are, are highly conserved.
Fish and mice and human beings, uh, all have them. There's a little bit of different
shaping and arrangement, but it's basically the same logic. And are there neurons as the way you
describe it, it sounds like a neuron might have mostly just serotonin. So when that neuron fires
at the end of its synapse, serotonin is the only chemical that comes out. Is that, is that the case
for neurons that each one only can emit one neurochemical? So it's a largely binary signal
or are there any neurons that can secrete more than one neurotransmitter? A relatively recent
understanding has been that there are multiple neurotransmitters that can be released by the
same neuron. We still refer, for example, to the dopamine neurons as dopamine neurons because
that's what that's, that's what makes them special. That's what they can do that other neurons can't
do. But what we've discovered recently, what the field has discovered recently is that dopamine
neurons, some of them also release another neurotransmitter called glutamate, which is
an excitatory neurotransmitter. It stimulates the downstream cells. Other dopamine neurons can release
a different one called GABA, which is an inhibitory neurotransmitter. It shuts down
the cell that's receiving the signal. So there's actually a great deal of complexity and that's
not all. There are also other things that can be released at the same time, things we call
neuropeptides. And there's a lot of complexity on the other side of the synapse too. Different cells
have different receptors for the different chemicals that can do totally different things.
You can have a receptor for glutamate that makes excitation happen, or you can have another receptor
for glutamate that doesn't do that, but makes a longer pattern of modulation happen. That's not
even a direct excitation. So that's just a, just a flavor of the complexity. But broadly speaking,
you'll see us still refer to things like dopamine and serotonin neurons, because that's the first
level of complexity. So prior to the work that we're going to get into here, what tools existed
to really try to establish causality between the stimulation of one region of the brain
and some sort of response, be it a phenotype or an impulse, or I mean, was there ever any way to
imagine how one part of the hypothalamus was responsible for a type of thought or emotion? I
mean, how was that probed? Yeah, this was a big challenge that neuroscience faced, which is
finding out what actually matters for function. And what we did have, we had ways of listening in,
we had ways of putting in electrodes to listen, to pick up electrical patterns of activity. You
can put an electrode in the cortex or in the hypothalamus or in the brainstem, and you can
pick up the chatter of neurons as these little electrical impulses go by. And you could use the
same electrode, you could also stimulate, you could send current in through this wire effectively that
you that you've placed. And yeah, that has an effect. And so you can make things happen by
just sending current into the brain. And at some level, though, this is just a scaled down version
of the electroconvulsive therapy we talked about, which is also just current being put into the brain
causes things to happen. But there's no cell specificity, every single neuron in the brain is
electrical. And all parts of every neuron are electrical, not just the cell body itself that
has the DNA in it, but also every part of the axon, every part of the dendrite, all electrical. And so
if you send in current to a spot in the brain, even with a tiny electrode, you're affecting every
single cell near the electrode. And not just that, every little bit of wiring that happens to be going
through there. So there's no cell type specificity because every cell is electrical. And that's still
though, there's work you can do. And so you can you could stimulate a region of the brain and see
if that causes something to happen in the animal. And there was a great deal of really foundational
work in neuroscience going around and stimulating different parts of the brain. It was discovered
that if you put an electrode in the parts of the brain where dopamine neurons live and where the
axons come out, that rodents will really work hard for that. They like that, it seems. We can infer
that because they will press a lever thousands of times a day to get a burst of electricity to the
dopamine neurons. And so that little clues like that are built up over time. But then there was
always complexity as we dove deeper into it. We realized, wait, this is not just the dopamine
neurons. In this region of the brain, there are a lot of other cells and connections. So is it
really the dopamine neurons? It's this region, but what really are the cells? And so there was a lot of
uncertainty in the field as to which cells were actually doing what. And so we had that. But then
there was not a good way to turn things off also. And so in science, we like to add things and see
what happens. And that's testing whether something is sufficient to cause an effect. And we like
doing that. That tells you something. But then we also like to take away something of interest. And
we can see what is lost with that. And that's called, that's testing the necessity of something.
How much is that needed? And so we would we would have liked to turn off cells and say, okay,
now what's different in the animal and their behavior? And there was not a great way of doing
that. Crude ways, if you stimulate really hard with an electrode, you could effectively exhaust
the cells and make them not fire anymore. And that was sort of the state of the art,
both clinically and research wise, in trying to create a local inhibition. But again, not cell
type specific at all, because all the cells are electrical. And that's the kind of situation
situation that we found ourselves in. Not too different clinically or basic, you know,
no cell type specificity. So do you remember where you were, what you were doing the very first time
you learned what a channel opsin was? So this is an interesting thread that the there are these
plants that make and small plants, in fact, single celled plants that make channel
red opsins. These are single proteins that live in the that are placed in the in the surface
membrane of cells, but microbial cells, not not in our cells in in algae, single celled algae.
And related molecules are present in ancient forms of bacteria. And these these have been known to
exist for years. And and this class of protein is really interesting because they're light activated
electricity generators. These are single bits of biology, single biomolecules that do an amazing
job. They receive a photon of light and they move charged particles ions across the surface of the
cell. Now, there's a huge family of these, these are called the microbial opsins and a subfamily
of them is called the channel red opsins. Now, what's amazing is that these proteins were known
broadly in biology, in biochemistry for decades. They've been discovered in 1971
by Dieter Osterhelt and Walter Stakinius, who are at UCSF. And this was part of the training of
biochemist biologists in in Lubert Streier's beautiful biochemistry textbook. There's a page
on the bacteria red opsins and there's a this was that's that's where I learned about it.
You know, these these proteins, they have a photo cycle, it's called they have a
choreography of movements of the protein after the photon hits that lead to an ion,
a charged particle moving across the membrane of the cell. So this, but so this was, you know,
a class of proteins that was was well known. And, and it turned out that these microbial
opsins turned out to be the key for for optogenetics, the technology we developed
that brought this cell type specific causality that made it possible.
I want to understand this a bit more, Carl. How? Because so it sounds like, okay, because
I also had Lubert Streier as a professor, I have his textbook, it's one of the few textbooks I've
still kept. First of all, I don't remember that. So I mean, like, that might be a page in that book,
but I was not paying attention during that lecture. So it's it sounds to me like you knew
about these even back in medical school. When did the idea come to you that said, wait a minute,
I can now genetically insert these things into neurons and effectively put a digital switch
into a single neuron? How and when did that idea cross your mind? Yeah. So there was a coalition of
a coalescence of different threads that happened that were partly plausibility threads. And, and
if you look at this historically, anybody in theory could have thought about this and tried this
in, you know, in the late 80s or all through the 90s, these genes were known.
Somebody could have put them into neurons and tried this, but it wasn't technically plausible
for many reasons. They were not until the 90s and particularly the late 90s, they were not good ways
of introducing genes into neurons. Neurons are a little bit tricky. They're very finicky and
sensitive. And, and I knew this because this was, you know, this was a theme in my PhD work and
also in my postdoc work, you know, can we, how can we get genes into neurons even in a cultured
neuron preparation? It's not easy. And so that was, that was certainly part of it, part of why,
I mean, why nobody had had tried this before. But in the late 90s, that started to change. And,
and I did an experiment introducing genes into, into neurons as part of my postdoctoral work in
the Malenka lab that was in. And so this was something I was, I was good at. I'd, I'd develop
the viral tools and the ways of introducing genes in that were, that were plausible.
Tell folks a little bit about how that works. Yeah. We're obviously, you know, these days,
I think even the lay person is somewhat familiar with genetic modifications. People have some sense
of how these have even been used to help develop vaccines and things like that. But let's start
from a place, assuming people don't even really know the difference between DNA and RNA and just
explain how you could use this thing called a virus to do your bidding with respect to the
insertion of a foreign gene. So this is, and this is by no means a minor thing. In some ways,
this is, this is the whole ball of wax, as we say. How do you get a gene into a neuron in a,
in a specific way? So this is the technological aspect of this in some ways is everything. And
so it's definitely worth the time to talk about this. You know, how do you, how do you do it? Well,
so DNA is, is the instruction manual for making proteins, things like proteins,
biomolecules that have a job. Each gene is a bit of DNA. It might be a sequence of what we call
nucleotides. They have A, G, C, and T. There's four kinds of them and they come in different
sequences. And by the order in which these nucleotides appear, that is a code, that's the
genetic code that dictates which protein will be made, a biomolecule that, that has a particular
structure and a job that comes from its structure, like being in a channel or something in the
surface of a, of a cell that receives a photon and lets charged particles go across. That's the protein.
The instructions for making it are encoded in the DNA in the gene. And so that, so how do you get that,
that gene into a cell? Well, it's not so easy. You know, these days, particularly with the
coronavirus pandemic, I think the general public is, is much more aware now of how this can be done.
Viruses, and there are many kinds of viruses, they are little bits of biology that basically
exist to get DNA and RNA into cells. And so they have a little bit of this genetic code material,
DNA or RNA, and they have that encased in a coating that might have some lipids or fats
and some proteins. And then that floats through, liquid floats through the air, hits a cell,
and fuses with the cell, gets the DNA or the RNA into the cell. And then that triggers the
creation of new virus particles. And that's how the virus spreads. So viruses are professional
introducers of genetic material in the cells. They are extremely good at that. They are evolved
for that. And this, this DNA, RNA distinction is interesting. Some viruses work with DNA.
Some are RNA. What is RNA? This is also something that the coronavirus pandemic has brought to the
public's attention very recently. That's the step in between DNA and protein. It turns out,
for various reasons, it's useful to have an intermediate step. First, the DNA gets turned
into RNA, very similar structure, but then that gets turned into the protein. Some viruses work
with DNA, some are RNA. So this, it turns out, is then very useful for the biologists because
if you want to get a gene into a cell, and in my case, suppose you want to get a gene for making a
light activated channel, if you want to get that into a cell, how do you do it? Well, you get the
DNA into the cell. And what's the best way to do that? Well, use a virus. And there are viruses
that are dangerous and lethal, but there are also safer, weaker viruses. And then there are
modified versions, even of those, that virologists have engineered to be extremely safe, to have
lost the ability to propagate from one cell to another, but can do that first step, can
bring DNA into one set of cells, and then the life cycle, if you will, stops at that point.
And those are the viruses that I had experience with from my postdoctoral work,
safe modified viruses that can be used to shuttle bits of DNA into cells. And so that's the core
technology. And again, this was a relatively recent thing, and particularly for neurons,
a relatively recent thing. The technology for doing that was not so clear in the past.
The other thing that I want to point out is that there were many people who were thinking about
this and trying this. And we did, from my lab, publish the first paper that used a microbial
opsin to get light sensitivity, but it was, as it turned out, quite a close call. We published
the paper from my lab in 2005, and that came out in the summer of 2005. Within six months,
several other papers came out. They all were submitted right after ours was published,
and so clearly many people had been thinking about this. They saw our paper came out,
and then rushed to submit theirs. And these were big time labs, people who were very respected
and thoughtful, including, this is something I didn't know, but the brother of my PhD
advisor. My PhD advisor was Dick Chen, his brother Roger Chen was a Nobel laureate
for his work with green fluorescent protein. It turned out he was also working on this as well.
I talked in my great length about this. Of course, he did okay. He got a Nobel prize
for other work, but all this was going on before his Nobel prize. And so he was quite,
I think, frustrated that he wasn't able to get to this moment as quickly. So it was a
sort of a broad awareness in the field that the technology was now available. We could introduce
genes into neurons, that these microbial opsins existed. People had wanted to get cell type
specificity for a long time with neurostimulation. Francis Crick of DNA double helix fame had been
calling for this sort of technology for years. In fact, in 1999, he'd even suggested that not only
did we need a way in neuroscience to control individual cells, individual cell types, but he
said maybe light would be a good way of doing it. He didn't have an idea of how to do it, but he said,
light would have some good properties. It would be fast, it would be relatively noninvasive, photons
could scatter through tissue, and most neurons don't respond to light at baseline, unlike
electricity. And so it would be a way of getting great specificity. So there was a broad awareness
that this kind of thing suddenly might be possible. I have two unrelated questions, Carl, about this.
The first is, when you introduce the virus, is it one virus that can introduce the gene to one
neuron and that's it? He said there's no replication capacity of the virus. So does that mean that the
dose of the virus you give determines how many cells will pick up the channel?
That's correct. So you can give a very high concentration of viral particles and that will
mean that you get more cells. Also, you'll get more copies per cell. You can have multiple
viral particles infecting the same cell and that is actually very important. Another big issue with
these microbial options is they generate tiny currents. They're not as professional at generating
huge currents as mammalian ion channels are, which was a big reason why I think a lot of people didn't
rush to this as well. People looked at those current sizes and said, this is not going to
work. Most existing methods of introducing genes gave you maybe one to seven copy numbers of the
gene, as we say. So not enough to control a neuron and that was a huge issue. But with the viral
technologies, you could get hundreds or more copies of the gene per cell and you could get
much bigger currents with these microbial options. So then again, my experience with the viral tools
was critical. Just give us a sense of the current. So when you talk about a normal mammalian neuron,
how many do we measure these in picoamps, nanoamps? Yeah, picoamps and nanoamps are exactly right.
So an action potential is how many picoamps? Yeah. So a couple of ways we can look at it. So the
action potential, this is this blip of electricity that propagates through down the axon of a neuron.
It can be triggered by signals that are in the order of 100 to 200 picoamps. And then it becomes
a voltage impulse that's about 100 millivolts and that propagates down the cell. So if you're in the
hundreds of picoamp range, you're in business for controlling neurons. A single option is capable of
what? Vastly less than that. And so a couple issues come up. So first of all, what we
found is that if you don't have a high copy number, the currents that you're generating are
on the single or less picoamp level. We haven't done, because the currents are so small,
you typically don't even do the experiment you're asking, the single channel current
measurements. Since then, out of scientific curiosity, we and others have looked at the
currents that are generated and they're extraordinarily small. We only get
to the hundreds of picoamp level by probably expressing 100,000 to a million opsins per cell.
So this was the key issue. There was many orders of magnitude, as we say,
several factors of 10 away from where we needed to be with these opsins, unless there was a way
of introducing many genes and getting very robust, safe expression.
How do you introduce the virus? So let's just say we're talking about a mouse here,
and you decide you want to test in this particular region of the Pons. So a part of the brainstem,
you want to exactly get it there. How do you direct the virus to exactly the cell you want
to get this specificity? So this is the other technological challenge that had to be faced.
It was not obvious how this would be done. Where would the specificity come from? Yes,
none of the cells respond to light. Yes, maybe we could add a gene that makes the cells respond to
light. But wait, hang on a minute. Where's the specificity going to come from? How do we get
this gene only into the cells we're interested in? Well, all right, what could you do? You could
concentrate the virus and do a very focal injection into, let's say, the Pons. And so
you could create a little hotspot of virus, and then that virus would get into all the cells
that are in and around that spot in the Pons. And that's good. That gives you some spatial
specificity. You're now at a spot. And that is already a big leap beyond the electrode,
because the electrode and the virus both so far and how I've described them are not cell type
specific. But the electrode is going to be stimulating all the axons that happen to be
going by. If you do a viral injection at one spot, viruses are not very good at getting into axons.
They're just going to get the cells, the little spherical cell bodies that live in that region.
And so right away, that gives you some specificity. You're getting less of the
cross-streams of activity being stimulated. But it's not enough, because even if you're just
getting the cells, the cell bodies there, there are many different kinds. There are the dopamine
cells, but right next to them, there are the GABA cells, and next to them are the glutamate cells,
and they're all jumbled up together. And there, you're not too different from the electrode.
Now, if you put in light, you're still going to be stimulating all these cells. And so what you need
is a way to make the production of the opsin cell type specific. Okay, so how are you going to
do that? Well, the virus, there were many possibilities we could think about. And this
probably, till we really solved optogenetics, probably took till 2009, because this was the
critical issue. How do you get a versatile, generalizable way of targeting specific cell
types? And back in 2004, 2005, there were some possibilities that we and others could imagine.
You could try to imagine engineering the virus capsid, this coating of the virus that has
proteins on it. There were theoretical ways and even possible practical ways of engineering
capsid proteins so that they would only target one kind of cell, because that kind of cell had
something else on its surface, and maybe we could create some kind of lock and key mechanism.
Yeah, so just like a coronavirus, its lock and key basically works through the ACE2 receptor.
If you knew what a potential surface protein or receptor was on the dopaminergic neuron,
that could be your entry. That would have been the first thought that would have come to my
naive mind. Yeah, and that was plausible. It could work. It had some
drawbacks, which are that you'd have to... First of all, we didn't have that richness of
understanding. It wasn't as if there was some lookup table. Okay, dopamine neuron has this,
but then make put this on that. That didn't exist and still doesn't honestly. So it was more just,
okay, there's going to be a lot of work. Every time you want to target a particular cell type,
you're going to have to now do some deep dive into all the proteins it expresses,
and also all the cells that are nearby that you don't want to target and make sure...
You're not crossing them.
...whatever your strategy is, is not giving you some cross activity. And so we initially
plausible, and then as you start to think about it more, you're like, oh, this is never going to be
versatile, generalizable, practical, and indeed it still isn't today. So that wasn't it.
Now, another strategy is that is working with DNA. Each gene, each bit of DNA in chromosomes,
in genomes, has this code for the protein, but also near it, it's got another bit of DNA
that's called a promoter or an enhancer. And this is a bit of DNA that doesn't code for a protein.
What it does is it attracts what are called transcription factors, things that decide
whether that bit of DNA gets turned into RNA and then into protein. They, by changing the structure,
by changing things around the gene, they determine whether this gene is expressed at all. It could
sit there quiet and not make the RNA and the protein, or it could be active, make the RNA
and the protein. Turns out that is critical because that was a path forward. We could work with
the bits of DNA near genes, promoters and enhancers. This gave us some leverage, not all
of it, but some of the leverage. And if you think about this, well, think about a dopamine neuron
again. So what is a dopamine neuron? Well, it makes dopamine and it releases dopamine. Okay,
now how does it make dopamine? Well, it's got its own biomolecules that make dopamine. It's got
enzymes that turn other precursor chemicals into dopamine. Now those enzymes are made
chiefly in dopamine neurons. And why are they only made in dopamine neurons and not in your
big toe neuron? Well, it's because... Or more importantly, not in the serotonergic
neuron right next door. I mean, that's the key insight is you exploit the promoters
that are making unique enzymes to a particular neurotransmitter.
Exactly right. And so it turns out each cell type is defined by its job,
just as in many cases we are defined by our jobs. And this is a critical thing because
a professional dopamine producing cell is going to have by its dopamine enzyme encoding genes,
it's going to have promoters or enhancers that dictate in this cell type, this gene will be
active. And so what we did was we said, okay, let's see which of those bits of DNA, those
promoters and enhancers can we borrow from, let's say, the tyrosine hydroxylase gene. This is a
gene that helps make dopamine. We could go take a little bit of its promoter and we could put that
in front of the channel rhodopsin gene, package that whole thing up into virus infect cells. Okay,
now you inject- You could almost administer it systemically at this point and it's going to
go exactly where it is a very elegant solution, Carl. Yeah. And in fact, the systemic thing now
in some ways is done in some settings. It's more costly actually because you have to use a much
higher load. Make a lot more virus. And actually the focal injection gives us other advantages.
So we still actually prefer the focal injection, but you're right that the specificity is now
in large part taken care of by the promoter. And so you can inject that in. The virus gets into
all the cells, the serotonergic cells and the dopaminergic cells, but the gene is only expressed
and the opsin is only made in the dopamine cells as a result of it. So I have another technical
question, Carl. So let's go back to your garden variety cold causing adenovirus, right? So
you're out and about in the park or you're on an airplane and you happen to catch this cold from
you happen to catch this cold from somebody. That adenovirus is going to go and it's going to infect
the epithelial cells lining your trachea, probably get into your lung or something like that.
It's going to incorporate its genetic material into your machinery, which will then make its
proteins. That's how it replicates. And of course, the immune system is very good at recognizing this
because it's either going to put soluble antibodies to antigens on the surface or if it's
done through class one and class two, the T cell system is going to come and through antigen
presentation will recognize foreign antigens being presented on the surface of a cell. So in other
words, the host cell, your cell will hold up its little hand and say, look, I've got this little
protein in me. It's the T cell will come and destroy that cell. How do you prevent the immune
system from standing by watching you do all of this very elegant genetic engineering and then
just coming along and big footing you because it says, wait a minute, that channel options not
supposed to be here. Are you just getting lucky that it's not being presented on the MHC class
one or class two as a peptide or meaning pieces of it because obviously it would be much larger
than a nine to eight amino acid peptide. But yep. This is a great question. This was another
energy barrier to tackling the strategy. Everybody thought and rightly so this is a
potential concern, right? The immune system is going to attack the cells making this foreign
protein and kill them. Well, a couple of things helped us here. One is that we were working in
the brain and as you know, the brain is what we call an immune privileged organ. The T cells and
B cells that patrol our bodies don't have free access to the brain. They're kept out and that's
pretty interesting situation. Why is that? A lot of interesting evolutionary speculations to that,
but it's a fact and so they can't get in. Without that, no doubt things along the lines of what
you're saying would be relevant. We've actually even recently explored this sort of thing.
People have been interested in peripheral, not central, peripheral optogenetics and it works,
but people see loss of the expression and the cells expressing the
options over time, over months and the immune response is certainly part of that. But in the
brain, that doesn't happen. That's a great question and here we definitely leverage the immune
privilege. This was very helpful, Carl. I think maybe for the listener they thought,
boy, these guys want to do a lot of detail here, but I think this was really important because
I think only now can we understand the magnitude of A, what you and your team accomplished in what
scientifically is considered a nanosecond. I mean, in four years that you were able to do everything
you just said and now we're in 2009, 2010, you have the capacity to introduce these options
to very specific cells such that you could say two neurons, which are different, I can put this
gene into one and not the other. This is unparalleled. You now have this capacity
to use photons to turn neurons on and off with precision that could never be achieved anatomically
under anatomic resolution. That's right. So what was the first question you sought to ask
using this technology from a neurobiology and neurochemical standpoint? Well,
we've talked about dopamine a lot and in 2009 there was an experiment that I and the whole
field had wanted to know, which really is, is it the dopamine neurons? Is their activity what
what animals are getting from this stimulation of that region or is it something else, some other
cell type that's nearby? Is it the GABAergic or the serotonergic cells that we know are right nearby?
And in 2009 we did that experiment. So we introduced a channel retopsin, an excitatory
channel retopsin just into the dopamine neurons of this spot in the midbrain that's called the
ventral tegmental area or VTA. It's got all these other kinds of cells, but that's where the dopamine
neurons also live. And we used a souped up form of the promoter strategy I just told you about
to get the gene into the dopamine neurons. And we asked a very simple question.
If you have a mouse and you give it a two room house to live in, it's a very simple house,
two rooms, I can go back and forth from one room to the other. So kind of just like a New York
apartment. Yeah, on a good day. Yeah. Then what if you turned on the laser light, the light that
activated the channel retopsins on the dopamine neurons, but you did that only when the animal
was in one room and not the other room. And what we found is that if you did that, the animals
preferred to be in the room where the laser light had been applied compared to the other room,
which was equivalent in every other way. So this would be the analogy just to,
sorry to interrupt, but just to make a really crude scenario. You could have done this experiment
a hundred years ago if you said, I'm going to put sugar water in one room and not in the other.
Is there a preference that the animal has for it? Presumably it would always want to go to the room
with sugar water or cocaine or something pleasurable, but yet here you were able to do
that without anything other than the excitation of a particular neuron. Exactly right. And in fact,
this test is an old test. It's called the conditioned place preference test. And yeah,
it's a animal now prefers a place. And it's because of the conditioning is how it was done
classically. Just as you're saying, you would pair something good like cocaine or sugar or
food or a social interaction, a mate, something like that. And you would see later that the
mouse would choose to spend time in there revealing to us by its behavior that this
thing was positive in value to it. And you can do the flip side too. You can do a negative thing.
You can make it feel mildly nauseous. You can give it lithium, which we give to patients too
in one side effect. You can have as mild nausea. You can give a mouse mild nausea that way,
but only in one room and then it'll avoid that that room. And that's conditioned place aversion.
So the animal can report to us the sign, if you will, the valence positive or negative of its
experience by where it chooses to spend time. And that's incredibly valuable. This harkens back to
my very first wanting to be a neurosurgeon because a human being could tell me what they were
feeling. Well, of course, a human being is more eloquent, but behaviorally a mouse can report
whether it's something as a positive or negative value to it.
And that test, Carl, when you're looking for the positive valence, what's the frequency with which
you would expect that to be the case? I mean, presumably it's more than 5149 in favor of the
dopamine firing. Just give us a sense of if you ran that experiment a hundred or you ran a simulation
of that experiment a hundred times and you always fired the dopaminergic neuron with your opsin,
how many times out of a hundred would it go to the positively valence side?
We try to keep things in. You can make this as extreme as you want.
So the answer is a bit flexible, but with typical rewards, with sugar water, with a social
interaction, the number you're looking for is sort of 70, 30, or 80, 20. That's kind of the level to
which the mouse will prefer one chamber versus another, one room versus another in terms of how
it devotes its time. But you can actually, you can make that, you can push those numbers,
both optogenetically using light or with stimuli up or down by making the experience more extreme.
It's quite a flexible test. And we had later versions of this, you know, that in some ways,
the animal's expressing its subjective sense, we think, by where it's choosing to spend time.
You can also make a more souped up version of that test where the animal actually has to work
to get the light by pressing a lever or poking its nose in a little hole, a nose poke, and
trigger a pulse of light by each of its actions. So this is a slightly more advanced version where
you say, how hard will you work for light? How hard will you work for a precisely defined
set of activity in your precisely defined dopamine neurons? And if you deliver
light, you can get an animal to press a lever thousands of times a day to get that light.
And so now there is no doubt that the activity of dopamine neurons in this way is positive.
And it's not just positive, it can be extremely positive. Animals will work very, very hard to
get it. It's just amazing that this could be done. Let's keep going. I can only imagine how
excited you and your colleagues were by this finding. And of course, it probably only
whets your appetite for the breadth of questions that you now want to ask.
Where was the clinical community in recognizing the value of this tool? So you have all of these
questions that have for, I think it's safe to say, thousands of years been, in other words,
even before the codification of medicine as we know it today, we've always wondered things
like what regulates mood? How can two people anatomically be nearly identical and yet one be
happy and one be sad? Where do memories reside? What is a memory? What is a feeling? What is a
thought? All of these things. And yet I suspect that this experiment, as simple as it was,
for the first time gave you a profound sense of optimism that you now have a tool finally
to ask questions. So you're splitting your time here, right? You're still an on the ward
psychiatrist. So on the one hand, you're doing kind of the most cutting edge science in the
field. And at the other end, you're still trying to help people who are bringing these questions
to your mind. How many of your colleagues in psychiatry, not necessarily your direct colleagues
at Stanford, but just, I mean, the community more broadly, how appreciated was this tool
10 years ago? It's actually very interesting that you ask that the appreciation in the
scientific psychiatry realm, and these are clinicians, psychiatrists who also have
some interest in the science side. The appreciation was very quick and immediate
because I think the psychiatrists know and knew better than anyone else how much specificity was
needed and wanted in their field. And I had, this was, by the time we got to 2009,
the generality of that targeting method was key because then people knew, okay,
this wasn't just a parlor trick, a one-off, a demonstration that you could get some kind of
photosensitivity in one cell once, that this was actually a generalizable versatile method. You
could apply this principle to any cell type. It was done in freely moving mammals and mice,
of course, having our same brain structures, our cortex, our hypothalamus, and everything in between
the. The significance and the opportunity was pretty clear to everyone by 2009,
particularly the psychiatrists. And so then there was a lot of a great deal of interest,
and because the technique was generalizable, it was very widely adopted. And we sent the
clones, the bits of DNA to thousands of labs around the world and many thousands of discoveries
were made by other labs, which was great after that, really showing that anybody could use it
to tackle any question, any disease, any symptom in diverse animals. So after 2009,
it was off and running. Between 04 and 09 though, those were hard times because we were still
putting the pieces together, solving the light delivery, solving the virus issues, getting the
cell type targeting to be generalizable and versatile. And I would say it wasn't really until
2009 that we could look at this and say, yeah, we've done it at this point.
Was this work funded by NIH?
Yeah. So early on, I had some initial trouble getting grants, but then pretty quickly,
once the opportunity became clear, both the National Institute of Mental Health and the
National Institute on Drug Abuse, two main institutes of the NIH immediately were very
supportive. And then later we got a great deal of support from DARPA and from the National Science
Foundation. And then also from a number of private donors, people who in many cases came through
the psychiatry setting, friends or family members who had suffered from psychiatric disease, and they
had heard about what we were doing and wanted to support it. So we ended up getting both federal
and nonprofit institutions and private donors and it all came together. But until, really until we
had things working in this generalizable way, times were a little bit tough.
Well, I mean, it is, again, remarkable now as you sort of look back at it to think that,
A, that it all worked out. I mean, there's a hundred steps that this could have failed.
And again, I'm still amazed that it really only took four years, although I'm sure there were
times in there it felt like it was taking forever. But I mean, as you know, you're such a historian
of science as well. I mean, it is a remarkable period of time. So let's talk about some of the
other questions that you wanted to probe with this technology. So what about any of the other
neurotransmitters or neurons in particular? Where did you turn to next?
Well, we were particularly interested in harkening back to my, what got me into psychiatry in the
first place. I wanted to understand internal states of mammals and how they can go wrong and
create symptoms. And if you work with animal subjects, with mice, for example, you have to
figure out what they can report that matters. And one thing they can report very well
are these universal things that all mammals experience, anxiety and social interaction
and caring for offspring, for young. These are quintessential mammalian
states that matter. They can go wrong. And so I wanted to study them and I wanted to study them
in ways that were now precise and causal and had to do with specific cell types.
And so one of the first things we did was anxiety. And, you know, as a psychiatrist, I
specialize in patients who suffer from depression and also social
difficulties, autism spectrum disorders. And a common theme in both autism and in depression,
anxiety is a big part of that. Anxiety is not a small thing. Anxiety can be absolutely crushing
to one's life, to one's interactions, to occupation, to even being able to go out in the world.
This is a very potentially severe disorder in many people. Of course, anxiety, though,
is also can exist in a normal healthy range too. And it only becomes a psychiatric disorder
when it exceeds that healthy range and verges into or in many people, unfortunately,
goes way beyond into a very pathological extreme. How do you define that maladaptive transformation
from normal anxiety, which I suppose you could even make the case if a person was incapable
of experiencing anxiety, they could probably injure themselves and they might be socially
quite destructive. So in other words, there must be some evolutionary basis for anxiety
and self-preservation. But as you point out, I can't imagine anybody listening to this hasn't
been personally experienced or hasn't personally experienced or known somebody who has experienced
anxiety that has crossed too far. But I mean, is this something that falls into the DSM-5 where
there's an actual criteria? There must be, right? Yes. Yeah. There are. And in fact, it's the
criterion for rising to the level of disorder in the psychiatric literature and in the DSM-5 or
diagnostic and statistical manual is that it's only a disorder if there's impairment in what we call
social or occupational functioning. So you could have any symptom in psychiatry, even a hallucination,
for example, but if it's not impairing your life, your social occupational function, we don't call
it a disorder. And in fact, I've had patients who were hallucinating, but it was in a way that was
not disrupting their life. I had a blind patient who had visual hallucinations, but he was fine
with them. They weren't distressing to him. And so we wouldn't say it's a disorder. It's just
something happening. So that's the criterion we use. And of course, it is somewhat flexible
because different people have different social and occupational situations. And this is a challenge
we have in psychiatry, but maintaining that as a criterion is very good because it ensures that we
only treat things that need to be treated. So then you think about anxiety. Well, if you can't
function, if you can't leave your apartment to go to work, well, that's impairing your occupational
functioning. And so there are people who have anxiety easily in that realm or far beyond.
And those are people we want to help. On the flip side, as you point out, there are people who
have risk-taking behavior that's extreme because they don't perceive or worry about threat. And
that's also a problem. So anxiety, we need to treat it in patients who are severely affected.
And the problem is, in anxiety, there are medications that help, but they come with
some problems. So the most effective anti-anxiety medications are things that relate to
Valium and Xanax and Ativan. As you know, these are medications that work,
but they can be addictive. They can cause the human being to adapt to the dose and to make it
very difficult to stop them. And they also can cause... Do we think that they primarily work
through their GABA agonism? Is that the primary belief? Yes. So you talked about GABA earlier.
This is a relaxing, for lack of a better word, neurotransmitter. This is a non-excitatory.
That's right. That's right. And that's exactly how these act. They act, in fact, directly on the GABA
receptor and they facilitate its action. And so this is... They work. They just have some problems.
And not everybody can tolerate them. They cause some cognitive slowing and sedation and so on.
It's like they have some issues. In which neurons in particular do we think that they're
concentrated in their action in. That is a great question. It's subject of a lot of research. If we
understood that deeply, then we could make a separate intervention targeted to those cells.
The problem is that we don't yet know that exactly. We don't know exactly which cells are
the most anxiety relevant cells that these medications are targeting. There are some hints,
but I would say not factually known yet. But you're getting to this key point where optogenetics
was helpful because then we could ask that and answer that question. We could say, okay, which
cells govern the different features of anxiety? And then, now, what am I talking about here with
different features? Well, actually, this is kind of interesting when you think about it. So what
is anxiety? Well, it's actually got different parts to it. First of all, there's physiology.
We've all been anxious. We know heart beating faster, breathing faster. So there's physiology
that changes. Then there's also a behavioral change. When we're anxious, we avoid the risky
situation. We have an impulse to avoid. If we're anxious out in the open, we avoid going out in the
open. And mice do this too. And then finally, there's a negative quality to it, which may sound
trivial. This is the negative valence. This is the hardest part to put your finger on.
This is the hardest part to put your finger on. And it's the most mysterious and...
Perhaps the most difficult, meaning perhaps the most difficult to experience.
It's the most difficult to experience. And it's also the most difficult to understand why we have
this. If we're already avoiding the risky situation, why does nature also have to make us
feel bad? And there are some very interesting evolutionary discussions one can have about that.
The fact is, though, that's how it is. Anxiety feels bad. And that's what makes it, in many cases,
so clinically, causes so much suffering in addition to the behavioral dysfunction that happens.
So actually, anxiety is complicated. It's got these different parts. And they all come on
together, all go away together. And then you've got to ask, okay, these are so different. They're
probably controlled by different cells, right? So you've got behavior, and you've got breathing,
and you've got inner subjective sense. These are all very different, probably different
cells are doing it. So then right away, you've got to ask, what are we going to target? And so we
thought we need to figure out this. And so we used, in 2013, we did an optogenetics experiment
that targeted different parts of what we thought could be the anxiety pathway. And we found that,
indeed, different cells control each of these different parts. There's a set of cells that
control the breathing changes. And there's another set of cells right nearby that control the
behavioral changes, avoiding risky situations. And there's yet a third set of cells that control the
negative valence, the internal state. Each cleanly controls a separate feature of anxiety.
And we did this with optogenetics, introducing light sensitivity.
And then reproducing each of these completely distinct manifestations of anxiety.
Exactly, exactly. So we found we could turn up or down each feature in mice completely separately
from the others. We could have animals that, and this got so interesting philosophically,
we could make animals avoid the open area, the exposed realm that people and mice, but we don't,
many people don't like being out in exposed areas. Mice definitely don't, because that's when they're
going to get eaten. We could make mice be much more avoidant of an open space
with a specific cell type optogenetic intervention. But the mice didn't care that this was happening.
There was no negative balance to it. And this was so interesting that we could create the behavioral
avoidance of anxiety without the mice, without the negative feeling, having this negativity.
And so that it turns out then that behavioral states that mammals have, they can be cleanly
broken apart into these features, and we could show that with optogenetics. That was one of my,
one of the papers from that period of time that was most interesting, because it was so
interesting in that regard. And other people, Katherine Dulock, for example, at Harvard has
done some great work on parenting another quintessential mammalian state using the same
set of techniques, optogenetic techniques that we described. She did this in 2018. Mice are
pretty good parents. They take care of their young, mostly. That can break down at times,
but they care for their young. And Katherine Dulock's lab did an amazing experiment. They
optogenetically found that the different parts of parenting could be broken down into their
sub features as well. And the two parts of parenting that were broken down in this way are
going out to find the young and bring them back to the nest. So go and get your kids and bring
them back home. And anybody who has kids knows that's a big part of being a parent. You got to
corral them, get them back to the safe spot. But that part of parenting, the mice do very well.
They also care for the young. They groom them. That's an extremely important part, both human
and mouse parenting, of course, is grooming the offspring. Turns out there's a parenting
controlling area, but the go and get the kids cells are different from the groom the kids'
cells. And you can optogenetically break them apart very cleanly and show how this parenting
state is assembled from its features. And this kind of thing has been, those are just two examples,
but that kind of thing really gets to the heart of what's so interesting about the brain is how
do these complex states, how are they pieced together from cells? Why does anxiety track so
closely in people with autism? Have you been able to glean any insights into that?
You know, autism is something that interests me immensely. What do we really understand about this
disease? I think we know that it's got a significant genetic component. It's not
entirely clear what triggers it. But, you know, it's phenotype, of course, exists on a
pretty extreme spectrum in terms of functionality, superpowers and super deficits. But what do we
know about autism? And then specifically, why is it that anxiety tracks so closely in people with it?
This autism is one of my main clinical focus areas. This is actually my clinic office here. I see
patients with autism spectrum disorders here. I know that they are hard to treat. There's not a
medication that treats autism. But as you say, a lot of them are very anxious. And that I can help
with. I can help them with their anxiety, with medications like the benzodiazepine class of
medications that we talked about. Those help the anxiety. They don't help the social problems per
se, but they help with the anxiety. And why is that? Why are these patients with autism so,
why is anxiety such a comorbid symptom, as we say? Why does it show up so much in autism?
Well, the human social interaction world is very complicated. It's very fraught with possibilities
for misunderstanding, catastrophic errors of interpretation, embarrassment, humiliation,
confusion. We have a very social world that we've created. And people who have
difficulty with keeping up with the fast rate of social information and making sense of it,
it's a very anxiety-provoking situation. When you're talking to somebody, how do you know
where to look, what to do? What part of them do you pay attention to? Do you look at their eyes?
Do you look at their mouth? Do you look at their body movements? God forbid, there's more than one
person. In a conversation with three people, how do you know who to look at? How do people know what
to say next? To someone on the autism spectrum, these are extremely challenging situations,
because it's very hard to keep up with this high information rate of the social interaction. And
this is something in the book, Projections, that we've talked about. There's a whole chapter,
a story on autism and on how this might happen neurobiologically, how this information overload
might happen. We have patients who are as confused by social interaction and as overwhelmed by it,
as you can imagine, somebody not knowing the language, not knowing the customs of a culture,
and being placed into it while extremely consequential things involving them were
happening in real time. And that's kind of the situation. And so you can understand
anxiety being a big part of autism, just being unable to predict what happens. And so these are
patients who we can help with their anxiety, still not yet with their autism. The genes that are
linked to autism, there are many. It's a very genetically determined disease, not completely,
but heavily genetically. The problem is, like so many of the psychiatric disorders, the genetic
underpinnings, it's a patchwork. It's many different genes that all contribute a little bit
in those cases. And so with all the beautiful genetics, which has given us a lot of insight,
it hasn't led to treatments because there's not a single gene, single protein,
single cells intervening yet. Are you optimistic that that's going to change? I mean, what does
the treatment for someone with autism look like in the coming decade? Let's keep it relatively
short term. Well, the exciting thing is Optogenetics has given us a window now into what could be
this sort of 10 year time scale of autism treatment because now, and again, mice are social,
not only do they parent, but they're also social. They will choose to spend time with another
even same sex member of their species compared to being alone. And they have complex interactions.
They have a give and take. They exchange information. And there's a lot of it.
And if you make mutations in some of the genes that are most powerfully related to autism,
that come from the human literature, you can make mice that have impaired social interaction as
well. And we've done this and we've studied these in laboratory and we've asked, can we correct
the social deficit of these mice? And we can. And this is a whole thread of work in my laboratory,
studying social interaction and asking which cells, which circuits in the brain can improve
social interaction, including in these autism mutation mice. And what's pretty interesting
is that if you think about social interaction, just like everything else, and the parenting
example made that clear, there are different parts to it. Part of a social interaction
might be the motivation, the drive to be social, and that could vary in people. Also,
the cognition, the understanding, the insight, that could be separate. That's another part of
being social, is understanding what the heck's going on. And probably different cells affect
each of these. And indeed we found that. So there are some dopamine neurons that do seem to increase
the drive for social interaction. But then there are other cells in the front of the brain,
some of the most advanced complex cognitions happen, the frontal cortex, that may be more
involved in the information fire hose that's coming through with a social interaction. How do
you keep up with it? How do you make sense of it? That may be more of the cognitive side. And so
just like everything else, you've got to figure out what's most important. And we found those
though. We now know the cells that can improve social interaction in these different areas.
And now that we understand these cells better, you can imagine designing medications that for
the first time are aligned with a specific kind of cell that's known to be important in social
interaction. And that's the exciting opportunity for the future. We're not there yet, but at least
now we have a causal cellular understanding, and that opens so many doors. Is it your belief,
Carl, that at least in the next decade or so, optogenetics will be the tool for establishing
cellular signal-wise causality, but not be the mode of treatment? In other words,
I'm sure people ask you this all the time. I certainly have a thought on this, but I thought
it's worth asking just to make sure everyone's on the same page. Is it your belief that patients
are going to be coming into your clinic with probes that you will be lighting directly
to actually change the neurotransmitters via the light? Or is it that we'll just use that as the
tool to establish where to target our treatments? Or do you think it's going to be a combination of
these? Optogenetics, in my view, is by far the most important aspect of it is it's a discovery
and understanding tool. This helps us because this brings so much that we didn't have before.
Understanding what actually matters, what makes things happen in the brain,
at the level of cells is the opportunity that optogenetics creates, and that understanding
then opens the door to every kind of treatment. Once you understand that, which cells are actually
causing and relieving symptoms, you can design medications that address those cells, you can
design brain stimulation treatments targeted to those cells or their axons as they project across
the brain. It opens up every door in principle, providing this causal foundation. That said,
so that I see is by far the future. It's the understanding that opens every treatment door.
That said, my friend and colleague, Botan Roska, in Switzerland, just this year
was able to confer a form of sight onto a blind person with optogenetics. This was just published
in the journal Nature Medicine this year. Ten years ago, he and I had collaborated on a study
where he put one of our microbial opsins into a human retina, cadaveric, after life. He had ways
of keeping the retina alive for some time in these donated retinas. He was able to show
optogenetics worked perfectly well to control human retinal neurons. He spent the next 10 years
going through all the hoops of going through primate studies and then clinical trials.
Then just this year, he's a vision scientist and he focused on retinal degeneration and was able
to take a human being who was blind from retinal degeneration and he was able to create light
sensitivity so this person could accurately reach for objects on a table that was not possible before.
Literally, making a blind person see, at least to some extent, can happen. I think there may be
cases like that. Of course, they're uplifting to see, but the biggest picture is that it's a
discovery tool. I want to pivot a minute to talk about your book because I think it becomes a great
place for us to now talk about some of the mental illnesses that people will be familiar with,
depression, mania, and its cousin bipolar disorder, eating disorders, all of these things that you've
written about so eloquently. First of all, I want to tell you that if I'm not already in complete awe
of your scientific achievements, I'm equally in awe of your writing achievements. I just don't
think it's fair that one person can be so gifted on two dimensions, Carl. It's really disappointing
and I hope there's something in life that you're horrible at so that I don't feel even worse about
myself. No, seriously, your book is unbelievable. It's called Projections and I've read it twice.
I will encourage every listener to read it because it will shatter some of the images people
have of scientists because you don't write like a scientist. I say that as somebody who's in the
process of finishing up their book. The biggest challenge I have in writing is making it accessible
to everybody, making it interesting enough that someone for whom this is not their life
wants to read it. You've done that in spades. This really reads like at times poetry.
I know you've always had an interest in writing. Did it require much effort and discipline to write
about such technical matters at times, but also to write about the clinical conditions,
the psychiatric conditions that everybody's familiar with? It seemed effortless that you
were able to do this in such an easily accessible and artistic way.
First of all, thank you, Pete. It means so much to hear that. You never really know when you
take a step like this or a risk like this if it's really working. This was a risk. This was
something that was very different. It's not what people expected. As you say, not a typical
scientific text at all. The goal I had was to help everybody in the world, whatever their
background, I wanted to help them understand and feel what these altered states are. That's such
a big part of the book is to work with that feeling, to help people understand and feel
for themselves what mania might be like or what the fragmentation of schizophrenia might be like,
or the crushing pathological grief of bereavement, or the incredibly complex
states of eating disorders where you have these astonishing behavioral patterns that seem so
inexplicable compared to what you would think would be what we were evolved to do.
Everything from these uplifting exuberant states of mania to the depths, I wanted people to feel
this. I had to do this with the writing, with the words. I wanted to do it with the writing
and the words. In each chapter, the writing is adapted to cause that feeling. In the mania story,
the words are exuberant in the way that mania is in the schizophrenia or psychosis story.
There's a fragmentation and a disorganization that happens. In all these cases, I had to work
with words in ways that are not typical for a scientist. Of course, I wanted to do it. This was
my initial passion in life. For me, it was incredibly fulfilling, actually, to come back
and be able to do this. I'd always wanted to do it. I had now not just the desire, but I had a
mission. I had something I wanted to tell. I wanted to share with everybody. For me, it was
incredibly addictive, actually. I did the bulk of the writing over a couple years from
2017 to 2019 or so, and then wrapped it up in 2020. I looked forward to this so much every day.
I would block out a couple hours, but a different time each day, depending on my schedule. Life's
complex now. I've got five total kids. Things are hopping at home. My wife, Michelle, is an
incredibly accomplished MD-PhD herself, also running clinical trials. Also one of our classmates.
Also one of our classmates. Of course, she's in the hospital a lot. No day is as simple or predictable.
The writing time would be at different times, often very late at night, often early in the
morning. I tried to block out two hours, but I would find I would look forward to that like
almost nothing else. I just relished the joy of finding the right word and spending days
thinking about trying to find the right turn of phrase. It was incredibly uplifting, honestly,
even though, of course, a big challenge logistically. One of the things I love about the
book is how you really try to dive into the evolutionary basis for mental illness. This is
something I'm always obsessed with. I always love trying to think about things through an
evolutionary lens. Sometimes the answers come a little easier than others. One of the places
where it comes up is in the story of Alexander. This is a gentleman, won't give away the entire
story, but basically post-9-11 is triggered into what sounds like his first manic event, correct?
That's right. That's right. Which then gets into this discussion of mania. What is mania?
One of the things I found very interesting about this was the discussion about the evolutionary
basis for mania. This is interesting to me personally because this is a very personal
story, I guess, but when I was in residency, I was encouraged by my wife actually to see
a psychiatrist. She had some concern about some of my behaviors. The psychiatrist, after one day,
I don't know if she was right or wrong, but she decided I was hypomanic. That was her diagnosis.
That, of course, got me very interested in, well, why is this the case? How does she know?
Why would this be? I began examining everything I'd ever done in life.
One of the things I came across was at the time, it was a psychiatrist at Hopkins,
so this would have been 2004, 2005, had written a book suggesting that the prevalence of hypomania
in North America was higher than anywhere else in the world because it had the highest
concentration of recent immigrants. The argument was, well, by definition, if you have a collection
of people who are one to five generations away from people who had basically the nerve to leave
a comfortable life elsewhere, and in the case of certainly my parents and many people who came here,
basically to come to nothing. You don't know the language, you don't know the culture, you don't
know the people. It wouldn't be surprising that you could concentrate hypomania here.
A, I'm curious as to whether you have any thoughts about that theory, but perhaps more importantly,
let's dive into this evolutionary basis for mania because the point that you get into about
how there are sometimes wherein traits are very valuable at the population level and not at the
individual level, I found that fascinating. Well, first of all, that's a very interesting
route into this discussion, which is the immigrants, the recent immigrants, and the
possible genetic link to have the, in recent times, to have the get up and go to leave,
to take the risks, to have the energy, to have the motivation to actually make it happen,
sustain it, this complex goal with so many possible downsides. That's no small thing.
Some people wouldn't want to do it, some would. And mania is, it's one of the poles of bipolar
disorder, which is a very genetic, highly genetic disorder, one of the most in psychiatry, bipolar
type one disorder, extraordinarily genetically determined. And what is it? Well, it's not these
two poles. Just to be clear, Carl, does that mean that bipolar stems from bipolar, or it just
clusters with other psychiatric illness? So in other words, schizophrenia or significant depression
would also be genetic precursors to it. What it means in this case is that it's, if you look at
monozygotic twins, especially those that are raised apart, that's where the most pure
information comes from. You can look at the concordance of mania or bipolar disorder appearing
in each of these twins, identical twins. It's more than 50% for bipolar type one, in fact,
verging above 70%. So you have a very strong bipolar type one genetic. And just out of
curiosity, what is it for autism in that same setting? Autism also high, maybe just a touch
under that. With depression, it's like 50%. And so most of the psychiatric disorders have
strong genetic links. They tend to be less than 80%. But in this kind of 50 to 80% range for many of
the severe ones from depression, schizophrenia, to autism, to bipolar. And so this is something we
face in schizophrenia and in autism. But in bipolar, it's extremely strong. So right away,
we know there's that link. And mania is the positive pull of bipolar disorder. The other
pull is depression. People with bipolar type one have had at least one manic episode where they
have a period of time, could be a week, where they've had this very clear, discrete state of
elevated mood, increased goal directed activity, projects, plans, spending, taking risks, faster
speech, not needing sleep, truly not needing sleep, not nearly as much. And, you know, honestly,
even though this causes problems, and serious problems, and not to sugarcoat it at all, mania
can do terrible things. People make very poor decisions, they can be fatal.
Yeah, I was just gonna say, aren't people even slightly more likely to harm themselves
during a manic phase than the depressive phase? Yes, or the transition from out of depression
to mania, that's actually probably the most risky time when they might still have some
of the negativity from the depression, but now they have the energy to.
Yeah, exactly. And so that, not to say there's, you know, it's a problem, but yet at the same
time, you know, some of my most memorable experiences in talking with manic patients is,
I actually love talking to them because there's such a charge of energy, anything's possible,
they're funny, they're warm, they're charismatic. And it's so easy to see that this is a state
that's, it's not a bunch of random things happening in the brain. This is a coherent
state of elevated mood, it's consistent, you see it in one patient, you see it in another patient,
it's something that's there that human beings have as something they can do, a sustained
state of elevated mood and energy. And you look at that and you think, okay,
you know, why? And also, you know, what does that mean for treatment? Is there an ethical issue
with treatment? Is there, are there cases where mania is positive? And this is something that the
story in the book and projections really made me think so hard about. This was actually when the
seed for the book was first planted in my head. It was just 20 years ago, right after 9-11,
and this patient Alexander, he had never had any psychiatric illness at all, nor in his family.
But he was flipped into a completely classic full-blown mania after 9-11. He had no particular
connection. In fact, he was on a sailing trip in the Mediterranean with his wife at the time,
came back home after 9-11. And a couple of weeks later, he was manic. All these symptoms that we
talked about, and it was a huge problem. He was, but his, but he had this appropriate, or at least
aligned quality to his symptoms. He wanted to, he was, you know, he was retirement age,
but he was training himself to go into battle. He was rappelling down trees. He was running
through the night. He was reading about military strategy. And then it verged into this, you know,
very difficult, emotionally challenging. He was screaming. He was hyper-religious. Everything had
become quite extreme and incompatible with his life. And so that ended up bringing him to the
hospital. But, you know, looking at this and we think, okay, this is a state of elevated mood and
energy. It was triggered by context. And this is actually the flip side of what you're saying with
the immigrants. Not only is there likely to be a set of conditions that led to these people being
able to take, have the energy and willingness to take the risk and meet all the incredible challenges
of moving across countries and cultures. But then, you know, that's not this fight or flight
response of a minute when you've got a threat and you have energy and then you meet the threat and
then it's gone. We're talking about you need a sustained level of energy for weeks, months,
years even, and to take a risk and a life shift like that. And so, you know, this is,
everything is on a spectrum and you've got mania and then you've got this hypomanic state in between
that makes a lot of sense that people who are able to sustain this elevated energy state are those
that would be our immigrants. And it's a, and again, you have to look at this and think,
it's a spectrum. Definitely it can be bad, but we have to value the whole spectrum and understand
the whole spectrum. It's part of who we are as the human family.
Why do you think that in the bipolar condition you have this pairing of such opposites?
Is the depression a necessary part of bipolar to basically allow the recharging after, you know,
this unbelievable discharge of emotional and physical energy? Because otherwise, it doesn't
seem like these would, you know, like for example, why doesn't it just go normal affect mania, normal
affect mania? That's a great question. We don't have the answer. Some people, some fortunate
people are like that. There are, you can get a diagnosis of bipolar disorder without ever
having a depression. One episode of mania gets you that diagnosis of bipolar type 1 and those people,
there are people who haven't hit a major depression yet. That said, most of the time there is that
other pole of the disorder. And what is it? We don't know. Short answer is we don't know. But
a lot of interesting ideas. One could be sort of aligned with what you're saying, that there's some
resource that's exhausted. Is it, you know, it's not a resource that we know what it is. We can't
point to it. Is it a neural circuit, you know, state of some kind, a capability of a neural
circuit that can become exhausted. We know neurons can run out of energy. This is part of how the
brain stimulation to cause inhibition works, but that's all in a very fast time scale. You can
exhaust neurons on seconds to minutes. It's not known what really could get exhausted on the
week's scale. We don't know what that would be. Or maybe it's the termination mechanism that it
just overshoots. Or maybe it's just that what's lost is a, the homeostatic thing that keeps energy
in a tight range. And then it could go in either direction because you've lost some break that's
present on either side. Not known, but a very interesting question. What is technically the
most common psychiatric disorder? Is it depression? Actually the anxiety disorders, if you group them
together, anxiety is the most common. And that is, but depression is certainly up there. That's
in the top group for sure. Anxiety disorders are so underappreciated. A lot of people don't talk
about them. A lot of people can make it through the day with anxiety, even if they're suffering
terribly. So yeah, anxiety is most common. What has optogenetics taught us about depression?
So this, you know, this is my clinical specialty. I have, you know, right here in this office, I have,
you know, we do, I do vagus nerve stimulation. For example, this is a VNS therapy radio
frequency controller. We have, we still do here electroconvulsive therapy. We do transcranial
magnetic stimulation. Clinically, though we're looking for guidance from the science because
it's still not known clinically what actually is going wrong in depression. We don't actually know
that in a way that can guide therapies in the way that we'd like. And what's the, what's the
scientific situation? Well, optogenetics has helped quite a bit because, and again, picking up on this
theme, of course there's different parts to depression. And this is how we diagnose it. We ask
about all these different parts. There's depressed mood and that's this negative state. Okay.
There's hopelessness. So it's kind of the opposite of mania. A manic person thinks anything's
possible. Depressed person thinks nothing's possible. There's a deep discounting of the value
of effort. And this shows up as hopelessness. This even can lead to suicidality and certainly severe
social and occupational dysfunction. And then there are other parts to depression. There's
something called anhedonia, which is really interesting. This is the absence of pleasure.
Yeah. This is perhaps the most insidious component of depression by far.
Right. Right. And it's not commonly known. You don't, people on the street don't talk about
anhedonia, right? It's, they'll say they're depressed, but nobody talks about their anhedonia.
But it's an incredibly important symptom. It's a core, such a core symptom of depression that
actually you can get a diagnosis of major depressive disorder without depressed mood.
If you also have anhedonia, it's that important. And it's the absence of pleasure or joy from
things that normally bring pleasure or joy. And we've all had a cold and we've known that taste
is gone, food has lost all joy. It's things, even without the cold, with the anhedonia of depression,
all the joy of food or social interaction or your children, your grandchildren,
a book, a movie, all the joy of life is gone. And this is a horrific thing. It leads to very
serious problems. And that's something that Optic Genetics has helped us understand.
What do we know about that? Yeah. Where do the neurons reside and what are the neurotransmitters
involved in the propagation of anhedonia? So, so again, you might say, how are you going to
test this? And you can, you can set up very simple behaviors with, with animals that, that provide
some insight. First of all, you could provide a simple choice for animals, mice like us, like
sugary drinks, and you could give the animal a choice of a sugary drink or just water. And normally
a mouse will prefer kind of like we do, they'll prefer the sugary drink and, and by a factor,
you know, two to one or more. But a mouse that's been stressed, it's had some unpredictable events
happen. It's had its sleep disrupted. It will not prefer the sugar water nearly as much. It won't
care as much. And so such an interesting thing, given all the evolutionary importance of a small,
high metabolic rate, mammal needing sugar, and we know the reward that we feel from, from sugar and
presume it's very similar for them, and then not caring sugar water, regular water. So in other
words, if you had them going 50 50 between sugar water and regular water, that would be even more
telling than if they disproportionately went to the regular water, right? You would be looking for
a complete amelioration of the effect of the sugar water would suggest that they have basically lost
interest. That's right. That's exactly right. And that in fact happens. And so, so we, we and others
have explored this, this kind of thing with, with optogenetics. And we found that there are,
uh, you know, pathways and coming back again to the, to the dopamine neurons, which are
tightly linked to mood and mania and depression. These, but they're a complex set of cells. Some
send connections to one part of the brain. Some send connections to another part of the brain.
We have found some interesting pathways that relate to those dopamine neurons where you can actually
affect how potent a normal rewarding stimulus is by something going on in the frontal cortex.
And the frontal part of the brain and overactivity in the prefrontal cortical areas can cause
anhedonia in rodents. An overactivity seems to cause an inability of the dopamine neurons to
recruit, reward circuitry. And so this is an insight that optogenetics brought us and it's
something that we're following up mechanistically. It's kind of an interesting thing that there's,
what we found is that again, using optogenetics, that the frontal cortex can suppress both positive
and negative things. It can suppress fear. It can suppress anxiety. This is part of how we exert
cognitive control over situations. We can enter a scenario that we know is risky if we think about
it enough, if we, uh, frame it enough for ourselves cognitively, if we review the need for it, for
taking this action. And so our, our frontal cortex can help us by tamping down negative
aspects, but it also, when overactive, it turns out can tamp down positive aspects as well. And
optogenetics has given us a causal insight into this. And so that's just one example, but all the
other features of depression as well are susceptible to optogenetic study and we've got insight into
them. Hopelessness being another one. And so here, you know, again, you might ask, how do you,
how do you measure hope in an animal? Well, you know, you can, you can put an animal in a
challenging situation that is not escapable. Animal can, can try to get out of this challenging
situation. And then would that be like a maze that doesn't have an exit? Yeah. No, no way of
getting out exactly. So it doesn't have to be painful. Just, just something that an animal would
want to get out of and eventually they give up. We can do this actually in fish as well as in,
in mice. And that giving up is effectively, it's this hopelessness. It's this discounting
of effort. And that can be an appropriate thing. Let's say, of course, if the situation truly is
hopeless, it really is not good to keep devoting effort to it, right? If you, if you keep flailing
against an insuperable situation, you're burning energy, it could cause physical risk.
You're distracting yourself from other things. Withdrawing, entering into a passive coping state
is actually adaptive up to a point. The problem with depression is it becomes extreme. So it's
maladaptive. It becomes maladaptive. You discounted the value of everything. And then it's got this
mysterious negative balance to it too, which is of course also part of the problem. What do you
think is the evolutionary basis for depression? This is something that is so ubiquitous. I think
I can, based on what you said earlier, see the evolutionary basis for anxiety. And maybe we could
just argue that, that the pathologic version, well, we could discuss why maybe it's been amplified and
what it is about our environment that perhaps does that. But depression is a less, less clear
to me and certainly mania is clear, right? I think we've made a very compelling case for why mania
could be, why evolutionary pressure could have favored the propagation or at the, at a minimum,
the maintenance of this. Why depression? It seems to be counter to your ability to mate, to find
food, to defend yourself. I'm struggling to come up with one evolutionarily valuable tool that would
be better in a depressed state. You know, and this is a great question. I think about this all the
time. And part of what we've discussed already may provide some insight, which is this, this withdrawal,
this passivity. It is in some cases, you can think of it like a hibernation, you know, if,
is it, is it like, is it worthwhile for an animal to actively try to cope with winter by running
around trying to find more food all through the winter or to withdraw, to sleep more, to, to not
see the value or feel the value in going outside and doing anything. And clearly, no matter what
you do, you can't fight winter, right? The best thing is to conserve your energy, ride it out on
some time scale that's appropriate. And so you think about now, think about depression. It comes
with this low energy. It comes with this hopelessness, this discounting of effort, this lack of
motivation to go seek things to be enjoyed, reduced, you know, drive for social interaction. All these
things can be part of depression. The negative aspect is the one part that's, that's, that I
can explain. And that's, that's of course, the clinically significant problem. Why does it feel
bad? And this is not just feeling bad. This is agony. This is psychic pain is the kind of thing
that drives people to seek suicide. Not to discount that at all. We don't understand why
depression feels bad, but the passivity of coping that can be adaptive. And it's, it's perhaps,
you could, you could see almost depression as a, as a hack, a bad hack, maybe one that's not fully
evolved yet, just like mania, not fully evolved yet, not under all the right controls to make it
more generally suitable and reasonable. Depression, the easiest way to make it happen
is to remove the joy, to remove the energy, to seek out reward. And then you've got an organism
that's going to be passive, that doesn't see a path to, to, to something positive. And
evolutionarily, if you, if you take this, this viewpoint, maybe one way of getting to that goal
that had some at the population level, some adaptive value included having this negativity,
this negative state to it. And this is pure speculation, you know, but it's, it's important
because depression is very genetically determined. It's, it's common, it's biological. And at some
level, we have to deal with the fact that we have evolved to be where we are now. And we have this
high rate of, of, of, of depression. And so we have to include in our thinking, the biology and
the evolution together. And so that would be my, my, you know, my, my take on it. Of course,
it's very hard and I wouldn't claim to have a definitive understanding.
Two unrelated questions. I don't even know which one to ask first. So I'll probably just ask them
both and then let you take them whichever way you like. The first is sort of a desire to understand
where depression specifically, but even other mental illness fits into our closest relatives,
the primates, right? Do we have a sense that our primate relatives are as afflicted by depression
and or other mental illnesses as much as we are? Let's start with that. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, we can, one of the clearest things we can see is that, you know,
non-human primates can certainly enter into maladaptive states that look like grief. In
bereaved states, there are cases where you can have a, a young non-human primate who is old enough to,
to feed itself, but who has lost a mother, let's say has lost its mother and loses the
motivation to feed and protect itself and stay with the, the troop and ends up dying as a result.
This is a clearly maladaptive state documented that in a non-human primate, you could call it
something like that, a depressed like state, deriving from bereavement and presumed
to anthropomorphize something like grief associated with bereavement. So I believe these,
you know, these states are, are shared by our, by our non-human.
Any evidence of self-harm in, in, in non-human primates, does it ever get to the level of,
I mean, you know, suicide is a top 10 cause of mortality in the developed world. It's
important to make sure people understand the significance of that statement.
In the developed world, when you think about all of the problems we've been able to solve,
one of the 10 leading causes of death is self-harm. And, and by the way, if you really include
overdose as a subset of that, it probably leap frogs into the top seven. Is there evidence that
this occurs in other species? So a really interesting question. And
the short answer is no. And there are less suicidal forms of self-harm that can happen.
Now and then you'll see animals, you know, carrying out behaviors like, you know, headbanging and
things like that. But in terms of a true suicide, the volitional ending of the self,
there is not a animal model for that. Let's say it's not clear that that happens. And if you think
about it, as much as we'd like to have that, so we could address this, this urgent, enormous
clinical need that's not going away, we would love to have some way of studying this.
We don't have it. And if you think about it, the ending of the self is an extremely
cognitively complex thing. And it's, if you think about the act of suicide, which we don't
understand, and it's a horrific thing, but you've got, there has to be some understanding
of what that means, that there is an ending of life, an ending of the self, and that the
pain that's being felt now would not be felt then. This is a level of understanding of
the universe that it doesn't seem that animals that are not us actually have. We could be wrong.
I'm completely willing to admit that. There are amazing animals, you know, dolphins and
whales and elephants have incredibly complex and amazing minds. They may be better than we are at
some of these deep concepts, but they may have less clear ways to express it. They may have
maybe not having fingers and hands to do things that we can do. They may not have the ways to
express it, even though their cognitions may be just as complex. And so I think there are two
factors. One is, you know, the things that set us apart, our brains and our hands, those two don't
come together in any other animal. And I think that's why you don't see suicide elsewhere,
at least as we understand it. Our colleague, Paul Conti, close, also friend for medical school,
who trained with you in psychiatry, has just written a wonderful book on trauma.
And so it begs the question, what role does trauma play in the amplification of depression?
We know, as you said, that depression is highly heritable. But like most conditions that are
heritable, there tends to be environmental triggers that can bring one person to have it
and one not to have it, even if you take the most extreme example of the monozygotic twins raised in
a separate environment, one comes down with something, there's clearly some difference.
So what role do you think that early childhood trauma plays in all mental illness, but I guess
specifically depression? And do you believe that that could be epigenetic? In other words,
do you believe that this thing can irreversibly mark the gene and then be transferred to subsequent
generations? Subsequent generations, yeah. So the effects of trauma, the lasting effects
of early life trauma are unfortunately very clear. You can see in animals as well.
And they extend beyond depression for sure to include the personality disorders like borderline
personality, for example. So there's no question that early life trauma has lasting psychiatric
influence throughout life and can cause very severe problems. In many ways to look at this,
why is it happening and how is it happening? Is there a wiring change? So is the lasting
quality due to a physical structure of the brain as a circuit? That's one level at which it could
happen. And the brain is very, brain circuitry is very tunable that way, especially in young people.
And so you could imagine that early life experience with trauma sets up the human
to expect in some ways that the world is a harsh and unpredictable place and that the
value system had better be set up to deal with that because that's how it is apparently.
And so you could almost imagine an adaptive, though very unfortunate, process going on where
there's a period of youth where you're gathering statistics about the environment, deciding what
the adult should be like, and then implementing that. And so early life trauma could intersect
with such a process very unfortunately and create people with a lasting state of depression, for
example, expecting aversive things to be present at higher rates and negative consequences of
actions to be present at a high rate. Now, that could be for sure the case as far as an evolutionary
logic, but there's no doubt that this happens in terms of the behavioral effect and the psychiatric
effect, the lasting effects of early life trauma. Now, if it's not neural circuitry, what else could
it be? It could be genetic or epigenetic, as you say, you're not changing your genome from childhood
to adulthood, but you're changing the transcription factors, the promoters and enhancers. You could be
affecting gene expression throughout life. And that, at least through the life of that individual,
we understand how that mechanistically could work. And then finally, you raise the
intergenerational aspect. In human beings, this is very hard to separate from, you know, it's the
nature and nurture thing. Of course, you've got the parenting that's linked to what might have
happened in the prior generation. And I'd say it's still controversial to how much intergenerational
transfer can happen, although in animals there are mechanisms.
You wrote about the, well, at least you wrote about your musings, your exploration of the idea
of the evolutionary basis for tears. I found this completely fascinating.
A, I found it fascinating because I'd never once considered that. And for someone like me who
is often thinking about the evolutionary basis for this feature or that feature, it was interesting
to me that I hadn't considered that. Say a little bit about that.
Emotional tears, and by that, you know, the liquid coming from our tear ducts at times of emotion,
this is apparently, as far as we can tell, it's a human trait. Our great apes don't do this,
and even some human beings don't do it. So it's a special thing. It's not that we are the only
ones that grieve, but we're the ones that secrete this fluid from our eyes at these extreme moments.
And this has been studied. There are scholars of tears, as it were, and you can do things like
add or subtract tears digitally from pictures of faces. And these have enormous impacts on
the reactions of people seeing these images much, much greater than a smile or a grimace,
and particularly creating a desire to help. When we see tears, we want to help that person.
And so this intersects very closely with the, I think, with the involuntary, largely involuntary
nature of tears. It's a truth channel. It's not so easily gameable. It reveals something
that in a social grouping, like those that we've evolved to maintain, it is an involuntary
expression of something, the world changing, of needing new systems in place, and it triggers
this outreach from people who see it in a very powerful way. And this question, can an emotional
change cause something like this to happen? It would be a very easy rewiring to happen. There
are already axons that come from emotional regions and go to the brainstem that control the breathing
rate, for example, in anxiety. And right next to those breathing rate regions, there are
regions that control the tear ducts. They're right next to each other in the brainstem, and a very
tiny, tiny rewiring little axon just going in one slightly different direction would create
this state of expressing this visible manifestation of an inner world. And for a social
species like ours, it could be easily, evolutionarily selected for. And so there's, in the story,
a storehouse of tears and projections. This is something that a patient's story helped bring to
the forefront of my mind, and we talk about it quite a bit. Yeah, I won't give any more away
from that story because I want people to read it for themselves. Well, Carl, I know that we've
kind of reached the limit of our time and you have another commitment today. As you can probably
imagine, I could continue this discussion for probably another couple of hours, and I gather
you could as well if it weren't for this other commitment. So I think what we should do is just
commit to sitting down again next year at some point. And continuing this discussion, there are
so many more questions I have about personality disorders. And another topic that we didn't even
get into today that we're both very interested in is psychedelics, both from the traditional side,
even to the non-traditional side, the use of ketamine, psilocybin, LSD, MDMA, all of these
things, which are an enormous interest of yours clinically and scientifically as of mine. So
I want to again congratulate you on not just your recent Lasker Award, which again, I'll make sure
in the introduction to explain to people what the significance of that is, but also your remarkable
achievements over the past two decades and this remarkable work that you've written, Projections,
which I suspect many people are going to be reading after this. So, Carl, thanks very much for
spending time with us today and for educating us on this amazing journey you've been on.
Pete, it's been great. Great to reconnect with you again on an incredibly enjoyable conversation and
look forward to talking again. All right. Bye for now. All right. Take care.
This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the
practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the users' own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash
about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.