Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, David. Great to see you today.
My pleasure as always, Peter. Good to see you.
It's been a while since we've seen each other in person. I feel like it's probably been,
I don't know, three or four years, right?
Easily. Easily. We've spent many an hour on Zoom together in the last couple of years,
but it's been a while since we've been in the same state, in the same building, in the
same room at the same time.
Now you're no stranger to this podcast in the sense that I feel like you probably listen
to podcasts before anybody. In fact, I think you and Nir Barzilai must hold the record
for being the first people to listen to a podcast because, you know, they come out on
Mondays and it's barely the early part of the morning. And usually you and Nir are the
first two to send me an email with your thoughts. So I know you're a fan and it's great to have
you on. I've been wanting to do this for some time.
Well, thank you. I really admire the podcast and I admire Nir Barzilai. So to know I'm
in league with him is pretty cool.
So you're one of the most interesting people I know and I always love just spending time
with you and talking with you about subjects. And I think one of the things I've always
admired about you is you're known for being in a field such as obesity, which tends to
attract a lot of dogmatic thinking. And yet you tend to approach this field with a distant,
you know, sort of lack of emotion, right? You just come at it very sort of intellectually.
And I guess I realize, as I'm saying, that it speaks disparagingly of people in the field
of obesity, which is not really what I'm trying to say. But I think for many people
the field of obesity is a loaded field scientifically even, let alone sort of politically and all
the other things that go with it. So I've always assumed that that's because your background
is slightly different than maybe some of the people who came to obesity through physiology.
So tell us a little bit about your background. What did you study? What did you do your PhD?
And that sort of thing.
Sure. You know, I sometimes will have people say, you know, why are you like this? Or why
did you do this? Why did you choose that? And the truth is, even as a scientist, often
say, following my friend Don Rubin, who I admire a lot, we may be able to figure out
what the causal effect of X is, but we may not be able to assess whether X caused Y. So
I don't really know why it turned out the way I turned out. But even as a kid, I was
always the kid asking questions. Sometimes that would interest people. Sometimes that
would annoy people. And that's true today. But I was always one saying, are you sure?
How do you know? Where did that come from? What makes you think that's true? And then
of course, my kids fed it back to me as they were growing up and heard me say it. And when
I would say to them, don't do that, you'll get hurt. They'd say, what's your evidence
for that data? So, you know, I went to college and I started out knowing I wanted to be a
psychologist. But what that meant to me at the time was Hitchcock films, right? I was
going to interpret people's dreams and I would figure out what the meaning of the clock
in the dream was or something like that. And then the person would be cured and it would
be a great movie. And then as I got to college, I started to think about, well, what's the
evidence for these things? And that sort of opens up this whole can of worms about asking
about evidence. Became more and more cognitive behaviorally oriented, still thought I wanted
to be a clinician, got to graduate school. And I asked the professor at one point as
we're being trained in graduate school, PhD program, to administer IQ tests. And we're
learning these different theories of intelligence. Some people think there's one factor, some
people think three. One person thought 144. And I said, well, who's right? And the professor
says, well, they bring their different evidence to bear and they argue. I said, well, what's
the evidence? He said, these factor analyses. I don't really know what that is. What's a
factor analysis? He says, well, you have to go study multivariate statistics if you want
to understand that. So I don't like to take anybody's word for anything. So I went and
studied multivariate statistics and became more and more involved with statistical analysis
to the point where eventually later in my career, people started thinking I was a statistician.
And I stopped fighting it. I said, OK. The American Statistical Association thinks so,
and the university thinks so, and the NIH and NSF thinks so. I think so too. And so
that's great. So I sort of became by evolution a statistician, having been trained as a psychologist.
But I think all of that comes down to evidence and all the thinking that people are no different
than anything else. Body fat is no different than any other variable. And that still has
to obey the same laws of probability and physics and mathematics and so on that we apply to
anything else. And I think we often forget that. People talk. And so folks who study
people think about the words that people say. Whereas if you're studying atoms and molecules,
you don't think about the words they say. You just apply scientific methods. The same
person who would never question a diabetologist on what the beta cell of a pancreas is doing,
unless they themselves are a diabetologist studying the beta cells of the pancreas, will
say to an obesity researcher, well, this is how obesity works. And it's this aspect of
food or that aspect of culture or that aspect of child rearing based only on the fact that
they were children or had children and had some experience. And so to me, it's just taking a step
back and just treating, as my old boss in biostatistics used to say, whether it's X's and Y's,
they're just variables and applying the same laws of thinking to all those systems.
So when was it either post PhD or during PhD that you were drawn to obesity in particular as a
clinical field? You know, I actually started as an undergraduate. And so it was, I think,
was a sophomore. And I took a class at Vassar College. And I should say that all my remarks
today just reflect my own opinions. I'm not speaking for Indiana University or Vassar College
or anybody else, just myself. And I took a class at Vassar College on human emotion and motivation.
And we studied the theories of Stanley Schachter, who at the time was a professor of psychology at
Columbia University. He's since deceased. An amazing, brilliant man who wrote a book called
Emotion, Obesity and Crime. And he talked about the connections among these and how the distinction
between our cognitive state and our physiologic arousal state might lead us to certain kinds of
behaviors, including in the case of some people, eating more calories than they might otherwise
eat. And his experiments were so creative. I just loved it. And he would put like a clock on the
wall. And he would have the clock move a little faster, but not perceptibly faster. And then he
would bring some students in and give them some work to do under some ruse. And then the clock
would say for some of the students at 11am that it was noon. And he'd say, by the way, I have a big
tray of roast beef sandwiches out here. So, you know, whenever you're hungry for lunch, just let
me know and you can have some sandwiches. And for some people, the clock wouldn't say it was noon
until 1pm. And for some people, it was noon at noon. And he'd say, who would be following the
clock and who would be following the actual time? And obese or overweight persons were more likely
to follow the clock. And this became the external theory. And then it didn't always work out. And
then you'd have another experiment. Well, it only holds up under this circumstance. And it was
incredibly creative how we'd keep looping through. And so I just got hooked on it. Then we had to
write lots and lots of papers at Vassar College. I got a great education in writing and thinking
there. Not so many tests, lots of papers. And so when I would take Physiologic Psychology, I would
write about the Physiologic Psychology of obesity. And when I took Behavioral Psychology, I wrote
Behavioral on obesity. When I took Developmental, I'd write about Developmental aspects of obesity.
And I love the fact that you not only could, but in my opinion, had to look at obesity from so many
of those different angles that no one thing was going to do it. Everybody's got their pet thing.
This nutrient is toxic. It's this food marketing practice. It's this cultural practice. It's
exercise. It's not exercise. I think there are many factors involved and I enjoyed studying it
and still do from many angles. Now, this is happening in the late 80s, correct? When you're
in school, finishing your PhD. Mid to late 80s. And at the time, what was the both political and
medical view of obesity? I don't think it was the same issue it was today. Was it? Obesity rates
weren't particularly high in the 80s or were they? I don't really recall. They weren't as high as they
are now. And there had been steady increases. If you go back and look at data from at least the
1700s forward, there have been relatively steady increases in obesity rates in westernized,
industrialized countries since then. But there seemed to be this wake up moment in the late 90s,
in the early 90s with the NHANES III. And so at that point, we didn't have the NHANES, which is
the National Health Nutrition Examination Survey, which annually does today a survey of a representative
sample of Americans with measured heights and weights. That's how we track obesity levels. At
that point, it was only done every few years. And so there was this big gap in years between NHANES II
and NHANES III. So NHANES II had happened, I think, in the early 80s or mid 80s. And obesity rates
were climbing, but not dramatically. And so obesity was an issue, but it wasn't on top of everybody's
mind, especially for kids. Pharmaceuticals were still seen as the realm of charlatans at that
point. If you were a doc and you proposed, promoted the use of obesity medications, you were called a
diet doc, and that was like a very bad stigma. There weren't many good medications available.
Surgery was still looked at as a very peculiar thing for very extreme cases. And even many medical
professionals distained it. And then something happened in the very early 1990s, which is the
NHANES III data came out. And what you saw was this big jump in obesity levels. And that got
everybody's attention. And words like epidemic started to be used, especially around childhood.
And the public health policy and environmental perspective came in. And things started to shift
in the mid 90s. And that was when you had people like Kelly Brownell, probably one of the most
forceful voices at the time, who was a sort of old school, University of Pennsylvania,
colleague of Tom Wadden, devotee, a student of Mickey Stunkard, of the cognitive behavioral
individual clinical treatment approach to obesity, suddenly starting to say, maybe we've got it
wrong. Maybe it's this environment. I don't know if Kelly coined the term toxic environment,
but he certainly either coined it or popularized it. And people started to think about prevention
and children and the overall environment, the political, economic, social, food marketing
environment we lived in. And it all started to take off. And ideas from the cigarette world,
the same public health people who had been battling cigarette companies and tobacco for decades,
many of they and their tools came in and said, we know how to deal with things that are environmental,
social, political problems. And it began to be seen as an environmental, social, political problem.
And in some way, a lot was gained because we got a lot more funding for it, we got a lot more
attention, a lot more efforts, a lot more research. But in some ways, it was lost. In the early 90s,
when I kind of grew up in the field, I grew up in the first federally funded obesity research
center, which is the New York obesity research center for a long time, the only one. And by gosh,
if as a young postdoc, I were to say something that didn't quite jibe with physiology or genetics
or anatomy or clinical medicine, there was a physiologist and a geneticist and an anatomist
and a medical doctor who would say, uh-uh. And they knew all, they knew each other,
they knew the arguments, they knew the literature for the last 20 years.
Then the public health people came in fresh without kind of knowing so much. So on the one hand,
it launched things up a lot, which was great. But on the other hand, back to what you were
saying earlier about the dilution of the rigor of the field intellectually, it became a lot more
of opinion, a lot more of advocacy in the absence of rigorous evidence showing what worked. You're
just saying, this seems like it ought to work. So David, prior to NHANES III and prior to
Kelly and others saying, hey, we should look for something else, what was believed to be the
environmental or otherwise trigger for obesity? In other words, what was viewed as the cause?
Yeah, I don't know that there was a single cause. I mean, clearly, what some people today call the
energy balance model, which we can go back to and ask whether that really is even a model in some
realistic sense, I think was then and still is today by most people in the field, except that as
valid, but maybe not as a model, maybe as a description of what occurs.
Yeah, I was going to say that's sort of a tautology and doesn't really tell us anything.
It's implied and obvious and not explanatory.
Right. I think not explanatory is maybe the best way of describing it in some sense.
The analogy I would use to that is I think the energy balance statement, I won't say model,
say the energy balance statement is as long as you accept the laws of thermodynamics unequivocally
correct in the same sense as if you accept Euclidean geometry, the statements about the
relationship between the legs and the hypotenuse of a triangle are unequivocally correct.
But if I say to you, I have a triangle of this size with legs of length A and B, and I proportionately
imagine another triangle that has legs greater than length A and B, it doesn't cause the
hypotenuse to be bigger. It means the hypotenuse is bigger. And if I say I imagine one with a
bigger hypotenuse, it doesn't cause the legs to be bigger. It means the legs are bigger.
And any question about whether the legs cause the hypotenuse or the hypotenuse
cause the legs is nonsense. They don't cause each other. They're inherent in the definition of
triangle just as inherent in the definition of energy is the law of conservation. And it just
says delta energy stores equals delta energy in minus delta energy out. It's just a statement.
So was the belief though that this was behavioral prior to NHANES III was the belief that,
well, if a person is overweight or obese, they are just eating more than they're expending
because of a choice? I think it's almost hard to answer that because I think the thinking was,
and still remains, so sloppy that people don't even distinguish among things well. I was just
invited to a panel literally today that I'm going to be on in a few months where somebody said,
we're going to contrast for obesity the relative influence of biology versus behavior.
As though we could behave without biology. I mean, I don't know about you, but I'm not a
disembodied soul. And if you're a disembodied soul, maybe. But for the rest of us who are in the
material world, you behave with a body and it's got to obey the same laws of physics and so on
that any other body has to behave. So I think there's a lot of sloppy thinking, but I think if
you really drill down and you got to smart people who understood, they would say, of course, they're
a genetic component. Any rancher could have told you a hundred or more years ago that there's a
genetic component. We can selectively breed animals for being thinner or fatter. That shows you there's
a genetic component. There are many other things I'd show you that, but that's probably the strongest
prima facie evidence. You can selectively breed animals to be fatter or leaner.
It's prima facie evidence. But by the way, is the concordance of identical twins separated at birth?
I've always found that to be one of the most interesting ways to assess everything from
autism to schizophrenia. Like it's really a beautiful natural experiment. But I don't know
what the concordance is with respect to obesity and identical twins separated. Do you? Yeah. There are
a lot of different ways to quantify that, and we've written a couple of papers on it. But I think
the easiest way is just the Pearson product moment correlation coefficient, the ordinary
correlation coefficient of BMI twin to twin. And it turns out that for monozygotic or identical twins
separated at or near itly after birth, it's nearly the same magnitude as it is for twins reared
together, which is about 0.9 ish. Wow. It varies from study to study. So it's very similar. And so
it's probably now, of course, you can argue, well, that also takes into account the
contribute or environment. Yeah, exactly. Maybe some epigenetic things. But bottom line is whatever
those things are, they're not just the child rearing of the home. It looks like for many traits,
including obesity, the child rearing of the home does have an influence, but it's not a huge
influence. That's an incredible degree of concordance. It sure is. When was that realized?
When were those studies first done? Well, it's interesting because you can go back to quite some
period of time to find the hints of those studies. And often when you look at science, it's often
that we at some level, we kind of knew something. The information was sort of there, but there was
this moment where a key figure had to come in and both see it and say it with a degree of crispness
that wasn't there before. As I said, so lots of people could have seen the ranching data and the
mouse data and family data. In 1923, Davenport, who he's kind of looked at now probably as a racist
from the past, but at the time, Davenport published under the Carnegie Foundation these studies of
concordance of families. And you could have seen the genetic component in his 1923 data,
but it was Albert J. Mickey Stunkard, who was someone I had the great privilege of knowing
and a wonderful, wonderful man. And Mickey did the first major high quality twin and adoption
studies, and he did what he was great at. He got on a plane and he went around the world and he
met bright, young, interesting people and he said, you have resources and you have ideas and you have
data and you're smart. Can I work with you? Can we work on this together? And he got Torquilled
Sorensen and other people to start working on twin studies with the great Nordic data,
Sweden, Denmark, and so on, and adoption studies. And it was the twin and adoption studies coming
out of Sweden and Denmark that I think really nailed it. That finally, New England Journal of Medicine
with Mickey Stunkard behind it, with clear writing, with high quality data, people said,
we got it. There's a big genetic component. And this was approximately what year, David?
This would have been 83 ish plus or minus a couple. So again, trying to bring this back to
kind of the clinical side of things. So if by the early eighties, it's or it should be patently
clear that genetics are playing an important role, it would be at least a decade before people would
say, well, pharmacologic therapy might make sense here. Just as, for example, if somebody
is genetically more likely to have hypothyroidism, right, a very relatively straightforward
endocrinology or endocrine system to understand, we wouldn't really think twice about replacing or
you know, abrogating thyroid hormone as necessary. So where was that disconnect where it's the early
eighties and we realize there's a very strong genetic component to this, we probably have some
medical tools that we could use. But it still seems like that wasn't being done. So what what
was being done? Were was it just a case of counseling people to eat less and exercise more?
It was mostly developing the tools that would help people reduce energy intake. And I think today,
that's still most of what we do. So even surgery and drugs, mostly, but not only help people reduce
energy intake. We know that reducing energy intake works, it's just really hard to do and telling
people to do it and saying, I'll try to do it is not all that effective. And so all these things
were tools and we use the tools of behavior therapy, starting in, I would say really the
60s is probably where the formal behavioral stuff really kicked in with I think was Stuart
and the behavioral thinking about obesity, then it continued to get better and better,
all the way through present still continues to get better and better. But my sense is that, you know,
we've been asymptoting for a long time. That is, we're getting incrementally better,
not meaningfully better with many of the behavioral cognitive things. What happened then
in the early 90s is, and I remember because I was a postdoc at the New York obesity research center
at the time, is a few people started to really kick in with pharmaceuticals. And they started to come
out of this idea that you're a diet doc and it's a bad thing. And fen-phen, which now we know was
dangerous and is gone, at least one of the fens in fen-phen, that came up and that caught people's
attention. Tell folks a little bit about fen-phen. Many people listening probably won't be familiar
with what it is, how it worked, and what the unfortunate consequence was in a small but
non-trivial subset of people. So fen-phen was, is a nickname for two drugs used in combination,
fentramine and fen-fluoramine. Fentramine is a drug that was and still is approved by the FDA
for the treatment of obesity, though it's never been approved for long term. So it goes back a
long way. It's a catecholaminergic agonist. It's a relatively safe drug, though not a,
no drug is perfectly safe. And it's modestly effective. Fen-fluoramine is a selective
serotonergic reuptake inhibitor, which I think originally was used for depression.
And people realized sometimes those drugs, those SSRIs cause weight loss. Somebody realized you
could put those two together and seem to get better results. So that became a big craze.
And there were many unscrupulous medical providers who did provide that in ways they
shouldn't have. But there were many scrupulous medical providers who used it carefully and
thoughtfully. And it did seem to have much better benefit than other people had predicted before
that. And so suddenly, pharmaceutical treatment was no longer the realm of drive-through pill mills
and charlatans and diatox and rainbow pills and so on. It was starting to be credible. You had
people like George Bray, who's still around today and working on obesity, jumping on board and
starting to really think through all the cornucopia of pharmaceuticals we knew about and which ones
might be useful, others weighing in. And then a very smart young person whose name I no longer
recall, but who was a pathologist, not an obesity researcher as far as I know, at the Mayo Clinic,
started noticing some people coming through as cadavers. And she was being asked to do autopsies
and did autopsies and started noticing a peculiar valvulopathy that she didn't see very often. And
she started seeing a little run of cases and then noticed that all of these cases had been on fen-phen
and reported it. And then many, many other people started to investigate it. And very quickly,
people realized, in fact, this did produce a certain valvulopathy. And further investigation
made it clear it was the fenfloramine component, not the fen-ter-mine component that did that.
So the fen-floramine was withdrawn. Fen-ter-mine is still used today. But I think what was
terrible, of course, is that one of the many drugs in the history of obesity that hurt people.
But what was good about it is that it really started getting people thinking more about
obesity as a serious medical disorder that merited serious attention from credible physicians
and credible scientists working at the molecular, pharmaceutical, and physiologic level.
And how much of fen-phen's mechanism was understood? I mean, obviously, at the superficial
level it was. But in terms of its direct action, was the belief that one component was simply
increasing energy expenditure while the other was reducing appetite?
I don't think it was quite that simple. And I don't think with any of these things, we ever
fully know the components. This is where you know far more than I. But I mean, even in the case of
statins, which we think so highly of and use so well, whether they really have their beneficial
effects by reducing LDL cholesterol, which is sort of the initial thought, or through other
mechanisms, I think is even being debated now. I think we suspected and still would believe
that they reduced appetite and therefore helped people control their food intake better, that the
two things did it through slightly different mechanisms, one being more serotonergic, one
being more adrenergic. They may have also had effects on energy expenditure, albeit probably
modest ones. And that was probably more the fentramine than the fenfloramine. In terms of
the mechanism for the valvulopathy, I'll have to leave that to you. That's out of my realm.
And when was fen-phen pulled? Was that the mid to late 90s?
I think it was the late 90s, but I don't remember the exact date, probably 97-ish somewhere around
there. What about gastric bypass and other surgical approaches? Now we have sleeves,
ruin why, all sorts of different approaches to it. But when did that sort of go from being
presumably incredibly fringe to, quite frankly, where we are today, where this is something that
will be covered by an insurance company if the BMI is high enough?
I don't know that there was a single moment, so I think there's been a sort of a relatively
steady march, but I do think there was one key step that was kind of a step function in the
credibility of it. And that was the Swedish obese subject study as from Lars Schostrum in Sweden.
Surgery had been around for a while. Interestingly, even among physicians and scientists,
it was very controversial, and still is. Some people think it's Bob Eric, some people think
it's uphorn. Again, I think you just have to take the data as it is. You might say, wouldn't
it be better if we had a world where no one needed surgery, where our solution to obesity
was not let children start to gain weight, and then when they become massively obese adults,
give them surgery and rearrange their internal anatomy? Yeah, it probably would be better.
But that's not the world we live in. We live in this world, and in this world,
that's the most effective, life-saving, life-changing treatment we have, and it's a good one.
And so what happened is many physicians would battle among each other. I remember John Kral,
who's since passed on, a very good surgeon, one of another physician colleague chastising him over
dinner at a conference and saying, when you're done with a patient, Dr. Kral, they will never
eat normally again. And he said, no, when I'm done, they will never eat abnormally again.
So there were these real vitriolic battles. I think what happened is the surgeries, of course,
got better and better and better. I said, everything else, people learn how to do things
better. Mortality rates went way down. Efficacy went up. But what Lars Schostrum did is he said,
I want to look at whether this prolongs life. And I remember him telling me many decades ago
that his senior mentor, Per Bjornthorpe, who was known for fat cell theories and the Apple versus
Pear idea, where I was originally Jean Vague, was Apple versus Pear from France in the 1950s.
But then in the 80s, really, 70s and 80s, Bjornthorpe was one of the big people who picked it up.
Bjornthorpe laughed at his mentoring. He says, Lars, everybody knows this. Everybody knows that
surgery will cause weight loss and help people live longer. There's no point in doing this study.
And Lars said, you may be right that it does, but we have to do this study because everybody
doesn't accept and believe that and hasn't been shown. And I think we know over and over again,
you've got to do the experiment. As John Hunter famously said to Edward Jenner, when Jenner says,
I think, and he's thinking about the first vaccine, and Hunter comes back and says, why think,
do the experiment? You've got to do the experiment and show it. So Schostrum didn't do a pure
experiment. It's not a randomized trial, but it's a controlled trial. And the IRB at the time didn't
think it was ethical to randomly assign people to the surgery or not. So if they're willing to get
surgery, he would find a closely matched control and give them usual care. And then what he showed
well more than a decade later in the New England Journal of Medicine is that the surgery reduced
mortality rate. It reduced obesity, very powerful effects, clearly a life saving and a beneficially
life changing treatment. I think that was probably the big jump. And then since then,
many other trials, some randomized, have been done showing positive benefits on many things,
including longevity. Do you recall what the risk reduction was in all-cause mortality in that study?
I don't recall in that study per se, but when you look across studies, it varies quite a bit from
study to study. There's a lot of heterogeneity, but it's usually well on the order of a 50%
reduction, sometimes a little bit more. And maybe getting to in the weeds on this, but
how does that change when you do and do not correct for the presence of type 2 diabetes
at the outset? In other words, I would imagine that that's a combination of people who had and
did not have type 2 diabetes. And do you have a sense of what the differences are amongst those
two cohorts? Your premise is correct that it is among people who do and don't have type 2 diabetes.
But no, I don't know at the top of my head. I share your intuition that it's probably stronger
among people who do. And we need to also look at many different factors. So for example, in the
Swedish Obese Object Study, and I'm not sure this would hold up at all, one of the things that was
very puzzling and surprising, at least to me, was that although diabetes really came down and stayed
down very well, even if weight came back up a little, which it did on average, hypertension
came down very well, but did not stay down very well. It would come back up. And why that is,
is it damage to the endothelial elasticity that's not really repairable, and so you get a
short-term effect of negative energy balance that's not sustained? I don't know. But it goes
back to that John Hunter thing. You've got to do the experiment. And so we can't make our priority
assumptions about the effects of treatments. We've got to do the experimental look at the effects of
treatment. It's interesting that hypertension would return, and yet mortality would still
improve, which suggests that perhaps the benefits of improved insulin sensitivity, which do persevere,
play a greater role in mortality than body weight, which does not surprise me,
but also hypertension, which is somewhat surprising, given how causally related hypertension
is at atherosclerosis. Well, it may not be a greater role as much as an additional role,
right? So it could be that if you got the hypertension down, you'd get an even bigger reduction.
So when did this idea of kind of an obesity paradox, which I know you've written about,
when did that start to become observed? I think that phrase obesity paradox has never been
really crisply defined, and whether it really is something that's a paradox is not clear. People
use it to mean at least two different things. One thing is that there's this so-called U-shaped
curve, more accurately concave upward as a bathtub-shaped curve, if you imagine a Cartesian or
XY plot in which the Y or ordinate is mortality rate or some function of it, and the X is BMI or
relative body weight or something. So one is that it is U-shaped, that it's not monotonic increasing.
And so people at the very thin end also die earlier than people in the middle, just as
people at the very heavy end die earlier than people in the middle. Now, the Duchess of Windsor
has supposedly said, you can never be too rich or too thin. And she may have been right on the rich
part, I don't know, haven't gotten there yet, but apparently not on the too thin part. Now,
we can argue whether it's causal, and there are lots of arguments about whether it's causal.
But that's one thing, it's the idea that thinner people than sort of intermediate levels of BMI
also die earlier. That's one part. The other part is that even though obesity is associated with
increased mortality rate or decreased longevity, that when you look at people who are sick
or injured, they often live the longest. So somebody comes in with kidney failure,
or someone comes in after a major injury or a major infection, they're in the hospital,
it's often the heaviest people that live longer. And that started to be talked about 10, 15 years
ago, maybe. It's very difficult to disentangle cause and effect. We can observe lots of associations,
but it's just hard to know what to make of all of these associations and what's causal.
As the philosophers say, the hypotheses are underdetermined by the data. There are multiple
hypotheses that are consistent with the data. That's why the randomized experiment allows us
to do things that otherwise we can't do, sort of eliminates more competing hypotheses. So
I don't think we know what's causal yet. We've thrown out a model, a man named Doug Childers
and I, who's a postdoc, who was a good mathematician working with me, in which we said,
what if obesity makes it more likely that you get a major illness or injury?
So it's not good for your health in that sense. Age, of course, also makes it more likely that
you get a major illness or injury. But once you get a major illness or injury, being heavier,
more obese, may reduce your risk of dying from it. And an analogy I use is this. Suppose you and
I are sort of going for a hike on the edge of the Grand Canyon and we go to some outfitter who's
setting us up. And he says to you, who's about 10 years younger than me, I think, and he says to you,
you have a choice. I can give you this fat suit you can wear. It has lots of padding on it.
If you fall off the cliff, it makes it much more likely you'll survive.
But it makes you a little clumsy, so it makes you more likely to fall off the cliff.
You might say, I've got good balance and good eyesight and I'm young and strong. And no,
it comes to me and I say, I'm not quite as young and strong. Maybe. I don't know. It comes to me,
somebody 10 years older than me, that person says, I'm really struggling with my eyesight or balance
or strength. I'll take the fat suit. All right. And so whether the fat suit is good for you may
depend upon your probability of falling to begin with. And under that mathematical model, we can
show, in fact, that the point of BMI, the nadir of that bathtub-shaped concave upward curve,
should keep moving to the right as you age, which is exactly what it does. So we have a model that's
consistent with the data, but the data don't prove our model. There are other models that
would be consistent with it. Let's give people an idea of what those numbers look like. So just
for someone listening to this, maybe I'm not even watching, it can be hard to imagine what we're
talking about, right? But a U-shaped curve that at its nadir is giving you the optimal BMI. This
would be the lowest mortality. And what you're saying is rather than just plot one of these
curves for everybody, let's plot them by decade. So what does the U-shaped curve look like for
people in their 20s, in their 30s, 40s, 50s, 60s, up to their 90s? And what you're saying is,
if your hypothesis is correct, one place you would expect to see that is that these curves would not
only not look the same by decade, but they would move rightward, meaning the nadir is getting to
a heavier and heavier BMI. Can you give me a sense of how much movement there is by decade?
Yeah. In fact, I'm going to smooth over things. So the story I'm about to tell you is not perfectly
true, but it's sort of a roughly true, and it sort of conveys the sort of nice element of this.
The average American might gain about a pound a year. For an average height American,
about six or so pounds might be a BMI unit, right? If you gained about six pounds,
you might gain about a BMI unit. And so that might mean that over six years,
you'd be about one BMI unit heavier. And that's not too far off from how the nadir moves. It's
almost as though your weight is increasing to keep you on at the nadir, which is an interesting
speculation. And if you looked at people who are maybe 20 years old, that nadir might not be too
far from 20 in some populations. An astute reader of the epidemiologic literature who's listening
now might appropriately be saying, hey, wait a minute now, Alison needs to make distinctions by
age, race, and sex. He's doing age. He's not doing race and sex and other factors, and they'd be
right. We can come back to that if you wish. But putting that aside for the moment, very loosely
speaking, you might say that nadir might be far down near 20 when you're 20. And by the time you're
80, it's not to 80. But by the time you're 80, it might be well above 30. It might be in the low
30s where that nadir is, which is we generally say 30 is the beginning of obesity. And for those
who are not used to BMIs, I used to lay it out like this. The supermodel, Kate Moss, at least from a
few decades ago when she was the top model, had a BMI, I think, in 16 to 17 range. We say that about
18.5 is sort of the beginning of normal weight. We think less than that is underweight. My BMI
right now is probably 21-ish. Bill Clinton's at the height of his presidency. He's since lost
way. He was probably 27, 28. We say 30 is where obesity begins. And a secretary sumo wrestler,
top class sumo wrestler, about 43, 44. So that gives you a sense of what those BMIs are. And so
it's really 30, 32, where you see people 70, 80 and above having that lowest mortality rate.
Is there a risk that we're looking at confounders here? I don't know if this would be a confounder.
It wouldn't seem like it would be a confounder in this year, meaning in this time and place we're
in. But would it be a confounder for affluence, for example, as it may have been hundreds of years
ago? You know, other things like that. And the other thing about BMI is, you know, when you look
at other data that look at body composition, do we see the same thing hold up? So you can have a BMI
of 30 and not even though you're obese by BMI, no one would look at you and say you're obese.
You might have a body fat of 15 percent, which is pretty low and be incredibly muscular, for example.
So how do we reconcile one, the potential confounders of that type of an analysis with
sort of this other next layer of granularity in the data that look at adiposity versus lean mass?
Let's start with the confounding question. Now let's get to the body composition. Of course,
the confounding question is a nightmare. This is the challenge of observational research in general.
And there's no simple solutions to it other than, in my opinion, trying to triangulate on the answer
with multiple studies. What we really want is the pure randomized experiment in humans,
in large samples, with perfect compliance for many years. And we want to randomly assign people to
be obese or not obese. Obviously, we can't do that. So what do we do? Well, we look at observational
epidemiology. We look at randomized trials where we have people lose weight. We look at non-randomized
trials like showrooms with surgery. We look at mouse studies. You know, we look at all these
different things. We try to just put the puzzle together as best we can. But there's absolutely
a lot of possibility for confounding. Cigarette smoking was one of the early ones. Very famous
paper by Joanne Manson and colleagues published in New England Journal, excuse me, at JAMA,
pointing out that the quote right way, according to them, to analyze BMI and mortality data was
you must exclude ever smokers. You only look at never smokers. Otherwise, you may have confounding
by smoking. Smoking makes you thinner. Smoking kills you earlier. You've got to take care of that.
You've got to throw out the subjects who die early because subjects who die early may have
been sick. Sickness makes you thinner. Sickness makes you die earlier. That is a confounder.
We've since proved mathematically that that's not a good thing to do. But for a long time,
it was believed. Is that even true, David, on the low end? Because that does strike me as one of
the most obvious explanations for the uptick in mortality at very low BMIs is all of the
delivered disease, the kidney disease, the types of chronic diseases that actually do
lead to muscle wasting and things like that. Are you also including them in your analysis?
So yes, we are. What we showed is not that that confounding doesn't occur.
That confounding absolutely can occur, or we agree that it can occur. We speculate. We think
it's likely. What we've shown is that throwing out subjects who die early in the analysis doesn't
help or doesn't reliably help. It was very interesting back to the discussion of the field.
When I went to analyze my first BMI mortality data set, I had no training in this, so I get a data
set and I'm about to try it. I don't know what I'm doing. So I call up my friends and I say,
I read this paper in JAMA and it says you have to eliminate the early deaths. But how do I do
that? How do I pick how many years to do? Exactly how does this work? And it was interesting because
when I would call the epidemiologists and I would say, how does this work? And then I'd say, by the
way, is there a reference that explains and proves that this works? They'd say, no, it's obvious that
it works. I said, well, it's not obvious to me. And they said, well, maybe you're not smart enough
to be an epidemiologist. Okay. Those words were actually uttered? Jokingly. But yeah, then I would
call my friends with statisticians and I would say, there's this paper and it says you have to
eliminate the early deaths. They would laugh at me like, what? That's the most ridiculous thing
I've ever heard. We don't just throw out data and think it makes things better. You've got to have
a model that you fit things to. So we then got a small grant from the CDC and we looked at
mathematical proofs, computer simulations, and meta-analyses. And the mathematical proof showed
it not only didn't have to help reduce the confounding, it could make it worse.
Simulations showed the same thing in realistic data scenarios. And then the meta-analyses showed
that on average didn't make much difference at all. So throwing out the subjects who die early
basically just reduces your power in most practical situations. Then they would say,
you've got to not control for the intermediary variables like the diabetes and hypertension.
That's probably true. I think I would agree with that. Later in subsequent paper in 1995 in the
Journal of Medicine, that same group said, you've got to throw out the subjects who have more weight
variability. All the things they said in 1987 weren't enough to flatten out that left end of the
U-shaped curve. So they said, throw out the subjects who die, who have a lot of weight
fluctuation. And that didn't completely get rid of it, but got rid of most of it. That's the bigger
one. But what it means is unclear. Katherine Fleagle has written very well on this and talked
about these different things and how much you're throwing away and pointing out, yes, these are the
patterns we observe, but what they mean causally is unclear. So that's the whole confounding issue.
The bottom line is it's likely that there's confounding by cigarette smoking and socioeconomic
status and stigma. That's one of the big things, right? How much does obesity kill you because it
stigmatizes you and it creates some stress? Could be. And that may be, by the way, why the BMI
associated with the lowest mortality has been increasing over calendar time. That's not just
with age of individuals, but if you compare data collected in the 1970s to data collected in the
1990s, obesity doesn't, from an association point of view, look quite as bad in the 1990s as it did
in the 1970s. And that's true in Denmark and that's true in the US and it's true in meta-analysis,
although again, not for every age-race sex group. Why is that? And maybe it's stigma. Maybe it's that
if you think about, you watch like the Three Stooges, those old TV shows, and there was Curly
and he was often mocked as the fat guy, right? By today's standards, he's not that big. And so,
what stigmatized changes over time as different BMIs become normative. And so, it may be that
that's partially accounting for it. So, there's lots of potential confounding going on there,
but there's lots of other possible explanations. So, bottom line, we don't know. And the real
important question then is, what's the effect of intervention? This goes back to my friend
and someone I really idolized in the field, one of the clearest thinkers, Don Rubin,
statistician at Harvard, talks to another Rubin causal model. And he's always asking,
what's the intervention? If you say, does this cause that? What do you mean, compared to what?
It's always got to be compared to what, right? And so, if you say weight loss is going to increase
longevity, that's the question. Well, how are you going to achieve that weight? What are you going
to do to get that? Well, then if it's surgery, then what's the effect of surgery? It's a GLP1
agonist. What's the effect of a GLP1 agonist, et cetera. So, that I think is the key question.
And I think what we're starting to see is some of those things do prolong life, surgery,
SGLT2 inhibitors, GLP1 agonist, and so forth. Now, to your other question about body composition,
many people like to point out that BMI is a measure of mass divided by stature. It was
developed by Adolf K. Ley, who was a Belgian astronomer, epidemiologist, statistician,
mathematician back in the 19th century. Brilliant guy. We actually named a professorship after him
and I held that title. I was very grateful for that opportunity back when I was at the University
of Alabama at Birmingham before I came to IU. And Kaitlin made it, you would think that BMI,
or rather the mass of a three-dimensional object ought to increase in proportion to the cube
of a linear dimension. And if in fact we were spheres of uniform density, that would be true.
But I don't know about you, I'm not a sphere of uniform density. So, it turns out not to work that
way exactly. Turns out that empirically, it works closer to the square for adult humans.
Kaitlin realized that and so he said, take mass or weight over stature squared, the square of stature.
That's, then it was called Kaitlin's index, now we call it BMI. It was sort of rediscovered in the
60s or 70s by Ansel Keys and term BMI, body mass index. And every few years some smart person likes
to come along and says, it should be cubed. We get it, we knew that like a couple hundred years ago
and we worked that out. Then they say, and it doesn't really take into account body composition.
We say, we know that. And they say, the NBA center would have a BMI greater than 30 and yet look how
strong and fit that NBA center is. We go, right, if the NBA center comes to your clinical practice,
don't measure his BMI and diagnose him with obesity on that. And what physician in his or
her right mind would do such a thing? So, clearly we get that. BMI is a useful tool for epidemiologic
research and some simple physiologic research and some simple clinical trials. It's not a perfect
clinical tool. For the average person, it works okay. Now, do we have to be worried about different
ethnicities? Obviously the two that come to mind would be Asian and East Asians because,
I think most people are kind of familiar with this idea of skinny fat, right? So, you have
someone of East Asian descent whose BMI is 26, which by all intents sounds just wonderful.
But they have metabolic syndrome, right? There's nothing about this person that's healthy, right?
Every metric across the board, tons of visceral fat, very little muscle mass, et cetera.
And that's a different phenotype, right? That's a slightly different phenotype than perhaps
the model was built on. So, how much is the metric that we use for BMI?
20 to 25 being perfect, 25 to 30 being overweight, 30 to whatever it is, 40 being
obese and then morbidly obese kicks in at some point, I'm sure.
Is that validated on other ethnicities as well?
Yes and no. So, with a few exceptions, the idea that there is a curve and that it's a generally
concave up curve, yes. Although again, there are exceptions. But the shape of that curve
is not the same in every age, race and sex group. It does seem that the right side, the part where
you're getting too high in BMI and risk is going up, seems to occur a lot earlier
among people of Middle Eastern and East Asian descent. And so, that's a very simple model.
You know, it's just sort of says, oh, it's all a curve for everybody. A slightly more complicated
model says, well, we know some of the other factors that come in, like how much of your fat
is subcutaneous versus how much is visceral. And it's just that that group has more visceral fat
than that group for any given body mass index and therefore adjust the curves. And there's probably
some truth to that. But it's probably even more than that. So, for example, a lot of these statements
we hear, and this goes back to way back when I said way at Vassar College, I loved the complexity
of it, that you had to look at it from some obesity from so many different angles. And that's still
true. The narratives we have about obesity, including about ethnicity and obesity, are grossly
oversimplified. So, we often hear obesity is selectively a disease of the poor and uneducated
that often in this country it's stated, minority status leads to less income,
less education, which in turn leads to poorer access to health care, poorer habits, poorer
living environments, which leads to poorer health and reduced longevity. And there's probably some
truth to that. But it's not one-to-one. It's not simple. So, for example, when we hear that there's
this inverse relationship between socioeconomic status and obesity, which we hear over and over
again, first shown by Mickey Stunkard, again, in the 1950s in the Midtown Manhattan Project,
that's true in white women. It's reliably true in adult white women. When you go outside the
group of adult white women, not always true. If you go to African-American women,
virtually no association between socioeconomic status and obesity. When you go to African-American
men and you look at their obesity levels, they're very similar to the obesity levels
of European-American men, white American men. But if you look at African-American women's obesity
levels and you compare it to European or white American women, much higher. If you bring
Hispanic Americans in, both men and women have higher levels of obesity than do European-American
men and women. So now you have an ethnicity difference, but not a gender by ethnicity
difference. Whereas in African-American, you have a gender by ethnicity difference.
When you look at mortality, the African-American curves follow similarly, but not identically,
to the European-American curves. But in our research, we can't find an association between
BMI and longevity in Hispanic Americans. Wow, just say that again. That's pretty
interesting. And that's across all BMIs? We've been unable to find it. Now, you know, the data
sets we have are not perfect. The follow-ups may not be long enough. The sample sizes may not be
big enough. You know, you can always question things. I don't say it's causal. I'm just saying
this is what we observed a few years ago when we got every data set that was publicly available
that we could get our hands on that involved Hispanic Americans and BMI and longevity. And
we analyzed them all together with common methods as carefully and thoroughly as we could. We could
not find an association between elevated BMI and mortality. As someone who sits on the opposite
end of the spectrum, right, where I don't at all concern myself with public health,
I don't, I'm not trying to make grand observations about what's happening in society across
ethnicities or anything like that. I really just have the luxury of looking at one person at a
time and trying to make a determination about the best course of action. You know, my view of BMI
is generally quite negative, right? It's that it's the, it's the maybe the least bad tool available
to get massive data sets and make broad assessments of what's happening at the population
level. But to your point earlier, at the individual level, it offers very little insight relative to
other tools. You know, when we have patients do DEXA scans, I tell them that, you know,
we're going to get four important pieces of information out of this. But one of them's
really the least important to me, which is your subcutaneous fat. That's the first thing people
want to look at when they have a DEXA scan. They want to see what's their percentage of body fat.
And they say, but there's three things that are much more important to us, right? One is your
visceral fat. One is your bone mineral density. And one is your appendicular lean mass index. So
how much muscle mass do you actually have? And we'll look at your subcutaneous fat. But the
reality of it is that doesn't really seem to matter because, A, that seems to be incredibly
genetic, right? Body habitus in that regard, very genetic, and relatively uncoupled for metabolic
health. So the vat, the visceral adipose tissue, seems to be much more tightly correlated to what
we see when we look at more sophisticated biomarkers of insulin sensitivity and metabolic health.
You know, any evidence of liver fat, all these other things tend to track much more closely with
that. So, I mean, I guess my view on this is that I'm glad that I get to look at these other metrics
because I don't have, I have the luxury that a statistician or an epidemiologist doesn't have,
right? Which is when you do things at the individual level, you have much more data
and you can be much more nuanced in your appreciation for things. But I can't help but
wonder if at the population level something better than BMI will come along one day,
for which there will be enough data to actually do what's out there. And again, this example
with the Hispanic subset, that's just, that's mind boggling to me. And it really speaks to,
I think, the futility of that measurement in other populations. That is one plausible interpretation.
And I don't think we're far away from these better tools. So, for example, we published some work
years ago on the idea of using 3D photography, where, you know, just take a picture of somebody
from a couple of angles. You know, this came out of work experience way back at the New York obesity
research center where Steve Himesfield, who was my mentor, would study professional basketball
players. They would bring the teams in from New York to him and he would, he was the king of body
composition, and he would study them. And in talking with some of the technicians there who
did this every day, who measured people's body composition every day, they would say, I can look
at a person and tell you how much fat they have and I'll be very accurate. They were good at it.
I said, well, if you can do it with your eye, why can't my camera do it? So, we got an NIH grant with
Olivia Fuzo and I and Steve Himesfield to look at this, published a paper on it. Since then,
many others have done it. And I think Amazon may be working on this or already have something out
on this. So, I think we'll get to the point where we have 3D photography, right? So, that's
Archimedes principle, right? Eureka, I found it, the crown goes under the water, he knows how much
gold is in it because he knows how much water it's displaced. So, if you can weigh it and you can
measure it, if you can measure something's weight and volume, you know it's density. If you know
about human anatomy, you can figure out from density, body fat. That's Archimedes principle.
That's what we can do with a camera. So, we have that. We have DEXA. We have plathysmography.
We have isotope dilution techniques. All of these can start to be used more on mass,
on and on. And so, I think these will be coming and we'll do better with that.
But I also think there's this idea of fit for purpose. You know, if you were to say to me,
you know, is your, is my vehicle that I drive, is this, you know, precision enough for the Indy 500?
No, I mean, they need better vehicles. But I'm not in the Indy 500. I'm just
driving five miles to and from work every day. It's fine. And so, I think it's fit for purpose.
If you say to me, tell me how many, what proportion of that country has obesity? BMI is probably
perfectly reasonable. If you say, I just want to know on average what's the approximate correlation
between obesity level and whether you play golf or not, it's probably okay. But if you want to say,
I want to help this individual patient, especially at the sort of, you know, the kind of
artisan level that you go at, then you need the better tools.
Well, the other thing that comes back to your friend, Ruben, is
you're still limited in the what to do, you know, the now what question, right? So, if you say,
well, we're going to take our tool of BMI extrapolation and we're going to look at
the state of Indiana and we can pretty accurately probably plot out the histogram of exactly what
the BMI is by age and by demographic and all those things. It's the so what question. Well,
what do we do with that information? What's the implication of this? Are people in Indiana more
or less healthy than people in Kentucky? And are they more or less healthy than the average American?
And more importantly, are they more or less average than the average, more or less healthy
than the average person on this planet? And what can we do to improve their health, even if we don't
want to compare them to anybody other than an absolute standard and say, could everybody become
healthier? Could we extend the life of the average person in the state of Indiana by three years?
What would the intervention need to be? And that obviously becomes a much more complicated problem,
but it's a more germane question, right? It's not a fanciful question. It's a question that we
literally are asking. And so this becomes tough because when I talk to people, even physicians,
even highly educated scholars, there's this bifurcation. There's the data and those look at
the data. And if they really know the data and they're really honest, they say, we agree. Surgery
works, pharmaceuticals work, individualized or group-based clinical treatment with behavioral
cognitive techniques work somewhat for some period of time. Meal replacement formulas work somewhat
for some period of time. But all the public health stuff we've tried now, you really are honest and
you really scrape away the obfuscated data. There's virtually no evidence thus far that any of those
community, school, public health things for obesity work. Doesn't mean that we won't get them
someday, but right now they don't. So when people come and say, well, what do we do about the state
of Indiana? And I get this question a lot. See, what's your goal? Is your goal to expose people
to ideas so that there's some really smart kid, right? The next Marie Curie, the next Einstein,
the next George Washington Carver is there in that classroom. And maybe the thing you do to
try to reduce obesity has no effect on obesity, but that kid is thinking about it for the next
15 years. And then when they become an adult, they go, I got an idea. And suddenly someone's
smarter than we are with new knowledge, cracks it. Is that your goal? Then it's consciousness
raising. Okay, fine. Is your goal to say to communities, we know you're suffering and we
know this is concerning and we want you to know we care and we're trying. We're not really going
to necessarily reduce obesity levels, but we want to know you care. We want you to know we care. And
you want farmer's markets in the school parking lot. You want vending machines changed. You want
running tracks built in your neighborhood. We'll build running tracks and so on. And we'll feel
better about we're caring for each other. Fair. But it's probably not going to affect obesity,
given what we know right now. Or do you say, I actually want to have less people suffering
with and from obesity. I want obesity levels in some definable, countable number of people to go
down and I want the health to improve. I'd say as you know, it's not going to win you any feel good
awards, but surgery, pharmaceuticals, and to some extent individualized treatment, or, you know,
cognitive behavioral group based treatment, including things like meal replacements and so on.
Those are ways to go. You could take if the state of Indiana handed me 10 million dollars and said,
make a difference. I would not go build farmer's markets in schoolyards. I would say
it'll only be a small number of people, but let's give bariatric surgery to a subset of people. And
those subset of people will likely live longer on average. What's the best explanation for why
weight loss is not particularly difficult, but weight loss maintained is incredibly difficult?
There's probably no single explanation. And I think that question of why
is a tough one. Do we mean evolutionarily why? That is what happened in evolution that got us
to be what we are today that leads to that. Or is it biochemically and otherwise why there's one
of the mechanisms involved? And I don't, from either point of view, I don't know all the answers.
From the evolutionary point of view for a long time, the meme was, it's the thrifty gene hypothesis
from James Neal, right? So the idea is that animals in general and including and especially humans
throughout evolutionary history were on the brink of starvation. So anything you could do
to preserve energy, you did. And anything you did that when given the opportunity to get more energy,
eat as much as you can while you can. And then you get into this modern environment where there's,
for practical purposes for most of us, unlimited consumable energy, you overconsume.
I think that's simplistic for many, many reasons. First of all, as the lawyers say,
objection that assumes facts not in evidence. That is, it's not at all clear that humans have
been on the brink of starvation throughout history. In fact, Robert Fogel, who won the Nobel Prize
for looking at these old data going back to at least the 1700s of British naval recruits and
other places, you see BMI sort of on average there going up over the centuries. But there's
a little fluctuation as things get better and worse in places. Second thing is,
how does this account for pregnancy? Now, maybe now the latest data from John Speakman and
colleagues in science with all the double-dibbed water about three months ago, maybe suggests that
during pregnancy, women's energy intakes don't need to go up that much, but they still go up.
And so if humans have been reproducing for millennia, where did all that extra energy
come from if we were on the brink of starvation all the time? And then the last thing I'll say is,
anybody who ever goes fishing knows that the idea that every animal is hungry all the time
and is going to grab every bite of food you throw in front of it has never been fishing.
But you can see that beautiful bass sitting in the clear water in front of you, and you can dangle
your worm or killie or whatever it is you've got, and sometimes the fish just looks at you.
So it's not at all clear that this is the case. Some animals do get obese when given unlimited
food, some don't, both within and across species. There's lots of differences. So that's that.
John Speakman came along and he said, I'm not sure I'm buying this whole idea. He said,
I think it's freedom from predation. Back in history, we were prey. Then there was a certain
point where we learned to use tools and hunt together, and we stopped being prey and we
started being predators. And when we switched from being prey to predators, then we didn't need to
hide in our burrows and eat the least we could because every time you came out of your burrow,
you were potentially exposed to a predator, we could sort of walk around and eat kind of ad lib.
And in that case, the genes that were being selected for that gave us satiety mechanisms
that kept our weight down no longer were being selected for. It wasn't that nature was selecting
for genes that made us fatter, it just wasn't selecting for genes that kept us thin. And then
what happens is called drift. Mutations happen and things just drift. So he calls it the
Drifty Hypothesis. And it's really less, it's less about the thinness. The thinness was really a
consequence of what the genes were probably selecting for, which presumably was lower
appetite or something like that, right? Probably. And I think these things, it's not one, there's
not one factor, right? We see this, for example, in the evolution of sexual reproduction, which is,
it's called the queen of questions in biology, right? Nobody can really figure out why do we
have sexual reproduction when asexual reproduction seems so much more efficient from a genetic
fitness point of view. And people have proposed different hypotheses for it, and no one seems to
work mathematically. And what it may be is that it's only by putting them all together that it
mathematically works. And it's just an inelegant solution. You see similar things in physics where
it may be, you know, these beautiful, simple mathematical things may not hold up. You may
just have to have ugly composite theories. Say a bit more about that. That's interesting. I've
never heard the argument for, I don't actually know much about asexual reproduction. I don't
spend much time thinking about plants or other life forms that do it. But what's the argument
for why we would be better off with asexual reproduction? Well, think about something like
Daphnia, which is a species that can produce both sexually and asexually. There are many species
like this all the way up through some vertebrates. And if an organism reproduces itself asexually,
just sort of makes a copy of itself, think about what it's done is it's reproduced all of its genes.
And so from the Dauchins, the Richard Dawkins point of view, the selfish gene,
those genes all got their way. Those genes all won. They got copied and genes that are good at
getting copied will get copied again in the future. So you have more of those. That's how
evolution works. Whereas if you reproduce sexually, you get another partner. Now, of course,
this assumes other, this invites other questions like, well, why are there only two sexes? And
why in fact have sexes at all? You could exchange DNA without having sexes, right? Bacteria do it
through conjugation. But we'll put that aside for the moment. Say there are two sexes, male and
female, they come together, they mix up their genetic material. The offspring has roughly 50%
of the genetic material of one parent and 50% of the other. And now you only copied yourself one
half. And so you didn't win as much as if you copied yourself entirely. So why would you ever
switch to sexual reproduction? It's very inefficient from a genetic fitness point of view.
Now you can hypothesize things. The most compelling hypothesis I've heard to me is the so-called Red
Queen hypothesis, which is from Alice in the Looking Glass where the Red Queen is running with Alice
and Alice at one point says, we don't seem to be getting anywhere. And the Red Queen says, oh,
in this world, you have to run as fast as you can just to stay in place. And Alice says, oh,
in my world, we run and we actually get somewhere. And so the Red Queen hypothesis is the idea that
you keep running as fast as you can just to stay steady. Well, what does that mean is, well,
as you're living a long time as a human, there are these microbes in you and they're
evolving much more rapidly because they have a much more shorter generation time.
And as they evolve, they start to get good at getting past your defenses and your locks.
They start developing keys to your locks. And you want to reset the locks. The way you reset the
locks is by getting a partner and mixing up your DNA with them. So the idea that it's a way of
keeping up with the Joneses where the Joneses are the bacteria, the microbes in your body.
That's that's super elegant, right? Because if you think about it, if it was all asexual,
we'd have a population of identical people. I mean, we would, for all intents and purposes,
it'd be interesting to do the math on what it would look like, but you might only have
a few hundred thousand gene pools as opposed to much less diversity, much less diversity.
So from a species point of view, if you believed in group selection, right, then you say, oh, right,
it's good for the species. But then the smart evolutionary biologists come along and say,
yeah, but that's group selection. It doesn't make sense. Selection occurs at the individual or gene
level. You've got to explain how it makes sense for that individual, how it enhances their fitness
or their genes' fitness. So you say, okay, well, if only half the genes get reproduced,
then it's got to be double the fitness level to break even. And that doesn't seem like it really
holds up. So what people have said is, you know what, if you take a handful of things,
which I can't explain them all right now, this is Mueller's ratchet and this, this, and that,
and you take all of these things and you put them together, then maybe the math works.
But it's very inelegant. It's not one nice little theory. And it's probably the same thing with
people and evolution. So there was Neil with the thrifty gene. That is, you need to be selected to
get food when you can. There's probably some truth to that. Maybe not everybody's dying of
starvation. But if you're not getting enough food, you may not be big enough to win the battle for
mates in a polygynous physical combat mating system. And so that may, that may select for
wanting to eat more. You may not be, think of the Frisch hypothesis, you get too thin as a woman,
you stop menstruating. So it may be that it's not that you die of starvation, but that your
reproductive fitness goes down. On the other hand, the predation, the freedom for predation idea that
John Speakman puts out is also legitimate. And there are yet others. Gary Beauchamp from
Monell Chemical Census Center has talked about the idea of the safety of food. Is it possible
that if you're back in time and you're not eating out of a refrigerator in a modern safe food supply
like we have, you know, we love to insult our food supply, probably the safest food supply in history.
Every time you eat something, you're exposing yourself potentially to microbes and toxins,
not just predators. And if you eat less, you're less exposure. So there's again, there's an
optimization problem. But as you now have a safer food supply, you can relax that constraint a little
bit. You can even think about it socially. If, if I were in a species where I'm just out on my own,
all right, if I'm, you know, species that just eat eucalyptus leaves or something, it doesn't depend
on anything else, then maybe I can eat the last eucalyptus leaf. But if I'm a species that very
much depends upon cooperative living, right, if I am so hungry all the time, that I'm willing to try
to kill you for the last bite of chicken, and you're willing to try to kill me for the last bite of
chicken, that's a bad situation, especially for me, because you're a little bigger than me and did
more martial arts, you know, so, so that's not good for fitness. It might be good to have satiety
mechanisms, just so we can preserve some social order. So after you and I eat a little chicken,
we can actually work together on building tools and engines and steam engines and airplanes and so
on. This is super fascinating. I could go down this path forever. I think we'll come back to this
next time we have dinner, because having this discussion over a meal would make it even more
because having this discussion over a meal would make it even better.
Let's march on to the topic of nutritional epidemiology. We've talked a little bit about
epidemiology. Obviously, epidemiology is married very closely with statistics. Without statistics,
you can't really do epidemiology. But it's a field that I think even the casual listener of this
podcast will understand has its limitations, if by no other means than they've heard me rail on it
many times. So I don't think we need to define it. I think people understand the nature of it.
But let's talk a little bit about your, your, your views of it, because I think you
I wouldn't say you're in either camp, right? There's a camp of people that would say
there is absolutely nothing wrong with epidemiology, nutritional epidemiology.
It is a masterful tool that provides exceptional insights without which we would be lost.
The other end of the spectrum, I'll acknowledge I'm a little closer to the other end of that
spectrum. There are people who say this is a tool that has probably reached its peak of utility.
And the epidemiologist should probably focus on other problems outside of nutrition now.
You're probably more in the middle of those, but I'd like to hear you talk a little bit about the
bookends and how, where you settle out and why more importantly. I appreciate the opportunity
to comment on this. It's a topic that I feel really does need more, more courageous addressing.
And I think that you have characterized it well. There are at one end the people I would call the
abolitionists. You're, I agree you're close. Our mutual friend Gary Taubes has said,
at some point we need to recognize that nutrition epidemiology is a dead science.
I'm sorry, that was John Ioannidis, another mutual friend who said,
nutrition epidemiology is a dead science and it's time to bury the corpse. Gary Taubes has been very
critical, mean of tea cults. You, many others have pointed out that perhaps this is just a worthless
waste of time and misleading. At the other end, there are a number of people.
They, they tend to be concentrated in Boston it seems. There's a little school out east there.
I forget the name of it. It's in Cambridge is it? Yeah. Okay. Anyway. Yeah. I think I've heard of it.
Yeah. I think I've heard of it. And there are other places that believe this, but it's probably
strongest in Boston that sort of seemed to be the defenders of the status quo. Let's say,
nutrition epidemiology is imperfect as all tools are, but it is still a very valuable tool. There's
nothing seriously wrong with it. Those who criticize it are naive. And I look at this,
I'm naive and ignorant. And I look at a quotation like that and I think, really you're telling me
that Gary Taubes and Johnny Annietes are naive and ignorant. If you want to tell me you don't
agree with them, that's fine. Naive and ignorant come now. Not really. So we know that there's
something wrong there. When we look at the evidence, it's very clear that many findings
from nutrition epidemiology have not held up once we've done randomized controlled trials.
Now some people will say, no, you're wrong. And I've had arguments with people from Boston about
this. And they said, you're wrong. If you look at these meta-analyses, it looks like non-randomized
studies on average give very similar findings to randomized studies. But often they're citing
non-randomized intervention studies, not non-randomized observational studies. And they're
often not citing nutrition studies. They're citing pharmaceutical or other medical treatment. So those
are very different situations. When you look at the nutrition epi, it's not clear to me that these
things hold up very well when they are studied. In fact, it seems to be more the norm that they
don't. If you look at other things going on, as John Annietes probably better than anybody else
has done, but many of us have done, and you start to peel the hood open on these. And you really
look, you see a lot of things that look like obfuscation, exaggeration, sweeping under the
rug of measurement error, and so on. So we've got huge issues with confounding. We've got huge
measurement problems. And so I think many people, including me, say, no, the status quo is not OK.
It's not just minor fine tuning. We need reformation. But we also need to use these
tools well. This field is not going to go away whether you want it to or not. So my feeling is
reformation is essential. The status quo is completely unacceptable. But abolition is neither
realistic nor desirable. And I want to cite one paper we did, which I think makes an interesting
point. This paper, you know, I often end reading the observational epidemiology nutrition study
in which the author correctly and honestly points out that it's an observational study,
as association, not necessarily showing causation, and then says, but how could I be wrong? Well,
it could be that this measurement error creates this problem. They say, but I used a validated
food frequency questionnaire, so it's really OK. Could be confounding due to socioeconomic status.
But all of my subjects had the same profession, so it's really OK, as though the nurse
who works in a poor school in rural Indiana has the same socioeconomic status as the nurse
who is the married to a billionaire. Of course not. They say we control for we only have to
never smokers and so on and so on. So really, it was OK. They dismiss the idea that it's not really
causation. And I got this idea once and I said, you know, what they're saying is if I measured
everything well and I controlled for food intake and I controlled for diet composition and housing
and socioeconomic status and genetic background, then it would be OK. So I said, you know, you
could never do this study in humans, but I realized I've done this in mice. And we had a mouse study
where we randomly assigned mice to eat different amounts of calories or food energy, but all on the
same diet. So composition was fixed. The mice had no choice. There were no restaurants. There was no
grub hub. There was no door dash. We gave the mice the same food. They all ate the same thing.
No self-report. They're all genetically identical in probability because they're,
you know, inbred isogenic strain, all C57 black 6J mice. They're all in the same housing conditions.
There's no smoking, et cetera. And then we take these mice and we randomly assign them to low
calorie, medium calorie, high calorie effectively or ad lib, ad libetum. And what we find is the
more calories we assign them to be allowed to eat, the shorter they live. No big surprise there. This
has been shown a thousand times in the literature by Ray Walford and, you know, Rick Weindrick and
others over the decades. But then we take the ad libetum group. And within that, some choose to
eat more than others. And within that group, now we have an observational epidemiologic study
and we correlate amount chosen to be eaten with longevity. And those mice that choose to eat more
live longer. So the association in the observational component is exactly opposite
to the causal effect in the experimental component. And what people say to me is,
well, David, it's confounding. What you're seeing, probably almost certainly, is that the mice that
are the strongest and healthiest have the biggest appetites. They eat more. And what you're seeing
is confounding by general health, to which I say, right. That's the point. The point is even in a
study, an observational study that is more pristine than anybody will ever be able to do a human study,
which there's no smoking, no restaurants. Everybody eats the same thing. There's no measurement error.
You know, it's, they're all genetically identical in probability. We can't get the observational
study to reproduce the causal effect. And that suggests to me why reform is so needed. And we
talk about different kinds of observational studies. What I would love to never hear again
is the puerile analogy of there's no randomized controlled trials with parachute jumping.
You know what I'm talking about. That comes up every now and then. And there's a wonderful book
called Randomistas, like Fashionistas, Randomistas by Andrew Ley. And he says, actually, there are
randomized controlled trials of parachute jumping. So first of all, it's just not true.
But beyond the fact that the IRB approved that, you got to be in the army, I think.
Yeah. So, you know, the interesting thing there is that this is used often as an excuse to say,
okay, I can't do the pure, perfect, pristine, randomized controlled trial. So therefore,
you have to accept any old observational study. And I think the answer is no, no, we don't.
We may have to accept that we're going to draw some inferences from something other than the pure,
classic, pristine, randomized controlled trial. But in between that and any old
observational epidemiologic study, there's a lot of space. And what we're saying is we need to get
to this space here. So co-twin controls, right? You hinted at that earlier. How about we take your
identical twin? We randomly assign you to one and the twin to the other. Or if we can't randomly
assign, say, oh, Peter, you exercise a lot. Your twin brother doesn't exercise. But you have the
same genotype. Okay. That's a tight control. Or how about things in which we intervene,
even if it's not randomly intervened, as opposed to just observe. So we say, okay, in this town,
we're going to build a restaurant. In that town, we're not going to build the restaurant.
It's still an intervention study, even if it's not a randomized study. That's the realm of Brian L.
Bell, for example, looks at food deserts and things. He says, gee, you know, we built a grocery
store where there's a food desert. We're told that food desert's a problem and doesn't look
like things got better when we built the grocery store. That's a much stronger design than just
asking people how far away do you live from a grocery store. Yeah, no, look, I think that's very
eloquent. And that mouse study is remarkable, by the way. I remember when that came out. That
needs to be a Sunday email to my group. So let's remember that. I would highlight two things that
well, one thing that you've already alluded to and one that you haven't, but I would just
add it to my side of the ledger on why I struggle so much with the legitimacy of epidemiology.
Anything that relies on a food frequency questionnaire, I simply can't take seriously
for the fact that at least with every patient I've ever come in contact with to try to accurately
assess what they eat based on a food frequency questionnaire would be a fool's errand. It's
simply unrelated to what they eat. Full stop. The second issue I have with nutritional epidemiology
comes down to the hazard ratios that very commonly show up and lead to grand statements.
When you see hazard ratios like 1.16 and we talk about this like we have demonstrated the causal
relationship between bacon and cancer. I mean, what would the actual fathers of epidemiology
be saying in their graves if they were looking at these strength of association? And so
I'm not necessarily saying there should be no epidemiology, but boy, there needs to be a
referendum on how the media is taught how to interact with such studies on
how we scrutinize some of the methodologies behind these things. Because again, checking
a food frequency questionnaire once in an eight year study, it just doesn't mean anything. It
really means less than nothing actually. And yet it's amazing that that could be the basis
of an observation. So anyway, it's hard for me to say something good about epidemiology.
Well, on the measurement issue, which is often I think incorrectly perceived by some people as
the key issue and say, well, yeah, we admit the measurement of food intake is a big problem.
But other than that, everything's fine. And no, even when the measurement is near perfect,
as in my mouse study, it's still not fine. You don't have to go back to the fathers of
epidemiology or wait for the fathers of epidemiology. You can go back to at least Confucius,
who says to know what you know, and to know what you do not know, that is true knowledge.
And so this idea that we have to be honest with ourselves and each other
about what we know and don't know and how we know it and don't know it is clear. And I think that's
part of that reform. We need a greater level of honesty. Simeen Vizier just had a paper in
one of the peer-reviewed journals looking at or writing about epistemic humility and saying,
you know, when you get to the discussion section of a paper and you consider that
the hypothesis that you made, which now seems to be supported by your data, and you say,
but I might be wrong. And then you just systematically go through with the greatest
effort and art to show how you're not wrong, how you can dismiss all the competing explanations.
You say, that's not an honest epistemic humility. An honest epistemic humility, what do you say?
I really might be wrong. And here's all the ways I might be wrong that I and others should test
going forward. Michael Stravins in his book, The Knowledge Machine, does a beautiful
composition, decomposition, construction, deconstruction of this and talks about
the idea of communities doing this. And so that we need that sort of constructive battle,
but it needs to be an honest battle, right? We can't engage. The battle shouldn't be at hominem.
The battle shouldn't be undercutting each other by, you know, who you are and who you work for and
what your beliefs are. It needs to be a battle about the data. It calls out the iron rule of
evidence. And so if I say, Peter, your theory that X causes Y could be mistaken because your
measurement of X is not valid, you need to come back and say, I hear you. What if I measure X this
way? That's a legitimate thing. Let's do it and see if we can rule it out. And then we can go back
and forth and say, well, maybe the measurement of Y is not right. I think we need to be more honest
about that. I don't think the nutrition epidemiology field has been quite honest about the limits of
its measurement, but so have the attackers not. I've been careful about saying, I think measurements
of energy intake and expenditure from self-report methods are so bad that they shouldn't even be
used. That is, it's not enough to say, well, it's not perfect. It's so bad you can't even be
guaranteed to get the directional effect. So don't even use it. Better to not do the study at all.
But on the other hand, if you said to me, I want to know if people eat vegetarian or not,
or eat kosher or not, or eat after midnight or not. I don't know. Maybe people do report those
accurately. Maybe they don't. I also don't know. I think we have to ask for what purpose.
You mentioned very briefly, Katherine Flagle earlier. She also wrote a very famous paper about
the obesity wars. Give folks a bit of an idea about that. I thought very excellent paper.
Yeah. Katherine Flagle has been a colleague from whom I've had great respect for many,
many years. And she's very, very bright and very capable and very careful. And I've learned a lot
from her, actually. And she published a paper in, I think it was 2005, that really got people's
attention. And it was interesting in the way. It was a meta-analysis and combined pooling analysis.
Showed a few things. What was interesting to me is what people harped on, particularly the media,
was that BMIs in the overweight range were actually not strongly associated and consistently
associated with increased mortality rate. In some cases, were associated with lower mortality rate.
The media went crazy with this, as though it were new finding. Just as every few years, they're
right, the new finding that BMI is mass and not fat. The new finding that there's a genetic
component to obesity that we knew from decades ago. The media went crazy with this. The people
that are the defenders of, you can never be too rich or too thin, went crazy and attacked her.
And the bizarreness of it wasn't new. I mean, it was a meta-analysis. How could it have been new?
We all knew these data. You can go back to Linus Pauling, the double Nobel Laureate,
has a paper in the 1950s on BMI and life expectancy. And he's got a bathtub-shaped curve
there. So this is not new at all. But somehow, it was seen as new. It was in JAMA. The newspapers
went crazy. The people who were defending it went crazy. And they started attacking her
very vociferously. One investigator called it a worthless pile of rubbish. And to me,
these are very inappropriate statements. Who were the most vocal critics?
Some people in Boston seem to be among the most vocal critics. So that was kind of a very
interesting thing. But as I said, it was all on old news. Anybody been reading the literature
for decades was it? But I already knew this. What was actually new, and to me far more intriguing,
but got much less attention, was that the nadir was moving over time. That was we talked about
earlier, that in 1990, it wasn't the same as 1970. That is, to me, very intriguing. We actually had
have an active NIH grant built on that, trying to figure out what's going on with it. But anyway,
they attacked her. And these statements, you know, that it was rubbish and that she didn't know what
she was talking about, that there was nobody with a medical background. And these are all ad hominem
things. First of all, it's not clear there was no one with a medical background on the paper.
And even if it was clear, who cares? You know, the data are the data, whether you have an MD or
you don't have an MD. It's the data that matter. When I frequently say in science, three things
matter. The data, the methods used to collect the data, which give them their probative value,
and the logic, which connects the data and the methods to conclusions.
Everything else is not science. Now, if you want to look at other things as ways of helping you
make a pragmatic decision, that's fine. Right? So if I say, oh, I trust Peter, and he's a smart guy,
and I know he studies a lot, and he tells me I should eat this, that's maybe a very pragmatic
way of making a decision. But it's not science. Right? The science is the data, the methods,
and the logic connecting the data to conclusions, not whether I trust you or not.
And so all these ad hominem things were said, they attacked her. It was very, very vociferous,
very inappropriate. But there are many other people who have been attacked. I've been attacked. I know
lots of other people have been attacked for their beliefs. When Nina T. Cults had an editorial,
I think in Lancet, talking about some elements of nutrition and fat and carbohydrate, many people
wrote in, tried to get it retracted. This is a sort of regular occurrence now, when Brad Johnson
published on red meat roughly two years ago, big meta analysis showing that the association
between red meat consumption and negative health outcomes was not strong and compelling, as,
you know, in his words, again, rig vigorously attacked. People tried to get it retracted before
it was published, which thankfully didn't work, instead of just engaging with the data, the methods,
and the logic. And it's terrible. This happens. It doesn't only happen in obesity and nutrition,
but it happens a lot in obesity and nutrition. Yeah, but that's what I was going to say.
It does seem to happen disproportionately in this field. Why is that? I think it has to do with the
everyday experience. Right? So back to my example from early in our discussion about the beta cell
of the pancreas, right? If you are at a cocktail party in your neighborhood and you say to somebody,
well, I study diabetes. And here's what I think about the beta cell of the pancreas and how this
might work. Unless that person also studies it, they're not going to challenge you. They probably
don't know what the beta cell of the pancreas is. They don't have strong feelings about it. They
don't see it every day, so on. All of us eat every day. Well, almost all of us eat almost every day.
Food is culture. It's family. It's love. It's economy. It's commerce. It's political beliefs.
It's philosophical beliefs. It's ethical beliefs about whether you're a vegetarian or not. It's
the sustainability of the environment. It's so connected to so many emotional things. And we all
have that everyday experience. And we have to make decisions every day. Each of us decides what
to eat, what to feed our kids, right? Whether we wear our seatbelt or not, all these things.
We make these decisions and then we may want to justify them. We may need to believe they're good.
We may mistake our experience for expertise. And that's why I think when you get into any fields
where people have everyday experience, whether it's human sexuality, whether it's relationships,
whether it's child rearing, TV watching, book reading, music, eating, these are things people
have very strong feelings about and often will opine about, often quite aggressively,
in the absence of data. It is not only obesity. Statements about violence in media, statements
about how to best teach mathematics to children. People have very strong feelings that are often
quite in contrast to what the data show. So is there a path forward here? Because it doesn't feel
like there's, from a nutritional standpoint, I mean, I think you've already touched on a few of
them, but we've already seen some pretty exciting pharmacologic things come along. I think
semaglutide, the study that we've talked about before on this podcast, really kind of a remarkable
drug. It's certainly the most impressive thing that I've seen clinically for obesity. So the point
being, we're making great progress there. We talk about surgical treatments. 25 years ago, when I was
in medical school, I remember the first gastric bypass I ever saw done as a medical student,
watching, you know, surgical rotation. And this was an open, this was done before they were doing
them laparoscopically. It was done as an open, Roux-en-Y gastric bypass on a 400 pound man
who would die 40 days later in the hospital of sepsis. He never got out of the hospital. He had
an astromotic leak. That was a very dangerous operation. 25 years ago today, that operation
is done almost with that exception laparoscopically. It is an incredibly safe procedure and it has also
remarkable efficacy. So on this surgical front, on this pharmacologic front, we have made amazing
progress. We haven't made progress on the nutritional front. Are we going to? Not clear. You know,
New York Times reporter called me a few years ago and this was in response. There was an article
about president, I think it was president Taft, who was very obese and somebody had found some
letters between him and his physician talking about diet. And it was almost, you could pick
those letters up and said this was between a president and his or her physician today
and they would make equal sense. And the reporter said to me, this is a very bright
science nutrition journalist, said to me, David, why have we made so little progress?
Why have we not been able to find the diet that reliably causes sustained weight loss? And I said,
your question is premised on the idea that there is a diet that reliably causes sustained weight
loss. Why should we believe that that's true? So that's an important thing to think about.
I think one of the things that is perhaps a misperception and maybe a very problematic one
in our field around nutrition and weight loss or food intake and weight loss is that there is a
good diet with respect to weight loss, particularly such that for most, if not all people, if you just
ate the right way, you wouldn't have to count your calories. You wouldn't have to be uncomfortable
and hungry. You wouldn't have to feel deprived and yet you would maintain a good healthy weight.
I know of no reason to believe that's true. I know lots of people who argue, is it diet A or diet B?
Right. So this one thinks it's low carb and this one thinks it's high carb or low fat and this one
thinks it's don't eat at night and this one thinks it's, you know, whatever it is, eat paleo, you know,
etc. I'm just, maybe the null hypothesis is, you know, doesn't matter that much.
There isn't such a diet for many people. Now for some people, they do maintain a normal healthy
desirable weight without trying to restrict their energy. But maybe for others it's just not the
case. I think the paths forward are manifold and I think in some cases we are on the good path
and in some cases we are wandering in the drunkard's walk. We're on the good path, I think, on surgery
and pharmaceuticals. Clearly a long way to go but they've gotten much better. I'd love to see more
funding for those for good research and I think we need to, we are on a good path but I think we
need to get on a much better path about as a society making those available to people.
Right. If you have cancer we're willing to treat you. If you have obesity,
maybe not. Right. So if you're rich you can pay for that. If you're not rich, what do you do?
So I'd love to see more access to care and I think we're on a better path but we need to be on a
better path still. I think we're on a good path on stigma. A long way to go but I think as a society
we've woken up to say stigmatizing obese people is not okay. Do you think the pendulum's gone too
far? I read something, this might have been a joke, but I literally read that Adele was actually
shamed for losing weight. I don't know if that's true but if it was it would certainly suggest
that the pendulum has gone a little too far the other direction. I would certainly say that that's
ridiculous. I don't know if she was or wasn't but if she was that's ridiculous. To me the take-home
message is shaming people about their body habitus is not good in either direction. It's not a
directional thing. It's just shaming people about their body habitus is not okay. And you know
sometimes the counter argument is but it's good for them because it'll help them want to lose weight
and sometimes the argument made against the shaming is empirical. Well the evidence shows
that people who experience a lot of weight shaming gain more weight and then the causal
thing is thrown in and then people say therefore you shouldn't do it. Like you mean if shaming
didn't cause weight gain it would be okay to be immoral and cruel to others? No. I mean if you
replace things like sex and race in that sentence you're like no it's not okay to shame and denigrate
people because of their sex, race, age, body habitus regardless of whether it causes weight loss or
weight gain. Period. It's a moral issue. It's not an empirical issue and I think that's we have a long
way to go but I think we're making progress in people. Yeah I guess we can generalize this idea
that you shouldn't denigrate people because of age, race, sex. Maybe you shouldn't denigrate them for
other characteristics that are not you know moral failings. I think that on the basic science
we're making progress. We could make better progress if we tightened up the rigor of our
science. We could make better progress if we had more funding and many groups including the National
Academy of Sciences and I'm on a strategic council to increase the rigor of science, all of science
not just obesity nutrition but we're making progress. We know so much more about genes and
physiology and metabolism and cells with respect to obesity and nutrition than we knew 20, 30, 40
years ago. The one area where as far as I can tell we are not making progress and I don't think we
are yet on a good path. I don't think we're on a path at all is the sort of public health community
school-based, community-based, policy-based approach. I think we are continuing to look
for our keys under the lampposts because that's where the light is as opposed to where the keys
might be. I think we are continuing to ignore the data and keep saying the same old hackneyed
suggestions that people have been trying for decades and that when you really look at the data
have been at best not been shown to work and at worst been shown to not work.
And I think there are some people who are patently obfuscating those data. I think the cluster
randomized trials we see in the childhood obesity literature you know bring to mind the phrase that
rhymes with cluster muck and it just this is cluster muck, this is distorted evidence, this is
science gone wrong in the worst sense. I think we've got to clean that up. We've got to clean up
the quality of the science we do and start treating this like science just as much as the science
of quarks or tires on automobiles or beta cells of pancreases and treat it like real science and take
it just as seriously. Can you tell folks briefly what the cluster randomization problem is? Sure.
So a cluster randomized trial is a trial which instead of randomizing the individual unit of
observation might be let's say a child in a school who you either assign to the treatment group,
maybe it's exercise or the control group, no special exercise. You assign the entire an entire
intact unit such as a classroom or a school or a neighborhood or a family. There's nothing wrong
with that as long as you have theoretically at least two clusters assigned to each condition.
So you have some ability to estimate a variance although frankly with only two you have so little
power and robustness for practical purposes that would be invalid but theoretically it's valid.
But then you must analyze the data to take into account both what's called the clustering and the
nesting. The clustering is that you have people grouped and that grouping leads to more similar
individuals. So imagine that we did a trial and the trial was you and your brother randomly assigned
to eat low carb and me and my brother randomly assigned to eat high carb and at the end we see
a difference by an ordinary tea test and you say well hold on a second was that really the effective
diet or was that the Attia brothers are different than the Allison brothers? Well you have to take
that into account so that's you need more than one cluster right so if you get the Attia brothers
and the Jones brothers and the Allison brothers and the Smith brothers now in theory you can do it
but now you can't treat us like we're eight different people right what you really have
is four different clusters four different SIB ships four different sets of brothers you've got
to take that into account you have less degrees of freedom people don't do that reliably they don't
do it correctly often and that leads to many papers being wrong we've written countless letters to
editors about this I think we've probably had at least three or four cluster randomized trials
retracted as a result of letters we've written where people have had to come back and just say
the results don't hold up but until until this has changed we have people out there who understandably
say but I read these papers suggesting that this works gardening in schools makes kids thinner
like no that's not what the results showed but that's what the paper says and until we
become more rigorous and more honest we're not on a path so if I were to ask you now to speculate
outside of known things if you had to guess and if you presuppose that there is an intervention
or a set of interventions that could improve public health outcomes what would your guesses be
what would your guesses be what would you guess to test general education not nutrition education
general education there is provocative data I don't want to say definitive data there are
provocative data strongly suggesting that general education especially for girls and women
leads to lower bmis lesser rates of obesity and lesser diabetes than less education
so there are some studies in europe of policies where someone puts in a policy and it effectively
gives a cohort of people more education and then you see in that cohort less obesity especially
among women there's a famous study by the ramies who were a husband wife investigative team who
actually worked at uab when I first got there and they started this study decades ago at unc
and it was sort of head start on steroids it was they called it the abc adarian or a baccadarian
study and they gave these kids the super head start program and it was mostly just general
education there may have been a little nutrition education but mostly just general education
wasn't a weight loss study wasn't intended to be 30 years later they followed them up there's a
paper in science on this guess what the women have less obesity the moving to opportunity study
funded by the department of housing and urban development took families who lived in so-called
poor neighborhoods and they gave them either randomly assigned them either to control
but it basically got nothing or to housing vouchers but the housing vouchers required that
they move to less poor neighborhoods and what they then found years later in follow-up again
published in science and doing the journal of medicine is that there was less obesity and
diabetes in those assigned to move to the less poor neighborhoods and given the financial
wherewithal to do so so i could go on but these are things that suggest to me that education
general education may help and i think that may speak to this whole socioeconomic thing we started
that way earlier what is it about higher socioeconomic status that at least in some
groups at all but at least in white women seems to be associated with less obesity and i don't know
what the causal mechanisms are but that might be my best so somebody said to me you're going to be
the king for a year and you've got the federal budget and you can take this big chunk of money
and you can make an impact in obesity and diabetes i would say i'm going to divide it into four pots
one pot is going to be surgery and it's going to be both providing it and continue to study it
the next one's going to be pharmaceuticals both providing it continuing to study it
third pot is going to be some general education maybe general well-being safety security
starting in early childhood to see whether that alone is enough and it may be really reducing
disparities back to confucius confucius said we are not so concerned with an absence of wealth
we are concerned with a disparity of wealth and so it may be that reducing disparities is really
important and then the fourth pot would be basic research and i'd like to say let's look at
senolytics and let's look at microchimerism and all the things that you talk about so often in
your podcast that that a butt against both metabolism and obesity and nutrition but also
the fundamental uh fundamental senescence so i'd love to say can we use microchimerism to restore
people to younger metabolic states can we use senolytics to do that that would be my fourth
bucket those basic science questions now a moment ago you you touched briefly on um
the national academy of science engineering and medicine you were on a panel that
looked at the question of reproducibility in science correct this was two years ago i think
now the consensus i believe was that there was not a crisis but but we shouldn't
we shouldn't let our guards down am i sort of paraphrasing that correctly close uh the phrase
that that uh harvey feinberg who is the chair of it i don't know if it's his phrase but you know
he started using and and we followed is no crisis but no cause for complacency and the idea of no
cause for complacency or no complacency is we must make things better the no crisis is a tricky one
is a tricky one expense what you mean by crisis and some people say if you look at dictionary
definitions of crisis the idea is that's a system about to collapse so you know you need to go to the
icu if you don't get intervention you're going to die you're in crisis there's no evidence that
science is in crisis there's no evidence that science is about to die or it doesn't work anymore
not at all another way is to say things are getting much much worse rapidly there's also
no clear evidence for that there might be some things that are getting worse but on average
there's a lot of evidence that things are getting better my own belief is science is better and more
rigorous than it's ever been in history um and so in that sense no i still don't think there's a
crisis but there's a third way which is i think the spark for many social movements if you think
about what often happens is a social movement is you have a group of people that for example are
often often it's around oppression and they're oppressed and they're sufficiently oppressed that
people are unwilling to make too much noise and the status quo is only very slowly and grudging
and then at some point people feel a little bit more confident and a little less oppressed
and they start to speak and people say this state of affairs is not acceptable anymore
and if you were to say in that later point in time but it's much better than it was
in the earlier time someone might say it may be much better but we ain't taking it anymore
right things may be much better than they used to be things in 2021 are probably much better for
many situations than they were in 1921 and much better than than they were in 1821
but there comes a point we say you know this lead in gasoline or this lead paint lead in our paint
or this way in which we use heating or these kinds of lack of catalytic converters on cars
or this way in which we burn up fossil fuel or this way in which we treat different age-raised
sex groups it's just not okay anymore yes it may be better than it was years ago the world has
spoken we won't take it anymore i think that's where we are scienceing yes science is probably
better than it's ever been but we also see all the flaws and it must get better and that's why
marshall mcmutt the president of the national academy of sciences instantiated this new strategic
council on trust and integrity and rigor in science and very generously appointed me as one
of the three co-chairs marcia france cordova who's the director emeritus of the national science
foundation and i have three co-chairs and are working on trying to see what you know we as the
academies can do to try to help a little bit and many other organizations are also trying to help
on this how much of the crisis in science uh well i guess we're just decided we're not going to use
the word crisis how much of the situation in science is intrinsic is within science itself
and how much of it is a result of the public inclusive of the media's interface with science
i think it's both i think science is hard uh michael strevin's book which i mentioned earlier
the knowledge machine does a wonderful treatise on that and i think we have to recognize that and
but i think we have to make the distinction between normative errors and non-normative errors
and let's take an example of each so a few hundred years ago gallileo is under house arrest
the pope has said you know bad writing about capernicus stay locked up in your house but we
will kill you and from his house gallileo directs an experiment or not really an experiment a study
and he has um two colleagues go out to two tops of mounds or hills or mountains far apart
each holding a lantern with shutters and a synchronized watch or timepiece and he says
to them at a predetermined moment you guys open your shutters and you record when you see the
other guy's light and we'll figure out whether light travels instantaneously or not right is
there some delay until the light gets to you and they conclude that it's instantaneous they can't
discern any time now we know today of course that that's wrong ole roma probably is the first
person who convincingly shows it's wrong when he shows that a moon comes around at a time different
than his mentor domini cosini predicted but at the time that's the answer they get with their
instrumentation they couldn't have done better i would call that a norman vera i would not mock
gallileo i don't think gallileo did anything wrong i think we look at him as brilliant my god great
question great worry of working on it but things move along similarly when lion is pauling says
dna is a triple helix right before watson and crit come out to double helix um he didn't have
good x-ray crystallography date he's working at the edge normative error then there are other
things very famous non-normative error is people working out the size of the thymus gland of
children it worked it out from cadavers in the early 20th century guess what people don't become
cadavers at random poor people tend to become cadavers poor children tend to be undernourished
undernourished children tend to have smaller thymus glands so when physicians started seeing
children richer children coming in dying of sudden infant death syndrome and they examined
them they go it's a big thymus gland well it was actually a normal thymus gland because their
norms were from undernourished kids so let's irradiate these kids with big thymus glands
and prevent sudden infant death syndrome and probably cause lots of cases of thyroid cancer
because the thyroid and the thymus are very close to each other so that's an example of a non-normative
error because even a hundred years ago any epidemiologist or statistician could have told you
that is bad sampling and bad inference from bad sampling we need to make that distinction between
normative and non-normative errors and a lot of the errors that we have in nutrition epidemiology
today i don't think can be called normative errors anymore i think we have to say that was
non-normative the misanalysis of the cluster randomized trials these are not normative any
statistician knows how to do it people are either obfuscating or they're just woefully
ignorant and not using professional statisticians when they need to people using food frequency
questionnaires to draw causal inferences about some of these things we were discussed these are
not normative errors people should know better then there's the stuff about this sort of more
general public about believing things and how we how we promote our ideas and here's where i think
i think our root is us in the scientific community that have to take responsibility for it but it
branches out beyond us i think we need to be prepared to lose some battles in order to win
the intellectual war and what i mean by that is we need to be prepared to not use all the
rhetorical tools at our disposal at any one point in time to convince somebody that x is true even
when we're really worked up and think it's important we believe x is true we think it's
important that others believe x is true right because we want them to eat what we think is good
we want them to eat more broccoli and less ice cream we want them to take their vaccine wear their
mask wear their seat belt stop smoking we may be right about all those things right maybe people
should eat more broccoli and less ice cream and wear their seat belt get vaccinated and wear their
mask and seat belt but if we use rhetorical devices such as if you and i are debating
and i attack you on that hominin grounds or i exaggerate the strength of my evidence
or i don't honestly say that i've shown an association and not causation then in fact i
may win that battle that day on convincing people to eat broccoli instead of ice cream
but i've lost the battle in helping people think through what good evidence is
and elevating our level of dialogue and i think if we can get to the point where just as today we
changed our dialogue we think about the things people would say think about what a late night
comedian would have said 30 years ago in making jokes about wives and husbands and race and sex
that would never be considered acceptable today we are able to change societal norms about dialogue
can we elevate our societal norms of dialogue on epistemologic and empirical issues so that we can
get people to you don't have to be a genius to say oh you're telling me you have a treatment for x
was there a study was the study in humans was it a randomized study was it a study of the actual
outcome you're making a claim about was it a study that was long enough for this to be a meaningful
outcome was there a statistically significant result was the result big enough to matter was
the dose a dose i might realistically take those are not all that difficult questions to train
ourselves and each other to just reliably ask and if we just reliably ask those and reliably and
honestly answer them you would go a long way yeah it's interesting i mean it's impossible to
have this discussion without thinking about covet because covet has been such a polarizing
scientific phenomenon in a way that i've i've become quite frustrated in watching it right
i've and i'm trying to maintain a distance from it and ask myself the question is the reason that
the head of the cdc makes assertions about masks or vaccines or mandates because she doesn't think
that the people to whom she's speaking are intelligent enough to appreciate nuance
or is it because she doesn't actually appreciate the nuance herself you know and this gets to
exactly the point you made a moment ago which is the high ground is being lost right i think the
public's faith in science in the institution of science is eroding dramatically and i think covet
has accelerated that in a way that i wouldn't have predicted i remember having a discussion
with a friend in march of 2020 and i very very naively said to him i think that what we're about
to see with respect to the speed with which medications and vaccines are going to be developed
is going to elevate the consciousness of science in the public's eye i think the public is going to
look back in a year and say wow science is great you know just as in the 1960s the best and the
brightest kids went into engineering because they were inspired by the space race i stupidly thought
this might be the end of every smart kid becoming an investment banker and instead we might just see
more kids enrolling in science how silly of me to not envision what was coming which was
a world in which well-meaning public health officials simply failed to communicate the
nuance of science and lost so much credibility yeah covet has been unique and and i think you
know one of the things i was saying to to my wife recently is i hope i live at least another 20 years
for many reasons but one of the reasons is that i really want to see what the historians say
about the period of roughly 2016 to a year or two from now when hopefully
we are somewhat out of this pandemic
i can see it in the present i want to see it in the 2020 hindsight let me let me say two things
about your points one is about motivations and the other is about trust the motivations issue i think
is an interesting one you know i was having a conversation with a colleague many years ago
and i was ranting about university accountants and how they're there you know they drive me crazy
with little things and this friend of mine said to me he says think about you and your science he
says you're so fastidious about it you're so passionate about it you're so committed to it
one iota of bending the truth is not okay for you he says the accountant feels that way about
the way the accounting is done and that's their domain different people have their different
domains and if i were to say to you you know peter what are you professionally or you might say any
or what are you just more generally you might say you might say i'm a father you might say i'm a
physician i i'm a healer you might say i'm a scientist you might say a few other things
when i came to iu i was at a big retreat and friend of mine was there and we started going
around and introducing ourselves and i was sort of a new kid on the block and i said you know my
name is david alson and i'm a scientist and i study blah blah blah and he said you know the first
thing you said you're like you're the new dean here and the first thing you said is i'm a scientist
you didn't say i'm the dean of the school of public health he says that shows how you think of yourself
if i were to say if you were to say to me in your professional role what's the one thing
you must never compromise truth what's my one sacred duty pursue and communicate truth to the
best of my ability but if you said to some other people in my field who are equally good people
maybe better people who knows and you said to them what's your one uncompromising duty
some of them would say help people make their health better or enact justice
can't say they're wrong that's their value and i think that's what comes out a lot in public
health there are true believers who think they know the right answer they think eating this is
better than eating that in many cases they're probably right they think not smoking is better
than smoking i agree i think they're right and given those premises they say whatever it takes
to convince people to eat a and not b to wear their seatbelt to not smoke i'm willing to say it
that's my sacred duty is making better i think that's part of the problem what's our identity
who's speaking and i think we need to be clear when we are speaking as scientists then we must
not compromise truth and i think when we're speaking as advocates that's fine just say you're
an advocate say i'm not being a scientist right now i'm just telling you what i want you to do and
i'm going to say whatever i need to say to convince you i think that's important the other thing i want
to pick up is this trust idea i hear a lot especially from people within science and academia
especially from people who are somewhat on the left but not only on the left side of the
political spectrum who say trust in science is really way down in the last few years
and i'm not sure that's true in fact i don't think it is true depends what you mean by science
if what you mean is science as a process of developing and finding knowledge i know of no
evidence that it's down and the the results of the pew uh charitable trust in their surveys for
example suggest that it's not if what you mean by science is trust in individual elements of the
scientific community then i'm not sure it's down either but it's spread around so some people think
fauci is trustworthy and some people think weneth paltrow is trustworthy some people think david
alison is and some people think peter it is and some people think we're corrupt and ignorant and
confused and terrible um and i think the the challenge is that there are people who cannot
distinguish between the the statements of a tony fauci and the extent to which they are or are not
backed by evidence and the statements of a johnny anedes and this extent to which they are not back
versus the statements of a gwyneth paltrow or somebody else and i think that's the challenge
it's not that people don't trust science they don't know which voice to trust as a communicator
of the science and therefore they don't trust individual elements of the canon of science
and we see that very strongly in nutrition there's a nice summary on the pewchattable trust website
now indicating that trust in science is high trust in dieticians is high trust in medical doctors
who talk about nutrition in treating their patients is high but trust in nutrition scientists
compared to dieticians and medical doctors who talk about nutrition and compared to other
scientists is low so in nutrition we have met the enemy and it is us we have shot ourselves
in the credibility foot with our obfuscation and our exaggeration and our hype and i think
that pocket of trust is gone even though trust in science overall is not down
david this was this was a fantastic discussion you are always so lucid in the way that you
can talk about an idea including this very one i think this this this point that we're ending on
is is really really spot on and i think that this the difference between science and advocacy can't
be overstated and i think it would be amazing if people myself included all of us had the self
awareness to speak and know which hat we were wearing i mean that think about the problems that
could be solved if one you allowed people to wear both hats but they always had to have a hat on you
you couldn't you couldn't you know blind the listener from which hat you're wearing
and if you were wearing your scientist hat you would be delivering the nuanced hard truth
as messy as it might be as unclear as it might be with no regard for how a person feels when
they hear it and what action they may or may not take as a result of it and of course if you're
really just in the business of saying i want to change your behavior because i think it's in your
best interest i'm going to put the different hat on i like this idea we we i think there's
something here we we can come up with a two hat system and everybody gets to own two hats you know
every one of us in our lives have to deal with this we're both fathers as fathers you face this
all the time sometimes your kid says you can i do this and you say no and they could say why well
because i think you might get hurt or it's a bad idea or something bad might happen or you won't
get that good thing and they say do you know are you sure and they have a counter argument
and everyone say i don't know and i'm not sure i have no randomized controlled trial that climbing
that tree is too dangerous i'm just telling you i don't think it's a good idea but i have no i
have no need to pretend that i did a scientific experiment i'm your dad and that tree looks
dangerous to me and i'm telling you to get down from it right now and then there are other times
i'm acting as a scientist and i say this is what would constitute adequate evidence and this is
what we know just like confucius said know what you know know what you don't know brilliant thank
you david it's been a pleasure sitting here with you today thank you my friend great to see you
thank you for listening to this week's episode of the drive if you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription now to that end membership benefits include a
bunch of things one totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic paper
person thing we discuss on each episode the word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these
monthly ama episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely
access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this the qualities which are a super short podcast that we release every tuesday
through friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of the drive this is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that i believe in but for which i'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on if you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can head
over to peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook
all with the id peteratiamd you can also leave us a review on apple podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including
the giving of medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk the content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should
not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have
and they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
finally i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies i invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies