Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Hey Steven, thank you so much for coming over. As we were talking about, I don't really do many
of these in person anymore, often just out of sheer laziness, but I do enjoy it a lot more.
So the fact that I know it was a bit of a hassle, you had to probably change clinic or something
today, but anyway, really appreciate you coming out. And this is a topic that, you know, I think
everybody has questions on this topic and everybody, myself included, is comically ignorant on this
topic. I mentioned to you a few minutes ago, the extent to my knowledge from medical school,
I remember there's an optic nerve. I remember it's a cranial nerve. I think it's even the second
cranial nerve. There you go. You're ahead of the game. I remember something called a fovea. Right.
And I know there's a blind spot, but I've kind of forgotten why. So it's safe to say my knowledge
of this topic right now is probably at par with everybody's right. Well, that's, you know, not
rare, frankly, because the eye is so literally compartmentalized. We just don't interact that
much with other specialties. So it's not rare for people who are in other specialties to be very
ignorant of the eyeball. And that's fine because I think it'll help us keep the level of discussion
at an approachable level for everyone. Has there ever been a discussion about suggesting that
ophthalmologists don't need to do the four year MD degree? Like how much of what you learned in
medical school became relevant in your residency? Actually quite a lot. Honestly. Yeah. Because you
think about it, the eyeball, there's really nothing specifically magical about the eyeball. It's got
neurological tissue in the back, actual brain tissue in the back. It's got a vascular supply.
There are a lot of crossovers to other medical disciplines. All of the cellular processes are
the same. We operate adjacent to the eye. I think it's important for us to have a general sense of
medical knowledge, particularly because so many systemic diseases manifest as eye problems. There
is a discipline of medical training or of visual training, basically optometry, which deals with
the eye, but not all of the surgical stuff. So we work in a collaborative fashion with optometrists.
And those are the folks who are fitting glasses, they're screening for eye disease, they're
handling preoperative and postoperative care. In many cases, they're treating some diseases that
are specific to the eye, like glaucoma, for example. And we work in a collaborative fashion with them.
And does everyone in an ophthalmology residency spend time operating? There's no non-surgical
discipline to this, right? It doesn't bifurcate in the training?
Well, it does, actually. There are non-surgical ophthalmologists, but I think they all start out
as surgeons. To become an ophthalmologist, you're really training to become an eye surgeon. But there
are, for example, neuro-ophthalmologists, which are really more neurologists than neuro-ophthalmologists
than eye surgeons. In fact, it's typical that they don't do eye surgery. So there are some
ophthalmologists who don't do eye surgery. One of my lasting memories from residency was stealing
suture from the ophthalmology OR at Hopkins, because I guess for people who don't know,
the number of the suture, of course, gets larger. The suture gets smaller. So an o suture is like,
you can see how thick it is. It's like a piece of rope. One-oh, two-oh, three-oh. By the time you're
at four-oh, it's actually quite thin. Right. We use 11-oh. Exactly. In cardiac surgery,
you're using a seven-oh. Occasionally, there's some guys that would sew the distal end of a
coronary artery with an eight-oh. At that level, it's already very thin. Just the slightest tug too
much and it breaks. But then in ophthalmology, you guys were at 11-oh. So I used to steal 11-oh
constantly every night I was on call and practice suturing with 11-oh. The thinking being, if you
can tie an 11-oh with your hands and not tear it, that seven-oh, which normally is like a piece of
hair, is going to feel like a piece of rope. So I used it to help me develop a good feel for fine
suture. Yeah. And then I also realized I'm kind of being a schmuck here. I bet this 11-oh stuff's
really expensive and I'm just stealing it like there's taken to the call room all night.
More likely, it was probably 10-oh. But yes, it's, I mean, our tools are little tiny tools. And I can
remember, you know, our operating room when I was in training was sort of near the orthopedic surgery.
The exact opposite. And you hear this black and decker stuff going on over there. And our little
tiny tools are very, it's just a totally different. Is everything you do under a microscope
operationally? Like you don't operate with a naked eye, right? Right. I mean, there are, right. It's
all under a microscope. Either, you know, just to put it in a visual for people who may not be
familiar, we have a binocular microscope. So I'm looking through both eyes and this is either
mounted from the ceiling and has controlled by my feet. So the X, Y, and Z and the zoom focus are
controlled by a foot pedal. And that either comes from the ceiling or it's on a really large stand.
And so I'm sort of sitting, I'm looking straight ahead. But so the image is here, but I'm operating
down here. And it's interesting because sometimes my wife will kid me, I'll come home from a day of
surgery exhausted, but she said, she says something like, well, I don't really get it. You're just
sitting in a chair, sort of making these little tiny movements and there's soft music playing.
It all seems very, very sedate. It's incredibly stressful and exhausting. You do that.
Although I will say in your wife's defense, she has it harder because of the kids.
Yeah, that's true. For sure. There let there be no misunderstanding about that. It's way easier.
Well, actually I didn't realize, I never really thought about that, but the other advantage you
have is you don't have that cervical flexion problem that most surgeons have when they're in
an open, I mean, nowadays with more robotic and laparoscopic surgery, you can be in an advantage
neck position. But we have a different problem though. And that is that people tend to, and I
don't want to mess up the sound and microphone, but they tend to hyper extent. They tend to
to bring their head forward to come up to the oculars. Yeah. And that creates a whole other
set of problems. So there are ergonomic challenges for sure. And I remember early on in my career,
I was, I was coached very carefully on how to sit, how to have your spine arranged.
Don't crane your neck forward and make sure that your shoulders are down. It's, it's interesting
because when you train surgeons and you look at them, they're all sort of raising their shoulders
up and they're terrified that they're going to do something wrong. So they're in a very, very
compromised and stressful position. And then they tend to lift their hands up. So they're actually,
and again, I mentioned earlier that these are little tiny movements. So very small positional
changes can have a huge impact on the outcome of the surgery. Yeah. I have a number of friends,
two in particular from residency who have had multiple neck surgeries, including one that
required such significant extent of fusion that he could no longer operate. So he trained as a
cardiac surgeon and now does cardiac critical care. So still a great career, but after 10 years of
training as a cardiac surgeon, can't operate anymore. Yeah. I mean, surgery, it takes a toll
on the, on the surgeon for sure. So when you went to medical school, did you know you wanted to do
ophthalmology? Not really. I think I knew I wanted to do something surgical. I wanted to do
something with my hands. I'd kind of always been good with my hands and I could draw reasonably
well. And, and, and you get, as you kind of know, you get feedback early on in your surgical, in your
medical career. If you demonstrate that you're decent with your hands, people say, Hey, you're
pretty good with your hands. You should think about something surgical or maybe not. They say,
have you thought about radiology or something along those lines? And so I kind of knew that
I wanted to be a surgeon. Um, and, but really didn't know what type. And it was, I remember
a eureka moment where the first time I looked through what we refer to as a slit lamp, which
is basically like a microscope to look into the eye. The very first time I looked through that
instrument at an eyeball, I was hooked. I knew this is what I wanted to do. And that was something
you did during an ophthalmology rotation or were you doing an ER rotation and somebody came in with
something stuck in their eye? It was during an ophthalmology rotation and I'd had some exposure
to ophthalmology because a friend of mine's father was an ophthalmologist, quite a famous one. Um,
and I'd had a background in photography when I was a little kid, so I kind of understood optics well,
but that was during one of those one week, you know, do a little ophthalmology, do a little ear,
nose and throat, do a little bit of whatever it is. And that was, that was a nice thing about
medicine is that you kind of get to taste a little bit of everything before you decide you're going
down a particular pathway. So, um, it's funny, I didn't really overlap with ophthalmologists. So
you guys didn't do a general surgery internship, I'm guessing, right? Some of us do that. I did
what is referred to as a transitional residence, uh, internship where you do a little bit of
everything. You do general surgery, internal medicine, you, you know, you do a little bit
of everything and that's, that's very helpful. Um, and the, the general surgery part, I will
confess that was rough. I mean, as, as you well know, um, but it was nice to have exposure to
a little bit of everything. So, um, that that's probably a four year residency. I'm guessing
when you include the internship, that's right. Yeah. And, um, back in the day when you did it,
how, what was the bread and butter? You, you always kind of judge a discipline by what the
bread and butter is of the era, right? So general surgery, if you did it in the 1960s and 1970s,
the bread and butter would have been Bill Roth procedures and things like that, where,
you know, the most common thing you were doing was cutting out half of the stomach because of
peptic ulcer disease and things like that. By the time I got to residency, like I never did one of
those, right? Because, you know, H2 blockers and PPI is basically eliminated the need to surgically
remove part of the stomach for gastric or peptic ulcer. So, um, at the time you went through your
training, right? What was kind of the, where did 80% of the volume come from? What type of cases?
Yeah, still cataracts, cataract surgery, and then retinal disease. Um, you know, the scourge
of essentially diabetes where you had these very, very complex retinal problems. Uh, so those were
really the, the two main ones. So this is probably a good moment to, to sort of take a step back and
get into some of the anatomy and get me up to speed and everybody else by extension on what it
is we are talking about here, because even the word retina, cornea, these are like, I kind of know the
retinas at the back of the eye that like, it's just embarrassing even how much of a
Luddite I am when it comes to this part of the body. So, um, I can say this literally talk to
me like I'm a four year old. Okay. All right. Explain the eye. That's good. That'll work for
both of us. So, you know, it's funny. It's funny you mentioned that because I don't typically see
kids in my practice, but there is one disease state where I do see kids. And that's because
we did some research in that area that anyway, allows me to see kids. And when you explain the
eye to a kid and you say, well, the eye is like a camera and the film in the back, that's the retina.
And they look over at their parents. Like, what is this guy talking about? What is he talking about?
Film. What is that? You know, a 50 year old understands that, but literally the eye is kind
of built like a camera where in the very front you have the cornea, which is kind of like the covering
on the front of a watch. That's the thing that a contact lens would sit on. And then the next thing
you encounter is the pupil, which is the hole in the iris behind that is the lens. We refer to it
as the lens, but it's really one of a couple of different lenses inside the eye. But the lens
behind the pupil, then you have the vitreous cavity and then in the very back, the retina,
which attaches to the optic nerve. And that's what goes to the brain. So images come in, they're bent
by the cornea first, then bent again by the lens. And then they focus hopefully on the retina. So in
a perfectly sized eye and someone who doesn't need spectacles to see images come from, say,
optical infinity, which is for the purposes of our discussion about 20 feet or beyond,
where light rays come in parallel and they're bent so that they fall perfectly on the retina.
And what does that mean? Fall perfectly on the retina? Meaning, yeah, they
is the like, if you think about the back of the eye here, right? What fraction of the back of this
fear is considered retina? All of it. Everything. Yeah. All of it. The whole back of the eye is
coded essentially by retina. But there is the fovea you mentioned earlier. That's the point
where you cast your gaze. So the image that of the thing you're looking at falls on the fovea,
which is the very center, the bullseye literally of the of the retina. So when I'm looking at you,
images from you are falling on the fovea of both of my retinas. Now, if someone is nearsighted,
those images come into focus in a point that is not exactly on the retina. And so that that can
become a problem. And nearsighted, again, the way I used to remember this, because this is literally
how little I know, nearsighted means you see things near well. Yes, that's right. And those are people
like me who need either glasses or contact lenses to see things at a distance. Correct. So this is,
you know, typical cocktail party banter. Someone will say, I think I'm nearsighted or maybe I'm
both nearsighted and farsighted. So nearsighted means you see better up close. Farsighted is a
little trickier because farsighted people see better at far, but their far might also be kind
of blurry. It's just that the near vision is even worse. So that person who says I'm neither I'm
near and farsighted could be that's an accurate statement. That's a plausible. No, it's actually
probably that they're what we refer to as presbyopic, which is that they see well far away,
but their focusing ability is compromised typically through age and they can't see up close.
And we'll get into that. I want to get to that in detail because I experienced that a few years ago
in a manner that rocked my world because it didn't happen gradually. Yeah, that's exactly.
It seemed to happen overnight. So yeah, it's funny you say that some people
wake up on their 40th birthday and they say, I just can't see up close anymore. And for others,
it's a little more gradual process. But the reason that comes into play is that when we are young,
when we're born, the lens of our eye is extremely elastic. It's like a gummy bear
and it can change shape to bring near objects into focus. But as we age, and this is universal,
the elasticity of the lens goes down and we're no longer able to sort of zoom focus in and you
have to start pushing things farther and farther away or get some sort of optical aid like a pair
of spectacles to see up close. That process continues as the lens becomes less elastic and
harder, eventually resulting in a cataract where it begins to lose its optical clarity.
So now you have a lens that's stiff, hard, and starts to become opaque. So that's kind of the
cataract is a disease of the lens. Correct. And it's a natural, I guess this is kind of a gray
area. Do we consider this to be a natural product of aging the way our skin wrinkles
and the elasticity changes, or is it considered a pathology in the way that type 2 diabetes is a
pathology, not necessarily a normal consequence of aging that can be avoided? Yeah, that's a really
good and interesting way to look at it. So I think that cataract formation is a universal component of
DOE days on earth. I don't recall seeing many people in their 70s without some degree of
cataract formation. It starts to become universal. However, there are things that can pathologically
prematurely cause cataract formation. Some of them are sort of surprising, like being electrocuted
can actually cause premature cataract formation, but that's one sort of exotic weird one. But trauma,
head trauma can certainly do it. Just head trauma, not necessarily eye trauma. Well,
you know, the head is kind of- I mean, obviously the eye is in the head. And if the head receives
trauma, there's going to be a certain amount of trauma in the eye itself. Right. But point is,
it doesn't have to be direct trauma to the eye. Correct. Simply the coo counter coo forces of the
brain are presumably also being reverberated through the vitreous fluid. That's exactly right.
So if you think about the eye as a fluid containing organ and when it receives trauma, and just as you
mentioned with coo and contra coo injuries of the brain inside the skull, I think those same forces
come to bear on the eye itself. So I think it's more common when you do have direct eye trauma,
but I think even head trauma alone can predispose someone to cataract formation. Certainly diabetes
is a cause of premature cataract formation. Steroid use, corticosteroid use can lead to
cataract formation. So is the lens a vascular structure? No, it is not. And the protein,
if you think about the lens, it's kind of the shape and about the size of an M&M candy,
just like a plain- The chocolate ones. Yeah, the chocolate ones, right? You know,
just the ones without the nuts or pretzels or whatever they're putting inside M&Ms now. But the,
you know, a plain M&M candy. Yeah. And it's got a coating kind of like the candy shell.
And the protein inside the chocolate is optically clear when you are a kid. And that protein does
not turn over or exchange, but the membrane, the candy coating, the so-called lens capsule
can allow molecules to diffuse in and out. So a classic example of this is someone will
point out, Hey, you know, my vision, my glasses prescription suddenly changed.
It, I became much more nearsighted or I became much more farsighted in the space of a month.
And I went to the eye doctor and they said, wow, your glasses are totally wrong. And the first
thing I think of is go get your blood sugar checked because glucose can diffuse into the lens,
cause it to swell. And that will change the shape of the lens. The lens becomes physically bigger.
So it's like a thicker, more powerful lens. So it's an osmotic change, basically.
And the timeframe for that to happen is over a period of several weeks. So if the blood sugar
goes up, it may, there may be a lag of a month or two before the vision changes. And when the blood
sugar goes down, same thing, it takes weeks for that to kind of go back to normal.
So is again, I'm just so I'm almost struggling to organize my thinking around this. But the other
thing that comes to my mind when you think about an a vascular structure is what is the immune?
What is the immune systems behavior around the eye? Are these immune privilege sites? Are they
more or less susceptible to certain types of infections, systemic infections, that is,
obviously, I know we'll probably talk a little bit about sort of local infections, but yeah,
I mean, the eye itself is certainly prone to to damage from systemic infection. There is a blood
retinal barrier in the same way that there's a blood brain barrier that protects that highly
metabolically active retina from systemic disease. But the lens itself is relatively privileged from
an immune standpoint. It's within that capsule and it's hard for large molecules to get across
that small molecules can. And that's why it's going to be important from a pharmacotherapy
standpoint. It is. It's in for example, there is a technology there's a there's a medication
that is a lipoic acid, choline ester that is being examined as a way of softening the lens
to maybe break some of the disulfide bonds that become a problem and become one of the reasons
why the elasticity of the lens is lost. So you're saying there might be a day when there's either a
topical or injectable substrate that could go into the lens that could delay the onset of farsightedness
and the onset of cataract. That's the hope. This is sort of at the moment, it's a little bit of a
pipe dream because it's in the early experimental phase. But human trials have begun to look at the
lens softening properties of this particular compound. The trick is you've got to you've got
to use it in a topical fashion. So putting in an eye drop and that drop has to run the gauntlet
of going through the cornea, which has lipid layers and and water soluble layers. It's got to
get through all that into the aqueous humor in the front and then through the lens capsule into
the lens to actually do its work. And that's why it's that particular drug or compound is a choline
ester because that allows it to get through that the lipid layer in the front through the aqueous
through the water soluble portion of the cornea and then hopefully into the lens itself. And that's
not easy to do. So the lens is a relatively privileged area both from an immunological but
also a pharmacological standpoint. So that would help that would help it also stay clean stay clear.
Yeah, you know, it's got a you want the lens to be optically clear. Let's go back to a little bit
of the front of the eye. So the pupil we all recognize is the dark part. Right. And it
you know, we talk about the dilation and constriction of the pupil. Is the pupil itself
actually changing in size or is it just that the iris is moving the colored part of the eye? Yeah.
Is is it dilation means it's actually moving back and constriction means it's actually closing.
That's that is correct. It's the physical aperture changes in size. It gets bigger,
it gets smaller. So when they when you go to the eye doctor and they dilate your pupils,
they are physically opening up the pupil pharmacologically. And that's mostly so we
can see into the back of the eyes. And you do that by forcing the iris to move out of the way.
Correct. The iris has a it almost looks like the the like the the aperture of a of a camera. Yeah.
And so it you know, you can either constrict it or you can make it bigger. And interestingly,
one of the big pharmacological, I think, frontiers that were on the cusp of seeing
are drugs that intentionally shrink the aperture
in the pursuit of increased depth of focus. So students of photography will know that
the smaller the aperture, the smaller the hole, the more stuff is in focus at the same time.
So if you can make the pupil small pharmacologically and get it into the sweet spot,
which is probably about one point six millimeters, you can suddenly see up close again,
because you've you've expanded the depth of focus.
Wait, this is let me make sure I understand this. You're saying that putting the lens aside for a
moment, which is a great source of the pathology, the inability of the lens to move in and out.
And that call it the Z axis, if we want to give it that way. You now have another way to manipulate
your ability to see things close up. If you could force the aperture to be in a position that is
isn't necessarily dictated by the availability of light.
That's exactly right. So imagine it's kind of like squinting.
Yeah.
You know, if you can you squint, you're reducing the aperture through which you're looking and
you're filtering out optically. What's happening is you're filtering out all of the light rays that
are not perfectly parallel. And if you can get rid of those scattering rays that make the image
blurry and only use those parallel rays that happen to be coming parallel off of an object,
you can actually resolve it. You can actually see it. And that's why pharmacologically,
if you shrink the pupil, you could once again see up close.
Now, this is again, is a little counterintuitive to me because anybody who's in my shoes,
who's experiencing far sightedness or more, I shouldn't say that Presby.
Presbyopia.
Presbyopia knows that nothing makes it worse than darkness.
Correct.
And so you're in that rest. There's two scenarios where it wreaks havoc. The first is one of my
children has a train book that why these guys wrote a book in like six point font
that they know parents are going to read their kids in bed when it's kind of dark.
It's beyond me. There should be a mandatory 24 point font for nighttime books for little kids.
But anyway, he's got this one book and he even tells me before he wants that book ready,
he's like, daddy, go get your glasses. And then the other place is the restaurant,
where it's usually really lit. But in both of those situations, isn't my aperture narrowed?
Oh, no, no, of course not. It's the opposite.
So if you put the sun on something, you're going to be able to read it because your pupil.
So is that why light makes it different?
Some of it is just the absolutely it's pupil effect alone.
I never thought of it as just the light. There's much more light energy available
for you to resolve something. So yes, there are competing forces when you
reduce the size of the aperture, you're letting less light in. But the only light you're letting
in are those rays that happen to be parallel in perfect focus. You can actually see.
So in the clinical trial that we performed to look at this,
those competing forces were examined very closely. And we found that the aperture effect,
the depth of focus outweighed any loss of loss from from loss of light.
And how long would these eye drops stay in effect? How long would they be able to maintain
after you put them in?
I think about it depends a little bit upon eye color, believe it or not,
because something I want to ask about in a moment. Yeah.
I'm glad you brought that up. Yeah. Certain eye color, like light eyes tend to react more to any
given strength of dilating medicare drop or or constricting. But about six to eight hours,
maybe up to 10 hours. So this would be a once a day, maybe twice a day.
And would this have any impact? Would it compromise your far vision?
Quite the contrary. What was really interesting is that when we looked at patients who had their
pupil size reduced pharmacologically, their distance vision also gets better by the same
principle because their depth of focus is so good. So in the same way that you can squint and make
out a highway sign if you're a little bit nearsighted or a little bit farsighted or have a
stigmatism, which we haven't even talked about yet, which I don't even know what that is, even
though I have one. That's right. And squinting makes that better by the same token. The
pharmacological manipulation of your pupil will do that as well. And by the way, I think you will see
in early 2022 commercial availability of these of the first of these drugs.
So going back to the more complicated drug you were talking about that has it's complicated
because it has to make its way into the lens. That's right. I can now see why that would be
more about the cataract issue and not about the presbyopia issue, because this would be a much
easier way to solve presbyopia because you only have to basically get onto the iris.
Yeah. Well, you're looking at a drug that shrinks the pupil and works in 15 minutes
versus something that softens the lens that might work in 15 months. So I think they're
very different markets. And while that lipoic acid cholinester is being pursued as a presbyopia,
near vision aid or something to reduce the effects of, I think their real goal is to
reduce the incidence or delay the onset of cataract formation, which would be really cool.
Yeah. Is there any clear evolutionary explanation for why different eye colors have emerged?
What's the advantage of brown iris versus blue?
Yeah, it's a protection from UV light and from visible light. And in the same way,
the different skin tones have emerged. So typically you see dark eyed people.
Clustered closer to the equator because visible light and UV light and infrared radiation are
really destructive. And as you might remember, this is one of the few things that people remember
from medical school about the retina, but it's one of the most metabolically active tissues in
the body, if not the most metabolically active tissue. And because it's constantly being bombarded
with radiation effectively, it's prone to free radical formation. So what's called the retinal
pigment epithelium, which is the pigmented layer behind the retina, underneath the retina,
that is responsible for shielding the vascular supply behind the retina from all of this
radiation. Because that vascular network behind the retina has a very high oxygen tension,
and it would be prone to free radical formation if it were constantly being bombarded by UV light,
infrared radiation, visible light. And that's why you see in people near the equator more pigment.
And that's also true of the iris as well. So the other thing I do remember vaguely
from medical school is rods and cones. And of course, I also remember a few other things now
that we're talking about it, about which part of the brain actually does the signal processing
and stuff. So let's go back to the light hitting and what are the rods and cones and how are they
processing that signal? Right. So you might remember cones are primarily for your daytime vision,
and they're clustered in the center of your visual sphere. So in the center of the,
near the center of the, what we refer to as the macula, which is a central portion of the retina,
and the very center of the macula is the fovea. Right. So that's primarily where the cones are.
The rods are in the periphery, and they typically are responsible more for dim illumination vision,
like night vision, and they're very good at picking up motion. So, you know, as predators, we
want to make sure that we can hone in on where prey is, but as prey ourselves, we want to be
able to detect, oh, that's some kind of a tiger over there. Something's moving in my periphery.
I need to be aware of that. So that's primarily the difference in responsibility.
And is each rod and each cone, is it, is each one a single cell?
Yes, that's right. They're each highly specialized cells.
Obviously they have mitochondria. Obviously they have, is there, what distinguishes them? Do they
have photo receptors? Like what makes them unique?
They are photo, they refer to as photo receptors and they have stacks of structures within them
that are photosensitive and that causes a depolarization, which-
So they work like channel opsins do?
They use a photon to create an action potential?
Correct. Once the photon hits that particular cell photo receptor, then there's a change in the
membrane and ions flow. And that's how a signal is generated.
Wow. Okay. So all of that ion flow ultimately makes its way to the optic nerve?
Correct. That's right. And to the brain. And most of the visual processing is in the very back of
your brain. And about half of the overall brain structure deals with vision in some capacity.
And that's why, for example, when people have a stroke, there's almost always some component of
visual involvement in a stroke. So you may have a droopy face on one side and then a limb is droopy
as well. But if you map out the visual sphere, you will detect some deficit in the visual sphere
from most strokes. Now, people who listen to this podcast, on various episodes, we've got into the
brain and people understand that I think there's sort of the brainstem, the most primitive piece
of our brain that is basically responsible for autonomic function. You then have sort of this
midbrain that sits on top of it that we call the sort of reptilian brain, a lot of emotion there.
But of course, what in theory distinguishes us from all the other animals is this remarkable
cortical piece that sits on top of it. And how much of the visual processing is in that neocortex?
Is it virtually all done there? Is any part of it done in the midbrain?
Yeah. Stuff like pupil responses. The autonomic stuff.
The autonomic stuff. Those are in the midbrain. But the visual processing and the actual mapping of
the visual sphere and even as hierarchical as parts of the brain that are specific to edge
detection or moving edge detection or edges that move this way or that way, that's all been mapped
quite elegantly and it's in the cortex. Is there a cross? Yes.
Is the left doing the right and vice versa? That's right. But remember, you send information
from your left visual sphere to the right side of the brain, but you're getting information from-
This is the trick. I remember.
From both eyes. Yeah. So both eyes, yeah.
Explain how that works because this, I remember in med school needing to draw this a few times.
How long do you have? It's the simplest way to think about something is that at the pituitary,
there is something called the optic chiasm. You probably remember where the optic nerves cross.
Yes. The optic nerves cross.
Right. Some of the fiber, about half the fibers cross. So if a visual deficit is in one eye only,
we know that it is in front of the chiasm. Correct. And if it's behind that, it should
affect both eyes, maybe asymmetrically, but it should affect both eyes. And that could be
very helpful in localizing where a particular problem is. Now, a lot of that's done through
imaging, but it used to be there was quite an art to this clinical exam, which sadly we've lost a
lot of. Yeah. And I do remember both in neurology and probably neuroanatomy, kind of going into
these really crazy tests that you'd see the patient performing the test and missing a certain
thing. And you'd think they must be faking it. There's no way you could produce such a bizarre
deficit in this one part of this one visual field. But then of course you see, and look,
there's a tumor and it totally explains this once you understand how the nerves cross.
It kind of goes back to one of your earliest questions, which is, do you think that eye
surgeons need to go to medical school? Yes, because we diagnose brain tumors. We find things
that are systemic diseases that have ocular manifestations. So you're obviously well aware
that your brother and I are close friends and he's become pretty obsessed with hunting now.
And I'll take full responsibility at least for the part of it. I did not see this one coming. Yeah.
Well, you'll see where this is going. So he's become super obsessed with hunting. And
one of the things that hunting teaches you is how we stack up to wild animals. So if you're out
hunting an elk or an axis deer or one of these remarkable creatures, especially with a bow and
arrow. Yeah. I was going to say, how much technology do we have access to in this hypothetical
scenario? So let's talk about bow and arrow hunting, where you really, I mean,
if you really want to reduce the margin of error, you want to be inside of 50 yards to be
able to take that shot. Sure. So the way I always talk about this is animals have superpowers
and we just have to decide as do we, we have superpowers, our greatest one being our intelligence,
which allowed us to make the bow. Right. But I generally think of the three big senses,
right? Which is the sense of vision, the sense of smell, the sense of hearing. And
there's simply no comparison in sense of smell. We basically can't smell. We're effectively
useless creatures in nature. Agreed. Yeah. You know, they can smell us with, if they're
downwind of us, they can smell us a mile away, literally one mile away. If the wind moves from
you to them, they're gone. You'll never get close to them. Right. It turns out that the closest sense
we have to our prey is vision. Right. It's the only thing where we're almost on par with them.
Now there are some animals that can see better than us. You know, if you, there are certain
types of Rams that if you break skyline within two miles of them, they'll see it. And birds. Yeah.
But for the most part, like this is the one sense that we have that rivals the best. Right.
Uh, is that because we both had to, as you said, be hunters and be hunted for such a large part
of our revolution? Is that, I mean, this is sort of teleologic explanation I'm looking for, but.
Well, I think so. But think, just think about this for a moment. Imagine you are in the desert
and there is a single candle a mile away from you and it's pitch black. There's no moon.
You can see that, but at high noon in that same desert where there may be 200,000 lux illumination,
you can still function and see well. So many, many, many, many, many orders of magnitude of change of
illumination. Like it's astonishing that you can function in both of those environments.
Well, that's actually interesting that you make that point because as it gets darker,
we do tend to have an advantage over some of the animals. Now it turns out to be very short-lived.
There's a very narrow window at dusk and dawn where I think we can outsee them.
And maybe that's the benefit we have in that we evolve slightly better to have this greater range,
if you will. But I've always been amazed at like, why did we not develop a sense of smell?
Yeah. I mean, because we effectively can't smell compared to animals. I mean, it's really.
Absurd how different it is. And I don't know why evolution didn't push that harder.
And even our hearing, I think is, you know, we're not even close.
Nothing compared to them.
Yeah. But vision, you know, and if you ask, it's very common for patients to grab my arm
as we're going into surgery and they'll say, Dr. Dell, you don't understand. My vision is
really important to me. I've got to see. I've got to see. And we, I get that, you know, it's the one
sense that if you asked people which sense they'd be most willing to give up, it's the very last one.
Yeah. And in COVID, we saw many people at least transiently lose a sense of smell and a sense of
taste. And of course it's inconvenient, but it's totally survivable.
It's hard to function in the world as a blind person. And, you know, it's a fear that many of
us have. So it's a sense that we value very highly and also evolutionarily it's valued highly just
owing to the fact that so much of our brain is devoted to vision.
Yeah. This is a little bit off track, but maybe good for a PSA. When I was a kid, we did so many
dumb things without ever any concern for our eyes. I just don't think our parents knew enough.
Right.
And we didn't think about it. So I'd be out in the backyard chucking things around, cutting wood,
smashing rocks, never a thought to put on safety goggles. And now my kids who are both completely
obsessed with cutting down trees and like just, they're always, they're very active outdoors. I
mean, they just know like you're wearing your safety goggles if you do that stuff.
Cause I'm totally paranoid they're going to, you know, have one of these tragic accidents.
Do you see much of that stuff? I mean, do we?
For sure. And you, you know, you see a lot of eye injuries. I think injuries are one of the
main causes of devastating visual loss in young people. You know, if we take visual loss in general,
almost all of the big causes and movers of visual loss are senescence related or age related.
But in terms of vision loss in young people, it's a lot of trauma.
What are the most common traumas that you see?
You know, I think unrestrained passenger.
Like is it, is it object flying into eye or is it more?
I think it's more blunt trauma, frankly.
Okay. Wow.
Yeah. More blunt trauma. The eye is pretty well protected with the brow and the cheek,
but you know, there are certain things that can get in there and can directly impact the eye.
And so I think, you know, in a young person, trauma is something you have to certainly watch out for.
What is the velocity at which we can't out blink it?
Cause the other day my son was smashing beads and he didn't want to put his safety goggles on.
And I was like, look buddy, you got to get these things on. And he goes, no, dad. And he's like,
why? And I said, because you're hitting sharp objects with a sharp object.
If one of them flies up and hits your eye, he goes, I would see it and I would close my eye.
No, you wouldn't buddy.
Yeah. Let's just put it this way. Those are objects are flying at supersonic speed
and they, you can't blink that fast.
So do we have a sense of like what our reaction time is to blink?
That is known, but I've long since forgotten what that is.
Because you get the sense, like if somebody's throwing you a ball and you misjudge it,
you're going to blink like that's slow enough that you can catch it. But, but yeah,
but then there's other objects where you can.
Interestingly, you know, I've operated on a number of major league baseball players
and for them seeing the laces on the ball as hitters is enormous.
It's their career.
It is their career. And it's the difference between them hitting, you know, well or average.
And, and some of these players that we've operated on have been 2020 before they had surgery,
but they wanted to be 2015 or 2010. And what that means is, you know, again,
here's another nomenclature issue. What is 2020 vision?
2020 simply means that you can see at 20 feet, what a quote unquote normal person can see at
20 feet. If you're 2010, you can see at 20 feet, what a normal person has to get 10 feet up to
in order to see. So 2010 is better than 2020.
So some of these guys want to be 2010 or 20, you know, whatever it is, 2015.
We've been able to achieve that with modern forms of laser vision correction because.
Wait a minute. How is the, isn't this now getting into the performance enhancing side of things?
Isn't this kind of amazing?
You know, it's interesting. Yeah, for sure. And, and I had a discussion yesterday with a guy who
owns a soccer team. And I said, have you ever had your players tested for their vision? And
he sort of froze and turned white, turned white for a second. And he just said, it's so crazy.
You say that because we put them through this barrage of tests physically to see what their
heart, their lungs, their kidneys, all that stuff. We didn't check their vision. And there are ways
to boost human performance beyond 2020. The theoretical limit of how well you could see
is defined by essentially the pixelation of your retina, the spacing of the cells of those
photoreceptors that we talked about earlier. Does that vary from person to person?
It has to, but it's somewhere in the vicinity of about 2008 or, or so. And so if you can have a
sharp enough image, you could theoretically see better than 2010. And the only way you can really
achieve that is to remove some of the optical irregularities that we are all born with and
somehow neutralize them along with the glasses prescription. And we can actually do that with
laser vision correction currently. So why would it be beneficial? I guess we'll talk about laser
surgery and maybe you'll want to park this question until then. Yeah. Why would it be beneficial to an
athlete who for understandable reasons needs the best vision possible to undergo laser corrective
surgery versus just using contact lenses to accomplish the same thing? Is that possible?
Yeah. So if you think about contact lenses, anyone who's ever worn contact lenses knows that when you
put in a brand new pair of contact lenses, you can see pretty well with them. And then you begin to
regard that contact lens as a foreign object. So your body just begins to attack it, coat it with
all sorts of immunological debris. You are susceptible to pollen, dust, whatever it is that
coats this, this, you know, formally pristine object. And let's say it has, there is correction
for astigmatism in that contact lens where its orientation is important. Every time you blink,
that contact lens moves a little bit, all of those factors contribute to optical performance
that is less than what you can achieve with spectacles or laser vision correction. So
particularly soft contact lenses do a very, very good job, but they don't give you superhuman
vision performance typically. You know, it's funny. I experimented two years ago with a stronger
prescription than normal to get me to 2015 in my dominant eye for archery. Sure. Goofed up your
near though. That's the problem. I just abandoned it immediately after like six months of suffering
because it made my presbyopia worse. Yes. Goofs up your near. So I was like, this just isn't worth it.
Yeah, that's right. Yeah. That's the challenge when you pull the image farther and farther away,
you're doing the same thing with the near image as well.
So let's now talk about how to correct these. Oh, I guess let's define an astigmatism since I don't
know what that is yet. Yeah. I mean, it's when the eye is shaped like a football instead of
a basketball. And when you say the eye, which part of the eye specifically? The cornea, the very front
part of the eye typically. And how thick is the cornea, by the way? It's about as thick as a credit
card, like 500 microns. Yeah. Yeah. Like 550 microns, something like that. So half a millimeter.
Yeah, exactly right. So half a millimeter. And it's typically that is the location of astigmatism.
There can be astigmatism in the lens itself, the lens behind the pupil. You probably don't remember
which one I have, do you? I do. Which one do I have? You have corneal astigmatism. That's the
normal one. Yeah. It's very pedestrian. You're a very boring patient. But
the... So meaning, just to be clear, I'm not perfectly shaped around here. I'm a bit oblong.
That's right. Shaped like an egg or a football, an American football. So if you're walking along
the laces of the football, you would encounter a fairly gradual curve. But if you took a right
turn and walked perpendicular, it would be very steep. And so that means that the power
differs by meridian. So you need a different glasses prescription in this meridian versus
this meridian. And that can... And what's the prevalence of this? It's very high. I think
60 some odd percent of patients with glasses prescription have some significant degree of
astigmatism. Why has poor vision... I was going to say, why has poor vision been allowed to evolve?
I was going to offer that maybe really poor vision hasn't. Vision that would impair your
ability to survive through reproductive age probably didn't evolve. Maybe there was a day
when the genetic variability of eyes was broad enough that a subset of people had really poor
vision. The type of people today who maybe we don't encounter. Right. This is a super interesting
topic and it shows you how plastic, the evolutionary or actually the adaptive component of the eyeball
is itself. So the length of the eye is really what determines whether you are nearsighted or
farsighted. When you say length, you mean distance from front to back. Okay. So anterior posterior
length of the eyeball, primarily that is the main driver as to whether you are nearsighted or
farsighted. Those who are in the know and are watching this or listening to it also realize
that sometimes it's the curvature of the cornea that contributes to whether someone is nearsighted
or farsighted. But let's say for the purposes of this discussion, that it's the length of the
eyeball that is the main reason why someone is nearsighted or not or farsighted. So a very
nearsighted person has a very long eyeball. Let me make sure I understand that. Okay. Very long
ap axis. You're going to have a real hard time seeing things far away. Correct. And is that
because the further something is, the harder you have a time focusing all that light. Let's talk
about the genesis of this. Okay. Right. So if most of your work, most of your visual environment is
close, then the light rays from that close object are diverging. And so they are falling behind the
retina of someone who's perfectly targeted for distance. So your eyeball is really smart. And
it says, okay, so you're telling me everything is here close up. I know I'll just grow longer
so that these near objects are in perfect focus. And that is exactly what happens.
Over what time scale?
Over a period of months. So if you take a young person and you exclusively have them
perform near tasks, their eye will grow longer so that those near objects are in perfect focus.
So if you could do an awful experiment, it's been done, take a child and not put them in a white
room where there's nothing that they can see that's far away and just have them play with
close objects that they can reach. Yeah. And you would put that kid into glasses as a child.
That's called society in 2021 is children looking at screens, near objects for hours on end and not
going outside. There are two drivers of nearsightedness in the plastic developing human. Number one,
deprivation from outdoor light and number two, near work. So for example, there have been
cohorts of children. Most of these studies have been done in Asia where there is an epidemic
right now of myopia of astonishing proportions. I'm talking about 90% of the population
is now nearsighted in certain Southeastern nation cities. When that becomes such a dominant phenotype,
something is really oddly off. So this really transcends evolution because
if you can change something in years or months. It's not evolutionary. It's adaptive within
the eyeball itself. So if you take a group of children, and this has been done seven to 11
year old children, and you send half of them outside for 80 minutes during the school day for
recess and half of them stay inside in an indoor environment for their recess, the risk of or the
incidence of nearsightedness is 50% higher, it's half in the group that went outside. So you cut
your risk in half by going outside. Now, we think that without any instruction to go and look at
things far away, but just by the very fact that if you're outside, there's so much more to see,
and you're going to be looking further out. Right. And this has been further studied in terms of,
is it just being outside or is it the light? Yeah. It's actually both, but the light is really the
most important driver of protection from nearsightedness. So if you are outside on a bright,
sunny day, you're releasing a fair bit of dopamine from your retina and dopamine inhibits the growth
of the eye. So the worst thing you could do is stay inside in a dimly lit room and perform near
tasks. That raises your risk of nearsightedness 16 fold compared to kids who go outside.
I'm sure there's epidemiology that would suggest that the further you are from the equator,
does that imply that you have a greater risk of nearsightedness just based on the light part of
this argument? Yes. There is some data to look at that that shows that. And not only that,
they've taken children and given them equal intervals of outdoor activity, but the ones who
had noontime outdoor activity did better than the ones who were outdoors at 8 a.m. where there was
less illumination. And we know from animal models that it is illumination that is critical in this
dopamine release. So, you know, does that mean we need more skylights in classrooms or more windows?
We need more natural light. Could we artificially mimic some of the sunlight by making these rooms
brighter and and prevent some of this myopia epidemic? Is a photon a photon a photon? I mean,
does it I mean, I don't think that it's known, frankly, Peter, whether that's the case,
because there are difference. There's a whole spectrum of light. So is the blue light more
important? This is tangential. And we'll talk about this. I know. But blue light, you hear all
this negativity about blue light. Blue light is critical for wakefulness, for attention, for,
I think, for preventing myopia. And by the way, when we say myopia nearsightedness,
it's not just the inconvenience of wearing glasses or contact lenses or having laser vision
correction when you're 23 years old. There are pathologies that are much more common in very
nearsighted patients compared to the general population. It's much more common to see cataract
formation in myopic patients. They get something called myopic macular degeneration. They're at
risk for glaucoma. They're at risk for tears and detachments of the retina. So it's not just the
inconvenience of spectacles. These are disease associated conditions. So going back to my
evolutionary question, it's quite possible that over hundreds of millions of years, any deficit
in vision that would have prevented you from reproducing or impaired your ability to escape
prey would have taken that out. So from a genetic standpoint, our vision should be very good.
And in non-literate societies, it typically was. So if you look at hunter-gatherer tribes,
there is no nearsightedness. There are no Kalahari Bushmen with spectacles. It just doesn't happen.
This is amazing. This suggests that because my parents wore glasses, I should wear glasses is
not true. Or is there an epigenetic part of this where it can-
Both. There is a genetic component. And if you look at siblings of individuals who
wear spectacles, there is a higher incidence of myopia or hyperopia.
But that could be susceptibility, right?
It could be susceptibility.
And then the environmental trigger is what's going to do it in anyone?
And we don't know whether parents of reading children were reading children themselves.
So it's hard to separate out the genetic component, but there does seem to be a genetic
component as well. But the environmental component seems to be way stronger and more powerful.
So if you take parents who don't wear spectacles and you put their child in a dark room and give
them an electronic device or a book or whatever it is and have that child focus it near for hours
on end, odds are they're much more at risk for developing nearsightedness.
So when I just think about this hood lens of my kids, so my wife has perfect vision, I don't.
What is my diopter? I think I'm minus three and minus four.
It's about right.
Yeah.
So what does that mean in terms of the 20 scale? I'm 20-
You're probably like, it depends on how much you squint and look at the eye chart. We honestly
don't really attach a lot of significance to the 2100 or 2080, whatever it is. You're probably
in that ballpark 2100 maybe.
But I'm clearly at the point where without contacts, I can't drive, I can't do anything.
Right.
I mean, I know some people who are minus 15, they literally can't, they have to put glasses
near the bedside.
That's right.
I'll spend the first hour of the day without contact lenses.
That's right. Because you could probably, things are very well-
It's easier for me to read without my contacts.
Very, things for you are very well in focus at a typical normal reading distance.
Right.
So your eyes have been tuned like postnatally for near work. That's in your development,
you must have spent a lot of time reading or doing near tasks.
Well, that's the thing I was thinking about. I grew up in Canada, so from a light perspective,
it wasn't so great. Two months of no light whatsoever. But I didn't watch TV much as a
kid, maybe 30 minutes a day. I was mostly outdoors, so I don't know how much of it.
But I also didn't, I'll tell you, this is funny. I didn't need my first pair of glasses till college.
So it could also be that this happened later in my life as a result of more book work.
For sure. So the classic example is we see law students who have great vision when they
enter law school and then they read for 12 hours a day and then they come in and they say,
you know, I think my vision's going. And you look at them and sure enough, they become nearsighted.
And that's not rare in many graduate school situations where there's just grinding reading
for hours on end.
So when I think about our kids, because now I just think, well, what can I,
it's too late for me, right? But so.
Get them outside.
So they are. So fortunately they live outside. But when they're inside, they're obsessed with
playing with Legos and trains and trucks and, you know, I mean, that's near, right? So is it that,
hey, there's nothing wrong with that, but you just have to make sure they're spending a couple hours
outside a day?
I think the data would suggest that good illumination would be helpful as opposed to poor illumination.
Okay.
But, you know, you don't want to discourage near activities because those are really important
development.
That was the flip true. So you mentioned that hunter gatherers or illiterate societies
who are out by definition outside all the time.
Right.
There's no such thing as nearsightedness in them. Do they develop farsightedness?
Not really. I think that they are fairly well tuned if we want to use that term to distance
vision, to prey hunting and things like that. So distance vision is very well tuned. Now,
there's a whole host of other problems that come into play. Once you've outlived your genetic
usefulness, you've reproduced and you've imparted your knowledge onto the next generation, you can
go ahead and get cataracts because you're done, you know, genetically useful, your utility.
So the cataract is sort of like atherosclerosis, functionally, which is it really, it's the one
thing that really has no bearing on your reproductive capacity, but is otherwise inevitable
to our species.
It seems to be fairly inevitable to our species. And I've, as I mentioned earlier, I just haven't
seen patients in their 70s typically that don't have some cataract formation. Now, there are
patients who are 80 that are still functioning with cataracts, but the optical clarity of their
lenses has degraded to the point that it's not the way it was when they were 20. Maybe their
visual needs are significantly reduced at that age. But if you took an 80 year old lens and you
put it in a 20 year old person, they would be shocked at how poor their vision is.
That's really interesting. Now, earlier you mentioned that we think that senescent cells
are at least the soluble secretory products of senescent cells are probably playing a role in this.
Well, I think in the lens, it's mostly that the lens proteins are degrading or becoming damaged
over time, maybe with UV light, because we know light exposure is certainly related to cataract
formation, as are some of the other things that I mentioned, like glucose going into the lens,
corticosteroid use. We don't know what it is specifically about trauma that causes a premature
loss of clarity of the lens proteins. The trauma ones got me worried because I boxed for so long.
I took way too many hits to the head. I hope that doesn't come back to, I mean, I've already been,
I'm worried about that for other reasons. Let's just put it this way. The cataract would be the
easiest thing to fix. Yeah. Cataract surgery today is like a four or five minute procedure
and it's astonishingly effective. How often does one need to repeat that surgery?
Cataract surgery typically is not repeated. It's a once in a lifetime deal.
And what you're noticing is like you're wearing glasses that are dirty. Is that effectively what
the patient with cataract is experiencing? I think the first thing they notice is probably
changes in their night vision, glare, halos, streaks off of lights at night,
problems with contrast sensitivity for those who can appreciate that loss of contrast.
Those are really early signs of cataract formation. So then the patient comes to you,
they're 74 years old or let's say it's sooner. They're 70 years old. More like 64 or 54.
Okay. And you're telling them, Hey, Billy, you've got cataracts. Right. We're going to just ride
this out until you tell me you've had enough. Typically we let the patient decide when it's
the right time for them to have the surgery. Once we determine that the cataract is visually
significant, there are people who elect to have their cataracts removed earlier than they really
need them removed as a means of getting rid of their glasses prescription, because now the lenses,
the implant lenses that we put in to replace the cataract have advanced in function to the point
that they can fix the near vision as well as the distance vision as you know, the astigmatism,
the nearsightedness, the farsightedness, the presbyopia, all those things that we've been
talking about, they're all correctable with artificial lenses that we put in the eye to
replace the cataract. Wow. But earlier when you talked about during your residency, the bread and
butter was one of the pieces of bread and butter of your practice would have been cataract surgery
that didn't involve intraocular lenses. No, it did. It did. And there's a fascinating history
about the evolution of intraocular lenses. But back in those days, the implant lenses that were
put in were simply designed to give the patient good vision with spectacles, just to replace the
cloudy lens with something that was in the ballpark of good distance vision.
Sorry, I need to take a step back because I'm actually kind of confused.
Does all cataract surgery involve the placement of an extra lens?
Yes, that's correct. There are exceptions to nitpickers who will listen to this, but
virtually every cataract surgery that we perform involves the removal of the cataract and replacing
it with an artificial lens. Again, you'll have to pardon my ignorance. Does that mean removing
the entire lens or removing a diseased part of the lens that has a cataract?
So remember our analogy of the M&M candy? Yes.
So we leave the shell. Right. We open a hole in the front of the shell. Yes.
We take out all the chocolate and then we now we have kind of like a flattened bowl. Looks like a
Japanese teapot flattened. Yes.
And we put the implant lens in that bowl and that holds the implant in place.
Is it a viscous fluid that gets hardened or is it a hard object that goes directly in?
It's actually a bendable plastic object and the bendability of it.
Is what allows it to get in?
Allows us to fold it up and put it through a tiny incision and then it opens up.
That was a very big advancement. When did that happen?
1980s was when that began to become. What happened before this?
So this is a really amazing series of stories, but I'll abbreviate them in the interests of
time. But in the old days, in the ancient world, if you had cataracts,
the way they dealt with it is that they would just poke the lens of the eye backward and it
would drop down into the bottom of the eye so that you now had a clear optical pathway, again,
to let light in. And this took someone who was functionally blind and allowed them to see shapes.
So that was better than. Right. Because you don't have a lens.
So there's no way you can focus. You can't focus. All you can see are shapes.
But it's basically like taking someone who has no light transmission and saying,
we're going to let an unfocused light go through. Right. So some light's better than no light.
So that's what happened in Hammurabi time. Amazing that they under. I'm always amazed.
We look at that now and we say that's barbaric. Yeah.
The fact that they knew enough to do that is kind of amazing.
They probably tried everything else first. And that was the one that.
They probably dissected cadaveric lenses and tried to figure this out.
Yeah. And there are there have been artifacts uncovered that I think a lot of them were made
out of gold, but they would take a gold needle and poke it through the cornea. And then it was called
couching the procedure. They would just poke the lens and it would detach from its ligamentous
attachments and then drop down into the bottom of the cavity of the eye. And you see some of these
artifacts from Egypt. This was done in China. It was certainly done in ancient Greece. There are,
that was how you dealt with cataracts back then. By the way, it's just worth pausing for a moment
to to reflect. Like, so we're, if you're talking about the pharaohs, you're talking about what,
5,000 years ago, right? This is not in an evolutionary timescale. That's a, that's a
pittance. My profession is an old one. And you think like it would be better to be the
poorest person on earth today than to be the pharaoh of Egypt 5,000 years ago.
Yeah. I think in many ways.
Certainly it would be better to be in the bottom 10 percentile economically today than the top 10
percentile 5,000 years ago. If the best you have to your cataracts is some guy sticking a hot poker
in your eye. That's right. So then you fast forward to right after World War II. And there's
an ophthalmologist in the UK named Harold Ridley. And he notices that some of the RAF fighters
would have fragments of their canopy, their plexiglass canopy shatter when they were fired
upon. And these things would actually get inside the eyeballs shards of, of plexiglass
essentially would be inside the eyeball. And the dilemma was, well, what do we do with this?
And he learned very early on that these fragments were biologically inert, that the eye was perfectly
happy and people could walk around the rest of their lives with plexiglass inside their eyeball.
And that's a shard of sharp plexiglass. So, and this is one of those out of-
And this is in part because the lens is so immune privileged. This is-
Well, this is a foreign object that has now entered the eye, not necessarily in the human lens. It
might even be in the vitreous cavity or in the front of the eye.
So there was something about sharp plexiglass that didn't-
But there's something about plexiglass. So the light bulb goes off that, wait, you can put
plexiglass, which is essentially polymethyl methacrylate, you can put that in the eye and
the body doesn't really care that it's there, doesn't mount an immune response. So in Ridley's
book, which I've read, it's really amazing, but some intern asked him, well, when you take this
cataract out, are you going to replace it with a new lens? And he looked at this young intern in
a very British fashion, I'm assuming, and just said, that's the stupidest question I've ever
heard. And then he went home and thought, wait a minute, that's brilliant. We should replace it.
And then they lathed a lens from some spectacle maker that was about the size and shape of
the human lens. And actually threw eight of these in patients. And there's amazing footage of,
I think one of the first operations, they dropped the lens on the floor. And of course,
it's the only one they had. So they pick it up and rinse it off and they, it's fine. They put it in
and these patients did shockingly well. And this was viewed as heresy and there was 20 years of
your blinding people. But eventually the technology won out and it became.
So there were bad outcomes, presumably.
I think in the early days, for sure. There must have been for sure. And there were,
but like any new technology, the first iteration of it is probably
terrible and maybe just a little bit less terrible than the alternative.
And now it's a ubiquitously.
So I never thought, because basically I didn't realize until you said it that
polymethyl methacrylate is all over the body in terms of joints, like, and you do a, you know,
when you replace a knee joint, right? That the tibial plateau I think is made out of
polymethyl methacrylate. So presumably there's something about it that is just
invisible to the immune system.
Well, we don't, and we don't use that material anymore because it's stiff. It is not deformable.
So you had to, you had to, in the old days, you had to make a fairly large incision to get the,
to get this thing in first of all, to get the cataract out and then to get
the implant lens in to converging technologies made that go away.
The number one was we were able to take the cataract out through a tiny incision
because you break it and see, too, we break it up, we emulsify it essentially with ultrasound.
Now we even sometimes use a femtosecond laser to break up parts of it.
But the bottom line is that we can remove the cataract through about a two something
millimeter incision, which is very small, like the thickness of a pencil lead, basically.
And we can now take these implant lenses and fold them up and put them through that same tiny
incision. And then they can open up and be exactly where you want them to be.
Now, why is it important for the incision to be small? Well, if you make a big incision,
obviously it takes longer to heal, but it induces a stigmatism. So you want the incision to be tiny.
So does the using your M&M analogy, does the coating on the surface of the M&M grow back?
No, it does not.
So it's it's fixed. Whatever hole you put in there, they're stuck with.
Yeah, it's fixed. Now, sometimes the coating, the M&M candy shell can begin to opacify
after surgery, and we can treat that in the office with a laser where we can just disrupt
that coating.
So this has got to be like, my mom, actually, my mom's 72nd birthday is today. I don't know
if she's had any issues with cataracts, but if not, she's due for them.
My dad has, he's 83. I'm trying to think, he must have had surgery then by now.
Odds are.
Yeah, odds are.
So I can't believe I've really talked about this with him, but is it, it must be a game changer
for a patient to come out of the clinic or the OR whenever that wherever these, is this,
do you do this in your, well, you have an OR in your office.
We do, but cataract surgery, we do in an ambulatory surgery center. But you know,
maybe that your dad didn't talk about it because it was such a non-event, you know, you go in for
cataract surgery and the next day you're kind of back to your regular activities.
But wouldn't it have been a big event in terms of his ability to see?
For sure.
Especially now that the implant lenses can correct the near vision and the distance vision.
So that in addition to the added clarity from just removing the cataract, they patients
typically have this benefit of not needing.
So this is a procedure we should all be looking forward to when it comes.
Like you're going to know if I would go that far. I mean,
it's still surgery. There are risks associated with it.
What are the biggest risks?
No, I think that the number one thing we think about is infection, but it's extraordinarily
unusual to see an infection.
What's the rate?
Less than one in 10,000 cases where you'll see a serious infection.
It's like any other surgery in the body. You look for bleeding,
damage to the inside of the eye. You have to keep tabs on the pressure.
It's basically everything that you would look for if you were taking out an appendix. You're
also dealing with in the eye.
What fraction of patients do not have a material improvement in their vision or have some
deterioration of even another subset of vision? So yes, you've taken away my cataract.
I can see better in the sense of clarity, but oh my God, I became abjectly nearsighted as a result
of it.
Yeah, I think that's pretty unusual because the science behind getting the prescription
correct or very close to correct is pretty advanced.
And tell me what that entails. So if I came in and right now I'm in a cataract,
what are you assessing microscopically to make it so I'm getting the impression not everybody
gets the same lens?
No, they do not. And some of these lenses are expensive. So and they involve the patient
having to pay some extra money to get it.
More money gets you what?
I mean, I think the more money people pay, the more spectacle independence they get.
In terms of optical quality, all the lenses are.
How much does a lens cost? Or payer, I guess, since you're doing both.
I'm the wrong person to ask, honestly, I don't even know.
But directionally, if somebody has to pay out of pocket for one of these.
If they're getting just like regular cataract surgery and there is no attempt to get rid of
spectacles, it's probably going to be completely covered by their health insurance.
And if they're saying I want to go premium all the way, get rid of my class.
It could be thousands of dollars out of pocket if they want to get rid of all their spectacle
and dependence. And what patients will tell us is they'll say, well, what else
do I use every waking moment of my life forever?
They could go on a vacation for a week or two and spend that money and then the vacation is over.
But we find that patients value, as we pointed out earlier, their vision,
they value it pretty highly and their independence, I think, is really what they're trying to preserve.
This is this is a I had no idea that when look at look at how much I didn't know.
I didn't know you were I literally this is how dumb I am.
I thought cataract surgery is literally removing the sort of crud that's in the lens.
And I don't know, I just naively assumed it would like the good stuff would grow back.
Right.
Never knew you were putting another lens in, let alone that you could actually
use the new lens as a way to correct other visual defects.
That's right. And, you know, so the technology has evolved to the point where you can actually
correct those those those spectacle requirements. Now, many of our patients don't really care about
spectacle independence. They just want to see well. And that's easy to achieve as well.
But as these lenses have gotten better, our capabilities have gotten better.
If I needed cataract surgery today, right, knowing my diopter, the minus four, minus three business
with the slightest stigmatism, although I still haven't figured out how that's impacting my vision.
Right. I guess I sort of have it just but we'll come back to that.
If if you were going to swap out my lens, would you be able to correct the deficit of my magnitude?
We could. Yes. Yeah. Now, you know, the problem with a lot of these
eyes is they're they are attached quite firmly to people. And sometimes the patient's set of
expectations can be unrealistic in terms of what we can deliver. And so we have to really
carefully educate them on, well, what can these lenses actually do? Am I going to see like a
perfect hunter at dusk while still be able still being able to read up close? And maybe the answer
is yes. Maybe the answer is no. Can you tune it? Like, for example, if I said, you know, Stephen,
I don't care if I have to keep wearing contacts, I would love to not have to wear reading glasses.
Right. Because if I'm going to be honest with you, the reading glasses are a way bigger pain in my butt
than contacts because I just put my contacts in in the morning and take them out at night.
Right. Really doesn't phase me. Yeah.
The reading glasses annoy the hell out of me because I never remember to bring them to
restaurants ever. So I'm shining a phone light at my menu and putting it out here and or I'll be
reading the book to my kid at night and I'm like, oh, hang on, buddy, I got to go get my glasses.
Like that's actually more of an imposition of my life.
Yeah. It's not an unusual request where we can intentionally set your vision for near or leave
it for near. You can certainly do that. It's just an optical calculation to set the point of focus
where you want it to be. You asked earlier about, well, what happens if I come into the clinic? What
gets measured? Yeah.
Well, one of the first things that we have to do is make sure that the surface of the cornea
is tuned up from a dry eye standpoint because that those dry eye, you know, patients, they're
the surface of their corneas. It's not optically pristine. It's a little distorted.
Do contact lenses make that better or worse?
It makes it a lot worse and it can throw off our measurements, which can throw off our calculations
because it's kind of pretty simple Newtonian physics, right? If you know the length of the
eyeball and you know the curvature of the front of the eye and you know the index of refraction of
the stuff that's inside the eyeball, how bendy the material is, light bendy the material is,
you can correct for as long as you know where the implant lens is going to reside,
you can correct for placing that image on the retina.
So the more perfect the shape of the cornea, right?
The better that calculation. That's right. And that is probably the weak link in the measurement,
in the set of measurements that we take, because we can measure the length of the eye,
we can measure the length of the eye from front to back very accurately with lasers.
So we can sort of, it's almost like a sonar, but with light, we can bounce a beam off of the back
of the retina and we know exactly how long the eyeball is. And we know roughly where the
implant lens is going to rest when we put it in. And if we know some other dimensions of the eye
and use the front curvature as one of our pieces of data, we can predict what power implant lens
to put in. Wow. Okay. So is there anything left on the IOL front or is there another
huge step function of technology that's going to be coming there? Because it doesn't,
it already sounds pretty remarkable. Well, in the mid 2000s, I started getting involved in
product design for a type of implant lens that could actually zoom focus front to back, not
a bifocal or a trifocal where you had different zones of focus, but a lens that could actually
move or change its shape. And I developed an implant that we put in humans in multiple
clinical trials outside the United States. And we found that we could zoom focus kind of like
the human lens would, but the multifocals, which are the lenses we've been talking about,
they're like bifocals, trifocal implants surpassed the capability of what we could achieve with the
lenses that I designed. And until someone comes out with a focusing implant lens that can zoom focus
with the same degree of power as the bifocal and trifocal implants, it's not going to be successful.
But if we had a lens that could change its shape or change its position and zoom focus seamlessly
from near to far, that would be a game changer. And I assume that there's no, you don't take the
lens from a young person who's passed away and ever try to implant that into,
it doesn't work the way a cornea does. That's right. That's right. In fact, if you violate
that capsule of the lens, the lens immediately becomes cloudy. So here's an example, let's say
that you talked about trauma. So a typical scenario is somebody is working with a weed
eater or whatever, a weed whacker. Yeah. And a piece of a shard of rock or glass or something
goes through the cornea and embeds itself in the lens. And it might even be an optically unimportant
part of the lens. Maybe it's off to the side, but once that capsule has been pierced, inevitably,
lens protein starts leaking out, inflammatory cells become-
You violated the privilege site.
It's no longer privileged and within days you start to see a cataract.
And they need a new lens.
They need a new lens.
For sure.
Do they need a new cornea, by the way?
Well, they sometimes do, but oddly enough, sometimes an object will pass through the cornea.
And because it's traveling at such a high velocity, it's usually sterile and it'll go through the
cornea and embed itself in the lens or the iris or wherever. And some of these objects can be
left alone. But if the cornea has been damaged sufficiently that it's no longer able to
transmit a clear image, then it has to be replaced.
Wow. So let's talk a little bit about corneal pathology. So everyone's probably heard about
corneal abrasions. It's a very important reason. It's one of the few things I remember, right?
In surgery, you always tape the patient's eyes shut because you don't want an eyelid flipping
open in the middle of surgery and nobody's paying attention and a drape is running over
the eye and scraping the cornea. Is that the biggest insult that we think about for the cornea?
I mean, that's probably one of the more common ones. If you think about that eye that's
being left open in surgery while a patient is asleep and not blinking, that's sort of the
extreme version of dry eye where the cornea has completely dried out. And even if you weren't to,
if you didn't abrade the cornea, those epithelial cells would be so damaged by exposure,
just by not being continuously bathed in tears, that they would be severely damaged.
So dry eye is intimately related to corneal abrasion because you lack the lubrication that
normally takes place to prevent that type of thing.
And how much of an issue is that in our society?
Dry eye?
Yeah.
Oh, it's enormous. If you think about the things that cause dry eye...
I mean, there's obviously lots of medications that do it through anticholinergic side effects.
Absolutely. But think about all the antihistamines. Hormonal influences are profound in terms of dry
eye. Anything that causes dry mouth can also cause dry eye. In that sense, auto-immune conditions
can cause dry eye, so showgrins, rheumatoid arthritis. All of the connective tissue diseases
have a dry eye component to them. Perturbations of thyroid metabolism cause dry eye.
But a lot of women suffer from dry eye because I think it's mostly the influence of,
honestly, a lack of testosterone that is probably most intimately linked to dry eye. But we see
women on hormone replacement therapy that have miserable dry eye.
So you think the addition of estrogen and progesterone post-menopause could be an issue,
or do you think it's still just the lack of testosterone that you use?
I think it's the lack of testosterone.
Why do you think that?
I think it has to do with the health of the epithelial cells on the conjunctiva.
But there may be also influences on the secretion of tears from the lacrimal gland as well.
But dry eye is, I mean, I don't want to say it's universal in patients who are over a certain age,
but it's extremely common.
So what type of eye drops should we be using? How do we apply them?
Well, it really depends on the type of dry eye that you have, believe it or not, because there are,
we think of tears as just salt water, but that's really not what it is. It's really an emulsion
of lipids and mucin and all sorts of immune modulators and antibodies and all sorts of
things in this soup. Some of it is just what we refer to as the aqueous component of tears,
really just the salt water. But the sebaceous glands that are in the eyelids, we call them
myvomian glands, where the lashes come out of the skin.
Though the secretions of those myvomian glands can become dysfunctional, and that
means that the tears have a hard time gliding over the surface of the cornea, and that can lead to
dry eye. So all sorts of things that cause myvomian gland dysfunction, some of that
relates to diet. And some people believe that a diet high in saturated fats is more
likely to cause myvomian gland dysfunction. Certainly colder weather, like the sebaceous
glands in your skin respond better to sunlight, to heat. In a cold environment, those can become
plugged up, and bacteria can build up along the eyelid margin, causing inflammation. And when
there's inflammation, the lacrimal gland shuts down even more. So dry eye has really multi,
it's got a number of different causes.
Now, when I think about eye drops, I think about sort of the dropper that you try to get in your
eye, and you never get it, at least I can never get it in my eye, because I end up blinking all
the time. So then you try and drop it into the corner, and then let it sit up. But then I've
also seen like the mist, right? Yeah. So tell me about the different ways that one even applies.
Yeah, I think those are really the main ones. I mean, eye drops work pretty well for most people,
and that there are some mist sprays that, believe it or not, you can spray some of these, there's
one hypochlorous acid compound that you spray on the lids, and it sort of migrates into the eye,
and actually is very good for reducing the bacterial counts at the lid margin, which is
part of that inflammation cycle that is so critical in dry eye. But most artificial tears
come in the form of an eye drop. And that's okay. That's fine. And it's okay if you can't manage to
keep your eye open, or should you force it and hold your eye open? I mean, at some point,
you got to get it in the eyeball. Yeah. But that's one of just a whole bunch of strategies that we use
for treating dry eye. We add artificial tears, but we think that there's a very significant
benefit from supplementing with omega-3 fatty acids, especially high doses of omega-3 fatty acids,
and omega-6, certain types of omega-6. Yeah, which omega-6 is it again?
Well, it's what you'd find in blackcurrant seed oil, or borage oil, or evening primrose oil.
That's the GLA, gamma-linoleic acid. So that is very helpful in dry eye. And interestingly,
there was a very large randomized clinical trial looking at omega-3
supplementation in pretty high doses. Do you remember how high?
Three grams of actual EPA NDA checked. Correct. Yes. And the placebo arm was olive oil,
which is presumed not to have a benefit in dry eye. And it showed no superiority of omega-3
compared to olive oil. However, there's been a lot of criticism of this study.
It's called the DREAM study. It was put on by the National Eye Institute.
It turns out that if you bring people into the eye doctor four times a year,
everybody gets better. Their compliance with artificial tears gets better.
And were they using artificial tears?
They were. They were able to use whatever they would normally use to treat their dry eye.
So I guess like in the same way that if you go to the dentist four times a year, all of a sudden
you're flossing before you go to the dentist. Both arms of the study got better. But it is our
very strong clinical impression that omega-3s in high doses help with dry eye, primarily from a,
I think an anti-inflammatory standpoint. Let's go back to light for a minute.
So I've got some friends who are so fanatical about the importance of light that they never
wear sunglasses. Now, and I'm kind of, there's a part of me that thinks light is, wow, it's got
to be really important. I think about all the time I get outside and the light, it's great.
It's great. But I also like wearing sunglasses because it's a part of me that's sort of afraid
that too much UV light is damaging. So what's the balance of sunglasses versus not? And I want to
talk about polarized glasses or do they matter and all that kind of stuff?
Yeah. I mean, clearly there's a dose related phenomenon here. Too much light is bad,
too little light is bad. What's the right amount? I tend to recommend sunglasses for air patients.
Let's start with just the most obvious one. The most common site of skin cancer,
the lower lid, lots of basal cells, squamous cell carcinomas,
sunglasses certainly reduce the incidence of that. Then we look at the photo aging of the lens itself.
I think it's not a bad thing to delay the onset of cataract. And then the retina, macular
degeneration. I think there's pretty clear evidence that UV exposure, particularly of the
magnitude that you can get outside is associated with an elevated risk of age-related macular
degeneration. Now, do we see this in hunter-gatherers who have otherwise amazing habits and therefore
tend to be relatively privileged from optical pathology?
So the confounding variable there is that northern European ancestry is a risk factor
for macular degeneration, probably because of the lack of pigment. Because that pigment is
protecting that very vulnerable vascularized component of the back of the eye.
Oh, wait. So the darker your eye, the more protected you are?
Absolutely. In the same way that your skin is more protected or more melanin.
So light-eyed patients have more light getting in from the front of the eye.
So their iris literally blocks less light hitting the lens.
Yes. And the retina has less pigment behind it. And so the vascular supply to the retina is more
exposed to UV light. And that's the way it's evolved because they've been in environments
that don't have as much light available. But if you live near the equator or your
ancestry is from that area, then you're going to have more pigment from an evolutionary standpoint.
But I understand the fanaticism about wanting to have lots of blue light or bright light,
but I think that it probably is fanaticism. I don't think that, at least if your goal is
to reproduce, teach your children until they're 15 and then die, then get all the light you want.
But if your goal is longevity or the postponement of senescence, certainly ocular senescence,
I think it makes sense to protect your eyes from UV light.
So for example, you came over here today where it's middle of the day in Austin.
It's a typical Austin beautiful sunny day. You're driving with sunglasses?
Oh, for sure. Absolutely. 100%.
Okay. So you're in sunglasses when you're outside.
I am.
After what time in the morning?
If I'm outside and my vision is better with sunglasses, it's not worse with sunglasses
than I'm going to wear sunglasses. I don't wear them at night and I don't wear them
if it's very early in the morning. But if conditions allow, I'm going to wear them.
We talk about with sunscreen, the importance of you're still susceptible to sunburn in the
clouds. If you're at the beach all day and it's an overcast day, do you recommend people still
wear sunglasses even if it's not a clear blue day?
For sure. And sometimes, this came up during the recent eclipse because people were saying,
okay, I'll look at the eclipse. This one was a few years ago. I'll just use sunglasses. Well,
that's actually much, much, much, much worse because you're increasing the aperture of your
pupil because everything is dim, but you're letting through all this very damaging light.
Because no amount of sunglasses could block a straight shot looking at the sun.
Correct. So I think even on a cloudy day, I do recommend that people wear sunglasses.
Yeah. Okay. What are polarized glasses doing?
As you know, polarized lenses are essentially, it's a lens that has a bunch of lines drawn in
it all in the same direction so that some of the light is blocked. But in one meridian,
all the light effectively is let through. But perpendicular to that, none of the light gets
through. And polarized lenses have some pluses and minuses. One of the big minuses I found is that
a lot of the displays in your cars now, you get this really messed up cross-polarized effect
where the light coming off of the screen is polarized. And if you look at it through polarized
glasses, if you tilt your head, it gets brighter and darker. You cannot see it. And by the same
token, many of the windows or winds, I don't know if it's the windshield or the side windows,
but I've noticed wearing polarized lenses, which I only wear for fly fishing now,
that I would get these very weird effects by tilting my head because of the cross-polarized
effect. Essentially, you have two different polarized filters and it's letting through
variable amounts of light depending upon the orientation of your head and your eye and the
spectacles. I have found myself more comfortable in non-polarized lenses unless I'm on water.
The issue there is that the light bouncing off the water or theoretically a highway,
it's all pretty much a lot of it is polarized in one direction. That's the rationale behind
polarized lenses. And for seeing a fish, if you're a fly fisherman, for sure that's helpful.
I fly fish for the first time last month. And I could see getting into that. That is an art.
For sure it is. But in terms of polarization, there's no evidence that I've seen that
polarization versus non-polarization in sunglasses helps. It's really the UV filter
that is helpful for what we're doing in terms of protection of eye health. You could wear clear
spectacles as long as they had UV protection and still achieve the benefit of sunglasses.
Yeah, that's an important point, right? It's not the tint.
It's not the tint. It's the ultraviolet protection.
And it's the same as true in a car, right? I mean, the glass of the car is assuming you don't have
tinted windows, is still getting rid of most of the UV light.
Most of the UV, but not all. And dermatologists tell us this, that in truck drivers who are in
North America, they see more UV damage to the left side of their face than the right side of their
face by far. And in the UK, it's exactly the opposite. So even car and truck windows let some
UV light in. Okay, so let's now go back to the standard situation of nearsightedness.
So person comes in, they're nearsighted. Decision one is, I'm going to correct this with glasses
versus contacts. We'll start to talk about corrective surgery in a moment.
Yeah.
Do you nudge people one way or the other? I mean, I wore glasses for the first
four years that I needed corrective lenses. So that meant basically college.
Trying to think in med school. I think by med school, I was wearing contacts.
By residency, I went back to glasses because the call, you just couldn't be predictable about when
you were going to put them in. So I did all of residency in glasses. And then since that time,
I've been a hundred percent contacts. Yeah, it's funny because we'll see residents or fellows or
whatever, and they come in and on their one day off and they're seeing one of our optometrists.
When did you last have your contacts out? And they're like, I think it was June 30th,
right before my internship started four months ago. That sort of thing. And so as you know,
residents are notoriously bad about their own health hygiene because you're so busy. But
to answer your question more directly, I don't really see patients for regular eye exams myself.
But so the people who see me are seeking surgery already. But in terms of, hey, I'm at a cocktail
party and someone says, should I wear glasses or contact lenses or spectacles? Well, the safest
thing you can do is wear spectacles for sure. Wait, do you use glasses and spectacles
interchangeably? Yes. When I say spectacles, I'm referring to glasses to distinguish them from
stuff you drink water out of. So yeah, spectacles is the term of art for glasses.
So if you were thinking of some sort of exotic type of-
Yes, I was like, oh, there must be some glasses, but then there's a spectacle.
It's like down at ye olde spectacle shoppy.
Something like that. Anytime my wife talks about pushing the gas pedal, I'm like, throttle.
It's a throttle. It's throttle application. We need some gas. No, we need petrol. Okay.
Right. It's gasoline or petrol. It's not gas. Gas refers to natural gas. When you push that
thing, it's throttle application. Yes. Okay. No. Yeah. We're hard to live with, aren't we?
Okay. So spectacles and glasses are synonymous. That's the safest thing you can do. They're
going to work every time and there's essentially no risk associated with them. There's a big debate
about what the next safest thing is. Is it contact lens wear for 10 years where you might be
susceptible to infection or is it laser vision correction? But I tend to say if you're doing
fine with spectacles or contact lenses, do that. I was kind of hoping you were going to tell me,
get laser eye surgery because there's a part of me that just wants to do it for the sake of doing
it and getting rid of context once and for all. But you were very much in the camp of,
you asked me a bunch of questions. And at the end, your conclusion was these don't seem to be an
inconvenience for you. You've never once had an eye infection. You tolerate them really well.
They don't seem to bug you. Right. And you like your near vision. Yeah. Yeah. And so if you were to
correct your distance vision with laser vision correction and set both of your eyes for distance,
you would lose that near vision. So until maybe I get my cataracts fixed, then we can tweak them.
That's a whole other story. So let's talk about the advent of laser eye surgery. So I think
everybody listening to this has heard of LASIK. Yes. Most people probably haven't heard of PRK.
Right. Which we'll talk about. When did PRK came along first? Yeah, a little bit earlier. Yes.
And that was when? In the 90s? Right. So the approvals for PRK and LASIK were in the mid-90s,
1995, 1996. The first procedures were actually done in, the first procedure was PRK and it was done
in New Orleans. And I happened to be in training there in New Orleans. And this was performed by
a physician called Marguerite McDonald. And she did the very first treatment on a human eye. The
way this came about was that eczema lasers, which are the kind of lasers we use in LASIK and in PRK,
which stands for Photorefractive Keratectomy. Eczema lasers are and were used to etch microchips.
And an engineer at IBM realized that you could change the curvature or you could make cuts in
human tissue. And because of the nature of this ultraviolet laser, there was essentially no
bystander trauma to the adjacent tissue. So the tissue could be etched or cut. And because it
generated no heat, there was no immune response generated typically. So that these incisions or
whatever it was, they would heal without scarring. And I can remember vividly looking at the very
first patients that were in an FDA clinical trial that had PRK. And I was astonished that
you could look at them under a microscope and you could not detect that surgery had been done. That
was really a revelation for me where I just saw these eyes that looked like normal eyes. And the
only difference was the patients could see. So the first eyes were treated in 89 and then that led to
FDA approval in 95. And the treatment in 89 was part of clinical trials, Emes. For sure.
It was part of a clinical trial. So let's explain what PRK does before LASIK. Yeah. So the way it
works is that you have the cornea, again, like the glass on a watch, the thing a contact lens
would sit on. And let's say that the person is nearsighted. The cornea in that person is a little
bit too steep to focus the light perfectly on their retina. Another way of looking at it is that-
And again, the cornea is about two millimeters thick? No, it's about a half a millimeter thick.
It's about 500 microns, maybe a little more. So either the cornea is a little too steep or the
eyeball is a little too long, probably a little of both. We can't change the length of the eye.
By the way, the length of the eye is the one that we talked about being somewhat malleable during
development. That's right. And is the corneal shape hereditary? Is that the hereditary component
of vision? The corneal shape doesn't seem to change that much throughout life. It's the length
of the eye that changes, unless there's a pathological condition that changes the cornea.
So since we can't change the length of the eye, what we can change is the curvature of the front
of the eye. And if you think about it, you don't have to change the curvature that much. Think
about how thin a contact lens is. How thin is it? I mean, I know I can feel it, but I don't know
what that is. Is that also about half a mil? No, it's less. I honestly don't know. I don't
work in that world, but it's pretty thin. I mean, it's like a little piece of cellophane. If you
think about like an AccuView disposable- Yeah, it probably just feels thicker because of all the
goo on it. Yeah. So I'm sure someone will correct me and say, you should know how thick a contact
lens is. I don't, but it's thin, right? It's pretty thin. So it's just that little curvature
that needs to change in order to focus the light on the right. And just to use an extreme example,
so you take somebody who has a very minimal degree of nearsightedness. So let's say their
diopter is minus one, then you contrast the lens that they would wear to the lens that's someone
who's near blind at like a minus 10. Is the minus one creating more of a bend or less of a bend?
Meaning is it a bigger curve or a smaller curve? So the person who's minus one, their cornea is
less potent in bending light than the minus 10 person is. That minus 10 means their eye is 10
units too strong and we need to reduce the power of the eye. So how would you fix that with a laser?
Well, first of all, how do you fix that with the contact? So their lens has to look-
The curvature of their lens has to be effectively flatter than their eyeball. So you need a larger
radius of curvature or a flatter eye. I got it. Okay. So you would actually build up the outside
of the lens. Exactly right. Okay. So it's even easier to explain with laser vision correction.
So let's take a crude analogy, which is that the cornea is made out of wood and I have some sand
paper. Well, I can sand down the center of the wooden cornea and make the flatter. To take
the flatter off. And I'm removing some sawdust goes away and now that is flatter. And so it's
less powerful in bending the light and I can focus that on the retina. So in your minus one
example, we would remove about 20 microns of tissue. That's not a lot. You figure out human
hair is about 50 microns. So like less than half of one human hair's thickness.
And PRK does that directly. With an eczema laser on the very front part of the cornea. So
we, the way we do it is that the very front coating of the cornea is called the epithelium.
It's a very thin layer. Kind of like how thick is the epithelium there? So it's a,
it's about again, about 50 microns, something like that, 50, 55 microns. So
it's got a basement membrane. It's, but it's about call it 50 microns. So we remove that layer of
cells with, the way I do it is with a solution of some eye drops of alcohol. And it just sluffs
right off and it grows back. Just like isopropyl alcohol. Yeah. You could use that or ethanol.
So you anesthetize the eye before doing that, obviously.
That's a practice builder. Thank you for that tip.
How do we get the repeat?
I have a line known as coming back.
When are we on the eye first? That'd be really good. Yeah. So you, you anesthetize the eye
and then you put some alcohol solution on the front of the cornea. You remove that epithelial
layer, which is going to grow back in the same configuration. And then you use a very
carefully calibrated laser to change the shape of the cornea.
Again, dumb question. The laser's coming at what angle?
It's essentially effectively perpendicular to the, to the corneas. The patient's laying
down flat. They're on their back. And you put something into wire their eyes.
We're holding their lid apart for them. Are they sedated?
They're there. I mean, I honestly give people Valium because it's just sort of an intimidating
minute. You know, it only takes a minute. Here's what my fear would be in doing it is like my
desire to blink would be so overwhelming. I'd break the little eye barrier. Of course I wouldn't,
but I'd end up moving my head and you'd zap the wrong part of my eye and I'd be blind.
That's everyone's fear. You know, it turns out Valium is undefeated.
It's just a question of how much, but the, the, it's a very good drug. And, and so,
but to address what you, you brought up several things there. First is a lot of patients fear
that they'll do something to goof up the surgery. And there are a number of reasons why that really
can't happen, but let's go through the procedure from the beginning. Long before this patient ever
laid down on this gurney to have this laser treatment done, their eye was digitally mapped
using what we refer to as a way front sensing device. So think about this. We
send in a very narrow beam of light with a laser and we look at how it bounces back from the cornea.
It bounces back in a distorted fashion. So we send an ideal ray of light in or multiple rays of light
in, and they bounce back into distorted fashion. The amount of that distortion allows us to map
the, so you do a topo. It's much more than an autographical map. It's the entire,
optical pathway of the eye from the retina to the back and all the way to the back and front.
So we look at the entire distortion pathway and there's more than one way to do this, by the way,
there is a topography based way to do this as well, which is very effective. But the one I'm
describing to you is sort of the easiest one to think of. We send in a known uniform beam of light
uniform beam of light and look at how it bounces back from the back of the eye. That tells us what
are the distortions present in this eye? How much nearsightedness, how much farsightedness,
but also all of these physics terms of, we didn't do this in me, right? You only do this in someone
who's going to be a candidate. We may have done it in you just for grins, but we, you know, we
diagnostically, this is part of our workup for laser vision correction. And we look at how that,
how the, this particular eyeball, you know, Peter Attia's right eye distorts light as it goes
through the optical pathway. This technology was developed for telescopes that have to contend
with atmospheric distortion. So the way this works is that telescopes, and I'm talking about like
Keck, the best ones in the world, they send up a diagnostic laser into the atmosphere.
And the distortion that that laser is encountering is adjusted for in real time
with a deformable mirror, a very thin mirror. And that allows them to essentially correct for the
distortions of the atmosphere in real time. And those are constantly changing. We have the benefit
of not having to deal with real time evolving distortion, but we can take a snapshot of what
are the distortions of Peter's right eye. And then we can build them into the laser vision
correction that we do on Peter's right eye. Part of doing that means that we have to be able to
track your eye. So we have to lock onto and register your eye with the, with the equipment and any
movement that you make, part of your fear was I'm going to mess it up. Well, the laser can track
far more rapidly than you can move your eye. So while you're doing this, patients eyes can be
moving. They can. And it doesn't matter because the laser is moving. I mean, it's sort of annoying
when they, you know, so we tell the, we coach them, Hey, look at the flashing light. Yeah. But
that's really just to keep them in the ballpark of where the tracker can lock onto them. I like
knowing I'm not the only one that has this ridiculous fear. It's not a ridiculous fear.
Secondly, it's universal. When I say to patients, Hey, I'm not going to let you do anything to mess
this up there. Thank you. Thank you for saying that. That was the thing I was worried about.
Because you know, you don't want someone to laser your eye and you looked off to the side.
Oh, disaster. Not only are you blind, we also gave you a brain to. That's right. So the laser
will not fire unless you are within its range of tracking and it will move faster than you can
move. So PRK is, I like your analogy, basically changing the shape of this via the mechanism of
like kind of, it's not sanding it off, but it is vaporizing the tissue. It's vaporizing the tissue.
And it's a laser that's sort of scanning around the cornea where it does a little treatment here.
And then we know thermally that we don't want to do another shot right next to that one. So we move
over here and we want to let the tissue cool down for a few milliseconds. And then we go over here.
So the laser dances around. How many minutes approximately does it take? Does it take longer?
The worst the prescription is. Yeah, for sure. So like minus two, it might be 15 seconds.
That's it? Yeah. Maybe it's, yeah.
So minus 10 would be how long? Like a minute or so. It depends on the laser. It depends on the
overall treatment size, how much astigmatism and how many.
Oh, you're fixing the astigmatism as well. And all the little distortions, how much
coma, trefoil, all these, these are physics terms that I didn't really think I would become fluent
in. But all these little optical distortions that the optical physicists are very familiar with,
we measure and do our very best to eliminate with laser vision correction.
So the whole procedure is what? Half an hour by the time you get the eye,
get the, put this thing in the eye, put this thing in the eye, give them their volume.
For PRK? Yes.
Two or three minutes plus the volume time.
You know, it's the procedure. So take your volume an hour before.
Or maybe it's, yeah, it's like half an hour. We have them chew it up and then it works pretty quickly.
Okay. So talk about the recovery from PRK because one of the things I remember you saying when I was
sort of humming and hawing about this was the biggest drawback of PRK is the recovery takes
longer. But you otherwise, I think really talked about PRK as the gold standard.
You know, I think it's the only reason I might've said gold standard was that it came first.
It was the first procedure. And if you look at PRK and LASIK, which we'll get to in a bit,
if you look at those procedures, say 30 days later, they're indistinguishable in terms of results.
But the LASIK patients get their way quicker. So PRK, now I've removed your epithelium. So now
you have this, let's say it's a seven or eight millimeter diameter area of your central cornea
that has no epithelium. It's like having a big corneal abrasion, essentially. Luckily, we have
drugs, drops that can reduce the feeling of the foreign body sensation dramatically.
So we put those drops on the cornea, put a contact lens over the eye like a band-aid. It's really
like a just a regular soft contact lens. And then the epithelium begins to heal from the outside in.
And that takes 30 days? No, that takes about four days. But here's the thing. It's like,
if you were to have a cut on your arm, it would heal over, but you'd still be able to detect where
that cut was because those cells have not fully remodeled themselves. So the cut heals over or the
defect in the epithelium heals over in about four days, maybe less.
And then you take the contact lens off?
You can take the contact lens off then, but the vision is still not perfect yet because those
cells have to reorient themselves like a bunch of orderly bricks in a brick wall. And when the cells
first cover that defect, it's a very thin disorganized layer of cells that have accomplished
their mission of sealing the defect and preventing you from being susceptible to infection,
which is their job, to quickly cover the defect. But then the body can turn its attention to
reorganizing those cells in a more- So you do one eye at a time, obviously.
Not with PRK or LASIK, no. Because the level of vision, typically we do both eyes on the same day,
because the level of vision is probably about 20, 30, or 20, 40 within a day or two.
So when I say the visual recovery takes a while, you get pretty good pretty quickly,
but that last little bit takes several days. So you probably could drive a couple, maybe
two, three days later, but you wouldn't have 20-20 vision at that point.
So LASIK, the only thing I know about that is there's a flap involved.
That's right.
So presumably you're not shaving off the epithelium, you're cutting a flap, and how much of that
tissue you take off determines the shape of the new cornea when the flap comes back.
Right. So the laser that does the vision correction, all the little distortions,
the nearsightedness, the astigmatism, that's all the same laser.
So that part of the procedure is identical. But instead of doing that on the surface of the eye,
now we're using a step before that where we create a flap in the cornea using a different type of laser.
So we use a femtosecond laser to create about, let's say, a 100 micron flap.
So we are now under the epithelium.
So you've taken 20% of the cornea up?
That's right. About 20% of the cornea up. And now think of it as, in our analogy where we were
sanding a wooden eye before, now think of the cornea as a book. And in PRK, I'm removing the
first 10 pages of the book. Now I open it to page 100 and I'm taking out 100 through 110,
and then I close the book. The beauty of LASIK is that because that tissue removal is sequestered
under that flap, the body doesn't perceive that anything has been done. So it's very typical for
patients who have LASIK to be 2020 the next morning. And so that's the appeal of that procedure.
And that's why LASIK was developed post-PRK, presumably as a way to get around the healing
process of PRK?
Yeah, it was sort of a technological race. And the way it developed was interesting. And some of it
was in pursuit of more rapid visual recovery.
So what percentage of corrective eye surgery in the United States today is PRK versus LASIK?
I assume the lion's share is LASIK.
Yeah, I think it changes, but it's probably about 80 to 85% LASIK. And not to confuse things,
there's another procedure called SMILE, which is a very small, but perhaps growing segment of the
market. And we can talk about that in a sec, but the lion's share of it is LASIK. And there is a
but a significant chunk PRK. And we actually-
Are there more risks in LASIK than PRK?
Well, the risks are different because the risks of infection with LASIK are lower because you don't
have this hope-
You don't take your epithelium away.
That's right. But you introduce another step in the procedure where you now have a flap
and that flap can, if it's not performed correctly, that can lead to problems.
I think there is a little bit more dry eye issue with LASIK compared to PRK as well. Because when
you create that flap, the way tearing works is that a signal from the front of the eye goes to
the lacrimal gland, which then secretes tears. If you create a flap, you temporarily sever some of
the nerves that are sending the signal. And eventually over time, those nerves typically
regrow back and you reestablish that feedback mechanism. But I think you get more dry eye with
LASIK than with PRK and for longer. That is a controversial statement. There are people who
have data to show that they're equal, but I think they both result in temporary dry eye in most
patients. Some patients have dry eye for really long periods of time after both procedures,
but the majority of patients are kind of back to their baseline in about probably 60 to 90 days.
What about night vision or low light vision?
So that s fascinating. In the early days of LASIK and PRK, the weakest part of vision was night
vision. And that was because the shape of the treatment that we did and the diameter that we
treated was limited. So we couldn t really treat the peripheral part of the cornea that comes into
play when your pupil gets big. So if you are treating a central part of the cornea that is
smaller than a big pupil at night, you're going to see halos from that untreated peripheral part of
the cornea. Over the last, like, I don t know, from the 90s to now, the treatment beam patterns
have changed to address that issue and to treat that peripheral cornea differently. So now,
night vision complaints we find to be pretty unusual with laser vision correction.
Is there a difference in the cost of these procedures?
I mean, for us, no, but I m sure there are some surgeons who charge more for one than the other.
The added step of LASIK adds some cost, but PRK has more post-operative care, frankly,
because it requires more visits to see these folks. But we price them the same.
What are the, and how much does it cost, by the way? I mean, it s direction,
it s probably come down a lot in 20 years, right?
You know, I don t think that it has. I think it s been pretty stable. I think that you can,
I think it s probably about a couple thousand dollars per eye is about the average in North
America that you ll find. What are the exclusion criteria? Like, who is not a candidate for either
one? Yeah, there are certainly contraindications, some of them relative, but some of them are
absolute. I ll give you an absolute one. There are conditions of the cornea where the cornea is
biomechanically unstable, where the cornea is actually has a tendency to bow forward
in a pathological state. And that means that the cornea is not, it s a moving target, essentially.
So, further biomechanically weakening the cornea makes no sense, and doing either procedure would
do that. There are patients who have irregularities in their astigmatism that cannot be measured or
corrected with any laser vision correction. There are patients that have certain autoimmune
diseases that maybe render them as poor candidates for laser vision.
Based on the risk of healing?
Based on the risk of healing or perhaps the, just the overall health of the eye. And that sort of
extends to people who have other eye diseases like cataract or maybe glaucoma or retinal pathology.
You are typically operating on healthy eyes when you re doing laser vision correction. So,
if there s some other issue involved, you might not be a candidate.
And is there anything that, like, well, I guess given the differences you ve explained,
why are 15% of people still opting for PRK?
Well, there are certain patients where that s a far better option. So, we talked about how you re
removing pages from a book. Well, what if you have a really deep treatment that you need to do,
and the book is sort of thin to start out with? Maybe it s better to begin on page one than to
begin on page 100. So, sometimes. So, the stronger the diopter and the thinner the cornea that might
move you more towards PRK. Sometimes the thickness of the cornea will dictate it. Sometimes it might
be related to someone with pre-existing dry eye. And we re thinking, well, we have data that these
two procedures are about the same in terms of dry eye, but our clinical impression is that LASIK
makes them a little drier. So, maybe let s do PRK on this particular individual.
There used to be some restrictions in branches of the military.
Right. I remember that you couldn t have a flap in your eye if you were a pilot.
That all went away. So, pretty much all the aviators and pilots can now have LASIK or PRK.
In fact, the military is one of the largest providers of laser vision correction now
in the United States. But there are a couple of holdout special forces branches where they don t
want you to be, I think, maybe an army ranger. And that has to do with getting poked in the eye
and the possibility that a flap could be damaged. And some of this is sort of vestigial lore and
it s hard to change the military s rules. Yeah, but they ll just say PRK or nothing.
Yeah, but I d say that the overwhelming majority of the branches of service allow either treatment
and certainly all the commercial airliners, they allow PRK or LASIK. But with the caveat that you
have to get to the point where you can pass the flight physical. And the same thing is true of
people who want to be pilots or aviators. If they need to have 2020 uncorrected vision to be a pilot,
they have to have 2020 vision after laser vision correction.
Is it pretty much a given that you can at least get someone to 2020 after laser corrective vision?
I mean, the way the lasers are built today, it s typically the case that you can get them to
2020 or better than 2020 as we were describing before. And if you take them to 2015 and they
have presbyopia to begin with, does it get any worse or is it just that now they re noticing
it all the time because they never get a break from it? They never get to take their glasses off,
their spectacles, so to speak. Well, if you nail it perfectly so that their prescription is 0.00,
I think their distance vision will be phenomenal and their near vision will be whatever it is based
upon their age. So if they re 50 years old, they re probably going to need some near correction,
some spectacles for reading. If they re 41, 2, 3, 4, maybe even 45, they may not need
glasses for close up. And then you mentioned this smile procedure. I haven t heard of that. What is
that? Yeah, it s an interesting procedure. It s using a single laser, a femtosecond laser. And
this is, I want to go back to the book analogy where we opened the book to page 100. Well,
imagine if you could somehow create a little tunnel down to page 100 and snatch out pages 100
through 110 while keeping the incision really tiny and perform it through a very small keyhole
procedure. That procedure has gained some traction outside the US and in the US. It seems to be an
effective procedure. What problem is it solving given how effective LASIK is? I would say the
problem it was designed to solve was dry eye. But I think the problem it really solved,
especially outside the United States, was needing two lasers versus one. So maintaining and.
But you could do one with PRK. You could do one with PRK. But then you have the prolonged recovery
time. So the idea was could you get LASIK like velocity of return of vision. With a single laser.
With a single laser. And maybe along the way, reduced dry eye. Yes. There are pros and cons
to smile. The technology is evolving. I have not seen any data that shows that smile is in any way
better than LASIK or even equal to LASIK frankly. But it seems to be a very good procedure. Are you
doing it? I am not performing smile and doesn't mean that I won't in the future. And there are a
number of competing second and third generation versions of smile that will come on board. And
if one of them ever rises to the point where I think it's better than what we're doing, we'll
offer that. We didn't talk about glaucoma yet. I know every time I go to an optometrist or even
when I came in saw you, is that the one where you blow the air at my eye? Well, that's sort of a
that's just an intraocular way of measuring the intraocular pressure that we don't use,
but it has the advantage of not requiring the patient to be touched with anything. So you can
indent the cornea with a known amount of force from an air puff and look at how it optically
deforms the disadvantage to the air puff. And it's not really considered a, I don't think a gold
standard of measuring pressure is that if you blink really quickly and squeeze, then you can
have a false reading with that type of air puff tonometry. And we typically don't use that.
So how do you measure intraocular pressure? We measure it with two ways, both of which
indent the cornea, physically indent the cornea after. So that's why you anesthetize the.
After you anesthetize the eye with a known amount of force. And then you look at the amount of force
required to cause a certain amount of, of indentation. And what's the definition of glaucoma?
Well, the glaucoma is probably about a hundred different diseases, honestly, but they all share
the final common pathway of damage to the optic nerve, the nerve in the back of the eyes,
the cranial nerve that you mentioned at the beginning, that is somehow related to pressure.
So a pressure related optic neuropathy. Now what's odd about glaucoma is that there are people who
have totally normal pressures with relation to the population, but that pressure is too high for
them and they can develop damage to their optic nerve.
And the symptoms of glaucoma, are they all this? I mean, is it always some change in vision? Is
that what would bring someone to attention? If they weren't getting a screening test?
It's funny, you just sort of like triggered a memory of mine. I had a patient, I was,
I was in training years ago and I was explaining to a patient that, you know, glaucoma is totally,
has no symptoms at all. You wouldn't notice it at all. And, and yet if we don't find it,
it could be really bad. And the patient said, well, if it has no symptoms, what do I care?
You know, like what's the point? And what I should have said was it has no symptoms
until the very end. So in what happens is that your peripheral vision is damaged and most people
will not detect a slight reduction in their peripheral vision, particularly if it's segmental.
There's just one little area off to the side that they're, that they can't see,
particularly if the other eye is covering for that area. But as glaucoma progresses,
it can affect central vision and then it becomes symptomatic.
How much of a problem is this in the United States first of all, and then in the rest of the world?
Well, luckily glaucoma has become much more treatable. So the pharmacological management
of glaucoma has gotten way better. And there are numerous laser procedures that can treat glaucoma
and what are referred to as minimally invasive glaucoma procedures, or it stands for, you know,
MIGS, minimally invasive. Basically the management of this has gotten way, way better.
What are like the, what's the 80-20 of this? 80% of them are caused by what basically?
Yeah. So 80% of them are caused by what we refer to as garden variety, chronic open angle glaucoma,
which means that it's the glaucoma is not a function of the anatomy of the front of the eye
being too crowded where the fluid can't get out. It's more a problem of overproduction of fluid
inside the eye and the pressure is too high inside the eye. The vitreous fluid? No, it's the aqueous
fluid. And what causes that? Is that endocrine? Is that, do we not know? We do not know. I think
this has a multifactorial pathogenesis. There are certainly family history components to this where
we see it run throughout families, but it's not like inheriting. Does this run in parallel with
diseases like type 2 diabetes or is it uncoupled completely? No, not really. It's not really
coupled with diabetes. There's some, there's some relationship to hypertension, but, you know,
blood pressure, but ocular hypertension, we refer to eye pressure being too high.
You know, you see it in patients who are not hypertensive at all.
Wow. The lifelong incidence is what? I think you got me there. It's, I honestly don't know,
but it's common or it's very common. We, every eye surgeon sees glaucoma patients daily,
multiple glaucoma patients daily. So presumably like any neuropathy, if you catch it early enough,
it's fully reversible. And if you catch it too late there, you, you damage it or is it, because
this is not a central, this is a central nerve, not a peripheral nerve. So I don't, yeah, it's not.
Yeah. I think it's, it's, you can arrest the progression, but I don't think you can undo
the damage that has occurred. So once there's been optic nerve damage, it's not like sciatica.
No, I don't think so. I think once there's been damage, we expect that damage to remain. So it's
not unusual for a patient to have what we refer to as a visual field defect. So a little area
missing from their field of vision. And our goal becomes to prevent that from defect from getting
any bigger. And you can typically do that once you identify it.
At what age does it start to become enough of a concern that we should be screening for it?
Yeah. I mean, I think everybody, when they go to the eye doctor for a yearly exam,
gets screened for glaucoma. They're, the appearance of the optic nerve is examined as well as the
pressure. And those are probably the two most important things to look for with glaucoma.
So if you're screening annually, you're, you're being checked for it.
You're in good shape.
Yeah. You're being checked for it. The incidence does go up with age. And so in the fifties,
it's much more important to pay attention to glaucoma and beyond.
And presumably in the developing world where people aren't going to get eye care,
or even in the United States, if people don't choose to get eye care or can't afford to get eye
care, it's a bigger risk because they'll only present when they have symptoms.
That's right. That's exactly right. Yeah.
All right. So to summarize, you know, again, we think about kind of the longevity of the eye is
a pretty important thing, right? If you want to figure out a way to live to a hundred,
you, we, we spend a lot of time thinking about, well, you've got to really, really delay the
onset of atherosclerosis. You have to have a very aggressive strategy around the mitigation of
cancer, Alzheimer's disease and all of these things. But it's these other things, teeth,
ears, and eyes that I don't think get enough attention, right? I mean, it's, you don't want
to get to be a hundred and have no teeth and you don't want to get to be a hundred and be deaf and
you don't want to get to be a hundred and be blind. Yeah. Those all sound bad.
Yeah. So I mean, the things I'm picking up, unfortunately for many of us listening to this,
we can't go back and change what we did as kids. We can certainly make a change in our kids. So we
can make sure that they are outside in natural sunlight. Right. I don't put sunglasses on my
kids. Should I be doing that? Yeah. I mean, probably, you know, it's trying to get a kid
to wear sunglasses is tough. I, we can't come up with better toys. Like my kids love trains. So if
I could figure out a way to tell them that wearing sunglasses was train like, right? This would be
good. Yeah. It's tough. I mean, you see kids who are snow skiing, for example, and they're,
they should be wearing goggles because those have built in UV protection. Um, so that typically
works, you know, for that type of thing. But gosh, when they're water skiing, they certainly can't
wear glasses. If they're swimming, they can't wear sunglasses. Uh, there's a certain goggles
these days are pretty good. That's true. Yeah. Yeah. I that's, it's hard to get my kids to wear
goggles, but you know, there's a certain amount of just UV exposure. I don't think it's possible
to avoid. So the trade off is when in doubt, keep them out. Yeah. No hats are important as well. We
didn't really talk about that. You know, I think that that's a very good and effective way, but
it's not enough because a certain amount of light bounces off and hits the bottom of your cheek and
goes right into your eye. So it's, so for those of us that are now adults, basically, we've kind of
cast our lot, uh, with respect to that malleable period of changing the, the length. Well, you know,
we didn't really talk about like what nutritional supplements might have some of the fact. And it's
interesting because we know that with cataract, that vitamin C deficiency is associated with an
elevated risk of cataract, but it's been shown really conclusively that vitamin C supplementation
to super normal levels does not protect against cataract formation. And the things that have been
looked at, I know a C and E basically antioxidants have been looked at. They've had no effect on, on
cataract formation. There is a little bit of mixed, weak evidence for lutein and zeaxanthine
as possibly being protective for cataract. Also antioxidants, right? Yes, that's correct. And
you know, the macular degeneration, we didn't really touch on that very much, but that's a,
a huge problem. Um, you may have seen in the drug store, they sell arids,
AREDS formula for macular degeneration. That stands for the age-related eye disease
study. That was again, a national eye Institute initiative. And first they looked at, um,
CE and beta carotene with zinc and a little copper. I guess they put the copper in because
they were worried about copper deficiency with zinc supplementation. Um, and then they
got concerned about beta carotene. So they did another study where they took beta carotene out
and put in lutein and zeaxanthine powerful antioxidants. And what they showed was that
you could delay or reduce the conversion of mild macular degeneration to severe,
but it had no effect on severe disease. And it also interestingly had no effect on people
who didn't have macular degeneration. It didn't prevent them from going on to get it. But I think
most of us believe that there's something there. There's some signal embedded in that noise.
Is light also a big risk for macular degeneration? It is. It is. So again, it's this dose thing. We
want enough light so you don't become nearsighted, but not so much that you're frying your retinas
and giving yourselves cataracts. Um, but I do think that some form of, of broad spectrum
antioxidant protection makes sense. We don't really talk explicitly about screen use. Yeah.
Is there, I mean, you talked about it a little bit in that study in Asia where,
but I don't know if that was specific to screen use or just could have been just as much reading.
Yeah, it was not specific. Yeah. It wasn't specific to screen use. So when we know about
phones specifically and computers. Yeah. So, you know, this is a super interesting, obviously
topic and, and everything from people ask me about blue blocking glasses. They ask about,
am I damaging my eyes? Am I going to get macular degeneration? Because I'm looking at a computer
screen for 10 hours a day. I'll start with the easy ones. Uh, the amount of UV radiation coming
off of screens is sufficiently low that there has been no evidence at all that it's going to
cause macular degeneration. Um, in the same way that you can't get a sunburn from a screen.
I mean, the amount of blue light that you get from going outside is many, many, many orders of
magnitude greater than what you can get from screens. Um, but I do think that blue light can
mess up your circadian rhythm. And you know, it's, if you take someone and expose them to blue light
at noon, that's great. If you expose them to that at 11 PM and then you try to go to sleep,
that's messed up. And it's almost like we're running this gigantic experiment with humans
where they think about like you have a turtle. Let's say you take a species of turtle that
spends 90% of its time in the water, 10% on land. And we take that and flip it. Now it's 10%
in the water. And then we look at these turtles and we think there's something weird going on
with these turtles. Yes, they're surviving, but we've got them in a very altered environment
compared to what they were evolved to deal with. So giving people blue light from a screen that's
bright at 10 PM, 11 PM, and then asking them to go to sleep is a problem. So, you know, I really
try to limit it's not clear that it's damaging their eyes, not damaging their, their retinas,
or they're giving them cataracts, but I think it's messing up circadian rhythms. So although it is
hard to disentangle that from the total amount of light that they're seeing, which is also unnatural
and what comes with it, which is the stimulation. Right. You're thinking. Yeah. I mean, you know,
there seems to be a difference between watching TV and checking email before bed. Maybe none of them
are, maybe neither are ideal, but one seems demonstrably worse, at least for me. Yeah. I
think that's pretty universal. People feel that way that passive watching a TV is different than
I'm going to, I wonder where Winston Churchill is buried. You know, you go down some wormhole and
you're just, you know, you're just seeking information that takes you on these journeys. But
one thing I do, I do have software embedded in all of my PCs that changes the color temperature.
Like Flux or something. I love Flux. You know, and Flux is free, by the way, I think, for end users.
And it will take the blue light sequentially out of your monitor as the day goes on,
as the evening goes on to the point that it's like super amber as you get ready to go to bed.
I really think that's great. Anything else we should be thinking about? I mean,
the big takeaways for me have been the importance of sunglasses, artificial tears,
taking your contact lenses out as frequently as possible. Right. So don't,
don't sleep in them and stuff like that. I know it's not your field, but do you have a point of
view on daily versus the ones that, I mean, it just seems to me daily is if you can afford
them make more sense than the two week ones that you have to wash every night. Yeah. So, you know,
I think the most important thing is that you just get them out of the eye. We really don't like
extended wear contact lenses. So whatever type of contact that is, as eye surgeons, we tend to see
a selected sample of patients who are the problems, the people who have sight threatening
infections from sleeping typically in contact lenses. So yes, I realize there are millions of
people who sleep in their contacts and don't get infections, but the people who end up in my,
you know, office have had problems and some of them quite devastating problems. So I'm not a
big fan of sleeping in contact lenses in general, but if you're going to sleep in contact lenses,
I'd rather they be a perfect pristine new pair every single time and get them out as, as quickly
as you possibly can. So yeah, I talked about eye protection. Yeah. Again, I think we're a little
more aware of that now than when we were kids. The other thing takeaway for me is not to be so
afraid of cataracts. They're inevitable and you can actually, there's a potential silver lining,
which is not only the improvement of your vision, but potentially the correction of other age related
visual changes. It is interesting that once word got out in the community that this was something
that could be done, you do see people coming in asking for cataract surgery, I think a little bit
sooner than they otherwise would because they know that this added benefit is a potential
possibility. So, and you know, in the old days when we did not have intraocular lenses or the
generation, a couple eye surgeons before me did not have intraocular lenses, you'd have to wear these,
what were called cataract glasses, these super thick lenses that were very, very powerful and
magnified everything and didn't really work all that well optically. So in that context,
Wait, you wore those post cataract? Post cataract, yeah. Cause there were no implant lenses. Oh wow.
And your prescription was typically about a plus 10. So you know that a minus 10 is a very,
these people can't see without these glasses. That's right. And so these are like the Coke
bottles that, and that's where glasses and spectacles meet. Do people even know what
Coke bottles are anymore? So the bottom of a Coke bottle is a really thick piece of glass. And this
would magnify your eyes and make your eyeballs look enormous. And then you would have this,
all sorts of optical distortions because it's very hard to make a super powerful magnifying glass.
With a long enough focal length. Without peripheral distortion. And so you in that
context would put off cataract surgery as long as humanly possible. So that's really not the case.
Cataract surgery one and done. I mean, you said it is, it should be, but do people ever need
re-operations? I mean, it's not unheard of where someone will have an implant lens put in that
isn't functioning the way it should. And that can be replaced. Is it difficult to get the old lens
out since you can't use the same technique to melt it away? Not really. You can just fold it,
pull it out or cut it in half. So it doesn't get re-epithelialize or the crispy or whatever,
the candy coating of the M&M doesn't stick to the new lens. A little bit, but you can free it up
and take it out. You can swap out an implant lens. It's something that we don't do it. It's not like
changing your shirt, but you can certainly do it. It's another operation. One other question I had
on the laser surgery, I forgot to ask was how stable does your prescription need to be?
Because if I understood correctly, again, there's two things that are driving that, right? There's
the length, which presumably that's the part that needs to be stable. You don't want the length to be
changing. That's right. But the shape of the cornea you're actually fixing. So if there's anything
that's changing there, do you care? Well, there's really three variables. If you think about it,
there's the cornea, the retina, the length of the eye, I shouldn't say retina, but the length of
the eye and the lens itself. So we know that the lens is going to continue to change throughout
life, but typically not until you're in your 50s, 60s, 70s when cataract formation will start to
affect the light bending power of the lens. The cornea should not be changing. That would be a
sign up. You just have to make sure this length is fixed. That's right. And typically that,
unless you're someone going back to law school or you're reading 30 hours a day,
that is typically finished changing in the early 20s, like around 23, 24. So does that mean our
prescriptions shouldn't be worsening much as we age? They really should not be worsening unless
you're developing some cataract formation. Okay. Yeah. I think mine have been stable for about
15 or 20 years. So that means I'd be safe to have laser eye surgery from the standpoint of stability
of prescription. From the standpoint of stability of the prescription, that's right. And then at
some point in your future, and we tell patients this, at some point you're going to start to develop
some cataract formation and hopefully the boxing won't have any effect on that. UV exposure, you
won't have any effect on that. Genetics will be in your favor. But if you're a
I didn't mention radiation is another, we see people who do fluoroscopy, like health professionals
who are involved and exposed to ionizing radiation. I mean, if you're the tech, if you're the ship
captain who smokes on a boat that's carrying nuclear waste and you're diabetic, you're going
to get cataracts. A lot sooner. A lot sooner. Yeah. Yeah. So that last thing I want to talk about was
are we ever going to have a day when just as we look at hemoglobin A1C today, which is a pretty
crude, unimpressive way to assess glycosylation. Right. I've ranted on this elsewhere, so I
won't waste your time with my rant on why I think hemoglobin A1C is not especially helpful outside
of extremes. But I don't know why. I just think the eye is the most sensitive end organ to excessive
glycosylated hemoglobin. And it's also one of the few things you can look directly at. Yeah. So
you know, I know when I was in your office, just for giggles, I wanted to have you do like
basically an angio of my eyes, noninvasively. Noninvasively. And I thought that was really cool.
I like knowing that I had beautiful little vasculature back there. Your capillary network
was the envy of everyone in the office. Really, really good. No, but what's so cool.
What stands in, I mean, is there going to be a day when everybody's doing this every year and
when we see changes there, we say, you know what? I don't care what your, your hemoglobin A1C might
only be 5.5. Right. You quote unquote normal. Right. But that might actually reflect higher
turnover of RBCs. And in reality, there's a problem. You know, so one of the really interesting
things about the eyeballs that is a transparent organ as you point out, so you can just sort of
look in and see what the problem is. It's not like, okay, there's belly pain. We need to do
some testing. Yeah. It's like this plane where you have to use more complicated tricks. That's right.
You can just look in and, and because for example, we have a layer of brain tissue
readily available for us to observe, including its capillary network. So we can look and see,
are these capillaries damaged, which is something you see in diabetics? Are they
exudating fluid? Are they leaking fluid? And that's a very early sign of diabetic retinopathy.
Could you, for example, image the lens and determine is glucose leaching into this lens?
Does it contain more glucose than you would expect a normal individual to have in their lens?
Might that be a screening technique for, for diabetic disease? But I think probably yes.
And what about the fact that diabetes manifests primarily as a microvascular disease in so many
end organs, and you can actually directly visualize this microvascular disease occurring.
So if it's in the eyes, probably in the kidney, it's probably in the toes. And those are things
that we can directly observe. And again, it's not binary, right? So it's not, you know, we,
we make a diagnosis in a very binary fashion when the hemoglobin A1C hits 6.5% person has type 2
diabetes, but you know, at 6%, we just say they're pre-diabetic and at 5.6%, we say they're normal.
But of course, if you understand everything we're talking about here, that couldn't be further from
the truth. It's not like a person's going to be perfectly pristine, and then they're going to be
diabetic. This is a spectrum. And I just think that this to me is a much more interesting way
to go about gaining kind of a foothold in our understanding of a person's metabolic health,
is to sort of create this as now a new standard, right? This is something I'm going to create as
a standard for myself, right? Which is, I want to make sure that these, you know, nearly invisible
arteries and capillaries are perfect. And when they cease to be, it's going to prompt investigation,
right? Whether it be lipids, whether it be glucose, whether it be any other thing that we can,
that, you know, blood pressure, right? I mean, all of the things that can damage a microvascular
system, this becomes a beautiful window in which we can look at them. What is the cost of doing
that test? If a person said, I just want to. Yeah, it's super inexpensive to do, but I honestly
believe that we would see perturbations in the glucose migration into the lens way sooner than
we would see architectural changes in the retinal microvascular. I think that the first. You measure
that via pressure or shape as well. So the technology to measure glucose in the lens doesn't
exist commercially, although it's being studied. You could look at how the lens
essentially reacts to light that you shine into the lens with a particular wavelength and determine
how much glucose there is in that lens. And is that abnormal compared to a normal population?
But looking at the retinal vasculature, we can do that with ocular coherence tomography or optical
coherence tomography, I should say. And we can image in a noninvasive way the capillary network.
But again, I think that's going to have the changes there would happen after.
But I bet you see a lot of damage there in people who are unaware of their metabolic state.
You do for sure. And it's not the canary in the coal mine. You're saying the canary in the coal
mine is actually going to be the lens distortion due to the osmotic effect of glucose in initial
diagnosis and screening. Yes. But what happens very commonly is that a diabetic will come into
us and say, my sugar is well controlled. My doctor told me I'm under great control. And we look at
their retina and there's no way they're under great control. They have fluid exudating into
their retina. There are what we refer to as hard exudates. There are micro aneurysms in their
capillary vasculature. These are signs that their diabetes is out of control. And then we'll say,
I'm glad that your A1C was normal. Would you mind going back to your doctor and mentioning that
we see direct evidence of problems with your microvasculature and it's probably all over.
And how did the endocrinologist receive that news?
Yeah, typically they will accept it. They'll say, okay, well, for this individual,
that level of A1C is not acceptable. Yeah. And they've been typically very receptive because
they know we can directly visualize. I mean, look, this is sort of my soapbox,
but I really think that ophthalmology should be more integrated into medicine than less because
you guys do in some ways operate sort of outside of what the surgeons and the internists and
endocrinologists do. Obviously, here's an example where you're kind of saying, look,
I'm seeing something and it's important to your systemic health. I think there should be more of
an integration of this. I think, again, you said it earlier and I think people might not have
appreciated what you just said. You get to directly look at the brain. You get to directly
look at the central nervous system in a way that a gastroenterologist can directly look at the colon.
Right? That's why colon cancer screening is so freaking effective. You get to look with the naked
eye directly at a polyp as it becomes cancerous. That's one of the reasons I didn't become a
gastroenterologist. And we are thankful for them because of all they can save us from. Absolutely.
No doubt. No doubt. But it is amazing that we have the ability to directly observe
brain and the vascular tree. And so that's very, very helpful.
Steven, this has been super interesting to me. I was a little intimidated coming into this one
because I didn't have the amount of time I normally have to prepare for this and try to get
up to speed on the topic. So I came in blind and ignorant, but you did a masterful job of
accommodating my ignorance and I learned a hell of a lot and I'm sure everybody else did.
Well, thanks for having me, Peter. Really appreciate it.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits
include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every
topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple
Podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.