Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Ryan. Looking very forward to having this discussion with you today. I've been a fan of
yours for a long time, actually. And running is kind of like, I don't know, it's sort of like F1.
It's not really that popular in the United States, although it's becoming more so. I mean,
obviously, Netflix's Drive to Survive series has made F1 very popular. And I think also people
are starting to become a little bit more aware of runners after. Well, I don't really know what it
is, but I think Kip Chogi's two hour sub effort kind of got a lot of people in this country excited
about it. But anyway, I think for me, the interest in running started because I used to swim with
Alan Webb. So back in the early 2000s, when he was this phenom who sets the high school record for
the mile, and I'm swimming next to this guy in the next lane and just became kind of interested in
his journey and then obviously learned about you and the other runners of that generation. So anyway,
your transformation has been remarkable. I almost don't know where to begin. But let's just start
with because some people won't know a lot about you. So you grew up in Big Bear, right?
Yeah, correct. Southern California.
Yeah, but it's at altitude. So it's not like beach Southern California. People think so,
Cal, they think Orange County or San Diego, right?
Yeah, I mean, Big Bear is a really cool place to grow up. I mean, we're like two hours from the
beach. So it's one of the few places you can both surf and snowboard or ski in the same day. So,
yeah, we grew up with snow. I lived a mile away from Snow Summit. And it was just like,
honestly, it's like the perfect place to grow up as a distance runner. When you look at the best
guys in the world, they're oftentimes coming from Ethiopia and Kenya, places that are at
7,000 feet altitude. And that's exactly what I was at. And so kind of just found myself in like the
perfect scenario for a distance runner and even in the sense of being able to live high and train
low. So when I was growing up in high school, my dad was my coach, started a cross country and track
team just so I could run. There wasn't even one available at Big Bear High School. And we would
drop down like twice a week, drive an hour down to sea level, get on a track at sea level, run some
super hard interval sessions, and then pop back up to altitude. So it was, you know, we're kind of
before our time in a lot of ways, you know, like the research and studies are showing how beneficial
that kind of training is, but we were just doing it because it just made sense. It was the environment
in which I found myself and pretty crazy to look back on it now and see how things like that really
do kind of contribute to the trajectory of the path that you're on.
And I suspect there's something to being in that environment when you're young during the formative
years of your cardiovascular system. I look at like my daughter who's 13. And she loves volleyball and
basketball, but doesn't like cross country or track. And I, I'm trying not to be a psycho about it. But
I'm also sort of telling her like you have this really narrow window in which your cardiovascular
system is quite malleable. And like I'm very fortunate that because I was involved in boxing,
I had to do so much cardio, both aerobic and anaerobic training during those formative years.
And even though I'm a fraction of that level of fitness today, I can still ride on, you know,
what I had then, but I feel like if you don't push that system hard in your teenage years,
it's very hard to develop it later. I don't know if that's true, but that has been my impression.
And then to take that one step further, which is what someone like you has been able to do,
to have that altitude arbitrage is I think just unbelievable.
Oh yeah. I mean, I, the effects of cardio at a young age definitely play on later in life.
Like now, for example, like I really don't do much cardio at all. Like last year I had nine
months where just focus on strength training, just trying to get as big and strong as I can.
My weight went up from 167 to 192 over nine months. And I was literally doing zero running,
none, like no other cardio, no biking, no swimming, nothing. I hopped on a treadmill
at the end of that period when I was at my heaviest, just to see like, let me see where
my miles acts. I was going to train for this challenge that I tried this 500 pound deadlift
into a sub five minute mile. So I was like, let me see where I'm at. Just starting wise,
hopped on a treadmill after my weight session, 518 for the mile with zero, zero training.
And I think that goes to kind of like what you're talking about. Like when you develop that early
on and like you just need little touches here and there, I take pretty short rest between a lot of
my lifts and that's like enough to keep me in 518 mile shape without even trying, you know? But
yeah, I mean, there's a ton of interesting things. Like they talk about kids who are born at altitude
and how they have greater potential for cardio development over time. But it's kind of interesting
like looking at my family, I'm in the middle of five kids, my youngest brother Chad, he's super
into endurance stuff. And he was born at altitude where I was born in Seattle, Washington.
So how old were you when you got to Big Bear? I was five years old, so pretty young. So I spent
most of my time at altitude, but he was born in altitude, but we didn't really see a whole
drastic effect. I mean, he was a really good runner. He won the national championships in
high school, cross country. So a stud runner went to Oregon on scholarship and all that stuff. But
between him and I, there's not like a huge difference in what we've seen in terms of
our top end potential for cardio. Well, the other thing that you alluded to that I wanted to talk
about later, but we might as well just talk about it now because you brought it up. And I think
it's an important thing that I became pretty interested in many years later when I was
swimming and trying to look for ways to improve was basically the matrix of living high,
living low, training high, training low, and coming up with what was the optimal scenario.
And it turned out, as you pointed out, this is something for which we have a very clear answer
today. The answer wasn't clear 20 years ago. Today, the answer is crystal clear, which is the best
results are attained from living high, training low when it comes to intensity. So you can live
high, train high for low end aerobic efficiency, but you have to train that anaerobic peak at sea
level. And so I remember swimming up in Colorado Springs at the Olympic Training Center when I
would go up there for some swim camps and stuff, and being a guy who lived at sea level who would
then go to try to push it hard in Colorado. I mean, it was a total waste of time. I mean,
it was a complete waste of time to try to do any top end anaerobic stuff when I hadn't had any
ability to do that. In fact, it was the exact opposite you'd want to do. And so I had friends
who lived at sea level, but they would have oxygen deprivation tents that they would sleep
in at sea level to functionally replicate the living high so then they could train at sea level.
What you described growing up is really the kind of perfect way to be able to do that.
You made it sound like that was just sort of accidentally discovered though. You guys just
sort of empirically stumbled upon the efficacy of that training?
Yeah, yeah. It was just kind of like it just felt good. You know, anytime I'd pop down to sea level
to do track workout, it's kind of like you're saying Peter, it's like I try that stuff at
altitude and like running 400 meter repeats on short rests or like longer aerobic efforts where
you're trying to do like mile reps at super fast. You just, you've got to do it. You have to structure
it different at altitude. Whereas you go down to sea level and you can, you can spend a lot of time
at race pace, you know, working on that turnover, which you just can't do it out the two without
breaking it up more. And so that's what we do a lot of when we're up high, staying up high for
intervals is we'll just break things up where you're doing a bunch of 200s on really short rest.
But yeah, we just enjoyed popping down to sea level for those sessions just felt good. And it
was working right? Like the results like were very obvious. But yeah, the whole altitude thing is
really interesting because my wife, Sarah, who's a professional marathon runner, she's run 220 for
the marathon, which is the second fastest ever by an American. And it took her she grew up at sea
level in Santa Rosa, California. So when you're talking Peter about going up to Colorado and
doing the swimming stuff, there's also this effect of like how many years have you spent in
altitude? So like, for example, I am super good at altitude in terms of running, you know, like I can
run pretty close to my sea level times at 7000 feet altitude. What does it do at any distance?
So particular, I'm thinking about like marathon training. So like, what's most important marathon
trains or thresholds? So 15 mile thresholds, we just run 15 miles at that kind of marathon
intensity. And I could run 1215 miles at 448 per mile, which is about marathon pace at 7000 feet.
And if I pop down to sea level, maybe I'm running like 442 pace 440 pace, but I didn't get a huge
conversion from altitude to sea level. Whereas someone like my wife, Sarah, who wasn't as a
custom altitude, she'll get sometimes like 20 seconds a mile where she's running that much
slower at altitude that much faster at sea level. But she's also gotten better the more time she's
spinning altitude. So she first we moved to Mammoth Lakes out of college after we graduated
from Stanford in 2005. And she was hating living in Mammoth at 8000 feet for such a long time.
But gradually over time, like she's gotten much, much better at altitude, probably still not as
good as like I was when I was in my prime. But now we have to even go up to higher altitudes to get
similar effects to what we were getting before. So we have a place in Crested Butte, Colorado,
where we're sleeping at 9400 feet. And every time she goes up there, we see a massive jump in her
fitness, just from doing like a month stand up there. So you have to keep like kind of playing
with it because you realize like the science is there and your experiences are true. But also your
body's dynamic, it's always changing, right? So you got to like, you just can't repeat the same
thing over and over and over again. Like you have to realize like my whole body is always changing,
always adapting. So I got to be throwing new things at it. And that's like a big thing I've
learned in the lifting space as well. It's like if I'm just doing the same lifting all the time and
not like trying new mechanisms to add weight to the bar or different tactics, like I'm just not
going to see growth, right? So it's just it that's the fun thing about running, training, lifting,
it's all just an experiment of one. And it's just all just a giant experiment, right? And there's
always like tweaking little variables. And that's what I love about fitness, running, all of that
stuff is I love seeing growth. I love just like the frustration of not seeing growth, getting
plateaus and be like, what is going on right now? And like, my mind's just like chewing on this over
and over again for like months and months. And then I'm just making little tweaks, little tweaks
till I find it, then you find it and bang, it clicks, you know, and whether it's in the weight
room or running all of a sudden, like you're doing what you couldn't do before. And you're like,
Oh, I just love I love learning and growing in that way. You know,
well, you really touched on a lot of things there. But one of them is this concept of progressive
overload. And I think that that is one of the hardest things to really do when you're training
yourself as most of us are, right? Most of us, you know, we're just kind of weekend warriors and
we're sort of our own coaches. And it is very easy to get kind of comfortable. And again, it's true
in the weight room. It's true on the bike. It's true if you're running or whatever it is you're
doing. But therein lies the challenge of being able to progressively overload, which doesn't always
mean weight. It can mean sets. It can mean reps. It can mean reduction in rest time. There's so
many ways that one can progressively overload. Lately I've become pretty obsessed with blood
flow restriction and weight training. So that becomes another way to progressively overload
using a fraction of the weight that you would normally use. So I've been doing some of that too.
Oh, you have. I love that. Especially for runners because like runners, like I got hurt. I was
training for the Beijing Olympics. I was at the Olympic training in Chula Vista working with the
strength coach. He had me on one of those vibrating platforms to warm up for squatting.
And it worked great. Like I was able to like warm up and get into a much deeper squat than I never
got into before. But like as a runner, like most runners are super tight and like the ankle
mobility isn't there. Like shouldn't be down in a butt to the ground squat. It's just not beneficial
for distance runners. It's not specific for distance runners. Right. And so anyways, long story
short, I ended up tweaking like the connection to my patella and that bothered me all the way
up to Beijing in Beijing. I was kicking myself so much for getting hurt lifting, you know?
And so things like that. You had a pretty good run in Beijing though. I mean, you finished 10th,
if I recall. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I was 10th there, but it just to me, like it wasn't about what place
I finished. It was this, the sensation of clicking. Yeah. You didn't click. So you went out a little
slow in that race, if I recall. You were very tentative, like the first 15K. And then you
actually kind of came back. You basically, I don't know if you negative split by time,
but it seemed by effort you certainly did. Yeah. I mean, we could, I wrote a book about like
that whole experience, you know, like so much went into that. But I also wasn't clicking in training.
You know how you can tell when like in training, it's like, oh, I just feel like before I ran the
Houston half, like I'll, I went for a run in Big Bear a couple of days before that race. And it was
snowing like crazy. Like those big old snow, like snowflakes are come down super slow and
it's just stacking up. I was literally running like a foot of snow on the roads. They hadn't
even been plowed yet. And I felt like Tigger, like I just felt like I was just bouncing along.
It's effortless. Like when things are clicking and training, then it's like, whoo, this is going
to be fun. You know, you're kind of licking your chops kind of feel going into Beijing.
I didn't take a big break after running 206 at the London marathon in April. I didn't take my
customary two week break where I put on 10 pounds and don't run at all. I didn't do that. And so then
I was just kind of flat, like the whole buildup for Beijing. So I wasn't, I wasn't right going
into the race. But then there's also this thing of you're talking to the scientists and we're
doing like all this stuff at the Olympic training center where they're prepping us for the race,
talking about how hot and humid it's going to be. And it was one of those big life learning
experiences for me where, um, the, the storyline is it's going to be so hot and humid. It's going
to be slow. It's going to be one in like two 12, two 11, right? And so we're just buying this story
and we're just hearing the story over and over again. And I didn't do what I learned to do after
that, which is like, you got to be like the samurai. It's like, you got to be ready for any situation
that's going to come, you know, and not expect anything. So like the same is like expect nothing,
be ready for anything. And I wasn't in that state of mind. I was like, all right, it's going to be
chill the first mile or and, and right from the gun, Sammy's just like gone. The guy who ended up
winning the gold medal just took it out super hard, right? And it was like a mentally, I got
hit in the chin with an uppercut, like right on out of the gate, you know, cause I wasn't,
I wasn't ready for that scenario at all. So then you get back and you're in like 60th place and
you're trying to win a medal and you're like, you don't win a medal from 60th place. I mean,
you can, but you have to really like coach yourself through some tough spots because
you don't have momentum on your side. And a lot of like competing well in anything is getting
excited while you're out there, right? Like you got to be just building this like snowball of
excitement as the race is playing out. And I was having the opposite experience of that where I was
like, I'm not where I want to be. I'm too far back. Can't even see the leaders. The helicopter is like
way off in the distance, you know? And and so I had to kind of coach myself through that. And
actually how I did that was by encouraging other guys around me, which isn't a normal tactic that
you do, but as I kind of like encouraged other people, it encouraged me that like, I was like,
able to hold a conversation with people. And I just felt better from just like trying to actually
help other people out. And it shifted what was happening inside my mind, inside my heart. And
I was able to kind of find my own rhythm and start to work my way up in that race and finish 10th,
which I wasn't stoked on at the time. Like I was trying to get a medal, but it's funny,
the further removed you get from these things and the older you get, you appreciate it more.
So I look back on it now proud of the performance. Was Meb also, I mean, Meb's got a silver,
if I recall, in Athens in 04, right? Yeah. And then he, was he there in 08? He wasn't. No. So
we were training together up in Mammoth Lakes and he was dealing with a lot of injury issues
going into it. So he, I think he DNF'd at the trials that year in 2007. He had some gnarly
kind of hip stuff going on. And that was actually really cool to see Meb in that situation where
he went through so many injuries, so many down times, and like, even like mentally struggling
with how to handle that and see him pop out the other end of that when New York, when Boston
was just incredible. So he's, we were neighbors in, in Mammoth when we were training, we lived like
400 meters apart. And he's always been kind of like a big brother to me. So I'm such a good dude.
And yeah, I was, you know, in that race when he won Boston, and that was such a special experience.
I remember I was, I was having a bad day. It was a horrible day for you though. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. I was running terrible. Yeah. But I just remember coming up over heartbreak Hill
and you know, we don't know what's happening out there. I knew Meb was away and I knew that like,
our group was pretty far back and I knew he had a chance of winning it, but you don't know
what's happening. So I, I was coming up over heartbreak Hill and I remember just yelling at
the spectators on the side. I was like, how is Meb doing when he came past here? And they're like,
he was winning when he came past. And I knew if he got over heartbreak Hill and the lead,
he was going to win that thing. So it's funny. It's special. It is hard to believe that that was
2014 because that's just one of those races that is seared in my mind. I remember it so well,
because I used to, I don't want to say I trained with Meb, but we trained at the same place in San
Diego. So there's this place called Fiesta Island. It's, it's perfectly flat. So that's where all the
time trial races are. So three or four days a week, I would do my training on Fiesta Island.
It's seven kilometers and it's perfectly flat. And, and Meb would do his tempo runs there.
And early on a Tuesday or Thursday morning, we'd be the only two guys out there,
me on my bike, him running. And, you know, I think it's actually worth pointing out to
people listening to this who aren't familiar with some of these times, just how fast you guys run.
So you threw around some numbers earlier, like, you know, marathon pace, 442 to 448. I mean,
these are such insanely fast speeds that I think the, the likelihood that a person could run that
speed for half a mile is virtually zero, right? Like I know right now I could not go out and run
800 meters, half a mile at that pace. There's simply no way. Yeah, which is funny because I
can't either. I know, but it's just, it's so fast. And I used to have a sign in my office that said
442. So it was a pace clock and it said 442. And it actually came from, I remember getting this idea
off something one of your sponsors did for one of your races many, many years ago, they had
a treadmill set up to that pace. And the idea was they just had random people show up and they're
like, how long can you hold the pace that he holds for a little over two hours? And so they'd put a
harness around a person's waist and they'd make them run at 442. And these people were getting
shot off the back of this treadmill after 30 seconds, 40 seconds. One person made it a minute,
right? And the reason I had that sign up in my office was I was very circumspect slash put off
by the notion that people would say, hey man, we're training for a marathon, not a sprint.
This is a marathon, not a sprint. And I tried to make the point to people that,
okay, but if you want to win a marathon, it feels like sprinting. So let's be clear. It's one thing
to go out and run a marathon and take six hours to do it. It's another thing to go out and win a
marathon. So if you're trying to win a marathon, you have to understand the pain that these guys
are in. You have to understand what 442 means. It is insanity. And yes, for you,
it is below your threshold, but your threshold is so high. So looking at,
Meb win that race and having seen him in the months leading up to that, and I'm on my bike
and I'm seeing how fast he's running, doing his tempo repeats and stuff. It's just,
it is really amazing. And I do think it's one of those things where I wish everybody could try to
run at that pace and do the exercise that was done on that treadmill or something like that.
Because otherwise I think a lot of what we're going to talk about today is very hard to understand
from a physiological standpoint. Yeah. I mean, if like people just go out to the track and just
try and run 200 meters at a, yeah, like my, my half marathon pace is 433 per mile. Right. So
that's 34 seconds per 200. So if you just go out to the track and try and run a 34,
it's pretty crazy. Cause yeah, like, you know, guys, when they're racing, they make it look so
effortless like Kip Chokey when he's running sub two, like it looks so slow. So, and it's 34 seconds
per 200 is what he's running. And that is very fast, like 200. But yeah, I mean, what you're
talking about, Peter is super important. Like distance runners are not slow, like, like world
class marathoners. Like I want the guy now I'm coaching, you know, I want the guy who can run
49 seconds for 400. Like that's the kind of speed you have to have. Now you don't have to have that
speed while you're doing marathon training, but you need to have had that speed before that. Like
as a kid growing up, that's why I like with kids, I'm like, get as fast as you can. Because if you
want to be a world-class marathoner, I need 49 seconds speed, right? Like that's the kind of speed
that Kip Chokey has. And then that carries you on to be able to run a great mile to be able to run a
great 5k. Like it's all built off speed. Like that's what we work on with training. It's like,
let me develop your 5k speed, your mile speed first, which is directly correlated to your sprint
speed. Let me develop all that. And then we'll grow that into 10 K speed. Then we'll grow that
into half marathon speed. And then we'll grow that into marathon speed. But marathoners are,
they have wheels and we would have to train in training. I'm doing 50 meter sprints twice a week
in the middle of marathon training, 50 meters sprints, like little hill sprints. We're in the
weight room. Like you got, it's a power to weight ratio. Like, so you gotta have power. And that's,
that's an area I've grown a ton in since I've retired from running. And as I look back at my,
the weights I was doing, I just kind of like scratch my head. I'm like, Oh, I wish I could
go back and do things a little bit differently in the weight room. Cause I don't think I was using
my time effectively there, but yeah, it's power is so important for, for distance runners of all.
I mean, last, maybe if you're doing like super ultra stuff, maybe it's not quite as important,
but the marathon, I think it matters everywhere. And I think I know that Meb was doing deadlifts
as he was preparing for 2014. I mean, um, one of the, I talked to a guy who had, had, had overseen
part of his strength training program. And one of the things he was really fixated on was
his strength to weight ratio is measured by a deadlift. Yeah. Hex bar deadlift, right? That's
right. Hex bar deadlift with a, um, high eccentric, pardon me, high concentric and a dropped eccentric.
So no, so you pick it up, drop it, pick it up, drop it. Right. So the reason for that being the
eccentric tears, the muscle fibers was you're tearing muscle fibers. That's what's creating
hypertrophy. We didn't want any hypertrophy. We just wanted the strength. So it was pick it up,
drop it, pick it up, drop it. When Meb first started, if I recall, his strength to body weight
ratio for a single rep max was 1.3. So pretty pathetic, right? If we can be honest, right?
He could only deadlift 1.3 times his body weight. Um, I believe going into Boston,
he was able to get to three to one, maybe it was 2.7, but it was in that vicinity.
And the logic for this was really just physics. When you run, you have to hit the ground with a
toe, you know, whether you're, let's assume you're toe striking, not heel striking, but your foot
has to hit the ground. The harder you hit the ground, the harder the ground hits you, the
harder the ground hits you, the higher you go, the higher you go, the further your stride.
And so, um, they basically had calculated that for Meb to run the pace he wanted to run in Boston
that year, he needed to add four inches to his stride. And to do that basically required
taking his maximal force per unit body weight from something like 1.3 to 2.7. That was going
to translate to four more inches of stride. So he didn't increase his stride rate. He just increased
stride length and that was done through strength. And I think I suspect that that's becoming more
understood in running now, right? Because, you know, there was a day when I suspect runners were
told, don't lift weights, right? You want to be as skinny as possible. Uh, it's not about that type
of strength. And I'm guessing that that's not at all how you coach your runners. No. Yeah. We're,
we're super into strength, right? And kind of like you're saying, like your, my understanding even has
changed so much throughout the years where like I used to always think of like, think about your foot
action hitting the ground. I always thought it was being like a tiger paw and you're like pulling
the ground when really that's not what you're going for. You're going for like you're saying
you're stomping the ground. You're putting force into the ground. That's going to shoot you up and
out. Right? So like, and I never thought about that way. I was always just trying to like paw
the ground. And so that's where you want to use your glutes too, right? Your glutes are your
strongest, biggest muscle. And yet like so many runners, myself included as a pro runner, I had
very underdeveloped glutes. I would have been way faster, way better if my glute strength was,
and your hamstrings were probably quite weak and probably incredibly tight. And right. Yeah.
And now those insights came from sprinters, right? So if I believe Usain Bolt has the
greatest, uh, force per unit mass ever measured on a, um, force plate treadmill. So these are,
you've probably seen these, these treadmills where what you run on the treadmill and it
tells you how much force you're putting into the ground. And I believe Usain Bolt is able to put
six times his body weight into the ground with each strike, with each foot strike. I mean,
it's just, it's crazy to think how strong that is. Yeah. Yeah. It's unreal. But yeah,
I think for people who are listening, if you're a runner, like try that next time you go out,
try like pushing through the ground rather than trying to paw the ground and like how you contact
the ground. So important. So a lot of people are rolling through the ground. It's very difficult to
utilize those glutes and to really put force into the ground when you're rolling from your
heel to your toe, right? So you've got to like contact the ground like midfoot and just be like
stomping the ground. But yeah, the weight training helps tremendously with that. So,
so, so important for sprinters for, yeah. And the hex bar deadlift, that's my favorite lift. Like if
I was advising runners or when I am coaching runners, that's the first lift that they do on
the day. It's the most important one. And the one that we're always trying to increase the amount of
load they're able to handle with that. Have you used this device called a G flight? So it's these
two little red boxes that shine a laser beam between them and they measure how high you can
jump and your ground contact time. Hmm. No, no, that sounds interesting. So it's super interesting.
So it's become a part of my training now. And so the way it works is it's shining a little laser
across the floor. So you lay these things down on the floor. And if you stand between them static
and you jump and come down, it will tell you with incredible precision how high you've jumped,
because it measures how long you're off the ground. And it's a simple way and it's a simple
physics formula to figure out how high you went. So that's really interesting. So one, you can use
it for static vertical jump. But I think where you would find it more interesting for your runners
is when you do depth jumps. So now you put it in front of a box and you have the athlete jump off
the box, hit the ground and jump up. Now it gives you two pieces of information. It tells you how
long you were in contact with the ground and how high you went. And the marker of a great runner
or a person who is very good at generating force is you should have a higher vertical jump when you
jump off a box and land and go up than just static. Most people don't. Most people will jump higher
static off the ground than off the box. And the reason is their ground contact time is way too
long and they dissipate way too much force. I forget the metrics that I believe you want to be
beneath 0.28 seconds of ground contact time. I think that's the number. I struggle with this. So
I'm still jumping higher from a static than off a box. And my ground contact time is always north
of 0.3 seconds. So this is one of the things I've been working on, not because I'm remotely
interested in running fast, but because I'm interested in my feet becoming very good at
load dissipation and load transfer and force transfer. So I think that's just a very important
skill as you age, whether you're walking down a flight of stairs, whether you're hiking.
But for a runner, I would suspect if you could get people down into a ground contact time of like
0.2 to 0.25, that's going to translate to exactly what you're saying. Because the way you describe
it, the sort of rolling foot on the ground, you're never going to get forced that way. You could be
spending 0.6 seconds on the ground when you're rolling your foot across it. Instead, you want
to be hitting it super quickly and getting up. Yeah. You know what blows my mind about that,
though, as we're talking about this? I'm just thinking, I'm sure you're familiar with Jim Ryan.
Yeah. So I'm just thinking about him and somehow he was a heel striker. And I know of like,
I think Dathan Ritzenheim is a heel striker. Obdy, I just saw him the other day up in Flagstaff.
He's also a heel striker. And like, how are these guys running so fast from heel striking? Like,
is it a thing where like they could be much faster if they weren't heel striking? Or like,
is there some kind of advantageousness to that that we're not aware of or seen? I don't know.
I'm super curious about that. I would put it in what you said earlier. It might be that a
combination of A, there are just some people who really adapt to a certain way of doing things.
And it might be that they run really well despite that. But everything I've read on this subject
matter and all the experts I've spoken to suggest that forefoot to toe striking is the way we were
meant to run. If you go back and look at kind of how our ancestors ran and you look at really how
force transfer would be most efficient, you don't want to be striking on the heel.
Yeah. I mean, that makes sense to me. But yeah, it's interesting to see people getting away with
it. But I'm with you. I'm always interested in like, not like, what can you get away with,
but what is optimal, right? Because I think it's easy to do that when you look at like,
how the Africans train, like we've spent a lot of time training in Kenya and Ethiopia.
And like, they don't even go cool down. And these are the best runners in the world on the planet,
and they don't go cool down. And I'm like, we learned to cool down in like middle school,
cross country and the importance of that. And you find yourself being like, well, maybe they
got it right. Maybe we shouldn't be cooling down. But I always remind myself like, well,
what is optimal? Like that's really what I'm after, not like, what can you get away with?
Yeah. So I've gotten so off track. I want it to kind of go through a bunch of other things,
but like, I just want to now geek out on all this other stuff. But I think just for folks to have a
bit of a sense of your trajectory, because we've touched on so many things. I mean, we very quickly
just in passing throughout there, the Houston marathon where you became the first American to
break an hour and you still hold the American record for that, a record that may stand for some
time. But let's go back. You're growing up in Big Bear, your dad, an amazing baseball player.
And you were typical baseball, basketball, et cetera. Didn't pick up running if I recall till
you were like 13 or something? Yeah, correct. Yeah, you did your homework.
Yeah, man. Well, I remember and you did like your first run, you just decided that I want to run
around the lake. That's a 15 mile run. How much did that hurt? Oh, it was the pain train the whole
time. Yeah. Like there was no like magic to that run, right? It was like just suffering the whole
time. I was in basketball shoes. I had no idea what I was doing. My legs just felt like they
just got pounded into a million little pieces like halfway through it. So I mean, we had to stop
multiple times. We stopped at a liquor store and got like a sobe, like a drink or whatever,
and stopped and ice my legs. And really like my dad wasn't there. I probably wouldn't have made
it around the lake, but that was such a learning experience for me now as a dad of for myself,
being like, how do we respond to our kids and their crazy ideas? You know, like this was just
some like crazy thing that I decided to do when I was 13. And yet look what it did. Like it totally
changed the trajectory of my entire life, like completely different now. And just some crazy
idea. It'd been very easy for my dad to be like, you know what? Let's just start with like a two
mile run instead of starting with a 15 mile run, you know? But that wouldn't have captured me in
the same way. Like I needed a hook that was just going to be like, I'm forever changed. Like the
trajectory of my life is never going to be the same. Like I needed something big like that.
And I'm so glad that he didn't like try and gun down my ideas. Just like, all right,
that's what you want to do. Let's go do it. I can't imagine that pain actually, because I had
a very similar experience at a far smaller distance when I was maybe 12. And I just woke up one day
and I was like, I want to go run five miles. I want to see how fast I can run five miles. And so
I put on my crappy shoes and I went out and I ran five miles and it hurt so much. It hurt so much.
And the next day I was like, I'm going to do it again. And I went out and I did it again and it
hurt so much. And I went out and I did it the third day and it hurt so much. And then something
on the fourth day changed. And on the fourth day I felt awesome. And then I just never stopped.
You know, I just started adding more distance from there. But when you think about how non-linear
running is, like if I was feeling that pain at five miles, five miles is a quarter of 13
in terms of effort. So I'm not just like what was going through your mind at the five mile mark,
at the eight mile mark, you know, what were you actually, were you, were you thinking,
I love this pain. I love proving to myself that I can do this. Or was the part of you thinking,
why am I doing this? Yeah. And I mean, there were so many thoughts. That's the thing about distance
running. It's really like what's going on in your head is hugely important. Right. And so like now,
like when I'm training athletes on the mental aspect of it, I tell them like you gotta have
whole bunch of different like arrows essentially that you can pull out and use. Because it's like
sometimes you use one thing, it doesn't work. You got to go to something else and it doesn't work.
So I have all these different tactics and managing pain and discomfort. But like honestly,
like one of the biggest ones that is most helpful for me is simply turning the mind off. You just
turn the mind off and you just like keep putting one foot in front of the other. Like it sounds
so simple and so basic, but like I can tell you like the last 5k of the Boston marathon when I'm
in a world of pain and just trying to get to the finish line as fast as I can. There's no like
profound thoughts going in through here. It's just like put one foot in front of the other as fast
as you can. Like it's that simple. Right. And it's so in those moments, like oftentimes I'm just like
turn the brain off and just keep moving. Like just keep moving. And a lot of it's just like
too like refusing to believe that you can't take one more step. Like you get yourself, at least I
get myself in trouble when I start thinking too far down the road. I'm like, oh I still have so
far to go. There's no way I could possibly do this. Like you get overwhelmed by the scope of the
challenge sometimes, especially when you're trying to do something you've never done. And that's
worse than the actual discomfort you're feeling. Right. It's that being overwhelmed thing is just
not a good feeling at all. And that's that's what makes people give up and give in. So if you can
bring yourself back to the present to what you're doing right now, what I found is there's always
enough to get me through this moment. There's not always enough to get me through like what's coming
all down the line. If I try to just like I'm going to handle all of it right now. It's like, no, just
just do what's right in front of you. Just handle what's this mile that you're in right now, which
is why I wrote my book entitled Run the Mile You're In. Because it's just like you just got to bring
yourself back to being present in this moment. And there's always enough to get you through this
moment. One of the things about running that strikes me as difficult in that regard is you can't
dissociate yourself from the visual cues of how much lies ahead. I used to swim long distances
and there was a there were a couple of really dogmatic rules that we had in in ultra distance
swimming. And one of them was never look up towards shore. You only know you're coming to land
when you start to see the bottom of the ocean. You typically don't get that until you're like
half a mile from shore. But this idea that you would ever lift your head up to look forward is
a total disaster. And I got a really bad taste of that on a swim that I was doing. It was a training
swim across Lake Tahoe. So this was not supposed to be a very difficult swim. This was a 12 mile
swim. And that should have taken a little under six hours. But I didn't do my homework. I didn't
hire a good boat captain and he didn't understand the navigation. So to make a very long story short,
we didn't go across the lake. We zig zagged across the lake. And when we hit this five hour mark in
my head, I'm thinking I should only be two miles from shore. So I look up at him and I say,
how much further do we have? And he says about two miles. And I say, or maybe four miles or
something. I forget what the number was, but it made sense. Whatever he said made sense. And then
I stupidly looked towards the shore and had a mental image of what it looked like. I couldn't
see the trees or anything like that. You could, it couldn't make out detail. So I just put my head
down and hammered for two more hours, for one more hour thinking, okay, but in an hour I should
see the bottom of Lake Tahoe coming up at me. And I didn't, it looked exactly the same. And I lifted
my head up and it looked exactly the same. But meaning we were much further than he told me we
were. And that is the closest I've ever come to like quitting a swim. I was mentally destroyed.
And then I said, how far are we? And he said, I don't know, I think like four miles. And I was
like, come on. Like, what are you talking about? Like you can't mess with a swimmer like, I mean,
I was so pissed off. But again, what did, why was I pissed off? I was pissed off because I had an
idea in my mind that was so far ahead. I wasn't in the, in the mile, right? I wasn't in that moment.
And I think for runners, like you don't have the luxury that a swimmer does to literally,
you, I could swim with my eyes closed. I can really drown out all of that other stuff.
And you gave that example of being in Beijing and it's not just that you know you're in 60th,
it's that you see the helicopter that's over the leaders and they're a quarter mile up the road.
That requires an extra level of mental fortitude in my mind to be able to run your race at that
point. Yeah. Yeah. And like I said, it all comes back to getting excited, right? If you're going to
perform well, you got to be excited about how you're doing. So it's like, how can you get
excited? Not just like make it through that moment, but find something to get excited about
in that moment, you know? So there's so much, I talk a lot about like reframing things in your mind.
And that to me is like one of the most helpful things that I use all the time, right? So like,
for example, I was just doing this crazy challenge. It's called Chopwood carry water, where I split a
cord of wood at my house and flagstaff and then drove to the grand canyon, ran down to the bottom
of the grand canyon holding these seven gallon blocks. Yeah, these are the big blue ones, right?
I saw this on Instagram. Yeah, they weigh like 62 pounds each when they're full. So I was running
down there. It's a 10K run, 6.3 mile run down to the bottom of the grand canyon, you drop 5,000
feet and then got to the Colorado river, fill them up and then farmer carry them out of the grand
canyon. And I remember being down at the bottom and filling up those jugs and just being like
looking up and having just run all down that. And I was like, what did I get myself into? Like the
sun was already getting down super low. And that was the hardest part of the whole challenge for me
was like just starting it out, right? Because I knew it was waiting for me. I knew how far I had
to go. But again, I just... So just to be clear, you carried 63 pounds in each hand of water up
6.3 miles at basically a grade of, I don't know, seven or 8% I'm guessing, right?
Yeah, yeah. I think it's like 7% grade. Yeah. How long did that take you?
Six hours. And help me understand what your hands were doing. Were you using grip? Did you have like
wraps around your hands or something? No, no, just hand in it. I have good calluses on my hands from
all the lifting I've been doing. But yeah, I mean, my hands took a beating. But actually interesting...
Did you ever have to like put the... Did you ever have to stop and put them down?
Oh yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I can only carry them like 50 meters at a time. So it was a lot of carries.
Yeah. That is actually more insane than your deadlift 500 pounds run a five minute mile attempt,
which also was super impressive. But this farmer's carry thing is ridiculous, actually.
It was such a crazy experience. But I was talking about reframing and I had to reframe a lot in that
because I thought, I think it'll take me like four hours to carry these out. And our goal was to try
to beat the sun. But like I said, the sun was already like... It was like three, four o'clock
when we got down to the bottom. So I was just like, found myself wanting to get frustrated about how
this was going, how long this is going to take. I'm never going to get out of here. All those
thoughts are going through my mind, you know? And I just had to like reframe it and come to peace
with like what was happening out there and just accept it and then get excited about it. You know,
like I was looking at the moon is coming up is so epic. Like it was dark. All my buddies are there
cheering for me, giving me food and water and stuff. And it was just such a beautiful experience,
but I had to reframe it to be able to see it that way because how I was seeing it at the bottom of
the canyon was like, oh man, this is going to suck. What I get myself into. I don't know if I can get
out of here. Like all those negative thoughts. But then as I was able to accept it and then
reframe it, then I was able to embrace this really beautiful experience and one that was
life changing for me that, you know, I'll never forget getting to the top of that canyon and
putting those jugs down and how good it felt to like finish that thing, you know? But I had to
change how I was thinking about the whole situation, which is what you have to do
when you're in a race and it's not unfolding how you want it to unfold.
Well, I can relate to that on a number of my swims where things didn't go well, but you're right.
There's something about saying I'm not going to quit. I'm going to put my head down and I'm going
to do this. When you get to the other end, it's pretty remarkable. And I've had the ability to be,
you know, coaching people when they do swims. And in swimming, once you touch the boat or anything,
you're disqualified. So it's a very, you can have zero assistance out there. And
one of the things that I learned from watching other coaches and then I would do it with people
is whenever a swimmer says they want to quit, I wouldn't let them do it, right? I would say,
no, no, no, I'm not going to let you do this. You got to give me another 10 minutes and then we'll
talk again. And if they still want to quit, I say, I need another 10 minutes and then we talk.
And then I make them do this three times. And part of it is just to show them that they can
swim another 30 minutes. So if you can swim another 30 minutes, you could probably swim
another four hours or whatever the amount is. But also you realize like, and this sounds so cruel,
but you also tell them, like you make sure they understand that what they're doing is you want to
quit right now. Just to be clear, you're saying you want to quit doing this thing right now.
Is that right? Yes. Okay. Well, if you know, after 30 minutes, then fine, you can come on out.
But I guess there's just no substitute for that feeling of when you finish. Although that
literally strikes me as the hardest physical thing I could ever imagine doing. Because it's,
say more about what the cardio struggle of that was like. Like what, you know,
are you kind of in a slow jog trot? Like what kind of pace were you moving at?
Yeah. So like basically a fast walk, you know, you, you want to make your legs and heart do as
much of the work as possible. Cause just holding that much weight in your hand becomes an issue,
you know? But really the reason why I'd say is even harder than running a marathon is when you're
running a marathon, like my heart rate's usually around 167. I have a really low heart rate.
What's your maximum heart rate? I don't know what it would be. Now at that time though,
I couldn't get it over 200. It was probably like 195, 197. Like I had a resting heart rate of 27
when I was at my fittest. Like it was, I've always just had a really low heart rate,
but it gets super low. Now it's nowhere near that. But all that to say, like usually the first 20
miles of marathon or maybe the first 17 miles, like feels pretty good. You're conversational.
You're floating along. Like it's just fun, you know, you're enjoying the ride. And then of course,
like it gets really hard and you got to get down and bear it. Whereas this was just like,
it was like I was doing interval training because I was right. Like I'm going like 30 second carry,
set it down, take as minimal rest as possible. What would a typical rest be when you did that?
30 seconds on. Yeah. Like 30 seconds off kind of thing. I would just go till I caught my breath
and go again. And so it was like, I'm breathing super hard when I set it down, catch my breath
just to where I'm breathing normally again and then go again. So just like I was breathing. If
you listen to the video, which we're going to have a whole video coming out here pretty soon,
like you'll hear me just breathing super hard, like a truck, like the whole time. And it's like
six hours straight of doing that was the most intense thing I've ever done before. Like I'm
not used to breathing that hard the whole time. So how much did you drink? Do you have a sense of
what volume you consumed of water and whatever? The amount of water and calories I was taking
it was insane. I had a, my buddy was helping me. I had a lot of buddies helping me, but one guy was
just in charge of doing my food and water after every third carry, I'm taking in water and then
I'm taking in sugar. Like I was eating gummy worms, like a maniac. I probably took in like,
like 3000 calories coming up from the canyon because I was just burning so much because
I'm like 183 pounds plus carrying 124 pounds of water weight and you're going up 5,000 feet. So
my body was just like, my metabolism was unreal. But that was a big part about being,
and why I wanted to do this. So check this out. Like the biggest to me, the most important part
of training, whether it's run training or weightlifting training is consistency. And it blows my
mind what my body's capable of doing in my athletes are capable of doing when you're just consistent.
So when I was training for this, I never did longer. Well, twice I did longer, but for the most
part I did 20 minute carries every other day. So that was all the training I did 20 minutes,
20 minutes with basically the same weight, 60, call it 65 pounds in each hand. And you would do
the same thing, 30 seconds on 30 seconds off, 30 seconds on 30 seconds off for 20 minutes.
Yep. And then off of that, I was able to do a six hour carry out of the canyon.
And did you do that at elevation? I'm sorry, at grade as well, not on flats.
No, just flat, which, you know, like I could have trained for it better, but like I'm a full-time
dad. I got my lifting that I'm into. I coach my wife, I have online training business,
run free training. So I have a ton of stuff going on. I don't have time to go do like our water
carries, but plus it's easy to be consistent when it's 20 minutes, right? Like I can't find an
excuse and be like, Oh, I don't have 20 minutes. Like I would get home late at night and put on
the headlamp. And if I hadn't done my carry, go do my carry because 20 minutes is nothing, right?
I can be consistent with that. Whereas if I'm trying to be like, okay, every other day I'm going
to do an hour. Nope. I'm not going to be able to stick to that. You know? So I think a big part
about being successful in running fitness is like, just make the bar low, make it easy to be
consistent, right? So yeah, I did all of that off 20 minute carries, but I knew what is super
important in doing any kind of ultra stuff is fueling, right? So I knew I was like, if I take
in enough calories and I stay hydrated, I'm going to be okay. I can get through anything, right?
But how much did you need to experiment with that? Because that was something I experimented with
a lot in my own very, very, very modest forms of endurance training was learning the fuel and
making dumb mistakes sometimes. Like I did this one training swim many years ago, and it was like
kind of your penultimate, like it was the longest training swim I would do before the actual swim.
So it was like a 24 mile swim. So I did an 18 mile was the last training swim. And someone had told
me, Hey, a really good way to avoid getting the runs is to take like, I forget what it is. Like,
what's the anti diet? Imodium. Yeah, exactly. It was Imodium. And I was like, well, you know,
it's funny. I've never had the runs when swimming, but I'd hate to get it. I should try. I just see
what happens if I take Imodium before this swim. So sure enough. And of course, like an idiot,
I don't just take the recommended dose. I take two X the recommended dose. And so I'm out there.
And in, in, I think at that time, my regimen was 200 ml of fluid every 20 minutes. So 600 ml an
hour of fluid multiplied by I think that turned into a seven, maybe an eight hour swim. And the
last four miles, I was about, I thought it was going to die. Like I was so bloated and it didn't
really occur to me why, cause it was like, you know, eight hours earlier that I had taken the
Imodium, right? Like I had never put two and two together, but this was the problem. So we finally,
we started in La Jolla, swam up to like, I don't know, Solana beach, and then swam back down. And
when, when we get back to shore and my friend who is guiding me pulls the kayak on the beach,
and I pick up the kayak to carry it with him. So I'm in the front of the kayak. He's in the back.
We're carrying it on the beach. It's like this beautiful day in La Jolla. Families are playing
everywhere. This kid had dug a big hole in the ground next to his sandcastle. And as we walk
by it, I just went, and I just puked like literally, it looked like eight liters of whatever it was.
I was drinking like hammer strength, something or other like into this hole. And I was like,
all right, note to self, man, Imodium, not for swims. But that's a dumb example. But like,
you know, you mentioned like the amount of sugar you're consuming, but I know some athletes who
just cannot put sugar in, they get really sick. They have to use more complex carbohydrates. So
how did you, how empirical were you both, let's go back to your marathon training when it was like,
everything's on the line. This is your, this is your job. How deliberate were you in figuring out
what was the right ratio of goo versus rice versus potato versus, you know, all of it in liquid?
How did you figure all that out? Yeah, we were, I mean, we were super specific with it when I was
running professionally. And I think, you know, the running professionally, my experiences,
they're carried over into this challenge, right? So from my experience, and a lot of our athletes
experience, like you can train your gut to take in stuff. It's when you throw new stuff at it,
that's not used to when you have, you know, adverse reactions like you're having. So like,
for us, number one, I'm loading for two days before the marathon. So and that was taken from like a
nutritionist that I was working with, he's like, Hey, listen, like spread this load out, like,
you don't want to blow it up and like be feeling terrible the day before this race, like load for
two days leading up to it. So what that would look like is I'd eat 400 calories of carbohydrate,
additional to what I'd normally eat when I'm training hard, right? So I wouldn't be like,
Oh, I'm not running that much the last couple of days. So I'm going to cut down how much I'm
eating. I would still eat like I was training and the 400 extra calories of carb. And I keep
those carbs like super simple. Um, cause you know, like a lot's going on with nerves and jitters
leading up to your race. And you just want to make it as easy on your system. Like there's a time and
place for complex carbs and high fiber diet and all that stuff. Like usually that's like how we're
eating, but the days before race was keeping it super, super simple. So for you, that was what?
Rice and potatoes.
Yeah. Like white rice. I was big on like the white rice, pasta, um, sourdough bread. I really
liked because it's lower glycemic index. Um, but it digests really easy. Um, maltodextrin is a carb
that I really like to take in and you gotta be careful. I've had some bad experiences with other
branded stuff. It's like, it's supposed to like, like, I forget what it's called, like glucose aid
or one of those things. I tried that before race and how my athletes try it. And they had a
terrible time with their stomach. So you never want to try something new leading up to your race.
You haven't tried before. So always try it in training. That's just like a given, you know,
but, um, I love maltodextrin cause it's a liquid calorie. So if I'm not hungry and it's, it's, uh,
tasteless, I can mix it up with the protein powder, shake it up, shoot it down. That is,
that's actually what my pre-race meal was, was a liquid meal because I'd wake up from all this
carb loading I'm doing the day before and I'd wake up really full and then I'd eat anyways.
So like three hours before the race, take my shake with the protein powder, maltodextrin,
a little bit of olive oil in there as a healthy fat to help slow things down a little bit more.
And then I was taking a gel right on the starting line, sipping all water the whole time.
And then we're, we would actually how I did my bottles and we get, so we get bottles every 5k.
So we get to put them out on a table. You can put whatever you want in it. You could strap a gel to
it if you want. But how I always did things is we would make them not very concentrated the first
bottle and then they'd get increasingly concentrated as the race was going on.
And then they get decreasingly concentrated lady later in the race. And the reason for that was
like, it's easier to absorb things when you're not as tired, right? So you kind of want to make sure
you're front loading your carb intake during the marathon because your body can just process it a
lot easier. I mean, when you get to 40k of marathon, like you don't feel like taking in carbs at all.
So oftentimes we grab that bottle, we take a swig of it and then like it tricks your body to think
it's getting carbs, right? And then we just spit it out. We wouldn't even drink it, but your body
thinks, oh, carbs are on the way. Like, and it responds like as if it's going to get carbs,
but it doesn't get anything. So that would give you a little jolt of energy just with 2k to go
there. But typically, yeah, the bottles would be not as concentrated, more concentrated. We put
a gel at 10k, a gel at 20k and that, no, no, sorry, a gel at 15k and a gel at 30k. And that gel at 30k
would be a caffeinated gel. Again, just to get a little bit more of a hit of caffeine. We time our
caffeine intake to where we're taking it also like 75 minutes prior to race start. Yeah. And caffeine
is a really interesting thing to talk about. I'm like intrigued by that one because that was one of
the things that when it came on board, it was like, oh, there's no going back. Like I couldn't
imagine doing a race without caffeine. And yet like people have such different experiences with
it. And you know, I've learned from like science recently how it does like increase your core
temperature, which is kind of detrimental to endurance activities. But the thing that's
interesting is like that, I understand the science behind that, but that just hasn't been my experience
at all. Like I am a hundred percent faster with caffeine on board than without caffeine on board.
And I've tried both ways. Did you ever experiment with Tylenol?
No, no, I never did. So there's some really interesting research. And I was actually talking
about this like a couple of weeks ago with Lance Armstrong. I don't know how it came up,
but we were talking about and same thing. Like he had never used Tylenol on the tour.
It's a pretty remarkable performance enhancing drug, right? So perfectly legal, right? Wada has
not banned Tylenol to my knowledge. But we're talking about like a one to 2% performance boost.
It's not entirely clear if it comes through the temperature reduction or the pain reduction,
but it was absolutely part of my stack during time trials, right? So, you know,
a time trial is like basically an hour of threshold, right? It's super painful. And I
feel like I was getting like a one, two, maybe even at times a 3% performance gain from Tylenol.
And I would take like a thousand milligrams, you know, an hour before the race.
So I'm curious if other athletes have tried that.
Yeah, I know. I'm not familiar with other athletes trying it, but I'm definitely going to try that
with my athletes now. Yeah, I would give it a try. And again, we don't even really know how
Tylenol works. So it's for such a common medication, we don't actually understand its mechanism of
action, but it is a very good medication at keeping temperature down, which is obviously its
first indication is to lower it, you know, for fever, but it also reduces pain and it does it
in a way that's different from NSAIDs. And, you know, outside of being needing to be careful on
the dose, because obviously it is a, it's a very liver toxic drug at high doses, but within normal
amounts like, you know, a thousand milligrams, you know, it's an incredibly safe drug. And it would
be curious to know how much of a benefit your athletes would get on that and how much you would
get from it. Yeah, I'll try that. Is there any application to lifting? If it's keeping your core
temperature down, it seemed that'd be helpful for lifting as well. I don't know. I haven't seen the
literature on lifting. You know where I did see literature on lifting, and this is freaking
hilarious. This was probably like eight years ago. I saw some papers that looked at how Viagra
improved lifting performance. So of course I went out and got a ton of Viagra. And in the end,
I couldn't do it, not for the reasons that most people would imagine. The reason I couldn't do
it is just the symptoms. I was getting so lightheaded from it because it's a vasodilator in part.
And so maybe my blood pressure is not that high. It's actually kind of low. And so maybe I just
couldn't tolerate the sort of lightheadedness that came from it. But the research was actually
pretty compelling. 25 to 50 milligrams of Viagra, boosting strength performance. And not just
strength. Actually, if I recall, it was more of muscular endurance, not strength actually.
And I didn't find the difference because of the symptoms that I had because of the side effects.
But that might be another thing worth experimenting with is kind of that 25 to 50 milligrams of Viagra
to see what does that do as far as not a mean maximal effort, but a submaximal effort repeatedly.
So probably you'd see more of that on your best 10 rep deadlift as opposed to your max deadlift.
Okay. That's interesting. So speaking at core temperature, have you played it all with
Palmer cooling? No.
Are you familiar with that at all? No. I mean, I used to check my core temp before and after
long swims because we had the opposite problem. You're swimming in cold water. And so sometimes
I'd actually swim with a rectal probe just to see how low. And usually your temp would drop like
four, five degrees. So you'd start at 98 or 99 and I'd come out of the water at 93, 94.
So you were getting a performance detriment when your temperature went too low. So really,
we really operate in this pretty narrow band of temperature, right? Too much and too little is
pretty bad. Right. Yeah. It's interesting. Like I've been a Dr. Huberman out of Stanford,
neuroscientist, he talks about Palmer cooling. So we've been playing with that a little bit.
Like there's some pretty remarkable research coming out of Stanford about the effects of that,
both in strength training and in the endurance space. It's a little hard. So how does it work?
So the best way is to dump heat core temp through your body is through your face,
your upper face where there's no hair. And then also through your hands and the bottom of your
feet. So they developed like this glove and they've had this for years. Like this was there at
Stanford when we were coming out. You put your hands in this glove and you dump heat. And the
thing is you don't want it too cold, right? So you don't want it like icy cold, just cool.
So that doesn't dilate your violation of dilation. Or constrict. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. And so then
you're dumping all your heat out, brings your core temp down and then you're good to go after
that. So we've been playing a little bit with that with like holding cold packs in your hands and
in between lifts, like holding cold things or putting your hands in cool water, dumping your
temp. And that's, that's kind of like one thing that we're playing with a little bit more,
but it makes a lot of sense to me. It's like why humans can do these persistence hunts, you know,
where they go and chase down animals. It's because the animal like overheats, it's not as good at
dumping temperature, whereas like humans are better at regulating temperature. So if you can
keep your temperature in that kind of optimal range, in theory, it should like increase your
endurance as well. So yeah, there's always like, I love like exploring this stuff and trying new
tactics out like that. So when you mentioned this now, I do recall, I have experimented with this,
what's called a cooling helmet. So I had this helmet that you, it had inserts into it that you
would put in the freezer. So like gel packs that you would freeze and you would put this thing on
your head. So I would ride on my trainer with this cooling helmet and it definitely made a difference,
but I never, for some reason I could never bring myself to do it like in a race or something like
that. But the other thing I've noticed on that effect was just this summer. So this was my first
summer living in Austin and obviously it gets super hot in Austin in the summer, hotter than
I'm used to in Southern California. And when I drive a race car, I've never used any form of
cooling device before. So I've always just drive like, you know, you got a fire suit on, so you
have no max suit on, you got a race suit on. And especially when you drive a closed cockpit car,
so not a formula car, you're not getting the wind as you're driving. And of course, these cars are
hot as hell because, you know, these are race cars, there's no air conditioning and you're just,
you've got all this engine heat coming at you. So you really get hot. And I've always just sort
of suffered through this, even though so many people I know say invest in a cooling vest. So
you have these vests that run ice water around your torso. And I was like, I don't need that.
I don't need that. I don't need that. I got this. I got this. I got this. And then finally,
one day my friend was like, dude, just try it. I mean, game changer, total game changer to drive
a racing car with a cooling vest on under hot conditions. So tell me more about this cooling
vest because we play with these things as well. I have kind of like the archaic ones that it's
like you put it, you fill it up, it turns into gel and then you freeze it. And it's just like,
it's slowly like gets back to temperature, but do these, do you actually like plug them in?
Yeah, this would not be great for a runner because it would be too heavy. But so it's a shirt
actually. And it has really, really fine, whatever little cables running up and down it.
And it has a little box that runs cold water through you, up and down, up and down, up and
down. And in the car, it's easy. You have a power unit, you're running it out of the car.
So it did occur to me, like is there a way, like if let's say the thing weighs an extra
six pounds, like what would be the cost trade off if you were on a bike with one of these things?
Like could one of these things be engineered to only add like maybe four or five pounds,
which would of course be detrimental on the bike, but would it offset by the performance gain you'd
have? But obviously in a car, it's an enormous performance booster, especially in close cockpit
cars. In formula cars, it's not as big a deal because you don't get as hot. You're getting
so much air blown on you. But yeah, it blew my mind what a difference that the temperature
would make in terms of performance and everything. Even like that night when you're done, the
difference between the day you use it and the day you don't is the difference between feeling like
you're going to die and feeling like, yeah, I'm tired, but I'm okay.
Yeah. And I bet you're like mentally in a lot better place too, right? It's like when you're
all super hot or super cold, like it's so easy to go mental really quick. So I bet it helps a ton
for you, like your focus. For sure. And even little silly things like you're perspiring less.
And even though you wear like a headstock of balaclava, like anytime sweat is getting in your
eyes, it's super annoying. You want to keep your hands on the steering wheel. So it's anything that
can get around that. So how do you implement that in a runner then? Like obviously I can see how in
strength training you can use that, but if you're training a guy to run a marathon, how can you
incorporate any of these cooling things into the actual race? Yeah. So I think part of it is like,
especially for guys who train in hot and humid places is just having it available beforehand.
Right? So at least like after you do your warm up, you do your drills and strides,
you're getting your core temperature back down by doing some heat dumping with your hands, you know?
And then if you're doing training, such as interval training, you know, you can get it in
between sets. So I'll have like a bucket of cold water at the track and just between sets, go put
your hands in there, dump a bunch of heat, and then back out it. And it definitely like, I feel
like it makes a big difference. You know, I feel like it's super helpful, but in terms of like
applying it while you're actually running, that's where you got to get more creative. So we've done
things with like these packs that you break, you know, those instant cold packs, break those open
and just hold them and you don't have to do it for like, I think like two minutes is kind of ideal
to hold them for that long, which is kind of a long time. That's kind of a hindrance, but if it's
worth the trade and you're getting the performance benefit from it, then it's, you know, maybe worth
it. But yeah, like I'm curious, I haven't tried the gloves that they have at Stanford that they
use on the football team and a lot of the athletic programs. But again, like you can't like, you know,
stop your run in the middle of a race and put your hands in some cold glove. But who knows like
what the application could be. It just, it just requires somebody to get creative with it, you
know, and figure out a way to make it more applicable to running. Like when you're mentioning
like the biking, I was like, Oh, it'd be cool if they could make like somehow the handles
be colder, you know, put some kind of technology in there. So then you're getting palmer cooling
while your hands are on the handles, like things like that. They find a way to do it in a lightweight
way. It could be like really powerful, you know. Yeah. That's actually a great idea if it could be
done again, really light because these days most bikes are, most bikes are coming in at below the
UCI limit of whatever it is now 14.9 pounds. So most cyclists actually have to add ballast to
their bikes, you know, in the Tour de France, like most cyclists are actually adding weight to their
bikes to get them up to legal weight. So yeah, there's definitely a bit of room to play with
there. I don't know how much, but that would be, that would be pretty cool. So speaking of Stanford,
that's where you go to college, right? I assume you were recruited very heavily to every, you know,
top running powerhouse program there was, right? Yeah. Yeah. Which was cool. Because I was in the
middle of five kids growing up and my dad was a teacher, my mom's a stay-at-home mom. So we're
always like, you know, pinch and pennies. So I knew like part of running for me is like, if I'm going
to go to a good college, like I'm going to have to earn my way there kind of thing, you know?
So yeah, it was pretty cool to like be getting recruited all over the place. And it's funny
because Stanford was the one place I was like, I'm definitely not going to Stanford because,
you know, I wasn't heavily focused on academics in high school. I knew the academics, like they
don't, they don't cut slack to athletes there. Like we're in it just like everyone else, you know,
like there's not a lot of special assistants going on. So I knew it'd be like academically a super
big challenge for me as well as like the athletic part. And I was like, I don't know. I just don't
want to put myself in that kind of a challenging space. And it was, it was super challenging. Like
it was three years of really big struggle. And then, you know, I hit one cross country season
really well, was a part of a NCAA winning team, two years there in cross country. And then my,
my fourth year at Stanford, things just clicked. And that's the thing I love about running and
fitness in general, it's like everything can be going so wrong for so long. And then yet, like when,
when things start to click, it's such a good feeling when you push through and you get to that
point where it's just coming, you know, the weight's coming off the ground easy. And it's such a cool
feeling. That was the sensation I had during that fourth year, me and my teammate, Ian Dobson went
one, two in track. And at that point, like I was, I was having a very lackluster career at Stanford.
I'd never even been to NCAA championships in track, but again, in running, it doesn't matter,
right? It's just you and the clock and the other guys out there and everything was clicking. We
went one, two in C's and all of a sudden it was like deals are coming in and I had the opportunity
to run professionally. And I'm saying for my wife, Sarah, and we, we, I was planning on coming back
for a fifth year, but because things clicked so well that year, I'd seen some of my other
teammates come through Stanford, have a really good fourth year and then not do well their fifth
year and then have no contract. Right. Did you venture your first year? Yeah, I retried my freshman
year. I was, like I said, I was on the struggle bus. I was hurt. I was injured. I was sick. I'd
get poison Oak every winter. Like it was like the perfect combination of everything going wrong. I
was struggling academically. I struggled with depression. Actually left Stanford for a quarter
my sophomore year. I wasn't sure if I was going to go back. And, you know, I thought in that
situation that I could change what was going on inside of my head and heart by changing my
location. So I was like, I'm gonna go back home. The last place everything was clicking for me and
everything was working. I was sick of the struggle, you know, and I went back home and got even more
depressed. And I was like, well, that, that was stupid. Like go back to, to where I knew I was
supposed to be and that was Stanford. So I went back there and then things gradually started to
get better. And, um, but yeah, I had my struggles at Stanford, you know, like it was a beautiful
place to go to school, love the people, the environment. I still like to go back and visit
there, but it was for the most part, like a big, big struggle in, in all areas, athletically,
academically. And, uh, so yeah, but again, I hit it that fourth year and then the doors came open
to thrown professionally and, uh, left the farm after that. What do you, what do you think changed
and clicked? Like what, what do you think you were struggling with from a running perspective? Um,
because I think in high school you ran a four Oh two mile, which I know you wanted to break that
four minute barrier, uh, which is pretty rarefied air. Isn't Jim Ryan and Alan Webb,
the only two to do that or has someone else now broken four minutes, uh, for the mile in high
school? Yeah. At the time when I was running, there was only four guys who had done it. Um,
so yeah, Jim Ryan, two other guys blanking on their name, then Alan. And, uh, you know,
I was the same year you mentioned swimming with Alan. I love Alan, like good friends with him,
such a good dude. Um, but yeah, I remember watching him run three 53 at pre and it was just
like, my head exploded. It was like, I can't believe I just saw that. That was just like,
that was unbelievable. Right. Like that. Yeah. And then he went to Michigan and struggled, right?
I mean, it wasn't, yeah. Yeah. He struggled his sophomore year. Yeah. Him and I like have a lot
of parallels, even like the year that we both hit it big 2007. Um, he set the AR in the, in the mile.
I set the AR in the half. And, um, we were like crossing paths all the time too. Like I was this
roommate over in Europe in 2006 when we were over there racing that summer, we were both struggling,
for various reasons, you know, but, um, we, we both like have very high highs and very low lows.
Alan and I are pretty similar that way, you know, but he's definitely like one of the most talented
runners I've ever seen. Like the amount of talent that guy has, he just, he, he has such a good work
ethic that sometimes it comes back to bite them. Like we'd be on the track in Europe and he goes,
does his run and then he's doing like hurdle drills and plios and all this stuff for like hours
afterwards. And we're all like have left and we're showered up and eating and he's like still out
there grinding, right? So he just like would be so intensely focused that, um, you know, when it was
clicking, it was great, but I think sometimes he kind of overcooked himself a little bit, but,
uh, man, it's such an immense talent and it was so cool to get to see him have his moment, you know,
run three 46 for the mile was he was just, he was insane that year. He was just on fire. He's just
untouchable. If, if the Olympics would have been that year, he'd been a gold medalist, like without
a doubt. Do you remember his Olympic trials in 04 in Sacramento when he just ran away from the field?
Like I, you know, that's again, just one of those moments I remember. Cause that, that was actually
the summer that I think 03 and 04 were the summers that I saw him the most at the pool. And like you
wouldn't believe that that was a 1500 in terms of the margin of victory he had over those guys,
right? Like that looked like a 5,000 or a 10 K in terms of how far ahead he was of everybody else.
Yeah. I mean, he was so dominant when he was on, like people weren't beating him. He was,
she was impossible to beat. So he was fun to watch in his, in his prime.
So what do you think changed in your senior year? Oh yeah. Yeah. We were talking about that.
I know. I keep distracting you. I'm, I'm, I'm, I'm doing a horrible job here today. I keep taking
us on these tangents and I just, yeah, this is more of a dinner conversation than a podcast.
Yeah. No, I like it. I like it. Um, so funny thing is I'm always very concerned with the nuts and
bolts of training, what I'm doing, right? That's always my focus as an athlete. And yet what I've
kind of the lesson that I've had to learn from the time I've gotten into sports since a kid until now
at 39 is like, it's way more important how I do what I'm doing, meaning like my heart condition,
what's going on in my head, then what I'm actually doing. So like, for example, like my tendency is
to try to prove myself in training to myself. Like I'm not really trying to prove myself to anyone
else. I just want to know I'm fit. I'm ready to go. Right? So oftentimes I'll come to these workouts
and I'm racing them. It's like, I'm going head down, like all out, like everything I have inside
me. Oftentimes I'm going harder in training than I'm going in racing. Right. And yet like that is
not the best way for my body to absorb the work. Like I need to be making deposits, not making
withdrawals when I'm training. So if I, if I go into these workouts confident in who I am,
knowing the purpose of the workout, then I'm in a much better place. I'm absorbing the training a
lot better. So, um, what happened to answer your question was my identity was all wrapped up in my
performances. Right? So, and that's why I struggle with depression is I look in the mirror in the
morning. I was struggling with my running. I was hurt. I was frustrated with how things were going.
I wasn't getting better. And so I just saw myself as a failure, you know, and, um, is very difficult
to have that happen every single morning. Get up, look in the mirror, failure, failure, failure,
failure, you know? And so when I went back home, like my faith has always been a huge part of my
life. And, uh, I started to realize like, I need to see myself how God sees me and how God sees me
has nothing to do with my performance. Right? It's like, think about like your kids, right? Like,
you don't really care how good they are at a certain sport, right? Like you love, right?
It's unconditional who they are. Yeah. And so like, can I love myself that same way, right?
Oftentimes like we're able to love other people and treat other people a lot better than we actually
treat ourself in our mind, you know? And so I started to kind of get to the bottom of that and
be like, you know what? Like God loves me regardless of how I do. So I'm going to choose
on a daily basis. It wasn't a one-time thing. It's still something I have to cultivate to this day.
Like I'm going to choose to love myself regardless of how I'm performing, right? Like what really
makes me special has nothing to do with how fast I am or how much weight I can lift or any of those
things. And as that began to sink in, it took all the pressure off myself. Like I was just carrying
around this like heavy burden to every single workout, every single race. Because if I wasn't
proving to myself that I was important by running fast, I was hating myself, right? And so as I took
these weights off and be like, no, actually I'm cool with who I am. Like actually I love myself,
whether I have a great workout or a bad workout, that just took the weights off. And it also made
me fearless too. It's like, okay, now I can go out and just air it out and I'm going to fail a bunch
of times and I can live with that. I'm okay with that, right? So there's something powerful about
coming to peace with the worst case scenario. And it might sound like a place you shouldn't go,
before a race, but oftentimes I do like to go there. I'm like, okay, like I could go out with
all these African guys, go out under 62 minutes for the half marathon in route to a marathon at
Boston. I might blow up, might not work out. Like, but hey, I know I can handle that. I know I'm okay.
I'm cool with myself if that happens and I'm gonna give myself a shot. And I think that's what we're
kind of lacking for a lot of American distance runners is the willingness to put yourself out
there to take a big risk. And that's what the Africans, their mentality is just like, no, you
just go with the lead group. And if you blow up, don't take it personally, get up and go again the
next time, right? Like they don't take their failures personally. Whereas like Americans, myself,
like I take it super personally, right? If I fail, that means I'm a failure. For them, it's like they
fail, like that's just a part of the process. Who cares? Like just go again, you know? So as those
weights were able to come off me, my approach to workouts, to races changed, things started to
click a lot better. A big thing is I learned also too, like I didn't have to beat my work, my teammates
in training anymore. Like I could just work with them. I didn't have to try to drop them. Even if
I could drop them, I was like, I don't need to, like I'm secure in who I am, you know? So that was
a huge shift. But again, it wasn't like all of a sudden, and bam, the results came. It was like
years and years and then it turned into something. So that was really the most freeing thing I think
I've experienced in my career in terms of what's going on internally that freed me up to enter into
my full potential in running. And despite how much of just this kind of very friendly person you are,
I would imagine that you kind of alienated a lot of teammates when you came in with that mode of
every workout is hammer time. Yes. A hundred percent. Like I would go home over the summer
and usually it's supposed to be kind of like chill base building training, right? And I would just
train my brains out and I would come back and I would just be blasting everyone all the time.
Yeah. I remember talking to now like one of my good friends and teammates, Ian Dobson,
and he's a big reason why I did so well coming out of Stanford in my first years as a pro runner.
He's like, dude, yeah, we used to like not be a fan. Like you're just always trying to like,
like you'd always come back in super good shape and you're always taking it to us. And, and that
changed like as I was able to work with guys, I got along a lot better with them. And I just learned
like just communicate with people, right? Like if I tell these guys, like I'm working out with my
teammates, hey guys, like I'm feeling really good. I'm just gonna go a little bit quicker if that's
cool. Like that's a lot different than just like taking off without saying anything. So like for
people who are working out in like group environments, like it's crazy just how that
little communication within the group can really shift things, the dynamics of the group and make
it to where like everyone's cool with what's happening and you're not just like throwing
in random surges. And there's a lot of that that goes on and running, you know, within groups,
like there's races and different characters and people who can't work out in groups. And
it gets, it gets a little bit intense at times, but if, if the communication is there, like guys
can work together and actually make each other better. So when you turn pro, is that what? Oh,
five. Yeah. Um, and I think your lead sponsor is a six at the time, right? Yep. Correct. So had it
entered your mind yet that you would find your sweet spot in this half marathon to marathon
world, or were you still thinking, you know, I'm going to be a 5k, 10k guy. Like what were you
thinking in Oh, five was going to be, uh, the place where you would make your mark? Yeah. So I never
thought I'd run a marathon. Right. So I grew up like loving the movie pre Fontaine and you know,
that scene where he's like, no one's going to tell me I'm not fast enough. You know, but like the
truth is like I wasn't fast enough. I wanted to be a miler, right? And kind of like what we're
chatting about earlier, the importance of speed. It's like only having, I ran 50 for 400, um, in
high school, but only having that kind of speed limited my upper end potential. I mean, in the
5,000 meters, guys are closing in 52. So if your top end speed is 50, like you're gonna have a hard
time closing in 52, right? So your best 5k is like 13, 16, 16. Yeah. And put that in perspective.
What's the American record in the 5k? Good question. Where's it at now? It's around 1250, give or take.
Yeah. So at the time, like that was one of the faster times coming out of college, you know,
things are definitely shifting a lot with, uh, you know, the new shoe technology and stuff in
terms of times. Um, but yeah, at the time, like that was a pretty solid run. So, and, and that's
why like coming off the wake of that, I spent a year professionally just focusing on the 5k,
didn't improve it all over the 5k. My 5k stayed roughly the same. I think I ran like 1320 something
1322 the next year and the Beijing Olympics were kind of on the horizon. The trials was coming up
the following year. And it's kind of one of those things where I was like, I got to figure out
like my vision for my running was always to run with the best guys in the world. And what event
not am I going to be most competitive in here? And you know, I'm 23 years old. I got to figure
this out. And so I, there was all of a sudden an openness to longer distances. Um, whereas before
I'd always been, like I said, very close minded, just being like, I'm just want to be a world-class
miler like Alan was, you know, uh, so how many half marathons had you run before Houston in 07?
Zero. That was your first half marathon. Yeah, that was my first. I had run a couple 20k's,
which is essentially the same thing. It's like a, a K less. Right. So, um, but yeah,
I got worked on the track that first year and I'll never forget. I was in London,
I was racing against, um, Bekayle, which is the world record holder at the time over 5,000 meters.
And, uh, I remember I was coming down the back stretch of the track and I was watching on the
jumbotron, Bekayle and Craig Machram, an Australian guy finishing in this kicking dual. And I was like
nowhere even close to him. Right. And it was kind of like one of those moments of being like,
yeah, this isn't, this isn't my best event, like a moment of realization. So then that openness
allowed me to start experimenting with longer stuff. So I went home that summer, started
training for some longer distance stuff, did the world 20k championships, the US national 20k
champs, and it was clicking pretty well. And then I got into marathon training over the winter,
over the late fall slash winter. And Houston was just supposed to be like a check-in along the way.
Let's see how this marathon training is going. I was planning on debuting at the Los Angeles marathon,
because there weren't like a lot of offers out on the table, having not really run a lot of longer
distance races. So take me back to this race in Houston. Cause I don't, I don't think, I think I
missed somewhere in there that that was actually your first half marathon because obviously the
result of that race is so out of this world that it's, it's easy to miss that little detail. So it's,
it's the beginning of 2007 year before, you know, a year and a half before the Olympics,
you're sort of trying to figure out where you, where you belong in this running world. You show
up to Houston. It's, and at the time the American record for a half marathon is an hour and 55
seconds. So tell me what you're thinking at the start line. What are your expectations? What are
you there to prove to yourself? So I had written down on my hands, this was like before the days of
like a GPS watch that isn't overly cumbersome, you know, like they're the big old brick ones,
but not like little nice ones. So I was just using a Timex watch, right? And so I had written down on
my hand, like three different categories of times that I was going for. So like one, if I was having
an A day and that was like just under American record pace, one, if I was having a B day, which
was like 61 30 or something and one for like a C day, like 62 flat, right? And and like I said,
training was just going phenomenal. Like where I was blowing my own mind, but more like it's the
feeling like that's what I love the most about athletics and about running and about that day.
Like I described Houston as being like heaven and hell at the same time. It was heaven because like
I was floating the whole time. It felt easy the entire way. It was insane. Like the coolest
sensation, one of the coolest bodily sensations I've ever experienced in my life. And if I could
go to heaven and experience that feeling of running like that every single day, I would like it was
unreal. But the reason why it was also hell and it kind of haunted me is especially all throughout
my running careers, I can never get back there. So it is my best half marathon by far. I never
broke 61 again, and I can never figure out how to go back to that place. And you went 59,
59 43. So you obliterate the American record. Like that's over a minute off the American record.
Right. And so I was running going back to the story of the race, like the first mile,
I was just going out and you know, now we have so much science and technology and heart rate we can
go off of. And we're looking at our watch a million times, but again, I'm just looking at like my
normal time X watch. And so I am what's happening in my mind in that first mile is I'm literally
like going into my mind's eye, picturing myself back on green church road in mammoth where we
trained and being like, if I was running a 13 mile threshold, could I maintain this effort that I'm
currently at? And the answer was yes. So I was just rolling with it, right? Came through the first
miles like 535. I was like, that felt too easy. Like I wasn't supposed to be running this fast,
but that just felt too easy. So let me just like notch it down a little bit more. And it
effort that I know again, going back in my mind's eye, I know I can hold this effort to the finish
and next mile is like 5432. And then the next mile was like 428. And I was just like starting
to scare myself a little bit. I was like, okay, like let's not screw this thing up. Like obviously
you're going to have a heck of a day today. No one else is around like mebs in the race and all those
guys like from the very first miles, just me and the roads, right? But it didn't matter. Like I was
so mentally clicked in and like everything was just firing is just like all how it's supposed to
be, right? Like the most magical sensation like I've ever had. And so I just kept pushing and just
again, like it's waiting for it to get hard almost. And it never, never did. Like I had one issue out
there around mile nine where my stomach got a little bit turny because over half marathon,
we're not taking in any fluids if the weather's right, the cool conditions and it was a nice,
cool, perfect day to run in Houston that day, flat course. And so I wasn't taking in anything
around mile nine. My stomach got a little bit upset and that passed a couple minutes later,
but literally like it was easy the entire way. Like I'm still super curious if I had pacemakers
and if that was a full marathon, what I could have run that day. Cause I got myself back in
really good shape, but never that kind of shape over half marathon again. And, and looking back
on it, that's why I like, I'm such a big proponent of speed now, right? It's like I had spent not just
the last year focused on 5k development. I had spent my entire running career from the time I was
13 for 10 years until I was 23 working on speed, working on five. And then all of a sudden I piled
on marathon training where I'm hitting longer thresholds, higher volume than I've ever done
before and bang, there it is. Right. And so that's why that 5k speed, like I can't emphasize it enough
with my athletes. I'm coaching now. Like you just, you have the further away I got from that 5k
fitness, the harder the half felt the harder the marathon felt. But that day in Houston, it was
just like a warm knife through butter all day long. When you crossed that finish line, did you feel
like, you know, I actually could have gone a little bit harder. Yeah, that's interesting, right?
Because I'm talking about how easy it felt yet. Like I wasn't like leaving anything in the tank
necessarily, you know? So I felt like I was running as hard as I ran practice. But I mean, if you watch,
go back and watch like YouTube video, I mean, like I didn't, and that's why like when people do like
kip chogi breaking too, like he didn't look crazy tired after that, right? But there's also, you get
this huge hit of adrenaline when you come across the line, do something like that. Like breaking
60 was kind of a lifetime goal for me. And then to go and do it, my first marathon and like period
was crazy too. Like, so my parents were on the lead vehicle. My wife was on the lead vehicle,
my agent, my coach, they're all on the lead vehicle. So I'm literally staring at them the entire race
and they're not allowed to cheer or anything. But you know, like any athletic performance that I've
done, like I was just a piece of the puzzle, right? Like it wasn't all me, like my mom, like
she provided the safe place for me, my refuge. Every time I would come back all rattled because
I had a bad workout, I got hurt or whatever. Like she was like, she provided that home that provided
that refuge. My dad was my coach. My wife was there for me through the depression at Stanford and all
the times, all the good, all the bad, you know? And so staring at the people who are your team,
the entire race was like hugely emotionally empowering for me as well, you know? So I'll
never forget. I was actually, they get to the finish line, the lead car, they kind of zip up
the road a little bit. They drop my parents and Sarah, my wife, like 200 meters before the finish
line. And they have to like, they're like running back to try to get to the finish before I get
there. So I'm coming down the finishing stretch and I see my mom just like booking it, like trying
to make it to the finish line before I get there. And I actually passed her. She didn't make it. So
like, if you look closely in some of the, they might've blurred her out in some of the pictures,
but like she's in the back like sprinting behind me. But yeah, I'll never forget like coming across
the finish line, giving my parents a big hug, giving my wife big hug, my coach. And it was kind
of this, the sensation of like, we did this, you know? Like it wasn't so special because I felt
like I had done anything incredible, but it was like, we all did this thing together. And it was
just an amazing lifetime, you know, moment that I'll never forget.
Now from a professional standpoint, how much did your life change in that moment? Because that
really puts you on the map as America's great hope for the marathon in 2008, right?
Yeah. I mean, it was huge. I went from, you know, like a guy who was decent on the track,
NCAA champs. I had a little bit of credentials behind me that put me inside of the top 10
all-time performers over half marathon. So it was kind of like all of a sudden this moment of
realization of like, oh dang, like I have a chance at this. Like I have a chance at meddling
in Beijing. Like I, you know, there was just the excitement of like, I found it. Like I felt like
I'd been hitting my head against a wall for so long with the shorter distance stuff. Just wasn't
quite clicking, right? Like it just wasn't quite me. And that day in Houston is like,
this is what I was created to do, right? And I think it's, we all have this kind of experience
in life where we're kind of searching out like, what am I here for? Like, why was I created? Like,
what is my giftedness? When you find like that area where like, this is why I'm here. This is
how I was made to, this is what I was made to do, right? It's kind of that moment of like, whoa,
like this is, this is it. This is my thing, you know? And it did like create a little bit more of
heighten my own expectations, you know? Like after that, like I never showed up in another race
thinking I couldn't win or not having high expectations for the race, you know? So that
was maybe a little bit of a harder thing for me to manage. But it was just more than anything,
just a cool moment of like realizing like now I'm in the club, you know, with the best guys in the
world. I think you said it really well, right? Which is this was heaven, this was hell. And
the hell part of that is something that I've always observed great athletes with just a
tincture of sadness too, because the stage on which you compete is the most brutal stage,
because it's the one for which you have the shortest half-life, right? So, you know, when you
say like, this is what I was meant to do, on the one hand, most of us can not even relate to what
you're talking about, right? Like I can't relate to being the best in the world at anything.
Anything. I couldn't relate to being the best, the best, the thousandth best person in the world at
anything. Anything, right? Physical, not physical, doesn't matter. But now when you take that thing
that is your gift and you acknowledge that, well, actually it's something that is very fleeting,
right? Like there's a very narrow window in your life in which you get to be really good at this.
And by the way, as a runner, technically it's a day, right? Like you're going to have a single
best run and you don't necessarily know when it's going to be. You might be very good for a
decade, but there's really going to be a time when you look back and say, that was the best I could
ever do. Obviously for the half marathon, we know when that day was. Four years later, it would be
your best marathon of all time. But I think for some people, I would imagine at least that makes
being a retired athlete or an athlete who's passed his or her prime a very difficult process.
Do you talk with your athletes about that? Even though they're on the upswing, right? They're in
the part of the, hey, I want to get better. I want to get better. But do you spend any time with them
talking about, hey, first of all, enjoy this like crazy because it's going to be gone and it's going
to be gone probably by the time you're 30 and you have the rest of your life to not be the best at
this thing. And secondly, here's how you can prepare for that. Yeah, absolutely. I mean, I talk a lot
with my wife about that because she's 38 turning 39 in April and she's actually running the best
stuff she's ever run still, which is incredible. And I think speaks to like why women age better
than men in a lot of ways. But what was really impactful for me at the end of my career
was this moment I was in an airplane. I was looking out over everything and just trying
to get clarity about what was going on. So I just been through four years of massive struggle,
right? And what I felt like was just kind of like having a little prayer sesh with God. And
what I felt like was sensing is just this reminder that it's not meant to last forever.
Because I think like you're saying Peter, it's like when you're in it, you feel like it is going
to last forever and it is supposed to last forever. But that's actually the like what makes
life so beautiful, right? Is that like nothing lasts forever, right? It's like what makes the
sunset so beautiful. It doesn't just stay in the sky forever. So what makes life so special because
it's not just going to go on forever, right? So having that moment of realization that this,
it's okay for it to not last forever. It's okay that like that was my day. And I did, I savored it
for everything is worth, right? And that's absolutely what I tell my athletes as well, like
savor every second of it, right? But life is going to change. You're going to enter into new seasons.
And life is beautiful every single day all around you, right? So like having this perspective of
yes, this is very important. This is what we're going after. But like true beauty is around us
all the time. If we have the eyes to see it and the ears to hear it. And so like removing ourselves
from performance some ways can be super, super helpful. Not only as we transition out of sport,
but even when we're in sport and just being like, this is something that is adding to my life. It
is not my life, right? And like I can have this day in Houston, have this very beautiful experience,
this very magical day, but I can actually just go for a walk outside my house and look at the trees
and look at the sun and the stars and be outside in the moon and get the same kind of like gratitude
for life just by simply entering into nature and being fully present in it. So I've definitely
like my perspective has changed as for a long time, just all wrapped into this performance,
performance, performance, performance, you know? And it's easy to be that way. And I do enjoy going
after performances. I love like seeing growth, seeing change in the body, seeing adaptation,
going after big goals. Like I love that's still very much who I am. And I think that's something
that helps people transition out of the sport. A lot of people talk about having a sense of identity
loss when they stop doing whatever their sport is. But for me, like I had to figure out how do
I stay true to who I am? Because running was just an expression of who I was, right? And it was
like my painting, right? But now like I have to find another mechanism to express who I am. So
I'm doing that like in the lifting space and these crazy challenges that I'm doing, I'm still like
finding a way to express myself. And I think that's what as humans like we want to have that
experience, right? Like we're here for a reason and we want to express ourselves on our canvas,
whatever it might be. And when you lose that ability to be able to express yourself,
that's when things can get dark pretty quick, right? So like for people, for my athletes who
are transitioning out of the sports being like, okay, like how do you stay true to who you are?
Like I love physical challenge. I love seeing growth. And so I'm going to express it now through
lifting. And that's going to come to an end at some point. And then I'm going to find another
way to express it. But I think as long as we're continually finding ways to be ourself and to
express ourself, we're going to be happy individuals. In some ways, your experience
post this amazing breakthrough in the half marathon is kind of paralleled in a way with
what happened in 2011, right? So you go into Beijing in 08, in some ways with the expectation
of the running world on your shoulders, like you're going to medal in the marathon. Your
trajectory has been unbelievable. We talked about that race, 10th place finish still very impressive,
especially the way in which you did it where you went out a little tentative and then had to kind
of try to reel people back and go from 60th to 10th. Now let's fast forward. It's 2011.
How were you feeling going into the Boston marathon that year? What was it about your
training that led you into that race so poised to do so well?
Yeah, so I had a big transition. So I was trained up in Mammoth and in 2010,
I left the Mammoth Track Club. And again, a big part was my faith was inspiring that decision.
I've always just been a super spiritual person and have a ton of respect from people of every
faith, tradition, and background. But for my own journey, I just love that part of life,
that spiritual dimension. And I was just really desperate to experience God in some way, right?
So I decided to leave the Mammoth Track Club and essentially have God as my coach. But really,
that just looked like me spending a lot of time in prayer, trying to connect with God. And again,
that's where I got this kind of revelation. It's not about what I do. It's about how I do what I
do. That came from that season. So I kind of went through the season and then I was kind of
experimenting with some new styles of training that I'd never done before. And again, new stimulus
always is helpful for the body, right? So I'd been kind of in the same routine,
the same doing the same structured training. And there's little variations.
Tell me a little bit about that. Because one of the things my wife actually insisted on today,
and I'm not doing a good job of it, though I promise I will, is she, my wife's a runner,
and she really wants to know every detail about your training. And so maybe we can talk a little
bit about it here in the pre-transition, so i.e. in the 2010 Mammoth Days, kind of what's your
volume? How did you warm up? How much body work were you doing? What kind of stretching? All that
sort of stuff. Like what were the tempo runs like? And then I'm curious to hear what that looked like
when you basically became self-coached, right? Post, post that departure.
Yeah, so it's pretty simple, you know? It's like just to lay out like a quick sample week. Like
every Tuesday I'm doing interval sessions where you're working on that kind of like 5k specific
kind of speed. Things like 6xmile, 10xk, 800 meter repeats, 400 meter repeats. I've kind of
since gravitated more towards shorter distance repeats, 400s, 200s, things like that. I think
that's way more important for marathoners because you kind of want a lot of differential between
how fast those Tuesday intervals are compared to your like Thursday or Friday threshold.
Prior to your departure when they were one mile repeats and 1k repeats,
let's say the main set was 10 by a kilometer or 6xmile. That's the main set. What's the warm-up?
How do you go from like when you arrive at the track, what's the first thing you do?
So we do like 20-minute easy jog and then we'd come back, do some like dynamic flexibility or
maybe some static stuff but not a lot of static stretching going on. Stretching has not been a huge
part of like my running. You actually want some tension in your legs. Think about it like your
muscles being springs. Like if there's some tension, a tightly wound spring is going to respond to the
ground quicker, right? Compared to like a slinky that's super slow. So you actually want a certain
amount of tension, healthy tension. You want full range of motion. But so we're doing a lot
so like mobility work to get that full range but keeping some tension in the legs. So not a lot of
static. That 20-minute jog for you is what pace? That's like eight minute mile. I mean, how slow?
Yeah, yep. Kind of like that eight minute mile pace kind of range. Kind of just like let your
body do what it wants to do but no effort, right? You're not breathing hard. You're conversational
the whole time. Get back, you do that dynamic flexibility and stuff. Go into some drills and
strides. And I have videos of all this on my YouTube channel, Run Free Training YouTube channel.
People are curious to check it out. But drills and strides before maybe like it takes like
five, 10 minutes to do that. The strides are maybe like six times a hundred meters,
something like that. And then change shoes into your racing shoes and then straight into the workout.
And then you would do, let's say it's a six by a mile. How fast would you run that mile? So if your
your half marathon pace would be a 432-ish, your marathon pace would be a 442 to 445.
How much faster do you need to run that mile? So yeah, if we're doing it up at altitude,
I would typically be running right around that kind of 430 pace at 7,000 feet. So if you're down
at sea level, that's kind of equivalent to like 420-ish, maybe a tad bit under. So that the six
by a mile and the K's, that's more of like 10K specific workout. But again, I would kind of
gravitate more towards like 5K specific stuff. How much rest in between each set?
So with the miles, we'd keep it fairly tight, like 90 seconds to two minutes. Again,
kind of depends. It's like when you're at altitude, you take a little bit more rest,
but it's crazy. As you get fit, you recover super fast. And the intensity, it's like we're not
doing like max sprints where those guys got to take like 10 minutes between sprints. Right.
Like we're very much like when you're doing that 10K range, ideally you're running an effort,
you should be able to hold for 10K and you're stopping at a mile. So you're not like killing
it, you know? So anywhere between 90 seconds and two minutes on the rest. Walking during the
90 second recovery or standing still? Yeah, you're walking. Kind of sometimes we're like walk jogging,
just like slow walk jog. Kind of depends. Like I like doing in and out kind of intervals too.
That was like one of Prefontaine's workouts where he'd do like 200 meters fast, 200 meters kind of
moderate. So the moderate part would be at like eight minute pace or even faster, like seven minute
pace. And then the fast part is like goal 5K pace or slightly slower than mile pace even. So there's
a lot of different ways, variations that we take on those workouts. And what would be the cool down
at the end of that main set? And then a 20 minute cool down. And then the whole day, you know,
we're just spent like resting, doing some mobility work, eating, ice bath thing, which,
you know, it's funny, like the science on the ice bath has changed quite a bit. Like we would go
from these workouts in long run straight to the creek, straight into cold water. Whereas, you know,
the science is now showing you want your body to respond to the inflammation first. So that's more
what we do now where we would do an ice bath. I don't, we don't do a ton of ice baths in general,
but there's a whole bunch of other good positive effects of ice bath thing like dopamine going up
10 fold and all this stuff. Right. That's enough. Some antidepressant effects. Right. And would you
be doing two workouts on that day or one? So yeah. So then we'll come back in the afternoon,
just like a 30, 35 minute easy run, and then go straight to the weight room and then do our leg
lifting. So that's, that's a mistake. I see a lot of runners make is you want all your leg stressors
to be on the same day. And it's not what you feel like doing. Like you don't feel like doing
weights after doing a hard run. You do the hard run first, and then ideally you come back in the
afternoon. You could do it right after the hard run, but you probably won't get quite as much out
of it. Cause you're bringing fatigue into the lifting. If you space it out a little bit more,
you usually feel better during the lifting. So yeah, we do our hard leg session in the afternoon
and then, and then head home, eat early to bed. I always describe my life was more of a professional
sleeper than a professional running. Like honestly, I was just sleeping all the time. I
would book out every single day from one to 3 PM would be my business meeting. And so no calls,
nothing scheduled during that time. And those were just two hour naps every single day. So
the sleep and that's the thing. So what were you sleeping like 10 hours a day between the nap and
night? Yeah, yeah, probably right around there. I'm like, I'm probably in bed for nine to 10 hours
every night, but there's also be some restlessness from the hard training and, and honestly,
maybe even from sleeping too much, you know, I wasn't very sleep deprived. So sometimes I'd
wake up in the middle of the night, be starving, go get some a snack, get back in bed, lay there
and awake for an hour or two, then fall back asleep. But just you want, it's like, like the
Kenyans, the Ethiopians, they spend a ton of time off their feet as well. Right? So it's like when
you're not training, you're trying to not be doing anything. So we're like runners, pro runners are
very lazy people like from day to day, like don't go for walks or hikes or do anything. It's just
train, eat, sleep, stay off your feet. Like, and you're always aware of that energy expenditure.
You're trying to save as much as you can for your training. I remember in high school, I grew up in
Canada and so we had a lot of really amazing Jamaican runners. Of course they were sprinters
and they used to just tease each other so much because they'd be like, they'd be like, look,
we are the laziest people you will ever meet. And if you want to make us run faster, just put a
couch at the finish line. Like whoever can get to the finish line first gets to lay on that couch.
But it was really work hard, play hard, right? It was really like super intense workouts these guys
would do. And then as much nothing as possible to really conserve energy. Now, as you probably know,
cyclists have to work very hard deliberately to calorie restrict and often they show up
to major tour events, right? So not the one day classic stuff, but when you're thinking about
the Tour de France, the Giro, the Vuelta, these sort of huge stage races, they're very depleted,
right? They're showing up, like they're trying to be as light as possible. Everything comes down to
this one single metric that I think running doesn't quite have, but in cycling you have this thing
called Watts per kilo. Everything is Watts per kilo. If you lined up all the cyclists at the
beginning of the Tour de France, and you could know what everybody's threshold was in Watts per kilo,
that would predict the order they would finish barring a strategic mishap or an injury or an
accident. How deliberately were you watching your weight during this period of time? Or were you
basically just saying, I could eat as much as I wanted and my weight would basically float to a
level that I was happy with? Yeah, no. I mean, I was very specific with it. And preface all this
with just saying, it's not the most healthy lifestyle, right? Doing what I was doing,
training the level I was doing wasn't optimal for my health. My testosterone was clinically low
every single time I tested it, right? How low? In the hundreds, like 150, something like that.
So you had the testosterone of a woman. Yeah, which is really interesting. How do you run so
fast with such low testosterone? I don't understand that. Yeah. When I finished residency,
my testosterone was in the two twenties. So it was probably in the low 200s throughout all of
residency, and not because of training, just because of sleep deprivation and a whole bunch
of other factors. But wow, that's 100s is staggeringly low. Yeah. And it would kind of come back up
when I take these two week breaks, right? So going back to the weight thing, I would take,
I would get down to, ideally I raced my best at 137. I got, I'm five foot 10. I got down as low
as 127, but I wasn't, if I was less than 137, I was getting worse, which is really interesting.
Cause I was on Lance's podcast and we were chatting about this and he said he didn't ever
feel like he could get too light. Whereas I was much the opposite. If I was under 137, it was,
it was not good for me at all. Lance was a really big cyclist for his type of racing. I mean,
Lance's race weight was like 160 to 165, which for a guy who's five foot nine, five foot 10,
that's quite a lot of weight for a guy who was such a good climber. And I think today we see
guys being quite a bit lighter in the, in the, in that group. Like I think a GC contender today
is God, probably like 140 pounds, you know, five, five nine 140 would be a great cyclist build.
So for you to be, so if you're, if you're optimal, which by the way, 137, that still
strikes me as crazy light, but if you're 137, were you managing up to that weight or down to that
weight? Down to that weight. So, so yeah, I take these two week breaks where I wouldn't run at all
and literally it was like donut eating competition for two weeks. So I would, I'd literally put on
like over 10 pounds in that two week period. And I hated myself for doing that. Like it wasn't good
for me emotionally or mentally, but it worked every single time for my buildup. So again,
I'm not saying like athletes should do this, right? But my problem was I was getting so lean and so
like I, I should have taken a more healthy approach to putting on weight, to being good to
my body, shifting my macros around during that time off and doing a healthy way, not with a bunch of
crap like I was doing. But I'd put on those 10 pounds, 12 pounds, get up to like 150 ish. And
then it'd be like a six month gradual reduction in body weight to where I'd get to that 137,
just like a couple of weeks before my competition. And then I was, I was good to go. But also too,
like I think it's highly specific for athletes. So like I said, I'm in the middle of five kids,
my brothers who aren't athletic, like walk around at like 165 to 170. So that's probably where my
natural body weight should be somewhere right in that range. And so I was trying to get down to
weights that were pretty far from my normal, right? So, and that's why it was like pretty unhealthy
for me to be and why I couldn't stay down in those 137s, 140s for very long. Cause I would
just get super, super rundown. My motivation would go down. My training would go to crap.
So, you know, I was again, if someone is more naturally made to be a marathon or smaller frame
sits already, like their normal body weight would be like my wife, Sarah, like she sits around like
110 ish year round. But even if she wasn't running, she'd probably be about the same weight, right?
So she can sit at that weight year round, no problem. Whereas for me, like it's not healthy
for me to be down at 137. So I have to come back out of it. So that's where it's really important
for people to just know their body and where it should naturally be. And then realizing, okay,
if you're going to manipulate it down to a range where you're the fastest and the lightest at,
you got to come back out of that as well. Yeah. My wife's the same way. Sure. Her walk
around weight is 110, 111, and she has to work to maintain that weight as opposed to do anything
else. And I think that's probably why she's just a good runner is it's just, she's naturally so
light that it comes to her easily in that regard. So tell me what volume, what was your weekly
mileage when you were still training with Mammoth? So it was probably, you know, again, this was like
pre-garmin days, it's probably around like 110 or so. I thought it was more than that, but then we
got garments and started measuring a lot of the loops we were doing for our easy running. We're
like, oh, these aren't nearly, they're like a mile shorter than we thought. So it's probably a
little bit less than I thought, but those easy days are just chill. And then I think this is the
other mistake that a lot of runners make is they're just kind of running the same all the time.
And that will get you to a certain level, right? Like there's a place for that. But if you really
want to see how good you can get, you got to like have your hard days super hard and your easy days
super chill. So like oftentimes, like, you know, like I said, I'm running 12 miles under five minute
pace. And then the next day I'm coming back and running like 830 pace for an easy run, just super,
super chill and slow. So having that kind of variance between pacing, I think is super important.
I mean, it's not really rocket science, right? It's like you stress the body, you rest the body,
it adapts, and then you keep repeating the cycle over and over. It's not rocket science, but I mean,
if there's one thing that I spend a lot of time talking about with my patients when it comes to
this particular aspect of training, it's, and again, this isn't to train them for to become
competitive athletes, but it's important from a physiologic standpoint, as we think about
longevity, it's most people are training in this garbage zone, where it's too high an intensity
to build a true aerobic foundation and too low an intensity to truly stress the body glycolytically.
So, you know, we talk about it in zones, right? So there, we think zone two is how we describe it.
And this is, we define it by lactate metabolism. So zone two is that all day pace. Lactate has to
be below two millimolar. You have to be able, this is a pace you should be able to hold all day from a
metabolic standpoint. You probably can't hold it all day from a muscular and structural standpoint,
but metabolically, you should be able to hold this pace all day. And that's easier than, you know,
people are used to training. And then at the other end of the spectrum, there's like gotta be
this real push pace, kind of your four by four pace, right? Four on, all out, four off. And most
people aren't used to that level of discomfort. So they're kind of in this no man's land. So they're
suffering two problems. One, they're in a physiologic no man's land and two, there's no variability to
it anyway. So even though you say it's obvious, I think it's important for people to hear this
discussion because I don't think enough people understand both for performance and also longevity
why you have to be at the more extremes of kind of zone two, zone five is where the progress comes.
And one kind of like easy way to help manipulate this system a little bit is if you're a coffee
drinker and you talked a little bit about caffeine, but like we'd only have caffeine before our hard
days. And then so the easy day, like you feel like death, like you're tired from the workout,
but also cause you don't have caffeine on board and you you're just kind of forced to take it
really slow. Like you don't feel like you could run fast if your life depended on it. So if you
try into like a lot of the clients we're working with run free, it's like not reasonable for them
to not have any caffeine on the day, but we're like, let's at least manipulate it. So you're
having it more so before the hard workouts and then a lot less on the easy day. And there are
some athletes I'm sure you've seen that don't really get a benefit from caffeine. Like I never
got a benefit from caffeine. And to this day, like I can drink coffee at any time of day,
has no bearing on my sleep. So I get no up from it. I get no down from it. I just, I could drink
three coffees a day for a month and then stop experience, no headaches, no withdrawal,
not even notice it. And there are different genes that are responsible for caffeine metabolism. So
people do sort of vary in that, but I've always been incredibly envious of the people who are
very sensitive to caffeine because it's an awesome tool to have in your toolkit for just this purpose,
but also just for wakefulness and overcoming jet lag and travel and stuff like that.
Yeah. Yeah. When used correctly, it can be super helpful. Of course, like when abused and if you're
sensitive to it and you're drinking it later in the day and it screws up your sleep, then it's,
you know, stops being helpful. But yeah, yeah, it's interesting. It's like, like I was saying,
everyone's an experiment of one, right? So that's why you got to just play with stuff till you find
what works for you. So once you became self coached, did you, how did the workouts change?
What did you do leading up to 2011 Boston in terms of volume, intensity and everything else?
So one of the big adjustments I made, I started spacing things out. So I don't think I finished
the week. So we had the intervals on Tuesday, you know, and then like a long threshold on Friday.
So you get two easy days before that. So you're feeling a little bit better for that threshold.
And tell me about the threshold threshold is a constant. It's like a simulated slightly higher
than race pace, shorter distance. Yeah. Yeah. And it gets more towards race pace as it gets longer.
So we grow those out. You're starting out at maybe like five or six miles and then you get to
where you're doing 15 miles straight without stopping. And I would do three of those every
single 12 week buildup for a marathon, which that would be a very typical buildup for marathon,
about 12 weeks. I make sure I get three of those long thresholds in. And those were my
biggest indicator workouts. It's kind of like whatever I knew I could hold for 15 miles in
training in the context of hard training, right? So it's not like you don't fully taper for this
workout and just bang the heck out of it and be like, Oh, I can run this for a marathon. It's like,
no, your legs like need to be a little bit fatigued. You need to be in the middle of hard training.
But then generally speaking, whatever you can run for that 15 mile threshold,
you can hold for a marathon, which is also kind of like mind blowing and hard for first time
marathoners to believe that. Cause you're like, how do I go 11 more miles at this pace? But that's
the magic of tapering the energy out on the course, the carb loading, all that stuff. Like
your body finds a way to be able to hold that through. So that, that 15 mile threshold or
that threshold of varying distances on Friday and then Sunday coming back with a long run.
So again, you're doing that long run with a little bit of fatigue in your, in your legs.
That'd be anywhere from an hour 45 to two and a half hours. But during that time work,
and we would go off time, not distance, but we're covering, sometimes I'd be running over
the marathon distance for two and a half hours. Right? So those are, those are high quality
efforts. Oftentimes it's kind of like medium pace. So say maybe six minute pace for the first half of
that. And then the second half of that we're doing like fart like style running where you're
practicing changing gears on tired legs and just hitting that aerobic end a little bit harder
towards the end of it. But a lot of it is just like mentally learning, like how do I turn my legs
on when I feel really dead, when I'm 25 miles into this race? How do I, what cues can I go to,
to turn things on and to change gears here? Cause it's, it doesn't matter if you're running
six minute pace or eight minute pace, when you get 20 miles into your run, you feel tired. Right?
And so you got to just learn like, okay, what mental cues can I pull on here to turn everything
on? Okay. So, but everything you just described was how you were doing it before 2011. So then,
and then how did you tweak that formula? So I started spacing things out a little bit more.
Started just taking two easy days between every session. So I was, I was focusing on like a nine,
10 day cycle, but then I was making those workouts higher quality bigger. So like one workout that I
implemented instead of saying like those Tuesday short sessions, which just might have been a
little bit again, I think I got too far away from 5k fitness. I should have spent more time developing
that, but, but this workout I absolutely love for marathoning where I do 20 by a thousand meters
with a 200 meter easy jog between each thousand meter. And that was done faster than marathon
pace. So the goal is to like drive your threshold down. So you spend all this time doing threshold
running at a certain pace, and then you're going just a tad bit quicker than that for
these broken up thresholds. And so how much quicker, so your, if your marathon target pace
for a K is what is two, just under three minutes or just over three minutes? Yeah.
Three minutes is a 206 and change 206 30 marathon. So yeah. So like maybe I'll be shooting for like
two 55s, like five seconds, okay. Quicker kind of feel. How many days would, let's just assume
we're talking about it as a week, even though it's a nine day cycle, how many weeks would you succeed
on that day where you would actually go to 55 or better for each of the 20 K versus
fail somewhere along the way? You know, actually I think I was pretty successful most days, right?
But I think a lot of that is because I wasn't trying to bite off more than I can chew, right?
Like I wasn't trying to hit home runs and workouts. Like they were workouts where I was kind of set
up to see success and often to like my thresholds would just get better every time I would attempt
it, right? As the build up is going, I'm getting stronger, I'm getting in better shape. I'm also
getting lighter, which is making things a little bit easier. And so usually I've seen pretty good
progress from that 12 12 week buildup where I'm getting pretty almost what would happen though,
more likely than not in almost every single buildup I have is you get little niggles, right?
Where you get little like foot pain, little knee pain, just little things that pop up. So if I
missed a workout is usually more for that reason. And then that's when you got to like go to the
cross training, which is an area I've also like learned in and grown so much in and utilize a lot
more now as a coach than when I was running. But when I was a runner, I was just kind of like the
old school, like, like run or die kind of mentality, which is not not a helpful mentality to have.
So what did you expect to happen on that April day in 2011?
So I was coming off a terrible half marathon. So a month before that race, I ran, I don't even,
I can even tell you my time. I don't think I ever looked it up. It was like 66 minutes or something
for a half marathon, which is, you know, seven minutes off my personal best and training and
being going super well. Things have been clicking well. I thought it was in really good shapes.
Kind of one of those scenarios where you go to the start with this really high expectation,
but then it's easy to have that like shattered, you know? And so things just weren't clicking in
the race, created negative mindset, negative snowball excitement gone. And then you're just
trying to get to the finish line, you know? So not a good run at all. Super been out of shape
afterwards because I didn't know why. How long was that before the Boston marathon?
A month, a month out. Yeah. And so, you know, that's one that you want to go well to create
confidence, right? And, and again, I had no reason to describe, I didn't know why it went so bad.
Nothing I could put my finger on. So those are the hardest ones to manage mentally, right?
So, uh, but, you know, I got back up and just started training again. And
I found this over and over again, not just with myself, but with athletes like coach,
oftentimes like these races when you're in heavy marathon training won't go well,
but then they'll turn something on inside of you. It's like neurologically, all of a sudden you're
like firing. And so I came out of that race and just started feeling phenomenal, like, like similar
to how I felt before Houston. And it was a very like quick change. It was like the next week, all
of a sudden I was like, like I said, training had been going well before, but it got taken even to
the next level. And there's all these different factors going into why that might have been. I
think the race helped. Also we headed back to Stanford to train at sea level. And so that,
it was very much how we'd utilize altitude pre-kids. We have kids now, so we can't do this, but we had
been like two months up at altitude, dropped down to sea level for a month, go back up, drop back
down. And that was taken from Jack Daniels, who's done a ton, a ton of research in the running space.
I think probably one of the most brilliant minds in running, in my opinion, especially from a
scientific perspective. And I was asking him, corresponding to him and like, Hey, what's the
best way to utilize altitude? And that's what he recommended. It's like go up to altitude,
shoot back down. Because what you see is you see a big dramatic increase in your hermatic rate
hemoglobin early on in those first three weeks, and then it just starts to taper off. Right?
And so then you, then you head back down to sea level and it's going to go back down. But then you
see when you come back up to altitude, again, another big dramatic shift. So you just always
want that shifting up. Right? So that's what we're doing. We headed back down to sea level.
And again, there's positives to training at sea level. Like I'm sleeping way better when I'm at
sea level, I'm running faster, able to do workouts I can't do at altitude. And so things just started
clicking like crazy. I was doing, again, I also started having caffeine every single day. And that
was the first time my career I started doing this. And and so I started running my easy runs a lot
quicker. And I have no idea if this like was something that was obviously it worked, but I
don't know if it was be in despite of this or because of this, you know? But I was running a
lot of my easy runs at like 530, 520 pace and just like floating through it, just feeling even like
the day before the race, do an easy 30 minute run plus like six by a hundred meter strides. That's
kind of a custom run for us before the marathon. Like I'm so glad Sarah wasn't there. My wife,
cause she would have killed me for running as fast as I did. I was by myself and I was just
hammering. I was around like 530 pace, but it was just easy. I was just floating. Wasn't even
breathing. What was it? What would be the difference in your hematocrit? How much would
your hematocrit vary between sea level and elevation? That's a good question. You know,
I don't remember off the top of my head. We weren't super great about doing bloodwork. I wish we'd
done more of that. Like we would do it just kind of like, it seemed like random times, you know,
we'd pop down the Olympic training center, get some blood work done and see where it was at. But
to be honest, I can't remember the differences, but it would, it would come up pretty significantly
in those first three weeks for sure. So yeah, just feeling like a million bucks heading into
that race. But I did have this like kind of thing hovering over me of like, you just tanked a half
marathon kind of thing. But then the day before the race, I remember talking to the race, one of
the race organizers, and she's telling me like, you know, like we're supposed to get a really good
tailwind tomorrow, right? And I was just, when I heard that, I just lit up inside because I get
excited about running fast. Like I'd rather break a world record than win a gold medal. Like that's
just how I am, you know? And I remember talking to Bill Rogers, who won the Boston Marathon four
times, won New York four times. And he was telling me, he's like, he's like, you know, about once
every 10 years, you get a wicked tailwind in Boston and then you can really roll. So he had a
year when he got a tailwind, he stopped four times in the race to like tie his shoe to walk,
to get water. And he still ran 209. And so his words like were in my head and standing on the
starting line in Hopkinton that morning, and I'm looking at the flag and it's just going the exact
direction we're going to run. I was like, I'm never, never going to get a day like this again,
like I'm going to make the most of it. And I always like to go to the front and lead, like that was
kind of my signature, but I didn't, I didn't let one moment go by in that race where I wasn't
pressing. I was like, I'm going to get everything I can out of every single mile. And so we were
rolling. We were like a lot of our miles in the four thirties during that race. We came through
the half in 6152, I believe was our split. And the race, the race organizer was on a motorcycle in
front of us and he saw our split at halfway saw the clock and he's like, he radioed his clock guys.
Like, Hey, you guys messed up the clocks. It says 61 50. And they're like, yeah, that's right.
And so we were, I mean, at the time the world record, I believe was like low two Oh four.
And so we're under world record pace. And again, like the first half of the Boston marathon is
slightly down. So, and we had the wind at the very end as well. Yeah. You have heartbreak
Hill like all through 17 and a half miles till 20 it's like up and down Hills. So it's, it's
typically known as a challenging slow course. But again, if you get the right wind and you make
the most of it, cause these aren't pace races either. Like most fast races, you have pacemakers
in there and they're in charge of pace. Guys are just tucked in for most first 20 miles at least.
And then they're off and running the last 10 K. Well, in this race, it was just me at the front,
just hammering and all of Africa sitting on my back behind me enjoying the ride. But I didn't
care. I was like, I'm gonna make the most of today. I remember one, one memory from that race was one
of the guys on the side of the road. Like some of the spots, like especially early on in Hopkins
and you're just going through neighborhoods and stuff, people out in their lawn chairs.
And one of the guys yelled at me and he's like, Hey, Ryan, don't let them steal your tailwind.
And I was thinking about that for a while. I was like, is that possible? Like, I don't think so,
but, uh, lots of kind of funny, funny memories from that. And, uh, it was just cool to like be with
those guys, be in the lead group and, and also to get to push them along to something that would
have, it was a super historic day, you know, like the top two guys went on to run two Oh three low,
like two Oh three Oh four or something like that, which was well, like almost a minute under the
world record at the time. And, uh, you know, I finished fourth and ran two Oh four 58, but I'll
never forget, uh, another memorable part of the race was coming through with a mile to go and, uh,
seeing they have a clock at a mile to go and it was right at two hours. Right. But I'm in the like
serious pain cave, right? It went out super fast, super late in the race. No one's around me. And
I'm just like holding on for dear life. And I was like, I saw two hours flat. I was like, okay,
like if I break five minutes for this last mile, like I'm gonna be under two Oh five. My PR at the
time was two Oh six 17. So I was already, again, I was gonna run a big PR no matter what I was like
two Oh five. That's insane. That sounds pretty good. You know, there's a part of me that is like,
just enjoy this last mile run like five 30. Just soak it all in and just enjoy it. But then there
is a part of me is like, you know what, you might never be here again. Like why don't you just put
your head down, grit your teeth and bear it, try to break five and get under two Oh five. And so
that's what I did. And it was a world of pain. That last mile is a blur. Um, the crowds in Boston
are just insane though. Like I'll never forget running down Boylston street and just the crowd's
just going crazy. And you know, I was in fourth place, but I didn't even care because like to me,
performance shifted away from like beating other people to me maximizing my own potential. And
that's what I get most excited about. And it's like that with my lifting too. It's like, there's
guys deadlifting well over half a double what I'm able to do. Right. But to me, like that's not
important. It's about like me optimizing what I've been given my gift and also just seeing the,
the fun part of the scene, the growth and the improvement. Right. So coming across the finish
line, I just like put my hands out and just soaked it all in, yelled super loud. My wife
was there at the finish to give me a big hug. And, uh, it was super special. I felt like I'd won
the race, even though I hadn't. Um, but one of those, those moments where it's like, this is
again, like Houston, like one of those magical days that, you know, you may never get again.
So just soak it all in and enjoy it. But yeah, special day. So, I mean, to me, the most amazing
part of your journey is not the successes. It's the, it's, it's the way in which you've been able
to kind of carry yourself through the failures. Right. And I think, you know, you got this
parallel between 07 and 08, right? Where, and then we see it again now here in 11 and 12. So
how are you feeling going into London? Again, I think the expectations early in that season are
very high, right? When out of a two Oh four, I was, you know, I was like, I'm going to take a
shot at winning this race, even though, you know, I'd just been beaten by a minute by those guys.
So I knew, I knew it wasn't, you know, like I was expected to necessarily win, but I knew I had a
shot. Like, you know, if you run two Oh four for the marathon in those days, like you have a chance
to win a gold medal. So, um, yeah. Uh, and again, I, this was a theme going back to Beijing talking
about not putting on the weight after I ran London leading up to the buildup for Beijing and how that
made my training flat. I did the same thing. Um, and this is one of those things where it's like,
okay, like having a coach is a helpful thing. Cause if a coach, if I would have told a coach
what I was going to do, he'd have been like, that's a really bad idea. Let's just stick with
what we know works for you in this situation. And that's putting on 10 pounds. But instead of doing
that, again, my heart was good. My intentions were good. I was like, okay, like, again, like faith's
a big part of who I am. I really want to hear God in a way that people use across all traditions
to do this is through fasting. Right. So I, instead of putting on 10 pounds, I did a one week
fast where all do close to the Olympics. So let's see, Boston was April 15th and the Olympics were
August. So, you know, it was enough time till we're asking to get a full buildup for the,
for the game. So I had plenty of time to like put on weight and do my usual thing.
But again, I just wanted, I wanted clarity on how to train for this thing. And so instead of my
weight going from 137 to 150 during that two week period, it went from 137 to like 130 flat. And
that was just, I started the training in a really depleted state. My body wasn't in a good state. I
was mentally and spiritually, I was in the best spot I'd ever been, but my body wasn't ready to
go at all. It was, it was needing a break after that, you know, but I began my training and came
back and I was running pretty well initially. And then it just kind of went downhill from there. And
it actually kind of became a miracle that I even made it to the starting line, considering how
poorly my training was going, just nothing was working. And this is what I tell myself in the
weight room now all the time, wherein I'm getting stale and training and not seeing growth. If I'm
not eating enough food, if I'm not taking enough calories, it doesn't matter how I'm training,
it's not going to work. And that's, that's how it was for me in that buildup is like my body is
depleted. I didn't have enough calories on board. So it didn't matter how I train, it wasn't going
to work. So just a frustrating period of training leading up to that actually had to take my watch
off for all my workouts, because it was so discouraging to see what my workouts were and
see how slow I was running them compared to what I was accustomed to. So that was good for my mental
health. And I think there is a point that can be helpful for people out there sometimes just get
away from the data, take all that stuff off and just go off feel. And that was helpful, but it
wasn't enough to get my body back into the state it needed to be in. So, so what did you feel at the
start line in London? Did you feel like, was there any hope in you at that point? Or were you like,
look, I'm here at this point out of an obligation to my country, I'm representing my country,
I'm wearing the flag of my country, but this is going to be the most difficult two hours of my
life. Yeah, you know, there's, I'm very optimistic, optimistic person. So I'm pretty good at generating
hope. So, and it did help not timing my workouts. So there was a little bit of mystery of thinking,
oh, maybe I'm actually in a lot better shape than I think and feel here, you know? So there was some
genuine hope on the starting line that, Hey, and that's the thing with running that I've experienced,
sometimes like training can go really bad and you can just pop on, have a big day. So there's always
that kind of thought in my head of like this, you know, like let's not think that something special
couldn't happen today because it could, but it became obvious like really early on in the race.
The pace felt super hard, super fast. And then as is the case oftentimes when I get too lean and too
light, I have all these injury issues, right? So like I had all this hip stuff going on before the
race. Luckily, like my Cairo guy, John Ball is amazing, had me in one piece on the starting line,
but then very early on in the race, it was like, then my right hamstring started hurting. And
that's ultimately what led me to drop out as I was in the middle of that race. I was already
starting to limp a little bit. It wasn't even the middle. It was early on. It was like seven miles
into the race and I was limping. I was like, all right, like what do I do here? What's the right
call? You're trying to kind of coach yourself through it, not give up hope, but then at the
same time, you want to be smart. This is my livelihood, you know? And I'm looking out for
the long term. And I was like, I'm willing to be that guy who comes limping in like seven hours
after everyone gets the cheers and inspires people for just hanging in there. But at the same time,
I also want to be good to my body. And I've been not good to my body a lot. And that was just kind
of like a moment where I had a sense of clarity that I needed to be good to myself and call it
a day. So that was actually the first race I ever dropped out of in my life was the London marathon.
And it felt so surreal. I remember stepping off the, cause it's a loop course, you know,
as you're going past the finish and the start a number of times. And I think it was the second
loop. I could be wrong on that, but I think it was the second loop when I dropped out and I remember
stepping off and I almost started running again cause it just felt so wrong. It felt so weird. It
felt like I was in someone else's movie or something. And, but then ultimately I just
walked off the course and then began the long process of working through that mentally and
emotionally, you know, what was that like? Well, it started with Cinnabon.
Funny, funny thing. So the next day I'm like touring around with my family in London. And
Sarah knows like how I tend to go to food when I get emotionally low, you know,
and yeah. So we pop out of the subway onto the streets and it's like, it's like Cinnabon is
like heaven. It's like right. My eyesight is just like, ha Cinnabon. And she sees me, look at it.
She looks at me and she knows exactly where I'm going. You know, she's like, don't do it. Don't
do it. But of course I went to Cinnabon and got a big old cinnamon roll. Now I'm sitting out on the
curb just eating it. And I look up and like someone's like taking a picture of me in my
Cinnabon and I was like, I felt like I was going to be on like Esquire magazine or something.
But no, actually I've learned to pick myself up so many times I've gotten a lot better at it.
And for me, it's kind of like I need this period of just being sad and just let myself be sad for
however long that takes. The period of kind of like mourning the loss, you know, because this
was a big goal for me. And then for me, the next step then is like, okay, restore hope. So what is
the next thing I'm going after? Find that target, put it on the calendar that begins to restore my
hope. And then like, I have a little meeting with myself of things I'm going to tweak different, do
differently, do better. So that also gives me just way more hope that I'm not just going to repeat the
same experiment I just did. Right. So like I'm doing this right now with myself. I'm going back
after this sub five minute mile and sub five deadlift. I'm like, I'm going to tweak this, this,
and this. And like, I really believe it's going to work this time. Right. And so you've got to,
you've got to, that's the starting ground. You have to believe that your training is going to work.
That's why it's so important for athletes to believe in their coach. Like if you don't think
it's going to work, it doesn't matter what it's going to prescribe. It's probably not going to
work. Right. So that, that belief is so, so important. So, you know, I picked myself up and
got going again, but then the problem was, and is common in the case with runners is then you have
all these compensation issues. Right. So I had that issue in my upper high hamstring where
attaches there, and then just ran through that. And that started by the way, because I had
plantar fasciitis training for the 2012 Olympic trials. I got that right before the trials,
had no choice, had to run through it. And then that persisted for like eight months. And so
low compensation, get an injury on the other side and upper hamstring in the games.
Then I tore my left quad building up for New York. I tore my right quad building up for
Boston. Then I got a sacral stress fracture on my left side after that training for my next
marathon. And it was literally marathon after marathon. I'd sign up for it, get the deal all
worked out, not be able to do it. Cause I'd get some huge injury that would put me out for a long
time. And I didn't have a lot of injuries leading up to that. I always considered myself to be super
durable. And yeah, so it was just injury after injury. And that's kind of that four year wild
ride of trying everything I could think to try. And ultimately nothing was working. But you know,
as I look back at it now, I really think a big piece of it was the nutrition piece. And I started
to be in a better mental health point to where like I didn't have to use food as like a binging
mechanism for after these bad races. But that actually, I still needed to put on the weight
though, right? I still needed to get my body in a good spot. And I wasn't doing that because I
didn't need to do it from an emotional mental standpoint, but then that was also killing me
at the same time, physically speaking, right? So if I, you know, looking back at it, I would say
that was a big, big part of why I had so many struggles from 2012 up until my retirement in
2016. And if I could go back and do it differently, I'd actually do something like my mom always
wanted me to do. And I never wanted to. And that is to, she's like, you should just take like three
months completely off and like not run at all. And I was like, you crazy? Like I'm never going to
do that, you know? But that actually would have been super helpful. Just get away from it, get my
body back in a completely good spot. And now, you know, like I feel so much better in my current
lifestyle, folks on the lifting, doing very minimal on the endurance and, and even like my testosterone,
like I just got a testosterone blood test result recently and it came back at a thousand. And like,
I didn't think that was possible for me, but again, the lifestyle shift, lifting heavy,
eating more calories, just having my body in a better state, sleeping a ton is just allowed me
to kind of like restore myself. And that was exactly what my body was telling me. It was like,
I've, I felt like my body was saying to me, I've given so much to you over the last 20 years,
like you've pounded me into the ground with a hundred mile weeks after a hundred mile weeks.
Now it's time to get back to me. And so that's ultimately like why I got into the lifting. I was
like, I want to get back to my body. I want to build it back up. I want to make it strong. And
there's this thing of like, okay, like I did something I was genetically gifted at. Now let
me see what I can take something where I'm not genetically gifted at all. The opposite of that.
And again, I just love like the challenge. I love lifting hard. So every single day I'm in the weight
room, I go to failure and I know that's not recommended, but that's just who I am. That's
what I love to do. So that's, that's what I do, you know? So I feel like in a really good spot now,
but I'm curious, like if I would have allowed myself to get into a similar state as I'm now
and then went back to the running, how that could have went. But the ship has definitely sailed on
that. And you know, walking around it, 185 pounds now, or even like I'll go for runs. And it feels
like a completely different sport at this body weight compared to, you know, 137 pounds.
Yeah. And it's even different from cycling. I mean, both sports punish you for the weight,
but one of them you feel it much more than the other. I mean, in running, it changes your
gait. I mean, my wife, even though she weighs exactly what she weighed before having kids,
she's tried to explain to me that the shape of her pelvis has changed since having three kids.
And she said she has ever since having, especially the boys, because they were so big,
she's like, I've never felt the same running again. She's still, you know,
weighed thin, 110 pounds. To me, looks like she has a nice stride, but she's like,
it doesn't feel the same. I don't float anymore. Like literally her pelvis is just in a different
shape now. So, you know, that's an example of something that I think women can experience.
And then of course, just the change in weight. Yeah, it's huge. It's huge.
So what would you say to someone who says, you know, I love exercise, but cardio is the only
thing that matters. And they're not doing a hundred mile weeks, but they're doing something
cardio every day, but they're sort of averse to strength training. Given that you've experienced
both ends of this spectrum and at very extreme levels, how do you think about this in terms of
overall health beyond performance? Yeah, I mean, I think when you think of health, you have to
think about all these different levels of health, right? So like, what is your hormonal health like?
Because that's going to really affect like your mental health, like how motivated you are,
like your energy levels, all that stuff, right? So I just know from myself, my own experience,
like number one, like you can run every single day and be healthy, right? But you do need something
especially as you're getting older to offset how depleting of the body that can be, right? And that's
where heavy lifting comes in. And I think I just say the word heavy and I can feel like all the
runners being like, oh, I don't want to do that. And I was the same way. I hated lifting heavy,
but I think there are there's ways around that, you know? And like we mentioned BFR a little bit,
like I love BFR for runners. Because like, if you're not, here's the thing with lifting,
like I've been lifting super heavy for six years and I've never gotten hurt lifting,
but that's just because I'm in, I have crap form when it comes to a lot of things too. So it's not
because my form is good, but I am intuitive in there, right? Like if something's not feeling right,
like I don't put on the weight, I don't go down. Like I'm very cautious in the weight room, right?
So there are ways to like lift heavy and healthy. So like for runners, for example,
the stuff that I love to prescribe to our runners are hex bar deadlift with the handles up.
So you're not going down as low, you're not loading up the lower back as much.
That's much more running specific strength that is going to be great for your power development.
I also love half squats, you know, for the same reason, like a lot of running is just hip extension,
right? It's like every time your foot contacts the ground, your hips have to extend to get out
of that position. So we need to do things that really focus on that. So half squats, great for
your liability of getting hurt. Half squatting is way less than butt to the ground. So you can load
up the bar super heavy with the half squat, get all the hormonal benefits of lifting heavy,
get the bone benefits of loading up a bar and having it on your back and avoid things like stress
reactions, your bone density up that way. And just feel really good coming out. There's just
no other feeling than like lift, having a bunch of weight on your back and setting it down. You just
get this like huge rush of like, I don't know what is endorphins energy, but I always just feel
amazing coming out of the weight room energy wise, you know? So there are ways to lift heavy in a
healthy way. And then again, like if you don't even have access to heavy weights, you can do things
like BFR. And I've been playing a lot with BFR and I really like the feel of that as well. And
I think it's a way for runners who are maybe skinny, more concerned about getting hurt to get
the same benefits of lifting heavy without having to put a bunch of weight on the bar.
Do you ever have runners run in blood flow restriction? I for the first time really,
like a couple of weeks ago, did some sets on the air bike. So like, you know, those air dying bikes,
I did like two minute sets with heavy BFR on my upper thighs. And I remember thinking,
well, I remember not knowing what to expect, right? I remember thinking, okay, for two minutes,
I should be able to hold 300 Watts or whatever. And it's like no freaking way. Like I was
struggling to hold 200 Watts for two minutes. And it wasn't that my heart and lungs were blowing up.
It was like just the absolute pain in my legs. So I thought that was kind of interesting. And I was
like, huh, I wonder if, you know, I was still cycling. Like if this would be an interesting
form of cross training. I don't know if it would translate to running because I can't really walk
when I'm in the full BFR. So maybe it just wouldn't work and maybe it's only amenable to
being on a bike. And I also think there's certain exercises like I once stupidly tried to deadlift
with BFR. It was very lightweight, but I also thought it was altering my form a little bit.
And I didn't think that would be beneficial. But I love it. I do BFR every day that I lift. I do at
least one to two sets. That's interesting. I'm definitely going to try the BFR on a run next
time I go for run. I'll be curious to try that. Yeah. You won't be able to go as heavy as you do
for list. Like at least on my device, it allows me to select like low, medium, or high intensity.
So maybe if you set it on a lower intensity, but if anyone's going to experiment with it, it's you.
So I'm curious to hear what you think. Yeah, I'll try that.
Something else I wanted to ask you about, which is, you know, we talk about sports like cycling,
where drug use is just the norm. There's never really been a clean era of cycling.
We're probably in the cleanest era now for the last 10 years. But there was just no way you were
going to be able to compete and be one of the 10 best cyclists in the world if you weren't using
a performance enhancing drug, non-negotiable. So if you didn't want to use those things, you
were free not to, but you were not going to be in the top 100 or whatever.
How much? Well, I guess it doesn't seem to me that distance running has suffered the same thing,
right? We see it in track and field all the time. How much buzz has there been about performance
enhancing drugs at the marathon level, at the world class marathon level? I just, I haven't
been paying attention to it, but I really don't remember hearing much about it. And I'm curious
as to whether or not that's been your experience. And if so, why, why do you think that marathon
runners, which would certainly benefit from tons of PEDs, haven't traditionally used them?
Yeah, I think the thing that is the culture, right? So like for me, I knew guys who 100% weren't on
it and were winning races, Meb, for example, he's, he's winning Boston, he's winning New York,
he's winning medals, Dina's winning a medal at the Olympics and 100%, no, they're not on it,
right? So I think that's huge, right? If you can think of one person who's doing what you want to
do and they're not on it, you're like, then I can too. You know, and you look at like Lance and the
cycling culture and it's like, if that's not the case, then it becomes very difficult, like to me,
to be optimistic on the starting line, right? So like I always chose to believe everyone was
innocent, even if I heard rumblings, just because like I didn't want to be at a mental disadvantage.
Like if I believe this person next to me is on something, then they already got one on me
because I think they're just gonna be superhuman because they're on a PED, you know? So I always
just believed everyone was innocent. I never like concerned myself with too much about it. And also
like, honestly, I've been around a lot of training groups in the US, a lot of different athletes.
I've never heard of anyone talking about taking it, about having access to it. Like I wouldn't even
know the first step to even like, how do you even find this stuff, you know? Whereas there, it's not
like that everywhere though, you know? Like I've been in Kenya and they talk about it a lot over
there. And I'm not saying like Kenyans are dirty or anything like that, but the culture there is one
where it's talked about more there. And I think that alone makes you think more athletes are on it.
And there have been like guys getting busted, not just from Kenya, but from all over the world,
you know? So it does happen. What are the drugs of choice? Is it EPO? Is it testosterone? EPO,
yeah. And then there's, you know, lots of like kind of gray line stuff too, where people are just,
you know, looking for every advantage they can get and maybe crossing some of those lines and,
you know, with Alberto and all that like stuff. So it's, but again, like,
That's right. I forgot about that. What was the controversy around Alberto Salazar?
So yeah, I wouldn't even be able to like, it was a large document of case thing of all the stuff
that was supposedly going down. Honestly, like I kind of stayed out of all that and didn't even
fall out closely. I wouldn't even be able to do it. But you're right. I guess there has been some
rumbling about it. You obviously spent a lot of time in Africa. I know you've adopted four
girls from Ethiopia, which probably speaks not just to your, you know, sort of love of children,
but also like how much you've embraced that sort of East African culture. Having spent as much time
there as you have, do you have a sense of what makes them great? How much of it is their genetics?
How much of it is the environment in which they're raised? How much of it is the training, the mindset?
Again, I would imagine if you're born poor in Ethiopia or Kenya, running as a way out would be
viewed as, you know, playing in the NFL here or playing in the NBA or the major leagues. Like it's
it is their sport. So when you think about all of these different factors, what explains
the absolute greatness of this population in this really relatively small part of the world?
Yeah, I mean, it's the perfect storm of kind of everything you mentioned, right? It's like
highly motivated individuals who are highly genetically gifted. Like you were talking about
your wife's pelvis and it widening, like there's like, I think some theories about their pelvis
being really small and not being helpful for distance running. But I mean, like I just,
I walk behind my kids on hikes sometimes and just look at how narrow their shoulders are and how
small their bone structure is, right? And I'm just like, this is crazy. Like they're just so
small. And like, I'd be running next to highly giver slosie, one of the greatest distance
runners of all time. And I remember the first time I ran with him at the London marathon,
I caught up to his group and I was like, I'm running next to highly like this is insane.
And I just could not get over how small he was. I was just staring at his back. I was like,
this guy is tiny. So I mean, there's like this whole huge, like their, their makeup, their body.
And to be honest with you, I think there's a lot more there actually. I think they can run a lot
faster than they're even running. Like as we, I'm curious, like, like their approach to train versus
our approach to training, like who's doing it right? Not that it's one or the other, you know,
it's probably like a blend of the two, but you're thinking if they adopted some of what you've
talked about and what others have talked about as far as more strength training, more gap between
intensities, they might even be able to, to be better. Yeah. Cooling down, you know, things like
that. What makes Kip Choggy so great in your mind. And I think he really is the greatest marathon
runner today. And I don't think that's just on the basis of doing this incredible, you know,
feat of breaking two hours in a, in a very controlled unofficial way, but, but also just
his overall marathon performance on the racetrack. What is it about Kip Choggy? Have you, I don't
suppose you ever ran with him, right? Was he, was he there in 16? No, I don't think we ever,
we were, we were coming up at the same time. Like we're very similar in age. I don't know
his exact age or if he even knows his exact age, but we're right around the same. So we crossed
paths a lot. Like I saw him at the London marathon a couple of years ago when I was there.
But I think, you know, obviously like genetically gifted, but also his like humbleness. I think
that's a huge thing. It's like when you start to think you're great and that you've done all this
great stuff, it almost makes it harder to get back there, right? Or to exceed it. It's like when you
buy into how great you are, that I feel like it kind of sets the limit on you. It's like, that's
your cap, right? And he is so, like I've never seen anyone as successful as he is. I mean, he's
got to be getting huge paydays to do these marathons, right? And yet living in super simple
place with sharing a room with training partners. Like, come on, like how many like multi,
multi-millionaires do you know that like do that, right? So like, I think there's something about
like his mentality and humbleness. And that's really what I've always found most inspiring
about African runners, whether it's from Kenya or Ethiopia, and why I enjoy being over there so much
and have fallen in love with their culture. It's just this like carefree, fearless mentality of
just like, I'm just going to put myself in it and go for it. But Kipchoge also balances that with
like being very controlled. It's like he controls his strengths so, so well. And I think that kind
of sets him apart. Like when you read about his training, he's always talking about running like
80% max and everything being super controlled. And I don't know, like I have personally have not
gotten results through that type of training, but it's without a doubt it's working for him. I mean,
he's by far and away the greatest marathoner to ever walk the planet, right? So whatever he's
doing is working. But I honestly, I feel like a big thing is just his mentality, like his,
his mental approach to training and racing is the most composed I've ever seen in an athlete.
So I think that's a huge part of it. Do you think we will see a sub two hour marathon as
an official marathon in our lifetime? I think we will without a doubt. I mean,
so a woman just ran 62 minutes, 62 50 or something for a half marathon, which is absolutely insane.
So that predicts, that predicts 210 as a full. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, she could potentially run,
be the first woman to break 210 for the marathon. And we're just seeing huge performances like this.
And I think, you know, how much of it is the shoe? Yeah. I was just going to say,
how much of it is the shoes? Yeah. The shoe thing is really interesting. Because I don't think it's
just the technology, like the technology without a doubt, like people are running two minutes faster
over the marathon with these shoes on. But I think it's affected the psyche a ton. I think
what people think is possible now has just been blown up, right? And so now like we're just getting
people trying to do insane stuff. I mean, like a sub two hour marathon, like that would have never
happened if we didn't have these shoes. Like I'm sure even Kipchoge wouldn't have even tried,
right? But now it's kind of opening the doors of like what's possible here. And then you see a
woman around 62 minutes for a half. And you're like, if she can run 62 minutes for a half, like
in an actual race, that wasn't even a set up Kipchoge type situation. That was the actual race,
like people can do it in the marathon. So I'm certain we will see it. And who knows too,
like what other kind of technological advances will happen in the coming years. But, you know,
the shoe thing is, has been profound from technology standpoint, but also from a mental
standpoint for athletes. Speaking of a mental standpoint, of all of the stunts you've done,
and I've followed many of them, the seven marathons in seven days, i.e. seven consecutive marathons
in seven days on seven continents is in and of itself ridiculous, but it's made only more
ridiculous by the fact that you didn't train for it. So tell people a little bit about this
thing and the extent to which you both got better during it and then kind of crashed at the end and
how painful that last one was. Yeah. So I was retired from pro running and one of my pastor
friends from LA, Matthew Barnett texted me. He's like, Hey, I'm doing this crazy challenge. Seven
marathon, seven days, seven continents. And there's something just captured me about it.
Similar actually to when I was 13 and went on that first round around Big Bear Lake. It's like
a similar kind of feeling where it's just like, there's just something about this that like,
I just got to do it. So I texted him back. I was like, let me know if you want me to join you,
man. I'd love to go. And again, running zero at this point, just in the weight room, just
focus on strength training. And so, you know, he's like, okay, let's go. It's on whatever.
So we ended up doing it and I was, I started training for it. So I was like, okay, like if
I'm gonna do this, like I want to enjoy it. But then I was hating the training for it. It wasn't
enjoying it. And I was starting to get a lot of those same fatigue issues that came when I was
running professionally. So I was like, you know what? Either I can enjoy my life for like the nine
months leading up to this thing and not run hardly at all or, and have a really bad week or I can
like train for it, not really enjoy my life for nine months and then have a good week. I was like,
I'll take the nine months of good living. So I decided not to train for it. I mean, I did do,
I was running like three days a week, like between five and eight miles. Eight miles was my long run
leading up to that. And so I was taking on this challenge where we're going to have to run 183
miles, I think it is in a week, which is by far the most I'd ever done. I think the most I'd ever
done was 140 miles and you're hopping on airplanes. Like you run, you get on the airplane, you run,
you get on the airplane, right? So yeah, it was quite the experience. Definitely like trip of a
lifetime. It was like a group of people. So there's like 30 of us, Richard Donovan puts it on,
it's called the World Marathon Challenge. And he just, the guy who puts it on Richard is such an
amazing dude. This guy's taken 30 people around the world running marathons every day. I never
saw him stressed once. I never even saw him close to stressed. How much does one pay for the privilege
of doing this? I believe it's like 40 grand. So it's a bit of a trip. But you're also...
Yeah, because they're flying you privately, obviously you're chartering a flight.
Feels the only way you could make this work. So the first one, I think if I recall was South Africa?
Antarctica.
Antarctica. Oh my God.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah. That was the coolest marathon. You're running on snow. It's like a seven mile loop course.
And I thought Antarctica is just going to be like flat, just white, you know? But there's all these
mountains. We're on a glacier. There's all these mountains going. We had to take like a
Russian airplane to like get down to there. It looked like something out of a movie. It was
super cool. So yeah, we did that one, hop on an airplane.
And how did that one feel?
It felt pretty good actually. Funny though, I was super into lifting, right? So my great idea was to
take in 50 grams of protein like every seven miles or something. So I was like,
I don't want to lose my gains. So which is like the opposite of what I usually do, right? Usually
it's like simple sugar. So I'm doing this and I get to like mile 23 of this race and I am so out
of it. Like I'm like, I need sugar like stat, like right now. Cause my protein bars, like hardly
any carbs in it. So they have this little tent that's set up and they, they put all these like
dried fruit and candy and stuff in there and it's an unmanned tent. So I crawl in there and I just
grab like as much candy as I can. And I started feeling better immediately. So like right after
that, I kind of learned my lesson. I think I ran like three 30 something on that one.
Which is kind of amazing. Like three 30 is still a fast marathon for a
okay. So then where do you guys go from the Antarctica? Where's the next one?
So then we went to Chile and we got to sleep in a hotel room that night. So that was nice.
So there was only two nights during the week where we got to sleep in a hotel room. And
that was one of them. So ran the next marathon and actually felt pretty good. You know,
we're on concrete, not snow. So it felt a little bit better. It was warm.
What was the temperature in Antarctica when you ran that?
So it was supposedly really cold, but it must be like a dry cold cause it didn't feel that bad to
me all. Like I was in my regular run stuff that I would do if I'm doing a run here and flagstaff
in the wintertime. Like I had full tights at a long sleeve and I had like a, like a shell jacket
and gloves, like mittens and a beanie. And I was totally good. I wasn't sweating at all.
Cause they say like, you don't want to sweat and it freezes on you and get hypothermia, you know,
but I was, I was totally good. So yeah. So then, so then South, South America, you ran,
how fast you run that one? I'm trying to remember what my time was. I think it was a little bit
faster than the Antarctica, but not a lot, but I didn't, it was nice cause the Antarctica one
doesn't beat up your legs cause you're on a snow. So it's a little bit softer. We always do all of
our easy running on, on soft surfaces to keep from beating up your legs. And I was also in like the
most cushy shoe I could find cause I was like, my legs are going to take a beating. So I think at
that time I was like 170 pounds. So I was prepping myself for that a little bit. Then we flew to
Miami and that was kind of fun. It was like a homecoming back to the States, you know, but also warm.
And I had a little bit more trouble in that one. I think I was a little bit slower than I was
in, in Chile, but not much. Like maybe I was like, again, like 330 or something like that.
And then we flew over to Spain and I had the worst day ever in Spain. Luckily you're like one
of my Dutch friends, Jop, Jop, he came over and he was with me on the bike the whole time. And I
was just in the worst mood and having the worst day ever. I was like running is the worst thing on
the planet, which I've said that many, many times. That's actually not a new thing for me to say,
even when I was running professionally, running can be like your best friend and like your greatest
enemy at all at the same time. All right. So that's Europe. So then which continent next? Asia,
I'm guessing. So then we had to Morocco for Africa and we got a hotel room slept in that one. I was
like, all right, considering how bad I felt less than 24 hours ago, I'm going to start out just
super chill and just like make it through this. Right. So I start that way. And then again, the
mystery of running, why you'd all of a sudden feel so good. I have no idea, but I just started
feeling like a million bucks. Like I started charging. Like I felt like my old self, I was
like mentally super engaged and like just came home super quick. Like I went out really slow and
then ended up running like three Oh four, which for me off like zero training was like really good,
you know? And so then I was like pumped. I was like, all right, now it's on. Like I'm going to
just get faster and faster every day from here. You know? So then is Dubai the next day?
So then yeah, Dubai is the next day. And the problem was though, then after Morocco, I'm
walking to get food with my buddy and I just develop a little bit of a limp and he's like,
Hey, why are you limping? I was like, Oh, my hips kind of bother me a little bit, uh, whatever,
you know, just shake it off like you usually do with most running things, you know? But then the
next day in Dubai is like my hip was on fire. And I was like, this isn't good. Like something's
really wrong here. So I ended up walking like the back half of that marathon, a lot of it.
So I don't know what my time was there, but it was probably up over four hours, you know?
And then we head on the airplane to Sydney for the last marathon in Australia. And it was crazy
this whole time. Yeah. We're on a private jet with like, you know, food and everything movies.
I didn't watch one movie the entire week. Whenever I was on the airplane, I was asleep. I was so
tired. Um, so we land in Sydney and I tried to stand up and I put weight on that leg where the
hip was bothering me. And if that kind of like, take your breath away, wincing kind of pain that
you get like super sharp. And I was like, Oh, I'm in trouble. This is not good at all. Like I had a
hard time putting any weight on it at all. And also to like, I was so sick of all the little tiny
things you do as a pro runner, like the mobility, the stretching, all that stuff that I wasn't doing
any of that anymore. So I didn't wear my compression socks the entire week. So I got to Sydney and my
ankles look like elephant ankles. Like they're so swollen, but like to the point where it was painful,
I was like, I didn't know you could actually get pain from this, but like I could like barely like
bend my ankles. I was a mess. So I put on my same singlet that I wore my first marathon at the
London marathon in 2006, 2007, the same single that I wore in that race. I put it on cause I was
like, this is my last marathon. Like this is my goodbye tour here. You know, the same way I went
in with a big long run, 15 mile run around big bear. I'm going out with a bang too, you know?
And I never got to say goodbye to the sport. It's like, I just like kind of faded out and all of
a sudden I was gone and my body wasn't able to run. I never got to say goodbye to the sport that I
loved. So this was my chance to say goodbye. And so this last marathon, Manly Beach, we did a mile
out mile back for the whole marathon, but it was, it was sick though. Cause it was lit up by the moon,
the stars, all that stuff was just blazing. We're running for some reason. We started like 1 AM. I
was like, why can't we get some more sleep? We're running 1 AM. And, uh, was that because it was, uh,
too hot to run during the day? No, I think, I think Richard's thought process was just,
you wanted to get people enough time to get it done. You know, it'd be like such a sucky thing
to like not finish it within the seven week period because you had a really bad last day. So I think
he was thinking like, yeah, yeah, yeah. The seven day period. So, so I think he's just trying to
give people as much time as possible. And so it could have been good. Like for me, like I kind
of needed it that day. I, I like got a massage in the middle of that, but I went on to find out when
I went home, got MRI that a stress reaction in my hip. So massages aren't, aren't the best for
stress reaction. It doesn't do a whole lot, but, uh, yeah, I'll never forget like coming across that
finish line, the sun was up at that point. It took me five and a half hours. It was like the longest,
slowest, most painful marathon. It's like every time I put my leg down on that concrete, it's just
like getting zinged with like that super sharp pain, you know? But I mean, after you've run six
marathons in a row, you're like, I'm do whatever it takes to get through the seventh one. Like I'm
not stopping now. And I'm never signing up for this trip again. So I got to get it done, you know?
So I came across the finish line and these are just like all like runs that are set up by
volunteers. So not like a ton of people. They're not like big productions, like major marathons,
but still super cool. And I came across the finish line and I took off my shoes, left them on the
finish line. And it's something I kind of stole from wrestlers, Olympic wrestlers after they,
they wrestled their last match, they leave their shoes on the mat. It's just kind of the symbolic
way of saying like, I've given everything I have to give. And now like the season's over, I'm
walking away, leaving my shoes on the mat. So I did that. I walked away barefoot from the finish
line. And it was actually, even though it was just kind of like me and a couple of people got
super emotional at that time. I was like tearing up as I was walking back to the hotel, just because
you know, running gave me so many gifts. It was so life altering for me. And the most beautiful
part of all of it was the people, you know, meeting my wife, my kids, all the people I
crossed paths with continue. Like I wouldn't be chatting with you right now, Peter, if it wasn't
for that, you know, like that, that is what I hold most dear from, from all of the experience, you
know. And what's cool about that is like, it doesn't matter what level you run at. Like we all get to
experience that, you know, you sign up for any race and you're out there with a 50,000 amazing
people that are on a journey with you and we get to do it together, you know. So that whole
sentiment just like hit me super hard, just saying goodbye to the sport I love. But then, you know,
it's been such a beautiful transition though of like realizing that that whole season, it felt
like it was for me, you know, like it was my thing that I was going after seeing how good I can get.
But I've since kind of realized like it wasn't just for me, like everything I learned in that
season was meant to be passed down and it was meant to be shared and meant to help other people.
So it kind of launched me into the season of, you know, moving into the coaching space, coaching my
wife, coaching other athletes in person, starting run free training where we coach runners of every
single discipline, you know, every level, super slow people, middle school kids, like all the levels,
because like just it doesn't matter where you're at, right? It's a mat. We just want to be on the
journey with you and want to guide you well and help you on your journey. So it was really
special to kind of like realize that even all the mistakes that I made, they weren't for not,
you know, I'm on this podcast, I'm able to share it with your listeners and hopefully they won't
make the same mistakes and they'll be better off for it, you know? And that's really kind of like
my goal now is like, how can I help people take this thing living to the next, not just running,
but living, be happier people. Like I'm far more concerned with my athlete's happiness than I am
with how fast they are, right? Like I want them to enter into the good life and I think running is
a way to do that. Lifting can be a way to do that. It adds to that, but more than anything,
like I just want them to find, I want them to find joy, you know?
Well, Ryan, it's been a joy sitting here talking with you about this and I hope we get to meet in
person one day because there's, I hope we get to work out in person one day, actually. That would
be a ton of fun to lift together and I'd love to try some of these crazy things you're doing. Not
all of them, but actually I'm really intrigued by the, I wouldn't be able to do it with a fraction
of the weight you just described, but the farmers carries up the Grand Canyon. That's something that
I could see wanting to do that one day. The Grand Canyon is such an amazing place to me. I've only
been there once, but it's still probably one of the most significant things I've ever done.
Just the season of my life in which I got to do it, the manner and how we made it physical.
I sort of made it a hiking swimming trip, so I swim in the Colorado River and then in each of
the waterfalls on the way up because you have these four huge waterfalls that get progressively
smaller as you go up. I was actually just talking about it with one of my kids last
night when I was reading him a story and the Grand Canyon came up and he's like,
is that a real place? I was like, yeah, this is real, man. When you guys get a little older,
we're going to be going back there. Yeah, you need to bring the kids up,
start doing 20 minutes every other day. I'm sure you have 20 minutes and we'll go do it
together. That'd be so fun. Awesome, man. Well, I really appreciate this time, Ryan.
This was so much fun for me to just kind of be able to pick the brain of one of the world's
greatest. I loved it, Peter. Awesome chatting with you, man. Thank you for listening to this
week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss,
we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content
without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price
of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally
kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we
discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA
episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private
podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this.
The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday,
highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive.
This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily
listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting
paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time
goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over
to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.