Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
In you go, it is so great to be sitting down with you again. Last time of course we did this in
person, but these days I've become too lazy to travel around and do podcasts in person. So do it
by video. But that said, I really hope you can get out here to Austin so we can train together
and do some cool ex-fizz. And also I need to get out there to sort of do some of the ex-fizz
stuff we've talked about. But you know, I almost don't know where to begin because there's so much
stuff we talked about last time that we want to double click on this time. There's so much that
has changed in the interval from when we spoke, gosh, probably two years ago, a little over two
years ago. I thought one place we could pick it up, something we didn't really talk about last time,
was your work with Tadi Pogacha because of course I don't think anybody knew who he was two years ago
or two and a half years ago. And of course now he is, I don't know, I mean I think it's safe to say
he has the potential to potentially go down as the greatest Tour de France cyclist of all time,
given how young he is, not to put that expectation out there, but to win the tour at such a young age,
to not just win the yellow jersey, but the white jersey, the polka dot jersey repeatedly. He looks
like something of a different species almost. And I say that not in the way that people typically say
those things of cyclists in a way that's suspicious of anything. So I don't know, maybe for the listeners
who are not familiar with the Tour de France, not familiar with your work with the UAE team and your
work with Tadi Pogacha, maybe give folks a little bit of an update as to what you've been doing with
in professional cycling over the past couple of years.
Yeah, well, first of all, thank you very much for having me here. It's an honor and really excited
for this and I appreciate the opportunity. I had a lot of fun last time and I hope to have fun again.
Yeah, my work with Tadi started in late 2018 when he signed up for the team. And yeah, I was introduced
to him by our CEO, Janetti, and our general manager, Machin. And they told me, hey, just start working
with this guy. And he was what at the time, 19, maybe? Yeah, 19. It was 19 at the time.
Just turned 19, in fact. And yeah, so I started to work with him. And right away, I realized
that he had very good potential. And I think like a couple of months earlier, no, or later,
I forgot when we had that podcast already told you about him. And yeah, and I told that, yeah,
we have a guy that has good potential. And yeah, that was today.
And to put it in perspective, I mean, has good potential is one thing to then go and do what he
did is would make that statement the understatement of the century for folks who maybe don't follow
cycling as closely, right? Yeah, I mean, I try to be cautious, right? And I don't usually say
that a lot of people who have. We talked about it over dinner that night.
Yeah, yeah. When I say someone has good potential is very good potential. I don't usually say that
lightly of anybody, right? What did you see in him in 2018, 2019, that led you to believe that
even amongst that class, because professional cyclists, you know, from a physiologic standpoint,
are all very special individuals. What did you see in him that made you think he has potential in
your understated way? Well, first, the physiological testing that we we started doing right off the
bat, I saw like that he had amazing capabilities, you know, the oxidative capabilities, like ability
to clear lactate and and to put out create amount of power output for long periods of time.
So when you say that, was it specifically his FTP that impressed you? Or was it his, as you said,
lactate clearance, was it shorter bursts of power that were higher than FTP, but the speed with which
he could do with the successive repeats that he could do? I mean, tell me some of the testing you
were putting cyclists through and how he stood out. So it's kind of like similar tests that I did to
you. Right. And this is kind of like where I saw that at a given power output, his lactate levels,
blood lactate levels were extremely low. And since I've been doing this specific protocol for 20 years
with professional athletes, professional cyclists in this specific case, that's where I have my
cheat sheet, right, where I know I can categorize where people are. And I was like, he was like,
whoa, wait on the other side, you know, way above almost everybody that I had tested or around the
same category. And for that age, that's what I saw. Like, whoa, first of all, he is at a different
category and he's his first year pro, he's pretty much a junior. And and then that's where like,
I could see he could sustain a high amount of power with very low lactate compared to the rest.
And then throughout the trainings, looking, we use training peaks, the software, looking at training
peaks, that's where I would see his different abilities to sustain a given power output for
the whole day, or for a specific effort, a glycolytic effort and a climb. And it would see
the power output that he would be putting out. And so altogether, then I saw his trainability,
how easy he would get the concepts, how easy he would be comfortable with the training, how easy
he would recover. I, you know, I like the feedback, I talk to him once, twice a day, and over WhatsApp
too, you know, the feedback. And I know very well when a hard week is or what a hard week is.
And when you see this kid telling you, pretty good, I'm recovering very well. When other ones
are telling you, woof, I had to take it a little bit easier today because I couldn't do this effort.
And we're talking about high level pros. And you see this kid telling you like, yeah, no problem.
That's where you start putting together things. And also, around the same time, with my two
colleagues at the university, Angela D'Alessandro and Travis Netcov, we developed, we started to
developing a platform for metabolomics where we can look at, you know, hundreds, if not thousands,
of metabolites in the human body. And we did it at the Tour of California in 2019, which was like
around April. That's where he wanted. And that's where when we analyzed all his metabolites. And
we did already at the training camp in January 2019. And we already saw, wow, this guy has different
metabolites at the glycolytic level, oxidative level, recovery level. And we confirmed that at
the Tour of California. And this is where putting all together. So like, yeah, this guy is different.
So going back to what you said about lactate, I assume that one of the data points that is
most telling of a cyclist is if you plot on the x-axis watts per kilo and on the y-axis
lactate production, that would be a very, I mean, that might be one of the most telling
graphs you could generate to predict success in the Tour, correct?
Absolutely. Absolutely. You see someone at, you know, for example, a normal temple climbing in the
Tour de France, Temple, that is the whole peloton going up.
It's got to be four.
It's about five watts per kilo.
Is it five watts per kilo? I was about to say, wow, yeah, I was going to say four and a half.
Okay, so wow, the whole peloton is going up at five watts per kilo.
Yeah, something like that. And that's what you see, like someone at that intensity might have
already six millimoles. So you can tell it's going to be very tasking. And others might have one
resting levels, you know? And this is where like, this is it really, really predicts performance.
And you can really predict performance in an incredible way. In fact, when we go to these
training camps, like I'm going to go next week for the first training camp of the year for the team,
we do this physiological testing. And I do this protocol, and I get this data. So right away,
I tell the team managers, this guy is way above the rest. These three guys are really, really good
immediately behind it. These two guys are the third level. And then we have all these guys
that they're like really, really bad form. And it pretty much works, you know, then we do different
training, racing simulation, and the teleboom right away. This is how it is. So this is why
it's very predictive. And the same thing too, moving into the season, you see, okay, all these
three guys are going to be at a very good level when we start the season. This guy who we thought
that he was going to be a very good level, he's not there at all. So and that when the season
starts, you see that it reflects very well what's going to happen. Yeah, it's one of the things about
cycling that I really love. I mean, I don't know if you saw, but I interviewed Lance Armstrong back
in, oh, gosh, probably back in June, or maybe it came out in September. But, you know, one of the
things that we talked about was both on and off EPO or blood transfusions. You sort of knew where
you stood before the race based on your FTP in watts per kilo. So, you know, when he was, he talked
about when he was off EPO, he could hold 450 watts for 30 minutes. So that would be slightly below
FT, that would be slightly above FTP at 70, I think he was 70 to 75 kilos, but it was in the
ballpark of six watts per kilo. And then of course, on EPO, it was 7.1 watts per kilo, a huge
difference. But you knew that number going in. And you sort of knew like, only the GC contenders
could do that. I think that's the thing that a lot of people don't understand about cycling,
which is there's relatively few moments in the tour when you need to sustain that level,
but they always occur at the most important strategic times, right? And that's sort of where
the race is won and lost because the race is won and lost by minutes. It's for a race that is,
how many hours does it take to complete the tour? A hundred hours or something?
That's a good question. Yeah, an average about four and a half, five hours a day.
Yeah, so it's something like that.
It's about a hundred hour race. And yet the difference between the first, second, third guy
will be in some cases seconds, in some cases a few minutes for someone to win by five minutes
is considered a blowout. And so what it really tells you is that there are a handful of minutes
in that race. There are a handful of climbs and time trials that set apart the winners from
everybody else. And that's to me, that's one of the beautiful things about cycling physiology,
is you have these metrics and now I think it's not just FTP, it's watts per kilo with
lactate production. So it gets even more into kind of the critical physiology of recovery.
Yeah, and in EFI we use this metrics a lot for the competition. And we did it this year through
the France. So knowing the power output that he could sustain for, as you very well said,
for specific times and climbs, we knew his capabilities. And one of the things that we
knew was that in the Alps, he was at a very, very high level. So, you know, like that famous stage
where he broke away and called the Rome 35 kilometers to the finish line, we are seeing
not only his data, but we see by knowing our writer's data, you can also guess the other
writer's data too, right? It's not rocket science. So we knew that he was at a very high level
and discussing the tactics, you know, because it's part of the thing that we do. We observe
the data that we have, the data that we think the other ones have, and we structure a strategy for
the next day. And hey, does he have the legs to attack? Should he be holding back? Or what
should he be doing? Clearly, it was like, well, tomorrow if he attacks 35 kilometers to the finish
line, he's going to get there with three minutes because the other guys, they're not at that level,
you know? So, wait to the end of the tour where we can try to solve the situation. So we knew his
capabilities very well and discussing this with him and the manager. Yeah, that was the strategy.
First test the legs and like if you had in fact good legs, boom, try to go for it and that's exactly
what he did. Now, how much of that are you going to determine after a night of sleep, right? Where
you say, we're going to look at his resting lactate first thing in the morning. We're going to look at
his heart rate overnight. We're going to look at his heart rate variability overnight.
So in addition to the subjective, for example, how he felt during the previous days attacks,
coupled with some of that objective data, does that partially formulate the strategy also? Or is
it mostly based on historical data from training where you say, I know that when he's at this many
watts per kilo for this many minutes, he has the capacity to recover. Yeah, I see it. It's more the
latter, right? Where we have all that physiological data and the trends and how it is. And what we
see at this level, these guys, they're so good at ignoring their feelings. Sometimes it's just
kind of how they wake up. You know his capabilities. So if he wakes up fresh and say, how are you doing
today? Like, oh yeah, it's like a baby. Like boom, then you're ready. And sometimes, yeah,
it's just we try not to focus on many other metrics the day off because we have already
things. And sometimes heart rate variability might not be very precise. And we don't want to
put some ideas in the head. And if I'm speaking with him, and I'm not going to mention any brand
or anything, but looking at heart rate variability someday, he said, look, today, he told me that I
was fatigued, that algorithm. And I went out there and beat my record, right? And the clients,
obviously, I'm not fatigued. In other days, it tells you you're in top form and I feel a little
more fatigued. So this is what these algorithms, we need to be careful sometimes and might work with
maybe general population, but with this type of athletes, at this level, I really feel that
it's better once you have all the work done. And they know, you know, their capabilities,
like, are you ready to go? It's like a top performer at a theater, right? It's like,
you have worked very hard. Now it's up to like, are you ready to go? Do you have a good net lead?
Are you ready to perform? And a good performer will say, yes, I'm ready to go.
I agree with you completely. Even for me, and I'm not at top level anything, I have not found
the predictors of, you know, readiness to be very accurate or to necessarily reflect how well I'm
going to perform. I've had amazing performances by performances, I mean workouts, right? Like,
that's, that's the only metric I'm performing in. I've had amazing workouts. When my prediction
was that it would not be good. And I've also had the prediction saying, you're on top of the world
and I've not performed well. So, you know, I wish I could say with more clarity what the frequency
of those deviations or discordances are, but I can agree that putting the wrong idea in somebody's
head, when the predictive, when there's nothing you can do about it. I mean, that's the other thing
too. It's sort of like, at best, if it was perfectly accurate, it would be great because
you could say, look, today maybe we shouldn't attack. Today it's damage control day. You know,
one of the things I want to ask you about here, and you've spoken about this publicly, so it might
be that you're just going to restate the views that you've shared publicly. But I've always felt
that now that we have such great transparency from the sort of that high octane era of sort of the
maximum, probably cheating in cycling, which, you know, in my view is kind of that two decades of
the 90s and 2000s. And we pretty much know now what kind of numbers cyclists were putting out
when they were being assisted by EPO and blood transfusions. And we sort of know that the best
of the best were able to put out somewhere between about 6.8 and 7.1 watts per kilo at FTP.
We also know today that cyclists are not doing that, right? Those numbers are nowhere to be found
in the peloton. Now that's information you and I share confidentially, right? That's not public
knowledge, but I know it, you know it, and anyone coaching people at that level know that nobody's
putting out 7.1 watts per kilo. You don't need to be at 7.1 watts per kilo to win the tour today. You
could probably win the tour today at 6.1 watts per kilo. Do you think that making that data public
would put to rest a lot of the criticisms that say the sport is still, you know, they've just found
new ways to cheat, but it's still basically a dirty sport because I think when you look at the data
objectively, it would be very hard to say that today based on what we know from the era when
drug use was rampant. No, I think you make a very good point. And it's something that,
yeah, it frustrates me, right? When people think that they're doing 7 watts per kilogram, you know,
or 7.2, you know, and then you have the real data from the day. And it's way lower, you know,
you see like, you know, for example, like the short climbs where they would do maybe 7.2,
now they're doing 6.3 maybe. And the longer climbs, they're doing 5.5, 5.8. So it frustrates me
because I see this data and I always like, gosh, I wish I could just boom, release it. And I have
absolutely no problem. I know Tade has no problem with that. It is more of that. And we debated it
with the team. Let's do it, you know, like why keeping all this. At the end of the day, people
can figure that out. And some people, when I see an internet, because you can see the, you know,
like the weight of the cyclist, the grade of the climb, the grade, the stars, the time,
and the wind, you know, you can be very accurate at knowing that. And I see some people that are
quite accurate on the internet, but I see other ones are all over the map, you know, otherwise
they say, I did the formula and it's 7.2. Like, my gosh, I wish I could show him, hey, this is the
real data that we're seeing. But I guess like two points there is like, one, it's private data that
the team considers, like, release it. That's team policy. But the other one, too, is like,
you know, even if you release that data, there are always going to be people that are not going
to believe you. Or they might say, oh, they probably altering the data. Or they're tricking
it somehow. Or putting more weight to the data so it looks like there's less power output. And I
don't know if it will be an endless fight, you know? But I don't know. I don't have the answer.
I just have that frustration that I wish that I could really show the data and people can see it,
you know? But there's always going to be someone who is not going to believe it and going to make
it a lot of noise out of that. But yeah. But yeah, that's the other thing, too, is like,
other teams and other writers are releasing their data. Right? So by releasing their data,
you can see pretty much where Pogacar is, you know? Like, okay, if it's a minute ahead or 30
minutes seconds, or sometimes with the same time, you can see, you know, like, whoa, if whatever the
writer has done and has entered in Pogacar's group or 30 seconds later and has done 5.9,
Pogacar is going to be in that neighborhood, right? Not going to be seven, you know, with 30 seconds
ahead. You know, in the spirit of releasing data, the other thing it would potentially do,
especially if you could see it in real time. I don't know if you watch Formula One, but one of
the things about Formula One that I think the sport has been able to do because of the advances
in technology is make more of the data available to the viewer. So if you're watching Lewis Hamilton
driving a lap, you know, you see what he sees now. You can see, and it's not like the end of the
world data, but you see his speed, you see what gear he's in, you see the difference between
throttle and brake pressure. They could show even more data, certainly, and someone who drives
would appreciate it if you really saw brake bias and if you saw brake pressure and lockup and things
like that. And you can hear the drivers speaking with their race engineers. So, you know, it
basically allows you to come more and more into what they're doing. This year they introduced a
new camera angle, which is what the driver sees. And I think it's fantastic because historically
you see above them and it looks so smooth, but that's not at all what it feels like to be in a
race car. So now they just literally put like a camera at their shoulder and now you see how
restrictive the halo is, you see the bumps and it looks a lot faster. You know, I've had this
discussion with a number of people, which is if you could show the same sort of information in
cycling, if every time the camera went over to a cyclist, you saw their heart rate, their watts per
kilo, their speed, you know, all of these other things, and you could hear some of the communications
back and forth with their teams. Yes, that changes the sport. Strategically now you have to be careful
what you say on the radio, but it also allows you to see kind of the human element of this sport a
little bit more. Do you think that will ever happen where you'll be able to flip on the Tour de France
and you'll be able to actually see real time physiology? I would love to see that that day.
I would love it because it would be so much fun right for the viewer and as you see, I mean cycling
has so many possibilities, you know, to engage people more and be fascinated by the physiology
and looking at these numbers. You know, there's this, it's already in a way, you know, you see
some cameras already installed in the front and the back. So it's called with Velon, right? So you
can see really cool when that, I mean, images when they're preparing a sprint that is like what feels
inside. And you can see it's really scary. Sometimes you can appreciate how difficult it is to be at,
you know, like 40 miles an hour sprinting or 35 miles an hour leading to a sprint or in a descent.
Or 70 mile an hour descent. 70 mile an hour descent, exactly. And then you can see the power
also output in real time. It's still in that, I think it's a great step. You don't see no
the riders, but it's estimation only the riders will wear that Velon or the Velon decides to do
that. I think that they're still not doing that with all the top contenders. But I think it's
a first step and I really haven't spoken with them, but maybe it's like, Hey, let's see what's
the feedback. And I think that people are loving it. And I would expect that this will increase,
you know, and I mean, I would love at some point, you know, and as you know, very well,
in the world of biosensors, right? It's going to revolutionize sports where we're going to be able
to see, you know, so many different parameters of us. Imagine you could see lactate and glucose in
real time, which of course is technologically feasible already. So it's just a question of,
yeah. So I think that would love for all sports too, right? Imagine you can see an NBA basketball
game, right? And see that the lactator of LeBron James compared to the other ones, right? I mean,
I would love to see that as a spectator and I hope that someday we were able to see these parameters.
So last thing on the tour, talk to me about Vantu this year. That was a tough stage.
Also, I mean, kind of showed, it looked like his toughest stage. Was that a fair assessment?
Yes, probably. Yeah.
And what's amazing, I think, is the poise on that stage. It's hard to tell if he was really
struggling on the ascent of Van 2 or he was just deciding strategically, I'm going to conserve a
little bit of energy here. What was your take on that? Or what can you say about that?
Well, it was a very difficult climb and a very long climb. So, you know, Tade, his mentality
is wired like a champion. And he, when someone goes and they were full gas in the last part
when we knew they were attacked. And Tade knew that, okay, this is not going to be the top of
Van 2. It's not going to be the end of the stage. I have a long descent where I can make it.
Very, very long descent. And I have some partners with me that can help me out. So I'm not going to
panic at all, but I'm not going to also try to waste a lot of energy because I need to. Now,
I have, he also had a big gap. The whole different thing would have been if he had
20 seconds. But having a big gap and knowing that you have a big descent and how calm he is,
that's one thing that is a very important strategy. And this is what happened.
This reminds me in a way what happened the first year that he was pro when he was 19 at the
Tour of California. It was the previous stage before what's called Bear Lake. No, what is the
mountain? Bear Lake. I think it's Bear Lake. Yeah, it's the top mountain in the Tour of California
where it's going to be decided. So the day before, two cyclists, George Bennett and Ygitta,
attacked in a short but very steep climb. And there were only like 12 riders left and Ygitta
and Bennett attacked. Then there was a descent and a long highway all the way to the finish line. So
there was plenty of time to catch them up. But Tade didn't follow them up. Another rider would
have just followed their wheel and Tade decided, no, I'm not going to follow them. We have time
and I'm going to take the chance because I'm confident for tomorrow. And when I asked him,
as soon as he crossed the finish line, I'm asking, are you okay? Why you didn't follow their attack?
And he said, well, I just wanted to know who is going to be good tomorrow. So I know those two
guys are going to be good tomorrow, but I wanted to take my time and see the other 10 guys, how
they're breathing, what's their body language, and take my time to observe, to start preparing
my strategy for tomorrow. And in fact, that's what he did. So they were then caught up, you know,
like two or three kilometers to the finish line. So all those 12, 13 guys, whatever they were,
got together and the next day, in fact, he noticed those two guys attacked, he just followed them and
he just eliminated one by one. But that's how this guy thinks, you know, his strategy, like,
no panic, plenty of time today. I have a good gap in the GC. Why am I going to go full gas when I
know that he's going to go full gas and he might lose energy for tomorrow. Because he might pay
for this at this time of the two of the friends, we have plenty of time to catch him up. So that's
kind of the strategy that he had, too. How much time does someone like Tadi spend in Zone Two,
which we're going to talk a lot about, right? So and let's do it more as percentage of training
time, because I think absolute numbers will be very large, given that that's his job. But when
you think about the percentage of time he spends in that energy zone, how does it change over the
course of the year? So presumably, during the winter months, a greater amount of his time would
be spent there as he's base building right before a race when he's kind of sharpening, maybe less.
But what would be the range of time? Yeah, that's a good question. So yeah, when and you're right,
when we talk about percentages, I like to put it this way more like a percentage of days dedicated
to cultivate that energy system. Obviously, if you put in just every single minute together,
like the majority is going to be that. But I would say more in days. So yeah, in the winter
months might be about 80% or 70 to 80% of the days as the season gets closer, he starts increasing
more than 10 city days and sessions. And then you have you start the season. So when the start of
the season, racing and you have it depends, right, you might have one stage race of five, seven days,
and then you have a five day block or one week to recover, and they have the next stage rate. So in
that week, we do a lot of recovery, we may do some sessions here and there. And then after a few
blocks of races, that's where you have another long time to train period to train, going to altitude
towards the Tour de France or towards the next goal. And that's where you may revisit, you know,
those different energy systems and train specifically. But yeah, we alternate and I
think it's each energy system has a time in the year and in the calendar where it's built
in order to try to achieve what we want. So let's remind people now with this, you know,
I've put out a few posts on social over, gosh, the past year, and even in the past little while,
and anytime I'm talking about zone two, it's really one of the topics that generates the most
curiosity, the most the most inquiry from people. I think people really intuitively kind of resonate
with this. And then of course, a million questions follow because there's there's so much minutia and
detail around it. And a lot of that we're going to cover today. But let's start from a place of maybe
someone hasn't heard the first podcast where we go through some of the semantics of this. Define
zone two. Okay, so zone two, right. I started using it like about 25 years ago. And I just
have a very simple name. So it is from my point of view, it is the exercise intensity at the one
you are stressing the mitochondria and oxidative capacity to the most. This is where you're
recruiting mainly type one muscle fibers. This is where you are mobilizing the highest amount of fat,
both from lipolysis from adipose tissue as well from fat oxidation inside the mitochondria.
And this is also where you stimulate all those energies that enter that bioenergetics, which is
oxidative phosphorylation. This is where you burn both the fat inside the mitochondria, as well as
the glucose inside the mitochondria. There's not a very high glycolytic flux that it's going to be
transforming to pyruvate and reduced to lactate. But that flux still is oxidized inside mitochondria.
And this is looking at from bioenergetics standpoint, this is what I would consider the
zone two. And what I have seen is that throughout the years is that this is the exercise intensity
that achieves or stimulates that mitochondrial function and fat oxidation and lactate cleanse
capacity the most. Because that's the other thing too. This is where there are other things
involving lactate. So lactate is a great fuel to the cells. It's in fact, it's probably the preferred
fuel for the cells, for most cells in the body. This is a work that my colleague and mentor and
friend George Brooks discovered. You should have him someday in the podcast because he's fascinating.
I mean, I will not be surprised someday soon. We hear that he wins the Nobel Prize. He's amazing.
And every time I talk to him, I still learn a lot of things. And I've been translating a lot of his
research. But yeah, that's how I see that you have within the mitochondrial function, you see
how lactate is oxidizing the mitochondria back to energy. And that happens in those muscle fiber
types. Those muscle fiber types and the mitochondria, those fiber types also develop these
transporters, which are MCT1s, which are the ones that transport lactate inside the cell and inside
the mitochondria. So when you stimulate that training zone, you stimulate all these energy
systems and the components that come with them. So let's talk about the different ways that one
can go about estimating this. Based on the definition you've just given, it seems to me
that the purest way to estimate this would be via indirect calorimetry because that will actually
tell us the fat oxidation. Is that a fair assessment? Yes, it's a very good assessment.
And that usually correlates with the fat max. That's how we call it too, right? With fat
oxidation. When you see this, you start oxidizing fat and my increase in cases and gets to a point
that it maxes out, which is the fat max. And then it starts going down sharply. As exercise
intensive increases. So let's tell people how that's measured because I think it's, we do this
with all of our patients and I find it to be not that easy to explain because there's some physiology
involved and there's some math involved. But let me try to see if I can explain this to folks. So
you hook me up to an indirect calorimetry. So you're going to put a little plug on my nose,
you're going to put a mask over my nose and mouth. That mask has the ability to measure
the amount of oxygen that I consume because it has a sensor for O2. So it knows that the O2 that's
coming in is at 21%. The air is coming in at 21% O2 and whatever I exhale is the difference between
that. So you can now tell how much O2 was consumed and you can have a similar sensor for carbon
dioxide. So you know how much carbon dioxide is produced. So it's very easy to measure consumed
oxygen and produced carbon dioxide provided you can completely isolate around the nose and the mouth.
As you hook a person up to some form of ergometer, usually a bike, but it could be a treadmill,
a rowing machine or something like that, you can increase the demand on the muscle. So you
increase the wattage or the speed or the something. You then get out these numbers,
VO2 and VCO2, which are what we just talked about. So consumption of oxygen production of carbon
dioxide. These numbers fit into a relatively straightforward linear equation called the Weer
equation. And it tells you three things. It tells you total energy consumption in kilocalories per
minute. And then the ratio of VO2 and VCO2 tell you how much of that energy is coming from fat
oxidation and how much of it is glycolytic. So at any moment in time, you can look at a VCO2 and a
VO2, which are usually measured in liters per minute. And you can convert that into a total
grams of fat oxidation and a total grams of glucose oxidation per minute. And so you could
then plot on the X axis work or power, and on the Y axis, you could plot fat oxidation.
So again, describe for people what the shape of that curve looks like and what differentiates
Pogaczor from the average human being. Yeah. So again, I mean, you explained it very well.
And yeah, those are based on stoichiometric equations based on the combustion of carbohydrates
and fatty acids are done in the body. Already in the 1920s, Francis Benedict was one of the first
ones who started to look into this at this level. And obviously, we have evolved into
doing it in a more automatic way with this indirect color imageries, machines or colds or
metabolic cards. So yes, as exercise intensity increases, you need more oxygen. So you review
increases, and then you produce or give up more CO2. So this is kind of what it shows when you're
in a more like politic state, more, more fatty oxidation state, you still consume oxygen, but
you do not produce as much CO2. When you are more into a more glycolytic state, which is higher
exercise intensities, when you're recruiting the type two muscle fibers, and therefore using more
glucose for energy purposes, you're going to consume more oxygen and you're going to produce
more CO2. So plugging in all these numbers into these stoichiometric equations, it's going to
give you that profile in the x and the y axis, and it's going to see what is the
the fat oxidation throughout a ramp state, a ramp test. And this is where you're going to see
that elite athletes like Bogatr, they have an amazing fat oxidation capacity compared to
other competitive athletes or recreationals or people with even type two diabetes or metabolic
syndrome or in a recent study we have published with COVID patients. So it reflects in a way
ultimately what happens in your mitochondria and how the mitochondria oxidizes those fuels
at different exercise intensity. So for example, let's say at an intensity of 200, let's say 200
watts, like an elite athlete doesn't need to incur in that glycolytic capacity as much as someone who
is not very well trained. So the elite athlete, they can still recruit the slow twitch muscle fibers
and rely a lot on fat to produce ATP because they have an amazing mitochondrial function
and they're very efficient metabolically speaking. Therefore, they're going to be oxidizing a lot of
fat. However, someone whose mitochondria are not working as well, whether you are like a
recreational athlete or sedentary individual or someone with type two diabetes, which is one of
the hallmarks of the disease, that mitochondrial impairment or dysfunction at 200 watts, you fully
rely on glucose pretty much because you cannot sustain that effort with fat alone.
And this is what you're going to be seeing in this gas exchange, the CO2 and the VO2,
you can just plot it into the equation and it's going to give you all that what I call metabolic
map where you see the fat oxidation, the carbohydrate oxidation, and then I plug in
also the lactate and that's where everything comes together quite well. And you can then
first, in an indirect way, calculate the mitochondrial function and metabolic flexibility,
how flexible they are at using fats or carbohydrates. And also you can determine
training zones. And this is what I've been using this methodology for,
poof, about 16 years, 17, something like that. I didn't think to ask you this earlier, but
if you have it handy, do you want to pull up a graph of what fat oxidation looks like versus power
so that people can see the difference between a highly trained individual, a reasonably trained
individual, an untrained individual, and at the other end of that spectrum, somebody with type two
diabetes? Sure. So let me share a screen then, right? And hopefully this works. Okay. So this
is from a publication, right, that my colleague George Brooks and I published in 2017. So this
is the formula and we have realized that this is flipped. So we need to, we're working now with the
editor to change it because the formula is flipped here in the method section. Which is so funny by
the way, I like seeing that. I'm embarrassed to say when we do this for our patients, we do it in
two steps, which yields the same result. But we first calculate energy expenditure using the
Wir coefficients of 3.94 times V02 minus, or plus one point, I think it's one two times VCO2.
And then we convert that to fat ox and carbohydrate oxidation using the ratio of
VCO2 to V02. And I never even thought to do what you've done here, which is so much more logical,
which is combine them into a single equation for each. Well, we use what Freiand observed already
in 1983. And this is Freiand's equation. And it's been validated with tracers, with
stabilized top tracers. And yeah, and that's what it shows. There's a very high correlation. Now,
furthermore, in study that we were going to be publishing soon, we have validated this
fat oxidation and carbohydrate oxidation directly with mitochondrial respiration.
So in muscle biopsies, we inject directly fatty acids, pyruvate representative of carbohydrates,
right? And glutamine representative of amino acids. And then we can see that there's a very high
correlation between this indirect methodology to look at mitochondrial function and the direct
methodology, which is through muscle biopsy and injecting the substrate and see how it's oxidized.
So these two graphs are really powerful. So let's talk about what the first graph is showing us.
So both of these graphs, it's important to note, have the same x-axis. In other words, the
independent variable here is the workload in watts. That's the metric that matters in cycling,
which is, I think, the easiest way to do this test. And so you're increasing wattage. This is a
progressive increase in workload. And what you're plotting on the y-axis, your dependent variable
here in the first graph, figure one, is blood lactate. So what stands out to me is a couple
of things. So you have the triangles represent metabolic syndrome, the squares represent kind of
a modestly trained athlete, and then the little diamonds represent a professional athlete.
The first thing that stands out to me, and we're going to talk about this later, so I'll put a
little pin in this, is that the people with metabolic syndrome have a resting lactate that's
almost two millimole. Yeah? Yes, we see already this. And I think that it's going to become more
and more as a biomarker, like resting blood glucose levels. What is your resting lactate?
And you can see already in patients with type 2 diabetes or profound metabolic syndrome,
that yeah, as you said, perfectly resting levels are in the neighborhood of like 1.8
to even 3. Right? Yeah. So one of the metrics that we've discussed at length, and we'll revisit it,
of course, is using this lactate level of about two millimole as being that threshold. So once
lactate exceeds two millimole, the individual is now escaping out of zone 2, and they're actually
now into zone 3. So when you look at these data here, you can see that the individual with
metabolic syndrome is basically tapping out zone 2 initially. So any incremental workload that is
placed on them takes them right out of zone 2. So they're, for all intents and purposes, by the time
they're at 100 watts, they're already at the threshold of their zone 2. Now conversely,
when you look at that sort of medium trained or reasonably well trained individual, or what we,
I think it's referred to as moderately active, healthy individuals, you know, they start out
with a lactate of about one, and it's not really until they hit about 175 watts that they pass that
inflection point. And then when you look at the professional athletes, the professional endurance
athletes specifically, you know, they're starting out at a lactate level of 0.5 millimole, and they
stay relatively flat until they hit about 300 watts is when they finally cross over that threshold.
Now what's not captured here is that as you move from left to right, the athletes are getting
lighter. So this graph, if I'm going to be critical of it and you go, I would say it should be done in
watts per kilo. And that would show a much starker difference between these. And in our patients,
when we benchmark them, we benchmark them in watts per kilo for this reason so that you normalize by
weight. And yeah, and I'm certain, Robert, you're absolutely right. It is that, and that's how we
do it also. Yes, of course. It's like one of the reviewers didn't allow us to use watts per kilogram.
So that reviewer was an idiot. So that's fine. I won't hit it against you because you have an
idiot reviewer. But yes, how it is in review papers, you want to show something and eventually
it's changed and it's not exactly what you want to show, you know, because otherwise they don't
allow you to publish it. But anyways, so what's amazing here is that person with metabolic syndrome
is probably about one watt per kilo easily, right? Or, you know, one to 1.3 watts per kilo
is their zone two. When you look at the modestly trained individual, they're about two watts per
kilo, right? They probably weigh maybe two to 2.1, 2.2 watts per kilo. That professional endurance
athlete probably weighs in the neighborhood of 70 kilos. Yeah, exactly. So, you know, they're in
the ballpark of four watts per kilo. For our patients, Inigo, we typically want, we set the
aspiration at three watts per kilo. So again, our patients aren't professional athletes, but we
think that three watts per kilo would be kind of the elite level that we would want to see people.
And then of course we stratify from there. Okay, let's look at the lower figure,
figure two, just beneath this. So here we're looking at the same group of individuals.
We have the same independent variable, which is work, but now we're calculating fat oxidation
as a function of that work. So now your dependent variable is fat oxidation, which again,
very easy to calculate via indirect calorimetry. Two things stand out again. The first is the
obvious, which is the fitter the individual, the higher their absolute capacity for fat oxidation.
But something else stands out to me, Inigo, and I have now seen this repeatedly across multiple
datasets, which is a fit individual actually increases fat oxidation to a local maxima
before beginning that decline. Whereas most mortals begin at a maximum and decline from there.
Can you explain why that's happening? Yes. Yeah, it's something that I agree. I see this all the
time. I think that on one hand is how you start a protocol. In this case, we started like a one.
We start about one to 1.5 watts per kilogram. And that obviously for a elite athlete is
trivial. Low resting levels. This is why they're very low. And they don't need to use much fat for
energy purposes until you push them more. And that's when you get to like 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5 watts
per kilogram. And again, this protocol comes originally from the work that I've been doing
for 20 years. This is in protocol with elite athletes. Now, when you do the same protocol
with other populations, especially people with metabolic syndrome or not very fit,
and you start at 1.5 watts per kilogram, that might be too much. And I'm sure you have observed
that if you start at 0.5 watts per kilogram, you might see a higher fat oxidation. And then you
might see the same phenomenon. So on one hand is that protocol, but on the other hand, yeah,
sure, it's like 0.5 watts per kilogram. It's like nothing. It's close to resting levels almost. So
it will take you for a long time. But that being said, I think that one thing that we're doing with
populations, more clinical populations is really starting at a very low level, even up to 50 watts
or 25 watts sometimes. So we can start with this point because if you start at 2 watts per kilogram
or 1.5 watts per kilogram with someone with a significant metabolic dysregulation, you're
going to miss the fat max. Yeah, I agree. We have been struggling to tune our algorithm to
exactly that because I actually think that, and I had this discussion with our team a week ago,
which was the physiologists who are doing this with our patients are probably over-cooking the
people who are not fit during the warmup. So they do a warmup and the warmup is actually too
stressful and it over-cooks them and then we're missing kind of the true max fat.
Okay, so the next thing I want to point out here is that the, and let's just look at the fittest
person, but it's true for all of them, but it's easiest to see here. Fat max, so fat max ox,
right? So maximum fat oxidation is occurring earlier than lactate is 2. And that's true for
all of them, except for the met sin person because it's so low. But if you look at the
moderately fit person, they're hitting maximum fat oxidation at about 130 watts,
but they're hitting lactate of 2 at 175 watts in the upper figure. And the professional athlete
is hitting an absolute fat oxidation maxima at a little shy of 250 watts,
but they're hitting lactate of 2 closer to 300 watts. So I guess the question then becomes,
which one of these do you think, well, you've already answered part of the question, which is
we're really defining zone 2 as the place where maximum fat oxidation occurs. But I guess this
would suggest that using a lactate level of 2 is maybe overestimating where that is. And should we
be using a lower level of lactate, such as 1.5 or something like that?
Yeah, that's an excellent question. And this is what I've been learning all these years,
is that the blood lactate levels might change between different groups. And it's everything
related to the lactate kinetics and lactate oxidation in the mitochondria. So for example,
elite athletes, and I did this, it was part of my doctorate thesis and some of this that
I never published it 20 something years ago. But the same blood lactate concentration
does not correspond to the same, in an elite athlete, this not correspond necessarily to
the same lactate concentration in a recreational athlete, the metabolic stress. So for example,
2 millimolts or 2 millimolar lactate in these elite athletes might be
a higher metabolic stress than 2 millimolts in a metabolic patient. So this is why,
and it would be very difficult. For example, you can have, let's say 2.5 millimolts, you can have
a metabolic syndrome patient exercising for a couple hours without a big deal. You try to do
that with a professional athlete, and they're going to be hurting. And in fact, one of the
things that I observe is like I used 4 millimolts or millimolar, which is kind of that gold standard
has been forever like the lactate threshold, etc. And if you put a world class athlete at 4 millimoles
of lactate, at the intensity in power output that elicits 4 millimoles, and you put a recreational
athlete at the power output that elicits also 4 millimoles, and you say now go, right, and see
who lasts the most, intuitively we're going to say obviously it's going to be the professional
athlete, it's the opposite. And this is the data that I saw 20 something years ago, where the
recreational athletes at the same blood lactate concentration would go about 30% longer period of
time. And that's because metabolically is not a stusking. And the main reason is that the lactate
that we see in the blood, it reflects the mitochondrial oxidation. So someone who has,
obviously when we're talking about, you know, high power output, when you need a lot of glycolysis to
produce energy, you're going to produce lactate. Lactate is the mandatory obligatory byproduct,
not waste product, but byproduct of glycolysis. So the higher the glycolysis, the higher the lactate.
Now that lactate has two routes mainly. One is going from the fast twitch muscle fibers,
to the slow twitch muscle fibers. It's the lactate shuttle that George Bush discovered,
and it's oxidizing the mitochondria of those slow twitch muscle fibers. If you have a very good
lactate clearance capacity, right, you're going to be oxidizing it very, very well for fuel.
Therefore, you're not going to incur in the second step, which is exporting it to the blood, right.
When you have a poor mitochondrial function, it's going to get to a point that that
capacity is going to get saturated at a lower power output, and therefore you're going to be
forced to explore that to the blood. So that's why looking at blood lactates might not mean the same.
I'm not saying that these parties are huge by no means, right, but as you very well said,
those two millimoles might not correspond in a little athlete with a fat max, but might be
more maybe towards 1.5, whereas maybe in someone with a more recreational metabolic syndrome,
it might correspond fair. I don't know if it makes sense.
It completely makes sense, and this is definitely the level of nuance that I don't think we captured
in the first podcast. I want to now ask a more telling question specifically for the middle
person here, so the one that's called the moderately active individual, where again,
we have a disparity, right, so based on these data, the moderately fit individual
hits a lactate of two millimole at 175 watts, but hits a max fat oxidation at,
gosh, 125 watts, so it's a 50 watt difference. So now the question for you is, when that person
comes to you and says in you go, I want to improve my metabolic function, I want to improve
my mitochondrial performance, I want to improve my fuel partitioning, my flexibility, all the
things we talk about, are you going to train them as a zone two of 125 watts or as a zone two of
175 watts as represented by these deltas? That's a very good question, and normally I would try to
do something in the middle. Normally, and again, this, yeah, it might not coincide perfectly,
but normally they do quite well. And another parameter that if you allow me, I can show you
in this paper, this is what when decided, we see individually, right, the lactates,
and then we see the fat oxidation. But then where I decided to cross them over,
right, and this is what we saw in this graph over here. So this is, can you see it okay?
Yes. So this is where you see that the lactate versus, I mean, sorry, the lactate versus the fat
oxidation, right, in the elite athlete, and the R is 0.97. This is true both for running equations.
So this is an average, right, of all of them. And this is where you see the same pattern,
the same graph for the moderately active. And this is also what you see in the people,
person with metabolic syndrome. The correlations are very, very strong. They're almost perfect,
right? So this is what normally fat oxidation and lactate, they go together, right?
So for people who are going to be listening to this Inigo and not able to see what we're seeing,
can you describe the differences between these graphs? These are obviously showing the same data
that we discussed earlier, but now we're using two y-axes. So let's even just talk about it as
looking at the elite athletes. So you're basically plotting the decline in fat oxidation, or in their
case, the initial increase in fat oxidation followed by a decline in fat oxidation. And on
the same graph, you're showing the increase in lactate production, again, both plotted to the
same x-axis of power. Does the cross point here indicate any significance? So they're crossing at
about 325 watts. Is there anything about that that means anything? I mean, to me, I think it's an
artifact of the graph because it's really just a function of how you scale it, correct?
Yes, yeah, exactly. I mean, it shows to me that the crossover point for blood lactate and fat
oxidation, it's very high, obviously, in the elite athletes, very far to the right.
Right. So and then of course, in the moderately fit people, it looks like it's closer to 180 watts.
Exactly.
And in the unfit individual, it's about 125 watts in person with metabolic syndrome.
Yeah. And again, I mean, if you started, and I'm sure you have seen this, but if you started with
the metabolic syndrome, for example, at 25 watts, you might see, or even in the recreational athlete,
even earlier, you might see a similar pattern as you would see in the elite athlete, but a much
lower watts, obviously. It is that we just did the same protocol for everybody just to show the
concept, right, that both fat oxidation and lactate go together. And also, when we look into,
and I'm sorry, I should have gone to this directly, when we look into fat oxidation and
carbohydrate oxidation, we see the same concept, right? So we see as exercise intensity increases,
you need to oxidize more carbohydrates. And then as exercise intensity increases,
you may get to the fat max. And then when you moment you switch to the glycolytic fibers,
you cannot use much fat for energy purposes. So you see a sharp decline, and eventually fat
oxidation disappears. And it's all food glycolytic. And the same pattern we see in the rest of
populations, with also very high statistical significances and correlations. So that's where
all these elements, fat oxidation, carbohydrates, and lactate, they're very well connected.
If we look in the other graph, this is the correlation between lactate and carbohydrates,
right? We see that overall, the correlations are quite good, because, yeah, lactate is the
byproduct of glucose utilization, right? You may see that in the elite athletes, though, the gap
is wider here. And this is for the same reason that we've seen earlier, they use a lot of glucose.
They're using so much fat there as well, is really the point, right? So the bigger the gap
between the blood lactate curve and the carbohydrate oxidation curve, the more efficient
the individual is, the more they're able to oxidize fatty acid, then they have to require glucose.
And clear lactate. Yes. Again, the mandatory byproduct of glucose oxidation is lactate.
So here, the lactate doesn't show up in the blood. Yeah, that's interesting. It's hard to
disentangle those two, because you mentioned a good point that I omitted. This in part reflects
the lactate shuttle. This in part reflects the ability for them to reuse lactate as a fuel,
as opposed to just letting it get out there with hydrogen and start to poison sarcomeres.
So let me see the other slide that you wanted to show that explains, I think, how the MCT
transporters work. Yeah, so this is a little bit more of the bioenergetics of the cells, of the
main two substrates, which are fatty acids and lactate, I mean, and pyruvate, and also lactate,
right? So normally glucose goes through glycolysis and it ends up, and this is the cytosol, this is
the outside of the mitochondria, the inside of the cell. And glucose, once it enters the cell,
it's oxidized to pyruvate. That pyruvate needs to enter the mitochondria through what's called
the mitochondria pyruvate carrier, and it's oxidized to acetyl-CoA, which enters the crep cycle,
right? This is a complete oxidation of glucose through oxidative phosphorylation in the crep
cycle and electron transport chain. Then fatty acids have the same mechanisms to, I mean,
they also get converted to acetyl-CoA, but through different mechanisms. Fatty acids are transporter
through CPT-1 and CPT-2, go through beta-oxidation, acetyl-CoA, and enter the cell, right? But every
time that you use glucose, you produce pyruvate, and every single time that pyruvate is going to
be reduced to lactate, always, right? And this is the key concept. So when you have a constant
glycolytic flux, right, you're going to, in one of the steps of glycolysis, you're going to utilize
NAD, right? And it's going to be transformed to NADH plus hydrogen. So if you use this mechanism a
lot, you're going to replenish NAD. I mean, you're going to deplete NAD. The only way that rescues
NAD is the reduction of pyruvate to lactate, which replenishes NAD going back for glycolysis,
and this is absolutely necessary for the continuation of glycolysis. But anyways,
this was an aside note, but this lactate enters the cell, right, through a specific, I mean,
the mitochondria through a specific transporter, MCT-1, and has a specific enzyme, LDH, that
oxidates lactate back to pyruvate and going back to the Krebs cycle. So again, this is an extra
fuel, but for that, you need to have these transporters very well developed.
Yeah, let me try to explain this to people who aren't able to see the graph, because this is
such an important point, right? So you're showing a picture of the mitochondria, and we're looking
at the outer mitochondrial membrane. We're talking about three transporters, three things that let
substrates from the outside to the inside, where they will undergo the most efficient form of ATP
production. So the first is we have the fatty acids, they enter directly, and they undergo
an oxidation where they get truncated into little two carbon chains, and they enter the Krebs cycle.
We get that one, and we know why that one's very good. What I think is very interesting here is
when you contrast the two different fates of glucose byproducts. So the traditional way that
we think about this, glucose being reduced to pyruvate, pyruvate directly entering the cell
through its own carrier, and then being converted to acetyl-CoA, which follows the same fate as the
fatty acid. Now, when energy demand increases, and we just looked at graph after graph that
demonstrate that no matter how fit you are, at some point, you have to produce more lactate.
So you now don't have sufficient cellular oxygen to go down that first route, so you start making
lactate. But if you have enough MCT1 transporters on the outer mitochondrial membrane, you can now
bring that lactate in the cell and actually do the reverse of what just happened. Turn that lactate
back into pyruvate. Pyruvate becomes acetyl-CoA, and everybody wins the game again, the game being
won, of course, because now you're making 32 units of ATP instead of just the two units you would make
converting pyruvate to lactate. So it begs a very important question, which is, earlier when you
spoke about what makes Bogacar so remarkable physiologically, one of those things is he must
have a boatload of MCT1 transporters on his outer mitochondrial membrane, and that must
explain in part why his lactate levels are so much lower than everybody else's at a comparable work
level. How much of that is genetic, and how much of that is a result of his training?
Exactly. So you're right. He has a much higher level to oxidize lactate, right? So there's a
genetic component, no doubt about it. But there's also an epigenetic component, right? And as we
know nowadays, the genes are not your fate necessarily, right? From the genes to be
able to be transcribed and form a protein with biological action,
the probability is less than 20%. That's kind of what the science is showing roughly, right?
This is the whole from genetics to transcriptomics, proteomics, and metabolomics, right? It's about
20% chances that one gene is going to be ultimately expressed. Obviously, we're still trying to
understand all this. So these elite athletes, probably they have a much higher possibilities,
right? But there's a long journey. And this is where epigenetics occur, right? It's like what
you eat, how you rest, how you train. And I think that the training is also an important component
of this. This is, for example, why we train very, very specifically this energy system.
And we try to dial in as much as we can specifically to try to stimulate this bioenergetics
system and increase the MCT1s, the transporters for lactate, as well as all the components in the
Krebs cycle, right? Which is the mitochondrial respiration. And also to increase also the
mitochondrial pyruvitic carrier, because as we might discuss later, this is already dysregulated
in people or downregulated in people who are sedentary, right? But the thing is like, if you
see this next slide, can you see it? Okay. So this is what makes the difference in these
athletes, right? So this is a fast twitch muscle fiber, and they use glucose. So this is when you
are like a high exercise intensity climbing or running at a high intensity, or swimming,
or whatever the activity you do, you need glucose. Because glucose is, as you said very well, it
yields less ATP, but it does it much faster, right? Than the diesel gasoline, which is the fat.
But when you use glucose, you always produce pyruvate. So the higher the intensity, the more
glucose you need, the more pyruvate you will need, and the more lactate that you will produce.
So that lactate has, as I said earlier, two routes. One route is like, it's exported through
the MCT force, which is the transport of lactate outside the fast twitch muscle fibers, something
that also is strainable, right? The capacity to export lactate through high intensity exercise.
And then it travels to the adjacent slow twitch muscle fibers. And if we blow up this mitochondria
in the slow twitch muscle fibers, this is what will happen. The entrance of that lactate, it goes
through another transporter, MCT1, it's the same family, but instead of four, it's called MCT1.
And as I mentioned earlier, that lactate is converted to pyruvate in acetyl-CoA and goes
into the crypt cycle. So in these well-trained athletes like Porgatsar, for example, they have
an amazing ability to oxidize the lactate inside mitochondria, right? At some point, every single
human gets to a point that they cannot sustain the effort anymore, right? But what makes the
difference is, oh really, it's like these guys can do 400 watts for a long time versus a mere mortal
who can not even do two strokes at 400 watts, right? So what happens is like when you have a lot of,
when you don't have the right MCT1 and mitochondrial function, this lactate is going to
increase and accumulate, right? And it's not lactate per se, but the hydrogen ions associated
to lactate elicit an acidosis of the microenvironment of the muscle, which is something
that we know and we have learned also from cancer, the famous cancer microenvironment,
which is very acidic. And that's going to interfere with different functions in the muscle with both
the contraction of the contractive force and the velocity of the muscle fibers.
I'm not saying that this is the cause of fatigue by no means because there are multiple theories
and we're still trying to understand the central fatigue as well and everything probably is
interrelated or it must be interrelated. But the bottom line is like when this lactate cannot be
oxidized, it is exported to the blood. And this is why you see that people with metabolic syndrome,
for example, or type 2 diabetes who are characterized by having a very poor mitochondrial
function, they cannot do an exercise oxidized this lactate. In the moment, they start using glucose,
which is very fast also because they don't have the fast twitch, the slow twitch muscle fibers
mitochondria to use fat. They need to rely on glucose. That's that metabolic reprogramming or
partitioning they have. They produce lactate, but they cannot oxidize the lactate. That's why this
lactate chooses, mandatory, the route of being exported to the blood and in the blood, then it
goes to any tissue in the body. So this is what I meant earlier about what is 2 millimoles versus
1 millimole. Whereas pogat's are, for example, he oxidizes a lot of this lactate. So by the time
the pogat's saturates this transporter in this mitochondrial capacity to oxidize lactate,
it's a tremendous amount of power output and a tremendous amount of glucose that he puts out.
So this is why that the 1 millimole or 1.5 millimole in a world class athlete doesn't
necessarily represent the same metabolic status of a 1.5 or 2 millimoles in the blood of a normal
person. Does it make sense? It makes complete sense. This is a fantastic tutorial in muscle
physiology. And again, this very important distinction between lactate production
at the local level and lactate that we measure at the global level. That's the challenge we have.
When we are measuring lactate, we cannot impute lactate clearance and lactate production. We can
only impute the sum of those. Exactly. And we think, I mean, it's originally thought that
these athletes, they don't use as much glucose. Well, in fact, the Richard Shoe's and Brooks and
his team showed it, and others too, that well-trained athletes, in fact, they use more glucose
because they have to. You cannot do 400 watts with a massive amount of carbohydrate oxidation.
And this is what we also see in the indirect colorimetry, that you see people, recreationals
for people with metabolic syndrome, they have like four grams per minute at max carbohydrate
oxidation, whereas elite athletes, they can get to six and a half, right? Cramps per minute. It's
massive amount of glucose and they produce a lot more lactate. But the key is like, it doesn't
show up in the blood. It's the rate of appearance in the blood because it's oxidized in the muscle.
So it doesn't show up in the blood. It's the balance of lactate production and lactate oxidation
without getting to the blood. And this is what it correlates a lot also with the fat
oxidation as well. And the graphs that I was showing earlier.
So one of the things I want to ask you about here that is a bit of a confounder when we do
this type of analysis is the carbohydrate content within the diet. So I'll share with you
my data, but I've now seen this with multiple people, including one individual who's remarkably
fit. So God, it's how many years now 10 years ago, I was on a ketogenic diet for three years.
And part of that three year window overlapped with the very end of that three year period was
when I kind of got back into cycling. So at my fittest as an adult cyclist, I was back eating a
lot of carbohydrates, but there was about a six to 12 month period when I was still in ketosis
and I was kind of getting back into cycling shape. And I do have one VO2 max test from that window
of time, probably six months after getting back to cycling and still on ketosis. I've gone back
and looked at the data and they're very interesting. So what I would observe is maximum fat oxidation
was 1.3 grams per minute. And that occurred almost immediately. And it sustained until I hit my,
well, let me think. It was sustained until about, so at the time my FTP was about 4.1 watts per kilo.
This would have been sustained until about 3.5 watts per kilo. So at 3.5 watts per kilo,
I was still oxidizing about 1.2 grams per minute. And then that sort of fell off and glucose
became then the dominant fuel source. At the completion of the test when I was done,
when I failed, I was obviously not oxidizing any fat and glucose oxidation was just under
six grams per minute. Yeah, about six grams per minute, about 24 K cal per minute. So
I've also seen this with another athlete who's been in ketosis for seven years.
He's a very fit cyclist. Actually, he just sent me his data. And it's comparable, right? So he's,
in fact, he's much fitter than I was. So his FTP, his 20 minute FTP test is about 412 watts for 20
minutes. And surprisingly, he has decent glycolytic power. So that's the other thing is I never really
had good power at the low end because I only cared about time trialing. So it didn't matter
how much I could hold, how many watts I could hold for two minutes or three minutes. I only
cared about one hour. But this guy could still hold 1,200 watts for 15 seconds. Even for three
minutes, he's north of 500 watts, 600 watts. And again, fat oxidation is well is, you know, 1.5
grams per minute. So it becomes a bit confusing because it would be very difficult to define
zone two by maximum fat oxidation. So ketosis is an extreme example. But given how much our Q,
respiratory quotient, the ratio of VCO2 to VO2 depends on baseline carbohydrate intake.
How do we make the adjustment so that we understand and we're not being misled? Because
if you just looked at my data, you would dramatically overestimate my mitochondrial
efficiency. Is that a situation where you say, well, actually the lactate might be the more
and unfortunately, I don't have lactate data from that test. So I can't tell you
what my lactate levels were doing. But again, there might not be a problem in the peloton
because you're not going to be in ketosis if you're trying to win the Tour de France. But
we do see a great degree of carbohydrate and fat variation in the diet amongst people that we're
trying to test. So how do you make that correction? Yes. So I, in my humble opinion, what we see in
these cases, because I see them all the time too, is that there's an artifact in the metabolic heart.
The metabolic heart measures gas exchange. And then through the equations, it kind of says,
okay, this person must be burning fat or burning carbohydrates. Right.
But it was calibrated, the equations are calibrated on high carb diets, presumably.
Yeah. And so the thing is like, as you exercise, no matter what fuel you're using, you keep
increasing oxygen consumption. Right. But if you don't have much carbohydrates, you're not going
to produce much CO2. So that's going to tweak, you know, mislead that my stoichiometric equation,
because the algorithm is going to think that, oh, whoa, he's using a lot of oxygen and not
producing enough CO2. So he's got to be burning a lot of fat. That's when you see fats in north of
one gram per minute. Right. So those are fat oxidation that I think they're an artifact.
And I see this because three days later, you know, when you change the diet of that person,
three days later, that person's fat oxidation might be 0.35. Right. So there's no way that
the mitochondria adjusts, you know, first, like it reflects a very high fat oxidation capacity.
In someone who we know very well, who is not an elite athlete, whose mitochondrial function is not
incredibly high to be able to oxidize so much fat, right. And in three days,
it reduces like by three or four times. Right. So I attribute this to an artifact of the gas
exchange. And this is where looking at lactate, it should give you those parameters. You know,
normally what I see in this individual is that you see maximum lactate of two, three,
minimals. Right. Because simply they don't have carbohydrates. Also the thing where you see that,
yeah, my maximum grams per minute of carbohydrates were in the six, but you're in ketosis. Right. So
how can you have enough glycogen or glycolytic capacity to elicit such a high carbohydrate
production? Well, I mean, I think even when you're in ketosis, you know, you're you still
remember my blood glucose is still, you know, four to five millimole. Right. I mean, it's it's
it's so so I would really like to see this studied because again, even if you're only eating 50 grams
of glucose a day, think of how much glycogen you're making from all the glycerol from all the fat
that's being converted to ketone. So I mean, I think Jeff Volek and Steve Finney have looked at
this and when they put people into very, very strict ketosis, but do muscle biopsies, they're
still seeing 60 percent of the glycogen content in the muscle that was there under high carb
conditions. Yeah. So I mean, I think my capacity to oxidize five and a half to six grams of glucose
per minute was still there. It just wasn't, you know, it just took a long time to get there,
I think is the difference. So I guess the question is, if the VCO2 estimation is off
because of the stoichiometric coefficients, do you think the V02 estimation is off also?
I don't know. I don't think so because, you know, I just hit very well, you know, like other, you
know, like ketones are used for energy purposes. And then we have a third element which is absolutely
key in bioenergetics, which is glutamine. Right. Glutamine lysis is highly expressed and utilized.
We have learned that from ICU patients. ICU patients is a great model to study metabolism
or stress metabolism. ICU patients, they utilized for wound healing about three times more glucose
at rest than what we have. Right. And it's part of the healing process. Glucose is instrumental
for cell proliferation, wound healing. And part of it is lactate too, as a by-product in a single
molecule. But we see that, and this is a study that we published looking indirectly at methodology
to look at glycogen. And we did it with a pilot study. We did it with ICU patients. They don't
have glycogen. And it makes all the sense in the world because if you enter ICU, first of all,
normally... Sorry, when you say they don't have glycogen, you mean liver glycogen, muscle glycogen,
depleted by how much? Yeah. And depleted to what level? Yeah. So let's say that you have 500 grams
of glycogen if you have a full high carbocation diet. So that might not be the case of someone
entering the ICU. First, because they might not be elite athletes, or they might have maybe 300
grams, or they might not have that adaptation to homework glycogen. So let's say they have 300
grams or so. And then by the time they get into that condition, the body uses about three times
the glucose at rest. Now, an athlete used that same glucose, but a higher intensities, but only
for a reduced amount of time, two hours, three hours, four hours, whereas the ICU patient is 24
seven. So eventually, the body is going to run a glycogen in the muscle, or it's going to be in
their huge stress. So the body has evolutionary mechanisms. This is a wonderful machine,
and it needs to continue. So it increases another route, which is glutaminolysis.
So glutamine is an excellent source of fuel. It enters directly the mitochondria. We have seen in
the publication that we're going to show now that when we publish it, is that when we inject
mitochondria with glutamate, it's incredibly well oxidized. And what's the source of glutamate in
these ICU patients? Are they breaking down muscle? Exactly. So this is where Cacexia comes into
place. We know that pretty much every single ICU patient becomes Cacectic or suffers from muscle
waste. And this is the syndrome, right? For ICU muscle waste syndrome. And this is where like,
why do they get Cacectic or catabolic, right? And why they overexpress tremendously levels of
glutamine because they need it for either enter the Krebs cycle for energy or for gluconeogenesis.
So this is one of the things that we learn a lot from ICU. These ICU patients, they have
hyperglycemia, right? Yet they're not giving them usually because they have hyperglycemia. It's true
too that in the acute ICU phase, they also have insulin resistance, right? But obviously,
this hyperglycemia and ICU doctors historically have seen this. It's like, whoa, this patient has
hyperglycemia of the chart. So obviously, we're not going to give them IVs of farias, of glucose.
We're going to give more protein and farias. And in fact, glutamine has shown that increased
survival in these patients, right? But where is this hyperglycemia coming from when you do not
have glycogen? It comes probably from proteolysis, right? Where you break down protein from your
muscles to release glutamine. But I mean, I think we could, we would only know that if we understood
hepatic glucose stores, because regardless of how much glycogen is in the muscle, it's never going
to make its way into circulation because the muscle can't fully dephosphorylate it. So do we
have a sense of what the hepatic glycogen content is? Because I can't imagine the body would ever
let anything compromise that, given that if the liver can't produce glucose, continuously,
the brain dies. So it might be that this is true, true and unrelated, right? It could be that the
muscles are depleting glycogen because of high utilization. But the liver through gluconeogenesis
has plenty of glucose. That's what's making it into the circulation because of hypercorticillemia,
because of other acute phase reactants. And so we have hyperglycemia, but it's all being mediated
by the liver, which has no trouble maintaining glycogen levels. And again, from an evolutionary
perspective, you much rather err on the side of hyperglycemia than hypoglycemia under a period
of stress. Absolutely. And it's necessarily, and that's I think what's the source of that
gluconeogenesis, right? So it's probably glutaminolysis, right? Coming from the muscles.
So this is what, this is my hypothesis, right? That those muscles, they eat themselves to feed
themselves or to feed the rest of the body, right? This is why- So that would suggest that exercising
ICU patients would be important, right? Absolutely. So getting some load-bearing resistance,
even of course they're in a bed, but sort of moving their extremities against a load,
supplementing with amino acids could actually improve outcomes. Absolutely. There's a lot of
research in this area. My colleague Paul Wishmeyer, who used to work here with me at the university,
now he's in Duke. He's doing a lot of research and practical work with that. But with this,
it's like, yeah, this hyperglycemia probably comes from gluconeogenesis.
And again, this is what, going back to where we started, yeah, could be that there's a lot of
glutamine released, you know, when you're also in a ketoacidosis state as well, especially in the
first phases of that, right? We know cortisol is very high at first. The same thing that we see in
ICU patients, that the two main parameters that are predictors of mortality at the ICU
is hypercorticellinemia, high cortisol levels and high lactate levels, right? They both are
completely related, right? Yeah. Anyways, yeah, I think this is fascinating. It's a great model
to understand metabolism, stress metabolism of these patients and the ICU patients. And those
are the two ones, once you exercise, and this is a very important concept for people with type 2
diabetes, with type 1 diabetes and hyperinsulinemia, is that you have insulin resistance, right?
And you have difficulty to translocate, therefore, to translocate the group for
transporters to the surface of the muscle, the sarcolemma. And we know that probably the first
tissue or organ where diabetes debuts starts is the skeletal muscle. Absolutely. Because about 80%
of the carbohydrates that we have, they're oxidizing in skeletal muscle. And because we're
at risk, should be oxidized within the mitochondria of the skeletal muscle, that pyruvate, right? This
is what we're doing research, I think, clearly. But when you have insulin resistance, you cannot
translocate those transporters. Now, we have a second way to translocate those transporters that
not many people know about, and that's muscle contraction. Right. This is the insulin
independent glucose uptake, which also seems to be heavily dependent on fitness,
right? The fittest athletes here require virtually no insulin to translocate glucose into the muscle
through the insulin independent pathway. And actually, I think we may have even discussed this,
I don't know, over dinner one night, but you look at the type one diabetics who are highly,
highly active require very little insulin. Exactly. And this explains hypoglycemia
in this patient shortly after they start exercising, right? They might have something
to eat and they inject themselves with insulin and there's nothing you can do once you have
insulin on board, right? So that insulin is going to translocate those transporters and it's going
to start bringing insulin inside. But in the moment, I mean, sorry, glucose, thanks. In the
moment you start exercising, you do the same function through contraction of the muscles.
So you have two mechanisms acting at the same time, pooling more glucose inside the cells,
leading to hypoglycemia. So this is what we learned a lot with type one persons with people
with type one diabetes and exercise, but this concept and then we can prevent them. So for example,
do not inject yourself before exercising, right? Because exercise alone is going to take care of
that glucose, right? But we can take these concepts also with people with type two diabetes
that they have an insulin resistance or pre type two diabetes. Like why not exercising right
after you eat, right? Because that carbohydrate you have, you have insulin resistance already,
but when you exercise, you're not going to need that insulin and yet you can translocate those
transporters and you bring glucose levels down. And I'm sure that you see this all the time where
your glucose sensors, where your texts come, right? Yes. And I've gotten periods of time when I've
done incredibly frequent lactate testing. So, you know, lactate testing every 30 minutes for a day
or something insane like that, which is incredibly expensive and incredibly painful on your fingers.
But you learn how much, for example, a meal impacts lactate. So when I wake up in the morning,
my resting lactate level varies between, and this is, I've been tracking this over a period of
probably 40 days. So 40 days of tracking. What range do you think my morning resting lactate
level has been over a 40 day period? How much variability do you do in the morning? First thing
in the morning? I would say, you know, like in the neighborhood of 0.8 to 1.2, 1.3.
A pretty good guess. So 0.3 to about 1.1. Okay. But that's a pretty big variation.
And probably median level of about 0.8. Yeah. Would be the median. The median of wine,
which is normally in the feeding individual, right? Yes. So then what I can do is I can eat a very
high carb breakfast and go and do a zone two ride, or don't eat anything at all and go and do a zone
two ride. Very different lactate performance curve. Absolutely. So the high carb meal raises lactate.
So it becomes a bit of an artifact in a way, which now gets me to some of the, we've talked
about this at the level of the most precision possible, the way in which I would measure it
in a patient, you would measure it in a world-class athlete, where we have the ability to do indirect
calorimetry and lactate testing. But now I want to talk about it in the way that we train people,
normal people. So we've talked about this, call it, you know, difference, right, between
the lactate level that you measure in the blood, which is now heavily influenced by production
and clearance. And then we've talked about the gold standard, which would probably be fat
oxidation, but even that can be confounded. But let's take off the table the people who are
consuming a high fat, low carbohydrate diet, because that confuses things a bit.
If I have a patient and I'm looking at their biometrics and we do a zone two test based on
looking at their fat oxidation during an escalated test of part of a VO2 max test,
and it comes back that their maximum fat oxidation, which is, you know, 0.3 grams per minute,
occurs at a wattage of 1.5 watts per kilo. That's a pretty average person.
And I say, I want that number higher, both the absolute number of fat oxidation,
but where it occurs on the graph. Now I want you in a year to be 2.5 watts per kilo.
Let's talk about two things. One, how they should train, and that means duration,
intensity, frequency, et cetera. And secondly, what we should use as the readout to know where
in the right training zone, given that they won't be able to train daily or weekly or whatever
frequency with indirect calorimetry. And by the way, let's assume that some people will want to
use the point of care lactate meters and some people will not. So let's start with what's our
surrogate for training zone. And starting with what we knew. So we learned that 1.5 watts per kilo
was maximum fat oxidation, but we want to increase that to 2.5. So what metric do you use to train
them? So yes, normally what I do is like starting with the metabolic test, I translate that
information into whether it's watts or speed or heart rate. All of it normally they correlate
quite well. And you can individualize it. There are people that don't have a power meter. You can do
heart rate, for example, or people that just obviously they run or they walk. You can do speed
or heart rate as well. They're very good surrogate. So that's a first metric, the surrogate. Then
it's about, at least from my experience, the three main principles that I've learned over the years
on how to apply this. So first is frequency. How many?
Before we go to the frequency and the duration, I do want to go back and ask you another question.
We have some patients who don't want to use a lactate meter, either because it's cumbersome
or somewhat intimidating. We also add another metric, which is relative perceived exertion,
RPE. I'll tell you what my rule of thumb is, but I'd like you to sharpen it, refine it, throw it out,
make it better, whatever. I tell patients based on my experience, so I don't know how
extrapolatable that is, when I'm in zone two as confirmed by lactate levels. So call it 1.7 to 1.9
millimole, which is what I target. I can carry out a conversation. So I can spend my entire,
because I do most of mine on a Wahoo KICKR. I put my bike on a Wahoo KICKR.
I can spend the entire 45 minutes on a phone call. Yes, absolutely. But it's not as comfortable
as this discussion here. Exactly. I'm a little more strained. Yeah. But if I can't talk, if I
feel like I can't talk, I'm too high in the intensity. Yeah. Do you think that that's a
reasonable surrogate for people to use across the spectrum of not particularly fit all the way up to
Progacha? 1,000%. And I use the same metrics also with people who, like you mentioned, they
don't want to do a Wahoo KICKR meter, or they don't have access, or I get hundreds of emails about
where can I do this test? Or is there anything that I can do? And I agree 100%.
That with everything that we know at the granular, cellular level by injecting fuels and
frustrates directly into the mitochondria, we cannot get more cellular level and scientific
like that. The surrogate or the precipice exertion, it works beautifully. I know that
people are coming out with different algorithms based on higher variability or the DFA, 1 alpha,
you know, etc. But honestly, I agree 100% with you. If you can always tell people if you can
exercise whatever the exercise you do, and maintain a conversation like you and I are doing,
you're way too easy. You're probably zone one. If you can talk, but it's some form of strain,
you can talk for two hours, right? But we're talking like that.
You're just at that threshold of the person put it this way. The other litmus test I tell people is
the person on the other end will know you were exercising.
You will not be able to mask from them that you are exercising.
Exactly. And in fact, I have many conference calls with, you know, like people that I know
to be respectful, but I do on the bike, you know, work, as you said, you know, they call me and I'm
on the bike, either outside or in the trainer and it's like you're exercising, right? Because
you can feel it. But yet I can maintain a full hour meeting on the bike, right? And without
bothering the other person because they can understand it. But is it if you cross to the
point where you cannot maintain that conversation, that's where you is because yeah, you need to
breathe much faster because you're producing more CO2. And that's probably because you're already
transitioning from the slow twitch muscle fibers to the fast twitch muscle fibers, more glycolytic,
more lactate, more CO2, more buffering capacity. So it seems old school, but it works beautifully.
Agreed. And the other thing I do because I really like people to triangulate and give them a starting
point. So if someone has not done a metabolic test yet, and we're just and that's usually the case,
by the way, is that we're starting with just a zone two training protocol. I also give them some
ranges on heart rate. Now here I have found much more variability. So the first thing I say is
to do this, you do need to know your maximum heart rate, not your predicted maximum heart rate,
but your actual achieved maximum heart rate. In my experience personally, so this is I don't know how
much I can extrapolate this. My zone two is actually at about 78 to 81 percent of my maximum
heart rate. But I know that for less trained people, it's lower. So I tell people a broad range
of 70 to 80 percent of your realized maximum heart rate is a good place to start and then make
adjustments based on relative perceived exertion. Yeah, I agree. What do you know about heart rate?
And yeah, I would agree that I usually also say the same thing somewhere between 70 to 80.
That being said, right, if you want to. That's a big range. Yeah, it's a big range. Exactly. So you
can be at 70. Let's say at 1.7 millimoles and then at 80, you can be at five millimoles.
Right. So you're completely away from one zone. But as you said, it's a good starting point. And
then as you very well said, and I agree 100 percent with you, is like, yeah, then you tweak it with
your perceived exertion. I agree. The other thing too with the heart rate, and this is where
the heart rate variability, there are different interpretations. So the modern interpretation,
the heart rate variability is the differences between beat to beat. And that's where there are
different algorithms. For me, the heart rate variability is more at a broader spectrum and
is more on the adrenergic activation that you have. So for example, your fatigue today,
right, first of all, normally you're going to wake up with your resting heart rate a little bit higher
than normally. So that if you're a normal heart rate, let's say it's 50 and you're in fatigue,
you might wake up with 65. So that alone is a heart rate variability concept. It varies from
the norm to one day. So that's our red flag that you might be tired that day. It might not happen
all the day. I mean, it might not be super sensitive, but it is very sensitive for elite
athletes without a doubt. The second aspect is like when you go out there and exercise.
As you might see, there are days that you are like 130 beats per minute, whatever you think your zone
two is 130, 138, for example. But some days it's really hard to get the heart rate, right? Extremely
hard. And you're already struggling at 110 beats per minute or 115 beats per minute, where that's
not the norm. That's another deviation. That's the variability of the heart, right? So this is
what I've been historically used for heart rate variability, which tells me a lot more information.
This is what all the athletes also tell you, like, man, my heart rate doesn't get up today. You see on
training picks, you know, you see when someone is fatigued, they do an interval and they know they
always 180, 185, let's say they lack the threshold. And today they cannot get up until more than 170.
You see in the competition, the first week of the Tour de France, the maximum heart rate,
let's say it's 195. Last week, the maximum heart rate is 170, right? That's what I interpret by
heart rate variability. And I know that a lot of people make to the size of me because all that has
nothing to do with, I respect all that. No, I think it's macro versus micro. I agree. I read it as
macro versus micro. I'll share with you an interesting self-experiment I've done a couple
of times. It's not pleasant, but it's interesting. If I take a huge dose of a beta blocker,
and the only beta blocker you can do this with, if you have low blood pressure, as I do, you have
to be careful, but propranolol is fine because it really disproportionately lowers heart rate,
but not blood pressure. But I've done this experiment a few times to test an idea, which is
would taking all of the gas out of my heart rate allow me to push harder and generate a higher
zone two. And it turns out it does. So my zone two is just under three watts per kilo. I really
want to talk with you about getting over three watts per kilo. I'm still furious because in July,
remember I was at 2.95. I was just kissing on the door of three and I've actually come back a
little bit. I've come back, I'm now at about 2.75 to 2.85. So I've lost a bit. No, I think we're
going to talk about training in a moment. So, but what I noticed, so, and for me, I'm at that upper
end of maximum heart rate. So, so I'm going to be doing that at about 80, 81% of maximum heart rate.
But when, if I took propranolol, you know, 60 milligrams of a time release propranolol,
I will be able to get over three watts per kilo and I'll do it at a heart rate of 68%
of maximum. Yeah. But it feels horrible. Yeah. I feel like I'm going to die. Yeah. It is the worst
feeling in the world. It is like somebody has, and it's not pain. It's, it's not like,
I don't know how to explain it other than it feels like what it feels like when you're over-trained.
It feels like you just can't, you can't get moving. It's like an engine that's being taken
from 9,000 RPM to 6,000 RPM, but yet somehow is able to generate the horsepower,
but it just doesn't feel right. So, you know, that, that's sort of my, that's, that's my drug
cheating way to ramp, to get over three watts per kilo, but more to illustrate the point, right?
Which is when you put the governor on heart rate, you can, you can get there at a lower heart rate,
but it, but, but there's just some, subjectively it's a miserable feeling. Yeah, no, absolutely.
It's a, yeah. And this is kind of in a way what happens when, when you're fatigued,
when you don't have enough fuel, right? So again, going back to like my heart, it doesn't get up
today and I'm struggling kind of like, you know, it's like if you were taking some better blocker,
right? But the thing is that it has to do a lot with fuel. And, and, and, and, for example,
and I experiment this a lot too. I, I try to understand how this works. So I do maybe
the intermittent fasting for a few days and I go out there and I'm not good at adjusting at that.
And I cannot do that. I know others can do it. And I admire that. But I can see in my heart rate
right away, right? When you don't have enough glycogen storage is, it's very possible that
adrenergic activity is decreased. You need to break down glycogen. And we know that what takes
to break down glycogen is for a lace, right? In the, in the muscle. And that's directly regulated
by catecholamines, right? So when there's a decreasing glycogen, this is my hypothesis,
right? When there's a decrease in glycogen storages, because of the evolutionary mechanisms
that humans have, the brain is the boss, right? The brain says like, I don't care about your legs,
but don't, don't use up all the glycogen because you have to give me and the liver has to give me
glycogen as well. So I'm not going to shut you down completely or breaking down glycogen,
but I'm going to slow you down. So I'm going to release less catecholamines so that you break
down. Now the collateral effect of that is the heart because the heart contractility is regulated
by catecholamines as well. So this is why using that, my version of heart rate variability,
it's quite useful. I've been using it incredibly successfully for 25 years with my athletes,
where I see that, Hey, your heart rate is not going up today. You know, usually it's 185, 190,
for example, when you do a lactate threshold, for example, and today it was 170. So tomorrow,
take it easy or pile up on glycogen, I mean, on carbohydrates or take it easy day. And you see
how you're going to be very responsive the next day, the following day. And in fact, that's what
happens. I would say 10 out of 10 times, but let's say nine out of 10 times, right? But I do that
with myself as well. And I see is also that I don't, I mean, I work a lot with the head, you know,
so, you know, you think a lot and the brain uses about a hundred to 125 grams of glucose daily,
right? When, when you go, and I don't know that fact, you know, but when you know,
when you work a lot of hours and thinking and thinking and thinking and stressed,
I'm sure that obviously that the brain might need a lot more glucose. So that's training your,
your glycogen storage is from the brain probably, and even from the muscles, because the muscle
can release glucose, it can utilize this one. Yes. How the muscle can, the muscle has phosphorylase
and can be a degraded glucose, the glycogen and that glucose can go to the, to the circulation
as well to feed other organs. I didn't realize that we had glucose one phosphatase in the muscle.
I thought the muscle glycogen fate was sealed in the muscle. No, it's possible. There are a few
studies I am happy to send them to you. I cannot refer them out of memory, but the muscles can also
release glucose to an expert glucose outside. I assume this is a relatively small amount.
Yes. Compared to what the liver is saying. Yeah, absolutely. Exactly. But it's possible too.
But what I mean, and I don't want to say, yeah, so, so those days where I'm thinking a lot and I'm
not very stressed and I'm not, you know, like dieting or anything, I just go out there and I'm
dead. And I'm sure that many people listening to this feel the same way. Like what the hell is
going on today? I don't have energy at all today. You know, so, and you will see that your heart rate
doesn't get up those days. And you can get to that by just training five hours a week or seven hours
a week. And sometimes people say like, look, I cannot be overtrained because I only trained
five hours a week. Yeah. But you're overworked. Yeah. And that does, that does a big artifact
where you're training. That's what most of us are inspired to pre-retire before 60, you know,
so we can have more time to exercise, right? And less time to work. But, but yeah, that's what I
do this. I take a day off completely. I sleep more. I increase my carbohydrate intake. And the
following day I can even break my PR on a climb or something, like feel like, like a million dollars.
So resting recovery is key for that. Yeah. I think this is a very important point. And it's
actually something I've only been able to pay attention to in the last year, which is I used
to judge my performance by training load. So, you know, again, we, I used to use training peaks when
I was training. I don't anymore, but the concepts of acute and chronic training balance. And, and
it was, you know, any day that was suboptimal could be explained by training volume in some capacity.
But now, you know, my training volume is relatively low. It's 10 hours a week of total
training. That's both, you know, cardio and strength. So that's, this is not a lot of training.
And yet when I'm under stress, work wise, you know, I'm just doing too much. I don't even use
the word stress. It has a real negative connotation to it. I just mean when I'm overworked,
when I'm doing too much, my performance, I have to either adjust my parameters for what I deem
successful, or I just have to sort of cut back on the actual training a little bit to make time
for more sleep or more relaxation. And so I think that's a very important point that I,
that is easily lost. So, so let's, let's now, so we've got a very good handle on the metrics
we're going to be using. So now let's talk about two scenarios. The first is the person who is new
to this type of training. So they've listened to this podcast, or they're one of my patients,
and I've made the case convincingly to them that you really need to do this type of training.
I want to come back by the way to a justification for that. So let's explain why high intensity
training is not sufficient, but we'll, we'll park that for a moment. But they really don't have much
of a background in this type of training, right? They, you know, maybe they do some high intensity
training, they do some weights, they play some tennis, but they really don't do the sort of
steady state sustained cardio that we're talking about. How would you structure a training program
in dose, duration, frequency for that individual? And tell me a little bit about the choices that
you would make if they're agnostic to running, walking, cycling, rowing, swimming. You know,
again, I have my biases there, but I want to kind of hear what you have to say about it.
Yeah, no, yeah, that's a great question. And I also know before that, I went to apologize to many of
your audience, because I, I get a lot of emails, you know, asking me about these questions. And
it's hard to, well, that's why we're doing the podcast. So yeah, you don't have to apologize.
It's easier to do it this way. But see, I get emails. And, and before I used to see people here
at the university, but now at the university, you know, we don't have these services. So I'm
trying to convince them that the services are important to offer to the population. But anyways,
I want to apologize, because I cannot answer to everybody. But yeah, so I have the three main
rules or parameters that I have learned over the years. So one is the duration, right? We have in
mind sometimes that this is like endurance training, one day, like, like, I only have it
six hours a week or seven hours a week, most right, to do this type of training or less. So
there's no way I can do that. It's usually less because they might have six hours a week for total
exercise. Exactly. And we're going to take half of that for strength training. Exactly. Because which
is very important, as you know, it is my it's where I fail, because I should do more of that.
And I try to get a little bit more of time to do that. But I, it's not easy. But I aspire really to
dial that in. But but yeah, you're right, they might have less than six hours. And then my thing
like, well, I'm not an endurance athlete. So you need to do four hours to do to accomplish this. So
therefore, I'm just going to move to do just high intensity and just get out of the way. Well, that's
not completely true. Right. You can accomplish very important mitochondrial adaptations, and very
important metabolic adaptations by exercising one hour. Right. So this is one is the duration,
let's start by the duration, right. So if you try to do that one hour to one hour and a half range,
you're on target. And is that in one setting hours? I'm sorry, is that total or one setting?
What do you mean? Meaning is it one to one and a half hours per week? Or
does that need to be in one continuous? Yeah, so exercise about? Yeah, I'm sorry. Let me let me
go back to that the frequency, right that the dose. So the frequency that I see is that this
type of training, ideally, needs to be done between three to four days a week, ideally,
what I've seen and how can I know this? I know this because I've seen in the laboratory, everything,
right, the person who trains one day at these zones for two days or three days or four days or
high intensity, low intensity, and I see the adaptations. How do I see the adaptations? Again,
looking at my account, I mean, that fat oxidation, black ticklings capacity, both surrogates of
mitochondrial function, right. So I've been identifying the dose of that training. So if
you train once a week there, chances are that you're going to deteriorate over time, and especially
as we age, something that I see, for example, in high intensity, exercisers, and bodybuilders,
that they have a very poor mitochondrial function, compared to people who do more,
a little bit of everything, right. So one day a week is not going to work. Two days a week,
it might maintain what you have. But if you're new to an exercise program might not be enough.
Three days a week, now we're starting to see for sure. Four days a week, now we're talking.
Ideally five days a week or six, but not everybody has, obviously six days a week to train. But
I think that we all can, I mean, you are a very busy guy. I'm a very busy guy. And we try to
squeeze four or five days a week, maybe six in the summer, but four or five days, it's achievable
for most individuals and put aside an hour to an hour and a half. So I would say the four days a
week is ideal. That's the first principle. The second principle is the duration, going back to
what I was saying. With one hour, maybe Poratza needs four hours, five hours, to keep increasing
those huge mitochondria for a long time. But a mere mortal, especially someone who might be
prediabetic or might be out of fitness or has an exercise in a long time or someone who's coming
from a disease or a mother who just had a baby and has been out of safe for a while. One hour,
if you walk or if you run, might be very, very good for you. One hour walk or run, you might
have to bring it up. That's part of the plan too. You cannot start off the bat with one hour. You
might start by 20 minutes, 30 minutes, 40 minutes, increasing it. It may be about an hour. And if you
bike, for example, about an hour, 20 minutes, hour and a half, that's what I see that if you do that
for four days a week, things are starting to move. Even if you bike on a trainer where you can be much
more efficient and you can really get straight to the wattage and stay there, because we tell patients,
you know, again, it depends where they are in their cycle. But if they're starting out, I mean,
we'd be happy if they give us 30 minutes, three to four times a week of dedicated exercise.
So do you see a difference between, I can't do zone two on the road. I can really only do it
on the trainer. I just can't stay at a constant level on the road with starting and stopping and
wind and hills and stuff like that. That's a very good point. That's why an hour and a half on the
bike, it might actually be one hour or so, right? Because you have all these artifacts. But you're
right. When you're on the trainer, you isolate everything completely. And what I also recommend
is about an hour if you can get there. But again, you know, like, yeah, sure, you might,
to me, it feels like a torture sometimes, you know, to be an hour on the trainer. I hate it.
I like to be outside, but we have to do it. I do it. I watch a movie or just catch up on work. I
have one of those special desks, right, where I can type or read articles or answers and emails.
Valky activity because again, you're not very sharp to think very intellectually.
But yeah, one hour might do the trick. What I've seen is like, yeah, in those people who haven't
done much at all, even 30 minutes, 20 minutes might start moving the needle, but eventually
it's not enough dose, right? It's like the body needs more, right? So if you can get to a goal
about an hour to an hour and a half, that should really work in my modest opinion, in my experience.
So that's the duration. And the third is always the frequency, which we have talked about,
which is usually the zone two. That being said, I think that it's also important to stimulate other
energy systems, right? Like the glycolytic system. And again, continue with the model that we do with
elite athletes. People think that elite athletes, whatever the sport are, all they do is high
intensity all the time and intervals, intervals, and it's the exact opposite. If you look at the
workload of an elite athlete, whether that elite athlete is, especially in individual sports,
right? It's easier to see this, whether it's a triathlete or a cyclist or a marathon runner
or a swimmer, right? Which is like a hundred meter swimmer is under a minute, right? It's
maximal exercise. If you look at the workload, it's very similar, right? The majority of the sessions
are in the lower intensity. They're not intervals, intervals, intervals. And I always say we cannot be
so naive to think that, you know, like the best coaches and athletes in the world haven't figured
this out when they're always trying new things and they want to try the cutting edge things.
Obviously they have said like, oh, our sport is swimming. It's under a minute. All we need to do
is like intervals, intervals, intervals, intervals, right? Well, if you look at what swimmers do,
they train and if you ask Michael Phelps, you know, hours and hours and hours and hours and hours.
Because if you can travel through the competition in that under a minute,
with a slightly better function to clear lactate, even if it's one millimole or less,
the muscle contraction force might be improved. So all the hours and hours and hours might be that
just to improve a fraction of a second. But anyway, so this is what I'm saying that these concepts of
glycolytic capacity and high intensity training, they're necessary, but they're not what the lead
athletes do. And if the lead athletes have the best metabolic function of any humans, why not
try to imitate their philosophy of exercise? And so just to come back to the frequency duration
question, I think the answer to the following question is going to be the more frequent training
sessions. But if you compared four training regimens that were four hours a week each,
one of them would be four 60 minute sessions. One of them would be three 80 minute sessions.
One of them would be two two hour sessions. And then one of them would be one four hour session.
So it's the same total volume. Is it safe and notwithstanding the brain damage of one four
hour session, is it safe to say that the four 60 minute sessions because it's a higher frequency
would be the optimal one there? I would say so. I think from my experience that it might be better
because it's the frequency is like it's like if you take a medication, right? If you take a
medication twice the dose and only three days a week might not work as well as if you take the
right dose every day. Right. Because at the end of the day, we're talking about the whole exercise
as medicine. Right. How do we prescribe that? You know, what's the dose? What's the frequency? I'm
assuming that you will have to take it as many days as possible. Right. So that would say that
it's better to do that. That being said, obviously, if you have the weekend and you have the possibility,
which I don't have to do three hours, go ahead. Right. And another thing I wanted to point out is
that, you know, for many people there, they need that adrenaline, right, for training. So other
people don't care. Right. Other people say, wow, I love this. I don't like to kill myself into
high intensity. But I think you need to do some high intensity. Yeah. So I want to talk about that.
So how do we bring in the other energy systems of the four pillars of exercise in my world?
Stability, strength, low end aerobic, which I describe really as they talk about this kind of
mitochondrial efficiency and then high end aerobic, which is peak aerobic capacity slash anaerobic
performance. So anaerobic power, peak aerobic, low end aerobic mitochondrial efficiency, strength,
stability of those four. I for some reason struggle to make the time for the peak aerobic
in part because I want it's the least enjoyable truth. If we're going to be brutally honest,
if you're doing it right, it hurts the most. Yeah. It's also no longer as relevant because
I don't compete at anything. Right. Like it was I actually really enjoyed that type of training
when I competed because you have to spend time in that energy system and you see the rewards
of, you know, repeating 60 minute, you know, 60 minutes of repeating two minute intervals or
something like that. So if we're if we're really talking about this from the lens of health,
maximizing health, the data are unambiguous that VO two max is highly correlated with longevity
in a unlike there are not many variables that are more strongly correlated.
So but the levels don't have to be that high. Right. We're not. I mean,
Pogaczor's VO two max is probably eighty five, you know, or it's probably in the eighties at least
in terms of milliliters per minute per kilogram. But someone my age to be considered absolutely
elite, which means the top two point five to two point seven percent of the population,
which carries with it a five fold reduction in risk to the bottom twenty five percent of the
population. My VO two max requirement is about fifty two fifty three milliliters per minute per
kilogram. So the question is, can I use that as the gauge for how much high intensity training I
need to do basically just enough to make sure I maintain that VO two max or do you think about it
in a different way? Well, I think about it more again, the bioenergetics energy energy systems.
Right. I think that ultimately and we know that longevity is also high related with mitochondrial
function and metabolic health. I think that more and more and this is why you see so many fields in
medicine nowadays, right, that everybody is stumbling upon mitochondria. Right. And so there's
an aging process where we lose mitochondrial function and there's like a sedentary component,
right, where we lose mitochondrial function. I wish that we could have a medication appeal.
You could take it and increase the mitochondrial function because it would increase metabolic
health and longevity. But the only medication that we know is exercise and the medic and within
exercise that the right the dose that we see that improves the most and also is sustainable in the
long term, which is another important concept. You know, very high intensity training is not sustainable.
Very extreme diets are not sustainable. If you combine both, it's even worse. And this is what
a lot of people are doing together. But you need to have some sustainability. But this is what
we see in this. This is important to improve that mitochondrial function. But going back to that
high intensity, I think is necessary because we also lose glycolytic capacity as we age.
And it's important to stimulate it. As you very well said, for all of us who are not competing,
I couldn't care less about being super high intensity because I'm not competing. But that's
it. I want to have also my adrenaline rush, you know, so like many people.
But how much does it feed into it? So for example, if I've often thought about this now,
as I just want to make sure my zone two is above three watts per kilo, would I be better off taking
that extra training? If I have one additional training session per week, should I make it an
additional zone to work out? So then I do four now, should I be doing a fifth one? Or should I
be taking that fifth one and doing a VO two max protocol? And that's that's what we'll typically
prescribe to our patients is a four by four protocol of, you know, highest intensity sustained
for four minutes, followed by four minutes of recovery, and then repeat that four or five,
six times. You know, when you put that when you put a warm up and cool down on either end of that,
you know, that's a little over an hour. So you could, would you spend that hour doing that in
an effort to make your zone two even better? Or would you just do an extra hour of zone two?
No, that's a really good question. So what I what I I agree, I agree that you can, if you have a
fifth day, you can convert it into any type of high intensity session structured. All right,
what I can tell people is, hey, if you're a cyclist or a runner, and you want to go with your friends,
that's your group, right? Yeah, right. Go ahead and boom, go at it. Or if you don't have the
possibility, what this is my situation, for example, where I don't have the time to train
more than an hour and a half, usually two hours max, right? So what I do almost on every session,
I do my zone two. So it's clean. And at the end, that's what I do a very high intensity interval.
And tell me the duration. So if you did an hour of zone two, yeah, so I do usually let's say an
hour and a half, right? So, and so you'll do an hour and a half of zone two, three or four times
a week. Yeah, I try, I shoot for four or five, but not all the time it's easy. But yeah, I shoot
for five and I try to be strict on that. But let's say that, yeah, the last, and unfortunately that,
you know, I, where I live, you know, like, I live in more in a, it's highlands area. And so you have
to go up. So the last part, I just, I just go at it, you know, sometimes you find another cyclist
and you just compete, you know, to see who's the fastest in that short climb. But I try to do like
a good five minute interval, roughly, where I really like kind of like a go hard at it. And
then I arrive home like, man, I kicked my ass today, or this kicked my ass today, or sometimes
you try it and you don't have the energy, as I mentioned earlier, oh my gosh, I can barely move
the pedals today. I just quit and go home. But when I feel fresh, you know, that's what I stimulate
that glycolytic system. What we know well too is that, you know, that increases the mitochondrial
function, it takes months or years. Increasing the glycolytic system, it takes much, much more,
less amount of time. You can do that in weeks or months. And you can just, if you stimulate on a
regular base, two days a week, or three days a week, at the end of that zone two, that's where
you can target both energy systems, right? The oxidative mitochondrial system and the glycolytic.
And we don't blunt it. We don't, we don't, we don't blunt the benefit we had from the zone two
if we immediately follow it with the zone five. No, because that's done, right? That's not,
why it seems like if you do the same things in the middle. But you don't want to do the reverse order.
Yes. And one of the things like- You don't want to start with the high intensity.
Exactly. One of the things like, because you start having all these hormonal responses,
and also you see you have high lactate levels in the blood. And what we know very well is like
lactate inhibits lipolysis. So if you have a high interval in the middle or the beginning,
and you don't clear lactate very well, you might have high lactate levels for a while,
and it's going to inhibit lipolysis, right? Also another study we have under review, lactate
the autocrine level, yeah, decreases the activity of CPT-1 and CPT-2. So interfacial with the
transport of fatty acids as well. So that's where like, if you do all these, you might change things.
You have high cortisol, cortisol, and anemia as well. And that's an important point. I'm glad you
raised that because I explained this to patients when they say, I went out and did a two hour ride
today. And it showed me that I spent 45 of those minutes, 45 of those 120 minutes were in zone two.
So I did 45 minutes of zone two. And I say, no, you didn't really do it, because you were going
up and down and up and down and up and down. And so that's not the same as spending 45 minutes in
the dedicated energy system. You're right. And if you I mean, when I look at training peaks, you
know, like you see the elite athletes, they're like, both power output and heart rate, this is
like goes together. Incredible. You know, whereas yeah, you're right up and down, the average might
be zone two, but actually, you're between oscillating zone one, zone three, zone four all the time.
Right. So tell me what's the difference between so if you don't mind sharing, what is your in
watts per kilo, what is your zone to in Colorado, where you're at altitude? Yeah, so I usually go
and and I'm not very good at, you know, like I understand I mean, doing this, but I'm, it depends.
What I'm saying is like, I don't look so much into this, I have done so many tests in my life, I was
since I was 15 years old, I was using a heart rate monitor, I'm talking about 1986. When the first
card monitors came out. So in other words, you're what you're getting at is you don't like to have
a lot of data when you're doing no, you're going off RPE. And you're not looking at your power meter
or a heart rate monitor, and you're not poking your finger when you're done. I do it here and there,
you know, because I still want to look at this and I do metabolic testing here and there. Right. But
I've done so much on me, since I was 15 years old, and I was obsessed by this. Now I got to a point
that I know my, my, my body quite well, where I can just go by the sensations and, and, and but here
and there I double check. But it's hard for you to then get at what I've observed the few times
I've tried to do my zone to at altitude, like in Colorado. Yeah. It's an enormous discount. I feel
like it's a 20% discount at altitude. Yeah, I tried to go like around, yeah, mine's around 2.5,
2.8 something that was per kilogram. When I, when I do it, and I, you know, like, about 120. So at
sea level, at sea level, you'd be over three probably, based on what I experienced going into
the first. I would say roughly. And one thing that I'm very proud of is that I have been doing,
because I do sporadically this testing and in all my PRs, because I think we have climbs here and
one day I go, I'm going to go for this climb. And I go full out on that climb. Right. And I'm 50 now.
And I have the same metabolic parameters there when I was 40. So to me, I'm very proud of this
because when you say parameters, you don't mean times up the climbs, which parameters are the same.
Yes. So I look at, you know, lactating power output. Okay, I look at VO2. I look at time as well,
you know, the PR that I had, it was similar. In five the other day, I beat my PR. What's your
VO2 max now? So my VO2 max now is four liters per minute. You know, so that's about 51, 52.
Okay, I was going to say your weight. But you could easily raise that if you lost, you know,
three kilos, which you could probably do. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah. And the thing is because I
obviously when I was a cyclist, I was 141, 143 pounds. And you were probably your VO2 was five
and a half liters or something. It was 76.7. So that's, let me see, it was 4.5, I believe,
between 65. Yeah, it was about 4.8, something like that. So now, you know, like 40 years later,
30 years later, right, I have decreased only about 0.5, 0.7. Right? Which, well, I'm really
happy about that because I'm not training like I did. But this is one of the parameters, but in
a decade, I haven't decreased my parameters. So this is to me, it's a proving point to myself,
at least that doing this routine, it helps to maintain, you know, that metabolic health that
you had a decade ago. Now, can you do this 10 more years? And when it turns 60? I don't know.
But what I know is that from others, I'm seeing it. So I see the typical person who just retired,
or as I discussed earlier, as prior to pre-retire at the age of 60 or a little before. In the moment,
they are, and these are like people like us, we are struggling to squeeze in time, you know,
and do five hours a year, six hours a week a year, or 10 at max. But then they have the whole time in
the world and they can sleep in, they don't have, they're not overworked, you know, they can
exercise. It's unbelievable and super inspiring how much they improve in their 60s. I've seen
people in their 70s with the metabolic parameters of people active, morally active in their 30s.
I saw the world champion in the cycling who's 81 in the category of 80 to 85, believe me,
there's a category of that, whose metabolic parameters were those of someone in their 30s,
healthy, active. So this is incredibly inspiring. Then I think that we're rewriting what's been
taught to us in the books. Now, in fairness, was that person of an elite athlete, were they a
professional athlete in their 20s and 30s? Never. And this is what struck me. He was a smoker,
hypertensive, and he started cycling because he needed to change his lifestyle in his 40s.
Because that's the same question, like, whoa, you must be doing this all your life. Like, no,
I started writing my bike when I was in my 40s. I was a smoker, I was heavy, I was hypertensive,
like, what? So it's incredible that 40 years later, he's in a better health than when he was.
But I'll tell you what I take away from that as well is the benefits and the importance of
compounding. You see, you alluded to it earlier, and I think the listener could be forgiven if
they missed this point. You can make relatively quick changes in your glycolytic efficiency.
You can take an untrained person with a VO2 max of 20 mils per gig per minute,
mil per gig per minute, and you could take them from 20 to 30 in a period of months
with the right amount of training, a 50% improvement in a few months. It's very
difficult to see a 50% improvement in mitochondrial function in a few months.
And you've already made this point, but I just want to restate it because it's important to
set expectations. And it speaks to why this level of training should be thought of in the same way
that you think of accumulating wealth, which is you've got it. It's day in and day out, day in
and day out, small compounded gains over years and years and years is why a 40 year old
overweight smoker can become a world champion at 80. It's because he probably never once again got
out of shape in that 40 years. Absolutely, absolutely. And this is incredibly inspiring.
When I see these people in their 60s just retired, and they come to do their first test,
and one year later they come back, it gives me the goosebumps because it is like, oh my gosh,
how can you improve so much? And they're like, look, I'm 64 and I feel strong as when I was in
my 30s. And so this is where we're going to be, and of course no medications, really good state
of mind, which is absolutely key for longevity. Normal diet, they're not as strict with one
days, they eat in moderation, but they can have a little bit of everything, which is also in my
modest opinion, is part of the enjoyment of life, eating what you like in moderation as well.
So it's an incredible inspiring to see all these examples. And in a way where we're rewriting what
we've been being thought for years, that once you turn 40, everything is going down,
you can really, really change. And again, you own your own body, and you can really
take ownership of that and improve it at any age.
So you mentioned drugs. I want to talk about one drug in particular and maybe some supplements.
You and I have spoken so much about this, and myself and another person are committed to
funding a study that we're going to be doing once we get through the backlog of COVID issues at the
university. But the question really arises around the use of metformin and whether or not there's
sort of a true impairment of mitochondrial function or whether the elevated lactate levels we see in
patients taking metformin is an artifact of the drug itself but says nothing of the mitochondrial
function. Do you have any more insight into this question that we struggle with greatly because
we have some patients who take metformin who receive much benefit from taking metformin,
but it makes it confusing to interpret their zone two data. And it makes me ask the question,
you know, it's a more important in those patients, it's maybe less relevant, but now it becomes
relevant when we think about using metformin as a geo protective agent, an agent to enhance longevity.
Yeah, that's the thing that we need a lot of research on that, I think, to understand this
better. Now, it's strange that it definitely seems to work in many patients, right? Obviously,
for those ones in the pre-diabetic first stage diabetes is that it's a very good medication
that's been used for a long time with good results. But how about the long term results,
right? We know that metformin inhibits complex one, which is key for mitochondrial function
in the electron transport chain. So we don't know the long term effects of metformin,
right? In longevity, this is where I think that we need more and more and more information as well.
We see, I see like someone showing up with a lactate of 3.5 millimoles at rest. And the first
thing I ask is like, are you going metformin? And me times a yes, and I'm sure you see the same thing,
right? Like, wow. So, so it's definitely an artifact. And why do you see at rest 3.5 millimoles
or 3 millimoles of lactate? And by the way, is there fat oxidation commensurantly suppressed?
Because when you when you metabolically test them on the cart, do you see in that individual a very,
very low fat oxidation? If not, it might suggest that that that lactate level of two or three
millimole is an artifact, but doesn't really speak to what's happening in the mitochondria, right?
And that's a great question. I haven't seen people taking metformin as a
medication, you know, for longevity, for example, for health, what I see people on metformin are
already clinical patients. Yeah. So in other words, it's confound. So of course, they're low,
because yeah, so they're taking metformin in the first place because of their clinical condition,
which is driven by a mitochondrial impairment or dysfunction. So it's difficult to discern,
but I mean, I'm sure you have more experience of people taking metformin.
We do. Yeah, but that's why this study that we're eventually going to get around to doing
is going to be so important because it will answer this question directly.
Yeah. And we can do with the muscle biopsies. And as you say, it's like, does it really
mess up with the whole mitochondrial function or can even like the mitochondrial function
overall override that inhibition of complex one and override other pathways?
I don't think we know the answer to that. Do you have an insight into any other supplements?
There's no shortage of supplements that are out there that are touted as sort of, you know,
longevity boosting agents and mitochondrial health agents. So the most talked about of all of these,
I think, is the precursors to NAD. So the most common of these would be NR or NMN,
both of which are pretty clear that they are precursors to NAD. There's certainly some debate
about how clinically relevant it is. Do you have a point of view on whether or not taking a
supplement that boosts NAD, at least in the plasma? I don't I still don't know how well it's boosting
NAD in the cell. But nevertheless, do you have a sense of if that is beneficial to the mitochondria,
both theoretically, but more importantly, experimentally?
Yeah, well, that's a great point. And this is like, I don't think we have the answer,
but I think we need to be cautious about how we interpret this data. It's definitely been shown
multiple times that NAD levels, the cellular level or any even mitochondrial level decreased
with aging. Right. Therefore, the whole thing, whoa, if it's low, let's take it. Right. But it's not
only NAD. I mean, if you look at so many metabolites, you know, in the cellular level,
in mitochondrial level, they're downregulated with aging. Right. The question is, why are they
downregulated? Is because mitochondria, per se, to start out with is downregulated. So it doesn't
need so much NAD because cannot take it. Right. Or other supplements or other metabolites. Right.
So this is this is at least how I think of NAD. It's as we mentioned earlier, it's very important
in glycolysis. It's in redox status, right, to maintain redox. And it's very important in the in
in Israel, three phosphate, two, three biphosphoglycerate phosphate, where NAD is utilized
to convert glycerate three phosphate to two, three phosphoglycerate, but it's depleted. And this is
what the only thing that rescues that is lactate. Right. As we mentioned. Now, taking NAD, is that
going to increase longevity? I don't think so. That's my opinion, because longevity is not just
one supplement or two or three or four or five. It's a compendium on an incredible amount of
things that happen at the cellular level. And I don't think that one supplement. I remember those
days where resveratrol was the thing for longevity. And everybody was not everybody. A
lot of people were buying resveratrol and their studies with mice showing that increased 50 percent
longevity in mice. So therefore, this is doing humans. Well, as you probably know, a lot of
people started to take resveratrol when they were 50 and they're dead now. You know, it didn't
increase. It doesn't increase longevity in humans. Right. Yeah. I mean, and I think, you know, I think
the data in the mice, we can debate the merits of that. I want to ask you about a theoretical risk,
though. You kind of alluded to it. Isn't there a scenario under which too much NAD could be
harmful? If you had an exist, if you took I don't know if this study has been done, but if you took
cancer patients or patients who had tumors that were undiagnosed and gave them if you boost, if
you doubled their NAD levels, wouldn't you actually favor the tumor's metabolism? Well, in fact,
we have done that pilot study with mice. So the whole thing is like looking at in my area of
research in cancer is cancer metabolism. Right. Yeah. And we know that glycolysis is key for cancer.
And any of these absolutely indispensable to feed that glycolysis, as I mean, as we have
alluded a few times, right. So the question is like, as you say, would NAD increase that
glycolytic rate or glycolytic flux therefore would be favoring more cancer phenotype.
So what we did, we have a pilot study, it's a pilot study, which is we're curious about it.
And we had a few mice, we have an NNF8 mice, four and four. So what we did is we transfected
tumors, we had triple negative breast cancer, it's very aggressive, and it grows very, very fast.
And so one group, we give them just water. And the other group, we give them
ribocyte, which is the NAD precursor, because NAD obviously, as you know, you cannot take it,
you need to take the precursor. And we observed the tumor growth over 23 days. After that,
the IRB at the university, because you cannot have animals with high tumors, right. So it was a flank
tumor, and you need to harvest them. So after, and we were measuring, you know, every five days,
the tumor growth. And we saw in these animals that there was about 15% increase in tumor growth
in the NAD group. So again, I-
And you saw that difference with only four mice in each group?
Yes, it's four and four. But all consistent, you know, we have statistical significance,
even with small four, I mean, there was no cross results. All the four mice, they grew cancer
at a higher rate than in the NAD than the control group. Again, that's where like, obviously,
this is not like a publishable, because we need a more-
Is that a study you'll repeat at a sufficiently powered size?
I would love to. And this is why we just did this pilot study. We had, because we have many mice,
and say, hey, let's give it a shot. And let's see, because there's a lot of hype of NAD. And
we saw this. So we would love to do it at a much higher level, because my question, which might be
a disruptive question is like, you know, what if you have a small tumor that you're unaware of,
like in the pancreas, or in the colon, or in the lung? Could NAD over time, day after day after
day, could favor that glycolytic flux to that tumor and increase the growth?
In the literature, I've never looked, because it just kind of occurred to me when you had that
slide up earlier, earlier, and you showed the mitochondrial slide. It occurred to me that you
have that lactate escape from the tumor. Hey, this would feed it. But has anybody in the literature
examined this question? It seems like a very common, it seems like a reasonable question to ask.
Yeah, there are a couple studies, I think once a review, it's more of the conceptual level. And
this is what got me thinking like, yeah, this is something that for us working in cancer
metabolism, we look into this, right? Looking at, you know, like obviously, one of the things that
we have shown is that lactate is an onco-metabolite. Lactate, we have shown, we have a first paper,
and we have like a good six, seven papers more to come. We've been working hard for three years
looking into this. But we saw that lactate regulates the genetic expression of the most
important genes in breast cancer. We're seeing the same thing now with lung cancer. And lactate,
as we keep talking about this, is the mandatory byproduct of glycolysis. And as Warburg saw in
1923, the characteristic of cancer cells, or most cancer cells, is the high glycolytic flux.
But what struck Warburg was not the glucose itself, it was the lactate production. So anyways,
we are showing that it's an onco-metabolite. So if you have a high glycolytic rate in a cell,
you're going to produce a lot of lactate, right? If you cannot clear that lactate,
it's going to drive self growth and proliferation, as we're seeing. And in fact, we're now blocking
lactate production, both through genetic engineering, as well as DCA, for example. And
we're seeing that cancer growth and proliferation completely stops within hours. So again-
Now that poses an interesting dilemma, right? Which is exercise would increase your capacity
for clearing lactate in the long term, but in the short term raises lactate. So it begs the question,
in a cancer patient specifically, what's the net impact of exercise?
Yes. So this is what we're working on, the hypothesis, you know, with my colleague,
George Brooks. So he's shown that acute response to lactate, it increases overexpression
about 600 and something genes, I forgot right now, right? All these genes are involved in cellular
homeostasis and in the benefits of exercise, right? So we know very, very well through his work
that lactate is a signaling molecule. Now, the question is like, we know this at an acute
exposure, which is exercise, you do exercise, boom, boom, boom, you're out. But cancer
doesn't do that. Cancer accumulates lactate, and it keeps accumulating. And this is the main
responsible for the tumor microenvironment, which is acidic. And the more acidic the tumor
microenvironment, the more metastatic the cancer is, and the more aggressive, like the more
glycolytic the tumor is, and this is very well documented, the more glycolytic the tumor is,
the more aggressive it is. And the more lactogenic that is more lactate, the more produces,
the more aggressive it is. Now, why is that lactate accumulating? That's what we need to
try to find out. But we know that that is not acute anymore. It's chronic exposure to lactate.
So can exercise counteract that? When we see that exercise might be beneficial for many patients,
but again, going back to the right intensity, we know the particles which are exosomes,
there are microbesicles in the body, they're main responsible for metastasis. We have seen that
and this is another publication you're going to have in breast cancer cells and lung cancer cells.
We are looking at the protein content and the micro-ironase of those exosomes released by these
cancer cells. It's incredible the information that they have there. If you were to genetically
engineer a molecule that can be injected into a tissue and transfer into cancer, you would
replicate an exosome. It has all the components needed. On the other side,
muscles also release exosomes. And this could be one of the benefits of exercise as an organ
in the crosstalk between skeletal muscle and many organs. We know that if you have a very good
muscle health, your health overall, the metabolic health is going to be good.
Could you be releasing great exosomes? They're very pro-oxidative, which counter the glycolytic
phenotype of cancer and could those exosomes travel directly to the cancer cells and penetrate
inside the cancer cells and transform the glycolytic phenotype of the cancer cells into
more oxidative phenotype and keep cancer at bay? We don't know yet, but we're suspecting that we're
scratching the surface of something that potentially could be a very interesting
thing to understand better the effects of exercise as well as neurotherapeutics.
The deeper I go in the rabbit hole into all things that relate to longevity, the more convinced I am
that if you're going to rank order things, if you were forced to rank order things,
there's nothing that ranks above exercise as the single most potent tool or agent we have to impact
longevity. And yet paradoxically, in the acute setting, exercise seems to do everything incorrectly.
In the very short acute setting, if you look at it in that narrow context, exercise does not appear
to be neuroprotective. But of course, when you look at the chronic impacts of exercise and what's
taking place after the bouts of exercise, the data seem undeniable. I want to kind of pivot from
exercise a bit into a subset of that, which is something you published this year in long COVID
patients. So we'll link to the study so people can see it, but you demonstrated that in people with
long COVID, even previously healthy people, they basically from a mitochondrial standpoint,
end up looking like people with type 2 diabetes when they're done in terms of fat oxidation,
lactate production. Yeah. So first question for you is what fraction of patients recovering from
COVID do you believe are susceptible to that phenotype? That's a great question and they're
trying to understand that. So everything is started by, you know, National Jewish Hospital is
probably, it's been always with Mayo Clinic competing for the top one immunology hospital in
the country. So you have these people with long COVID who are struggling, you know, they go up
the stairs and they can't breathe. So the first thing they do is they go to different doctors and
they end up going to this top hospital. So they do, you know, a pulmonary function test and it's
completely normal. Then they, okay, the next species is because COVID also affects the cardiac
muscles, right? So let's just do, let's look at the cardio function is completely normal.
And they're very good at this hospital where they do metabolic testing. They do CPAD testing. That's
how I called medically, right? The physiological testing and even lactate. We've been interacting
with them a few times. So they do lactate as well. So they contacted me and say, look, we're seeing
these patients. We have 50, 25 of them they had previously, you know, underlying conditions,
right? The other 25, they were normal people. And in fact, most of them, they were morally active.
Some of them, they were doing marathons, triathlons, you know, and the average is 50. So they're not,
you know, very old either. So, but their pulmonary function is completely normal and
cardio function is completely normal. So we suspected there's a metabolic issue here.
So they send me all the information, the raw information. And I apply the methodology that
we've been discussing, right? Looking at fat oxidation and lactate production as a surrogate
for metabolic function and or metabolic flexibility and mitochondrial function. And I was shocked
because they were significantly worse than people with type 2 diabetes and metabolic syndrome,
which could explain why these people cannot go up the stairs and where before they were doing
marathons. Now, what are the mechanisms? We know that viruses, multiple viruses are known to
hijack mitochondria for their own benefit, for reproduction. Could COVID do the same thing? So
I'm just, we are suspecting it. And we're trying to understand that at a more of a cellular level.
Now, unfortunately, the majority of these long COVID, because as you know, there are people with
long COVID syndromes that within weeks, months, they improve, they go back to normal. But there
are a handful of people that I am assuming they're going to be growing, right? That after one year,
they haven't improved a bit. This is the concern. Like can we do, can we use exercise as a
therapeutic way to stimulate mitochondrial function? If in fact there's a mitochondrial
dysfunction, which is severe, because if that's the situation, it's going to expose these patients
to multiple diseases, right? So this is an area of concern.
And this isn't talked about as much as what I think people initially spoke about here, which is
cardio, like basically myocarditis is what, and now of course we know that the risk of myocarditis
is actually much higher in young males through the Moderna vaccine than it's ever going to be with
COVID. But the rate with COVID is not zero. It's, I believe it's 2.3 cases per,
gosh, it's going to be a big difference. I think it's 2.3 cases per hundred thousand of people
with COVID are getting myocarditis. Most of those are transient. They recover, not all of them are.
So a subset or not. But this mechanism would be distinct from just myocarditis. Myocarditis of
course speaks to the inflammation of the cardiac muscle that would explain depressed ejection
fraction. But what you're describing is a far more diffuse problem, which is a global insult
on the mitochondria in the skeletal muscle, correct? Yes. That's what we suspect from this
data, which again is indirect, right? From the indirect colorimetry in the lactate that it points
out towards mitochondrial dysfunction. So that's what we need to do now, biopsies to understand
this set up better detail. What the heck is going on, right? Could be at the micro-profusion level
too. It might not be at the muscle per se, it might be at the micro-profusion, right? In the blood,
in the capillaries. Meaning something like microthrombosis that are preventing
perfusion and raising lactate that way. Could be, could be, you know, that's where we need to find
out. But we know from other viruses, right? That they hijack mitochondria and they interfere
especially with the fission and fission processes, right? Some causes increase fission, some other
causes increase fission, some other causes increase elongation. So we know there's a wealth of
studies out there from virology showing that, yeah, many viruses and bacteria, they also,
they hijack mitochondria and they disrupted significantly. Now, but most of the times,
you know, it, like myocarditis, it subsides, right? It's restored shortly after, you know,
the symptoms are gone. Now why this virus is different, that's what we are trying to understand
why people after one year, they are, and by the way, you know, most of these people, they had just
normal mild course of COVID. They were not hospitalized, they were not in the ICU.
Any evidence or inkling that if people go back to exercising too intensely following recovery,
it could exacerbate this problem? And do you also, yeah, do you have a sense of which strains
this was? This, your work would have been predominantly alpha and not Delta and obviously
not omicron, correct? Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. This is, this was done with patients over, you
know, yeah, yeah, way, yeah, even a mixture between the original variant and the Delta,
so not omicron. Yeah. So in this population, which again is presumably mostly alpha, maybe some
Delta, what was the distribution of male and female? So it was about, yeah, we had 35 females
and 15 males, so it was more female predominant. 70, 30, okay. Which again, maybe is too small a
sample to know, that could be more an indication of who's seeking out. And again, we don't really
know the denominator, right? We don't know, we don't know what this represents. Is this one
in a hundred thousand? Is it, you know, we, we, it could be one in a million if this was everybody
that's reporting it at the time. Yeah. Our guess is this, is like, it's a rare event, right? They
can loss that can last that long, right? But, you know, if, you know, we're talking about
millions of people infected, right? If it's one in a million, right? We're talking about, you know,
population that is going to need help. Yeah. I want to kind of go back to just a few other
questions that we didn't get to. So not necessarily in any thematic order. What's the relationship
between, or how predictable I should say, is the relationship between zone two as defined by maximum
fat oxidation and VO2 max. So if you run somebody through a CPET and you figure out that their VO2
max is at four liters, how, how predictably can you say at X percent of that you will be at maximum
fat oxidation? That's a very good question. There's another study that we're preparing the manuscript
with 225 subjects where we look at a fat oxidation, VO2 and the relationships. Going back to the same
thing. We tend and historically the research studies with exercise have been done based on VO2
max. That's been the parameter to prescribe exercise. You know, how many times we read
X amount of subjects, you know, they were exercising for six months at 60 percent of VO2 max or
whatever, right? Now that's another thing that I've been thinking of years. And by the way, when they
say that, do they mean the 60 percent of the heart rate that produced VO2 max or 60 percent
of the power that was produced that that is their max power at VO2 max? They're there. Yeah. I mean,
there's so many different ways you can do this that I've always found it. Absolutely. You have
to get into the methodology very closely. I agree. I agree. 100 percent. And this is where I think we
need to dial in things in better, right? Because yeah, 60 percent of the power output, I mean, 60
I mean, the intensity might be translated into power output, 60 percent of you to max and then
you translate into power output or you translate into heart rate, for example, or is it 60 percent
of the VO2? So, for example, if somebody is four liters VO2 at and then they hit that at 300 watts,
would 60 percent be 2.4 liters, which of course is not a very helpful way outside of a laboratory
to prescribe exercise to somebody, or would it be 180 watts, which is 60 percent of the 300 watts?
Yeah, exactly. I think that normally the studies they look at, okay, where do you hit 60 percent
of VO2 max? And then, okay, how many watts is this, right? Or what's your heart rate?
What's the wattage that corresponds to 60 percent of your max VO2?
Exactly. So, and in your study, what we are seeing, and this is what, because I've been curious about
this, you know, because we look at the cardiorespiratory adaptations to exercise and we look at the
cellular adaptations to exercise. Do they really correspond? Right? We know very well that
with athletes, you know, you can improve tremendously at the cellular level,
but not at all at the cardiorespiratory level, at least based on the VO2 max, which is the
representative of the cardiorespiratory adaptations to exercise, right? An example that I always give
when I give talks is like an athlete who used to be an average professional, and the VO2 max was
72.3 or something like that. And then two years later, he is a very good professional. The VO2
max is the same, but the lactate levels were incredibly better from like, I forgot, at five
watts per kilogram. He was at five millimoles and now he's at 1.7, right? So, this is where the
magic happened to this specific athlete, right? It was at the cellular level.
Yeah. And we see this across the board, right? VO2 max at the elite level does not come close
to predicting performance. Not at all. Not at all. And this is exactly so. This is why
we're putting together this study with all this population of different from people with metabolic
syndrome all the way to the France athletes. So, longitudinally, we see that, yeah, sure. VO2 max
corresponds with fitness in the same manner that watts corresponds with fitness, right? So,
we can also imply that, sure, instead of doing a VO2 max to look at longevity and fitness, we can
also do a power test or a speed test and a treadmill because we're going to see the same thing. Those
ones who are very poorly active, I mean, they have a very poor fitness. They're going to have a lower
VO2 max. They're going to have a lower power output. They have a lower speed, lower lactic
lens capacity, right? So, VO2 max has been forever a great surrogate, right, for fitness
and cardiovascular fitness and longevity. But we wanted to see if, in fact, it's really that
specific. So, in our study, we see that people in different categories, right? At the same VO2 max,
they might be in different metabolic states. So, some people at the same VO2 max might be
oxidizing a lot more fat or a lot more carbohydrates. So, that means that that does not correspond to
the same metabolic status. I would have thought that most people, by the time they're at VO2 max,
are, I mean, they would be disproportionately carbohydrate. So, really, you're just saying how
much fat oxidation still remains there is really what you're saying. And I'm assuming a very
untrained person has zero fat oxidation by the time they reach VO2 max, whereas a more highly
trained person would still have some amount. They might still be at 0.2 or 0.3 grams per minute.
Yeah. And for example, we see that, like a sedentary individual at 75% of the VO2 max
might be around three millimoles, whereas a work-class athlete at the same percentage of VO2 max
is about one and a half, right? So, metabolically, they're different. Yet, the VO2 max is the same.
So, if we prescribe exercise based on VO2 max, we might not do things correctly. Exactly. And
the same thing with carbohydrate oxidation. At a 75% of the VO2 max, like a sedentary individual,
oxidize is about two grams per minute, or an elite athlete oxidizes about three grams per minute.
So, that's a significant difference. And we also see that at 50% already. So, this is why
longitudinally, they correspond quite well. And same thing as fat oxidation. Fat oxidation at 50%
of VO2 max is about 0.0. Yeah, it's at 75% of VO2 max, 0.23 in sedentary, and 0.6 in an elite athlete.
So, and then we look at the different intensities. For example, an athlete that can have
at one millimole of lactate within the same group, not just comparing group, but we can see that
someone within a very same group, whatever the category they are, the lactate and the VO2 max
don't correlate. The correlations are sometimes 0.2 or 0.1 or 0.3.
So, while longitudinally- That's the R squared, you're saying?
Yes. Yeah, so basically, no correlation. Very poor correlation. When we talk about individual
groups, when we look at specific bone parameters, which is lactate with the VO2 max, it doesn't
really correspond. So anyways, this is what I think that we have learned a lot over these last
decades, where we can really pinpoint more at the cellular level to improve metabolism more than at
the carrier respiratory function, which is very important. Absolutely. They both are going to
improve, right? But I think that if we want to prescribe exercise, it's going to be more
specific. If we look at cellular surrogates like lactate, like fat oxidation, for example,
they're looking at VO2 max or meds. I mean, don't get me into there. That's a very prehistoric,
in my model's opinion, I don't want to offend anybody, but the whole med concept,
used for exercise, prescription, it's hard to swallow in today's times.
You know, Inigo, when we think about some of the muscle biopsy data, again, this term of
mitochondrial function, it's such an important part of longevity because it is one of the hallmarks
of aging, is declining mitochondrial function. I usually explain to patients that the type of
physiologic exercise that we're prescribing this zone to exercise is the way to measure
mitochondrial function. It's both the treatment and the test. But I'm guessing on the cellular
level, there's even more that we can talk about here. So the last thing I really want to talk
about today, because we've been, I know we've been going for a while, you've been generous with your
time. When you get into the omics, when you start to biopsy the muscles, when you start to look at
the mitochondria in a way that we can't do it, you know, in a regular clinical setting, what else
are you seeing that's that's differentiating the healthy from the unhealthy mitochondria or the
the high functioning from the low functioning mitochondria? Yeah. So there's this again,
I keep talking about papers that would have published, but we've been working for three
years quite hard. And now we cannot continue doing this, we need to start writing the papers, right?
You need more postdocs, you need more graduate students and postdocs with the writing.
But we have completed a pretty cool study and they're writing the manuscript now. Looking
between sedentary and active, we know already there are a bunch of research showing at the
cellular level, the difference between people with type 2 diabetes or mitochondrial, I mean,
metabolic syndrome and active individuals or even sedentary. We want to see also,
or want to show that people who are sedentary, they already have problems. And we wanted to
compare them with more active people who should be kind of how we should be as humans, right?
So we looked into the mitochondria, into mitochondria. So we looked at their significant
dysregulation at the mitochondrial level, everywhere you look in the mitochondria,
in sedentary individuals. You see a decreased capacity to oxidize, to burn glucose in terms of
pyruvate, fatty acids, amino acids. You see a significantly decreasing electron transport
chain as well, all the complexes. And you see also a significantly decreased capacity in the
transporters of different substrates. So one thing that really caught our attention,
and we think that this is something that we really want to emphasize and hopefully
on us in the future, is that we have identified that there is the mitochondrial pyruvate carrier,
which is, as I discussed earlier, that's the transporter of pyruvate into the mitochondria,
which is dysregulated already, down significantly down regulated in sedentary individuals,
compared to active individuals. Then we are matching it with the pyruvate flux, the oxidation
itself. So both the transporter and the flux are significantly dysregulated. What does this mean,
potentially? So that's shuttling all that's going to shuttle pyruvate to the other way it's going to
get in the cell, which is through lactate. Exactly. And also, what are the implications
of this? So again, these people don't have diabetes or pre-diabetes. This could be a healthy
person who's not active. Exactly. And this is what, unfortunately, this being the model
in most research papers out there, comparing the unhealthy with a sedentary health individual.
I've been pushing for years that the model should not be the healthy sedentary individual,
because that is the intervention. As humans, we're meant to walk or to exercise, so we need to look
at perfection to understanding perfection. The intervention of human evolution has been
becoming sedentary. And in fact, I had a hard time to get an IRB to study study, I have a
hard time with the committee to convince them that using active people as the gold standard
to understand imperfection, that's the way to go. Anyways, what we see is that these people
already, they don't have clinic, but yet they have a significant population. They don't have
clinical signs. Clinical symptoms, sorry. They're not clinical symptoms. They're the healthy
sedentary individuals. So they don't have insulin resistance, and they don't have
done regulation of good for transporters. Even hyperinsulinemia, are they hyperinsulinemic
when challenged with the glucose tolerance test? These people, they have no symptoms. They haven't
reported any glucose tolerance test that is abnormal, normal people. And then they have a
significant disruption in this mitochondria pelvic area. So which might mean that the first door that
might be jammed is that entrance of pyruvium-type mitochondria. Most of the research in diabetes
has done more at the peripheral level, if you will, glucose levels, more at the surface levels of the
cell, the glute IV, the insulin resistance, the pancreas, release of insulin, better cells, etc.
But what's the fate of glucose once it enters the cell? And this is what we're looking to this.
So the fate is pyruvate, but what's the fate of pyruvate? I just said very well, does it
enter the mitochondria or is it shuttled to or reduced to lactate? So I think that this is
important to see because it could be a marker down the road because again, these people don't
have clinical symptoms yet they have a significant dysregulation in their glucose metabolism.
So could this be 10, 15 years ahead of clinical symptoms and insulin resistance? So this is more
reason also to consider sedentary individuals to see how they have a metabolic dysregulation already.
Same thing we're doing at the fat oxidation level. The CPT-1 and CPT-2, the transporters of fat,
they're significantly downregulated as well. So that means they're not going to be able to transport
fat very well, which also matches to the fat oxidation itself where we inject fatty acids
into the mitochondria that are not sedated well. So they all match as well. So they have a dysregulation
already that is significant compared to motor activity individuals at the glucose metabolism
and fat metabolism. Then we see that many of these people who have diabetes or metabolic syndrome,
they have what's called intramuscular triglycerides, the fat droplet, and it's
adjacent right by the mitochondria. And it's a type of that in elite athletes, it's also there,
that fat droplet, but it's very active because about 25% to 30% of the fat oxidation comes from
that fat droplet adjusting to mitochondria, which it could probably is an evolutionary mechanism to
not rely on the adipose tissue, which might take time and have something right away there.
So when you say it's metabolically active, the difference between the intramuscular fat of the
athlete and the intramuscular fat of the person with type 2 diabetes, is it the flux then in the
person with type 2 diabetes, it's a static source of fat in the athlete, it's constantly turning
over and being oxidized and replenished. Exactly. Whereas in this population, it continues to grow.
My colleague Brian Bergman from the university is working a lot into the content of what's inside
this fat droplets. But one thing that we know is like, they're very high in ceramides and
triglycerides. And especially ceramides are key in the atherosclerotic process.
Therosclerosis is obviously it's a hallmark of cardiovascular disease. And ceramides are key for
this process. Historically, it's been thought and it's been shown that ceramides come from the liver,
they're released. But we're seeing that these intramuscular triglycerides are high in ceramides.
So could this be a connection between also cardiovascular disease and type 2 diabetes?
But this is only in the high turnover, high flux one, you're not accumulating them as much?
Yes. People who end up having type 2 diabetes, they accumulate this fat droplet.
Athletes as well, that's the athletes paradox. But athletes, as you said, they keep turning around
and it's very active. Whereas in people with type 2 diabetes or obesity, it keeps growing and
releases pre-inflammatory mediators. And it also is high in ceramides, which are key in atherosclerosis.
So this is where we're trying to establish the connections between type 2 diabetes and
cardiovascular disease at the mitochondrial level as a nexus. Because we know that about 80% of
people with type 2 diabetes, they also have cardiovascular disease and vice versa, which is
what we call cardiometabolic disease. So could the nexus of all that a mitochondrial impairment?
That's what we believe. Well, what I take away from this is we'll probably have to do a third
podcast in a couple of years because there's going to be a lot of data that's going to be published
then that isn't published now. There's going to be a lot more questions that we're going to have
answered. Again, I'm still really yearning to understand the effect of metformin in terms of
pure mitochondrial function and performance in a trained individual. So as always, I just can't
thank you enough for your generosity of insight and look forward to talking tomorrow when we
have a call about some other nerdy stuff we're going to get into. But thank you so much Inigo.
And also congratulations on the remarkable success of your team and Pagachar, who's an
amazing cyclist to watch. He's got everybody very excited about the Tour de France again.
Well, thank you very much, Peter, and all the listeners. I really appreciate
what you do. I think that the first time I met you on the first podcast, we were two and a
half hours talking about mitochondria. And I first met, I felt like this guy's crazy. There's
nobody out there who's going to be interested in listening to two and a half hours about
mitochondria and metabolic health. And you showed me that, yeah, the concepts are out there. And I
was in a moment where I was kind of, not many people are interested in this. And you were
already an inspiration for me to continue doing this. And there are remarkable work that you're
doing to educate people and inspire people. It's something that, yeah, it's transformational.
So I really appreciate the invitation, which is an honor.
Well, thanks for being with us today.
Thank you very much.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a
bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my
disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward
slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.