Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Hey, Nier, it's great to have you back. I was thinking about this when I was sort of
preparing for the podcast today. There's so much I want to cover today that I don't think
it's actually going to be possible. I'm pretty sure that we're going to talk as much as we
talk today and I'm going to be saying to the team, all right, let's talk about when we're
going to have Nier back because there's really just too many things I want to go through.
So anyway, thank you for making time and let's just get right into it.
So thanks, Peter. I'm happy to come back, but it's you who's coming to me every week
and I'm so grateful for what you're doing for this field and for helping all of us catching
this field of longevity that's going to come true very rapidly, I hope.
I was thinking about the first place I wanted to start and there's really no good one place
to start because there's just so much I want to talk about.
But let's start with centenarians. You know, you along with Dr.
Pearls are probably two of the people who have spent the most time studying this very,
very unique subset of the population.
So I think everybody knows what a centenarian is, someone who lives to be 100 or more.
But there's so much nuance about what it is about these special people.
And then, you know, there's sort of the pop culture view of this, which is people love to talk about
all of the bad behaviors that centenarians engage in, how much more they smoke,
how much less they exercise, all how much whiskey they drink and all of those things,
which are really cute. But when you study them scientifically and when you study their offspring
scientifically, as you've both done, we learn a lot of things.
And if my interpretation of the literature is at least partially correct,
it appears that genes play a significant role.
So genes don't seem to play a big role in people living to 70 versus 80.
But boy, when you start to talk about living to 90 versus 100, you know, relative to 70 or 80,
genes play a pretty big role. So tell me a little bit about what we understand
about the role that the parents play in determining the lifespan of offsprings, right?
How fortunate were these people to pick their parents?
Let me just tackle one of the things you said, that there's no much genetic impact
in people between 70 and 80. And it's true if you compare the lifespan of fathers and sons, okay,
or mothers and daughters or sons. And let me tell you why it's problematic.
My grandfather got a heart attack when he was 68 and he died. That's my grandfather.
My father got a heart attack at 68 and he had triple bypass and he died at 84.
So the correlation between age of death in different cohorts is not much revealing.
But let me say it now differently. Let's say it's 20%, okay? Let's say it's 20%.
If we understand this 20%, understand it really, we can use that in order to prevent
the 80% of the environment. Well, maybe another way to think about it near, because that example
is a great example, which makes it very difficult over discrete generations to make a comparison.
Do we have twin data? Because it seems to me that if you had monozygotic twin data,
that would be the gold standard for looking at the discordance and concordance between the role
of genes in separate environments, right? So let me tell you the problems with twins.
Twins are usually born small for their gestational age. In fact, it's more true that one of the
twins is small for their gestational age. Now, I've been doing studies with rats from before
when you ligate the uterine artery and make them small, they get diabetes, which they never get
at three months. We know that twins or that babies that are born small for age develop
age-related disease very rapidly. It's called the Barker hypothesis, right? It's observation
from Holland in World War II. So, and we actually determine some of the epigenetic manifestation
of what happens epigenetically when you do that. So I don't think twins are the right model unless
you understand that and account for that. Nier, this is super interesting. Can you tell me a little
bit more about that? I actually was not aware of the relationship between low birth weight and the
epigenetic imprint of that on reduced lifespan. And I assume healthspan or is it just lifespan?
It's mainly healthspan in humans that we know. You know, first thing that's obvious when you have
a small gestational age twin, there's the catch-up growth of the small baby. And those twins born in
the same day in few years, one of them is an obese child and one is a normal child. And as you know,
obesity drives aging very rapidly. So that's one mechanism. The changes in imprinting of epigenetic,
I would say for now that it's more of a description than a mechanism. There are many genes that are
involved and I'm not aware of a recent paper that says, you know, this is what happens.
So let's get back to the broader question, which is when an individual or when a cohort of individuals
lives to 100 and we compare them with a cohort of individuals that lives to 80,
what are the types of genes that seem to be offering protection to that group that lives to 100?
What is it that the centenarians have in a sort of polygenic sense that the rest of us schmucks don't have?
When we went to the centenarians, we had three hypotheses that we had to take care of. One is
that it's all the environment. Okay. It happens that they did exactly the right thing what the
doctors tell us to do now. The second, and it's not true, as you mentioned, it's not true. 60% of
the men are smoking and 30% of the women, 50% of them are overweight and obese and all that,
and not exercising and not vegetarians. The second hypothesis is that they have perfect genome.
We know that we have a lot of genotypes that are putting us at risk for a variety of age-related
disease. So maybe one out of 10,000 doesn't have that, and that's why they're flying in so gracefully.
So to be clear, part of that hypothesis is the absence of bad genes, not necessarily the presence
of good genes. Exactly. That only the absence of bad genes will allow them just to get without
diseases. Yes. I'll describe a very simple study that we've done. I'm sorry, I took you off your
track, but what was the third hypothesis? The third hypothesis is that there are genes that
slows their aging. So good genes. So it's basically... So it's okay. Fair enough. So as for the second
hypothesis, that they have what we call the perfect genome, we took our first 44 centenarians and did
whole genome sequencing at the time. Huge expense. But we only had those centenarians. Okay. We don't
have had the control, but we had a great instrument we thought. It's called cleanvar. It's an
accumulation of all the genes that have shown to be causing diseases. If you had a cleanvar variant,
you're very likely to have a disease. So we simply asked, do our centenarians have any of those
variants? And how many of those variants are there? At the time, there were 15,000. Now there are many
more. So just to put that in perspective for the listener, that I mean, we have between 20 and 30,000
coding genes, correct? Right. But these are variants of how many genes? Well, I don't remember how many
genes are in the variants, but those are variants that were found to be compelling. And by the way,
a lot of them are not. That's another story. So let's keep it simple. We had 15,000 variants
and we asked, do our 44 centenarians have variants? And the answer was each centenarian
had between five and six bad variants. Five and six out of 15,000 possible. Right. And we didn't
have a control, so we don't know how many the average person had. Right. But think of it,
those centenarians, each one of had five variants that will probably cause a disease and none of
them had it. And if you're asking, are those variants important? Well, we have two centenarians
who have the ApoE4 homozygosity that puts them at major risk, one of the best genetic risks
for Alzheimer's. The textbook says they would be demented at 70 and dead at 80 and they're at 100
and not demented. Genes for Parkinson's, for cancers, for other diseases. So basically,
the centenarians don't have the perfect genome, which left us with finding genes that are
protective. Right. That slows their aging, are protectives even against genes that are thought,
at least, as I'm saying, it's probably not totally true, thought to most probably cause a disease.
And tell me near approximately what year did you arrive at that conclusion?
This paper is more than 10 years old. I think we had several papers since then
confirming this. And look, like always, there are some,
there is a decrease also in bad genotypes in centenarians, some decrease. But really,
the majority of the study shows that it's not that it's not the perfect genome. It's something else.
We've very easily eliminated hypothesis one, which is centenarians live to 100 because of what they
do, their behaviors, their environment. You now make a very compelling case that it's not number
two, either. It's not that they lack any disease driving genes. So it is, in fact, this third
hypothesis. When did you actually demonstrate that? That's that's obviously a much harder one
to demonstrate because you probably have a far smaller library of disease sparing variants as
opposed to disease causing variants. So when did you start to arrive on what some of those variants
were? The story was interesting because remember we started the study in 1998 and there were other
parts of the studies that I didn't talk with you about. But one of the things we had is we start to
establish the phenotype. And one of the phenotypes that came up is high level of HDL cholesterol.
Actually, very high level of HDL cholesterol that was more obvious in the offspring of our
centenarians, even than our centenarians. So we have offsprings that have HDL cholesterol 130,
140, you know, the folds higher than it should be. And what we could do when we were when the
methods were poor and we were poor, we were going about genes that are involved in those
phenotypes. And we actually got a very compelling data on two genotypes that seems to be functional,
important, that are controlling lipid metabolism. One of them was a CTP genotype and one was an
APOS C3 genotypes. And those genotypes increased from about eight to nine percent of the homozygosity
in control to almost 20 percent in centenarians. And it's not only that. Look, when you have people
of all ages, unrelated, you can look at the trend of the genotypes. If the genotype is killing you,
then as you go closer to 80, 90 and above, those genotypes will decrease.
And if they are going up, and by the way, the slope that's going up is a very important
statistical tool, then they are very likely to be longevity genotypes. And this is what we found.
And it's so interesting. It was our initial discovery. And drug companies were at our
doorsteps immediately because not because they're interested in aging, but they said just a minute,
if we have if we make a good drug, OK, if the drug is really good, it targets exactly that
with outside effects, then we have already safety. We have safety because those guys for 100 years had
in both cases, by the way, suppression of the expression of those genes. It must be safe.
So let's develop the drug. And isn't it amazing how big the graveyard is of CTEP inhibitors? Yes.
And I don't totally understand it. And I listened to one of your podcasts. Yeah, Tom Dayspring and
I have discussed this in great detail. I think a lot of it comes down to not understanding the
biology of HDL. I mean, the biology of LDL is relatively straightforward. The biology of HDL,
I think it's safe to say we don't understand at all. I mean, that would be putting it mildly.
And I think the challenge with the CTEP inhibitors is they raised HDL cholesterol. So in one sense,
they reproduced the phenotype in its most crude sense. But you can think of it very simplistically,
I think, which is how do you raise HDL cholesterol? Do you raise it by putting more cholesterol into
HDL? Do you raise it by impairing HDL from conducting reverse cholesterol transport and
getting rid of cholesterol? Right. Those are two very different approaches to raising HDL. And when
you look at the centenarians and examine their phenotype, you don't really know what it is. You
would speculate that they have better HDL function. But the reality of it is we have other phenotypes
that exist in nature. I'm not sure if you're aware of this, but I've seen a number of papers that
examine people with HDL cholesterol that's very elevated who have very advanced atherosclerosis.
And in fact, the elevated level of HDL cholesterol they have suggests impaired HDL function and
impaired reverse cholesterol transport. And so I think that's probably the issue around why a lot
of these drugs have failed. And it obviously speaks to the humility with which all of us need to be
able to examine these phenotypes. And it's a clever way to go about doing it, right? A very
clever thing is look for phenotypes that are different and work backwards to find genotypes.
Right. So let me add two points to this. Absolutely. The trade-offs of this pathway are amazing.
On one hand, you don't clear cholesterol. On the other hand, you have high HDL. But
for me, it's not about the HDL because all the particle size are significantly bigger.
So you could say it's all about high dense LDL, right? That's the phenotype that we're depicting.
So I think this part is important. The other thing that was really striking,
I told you about those two centenarians with ApoE4 genotypes. They both had very high HDL
cholesterol and they were homozygous for CTP. And so it is possible, in fact, the major phenotype
for us of the HDL wasn't cardiovascular, it was cognitive function. And so when I'm saying
cognitive function, maybe we're talking about physiology. We're thinking of this physiology
from a heart perspective. And maybe there's a physiology of that from a brain perspective that
we don't totally understand. And by the way, I did ask Merck. I said to Merck, do cognitive function.
Okay. And they did. But the people they go to the study were between 50 and 70 years old.
Two years. So there's no results for that.
Nier, did you have, you might not know this off the top of your head, but even offline, I'd love
to hear what you learned about the variants of clotho that those people had, especially the ones
who were homozygous for ApoE4. You're probably aware, but there are variants of clotho that seem
to completely abrogate the effect of E4, meaning you take people with ApoE4, either hetero or
homozygous. And if they have this particular variant of clotho, they behave as though they are E3.
This is so interesting. So we published on clotho. And clotho was the example of what we call
a V shape or a U shape genotype. Clotho basically killed, seemed to kill 50% of our subjects by age
85. Okay, the genotype has disappeared by age 85. And all of a sudden, after that, it was the same.
Okay, it was the same. And our interpretation was that, you know, those centenarians were born
with clotho, but they were also born with longevity genes, which made the clotho not significant. Okay.
But another hypothesis is that the actual clotho that they had is a clotho that was protective in
another mechanism. So what about some of these other genes that have now come to light? So
Foxo, for example, tell us a little bit about Foxo. How did you arrive at that? What was the
phenotype that tipped you in that direction? Or did you arrive at Foxo through a pure genetic
analysis? Well, I didn't come up with Foxo. Foxo came out from Japan in Okinawa. And I'm using you
in the very liberal sense, Nir. I'm giving you and the field credit. And me is not only me, right?
It's a big team. And in fact, you know, the research now has changed very much. The teams
are really teams because you need to computational and the AI people and the doctors and the
physiology. So it's we. But let me start it differently. Because, you know, why did I start
centenarians? I started centenarians because all of a sudden, in the mid 90s, it became apparent
that you change just one gene in a nematode and they can live 10 times longer. Right. By the way,
the gene was bugging me because it's the insulin receptor, the IGF insulin receptor gene. And the
nematodes were insulin resistant. And they also had abdominal obesity. They accumulated fat in their
intestinal cell. It wasn't the right example, but the concept was right. And so I started the
centenarians. I told you about the first genes that I saw. And then I wrote a grant. And, you know,
most of the grants that I wrote ended up the hypothesis ended up being wrong, though we found
the right explanations. Mostly there was one grant that I wrote. And I said, I'm writing this
hypothesis, knowing it's wrong. And that is that growth hormone IGF signaling pathway have anything
to do with human longevity. I said, it's great. You know, we have the nematodes, we have this and
that, but this is wrong. And I was totally wrong about it. And I'm telling you the bottom line,
60% of our centenarians have genes that impairs growth hormone IGF signaling pathway,
including the FOXA3A. 60%. It's the most common genotype. It's not only genotypes, by the way,
it's micro RNA, it's genotypes on the IGF receptor, it's deletions of the growth hormone receptor.
There's lots of ways to get to this. But this is very common. And sorry, just to double click on
that a little bit near, I think it's worth maybe giving people a little bit of a primer on the
relationship between growth hormone and IGF-1. And if you want, we can talk about IGF-BP3.
Right. Well, okay. So the growth hormone IGF, I was trying to slide over.
No, no, no, no, I think this is important to the story. So please expand.
So I said, I said growth hormone IGF, and I'll stand by picking those two. But for growth,
there are actually hundreds of genes, okay? There are hundreds of genes. If you only look at
what determines height, there's hundreds of genes that are determining heights.
But the growth hormone is the growth hormone pathway or the growth hormone signaling pathway
that really comes from the pituitary controlled by the hypothalamus, but comes from the pituitary
and makes you grow when you need to grow. And it has its own actions, but also it has a specific
action of binding to its receptor in liver and releasing the second important growth hormone,
which is called IGF-1. It stands for insulin growth factor one. And so those are the hormones
that we're talking about. The advantage of IGF-1 is that it's measurable. Growth hormone is
measurable in provocation and in young people and not much in old people. So IGF is kind of the
biomarker for this action. IGF itself is really complicated because there are five, actually,
I hear that there are seven binding proteins and there's a lot of regulation in between.
But it's true to say that levels of IGF are really very good biomarkers, even if you don't
agree that there are causative for variety of health outcomes. And I want to say another thing,
you know that in nature, the dwarfs are doing better as far as longevity. The little dogs are
doing better. The ponies are living longer. And in animals, everyone, no matter how you interfere,
you're getting better longevity. Even the larone dwarfs that have deletion of the growth hormone
receptor, we don't know if they live longer, but at least they have less age-related diseases like
cancer or diabetes. But they have more alcoholism and suicide. And as you said, it's not clear that
they live any longer. They just seem to be spared of some of the chronic diseases in exchange for
others, correct? I'm always describing it that they are still unhappy to be short. They drink,
they cross the road and nobody sees them when they're drunk and they're being run over, right?
It's not natural. But let me tell you a much more optimistic story about that.
We discovered, and when I say we, it's Gil etzmon who was a fellow and then a faculty with us,
he's still involved, he's now in Israel, but we looked at all the pathway and we discovered
that our centenarians have deletion of exome 3 in the growth hormone receptor.
And Gil came to me and showed also the trend. And as I said, the trend is important. So
the homozygosity was 3% in our population and 12% in centenarians. And I said, Gil,
what's their IGF-1 level? And he showed me, it's significantly lower. I said terrific.
What was their maximal height? And he said, that's the problem. And he shows me,
they're significantly taller than the rest of the people, 2-3 inches taller.
Wait, the people that had 10%, the people that were homozygous were taller than the controls?
Significantly taller.
And 2-3 inches is not subtle. What was the relative Z score difference between them in IGF?
I don't remember. I'll get you the reference. It was like a 20% decrease.
And what about their IGF binding proteins?
There is nothing special there. There is nothing special.
No major difference.
No. But you're on the right track. So I said to Gil, what do you do with genetics? First of all,
you need to do validation. The paper is not accepted without validation. I said do validation.
So Gil got three other studies from all over the world, actually. And all of them were showing the
same thing. The oldest old had a false difference in their growth hormone in this deletion,
which was very compelling on its own. But still, why do they have lower IGF-1? So we went to-
Sorry, just to be clear, they had lower growth hormone. They should have lower IGF-1.
You're saying, but they were taller.
Why they were taller. Sorry. I meant why they were taller.
Yes.
So, Hasikoen, who's the dean of the Gerontology School at USC and one of my collaborator,
is a growth hormone expert. And he took the cells- And by the way, that's another thing that we have.
We have the lymphoblasts of our centenarians. So if you have a phenotype, if you have a genotype,
you can actually look at its action with lymphoblasts. And he took this lymphoblasts,
and he incubated them with and without growth hormone. And something really interesting
happened when they were not incubated with growth hormone. The phosphorylation of this receptor,
the activity of this receptor was lower, as we thought it would be, because they have deletion
of an axon. But when he incubated with growth hormone, it was almost like an amplifying switch.
They were phosphorylated three times as much. The same was with proliferation. Proliferation was lower,
and with growth hormone was increased. So what we understood that happened, although we don't
understand this switch mechanism, but when they go through puberty, okay, they are activating growth
hormone. They're very sensitive. They're sensitive, they grow taller. And once their growth hormone
decreases after puberty, they are tall, but their IGF stays low for the rest of their lives.
What fraction of centenarians share this genotype? 12%.
20%. 12%. Okay. I want to talk more about the genotypes, and I'm going to come back to a
question around this, so hopefully I'll remember. So this is now another big major axis, is the
genotype cluster around GH. We've already addressed the genotype cluster around CTEP.
Let's talk about FOXO, let's talk about TSHR, let's talk about some of the others.
Okay. Can I make a point, because I don't want to forget it, so you can add it wherever.
We recently published a paper, because we didn't understand so well why the literature is so
confusing us with the growth hormone and IGF. We went to the UK Biobank, which has really changed
our ability to validate and to learn and to get hypotheses. And they have 440,000 people who have
actually IGF-1 measurements. And we looked at the young people that had high IGF-1 level.
And we saw that for young people, high IGF-1 was protective from variety of age-related diseases
and from mortality, although not from cancer.
Yeah, I was just about to say it's a very complex relationship. IGF seems to protect from everything
but cancer, right? Right, except that, by the way, I'll get to cancer in a second.
On the other hand, people over the age of 60, it's exactly the opposite. Okay, they had more of
every age-related disease except cancer. And they also had increasing mortality.
What I'm telling you now, in other words— Sorry, was that a linear relationship?
Totally linear. Totally linear relationship. Totally linear relationship. What I'm describing
to you is what we call the antagonistic pleiotrophy hypothesis of age. Okay? The things that are good
for you when you're young can turn against you when you're old. Or in this case, yeah, in order
to do reproduction and to do evolution, you need a lot of growth hormone to get there.
But after that, you have to switch the energy because now you're going to have breakdown.
It doesn't make sense for you to expand growth in any way. And I think it was beautifully
demonstrated, and it also explained the confusion in the literature. It depends
if you looked at young people or old people or took care of that at all.
Yeah, one thing that's confusing about that pleiotrophic relationship is that the cut-off is
quite old, right? So if you really think about this just through kind of a Dawkins lens,
you would think that that cut-off would be done by 25 or 30. At that point, evolution is done with
you. You've served your purpose. Now, anything that you get after that is gravy and really not
under the purview of evolution. Evolution sort of stopped caring about you. Unless you buy the
argument—and I think this is an argument—that there's an evolutionary benefit to you being a
caregiver beyond your reproductive capacity. So maybe there's something to be said for that. But
are you surprised by how late in life we see that switch flip?
You made this argument. By the way, I would say I believe in the grandparent theory. But still,
if you had your kid and died the next day or survived for 100 more years, I think it's too
late for evolution. Number one. Number two, we show one of the most interesting things that we
show, and it's true around the world. People with longevity, with exceptional longevity, have less
offspring. From an evolutionary point of view, you should be losing longevity genes. In fact,
I wrote a paper one year— By the way, anybody with kids will immediately find that
completely intuitive. Especially in COVID times. They just suck all the life out of you. They're
incredible. I love them more than anything, but I believe that they are indeed shortening my life
on some level. I think there's hormesis. They'll come back and you'll be more resilient. It's okay.
But I actually wrote a paper saying, when people in the Old Testament
are quoting Metusilla to be 969 and Moses to be 120, maybe they were right. Maybe we had this
capacity because we're losing longevity genes because of reproduction.
That's really interesting. Has there ever been a serious study about the biblical stories and
if there's any way to assess any validity to some of the age-related claims that were made
merely 2,000 years ago? You know why it's a problem? Because the Orthodox people believe
that every word in the Bible is true. Exactly. You ask them, and I asked many, believe me,
I ask many, you think really that's happened? They didn't know how to count. They're very
skeptical. That's why I wrote the paper that I'm not skeptical. I think that's true.
I want to ask you another question about growth hormone. It's a hormone that
I've prescribed to patients when they're healing from injuries. I've seen pretty good literature
that says you're having, you tear a bicep, you have surgery to repair it, growth hormone for
eight weeks fosters rehabilitation better than if you did nothing. That's the very narrow window
in which I've prescribed growth hormone is typically around the healing from orthopedic
injuries. A couple of things I'll say, every patient I've prescribed it to, and there hasn't
been many, maybe half a dozen over the last 10 years, they all say I've never felt better,
which then helps me understand why this cottage industry of doctors out there exists
who run longevity clinics prescribing growth hormone. I've drawn a hard line in the sand with
my patients that I don't believe in the literature that would suggest that prescribing growth hormone
is a pro-longevity tool, but if I'm being brutally honest, and I tell them this as well,
I can't tell you that it's killing you either. I can come up with theoretical arguments why
prescribing growth hormone is going to make you feel better, but it's going to shorten your life,
but I don't really see any data one way or the other. Even when you look at extreme cases,
which are basically athletes who use, growth hormone is the most abused drug in all of sports,
because we don't have a test for it. You'd think that the morgue of athletes would be much bigger.
So what is your view on exogenous growth hormone as not necessarily a pro-longevity tool, but as
an agent that clearly helps health span, but might be not as destructive to lifespan as
I believe it could be? I think you're absolutely right. Look, we're talking about
chronic environment, and that has nothing to do with the fact that there could be indication
for growth hormone. You mentioned one. There is a paper about growth hormone after strokes.
We were actually interested in growth hormone in the brain. There are more examples like that. So
I don't think those are mutually exclusive. Right. And I've often wondered, by the way,
I haven't seen the literature. If you know of it, I'd love to see it. Would growth hormone be
protective in stages of early cognitive decline? But anyway, putting that aside for a moment,
what about this idea of the 50-year-old who goes to the longevity clinic and they're being given
low doses of growth hormone every single day? Typically, it's somewhere between 0.4
and one milligram daily. I'm not going to answer you about the dose, but I'm going to make the
thing that I think is very important. And it's getting us back to this antagonistic
pliotrophy. And it's relevant to tame and metform. It is possible that things that you're doing are
good for you when you're young and against you when you're old. Right. So when people are asking
me on any of those gero protectors, gero therapeutics, vitamins, when do we start them?
Okay. The answer is I really don't know. I think you shouldn't get some elytics before you're 70
or 80 years old. I think problem with forming, although we start the study at 65, most of the
studies so far that showed really large effect of metforming are people were recruited above the age
of 50. So I think it's 50. So I don't know to tell you for a singular patient who chronologically,
chronological age is 50 and biological age. I don't know what it is. You can determine it better.
Well, what do I tell them? I don't I don't really know based on literature, based on clinical trials.
So last question on this near based on the number of people that are taking growth hormone out there.
And I don't know how you would quantify this, but presumably it's not rocket science to figure it
out. But let's just say that there are hundreds of thousands of people in the United States alone.
Who are taking growth hormone daily as part of a
Geroprotective regimen. Why aren't they all dying prematurely?
We don't know that.
Assuming that they're older.
Well, that's true. We don't know it. But wouldn't we see a signal of it?
I think not because the people who are taking growth hormone are probably taking all
some metformin and exercising and doing other things.
Yeah. So fair fair point. There's too many confounders.
Yeah. I mean, again, my view is still and probably will remain for the foreseeable future that it is
not a great Geroprotective agent because I do have these concerns. But this is an example of
something where I really wish we had data. I want to tell you another thing that also
is is a gray zone for me. Most of the negative effect of growth hormone IGF in humans we see in
females, not in males, actually in animals too, in animals too. So I'll describe two things.
When we look at our centenarians that's done by Sophia Millman who's running the longevity
studies now. And she measured IGF one in in all our patients. And she looked at our centenarian
in our centenarian. So they are already 100 years old. Okay.
Is IGF one level predicts their longevity? And remember, centenarians are likely to die. 30%
of them are going to die each year. So so those with the lowest half of IGF one
lived twice as long as those with the highest level of IGF one.
And that's females only or both sexes? That's females only. Okay. Males. We don't have,
you know, the ratio of female male centenarians around the world is there 85 females for every
15 men. We have better results because most a lot of the female centenarians have never got married.
You know, nuns and other things going back to your problem with your kids, right?
But we need people with offspring. Our study is based on offspring because the phenotype,
the phenotype you capture in offspring and not in centenarians. In centenarians,
the phenotype is going down already. Okay. Those women also have better cognitive function.
And as far as muscle function, it's not different. In other words, they are not paying. I think a lot
of our problem when we come from sports, right? We're trying to preserve muscle. And I'm not sure
that low IGF is the best way to preserve muscle. I think maybe it's making the muscle
biology better, but it's not making the muscle any better.
Sorry, just to be clear, you're saying that the women in the bottom quartile, say of IGF,
are no more likely to be sarcopenic than the women with higher IGF, but they do tend to live longer.
And smarter and cognitively.
They have better cognitive function.
Right. With male, it's not, there is a trend, but it's not significant. So I think that
if you have male, you know, and that's my way out of that. If you, it's lots of it is males that are
taking it. I haven't convinced myself in my study that it's not a major sex differences,
the sensitivity to growth hormone.
Yeah, I'm just reflecting on the few patients in my practice who do take growth hormone. It is
prescribed by other doctors. I've made it clear that I'm not thrilled about it, but they feel
strongly about it and it's their choice. I think it's an equal, it's a very small number. It's an
equal mix of male and female, which again, gets to a question that we are going to talk about today,
which is health span, lifespan trade offs. So let's continue down this path of double
clicking on the centenarians and their bucket three genes. That is to say they're good genes
rather than their absence of bad genes are centenarians more likely to have Apo E2 than
non-centenarians, which is the protective variant of that gene.
That's the most common general longevity genotypes that we have. And Apo E2, either
an allele frequency or the homozygosity of Apo E2 is the most validated longevity genotype that we have.
Okay.
First of all, it's the truth if you measure if you measure genotype. It was hard for me to accept
it and it's only recently that I convinced myself. And the reason is that Apo E2 genotype is also
associated with diseases too. It's not so simple. And I thought for a long time
that what we have actually, we have a problem, it's ascertainment bias. That to our study,
we don't get people with Apo E4 because they are demented and they're not getting to our study or
to any study. So that we increase the proportion of other genotypes. But what convinced me
is that it should have been equally distributed between Apo E2 and Apo E3. And it's not.
It's really an Apo E2 phenomenon. And so although I don't understand totally the mechanism,
I'm convinced myself that there is something true in this and that Apo E2 by mechanism
that I don't totally get is the longevity genotype.
Presumably, this is backtracking a little bit on something you said.
I'm guessing centenarians have less LPA genotype.
LPA genotype is really interesting. Remember we talked about how we are losing cloto with age.
Until we regain it.
Right. We are losing a little LPA and regaining that. Now, what we've done
is with computational biologists, the system biologists, we interacted every one of those
bad genotypes with the longevity genotype. And actually the people with high, the centenarians
with high LPLiL-A all have CTP. They're homozygous for the CTP genotype.
So they have some protection to counter it. And by the way, they might be getting some
benefit from LPLiL-A. There may be something that LPA, because you have to think,
LPA is common, right? It's about 10% of the population. So 10% of the population
overexpresses this thing. 10% of the population has an elevated phenotype for LPLiL-A.
And it's true that evolution wasn't selecting against atherosclerosis.
But there are arguments to be made that LPLiL-A could have played a role in managing
infections, for example, that this could have been a manner in which we fought oxidative stress.
So it begs to, you know, at least question the idea, do the centenarians who have it
get some benefit from it while having genes that offset some of its negatives?
Yeah. But you have to explain on a population base how all of a sudden at age 85,
you switch and this genotype becomes protective, you know? Yes, you're selecting a lot.
Yeah. Is that really necessary or is it just a denominator problem where at 85,
you've really eliminated so much of the population that you're now concentrating
the people who were never harmed from it. So in those people, they've never been harmed
by the gene. And now they are disproportionately rising to the surface because the population
around them has withered away so quickly. Right. So those are the two explanations,
either what you just said or that they're protected by other longevity gene and it makes
it irrelevant what this LPLiL-A. Although I don't think those are mutually exclusive. I think the
former is an explanation. I think that the latter is an explanation for the former. It's the
amplifier of it, right? It's what lets them get there in the first place is that using C-TEP as
an example, they happen to have a C-TEP mutation or a C-TEP variant that offers remarkable
protection against atherosclerosis, of which an interesting but kind of irrelevant phenotype is
high HDL cholesterol. And that's offsetting the damage of their LPLiL-A. And then eventually at
some point when everybody else has died because of their LPLiL-A, they're still standing. And they
might even be getting some benefit from LPLiL-A that everybody gets, but it's in other people's
cases, it's so dwarfed by the damage of LPLiL-A. Again, total hypothesis or speculation, but that
it's plausible, right? It is. Okay. Tell me about TSHR. I've never understood that one fully.
So the thyroid story is interesting because we found a correlation between high TSH and longevity.
And when I say correlation... As an endocrinologist, you're maybe give people the
two minute story on what TSH is and how it functions. You know, I promised to some of my
sisters are listening to you and I promised I'm going to be so simple. You want me to call me
again and ask me what did you mean? And now I'm falling into... I know. I'm doing a bad job of this.
I'm sorry. You're absolutely right. So TSH is really your control of thyroid function
in the sense that if you become hypothyroid, then this TSH, this hormone from the pituitary will
increase in order to get those thyroid hormones to be normal again. And they might fail and then
you'll be hypothyroid, but there's an effort to get those thyroid out of your glands. Okay. So
that's TSH. So when we see a high TSH in a normal person, we ask the first question, is their thyroid
gland not making enough T4 and or converting enough of that T4 to the active hormone T3,
which is the feedback loop that tells the pituitary how much TSH to make. So what you're
saying is we see a higher amount of TSH in long-lived people suggesting... And their children.
And their children. So maybe suggesting a subclinical or potentially a clinical degree
of low thyroid function or hypothyroidism. Is that a safe summary? Correct. And I'll tell you,
our discovery has led to several papers and to change in the thyroid association recommendation
of what to do with old people. The endocrinologist or the thyroidologist were looking for business.
So once TSH was above 10 and then they said, it might be subclinical at seven and we went to five.
And now if you are three and symptomatic, which we are always because we're tired.
So that's where the science came. And we pointed out to the fact, we did it in our study, then we
did it in a national study. And we said, you have to leave those older people because maybe
this is a physiological way for them to be well. And we don't need to increase their...
Tell me how high you're seeing the TSH. What is the difference when you age match them between
centenarians? It's like five to eight. Okay. So normal is like until five. Yeah. Okay. Or even
4.2 on our lab. Yeah. And changing baseline. So yeah. And look, their thyroid hormones
themselves are normal. Okay. It's really only the TSH. So normal free T4, normal free T3,
but they walk around with a TSH of five to eight. Right. Now here's the kicker. And this is where
I'm hoping the offspring can help us. Do you know what their TSH would have been in their 30s and
40s? Would they have also had a TSH of five, six or seven? Well, I think that's why we have
the offspring. And I don't have the answer for this yet, but that's why we have the offspring,
because we want to see the effects of those longevity gene as they get old, right? And to
see really what phenotype and what measurements are changed throughout. And I don't have the answer,
but a lot of them do have high TSH when they're 60. So they're U thyroid high TSH patients. Right.
Right. What's the hypothesis for that? Is this simply a biomarker of something else that is
unrelated to thyroid function? Or does it suggest that these people live right on the edge of
hypothyroidism without actually becoming clinically symptomatic? And that there's something
protective within running a lower RPM, running the engine a little bit lower, a little bit slower.
Right. So by the way, the growth hormone deficiency models are also hypothyroid.
Okay. So it might be part of the physiology of what we're seeing anyhow.
Have you looked at prolactin in these people and other pituitary hormones that tend to
move with TSH? We have prolactin. I'm not sure that we looked at TSH. You know, this TSH paper came
years ago. I don't remember that we're doing anything. It's a good question. I have two
endocrinologists that are looking at our data and analyzing it. And I'll be happy to come again,
or have them talk more about the endocrinology of those people. But
so we're just looking and so I don't have association with others, but the hypothesis was
that their metabolism is maybe slow. And although they're compensating by higher TSH,
still their metabolism, you know, it's like insulin resistant. You don't totally normalize the glucose,
although you have enough insulin for that, that there's a metabolic over metabolic advantages.
I'm saying it like that because I don't know that it's true. I don't really think that our data
supports low metabolism necessarily. But I do think as an endocrinologist that if an elderly
person comes and by incidental finding has TSH between five and eight, you don't have to go and
treat it straight away. Has anyone done Mendelian randomization on any of these clusters of genes
and looked for? Because we haven't really established a causal relationship here, have we?
In these genes? No. So we're trying to develop, you know, by the way, Peter, you just said another
word that nobody knows, right? Mendelian randomization. Okay, sorry. Do you want to explain
a Mendelian randomization? Well, I would just, I don't want to go long into that, but because we
have so much genetic data, and by the way, genetic data is disappointing because they're
not so predictive, most of them, you can find lots of genes for for obesity and you'll be lean for
lipids and you'll have normal lipids, right? But we have lots of genotype and we try to integrate
those genotypes in order to assess how much they are increasing the risk of us of getting a disease.
And usually it's not by much. What we're trying to do, we're trying to have an instrument that will
do Mendelian randomization to longevity. Okay, so we can see what's your genotype that fits
longevity more than anything else that's in evolution now. But otherwise, look, I have to tell you,
the reason this is not good is very simple. We're doing something so stupid in genetics.
We do lots of genotypes and we take each one of these genotype and we ask, is this associated
with obesity or diabetes or not? And we found many things and in order to, by the way, to make them
statistic significance without increasing their power much, we just need to get 100,000 more people
in the study. Okay. But we're not built with one genotype at the time. We're built with numerous
genotypes. And what we've started doing lately, and that's our latest nature paper, was to say,
just a minute, we're looking at the difference between centenarians and people without longevity.
And we're going to take all those rare genotypes, less than 1%, okay, because
to be centenarians, 1 out of 10,000. So we need to find rare genotypes. And by the way,
there are 80,000 rare genotypes just in our population. And then we take those genotype
and put them in pathways and look at the enrichment of the pathways rather with a specific
genotype. And then we get really important information. And by the way, the important
information that we got in the study in the summary statement is that the genetics of longevity
in humans is exactly what we learned from animals. It's the insulin signaling pathway,
it's the mTOR signaling pathway, it's the MEPCI pathway, it's exactly the same genotype, the
distinct centenarians and other people. And I think this is really very important for us because
people have blamed us that our animal models are not, you know, animals' models are not good. Yeah,
they're not good for diabetes, they're not good for Alzheimer, they're not good for other thing.
But for aging, actually, our models are really good because it's so conserving evolution. All
our animals, their skin, their hair, their skeletal, their get cancers, they get diseases.
So this is the same, but it's really the same pathways. And the first that comes out is the
IGF insulin signaling pathway. Yeah, which as you said, goes all the way back to C. elegans, right?
One of the simplest organisms we can study. All of this really points towards the importance of
polygenic risk scores. And, you know, when I talk to someone like Richard Isaacson,
who is so focused on understanding Alzheimer's disease, and Richard and I work so closely on
this, because it's obviously one of the most important things we think about in our practice.
I think of the evolution that we have had in our thinking over the past five years. In fact,
we're working on a paper now that's looking at this polygenic assessment of risk in dementia.
You brought up earlier APO E4. Obviously any listener to this podcast is no stranger to it.
We've spent so much time talking about it. One of the things that I would say is,
I would say is 10 years ago, we thought that being homozygous for E4, so being in that roughly
1% of the population that has two copies of the E4 gene, that was a death sentence, as you noted
earlier. That's a person who's going to have Alzheimer's disease by 60, and they're going
to be dead by 70. There's no way out of that. Their risk is deemed at about 20-fold that of
the general population. Then five years ago, we looked at the data again and said, it's still
awful, but it's not 20 times the risk of the E3, E3. It's 12 times the risk. Then we look at the
data again two years ago, and it's still bad, but maybe it's five times the risk.
And now we are looking at patients who have E4, E4, and they don't have, not only do they not have
Alzheimer's disease, more importantly, they don't have any of the early signs of it based on really,
really advanced cognitive testing that shows very subtle signs decades before.
And we're starting to look at other genes that are abrogating some of the effects of this.
And so now the focus has been less at looking at APOE4 and making a determination, and it's
looking at E4 plus Tom40 plus mitochondrial haplotype plus cloth though, plus a whole bunch
of genes and taking a polygenic approach to risk. It seems to me that this would be the most logical
way to do the same thing with respect to longevity, right? I mean, I think this is true with
cardiovascular disease. LPA is part of the story, but it's not the whole story, right?
Absolutely. Absolutely, you're right. You described the problem and the solution,
absolutely right. I would just tell you that in looking for those longevity genes that we just
published, 12 of them are associated, we're funded for that, but they are associated with
resiliency to Alzheimer's. And I think that not enough of the genetics is explaining not only the
genetics, but the resiliency or looking at the genetics of resiliency, which is what we're
calling longevity in this case, but the resiliency to diseases, which happens to diseases that you
get in young age too, not every genotype causes this disease. So I think you're right.
Would you put Foxo in that category as kind of a general resilience gene that is less
disease specific and more broadly protective?
Yeah, I actually count the Foxo3A as in the insulin signaling pathway, insulin IGF signaling pathway.
We can argue about it, but that's my bucket.
What are the genes that you would put in the general resilience pathway, not necessarily
disease specific or system specific as in the endocrine system?
We have 750 centenarians in our study. Now, they are all Ashkenazi Jews, and they are Ashkenazi Jews.
Why is that?
Not because religious is important, but because Ashkenazi Jews are genetically homogeneous.
They went through a bottleneck, an expansion, and then a bottleneck, and very few survived,
and they lived in isolation and intermarriage, and their genetic pool is much more homogeneous.
In fact, we can measure it. It's genotype specific, but we need between 20 and 50 less
times, between 20 and 50 times less people in order to get the same data. So think about it
that not 750, but few thousands, but it's still not enough to find all longevity genes. And one
of the things that we realize is that there are 50 ways to leave your lover. There are 50 ways
probably to get to longevity. It's possible there's only one person who's 150 years old somewhere,
and if we knew his genotype, he will solve the problem for anyone. And the genotypes we are
discovering are things like that. We have 20 genotypes in centenarians and one in control.
But those for geneticists who are dealing with 400,000 people in study, they say, well, in 750
centenarians, this can change any minute. So what can we do? Well, what we can do is look at the
function of those genotypes. And you know our friend Yuxin Xu, that's what she's doing with
our studies. She takes those discoveries and either takes the lymphoblasts of our patient,
or she does construct and express those genes in cells and see how resilient they are to injury.
So there are a lot of genes, and I think the biggest news for me now is that
American Federation of Aging Research has gotten contribution from a single guy,
$2.8 million, to recruit 10,000 centenarians across the United States and their offspring and control.
And I think that this will give us such an acceleration of understanding longevity and
such an acceleration of getting drugs that probably are likely to work and also things
that we don't know yet. Like who knows, some of the things that we discovered are in pathways
that were not, they're not in our longevity lexicons.
Nier, that's interesting. Only $2.8 million is required to recruit 10,000 centenarians plus
their offsprings plus appropriate controls? Well, let's see. Let's see where we get.
That seems like a very high ROI for that donor.
We hired two companies who have approaches, and actually there's a preliminary data,
a preliminary study to see what's the best way to approach these people, because it's all going to be
basically web-based, so we need their children and grandchildren, and we're going to send them
a swab so that they can do it with help and we'll get the swab at least as the first,
on the first pass, and be able to rapidly do the genetics and post it, by the way,
just immediately post it so people can start looking at it and making sense of the data.
And you're going to do whole genome sequence or exome?
Both. We're going to do mainly exome sequencing and maybe switch as the whole genome sequencing
price comes down, which it does. What's the current price of whole exome?
I don't totally remember that. The reason I don't remember is that our genotypes was done by
Regeneron, and they paid for that, so I don't remember how much it is now.
So let's talk about a thought experiment. You mentioned something earlier, which is what made
me think of this, right? So you said there's somebody out there maybe who's going to be 150
years old, one person that will concentrate all of these genes in perfection and they'll get to be
150. And if we could look at that person's genes, we might have an answer. I would push back and say,
or not, right? It might be that we're discounting the stochastic nature of this. And even if you
found that 150 year old person, and even if you identified which genes played a role,
the likelihood that you'll identify which environmental factors turned on those genes
or amplified some and attenuated others seems very low. So it begs this thought experiment,
right? If you took 10,000 identical people with whatever program you have of the perfect genotype.
So this is 10,000 people that have as many of the good genes as possible and is none of the bad
genes. We put them in a time capsule and we let them live their lives, but now we randomize them
to, I'm making this up, but three groups, right? One group is the base case. Go and live a normal
life. One group is the do everything bad that you possibly can. So I want you to start smoking when
you're 15. I want you drinking three drinks a day. Never exercise. You're only allowed to eat at
McDonald's. Oh wait, you go. And then the third group becomes the do everything right. We're
going to exercise. We're going to, we do the opposite. Give me your prediction of how long
each of those three groups lives. So Peter, I was trying to do things simple and you complicate me
again. And I'm taking back, first of all, when I said 150 human, I think the maximal of human
lifespan as a species for us is about 150 years, even if we argue, even if there's 122 somewhere.
And so I'm not sure. So this, and we die before the age of 80. So we're talking about 35 years
that we can realize it's a lot of years. We should realize that, but I think aging will improve by
other methods and mechanism that can break eventually this 115 years and maybe get us to 150.
The experiment, the experiment, they say, you know, when people are asking me, when will we leave 150?
I said, oh, in 150 years, because even if we start the experiment now, it'll take 150 years
to get there, right? We wouldn't know. So, so of course, this experiment, I don't know what.
I'll tell you what I'm getting at in the experiment. I want to understand how in the perfect genetic
makeup, how much can environment hurt or better? What is already a genetic lottery?
I totally understand. And I would take you back to the, and I meant to ask you that when you
describe that ApoE4 was a 20 fold risk and became smaller and smaller, well, became smaller at whom
and how their lives were different than those that we knew 20 and 40 years ago that have the
ApoE4 genotype, right? Yes, it gets back to the point you raised about your grandfather versus
your father versus you. Right. The environment, both in what we do, both in medical treatment,
in surgery, in all those things. Absolutely. And so you're right. We think that there are
master switch to longevity and some of them we're doing with exercise and food, right?
So you don't really have a sense of how much longer the group three could live than the group
one when you basically put amazing genes in everybody. Yeah. You know, it's not the things
that I'm doing predictions on. No, it's just, it's interesting to me because where I'm really going
at a macro level is most people don't have these genes. So the only interesting question is the
contrapositive of that, which is once you have a sense of what that could be now for the rest of
us, the 9,000, 9,999 of us who don't have centenarian genes, how much does environment make a
difference? And I know the answer is significant, but I'm curious as to how much you think that
is. For me, it's more, you know, some centenarians are coming to me and said, okay,
what can you do for me? And I'm like, you're it. I don't do anything for you. So, so, so for me,
the question, if those centenarians are willing and I'm starting to exercise them and to change
their diet, am I going to kill them or, or, or, or help them? And I really, that's how I'm thinking
about it. And I don't know the answer. Fair enough. So Thomas Pearls has written quite a bit about
this idea of dividing centenarians into buckets. I think we have the escapers, the delayers and the
survivors. Are you familiar with that terminology? Yeah, yeah, of course. But you know,
I'll tell you two things about it. First of all, Tom Pearls and Paolo Sebastiani are,
did terrific job and we're collaborating a lot and, and, and, and they've been great. And I,
I don't hear Tom talking about it because this is the point. Some people,
average life expectancy is 80, right? Some people are going to be 81, 80 to 83. It's not that 100
years old is any special. You're picking at one time people who actually aged before or will age
later. And what we've done together to kind of overcome that is, and that's very important thing.
We looked at our data in both studies and harmonized them and asked what is the health span
of centenarians versus by the way, cohort that lives now. It's not their cohort, their cohort died
before. And the answer is that it's not only that they live long, they get variety of age related
disease. 20, 30 years later, the people, the people, there are control group by age between 60 and 80
accumulate lots of diseases at 80. Only 10% of them don't have a disease in our centenarians
at after the age of 130% don't have a disease and are not treated with anything. But, but there's a
20, 30 years of health span. This is not really the important part, the important part that it's the
end of their life. They get sick and die. Some of them don't wake up in the morning. Okay. But they
have such a compression of morbidity. They are sick for months at the end of their life, unlike us
that are sick for years at the end of our lives. And I think this is, this is really the boundaries.
And so first of all, there is an example. There's example of humans that can live healthy and long
and have contraction of morbidity. And for me, it really says it's not that they didn't get older,
of course they got older, but at some point, they had great life, they have great health. And at some
point, they're checking out much quicker without diseases at the end of their lives. And this is
what we're trying to imitate. I completely agree. Although I'll throw a wrinkle into it near, which
is, could it be that, you know, the average person has their first heart attack at 70,
languishes with congestive heart failure for five years and dies at 75. The centenarian has their
first heart attack at 101. And, you know, they die six months later. Could it be that the reason that
the first guy languished for five years is he really technically had more resilience, given that
he was 25 years younger. And if so, you can now do a very grim thought experiment, which is,
we could easily replicate the health span, we could easily replicate the contraction of morbidity
and non-centenarians with a rule that says the moment you get a disease, you can't get a disease
you get a pillow over the head. Right? The moment you get your first heart attack, we're not going
to cat you, we're going to kill you. Right? I mean, I get a thought experiment, please, let's be clear.
But you would, you would immediately square everybody's longevity curve. For the most part,
you would contract that period of morbidity to replicate that of the centenarians, but you would
dramatically truncate lifespan as well now. And now you would even widen the gap between the
non-centenarian and the centenarian. So in my mind, it's been, it's very difficult to disentangle
the, the, the objective for someone like me, which is, I do want to lengthen lifespan, I do want to
delay the onset of chronic disease. And I want to compress the period of morbidity, not by having
you die quicker, but by having you live better, longer, if that makes sense. Absolutely. It makes
sense, Peter. And of course, your, your point is very important, but it's like, it's like the
podcast last week on the, on the COVID, you had a scientist and the advocates, right? That's how
you call them the scientists and advocates, which by the way, our mutual friend, David Allison,
that's, he was really the one who I think made me first realize we need to talk about these two
things totally separately. Absolutely true. And, and, and what you did, you really stopped me from
being advocate because you're absolutely right. I think that the reason that centenarians are dying
so fast is because they are already frail, they are aging, and so they are less resilient. But
on the other hand, without diseases, I mean, some of them are working as hedge fund managers until
107. Some of them are painting, as long as they have no pain and mobility, their life is good,
not like when they were 20, but their life is good. So I totally agree. But as an advocate,
I wanted to hide that, Peter, I didn't want to, but, but, but you're right. Why, why they are dying?
But you know what, I think it's still important for people. And I think this concept is probably true.
If you prevent aging and age related disease, you're going to compress morbidity too. One of
the biggest challenges I have with health span is I don't think that that we have great ways of
describing this in medicine. I think there's several issues with it. The first is our definitions,
I think, are not wonderful, right? We talk about freedom from disability and disease,
but that doesn't really capture it. I can tell you a lot of people who don't qualify for having
disability or disease, but their health span is still poor. And by the way, this gets, this
completely excludes a very important element of health span, which I think is emotional health.
So let's put that aside because it's not particularly age dependent. And it's, it's outside
of the purview, what we're talking about today. But if you just limit it to physical and cognitive,
in fact, if you just limit it to physical, right, you can, you can have people who can still carry
on activities of daily living, but one of them has a VO two max of 50 mils per minute per gig.
And the other is 30 mils per minute per gig. By the way, neither of those people would ever qualify
as disabled, because whether you're at 30 or 50 in VO two max, you can still do any activity of
daily living. But one of those people can clearly get more out of life, right? You can take someone
who can, you know, has the grip strength to hang on to a bar for 30 seconds versus hang on to a bar
for two minutes. Both of those people will see no immediate difference in their day to day activities,
but one person can do far more should they choose to, you know, one person can sit on the floor for
half an hour and play with kids and feel nothing. Another person, their back will ache for the rest
of the day. Neither of those people are debilitated or disabled. And therefore, health by health span,
you know, by traditional health span metrics, they're both equal, but they're nowhere near equal.
And so that's problem one that I have with the way we as a community talk about health span. The second
thing is nothing that you or I learned in our medical training even remotely prepares us for
how to help people be truly stronger late in life. It just wasn't part of our training, right? Like
there's nothing about that. So I guess my point here is it's hard for me to really interpret the
data and get at something I'm very interested in, which is do centenarians truly have better health
span or are they just dying later? And, you know, for the most part, they have this period of
compressed morbidity. So it looks like they have better health span. But do we really know that,
I mean, I think they do based on the literature, like I think a 90 year old who will become a
centenarian is functioning more like a 70 year old who will not. But it's still very difficult to
quantify. I don't think we have great metrics here. Do you disagree with me? No, I don't think that
health span is well defined. Definitely. But there so there so there are two comments that I will make
for the NIH right back to TAA. For them, what is aging is if we can prevent diseases,
that's their measurements, right? Which is not satisfying, not to geriatrician and not to
physician. OK, but that's how you get drug approved. For the economist, there are two issues.
One is what we're counting as the cost of medical cost, the medical cost of the last two years of
life. By the way, in centenarians, the CDC has data in centenarians, the last two years life
are third the cost in 100 years old and when you die in 70. OK. That is fascinating. I mean, to me,
that is something that speaks to what we're really aspiring to. And actually, that statistic
captures much more about the quality of a person's life. Right. But the David, sorry, Andrew Scott
had a paper in nature. I think I read it. Yes, he sent it to me. And he describes an economical term
that's called the value. And by the way, it's very hard if you want to know more about this paper,
we should talk. It's it. I had to sit with him in order to understand what he was saying, but
basically saying, hey, if you increase the health span of someone, it's not only medical cost,
because this guy is going to travel and spend money traveling and buy gadgets and buy houses
for his kids. You know, it's going to be their value of the person life is going to be increased.
And all of a sudden and some of those people, by the way, are going to still work. Exactly. Right.
They're not just playing golf. Right. So the economical value is is is is huge. So you can
do it economically. And the third thing I wanted to tell you is this story
about the real story about this hundred and two year old guy that I met. And I'm sitting and
talking with him and he's the nicest guy I've ever met. OK, he's so considerate. He's so he's
thinking about life in such a nice way. Nothing bad about his daughter-in-law. Right. And and so
I'm spending time with him. I'm going out of the room and I'm bumping into his son, who's 80
years old. Right. Yeah. And I'm telling this 80 years old what I'm telling you, you know, your
father is just the nicest guy I've ever met. So he looks in my eyes and says, you should have seen
the son of a bitch when he was my age. He was a terrible, terrible person. So then I realize and
you'll see why it's connected to what you just told me. Then I realized that because we wrote
paper about the personality of centenarians and you have to be positive and stuff like that. But
apparently he became positive only when he was already years old, not when he was 80 years old.
And then then you see papers like in University of Pennsylvania, they took two groups of people,
young and old people and show them bed slides, you know, cockroaches in pizza and good slides
like islands in the Caribbean. And they asked them to repeat what they've seen. And the young people
knew, remembered a lot from both bad and good. The old people remember less, but mainly the good
things. OK, so I'm waiting for this part in my physiology that I remember only the good thing.
But what I'm telling you is that think of the complexity now, right? Because your brain age,
you also retired, you lost your spouse, you moved from independence or you moved to somewhere else,
you moved several times, you get to 100 years old. So apparently there's changes not only in your
environment, but in your physiology where life can still look good to you. Is this wrong?
Actually, that's such an interesting point near. I know you mentioned already that a number of the
centenarians in your cohort were not married. What fraction were married?
No, my centenarians have to have offspring.
OK, so all of them were at least had a partner.
At least married for a while.
OK, and then what fraction of them have lost their spouse?
A lot of them, a lot of them, most of them, most of them. We do have.
And sorry, one other question here. What fraction of them have also lost children?
Also a lot of them.
This gets to something very interesting. Someone asked me once at a dinner party,
if you could wave a magic wand, how long would you want to live?
And I said, not that long, truthfully, because unless I could wave that magic
wand for the people around me, I think it would be an awful life.
Could you imagine if I waved a wand and said near, you have immortality and not just
immortality. I'm going to let you preserve your quality of life today.
So as smart and healthy and able as you are now, I'm going to let you do this for the next 500 years.
I would view that as an awful curse. Think of, you know, you'd have to watch your wife die.
You'd have to watch your children die, your grandchildren die. Sure, you could remarry and
do it all over again, but then they're going to die. So, you know, that's a silly thought
experiment, but I also think it gets to something I've never really considered with
respect to actual centenarians, which is the price of being a centenarian is giving up and losing
most of your friends. Right.
And how many funerals do you go to?
The most common thing that centenarian tells me, the thing that underlined their age is when
the children of their friends were long gone, the children of their friends started to die.
That's for them, kind of what's going on. We're losing now the second generation. You know,
what's coming next. You're absolutely right. I'm thinking about it for immortalists, right?
So immortalists, they have 12 billion years. We don't know, but one of the estimates,
12 billion years for this planet. I'm a little tired from some of the shit now.
Really, 12 billion years, January 6th. I don't know, you know, wars and stuff.
It's true. But what I try to tell you in a different words is that those centenarians
have been adapting not only because what got them to be centenarians, but because of physiology
of aging that allowed them to harbor and maybe to put in compartments, lots of their stuff.
Yeah, lots of grief.
And it's not that you come to centenarians and they want to tell you, first of all,
about the spouse that they lost. That's not how they are talking to you. They're talking to you
about where they went and what they do and they're going to a concert and their grandchild is coming
to visit them. At least the centenarian, you know, it's the centenarians in my study, right?
So it's not all.
Look, NetNet, I think living to 100 with preserved health span would be a wonderful thing. And even
if it meant you lost a spouse, a child, it means you probably have three generations of people you
know. One of the questions I love asking my patients is how many of your great grandparents
can you name? So we all have eight great grandparents and I say, tell me the names of them.
I've only had one patient who could tell me two of them. Most people can't tell me a thing about one.
I can't. I didn't even meet two of my grandparents. They died, you know, so young.
So if you think about that for a moment, and the reason I ask my patients this, by the way,
it has nothing to do with living longer. It's more about living better. It's basically,
it's a way to remind everyone, myself included, that we're not that important. Like, no matter,
you know what I mean? Like my point being is my great grandchildren will never know who I am.
Maybe in the age where they have video, they'll see a video of me or something, but like I'm not
going to be an important part of their life. Meaning the only people who I matter to,
are very narrow and close to me now. So let's not lose sight of that.
But these centenarians have a gift, right? Which is their great grandchildren will know them. And
when you use this example, when you can go to concerts with your great grandchildren,
that's amazing. When you could take a vacation with your great grandchild, and you're not only
able to give them money for college, but you go to their graduation, think about the implication
of how much of their life you've been a part of. So the flip side of everything I just said is,
I've never really met somebody who's dying at the age of 75. And that's a phenotype I've seen an
awful lot in my training, who didn't wish to have another year of life. It could, if it could be had
at a higher quality, which now brings this whole discussion full circle. 9999 out of 10,000 of us
will not live to 100, directionally speaking. But if we want to live an extra year, or five years,
what is the most important lesson we can take away from the centenarian?
That we can actually do something about. I want to start with what you mentioned before,
one of my darkest day in research, when Jay Leno in the Tonight Show said, you know, there's those
people at Einstein and they said the secret for longevity is don't exercise, don't, you know,
be obese, don't do. And you know what he said, if you die, you don't care anyhow. Right. And,
and that was the wrong lesson from the centenarian study. If you, if you're going to be centenarian,
maybe it's not important. By the way, it could be important for centenarians. Right. I mean,
this woman that I have that smoked for 90 years and died at 110, I just wonder, wouldn't she be
the next Madame Clement without smoking? So the lesson for most of us is still, right, exercise
and nutrition, whatever it means to everyone and everything else that you give, right? That's,
that's the lesson. And it's not the lesson from centenarians. The lesson from centenarians is that
there are longevity genes that could be translated into drugs. And I believe that they could afford
years of health spend, however we want to define that. And, and, and, and, and that's really what
I'm trying to, to say that is not an emotional part, but, but a clinical part. Would you agree
with my takeaway from this cohort, which is the, because the single most important lesson I glean
from everything we've said, and in addition to lots that we haven't said that you and I have talked
about elsewhere or that my own work has, you know, pointed me to based on my study of this problem,
their superpower is simply delaying the onset of bad things. Like bad things just happen to them
20 to 25 years later. So it's not that they don't get heart attacks. They just don't get them when
they're 65. It's not that they don't get cancer. They just don't get it when they're 60. It's not
that they don't even get dementia. They just don't get it when they're 75. And when the last time I
looked at the distribution of death for centenarians, it was shockingly similar to that of
non-centenarians with a couple of differences. They tended to have a little more atherosclerosis,
a little more heart attacks, a little less Alzheimer's disease, and I think a little bit
more pneumonia. But directionally, they had the same actuarial table of death as people dying in
their 80s. It was just a time shift. In fact, I reviewed the paper from Germany where they looked
at pathology. Okay. It's a pathological. They looked at a thousand centenarians that over the
years died in their homes. And they're right because in the hospitals, we kill them in other
ways. So died in their homes versus thousand. I'm not sure about the numbers of other people
that died at their homes. And basically the paper was funny because the title was like,
there's nothing special about the centenarians. They're dying for the same thing. But 30 years
later, okay, they missed the point. It was like a negative study. But you're right. You're right.
They're kind of dying from the same thing much later, much later on. So you can look at it about
what you said, the resiliency that got them there, the resiliency for anything that detect them to
get them there, or the fact that their aging was slow. And so what's the takeaway for us? To me,
the takeaway for us as physicians or people who want to have an extra five years of life or 10
years of life, even if we can't have an extra 20, is nothing matters more than prevention of
chronic disease. And by the way, you don't get to prevent it once you have your heart attack.
Secondary prevention is not prevention. We're talking ultra, ultra, ultra primary prevention.
And if health span is something that the medical system hasn't been poised to teach, ultra primary
prevention is also something that we haven't really been prepared to teach. So okay, let's
pivot to another topic that we visited last time. But I think so much has happened in the interim,
which is metformin. I probably get an equal number of questions near about the following three things.
So the frequency of this would be several times a week, a patient or a friend is asking me about
metformin, rapamycin, or some combination of NR, NAD, or NMN. Somehow those three things seem to
rise to the level of everybody's curiosity when it comes to Giro protection. Let's talk a little
bit about all of them. But let's focus on metformin. So for folks coming to this who
have heard of metformin, because I think at this point, many people have, but don't know much more
than that. Can you give a brief background of what metformin is? How long it's been around,
what it's historically been used for? And then of course, we'll talk a little bit more about why
we're going to talk about it. Oh, so boring. I also get those questions. What's the distribution,
by the way, what do you mostly get asked about while we're on that subject? The most common
question is, I hear you're doing metformin study. Can I volunteer? Can I be, can you assure me I'm
not on placebo? Yeah, I was just about to say, are you sure you want to volunteer? Okay. So,
so, by the way, I'll tell you something really interesting. I'm not, because I'm leading this
study, I'm not pushing metformin. Okay. Again, the difference between advocate and scientist,
okay. I'm doing this study. Okay. I believe in that, but I'm doing this study. So, I cannot tell
you that it's good. So, I'm not going to prescribe to anyone, even to my friends. I'm not going to
prescribe, but I have a method that works 100% of the time. There are two papers that I wrote,
one, I think in 2016 about metformin and TAME and the clinical data, and one in 2020 about actually
the mechanisms of action that was in cell, both of them were in cell metabolism, but the mechanism
of action, the fact that metformin actually hits all the hallmarks of aging, miraculously. I'll
explain it later. And I'm saying to those people, send it to your doctors and say, I asked the doctor,
what do you think about me taking metformin? And they're one of two things that always happen.
One could be that the doctors read the paper and said, oh shit, I should be on metformin myself.
Of course, I'll give metformin. Or the other is the doctor said, you know, I'm busy, but you know,
metformin is a safe drug and stuff. Let me just give them metformin. And that's the end of that.
And that's 100% success. Everybody can get metformin. Now I know that I'll get emails asking
for those papers. I'll put it in a box. We will absolutely link to those papers in the show notes.
But I think what people don't realize is that metformin is an extract of the French lilac. So
some people say it's nutraceutical. It is modified and it is a drug.
The three best drugs in the world are nutraceuticals, rapamycin, statins, metformin. There you go.
Right. But you need prescriptions. But also, look, one of the modifications was
metformin. It's an early form of metformin that kind of was a little too potent.
Too potent on the mitochondria and caused the trouble. But we're over that for 80 years.
But metformin was used initially to treat the flu and malaria and inflammatory diseases.
And it's at that time that people noticed that people with type 2 diabetes have lower glucose
when they took metformin. So the whole metformin moved to diabetes.
And that was about the 1950s or 60s, right?
Right. 1950s and 60s. Interestingly, in the United States, it was approved only in 1993 or so.
I came as a fellow to Ralph de Frontso at Yale. And my mission was to describe the
metformin, the mechanisms of action of metformin in humans. You know, I did insulin clamps and I'm
the first to describe that metformin decreased the patix-lose production rather than increased insulin
sensitivity in the periphery. It's serendipitous. I didn't think about it as aging. I came to Ralph
de Frontso and I did aging in another way to insulin resistant and aging, but not metformin.
But the point is there are billions, billions years of use. Remember, every patient takes it
for years and there are people on metformin who are 90 years old. I actually know them.
So people, there are billions use of year and I cannot think of a drug with better safety record.
If there are any side effects to metformin, they happen usually in the first week of use.
And that's even if you didn't take them the way you should, which is small doses with food.
And when I say with food after the first bite, when your stomach is full and then usually there
is no side effects, but three to 5% of people and maybe more with elderly have diarrhea that
doesn't stop. And we basically stop metformin in those people, whether there's, well,
yeah, to stop diarrhea. We don't know if there is something. By the way, in TAME study,
we're going to follow those patients that were sensitive to metformin and see if there's
something unique about them. That's one of the things we hope to do.
Well, we're definitely going to talk about TAME. So let's pick up the story 10 years ago.
All of a sudden, people start to notice things. People start to notice that diabetics who take
metformin when compared to diabetics who don't take metformin do better. And when I say do better,
I mean they have lower mortality from all causes and lower mortality from very specific causes.
And if you look at it in some extremes, if you compare the patients taking metformin
to the patients taking insulin, the difference could be 50, 80% difference in mortality.
Is that a fair assessment of where curiosity began to peak that this wasn't just a good
diabetes drug, but it might have some protection against aging?
Yes, absolutely. When one drug, we should just know that's the base of
gerotherapeutic. It has to be a drug that has effect beyond its disease, whether it's on other
diseases, whether it's on overall mortality, not a disease-specific mortality. That's when you have
to think this drug is a gerotherapeutics. And that's exactly where metformin fell.
And I would just add one thing. Look, some of those studies are association studies,
but some of the studies were clinical studies. The diabetes prevention program, the DPP,
is an NIH-funded study where metformin was one arm. There was also an arm of lifestyle changes.
Both of them were preventing diabetes in about 30%. And by the way, the study was stopped early
because it was significant after four years, although the study was funded for five years.
The UKPDS and many studies-
No, I do want to talk about that study near, and some of this, of course, you and I have
already talked about, but I think it's just good for people to be able to hear our discussions on
this. One of the challenges of these studies, and I think this is frankly true of every single
study I've looked at for metformin, is when you squint your eye at the study, there's always a
problem. And in the case of the DPP, the problem is the patients in the metformin arm could easily
fall out of that arm and therefore not be counted. So if they progressed to a need for medication
beyond metformin, or if they couldn't tolerate metformin, or if they were not compliant with
metformin, they were no longer counted. And so when you compare, and this is true not just of the DPP,
but of course, when you compare the metformin patients to the other patients who are taking
other diabetes drugs, you always have this potential confounder, which is you are
disproportionately selecting the healthiest people, which are the people who, A, can be
compliant with medications, which might say much more about their behaviors outside of medications,
whose diabetes is maybe just mild enough that it's always kept at bay with metformin,
never requiring other medications, including insulin. So am I correct in saying we don't,
to date, and tame we will talk about in a moment, but we don't to date have any clean example of a
study that demonstrates metformins, zero protection. Look, you're right. You can say it on many studies,
but it's certainly true with diabetes. Diabetes is a problem because it's a progressive disease,
no matter what. And you can go and go back to the data and show whether the people were metforming
from the beginning versus other have done better and whether it stops. And there's a lot of things.
But first of all, you're right. You're also right about we had this discussion about the mortality
data, and you pointed out that maybe the control, we're not controlled enough for getting them out
for some reason. You watch them all the time. You're absolutely right. Even the clinical
studies are not perfect studies, but there are still enough of clinical studies or small studies
that gives you the confidence. So for example, there are two studies on people with mild cognitive
impairment that were treated with metformin, one for half a year and one for one year. And some of
the outcomes have changed. And there is no difference in how they were treated. In other
words, they didn't have diabetes, so it's not that they switched to other medications. So there are
lots of examples like that. But you're right. If this was compelling on its own, you could argue we
wouldn't have to have TAME even, right? And really, TAME is not that there were not studies for each
one of the diseases, but there were no studies to be agnostic of the diseases. We don't care. Look,
we're targeting aging. We don't care what disease you have. And we don't care which disease you're
going to take to get. If you're obese and your mother's diabetes, you're going to get diabetes
next. We have to think in neuroscience that aging is going to drive your next disease. And therefore
it's the cluster that is going to count. And we're counting the clusters. By the way,
we had this discussion about mortality. Mortality, you get a point for mortality,
just like you get a point for a disease. And the important thing of the cluster
is that we cannot do TAME study. Imagine we do a TAME study, and in two years,
cardiovascular disease comes up as significant. As in significant reduction of cardiovascular
mortality. And the FDA will say, hey, we have to stop the study because we cannot go with the
study when with placebo, right? And it will ruin it for us. So the whole problem of the statistics
of TAME is to make sure that we're not getting to any significance in any disease, just to trends.
And the only way to stop, by the way, the one way to stop the study is if mortality is significant.
That will trigger a stoppage of the study. Otherwise, what will stop the study is the integral
approach of the cluster. Right. So statistically, you just can't, your biggest mistake here is
overpowering the study for mortality. And therefore, appropriately powering the study
for subs, subsets of mortality. Yes. Is that is that a safe assessment?
Subsets of mortality, you mean diseases. Disease specific mortality is what I mean. Yes.
Well, let's talk a little bit about TAME. This is something you and I spoke about,
God, two years ago. So this is a study that is going to look at people who do not have type 2
diabetes. Right. It's an exclusion criteria. And they are over the age of 65? 65 to 79.
Okay, so 65 to 79. No diabetes, no type 2 diabetes, any other exclusion criteria?
Yes, but it's not important for our discussion. So if you have cancer in the last year,
okay, things like that. Yeah, very specific. If you had the heart attack in the last three months.
But again, these people are going to be taking statins, they're going to be taking medication
for blood pressure, some of them will be overweight, some of them will be normal weight, presumably.
Right. The point the point here, though, is that, look, we don't want to recruit a bunch of
centenarians to get in our study. You don't want to be you don't want to recruit future centenarians here.
You're not going to get an answer. So they have to have something, okay, they have to have,
for example, walking speed less than six meter, you know, per second is is an inclusion criteria.
You have to have something. I see. So you don't want you don't want exceptionally fit people in
this group. Right. You know, it's almost like you want to take the patient population that
PredaMed started with, because this was a primary prevention study for cardiovascular disease
that found a statistical significant difference in under five years, I think it was four and a half
years, they expected to go for seven. So so it's you're really looking for that type of population,
you you really do want people who are going to I mean, it's morbid to say this, but you're looking
for people whose risk of death in the next five years is is high enough that you're going to move
the needle. Now, the the risk of that is you get a negative study, which means there is no difference
in all cause mortality, or even disease specific mortality. And the counter argument might be you
started too late. You know, that's like applying the brakes on a car that's driving towards a cliff
when it's only 20 feet from the cliff. Should this be a lot longer study, where you start this at
people when they're 50. And your your five year mortality expectation is very low. Again, I'm not
saying this can be done, because that's a very expensive study, but it is a risk here. Correct.
There are two arguments here. You know, first of all, we needed to do look to start to start a study
at 50, where you have to show mortality is a 20 year study, we cannot afford it, right. So we needed
to start it when people are starting to accumulate disease in order for us to have lots of events.
Our hypothesis is that the the aging part of your biology doesn't stop working when you had your
first disease, it's still going to get your next disease. Okay. And if we think biologically like
that, we should be able to intervene, as we do with animals quite late also. So that's that's one
thing. The second thing is, there are metformin studies which included elderly people, for example,
the DPP, the DPP, by the way, got 20% funding from the NIA in order to include 20% of the subjects
over the age of 65, which they didn't, they had 20% over the age of 60, but there's still people
over the age of 65. And their results were similar in prevention diabetes to younger people. So it's
an example, but we have several other studies that tells us that metformin will still target aging,
even if you started it, it's not it's not that the first disease canceled. Yeah, it just means
that you have a lower period to apply the brakes on. And it suggests that if if tame shows a
reduction in all cause mortality in a subset of people so old, in quotes, because when I say so
old, meaning in five years is really what I'm saying. It would suggest biologically that there
would be a benefit to starting sooner. But of course, then the question goes back to our original
discussion, how soon? So Peter, you you you said an end point of mortality in tame. There could be
only trend of mortality. So I'm sorry, I misunderstood. What is what is the primary
outcome of tame? It's the cluster of bunch of cardiovascular cancer, cognitive and mortality.
It's the cluster. Okay, you get one point for each one. I see. So let's define them again. So
you get one point if you die. Right. For everyone. You get one point if you have a major adverse
cardiac event. Right. One point if you have a cancer occurrence or recurrence cancer, right.
And an MCI or dementia. Got it. Do you have any points for health span outcomes such as frailty,
falling, breaking hips? This is in the 70 million program. Okay. So let me explain. We would like
to start longitudinal study where we capture a lot of the other health span issues, you know,
hospitalization and function and depression and all that. And we are still powered to do it at the
end of the study or as the study goes on, we probably wouldn't have money to do it longitudinally
through the whole study. But we have power at the end of the study to see if there are difference in
frailty, etc. Just a statistical question. Why is mortality given equal weighting to disease
occurrence? Is there a reason that mortality wouldn't be three points to one point for MCI,
mace and cancer? Well, it was question for each one of them. And we decided just that
we cannot rationalize that everyone is an outcome. You know, we basically said those are the outcomes.
We don't know which one you're going, you're going to get an outcome, you're going to get the point
for that. All right. It's by the way, it's the time until of course, right? Yeah. You're moving,
you're moving health, health span. Now earlier you spoke about how animal models are not really
great for Alzheimer's disease, cancer and cardiovascular disease, which I think any
listener of this podcast is well aware of those limitations. But you note that look, animal models
are pretty darn good for aging, given how conserved it is. And yet one of the challenges
metformin has had is in animal models. Now, Rich Miller was on this podcast a while ago. We spoke
about the ITP where metformin was successful in the ITP when combined with rapamycin, but alone
was not. Again, I think the ITP is a very rigorous type of experiment. I know you've
probably thought a lot about this. What explanation do you think exists for why
metformin did not succeed in isolation in the ITP study, which I'll just take for a moment to explain
to people the ITP. If you haven't listened to that podcast with Rich Miller, you should go and do so.
We'll link to the appropriate section here. But these are studies that are conducted using
a particularly good model of mouse that is kind of less troubled by the usual difficulties mice
studies have. It's also done independently at three separate laboratories concurrently. So I
think those would be some of the... And then the final thing is they look at all-cause mortality.
So tell us why you think that we could be misled by the ITP.
Let me make a big picture statement now. It is possible that some of the drugs that had mild
effect in ITP will have much bigger effect in humans. And vice versa. Maybe rapamycin is going
to be not as effective in humans as it is in animals. We just have to accept that we're all
Rich Miller if it's not true in mice, it's not true. Well, I don't think Rich says, by the way.
I've never heard Rich say that. I think Rich just says, this is what it is in this model.
I'm kidding. He started saying that initially and he took it back, of course.
I think one of the problems with animals is the dosage that they are using.
The dosage in animal where you were used, if you look back, as 0.1% in a solution to 1%.
1% is deadly. Because, listen, metformin, after all, is a weak cyanide.
Okay. It binds to a complex in the mitochondria. It probably affects complex one and also complex
three. It's not totally clear, but if you give too much, there is a trade-off. So you have to give
right. And I think that the studies in animals, except, by the way, mice, it's not true for
nematodes and there are several other fish. There are several other animals that live longer,
and healthier with metformin. But I don't think that 0.1% is really the appropriate dose.
What do you think is the... So you think...
I don't know. I don't know. There's no dose response.
But you were saying 1% is clearly problematic.
Yeah. I think 0.2% maybe will be better if we want to optimize that.
Because there's a paper that gets a lot of attention. I think it's 2013, the Raphael
Di Cabo paper, which gets touted as, oh, look at metformin. I got to be honest with you.
If you look at that paper, I don't know how the editors let the title of that paper slide with
the actual data. I mean, let's call a spade a spade. You had two groups of mice, one of them
getting 0.1%, one of them getting 1%. The group getting 1% were assassinated, to your point.
These animals were killed by the toxicity of metformin. The group getting 0.1%
lived a staggering 4% longer. Right.
It was basically a null trial that was touted as the definitive animal study for why metformin
works. It was kind of like... It's like an Onion article when you dissociate the title from the
actual data. Right. Look, the average when I took and make a table with all the longevity data,
then the effect of metformin across studies were between 7% and 10%, not a huge effect.
Well, that's pretty good. 7% to 10% in animal studies, if it's consistent, would be pretty good.
But the effect, the nice thing with metformin, the effects on healthspan is much...
What are the healthspan effects besides the metabolic effects?
Cancer. Say more. Prevention of cancers.
But isn't that effectively already captured in lifespan?
Rich Miller will give you a better thing. I mean, animals... Look, the problem for us with animals
is... By the way, it's the problem with centenarians also. They die with cancers. We don't know if they
die from cancer. They die from cancers. Right. It's like the prostate cancer issue.
Right. Cancer is several... As much as we say in humans, it's cardiovascular disease. Cancer is
probably the leading disease for that for animals. And it's true. For sure. So the other point is...
Which I think I'm trying to get to the bottom of that, but when you gave metformin to animals in
the ITP, in two centers, they had 10%. One was 11% and one was 9% increase in longevity.
But Rich Miller's point was minus 2%. And I just wonder if they're all actually delivering the same
dose and what's going on. I mean, do you think that...
So it wasn't significant, but it actually was... In two centers, there was a 10% effect.
Yeah. There's always an issue that could be methodologic. Do you think that the animal
studies in metformin are largely irrelevant once we have tame underway? I mean, one of the reasons
that we rely so heavily on all of the animal data for rapamycin and why the ITP, which has studied
rapamycin five ways to Sunday, starting at late in life, starting at early in life, high dose,
low dose, pulsing it, not pulsing it, continuous. I mean, every way you study it, rapamycin works.
And we have to look at that and really pay attention to it because I don't think we're
going to get the human trial of rapamycin. I don't know that we're going to get the tame equivalent
of rapamycin. And if we are, it's not going to be for some time. But now that we're moving to
a human clinical trial of metformin, should we even care about this question in mice?
Does it matter if it's 0.1% or 0.2%? No, I don't think, what I'm saying is that the preliminary
data from humans overall, right, as you said, there are problems everywhere. But you know,
it's the same story. It's a 20, 30% effect on each study, no matter how you look at it. It's a really
very impressive studies, and there's no better studies that came with different results. So
I think once tame is there, tame is there. I don't know that we need to go into animal studies and
discover more about metformin at this time. Will tame allow you, on its current budget,
which I think is 50 million, is the bare bones budget. Sounds crazy, right? On the 50 million
dollar budget, how much will you be able to look at mitochondrial function and omics that are
associated with other, you know, deeper markers that go beyond the hard outcomes that feed into
your primary outcome? Well, the NIA has given us a grant that is now delayed to do basically the
biomarker part of tame. So even with this 50 million and with the NIH money and with the IFAAR,
we're going to store lots of plasma, DNA, and other resources like cells and other things
that will then be open for omics studies. And we wrote a beautiful grant about that. In part,
it was preliminary data from our centenarian studies on proteomics. By the way, I just realized
I used the word omics. Do you want to tell people what the full suite of omics means
so that people listening to this know what we're talking about? Yeah. And it's really back to
something that I said before when I talk about, if I said my study, I mean our study. And when I
talk about teams, I'm talking about teams that have computational capacity. I talked about
Zeng Dong-Deng that did a lot of my study about Yuxing Su that is doing functional genetics. I'm
talking about Sophia Millman who are doing other studies. We're really big team. And the reason
to have a big team is very simple. We have, you know, I was, all I knew when I started my training
was insulin. I knew insulin. I know insulin signaling. Now I'm losing at billions of data
set that are under my teeth. If you think of genetics only, whole exome sequencing for 3,000
people, or my proteomics, which is 5,000 protein for 1,000 people, it's all big data. And in order
to do something with the big data, you have to ask the right questions because what we know is
the first paper that came out of the UK Biobank for Aging said that longevity is all about
assortative mating. Okay. Now, yes, if you're a smoker, you may marry a smoker. If you're a beast,
you will marry obese. If you're poor, you will marry poor. It all has consequence of health.
But we knew that without the UK Biobank, we knew that obesity is a risk for diabetes without the
Biobank too. So you have to ask the right question. And it's really only asking the right question
that you get the answer. So the question that is very important for us, there are two questions.
What are the biomarkers for aging? How can we do a test at 50 years old and know if we're 40 or we're
60? If we're 40, we skip colonoscopy. Okay. If we're 60, we have to do something about it already.
And the second part, and it's more important for me, is biomarkers that change with treatment.
We want to make sure that we, when we try all those treatments that we have in two, three months
and answer, are they likely to work? And then maybe we can get to phase two and phase three trial,
but we need something more immediate. And that's what TAME will try to provide. Now, in my study,
we did this proteomic and it was really incredible for many reasons, and I'll give you a tit beat,
but we have those thousand people and 5,000 proteins. And we asked what changed between 65,
the ages 65 and 95. This didn't include our centenarians. And the answer is a lot of proteins
are changing, but this is, I think, the most important part. A lot of the proteins that we're
capturing, by the way, number one is IGF related proteins. Okay. Number one that comes up even in
the proteomic, not only in the genomics, but then a lot of what you see is breakdown. You see
breakdown of collagen, you see degranulation of the thrombocytes, you see breakdown of extracellular
metrics, lots of things like that. And at first I said, okay, that doesn't tell me anything until I
thought, you know, whatever it is, no matter what we do, we have to stop the breakdown. You know,
this is probably going to be the best marker for any treatment. You just stop the breakdown.
It's funny, that seems so obvious, doesn't it? I mean, like it's when you're talking about
collagen breakdown and you think about this gets back to what we talked about earlier, you want to
really know what health span is. It's not some nonsense definition that the NIA gives us about
freedom from disability and disease. Who cares? Who cares if you have cancer, but you're living
in remission with it and you can climb three flights of stairs with a bag of groceries in
your hands. That's living, right? It's yeah, when your collagen is breaking down, your knees aren't
working. I mean, this is the essence of what we're talking about. Right, right. I think the proteomic
story is very interesting and I hope it gets its appropriate funding. And by the way, the other part
of proteomics, there are a few other aspects that are important. The proteomics that are the proteins
that are 10 to the minus 80 significance, the two top ones, when you express them in animal, they
live long. In other words, they're protective protein. When you get those proteins, you don't
know which are protective and which are causing problems. And that's a challenge because we are
saying, let's bring it to normal. No, you don't want to lower the protective mechanism. The third
thing that is really cool is the proton of females is much more stable. In other words, it's only half
of the proteins are significantly changing in women than in men between those ages. So you'd need to
look at actually different biomarkers for women and men. And by the way, this is something,
this was Eureka moment for all of us. From ITP and on, female and males have different biology as far
as aging. Some of the geotherapeutics both work for both like metformin and rapamycin, maybe not
equally, but work for both and some are not. Yeah, look at the 17 alpha estradiol, 17 beta
estradiol. I mean, that's a remarkable story. And then the last thing that is interesting,
those thousand people that I had, 500 are what we called opus. They are offspring of parents with
usual survival, no longevity in the family. And one are opal, offspring of parents with
exceptional longevity. The offspring of parents with exceptional longevity have half of the
biomarkers of the control group because they're younger, they'll get those biomarkers later. So
I think, look, I don't know that methylation is going to be the best biomarker for treatment.
I think methylations are complicated. They're kind of stable. They are going up, they're going
down, but they're kind of stable. I think proteomic is going to be a better biomarker. I think
metabolomic is very complicated because it so depends on how you establish the sample. You know,
if somebody was fasting less or more, if their insulin level was less or more, you're done.
That's sort of my problem with these biomarkers is, and you know, I mean, I don't know, you've
probably heard me rail on these biological clocks. I've never seen a worse biomarker than a biological
clock. These are so easy to manipulate and game. In fact, I need to do this just to demonstrate it,
but I'm too lazy, is get five copies of a biologic clock and do five different self-experiments. And
I promise you I can change my biologic age by 20 years. Right? When fasting glucose and vitamin D
level factor into a biologic clock, I'm sorry, that's useless. It might be valuable at the
population level. It is as useful as a warm bucket of hamster vomit at the individual level.
So we have to have things that can't just change on a day to day basis. Your fasting glucose,
the difference between 95 and 105 has everything to do with the meal you had last night, how much
cortisol was coursing through your veins if your water heater broke that night, if you got startled
in the morning when you before you got your blood draw. I mean, I'm just amazed near at the attention.
I'm sorry I'm going off on this tangent, but I'm amazed at the attention that is being given to
these clocks and the entire cottage industry of businesses that are spinning out this type of,
I think this is complete buffoonery. Peter, I have more positive outlook of life,
maybe because I'm so much older than you. So much older, yeah.
But you know, at least it's good for the economy.
Yeah, exactly. Hey, Theranos was good for the economy until it wasn't. Right? No. The other
thing is even with methylation and I thought methylation was very interesting until the
twin astronaut brother experiment. Then I stopped thinking it was very interesting.
Right? Remember you had the twins, right? The one astronaut went to the ISS for a year,
his twin brother stayed down here. You then looked at methylation clocks of them after a year and
they were vastly different. And then three days later, after the twin brother was back on Earth
for three days, they repeated the test and it was right back to his twin brother. Right. I mean,
come on, how biologically relevant can this be when it changes like that? Right. And I think,
have you had Morgan Levine? No. And I do, of course. And I haven't had Steve Horvath on as well.
I've communicated with him a little bit via email and I would certainly love the opportunity to
speak with him about this. But there's probably something interesting there. I'm just having a
hard time seeing that because again, what's the purpose of doing this? We have to never lose sight
of the purpose of biomarkers of aging. It's not so that you have bragging rights that, oh, I just
took this test and it says I'm 37 when I'm 50. No. The only reason you do this test is if it can
guide therapeutics. The only reason you do this test is if it helps you determine if I'm doing
this thing, is it making me better or worse? And my fear is I haven't seen a single test
that is validated at a level that would give me even a modicum of confidence in that. Right.
Right. I mean, I'm saying this in a very deliberately provocative way because I'm
waiting for you to say, oh, no, no, Peter, you need to look at this test. No. So I'm telling you,
I don't want to be a spokesperson. All I'm saying is I don't think a methylation, because it's not
mechanistic, I don't think it's going to help us when we come to gerotherapeutics, even if there
are examples. OK, I don't know what the examples mean, just like the example you gave. I don't
know what it means. Morgan Levine and Steve Horvat, by the way, they're really good and they're
responsible and they understand exactly what they did and what they didn't do. And Morgan Levine has
a mechanistic way of looking at epigenetics. Remind me what the inputs are to the Levine clock.
The way they're moving is so one thing that Morgan Levine is doing is she's saying, well,
if the methylation has a function, then I want to cause methylation and see that there's change
in the expression of those genes. And that those genes are something that we know are relevant to
aging, et cetera, et cetera, and then build a clock that is mechanistic, because the only
way this clock was built was to measure chronological age. Will you guys be using
any of the biologic clocks through tame as well? So what's going to happen with tame is there are
two things. We are going to have a committee that with time and we didn't decide, we're going to do
the right epigenetic test. And by the way, we're going to do epigenetic, not the clock epigenetics,
but enough epigenetic data on a genome, you know, on the genome wide in order to then
discover which are the ones that have changed with treatment. OK, that way.
But it would also be good near to have a clock running in parallel, wouldn't it?
Because if you can do this longitudinally with multiple data points, you sample people every
three to six months with multiple different versions of these clocks. And then you can look
at how well those clocks predicted the actual outcomes you will see over five to seven years.
That strikes me as a very valuable way to get at something that no one is doing today, because,
you know, in other words, take advantage of the fact that you have two things going for you that
nobody has today, which is a very large longitudinal data set with hard outcomes
and an intervention that is relevant and interesting to study.
If we're doing the metallation scan, we can obtain any clock from them. That's the idea.
Yes, that's my point. I mean, you'll have the bio. I'm just saying just make sure you're
collecting all of the data that goes into multiple clocks in a concurrent manner with it,
not just at a time A and time B. Right. And the second point is the NIA is going to have RFA.
Okay, for people who want to have sub projects in relation to what we collected,
those RFAs can be in centers. For example, there's a center that wants to look at skin aging.
Okay. If 250 people are enough, then for a project, then you have a center. If you need 500,
you'll take two centers. In other words, there'll be a process by which application will be reviewed
and people can come in and look at variety of things that they're interested in.
If it's not too late, make some crazy suggestions. And I don't know if this changes your IRB,
but are you going to be doing any bone marrow sampling even at time beginning and end?
Because I'll tell you one of the other things I'd really, really love to see with a study of this
magnitude is are you impacting immune function, specifically memory, T and B cell function?
Obviously, this is a topic that's very interesting in germane to COVID at the moment, but I think it
goes well beyond COVID. And it would be very interesting to know if metformin is having any
impact on immune function, specifically memory function, because it doesn't just play an important
role in infections, it plays a very important role in cancer. So look, the answer is mundane,
we're taking elderly people into a study, we're not going to torture them, we're not going to
have any excuse for them to leave us. It's the same with our centenarians. By the way,
we are in the centenarian, what we're offering the offspring, we're offering MRI of their brain,
we're offering them coronary CT, we're offering things, but we're not doing biopsies. That's in
another study. Are you doing brain MRI and tame? No. Just because of cost? Yeah, look, you could do,
again, we are powered enough to do things eventually, okay? Because it's not going to
happen before and after, we're not going to have everything from before and after.
This is only the things that we have to measure for the outcomes, but we'll have enough power
for anybody to do MRIs in metformin. What about exercise function? Because one of the things I
want to talk about before we leave metformin is the impact metformin may have as a negative impact
on cardiorespiratory fitness. So no, the answer is no. We're not going to have anything like that.
Because of cost? No, because of how much time can you get an elderly to spend time with you
every three months when really what you want to make sure is that they're taking their drugs.
That's why. How many centers? You said 30-3500 subjects? Yeah, well, we have currently before
before we get okay to expand the beat, we have 14 centers and about 250 people in each center.
All in the US? All in the US. I don't know. I mean, I think that would be potentially a
lost opportunity. Not that you have to do CPET testing every three months, but would doing it
every two years be an issue? At a minimum, I would look at fasting lactate levels or resting lactate
levels. You know, everybody has their pet idea for you. Right. Everybody has possession. And
but by no way, I'm saying it's not important. I'm just saying what are we practically ready
because at the end, we want the FDA. Look, let me state it again. I'm doing tame,
not because I don't believe in metformin because I need to have, we need to have
a target that's similar to aging. Okay. That's the reason. So let's talk a little bit about this
other issue, which is, you know, I've talked with you about my experience, right? So I took metformin
for, I don't know, eight years or something like that. But three years ago, when I really began
checking and constantly monitoring my lactate levels, both in and out of exercise,
it became clear to me that my lactate levels were too high. So my fasting lactate level was
typically above one millimole was between one and two millimole. And as a result of that, my
perceived mitochondrial efficiency was lower. And there's ample data to suggest that fasting
lactate level. Now, of course, this is not necessarily in people taking metformin, but if
you take lactate levels in people at rest, there's a high association between what that tells you
about their general health. So the less healthy an individual is the higher their lactate level is.
So for me, I just said, well, boy, there sure, there sure looks like a lot of compelling reasons
why metformin could be beneficial. But if I really stop to look at it, none of the cohorts of people
in whom we would infer that look anything like me, right, these are not people who are exercising
constantly doing all of these other things. So that was the decision for me three years ago,
I'm not going to take metformin anymore until I have better data. So now we have a couple of
studies that have looked at the impact of metformin on cardiorespiratory fitness, and we see that it is
indeed impaired. And then we have studies that look at the impact on metformin of strength
training. And we see a mixed response, we see that it does not appear to impact strength gains,
it only appears to impact hypertrophy. The good news is we know that strength matters more than
hypertrophy in longevity. I had a whole AMA on that, which you probably heard. So I think it was
pretty clear that we can say strength matters more. So what do you make about these potential
limitations with respect to metformin on cardiorespiratory fitness? And what do you think it
says about people who exercise a lot? First of all, I think one point that is very important is
when we go from a drug that has certain capabilities to personalize medicine, and all of a sudden,
it becomes about the person. And I think there's nothing I can say about what you're
observing except that lactate is one of the biomarkers of giving metformin in every patient.
In 1987, when I did the metformin study, metformin went from below one to above one in everyone who
took metformin. Lactate, you mean, yes. Lactate, sorry, what did I say? You said metformin,
yeah, lactate went up in every patient. It's almost a way that in, I hope in TAME,
you are measuring lactate if for no other reason than determine compliance.
Absolutely. By the way, there is a better test. The test is called GDF 15. It's one of those
peptides that goes up with aging. It's a protective peptide. It goes by three and a half fold in people
who take metformin. So there are other ways to look at it. So, okay, but this is the point
with exercise. And let me make the most important point. Okay. We can talk about muscle, but remember,
just like with exercise itself, exercise is not only about muscle. It improves brain function.
Okay. It decreases cancer. Okay. Metformin has many other effects. Okay. So let's remember that
metformin has other effects than its effects on the muscle. As far as the muscle is concerned,
what we've done with Charlotte Peterson, which you reviewed two papers of her during the time,
we took the biopsies and look at the transcript of the people who were on exercise and metformin
versus exercise only, right? That's the only thing we had. And the reason we did that
was because in supplement four of her first paper, she showed that the strength of the muscle
didn't change, which means that per grand muscle you did better. Okay. And we try to understand
what is the biology and it became very clear. Look, in order for muscle to grow, it needs to
activate mTOR. Okay. So mTOR is good for muscle and for muscle growth. It's not good for aging,
but it's good for muscle growth. A huge transcripts of mTOR has been decreased by metformin, which was
not news for us. On the other hand, there are other transcripts that had to do with inflammation
and autophagy and oxidative markers that were in people with metformin and not with exercise. So
there were trade-offs. Okay. There were trade-offs. You get less muscle, but the muscle is healthier.
Okay. So it's up to you. If you want... Is healthier, can we really say that? Or can we
just say is as strong? It's biologically younger or as strong. Yeah, whatever. They're trade-offs.
But how do we say it's biologically younger? Because the changing transcript that we saw
is from an old transcript to young transcript. Okay. So in our studies, we have people with
biopsies from people who are old and young and with every treatment and we've done it for
sveratrol and we've done it for metformin and we've done it for acerbos and for exercise. And now
we're doing it for fasting. We have young and old and we see if in old with intervention,
the transcript goes back to young and it does. So the exercising people without metformin versus
exercising with metformin, the with metformin group had a maintenance of the transcriptome
or it actually declined relative to the other group. No, no, it's transcript specific. Okay.
It's which transcript, which groups of transcript changed and did they change other with decrease
or increase? Did they change to resemble more young than old? And this was done on the patients
in the master's trial? Yes. And what was the duration of that trial? 16 weeks, I believe.
And what do we think we can learn in four months with respect to the transcript? Well, like how
much does it apply from what you've learned over a much longer period of time in a non-intervention
setting? I don't know. I think, well, first of all, the answer is what we what we learn in four
months. We learn what it is in four months, but I think it's a long it's a long period of time.
It's also a dynamic period of time in this experiment because they were building muscle
throughout time, right? So it is what it is in this experiment. But in this experiment,
the transcripts were younger by metformin and the emptor was increased by exercise.
And this was the trade offs. And what about in terms of the
cardio respiratory fitness differences? I'm listening to them. I don't have,
you know, I don't have biology. I mean, I guess what I'm getting at is the most plausible
explanation here for a blunting of of cardio respiratory fitness would be what you said
earlier, which is, you know, metformin is a mitochondrial inhibitor. It's a weak one at the
doses we take it, but it nevertheless is. So it seems to me that that's the most obvious explanation.
That's the place I'd be looking for the fire given where the smoke is. So do we think that
the net benefits of that are probably positive in some people, but in others, for example,
those who exercise a lot, it might not be beneficial because they're getting so many
of those other benefits of exercise, as you point out. Yeah, I look, I'm taking metformin and
exercise, but I have a different way. I'm thinking about it for me right now. We're very personalized.
Yeah. And this is back to the issue of when do we start metformin? And or what is the biological
age of those people who exercise and take metformin? And I would say that if you're young or
biologically young, I don't think you should take metformin when you exercise at this level. Okay.
And maybe Peter, Peter, you're, you know, you've been doing it for years. You're probably
biologically much younger than most people. I don't know if metformin is for your age and
for what you're doing for your health. I can tell you that I'm with metformin and fasting. My
exercise capacity has increased significantly. I'm not measuring lactate. I'm not exercising
the way you are. So I think those are good discussion. We'll find out eventually who can
or who cannot, but we have to make sure that we don't generalize where we're being so specific.
Yeah, no, indeed. I, you know, again, I said at the outset, I get asked about metformin constantly.
And, you know, in the end, the only the only people who are asking me for whom it really
matters are the patients. I don't particularly care what someone asks me on social media. But
it has been a change in my practice over the past few years where I'm really reserving metformin
only for people in whom I see an otherwise obvious indication, such as even a trace of
insulin resistance, hyperinsulinemia that is not otherwise, you know, treated with
the right amount of exercise, nutritional changes, sleep and things like that.
So it will be interesting to see what tame does and how it can change that practice.
But I also worry that it won't fully answer the question for our patient population,
because the tame patient population is not a very healthy population. By definition,
if they can't walk a certain speed, they're 65 to 80 years old, you're basically selecting
people who we expect to have a bad outcome in five years.
So it's a very important question for the for the world at large. But, you know, I think it's
important that people listening to this understand we may not get the answer we want for them for
the healthy 40 year old person. Absolutely. Remember, all I want with tail is an FDA
indication for aging. OK, that's all I want. What do you think that opens the floodgates for?
How does that change things now, assuming that we get there and that we now have an FDA
indication for aging? What follows? First of all, pharmaceuticals will jump in, right? And they
wouldn't make many mistakes because I think the biomarkers will be there from tame and others.
There will be more biomarkers, better biomarkers. And so that they could do testing two and three
months and find out if their drug is working and then do a face retrial. Now face retrial,
now face retrial. Think of it for any diabetes treatment. You need 12000 people.
For 10 you need 3000 people. The study is going to be much, much cheaper. We think
I think this is still a hypothesis that being tested, right? Is 3000 the right number? Yeah.
Yeah. If if it were looked the 3000 is a question of when and not if for me, how many years
will it take us? And I hope that we'll actually do the 3500 and not lose a lot.
Not lose a lot. Also the question is who's stopping the study? That's another thing. So
and in other words, that's administrative questions. But the reason we do that is to get
an indication that for the FDA is not making aging a disease, which is another big topic.
But for us, it's okay, you can call it whatever we want. But if there's a drug that targets
variety of age related disease and mortality, that's for us a gerotherapeutics. And this is
what we want to get all the other question when to use whom to use. You're absolutely right. And
and the one thing I didn't with the one thing we don't want is not to kill anyone
on the way to success, right? We're almost out of time. But one thing I want to just touch on
before we go, we've talked a little bit about rapamycin a lot about metformin. We didn't talk
about the other one, you and I probably get asked about a lot, which is the NAD precursors.
Where are you and your thinking on the efficacy of these as general protective agents? They're in
a different class because they're not pharmaceutical, they're nutraceutical. How is your appraisal of
the of the data in that space? You know, as a biologist, I have a problem understanding it.
Okay. On one hand, you give it to animals, and the animals are doing better. Okay, not not in the
ITP, but you're right. Not in the single most important animal study. They didn't write better.
Yeah, when you ask people, okay, follow, you know, follow the drug. Tell me where it goes. Where can
you measure it? You cannot measure it anywhere. And you cannot measure derivative of that.
And so I don't know where is the biology. So Joe Bauer, do you know Joe Bauer from UPM?
He's a really good NAD biologist. And he basically thought, you know what, the NAD goes,
we swallow that, it goes to our microbiome. Sorry, when he says NAD, you mean the NR or
NAD? You're right. Yes, yes, yes.
Right. Yeah. They go to the microbiome, and the microbiome either transfer the NAD or does
something, the microbiome itself does something, and you know, there's indirect health benefit from
a Dufferin system. And he actually did a really good study where he discovered that the NAD for
the microbiome comes not from the food, but from the gut, the gut walls. Okay. Everywhere,
everywhere you try to understand what's the biology, I don't get it. And when I don't get
the biology, I'm a little bit more worried of what kind of a placebo is it. I actually, one of
the studies I wanted to do, those short studies when I get elderly, do placebo control crossover
and do biopsies and look at the biology, I wanted to do NAD. And then I said, I just have so little
belief here that I'm now doing an intermittent fasting one, but I'm uncomfortable with it. Now,
saying that, I started taking NMA at one point. And what I noticed is my REM sleep has improved
a lot. And I stopped it and my REM sleep wasn't so good. I restarted it and my REM didn't get better
again. So, and then I tried another, there's a Japanese company, I don't remember the name of
the top of my head, that has really the best preparation. David Sinclair tells me about that,
has the best preparation of NMN, $900 a month supply for the low dose, $1,800 for the high dose.
I got some of the supplement as a present. More expensive than a PCSK9 inhibitor and
Rapamycin combined. Okay. Right. And my REM sleep didn't return. So, I'm currently not taking
anyone. So, what am I telling you? I'm telling you, I'm just not convinced. I don't know,
it's not the whole truth. You never know the whole truth, but I don't know enough of the truth
to make anything about it. Again, if people want to know, it's good for the economy. I'm not sure
that the preparations out there, look, they are very sensitive preparations. If they have a high
time shelf, I think you lose a lot of it. And I don't know which to recommend.
Yeah. I think it's always problematic when your rationale for taking a supplement is that it's a
mini stimulus program to the economy through the supplement company. I think as a general rule,
if we're going to talk about principles for trying to optimize your health, I would put that very low
on the list. Peter, I did many jokes. Do I have to go over and tell you which was a joke and which
is not? I know it's a joke. This is my joke right back at you. Yeah, exactly. No, no, this is my
sarcasm coming right back to you. Yeah, supplement company stimulus program, not a high on my list
reason for it. Anyway, Nier, this has been great. Thank you again for the generosity of your time.
And behind the scenes, people don't know how much I bug you and how much we interact on all matters
that pertain to this stuff. You're one of the few people that I know listens to every single podcast,
reads every single newsletter, and at least a quarter of the time sends me a note with something
remarkable in it that expands my thinking on a topic. So I want to thank you for that. You're
part of the people who spread the gospels, and I think it's so important. In fact, you're one of
the messiahs, really. That's an awful. I don't want to be a messiah of anything. And I want to come
clean. You know, I'm usually not there for the last half an hour of the podcast, you know.
It's a shame because I always say the best thing for the last half an hour.
Okay, next time I listen to the last half an hour. It's a pleasure, Peter, and any time and good luck.
And I'm looking forward not to this one. I'm not going to listen to, but to the next one.
Very well. Thank you, Nier. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive.
If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership
program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads.
It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of the subscription.
Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick-ass,
comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person,
thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is, nobody's show notes rival these.
Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely.
Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday
through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not
getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head
over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook,
all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute
the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including
the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is
not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users
should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about,
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.