Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Lane. Good to see you again, man.
Yeah. I'm happy to be back. I'm stoked for this. I know we had the marathon session the
first time, and I think we got through like a third of the topics that you were interested
in. So we'll see how we do this time.
Yeah. Yeah. Well, and of course, a lot of people had a bunch of follow-up questions.
So it's sort of some combination of all the things we didn't get to talk about the first
time, plus some new things I thought about and that you and I have had a bunch of emails
exchanged over the last few months, coupled with some of that residual stuff. But one
of the topics that people really want to hear you and I talk about, because I think there's
this belief that we are going to be so orthogonal in our views, and we will have not a single
thing in common, although I'm pretty sure this isn't going to be the case, is on energy
balance and the role of calories in weight gain. So why don't we just lead with the fireworks
that everyone is hoping for? So talk to me about energy balance, calories, and weight
gain.
So I think one of the big misunderstandings is people don't really understand what energy
balance truly is. So if we look at what most people think it is, is, well, I track my calories
in, I track my calories out. Therefore, if I am burning 2,500 calories a day and I'm
tracking 2,000 calories a day, I should lose one pound of body weight per week linearly.
And that's just how it should go. Perfect math. And when that doesn't happen, they go,
see, this doesn't work. And there's a lot of different reasons for that. But before
we get into that, let's talk about what energy balance actually is. So you have, it is calories
in versus calories out, or the energy you consume versus the energy you expend. And
it's worth talking about real quick before we get into that, what do we mean by energy?
A lot of people say, well, calories, they don't even exist. You can't look under a microscope.
No, you can't look at them under a microscope. What we're talking about is the energy stored
in the chemical bonds of food. And when you break that food down, when those molecules
go through metabolism and they go through glycolysis, the Krebs cycle, that energy is
liberated but captured ultimately as mostly ATP, which is our high energy phosphate. But
you can't just store a bunch of ATP. It's not practical for the body and ATP is very
unstable molecule. So we evolved to have fat stores or adipose tissue basically to store
excess energy. Now you can store some in glycogen. I would argue that you really can't store
some as protein. Some people will say, well, you can break down, you know, lean tissue.
To me, that's kind of like saying, let's build a house. So it's a reservoir for wood. I don't
really think that that's a great analogy. I built this amazing teak table such that if I need fire
wood, I've got it right there. Right. Like in practicality, are you right? Sure. Yeah, you
could, but that's not why you built the table, right? Yeah, that's the nuclear option. Yeah.
Right. For sure. But if you look at the contribution of glycogen to your relative
energy stores, it's actually really small. I mean, you're talking about, you know, 1,500 to 2,000
calories of energy. So your adipose is by far the biggest store and you store it that way
because one, it's economical for space because you can fit a large amount of lipid in the small
area and it's energy dense and it's relatively easy to convert to ATP. And it's anhydrous. So
therefore it's, you know, incredibly well packed as you said, right? That's a glycogen has to
track with all that water. It's not a very efficient way to store energy. Correct. You would
be 800 pounds if you were trying to store the same amount of energy as glycogen. So there's a
lot of really practical reasons why the body evolved that way. Now, when we say calories,
calories are literally a measurement of energy. And so this is really important to understand.
When people say, well, are all calories created equal? That's like saying our different notches
on your speedometer different. No, this is just a, this is just a unit of measurement. Literally all
that is. And you, you, you truly have to think of it as energy. So if we think of it as the energy
stored in the chemical bonds that can be transferred throughout these various metabolic
processes, and that's what metabolism really is, is trying to capture that energy. When we look at
what the energy inside of things is, that is essentially the metabolizable energy in food.
Now there's a couple of important caveats to that. Notice I said metabolizable energy,
because not everything in food is metabolizable, especially with regards to fiber and specifically
insoluble fiber. It used to be thought that insoluble fiber is completely, you can't digest
it at all. It's absolutely zero calories. And I wouldn't say that there's good evidence,
but there's starting to be some evidence that suggests that our gut microbiome can actually
extract some calories from the insoluble fiber you eat. That's coming from a friend of mine,
Suzanne Devkota, who's one of the premier gut microbiome experts in the world. She actually
did her master's at the same lab I was doing my PhD in. Very smart person has been to like the
Nobel ceremony, you know, like incredibly well-respected scientist. So there is some evidence
of that. And then when you come to soluble fiber, it's pretty, pretty variable. It's like anywhere
from one to four calories per gram. So anywhere from a normal carbohydrate amount to one calorie.
And it also probably depends on your individual gut microbiome. Right? So even before we get to
the calories outside of thing, we see that there is some variability and probably some individual
variability in how many calories one person can consume, and then actually have available as
energy. Lane, I like that you started with this. I'm just going to add a couple of points so that
we can build off this together. So let's even give people the definition of a calorie. And I think
we should remind people that when you and I and most people are talking about calories, we're
really talking about kilocalories. And some people will get those confused. So big C calorie is equal
to a thousand little C calories or a K calorie. But regardless of that nomenclature, I think most
people when they're saying I eat 2000 calories are of course referring to kilocalories. Each of
these, one of those, if I'm not mistaken, and you're going to be probably remembering this better than
me, Lane, one calorie, I believe is the energy required to heat one gram of water from 14.5 to
15.5 degrees Celsius at one atmosphere. Correct? That sound about right? Bingo. Yeah. Yeah. About
right. I actually have specifically forgotten the exact definition, but it's basically the amount to
increase the degree of water by one degree Celsius. So again, to your point, it's simply a unit of
energy, just as we would think of a jewel as a unit of energy. And I also want to highlight
something you said, which I think is a very important thing for people to understand,
which is when we talk about the conservation of energy, that also implies when you change forms
of energy. So when you eat food, the energy, as you said, is stored within the bonds. It is
chemical energy. We turn that into electrical energy via the electron transport chain,
and then we turn it right back into chemical energy, both in the immediate sense of ATP,
where you again now create the energy in the phosphate bond. But more importantly, as you said,
when you're storing it, you're putting it right back into a hydrocarbon. And it's those carbon,
carbon, carbon hydrogen bonds that if my memory serves me correctly, are the most energy dense
bonds within our body, much more than say a carbon oxygen bond would be. Correct. And that's why,
you know, we see fatty acids have much more calories or much more energy per gram compared
to carbohydrate because carbohydrate has more oxygens. Whereas fats through beta oxidation,
where you're having lopping off two carbons with hydrogens, you can pretty much, I mean,
it's not direct, but you can pretty much create acetyl-CoA right from that, which then goes
directly into the Krebs cycle. Whereas glucose, there's a lot more involved in getting the ATP
or generating ATP from that. Now, glucose does have benefits in terms of amount of oxygen required
to generate the same ATP. It just depends on the metric you're looking at, right? And then,
of course, the final point you make there, Lane, I think is worth restating because it is so
important, which is, and this will come up later, I think, when we talk about genetic differences
in tolerance to amounts of macronutrients and things like that. But you can really liberate
different amounts of energy from the same foods, depending on many things, but presumably based on
your gut microbiome. That's probably one of the things that's going to create a pretty sizable
delta when it comes to how much food you're capturing. In other words, how much of that
chemical energy you're able to recoup and repurpose into electrical energy?
Yeah. I mean, there is evidence, for example, that obesity-prone people, that they have a
flora of gut microbiome, or sorry, a gut microflora that is better able to extract
energy from the foods they eat. Now, that could be reverse causation as well. It could be that
obese people eat a diet that causes this kind of gut microflora to bloom, so on and so forth.
So we've got to be careful about establishing correlation versus causation. And I will say
that when they look at, because they can actually assess how much energy is lost in fecal matter,
it's usually around 5% to 10%, depending on people. And most of your 95% of your
Gaussian distribution falls in there. So it is a significant difference, but what I would tell
people is be cautious about saying, well, this is why we see huge differences between individuals.
Maybe for certain individuals, but I think for the vast majority of people, unless you're
literally an outlier, it's probably going to be somewhere relatively close. So I think establishing
that, okay, we understand that there is some variability in how much energy you can extract
from the food you eat. And I'm going to come back to that as well, because there's another aspect,
the tracking portion that we need to talk about as well, that confuses people. Now, let's talk about
the energy outside of things, because this is way more complicated. So there's different ways
people have broken it down. But essentially, you have your BMR, which is your basal metabolic rate.
And what that that's usually about 50 to 70% of the energy people expend per day. And the way I
told is it's basically the cost of keeping the lights on. And we would determine that if you
were putting somebody in a metabolic chamber, I believe that we don't require them to be sleeping,
but it's laying up laying there, but being awake, correct. And that's slightly different from your
energy expenditure while sleeping. Yep. And there are some like you have RMR and you have BMR. And
there are some subtle differences between the two. But I mean, essentially, it's very similar.
I've had my RMR assessed, which is basically you go into a lab, you lay down, they make sure you're
stable for 20 minutes, you don't talk, you don't listen to music, you don't do anything, you just
sit there and breathe, or you lay there and breathe. And I mean, RMR and BMR are going to be very
similar, I'm going to simplify it for our audience just because it's an already complicated subject.
But that's basically the cost of keeping lights on. So the other way to think about it is if you
were in like a coma, per se, where you're awake, having some brain activity, that sort of thing,
but you're not moving, you're not physically moving. That's still about 50 to 70% of people's
total daily energy expenditure. And that's what we refer to as metabolic rate.
And when you had yours measured, Lane, did you have it done using indirect calorimetry?
Yeah, so mine was, when I had it done, I'm anywhere between 1900 and 1950 calories per
day pretty consistently. Tell folks how that works. Because I think when most people say,
I just had my BMR measured, it's usually not the rigorous way that we're talking about using
indirect calorimetry. It's usually relying on heart rate and respiratory rate, which
can probably give some approximation, but it's probably important for people to understand that
there's an enormous error that's introduced when you make that approximation. So what's the
rigorous way to determine energy expenditure? So direct calorimetry is the most rigorous way.
And that is literally, you know, kind of in a bomb kilometer, right? You're in a metabolic chamber.
And they are looking at, you know, how much heat you're generating, essentially. And from that heat
that you generate, they're able to determine your total daily energy expenditure. And then using an
equation based on your oxygen consumption versus your CO2 production, they can determine what from
that is your BMR, which is actually the same way they do it for indirect calorimetry. So you're
wearing, you're inside this like hood and you're breathing into a tube essentially. And basically
your metabolic rate is very closely associated with how much oxygen you consume. So how much
oxygen you consume versus how much CO2 you expire will one, give you a really good idea of your
metabolic rate, because the end products of metabolism are CO2 and water. So when everything
goes through this process of breaking down carbohydrates and fats, it all, if you talk
about like what happens to body fat, it ends up as CO2 and water. Okay. So if they know that, and you
can use a constant for water, if they know that, it's also why they can use doubly labeled water to
estimate energy expenditure. We'll get to that later. But if you know that, and you know these
constants and you make several assumptions, I mean, again, this isn't direct. You're making
assumptions. You're making assumptions about how much is being generated. You can come up with a
relatively accurate estimation of your metabolic rate. And for reasons that I can't explain,
this is something I can never forget, which is the coefficients for that equation,
the WIR coefficients, right? So energy expenditure is 3.94 times VCO2 plus 1.11 times VCO2. So as you
said, it's heavily weighted to oxygen consumption. It's nearly four times the consumption of oxygen
plus about one times the production of carbon dioxide. And that gives you that. And for anybody
listening to this who's ever had a VO2 max test, I would encourage you to ask the lab that does it
for you to give you the raw data, because what they'll spit out for you, usually in 15 second
intervals, is VO2, VCO2. And while the purpose of that test might be to determine your maximal
VO2, you can also plug in these two variables to the WIR equation and get how many calories per
minute you're consuming or requiring to maintain that energy output all the way to your max. It's
actually quite remarkable when you consider that a highly trained individual will easily get to
20 calories per minute of energy demand. Yeah. I mean, if you think about, you know, we say lean
mass is by far the biggest correlate with total daily energy expenditure and resting metabolic
rate. Lean mass requires quite a bit of oxygen compared to like adipose tissue, which is
relatively nonvascular. So it makes a lot of sense that you would see that. And then if you
think about activity, obviously if you start doing activity, it requires a lot of oxygen.
So we have our BMR, which is about in terms of the energy outside of things. And I guess I should
define that. Energy out is your total daily energy expenditure. So all the energy you expend in a day,
that's your TDEE, we call it. And the biggest portion of that is your BMR for most people.
Now, if you're an elite athlete who trains like six, eight hours a day, you can get to the point
where your physical activity is actually greater than your BMR. So don't be those listening. Don't
be dogmatic about these numbers. But for most people, 50 to 70% is a relatively accurate
representation. For me, it's probably about 55 to 60% of my total daily energy expenditure,
because I do train like two, two and a half hours a day. So that is a significant contributor.
So we have that. Then we have what's called TEF, which is the Thermic Effect of Food or
Diet Induced Thermogenesis. And this is anywhere from five to 10% of your total daily energy
expenditure for most people. Very, very hard to measure. Usually it's expressed in terms of
calories per minute, because they're only looking at it in the short term. And when we do studies
of total daily energy expenditure, I mean, usually what they're doing is using a constant for TEF.
They're making an assumption because it's just so hard to measure, unless you're just measuring
that over like the course of a couple of hours or maybe a day at most. But we feel relatively
confident based on the studies out there that it's about five to 10% of your total daily energy
expenditure. So not a big contributor, but still. But it also seems to be macronutrient dependent,
correct? It is. It is. So that's one of the things I'm going to get to.
We'll come back to that when we get to you.
Yeah, yeah. And then if we look at the last component, we have our physical activity. And
this encompasses all physical activities. So people hear this and they think exercise,
but actually the biggest, for a lot of people, their biggest component of physical activity
is actually what's called NEAT, which is Non-Exercise Activity Thermogenesis.
And that is something that's actually extremely modifiable. And we see it in terms of one,
people who are obese resistant, what we term obese resistant, they tend to fidget a lot. They
tend to move a lot. I was like this as a kid. I still am. Whereas people who are obese prone
tend to have very low NEAT. In fact, there was a study done by Liebel in 1995 where they overfed
people by, I want to say, a thousand calories per day. And they determined this. They looked at
their total daily energy expenditure in a metabolic award. So very accurate. And then they took that
number and added a thousand calories on top of it. And they looked at how much weight people gained.
Some people gained more than they expected. One person did not even have significant weight gain.
And what they found was this individual's NEAT, their spontaneous physical activity,
went up so much it just compensated for that extra calories. And so I think this is what
people really don't understand as well. I want to be very purposeful about how we define NEAT
because when it comes to NEAT versus exercise, exercise is purposeful. So something I'll hear
a lot is, well, I'm going to go do a walk and get my NEAT up. No, you're doing exercise. Maybe I'm
being a little bit pedantic, but it's important because NEAT is what I'm talking about. Fidgeting,
not right now because now I'm thinking about it, but I'm waving my hands around. I'm kind of
moving from one foot to the next. I've seen Peter that you move your fingers and you'll
kind of twitch your neck. That's what all that stuff, even though it seems like nothing,
thousands of those movements over the course of a day actually add up. So then I have people say,
well, I'm just going to tap my foot to get NEAT up or fidget. Well, guess what's going to happen.
Whenever you try to do something that also requires your brain, you're going to stop doing
that because you actually can't really do two things at once in terms of thinking about it.
So this truly is spontaneous energy expenditure and appears to be modifiable by about five to
600 calories per day. And we do see this with overfeeding and underfeeding. So people who are,
and we'll get into talking about metabolic adaptation and how this affects things,
but people who lose like 10% of their body weight, they've seen up to a 500 calorie reduction in
NEAT. So that's a big portion of it. And then obviously you have your purposeful exercise.
So if we look at energy out or energy in metabolizable energy, energy out, BMR, TEF,
NEAT and exercise, I'm simplifying this equation a little bit, but though that's essentially it.
So when people, if people want to invalidate energy balance, what I always say is, listen,
you ate those carbons, something must happen to them. You cannot just, they don't flutter off
into oblivion and you don't create them out of nothing, right? Something has to happen to them.
And we have a lot of metabolic tracer studies to pretty much know what happens to them.
I think the confusion becomes, well, I tracked my calories. I ate in a 500 calorie deficit and
I didn't lose weight. First off, if we look at where these mistakes come in, people weigh
themselves sporadically. And if you only weighed yourself once a week, I would say it's virtually
meaningless. When we are trying to get data on people, we're very regimented with how we do it.
So it's you weigh in first thing in the morning after voiding your bladder and bowel, if possible,
fasted, first thing you do, as soon as your feet hit the floor after you've gone to the bathroom,
you weigh in. And then we take that weight every single day. And then we look at the average and
then we compare week to week averages. Because anybody who's ever tracked their weight, and I'm
sure you've had this experience, Peter, where you're eating very consistently, you're tracking
your weight and it'll easily fluctuate by one to 2% per day. So if you're 200 pounds, you could be
204, you could be 196. And I always tell people, it's like the stock market. Sometimes there's a
good explanation for why it goes up and down like that. But other times there's no good explanation
whatsoever. And you don't just want to take like one isolated data point. And this is also with
people who get DEXs done and they go, they freak out because I've lost a pound of lean body mass.
No, you went and had it done at a different time where you're less hydrated.
Or on a different machine or with the different software.
Tech. Yeah, I tell people, I don't want to tell them not to get DEXs done, but unless you're going
to do it, same tech, same machine, same conditions, it's unlike cool. It doesn't really mean anything,
but you haven't. So when you look at that, so you can have somebody theoretically, and I've
shown this example with clients, where I've said your average weight is down by a pound. But if
I had weighed you on this day last week and this day this week, you would think you were up by two
and a half pounds. So people will start doing a calorie deficit diet. And they'll say, well,
see, I gained weight, so this doesn't work. No, that was a fluid shift from day to day to day
changes in weight are much more dictated by fluid shifts than they are adipose tissue levels. But
your weekly and monthly changes in weight are much more dictated by your actual body mass.
So that's one thing that confuses people. The other thing that really will kind of confuse people
is thinking that they can track their energy expenditure accurately. So these watches,
there was a recent study done in 2018. I guess some people went, I consider that recent. I do
because the years tend to blend together for me now. But they looked at about 20 different devices
and found that these overestimate your exercise energy expenditure by
23 or sorry, 28 to 93%. So if it says you burn 500 calories, you probably actually burn more like
260 to 400 calories. Right. And so again, people say, well, I, you know, I burned 1000 calories on
the treadmill today. Like, you know, and I always tell people, what do you think is more likely that
you have found a way to violate the laws of thermodynamics or that this watch might not be
accurate because I'm going to go with the latter. So there's that it's very funny how like,
people are very distrustful of certain things and other things. They're just like, oh yeah,
I totally trust this thing. So there's that. And then there's also the fact that we can't
completely accurately track calories in either, because there is up to a 20% error label that's
allowed in foods. So I think that's where some of the confusion comes in. The other thing I will say
that's worth saying that will really upset some people is people are horrible estimators of their
energy intake. Horrible. There was a study done, I think it was back in the 90s where they took
self-report people who were self-reportedly resistant to weight loss. These were people who
said, I eat 1200 calories a day, I can't lose weight. They put them in a metabolic ward and
they also had them do doubly labeled water, which is basically a free living way of determining
energy expenditure. Plus they had the direct callimetry and they said to them, we want you
to track your food and report it to us, but we will know if you're incorrect, like we will know.
So the average under-reporting was by 50%. So they were under-reporting their energy intake by 50%
on average. And that's right in line with a lot of the other studies. Most, if we look at people
who are overweight and obese, most of them under-report by 30 to 70%. The demographic of obese
women tend to be at the higher end of that. Obese men tend to be at the lower end of that. And then
even lean people-
Yeah, I was about to say for lean people, would the same bias, I mean bias might be the wrong word,
but would the same error in reporting still exist?
So there is an error, it's less. I think it's around 18%, but even dieticians under-report
by about 10%.
That's kind of amazing that they could be within 10%.
Yeah. Some of the subjects actually argued with the researchers about it, which is funny.
But people don't like that kind of self-accountability sort of thing. And what I'll tell people is, now,
the message people will hear when they hear that is, you're saying I'm a liar. And I don't think
that people were necessarily lying. I think people are horrible estimators of their food intake.
Because if I put a salad in front of you and I dump 50 grams of oil on it versus 20 grams of oil,
versus 20 grams of oil, you will have absolutely no idea of the difference. You might be able to
taste like a little bit of difference in mouth feel, but most people go, ah, that's a salad.
It's got some dressing on it. It's probably 200, 300 calories. Meanwhile, it's got nuts.
It's got bacon, eggs. It's got oil, all that kind of stuff. And I'm not saying anything,
those things are inherently bad. I'm just saying it's all energy. So I think that's another big
component is people are just horrible estimators of their food intake. And what I'll tell people
is if you really believe that you are not able to eat in the calorie deficit, lose weight. I want
you to just for one week, track every single piece of food you put in your mouth. No licks, no bites,
no snacks, not an account. I'm not saying you got to do this for the rest of your life,
but just do this for one week. And usually I'll come back with people who are mind blown.
They'll say, well, I thought I was eating 600 calories. I was eating 2,700 because they didn't
realize it like they grabbed that handful of nuts, or they grab a handful of potato chips,
or whatever it is, when they take a bite of a candy bar. And yeah, in isolation,
none of that stuff is a big deal. But when you accumulate it throughout the course of a day,
it can be a big deal. Yeah, about eight years ago, when I was really, really interested in this
topic, I had the luxury of being able to spend a couple of days, probably about a total of six days
in total inside a metabolic chamber in two day blocks. So three, two day blocks, or four,
two day blocks inside a metabolic chamber. Probably wasn't actually very much fun at the
time, but actually it was the most fun thing ever, Lane, because it was everything I love.
First of all, I got to be in a room. Nobody could bug me. And we had arranged it so that I could
do all my exercising. So I had my bike on a fluid trainer. I had tons of weights in there,
plyometric box, a bed. It was a dream. It was literally a vacation. And I had this amazing
food being prepared by a metabolic kitchen. You've got this staff that is making to the
gram everything that we had agreed at the outset we were going to be testing. And then after the
fact, I went and did the 10 day doubly labeled water experience, which I guess we could explain
for people what that is. So water, everybody knows is H2O, hydrogen two oxygen one. But it turns
out there's a heavy form of hydrogen called deuterium. And there's another form of oxygen
that doesn't have 16, I'm so glad in my chemistry now, is it 16 protons or is it?
A neutron.
A neutron, 16 neutrons. So instead they have one with 18 neutrons. And so you drink a D2 regular O
and then an H2 heavy O. When you drink this, you basically get to exploit a trick, which is by
collecting your urine, you're measuring the hydrogen that's coming out without measuring
the carbon that's coming out. So you can impute what your VCO2 is effectively. And you collect
urine serially. And over the course of 10 or 12 days, you get an estimate. And so the only
instruction to me when doing this was try to be weight stable for that period of time,
which I was able to do. And it was interesting. That was a time in my life when I was really
tracking ins and outs pretty well, mostly just out of curiosity, not because I was trying to lose
weight or gain weight. I wasn't. And by my calculations, I was about 4400 calories in,
which would imply about 4400 calories of energy expenditure. The DLW ended up being 4200.
So I was surprised it was pretty close because I agree. I expected it to be way far off.
But it was such an amazing experience. And it's like I almost wish stuff like that could be done
commercially because of course I had to do this with an awesome guy named Eric Ravison at the
Pennington Biomedical Research Institute. And Eric's staff had done this for me. So it was,
you know, I was able to do this in a research lab, not, but this would be an amazing thing that I
wish you could order a home kit, drink this stuff down, run it out for 10 days and truly get a sense
of your energy expenditure. Right. What I would say is most, so since you're supposed to be weight
stable, most people could actually do it just by default because at the end of the day, if you're
weight stable within a reasonable amount, then whatever you're eating is actually for all intensive
purposes, your total daily energy expenditure. Oh, yes. Yes. I'm just saying it's so hard for
people to met to your point. Like that's, that is a hard thing for someone to do unless they're
going to have a food scale with them everywhere and they're right. Yeah. Yeah. And then the other
thing is it becomes a little bit of an artificial exercise. Cause even if somebody says I'm willing
to for 10 days measure everything, then you get this sort of Hawthorne effect of they won't take
that extra bite of the candy bar. Cause A they don't want to measure it and B and they won't grab
the handful of nuts and they won't do this. That and the other thing. Whereas if you say, look,
I'm just going to eat the way I normally eat for a week and not measure anything. All I have to do
is maintain my weight, which means if I get on and do what you're saying, right? Every morning you
get on that scale and you kind of tweak it up and down, then you can say, okay, in a truly free
living environment without the Hawthorne effect, this is my energy intake. So it's so funny. You
say that in science, we know that right down to individual particles, when you observe it,
it changes its behavior. Absolutely. And that's true for just on the atomic level.
And it's true for people. And in fact, that's, we have a coaching team called team bio lane,
where we do, we do one-on-one coaching. And we have a team of seven coaches. And one of the big
things that we train our coaches on is like, Hey, if somebody's like really resistant to something,
just see if they'll just track what they're already doing. Right? Like just, just to enlighten
them, right? And we'll tell them like, listen, we want the raw data. We don't, don't change
anything. And almost every time just by them doing that for a week. Wow. You know, I lost
half a kilo or a kilo this week. And it's like, yeah, like you said, it's, you didn't take that
extra bite of snacks. We have that problem actually in our practice with our patients, because we,
for at least half the patients, once we do our intake, we realize nutrition is going to be an
important thing to modify. And a lot of times we want to see what the baseline is. And so we go
one step further, which is we do exactly that, which is, you know, we don't want to see you do
anything different, but we really go out of our way to say, please do not change anything. In other
words, eat that candy bar and grab that handful of nuts and take that extra, you know, pour that
glass of wine a little taller than you think it should be like, do everything naturally. And even
still to your point, it's almost impossible to get a true baseline once you apply those constraints.
Yeah, we can go over the, that just shows you how inaccurate 24 hour food recalls can be and all
that kind of stuff. So yeah, and so I think those are some of the biggest misunderstandings. Now,
I do want to address the whole is a calorie, a calorie thing. Yes, all calories are equal.
Because again, calories are just a unit of measurement. All sources of calories are not
equal in terms of their effects on energy expenditure and metabolizable energy. We already
talked about soluble fiber and insoluble fiber. And then if we look at the TEF of various foods,
protein. So let's start with fat fat, fat has the lowest TEF. So if we talk about TEF is basically
the amount of energy the system has to put in to extract the chemical energy out of food. So you
can't just put it in and then boom, you have the energy, your body has to do work to get it. Now,
it's always a higher net, even on stuff like you know, people say, well, celery is a negative
calorie food because your money has to put more, no, no, no, they're, unless we're talking about
tree bark, there is no energy negative food, right? Even celery has like 50 calories, I think it's
or it might be five calories per hundred grams. So very, very low, but still not negative. We would
not have lived long as a species if we had energy negative foods. So if we think about how much
energy has to go in to get energy out, we have, you know, how many calories you consume and present
as metabolizable energy. And then how many calories we net out of that after the energy
expenditure required to get the chemical energy out is done. So if we look at fats, fats are the
lowest and they're about zero to three calories. Meaning if you eat a hundred calories from fat,
you net about 97 to a hundred calories. And then we have carbohydrates. Carbohydrates are about five
to 10%. So if you eat a hundred calories of carbohydrate, you net about 90 to 95 calories.
Protein is around 20 to 30%. So if you eat a hundred calories from protein, you net about 70
to 80 calories. Now people will hear that and they make a much bigger deal of it than it actually is,
because when you consider how much of a proportion of your overall energy expenditure it is,
and I do this example where I'm like, let's double your protein and see how much more TEF you get,
it ends up being like 150 calories if you double your protein, right? And we're talking about people
already eating like, you know, a standard amount of protein to a really high amount of protein.
So yeah, it helps, but it's probably not the cure for the obesity crisis, right? So it is important.
It's important to talk about although I mean, to push back on that for a second, Wayne, I've never
thought about this until you said that. One of the challenges when thinking about weight loss,
sustainable weight loss over a long enough period of time is how much is enough on a daily basis
before an adaptation would take place that would correct it. So for example, if we were talking-
You're asking the right questions.
Yeah, yeah. So if we were talking about, let's just say one of your dieticians came to you and
said, Lane, I've got this idea. I've got this patient who is truly by every metric 50 pounds
overweight. Like, you know, we could do it on lean body mass, body fat, whatever. But this,
if this guy's 50 pounds lighter in a year, everything about his life has gotten better
from a health perspective. And this person said, look, I'm going to double their protein intake.
And let's not make it the extreme example of where you're getting an extra 150. Let's just say it's
a hundred calories or 75 calories. If you could create an energy deficit, and this again assumes
that you can change nothing else. And I mean, there's so many silly assumptions, but think of
this almost more as a thought experiment. If you could create an energy debt of 75 calories per day
by a macronutrient shift to more protein over a long enough period of time, could it be relevant?
It could. However, what we're neglecting to talk about is something I briefly mentioned
which is metabolic adaptation. And so I think this is the other big thing that confuses people.
They think energy in, energy out. These are static things that do not affect each other.
And the reality is they are intrinsically tied to each other. So anybody who's ever tried to lose
weight, if you went on a, let's say a 500 calorie deficit per day, which is a pretty significant
deficit. Do you just lose linearly one pound per week until you no longer exist and you die
because there's no more body weight? No, we all know that eventually like that plateaus, right?
Now, part of that is just because you have less body mass. So your body has to expend less energy
in order to just maintain upright posture and those sorts of things. But then there's also the
neat component. As you lose weight, you become spontaneously less active. We see this in animals
all the way up to humans. Then not just that voluntary exercise tends to go down past a certain
point. Like if you're very obese and you start to lose weight, it's not really going to affect this
that much because you have such an energy surplus. But especially people who are going average to
lean, your vault, like your will to exercise will go down. I've definitely experienced that during
contests, perhaps getting very lean, you know, just having to like will myself to get up off the couch.
And then if you look at their BMR, you actually get a reduction in BMR above what you would expect
based on the loss of lean tissue and fat tissue because fat tissue is somewhat metabolically
active. There's actually up to like on average a 15% reduction in BMR. So almost at every level of
energy expenditure, your body is kind of fighting you to get back to homeostasis, to reestablish
homeostasis. And so we see this in people who lose weight. So if we take people with the same lean
body mass and fat mass, people who have never been obese, people who have been obese and weight
reduced, the weight reduced people will have a lower BMR than the people that have never had to
lose fat. And so it's like this evolutionary, John Speakman had a really good paper on this,
thinking about this kind of getting into set point theory, that we have this kind of native
set point that the body likes to be at. And the idea is kind of okay, what are what's regulating
the ends of that set point. So we understand that if we get too lean, lose too much fat mass,
we die. That's a really negative outcome for evolution, right? You can't pass on your DNA
if you're dead. At the higher ends, because there are there are things that work against obesity,
like we already talked about that neat goes up if you overfeed your BMR also goes up if you overfeed.
But obviously, based on what's happening in society with this shift towards adiposity,
the regulations on the going up are not as strong as going down. And so if you think about it from
an evolutionary perspective, the risk of getting too overweight in the short term, because obesity
is not going to kill you when you're 40. It's going to be the difference between you dying at 80
versus 70. That's what the research tends to suggest. The risk in the short term,
is predation, or, you know, fighting or that some sort of physical altercation where you can't
defend yourself very well, you can't run away. The risk of predation, after man learned how to use
tools, pretty much went to zero. I mean, yes, you have shark attacks, and you have these things, but
I mean, there are essentially lightning strikes when humans get killed by animals or even other
people. I mean, it's very, very rare. But then we look at the risk of starvation is very real,
even now in some parts of the world, and was very real in this country until the 1900s. I mean,
even into probably the early 1900s. And so it makes sense that the regulatory mechanisms
were more powerful on that bottom end to prevent people from becoming too lean,
than they are on the top end. And so bringing this back to energy balance,
you have to think of energy balance, like a car that changes its gas efficiency based on how
full the tank is. So think about if you had a car, that when you have the gas tank filled all the way
up, it gets horrible gas mileage. But as that gas tank starts to go down, and think about your gas
tank as your body's adipose stores, your energy stores, as that gas tank starts to go down,
you become more and more and more efficient to buy the time there's very little gas left. It's
just sipping gas. It really is kind of a dramatic comparison, but it is an apt comparison. And I
think the biggest thing to take away is we cannot know, and we can know at a snapshot in time what
your energy expenditure probably is. But it's likely to change. And it's a sliding scale,
and it depends on a lot of variables. And so that's also led people to say, well, see,
we can't accurately track calories in, we can't accurately track calories out. There's no point
in tracking calories. And what I would say is that you're kind of throwing the baby out with
the bathwater. I'm not saying you have to track calories to lose weight, because obviously you
don't, because there's all kinds of methodology that people use to lose weight that doesn't
involve tracking calories. But it would be like saying, well, keeping a budget is worthless,
because I have multiple streams of revenue, and I have investments. And so I can't know exactly how
much income I'm getting. And also, you know, things pop up like your car breaks down, you know, you
have repairs to your house, so you can't exactly know what your expenses are going to be. So therefore
keeping a budget is worthless. And what always, so the comparison I make is, you don't have to
keep a budget to save money. But it's a useful tool, it gets you in the ballpark, and it gets
you a baseline. And I would say the same thing about tracking calories. And it might be that the
act of keeping a budget alone is what enables you to think twice before a frivolous purchase,
as one example, right? And we know this too, when people try. So what's so funny is the
parallels here. So did you know that the average person, I'm kind of a finance nerd, average person
under reports their debt by about 155%. And again, it may not even be a lying thing, it might just be
they have really horrible ideas about how much debt they actually have. And so same thing when you
have people track their budget, well, now all of a sudden, they're on their best behavior, because
not only do they don't want to admit to anybody else, they don't want to admit to themselves,
where they're actually spending their money. And so I use that comparison a lot when it comes to
tracking calories. And we use it a lot with our clients is, hey, look at this thing like a budget.
So Peter, you made the example that you were maintaining your body weight on 4400 calories a
day. And by the way, for the listener wondering, I was training a heck of a lot more than I train
now. That's when I was, I mean, truthfully, probably exercising three hours a day.
So you had a very large budget, right? Now, if you have a large budget, if I'm talking monetary,
can I is it is a sports car a good purchase? I mean, you know, if it brings you happiness and joy,
sure, but not if you can't afford it, right. But if you can, if you make a if you have a large
enough budget, you can pay your mortgage and you can pay your utilities and you can, you know, do
all the responsibilities that you need to and you still have some leftover to buy that sports car.
And it brings you happiness. I would say go for it. Right. By the same token, if you make, you know,
50,000 a year and you're going to buy a $70,000 or $100,000 sports car, I would say that's probably
a really bad idea. Right. Unless you've got a ton of money sucked away in the bank. And so by the
same token, when people see, you know, kind of like, you know, what I what I really tend to utilize
flexible dieting for myself and a lot of our clients, people say, well, they're just eating
junk food all the time. No, no, what you're seeing is people are posting this because they're so
shocked that they can eat some junk food and lose weight that they tend to post that stuff. And
people say, well, you know, that can't be good for them. And my response is, you know, everything is
on a continuum here. You know, there's a big difference between somebody having like a small
bowl of ice cream that they fit into their budget for the day that allows them to kind of
feel less restricted and feel like they're they're not missing out, that prevents them from having
a huge binge session, you know, down the road when their willpower eventually breaks. It doesn't
work for everybody, but it works for some people. If they can have that little ice cream, but they're
still getting enough dietary fiber, they're still hitting the protein, they're not going over calories,
they're getting micronutrients in, I would say, what's the problem with that? Right?
This is probably the question I actually get asked the most lane from patients. And I'm guessing you
do a lot, which is, Peter, do you think it is better to be completely restrictive
or to have frequent cheat meals like one meal a week or one day a week where you go completely
off the rails or just to have a little bit of stuff that is an indulgence every single day? And
I actually I don't have a great answer for them other than there is no right answer here. And
even for an individual, that might change. And I'll use always my example, which was for three
years, I was on a ketogenic diet with the exception of one day. So in whatever 365 times
three is for that many days, I never deviated from a ketogenic diet except for one meal
when I had about seven pieces of cake at my wife's birthday. And I said, that was really
interesting. Like I'm amazed I was able to do it. I look back at that period, which was 2011 to 2014.
And I think I don't know how you did it. I could never do it again. It'd be very hard for me to
go on a ketogenic diet for more than two weeks now. So and if I did, if I try, if I if someone
put a gun in my head and said, I really want you to do this for a year. I just can't imagine I
could. I mean, the reality of it is like that would be a very difficult thing to do. And so for me,
like I don't know what the word is, but like I can definitely get away with a daily indulgence
or a weekly indulgence. And it's very easy for me to go right back on program because I basically
follow a very simple rule, which is never do too bad things back to back. Like if you ever if you
ever miss a workout that which sometimes is going to happen, the single most important thing is
making sure the next day you work out. Yeah, get back on the horse. Yeah. If you and if you ever
have like a complete blowout meal, the single most important meal is the next one. So so that
works for me. But I also realize in working with so many people, there are some people who do very
well in a highly, highly restricted environment. And when they deviate from that restricted
environment, it sets them off on a path that doesn't make sense. So I mean, do you have any
insights for helping someone predict where they're going to be? Or do you just say, no, you know what?
Just try them all out. Try all of these approaches and let's revisit in a month. I think part of it
depends on person's personality and their individual psychology. What we know is that if you want to
lose weight specifically, you are going to have to use some form of restriction, right, whether it's
calorie counting points, carb restriction, fat restriction, you know, unprocessed food, whatever,
you're gonna have to use fasting, you're gonna have to use some form of restriction, right,
either some form of dietary restriction, calorie restriction or time restriction,
you have to do something there. And all of them, when we say calorie restriction, we talk about
counting calories and active loop, but all of these things work because they restrict calories.
That's that's also important to note. I want to come back to that, by the way, because this is
to me the crux of where I think people will assume you and I don't agree, but I'm pretty sure we do
agree. But let's go with that thread. And then I'm going to come back to the jugular question around
that. Very simple. You have to have some form of restriction, but you should pick the form of
restriction that feels least restrictive to you as an individual. And this is where people get
really crossed up. And I'll give you an example. People find will find that form of restriction
that felt really unrestricted to them. And you hear it all the times. I tried intermittent fasting,
it felt like I wasn't even dieting, I lost 50 pounds, and it wasn't even hard. Then they will
assume that this is the right one, that this is the right approach for everyone because it was
the right approach for them. And we tend to retroactively then try to justify why physiologically
that also is the best approach. And this is why you hear people make kind of crazy claims about
whether it's low carb or intermittent fasting or any one of these diets, which are all excellent
tools. You know, people think that I don't like ketogenic diets or that I don't like intermittent
fasting or anything like that. And that's not true. I just am not a fan of insane claims about
those particular diets. And I think part of the problem is people will say something like, well,
I tried restricting calories, that didn't work. I went on a ketogenic diet and I was eating more
in lost weight. You probably felt like you were eating more. But unless you were weighing out,
again, you were weighing out. And the other thing that we should talk about is when you go to a
ketogenic diet where you have really limited food choices, there's not a whole lot of options for
snacking. You're mostly eating kind of like defined meal foods, right? Intermittent fasting,
you're not really snacking, right? You're having defined meals. By the way, that is a very, very,
very vigorously present characteristic of people who lose weight and keep it off is they don't
really snack. They have defined meals. And there is, I realize I'm going on a tangent here, but
there is something to be said for snacks do not appear to be as satiating, not just because of
the food, but because of the mindset, because when you snack, you tend to do it like not being
mindful about it. And it doesn't have the same satiety effect. So one of the things we tell our
clients is, hey, stop snacking. Not that again, if you like snacks and they work for you and you can
fit them in your calories, it's fine. But if you're having trouble, try stop, stop snacking.
And they say, oh my gosh, like, I didn't even really feel like I was that less hungry. And all
of a sudden I'm losing weight again, cut three, 400 calories out. Yeah. I'll add one point to that
lane, which is when, so I agree just empirically that if you can absolutely eliminate what you
eat between defined meals, and that could be two or three meals per day, most people will have not
just an improvement of body weight and body composition, but biomarkers get better. I mean,
you tend to not be snacking on the best things to begin with.
And actually this is where one of the things where I have found fasting to be a valuable tool
because if you put somebody through a three, five, or even longer day fast, I'm talking
water only fast, even once in their life, they learn a very important lesson, which is I'm not
going to die if I'm hungry, acutely. If I made you fast for 40 days, you might die. But I pretty
much don't think there's a human being on this planet outside of the most sick individual who
couldn't go five days without food and subsiding only on water and minerals. And something about
doing that, even if you do it once for no other reason, it teaches you a couple of things. One,
you can do it. That's a big aha moment. Two, hunger comes in waves. So that five day period
of eating nothing, you will have periods of time when you literally want to eat your arm,
and you will have periods during that five days when you have forgotten that you're fasting.
And so when you take that mindset into, okay, Lane, I just put you through this five days of
very difficult fasting. Now we're going to go to a regimen where I just don't want you to eat
any snacks. And that means from noon till six, I don't want you eating anything.
And now all of a sudden you're like, at three o'clock, I'm really hungry. But you now anchor
that to something that was so much more severe, which is, wait a minute, I'm really hungry because
I haven't eaten in three hours. I'm going to eat in three hours. I think I can make it. And at least
for me and for a number of patients that I've used this sort of method with, it's a very powerful
tool. And you don't need to become a fasting guru to do this, right? You don't have to do a quarterly
fast to experience this. I think just one fast will teach a person this lesson. And I certainly
remember the first time I really had that aha moment when I did my first really long fast and
realized everything that I knew intellectually, but all of a sudden it emotionally made sense as well.
Well, people confuse hunger and appetite a lot. So there's, here's the other big thing is people
say, well, you don't get as hungry on the ketogenic diet or you don't get as hungry on the plant,
plant-based diet. You don't get as hungry on XYZ. I say that's true, but there's a lot more reasons
people eat other than hunger. In fact, I would argue that some of the major reasons people eat
has nothing to do with physical hunger, that it's actually societal cues, stress, and various other
things. And so one of the things we'll tell our clients, boredom is a big one for me. Absolutely.
One of the reasons that exercise people, one of the reasons exercise works so well is one,
it sensitizes you to satiety signals. That's actually the most powerful effect it has on
weight loss. You actually become more sensitive to your satiety hormones, but two, you're spending
an hour doing something physical where you're not bored and eating, right? So it makes a difference.
But one of the things we tell our clients is like, listen, if you want to lose weight,
you're going to be hungry at some point. Like this is just something like physically hungry.
You will be. And like this is coming from somebody who has been stage lean as a body builder with
absolutely minimal amounts of body fat. When I talk about the level of discomfort,
it is an all consuming, you cannot think about anything else other than when you're going to
eat next. When you finish your meal, you're hungry five minutes later and already thinking about your
next meal. And the level of fatigue is so high that the best way I can describe standing up off
a chair is a monumental effort. There's no other way to describe it. And we talked about this in
the first podcast, but just because I find it so amazing, can we can we relive a few minutes of
that lane? So going into a show, we're obviously referring to your bodybuilding stuff, not your
powerlifting stuff. You'll be what, 4% roughly on stage? It depends on what the metric. I mean,
I've I've caliper it at 2%. In DEXA is the gold standard. But again, it's still I tell people,
unless you're a cadaver and they're excising your adipose tissue, you'll never know exactly
what your adipose tissue is because all these measurements make assumptions. On DEXA, I was
probably five or 6%. That's where a lot of stage lean bodybuilders end up end up being.
So how many days leading to that moment on stage? Are you really in the throes of this type of
discomfort that you're describing? I will tell you that on calipers, I can get to about 7%
come down from like 14 or 15, which is where if I'm up to like 230 pounds, I'll be 14 or 15,
probably more like 15 on calipers. Get to seven. No problem. Like that doesn't even hardly faze me.
I've done it so many times. From seven to two or 3% is exponentially more difficult.
And that'll take you how many weeks?
Probably 12 to 16 to go for those from seven to two. Because again, it's not just losing the
weight. It's also maintain the lean mass to maintaining the lean mass as a drug free athlete
is extremely difficult. Those conversations I have with our client, our team, Bialand clients
all the time, and if we want to do a show is 12 weeks is not going to do it if you're drug free,
unless you're already extremely lean. The best natural bodybuilder ever coached his name was
Brian Whitaker. And he won the WMBF lightweight world title six times and is the only man to win
the WMBF overall world title and the IFPA overall world title, which were the two biggest federations,
the only man to ever unify them. And this guy at 12 weeks out, you would say he's ready.
And then he would lose 10 more pounds from that. And of those 10 pounds, how many would be fat?
Probably six or seven visit this is the problem is is the loss of body fat and lean mass.
What we see in I realized we're going off of the tangent, but this is really interesting is
when you're looking at people who are like overweight and obese, it's they can lose almost
100% fat tissue. Now, what people don't realize is adipose is actually about 13% lean tissue.
So it is very normal to see about a 13 to 20% loss of lean tissue when dieting, because even if you
lost just adipose tissue, you would lose some lean mass. You mean lean mass in terms of some of the
water loss water and adipose also has protein in it as well. And part of that is lost during the
during the remodeling of the tissue. So you have that. But then as a drug free bodybuilder,
again, it's important to make that distinction. Because if you're on steroids, that obviously
changes the physiology and tilts things much more towards retention of lean mass, if not building
some. As you get leaner and leaner, you are going to have a progressive shift of more and more lean
body mass loss for a few reasons. One, because your adipose stores are lower, your body is sending
out hormones to try and conserve fat tissue. So think about it from this perspective, if you are
200 pounds, and 190 of that is lean body mass, because you're just a little bit that last little
bit of body fat. Now guess where the biggest reservoir of energy is? It's the wood table.
Now, right. So now we're in emergency mode. And okay, well, now we can start to tear the house down,
because it's more important to keep this fat tissue than it is to keep this massive amount
of lean tissue. Right. So it really is interesting. So for him, people might look at that and say,
well, he lost 10 pounds and almost half of it was lean mass. Yes. But one of the fundamental things
that people do not understand is the best way to look as muscular as possible is to be as lean as
humanly possible. And I would encourage your listeners to go look up a guy named Brian Whitaker.
He's actually a professor of economics at Oklahoma State, one of the greatest natural
bodybuilders of all time and also very smart guy. Lovely person too. Like his gluteus muscles,
he's so lean that he has veins in his glutes and striations that look like fingers. I mean,
it's really incredible. Right. Which is something you typically, I remember the first bodybuilder
I ever saw that in, which is not to say it was the first bodybuilder it appeared in, but I remember
as a kid seeing that in Samir Banu, who was the 1983 Mr. Olympia. What's that? And I was like,
I remember as a kid, like, I'm maybe 13 years old seeing him and looking at the striations in his
lower back and in his glutes. And it was exactly that look that you described. Yeah. And yeah,
to think that one could achieve that without steroids and diuretics is pretty amazing.
Yeah. And so like Brian was about 160 to 165 pounds on stage and he's five foot nine. But if
you would see picture, if you saw him in his shirt, you would go, oh, he's nothing. He looks athletic.
You know, but then if you, if you see him in, you know, with his clothes off, you would say,
oh, he's 200 pounds at least. And sorry, you said he's five nine and was 165. Yep.
Yep. Actually that's, you can't hardly see it, but the photo right there. Wow. We did a, we did a
three times bodyweight deadlift challenge and his at Oklahoma state years ago. And because Brian's
also very strong. Um, that's him there. And he would walk around at what? In his off season,
one 85, you know, one 80, something like that. And it still looked very lean. Right. So again,
when you're talking about bodybuilding and I realized probably lost about 90% of the audience
talking about this, but we'll bring it back to the other stuff in a second. But I think bodybuilders
can really teach important lessons about physiology, you know, in terms of, you know,
energy metabolism. I think I agree with you. I think it is such an underappreciated discipline
because it's very easy to dismiss bodybuilders as, you know, drug using whatever and everything
you're saying applies to the steroid using and the natural. It's just in the natural,
it's a bigger lever, but it's still a huge lever. If you're a, if you're a drug competing bodybuilder,
like they can't, they are, I mean, whenever I interact with these guys, I am blown away at
how dialed in they are on their nutrition. Yep. Insane. And so one of the things we tell our
clients and one of the things I've heard so many times from different competitors is
you have to learn to sit with your discomfort and that, that can apply to many things.
I mean, even in like business, I'm sitting with my discomfort right now because
we've expanded our businesses and our expenses are way higher. Now we're making good revenue,
but the, the, the 20 year old lane in me goes, it would just take one bad month and these expenses
will crush us. You know, like that, like that, that kind of voice is in there. So it's, you know,
talking yourself through and sitting with that discomfort when it comes to food,
it's really asking yourself, okay, am I actually hungry or am I just queued up to eat right now?
And then the answer is yes. If it truly is physical hunger, it's really talking yourself
through this and saying, okay, what are my goals? What's important to me? Do I,
could I eat sure? Is it going to make it more difficult later? Like for example,
if you're hungry at 11 a.m. Okay. Well, if I eat a big meal now, I'll feel better now,
but then what's it going to be like later? You know, all these things weigh in. And again,
there's no right or wrong answer to this, but what I would say is most people can handle a
lot more discomfort than they think they can. And just because you're uncomfortable,
doesn't mean you have to do anything about it. You can, you can sit with that. And I think a lot of
people really haven't done that. And even that like internal conversation, like in it, again,
this is why obesity is so difficult when we talk about people, because it's not people want to make
it about the X's and O's. It's not about the X's and O's. It's not about eat this protein, carbs,
fats. It's not about any of that. That stuff is, I remember when I first got into coaching people,
you know, 15 years ago, I was like, well, if I just tell them to eat this, they're going to lose weight.
And then you realize that like stress and trauma and hardwired habits and behaviors are so
difficult to change. And it really is, if you look at the research data,
it really is more, I know my cat's making a special appearance. He's the best cat. It really
is more about changing people's habits and behaviors than it is about the X's and O's.
And I mean, even right down to like sports, I'll use this comparison. X's and O's matter.
But you know what really matters for a head coach, leadership. That's what really matters.
Being able to get, communicate and get everybody on the same page and changing, you know, what do
they call it in the NFL? They call it changing the culture. This person came in and they changed
the culture of this team. That's not X's and O's. That's habits and behaviors. There was a really
great systematic review by a gal named Marie Shbrekli. She's doing her PhD over in England.
And Humble Brag, she actually messaged me and said that reading my book is what inspired her to go
to her PhD. And now she's done this great systematic review. So that's always like the most
cool thing when I hear that. She did a systematic review and looked at people specifically who
lost weight and kept it off. What did they have in common? What were the things that identified as
being really difficult? And what were the things that they identified as being really motivating?
And the things that came up weren't dietary really. It was their environment. It was their habits,
their behaviors. You know, one of the big things that came up was support, either good or bad,
that support made a big difference. And specifically support in terms of like,
I believe in you. I know you can do this. How can I help you? Those sorts of things versus
the criticism, micromanaging type of support. And then also stress was a big one.
Trauma was a big one. Binge eating was a big one. That's a really underappreciated part of this,
is the binge eating component. I think a lot more people struggle with that than would like to admit.
Because if you look at people, I would say Monday through Friday, a lot of people do great.
And they get to the weekend and they get the pancakes in the morning. They're drinking
throughout the day. By the way, everyone, alcohol has calories and it's really calorie dense.
And also causes you to make not so great food choices. And so a lot of people eat 1,500
calories the week and then they'll easily go 4,000 calories on the weekends.
So a lot of this is just reprogramming habits and behaviors. And that's what really came up in that
systematic review was it was not, Hey, this diet came out as this was what these people were using.
No, there was no one diet that came up as being superior to the others. What came up repeatedly
was these series of habits and behaviors that people had that helped them do this.
Yeah. And I think, you know, bringing it back now to the energy balance question,
I think today we know a lot more than we did 10 years ago. I think 10 years ago,
at least for me personally, there was still an open question about the impact of different
macronutrients on energy expenditure, both deliberate and non deliberate. So,
but I think when you look at the body of literature and, you know, I have to declare my
conflict here, right? So I used to be part of an organization that actually funded two of the,
you know, really big studies in this space, one out of Boston Children's Hospital by David Ludwig,
and then one was a consortium of people that included Rudy Leibel, who you mentioned a moment
ago, Kevin Hall was the PI, Eric Ravison, Steve Smith, et cetera.
That's like the heavy hitters name of metabolism right there.
This was the six PIs on this study were six of the biggest names in all of this space. And this
was a very rigorously done study. And look, was it a perfect study? No, it was a pilot study. It was
really designed to be the study to work out the kinks to do the enormous study that actually
never got funded. But it was still a very good study. And it still answered important question,
which was at least comparing a relatively clean standard American diet to a ketogenic diet,
it'd be hard to make the case that there was more than 50 to 150 calorie difference in energy
expenditure at an isocaloric swap. Now, there's different ways to interpret that. Some would say
that's huge. If you have a 50 K, which is what the difference was in the chamber versus 150 or
160, which is what the W labeled water showed, that could still be very significant over a long
enough period of time. There has been a significant debate about the validity of doubly labeled water
in a ketogenic diet. You mentioned John Speakman, he and Kevin Hall wrote a review about this
suggesting that doubly labeled water really doesn't apply. There's an artifact in a ketogenic diet.
So if you just look at the chamber data and say, well, you know, 50 K cal per day,
does that really matter? Not sure. But regardless, it wasn't 250 or 500 K cal per day. And to me,
that was a very important insight because prior to that point, I didn't really know because if you
look back at, you know, the Vermont study from the 1960s, if you look back at Ansel Keyes stuff
where they didn't have metabolic chambers, they're on wards, but it wasn't quite the same.
It was really unclear to me. I would say today the evidence has to be overwhelming that if,
for example, a ketogenic diet produces remarkable weight loss, it has to be doing it through intake
reduction, not through an increase in energy expenditure. I think that you're 100% right.
And I'm going to take that kind of piecemeal. So the first thing I will say is let's throw out
the energy expenditure stuff for now. And I know we just spent a lot of time talking about energy
balance. It's important, but we're assuming that these measures are accurate. There's even error
in direct calimetry because you can only measure as accurately as your equipment that you have to
measurement. That's right. And those numbers I just touted, you could argue that they were at
the limit of detection, at least for the indirect calorimeter. Absolutely. The 57 K cal per day
was probably right at the detection. So it could have been zero, it could have been 100.
It's we're really on a razor's edge of detection. And I think that the point you made was that the
carbohydrate insulin model of obesity would predict a much bigger change in energy expenditure. So
therefore, at least that version of it, it has to be falsified based on that. And even with the 150
calories, that would not explain the difference. And again, if we look at studies that assess loss
of body fat under controlled environments, we just don't see differences between low carbon low fat
when calories are controlled calories and protein are controlled. We don't see it. In fact, there's
actually a very small favoritism towards low fat. But again, I think that that's probably a data
artifact and not actually a real difference. There was, you mentioned David Ludwig, there was a
recent or more recent meta analysis he did that got a lot of buzz because basically his assertion
was that, well, if you look at the short term data, yes, there doesn't appear to be much difference.
But if you look at after 17 days, there appears to be a large difference in the energy expenditure
anywhere from like 150 to 300 calories per day favoring low carb. Was that with doubly labeled
water again? That's it. So that's so the issue was and I went through this with a fine tooth comb.
And again, the meta analysis itself was very well done. The statistics were very good. But when
there was metabolic chamber data available or doubly labeled water, they use doubly labeled water.
Now, what I would tell you is that's like saying I've got caliper data available and
dexa data available, but I'm going to use the caliper data. Well, that's fine. But keep in mind
that dexa is what calipers are validated against. So you're talking about a primary measure versus
a secondary measure. By the way, I've already forgotten Kevin and Kevin Hall and John Speakman's
primary criticism of DLW in a KD. Do you remember the gist of the thesis where the artifact comes
from? Yes. So basically, there's more CO2 produced than is accounted for in the constant of the
equation. The 1.11 is probably too low a number. Yeah. So you overproduce CO2 compared to what the
prediction would be based on that equation. And so basically what that means is that in a low
carb setting, you're probably getting an artificial increase in energy expenditure.
Oh, so the 1.11 would actually be too big. It's probably too big a coefficient.
What I went back to is I said, okay, you know what? Let's say that this isn't an artifact
or an effect of the differences in measures. And again, direct calimetry, if you're on a
standard diet, the association with double the level water is an R of 0.8, which is pretty good
for free living stuff. Yeah, but it ain't 0.99 either. 0.8 is good, but not exceptional.
And then a low carb is 0.5, which is a pretty big difference from a 0.8. It basically just means
it's not as tightly correlated. Let's throw all that out. I went through every single one of those
studies that Ludwig looked at and then looked at, did they measure body composition? And what did
the body composition stuff say? Because what do we really care about? Do we care about what energy
expenditure says on a readout or do we care about losing body fat? I mean, I think most people would
say we care about losing body fat. Not one study saw a difference between the low carb conditions
or the low fat or balanced diet when calories and protein were equated. So to me, that's truly
the metric and that's what we care about. So to me, that's actually great news because what it says
is, hey, do whatever diet you prefer. If you like low carb, heck yeah, it's certainly not any worse
than doing a low fat diet. If you don't like low carb, there's other options. By the way, you can
just do a balanced diet too. There's nothing wrong with that. I think balanced diet sometimes can be
a little bit harder for people to moderate unless you're doing some kind of portion control.
But yeah, it says that pretty much you can do what you want and still lose body fat.
That's not, I'm not trying to throw shade at David Ludwig, even though I have on Twitter before.
But it just goes to show you that if you change the inputs for a study,
and this is one of the really fundamental problems I think is out there, is people, and even like
some doctors and scientists just aren't equipped to understand studies, to interpret studies
correctly. And people have asked me like, how can I get better at reading this stuff? And I hate to
be somebody who sits in an ivory tower, but I'll tell them, like, if you really feel so passionately,
go to grad school. Because that's, I can tell you sitting down with my PI, Don Layman, who I'm
sure you're very familiar with, and just talking about studies and having him, like literally,
not in a nasty way, but just crush me so many times based on my hypotheses and everything,
and say, well, if you consider this, that was so enlightening for me. I mean, the best part of
grad school was just sitting around a table with graduate students and my and Don, and just
wrapping back and forth and doing these studies. And you just really get a good idea for how to,
like, look critically at this stuff. And now on to the point where I tell people, I'm like,
I don't get excited about one study, wake me up when there's 10. You know what I mean? Wake me
up when there's 10. And even then, I'm going to look at the how it was done and make sure. And I
tell people, I hear this a lot. I don't trust science because this study says this thing,
and this study says that thing. I said, if you truly understand what you're looking at,
you understand statistics, you understand research design, when you go into the methods and you look
at the results, don't read the conclusions of the authors. Look at the actual results,
look at the methods, and you can usually understand why they seemingly found different results.
Yeah, I'll put in one shameless plug for something we did. We have a series on the
blog called Studying Studies where we go through all of this methodology. But I agree with you,
it's not a substitute for getting reps on the field. In other words, that's sort of like reading
everything about playing a sport, but you actually have to play. And one of the things we've done
internally, and we've toyed with the idea of if we should just put them out there, is Journal Club.
So what you describe is basically Journal Club. That's really how you learn how to read studies.
You sit around with a bunch of people and it's formal, right? We had it every Monday morning,
I think, or maybe Thursday afternoon, I can't remember, but twice a year, depending on the size
of the lab or four times a year, you present a paper for an hour and everybody else's job is to
see how you've maybe missed something or misunderstood something and really poke and pry.
And so every single week you're getting those reps on the field and you get pretty darn good
at reading the fine print. So we do this once a month internally with our team, in part because
it's just such a fun experience. And two, it gives us a chance to pick a paper a month and really
dissect it. So maybe at some point we'll put those out there just so people can at least watch. It's
one step closer, I guess, to doing the reps, but yeah, you kind of have to do it.
Yeah, it's tough. There's no substitute for that experience. Now, that being said,
like one of the... So understanding this, I started thinking about, how can I help people with this?
And so we're actually going to have like a periodical, a research review coming out
monthly through our website that's going to be subscription-based that we're going to take.
There are other research reviews out there, but we're really going to try and make this like
for the layman, for somebody who has no... We're going to say, here's what they looked at,
here's what they found, here's what we think they found if we disagreed. Because I've read
studies where I'm like, I read the author's conclusion, I'm like, well, that's not what you
found, you actually found this. And then we're going to say, here's what it means for you
practically. So that's funny that we both kind of like seen that need, because... And again,
a lot of this is also media driven, because it's about what's the most punchy headline we can get
out there. And so I remember a great example was like, this happens so much with mechanistic stuff.
It's like there was an article and it was something to the effect of smelling your
partner's farts might help prevent cancer. And what the research study actually showed was that
one of the volatile fatty acids that's produced by the gut microbiome in response to fiber
may have a protective effect on breast cancer when they gave it to animals in a high dose.
And it's like, that's a long way from you taking a sniff of your partner's fart and preventing
cancer. But that's what confuses people. All right, let's pivot to another application of this.
Everything we've talked about so far has really set the stage for understanding
the role that macronutrients, but more specifically, calories and energy intake and
expenditure play in weight loss. Let's now talk about a very specific macronutrient,
which is protein and its importance in muscle acquisition. So I have a saying that I'm sure
many others have said, and I'm sure I'm paraphrasing it from somebody, but never in the history of
civilization, I will assert as a 90 year old person said, I wish I had less muscle.
That can't be uttered, right? If you want to be metabolically healthy,
the best thing you can do is have lots of lean body mass. It is a metabolic sink is the best
way to describe it. If you look at people who are even like obese, who are power lifters,
they might have like some elevations in like blood lipids and whatnot, but usually their
insulin sensitivity and blood glucose is still okay. If you look at people who train really hard,
even with excess adiposity, I mean, they see this with people who are obese, who they start them just
exercising without exercise. One of the only things that we know of that without even weight
loss improves metabolic health and substantially, really substantially. And I think I was actually
on the Rogan podcast and one of the points I made a few years ago was I said, this was the one with
Dom. Yes. So I said, you know, a lot of people get real caught up in carbs and fats and all this,
and they're not even exercising. Well, you're literally, you're, you are stepping over
dollars to pick up fractions of pennies right now. Like if you just got active and it's not
even a high dose that's required. It's not, I mean, a high dose is great, but just going and being
sedentary and walking, you will see improvements in health markers for, you know, a hundred minutes
a week. That's it. And then obviously there's, there can be a linear effect. But you know,
people will look at me and I remember I had my blood work done a while back that I do have
familial hypochlorosterelemia. So my LDL tends to run a little bit high, but you know, people
who are speculating that I would have like really high inflammation because I talk about, you know,
I still will eat, you know, um, probably around 70 to 80 grams of sugar a day, but I'm also getting,
you know, 60, 70 grams of fiber along with that. Oh, your CRP is going to be all of it. My CRP
wasn't hardly detectable. It was on the low ends of detection. And again, that just speaks to the
fact that there is a big difference between somebody who is a athlete training hard, who has
a lot of muscle mass versus somebody who's sedentary with excess adiposity. It's just,
it's not even comparable when you talk about like food choices and whatnot. You have a lot more you
can get away with, with, with a lot of muscle mass. And your point that being older and frail,
people don't think about this. This is something that, you know, everybody's kind of like, well,
the funniest thing I get Peter is people say, Oh, you do all that heavy lifting. You're going to be
in pain when you're older. You're going to be in pain when you're older, regardless. You might as
well be in pain and strong versus in pain and weak. I have members of my family who I love dearly,
who have been sedentary for a long time, who have all kinds of sciatica and back issues.
I mean, I have had back issues from heavy lifting, but they come and they go and, you know, I'm
still here. I'm still able to lift. And honestly, I find most people who have experienced activity
and inactivity will almost always tell you if they're being deliberate and how they recall it,
you're generally in more discomfort when you're inactive. Oh, for sure. Sitting down. I, again,
I don't remember where these zingers came from, but none of them are mine. But this is one of my
favorites, right? Sitting is to lower back pain. What bourbon is to alcoholism. Hell yeah. The,
the, the worst thing you can do is be a mobile. I say as I'm sitting here, right? I know it's your
standing. Yeah. So part of journal club in grad school, we had seminars every week where people
would either present their exit seminars for their PhD or we'd have outside speakers come in. And one
of them interestingly was a lower back pain specialist. And this would have been circle like
2007, 2008. And one of the interesting things he said was if we, which is now kind of common
knowledge, if we MRI an elite athlete, a lot of times I'll look at their MRI and go, Oh my God,
you must be in horrible discomfort. And they go, really? No, I feel fine. You know, and they've
got all these disc bulges and herniations and whatnot. And they're completely asymptomatic.
And then he'll, he said, we'll have sedentary people come in and they'll be in excruciating
pain and I'll pull up their MRI and they've just got a little tiny disc bulge.
There is probably no more diagnostic test that is uncorrelated from clinical outcome
than an MRI of the lumbar spine. Again, not a specialist, but I've, you know,
I've spoken with lumbar specialists like Stu McGill. Um, you know, they say, you know, it's,
it's data. It's kind of like a DEXA. It's like it's data, but you know, it shouldn't really
dictate treatment. Treatment should be based on pain and what triggers your pain.
And that's a whole nother rabbit hole. The pain, the pain world is a whole nother rabbit hole.
The idea that people think the human body is like a bag of meat that's just connected to your brain.
And now we know that pain is more like an emotion than anything, but I digress.
So let's talk about it now through this lens though. Right? So I want to talk about it.
Whether we're dealing with a 50 year old woman who comes to you, who's never lifted a weight
in her life. Okay. So she's the mom of three has never touched a weight. Um, she's going through
menopause. So now she's actually starting to put on a little bit of weight, maybe for the first
time in her life. So she's actually starting to get a little chubby and you know, she, you wouldn't,
she's not overweight, but she just feels she's, you know, her clothes are getting a little bit snug
and her assumption is I need to do more cardio. I need to be more active and it probably needs to be
disproportionately cardio. And so, so you look at her and you make the diagnosis,
ma'am, we can do some cardio. We got to put some muscle on you. So you do a DEXA on her and she
comes back 30% body fat, but it's kind of skinny fat. Her ALMI is six, right? So meaning it puts
her at the 10th percentile of muscle mass. Um, what are you going to do with her and what are you
going to make her eat? Yeah. So I think the first thing to say is that muscle is a lot like bone
in that you want to lay down as much as possible because eventually it's going to start receding.
But it is still possible to add muscle. So people will hear that and go, well, I'm 50. Yeah. No,
in fact, right across the street from my lab at the University of Illinois, trying out my lab,
the lab I was in, uh, right across the street, uh, at the exercise physiology building,
they did study an 80 year old frail elderly. Well, they basically had them start where they would
squat to a high chair and come up gradually. They put the chair down. This was like a 16 week study
and I don't have the citation, but I just remember talking to the other grad student about it. So
please forgive me, everyone out there. But they said they were amazed because by the end of it,
one, these people as a percentage of their body weight increased their lean body mass
pretty much the same amount that a 20 year old does. Okay. So the relative increase was similar.
Now they're, they're less overall, they had less overall mass they put on because their weight was
lower to start. And they said by the end, some of them were actually able to add weight, like
extra weight and squat all the way down to a parallel chair, which the people in the study
were completely mind blown that this was possible for them. And it's 16 weeks. It's not even a long
time, you know? And we're talking about people who like probably think that they're heading for
a wheelchair, you know, like it is never too late to get active. So that's the first thing. Right.
And let's bring it back to your finance example. It's never too late to start saving. Absolutely.
True that you're better off if you can, if you can be one of the fortunate people who write out of
college or who doesn't even go to college and go straight to work out of high school or whatever,
and you can start saving right away. Well, that's fantastic. But just because you've made it to 40
and you've been scrapping by and you haven't been able to save, but now you come into a little bit
of disposable income and you can start saving, there is zero downside to that. Better late than
never. Absolutely. That's a great comparison. I actually never thought about that before. So
I'm going to steal that for later. Take it. So I'll give correct attribution. And then as far as
diet wise, so give me a typical because I can tell you what when I see that woman in my practice,
which I see all the time, I'll tell you what she looks like. And I want you to compare it to your
version of that. But when I see that woman, she looks exactly as I've said, right? So she's 50.
She's going through menopause. She still looks normal, but the composition of her body is really
changing. You do that, Dexa, she's 30 to 35 percent body fat, very little muscle mass.
You take as close scrutiny of what she's eating. She's getting 50 to 60 grams of protein a day on
a good day. And when you do a strength metric assessment on her, she is incredibly weak,
even as even if you were to compare her to another female at an appropriate age adjustment.
And, you know, I have a very stark conversation with her when I pull up something called the
death bars. So the death bars are this analysis that Bob Kaplan did for me, God, probably about
six months ago, a year ago, which is basically just causes of death by decade. And I double
click on accidental deaths. So I have a we this death bars is so cool because you can double
click on it all over the place. And once once you call out accidental deaths, you realize
something really interesting. Unlike cardiovascular disease, cancer, Alzheimer's disease,
which are very age dependent, meaning the older you get, the more the incidence goes up. Generally
with cancer, it actually comes down a little bit in the last decade. Accidental deaths are
basically the same forever once you reach the age of 10. So from 10 year olds to 20 year olds,
and 80 year olds to 90 year olds, they all have the same number of accidental deaths per year,
more or less. What differs dramatically is the type of accident. So in young people,
it is disproportionately, sadly, overdoses that are the lion's share followed by automotive
accidents. In the oldest subset of the population, it becomes almost entirely accidental falls.
It is. And when you show somebody this graph, because it's so pronounced,
I've never seen a person who doesn't just stop in their tracks because they cannot believe how much
morbidity and mortality results from falling and frailty once you reach about the age of 70, 75.
I mean, the data is there to back it up. The, I believe I may butcher this citation,
but I believe there was a study by Bob Wolf that was kind of a review that showed essentially
after age 65, you could tie the majority of deaths to some kind of lack of muscular strength
or lack of muscle. And if you look at, they've done these meta-analyses of mortality,
showing that your lean body mass is inversely, inversely proportional to your risk of mortality
after age like 50. And by the way, strength is even slightly higher. So, yeah. So the hazard
ratio for being strong to not strong is about 3.2 for all cause mortality. Think about that.
Which is a big hazard ratio. It's a freaking staggering hazard ratio. But you're talking
about on the level of smoking right there. No, it's higher than smoking. Actually, smoking is
about 2. So to put that in perspective, right? End stage renal disease is about 3.
And the only thing that's higher, and I talked about this on another podcast, is elite,
meaning top 2.5 percentile of VO2 max compared to bottom 25th percentile of VO2 max.
That has a delta of 5. 5.1 is the hazard ratio. And of course, these are not mutually exclusive.
So why not have remarkable cardio respiratory fitness, muscle mass, and strength?
Yep. So I think one of the big barriers, especially with the type of client you're talking about,
is, well, I don't want to get too bulky or too muscular.
Can you dispel the myth of accidental muscle, please?
Yeah. So as someone who's spent their entire adult life trying to get too muscular,
and basically just looks really fit in a t-shirt, yeah, don't worry about that. You're going to be
okay. And if you do start to get too muscular, you can always just back off. That's pretty easy.
That's like saying, I mean, literally, let's use a financial comparison.
I'm worried about getting too rich.
I might get too rich and, you know, like, okay, well, if you're worried about that, you know.
We've got some great philanthropies that we can introduce you to.
Yes, exactly. So it's like getting in a car and worried about becoming a NASCAR driver
spontaneously, you know. Just the amount of benefit you will get from three times a week,
30 to 40 minutes of resistance training, not even crazy intense resistance training,
just an amount that forces your body to adapt will be unbelievable in terms of your level of fitness
and your ability to live a long, healthy life.
So tell me what you would do. So let's use this, again, this generic, but rather very specific
example of this 50 year old woman who is not completely unfit. So let's even give it to her
that she's she still does yoga, doing some cardio, walks, does some stuff,
but she's never lifted weights before. Tell me what her first four month program looks like from you.
Probably going to see what first off what's reasonable for her lifestyle. Like,
what can she actually do? So let's say she says, Lane, I'm willing to commit to 45 minutes,
three times a week in the in the weight room. Great. I think that probably lower body strength
is a little bit more important than upper body strength in terms of preventing falls.
I mean, we always think about falls from a bone density perspective. We don't want people to fall
and break their hip because that that specific fall is pretty much a death sentence if you're
over the age of 65. So but people worry about the bone density. Well, if they didn't fall in the
first place, if they had the muscle mass to catch themselves, you wouldn't have to worry about that.
And also, by the way, bone density is increased by lifting weights much more than anything you'd
ever get through your diet. So I would say, let's just see what you can do. And then I would probably
do two lower body days, one upper body day could even flip flop it on alternating weeks if you
wanted to even it out. And it'd mostly be honestly, just some machine stuff that's very easy for her
to do to get in there because honestly, she never trained before. Everything's going to cause an
adaptation. And that's what we're looking to get. Like, I'm not going to have her come in and try
and free squat or deadlift or anything like that. Like, that's a really horrible idea. It's just
going to frustrate her and not actually apply the load where we want it because she's not going to
be able to balance it very well. So when you say machines, would you be thinking like, look,
you'd be happy with her doing a leg extension, a leg curl. Absolutely. Yeah. Would you have her
do anything that's a little more compound and complicated, for example, holding dumbbells and
stepping up onto a bench where now she has to manage grip strength with a bit of balance and
also getting the leg load or is that not first cycle? I probably wouldn't do that in the initial
weeks just because the soreness is going to be so high. It's going to impede a lot of that movement
well. And people tend to think about soreness in the wrong way. It's correlated with muscle growth
and strength, but it is not causative. And so what I'll tell people is if you're sore all the time,
you're probably training incorrectly. If you're never sore, you're also probably training
incorrectly. So it's something that if you're doing an appropriate amount of volume and intensity,
there probably should be some soreness from time to time. But if you're getting sore all the time,
then your programming is pretty bad. So what I'm trying to do in the initial stages is just actually
get enough to adapt and not cause enormous amounts of soreness because one, it's going to be-
Can discourage her as well.
It can be discouraging. That's it. I mean, if you can't go about, like everybody's known that like
feeling after their first like hard squat day, like good luck doing anything, you know. And so
that's going to be a discouraging thing, especially if somebody's got life, like not all of us are
meatheads who love that feeling. And also it's going to impede her subsequent sessions, right?
So she's not, especially if you're talking about something like a step up that requires more
coordination. If you're overly sore, that's going to be really, really difficult. So I'm probably
going to try and get her through like four to six weeks, which if we look at the data on muscle
protein turnover, I think we talked about this last time a little bit. You don't really see
increases in hypertrophy during the six weeks, the first six weeks of resistance training. What
you're getting is actually a remodeling of the tissue to be stronger, more resilient,
and it starts protecting itself against damage. And so that seems to be where muscle protein
synthesis goes up, but muscle protein degradation also goes up. And so basically you're kind of in
this futile cycle where it's just turning over the tissue. After about six weeks, muscle protein
degradation tends to go down, muscle protein synthesis stays up. And that's where you start
seeing those increases in hypertrophy and lean mass. Now, does a trained athlete also go through
that? Or have you long since passed through that? And are you now generally at the point where
degradation is not having this disproportionate rise relative to synthesis? So it's a great
question. And I actually have a, I thought you might ask this, so I actually have a paper from
Damas et al. pulled up, which is really interesting. So if we look at myofibrillar
protein synthesis in response to resistance exercise, we see what tends to happen is
the amplitude of muscle protein synthesis in trained people is a little bit lower
than untrained. So you don't have quite the same response. It depends on when you measure. If you
measure it 16 hours post, they're about the same. They're about a 40% increase. If you measure it
four hours post, trained is still about 40%, untrained is about 70%. So you've got a little
bit of difference in amplitude, but what really is the difference is the duration. So in trained
people, it's back down to baseline about 10 to 20 hours after the initial resistance training
bout. Whereas the untrained people still have elevated rates of protein synthesis, even like
three days or even like two, three days later. And sorry, Lane, this is just synthesis or this
is net accumulation. This is just synthesis. Got it. So it could be offset by degradation.
It could be and degradation is much more difficult to measure. Unfortunately,
we do have some, so that if we get into the techniques that are used to measure this,
what you find is you really can't measure all three things at one time, unfortunately. So you
can measure kind of the net balance. We do that with what's called an AV balance. So you're looking
at, you take a labeled amino acid, you're infusing it and you're looking, you're sampling in the
arterial of a muscle bed and then the venous of the muscle bed. And so basically depending on how
much of that label shows up in the vein versus the artery, we know how much is being retained
in muscle so that we know what the net is. You can infuse a second label to presumably get
synthesis as well. And then you can figure out the difference of degradation. But the problem with
this is it requires a steady state. You can't do it when you've trained or had a meal or anything
like that. It's pretty much exclusively fasted because there's too many assumptions you have to
make about the rate of appearance versus rate of disappearance and those sorts of things.
You can measure synthesis very easily. Well, I wouldn't say very easily, but much easier than
degradation. And you can measure degradation, but the problem with degradation is how you're
measuring it because it's, we know that for example, out of every amino acid that's used
for protein synthesis, seven out of eight of them are actually from degradation. So it's
amino acids being recycled. Yeah, I remember this of all the things we talked about in our first
episode, Lane, this was the most novel to me. And it's the one thing that I literally find myself
thinking about every day when I finish a workout and go and get a protein shake is I wonder how
many of these amino acids in said shake versus these amino acids that I've just eviscerated from
deadlifting are actually going to be the ones that form through the summation of new myofibril
synthesis. What I would say is don't think about it that way. What I would say is if you want to
maximize muscle mass, you want to maximize protein synthesis obviously and maximize deposition.
And so kind of the theory at first was, all right, if it's only one out of every eight,
and you can only really deposit about five to 10 grams per day net in muscle overall of amino
acids. I mean, that's kind of the max. Say that again. Yeah, so about five to 10 grams a day.
Now think about if you do that over the course of a year, every single day,
I've done this calculation before, so I don't remember it exactly. So I'm going to estimate.
That would be about, look, if you do the math on 10 grams a day, that's eight and a half pounds.
But what do we know about muscle tissue? It's about 70%.
70% water. Yep.
So we're just talking about the actual protein content. So if you take that eight pounds and we
divide it by points or if you take, yeah, 0.3, take eight divided by.
Yeah, it's about 26 pounds.
About 26, that's a lot of lean body mass. Yeah.
Right? So I would say that's a lot of lean body mass, even for a novice trainer. So
we know that it's like the max is probably about five to 10 grams per day in terms of drug free.
Do you know how much that can go up to with anabolic steroids?
I'm not sure quite honestly. There's just a dearth of information about that just because
it's hard to get IRB approval for doing research on steroids.
Yeah, I mean, it would simply be basically the anecdotal evidence of looking at a professional
bodybuilder and asking, you know, for a native.
Yeah. I think the magazines exaggerate a lot of stuff and I would even say 30 pounds of
actual skeletal muscle wet tissue would still be a ton for someone on drugs. I mean, that's a lot
of skeletal muscle tissue. Think about, go to the store and look at 30 pounds of beef.
Oh yeah. Yeah. No, no, it's insane. I mean, look, we just had a female patient in our practice
who went from being not very active to getting very active. And she had a DEXA scan
separated by five months, which I generally don't like doing DEXAs that close together.
But the cardinal sin was just through circumstances were done at different facilities.
The DEXA suggested she gained six pounds of lean tissue. I just said I can't,
one of these DEXAs was wrong. That's six pounds of lean tissue in five months.
I don't know for a woman who maybe I mean, is that possible?
It might. She probably did gain some. Yeah.
I mean, consider also like. Is that would that be expected? I mean, we'll know,
I guess when we repeat it at the one year mark from the beginning, because maybe it'll plateau.
And this would be this remarkable adaptation out of the gate. But it struck me as a lot of lean
tissue. But I mean, if you want to gain eight pounds of lean tissue, lean tissue on a DEXA,
take a DEXA. It could be a lot of water. Yeah. Take a DEXA, jump off, drink a gallon of water
and jump back on and you'll have gained eight pounds. So that's my point. There's the hydration
artifact and all these other things that could be doing it. Yeah. But she probably she probably
did gain some. Most people's lifestyles aren't that volatile that you see that difference.
So she probably did gain some. But in terms of muscle protein synthesis and how much you deposit
muscle, people say, well, if you only need 50 grams to meet your requirement in terms of
being a positive nitrogen balance, because that's how that's determined as nitrogen balance.
You mean the, the RDAs are based on just that. Correct. Yeah. Which are, I mean,
can we dismantle the RDA in a minute? We'll come back to that.
It'll kind of get to that. Yeah. So people say, well, just throw 10 grams of amino acids on top
of that. That's just go to protein on top of that. Because I mean, you're there, right?
That's, that's not how it works. You're, you're assuming that every single amino
acid after that just goes straight to lean tissue. You've already mentioned the thermogenic effect.
How much of that, correct. How much of that is actually coming from the protein itself being
inefficiently metabolized versus a stored energy source. Do we know that?
I would say it's more about the oxidation of the protein and where it's going. But I'll get to
that in a moment. The thing to keep in mind is that in order to maximize your deposition,
to get that five to 10 grams, you need to maximize protein synthesis. But to maximize
protein synthesis requires a disproportionate amount of total protein. So in order for you to
maximize protein synthesis, we think it's around 1.6 to 2.4 grams per kilogram of body weight.
Sorry, say that again. 1.6 to 2.4 grams per kilogram
of lean body weight or total body weight? The meta analysis on this was total body weight.
But if you want to say lean body mass, then you could pump it up to like two to 2.8 grams
per kilogram of lean body mass. And you're pretty much at the same number unless you're like obese
or super lean. And people will like quibble about that. And I'm like, let's just just get in the,
just get in the ballpark. Right. Which, which kind of winds up with that old like one gram
per pound of body weight number. Right. So you need a disproportionate amount of protein
to maximize the deposition. And so yeah, it's just kind of an interesting fact. And the other
thing people will say is we have this, one of the ways that protein is assessed or needs are assessed
is what's called the indicator amino acid method, or they also look at direct amino acid oxidation,
but usually the indicator is kind of the one that's the gold standard. But if you look at direct
amino acid oxidation, so I did this, I pulled up a bar of direct amino acid oxidation, which basically
is like, if you feed a certain amount of protein, if you're feeding increasing levels of protein,
and you look at the oxidation levels of a specific amino acid, it'll be kind of flat.
And then you'll hit an inflection point and kind of go up linearly. And they've said, okay, that
inflection point right there, where you start increasing amino acid oxidation, that's obviously
wasteful, right? That that's extra protein you don't need any more than where that inflection
point is. And then if you look at what actually increases muscle protein synthesis, it's right at
where amino acids start getting oxidized. And do you think that that's just an association?
Or do you think I think it's an association, you don't think that that's causative? No,
I don't think it's causative. I think it's more if you think about it from a teleological perspective
of evolution, it would, to me, and this is one thing Don Lehman was great about, he would always
ask me, why do you think this is happening? You know, from an evolutionary perspective,
it would make sense that at the same amount of protein that you can start using it for energy,
that you can also start building extra tissue. To me, that actually kind of makes sense. You've got
such a surplus that now you can begin to build more lean tissue. And did you say that on average,
that was going to occur at roughly two grams per kilo? Well, that's that's going to be the like,
the higher end of that linear bar, I'd say, so maybe you're probably gonna have,
you're probably going to see amino acid oxidation. I don't know the exact number I could find it if
I dug through enough stuff, but you know, probably around one gram per kilogram of body weight protein
intake, something around there. Oh, I see. So you even start to see that at such a low level. Oh,
yeah. Basically, at the RD, once you pass the RDA, you'll probably just start to oxidize amino acids.
Right. So you really got to think about protein as you've got to throw in a lot more to get out
what you want. It's kind of like so it's just a very inefficient system. Correct. Which works to
your advantage because again, like that wasteful feudal cycle is wasting energy, you know, you're
spending more energy and is that all through gluconeogenesis lane? All of that oxidation is
it going to the liver to make glucose? It's been a while. So forgive me, I could be wrong. There is,
I believe, some direct amino acid oxidation in terms of you have to deaminate it first. But after
that, there's some pretty quick ways to oxidize some of those intermediates. And some of them can
enter the Krebs cycle directly. That's right. Yes, yes, yes. I we do see some paths for amino acids.
Yeah, think about alpha. Yeah. Think about ketoglutarate. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. So that's a direct,
I believe, from glutamate. Yeah. So yeah, there are these places. And I think it's like 60% of
protein is gluconeogenic. That's right. Not all of it is. Yeah. Right. And there is some specific
ketogenic amino acids. See, this is like, if I was still in grad school, I would know this.
This is a Dom Dagestino question. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I think one of the branch chains is actually
ketogenic. So, so you can there are pathways to both. But that's the beautiful thing about
metabolism is like nothing is actually wasted, you know, if it's given off as heat or something
like that, it's because there was a reason for it. You know, if it's, if it's metabolized in the
glucose, it's because there was a reason for it. It's one of the beautiful things. In fact,
one of the pieces of artwork I want to get in my office is the chart of metabolism. You know,
it's just such a cool thing to look at. And, you know, you almost as a scientist, I can look at
that and go, you know, I could believe there's a God. Just from like how beautiful that is.
You know what I mean? Sorry, I realize I'm digressing here. But no, no, no, this is actually
great background. So let's go back to our woman. She is now, you got her in the gym. She's there
three days a week, 45 minutes at a time. We're doing kind of two days lower body, one day upper
body to start for the first six weeks. The goal is don't, don't get hurt. Don't get too sore. Build
up the, build up the habit of doing this thing. Find some resilience, get the tissue resilience.
You're probably overly degrading muscle and not so much synthesizing. So don't expect to actually
add lean mass. When you do your intake assessment on her, you find out she, so let's say she weighs
135 pounds. So that's what 60 ish kilos. And you find out she's eating 50 grams of protein a day.
So she says, and I don't know, you can probably think better through how many calories she's
probably getting on average, but let's say she's getting 2300 calories per day of which only 200
is coming from her protein. How do you change her macros with obviously the most important being the
protein? Yeah. So I think the, one of the biggest things that I really work on people who they say,
well, you know, I, you know, if I can't, I, especially with like our, our, our app carbon
diet coach, um, a lot of people are like, man, these protein, again, I've seen it on Instagram.
Yeah. It's called carbon diet coach. So basically it's, it's for, if people feel like they have a
little bit more independence or, uh, they can't afford a one-on-one coach. So basically the app
is a nutrition coaching app. If you put in your metrics, it will give you macros to follow,
has a food tracker. And then every week you check in with the coach, which is an algorithm
and it will adjust your macros based on your progress. So we have like, we've had thousands
of awesome testimonials. So it's pretty cool to see, but one of the big things we'll get,
especially from like gen pop is how do I hit these protein recommendations? And when I go in,
most of their protein sources are really fatty cuts of meat. That's, that's one thing. And so
I'll say, okay, one pump up your portion size, but let's select leaner cuts of meat, right?
Because you're not necessarily trying to increase their calories. You're trying to basically keep
them almost isocaloric, but shift more to protein. Absolutely. And, and sometimes even like in her
case, I wouldn't necessarily recommend it because she's already kind of small, but if people do have
a little bit of excess body fat, especially if they're new to training, they can recomp. They
actually absolutely can recomp, lose fat and gain muscle at the same time. And in that case, that
might be a place where I would do it just because it sounds like she has a little bit more body fat
than she probably should for her body weight. That's right. She's probably by BMI. Let's
assume her height is such that by BMI, she's totally fine. She's at BMI of 25.
But we would love to see her be at 22% body fat in two years instead of 35% body fat. And we would,
in two years, I'd like to see her have, you know, 10 more pounds of muscle. Yep. And that's pretty
reasonable goals. And so one of the things I would say is, okay, let's look at the portions of,
if you are eating meat, let's look at the portions of meat you are eating. And, and sorry, what's
your protein target for her? You know, a lot of it's going to be one, what can I get her to eat?
Right? Like if I can throw it starting from starting from theoretically exceptional. And then
yeah, I would probably say if we could get you at like 120 grams. Okay. So about a gram per pound,
almost. Yeah. And it probably could be a little bit less 110, you know, because she doesn't have
a lot of lean body mass. So probably 110 is going to be just fine anywhere in that range,
it can be just fine. Okay. And then your strategy is what, how do you, how much in shake, how much in?
Yeah. First thing is breakfast. Okay. So breakfast is where most Americans are very low in protein,
because most breakfast foods either don't eat breakfast, or it's a banana or it's cereal or
it's oatmeal or whatever. Oh, and so I'm going to just keep making shit up to be funny. She says,
but lane, the thing that has been so helpful for me is I do time restricted eating. So I,
do just two meals a day, lunch and dinner. First thing I would say is, okay, why are you doing time
restricted eating? And she'll say, because it really helps me maintain my weight. This thing,
I would say is, okay, you can probably still get the vast majority of the benefits of time
restricted eating, just throwing down a lean protein source or a shake in the morning. Right?
And now you're, you're getting in, boom, another 25 or 30 grams of protein. You're stimulating
protein synthesis and protein itself. I mean, high protein diets actually mimic some of the,
the things that go up during fasting. So I would say that protein acts a little bit differently.
And one of the things I said to people, if they are trying to increase or maximize lean body mass,
but they want to do, you know, time restricted eating for the benefits of satiety and like
lifestyle, cool, do that, but throw in a protein shake in the morning, just because it's, it's not
going to mess up, you know, many of those things. And it's going to help with lean body mass.
What about mTOR, right? I mean, mTOR is responsive to amino acids. And of course,
I'm going to argue you're not getting much mTOR suppression with an overnight fast and skipping
breakfast, but you know, where it is, you know, but what about low IGF and all of these other
things that are, aren't these the important pillars of longevity? Isn't all this extra protein
you're making me eat at odds with that? Let me answer that question after I get to how I'd
add more protein. Okay. Okay. Because that's really, really, I was talking about somebody
about this the other day and it's a great question and so many people mess it up.
So the next thing I would do is, okay, let's look at lunch. Where can we get more protein?
If it's not a, if it's not a shake or anything like that, let's pump up, you know, some lean
protein in the sandwich or, or let's add it to your salad or, you know, whatever it is, whatever,
I don't want to like fundamentally change how she's eating. If the calorie amount is okay,
I want to make small changes that aren't going to feel disruptive to our current lifestyle,
the minimal disruption of the current lifestyle. In fact, the research shows that in terms of
dietary adherence, the less you can change, the better they will do because it's already
close to their current lifestyle. So then if we get to dinner, which is where most people get about
65% of their protein, again, assuming we've gotten, you know, 20, 30 grams of breakfast,
20, 30 grams at lunch. And again, people say, well, how many shakes can I have? Hey, if you like
having shakes, there's nothing wrong with shakes. Absolutely nothing wrong. Go, go ham. Like,
there's nothing wrong with it. I want to make sure we come back and talk about shakes and proteins
and the different types. So between the two of us, let's remember that because that's,
I think that's another question. Shakes. And then we got to talk about mTOR first. And then at
dinner, obviously, okay, if they've been having fattier cuts of meat, which a lot of people,
they have a rib eye, they have, and again, I'm not saying you can't have those things,
but again, if calories are consideration rib eye, T-bone, those sorts of things, okay,
well, let's move to like a sirloin or a filet or chicken breast, or like, even like you can get
pork chops that are really lean too, that are very tasty. So, or, you know, venison or just,
just some sort of, by the way, I had a, I was in a place called Steelbok here in Tampa and they had
a venison rib eye or something like that. I think it was a venison rib eye. Amazing. It was like four
grams of fat per serving. Amazing. So you can really just by simply changing the cuts of meat,
you can pump up the protein, reduce the fat, your calories kind of stay about the same.
And then again, I like to use shakes wherever somebody just says, Hey, I just don't have,
especially as people get older, they, they tend to consume less protein and have less of an appetite
for protein, especially like the mastication is, as people get older, they, they just don't like
having to chew as much. And so shakes can be a really, really useful tool. And even if like
somebody's having a carb heavy breakfast, typically like a cereal or something like that,
there's such good, like ready to drink shakes out there right now, instead of milk on your cereal,
just put a protein shake, a vanilla protein shake, and boom, you've got 30 grams of protein instead
of eight, you know? So the really, I mean, now, I mean, Peter, I'm sure you can speak to this
compared to what I started like in the late nineties, early 2000s. I mean, literally,
I got a can of unflavored protein from GNC one time. I was like, Oh, I can do this, you know,
because it was cheap and I was a college student and I could not do it. It was like chalk. It was
literally like chalk. My first, when I was in high school, there was this brand called Sheckley,
I think. Um, yeah, it was, it was pretty bad, but boy, we would, and the protein bars,
which again, not the best tool, but again, what are we replacing it with? Right? So if you're
having a protein bar instead of like a really, you know, a burger or something like that, great,
great alternate substitute. And there's some great tasting ones out there now.
Now your question about Mtor and IGF one. Oh, sorry. Just going before we wrap up her.
So the biggest change you've made is you've doubled her protein intake, which in reality
is almost an isocaloric switch. Like you're, it's a rounding error in terms of how many
additional calories you've had. Are you paying attention to what percentage carb versus fat in
this woman, given that our primary goal is going to be hypertrophy over the next couple of years?
So the research on hypertrophy leads me to think as far as carbs and fats go,
it mostly doesn't matter as long as you're not at the extreme of either. So if you are very,
very low fat, it can impair testosterone levels. Now they've never, not really shown like an
impairment of lean mass accrual, but they haven't really measured it either. And I would say that
if it impairs testosterone enough, you may get an impairment of lean body mass. As far as how much
as far as how much fat that is, it's very difficult question. Cause they've done it as a percentage
of calories, which to me is almost useless because obviously if you know, 10% of calories,
if you're eating 5,000 calories is still probably enough fat. And as you have more calories, you
can also create fat or spare fat from oxidation by using more carbohydrates. So first off, it's,
it's a calorie amount issue as well. But I would say if you're going to get at least 20% of your
calories from fat, you're probably safe. And as an absolute floor, you know, like 40 grams of fat,
again, I'm guessing. So please don't be dogmatic about these numbers to those who are listening.
But then also like a ketogenic diet does appear to impair lean body mass accrual probably through
a few different mechanisms. Even though carbohydrates aren't stimulatory for muscle protein
synthesis, they do inhibit muscle protein degradation. And fat doesn't appear to have
the same effect. It's probably an insulin effect. Insulin doesn't inhibit muscle protein degradation.
And it's also a bit of a, it's almost impossible to be on a ketogenic diet. If you're actually
generating sufficient ketones, and that's your metric for saying you're ketogenic with the amount
of protein that we were talking about anyway, because for someone your size, it would be very
difficult for you to get high levels of beta hydroxybutyrate with the amount of protein that
you would need to be in that positive nitrogen balance anyway. So correct. So I think
the, the other way that it probably impairs lean body mass accrual is through just effect on
training because you know, resistance training is anaerobic for the most part, right? So her
glycolytic capacity goes down. Yeah. And that requires glucose. Yeah, yeah. So it's, you know,
the research shows that if we're talking about ultra endurance or even endurance in terms of like
under 65 70% of a VO two max ketogenic compares to be just fine. But once you start getting over
that 65% VO two max, there does seem to be a significant impairment in performance. And that
could also be so there was a couple of 12 week studies looking at lean body mass accrual and
showing an impairment with the ketogenic diet. My guess is it's one through not inhibiting muscle
protein degradation as much and two just through not performing as well. And they do they did show
lower strength accrual as well in the ketogenic diet group. So so your fat to carb ratio in her
given that we're not going to go to any extreme. And I noticed in your programming, because I,
you know, some of the stuff that you've written about you talk about, look, here is where you
kind of customize it based on how you respond to carbs. So some people, carbs really increase their
appetite, they, you know, create brain fog, all sorts of things. If you're in that camp, you're
going to push to a lower carb variant here. If you're someone who tolerates carbohydrates very
well, you could easily be on a higher version there. And that becomes the secondary fill after
the primary bucket of protein is established. Absolutely. Protein and calories most important
two things, how you distribute your carbohydrates and fats should be based on what you could adhere
to and what you enjoy. And you know, whether it's I could argue that like brain fog or appetite that
it depends on the type of carbohydrate, a lot of it might be possibly placebo as well, just based on
things that have been said in the media. Regardless, if you know that you just prefer a lower carb diet,
then there's absolutely nothing wrong with doing it as long as you're not getting to the extreme
end of a low carb diet. And even then it's a it's a it's a balancing act, right? It's it's okay,
you know what, I really, really enjoy the ketogenic diet. I understood, but my goal isn't to be the
biggest, most muscular person I could possibly can be, but you can still gain lean body mass on the
ketogenic diet. And so this is where like nutrition communication really requires nuance.
Because what somebody might hear what I just said is like saying, you can't gain muscle on
the ketogenic diet. No, I'm just saying you can't gain as much, but you can absolutely gain muscle.
Same thing with intermittent fasting, you can absolutely gain muscle and intermittent fasting.
Are you going to build as much? Probably not quite. But again, it depends on what your goal is. If your
goal is my primary focus is muscle mass, then I would say, okay, protein, calories and making
sure you have enough carbohydrate as well. But if your primary goal is maintaining body composition,
if you put a little bit less muscle mass, but you like being low carb, then then do it right.
So it's really going to boil down to for this individual lady, hey, what do you what do you
what do you like best? And then even for some people when you know, if they get overwhelmed
by like protein, carbs and fats, I'll say, hey, hey, just track your calories and track your protein.
That that's it, right? Like those are the big buckets. And then if you want to get more granular,
you can write like I get granular because I want to make sure I'm kind of getting a consistent
amount of carbohydrates and fats because I don't want my performance to fluctuate very much. I also
don't want my body weight to fluctuate a ton because I use that to track various metrics in our app.
But I you know, for most people, calories and protein, two huge buckets, and you're getting
9099% of the benefits. Now I want to come back to your your what this person might say about mTOR
and IGF one, I've heard these things are bad. You know, what would you say? And there's been a lot of
I know, David Sinclair has brought a lot of stuff and saying, you know, I'm really trying to limit
mTOR and IGF one. And it will never cease to amaze me. How many scientists do not understand the
difference between a short term truncated acute response to a stressor versus dysregulated
signaling that persists indefinitely. And what I mean is, when you look at mTOR elevations that
that lead to cancer and whatnot, those originate at what I would say mostly insulin resistance.
So you're having elevations in insulin, you're having elevations in insulin signaling through
AKT, which which can then transmit to mTOR. And so it's like this chronic kind of low level pushing
that button, right? As opposed to a pulsatile. That is a big difference between a dose of protein
that causes mTOR to rise go back down in a natural rhythm. Okay. Also tissue specific,
we're talking about in skeletal muscle, not liver, not brain, necessarily those sorts of things.
IGF one, same deal. And what I will say is, where are all the resistance trained people
that are getting cancer by the droves? Because if you want to talk about amplitude of response
from mTOR resistance training, dwarfs what protein does. If we look at the meta-analyses on cancer
incidents amongst resistance trainers, and there's getting to be some now, we see lower levels of
cancer in people who resistance train. So what that tells me is there's a difference between
these two signals. And I want to point out something there, because I think it would be
very quick to say, but Lane, there's a healthy user bias there, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
I don't think what you're saying is that that proves that lifting makes you live longer.
I think what you're actually saying is no, it's the contra-positive. It demonstrates that lifting
doesn't increase mTOR to the point of it being detrimental to your health. That can be asserted,
I think from that observation. Or that it's tissue, also tissue specific. That's part of it.
Let's use a different example. So let's look at exercise in general. So if you were, Peter,
if you got educated in medical school but knew nothing about exercise.
Yeah, I love this. This is one of my favorite discussions.
You know where I'm going with this. And I told you, I'm going to do something that's going to
elevate your heart rate, elevate your inflammatory markers, elevate your reactive oxygen species,
increase your blood pressure.
Increase hepatic glucose output.
Yep.
Yeah.
What would you say to me about that?
Of course, I'd say, yeah, this can't be good for you.
Don't do that. And what is exercise? It does all those things.
Sure.
Right? So why is exercise good for us? Because that is a short-term stressor. I mean, we use
the term hormesis if you want, that the body responds to and it actually acts kind of like
a vaccine. I realize that's like a really triggering term for a lot of people right now,
but it's like a vaccine, right? It's a controlled dose of a stressor that your body can handle.
And I kind of look at protein, this, I wouldn't say protein is a stressor necessarily, but again,
it's this acute response versus a chronic hum, right? Your inflammatory markers,
like people who deal with elevated inflammation, it's not actually super high elevations,
but it's just all the time. That chronic pulse on that, that is the problem. That is the issue.
And again, you said they might say, well, there's health and user bias there. And I would say,
well, so what? Okay. So you're saying that people who have high rates of IGF-1 and mTOR who are
healthy, okay, well, show me them getting higher incidence of cancer.
You can't, you can't because all these things are tied together because people who have high
levels of mTOR activation and IGF-1 typically have insulin resistance. They have poor dietary habits
and poor lifestyle habits. So I would say that it, okay, that's a fair point. There's confounding
variables, but all these things are tied up together. You can't really separate them.
And again, am I saying that mTOR plays absolutely no role? No. But, you know, you're cut, again,
it can be cart before the horse sort of thing. Like people say, well, rapamycin
is an mTOR inhibitor and that's a cancer treatment drug. And I would say, yes. But do you think it's
a good idea to take, do chemotherapy to prevent cancer? I don't think so. I don't think radiation
is a good idea to get into it. It's not even really true because rapamycin is not really,
I mean, it's never really been a particularly successful cancer therapeutic. It used
constitutively, which is how it would be used. Obviously, I think rapamycin does have significant
longevity benefits in basically all models that aren't humans. So the extrapolation would be
pulsatile rapamycin is probably beneficial, but it's in that application, it's not really
being taken to constantly suppress mTOR. Because remember, if you took it all the time, you're
suppressing mTOR complex two and mTOR complex one. So yeah, no, I agree with that point actually
completely, which is that tissue specificity and time course are very difficult things to
infer from the outside, which is sort of the meta view of all things equal, IGF levels have a J
curve with mortality and therefore very, very high levels of IGF must be problematic and high protein
increases IGF and therefore must be bad. And I think it's important to also understand the
following and that is, I think we have this idea, I think I might have missed this on the last show,
but I think we have this idea that there's this perfect diet out there.
It's going to be the one diet that's going to help reduce cancer and cardiovascular disease
and mortality and all and the fact is that there's probably trade-offs for everything.
I know there's people out there that will say that protein increases cancer. Well,
there's a ton of confounders to that. Like somebody saying, well, there's healthy user bias, sure,
but there's ton of confounders to people who eat high protein. Most protein in these meta analyses
looking at cancer, I mean, you're talking about high protein is above 70 grams of protein per day
or 1.2 grams per kilogram of body weight. Okay, well, where do most people, most Americans eat
high protein by definition of the RDA, but where is it from? It's from burgers and hot dogs and
like a bunch of processed meat. So what does the cancer incidence say about people who have high
protein but an overall healthy diet? And there was a really interesting cohort study out of
Alberto and 100,000 people where they said, okay, we're going to look at meat intake and I think
even red meat intake specifically. We're going to look at low, medium and high levels of red meat
intake, but also with low, medium and high levels of fruit and vegetable intake. And because here's
the big thing is most people who eat high levels of meat and protein eat low levels of fruits and
vegetables. What they found was that at the highest levels of meat intake, but also with the highest
levels of fruit and vegetable intake, there was no difference in cancer incidence between the lowest
level of fruit or the lowest level of meat intake. And even with the highest level of fruit and
vegetable intake, it's not an issue. So what that seems. It's a marker for overall diet quality is.
Bingo. So and I, again, I don't want to extrapolate too much out of one study,
even though it was a large study. But what that would seem to suggest is that overall diet quality
is the big rock that we're looking at here. And you can achieve good diet quality on a whole host
of different diets. I mean, you can have a ketogenic diet. That's very poor quality diet.
You can have a ketogenic diet. It's very high quality diet. You can have a plant-based diet.
It's very low quality and you can have a plant-based. It's very high quality. You can have
intermittent fasting, this low quality and so on and so forth. A lot of it boils down to like,
what are the food choices you're making on balance? Are you getting enough fruits and
vegetables and minerals and, and, and micronutrients? And even then, you know, it's so interesting.
Every time we try to say, okay, well, fruits and vegetables have these, you know, these benefits
on health that we see pretty consistently. So let's try and take out these isolated micronutrients
and give them in a supplement. We just, we're always disappointed with the results. And it
just seems to be a little bit of mother nature's kitchen. You know what I mean? That you kind of
have to eat the whole food to really get those benefits. But yeah, I think, again, if the mTOR
story were true in terms of dietary protein, we would have expected in that study to see a linear
increase in cancer, especially at each level of fruit and vegetable intake. But we didn't. What
we saw was more of a linear inverse association with fruit and vegetable intake is what we saw.
So let's not talk about a different example of a person who comes to you. So now let's just use a
male instead of a female last one. And let's talk about kind of a 40, 50 year old male who's trained.
So they have a training background, but, you know, they are also realizing what you said earlier,
which is, hey, I'm going to start losing muscle mass as a, at a pretty good clip once I'm in my
50s. And certainly by the time I'm 65, it really starts to nosedive. So the aha moment is I need
to build up as much of a reservoir as possible. So there's a person who says, look, I've always
been an athlete. I've always done X, Y, and Z, but I've never really thought about muscle mass.
I want to start thinking about it now. Maybe I've got a decade to pack as much on as possible
before I'll go into that. Just maintain it as long as I can mode. Okay. So this is a person who
they're lifting weights three days a week, an hour at a time. They even do some, you know,
they squat, they deadlift, they do a whole body sort of, let's say they do a whole body split
every day for those three days. And let's say their DEXA scan is 20% fat. So they're probably
middle of the pack. Maybe they're probably 20% fat would probably be 25th percentile actually
for a 50 year old. And now they come to you and they say, Lane, okay, I want to go all in. Like,
I want to know, can I be 10% body fat? So they're not trying to be a bodybuilder,
but they want to be 10% body fat in two years. And let's just assume that their BMI is 25 as well.
No, let's say it's not. Let's actually, they say their BMI is 27. So they're technically a little
bit overweight and they've got a little extra body fat. How are you going to change their training?
How are you going to prescribe nutrition? Yeah. So let me ask a question back. Yeah.
Have they been training consistently up to this point?
Yeah, they've been training relatively consistently. But when you look at it, you realize
they're not really in a progressive overload mindset, right? Like they've become a little
comfortable in their training. If you dig under, you'll notice that they haven't really
increased the weight in anything they're doing in five years.
The first thing is looking at the resistance training is, okay, just what you said. All right,
you're doing three sets of 10 on everything. That's right. And you slap a plate on, you slap
two plates on and you do the same thing you've been doing. Adaptation is never comfortable.
So what you're trying to do to grow muscle, you're trying to induce adaptation.
Muscular hypertrophy is an adaptation to a stressor placed on the body. In this case,
the stressor is volume and mechanical load, right? So either you need to increase the weight,
the repetitions, or the number of sets. And doing so is going to be uncomfortable.
Your body is going to tell you it's uncomfortable. And I've had this, even my own coach, who I know
is coaching me for nationals this year for powerlifting. It's so funny, I was like,
you know, starting to kind of have this linear effect coming back from these injuries I've had.
And then one week, you know, I kind of had a dip in performance. And I also was feeling really beat
up. And he just responded one line said, adaptation is never comfortable. And it's so true. It really
is. And we talked about this sort of thing. So just mentally gearing this person up for the idea
that, hey, you know, you've been comfortable, we're going to go start doing some things that are
uncomfortable. And whether it's those particular exercises he's been doing, it sounds like he's
been doing big compound movements. So probably going to keep him on that. I would like to get,
you know, video feedback to see what his form is like, especially with, you know, injury
considerations as we age and pain. So getting some feedback on those, making sure that, you know,
he is getting the requisite amount of load, aggressive overload. And also at this age,
and we're trying to push now, it's also about knowing when do we build in some tapers
so that he can actualize those gains and recover as well. Because here's the thing about adaptation
at a certain point, if you've been training for long enough, and you're old enough,
the amount that you need to cause adaptation versus what is going to cause you to overreach is going
to become closer and closer and closer, right? When you first start, when you first get into
training, you need almost nothing to adapt, right? Like you come in and do one set of leg extensions,
you will get an adaptation from that, right? If you do it consistently for several weeks,
been training five years, one set of leg extension is going to do absolutely nothing.
It might maintain what you have. That's it. And so if you want to push adaptation,
you have to push harder, which is going to create more of a recovery deficit. And so while your
recovery is going, your recovery recovery capacity is going to increase as you get older and have a
greater training experience, it's not going to increase as much as the amount of stress that
you're going to have to apply to adapt. So again, I think having built in tapers is really important.
And whether you do them responsibly in terms of, okay, this person is beginning week to week,
we've seen he's adding five pounds, oh, this week we had a dip in performance. Now maybe we
reactively do a taper, that's possible. Or whether you build them in systematically to try and get
ahead of that curve, either way can work. In the latter lane, what is the typical
duration of a build cycle taper cycle? It's probably going to get progressively closer
together the more advanced you get. So I'll give you my situation is kind of unique. So
I get my kids week on, week off. And we have noticed that the weeks I get my kids, I get less
sleep, I have a little more stress, and my performance goes down a little bit. And we
see that and I also I track bar velocity as well. So how do you do that? What equipment do you use
for that? I use a device called rep one, which is a accelerometer. It's available for purchase by
private individuals, it's about $400. So it's really honestly, it's nerd stuff, if you're really
dialed in. But I like to use it because I if I don't push the weight, I can try and look at the
speed and see, you know, comparatively, okay, compared to last time, did I move the same weight
faster or slower. And so when we look at my performance in terms of strength, RPE, speed,
all those measures consistently show them typically on weeks that the kids are with me.
I'm just not quite as good. I'm about 90 to 95% as good. So we've actually built in micro cycles
of tapering. So it's sort of a push week, a slightly back off week, and one week at a time.
Yeah, now overall, through these micro cycles, we're trying to walk up the volume and the
progressive overload. And then after, you know, probably four to eight weeks, we'll do a much
bigger taper where we pull back on everything. But we do micro tapers in between now. So for this guy,
for this guy, probably for it. Yeah, 48 weeks. Okay, so you'd say, look, I'm going to guesstimate
split the difference. For six weeks, I'm going to push you. And then you're going to back off how
much and for how long? So I like to back off the volume and also the intensity a little bit.
So whereas maybe we're up to, you know, a 789 RPE on most sets. And when I say RPE,
we're talking about rate of perceived exertion. And an easy way to think about it is if it's a 7RPE
on a set, then that person could have done three more reps before they hit absolute failure.
So most RPEs to me for advanced people should be close to seven or eight with a few sets pushing
into a nine and very rarely should you push to a 10. There's quite a bit of literature out there
to show that you get a you get basically the same hypertrophy training close to failure that you do
going to absolute failure. And the it's not necessarily that failure is bad. It's just the
amount of recovery deficit it creates, the amount of taxation it creates is disproportionate to the
stimulus. So what we really want to do is maximize hypertrophy while in stimulus while minimizing
fatigue. Because if you're, yes, sure, you can get a similar stimulus by going to failure and
maybe even just a little bit more. But if it then causes you to have performance decrements the
following week, or not be able to push as hard overall, we have to think about this as an overall
training program and not just isolated workouts. And that's I'm very purposeful when I tell people,
I go into train, I don't go into workout, right? Like working out is just an isolated workout.
And I've had so many people with big egos who say, well, I couldn't possibly not train to failure.
First of all, I've watched them, they're not actually training to failure. Like I know what
actual muscular failure feels like on a squat, for example, a free bar squat. So people I've seen this
on Dr. Mike Israel's Instagram too, because he talks about training shy of failure a lot as well.
And people will say something like, oh, you train like a wuss, you know, this isn't that hard.
And what I want to say to them is I have done, so probably one of my most impressive squat sets is
I did 480 pounds for 14 reps. And I've done 405 pounds for 21 reps before I couldn't move.
Afterwards, it probably took me first off, it probably took me five minutes just to get my
breath back, just to breathe enough to like be a functional human after that. Then as far as like
going to do another set, first off, when I hit that 480 and I grinded out that last rep, that 14th
rep, I was so fatigued. I couldn't rack the right side of the barbell because for whatever reason,
I'm a little bit lopsided and it sits just a hair lower there. I could not fully lock out my glutes
and lower back and I couldn't rack it. And there was actually somebody had to run over from across
the gym to help me rack it, even though normally it's no problem. And then I laid down for five
minutes just trying to get my breath back. And then when I got up, if you told me I had to go
squat 480 again, I'm telling you I couldn't have gotten a single rep, even after resting 10, 15
minutes, there's not a chance in hell. So this idea, so you're telling me if I stopped two reps
shy of that, that that would have felt easy. Or that it would have failed to produce benefit.
And actually with compound movements specifically, you don't have to get as close to failure to get
the benefits with compound movements. By the way, I feel so much better hearing this today.
Today was a deadlift day and this cycle I'm doing trap bar, which I actually don't like very much,
but I did sort of my trap bars. And then I was supposed to go to hip thrusters after and I was
not feeling great on it in a really, it just didn't feel like it was going to, so I was like,
you know what, I really missed doing sumo deadlifts. So I went and did sumo deadlifts and they felt
great. But on the very last set, I added a bunch more weight on. And at the sixth rep or eighth rep,
I was like, I feel really good, but something tells me if I try to get to 10 today,
I'm going to push just a little too much. So I sort of bagged it at eight. And afterwards,
I was like, I'm really proud of myself. Like I didn't do something stupid because today's one
of those days, because, you know, to deadlift two different deadlifts on one day and it's at the end
of the workout, like that's, those are the moments when you make mistakes. But, but I like knowing
that, and that was probably truthfully, I think I probably had four reps in me left. So that might
have only been a six or a seven RPE, but you still get benefit. Absolutely. And the research shows
that. So what was popular a few years ago was kind of the effective reps hypothesis. I don't know if
you've heard of this. What's that? So basically the idea is that the majority of the stimulus that
you get for muscle growth is in the last five reps before failure. So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to do 20 reps before failure. So whether you're doing 20 reps means you need to get to at
least 15 reps to really get a similar stimulus. And in terms of volume and progressive overload,
you really need to think about volume in terms of just number of hard sets within like a five RPE.
But the research shows that that's much more accurate for isolation stuff than it is for
compound. So compound lifts are kind of their own beast. You can train at a sub five RPE and still
maximal EMG recruitment and quite a bit of hypertrophy. Whereas with isolation, you pretty
much have to take it close to failure. And then the other thing I would say is that exercises are not
equivalent. That's a big thing. It's like, all right, let's do a five RPE on a squat and then a
nine RPE on a leg extension. I'll tell you the nine RPE on a leg extension. I can do that all day.
I'll take that. I was just about to say that is infinitely less painful.
Exactly. Versus a big compound movement that requires core and stabilization and breathing
and creating intra abdominal pressure. You know, all that kind of stuff, you know, factors into
fatigue. So, you know, for this individual. Yeah. So tell me about sets and reps here. So
again, let's assume he's much more interested in hypertrophy than strength. He's not going to
power lift. What's the rep range you're going to keep him in for compound movements and for
isolated movements? Variety is the spice of life. And the research shows that from one rep to 30
reps, you can build very similar amounts of muscle. So this is amazing, right? Because the
conventional wisdom says, oh, my God, if you're doing fewer than I don't know what the number is
that they would say if you're doing fewer than six reps, there's no hypertrophy. It's all strength.
Right. That's what that's what conventional thinking would say. And what I will say is there,
you know, there are benefits to being in that hypertrophy rep range of, you know,
six to 15 reps. That's kind of like traditional. So here's the benefits and downsides. One of the
nice things about the six to 15 reps is you can accumulate quite a bit of metabolic fatigue,
you can use relatively heavy loads, and you can get quite a bit of volume in that rep range.
If you're doing like really heavy weights for low reps, say under five reps,
you functionally would have to double your number of sets just to get the volume, right?
Probably not because it's more about the number of hard sets. Okay.
But doing a hard set of five is not the same thing as doing a hard set of 10.
You have fewer of them in you, presumably, right?
Probably. There's probably a greater fatigue effect. But some people, again, like me,
if you told me I couldn't train, you know, under five reps, I'd be like, I'm just gonna be bored,
you know, I don't like doing high reps. It's just I get bored. So for me, and the same thing with
clients, again, adherence is number one, right? So if he says, Oh, I'm not worried about creating
strength, but I really like lifting heavy weights. Okay, we're going to find a way to incorporate
that. But it might be where, hey, we're touching one set that's under five reps, and the rest are
going to be, you know, six to 10 on these compound exercises, then on the isolation exercises, you
know, we'll go 1520, you know, just for some variety and whatnot. But really, the research,
at least in the short term, and when I say short term, I mean, like 12 weeks,
we don't see differences in hypertrophy between anywhere from, you know, low reps to 30 up to 30
reps, as long as the number of hard sets are equated. So really, it says do what you like,
do what you enjoy. And what is that? What is that sweet spot for hard sets, if we just pick 10 reps,
so then we can do the math and go up or down. So the sweet spot is what maximizes per body part
is probably about six to 10 sets in a session. Okay, so they don't really,
they don't really see, you know, improvements above 10 sets. Now, here's where this gets a little
bit complicated, because if you rest longer, each set actually becomes more effective as a stimulus
for hypertrophy, presumably because you perform better, and you can use more weight and do more
reps on that individual set. So the number based on the meta regressions out there, and I think
James Krieger did a really good one. The number seems to be like if you're resting kind of like,
you know, more than three minutes between sets, six sets, if you're resting like one to two minutes,
it might be more like 10 sets. But again, the other thing to keep in mind is you don't have to
just jump to like 10 sets immediately, you know, per body part, you know, whatnot, that's a lot of
sets. You should probably use what is ever allowing you to adapt at the time, if you're somebody who
is, you know, relatively new to training, you start doing 10 sets per body part,
like one, what's going to happen once you plateau, that's a lot more sets you're going to have to add
on top of that. And two, you're probably going to outpace your recovery capabilities, right? You
like, when people tell me they're going to do, I know you you talked about covering squatting and
deadlifting every day. What I would say is you better be in a real you better be in very good
physical condition to do that. And even then there is a expiry date on that.
And I've talked to people who have done this, to be clear, I've never done this, I look at the
people who have tried it in awe, but I just I'm not willing to give up so many other things I do
exercise wise to just make sure I squat and deadlift every single day. But what I notice that they're
doing is they're being very clever in that they're not every day is not a crushing set of that,
right? I mean, yeah, some of those days, it's a very, very low volume, low intensity that functions
effectively as a recovery day where they're basically working on the muscle memory in the form.
Yep. But so for example, in the case of this guy, if he says, Lane, I'm willing to train as
much as you need to tell me to. So even though currently I'm doing 360 minute workouts a week,
if you tell me I need to be in there five days a week with two rest days, and that should be two
hours a day, I'm willing to do it. Where would you say again, let's assume that his form is decent,
you're not concerned about overuse. Where would you want to put him? If he's not looking to
powerlift, and he says, I don't really care about exercise selection, just pick whatever.
I'm probably not going to be doing a lot of free squatting and deadlifting,
even though that's my personal love. Because those do create a very high recovery debt.
And not just that, it's very mentally taxing. I remember when my wife Holly moved over,
and she's a phenomenal athlete, like went to the Junior World Games as a track athlete,
like won the natural Olympia two years after she started lifting weights. I mean, just incredibly
genetically gifted and hardworking person. But she would look at me doing like triples on squats,
and then resting 10 minutes between sets and say, why are you resting so long? That can't possibly
be that difficult. Meanwhile, she's over there doing sets of 10 resting, you know, she's slapping
a plate on each side doing sets of 10 and resting, you know, a couple minutes. And I said, well,
you'd have to really do a powerlifting me to understand. And then she did one. And then she
was like, Yeah, the amount of intense mental focus it requires when you have that much weight on your
back and you know, like this could literally kill you. Obviously, you have safeties and spotters and
whatnot. But just, you know, strapping 600 pounds across your back. I mean, there's a reason you're
adrenaline spikes. So after that, she understood, but that's a lot of recovery debt to create for
something that you could get a similar stimulus by doing a hack squad or a leg press or that sort of
thing, as long as you're working through a full range of motion. That's the other thing, very
important to work a muscle and a long muscle length. In fact, there was actually a recent
meta-analysis that came out looking at partial range of motion, but partial range of motion at
different muscle lengths and found that while partial range of motion at shortened muscle lengths
does not produce the same hypertrophy as full range of motion, partial range of motion at
length and muscle lengths produce similar hypertrophy as full range of motion. So let
me make sure I understand that lane. So let's just use a bicep because it's easy.
At the lengthened part of the bicep, when you are straight armed, you're saying a partial rep from
straight to say 90 degrees is more effective than if you just do the top of the bicep. So
and let's assume you do the same range, but because at the shorter range, you're not seeing
presumably as much adaptation or recruitment by the muscle.
Presumably, although the bicep might be a little bit different because you would actually have to
be on like an incline bench to truly get the stretched range of motion because otherwise,
in a traditional dumbbell curl, that the top end is actually the more difficult component of the rep.
Whereas if you kind of pre-stretch it, now you can make that bottom part a little more difficult.
So but if we think about something like a squat, right, like a partial range of motion, squat,
if you're doing a partial range of motion in the bottom half, that is not going to be easy.
Right. So I think it's more about working the muscle in the difficult
regions, but the stretch component does seem to be important. So what I would say is like,
I would really, I really am a big fan of like something like a hack squat for leg development
if you don't care about, you know, being strong on free squats. Because if you get a good machine,
you can take it through a really full range of motion. You can really get a good stimulus for
the quadriceps and some of the rest of the leg muscles. And it's not crazy fatiguing. So
something like that, a leg press, there's also like really good pendulum squats. I really like
a good pendulum squat if you guys ever tried that. So it's kind of like you sit in a seat and it's on
an arm. So where you're kind of going, so if there's a pivot here, and the weight is loaded here,
and you get in here, hopefully I'm just displaying this. And then as you go down, the weight's here.
Basically, as you get lower, are your hands loading in front or are you loading? Yeah, yeah.
They're right here. So as you're getting lower, it gets a little bit easier because of the pendulum.
And then as you get higher, it gets harder, which actually works on your strength curve,
because the hardest part of the squat is near the bottom and the easiest parts near the top.
So I really like those two, because those are exercises that you can really work through a nice
full range of motion and create a lot of stimulus. And like I said, I think full range of motion
or training in that stretched position is very, very important. And so, you know, I usually like
to have kind of like two main exercises for a big muscle group like that. You probably don't need it.
You probably could just do hack squats for five or six sets, you know, that sort of thing. But
people like variety. And then I would do, you know, and I would keep those between, you know,
a six and an eight RPE most likely, and then, you know, go to a leg extension and leg curl and those
sorts of things. And or, well, I'd probably do an RDL, some sort of RDL, because it's not as fatiguing
as a deadlift, but you're still activating similar muscles. Once again, keeping that between a six
eight RPE. And are you going to are you going to coach that with like, obviously one leg? Are you
going to do Ipsy or ISO grab on the kettlebell? I would probably do a barbell, honestly, and do
both legs. And then if, you know, if we felt like there was some imbalance or something like that,
or they just wanted some variety, you could do single leg. It is going to if muscular hypertrophy
is the primary goal, you can create more stimulus using, you know, both legs at the same time.
And then with then doing some like isolation stuff, low rest periods, higher reps, you know,
10 to 20 repetitions, going to a little bit higher RPE, you know, like a nine, an eight or nine RPE,
I think those are fine. And then if somebody said, you know, I just I've got to take a set to failure.
It's, you know, part of my credo. I came from the 80s bodybuilding. I said, great, take the last
take the last exit, last set of the last exercise of an isolation to failure and go nuts, right?
Like do something like that. And that might be how I build out a leg session, you know,
like the the bigger compound exercise is a little bit lower reps, you know, maybe five to 10.
Then as we progress through, you know, more isolation going into the higher end of the
rep range and maybe taking some a little bit closer to failure. And is he going to do this
two or three times a week? So frequency, interestingly,
I think that the men analysis so far haven't been sensitive enough to pick it up. But
what it says is that for legs, it doesn't matter. One time a week is enough. But for upper body,
two times a week, I think probably multiple times a week for both is beneficial. Your
pH three program is about five days a week, right of total, but it was five days, it was five days a
week, three days of lower body, three days of three days of squatting, two days of deadlifting,
three days of bench pressing, and also accessory on those days as well. What I will say is for the
most part, frequency is more of a tool to distribute volume than it is an individual
hypertrophy stimulus. But it does seem to me that it would make sense. And again, a lot of people,
scientists have gotten in trouble saying, well, this just makes sense. But it would seem to me
that if you have a muscle protein synthesis response, especially in trained individuals,
that's only, you know, 16, 20, 24 hours, that multiple doses of that are probably better than
just doing one dose and thinking you've got it all. So again, I think part of that's just we don't
have enough studies yet. And we don't have the sensitivity to detect that. And also, the studies
are so heterogeneous in terms of the population that's used, their training status, the type of
exercises that are used, how RPE is measured, how intensity is measured, how volume is measured.
It's really hard to get good meta-analyses of these sorts of things. I do think in the next five
to 10 years, there's going to be like, the amount of hypertrophy research that's come out in the
last five to 10 years is literally an explosion compared to pre-2010. I think I read one meta-analysis
on hypertrophy from resistance training in the entire time I was in graduate school.
Are there a couple that we should link to in the show notes here that are just,
if someone's going to say, like, I'm willing to wade through two meta-analyses on this,
are there a couple you'd recommend?
Yeah, there's a few I'd recommend. And I'll send an email to you guys.
Perfect.
Yeah. So some of that would be some of the stuff that's been done by James Krieger and some other
folks that really kind of looks at, all right, like set number and volume and those sorts of things.
But for this guy, I mean, really, if I had to, putting out like an actual program
day-to-day is difficult just because a lot of it boils down to personal preference in terms of how
I'm going to program it.
And presumably, you'll get feedback, right? So you might say, like, this is what we'll start with,
but we're going to modify it after this first cycle. So let's talk about his nutrition now.
Let's pretend that you assess him. So I forget what I said he weighs. Let's make up a weight.
He's 175 pounds. He's 180 pounds. I don't know, whatever. And I think we said he's
20-ish percent by DEXA, low 20s. And let's say he's eating 120 grams of protein a day.
So right off the bat, you're going to say, hey, you're a little light on protein.
This guy is going to be willing to eat anything you say. So where do you want him?
Do you want this guy at 180 grams a day, 200 grams a day?
What was his body weight again?
Let's say 180.
Yeah. I mean, if he likes protein, I would say, you know, you're not having
any downsides to having 200 grams a day. And that's a nice number to shoot for. So I would
probably start somewhere around there, making sure his calories are adequate as well for
facilitating recovery and enough carbohydrate and whatnot.
So in this guy's case, because he really wants to gain lean mass,
how do you think about cycling him in terms of making him hypercaloric? I mean,
where are you trying to put his energy balance? How much weight do you want him gaining?
Since he's been training for a long time and he's older,
the likelihood that he's going to be able to gain lean mass without at least some body fat is
probably pretty low. And I get this all the time for people. I want to gain muscle and lose fat at
the same time. Well, if you are our subject, a, the lady who'd never trained before, absolutely.
I mean, you heard me. I was like, yeah, we can recomp her. No problem. She's going to gain some
muscle and lose some, some body fat. When you've been training for a long period of time,
you have to have everything lined up just to gain ounces of lean body mass.
And so part of lining that up is also a slight caloric surplus. There is a new meta analysis
that came out that showed that an energy deficit, it's not quite the same thing, but they did show
an energy deficit in pairs, lean body mass accrual. So it's not enough just to eat protein.
It makes sense because we do see in an energy deficit, decreased rates of basal protein synthesis.
So it makes sense. I mean, if you earn an energy deficit from mechanistic perspective,
it activates AMP kinase, which had hit, which is an inhibitor rim tour. So it makes sense.
It also makes sense from a teleological perspective that if you don't have excess energy,
you know, this remodeling is extremely energy expensive. Why would we want to create more of
it if we don't have the energy to support it? So a protein sparing fast isn't necessarily
going to save you from losing lean mass. If it, because again, if it's, it's, it's, I mean,
it might be better than a carb fast. You know, in other words, if you're going to eat a thousand
calories a day, you're probably better off having them be as much protein as possible.
But just because you have 200 grams of protein in your diet, if the calories are exceptionally low,
you're, you're probably losing lean mass. Is that my, is that how I'm hearing?
What I would say is a day of an energy deficit is not something I'd really be worried about.
No, no, but I'm saying, let's say somebody took this approach and said, look, for two weeks,
I'm going to go a thousand calories a day, virtually all protein in an effort to get as
lean as possible without losing lean mass. You might be able to not lose lean mass,
but the likelihood you would gain lean mass is very, very low for somebody who's been training
for a while. And so yeah, it's, it's one of those things that the more advanced you get,
the more things you have to have lined up correctly to continue to push, especially if
you're drug free. So yeah, for me, like I've, and you can do it in sprints. You can do it in,
in, in different sections, you know? So I'll like I've, I went from, I was in the 230 pound class
back in 2019. And then I just started to drop back down to my original weight class of 205 pounds.
I did that over the course of about a year, but that was taken in sprints. So I would do
fat loss sprints, for example. So I would do like two or three weeks of like a pretty aggressive
deficit, like 750 to a thousand calories a day. This is for powerlifting. Yeah, that was for
powerlifting. And what body fat is your performance at its best? How, because you obviously don't want
to be powerlifting at 7% body fat. I'm still pretty good at seven. Really? I still maintain
pretty well. Yeah. I still maintain pretty well. Maybe not quite as good. I will, let me put it
this way. I can still perform well at seven, but if I have a couple of days where I'm not dialed in,
I'll start to feel it. So I've got, I've got, I'm right on that edge. I'm teetering on that edge at
seven on calipers, that is. So I did it over the course of the year and I did it in sprints. So I
would do three weeks, lose like target, trying to lose five, six pounds. And then I would go to
maintenance for like at least as long. And I kind of built that into my lifestyle. You know,
I really liked that for a lot of clients. Actually a lot of our team, violin coaches
use a lot of what we call diet breaks where the people were eating at maintenance. So it's like,
okay, vacation coming up, diet break for two weeks. Everything looks like it's going to be
normal for three, four weeks. Boom. Let's do a fat loss sprint. So coming back to building muscle,
I'll do sections of, okay, I'm overfeeding in this slight caloric surplus for about eight weeks.
Okay. We gained, you know, three pounds of body weight. I'm going to maintain for a little while
just to make sure it doesn't get too out of hand in terms of body fat level. Now I've kind of got
adjusted this. Now I'm going to do another, you know, six to eight weeks. What I'll tell people
is if fat loss should be slow, at least for people who are well-trained, if fat loss should be slow
to retain lean body mass, then weight gain should be snail's pace.
So what's the rule of thumb for this guy then? If you, if he's going to gain
five pounds of total body weight, of which we're going to hope three is lean, two is fat. Is that
a good goal? How long would you want him to take to gain five pounds? Probably at least 12 weeks.
Okay. So he's doing that once a quarter. But it might be something more like where it's six months,
but there's, you know, 12 weeks where we get them up five pounds and then we say, okay, let's trim
a little bit of this fat back off that we put on. We lose three pounds. Then we do another
gaining cycle, put on five pounds. And what tends to happen is the composition gets a little better
each time. And again, this is now, this is completely anecdotal, my coaching experience.
But when you put on weight, and we see this in studies, it's for trained people
for trained people, it really depends. But it's somewhere around 50, 50 lean mass to fat mass,
sometimes even 40, 60, if you're really well trained. So 40 lean, 60 fat. Wow. So the implication,
by the way, is when you're gaining weight, you're getting fatter by body composition,
because you're presumably starting out at less than 50% body fat. Well, it depends on the training
status and a whole host of other factors. So that's an important thing for you to tell this guy,
which is, hey, if you're going to be rigorously following body comp, don't be disappointed if
your body fat goes up in that cycle. We're playing the long game here, right? It's like investing,
we put it that way. So it's like investing, you're taking money away from you now in this immediate
moment that you could have. So hopefully you have more money later. Right. So the good thing is that
when we lose body fat, we tend to lose, for resistance training, we tend to lose mostly from
body fat. Right? So if we're doing this cycle over time, hopefully each time it gets a little better.
Now, there are limits to this. Eventually you bought up against your genetic limit of,
or probably your genetic limit. What I always say is you never really know if you're at your genetic
limit. And what I always tell people is I show them this picture of me at 21 years old, where
I'd been resistance training hard for three and a half, four years, where most people say you hit
your genetic limit, you know, somewhere around there. And I show that picture and I show a picture
of me now at age 40. And I mean, the difference in my leg musculature and my overall musculature
is enormous. But if you had just gone year by year, you would have seen very little difference.
Right. And so what I'll tell people is, you know, you might think you're at your genetic limit,
but you're probably not. And it's probably more like an asymptote. Yeah. Yeah. So you never,
you never really hit like a hard cap limit, but the gains become so minimal that it's almost not
measurable. So yeah, I think when it comes to, you know, these, like this kind of person,
one really focusing on, okay, making sure that they can do a lot of resistance training,
because it is going to take quite a bit of a stimulus to get in there, focusing on stimulus
versus fatigue. So doing high stimulus, low fatigue movements so that they can accumulate enough volume
without overreaching all the time. Because if they can train for 12 weeks without needing a taper
versus six weeks, I mean, that's more stimulus, right? And then putting them in a very slight
caloric surplus. And when I say slight caloric surplus, I'm talking about 100 to 200 calories
a day and over their maintenance. And now what does that look like? Well, that means that you're
going to have weeks where you don't gain anything. Anybody, I don't know if you've ever done this,
Peter, like doing, where people have like tried to do a super lean gaining phase. What tends to
happen is people get really frustrated because the weight comes on so slow that they end up just
throwing down a bunch of calories so that they can say they gain the weight and it doesn't go well.
And what tends to happen is weight gain comes on in chunks, just like weight loss tends to happen
in chunks. Weight gain tends to happen in chunks. You can be stable, stable, stable, even though
you're in a calorie surplus. And all of a sudden, boom, your weight's up two pounds, you know, just
randomly and it sticks. And we don't have all the explanations for why it happens that way, but
just know that that's normal for those listening. And again, don't look at, oh, I gained two pounds
from the past three days and it's not going down, it's staying. Look at the fact that you've been
doing this for four weeks now and you gain two pounds on average. So you're right in line with
kind of what the goal was. So you want to look at that monthly, that really that monthly month
to month average in a gaining phase and say, okay, am I hitting my milestones in terms of like the
overall rate of progress and try to not worry too much about those little things?
So, Lane, I don't know how we did this again. We're at this point where I've got through about
a third of what I wanted to talk about. But nevertheless, there is one other thing I wanted
to kind of talk about and it actually feeds really nicely into this sort of case study of this man
and this woman, which is that of like kind of the most important supplements or the supplements we
most hear about and what is their utility for the purpose of hypertrophy training? So let's start
with the most common of these, which is protein. We talked about it already. You alluded to the fact
that this woman might not be able to get enough protein in actual food. So you might talk about
shakes. So where does whey protein stack up in the hierarchy of proteins and should we be looking
at other sources? Top of the list, whey protein, high in leucine, high in branched amino acids,
high in essential amino acids generally tastes good, generally well tolerated. I will say if it's
a straight whey concentrate, a lot of people have difficulty tolerating a straight whey concentrate,
but a blend of concentrate and isolate is what most proteins out there are and most people can
tolerate them well. What's the source of protein and whey? Where does it actually come from in
terms of? So basically from cow's milk, if you centrifuge off the fat, so if you centrifuge off
the fat and then you take that what's left over and you add, you precipitate out the casein,
which is the non-soluble fraction of cow's milk, the soluble portion that's left over is whey.
It's what's called whey and mostly consists of proteins called lactylbiumens.
And it's just a very high quality, easy digestible, very bioavailable source of protein.
In terms of muscle protein synthesis, it's the tip tops. It always scores the highest.
In our research, it was always the highest. It was no statistical difference from egg,
but when we did it versus egg, it was always just like a little bit better. So my guess is if you
had a high enough subject number, you could maybe pick out some statistical difference.
Is there a brand that you favor or are there brands that you think are the best brands to go for?
Incoming shameless plug. So I actually have my own supplement line called Outwork Nutrition.
And we have a...
What's it called?
Outwork Nutrition.
Outwork.
Okay.
Yep. And we have a whey protein isolate. The reason we did an isolate, isolates are a little
bit more expensive than a concentrate isolate blend, but there are people with lactose
intolerance. There are people with a sensitivity to the lactylbiumens. And so an isolate is
generally well tolerated. Some people with really high sensitivities to the lactylbiumens
can't tolerate an isolate. And if that's the case, they could probably do a hydrolysate,
which is a little more expensive and doesn't taste as good, but still a good option for those that
have really sensitive GI's. But like I said, an isolate is generally tolerated well by people.
And ours is called Outwork Nutrition Build. So it's just low carbohydrate, low lactose,
low fat, high protein, high leucine. So I think our leucine contents over 11%. I think it's
actually 12%, which is very high. And then the carbohydrate content, depending on vanilla or
chocolate, is like one to four grams. And then the fat content is less than a gram of fat. In fact,
the vanilla is zero. Are there any other brands that you would say, hey, I trust that brand?
Because one of the things that I think, as we talk about supplements, you always got to be
careful. Yeah. What would be three other brands that you would put in your body?
Yeah. I mean, Legion, they make good stuff. And I think some of the big companies,
Optimum has been doing protein for years. And most companies are sourcing the same stuff. To me,
a good company is somebody that markets responsibly. But then another one, EAS has
been making stuff for years and they make stuff that's very, very third party tested,
all that kind of stuff. There's a bunch of good companies out there. What I would say is make
sure nobody's using a proprietary blend. Proprietary blends are usually just a way
for people to hide stuff. Two, make sure that nobody is doing what's called nitrogen spiking.
So what you can do to pump up the protein and nitrogen content of some of these proteins
is add individual amino acids that have nitrogen that are actually lower cost than just the protein
itself. And actually creatine is like they actually put creatine in some of these, not that
creatine isn't good. Creatine does work, but you're not taking away protein that's not a good
creatine. You take creatine to get creatine. And they do that because it's actually cheaper
and it pumps up the protein content. And how would you know that when looking at the label?
Oh, it's on the label. Oh, it'll say it.
For example, I think they spike with glycine too. So if you look on the label,
they might say whey protein and then sweeteners, preservatives, oh, glycine.
That's nitrogen spiking. So I would make sure that companies aren't doing that.
And to me personally, I mean, even if a company makes a good product, if they make insane claims,
I mean, listen, I would love to say that our protein is the most anabolic protein on the
market. But the fact of the matter is it's a high quality whey protein isolate at a competitive
price point that tastes really good. And you can get another whey protein isolate that would build
just as much muscle. So I'm not going to claim that. So I would say just the ethical side of me
says just look for something that's promoted responsibly. So yeah, those other companies
are just fine and I would recommend them. All right. So let's look at a subset of that.
Is there utility in using branched chain amino acids specifically in workouts where these are
typically coming as far lower doses? There's only three branched-chain amino acids and they're
typically giving you five grams per serving. Any utility in the in-workout BCAA?
So this was something that I've changed my mind on. And I will tell people like I'm a BCAA,
my PhD specifically is on leucine. I mean, it's right back there. He says leucine right on the
cover is one of the words. And I used to say, hey, I think supplemental branched chains are useful.
And I just I can't support that anymore. If you're getting enough total protein in,
it doesn't seem to be a benefit to supplemental branched-chain amino acids. The only thing I would
say that there might be something is they may reduce muscle soreness, but it's never been
compared straight up with like a comparable amount of whey protein. So it's possible that that's just
like a total protein effect. And the only case I could really make besides maybe soreness is also
for people who just cannot get high quality protein. And so for example, if you're a vegan
and you say, you know, I don't want to take whey protein and I can't take XYZ and my stomach
doesn't tolerate these proteins and I want to pump up the quality of my meal, then supplemental
branched chains could make it an impact. And we actually did a study in our lab where we looked
at whey protein versus wheat protein. We saw that whey protein obviously had a much bigger response
than muscle protein synthesis compared to wheat.
Sorry. And that's obviously gram per gram, right?
Gram per gram. Yeah. We, isonitrogenous. But when we added leucine to match the leucine content of
the whey, we actually got the exact same response. So if you're somebody who's plant-based and you're
concerned that you're not getting enough high quality protein, you could actually add supplemental
branched-chain amino acids to your meals or your protein and you would pump up the protein quality
doing that. But obviously the best outcome is just getting it through diet or shakes. And then
if you have to add supplemental branched-chain, you can't. But-
Any role for supplementing leucine specifically? So if someone says,
Lane, I'm buying your brand, I'm consuming it, I'm just going to add five grams of leucine every
time. And by the way, leucine tastes horrible. Horrible. It's literally one of the worst
tasting things on the planet. Yeah. No, I just don't think there's a benefit to it.
I wish there was. I mean, I went into, I did my PhD thinking I'm going to find the secret
anabolic trigger and just get enough protein. Okay. Let's talk. You mentioned it already,
creatine monohydrate. Yeah. Very popular. Back in the day when I was a kid, it was 30 grams a day
loading and then a maintenance phase. I think these days people are just doing five grams a day
every day, right? Yeah. I mean, loading will get you... So really what you're looking to do is
saturate your phosphocreatin stores in your muscle cell. And you can do that through loading
or you can do it through maintenance phase. If you do it through loading, it'll saturate in five to
seven days. If you do it through maintenance, it'll take about three to four weeks. Downside to
loading, more GI discomfort, more bloating, more just overall discomfort, but you get saturated
faster. Downside to maintenance just takes a little bit longer to get the benefits. That's all.
What are the main benefits of creatine? Are they on the strength side, the hypertrophy side,
the recovery side? All above. So yeah, it increases lean body mass, increases strength, exercise
performance, and we're actually... There's possibility that there's cognitive benefits as
well. Interestingly, we're finding out, but I would tell people do not get caught up in the hype
of these other forms of creatine. Creatine monohydrate has been shown to saturate the
muscle cell 100%. You cannot get more than 100%. And the other forms of creatine are simply
in existence to remove more money from your wallet. And here's... This is kind of like I
use the comparison of big screen TVs, right? Remember when my first big screen TV I bought,
it was 42 inches, big screen, LCD screen. I bought it in 2008 and it was $1,000, right?
What would that go for now? You could probably get it for 200 bucks.
Yeah. Yeah. Like here, here's a stick of gum. Can I have that 42 inch screen TV? Sure.
Why? Because everyone makes them and there's such a competitive market that the margins are
this big, right? So what does everybody have? Everybody has creatine in their supplement line.
So the margins are so thin, nobody makes money on straight creatine. So they have to come up with
other forms of it to justify charging you more. And you hear things like, well, our creatine
doesn't bloat you or our creatine doesn't cause water retention. Well, I would tell you that the
water retention, hydrated cells and anabolic procell, the water retention from creatine is
inside the muscle cell, which is a good thing. And there's research studies to show this that
it does not increase extracellular water. That's actually intracellular water. So are you saying
that your creatine is not anabolic then? And then you have things like buffered creatine.
You don't need to buffer creatine. Creatine is stable in stomach acid. And then there's
creatine ethyl ester, which has actually been shown. So there's just a ton of marketing nonsense.
Yeah. Creatine, trimalate. Do you make a creatine supplement?
Yeah. So our recovery supplement, so we have a supplement called recovery and creatine is one
of the ingredients there. So there's five grams of creatine monohydrate. And do you think that,
is that a daily thing someone should have even on their nonlifting days?
Probably don't need to take it on your off days from lifting.
If you're doing cardio on a nonlifting day, do you benefit at all from creatine there?
There's no rule studies to know. What I would say is it's very cheap. You're not really missing out
on anything by having an extra dose. So I would say take it daily. If your budget is really real
thin, then take it on the days you train. Any other brands that you respect and just trust that
they're not doing any nonsense, which is basically the same. Look for the no claims and the trusted
brands. Yeah. And no crazy claims, no pushing other forms of creatine is better and no
proprietary blends. That's one of the best ways to know. But the great thing is there are a lot
of good companies out there that are marketing more responsibly now. Okay. Last one, nitric oxide
or these nitric oxide boosters. I remember this was one of the things that got so much attention.
I want to say like 10, 15 years ago. Truthfully, I don't know how much attention it's gotten now,
but I did see a paper about it recently, which is what made me think about it again.
Yeah. So nitrates and nitrites do appear to enhance exercise performance. So like beetroot
juice and those sorts of things and sources of nitrite. So there was a recent meta-analyses
looking at this and the effect size was actually pretty impressive for power.
There was like 5% or something. It was huge, wasn't it?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Really impressive. 5%, which I mean, like that's the difference between
first and last, if you're talking about the Olympics, you know. And the effect size was
a 0.42, which isn't considered a large effect size, but it's approaching a modest effect size,
which for supplements is really impressive. I mean, that's on the order. I don't know off
hand creatine effect size in the meta-analysis, but it's got to be close to that. And what I will
say is a lot of supplements appear to not have in them what they say they have in them in terms
of these nitrates. The other thing I will say is like something like citrulline malate, which is a,
it can be recycled into arginine and then into nitric oxide. So citrulline malate or citrulline
specifically actually increases blood nitrate levels more than arginine itself. So it actually
increases nitric oxide more than arginine. Arginine is the direct substrate. That's because
citrulline is actually much more bioavailable, whereas arginine is mostly extracted by the
splanknic tissues, the gut and liver. So you're actually better off taking citrulline, which is
in our pre-workout, of course. So there's another shameless plug. But really, if you're looking at
citrulline specifically, like six to eight grams, you know, at a dose. And this is more to increase
performance than hypertrophy. Is this going to? Yeah. I mean, presumably if your performance goes
up, you have more stimulus, you might see the gains there. Yeah. There is some evidence that
citrulline can actually stimulate mTOR, but I'm not sure it's enough to actually create like
hypertrophy on its own. So were you consuming something besides water or electrolytes in the
workout? You've obviously got a pre-workout. Are you drinking your, sort of the citrulline would
be before? Obviously the whey would probably be after. Where's the creatine falling post or pre?
So the timing doesn't seem to be real important. There does seem to be a little bit better response
to after. Not sure why, because it really, to me with the mechanism, it shouldn't matter because
it's a long-term thing. But that's actually why we included the creatine in our recovery product
and not the pre-workout for a couple of reasons. One, it doesn't seem to matter when you take it,
or it doesn't, you don't, it's not an immediate effect from creatine. So you might as well take
it post. Might be a little bit better effect post. So, you know, there you go. And then in
the pre-workout specifically, there's a couple of things in there that are already semi-gut irritants
for some people. And creatine can be a gut irritant for people. We didn't want to compound those too
much. So that's why we kind of separated it from our pre-workout. But there's a lot of pre-workouts
that do have creatine in it. And especially when you pair it with a large dose of caffeine,
it can just really give people a lot of GI discomfort if you're not careful.
So then in workout, are you drinking something?
I usually just, like people are going to laugh, but I'll like a Gatorade Zero or something like
that, you know, in water. I just, you know, I've looked at the intro workout stuff. I mean,
you know, if you're working out for two, three hours at a time, maybe it's useful to get some
glucose and carbohydrate in to maintain performance. But, you know, I think bodybuilders
or weightlifters tend to overestimate like how difficult their workouts actually are.
You know, really, you only need to worry about glycogen, resynthesis, you know, the speed of which
if you're somebody doing multiple events per day, like if you're a bodybuilder, you're going to be
24 hours to your training in any way. Like you're going to resynthesize that glycogen as long as you
get enough total carbohydrates. So I'm not real huge on intro workout nutrition, as long as we're
not talking about really long workouts, or we're not talking about multiple sessions per day.
Well, Lane, I've taken us way past our time. But as always, super enjoyable. Can't wait to do it
again. There's a lot of stuff to follow up on here. So the show notes will have a ton of the
detail we've talked about an offline you and I can connect and make sure we've got the links to some
of the things we spoke about. So thanks again, man. Appreciate it. And congrats on being by the water.
Thanks, Peter. I appreciate it, man. Really enjoyed it.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you
more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get
back much more than the price of the subscription. To that end, membership benefits include a bunch
of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic,
paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes
rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple
Podcasts or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare
professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously. For
all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward
slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.