Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Hey Kelsey, thanks so much for making the time to come all the way to Austin. I really appreciate
it. Although I'm not going to take credit for the fact that you came here for this. I think this was
an opportunistic time to sit down. For sure. I mean, I definitely did come here for this and
there are some other great people here that I get to visit. It's perfect. So thank you for having me.
Yeah, I know my wife is really upset that you don't live here.
You know, it's funny because I went out with them last night and there's this draw to this
place because there's a lot of good people here. And I think during COVID I understood why everybody
was leaving and I really couldn't stand LA and there was just a thousand reasons the past couple
of years have been hard. But all of a sudden suddenly I really love LA again. So I'm going
to hold on and just visit you guys every month. That's the plan.
So where'd you grow up?
I grew up in Winter Park, Florida.
Got it. Okay. And when did you start swimming?
I was probably four and I probably raced in my first race at six.
Wow. So when did you realize you were a good enough swimmer to be a collegiate swimmer?
You know, it's funny. We talk about this with sports and kids these days. It just wasn't on
our radar the way it is for kids now. I lived in Florida. You wanted to be outside. You wanted to
be with your friends. So we swam and little by little I, you know, I'd win a few races,
25 butterfly, something on backstroke and it was just something fun to do with your friends.
So I don't even remember thinking about college until maybe ninth grade when I won. I think we
got second at state and then my sophomore year I won state and what event? A hundred back and
hundred fly. Did you swim IM as well? I didn't. I was terrible at breaststroke. Horrible. There's
a bunch of jokes about that we could go into, but I won't right now. Yeah. I don't, I remember
thinking like, Oh, wow, that's great. Like I just won Florida's, you know, state championships,
but I also remember just loving my team and that like winter park high school one. And at that
point you really didn't talk to coaches that you didn't know recruiting, especially female
athletes. It wasn't huge back then to get a scholarship title nine. I've got to look that
up because I messed that fact up all the time. I feel like there weren't a lot of people I'd
ever met that had a scholarship that were girls. And so it wasn't until maybe my junior year that
my coach said, you know, a couple of coaches have called and said that, you know, you could get a
scholarship. And my family wasn't into sports. They just didn't even, I mean, they came to my
swim meets, but not really a lot of, um, they just weren't, everybody did their own thing in our
family. It was not how parents are now that are driving their kids and doing special coaches and
meets and stuff like that. So how I remember it was just, I had a lot of energy to burn off and
swimming was the one thing that after I was done, I felt like I burned that jet fuel off. That's all
I remember really. And then it just got better. And then coaches started to talk to me. Um, and
then the rest is kind of history. So what do you remember about getting to UNC? You went to a
basketball game with one of my girlfriends whose dad had gone there. Maybe this was my junior year.
And long story short, but he hits her brother dated the swim coach's daughter. And so at the
basketball game, which is huge in chapel Hill, it might've been a Duke Carolina game. I don't know,
but I remember it was a big deal. And someone said, Oh, Carolina is impossible to get in out of state.
And I thought, well, then I'm definitely going to try to get in out of state. Um, and so I,
I met the swim coach and he said, you know, call me when you're the end of your junior year,
when you're a senior. And I tried to get in. I don't think I got into Carolina at first. And
they had already given a scholarship to a girl from Ohio. She was going to swim 200 backstroke,
hundred backstroke. So I got an offer for Miami FSU and I think Florida, but I wanted to get out
of Florida so badly because everybody I knew was going there. And I was like, I want to have a new
experience. And so I just held. And then that spring, the girl decided to go somewhere else.
And so they gave me a, did you turn down those other scholarships? I did. Wow. I did. They were
in state schools and I, I, I didn't want to, I just didn't want to go there. And if I, I was,
I didn't want to swim. It was all because we were swimming against all the same people I grew up
with. I just knew I needed a new experience and I was kind of set on chapel Hill and somewhere deep
in my soul. I knew it would work out, which I have no idea why or how. And I remember coming home and
we had answer machines then and I hit my answer machine and it was coach Frank comfort. And he
was like, girl, we got a spot for you. We'll give you a partial scholarship. And if you make NC two
A's, we'll give you a full. And so I spent the first two years with just tuition and then my
parents paid room and board. And then once you made NC two A's, you got a full scholarship. So
my junior and senior year. So you swim fly and back. Yep. Both distances. A hundred back,
200 back, a hundred fly. Those are where my three. Yeah. Didn't want to do the 200 fly.
God, my arms would kill myself. I wanted to carry that third 50. I just be like, why am I doing
this? What did you say? Brutal race. What'd you swim? Well, I just swim like long distance swimming,
like ultra distance swimming. Of course. But when I swim in the pool, the only thing I could swim
was breaststroke. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. So I was decent breaststroker, right? Horrible. I couldn't
swim backstroke if my life depended on it. Funny. And okay. At butterfly. So short axis strokes were
fine. Pretty bad freestyler, despite the fact that I could swim for a long period of time,
but not fast. Right. Interesting. But I loved I am. That's why you, I bet you would have been
a decent IM or even if your breaststroke wasn't, no, I would, I would burn it out. Butterfly.
You didn't have anything left for free. And then they would just pass me. I had something
left for free, but I wasn't good. I just, I wasn't, I wasn't. I guess that's true. I think with IM,
I think having a strong breaststroke is valuable because it's late in the race and everybody's
tired and it takes up the most time of the race. So if you can, I remember swimming like at a
master's meet, if I could take six seconds out of somebody in a breaststroke, right? They could be
faster than me and the other. Nobody's going to take anything out of you on the fly because it's
the beginning of the race. Like you just, everybody's sort of conserving energy. Yeah. Yeah. That's a
fair point. But what year did you matriculate? I graduated from high school in 95 and Chapel Hill
in 99. Okay. So what year did you meet Nate? So I met Nate in 1998, 98. So the summer. So you were
going into my junior year. I think I, and I, I met him the summer of 1998 and I had just finished
my sophomore year swimming and I was just kind of a hot mess. I'd gained a ton of weight. I ate like
cream cheese and croissant sandwiches. Cause we were had like, um, what's it called training table.
I just really let it fly with penny draft and just nights out just my face and my body was just not,
not primed for winning anything. Um, I started dating a guy who had a weed problem and you know,
I kind of dabbled in that very little, but I, I was, I was running with a crowd that wasn't
conducive to being excellent. So you didn't hang with most of the swimmers. I did. He was on the
swim team. Okay. I was going to say, I would assume the swimmers would date a lot each other
because you have the same schedules and training. And at Caroline at the time you couldn't rush a
sorority or fraternity if you're on a swim, if you're on a athletic team. So basically they had
you, that was your group. Um, so I was really kind of insular with the swim team. I didn't love it so
much as I did in high school. I didn't love that. I felt like my, that my scholarship was depending
on it, that all of my friends did the same thing. Cause in high school we all had 12 girlfriends,
but everybody was different. I was the swimmer. One was the nerd, one was the smart one. One was
the party one. And once I got to chapel Hill, we were all fighting for NT2As or for the spot on the
relay. So it was just a different experience. So I dated this guy for awhile. And then
my summer before my junior year, I met Nate at a bar. And had, was Nate a senior at that point?
He was going into his fifth year senior year. Yeah. Cause he'd redshirted his for a year. Yeah.
Okay. He was going into his fifth year and I met him at a bar and, um, I just remember him walking
in and just absolute enormous man with more confidence than you've ever seen in your life,
more swagger for a huge fat guy that you couldn't, I mean, unbelievable. And I met him that night
and he, he gave me this napkin that said, if you want the best say goodbye to the rest,
go home with me and I'll make you happy. And I mean, I was like, what? But the funny part is
years later I met a girl at a wedding and she's like, you won't believe it. I know you're married
to Nate, how good shit it, but he left me a napkin one time in college. And I was like,
mother of God. Um, but yeah, I met him that night and then we didn't really,
we didn't see each other for a while. Um, but it turned out one of my roommates was dating a guy
on the offensive line named Ryan. And so a couple months later we had a house party where we watched
X files, which is a great thing. And just everybody partied and got drunk and danced and Nate was there.
And at some point that night a guy called that I was dating and Nate just walked over and took the
phone and was like, she's with me now. And that was it. Wow. So what is it that you liked about
him in that moment? Because on the one hand, it sounds like you were kind of amused, but I mean,
what did you see at that moment? I mean, from the minute I met him, if I'm honest,
like I knew there was something and he was nothing. I grew up in my father's a lawyer.
My mom was very politically active, a country club, you know, very kind of rigid, you know,
lots of, um, my town was very Southern and Christian. And, um, when I met Nate, he was so
different. He was like a poor kid from Allen town, just a guy that hustled. And I just felt he was
different. He was connected. Like when he'd sit and listen to you, you felt like you were the most
important person in the world. And he did it with everybody. I could see how he interacted. There was
a way when he walked into a room that you could tell everybody loved him and he loved them. Um,
so I knew that first night something was different about him. And then the night that we kind of
started dating, there was just a joy to Nate that was different and an extreme way of living,
which was concerning then and concerned me my entire life with him. But he was here for the
moment. He was here to have a good time and feel it all experience at all. Um, most loving human
being you'll ever meet truthfully. So I couldn't understand how I was attracted to him because it
just didn't match anything that I had imagined. Um, but when we started talking, the things he
was talking about were the same thing as me. Like, what do you want to do with your life?
Who do you want to be? What books have you read? Um, what type of spiritual practices do you have?
And we were, you know, 19 and 22. And I remember he was on this deep search for meaning and purpose
and how do we serve? How do we get the most out of this life? Um, and so we kind of both started on
a spiritual journey at a very young age. And that's what I loved about him always. So married a
really fat, 300 pound, amazing defensive tackle. What year did you guys get married? We got married
in 2002. We got engaged at the world trade center in 2001 in July couple months before 9 11. At the
top of the tower. Yep. And I remember Nate being like, do you think that's a good sign or a bad
sign? And for a long time I was like, I think it's a good sign. And then after everything happened,
I was like, maybe it was a bad sign. But, um, yeah, we loved living in New York. He played for the
Giants. And so we lived there for a while and then we got married in 2002 in Florida. So, you know,
Nate was not the guy who was going to get drafted in the first round. So what was your thinking as
you were saying, okay, I'm really serious about this guy and he wanted to play in the NFL. Like,
who doesn't play college football and wants to play in the NFL. So what were you thinking about,
his chances and, you know, obviously he had an amazing work ethic. How far did you think that
that was, you know, did you actually think that could get him out of college football? I actually
can hear him laughing. I, I was like, you'll never make it, which was always what I'd say to him.
Like the worst. I hope you like, you don't have a shot in hell. Like you haven't started. And he
was like, I'll just work my way. If I can just get a shot. He was always like, I can just get a shot.
And so truthfully, when the draft came, I had never, I'd seen him play in college, but he wasn't
a starter. He started almost lost his scholarship. Didn't you? Yeah. He almost lost it. And, uh,
Mack Brown was the coach and he was like, listen, buddy, this isn't going to work for you. He was
like fourth on the depth chart or something. Yeah. He was behind like Vani holiday and some of the,
I can't remember, uh, Dre Bly. It was just a big year at chapel Hill. We'd beat FSU. And I remember
just thinking like it's not going to happen, but we were young and I didn't, you know, I still had
a year and a half of school. And so I remember he went to the combine and he, he had a really fast
40 and he hit, he had a good combine and Caroline had had a great year. So he was back up to some
guys that were going first and second round. Um, but truthfully, the day of the draft,
I didn't even understand it in our families, his family to not into football, my family,
not into football. I actually thought it was an archaic sport, both sides academics on both sides.
Um, and Nate was like, if I could just get a chance on a practice squad, then I could make it.
And then we could save a little bit of money and then we could maybe buy a house someday. I mean,
that was pretty much the way we thought of it. Um, so when he got called by the giants to be on
the practice squad, everybody was shocked, but also knew that there was nobody that made the
good guys try harder than a guy like Nate, cause he would just literally go until he couldn't.
So I think I was surprised and it was more just, we were young and I was like,
good luck. Like hope you make the team. But we, I wasn't ever that invested in his career. Um,
I just wanted him to do it and get out safe and then make some money so that we could
start our real life. So did you know Jeff Saturday when they were roommates? Oh yeah.
Oh yeah. I mean, Jeff's still one of my best friends and his wife. So we all lived together.
Jeff and Nate lived together from freshman year. And I mean, the story about Jeff is,
yeah, tell that story. I mean, that's just, it's an amazing story, especially in light of what
Jeff Saturday went on to become right. One of the greatest centers of the game. And to think that
he got overlooked and then tell people how that happened. So Jeff and Nate were roommates
freshman year. And Jeff tells this great story about when he first met Nate, um, he, he went to
introduce himself, but Nate was sobbing, hugging his parents. And he was like, wait, I'm, I'm like,
going to be rooming with this like cry baby. Like what's happening? Jeff's a guy from Georgia,
grew up kind of a rough life, very tough. And they ended up being best friends. They played
together along with Chris Kaldorf, who was up for the Heisman. There was a group of them
and when we all were waiting for the draft, Chris had been the quarterback and Jeff was the center
and we were certain they were going to go in fourth round, fifth round. And we all just sat there and
you kind of just sit around back then and just wait for the phone to ring. And there's no cell
phones or anything. And nobody called, nobody called, nobody called. And then the only person
that got called was Nate. So Nate went on to the giants and got on the practice squad and barely
made it through that first cut, but he made it. And then he got released by the giants and the
Colts picked him up right away. So Nate moved to Indianapolis. And at that time, Jeff was,
wasn't sure he, I think he got a shot at Baltimore on a practice squad, but didn't make it. So he
came back to North Carolina and started working at like a pet boys. And they didn't think he had
a shot. It was kind of over. He was too short. I mean, Nate used to always tell him and Jeff,
if you're listening, they said, you know, he has short arms. He'll never make it as a center. And
they wrote all these awful things about him. And Nate just always went up against him in practice
for four years. And he was like, he's the best guy I've ever played against. So at some point,
Nate was still barely making the Colts trying to just get, you know, you want to get paid week by
week if you make the team and if you play. So it's not how people think. And so at one point,
Nate said he had a really tough practice and the guys that he played against, he's like,
I just walked away being like, those guys don't even close to what Jeff did. So he walked into
Polian's office in like dirty sweats. Polian doesn't even know who he is. He has no clue. He's
like, who is this guy? Cause he's just like a guy trying to make the team. And he said, there's a
guy in Raleigh, North Carolina, that's working at an auto parts store right now. His name's Jeff
Saturday. And he could kick all those guys' asses that I just played. And coach said, well, if you
want him to come live with you, I'll give him a shot. And then that was it. And the rest is history,
six pro bowls or whatever it is. He'll be a Hall of Fame. And I still get mad because Nate and I
are like, and he got us a comforter for our wedding. Like we're like, Hey buddy,
like we kind of started your whole career and all we got was like, we got this lousy comforter.
Yeah. Just one of the greatest guys, biggest heart. Um, it has gone on to have an exceptional
career for sure. So let's go back to, let's start at 99, right? So you were the Rams,
you're in St. Louis. I remember this year very well because I mean, Kurt Warner, of course,
so at the beginning of that playoff run, did you think this is really going to happen? Were you?
Yeah, it was really fun for the first time. I was like, Oh, this is fun. And we were winning.
I was still in college, so I would fly. Oh, that's right. You, this would have been your senior year.
So I was still in college and it was, it was just fun. And we were winning and we were winning. And
Kurt was an exceptional leader, spiritually, emotionally, everything. And the team just had
a bunch of really good guys on it. And it was fun to be a part of that team. And I think
I've always felt like the energy matters the most. And there was something that was telling us the
energy on this team is good. So every time they won, you just now it gets more, you're like,
please win, please win. Then you're like, really? Cause you know that this, this may never come
again. And most of the time it doesn't. And we had Dick Vermeel as a coach who's still probably one
of the greatest humans to me and still continues to come to my house twice a year to see the kids
and just have dinner with us. Just an exceptional advocate for his players as human beings,
way past, you know, their football. Nate loved him and he was the one that gave Nate a shot
multiple times just because of his character. Cause it takes like, he's not that good,
but he really makes the other good guys better. So that year was just exceptional and it was fun.
And St. Louis was on fire and that, that city needed it. And I remember when we made it to the
last, I'm the worst about football, the last playoff game, whatever happened last night that
we all just watched the divisional champion. I was like, Oh my God, we could, we could win the
Superbowl, but I was young and I, so I got there and I was wearing some like nerd outfit and all
the other NFL wise were like smoking hot and looking so cool. And I think I had like my backpack,
but I just didn't know we didn't, we weren't into it like that. And I remember the last play came
and it was that big play where Mike Jones was tackled. I forget who I remember. Anyways,
it was that last second. And I remember thinking, and I told Nate this and he was very offended.
I was like, whatever you do, don't put Nate in. Like, please don't put him in because I didn't
want him to be the guy that lost. I was like, I can't live with it, but they tackled the guy
before he got in the end zone and the Rams won. And it was just exceptional. It was an exceptional
experience. And there's, I don't know if you know this, but they have two parties for both the teams.
Just one's a lot more fun. They're identical. So each team has a hotel and each team has the same
exact party ready, but one's just the real, the party. That's the better way.
Because they both have the t-shirts ready as if they're going to use it, right? Yeah.
Yeah. Your NFC champion or not. Yeah, exactly. So I just remember it was fun. We danced. We,
we had a great time. We never took any of it for granted. We loved all of it.
And Nate was in a ton of pain. Always. Yeah. You, you wrote about that a lot in the book and,
it's sort of interesting when you think about how early in his career he was. I mean, he was in pain
before he made it to the NFL, which is something that we would assume, well, you know, God, if a
guy's been in the NFL for 15 years, I can sort of see why he wouldn't have toes anymore and why he
wouldn't be able to feel his hands. But you don't think of a guy who's 22 trying to get into the
NFL already under that type of discomfort. Yeah. He was banged up because first of all,
when you play on the line, that's a whole nother ball game. And when you are not a starter that
kind of gets to take breaks. So Nate was the workhorse. And so he took so many hits. And
when he got to college, I don't, I don't want to mess up the weight, but he was skinny,
not skinny, but he was a basketball player in high school. And in order to play the position
that he was welcome to play at North Carolina, he had to gain a ton of weight. So he, by the time,
I think when we got married, he was 300 pounds and maybe he was like 220 when he got to Carolina.
So he force fed. So I think the weight he put on his body put to move that amount of weight around
that fast and that often took a toll pretty early. His neck was a 21. Could that be right?
It was enormous. And I remember the first night I slept with him,
not literally, but maybe I don't know, you know, you know what I mean? But I remember being like,
this snoring won't work. This is, this is a game changer. Like we're going to have to make a move.
And when he got to the Giants within a couple of weeks, they gave him a sleep apnea mask at 22.
So for our entire time together for 21 years, I never had slept with a man that didn't have
a sleep apnea mask, which is awful to look at, but it has this wonderful white noise sound.
And your husband doesn't snore. And it helps him sleep. And I remember he used to say like,
I could die without this. I'm like, no, you couldn't. So early on, I think he was just too
big to do what he was doing without paying a price quite often. And he was, but he wasn't
a complainer. He's like, I choose this, but you could just tell he spent a lot of time just
managing where to put the pain, which was out of his mind and just accepting it's,
it's what it is to get us where we want to get to, which again was always save some money
and then then go start the life that I wanted to do to serve people or do whatever.
What did you think at the time, not knowing necessarily what you know today, because I
think today you have much more perspective on that. But when he was 23, 24 years old,
what did you imagine he was going to be like at 50 as a result of the injuries he already had?
Like, did you think, did you, did you have a vision in your mind of when we're 60,
we're going to be just, we're going to be hiking in Peru, you know, backpacking with our grandkids.
Like, did you, did you think that it was all, this was all going to be okay. And these injuries are
going to go away. Well, he was always into health. He was always into, um, learning about his body.
He took great care. He had great people, Mike Clark, great, great people that were doing good
things, taking care of his body. He was always very, well, there's double side tonight. He was
always very aware of what he put in his body and taking care of him through PT and ice baths and
all that stuff. But he also loved like wings and beer and partying. So I don't know which is which,
but I definitely thought that when he was done, he would lose the weight
and he would become hot and skinny and we would live a happy life.
I mean, I never thought that I never thought he would stay so big. And that's kind of a side note.
I think when those guys get really big, it's part of, it's part of what they love about themselves.
There's a respect that they get when they walk into a room. They don't actually want to get that
much smaller. Um, one of our best friends, Tony is, but he was always fit, but he really, and Jeff,
Jeff did too. They both got really skinny. I think Nate secretly loved being big. Um,
because he would lose weight, but he never really loved himself at two 35. He loved himself around
two 60. And I think that was still too much weight. So as the years went by, that would be a fight
that we had quite often. Like when are you going to start, like when are you going to start doing
what you promised you would do, which was lose all the weight and stop dipping and, you know,
don't drink as many beers and don't eat chicken wings and nachos. And it just, he would have
spurts of it, but the Allentown in him just couldn't, couldn't be stopped. So you guys married in
oh two married in oh two. And then he retired in oh two or oh three. He retired, um, right before
my son was born. So I think oh four. Okay. All right. So was that a happy day for you?
It was mixed. How so, um, well, he didn't have a job. He didn't have a lot of life skills.
Emails had just started. We had just started technology was not Nate's jam. Um, he lived in
in this, in a world way up and way up in the sky. He lived in big dreams and big hopes.
And I was like, we have a baby on the way. And like, what are you going to do for a living?
I was a pharmaceutical sales rep, which was not my ideal job, but it was a great job to have
coming out of college. I didn't know what he was going to do. And I think a lot of guys,
when they transitioned out of football, most of them only play three to four or five years.
You kind of just get dropped into the world again. And all your friends that you went to college
with, they've been working for five or six years and you now are starting at an entry
lab jobble, like maybe 40,000 a year. You're used to making that a week. You used to everyone
worshiping you. It's a huge transition to for these guys. People, it's very easy.
If you're not mindful of it to lose sight of what the median experience is like in the NFL.
Not the mean, right? Because the mean gets dragged up by the Tom Brady's, Aaron Rodgers,
the guys that have remarkable longevity, remarkable skill, make remarkable money.
But if you talk median, like what's the guy right in the middle, the 50th percentile guy?
Yeah, he might be in the league for three years. He might have made a million or two over three
years before taxes, before paying agents, and then the other thing is what did that do to his
life expectancy statistically? Just how many years did he pay for that? And when you look at it that
way, you know, it's sort of like any sport, right? I mean, I shouldn't say any sport. I think
football is one of the worst boxing would be another example, right? It's very easy to see
the guys at the top of that. But the pyramid that those guys stand on is a base this wide that's
getting crushed. Yeah. And I think, and I mean, obviously, the last four games that we've watched
the past two weeks have given me this dual experience that I continue to have around
football, that it is this great unifier and this great community builder and this wonderful thing
that brings people together and brings a bunch of people joy and brings the players a lot of
opportunities and a lot of gifts and gives their families a ton of things. And then there's this
whole other side that we don't see a ton of, which is the guys that played three years and
are still beat up or they don't have any money or they couldn't transition. I don't know. I don't
know how to, especially after the past two weekends, watching these playoff games, they were so fun.
And it made you love football and it made you see this is a great thing. And I would never let my
kid play and, you know, I would never have a kid in a helmet, but I don't, I used to think I had all
the answers about certain things and that I had, you know, a really strong opinion one way or the
other. And I'm probably more conflicted about a lot of things in life than I ever was. And maybe
that's a good thing. But I feel conflicted about football and I can't speak for Nate because
he's not here, but I would love to hear what he has to say, what his perspective was.
I know what his buddy's perspective is. And I do think that it's a great honor to play that sport.
And it's like the, you're like the king of what everybody wants to do. You know, you get this
opportunity that kids dream of, but there is a price and we don't really show that side of it.
We don't tell kids like, what's that guy doing 10 years later? Like we don't do ESPN spotlights on
that. Right. Remember when MTV used to always do that? Where are they now? Oh my God.
My roommate in med school, this was our, this is the only thing we would watch on TV. Every single
week we would never miss it. And what we loved about it was it was always the same story. You
could just plug in a new name of a band. Like this week it's Motley Crue. Right. This week's
it's Guns N' Roses, but guess what? It's the same story. That's actually an interesting just idea.
Like where are these people that were so amazing three years ago or five years ago? What do they
do now? Where do they live? What does their crib? What does their crib look like today?
How are they financially? How's their relationship with their children, with their kids?
I have obviously been surrounded by guys like Tony Gonzalez and Jeff Saturday who are exceptional
men, husbands, friends. But I know that is not always the case. So I don't know. These discussions
have been had at length. The book has brought out a very strong opinions on both sides.
I'd like to come back to that because I think I too feel conflicted about a lot of this stuff.
So what city were you guys living in when Ned retired?
So basically when he got released by Kansas City we went out to visit a friend that lived in
Manhattan Beach, California and he said you got to come to this little town. It's so great. And so
we went out there and then while we were there he got picked back up by I don't remember what team.
Maybe the Rams again. Vermeel always grabbed him again when he could. He's a good man. And I said
I'm just going to stay. I'm not going to keep bouncing around. I'm going to get a job because
someone's got to get a job. Someone's got to take care of this family. I said he was like police.
So I stayed and he played about another year and a half. And then his last team was the Cardinals.
They gave him a shot. But he was done. I mean he was emotionally done. You have to really want it.
And he was so tired of sitting in the meet. There's a lot of sitting in football. There's a lot of
film and watching. And Nate was like after a while this is just like this cannot be my life.
Can't just be watching like run X and O's. Like he had big dreams to change the world.
And so once he got cut we moved back and we moved into El Segundo. Pretty quickly after that we got
pregnant. And he went back. Both of you? Both of us got pregnant. Nate looked pregnant. I looked
really pregnant. So we lived in El Segundo. He went back and got his master's in social work.
Yeah did that that did that surprise you? That I mean in a way I'm sure it didn't because of
how much he loved the world and wanted to help people. But did it surprise you that that was
the chosen path? So he comes. His dad was a minister at Harvard and his mom was a professor
at Holy Cross. So he comes from an academic kind of service oriented family. That was if like some
kids are told to be bankers he was told to serve. So that was pretty much in his soul. So I don't
know. And he didn't have a ton of skill sets. What did he study in college? Like every good
studied football. No he studied communications like we all did along with the help of many people.
That's back in the day. So yeah we didn't he didn't have any he didn't he hadn't had an email
everything when you're in the NFL. That runs with a funny story.
I'm going to try not to name names here because it's not. Please just make up a pseudonym. Yeah
yeah but so so about the I don't know I won't even tell what year because then you could figure out
who it was. But years ago a few years ago I was helping out a buddy who wanted me to come
and do some work with the kids who were going to be probably the top 10 picks out of college. So
had the potential to be so I mean they all went in the first two rounds including Heisman trophy
winner. So there's 10 of us there the guy who brings me in to help me and then there's these
10 kids some of whom are playing right now and are the best in the NFL. And so the guy who had
me come in talk to them he's like hey look you know we did some blood work on them we want to
talk about nutrition we want to talk about you know like what can they do to optimize their
performance. So he brings me to this conference room it's beautiful and it's in Petco Park in
San Diego which is where everyone is meeting. And you know I'm starting to try to explain like some
of the biochemistry but and I'm keeping it I'm not believe me I'm not going all in on this right
I'm just doing like you know glucose you know glucose right and oh god what did the guy say so one
of the guys goes he's so bad the guy who won the Heisman was like I don't know which I don't
understand any of this and one of the other guys who I think honestly I could probably say is the
single most successful one that came out of that class he's like dude did you not take biology
and he goes well I took it yeah I mean what do you what do you call taking what's your
definition of taking yeah I mean I just don't know and this was 25 years ago right am I that old
yeah this was it was it was just different it was different back then and he didn't have it I don't
know what a lot of these guys do you know I didn't know so I wasn't surprised I was just glad that he
I thought I remember thinking because I managed a lot of his life because he was up you know in a
marriage they say someone's the balloon and someone's the rock he was like the biggest good year blimp
on the planet earth and I was the most uptight and erotic best rock you can I mean there was no fun
no joy no nothing and he would just float around and so I was I mean I think I probably said like
you need to go back to school because we needed a transition we needed something we're like he
learned how to type because remember we have tutors and stuff in college and so and they we
have lots of practices and we need a lot of help and so I would just remember thinking I don't
think he can go get a job like that would just be a disaster like he'd be like and also your ego has
to adjust to be nothing from being like signing autographs as a Super Bowl champion to being
like an assistant to I don't know whatever you get when you're 24 25 so school seemed like the
best way to slowly modulate back to a normal life like have things responsible and you have
due dates and deadlines so and he had this he had a dream to help people but he had no idea what it
meant to be a social worker how much you made and he couldn't comprehend and I remember when he
finished he graduated valedictorian which was exceptional because he barely got out of Chapel
Hill and he went to an interview and he's like they said it's $50,000 for the year he said I
don't even know that is slavery I was like this wrong word he was like he was like and you know
every time I fucking want to take a vacation I have to ask somebody with a sheet and put the
dates down I mean what are they written I mean he was he the TPM forms whatever they're called
yeah he was just like what are you talking about and he's like I get 10 days and I was like welcome
to the world but it but it was so he couldn't believe it he was just that's kind of amazing
isn't it he was floored he's like this is outrageous because football you have like a good four months
to do whatever and you've got money in the bank and your people high-fiving you and life is good
and then you go back to and they're like you could I remember listening him talk to HR and he's like
so what if I don't want to what if I want more vacation days and they're like nope he was like
this is he was just blown away by it so he was pretty depressed during that period of our life
and I remember I remember early on being like listen I didn't sign up for I need to know can you
do this are we gonna make this because you already had Jack right I had Jack and I said I don't know
what you have to do to make I didn't need him to be happy but I I was like with this transition
we knew going into it that this was a problem most most guys I think 70% end up broken divorced
after they're done that's a really big number that's staggering of people that just fall apart
and the average years you play is three so I mean that's a lot of people that are literally
falling off a cliff after they do professional football in their mid 20s mid 20s within and
they're probably the heroes so they go home and they like work at a bar in their high school
town because they they want to feel good again so we were just determined to find a new way but
it was bumpy it was bumpy he was sad he was sad and Nate was always very aware when he I don't know
if he had anxiety but I know he had depression and I know that he didn't want to feel bad and
he hated that he didn't he didn't know why and he worked really hard I mean he was well read
and he would try everything and so after a while once he kind of started to find some purpose
in the social work it got better and then at a certain point he's like I can't live on the
salary and like every good athlete does he decided to go into financial advising because there's
nobody you want to manage your money more than a football player no but he was great and he really
he felt that he'd seen so many guys lose a bunch of money to the wrong people so he
financed he loved investments he's he loved gambling so that's kind of what the stock market
is in its own way and so he moved into that at Morgan Stanley and loved it and ended up starting
helping guys that were in unions like just line workers and Verizon guys just like blue-class
blue-collar guys that just needed help with the money that they'd saved making sure it was
invested well so he kind of felt like he got the allen town and the finance stuff and was able to
serve and so that ended up being his career that he took on for the rest of his life and when did
you guys start to have those discussions about hey where's the 230 pound version of you who's
kind of getting back into what you know you had sort of imagined life post NFL would look like
I mean day one I mean I rode that man so hard for his whole life he could take more beatings
from me verbally and from coaches and teams I just I was tough I was like you you're this is
not going to work you you don't look good you're not healthy and he would he was always he wanted
to be better and so he would have times when he would get really in shape and he was probably the
guy in our neighborhood that everybody listened to health-wise because he had all the information
there was just certain things he he you know he would he would always do like sober January
February and then he was when the sun would come out again get a little dicey March April by the
summer he was full board just having a ball and then forget about it once the Yankees started
wheels were off and we would cycle through that did he ever go visit a doctor during this period
of time so the NFL has a program where you go once a year so I don't know the details on this
don't hold me on this but you either you sign something where you they say you'll never sue
them again and we'll give you care like you go every year to an NFL some type of physical
or you can do your own thing but we're not going to take care I don't know the details but we
chose the one where we we took some money you take a lump sum of something and then you can't
ever sue them about certain things and then they kind of put you in a program where they check in
with you every year mentally physically and so he would do that but I now looking back I actually
found his records from his last year and he had told me like everything was fine and then I
everything was fine except for this one page that was so not fine which was his heart and his
cholesterol and his weight and we didn't really talk about that I mean one thing I think if I
could go back and do different things in my marriage I would have had a different tactic
because I think I was so scared that I was mean and then it didn't feel safe for him to tell me
the truth so he just put it aside and was like I'll deal with that I'll take care of it but I'm
not going to get into it with her but I always wanted him to be skinnier and his mom I mean it
was the biggest thing that his mom used to say to him was like please lose the weight please lose
the weight but it was really hard for him was he still exercising lifting weights and things like
that he always worked out very physical very athletic I mean he was he was still really good
we played football every Thanksgiving in El Segundo and he was great fast talented strong yeah people
don't appreciate that you'd think well what's a defensive lineman or defensive tackle like
they're so big but they can't be that fast they are so fast the most athletic man I've ever seen
he could he was the strongest man I've ever seen and he had a work ethic physically that he would
just he could go forever he could also rest forever too he was extreme in every in every way good and
bad so your daughter was born in what year 2008 got it okay so fast forward to November of 2017
yeah you had some premonitions that something wasn't right I mean how how much of that do you
think you now look back at and think I can only appreciate this now through the retrospectoscope
versus at the time did you think there's something wrong with me like I'm really losing it
well there's two parts that my friends will tell you you were very vocal something was wrong
so I have witnesses that remember for about two or three years like something's wrong with her
she can't settle she's anxious and I would say I don't know what's wrong something's not right
and I was so scared I was nervous travel had become just really what were you doing the time
were you still working so I was working in Chapel Hill okay no I was working in recruiting
and medical recruiting and so the the team that I had in Chapel Hill was a group of guys that I'd
gone to college with that played football and so I would go back every month because my team was
there and for years I started in 2012 it was fine but then around 2014-15 I started just
dreading leaving the family but it made no sense the kids were in a great age Nate was doing great
but my anxiety was through the roof I'd wake up sweating I'd wake up and how long each month would
you have to be gone maybe three or four days do you think you were anxious that Nate couldn't
handle getting them to school on time or what do you think was upsetting you I mean I don't know
how spiritual I can get here but I I felt like something was coming it's the best way I can
describe it something's coming and the message to me was prepare like somehow something's coming
that's big you don't know what it is I can't explain it but and there was something about Nate
that was floating away and I was trying to get to him and I was also trying to manage this
unexplained anxiety that had you ever experienced anxiety growing up like were you an anxious person
by nature not I mean I wonder what my friends would say I wasn't anxious but I I needed to swim
six hours a day so I don't know I don't know what that means I've always you know energy yeah a lot
of energy but I don't remember being nervous or fearful I wasn't a lot of fun like I wasn't the
party girl I didn't do drugs I wasn't like let's stay out all night I was always like we need to
get home and very responsible but I wasn't anxious but I never was I never was a let go I was never
like let's just see where where the wind takes us but I didn't have panic attacks and those you
know the nights the nights that are just you can't stop your brain going those became more and more
and more the two years before he died and I had this sensation did you ever talk with him about
it all the time what would you say please don't die what would he say I promise I'm not going to
I won't leave you don't worry I'm here I'm something I would say like I can't live without
you like you're my best friend you're like the only person I know like you're the best dad in
the world okay I'm thinking about it and he would be like I'm right here I'm never gonna leave you
and fast forward I don't think he has but in many ways but yeah and I just was like Nate I can't I
don't know what's wrong with me and he's like you just need to calm down and his big thing was just
stop being afraid what are you so afraid of you're so you just say like you walk around so afraid
of everything like what if you just knew everything was okay like he's like everything's okay babe
like you're okay we're okay the kids are okay and that was always his message and there was
nights that I would go to bed and he would be watching a show and he was always watching
something really masculine like Oprah's you know final show and he'd just be sobbing you know and
or Mr. Holland's opus or some like show that just like you just and he would just cry and and I
would say what I'd come out and say like what's wrong he's like I just hope I I hope I have enough
time I hope that I can make a difference in this world and there there came a point where I would
wake up and I couldn't find him and I felt like he was gone and I'd scream for him and he would
be like I'm right here I'm in the other room but you'd literally scream I literally would and the
only reason I know this is all true is because I would tell my friends you guys I wake up and I
scream and I feel like Nate's gone and he always comes in and he says I'm right here don't worry
about it but so those things started to happen and in conjunction with that I said well I need help
so that's when I started to really dig into self-help and spiritual books and I was like where is
there's got to be an answer here and it turns out there wasn't an answer but there was a huge
toolkit I was about to be given for what I think I knew was coming and tell me more about that
so I feel like every when I started reading obviously Vishon's book The Code of the
Extraordinary Mind and that's kind of a book that I talk about because it it was pivotal for Nate
and I we read it together and then we gave it to Tony and when we gave it to Tony he loved it so
much and he's a big seeker of information and he then contacted Vishon who wrote the book and
through a bunch of beautiful synchronicities I got an opportunity to go to this event in Jamaica
and it was I grew up in a spiritual family everybody you know Wayne Dyer, Esther Perel
we did A Course in Miracles very open-minded religiously everybody could believe what they
wanted the idea was about love and God and being fearless I come from a very fear-based family but
we really believed in being fearless just no one had mastered it quite yet and so Nate kept saying
like I don't you got to fix this I don't know what's going on with you but you can't keep living
like this meanwhile Nate was just crushing life at this point he was starting a non-profit in Watts
and he was doing great in his career and he was just really happy but there was something about
him that I felt like he was I mean this is so cheesy but floating away I couldn't get to him
the way I couldn't his eyes didn't seem he seemed far away he would forget things
he like he was we were barbecuing and he put all the lighter fluid on the fence
and then lit lit the match and the whole fence lit up. That's not like where are my keys so what
did you think about that? I just thought like I don't I don't I don't remember do you think he
was being funny no because he felt terrible after he hated himself after he'd berate himself like
I don't know what's wrong with me I can't remember and he would forget his keys always and he would
he would make little mistakes so I don't know that he knew something was wrong with him too
and I can tell because he started doing like mind exercises and he was trying to get going
or he would just say like I don't know why I feel so down he felt really sad the last year
of his life he was just and it wasn't depression as much as it was just it wasn't him I don't I
it's hard to describe but besides Tony and Jeff who else was he still in touch with regularly
closely from the NFL all of them all most I mean all the guys that coach for meal so they were
retired by then as well how many of these guys could understand what he was talking about I don't
know that he talked about it with a lot of people his best friend Chris in the neighborhood was like
he just won't share anything anymore it doesn't seem himself Tony will say that Nate was always Nate
and I do think when Nate would get around his buddies and they're all drinking he would be
much more normal it was more when we were at home and that the hard part is Nate was always
different so but he wasn't always so sad there was a sadness to Nate did the kids appreciate this
they'll tell they don't remember this at all it was subtle and it was subtle in a way that
sometimes I don't even know if it was I don't know what it was it was just everything in me
said something's wrong and I know everything in him I got his like I found his journals after he
passed and a lot of them were like you've got to be more connected you're gonna find joy again
there's nothing wrong with you keep going you know just try harder like very much self-talk
trying to get out of whatever he was in how long after he died did you find the journal
very soon did you read it right away did you hesitate for a moment were you worried about
what you would find no the one thing about Nate and I was like I never I didn't feel like he hit
anything from no not not that he was hiding anything from you but were you afraid that you
might see that he was in a pain that you didn't appreciate I feel that I didn't I wasn't worried
about that then because I didn't know what I know now I honestly didn't know how sick he was
once I found out I was devastated because I was so mean I was mean I was I did I didn't know what
was wrong with him and so I wish I could and I wish I could go back and be kinder but I had no
clue and he was somebody who just was like he wouldn't put it on me he would just deal with it
on his own so I wish I could have if I had known he was so sick I would have been much kinder much
kinder so no I didn't I don't I don't really know what I felt at the time I would be making it up
if I said it just felt like I was losing my husband and he seemed different from all the other husbands
he seemed older and tireder quickly that's the thing like I remember Tony and he were it was
Halloween right before he died and I remember thinking like why does Tony look so young and
vibrant and Nate looks so tired and exhausted and there's a thousand reasons why now that now we
know but so you're going to keep going with the Jamaica story yeah so it's it's so it's early
November of 2017 and you don't want to go on this trip right so we go to New York about a month before
for a birthday and I have probably the biggest and the last panic one of the last panic attacks that
I've had of my life and I just said Nate I can't go to Jamaica and and he takes his sleep at me a
mask off and we're in midtown you know and he's like listen you lunatic you're going on this trip
you need to live you need to learn to live fearlessly like you have all these gifts and you are
trapped in our house and in all this fear and it's time for you to go and I want you to go on that
trip and I want you to come back changed and and and he's and he never told me what to do he was
very supportive but he was like this is a non-negotiable if we're gonna make it I cannot
live with this anymore you are fine we are good I promise you everything's okay and he was serious
like I he was very rarely serious but he was like you're going like I'm not we're not doing this
and so the weekend of November 8th I he took me to the airport and he never took me to the airport
because the guy loved to sleep and so it was an early flight but he's like I want to drive you
which was very out of character for him he don't he had no problem putting his wife in an uber
zero zero he'd be like good luck you're good so I remember we could even call the uber right yeah
he would do everything jerk um so we were driving to the airport and I remember I was texting with
Toby because she was we got so long story short we got invited to go to this event in Jamaica it
was like a spiritual retreat Wim Hof Steven Cutler um Marissa Peers Jim Quick great speakers people
doing great things and Toby through their relationship Tony and Toby's with Vision we got
to go to this event called a fest and it's a it's a three or four day event twice a year where you
go and you just talk to people that are doing great things and look into your stuff and hear
great speakers so I I'm texting Toby and Nate grabs my hand and he never did this and he was
like can you put your phone down can you just put your phone down this will break me and he said
just I just want to be with you I just want to be with you for this next five minutes until we get
out and then you can text her and so we just held hands and he drove you know he drove me to the
terminal and he just said like you're the most amazing woman I've ever met in my life he's like
I've never met anybody like you wow I'm really crying um he said but I just want you to know I
love you more than anything and I hope you go have fun and that you come back a better person and
ready to do what I know you're meant to do and I don't want you to worry about anything because we
are going to be fine and you know I just I love you so much so go have fun and we kissed and I
went on and of course because I've always been very cheap I decided not to get the talk plan
in Jamaica so we just texted for four days the most beautiful text you could ever imagine
just about what I was learning and how supportive he was and he was like you're doing so great this
is awesome I was like I'm going to be different I'm going to move more during sex it's going to
be great like you're going to love this and then it was the last day and I remember Wim Hof had
just spoken and his wife had died when she was young and he was left with four kids and I remember
thinking like that would suck that would suck so bad if your spouse left especially a good one you
know so I went and I got in the water and I was swimming because we had one more event it was like
a bike a boat a boat excursion I remember I was swimming in the water and I felt like I felt the
divine all around me and I remember thinking like everything's changed like everything's changed
like I get it now like I don't need to be afraid I could breathe and I thought to myself I can't
wait to tell Nate he's going to be so happy and if you knew the time I was swimming in the water
and you knew what was happening in Los Angeles it would blow your mind so I got out of the water
and I was still in my suit put on some jean shorts and I was getting ready to go smoke some
Jamaican weed and get on a boat and just you know be the new Kelsey just like in the moment
and my phone rang a couple times and it was a number I didn't know and I was like not today
you know I'm in Jamaica doing the thing and then my best friend called and she said listen
I don't want you to do the Kelsey I don't want you to freak out and she said but Nate was at
Skyzone Trampoline Park and he fell and we don't really know what happened we're gonna go your
your brother-in-law's gonna go get the kids and your mom's heading over to UCLA but everything's
fine go on to the boat and I remember I just took a breath and I was like he's dead and she's like
he's not dead and everything Peter in my body knew that man was gone like everything and so I
felt like I was just waiting for the rest of the world to catch up to what I already knew which
was this was the thing because I also when I got to Jamaica all my anxiety went away it was almost
like sliding doors and once I made the decision to go on that trip this was this was what was
going to happen and I assumed that if Nate was smart he knows if I'd been there I'd have been
like you don't die on me like I would have been crazy so on some level I think he waited till the
last day because I had gotten all the information and I'd met all the people and so many of the
people from Jamaica have been super influential in my recovery and my grief work and some of the
psychedelic things and so I told Toby I was like we're going to the airport she's like this is
ridiculous everything's fine and I was like I didn't even I wasn't even talking I was just like
packing and I was like get me there was one one flight and I was like get us to the airport and
so we were driving down this Jamaican road with like potholes and I was in a taxi and the phone
rang and I knew it it was my mom and she said the doctor would like to speak with you and I took the
phone and he said I'm so sorry Mrs. Chittick we tried everything we worked on him for 50 minutes
because he looks so young but he didn't make it and I remember I said you know is he dead and he
said your husband had a heart attack and I said is my husband dead and he said yes Nate is dead
and then I just said to them with no emotion he's dead and Toby was like who's dead and I was like
Nate's dead and she screamed and and then began what would be the most transformative painful
and probably beautiful last four and a half years of my life. So how long did it take you to get back
to LA? So there was one plane going back to the US that day so it was late Saturday night and I
knew I had to get home to my kids because they didn't know and I really didn't even know what
they'd seen and that's another discussion we'll get into because I didn't really know there's a
million things around that but they thought that he had fallen but as they now we I know more about
what they thought but there was one seat left and when I got to the airport they were like you
there's not enough time it was like 20 minutes the door was shut and through a thousand miracles and
I will say and I tell this to people all the time in your biggest challenges and crises there are
angels literally all around you I mean I've envisioned them just God gives you or whatever
you believe that the people show up for you and it is miraculous so this one baggage claim guy
was like just hold on and somehow he talked to them and it's in Jamaica two people a little more
laid back and they opened the door which I really didn't think was ever humanly possible I think
it's like the one thing I've never seen happen in life like they're like nope it's an FAA command
exactly so I got on the plane and I had the last seat I was in an aisle and I went into shock and
you know much more about the brain than I do but I remember thinking oh shit this is like what you
see on tv when the woman's kid dies and she like just falls apart and I felt like I was having a
break with reality so I started throwing up in a little white bag and I was hyperventilating I
couldn't I couldn't come back to I couldn't integrate it I'd never had had an experience
where you you thought you were going crazy and so nobody talked to me at all which I wouldn't
have talked to me now I always talk to people when I see them like that but I think they were like
enjoying their honeymoon or their girl strip and they're like lunatic you know in aisle seven like
get away from her so I just I panicked for about 20 minutes and then the um the seat belt sign went
and all of a sudden there's this beautiful Jamaican woman in this gorgeous dress and she's
standing next to me in the row in the aisle and she puts her hand on my shoulder and she puts a
hand on my forehead and she says baby girl I don't know what you're going through or what awaits you
on the other side of this plane but I want you to know that there are so many people praying for you
and God loves you and I love you and you are stronger than you think and she said um
she said slow your breathing down baby girl and decide who you want to be when you land
when this plane lands and I don't know what it was but I it recalibrated my breathing
and she kind of just patted my shoulder she left and then I actually spent the next four hours on
that flight the layover in Texas and then the flight home deciding hopefully who I would be
you know a week from now a month from now five years from now ten years from now because
on that plane ride I would got really clear that they had just lost their dad but they
weren't going to lose me and that kind of became my north star from then on and I got home
I went to my mother-in-law my mom picked me up probably the worst drive you could ever imagine
from LAX at about midnight and I went to my friend's house and do you want me to go into
this part yeah this is the part that you just you can't make it better but I got to my friend's
house where my kids were they were nine and twelve at the time and they had been waiting all day and
I had lied to them and they said is dad okay and I had said over facetime you know he's not doing
well but you know let's just keep praying for him and I because I couldn't bear to tell them over
the phone I had to be there and so now it's funny because we joke about that like you lied about
really big things I'm like I know I did but I I've admitted to it so I got there and I gave them
both a hug and I asked everybody to leave and I just said I said three things I said
your father would have never left us if we weren't going to be okay it just wasn't his style
do you understand me and they nodded no yes mom and then I said um I need you to know that I'm
enough I have no idea how I'm going to do this I don't know how to live life without your father
I don't know how to raise you guys without your father but I'm certain I'm going to figure it out
and we're going to have a great life and you guys need to stay being nine and twelve and don't need
to worry about anything because I've got this do you understand I said yes mom and then I said the
most important thing I need you to know is that you are not victims that you had the best father
for nine and twelve years and he focused all of his energy on you he loved you with everything he
had he was the kindest most patient amazing human being I've ever met and some kids don't get that
for a day so just always remember that you're the lucky ones do you understand they were like
yes mom and then I asked them both and they were tiny and I said what do you guys need
from me and they said if you're okay we're okay and so I mean I tell every mother like you would
become okay too um and that's what we've done we kind of from that point on fought for joy
while acknowledging excruciating pain and doing it at the same time now the days got pretty dark
oh yeah the first two years were just brutal brutal tell me about the lowest lows
I think the first night if you've ever lost someone suddenly you feel like you've been set on fire
I can't explain the physical pain of grief I always thought it was mental but um grief is
grief and trauma is very physical um you want to get out of your body you know I never understood
why people cut I never understood why you I never understood suicide I never understood
you know drive people driving into trees when the pain is so big you have no way to describe it and
I had tons of resources and love and support and I still thought like this isn't going to work
um the beginning was surreal and I just it's it's hard to imagine how you're going to live in a
world that so quickly becomes a planet you've never been on um he was everything to us like he
was he was he was the guy um I didn't even know an adult life without him in it and he was a much
better parent than me in a thousand ways so I knew early on like we had a huge deficit when it came
to honesty spirituality kindness service he was just exceptional I was great at like scheduling
carpools and I was like well shit that's not going to lead to like a good kid you know that
we've got problems here um and I think when the numbness wore off of like the the memorials over
and there was a thousand hard times I think the morgue was exceptionally awful to go see him and
see him dead which you didn't want to do at all you fought like hell not to yeah I mean I remember
thinking like what are you fucking kidding me I'm not going to go see I'm not going to say goodbye
to my husband dead like I thought it was insane that someone would offer that um by the grace of
god and I this is I don't have much advice about anything but if people have been through it trust
them they know this and I had another angel that was like you have to go say goodbye to your husband
and I had probably one of the most beautiful experiences um because I I got some closure that
I never thought I would get and I have a great story of when I went to the morgue and and I
was an awful experience and there was police and there's nurses and they pulled him out of a freezer
and he's just laying there and he has he's still intubated but somehow all that fades away and I
just started to talk to him and my best friend was there and I talked to him for about 10 or 15
minutes just told him how much I loved him and how grateful I was and how you know I would do the
best for him and the kids and then when I got up my I asked my best friend like how'd it go and she's
like reminded me a lot of real life you just talked at him for a long time and he just stared
at you kindly and it's like that's so true um so the morgue was tough the corners was awful
death is such a business and there's the legality and the do they ask you if you would like an
autopsy given that no foul play it's so when you know when you die in a public place in LA you have
to do it I see you have to do a autopsy so that was on the books from the beginning um I think the
at about six months I thought this won't work and I've never had when you say this life yeah I've
never had suicidal thoughts I've been depressed I've been down I've been anxious but I never thought
like how do we get out of here did you ever find yourself thinking like these kids now are the
greatest thing I have and they're my anchor to him but they're also kind of the anchor that's
holding me to this earth like it's a very different calculation to think about ending your life with
kids versus without well my mom used to always tell you the one thing you lose once you have
kids is the right to kill yourself she used to say that all the time she's like you know what else
you can't even kill yourself once you have them because it wouldn't be fair to them and I remember
thinking that but I also remember thinking I want to take them with me I remember thinking like we
got to get to him there was this a couple nights where I thought so this isn't going to work I've
tried everything this doesn't work I feel lost I'm I'm so broken I'm so scared emotionally spiritually
physically financially I didn't know how we were going to do it and so I I ended up I mean I people
talk about this in the chapter but I ended up just saying like I'm going to talk to my son because I
knew he was 12 and I knew he was in a bad spot so why don't tell me about that tell me about like
what you saw in both of them over that six month period of time just like I mean if you have kids
just especially I'm guessing like after Christmas right so it was my guess is it's a blur through
Thanksgiving and Christmas hell yeah and then January so dark dark in every way like it's
January is dark to begin with but when you've lost the person that you worshiped and the person that
kind of was the light in our family like he was just he was great he was a great dad they were so
sad and confused and just a different level of sad like the saddest like they just got screwed
for their whole lives and they'll never be normal again and kids just want to be normal and they
want to go to school and they don't want to be the person that's dealing with the great tragedy
they were embarrassed they were how do you know that they would say it's just like the worst to
not have a dad it's so embarrassing not to have a dad you know like it's just awful and like
nobody will talk to me Jack says no one he says no one makes fun of me anymore no one jokes with me
parents look down when I walk past them he said everyone avoids me so because you don't know what
to say and then there's always the kids who the parent was like you go say something to them and
they're like sorry your dad died you know or something like that but we just I couldn't we'd
done a bunch of counseling wasn't working at the time we couldn't find the right fit for everybody
and I've learned a lot about trauma since then but I think it was a little early for the kids to
be forced to talk about it and I don't know if you've read what happened to you the Oprah Winfrey
book with Bruce I don't know who I don't know but she talks about like kids it takes a while for them
to even be able to process what they saw and felt whereas adults we have enough life experience to
to be able to talk about it but watching their dad die it wasn't something they could talk about but
I kept trying to force them to do counseling and be like tell us about the day your dad died and
they would just you know they would close their ears literally physically and rock and I'd be like
I am we are gonna talk about this so I did a lot of things that I thought it's really interesting
they would literally react that way like a baby like they would go like like I can't hear you I
can't hear you and what did the therapist think of that did they recognize that as a sign that they
just weren't ready to talk about this yeah yeah I mean eventually eventually but they would do
things like and I don't want to say stupid things but like my daughter didn't want to draw about it
she didn't want to like take a crayon and show her dad dying at Skyzone she really needed to
forget about it for a bit to integrate what she saw my son's a little more mature and he really
needed someone to talk to other than me like he needed someone who didn't have a dog in the fight
to talk about what it felt like to lose his dad so he actually over time had a great relationship
with a therapist for a year and then as the 40 year old that he is inside at the end he was like
I think I'm done for now thank you so much for helping I'll call you if I need you again but Jack
really had a clear intention at that age of what he needed through this and he said it's just nice
to go talk to a woman that will listen to me and that was a dig at me because he's like all you do
is talk to me but there was just a night that I thought like we gotta go Jack like we gotta we
gotta get to dad and so I said you know Jack I'm thinking about killing all of us in tongue and
cheek which we use a lot of laughter and Jack was like tell me how we're gonna die mom and I
was like well there's so many different ways but I think the best one is that I'm gonna drown you
guys in the tub he's a great he's how old at this point he's 13 and he's like four inches taller
than me um he's like but you only let us fill that you know there's a drought in LA so you only let
us fill it up like two inches and he's like I'm so much stronger than you I'm like I know but it's
I'm gonna do the best I can he's like okay good luck and it the more we talked about the stuff
and the more we laughed the better it got and then a couple weeks later Jack said you know mom I
I if I had a gun I would kill myself and I said you know I totally get it I didn't say like that's
awful don't do it because I understood and I just remember thinking was well we just won't have guns
in our house that's what we never did but I I remember thinking I know how to avoid this
and I said just hang on for today and then tomorrow and little by little like he's like
I don't think I want to kill myself anymore um so we navigated through that the first year was just
the crying at night and the nights are really dark when you have grief and when you have little kids
because they need so much because they are at night is when everybody whether you're an adult
I don't know I mean I wake up in the middle of the night or I used to quite a bit with just terrible
anxiety and their fear was so big and I just didn't think I had enough energy to be there for them
on my own how were you sleeping I mean I don't remember I don't remember sleeping the first
year very much because I was always somebody always needed something the first year at nights
such as meeting the kids themselves somebody somebody would be crying somebody would be
losing it someone would be um not well and you slept in three different rooms well a lot many
times we slept together um my daughter slept with me for a long time after he died and just she
wanted to crawl back in my uterus like I thought to myself like I'll never be able to leave the house
again like my life's over I'll never be able to have fun again I'll never be happy again
but amongst all of that I also thought we're gonna be okay like there wasn't it was it under
there was a knowing somewhere that like this was just part of it but it wasn't always going to be
this way but it felt like it was always going to be this way so I toggled through hopefulness and
just devastation but I knew we needed to hold on to the fact that this was appropriate and it
wouldn't last forever like there we were built to last like humans are built to last we aren't the
first people who lost their father I think our generation hasn't lost as many people as generations
before so it's just much more rare for us and it's more shocking but this has been happening
yeah it's interesting you say that like you sort of imagine
let's just go back in time 10,000 years not that far but just 10,000 years perfect and it's
basically the same thing it's you and Nate and the kids um you know you're hunter gatherers so
it's a little different you don't have electricity and all that stuff but there's certainly a scenario
in which Nate gets an infection and dies there's a scenario in which an animal attacks him I mean
like as you said it's not that uncommon that this would happen knowing what you know now I mean I've
ever thought about it this way but do you get the sense that the the calcium 10,000 years ago would
have had an easier time with this and if so would it have been because of expectations or would it
been have been because of the community that you would have been stuck with like you wouldn't have
had your own house for example both I think the expectation that now everybody lives till they're
90 happily ever after married with two kids and a mom and a dad that expectation has set us up to
be much much less resilient because there's this like one way and it's um it's all about joy and
fun whereas I think 10,000 years ago you saw people recover all the time from awful things babies died
and people went to war and there was famine we have so much now that our anxiety is higher than
ever before and I I felt that way before he died because when everything as opposed to being really
joyful when you have so counterintuitive isn't it yeah yeah because now you have everything you
don't want it to you don't want to fall apart whereas back then they were like well shit this
is this isn't that good so whatever I can handle things we just don't handle things and we don't
we're not used to feeling extremely uncomfortable anymore life is so comfortable things are so easy
not for everybody obviously for people with resources well I mean I think for everybody
compared to 10,000 years ago 100 percent yeah and this idea that pain is bad and death is bad and
that's a whole discussion you know now I have a completely different relationship with death
I have a completely different relationship with what it means for the physical body to leave
and that Nate isn't gone and we didn't get screwed and there wasn't a right time for him to leave or
not so there's so many nuances that through the last four and a half years have changed the way I
feel I'm still toggling between all the different ideas around grief you know there's a whole like
my mother-in-law believes like I will grieve forever I will grieve forever and that's just
how it is and our country wants everyone to be happy and I'm not happy and I'm like that's fine
and that's a choice I personally now believe again I'm back to this the football analogy holding
two beliefs at the same time I can be grieving very deeply and very grateful at the same time
they don't have to be one you don't go through one stage at the other I miss Nate terribly and I am
so happy I don't know what to tell you I'm happier than I've ever been in my life and I've been
through the worst thing ever and then I had some medical stuff just I think that came up from grief
and all the things that I was most afraid of I've made it through and I am so excited about life
so I don't know so how long after Nate died did you get the autopsy results back
so we got the heart part which is so he died of cardiomyopathy of the left ventricle
and the doctor called and just said we could tell right away he was a football player
his heart was so stretched out it was so big and he said listen mrs cheddar you you want all big
muscles just not a big heart nobody needs to have a big heart physically you can have it spiritually
but you don't want a huge heart and he said when big men move that much weight around at that speed
it just it's it overuses it and the muscle just gives out he said big men and big animals die
early and he said he was 98% blocked in all of his arteries and basically his left ventricle just
had no more give so he explained it to me as a water balloon that had just been stretched out
and there was just no pump anymore and he said big fat people can live a long time if they sit
all day and watch tv but if you're out playing football at thanksgiving and you know on the
treadmill yeah and Ronnie he would run the beach and jump on the trampoline he's like your heart
doesn't do that he said your your husband had a huge i mean i love on his autopsy it said he died
of a enlarged heart which i just think is beautiful because he had a really big heart
put that on the tombstone exactly yeah that's true that's true so that was um about three months
after he died and then and did they also look at his brain presumably they didn't they did
but they didn't have the right tools so they're like i don't we didn't see anything i'm like well
what did you do i mean it's la county morgue or corners i don't they don't think they have the
equipment so when did it first occur to you to maybe get the people at boston university involved
we had just started to talk about this a couple years before and i'd gotten like the pamphlet from
the nfl that said you know whatever the players benefits and there'd been a lot of talk i hadn't
watched um concussion yet with will smith i have since then but i i knew and i if i'm being
completely honest i thought oh well maybe there'll be some compensation financially if he did have
ct but i'm sure i don't know if he did or i don't know but i want to make sure because it would
depend on whether i'd let jack play because he was going to loyola and he was gonna play football
most likely so i said i need to know if football had anything to do with it the heart thing pretty
much sealed the deal but i was like i wonder what was going on with nate's brain so boston
university was exceptional dr maki was exceptional lisa the whole group there is phenomenal and so uh
la corners sent his brain tissue and they coordinated it with boston and they went they
said it'll be about a year because we're gonna do a um we're gonna i don't i'm using the wrong words
we're like pathological and do interviews yeah the clinical clinical yep and so we're gonna
interview everybody and talk about it and his parents had an even more feeling of him
floating away and being different as did his brother and i think i lived day to day with
him so it's harder to tell the the changes because they were so gradual where did his brother live
he lives in l.a so we saw him a lot and the irony is his brother is just an exceptional been sober
14 years but for so long we were trying to keep luke alive and it was just the way that it switched
and nate was gone and luke is still here in a huge huge part of our life but luke said he felt
the same way like there was a floating away and his mom especially was like he is not the son
i knew five years how long did she feel that five years five years five years and his dad his dad
just a kind man he teaches he he said um he doesn't really know how he felt or he doesn't remember
but he knew that something was different about his son but he can't put his finger on it
um so about a year later um a little bit no maybe like nine months we got a call and um
honestly i didn't know i didn't know what they were going to say but i didn't think they were
going to say what they said and uh dr maki got on the phone and just said i'm i'm sorry to tell you
but you know nate had stage two almost stage three uh cte he has lesions all over his brain and um
i just want you to know that that would have been a really hard life
so you know part of my ability to be in gratitude where a lot of other families that have football
players aren't is that i don't have to live with a man that's slowly deteriorating before my eyes
there are tons of people who have husbands that are healthy heart-wise but not brain-wise
so that's where it gets tricky and that's where i continue to talk about it but again
and you know for people to sort of understand what stage two and stage three is i mean junior say
i was stage two when he killed himself erin hernandez was stage three when he killed himself
and you know if you looked at them from the outside notwithstanding sort of the criminal
side of what was going on with erin you know they could tie their shoes and walk around so you
wouldn't look at them and say well they're you know they don't look like someone who's in the
last stages of alzheimer's disease but if you understand their behavior their moods and what
people who are around them would say and of course in the case of hernandez his behaviors
leading up to everything um they weren't you know they were clearly not behaving the way they
would have behaved if everything was totally normal yeah i had seen junior say i had a party
about um because we used to live in san diego and um there's a good friend of ours who's a
very close friend of his and it was his 70th birthday and this was about a month before he
killed himself and i remember like just he looked perfectly normal like everything was perfectly
you know it's just great to see him and everything seemed totally fine and i couldn't
believe it a month later yeah that's the thing about this disease and i think it's why it causes
so much um discussion and disagreements and i mean i debate this with football guys all the time
and then i debate it with the other side which is my mother and mother-in-law they're like it's
football is the devil and then all the people that we love that are like listen it's the name of the
game you know signing up for it um i don't it's again so at times although you know you could
push back on that and say maybe that's true today was it true when they signed up for it
yeah meaning nate's generation yeah i don't think anybody talked about it i don't think everybody
was lying about it for a really long time and and now it's interesting i mean just to fast forward
there is no compensation anymore for cde and i'm i'm making this up so don't see me but i i would
think it's because anybody that dies that's played in the nfl probably has some level after the number
of hits you take um i don't know what to do i i cannot imagine living with nate the greatest man
i ever knew with a severe brain disease that would either put us at risk or him at risk
or at at 42 i mean that's young that's very young i mean did the folks at bu i don't know much about
cte um did the folks there say based on what we saw pathologically this was what the next 10 years
would have looked like i mean or this was the next five like could they tell you this is the rate at
which this progresses and this is what you were in store for the next five years we never got into
that but they said they would give you the list of symptoms of what it would look like and a lot of
it was already there with nate depression um increased drinking wanting to be alone fatigue
big outbursts you know anger i mean nate never yelled at me in 21 years i mean he we we got after
it in arguments but he never was mean and i remember i messed up like the internet or some
spectrum thing and he was like what the hell's wrong with you like i told you to fix internet
and i remember we both looked at each other and he was like sorry and i was like whoa
i just had never heard him snap and that stuff i think what dr maki was saying is that would have
increased because if you look at their brain scans they're just dead spots or like the lesions look
like they're just like sitting on that brain and nothing's firing there or it's firing incorrectly
it's not like ct makes you nicer you know you know like some people have to mention they're kinder
it's not that way um this is one of the trickiest things how did you tell the kids about that
i told was there solace in that i mean was that they do not find any solace in it which is
interesting because you obviously do i do a ton they do not they go they'll be like mom please
like okay we know he had ct but he's still dead we'd rather him be here they have no
my son always says like mom please stop telling people we're lucky he hates it is it possible that
he didn't witness what you witnessed in other words he never saw that his dad was deteriorating
hundred percent and i think he was little and he worshipped his dad he was just 12 you know he was
in sixth grade um i don't think any he was their hero he they he he never did anything wrong in
their eyes he was the best so they are like i don't know what what story you're making up about
this cte thing but that's i don't we can't even comprehend dad not being dad um so i try to honor
that now because yeah but i will say what jack did honor was i'll never play football and there
was something in my son's eyes that was grateful he didn't have to he won't admit that but i promise
you when he's 40 he'll tell you i didn't want to go do that sport yeah he loves it i mean he was
i've never seen a kid so happy last night is that when the rams won he loves being a part of
football he loves football he loves watching it we have great discussions around this in our home
they just don't like when i say we're lucky because we didn't have to see him sick
because in their world they're like we would rather so how long after nate died did you have
a good night's sleep without medication that's interesting we'll talk about psychedelics at the
same time but i you know the first couple weeks people like you need xanax you need ambian i'd
never taken anything and i remember i took them for about a week and i i woke up and i was like
god i feel so far away from everything and that was the first experience i had of like traditional
medicine taking you away from your pain and other things bringing you to it so you can work through
it which we'll discuss but yeah the exact opposite right yeah the exact opposite which is mind
blowing i remember maybe seven or eight months and sleep became a really safe place for me
how long after nate died would you wake up and not have that nanosecond of forgetting what had
happened do you know that experience where yeah like the next day you wake up and there's probably
like two seconds when you don't know that that just happened and then it kind of comes crushing down
and then at some point that goes away and there's never a moment when you don't know it didn't happen
yeah maybe the last six months wow it was i wouldn't have imagined it could last that
it was jarring to be honest it still gets me sometimes and sometimes i'll lay in my bed and
be like nate just to practice saying his name because it's it's a surreal experience because
it's like um it's alter worlds there's just no sudden death i think it's just you know everyone
asks that oh would you rather be sick or would you rather you know die suddenly i love the games we
play with people grieving which again do you think 10 000 years ago they sat around the fire
ever playing cancer or die in front of you i'd rather get killed by a saber tooth tiger immediately
or fall out of the tree break your femur and exsanguinate over the next two days then get an
infection and then die a month later that's exactly what people ask me all the time you know i don't
i still i can believe it completely and i still can't believe it i don't wake up shocked anymore
i don't have the pit in my stomach the deep um shock and grief is gone it's probably been gone since
around four years so i'm a couple months i maybe even three and a half there started to be some
space that some type of new neuro pathways that we lived in now were becoming not as worn but
as comfortable as the old ones were of the reality he lived in so for a while it felt like
every neuro pathway ended with nate every time the door would open i would think of nate every time
we would eat dinner i would think of nate every time i put the kids to bed every time i'd get in
the car he was everywhere he was like it was like his shadow and over time the more things we did
the more traveling i did the more um new people i met things started firing differently people
that didn't know nate places that i hadn't gone with nate and as that happened it's almost like
my brain started to um adjust to a new world that didn't have a minute and then i could feel the
stress go down you know today we live in a world where you probably have a billion videos on your
phone of you and nate and the kids did you ever have to make a decision about the frequency with
which you would indulge in watching those versus putting a limit on it or saying i'm going to put
this in a box right i'm gonna i'm gonna allow myself to do this for an hour a day but i'm not
for the other 23 hours i'm gonna do something else i mean did you hundred is such a great
question because i we talk about that all the time in grief groups it's it's cutting you get your
iphone out and you just let it fly um a lot of what i've started to do recently and i i started
early on in some of the practices from the buddhist or is setting a time to feel my emotions were so
big for so long and i still work on that like being aware that my emotion is not me but it's
just coming through me but i actually get to close the door if i want and i can open it when
i want that has been a practice that's changed my life the past two years which is okay kelsey do
you want to right now um feel really sad and really kind of get your eyes swelled up and put on some
like chicago and just like really go through some videos okay i'm gonna give you seven minutes to
do that and i work seven i know well because for a while like my girlfriend would call at night
and i would just be like it's been hours it's been hours just going and you know and i forward
them to people and i just would want feedback like you remember this you remember this and i
i would imagine your friends might not even know what to do so because they'd be like wow i don't
want to deny that this happened i don't want to deny that this is special but i also don't want to
keep her head down yeah let her drown and they even get tired people that are supporting grieving
people get tired of being there and being like i know you miss them i know so there's a dance
of saying like and your good friends will be like enough like i think that's good like we've we've
been down that road for about an hour now um and even now like i feel like i know sort of how to
help people that are grieving because i felt it but i still it's still a very tricky thing um
i don't know how i feel about the videos i'm so grateful i have them my kids don't look at
pictures they don't like it yeah so i was gonna ask you how did the kids participate in that
kids are a great thing to have and they're exhausting to have during grief
when you have kids and you're going through grief they keep you going in a regular life
and at the same time you can't really grieve until they're gone and they do not like to see you sad
but i i talked to a ton of people um who had lost parents when they were younger and i remember all
of them were like just please don't if if only my mom had been okay it would have been great but we
lost my dad and then we lost my mom too because she never got happy again so i remembered that
and in beginning i also felt like well my kids need to see that i'm really sad and show them how
to grieve because there's that movement too but what i realize it's a very fine line kids do not
like to see their parents sobbing it scares them so if i'm in a if i'm over in the corner shaking
and crying and being like i miss your father it's not it doesn't feel safe for a nine and 12 year old
do you think that kids are innately wired to move on from this quicker 100 my kids are exceptional
and in talking to other parents who have lost a spouse do you think that's true not just for your
kids but in general do you think that's true for kids that they are in that sense more wired to
move on because they live in the present moment they haven't played out a whole future they don't
know that they missed the wedding they don't know that he missed their graduation because they've
never had graduation that's all in our heads i think that if you this is just what's worked for
me if you create a home that is joyful and the person and the trauma is allowed to be spoken
about when they want and that there is that it's not something bad that happened it's something
that is we experienced and we get to decide how we want to tell the story i think kids can survive
amazing things much better than adults because they don't have preconceived ideas so yeah i think
kids are i think kids live in the moment too and if you're lucky enough i hit it right at the right
age because kids become so self-consumed around 12 that their whole world becomes their friends
and so once my kids kicked into that parents are kind of in the background like you're there but
you're in the background of their lives and nate's alive in our house very much so so it's not
something they also we talk about them all the time we still have pictures we have some i took
down a lot because i realized too um it goes back to the videos you don't want to be you want to be
careful with grief and pictures and videos that you let it in when it's the appropriate time
because if not it can it can become all consuming so we definitely have a poster board of pictures
but all the pictures in our house now mostly are of the kids and i and there's some of nate but
it's not like and we have an area where we have a super bowl and we have a picture of the family
where's his ring his ring is in the bank like the what's it called so deposit box yeah yeah
you don't want to wear it around a neck no i don't want to like a nose ring or something no um yeah i
think talking about it too my kids he's we talk about him all the time i'm like your dad would
say and they get really pissed if i'm like your dad would be let down and they're like you don't
know that so don't say it you don't get to pull that i was like i was just trying to get you um
we laugh a lot about the way nate died say more about that i mean who dies at skyzone
during toddler time wearing orange sticky socks i mean that's just ridiculous like you couldn't
make that up i think he's the first person to ever die i know i'm not supposed to say skyzone for
legal reasons or whatever but that's what i mean who does that like he's the first person in history
to jump jump die at during during toddler time playing basketball with his kids it's just
it's so bad it's good at least for a comic and for me and then i i think in the story i talk a lot he
died on 11 11 at 11 which again i just was like thanks buddy like there's just a thousand nods to
me it feels like that we're okay and that this thing's bigger than we think and that don't get
your panties in a bunch like this is just death um it happens all the time i think that's the other
thing the kids now we are we've been to enough grief things and enough grief camps that we we
think we're like people are dying all the time nobody else knows it but it is unbelievable how
many people are dying every day so there's a acceptance of death in our house that is probably
very different than in other houses so how long after nate died did you have your first psychedelic
experience so about nine months after and what was the lead up to that like how did you think
about going through that and what were you afraid of what were you hoping to get out of it so i had
gone to this event in astonia and up the summer after nate died and a bunch of people were talking
about psychedelics and i for grief work and a lot of trauma work and i had i i really didn't have any
i i got to a point where i was doing better but i i needed to access nate like i had this deep
desire to have a relationship with him and raise the kids with him even if he wasn't in this realm
and i remember i was having a conversation i was like i just need to get to him
because i know i believe that like the body went away but i don't i don't know where he is and i i
can talk to god i feel great with my relationship with god um i just don't know how to get to him but
i need to get to him because i was kind of starting to go crazy and this one guy was like have you
ever done mushrooms and i was like no but my brother did a lot in high school and i would never
and i don't like druggies and i think you guys are a bunch i'm very uptight and i
have two glasses of wine and i'm not fun and don't even ask and i'm gonna keep judging you
and i'm gonna judge you because that's what i do best and i'm gonna keep doing that because look
where it got me um and then they were like have you ever tried MDMA and i was like this is all
this is all ridiculousness because you guys are all exactly the kids i did not want to hang out
with in high school because my experience was my brother's an addict my brother-in-law is an addict
um oxy cotton and alcohol he's 14 years sober and then my my brother was just a partier you
knew followed fish and the dead and i just remember him being like gonzo a lot of high school
and so at some point i was talking to this this guy who'd done so many psychedelics i mean literally
the guy was crazy he was like telling me about having sex in a thorn bush and i was like why am
i even talking to this weirdo but i said you know i'm just not gonna do i'm never gonna try that
stuff and he said why i said well i'm afraid i'm not i don't want to die like my kids just lost
their dad i'm not gonna they're not gonna i'm not gonna jump off of a bridge after doing too many
mushrooms and he's like but you're already dead because you're so afraid of everything and i was
like oh so i talked to a couple of our friends and i said listen i'll be ready when i'm ready
and i mean there's this there's this saying in that community that says the plants you'll the
plants will welcome you or you'll you'll know like it's not something you can force somebody to do
you'll know when it's time and i got a call in october and of after he had died so almost a year
and they said we're going to do this group with these shamans are are you interested and i remember
it was very clear i could just hear it i was like i'm in and i would had probably a level 10 anxiety
going into it because i had never done anything i mean i wasn't even a drinker really just always
been an old-fashioned uptight fear-based neurotic person you're just classic and we get to this
house and it would be beforehand the shamans called and just kind of asked me what would i
wanted to work through and i said you know i have these couple of events that were very traumatic the
morgue the coroner's telling my children i couldn't remember anything from the time i'd gotten the call
um until i'd landed until after the plant journey so i had pretty much a whole story about getting
on the airplane and the woman helping you i didn't know where i i don't i still can't remember where
the layover was but i i couldn't remember a lot of that flight and so i knew there was some trauma
there that had been blocked out and i thought well i better be able to access that so so she listened
to it all and then we got together it was this beautiful group we talked about intention we
talked about um you know what we hoped to get out of it everything opposite of what i thought it
would be which was just like everyone popping pills and you know dancing to rave music and um just a
good group of people i could just loving people supportive and i kind of shared what i was where
i was at and they mean it's kind of a funny story so the first thing they gave me was well they gave
me something and i took it and i had a full-blown panic attack and i raised my hand and i was like
it's so i told you it's not working like i wanted out and she came over and was like we gave you a
placebo because we knew that you like this this one the first hump was going to be a big one for
you and she did kind of similar to what the woman on the plane did she put her hand on my head and
i laid down and she actually breathed me through my panic attack and she said that wasn't anything
now this is it and she said um just let it do its work and did you start with psilocybin or mdma i
don't i i i think i started with i don't know they won't tell me the exact they wouldn't tell
me exactly what and what and where but what i do know is i dropped it oh i remember we were all
laying in a circle and everybody by then was kind of laying down and everyone someone said have you
dropped in and i was like what what does it drop in like i don't know what does it mean to drop in
and someone you're that annoying person that's like it's the worst no and our friend which you
know but i will name nameless but he was like jesus christ like can we get this girl can you give
her more um but i was like when are we gonna drop in everybody is anybody else dropped in
and somebody was like you'll know when you drop in and i remember like three minutes later i was
like i'm in like it was just so ridiculous um it was just so embarrassing and he was like oh god
here we go babysit her all night um but within like three minutes i was back on the plane
and i was but this time yeah i was back on the plane right then and i started to cry and i
started to i was loud i mean my friend will tell me i was loud our friends were like you were loud
the whole time um but all of a sudden everybody in the journey space kind of came and sat next to
me and we kind of did the flight together and so i felt supported and so i cried and cried
and i said this is so scary he's dead you know i went through the whole thing and they were like
we're right here with you you're not alone we're right here you're safe look how strong you are
you're going to your babies and it felt like six hours from what i know now that you know i we've
talked about it it was probably like five or six minutes i did the whole flight again but with
support and it was like that first thing was over and i had peace about it i remembered the whole
thing i remembered what seat i was in i remembered you know transferring planes all that stuff and
then i got up i got some water and i was like oh my god i'm not i thought i was going to be like
drunk and crazy i was just regular again i woke up i got up i had i talked to some people i talked
to the shamans and i remember they were like would you like are you going to go in again and i said
yes and all i did was lay down again and this this whole process was insane to me that it was
i could modulate my experience safely by my intention and whether i close my eyes or not
i mean i was like this is not what i thought so then i revisited the morgue and i was really
angry i had a ton of anger that he'd left me that i had never accessed i mean rage like you
fucking left me at 40 you promised you wouldn't you're a liar you left me with a nine and 12 year
old you bastard i told you to lose weight and i was furious i mean i remember just a rage i had never
felt and you had never really gone through that stage of grief never in the previous year never
been angry at him i just felt sad for him scared for him where is he hope he's okay he's terribly
worried about my dead husband and everyone's like he's good focus on the people that are alive and
at that moment i had all the anger i'd ever had for him for 20 years but mostly for leaving me
because he had promised he wouldn't um furious to the point where my friend was like when you're
down with it i think we're good like you've like we got it and you're also disrupting the whole
group um did they take you to another so he took me up and then one of the facilitators came with
me and i said would you mind oh because my friend had said why don't you go find nate like you've
done the work you've gone through a bunch of things we're hours in at this point he said go
go find nate see what he has to tell you because you you wanted to find him and peter no shit i
went up there i laid down and one of the facilitators came in i said can you just remember whatever i
say because i think it's going to be good and i need you to write it all down and fast forward at
the in the next day the integration he's like it was too beautiful i couldn't remember anything i
just sat there and listened i'm like oh my god but i remembered most so i laid down on the couch up
by myself and i called for nate and i promised you he was just in front of my face and i know
everybody's listening to this if you know me you think this is insane but this is exactly my
experience nate was right there he's like i've never left and i said where did you go he's like
i'm still here i just um my body wasn't serving me anymore and i said what do you mean he goes
well look at this and he just took his whole body and just like threw it on the ground
like it was closed and he's like i'm right here and the first thing he did was he showed me my
kids and he said we all chose this they were born for this and the kids were kind of on a mountain
like game of thrones and he's like they called for this we all agreed to this they're stronger
than you think and then he gave me some like tips like he would have if he was here about
how to kind of raise them and what they needed from me and he's like you need to slow down with
adison or you need to just spend time one-on-one with jack like only things he would know and
then he said the biggest thing is you've got to live fearlessly and he said i'm going to show you
what it feels like and then we flew like around the universe and it was probably the first time
in my life i felt um free and he's like there's it's it's all okay we're all okay and you have
a choice right now to just have the best life and i want you to go live it and i'm i'm right
here you can access me at any time just call for me and we from that point on um we have a great
relationship and i i feel him he sends me songs and birds and hummingbirds and if i pay attention
he's everywhere and i totally i don't know where you go or what happens but i am very clear that
we're made of energy and if i can talk to god why wouldn't i be able to talk to nate and so now it's
this kind of um i mean i like i said it's just like it's even better than our marriage because
i talk all the time he just listens even more and he doesn't even he and then he just tells me things
in very quick um two or three words like you're fine yes slow down stop talking that's a lot of
stop talking did you ask him anything in particular that you had never asked him before
in that journey there i asked him why did you play football and he said because it was the
easiest way for people to respect me and listen to me so i could share with them about love
he said i never really loved playing football but i love that it gave me access to people so i
could talk to them about this stuff i really wanted to talk about which was never about football
he didn't talk much about football when he was done he hated it he hated to talk about it did
he still watch it yeah he loved because he loved to put some money on the game and be with his
buddies and just scream at a tv and have fun um he just he was like kelsey this is this this is
what you've been waiting for this is what you you knew this was coming you knew this was coming
you're fine this was my time's over like this was i did my part don't don't um don't worry about
me he's like it's exceptional where i am he was just it was beautiful and i mean i i mean maybe
it's the top one of the top three experiences of my life probably certainly something that most
people who've experienced it would would say yeah and i um you know i also and we talked about this
but xanax and ambien and the things they give you for grief work just put you black you out
and you have no idea what happened or i used to wake up and be like why is everyone sad like
you know and what what the mushrooms and the whole plant experience gave me was an ability
to go towards it and understand it and walk through it and come out of it being like okay
like we're all okay and for me i think i probably was most afraid of death most of us are but that
was the biggest fear of my life is i didn't want anybody i loved to die and i didn't want to die
and now of course i'm not like looking forward to it but i have great peace that this is so much
bigger and i've seen it and i've felt it and so i don't know people get tired because i'm so fired
up about plant medicine now from someone who's like you know i've probably done five or six since then
nothing quite as mind-blowing as that yeah what have the subsequent trips been like do you go into
them with a much more focused intention i've done both i've gone in with the focused intention like
i'm looking for some answers and i've also gone in being like just tell me what is for me it feels
like a download of information of um it feels like a connection that is so much bigger than
anything i could have just in my day to day the biggest thing about plants is this is important
i really need a lot of approval and i've spent my life trying to be great at everything and have
people give me attigirls and when i did that first experience and it's been subsequent and
all my experiences is my ego completely goes away and i don't i'm the biggest judgment i'm a comic
i try to make fun of everybody i like use everything against people and when i'm in those
experiences i have no judgments on anybody and i have no desire to be liked and no judgments on
yourself yeah i don't i don't i there's this like it's just 10 or 11 hours where i'm not
worried about what people think of me or what i think of them which it's such a relief you know
so for me that's probably that's the biggest thing i get out of those experiences is this
what would it look like if my ego just got out of the way and i just was present with what is and
with what who is and you just see good and i didn't ever feel like messed up i mean i literally
tell my friends who are still so against it you're none of it was scary and obviously i haven't done
any ayahuasca and i i'm not called to that at all right now currently in my life um but man it's a
lot better than getting drunk and crying you know i stopped drinking pretty pretty soon after he
died because i drink tequila and just sob and so i'm real clear now that alcohol is a depressant
to this day yeah i drink red wine now but i any type of alcohol cues anxiety because the sugar
makes my heart race and then if i can't sleep then it get then once this thing starts my brain
starts going it can be not a safe place so alcohol just doesn't really work for me anymore
did you talk with your kids after the psilocybin experience and tell them about it yeah no i haven't
yet you meaning as of yet as of yet so they might watch this yeah they might or actually i had some
notes when i had i left some notes at home and i was like jack can you take a picture of these
notes and i was like oh shit well there you go you're gonna if you read it um he's just now he's
16 now so he would understand it but they are both they hate drunk people they hate my my brother
mazak actually i mean obviously sober so there's been a connotation around drugs in our family
that it's it's really not good um so this will have to be a longer discussion and i don't really
know i mean i don't what do you think when do you talk to your kids about it have you talked to your
13 year old no not about psychedelics yeah me neither but um i actually that's not true i've
talked about it once with her through the lens of drugs okay and um sort of trying to explain that
you know um the legality of a drug is a second order consideration i mean it's an important
consideration obviously if you're trying to abide by the law but the the you want to think about
this first through the lens of the molecule and and i've shared with her this framework that i
borrowed from somebody else that i think is very valuable right which is um because i talk about
this all the time with patients right so you know one of the questions you ask a patient
during an intake with them is you know tell me how many drinks you have in an average week
tell me which recreational drugs you use um and this is not a judgmental discussion but it's you
really want to understand this and look a lot of times people say yep i use coke once a month i do
this i do that i do this one of that and so the the thing i discussed with them and this is sort
of what i explained to olivia once was you know there are certain drugs alcohol being a drug as
well where they change your state i love i've heard this podcast you did yeah yeah yes but they
don't change traits and then there are others that change your state and if you use them correctly
they can change your traits and so i said and by the way there are legal and illegal molecules in
both of those camps and that's worth noting and respecting but really the things in this camp you
have to really ask yourself how often am i doing this and why am i doing this and so you know i put
cocaine very clearly in this camp right it clearly changes your state and i've never done cocaine but
the people i talk to who love it tell me how great they feel when they do it but they can't make a
compelling case for me that it makes them better when they're not on cocaine 100 and the same is
true for alcohol in reality so so one you know you have to be careful about the use of those things
and obviously the things we're talking about psilocybin and MDMA at least have the potential if
done correctly to make you a better version of you long after that medicine is gone yeah i remember
you i listened to that podcast of yours and i that's exactly it like i am a different person
because of those experiences and i'm i'm better and the only reason i know that is because i'm
more i'm less afraid i'm more patient i think i have less answers i'm more open i mean all the
things that you you hope to get in therapy but it's very hard to get your brain to change and i feel
like tell me from a physician standpoint it opens up a pathway that was like blocked like it had a
blockade and you it was always there you just hadn't gone down it and so when i took psilocybin
it like moved that blockade and there there was a road i never knew that was just ease and love and
fearlessness and after i was done i started to walk down that road more often in my day-to-day
life because for so long it wasn't even accessible to me and now it's a road that i choose quite
often um and same thing with MDMA for me i've done that very rarely but it it's shown me fun
how to just be connected and and not again not judging and just um and if mom and you're
listening i know you guys had no idea i was so edgy but it gave me so now even if i don't do it
i remember the feeling i can access that that that neural pathway and i can go oh kelsey you
know what it feels like to be at a party and be calm and not worrying about getting home and
worried about the uber and and just like be here and i can almost get myself to that new road that
i always had but it just always had a huge blockade in front of it yeah and and i mean i think i think
those are two good examples of how those molecules work and i mean i think mdma really has this
ability to you know so create this empathy that is very difficult for most people to access
um on command uh or frankly not under the influence of that medication and that's to me
if you if you can craft the intention around that it's um you know it can really do an amazing thing
for a relationship as well yeah with yourself but also with somebody else especially if there has
been something that's gone really wrong sure yeah i mean it's probably been there's been a ton of
gifts of grief and i talk about them all the time but i think that that those experiences have been
and everyone hates me for it because once i get excited about something i get really excited so i
came out of it i can just blazing hot on uh plant journeys and now i kind of understand that you have
to be ready and have to want it and have to be ready to be open to it but i am and the other thing
i i do think that um at least in my limited experience um i think that the best of both
worlds is when you combine that work with the traditional work of therapy and i do think that
if there's one thing about the the new appreciation people have of psychedelics that i think is
dangerous it's that people believe that the plant or the molecule by itself can do all the work like
all i have to do is do psilocybin once a month or once a quarter and and it's all good and it's like
no those are incredible lubricants to allow you to do very difficult things when you're long off
the influence of those medications so i i also think like again it's impossible to say what
fraction of your recovery has been predicated on that experience versus all that came before it and
after it and around it um so that's kind of the one thing that i i tend to remind that's smart
because i've done a ton of work i've read a bunch and i i think the other big thing that i do
that has supported all of that is just i have i'm militant about meditation
militant and were you before i had started on the path but maybe 20 minutes a day here and there
maybe insight timer um once nate died it became a must and to this day and i i saw you guys just
got this on a bag but i will sit in with dispense i think dispense probably dispenses work has
probably changed my life the most in terms of a daily practice they're changing a thought
or watching a thought or um knowing that my feelings are transient and that i can change
a feeling through it changing a thought or i can say change or i can say stop and um it doesn't
mean they're not going to come but i do have some agency in how i feel and what i feel which i never
believed before um so i think if you if you like you said if you do the the psychedelics in
conjunction with a very deep meditation and you know a committed spiritual practice that gives
you peace whatever that might be you you have a great shot at coming out of pretty much everything
yeah it's i've always found it sad i guess i'm i'm i'm only saying something that i'm sure a
billion other people have thought or said um but it's remarkable that this isn't taught
alongside english science math to kids coming from school like you you can play the thought
experiment of what if from the moment kids entered kindergarten we had an emotional health
class as well that was part of the core curriculum where you learned to distance yourself from your
thoughts and right like and you know we're gonna spend 30 minutes a day on this course throughout
you know k to 12 yeah um how many different habits could we develop and how could we equip
ourselves um you mentioned something in your book that resonates deeply with me which is radical
acceptance when did you first encounter that term um tera brock i probably read it my mom was into
this stuff for a long time so this was always in the background noise of my life my dad left when i
was 15 and my mom really went on this like journey so these books and these people were part of it but
i the idea of radical acceptance that that that something wasn't good or bad probably happened
i mean after nate died i mean i don't think i think i knew of it in practice but when everything's
good seems good it's hard to you're like oh yeah good luck to those people that you know
have a sick kid or whatever i hope they just accept what is um and i always thought that before
i really experienced it that it is what it is was an annoying statement and it was kind of just like
a throw away like oh well it is it life's shit so just accept it and now i'm like no it's beautiful
it is what it is how wonderful is that like can you just be with whatever without it doesn't mean
it won't feel hard it doesn't mean it's not miserable it just means it is exactly what you
are going through and the resistance to that and the wishing it was different is what kills you so
a lot of people say how are you doing so well and i said because i don't wish it was different
that's pretty much it do you think your kids understand that i don't know i don't they're
still they were so young and they you know i'm i'm really working on understanding that they have
their own path to this and their own journey and we all have different relationships to nate
and different stories that we tell in our head i would say they are surprised at how great life is
compared to what they thought it would be when he first died sometimes they'll say i mean isn't it
great we're so happy again isn't it great that we have fun again um look look at how look at how
good our life is and so that's their way of saying like we made it in some way we we accepted
what is and we continue to build a life that was beautiful we talk a lot in our house about what
would nate want us to do and nate would want us to be joyful so if you want to honor your dead
person the best way to do it is live the life they would want you to live if they were here
so in that sense the kids you know we can't even take it out anymore he's gone and so our life is
this and we miss him and we're happy and we accept it and we miss him but yeah radical acceptance i
think it gets easier the more you do it so i mean little things you know you practice at the stop
light you're like and the light isn't moving and it's all the things we've all read but until you
have to practice it because you're in such a dark spot um i don't know that you you can and people
always say like oh can you transform without going through something big i don't know if you can i
don't know because i i had a i read it all and i intellectually knew it all but until i had to
really dig into those practices i didn't it i was glad i i would say prepare with them but until
you get to that point there is magic in that transformation when you do the work um i don't
know what are your thoughts you think you have to go through hard things i don't think i'm equipped
to answer the way you are yeah i suspect so but i mean i i was hoping not or at least in near miss
you know i i have a good friend rick elias who was actually on the podcast and um he was on that
united der you know uh u.s air flight that uh was going to crash and somehow made the miraculous
landing in the hudson river in 2009 and so in that sense you know nothing bad happened to him but
there was a two minute period where he really thought no no this is it i am dead he went through
all of that and rick is a you know that was 13 years ago this month and rick is still living
the life of the guy who was given a second chance i agree so you know could rick have come to this
same set of principles that guide his life today without that i just don't know my guess is there's
maybe somebody that could i don't know that i could yeah it's it's just interesting and i there's
just a real relief when you stop wishing it was different whatever it is when you stop wishing
whatever you're going through wasn't and you just go like let's roll like what would i what i what
i've got to learn what's on the other side of this um what will it feel like when it's transformed
into something different what can i get excited about it's i just i think that the the practices
work that's what i believe now i believe that you can get through things and i've got a lot of easy
easy ways because my situation is fairly easy if you look at it the way we can
spend some of it it's better that he's not here i was left with resources i always think too about
grief like if a woman has resources it's a very different experience than if you don't so you know
there's a thousand things that interact to make your experience what it is but internally
the stoics and then the buddhist and believing in something bigger than you those are kind of
key pillars at least for me what would you say to a man or woman or child listening to this right now
who's three months out from that tragedy based on everything you've learned to start just hang on
just hang on for now um i think i think i said humans are are built to last we're meant to
we're built to make it through things um and and do the work whatever that work is for you whatever
wherever you're trying to go do the work and the work will eventually support you um you know you
get like i think of it if you're over here and you're trying to get over here and there's a there's
you got to build a bridge if you once you build the bridge you'll get over there but you got to go
to work um the bridge isn't there yet and that's where the meditation and the reading and the
gratitude and the changing your brain that's those are each plank that you're building to get over to
the other side and if you do the work you're going to look back and be like damn like i never thought
i could build that bridge and you're going to be more confident and more joyful because you just
saw you did something you never thought you could do so life just got sweeter how hard was it to write
the book you know i didn't have any pressure around it and i know i think you're writing a book
um i didn't have any pressure on it because it was just not why i asked by the way
no no no um no but i i remember um jill talking about that you were writing when for me i had to
get the story out it was very personal because i wanted my kids to remember and i wanted to
remember because i knew i was going to love again and i knew i was going to date and i knew i was
going to have other relationships and time is a miracle when it comes to life because as time goes
on the pain just it does gradually get better and so i thought i better make sure that the story of
this great man is down so that my grandchildren and my great grandchildren will know where they
came from and who he was and how this all happened somewhere in the middle you think this
is such shit that yeah i was embarrassing to like i shouldn't even show it to the my worst enemy
because this is just blabber of nothing and i'm so bored with what i wrote it's so dumb and it's so
ridiculous that where i mean just stop now because this is torture for you and nobody's this is
horrible and then you get to a point where you've written enough and then it gets to an editor
and they make it a little better and they give you some feedback and you just start cutting stuff
out and that's kind of then it got fun because i was like just cut out all the junk that you tried
to make and just tell it like it is and don't worry about what people think and i'm so glad i
did it i can't imagine doing it again and i know i want to but i don't even know where you start it
feels surreal now you forget you forget sitting there looking at your computer being like this
possibly the boringest paragraph i've ever written more like i just like you just it's a
unique experience writing a book because the internal dialogue and anxiety and just disgust
with what you're putting out is really epic just because you're just you're you're reading
what you already hated that you wrote and it's just double flogging you know but i i would tell
people write it down because man it it helps somebody like somebody is is going to be helped
by it or get inspired by it and just go easy on yourself for the book what's the most surprising
thing that you've received as a way of feedback there's there's been so many people that have
written that i said thank you for showing um thank you for being honest and i think what that means
is the good and the bad like not trying to play grief either way like that there is a duality to
everything in life and people like thank you for letting us know that it was awful and you felt
like you were on fire and you couldn't wait to have sex with other people like thank you for
knowing that like you know that you lost the man of your dreams and you also get to meet other people
and have a new experience and that's gonna that's that might be exactly what was meant to be
this sense that everything isn't good or bad either way so there's a whole life i'm gonna have
that i never even knew possible and there was one that i really love that got taken away
so people say like thank you for giving it a multifaceted approach to this experience i'm
having did your kids read it before you published it no have they read it no they don't want to
read it they are terribly embarrassed by it and secretly proud they don't want it out and then
jack's like mom i'm taking your book to my school counselor because well she asked what your job was
and i didn't know what to tell her i said she's she wrote a book and i was like so he they're
proud of it but if they're also way more private than me i'm the least private person on the planet
so i'm learning to understand that they'll tell it in their time and they'll read it in their time
and they'll read it in their time and their experience will be very different from what i
wrote i'm fairly certain that they'll read chapters and go that's not how it went
like i didn't do that i didn't say that but we'll see i don't know i don't know how they'll be
well kelsie i um i i can't thank you enough you know um this is just such a beautiful story and
i i think people are going to be infinitely enriched whether they've experienced something
like this or whether they will because i think you know we all will yeah might not be as sudden it
might not be as tragic with a capital t but um the human experience is one of loss so um thank
you for everything you've done thank you so much for having me it really means a lot to me
thank you for listening to this week's episode of the drive if you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth exclusive content without relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription now to that end membership benefits
include a bunch of things one totally kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail
every topic paper person thing we discuss on each episode the word on the street is nobody's show
notes rival these monthly ama episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely
access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having to listen
to spiel's like this the qualities which are a super short podcast that we release every tuesday
through friday highlighting the best questions topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes
of the drive this is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and
necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts on products that i believe in but for which i'm not
getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in
as time goes on if you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can head
over to peter atia md.com forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook
all with the id peter atia md you can also leave us a review on apple podcast or whatever podcast
player you listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes only does not constitute
the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health care services including
the giving of medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information
and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk the content on this podcast
is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should
not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have
and they should seek the assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions
finally i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies i invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about
where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies