Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of the space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Marty McCarry. This name, of course,
sound familiar to you as Marty has been on this podcast a number of times. Most recently,
we spent a couple of episodes discussing COVID, which I can assure you barely comes up in this
episode. By way of background though, Marty is a professor at Johns Hopkins, which is where we
met many years ago. He's professor of surgery and also public health researcher. He's a graduate of
Harvard School of Public Health and served on the faculty of Hopkins for the last 16 years. He's
also served in the leadership at the WHO. He's a member of the National Academy of Medicine and
serves as the editor in chief of the second largest trade publication in medicine called MedPage Today.
He writes quite regularly for the Washington Post, the New York Times, and the Wall Street
Journal. He's also the author of two New York Times bestselling books, Unaccountable and The
Price We Pay. In this episode, we talk about patient safety, but of course, the real impetus
for this is the recent case of Radhanda Vaught. In case that name doesn't sound familiar, Radhanda
Vaught is a nurse or a former nurse at Vanderbilt Medical Center who made a medical error that
resulted in the death of a patient in late 2017. This case has garnered a lot of attention lately
for reasons we will get into in this case. The headline is that for probably the first time,
certainly to anybody's recollection, a mistake of this nature was prosecuted criminally. The
implications of this are pretty significant. We talk about that a lot, but we really begin the
discussion by talking about the culture of patient safety. What is the risk to a patient when they
walk into the hospital? What are medical errors? How do they take place and how big a problem is
it? We also talk about how much has changed in the last 20 years. I think Marty and I were pretty
lucky to train in an era that actually witnessed the transformation or witnessed the changing of
the guard in terms of the attitude towards this. One thing to note about this podcast is that in
an effort to get it out as quickly as possible, it's going to be an audio only episode and the
show notes will be relatively sparse. Without further delay, I hope you enjoy my conversation
about this very important topic with Marty McCarry. Hey Marty, awesome to be talking with
you about this today. I'm kind of bummed that we can't do these in video, but I guess that's the
nature of your other life. Anyway, no one else gets to see your beautiful face except me right
now. Good to see you, Peter. This is a topic you and I have been talking about privately for about
two months now. I think we decided that it was an important enough subject that we should actually
bring it to the larger sphere and talk about this publicly. That's the issue of patient safety,
something that's near and dear to your heart. You've worked on this tirelessly for almost as
long as I've known you and I think we met in 2003, 2002 actually we met. This has been something
that you along with many of your colleagues, people who I knew like Peter Pronovost have also taken
up the mantle on. When I think back to my medical training, Marty, when I think of the beginning
versus the end, that's a five year stint. A lot of changes actually happened. Something as simple
quite frankly as a timeout was not something that existed before I entered my residency. When I was
an intern, there was no such thing as a timeout, a surgical timeout in the operating room. We can
explain what that means to people. Yet by the time I left my residency, you couldn't do an operation
without a timeout. Clearly, the culture of medical safety is something that the field of medicine has
been struggling with for a couple of decades. Can you give us just a little bit of a history of that
with more color than my sort of clumsy approach at it? When we were a residence at that time,
it was around that time that we entirely blamed the individual. I specifically remember one of
the M&M conferences. I don't know if you tell people what M&M is. I think I've talked about it
in the past. It's very important for people to understand, especially in surgery, what M&M is.
So M&M stands for morbidity and mortality. And it's a weekly or in some smaller hospitals,
a monthly conference where things that go awry or any death on that department service will be
reviewed and discussed. And it's part of internal quality improvement. It's legally protected under
a special clause under quality improvement so that it's not discoverable in court. And we can
have the liberty to discuss things honestly. And it's an amazing conference. My favorite conference
as a resident, truthfully. Well, sometimes it was also entertaining, but your eyes would pop out.
I remember as a medical student, you listen to these stories. I mean, the Swiss cheese defect
of medical errors where everything goes wrong, the perfect storm of how you could this happen
and that happened and the patient ultimately was hurt by it or a near miss. And you see yourself
in these situations like, gosh, I could have done that. And I remember as a medical student,
my eyes popped out of my head. I'm just thinking, oh my God, can you believe that just happened?
And M&M after M&M conference, I would just be blown away. But I was also exhausted. And then as a
fourth year medical student, my eyes popped out a little less. And then as an intern, I was just so
tired, I would just kind of like raise my eyebrows as I'm half trying to get a nap in.
And then as attending, it'd be totally numb to it, completely numb to, yep, that stuff happens
and maybe we should try to do better. M&M is an incredible conference because you hear the
discussions of what we could have done better. Well, I think the point that it's not discoverable
in a court is also important. At least where we trained, I think at Hopkins, I always felt that
it was a very honest conference, meaning I felt that people really went up there and shouldered
the blame for mistakes. Yes. Without that, it becomes, if this were a conference that were
done in a court, you could never get to truth and reconciliation. What I loved about the conference
was the intense humility that you would see exerted by these powerful names in American surgery. I
mean, giants in the field say with all honesty, I didn't look carefully enough at the CAT scan
before the case. I should have recognized that there was an aberrant artery in that location
that I ended up getting into trouble with. I feel bad. I spoke with the patient and you'd hear these
incredible moments of honesty. And I thought that's healthy for the field. When we were residents,
the resident presenting who was often just completely getting fried for things that were
out of their control, right? You don't want to blame a nurse. You don't want to blame a colleague.
You don't want to blame your weak medical student who dropped something. You try to present it in
a neutral way and you jump on the grenade for the team. And I remember specifically there was a
trauma patient who died. And this guy had basically was dead on arrival and there's
nothing that we could have done medically. And when I say we as a profession, I was not in the
case. But the chief resident felt bad and basically just said, I should have pushed harder. I should
have just pushed everybody harder. And I'm thinking, yeah, we need to do our best, but you're beating
yourself up in this spirit of it's all about the individual's responsibility. Now we've matured to
recognize we need to have safe systems, right? We need to have the chest tubes in the operating room
or in the trauma bay so you can get to them quickly. We need to value non-technical skills
as doctors, not just the technical skills of doing procedures, but effective communication
and inspiring confidence in people around you and organizational skills. We just generally haven't
valued that kind of teamwork and communication skills. We've matured now to recognizing that
when something goes tragically wrong, we need to ask how can we do better? But how can the system,
how can the hospital be set up differently? How can the NICU be moved to be closer to the labor
and delivery ward? How can the elevator be held for the trauma team before they get there so they
don't have to wait for the elevator to come down? That's a systems approach and that is entirely
novel in the last 20 years of medicine. What was the impetus for this, Marty? When you think back
to before you and I trained, was there a single catalyzing event that somehow just finally took
hold literally during the time we were training or was it no single event but rather a gradual
progression? I'll give you an example. I think everybody's familiar with the story of how the
80-hour work week came to be a manner in which residents trained and that really came out of a
singular event. I don't remember the woman's name, Libby something. Libby Zion. A young woman who,
God, I don't even remember the story other than I think she went to a New York hospital. She was in
an ER and a resident took care of her, prescribed her a medication without realizing she was on
another medication. I believe it was a psychiatric medication. There was a huge contraindication to
this and I think she died of hypothermia or something like that. I mean she had a tragic
outcome in the ER as a result of unfortunately probably poor supervision on the part of the
resident as opposed to fatigue but it became a rallying cry around residents working too hard
and not getting enough sleep. Really, I believe that the family of Libby Zion carried the torch
on this and many years later obviously that resulted in the changes with the ACGME.
Was there a similar event that precipitated the push to safety or was it more an accumulation
of events? I would say it was that Libby Zion case and it happened in 1984. It came to light
subsequent but it was her father who happened to be a New York Times reporter and it showed for
the first time to the world what many of us had known and that is you can die not just from the
illness that brings you to care but you can die from the care itself and that can occur at a rate
that may be higher than we appreciate. She was given a medication that should not have been given
to her. She had a interaction that should have been recognized and out of that case came a ruling
that you can't have people working 48 straight hours because that was credited to be a root cause
and around that time in the 1990s when there was attention around this New York state set up a
commission to make sure you don't have people completely sleep exhausted doing procedures and
making critical decisions that the Institute of Medicine put out a report in 1999. They issued a
report, a groundbreaking report where they essentially reviewed records independently
and found that about in their estimate 44,000 to 98,000 people a year in the United States die
from preventable medical mistakes. Sometimes it was sloppy handwriting, sometimes it was ordering
something that should have been done on another patient, sometimes it was forgetting something,
sometimes it was the patient falling through the cracks but they identified what is now known as
a preventable adverse event also known on the street as a medical mistake and people were blown
away. I remember as a resident being told hey this report just came out from this giant institution
highly respected Institute of Medicine now called the National Academy of Medicine saying that maybe
up to 100,000 people a year died not from the disease that brings them to care but from the
care itself and there was protest and anger and the residents were like this is BS and within a
couple years thanks to some big national names including a pediatric surgeon who's made his
career this topic and with a lot of humility talking about how he made mistakes as a surgeon
this really quickly became adopted doctors resonated with it the public it's almost as if
everybody had or knew of a story and quickly this Institute of Medicine report put into stone the
idea that dying from medical mistakes if it were a disease would rank as the eighth leading cause
of death now what's interesting is Lucian Leape one of the co-authors wrote a dissenting commentary
afterwards where he said look it's much higher look at the methodology that we used we're just
reviewing charts not every mistake is documented and he actually thought it was an underestimate
let me push back a little bit not for the sake of pushing back but just to sort of ask the question
in a probing way so let's say it's a hundred thousand people die a year in hospitals because of
medical errors is there any way to determine how many of those are deaths in people who were going
to probably die during that admission anyway so these were accelerated deaths versus people like
Libby Zion who she was a young otherwise healthy woman with an isolated psychiatric illness
probably was not going to die anywhere near that hospital admission and therefore that admission
so think of it as like people who are on the edge of the cliff for whom the medical error pushes
them over the cliff versus people who are 30 feet away from the cliff for whom the medical
error picks them up over the fence and shoves them over the cliff it's a great point and the
study did not distinguish the two and it's true many times like if you look at the people in the
hospital they tend to be older and many times the medical error hastened the death but was really
not the primary cause of death but any medical error that resulted in death even if it hastened
an imminent death was counted as a medical mistake and that's of course very difficult
as it should be as it should be i think back to all of the ones that i saw i'll just tell one
story i may have even told this on the podcast before at some point and you'll appreciate it
because it was during my intern year very early so august i'm guessing maybe july it was either
the first or second month of internship we were not at the mothership we weren't at hopkins we were
out at sinai which is one of the satellite hospitals and you don't necessarily have the same
quality of the support staff there that becomes relevant in the story so a resident wrote an order
for a patient who is in the icu she was in the icu but going to be transferred out so she was
not ventilated basically just waiting for a bed to move to the floor and she was having a hard
time sleeping so he wrote for one gram of ativan instead of milligram exactly ativan is a benzodiazepine
that would normally be dosed somewhere between half a milligram and maybe two milligrams you
know maybe five milligrams right and that would be in someone who's used to a lot of that medication
what he meant to write was one milligram and not one gram so he wrote for one thousand times
the dose so that was mistake number one now almost without exception any nurse because this is back
in the day when you wrote an order on a paper chart any nurse would immediately recognize that
as an error but this just happened to be a brand new nurse and so she took the order from the chart
exactly as it was written as one milligram pardon me as one gram and transmitted that order directly
to the pharmacy which again any pharmacist with any experience would recognize that's a
super physiologic dose that would be enough to kill an entire i don't know gaga enough a stadium
of people but again the pharmacist was also brand new it was a night shift maybe putting the new
person on at the night shift when there's less action so the pharmacist sent up all of the ativan
that he had in the system which was tens of milligrams and said look i'll get the rest later
i have to reach out to another hospital to get it but you know whatever it was here's 20 or 30
milligrams of ativan and i'll get the other 970 milligrams later which again should have been a
red flag but wasn't and then of course the nurse administered this dose of ativan to the patient who
very shortly after stopped breathing now fortunately this happened in an ICU and therefore
the nurse was able to see that the patient had stopped breathing called the doctor they
intubated the patient and the next morning you know she was ultimately extubated and fine this
was a near miss it's a huge medical error but it did not result in death though had this occurred
on the floor it would have resulted in a death that story illustrates exactly what you spoke
about earlier which is the horrible swiss cheese effect of how many pieces can you line up and
still fit a pencil through exactly what the swiss cheese model of medical errors is it shows how
when we look back and review these catastrophic errors oftentimes every single thing is a little
off and what happens is sometimes we refer to as a comedy or error sometimes we call it the perfect
storm but it happens so that's the terminology we're using now is if it avoids a patient harm
it's a near miss and if it involves patient harm it's called a preventable adverse event
let's talk about how things advanced going from the early 2000s until where we are now what have
been some of the biggest advances and do we have metrics to objectively talk about whether or not
improvements have come along well it's amazing you sit in those m&m conferences and you just
start thinking gosh that mistake that lab test was never conveyed to the intern that patient was
getting two feeds into a tube that did not go to the stomach it's almost as if you can't reproduce
it here's something that's insane and you think gosh you can't make this stuff up and every error
appears to be unique but there are certain basic principle root causes oftentimes the physician is
exhausted burnt out didn't have the support or help they needed may have had what we call alert
fatigue meaning they're being pinged with a lot of unnecessary alerts yeah such that when a real
alert comes along it's easy to ignore exactly like you feel like the pharmacy is crying wolf
and every time you prescribe something there's some alert so people just click through them
sometimes you're actually prescribing a therapy for someone and you have to override five or six
alerts just to prescribe one treatment path in 2006 our friend peter pronovost who was at johns
hopkins tackled one form of preventable adverse event which were central line infections and
basically we had known for a long time there's a protocol that if you use it reduces the risk of
infecting the central line you put a full length down on the person you wash and just for folks to
understand a central line is an intravenous catheter but it goes into one of the very deep
veins so typically either a deep vein in the neck called the jugular deep vein in the neck of the
subclavian or a deep vein in the pelvis or in the groin called the femoral vein and you know it's a
big deal procedure both from the risk of infection and the risk of hitting an artery or puncturing
the lung and we saw so many central line complications when we were residents in medicine
nationally not just to johns hopkins nothing was unique there about it having a higher rate
of central line complications but the lines would get infected they would get clotted you had to
change them frequently many people had lines they did not need so a protocol was developed by peter
pronovost and the nurses in the icu to say look try to avoid the groin whenever possible because
those femoral lines are more likely to get infected just being down there in the groin
use a full-length drape wash your hands extensively use sterile technique wear a mask and
face shield and so we saw this protocol rigidly adhered to and a dramatic reduction in central
line infections and then peter had a relationship with the michigan hospital association
which then adopted it broadly in an icu collaborative of dozens of hospitals and they basically got the
median central line infection rate down to just below 0.5 which if you round down is zero
and this news that and what was it before peter because i remember it was a huge reduction gosh
three to five percent somewhere in that range a log fold reduction in risk log fold reduction and
it's consistent with what we saw when we were interns gosh taking care of infected central
lines was routine this was celebrated as a major milestone in patient safety here is one form of
preventable harm granted it's less than one percent of all the preventable harm in health care but we
succeeded we standardized something we got broad compliance it was a rapid adoption not the typical
17-year lag between evidence and broad adoption in practice that we see with other things introduced
but i want to add marty there was another change that took place
at least during my tenure that i have to believe had a significant impact so when i was a cocky
aggressive medical student i don't know how i got away with this but it was the wild west back then
i was putting central lines in people as a medical student now i never did it without supervision so
i always had a resident supervising me but it's pretty unusual i think for a third and fourth
year resident to be putting in central lines by the time i finished medical school i'd probably
put in 25 central lines and in part that was because i did a stint at the nih and i got some
expert experience there in the clinical service in oncology so it's pretty good at putting in a
central line i show up as an intern i mean i probably put in a hundred central lines as
an intern unsupervised again i'm very fortunate i probably put in 400 central lines in all of
residency i had one hema pneumothorax that showed up four days afterwards we never saw
the original x-ray so that was my bad to miss that but i remember by the time i was in my fifth year
that wild west was gone interns were not allowed to put in central lines only the second year
resident in the icu was putting in central lines and they were doing it under the supervision of
the acs in a florolab such that you could immediately get an image right after now i
don't know if that procedure stuck and it sure seemed a little aggressive given how i came up
but i gotta believe it was for the best do you know how that sort of played out and what the
protocol is now at a teaching hospital for central lines we used to joke that i'd put a central line
in somebody in the parking lot if they looked at me wrong well it's amazing how good you could get
at that technique and the students that had a broad experience before they started their
residency were definitely more efficient they would get the job done more reliably the fact
that you did so many before your residency probably explains why you were one of the most
highly sought after and regarded residents in our hopkins program i had no idea what my line
infection rate was all i knew is i wasn't causing pneumothoracys but that's right i guess my point
is really i would guess that complications like pneumothoracys also went down with this change so
it wasn't just that the work that peter and others did fixed line infections i think it brought
a greater appreciation to the seriousness of this procedure and i'm wondering did anybody follow up
and say hey guess what the rate of pneumothorax went from one percent to point one percent do we
have any insight into that so what you're describing is the move towards dedicated teams
by the time we finished our residency they had a central line associated a central line team
and then that matured into a dedicated team and then it turned into a rule that you really were
not supposed to put in central lines at all you were only supposed to have the dedicated team do
it and they were so freaking good because they were doing just that and then they started using
ultrasound so it's not like you take 10 20 probes until you aspirate blood and so that you served
all the success of this protocol that peter pronovost introduced and that team of course used
the protocol so it wasn't for naught but i mean the fact that we could conquer something like
central line associated infections that nobody thought you could ever tackle and the cost savings
and the avoidable harm associated with that that was a major milestone in patient safety
and then two years later after the pronovost publication on the central line toolkit or bundle
which within three years was becoming standard in many icus around the country
medicare decided they're not going to pay for a catastrophic medical mistake what we call a
never event something that should never happen regardless of the circumstances you should never
leave an instrument or a sponge behind during surgery unintentionally what year was that marty
that medicare said that 2008 that was a major step up until that time financial system in
medicine was not rewarding but if you had to go back and do an operation to remove a retained
foreign object you were paid for that procedure as well and medicare basically said why are we
incentivizing why are we rewarding this financially let's just agree to not pay for this stuff and
then other insurance companies started to follow and now it's accepted that's on the hospital if
you have a catastrophic medical mistake and then in 2009 the who organized a committee to address
patient safety at this time patient safety was the hottest thing in health care and we were
recognizing again people die from the care not just from the disease i had just published at
hopkins the surgery checklist with peter pronovost as my mentor and we put out a bunch of articles
and the who basically said we're convening people interested in patient safety we'd like to invite
you to present about your checklist i presented it a tool goandhi was chair of the committee
it was not that interested in the idea initially warmed up to it wait didn't he write a book called
the checklist manifesto or something like that he eventually saw the great story in the checklist
and wrote a book but initially he actually presented a competing idea at the who which
was something called the surgery apgar score which nobody adopted it was discarded people thought it
was dumb idea it was not risk adjusted baby's born and you do a rapid test that predicts
the baby's survival and this has been an old school score that was used to be done on babies
and it was the idea that you could do a rapid assessment in a matter of seconds and assess a
prognosis and he just loved that concept it was a great story and he thought we should do that for
all surgical patients well people were saying hey if you have a breast biopsy it's different from
having a heart bypass like you've got to adjust for the severity of the surgery but he just loved
the idea of a rapid assessment the committee voted unanimously against his proposal i remember
a tool was frustrated and he thought i don't know if i'm going to continue as chair of this committee
and then the committee said you know a tool the checklist is simple pilots already do it look at
the success in aviation it's low budget for our who committee to adopt a checklist to go up on the
operating room wall and the committee loved it so it became the initiative our checklist became
known as the who surgery checklist and to this day it hangs on the operating room walls of most
operating rooms in the world and eventually he did a study i was a part of a study showing how it
reduced adverse events and had an impact so that was a another moment in patient safety was in 2009
what year was that not to derail us but a story that got a lot of attention which was a heart
transplant at duke where did they fail to do a cross type or yes do you remember that story
yep so that was a major milestone in patient safety and a lot of good came out of the lessons
learned there so they were doing a heart transplant on a young girl at duke university
which is just to put in perspective we're talking top five places in the world you would ever have
a heart transplant would be at duke university yeah cardiac transplant they're definitely top
three or four in my opinion so they did not check a cross match which just for listeners you take
the blood of the donor and the blood of the recipient and you see what happens in the lab
does it result in sort of this hyper accelerated allergic reaction if you will that you can see
in the lab if so that's what we call a hyper acute rejection signal you abort the transplant it's done
routinely it's a standardized procedure somehow it's done before even a blood transfusion that's
right so in other words you i guess people should understand this if you were getting a blood
transfusion and your blood type is a positive it's not enough to go to the blood bank and say just
give me any old bag of a positive they still have to do a cross match they still have to take a bit
of that blood that should match with yours and yours and do that test shouldn't they i don't
honestly know the protocol for blood transfusions but certainly organ transplants something i'm very
close to absolute 100 routine as you can understand why i mean there's nothing worse i've never seen
it but i know of surgeons who have you put an organ in a recipient you sew it in and all of
a sudden the organ fails right in front of your eyes you see swelling you see this sort of ischemia
that's why we do a cross match well the cross match was not checked unfortunately the heart
failed the universe the hospital doctors of course felt terrible did everything they could
to prioritize her as a status level one high priority the highest priority to get a second
heart transplant they attempted a second heart transplant the transplant failed and it was a
tragic case all the way around it's insanely tragic because the woman died and then you could
effectively argue two other people died who didn't get a chance to have the heart that would
have worked for them that's right the opportunity missed so it was and over what what kind of cost
are we talking about well over a million dollars but even more concerning the lost years of life
in a young promising human being so you had now this recognition and how did the mistake happen
marty what did the autopsy show like obviously this is something that gets done before every
transplant and presumably almost never gets missed where was the swiss cheese on that one
what went wrong to prevent that cross match it turns out that a nurse in the operating room
sensed something was not right there was this feeling among within this nurse that something
just was not correct and what she had was alluding to was that they had not done that cross match
and she did not feel comfortable speaking up she had the thought hey wait a minute what was the
cross match did not voice that concern or voice it to the appropriate head of the operating room
the surgeon and felt terrible about it and it created this notion that do we know why it wasn't
done i can understand that maybe her spidey sense tingled but like why wasn't it done something that
is so routinely done do we know why it wasn't done i don't know if it's known but i've certainly seen
patients go to the operating room in my career where something should have been done beforehand
and it wasn't and i'm sure you've seen that so the idea of creating a culture of speaking up
or an atmosphere in the operating room where people feel that there's collegiality teamwork
and they would feel comfortable voicing a concern that no longer was a soft science it now
undermined a gigantic operation in a young girl and had catastrophic consequences so all of a sudden
standardizing what we do became more of a science that was another major step and then the ubiquitous
nature of medical errors got documented in a 2014 Mayo Clinic study where in a survey of
6500 doctors 10.5 percent of doctors surveyed say that they had made a major medical mistake
in the last three months say that again how many 10.5 percent of u.s doctors report that they made
a major medical mistake in the last three months now i might have felt like that in the lowest
points of my residency but i was surprised when i saw that now it may have been caught what we
call the near miss but it did sort of democratize the idea of hey if you felt like you've done
something like this you're not alone it's actually sort of part of this crazy life that we have
as doctors where you're getting pulled in all these directions and there's pressure and stress
and that's assuming everything at home is fine people are dealing with external pressures and
then in 2015 Mass General Hospital had a study done by researchers there which Mass General is
embarrassed by they've taken down the study from their website most of their studies get put out
in a communication sort of press release the link doesn't work anymore but the study showed that
about one in 20 medications administered in the operating room involved an error and that meant
that about 50 percent of operations had a medication error so every other operation has
some medication error most caught but they did the sort of in-depth analysis of 277 operations
at Mass General not a small shabby you know chop shop one of the three best hospitals in the world
certainly in the United States as they like to call it man's greatest hospital i would say to
sort of round out the history of patient safety the modern history in 2016 we put out a report
from my Johns Hopkins research team said okay we've been citing this 1999 Institute of Medicine
report that about a hundred thousand people a year die from medical mistakes has that number
changed in the last 25 years what's the updated number let's look at all the more recent studies
so we did a review and we showed a range where that number had a broad range and the median
point of that range was 250,000 deaths which just would surpass the current number three cause of
death stroke and would put it after cancer and heart disease which are far higher 650,000 a year
medical error if it were a disease would rank as the number three cause of death using this
estimate now it's not a perfect estimate we didn't do autopsies on every death we don't have good
numbers but we basically said look if we were to update the number it might even be higher
but the CDC does not collect vital statistics on medical errors because you cannot record a death
as a medical error because there's no billing code for error and that's how we record our national
vital statistics they use the billing code system now but it could also be a lot lower so how would
we put a 95 percent confidence interval around that estimate 125,000 to 350,000 now Joe Johns
put out a study right just before said it was 400,000 and that was the most highly cited study
up until that time and he would argue that our estimate was low we didn't do any original
research we basically pooled together the existing studies which are not perfect but we're just trying
to bring attention to it and as Don Berwick commented on the study whether it's the third
leading cause of death or seventh or ninth it's a major problem so there was a lot of discussion
heated discussion about this estimate this review article a survey was done a third of doctors
believed the estimate a third didn't know and a third didn't believe it and we had this kind of
heated discussion or spirited discussion for about a year and then the opioid epidemic hit
and opioids emerged as the number one cause of death in the United States among people under 50
opioid deaths were a form of medical error when they were prescription opioids i'm guilty of it
myself i gave opioids out like candy i feel terrible about it that is a form of medical
mistakes we just this year surpassed 100,000 opioid deaths in a trailing 12-month period
for the first time yeah 107 so are you saying that that estimate of call it 300,000 deaths
is including that 100,000 no this was prior but the 107,000 deaths in the last 12-month period
were any opioids so a lot of that now is fentanyl heroin it would be included that's right so we
don't know the estimate of prescription opioids we think it's down because we've gotten smart
prescription opioid abuse is probably way down because it's more regulated and fentanyl laced
products is driving a lot of the opioid deaths now but we were prescribing peter let's say you know
mid-career for me one opioid prescription for every adult in the United States that's how much
we were giving out opioids people didn't need it it was the medicalization of ordinary life
for some people with mild pain a lot of countries said look we only give opioids to people with
second degree burns or cancer end of life cancer and acute major surgery in the perioperative
i remember giving a talk in lebanon and i remember offering hey we're doing a lot of work on reducing
opioid prescribing i'm happy to give the opioid talk at this conference and they're like what are
you talking about that's an american problem we've never prescribed opioids outside of extremely
narrow scenarios complications of unnecessary medical care normal complications of unnecessary
medical care is a form of medical error and that's where we really tried hard to say let's broaden
the idea that people don't just die from disease they die from the care itself so that's a bit of
our journey in patient safety which really encompassed our residency peter up until recently
that has been the modern era of patient safety before then no one would ever talk about it
now when you're on rounds people say you know we could give a blood transfusion but the patient
is kind of a borderline indication in terms of whether or not they should get a blood transfusion
but we have to consider the fact that one in 80 000 blood transfusions can result in the wrong
blood type being passed on from the lab and hurting a patient we never considered the role
of human error in the care of our patients but now like hey do we need to keep people in the
hospital for a week after surgery there's the added risk of falling a new environment tripping over
your gown wearing slippers that are very slippery and they don't make sense they're uncomfortable
and getting an infection in the hospital there are risks to being in the hospital that we have to weigh
with the risk where does nosocomial or hospital acquired infection rank in the causes of medical
errors nosocomial infections specifically you're talking about yes it's difficult because some
people consider any infection after surgical care to be a nosocomial infection but not all are
preventable so there was the study out of so like even a wound infection after surgery would be
considered nosocomial that's right it would be but it's not necessarily preventable so nosocomial
meaning you're getting it from the hospital may not necessarily be preventable because we're not
going to eradicate bacteria from planet earth and there's a feeling that say with knee replacements
we're pretty darn good you get a knee replacement the risk of an infection is eight tenths to nine
tenths of one percent pretty darn good now what should it be you don't know we may be at the
baseline level they're wearing spacesuits doing the procedure using sterile technique i mean
they're using glue to close the incisions now over the closure so maybe this is the level that
we have to accept now there's a debate in patient safety some people say we have to achieve zero
harm and you'll hear that model a lot i worry about that that sounds a little bit like zero
covid to me which is trigger word it creates sort of an unrealistic expectation it might detract
from focusing on bigger things your example of knee replacement is a good one orthopedics have
really figured out how to do joint replacement in the most sterile manner imaginable i'm kind of
curious as to what the bigger opportunities are that are away from this patients falling through
the cracks normal complications of interventions they don't need there still are medication errors
but they're not from sloppy handwriting anymore they're from a lack of visual cues in the
patient's chart so now you're entering an order you don't have a binder in front of you with the
patient's name and you know exactly whose chart you're in you're flipping screens you're in
different tabs and you write an order for somebody who didn't need it or the wrong person or something
like that this happened to me actually about a month ago so we use an electronic medical record
in our practice and i was in one patient's chart looking at a bunch of labs and looking at a bunch
of things and we had just switched to a new emr we used one emr for many years and then we just
switched to a new one which has a completely different look and when you switch to a new
patient it's not entirely obvious yeah scary again nothing came of it because i wasn't there
to prescribe a medication but i was blown away at how long it took me to recognize that i was in
another patient's chart yeah and you do prescribe through this emr so there is a scenario by which
i could have said and again in our practice this is pretty low stakes because we're not prescribing
that many things but i take your point which is you always used to know what mrs smith's chart
looked like because it was the biggest one and you recognized your handwriting in it and you had all
of those other cues that told you where you were i mean that was a pretty miserable system and had
a lot of problems with it but that's one thing it had going for it over an emr and it was cyber
secure yeah so the old-fashioned docs who had very good handwriting you can think of probably
one that we know charlie yo they are basically saying look we have a good system people need to
write more effectively another healthy movement that came out of this patient safety endeavor has
been the idea that sorry works and what drives malpractice claims is your honesty with patients
not whether or not you make a mistake and i found that to be true in my practice that
if you're very honest with people they're incredibly forgiving i remember ordering a
cat scan i was busy it was between operations it ended up getting done on a wrong patient similar
name done on the wrong patient i don't know if i mixed up the names or the nurse made a clerical
mistake and entering the order because we do a lot of verbal orders you know as attending physicians
and this patient was already angry at me they had a pancreatic leak they just were frustrated
with their care i think their expectations were unreasonable but of course you got to be polite so
this guy was already pissed at me i figure great he just got a cat scan he didn't need it's very
obvious he didn't need it he was recovering now he's going to sue me or something i immediately
hear about this i run up to the patient's room and i say look sir i want to tell you something
you got a cat scan you did not need it was not intended for you i'm not going to sugarcoat it
and say we wanted to make sure and look for something it was a clerical mistake i take full
responsibility i'm sorry if you want the results i haven't even seen it yet i just heard about this
and i wanted to tell you first i'll get the results and share the results with you this guy
who had a pissed off look on his face as i walked into his room smiled and looked at me and said
doc thank you for being honest with me i really appreciate that and our bond grew we he developed
trust in me and i'm proud to report that guy and i are facebook friends today because he never
sued me and people are hungry for honesty we saw it during covid we see it with so many aspects of
medicine let me share with you a counterpoint to that story i'm not telling something that
isn't already publicly known so very close friend of mine here in austin his name is eddie margain
a wonderful guy and i've gotten to be very close with eddie and one night over dinner we were
talking about this and somehow he brought up the story of his wife lorena at the time i didn't
know this but of course she's written a book about this so again nothing i'm saying here is
is not already publicly known lorena was having some medical issues and had kind of a big workup
and sure enough they found that she had a mass on her adrenal gland so the adrenal gland for listeners
is a small but incredibly important gland that sits on top of the kidney so you have
two kidneys and therefore you have two adrenal glands one on top of each the adrenal gland
produces all sorts of relevant hormones but certainly the ones that we think of the most
would be cortisol epinephrine norepinephrine and she had this tumor on her adrenal gland and
obviously the treatment for this is to have it removed and you can live with one adrenal gland
so this is you know a relatively straightforward operation so she had the operation this was here
in austin and in the weeks that followed she went from bad to worse she just felt horrible
she couldn't understand what was wrong to make a long story short she ended up eventually going
back to see the doctor only to discover marty that he had taken out the wrong adrenal gland
he had removed her healthy adrenal gland and the one with the tumor was still there so now they
needed to go back and have that one removed and so now she is a person who has no adrenal glands
which creates a lifelong challenge you can't live without your adrenal gland so now you are
dependent on exogenous forms of glucocorticoids the story gets even more difficult because there
were more surgical complications and things like that lorana is about the sweetest person you'll
ever meet not a negative vindictive bone in her body and she only wanted one thing wasn't money
she just wanted an apology and the surgeon wouldn't give it you hear these stories and you
understand the reputation that the field of surgery can sometimes bring on itself he had a
million excuses egos the arrogance the hubris he could not bring himself to apologize to this woman
and the lawyers don't help either because many times the hospital lawyers who are
make a lot of policy for doctors they've made a lot of covid policies have been driven by
hospital lawyers general counsels of businesses they tell you oftentimes don't talk to them at
all that's right don't talk to the patient don't talk to the family we're going to quickly negotiate
a settlement and we're going to gag everybody in the settlement so they rush to the family oftentimes
before the family even thinks about a claim they realize what happened they rush to the families
and say you know we feel for you and your family they won't apologize and we would like to provide
some compensation here just sign these documents and then everyone's gagged for life and we have
not had an honest conversation about patient safety in america because of that and that's why i wrote
when i wrote the book unaccountable about this issue of patient safety and how we can do better
i wrote in there that we should ban all gagging in medicine this should be an honest profession
no gagging Lorena and Eddie are incredibly successful well off she said out of the gate
we're not here to sue there's no amount of money you can give us it's going to change our lives
we just want to make sure this never happens to anybody again and that's an honest request i
mean it's reasonable if you look at other industries they've achieved high levels of reliability
i'm too practical i'm a clinician as you are so i don't subscribe to the zero harm approach
i mean sure it's it might be a goal but we have to be honest and look for reasonable improvements
in this problem but look at aviation in the last 25 years how many plane accidents have we seen
in 2009 there was the flight going to buffalo where 50 people died that's about it in the last
20 years in 2018 there was a woman partially ejected through a window who died but say in
the interim nine years 2009 in the u.s in the u.s in the nine years from 2009 to 2018
six billion passengers without a single fatality rate today about two million people a day
pilots are not just jumping in the cockpit and start barking orders at each other they have a
systematic way to use checklists and pathways and have safety nets and they've created what they
call crew resource management that encourages people as part of the discipline to voice any
concern about safety and not to ridicule anyone who brings up that concern that's a life lesson
that can be used in any setting that you want people to ask questions and even challenge some
deeply held assumptions you may have without ridiculing them if you make fun of them once i
found if you mock a nurse once or yell at them for bringing something up because you're busy
they will never feel as comfortable voicing a concern to you and your patients suffer you
suffer from that lack of safety culture so marty we wouldn't be probably even having this discussion
if it weren't for a case that has gained a lot of notoriety slash awareness over the past year and
certainly in the past couple of months since the verdict on his trial but let's assume that a lot
of people aren't familiar with this case from vanderbilt can you walk us through in detail the
timeline of events if my memory serves me correctly this all took place in was it 2017 or 2018
2017 all right so take us back to that fateful day in 2017 so this is an amazing story on so
many different levels redonda vat is a 36 year old nurse who was hired at vanderbilt in 2015
now christmas eve 2017 she was taking care of a patient named charlene murphy 75 year old woman
who was admitted for a subdural hematoma or a brain bleed actually improved quickly and two days
later she was ready to leave and they ordered the doctors ordered sort of one last scan while she
was in the hospital the nurse redonda took her to the scanner and ordered some versed there was
some versed ordered which is a sedative to help people stay still during the scan this was ordered
in the icu before she came down or who ordered the versed presumably the physician who was caring
for her and the nurses will often say look can i have an open order for versed if i need to use it
in the cat scanner and every now and then the radiologist will order it while they're down
there they'll say hey this person's having trouble staying steady can we get a versed order
i mean how many times have you and i said yes to that request so it's a commonly used medication
in that scanner she goes into a system relatively new system that's got automated dispensing
there had been many complaints that there are too many alerts and you often have to override the
system because there was not good coordination between the electronic health records and the
pharmacy so in this system you frequently had to override alerts well she types in v e to order the
versed and up comes maybe through a default vecuronium which is a paralyzing agent it's a potent
paralyzing agent and gives it to the patient so just to be clear so she's typing in ve it
auto populates v ec vecuronium instead of ver versed she doesn't realize this she clicks on it
what is this like a little mobile pixus device that she's traveling with i'm assuming she's in
the radiology suite when this happens or is she doing this back in the icu i'm not sure the
location but it's clear that she typed in ve vecuronium comes out now she had to override the
alert there was an alert and the vecuronium came up as a powder when most people would know versed
as a liquid but there are other things that come up as powders and you just have to inject some
saline to suspend the powder that was a warning flag you know we talked about the swiss cheese
model she reportedly was distracted and she suspends the powder into a solution the cap
should routinely and by the way just for folks to understand why would vecuronium even be
there it's really only something that can be used when a patient is either in surgery
and they're fully anesthetized and on a ventilator or in the icu under the same conditions there's
no other need for vecuronium other than in a patient who is on a ventilator that's right so
presumably because this patient was in the icu i mean otherwise you shouldn't even have vecuronium
in the pixus system right that's right and the cap routinely has on the cap emergency drug
warning it has a little warning on the cap so there are a bunch of these sort of and it had that
did have that it routinely has that i want to be very careful with my words i didn't see
documentation that that one had it but it routinely has that as a standard thing now
she immediately because this is a potent paralytic agent paralyzed the patient and she died now they
were not in the icu to immediately resuscitate the patient it's a tragedy the woman was 75
otherwise going to go home van der bilt had documentation where two neurologists
listed the cause of death as basically the brain bleed and it was deemed essentially a natural
cause of death this was reported to the medical examiner and how is that even possible the woman
was presumably wide awake when she went down to have one more scan before leaving the hospital
that's right she dies on the scanner and the cause of death was stated as cerebral hemorrhage or
subdural hematoma that's right so the family was told what she just died on the scanner the family
has been gagged and basically is not speaking about the case although one family member told
the media that they want to see the maximum penalty to her and the grandson said that the
woman who died would have forgiven the nurse now the nurse immediately feels horrible says exactly
what she did recognized her mistake as the patient was deteriorating felt this i may have caused this
and admitted reported this whole thing was 100 honest i mean in an incredible way has even said
subsequently that her life will never be the same that she feels that a piece of her has died i think
we've all been a part of medical mistakes where we still think about that the medical examiner does
not investigate the case because the report is a brain bleed so in other words the death certificate
which is usually filled out at that moment let's walk people through how this works marty because
again you and i take this for granted because we've done it a thousand times i don't think people
understand how this works so this woman stops breathing in the MRI scanner i assume it was an
MRI not a CT if they were trying to paralyze her or trying to sedate her but whatever it was so they
declare her dead there or maybe they would take her up to the ICU and try to resuscitate her
further but certainly within minutes she's going to be declared dead do we know if they intubated
her and kept her alive for a little while longer until they declared her brain dead i don't know
the timing of the death but they attempted a full resuscitation right you would as soon as you
recognize this anybody who's recognized to be unresponsive like this and desaturating would
immediately be resuscitated the point is at some point when they cease to resuscitate her and or
when they declare end of life usually a resident fills out a death certificate at that point now
i don't know how many of those things i've filled out in my life but it's a very painful process
nobody wants to do it no no nobody wants to be the one to have to sign the death certificate
and fill it out you have to be very careful in what you write on it because it wants a primary
cause of death a secondary cause of death and you have to write on the right line and it has to be
i remember it has to be i don't know maybe this is done electronically now but certainly at the
time i remember having to redo many of these things they get sent back to me for months and
months and months until i got it just right but somebody had to write on that death certificate
subdural hematoma is the proximate cause of death well two vanderbilt neurologists issued this report
and this came up later the medical examiner down the road two years later changes the cause of death
to accidental they get tipped off by whom by a report that comes out so it'll be clear here
as i progress basically within a month vanderbilt this is per investigative reporting by the tennessean
quote unquote the tennessean reports that vanderbilt takes several actions to obscure the fatal error
from the public okay it was not reported to state or federal officials that's required by law you've
got to report it to the state and you've got to report it to cms center for medicare and medicaid
services was not done report any death or any death that is deemed accidental any what we call
sentinel event which is clearly a preventable adverse event related death it will be referred
to as a sentinel event they've got to be reported not reported to the joint commission you could
argue that's an accrediting body it's private you can break their rules it's not a violation of the
law but vanderbilt basically takes these actions to hide or obscure the error according to the
tennessean from their investigation they fire the nurse and vanderbilt this is two years after no
this is a month after a month after okay vanderbilt immediately negotiates an out-of-court settlement
with the family gags the family from saying anything about it everybody is gagged in the
family except for the grandson who is legally not included in the gagging he ends up speaking up
later the hospital when they're asked subsequently about the case say oh we can't discuss it because
of this legal settlement that we have by the way they don't say anything publicly fast forward a
couple months so just to make sure i understand we're a month after this woman dies the death
certificate and the neurologists all agree she died of subdural hematoma but clearly the family
has been told the truth which is why they're receiving a large settlement and asked to sign
a gag order and the nurse is being fired that's right the nurse redonda vaught gets a job at another
hospital as a bed coordinator which all hospitals have bed coordinators it's a hospital called
centennial in nashville and then you go all the way to the fall in october remember this happened
christmas eve so you're almost a year out an anonymous person reports to the state and cms
that there was an unreported medical error okay they basically got tipped off by some whistleblower
who's anonymous then the tennessee health department which is tipped off formally states that they're
deciding not to pursue any action on this tip off the agency actually said in a letter that the
event did not constitute a violation and therefore they're not going to do anything now just as an
interesting side note many of these state medical boards are basically sleepy organizations if you
know the story of dr death tell the story neurosurgeon in texas multiple horrific catastrophic
outcomes all believed to be sentinel events catastrophic avoidable medical mistakes
negligence and people dying in this practice over many years documented by laurel beal in this famous
podcast maybe at one point it was the most popular single podcast in the entire world of
podcasting titled doctor death and basically everyone knew of this doctor's problems
the residency program knew but they just graduated him to sort of get rid of him he had problems at
numerous hospitals nobody would say anything and this kind of speaks to this problem of
the old culture of patient safety finally there's something so egregious that happens that he gets
arrested and goes to jail now the state medical board didn't want to touch it for the longest
times that's typical of state medical boards they generally don't want to touch anything now
ironically you can meet dr death and kill people and they don't touch it but if you prescribe
ivermectin all of heaven and earth is coming down on you now i don't believe ivermectin has any
activity against covet i should just state that but it has no downside and i don't recommend it
i'm not but i mean right now they're going after people with who prescribe ivermectin with warnings
and they want your hide if you prescribe ivermectin just an irony so they basically say that she does
not violate the statutes and or the rules governing the profession they put out a statement
tennessee department of health this is late 2018 yeah this is almost a year after the event
and can you imagine what she's thinking like you just want it to be over things are escalating
did she ever speak to the family was she permitted to apologize to the family
she was under orders by vanderbilt never to speak to the family but she had said through the media
several times that she takes full responsibility she even said in her trial that she was a hundred
percent at fault which is i think beating herself up over something that was probably a combination
of her mistake and a system but i'll leave my commentary out of this so cms starts investigating
medicare when they send they take this seriously this whistleblower complaint they do a surprise
investigation at vanderbilt end of october early november they spend about a week investigating
vanderbilt they are pissed vanderbilt clearly did not report this clearly a violation and they
get so serious about this they basically conclude that the medical error was not reported in
violation of their rules and they threaten all medicare payments to the institutions
to vanderbilt they are serious and that's when this becomes public about a year after the event
because vanderbilt would not discuss it but a journalist was able to get a hold of this report
from medicare because it's public document it's public agency they have to request a follow-up or
did they just get it on their own that was not through a foya that was public information but
no names were in there so redonda void is still basically not a name in the united states at this
point now cms told vanderbilt if you cannot show that you have taken system-wide actions to prevent
this in the future we are going to suspend all medicare payments to vanderbilt university medical
center if you talk about a threat it's maybe the biggest threat in health care in the modern era
vanderbilt gives cms a so-called plan of correction you know here's what we're doing
we're taking this seriously and they don't release that to the public a journalist then
got that plan of correction through a foya request freedom of information act request try to get it
from vanderbilt directly but they were denied then on february 19th the name redonda thought
became public information when she was arrested for reckless homicide and impairment abusing an
adult now that's when people found out about what happened just to make sure i understand that she
was arrested she was arrested tell me how that happened so a d-aid saw the case and said we're
going to press charges that's right the district attorney in davison county basically said
we're gonna go after her let's stop there for a second how often does that happen that a medical
mistake happens and a district attorney presses criminal charges against the doctor the nurse or
technician or whoever is involved i have been in this field of patient safety my entire career
i've never heard of it with a nurse i have heard of outright fraud resulting in arrests for example
the doctor death story there's a doctor in michigan who was giving chemotherapy to people
who didn't have cancer i mean that's sort of cold-blooded fraud if you exclude two types of errors if
you exclude fraud so all financial crimes that are fraud and if you include like doctors who are
raping patients where they're just breaking the law i'm talking about a medical error that was not
made deliberately never heard of it never heard of an arrest for an honest medical mistake
and in fact one of the principles of patient safety that we have been advocating throughout
the entire 25 23 years of the patient safety movement in america has been the concept of
just culture which is a doctrine which says that honest mistakes should not be penalized they
should be penalized if there was mal intent or substance abuse or somebody should be suspended
from their role if they are an ongoing threat but honest mistakes should not be penalized and that
is a doctrine that has enabled people to speak up about this epidemic of medical mistakes in the
united states and that has been celebrated as these sort of giant milestone of the american
patient safety movement and it's a worldwide concept i've traveled the world and people
believe in the just culture doctrine the arrest of redonda voight undid in my opinion 23 years of
advancement in patient safety it undermined the very fundamental doctrine of just culture she
was arrested by the way she had the entire time in documents that subsequently came out immediately
admitted what happened at the moment this woman died and throughout and ever since and to this day
and i've had a recent interaction with her i can touch on that but basically the victim's family
one of the members of the family had basically said the patient would have forgiven her so the
trial started when right now we're about a year after but because of covid the trial doesn't start
until i think it was like this past fall right three months ago march 21st to 25th about a four
day period so in the interim there was a meeting of the tennessee board of licensure basically the
department of health you remember they had said they're not going to pursue this they then flip
the executive at vanderbilt university c right pinson who's actually a pancreatic
billiary surgeon i know him he sort of admits to this board that looks into vanderbilt and says
yes the death was not reported essentially i'm paraphrasing and that our response at vanderbilt
was too limited now at this point redonda vaught is getting a lot of national attention that she's
got big legal bills and she goes on a go fund me campaign raises over a hundred thousand dollars
and basically says in the go fund me campaign that look she made a mistake and she needs legal costs
i mean this woman could not have been more honest about what happened also around that time nurses
nationwide take notice there's millions of nurses in the united states they start getting
very emotionally connected to this they start showing up at some of these hearings in front of
the department of health and they say i am redonda that becomes a slogan that nurses around the
country take on they put it on social media they stand outside hundreds of them around the time of
her trial with signs i am redonda basically saying what you and i were saying it's every doctor every
nurse i talked to was talking with zubin debani same reaction i see exactly what may have happened
gosh that could have been me look at the study from mayo clinic 10.5 of people admit to a major
medical mistake in the last three months people reconnect with redonda vaught several dozen people
are out every appearance she makes her court plea in february of 2019 just about a year after
the incident year in a month she pleads not guilty now her lawyers argue that vanderbilt shares part
of the blame now several months later the tennessee department of health which said they're not going
to pursue action against her they flip they reverse their position and they go after her
and they use the argument that they must immediately investigate what they describe
as a threat to the public her lawyer knowing that they're going to go to trial for the criminal case
for murder or homicide he asks the judge to postpone the tennessee department of health hearing
because he sees wait i'm sorry marty i just missed something i don't think i was paying attention
this was homicide not manslaughter homicide this is homicide reckless homicide and abuse
now she has two hearings and for two legal proceedings ahead of her about a year after
the incident year and a half out she's got the tennessee health board and she's got the criminal
case to go so her lawyer says look tennessee health board they're acting like a bunch of clowns i'm
paraphrasing they said they're not going to take any action and then over a year later they suddenly
reverse their position what's going on so he makes this argument and the tennessee department of health
says very fishy they say no we must do this immediately we cannot postpone it till after the
criminal trial because she may pose an quote-unquote urgent threat to the public you can't believe what
you're hearing here the administrative judge elizabeth cambron decides not to delay her
department of health hearing and it goes ahead of her criminal hearing and she ends up going in
front of this board at the same time vanderbilt is just hanging out arguing they can't say anything
about the case this tennessee investigation says that they've obscured the circumstances
of her death and this grandson is so frustrated he makes a statement around then that says that
vanderbilt is engaged and remember he's not under the gag order he says quote-unquote that there's
a cover-up that screams there's a cover-up that screams covid comes hits this country if you
haven't remembered that's a coronavirus that resulted in two pandemics a tragic pandemic which
killed about a million americans and then a subsequent pandemic that followed called a
pandemic of lunacy but in july finally they get their trial the first one is the department of
health she says that the department of health hearing this is completely my fault her license
is revoked even though the board says things that we would sympathize with they say the vice chair
of the board says we all make mistakes and there have been many mistakes and failures in this case
suggesting basically that vanderbilt has part of the blame but they say our role is just to evaluate
the role of the nurse here and they revoke her license kind of ridiculous what their statements
are then three months ago it goes to the criminal trial and the davison county d-a glen funk has
his three assistant d-a's go to the mat in court and they aggressively and viciously went after her
these three assistant d-a's debbie household chad jackson and britney flat recently became
assistant d-a's it's kind of a new job for them and they go viciously after her and argue that
there was negligent homicide now she does everything she can to try to defend herself
now what's their argument their argument is this was such an egregious error i guess i'm just trying
to understand how this is homicide maybe i just don't understand the law well enough but if you
kill somebody while you're driving let's assume you're not under the influence of alcohol or
anything like that and you're not driving recklessly you're driving safely and you kill a cyclist
i'm not aware of a driver in that situation having i certainly know this was the case in
california when i lived there but i know that there was no instance in which a driver who killed a
cyclist faced criminal charges unless there was reckless behavior involved or alcohol so what
rises to the level of even manslaughter vehicular manslaughter is presumably what is that when you're
driving recklessly and another person dies as a result of it like i guess i'm just trying to
understand what the da's argument was here legally and then separately politically i don't
know if you can speak to either of those of course these are broader questions those are the same
questions i had i'll tell you what i know and that is that she was charged with quote unquote
negligent homicide and abuse of an impaired adult and found guilty of both of those charges now in
the arguments that they made they had cited 10 mistakes that she had made and it was kind of the
swiss cheese model that we had talked about with patient safety this is the perfect storm if you
will it was she was distracted she overrode the warning alert even though nurses at that hospital
say that they do that every day nurses said every day they override alerts that it was a powder and
not a liquid that the cap should have said it was a paralyzing agent there's so many things that they
point to that you can frame somebody you can make somebody look like they are doing something
that is can you imagine if they had the insights that we have at our m&m conference it would just
look really bad on the outside they did everything they could to paint these are aggressive young
lawyers now glenn funk who's the da who was getting a lot of attention around this time
because this is his office that was bringing the charges against a vanderbilt nurse for a medical
mistake that was an honest mistake that she admitted to immediately he had two other vas who
are running against him condemn this saying you know this is a farce what's going on something is
fishy here there are rumors conspiracy theories in nashville that maybe there was some entity
behind this oddly aggressive action against this nurse a competing health system andrebellt
university itself to bring attention away from its error and not reporting and other errors
related to this case i don't know i have no opinion on any of those but those are definitely
circulating ideas because to have a da so aggressively go after a nurse for an honest
mistake was such a significant charge it is odd it is odd now she was found guilty and sentenced
very recently and in the sentencing she was convicted of homicide that's right found guilty
negligent homicide and in the sentencing what was the possible range of sentences she could
receive i know what the sentence was and we'll talk about that but coming out of the trial
what was the potential the judge had considered three years of jail time but of course the judge
could have said whatever the judge wanted to say they could have said 20 years or a lifetime
negligent homicide is not something where i think there's a ceiling on how many years you can give
somebody did legal experts have a point of view on what was expected i've not heard any experts
comment on what was expected i think at every stage in this entire case people expected
the thing to end the da would say she's been through the ringer now we're going to basically
slap her on the wrist and do a settlement or something like that never happened and so as
this grows nurses around the country are finding they connect with her a bunch of letters that came
out just after this sentencing after the sentencing or after the conviction after the sentencing okay
let's tell people what the sentence was so the judge was merciful to give her three years of
probation and so there'll be no jail time for her but she's a convicted felon for the rest of her
life well not for the rest of her life because she got something called judicial diversion which means
that they can expunge her criminal record if she serves the probationary period on good behavior
so you know an act of mercy from god there and god i'm not referring to the judge i'm referring to
you know so the prosecution i'm sure was very upset with that sentence it sort of undermined
a lot of their efforts yep here is what one vanderbilt physician you know these letters of
support started coming out of the public here's what a vanderbilt physician wrote and i think
this vanderbilt physician speaks for many of us he said we cared referring to the nurse that he
worked with redonda voigt we cared for so many patients together what was notable what was the
consistent high level of attention i saw her to provide to so many of our patients and their
families when we worked together she was very conscientious and aptly cared for many complex
patients all these letters of support of people she worked with at vanderbilt come out lots of
vanderbilt physicians pissed off at what's happening they're not happy that their impeccable
medical care is getting characterized nationally by the actions of their administration here's
what the da's office did in response to these letters that were released they released this
letter i am sickened by those who rallied around her as a hero i thought she was a horrible
anomaly but now i think there are hundreds of thousands of nurses who must also be dangerous
practitioners since they defended the indefensible so readily that was lisa bergelko she is an
assistant professor at newman university she wrote that letter in support of the da's prosecution and
the da put that letter out in the public domain almost as a and who is this professor she's a
professor of what she's a professor of nursing i see she's a nurse herself so this is the saga
that we live with now and in my opinion we have had decades of progress in patient safety about 23
healthy years of significant improvements in the culture of safety in the way we approach safety
undone with a single group of assistant young district attorneys that decide to go after
one individual at the exclusion of doing anything about a hospital that unlike the nurse did not
admit to anything initially and broke the law what do you think is the fallout of this have you
spoken with nurses or doctors in the interval since the conviction explicitly about this and
do you have any anecdotal evidence that that's going to change the culture of reporting an open
and honest dialogue around medical mistakes there's a preliminary statistic that one in five
nurses in the profession are quitting during the pandemic now some of that is pandemic burnout
some of its a number of factors but a lot of nurses are leading the profession and there's
this feeling that they don't feel valued and this has been a bit of a smack in their face and so
hospitals around the country who are dealing with real critical nursing staffing shortages
are trying to pay attention to the concerns that nurses have about this case they're trying to make
it clear that this is not their approach i have talked to lawmakers at the state level in different
states we're thinking about passing protections for nurses to try to encourage people in nursing
if you look at the protection that police officers have they have an immunity intrinsic to their jobs
and should that immunity be extended to people like redonda vod it's delicate but this is now
a new conversation that has surfaced i also had an interaction with her and that is that she had
reached out for help to our friend zubin and zubin had passed that information on to me now i get so
many of these requests you know i've been unfairly sued or i'm going to court or i have a deposition
can you help i honestly just did not see the email i felt horrible once i saw that this blew up and
zubin had pointed out to me that he had sent me this email and i reached out to her and just
basically told her like if i can be an expert witness or help i'm happy to do so on your behalf
so i found her to have an incredible spirit good attitude i feel bad for her she was crying at the
trial when she was found guilty but that is my interaction that i've had with her maybe to put
a bow on all of this if you're someone listening to this and you're thinking about how you can
interact with the healthcare system it seems that the majority of medical errors take place
inside of hospitals is that a fair assessment yes it makes for a frightening experience when
you're going to a hospital because usually if you're going to a hospital even if it's
electively you're going to have an elective surgery or you know you're going there non-electively
which is even more frightening the medical side of it is bad enough in terms of what you're worried
about and what could happen but i think this discussion we've had over the last you know
whatever 90 minutes speaks to another threat that might even rival that threat my personal view is
it's less than that but we'll never know that answer potentially what can a person do if they
or their loved ones are going to be admitted to the hospital either electively or emergently to
reduce the odds of any of these medical errors they run the gamut from incorrect medicine
administration to unnecessary procedures there's no end to what these mistakes look like is there
anything that the patient or the patient's family can do to reduce the risk of that there's a lot
so first of all things are much better in my opinion hospitals are safer there's more awareness
when you bring up these questions or issues there's attention to them every hospital has
a patient relations department and if things just don't seem right if you feel that you're not
communicating effectively with your care team you feel care is not coordinated you have a concern
or there was an error you can call the patient relations department they've got somebody on call
24 7 that's basically a standard thing in the hospitals now it's important to have an advocate
with you anytime you get medical care you've got a loved one in the hospital it's amazing how it
seems that the care is just overall much better holistic comprehensive and coordinated when
there's a family member or loved one there could be a friend but they're they're taking notes they're
asking questions when you come in for rounds they're asking to talk to the doctor who's in
charge of their care at least once a day they sometimes set an appointment where they say look
i'd love to talk to the doctor and you can communicate this often through the nurse or
the nursing assistant to say is there a time i can plan to be here where i can speak with the
doctor caring for so and so it's important to ask about alternatives we've generally had this sort
of burnout mode response to any questions in medicine as residents where if they ask any
question you just tell them they could die if they don't have something done and you don't get into
the details and it's like look we got to just ship and load and unload the trucks if we're told
this person needs a CAT scan on rounds we're supposed to see that it gets done and we may not
have a good breadth of knowledge as a young trainee of the alternatives some people do a good job
other people may not be able to present those options well if you ask the right questions
and ask about alternatives so for example you're supposed to go down to have a filter put in your
large vein in your body called a vena cava and you might say wait a minute you know typically
we decide on rounds this gets done the intern explains hey the doctors want to put a filter in
they may or may not even explain it sometimes you get patient transport shows up to take you down
there and patients not really in the loop you know they're getting medications they don't even
know what they're getting what's getting infused what they're taking by mouth the more they can be
aware of what's happening ask about the reason for those and the alternatives the better the
care is going to be yeah that's a hard ask though marty medicine really is a foreign language and i
think back to when i was a trainee i'd like to think i was pretty good at explaining things
but you were you're laying there in a bed you've got an iv a nurse is coming in and
usually putting something into an iv or giving you a little cap with pills in it patients are
really intimidated to say can you tell me what each of these pills is and tell me what each one of
them does we now have a protocol if you will that our nurses are supposed to explain to the patient
every medication that they give them so let's say it's time for your twice a day
lasek medication which is laseks is a medication that's given to move body fluid from the third
spaces in your body into your urinary system so if you've got too much fluid in your body it'll
cause you to urinate some of that fluid out so the nurses will actually explain to the patients
i'm injecting some laseks medication this is a medication to address the swelling in your body
and it will cause you to urinate more and so this is actually a big effort right now in patient
safety and we actually had a protocol for a while where we had one of our doctors actually peter
pronevos say on the closed circuit television in the patient rooms ask us questions ask about the
medication that's being given to you you should know what it is and what it's for and you should
ask your doctor or whoever walks in the room nurse if they've washed their hands and it became this
sort of partnership where we want you to ask hey have you washed your hands before it was kind of
like how dare you ask me of course i washed my hands of course we didn't always do it but this
is the sort of new dialogue that we are trying to promote to make the patient a participant in their
care and not just a bystander and when you do it what i've noticed the more educated they are
or their surrogate the better the care is you know many times they just say wait wait this does not
make sense you know what we're doing here they were supposed to have this and this why not do
it at the same time this doctor wants to do this and this and so i do see improvements a change in
the culture a awareness and this effort to educate people and the more people can do it i mean you
are in the middle of a very complicated system of care when you're in the hospital i mean the more
you can be aware of what's happening the safer the care what's the biggest thing that has to
change or biggest three things that have to change to be sitting here in 10 years and say
we've cut that medical error death rate down by 50 what would have to happen payment reform number
one so there's not really a great financial incentive for better safety if a hospital is
safer what is their financial reward we know there's an altruistic moral reward and we know
people generally like that but a lot of times the cfo's are making the decisions they want to see an
roi and you bring in something to a hospital that say is going to reduce the number of misses in
radiology let's say there's a software program that will take a second look at chest x-rays and chest
CAT scans to look for lesions that the radiologist missed and if it's identified with the AI that can
pick up lesions now pretty sensitively but that lesion is not noted in the report by the radiologist
this is all sort of digital this is all computers are doing this they do the AI they look for the
reports look for the keywords that there's a tumor lesion coin size lesion and they can reconcile
in our systems whether or not there's a discrepancy and by the way what i'm describing is a real
product out there that's used at Sutter Health AI is used to look at the scans as sort of a second
check the same thing has been done with EKGs and then they look for discrepancies in the reports
and if the AI picks it up and the report doesn't then that list of that patient having an unreconciled
difference goes to the radiologist and they're to review that list of non-reconciled differences
between the AI and the radiologist now what is the ROI to the hospital on adopting that technology
zero negative it's a cost that's not rewarded and so what we've done is we've relied on the
values of executives to adopt technologies that they believe in many times the doctors are the
champions for this the head of radiology says you know i know this is not going to be great for our
bottom line but we're doing well financially let's adopt it let's be honest many hospitals had their
most profitable year last year and some hospitals have so much cash reserves reserves are so great
that they have investment arms and they're basically hedge funds with hospitals on the side
at this point some of these medical centers they have so much money in cash so we rely on
individuals and innovators to say there's no formal ROI that you're going to see on the bottom
line immediately but we believe this is better care and you're seeing that adoption very sporadically
and very haphazardly there's a lot of the patient safety innovations that make sense but they have a
tough time getting in so we've got to change the payment model that i think is the number one
but i thought you said that CMS was already saying we're not going to reimburse for
cases where there are errors that's a stick more than it is a carrot but has that changed the
culture that has changed the culture but it's only not reimbursing three specific types of errors
which are three types of what we call never events which is death of an ultra low risk person
in the operating room at the time of surgery a retained sponge or retained foreign object
there's an airway never event which you know nobody should die of an airway
lack of an airway exposure so these are very narrow events they're rare events and so yeah
CMS is not paying for it which has put a ton of attention on these issues and the reporting to the
state on these issues has created a ton of scrutiny around these events and those events are
i mean the counting process we do now coming out of surgery is intense you know it started off when
we were residents like yeah i think we got all the sponges and instruments out okay and then it went
to the nurse do we have all the sponges and instruments out on the set yeah we've got them
all then it was count them to make sure it's the same number we started with and then it was a
formal count that was recorded and now it's an RFID or scanned barcode scan system and so we've
matured a lot with that that's because of this intense scrutiny around this particular type of
mistake now if you over prescribe opioids after an uncomplicated vaginal delivery i mean OB doctors
will tell you you should not be giving opioids through uncomplicated vaginal delivery and yet
women will go home with a bottle or other minor procedures and so if you prescribe 30 opioids when
we know best practices would never allow more than 10 opioid pills in a narcotic naive adult
that's an error but are we even measuring it now at hopkins just began the measurement and data
feedback process for that type of error i wish there was more attention and if i could say one
more thing i probably shouldn't but what the heck during covid we saw this intense bias towards
laboratory research that the only real serious type of research is laboratory research done
under a hood in a laboratory at places like the nih and that's how we solve disease that all this
other stuff the stuff marty's interested in systems change standardizing processes that soft stuff
culture speaking up and that's not really science and so what you have is all of our health agencies
really entirely focused on laboratory medicine and what happens is you get young investigators
faculty they can't get grants to do research on this stuff they're not rewarded they don't get
promoted they're told by their department directors they got to you know have a lab or do something
lab related there's one small government agency that funds this kind of stuff called the agency
for healthcare research and quality massively underfunded fair amount of cronyism and how they
fund their grants as well but during covid we wanted to know the behavioral aspects how does it
spread when are you most contagious do masks work none of those questions were answered with good
evidence instead we had massive efforts going on in the lab appropriately it's not downplaying that
we need that but we need both and so the nih cdc never did a study to say is it airborne or surface
transmission instead they let that debate linger in the public domain for months from january until
april letting people argue opine on tv they could have done that study in 24 hours natural immunity
cloth masks and 95 masks the reduction in transmission all those studies could have
been done immediately they didn't because they were entirely focused on laboratory pathways and
blocking and medications and pharmaceutical solutions we need those but you saw the it come
at the complete exclusion of basic clinical research and we see the same thing with patient
safety that bias towards laboratory research is hurting us badly and as you know better than anyone
in the united states in the world where's the nih research for food is medicine and the
inflammatory state and environmental exposures that cause cancer and school lunch programs
instead we're talking about bariatric surgery and throwing insulin at people and second line
anti-hypertensives where's the science of sleep medicine at the nih so these are the giant blind
spots in our current national funding mechanism and patient safety is one of those blind spot areas
still i'm surprised i guess based on the recent reports over the past five years that it still
remains kind of in a blind spot because if you just looked at it through the lens of even if
it's the eighth leading cause of death and not the fourth leading cause of death that would still be
enough presumably to justify a more systems-based approach to the problem solving now i guess i will
say this it's a very different type of research and it's not really the type of thing that they've
mastered there's a well understood playbook for how you go from idea to grant funding cycle
results publications etc within the sphere of the type of research that they're currently funding
both translational and basic and clinical for that matter but this is different i don't know
i gotta be honest with you i don't come away from this discussion particularly optimistic
that either the system is going to get that much better or that an individual can do much to
protect themselves i feel like you or i if we're in the hospital with a friend or family member i
think we're lucky because we really know what questions to ask and we can probably reduce the
damage potential by a little bit not entirely i think back of the case of this woman who died
at vanderbilt i mean even if that was my grandmother it's unlikely i would have been in the
scanner with her i would have been waiting back in the icu there's nothing i could have done to
have prevented that mistake yeah and so that's what i'm kind of curious about is like where is
the innovation there what makes it impossible to give vacuum ronium to a person who is not
intubated that's kind of what i want to understand and you might say peter that's not the mistake
worth creating an enormous system around because that only occurred 10 times last year in the
united states we got to worry about the one that killed 50 000 people last year the movement is
formalized into a group called the institute for healthcare improvement which was started by don
burwick and he is a hero of patient safety he has spoken at every major medical center probably in
the united states talking about the culture of safety and all these issues we talk about safety
on rounds and now almost every hospital has a chief quality officer and their job is to oversee
these root cause analyses that's routine now for any sentinel event if the hospital is honest
which most are our hospital doesn't let things slip because they settled with a family who
had a 75 year old parent die in a scanner it doesn't matter where or when if there's a catastrophic or
sentinel event it's going to get a root cause analysis at johns hopkins i think that's the
case at most hospitals but to have a c-suite level executive focused only on quality and
safety within an institution i think that's progress i mean we're seeing now safety used
in a constructive way when we decide hey there's too many patients hanging out in the hallway and
broom closet in the emergency room that's not good for patient safety it is now part of that
conversation so i am a bit optimistic at the direction hospitals are also sitting on
tens of millions of dollars of surplus now every year many of them you know not half of the rural
hospitals and not all hospitals but what do you do with that money when you're a non-profit you've
got to reinvest it into something and so you're seeing more willingness now to invest in safer
technology and patients love it when they come into a hospital and they hear hey we do this this
and this for safety the fundamental problem in health care is that we have non-competitive
markets and the hospitals are competing basically on billboards and nfl advertisements and not on
quality and safety and so now with more public reporting that is starting to change when i wrote
unaccountable gosh 10 years ago it since turned into the tv show the resident i called for public
reporting of sentinel events and other infection rates and complication rates and readmission rates
and much of the medical establishment said no way this absolutely will never and should never
happen now we accept it nobody challenges or questions that we have public reporting of those
adverse events and when readmission rates became publicly reported guess what happened to them
they plummeted across the board because hospitals went to their doctors and nurses and said what do
you need to ensure that your patients don't bounce back after you discharge them and we started having
discharge coordinators and clear instruction sheets written at a sixth grade english level
so it's mixed in some areas we haven't made much improvement in other areas we do see
an army of people now dedicated to quality and safety that we never saw before well marty i guess
we'll be cautiously optimistic here but i really am as are i think many people in the medical
community deeply troubled by what took place in tennessee at all levels at the level of the nursing
board at the level of the hospital and certainly at the level of the da i think it's all a bad
precedent if your objective function is to improve outcomes none of this was in service of that yeah
it was a tragedy the silver lining is the groundswell of opposition to what happened to her is
encouraging and i hope people keep speaking up about this case yeah likewise all right marty well
thank you very much for this very last minute quick turnaround podcast that i thought was quite
timely great to see you peter thanks so much all right bye mark thank you for listening to this
week's episode of the drive if you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss we've
created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive content without
relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price of
the subscription now to that end membership benefits include a bunch of things one totally
kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic paper person thing we discuss
on each episode the word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these monthly ama episodes or
ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed
that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this the qualities which
are a super short podcast that we release every tuesday through friday highlighting the best
questions topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes of the drive this is a great way to catch
up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone steep discounts
on products that i believe in but for which i'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of
other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on if you want to learn more and access
these member-only benefits you can head over to peteratiamd.com forward slash subscribe you can
find me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id peteratiamd you can also leave us a review
on apple podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on this podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health
care services including the giving of medical advice no doctor patient relationship is formed
the use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk
the content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice
diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice
from any medical condition they have and they should seek the assistance of their health care
professionals for any such conditions finally i take conflicts of interest very seriously for all
of my disclosures and the companies i invest in or advise please visit peteratiamd.com forward
about where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies
so