Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hi everybody, welcome to episode two of five in the week of day spring.
This episode we cover lipoprotein basics, what's lipoproteins and lipids 101.
We talk about Goffman and the ultra centrifuge and how we came up with these whole ideas
of densities of lipoproteins.
We get into very specifics around the lipoprotein structure, their function and their metabolism.
We talk about how to measure the lipoprotein and the cholesterol content and what NMR is
and how it has changed the game a little bit.
We get into the distinctions between LDL cholesterol, LDL particle number and APO B. There is some
confusion here amongst physicians and presumably amongst patients.
So hopefully that will clear that up.
We get into the biochemistry of lipids and then we talk about sterols specifically as
a more broad category.
Now before we could measure anything to do with lipoproteins, if my memory serves me
correctly, it would have been the late 40s, very early 50s when the first assays were developed,
maybe it was 1951, that could actually just measure total cholesterol.
So you would take plasma from a patient, you would presumably in an assay break down all
of the lipoproteins and just aggregate the total amount of cholesterol and you would
yield that number which still amazingly shows up on a panel today.
You go and get a blood test and it might say your total cholesterol is 200 milligrams per
deciliter.
Am I correct?
That was the early 50s maybe?
No, I think they were analyzing cholesterol long before that because that's a molecule
you can take blood and dissolve whatever you got to dissolve and cholesterol appears.
So they had cholesterol measurements for a long, long time.
It's like the first lipid anybody could ever measure.
What you're talking about in the 50s is where John Hoffman discovered that, hey, wait a
minute, there are no lipids floating around in plasma because lipids are incredibly hydrophobic.
Your plasma is water.
You can't have lipids circulating in plasma.
So lipids obviously have to be within what I call water soluble lipid transportation
vehicles and that turns out of course to be a lipoprotein, a protein-wrapped collection
of hydrophobic and amphipathic lipids that just wouldn't be in your plasma unless they're
attached to a protein.
Peter mentioned albumin.
It's a protein.
So lipids can attach to albumin and be circulated around and other type proteins but albumin
is the most frequent protein in the blood.
So it serves as a carrier.
I think an albumin can carry like 17 molecules of cholesterol, a few of phospholipids too.
So it's a player out there.
We got a ton of albumin in our plasmas.
You'd be shocked to find out how much cholesterol is in it.
Not quite as much as in lipids.
Albumin is kind of an amazing protein.
It'll carry hormones.
It'll carry just about anything.
It's remarkable.
And it has everything to do with osmotic pressures and things like that.
So albumin is kind of an essential protein to say the least, performing many, many functions.
But when John Hoffman, a physicist by the way who had, physicists have been playing
with ultracenta fuge for a long time separating their radioactive particles and stuff, he
somehow wound up separating lipoproteins or saw things floating around in a centrifuge
test tube that he then identified as the lipoproteins.
So if you learn nothing else today, learn the first thing is lipids for the most part
go nowhere in the human body unless they're a passenger inside a lipoprotein.
Because if you believe there are a lot of lipid associated diseases, and I certainly
believe atherosclerosis, you cannot have atherosclerosis without a starol and lipid being in your arterial
wall.
And I know that arterial wall didn't over synthesize starols, creating a starol buildup.
Somebody had it delivered of starols there.
And that of course turns out to be a lipoprotein.
One of the places a lipoprotein should never deliver starols to, to any serious degree
of course is your arterial wall intima.
So being a Jersey guy, one of my standard jokes on a lecture circuit was atherosclerosis
is just the evidence of illegal dumping where a lipoprotein instead of bringing lipids to
wherever it's supposed to be bringing it was bringing starols to the arterial wall.
And over decades, you got a problem.
You know, it could do it for a few days, six months, you're not going to die of atherosclerotic
disease.
So when did it become clear?
So Hoffman figures out by first principles basically, he imputes that there's got to
be something that is transporting this very, very hydrophobic molecule through plasma.
It doesn't, you know, I mean, it's easy in retrospect to make light of what an observation
that is, but the next observation would be it would lead to be spherical.
Right?
I mean, it's to optimize the volume in which you could transport.
It would have to be spherical.
You're a mathematician, a volume of the sphere, the third power of the radius.
So if you're going to devise a transportation vehicle, a sphere is better than a flatbed
truck, you know.
So how long was it until, I mean, I know the answer to this question, but I just have to
sort of tee it up.
Who then went on to figure out these things occur in different densities?
It's not just one.
There's not just one spherical molecule that's transporting these things.
This is a beautiful story, right?
It was Hoffman.
He noticed that they're, and they weren't calling them April B and April A, they weren't
particles at the day, but they were different densities.
They were gigantic.
So explain what you mean by density because this term, you know, we talk, everyone knows
low density, low proton, high density, low proton, but tell me where that terminology
actually came from.
Well, I think it has to do with water has a certain density.
So it's whether things float in water or sink in water.
We know rocks sink if we throw it in a pond, so they're very dense things.
Whereas other things float on top of water.
They obviously are less dense than water is.
So everything is relative to water there.
So if you establish what you think is the density of water, things that float.
So when he separated these things in a centrifuge, the lipoproteins or these fatballs that didn't
move at all were obviously very buoyant.
Some sunk just a little bit.
So they were less buoyant, but still pretty buoyant.
And some went right to the bottom of the test tube, obviously incredibly dense.
And it turns out what makes a lipoprotein buoyant is a ratio of its lipid fat content.
Cause I think we all know fat floats on water or proteins check out the molecular weights
of proteins really heavy.
They sink, so they're the rocks.
So your density of a specific particle here, lipoprotein particle is going to be related
to its lipid content versus its protein content.
So our big monsters that are delivering, as I told you, triglycerides, but have a lot
of phospholipids on their thing, they have some proteins, but they have so much lipids
they float.
They're the buoyant ones.
And as they lose the lipids, they become smaller.
They might lose a few proteins as they shrink, but they're really using the lipids.
But they're fundamentally concentrating protein as they get smaller.
Because when you go from chylomicron, even though they're not the same lineage, so I
want to be very careful, you'll explain this in detail.
You do not go from a chylomicron to a VLDL to an IDL to an LDL to an HDL.
There are three separate lineages I just described.
But in size, they loosely track as the smaller they get, the more they've concentrated protein.
Within every category of lipoproteins, you talk chylomicrons, which intestinally produce
VLDLs, hepatic produce.
And the classic teaching is as VLDLs become smaller, you call them intermediate density
and low density, we now know the liver can produce an LDL without making a VLDL first.
High densities which form themselves in the things sort of go the opposite way, whereas
the VLDLs and Chylos come out as big fat monsters and lose lipids and become smaller and denser.
The HDL as it gathers lipids becomes bigger and more buoyant.
But within every class of lipoproteins, you're going to have a heterogeneous range of densities
from big species to small species.
And this is why to me, I like to tease because you always hear people talk about the small
dense LDL.
Within every lipoprotein classification, the smaller particle is always more dense than
the, so that's a redundant thing.
Just tell me dense LDL, just say smaller.
I know it has to be dense or if it's dense, I know it has to be small compared to its
sister particles within that family or so.
Somehow small has only been applied more frequently to LDLs because that's the killer one or HDL
is, oh my god, you want to have the big HDLs.
Another joke that's turned out, but for a long this while, if you don't have big HDLs,
you're in big trouble or so.
And if you've got the small LDLs, you're in the biggest trouble.
That basically turns out to be because if you have small LDLs, you need a ton of them
to carry whatever your lipid load is.
So you've got a super high LDL particle concentration if you have small LDLs.
And that's more related to its pathology per se than the size, not that that won't
cause certain functional characteristics of the LDL.
But the LDL, the kylos come out big and they shrink.
Now the reason though that differentiate kylo microns and the LDLs, IDLs and LDLs is they
have a lot of apoproteins on their surface, which they do lose as they shrink.
But there's one protein they never lose and it's the one that has the most massive molecular
weight, apo-hyperprotein B. So that's why they are never going to be as dense as an
HDL particle because an HDL doesn't have this monstrosity high molecular weight, APoB, on
it.
It's got other things, far less lipids.
But to some, the LDLs, IDLs, VLDs are always going to be way more buoyant because they
do have a little bit of an anchor on them, creating titter densities that APoB.
And it's the only, as you study apoproteins, there are probably up to 20 to 30 of them
now, all of which have certain functions that it sort of directs a lipoprotein down which
path it's going, a catabolic path.
The only apoprotein, by the way, get definitions out the way, apoprotein, apolipoprotein, lipoprotein.
An apoprotein is the protein your cell makes.
Once it binds two lipids, it's called an apolipoprotein and of course the whole particle itself is
called a lipoprotein.
So let me re-synthesize that.
The lipoprotein is the spherical structure whose membrane is made up of mostly these
phospholipids but also other lipids.
The apoprotein is the thing that kind of gives it its signature.
So for example, the chylomicron has a B48, the IDL, VLDL, and LDL have a B100, etc.
That's just called the apoprotein.
Once the apoprotein, and I assume it's covalently bound to the lipoprotein, that becomes the
apolipoprotein.
And we abbreviate that apo fill in the blank.
Yeah.
So if I took a VLDL particle and later on I'll tell you, boy, on a VLDL you're going
to find apo C1, apo C2, apo C3, apo A5, and including apo B. But it's going to lose everything
but apo B as it's transferred.
It'll lose most of the other ones because they're transferable.
They can jump on different lipoprotein if they so desire to.
Apo B never does.
For a bunch of reasons, it provides the structural integrity to that particle throughout its
existence.
But apo B turns out to be the ligand for receptors that internalize those particles when your
body don't need them anymore.
So the LDL receptor that everybody knows about-
So the ligand just for some people listening, it's like the key that fits into the lock.
If the receptor is the lock, the ligand is the key.
In biology, that's sort of how everything works.
The key has to fit the lock.
Correct.
And if it didn't, then that lipoprotein is going to stay in your plasma and probably
wind up going somewhere where it's going to create a pathological state.
So when was it figured out that apo lipoproteins are going to come and go, but there's one
of these ones that not only always stays, but you have one?
Because that's a big deal, the realization that apo B100, if you knew that concentration,
you had a proxy for how many particles you had.
Yeah.
So Goffman certainly figured out there were proteins involved here, but he wasn't applying
that nomenclature to them and everything.
Guys who further, a few years further down the road, Fredrickson, Levy and Lees started-
We've talked about those with Ron Krauss.
I never realized there are some very important structural and functional proteins on these
particles that we better start investigating and giving names to.
So their research led to the identification of all them.
And ultimately, I mean, we know now the amino acid breakdown of every darn apoprotein that's
in our body or on our particles and everything.
So it just, when one research invents a little bit of the story, other ones pick up the pieces
and start further elaborating on it with different studies and technology improves and some of
these things that were not a saleable at one point become that you can measure them and
identify their structure and everything.
So it's one of these evolutionary things.
And it just made such perfect sense too, because we knew these particles are changing.
So they're undergoing catabolic processes.
Why? What's doing that?
And then all of a sudden you figure out that these ligands, these apoproteins are keys to
various receptors.
Some of those receptors pull the particle next to where the expression of a lipid dissolving
enzyme or lipase.
And it starts to all make perfect sense to you.
So over time, we've identified numerous of these enzymes that can catabolize lipoproteins,
numerous of the receptors that temporarily bind these particles in place so they can
undergo this thing.
Is that lipidate fill the particles with the lipids or delipidatum?
So if you're listening to this and you're confused at this point, it's okay.
One, there's going to be killer show notes, but more importantly, we're going to take
a step back now.
I'm a guy listening to this.
I'm a girl listening to this.
All I know is every time I go to the doctor, he or she gets a blood test and it spits out
the following.
Total cholesterol equals this.
LDL, and they won't even, it'll be worse.
It'll say LDL equals this.
HDL equals this.
Triglyceride equals this.
And maybe it will say non-HDL equals this.
What do those things mean in relation to everything you just said?
Yeah.
First of all, the misinformation on labeling lipid metrics is one of the things that Miracle
hasn't given me a stroke yet.
I do a lot of peer review.
I'm going to, I want to associate editors.
That's why we're fasting you, Tom.
Journal of clinical lipidology, and I will reject a paper instantly that uses improper
lipid metrics.
Don't tell me your, the LDL is this because LDL is a low density lipoprotein.
It's not a laboratory metric.
You want to tell me what the LDL cholesterol is, the LDL particle number is, the lipidomics
of an LDL is the LDL oxidizer.
Not great.
We do have assays that will measure that.
So let's please all you.
Identify yourself as an ignoramus.
And like I've told this to many of the top lipidologists in the country who lecture,
stop telling people what's your LDL.
Ask them what is your LDL cholesterol?
What's your, if we don't all talk the talk, you're never going to understand the process.
So this patient almost assuredly is talking about total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol,
HDL cholesterol, and non-HDL cholesterol.
Yeah.
So I'll give you a quick, and by the way, Peter did mention something very quickly before
I just wanted to expand and he talked about, hey, APOB100, APOB48.
APOB is a giant structural, non-transferable, APOProtein that's on chylomicrons or VLDLs.
The intestinal machinery that synthesizes a chylomicron makes a certain type of APOB
and the APOB that is made in the liver makes a much bigger APOB.
It has a higher molecular weight.
So they knew the APOB that's being made in the intestine is much smaller.
So it turns out to be that the APOB in the intestine is 48% of the molecular weight of
the hepatic-produced APOB.
If you get into genetic APOB, you'll see APOB31 that has 31% of the molecular weight
of what's considered a normal APOB.
So when you hear APOB48, that should identify it as an intestinal-produced APOB particle
and a liver would be an APOB48.
And LDLs that come out of the liver should have APOB100 on it like the VLDL or VLDL,
it becomes an LDL, the APOB100 is still there or so.
Just keep, if you hear 148, what does that mean?
It sort of tells us the origin.
We are going to be talking about nuclear magnetic resonance and one of the parameters that used
to give you a lot on, less so nowadays, is VLDL particle concentration.
When you analyze the lipoprotein using nuclear magnetic resonance, it cannot tell the difference
between a chylomicron and a VLDL because NMR doesn't measure the proteins.
It's hey, that's a very big particle, so it has to be a VLDL or chylose.
Most of your big particles are VLDLs.
But if you're fasted.
Yeah, and even in a postprandial state, chylomicrons have half-lives in minutes, they're gone.
So the vast majority of VLDL particle number via NMR is still VLDL part of it.
There could be some powers in it.
All right, but I want to go back to our lady.
So her total cholesterol is 190 milligrams per deciliter.
So total cholesterol, remember my premise that lipids go nowhere in the body unless
they're within a lipoprotein.
It's not exactly true, but for today's purposes, that is true and certainly understanding lipid
metrics, that's true.
So total cholesterol would be the laboratory has separated all your lipoproteins from the
serum and they're take how much cholesterol is in this serum tube.
So where would that cholesterol be that they're analyzing?
Well, it would be found in, if there were any chylomicrons there that were hanging around
or maybe they didn't fast, some of it would be chylomicron cholesterol.
Some of it would certainly be VLDL cholesterol, a lesser amount because there's just so many,
so fewer of them would be intermediate density cholesterol particles.
And the rest would be in either LDL particles, low density lipoproteins or the high density
lipoproteins.
There are other types of LDL particles called LpA, which we'll talk about.
So total cholesterol is all of the cholesterol.
It is every single lipoprotein that's in a deciliter of your plasma.
And that is directly measured.
It is not computed.
That's an assay.
That is not a calculation.
That is assayed.
Anyway, there's always a coefficient of variability.
That's inaccurate.
And so if you want to use cholesterol for anything nowadays, because let's face it,
that was the first parameter looked at in the epidemic.
And they certainly correlated total cholesterol levels with the risk for heart disease.
But think about what I just told you.
It's the cholesterol within all the lipoproteins.
What is the, if you counted particles, what is the most numerous particles in your bloodstream?
The ApoB particles.
Well, actually the HDLs are more, but they're so small they don't carry much cholesterol.
So most of your, if you want to put a parentheses around it, atherogenic cholesterol would
be within your ApoB particles.
So if you want to ascribe any use to total cholesterol, it's a real poor man's ApoB
level.
In general, most people with very high total cholesterol levels will have a very high ApoB
That's the real reason they're at risk for atherosclerosis, because those are the particles.
Yeah.
I mean, the original epidemiology basically said, you know, you have to sort of applaud
them for doing the best they could with the tools they had, but let's take total cholesterol,
which is at the time, the only thing we could measure clinically.
Let's take the patients who were in the top 5% and the patients in the bottom 5%.
Was there a difference in their risk of MI?
And the answer was yes.
Correct.
It could be another at least decade until Framingham.
This is kind of an interesting story, right?
Part of the story got ignored in Framingham was that low HDL cholesterol and high triglyceride
turned out to be four times more predictive of MI than high LDL cholesterol.
And again, this is still crude measurements, but that sort of didn't come back into, people
didn't come back to try to explain why that might be the case until Jerry Reivan had sort
of done his work on metabolic syndrome.
But I also realized I'm going to get us off topic.
I want to go back to this other question.
So we've just explained what 190 milligrams per deciliter means.
When it says HDL, it really means HDL cholesterol as evidenced by the units.
So those will either be measured in millimole or milligrams per deciliter.
That's a direct assay or an indirect assay.
Yeah.
So Framingham, of course, did measure total cholesterol.
It was easily, they always did it.
They measure triglycerides too, although they really had no clue what they, where they
related to us, but it was measurable glycerides.
They called it glycerides back then.
And they did have a direct assay for HDL cholesterol.
They, you know, you could also measure, you know, you can centrifuge particles.
You can take out the LDL fraction and analyze how much cholesterol is in them.
That's theoretically the gold standard.
You can separate the HDL part, but that's too time consuming.
Nobody's got ultra centrifuges.
So to have real world tests, chemists had to develop direct assays.
So HDL assays were developed real early on.
So Framingham could not only measure total cholesterol, they could measure, directly
measure, not calculate HDL cholesterol.
What they could not measure, and it took a long time, was LDL cholesterol.
Without ultra centrifugation.
Without ultra centrifugation, correct.
In the 70s, somebody came up with a formula that here's a way of at least estimating
or calculating LDL, which took fire because by the 70s, they realize the most numerous
atherogenic lipoprotein were the low density lipoprotein.
So as Framingham started calculating LDL cholesterol, they, whoa, this is the story here.
So they calculate.
So just to be clear, what they're doing is they're directly measuring total cholesterol
because you can just do that off serum.
They precipitate out the HDL, right?
So you could measure the HDL without ultra centrifugation and you could measure triglycerides.
So now the formula for estimating LDL cholesterol became total cholesterol minus HDL cholesterol
minus triglycerides over five.
Why the triglycerides over five?
Yeah.
So Friedel-Wahl put two and two together and realized, hey, total cholesterol is in essence
LDL cholesterol plus LDL cholesterol plus HDL cholesterol A equals B plus C plus D.
So if I know parameter A and I know parameter D and I know parameters, say I can figure
out what parameters C is.
And so what he did was he said, I'm going to ignore chylomicron and IDL and LP little
A. Well, LP little A was at that point probably being not even, it was being included in the
LDL.
Yeah.
They were basically counted as, the, the collos are counted as VLDLs and the IDL is counted
as LDL.
Okay.
So therefore if I know the HDL cholesterol and I know the total cholesterol, if I only
knew VLDL cholesterol, I could easily calculate what your LDL cholesterol was.
So then it becomes, you have to know what is a VLDL particle.
And at least if you have a physiologically normal VLDL particle, most of those lipids
are in the core of the particle.
No triglycerides on the surface, no cholesterol ester on the surface.
If I only knew the composition of these particles, I could figure out.
So they came to the realization that on average a physio, at least in the 1970s, a VLDL particle
composition had five times more triglyceride than it did cholesterol.
And virtually in a fasting state, all of the triglycerides are not in HDL.
They're not in LDL.
They're not measuring column icons because you're in a VLDL.
So cholesterol in a VLDL has to be triglycerides divided by five because there's one fifth
as much cholesterol in a VLDL particle.
So VLDL cholesterol is triglycerides divided by five.
So now if I have HDL cholesterol, VLDL cholesterol, total cholesterol, you do the math, you're
a mathematician, Peter.
It's very easy to, aha, this is what your LDL cholesterol is.
Even as they calculated that and they applied it to clinical trial data, correlations are
very, very good.
And they knew that's probably where the money is because of our APOB particles, the particles
that are the ones delivering these sterols to the artery wall, the overwhelming majority
of them, 95% at the lowest end, 90% are LDL particles.
It's where the money is.
We need a metric of LDL and the calculated LDL C was earliest introduction to that.
Now down the road, people have developed direct assays of LDL cholesterol.
But you know what, turns out it's not that much more accurate than the calculated VLDL
cholesterol unless as you start to go up, up, up in triglycerides, that calculation
falters.
Which is something we're seeing more and more of today than we saw in the original framing
him.
Dad who said, oh boy, if your triglycerides get above 400, don't use that calculation.
It's ridiculous.
So they actually developed a direct LDL C to give us an LDL cholesterol metric and people
with triglycerides of 800, 1200, 4,000 where now you know what their LDL cholesterol is.
Whereas the formula would be useless there.
We now know that formula starts to become kind of erroneous at somewhere between a trigger
150 and 200 and the higher you go above 200, be careful with a calculated LDL cholesterol
and rely on direct LDL C.
And here's what nobody realizes.
The only value that calculated or directly measured LDL cholesterol brings to the table
is it's a better poor man's estimate of your LDL particle concentration than is total cholesterol.
So an LDL cholesterol would correlate better with APO-B or LDL particle concentration than
would a total cholesterol.
Down the road a little bit we've come to the realization that if we get another calculation
called non-HCL cholesterol that even better correlates with APO-B or LDL particle concentration
than does LDL cholesterol.
So that's why that's the new thing that's involved.
We also, thanks to your, I know you spent a little time down in Hopkins, some of the
lipid guys down there have invented a much better calculated LDL cholesterol, which they're
trying to get incorporated rather than the older calculation, the Frito-Wald that we've
been using forever and most labs entirely use nowadays or so.
So NMR, which is, you know, my first exposure to NMR was in high school when we were taking
organic chemistry and you learned that we had these tests.
I still remember how fun these tests were where they would show you an NMR spectroscopy
and you had to figure out what the molecule was by knowing where those spikes were.
So was Jim Otvos the guy that first figured out that you could use that stuff to actually
count the number of these APO-Bs?
Yeah, I think Otvos was certainly one of the early pioneers and over father time, the real
pioneer who evaluated lipids and lipoprotein using nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy.
He knew that lipids would emit specific spectral signals that he could analyze and through
very complex mathematics, turn them into a variety of lipoprotein metrics, including
you can do an NMR LDL cholesterol level and LDL triglyceride level.
In the future, that's one of the ways we're going to be measuring phospholipids on various
lipoproteins is NMR spectroscopy because as Peter says, every lipid has a different
spectral signal and if you know what you're doing, you can look at a spectral signal and
know what its molecular composition is and everything.
So Jim turned it into, you know, as we had all these lipid metrics that we're talking
about, cholesterol, even triglyceride metrics, deep down the guys know these are just poor
man's way, easily assayable ways of quantifying lipoproteins and it's a quantification that
matters in many cases or so.
So we have, it turns out in the long run, it's the number of APO-B particles that primarily
is what forces it into the artery wall, very little L, I mean, or other factors, but that's
the number.
But when was that pathophysiology first stumbled upon that it even mattered how many of these
particles you have versus, so let's just take out the estimates and let's assume that
you have the ability to measure the total cholesterol concentration within an LDL particle,
which is what's showing up when someone gets a blood test and it says direct, when it says
LDLC direct, that means they've actually measured it.
So now it's better than Friederwald's estimation, but that's different from if you have an NMR
where it says LDL-P nanomole per liter and that's counting the number of those particles.
So one is the number of particles, the other is the amount of cholesterol contained within
them.
We'll get to what a revisiting of Mesa and Framingham made unambiguously clear, which
is one of those predicts better than the other.
But was that really the realization that it was a gradient driven process by number or
was that understood beforehand or at least hypothesized beforehand and then more verified
by the experimental evidence?
No, early on they discovered it was the ApoB particles going into the artery wall and delivering
these sterols and everything that set off this maladaptive inflammatory process that
led to a whole other area of investigation or so.
So the particle number data came once they sort of identified a way of assaying particle
numbers and they almost evolved that this maybe ApoB came a little bit first, but then
Jim Opphos' work on LDL particles came at the same time and it clearly became evidence
that ApoB is a better risk factor and remember there is one ApoB on every VLDL, IDL and LDL
but 95% of the ApoB particles are LDL so ApoB is just a way for the labs to report to you
what an LDL particle concentration is.
Opphos identified an LDL particle concentration using these methyl signals coming out of the
methyl groups that are on cholesterol, ester and triglycerides and phospholipids and translated
into a particle number that wow, either ApoB or LDL particle number correlates a lot better
with clinical events or the presence of atherosclerosis.
You'd have an event but if we do some imaging we see plaque in your wall then does the cholesterol
measurement per cell.
So it's not a surrogate of particle, they are particle measurements, ApoB or LDL-P. So
ApoB is an LDL particle metric.
What too many people get lost at, hey, VLDL particles are an ApoB particle so VLDLs are
part, there's no doubt that VLDLs can get in the artery wall and contribute to it but
it's like a minor.
The number of VLDLs that get into the artery wall are infinitesimal, the number of kylos
that get in are infinitesimal compared to the number of LDL particles.
So yet are all bad guys and a VLDL per particle have significantly more cholesterol molecules
in it than an LDL but there are just so many more LDLs that collectively the LDLs deliver
more cholesterol to that artery wall.
I'm going to go back and do one more.
ApoB by the way gives us no information on VLDLs, it's an LDL particle metric.
You can't use it for anything else.
So don't call me up and say my ApoB is high because I got too many VLDL particles unless
you have a rare lipid disorder where there are no LDL particles to type 3 this beta lipoproteinemia.
That's the only time an ApoB is measuring it's a VLDL measurement or a remnant measurement.
That's not an LDL measurement but in everybody else ApoB, LDLP those are the tests you need
because although they correlate very well with LDL cholesterol if they're both high
in a given person, that person's at terrible risk but as you well know and probably because
of the metabolic makeup of our existing humans at least around throughout the world now is
some people have very high ApoB, LDLP, very good LDL cholesterol, some people have high
LDL cholesterol, perfect ApoB, LDL particle counts.
When those metrics agree they're said to be concordant.
Hey use them both.
Either one will give you the same information but what happens if you get a patient where
they don't agree these metrics in virtually every single trial ever looked at the risk
follows the particle metric more than the cholesterol metric.
So the only way to know who is discordant with a cholesterol metric and an ApoB or an
LDL particle metric is to do both of them.
You could also say hey if I'm just doing ApoB or an LDL particle count I don't even need
lipids and I'd agree with you except I think there is value in knowing what a triglyceride
is for other reasons.
So that's the real key and if you ever go to a doctor and you're told I'm very happy
because your LDL cholesterol is normal say well so am I doc but by the way what was the
ApoB or LDL particle count and if the doctor didn't do it you demanded do it instantly
because otherwise you don't know your lipid related risk.
Yeah we're going to upset a lot of doctors here because I've already and you've already
been in the business of that where people will hear you talk or something or read something
you've written or something I've written and they'll go to their doctor and say hey
I want my LDL P or my ApoB and the doctor says that's nonsense you know fill in the
blank TBD blah blah blah blah blah and it puts patients in an awkward position.
I mean I really feel bad about this because especially on depending on what country they
live in at least in the United States I think anybody can go to lab core directly and get
the assay without a physician's prescription but it upsets me I think the patients even
have to do that it upsets me that something that is such an important metric.
I would list LDL P as one of the five most important metrics I've talked about this that
every patient should know their LDL P or ApoB and that that wouldn't be sort of fundamentally
a part of screening somebody for disease and that a patient would get into a position where
they're having to argue with their doc about that is disconcerting and look hopefully this
is sort of why I do these podcasts is I think it's just as much to help physicians say look
just because I didn't learn this in my training doesn't mean I don't need to sort of pick
it up today.
Amen and I'm sad there's so much what I consider inferior lipid care being administered by
healthcare professionals in the United States but there's nothing I can do about that is
try and teach them one at a time or expose my writings and other people's writings and
the data on this as much as I can and is tragic with public health problem number one or number
two that this is lag so far behind in part retarded by guidelines and third party payers
who just don't want to pay for different metrics and other reasons behind it but a big part
is they don't understand it.
You have had cardiologists call you up.
I have had being recognized as maybe in northern New Jersey one of the hey hey Tom you know
you told my patient that you know what I said about LDL cholesterol doesn't matter
because you've done an LDL particle and you put you know not everybody believes that or
they give you some horseshit like that.
I said I'm on my desk hey doctor would you like 200 manuscripts delivered to your desktop
tomorrow I'll do it if you promise me you'll read them every single so you know it is what
it is.
I think the internet is help people in certain ways I think the internet is confuse people
in a lot of ways too because there are people out there who what we just talked about it's
pretty much fat who become deniers of the particle concentrations because whatever else
they're exposing as their way to cure heart disease somehow aggravates LDL particle count
they just choose to ignore it and look are there people with high LDL particle counts
who don't somehow yeah they're out there but the overwhelming amount of literature
says the odds or if you keep this for 20-30 years you're going down until somebody does
a serious study showing there are people who can escape this you're playing with fire to
ignore an elevated LDL particle count APOB I don't have a way of identifying who who
might have a high metric there is somehow protected against atherosclerosis.
Well I have lots of thoughts on this myself but and maybe we'll come back to it but I
and I think we've gone back and forth we had this fun email string a while ago with you
Ron me Alan I think Josh Knowles was on it as well where we just you guys were the first
people to be exposed to my new model which is the necessary but not sufficient sufficient
but not necessary neither necessary nor sufficient causalities because you can actually have
causal metrics that fit each of those buckets but we'll we'll digress and come back to that
I want to go back to one semantic thing you use the word sterile a lot I'm very comfortable
with it I want to make sure the listener knows the difference between a sterile a stan all
a zoo sterile a phytosterol we're gonna I think we're gonna touch on this later so let's
just hammer out the semantics right well cholesterol of course is the molecule we all fare because
it's been drummed into our head that cholesterol in an arterial wall is where what is plaque
it's a cholesterol core and that cholesterol can cause impaired vascular biology resulting
in clinical events so what is cholesterol and we certainly in Peter's notes here you're
gonna have pictures of the cholesterol structure and it's got four rings it's an aromatic compound
and off the fifth ring is a little tail sticking out which is a carbon chain so the precursor
molecule is called the storane so you have the the rings the four rings and you may or may not
have this tail sticking off of the 17th carbon in the fourth ring so all of the bonds are saturated
that is called the storane so if you unsaturated one double bond in that storane it's called the
storane and if you then stick a hydroxy group on the third carbon in the first ring it's called the
storol it's an alcohol because you got a hydroxy group now sticking out hydroxy being OH oxygen
yeah excuse me correct so you'll see the pictures in my illustrated diagrams there and that little
tail that sticks out on the other end of the molecule has a lot to do with what exactly type
of storol that is and how it will function in a cell or in a cell membrane or so so cholesterol
would be this four ring structure three of the rings have six carbons in it the fourth ring has
five carbons in it you have this tail sticking off of carbon 17 it goes out and cholesterol that's
a totally saturated tail every bond in it is the saturated fatty acid and then on the three position
you'd have this OH group the hydroxy group by the way since OH is sort of soluble in water that part
of the cholesterol molecule is soluble in water whereas that carbon chain sticking out so pure
lipid that's all carbon that's not soluble in water so when cholesterol does exist in a surface
membrane like a cell membrane or lipoprotein it's it orients itself so the hydroxy group is sticking
out in that allopathic tail is sticking into the core of the particle or so now the cholesterol
it's in the middle of the particle oh that the hydroxy group can't be in the middle of the
particle that's water so they stick a really long chain fatty acid they replace the hydroxy group
with a long chain or really any chain fatty acid mostly it's a long chain so you a storified
cholesterol remember I told you attaching a fatty acid to something is called the stir so
cholesterol which is the active form of cholesterol that can be changed into a hormonal bile salt or
function in a cell membrane becomes a storage form of cholesterol or a lipid core transportable
form of cholesterol called cholesterol now it's YL it's not OL ester and we abbreviate that as CE so
free cholesterol is either going to be abbreviated as a C or an FC and cholesterol ester it's very
difficult if I wanted to if I'm an adrenal gland and I got some cholesterol ester stored and I want
to make a hormone because I need cluster I have to deesterify that cholesterol ester to free
cholesterol if the liver has cholesterol ester storage poles and it does and it wants to make a
bile acid it has to deesterify cholesterol ester cholesterol is stored in huge quantities
and fat cells as cholesterol ester and it would have to be deesterified to be utilized to do
something else or so one little story I'll just tell before we get to the stan halls and all the
other stuff is one of my prouder moments in front of Bob Kaplan was when you sent an email like this
a couple months ago you sent this an email and you said see if you can spot the error in this figure
and it was like a figure that had a million things on it and I was like oh I'm not getting up until I
figure out where the mistake is and sure enough somewhere in there it took me about 10 minutes the
illustrator had written because this was out of a paper something they had written cholesterol
OL ester instead of cholesterol YL ester and and and when I responded to you and you responded in
the affirmative I was like I've got my stripes and that figure he's talking about came out of one of
the productions for the company that I work for we develop educational pieces for physicians and I
obviously drew it in labeled it but you send it off to medical illustrator who formats it for the
PDF or whatever and cholesterol cholesterol and they make the mistake even though I sent in the
picture where it was properly labeled because I had a heart attack the first time I saw and we've
since changed that but somehow Peter got a hold of an older version or something that probably even I
sent out and didn't recognize initially but yeah so it is cholesterol ester anything that's
esterified becomes a YL so you'll see lipids this discussion illustrates one of the challenges of
lipidology which is I find this to be certainly among the two or three most complicated subject
matters I've ever tried to master and again no one masters anything in life I mean that's sort of
the beauty of this you haven't mastered this but this journey of trying to learn it I am constantly
humbled by how hard it is it's just so goddamn complicated well that's true especially you want
to take it to the nth degree but you need to invest yourself in some degree of education to
at least be competent in today's a world or so so you have to know some of this stuff well and
that's something you have to be willing to learn some of this chemistry I mean you have to steep
yourself in biochemistry and understand the because the significance becomes enormous one double bond
in one of these things completely changes its properties and not to say that that's not true
in general in biochemistry but it's much easier to talk about blood pressure or to talk about
elevated levels of uric acid or insulin or glucose without getting into that level of minutia it is
not possible to discuss lipids without that that is the problem with a lot of people are spouting
off on the internet and elsewhere but always they just don't have an understanding of the
complexity of how this all works and fits together and why what you just said is wrong
because there's something going on stoichiometrically that you haven't even considered or so to finish
the sterile so a steroid is a sterile it's got another keto group stuck on it some place look
at all the hormones you'll see a double bond with oxygen attached but a stan all is you take and
let's take cholesterol as a stan all or a sterile and remember cholesterol at the third carbons in
OH group there's a double bond at carbon 5 to 6 in their first ring and then there's that tail
at carbon 17 if I desaturated cholesterol the double bond at C5 and 6 disappears that's called
cholesterol cholesterol it's a stan all a stan all essentially a saturated sterile changes the
characteristics of that my cholesterol free cholesterol can be readily absorbed in your
intestinal wall stanels cannot be absorbed and it's kind of funny our liver to get rid of our
body to get rid of cholesterol but sends it to the liver the liver sends it through the bile to
the intestinal pool is free cholesterol and your intestines more than capable of just reabsorbing
that cholesterol that delivers trying to evict except our little friendly microbes down there
in the gut convert a ton of the biliaryx redo cholesterol into a stan all called cholesterol
or there's an isoform of it called coprosten al it's a stan all cannot be reabsorbed so you poop
it away and that's how the body gets rid of cholesterol it changes a lot of it to a stan all
anthropologists have been measuring specimens for coprosten all that tells them humans live there
because they find that in certain specimens and that human had to excrete it you know so a stan all
is simply a saturate that adds other applications because hey if stan all cannot be absorbed and I
would like to have a metric of whether you're absorbing cholesterol or not if I measured
cholesterol in your blood shouldn't be there to any appreciable degree because you can't absorb it
if it is elevated in your blood for whatever reason and we now know why your intestine just
absorbed that cholesterol and if it's absorbing cholesterol which it tends not to what is it
absorbing in humongous excess cholesterol so cholesterol serves as a biomarker of are you or
are you not or what degree of cholesterol absorption is going on in your intestines and
the last thing Peter did mention he said phytosterols he called it a zoosterol I call
it zoology so I call it a zoosterol so I don't know who's right on that I'm gonna go with your
right yeah I'm just gonna give you that and I do have a degree in zoology when I went to
college and I was one of my majors and you're wearing just so everyone knows you're wearing
your Rutgers t-shirt right now as well from college which is perfect I wouldn't be here without
the euro Rutgers that's medical school is inconsequential I learned everything in Rutgers
pre-med at least the biochemistry and the physiology anyway so phytosterols what plants
are full of stearls their cell membranes are not cholesterol those there are some plants that do
have cholesterol and most do not but they have stearls that if I show you here's cholesterol
and here's what's in this plant you would think you're showing me a lot of cholesterol but if
you look closely you'd see that tail that's coming out of carbon-17 is constructed a little
differently or wait a minute if there's another double bond in one of those rings in there so
it looks like cholesterol but it's close but it's really not and since it was made in a plant
collectively let's call them phytosterols but we hopefully all eat a few vegetables during the day
so you're eating phytosterols unless you're a total non you don't need any vegetables and they get in
even in other things even you're eating shrimp and stuff fishy phytoplankton and stuff so there's
phytosterols and bunch of foods but your body knows the only sterile I need to function is
cholesterol I don't need any plant stearls why would I want a human to ever absorb the plant stearl
they would get in a way could they even be toxic you know so evolution must have figured out they
were so evolution made sure our intestine did not absorb phytosterols why to me it tells me there's
a certain level of which phytosterols are toxic well this becomes interesting because I had a
disagreement with a physician recently who jointly takes care of one of my patients because
the physician wanted to put this patient on phytosterol supplements because this physician
became convinced that it was such an elegant way to lower cholesterol it turns out about 10 to 15
percent of people in whom you give massive doses of phytosterols you do indeed lower their cholesterol
this physician felt that was a good idea I felt otherwise for reasons you'll explain I'm sure and
needless to say after a long discussion we agreed to stop the phytosterols yes and again to me the
best argument with that is if your evolution thought we need a phytosterols your intestine
would be encouraged to absorb phytosterols if somehow they brought some miraculous property
to the human body that enhance survival you'd want them in there and everybody's now plants
carry a lot of great stuff we're only talking about the sterile it's in the plant the phytosterol
other ingredients in plants do get absorbed and probably are good for you but not phytosterols
well there's data to show that phytosterols on a per molecule basis are probably more
atherogenic than cholesterol there certainly is that data there but again the people who just
so focused on lowering LDL cholesterol don't even entertain it won't even look at it or you dismiss
it as nonsense you know and it's never going to be studied in a proper type of trial that you'd
have to study it in you know so and as Peter just hinted if you're not a hyper absorber of
sterols probably giving a phytosterol supplement is good because it does compete with cholesterol
firms so you will absorb less cholesterol and maybe that's one way of lowering LDL cholesterol
but I would say who cares but it you would get a little bit of APO B reduction in certain people
with that but if you're a hyper absorber I'm polluting your body with something that evolution
didn't want in your body why would I do that so I beg anybody who's a big advocate of supplementing
phytosterols please monitor phytosterols in the bloodstream that's how you identify oh my god
you're the one person I absolutely should not be given this to and I can send you a lot of data
Peter's talking about showing you phytosterol toxicity in humans and stuff so and when we say
someone's a hyper absorber I mean you and I have both written about this ad nauseam so we'll link
to it rather than get into a diatribe but we're basically talking about and your analogy is my
favorite I've always borrowed it outright stole it I'd hopefully I've always given you credit you
got a ticket taker in the bar Neiman pixie one like one transporter he lets everybody in if you
can fill in the door yeah he lets any sterile and if you can fit through the door you're coming in
but then you've got this ATP binding cassette g5 g8 and that's the bouncer that's the enforcer
that's the one who in theory probably informed by Alex are is making some sort of decision about
you're a good guy you're a bad guy you got to go you got to stay when someone is genetically a
hyper absorber is the quote-unquote defect more on the the ticket taker or on the bouncer turns out
that it's both because now when we talk about absorption let's face it there's a million molecules
that can be absorbed by your intestine we're talking about sterile absorption right now and
cholesterol is a key ingredient for human life so evolution not only gave every cell in your body
the wherewithal to synthesize cholesterol it allowed your intestine to absorb cholesterol
because it certainly didn't want any cellular deficiency of cholesterol which has nothing to
do with plasma cholesterol by the way you can have an LDL C of three and have perfect cellular
cholesterol metrics so as evidenced by the hyper functioning PCSK9 patients so this Neiman
pixi one like protein in our proximal intestine recognizes sterols and there's a sterile domain
on here that binds tightly to sterols but it binds most tightly to cholesterol because cholesterol
has that structure it has a less avid binding to a phytosterol and it has minimal binding to a
stan all now ultimately it'll bind to all of them but cholesterol gets the first preference to be
pulled into the enterocyte xenosterol as I call it rather than phytosterol xenon meaning other
star all a star all other than cholesterol I would get in secondarily and a stan all they get in but
at much less concentrations so now the enterocyte has this sterile you just absorbed now the
enterocytes position is I gotta get this to the rest of the body so I have to take this sterile
and put it in a chylomicron that I'm gonna make or I could also efflux any sterile out to a baby HDL
that's looking for sterols I can lipidate an HDL so that's how sterols get out of the intestine
or the intestine can say we don't need any more sterols I'm getting rid of you and that's where
the bouncer comes in so these ATP binding cassette transporters ATP binding cassette transporters are
a sterile efflux membrane transporter so and this is important to distinguish because and again it
might be confusing but the diagrams will make it easier there's two effluxes you've referred to
there's an efflux on luminal side and then an efflux back into the body both of them are leaving
an enterocyte one ends up leaving the body if it goes out the ATP binding is that it's going into
the lumen it's being excreted with stool if you efflux on the other side of the cell into either
the chylomicron or into the HDL you're actually putting it right back into circulation and that
is such a crucial point here I'm glad you elucidated on that more so yeah remember we're talking about
the enterocyte like the liver and enterocytes have a lot of things they can do with sterols
so they can get rid of it or they can even use it remember enterocytes have cell membranes they
need some cholesterol for their own cell membranes and everything so they can ship it out a body needs
cholesterol in a chylomicron they can lipidate in HDL or they can return it to the lumen of the gut
where it'll go out your rear end so these abc g5 or ga transporters as you're called then it's a
heterodimer so you have one of each well efflux and they also have different affinities so unlike
the neem and pic which really wants cholesterol to come in less so phytostarols and not so stanols
which tells me evolution didn't want those other products in your body the abc transformer or
exporters they number one evict phytostarols first that's another evolutionary happenstance
to me that tells me the body evolution didn't want phytostarols in your damn body because why is it
giving you a phytostarol efflux protein in your intestine and the liver has it too just in case
a phytostarol ever makes it as far as the liver it gets evicted back to the bile it'll go back to
your intestine so second in line for exportation would be a stanol and third would be cholesterol
so your ability to absorb cholesterol is a happy working relationship between the expression of
your neem and pic c1 like protein and your abc g5 ga transporters so technically if you even had a
good normal degree of absorption but you couldn't evict any storals because you got a
loss of function of an abc g5 or g8 you're going to be a hyper absorber because then the only way
those storals can get out of the anthracite is in a column micron or in an HDL and by the way when
you do measure these phytostarols in the blood people it's like when you measure cholesterol in
the blood do you understand i've already told you where that cholesterol man it's the cholesterol
within all the lipoproteins so if i'm measuring cytosterol stig masterol campesterol which are
some of the names of the 50 phytosterols that are in our plant products what am i measuring
well since the vast majority of lipoproteins are LDLs i'm measuring LDL cytosterol LDL cholesterol
like i'm measuring LDL cholesterol so you're measuring there but god forbid that particle
invades an artery wall the sterols go with it and one last intriguing part of this story which
better put the fear of god of phytosterols into you that evolution didn't want it in
so it gave you a protein that will not absorb phytosterols if it's working right it gave you a
protein that immediately vix phytosterols but for any storol to go in a column micron what does it
have to be a storified how does the intestine storify cholesterol into cholesterol ester which
is what makes up a giant part of the core of a column micron there's an astarifying enzyme
acyl cholesterol acyltransferase a cat guess what is the favorite ligand for a cat cholesterol
guess what is not a favorite ligand for a cat phytosterols so they you just don't astarify
phytoster which retards them getting into your body and you know the real way to get in
that abca1 efflux transporter which is what lipidates a baby HDL parto it's not abcg5g8
abca1 exports storols into baby HDL and just for the listener again you're saying abc what you're
saying is ATP binding cassette so when they hear you say abc that's what you're referring to it's
an energy driven process so some of that phytosterols you're measuring in the blood are in HDL
particles also so that's the way they get in and i always make and you'd have to do a study improve
it we're going to be talking about HDL dysfunction suppose i measured phytosterols in your HDL and
it's very high it's probably a type of dysfunctional HDL particle you know so there's all sorts of
intriguing it would also you know not to get too esoteric but that would also suggest enterocyte
dysfunction because the enterocyte should also quote unquote know better that that's not the
direction of efflux i want it is but it's relying on the abcg5g8 to efflux it then it wouldn't even
get to an abca1 to efflux it on the other side and a cat is not going to starify it if it's all
being evicted really very little it would wind up being a starified and the last part of this
puzzle as peter thought you have a gut lumen side and you got a plasma side or a lymphatic side
which is where kalamikrons exit we probably talk about it somewhere today is this crazy process
they used to call reverse cholesterol transport which is another one of these idiotic terms that
should have disappeared a long time ago at least if you think it's mediated by solely by HDL high
density lipoproteins that's the part that's got to change a big pathway of how does the body get
rid of cholesterol we're all told oh it brought it back to the liver and the liver will get rid of
it in a certain way guess what a ton of it is just brought directly right back to the intestine
and the cholesterol in the particle or the particle itself finds its way into the enterocyte
through and then the enterocyte has another supply of sterols all of a sudden that it didn't absorb
and so what it then will do with that sterile what it wants it can efflux it through abc g5g
into your gut lumen and you can poop it away so the process of a lipoprotein or some other
trafficker albumin red blood cells bringing cholesterol back to the small intestine bypassing
the liver gets right out into your stool is called trans intestinal cholesterol efflux abbreviated as
tice and it's a major reverse cholesterol transport pathway now do we have a sense because
we're going to talk about direct and indirect rct in a moment i think that might as well this is
as good a foray into that as any do you have a sense of how much cholesterol is being reverse
transported so to speak through tice versus the sum total of direct and non-direct reverse
cholesterol transport yeah this has been studied even dynamically but you know the real small
studies and it probably varies individually depending on the complexity of your lipid and
lipoprotein transportation systems or so some in some people it's probably 20 percent and other
people it's been reported as high as 60 percent so it varies a lot but it's a major player it's not
this infinitesimal minor baby pathway that's inconsequential except in some rat in a laboratory
or something it's this has been proven in humans now they're i just read it's part of the review
process and a really cool article coming out in a journal clinical lipidology where because of some
biliary surgery the guy had the only way cholesterol gets out of this person's body was through the
intestine and he did so he shows you the body can get rid of cholesterol without a biliary system how
many articles do you review a year there's two things when you're an associate editor
the main editor will say here here's a submitted paper do you think this is pretty good if so send
it out to four or five reviewers they will send their review to you and then you make your decision
and send it to me and i'll make the ultimate decision but then also i'm also just a reviewer
where another associate editor would say i think tom knows a lot about this subject i'll ask him
would he please review this article to me so uh i don't know i probably get about 15 articles a year
where i'm the associate editor and probably double that where you're one of the reviewers are just
one of several reviewers or so but that's still about 50 papers a year that are coming across
and i am blessed at my stage of the game to have a job where i do have i don't have to see patients
anymore i'm not traveling throughout the united states a hundred times a year on flights doing
lectures here they're in everywhere so i am blessed in my current position or my true health
diagnostic peter probably when you hear this the first time you'll get a list of my who i work for
and who i don't that's the only company i work for nowadays and i'm their scientific academic
advisor so my job is to stay on top of the literature know all this stuff and explain it
so i have the freedom every day to spend time reading and edging and part of my education
anybody who's a reviewer or an editor with other you'll learn a lot doing that because i i don't
know everything that's sent to me for review but i'll sure as heck know where to go and get well
there's a small group of us that are very lucky we're having dinner with jamie underberg tonight
but you know jamie said there's like this group of like 10 people that you always send out the
most interesting papers to and about a year ago i had forwarded a number of these onto bob
caplin and he was like hey can you put me on this email too and i i mean we'll have to think about a
way for you to create a special group where because it strikes me that there's a broader
group of people who would actually like to get the once a week email from tom with the most
interesting lipid paper i've read this week yeah i think the best way of doing that is
somehow contacting me at dr lipid or so i mean you put a lot of this stuff out on twitter yeah
i do so you can research it but you don't get the commentary because your emails are sometimes so
great because what you'll do is you'll say look i know all of you aren't going to read this 12 page
paper here's like a 300 word summary of what you would learn and then that like for me to read that
then open the paper it's like it's quick and it's just the number one i really don't want to get
i don't know how many people listen to peter's podcast but it's immense i don't want 4 000 emails
to mars and there's two things as part of that email one would be my interpretation of something
which is fine that's day springs of no but maybe we can i can attach pdfs to it that i might to an
isolated friend yeah because of copyrights yeah yeah that's that's that's probably the bigger issue
that's part of an issue also so if it's open access great and if it is i've probably tweeted it and
you best bet and look people aren't afraid to ask me questions i mean a lot of them are asking
i and i ignore them but i will answer it my twitter followers no you're legitimate no
either direct message you yeah yeah all right so if i don't then uh there's a reason okay so let's
get back to the business of lipids here so we've done a pretty good job explaining one side of the
equation at how cholesterol is regulated a joe austerel would be cholesterol it's the only
sterile we the animal kingdom produces yes yeah yeah cholesterol is the joe yeah okay so the other
end of this regulatory pathway so we've described the reabsorption side pretty well there's a
synthetic side which you've alluded to obviously by making the statements that hey every cell in
the body can make cholesterol and most of the time it's sufficient for its needs obviously
exceptions well i'll let you explain what the exceptions are to that there are certain scenarios
and certain cells where they actually do need cholesterol from other tissues but let's just go
back to this synthetic stuff just briefly because i don't want to give anybody too much headache
how do we make cholesterol very complexly it's a multi-stage process 20 to 30 individual steps
where one molecule is changing into another into another and at the end of the day cholesterol is
made and it starts very small it's basically acetyl-CoA acetyl-CoA it's two carbon two carbon
chain molecule that keeps growing in length because cholesterol has 37 carbons in it so it has to grow
through much of that growth it's just a linear structure and at a certain point this linear
structure is long enough that it bends and changes into a sterile configuration lanoestral being the
first sterile that appears in the cholesterol synthesis chain by the way if i wanted a lab and
labs with liquid chromatography and mass spec could give you a lano cost a lano sterile
measurement and if it was up hey you're over synthesizing cholesterol that's not the one they
focus on they pick a more downstream a cholesterol precursor to do that but even you could pick some
of the earlier ones and they do serve as markers of cholesterol synthesis you know now the
cholesterol synthetic pathway is bifurcated tell me a little bit about that so once you
go through squalene and then that bends into a ring structure lanoestral has to become cholesterol
so lanoestral and there's cross talk between the pathways but it has one or two pathways that
it's going to go down and at the end of the day both pathways you'll wind up with cholesterol
and no good pathways don't come with names so they do what are the names of these pathways yeah
mr facetious yes well my favorite of course is the block pathway because if you die and i told
he was a twitter picture i put up recently he won the nobel prize for discovering this pathway
in cholesterol so it's probably important they give you a nobel prize for discovering this
pathway of cholesterol synthesis so the block pathway would be lanoestral goes through a lot
of precursors and becomes something called desmostral desmostral looks exactly like cholesterol
except in carbon 24 there's a double bond there's no double bonds in that tail that's on
the cholesterol molecule so if i just saturate that double bond and desmostral i change it into
cholesterol and of course there's a specific enzyme that does that if you inhibit can i guess it
yes if it's just so people can understand what these enzymes mean so i remember learning this
in in college all right so med school not college enzymes always end in ace right now you just told
me it was carbon 24 so it's it's probably going to have something to have it's going to have a 24
in there well and we often throw deltas into these things because delta denotes the position
of the bond and did you say that desmostral has a double bond at 24 and it has to be saturated
saturated so it would probably be something like a delta 24 saturate or desaturate correct all right
so that would be the enzyme so when you say that when you rattle that off it sounds crazy and
intimidating but it's logical right it is and this is why what you were talking about before
you really have to notice stuff or you might not be able and the presence or the expression or the
lack of expression at that enzyme is gonna are you going to use that pathway if you're using that
and you don't convert desmostral into cholesterol you're going to have a lot of desmostral in your
system are there consequences to that there's a human disease called desmostral or also instead
if it occurs in utero that kid ain't coming out alive or if he does he ain't living for more than
a few days and is that disease a genetic deficiency in the enzyme delta 2040 saturated it is yeah now
there's another pathway ln nostril doesn't and what determines what it is if you've got a double bond
at that 24 because it's going to go through that pathway now there's a ln nostril has another
pathway that goes through that's going to wind up with cholesterol and the pre-calorissoral the pen
ultimate as we call it the next to the last cholesterol molecule in that chain is something
called ln nostril some people call it lathe stearl i call it ln nostril l-a-t-h-o stearl and that is
called the canned dutch russell pathway obviously after the guys who discovered that by the way they
didn't get the nobel prize for some reason even though that was i think the nobel committee said
we already gave one of these things out and also that you can only have three people receive a
nobel prize oh so that would be two yeah so whatever everybody else i guess who worked in
blocks lab got no credit so but anyway uh so it's the canned dutch russell pathway so and it's kind
of interesting because in most people both pathways exist and there are some ways of jumping from one
pathway to another so at the end of the day you're going to make cholesterol or so but if you want to
start interfering with these pathways there are specific enzymes in each pathway that maybe that's
would be something you could play with or maybe if you're building too much of something there's a
lack of expression of that enzyme in you which maybe has consequences maybe it doesn't so it's
all important to know but some of this may be tissue specific one of the things i know it's a
big topic of yours and i hope we get into today is the brain everything i've talked about cholesterol
today that we're measuring in the blood has zero to do with cholesterol in the brain
cholesterol lipidology in the brain is might as well be in another different body it has nothing
to do with what the cholesterol is going on in the rest of your body the brain makes every
cholesterol molecule it needs and therefore there are no LDL particles delivering cholesterol to
your brain so again if with super aggressive and to be clear this is because the LDL particle
just doesn't fit through the blood-brain barrier correct even htls where a little bit of their
cholesterol might get into it's de-lipidated through these abc things and some of that might
work its way in inconsequential amount the apo b is i guess too big the brain doesn't make apo b so
but the central nervous system has to traffic lipids from brain cells to peripheral nerve cells
apo e is the protein transporter in the brain so cholesterol or any stroller is attached to apo e
in the brain and that's how it it traffics around there or so and again i got nothing to do with the
apo e that's involved with whatever lipoproteins are doing in your the rest of your body also
so just understand it but obviously i want to come this is such an important topic but i absolutely
want to come back because i'm glad you brought it up but that said at the moment i would love to go
back to the synthetic stuff so you've got each cell in the body can basically start with the most
simple carbon subunit which is a two carbon subunit acetyl-CoA and through a process of carbon
fixation go on to make these very complicated four-ringed structures they first and foremost the
cell uses these things they make the important part of the cell membrane and if anyone organelle
membranes and deposit that's right so everything from the Golgi apparatus to the ER to this movie
or ruffier etc you also you don't have to be i think a biochemist who look at a picture of a
molecule like cortisol estrogen testosterone and i think you could show a four-year-old
picture of those and then a molecule of cholesterol and they would be like hey those look similar
yeah it's like maybe i look like my mother and father or they did they have a an origin or did
they come from that so sure so certain cells can certainly transform cholesterol into reproductive
hormones or adrenal cortical hormones certain cells hepatocytes can transform cholesterol into a bile
acid i don't think there's any other cell that can change cholesterol into anything else so when
people talk about cholesterol metabolism there is no cholesterol metabolism it can be converted
into something in specific tissues but it can be excreted that's it there's no other way your body
can handle so do we is there any evidence that we use cholesterol for energy zero why there's no
energy is really coming out of the saturated the fats that have the most no double bonds that's
the most they're carrying the most ATP cholesterol is not producing energy cholesterol cannot be
metabolized and produce ATP in the process i mean to me that's the bigger issue right i think
some people get confused about this it's not that there isn't energy in a carbon-carbon bond or a
carbon-hydrogen bond because that's exactly what's being liberated in the metabolism of a fatty acid
the point is we don't have the enzymatic machinery to undergo the chemical process of breaking down
those bonds and liberating the chemical energy into electrical energy can't metabolize cholesterol
cholesterol ester which carries that fat can be de-esterified but your cells aren't making
cholesterol ester the liver is the intestine is but the adipocytes are my hypothesis for why that's
the case which could be entirely bullshit and i'm just making it up but it that's what hypotheses
are their guesses is that it would have been evolutionarily dangerous if we could have
metabolized cholesterol because in periods of fasting which we all did evolutionarily the last
thing you want your body doing is going after cell membranes and hormones as a source of energy so i
think it's actually a very deliberate design quote i use design in quotes to say hey no matter what
your cholesterol and your hormones are off limits during starvation and instead we evolved this other
remarkable pathway of ketosis which takes an ample substrate of fats and goes down the path of
metabolizing those and actually saving our muscle from the catabolic destruction that we would
undergo if we couldn't undergo ketosis this is the brilliance of peter it to me that he can
come up with what sounds like a super plausible thing see i'm not smart entirely bullshit so i
can tell you how to sell got cholesterol what it can do with it but he's figured out what sounds
like a really plausible reason and everybody's so worried about depleting cholesterol in the plasma
is measured by LDL cholesterol which has nothing to do with anything because actually there's more
cholesterol in your red blood cells than their own lipoproteins and you're not making that zero
by any means by using lipid drugs or something so but you can't deplete a cell of cholesterol beyond
a certain amount so you're going to scrub cellular function and you can't put too much cholesterol
in itself because it'll crystallize and kill that cell so that's why it's so tightly regulated
synthesis it influx and efflux now are there cells under certain circumstances for whatever reason
you can't make enough cholesterol yeah there there are pediatric disorders where if you don't
synthesize cholesterol things happen to you and utero well the other thing we see this in and i
didn't i don't even know why i started noticing this but this is one of the things i used to do
in residency that used to kind of piss off some of the attendings is i would do little experiments
and it was always a measurement experiment so it wasn't like i was putting a patient at risk other
than a few more milliliters of blood were being drawn but i remember once happening on a finding
which was maybe by accident i had checked a lipid panel on a patient in the icu and i saw
something interesting and i kept rechecking it in other patients over and over again i kept seeing
this which was anytime a patient was having a SERS response that's capital s irs systemic
inflammatory response syndrome so this is the vaso you know metabolic response to sepsis
infection trauma you name it enormous drop in hdl cholesterol and i think we could look at that
today and say it's very likely that what we were seeing was in that period of profound physiologic
stress the body is greatly ramping up its hormone production leukocorticoids and it's and others
and that would be one of the situations where cells were actually you know hdl was now delivering
cholesterol to the adrenal glands in a period of you know because that's about the most physiologically
stressful thing that an organism can respond to again i don't know if that's been documented but
it seems to me pretty logical that that would be a at least the most plausible explanation for why
hdl could plummet in patients who are going through that degree of stress yes and by the way it's the
reason you never do an all lipid profile in an acute situation because a lot of lipids are going
to be transiently changed or so here but peter's right we know this for a lot of reasons clearly
the your steroidogenic tissues need cholesterol to make their steroid hormones be they reproductive
organs or your adrenal cortex and in the situations peter's talking about cortisone is a pretty
useful hormone to have around or other mineralocorticoids and things like that are so so clearly
the those organs those tissues are going to need a lot of cholesterol pools to make all that
so they they turn up their synthesis rates so they make a lot of cholesterol
but they would also tune up their hey let's gather some exogenous cholesterol so to speak
so those cells would up regulate ldl receptors and that's a case where there's a tissue that
might under certain circumstances pull in ldl particles full of cholesterol ester they would
de-astarify it and use it but in a physiologic person who's not in one of these acute situations
the adrenal gland most of the time just makes all the cholesterol it needs but if it needs a
secondary source that's why you have hdl's hdl's have a half-life of five days one of the reasons
they circulate for five days is it's a floating plasma reservoir of cholesterol for tissues that
might actually need cholesterol now my nose cell that i talked about before doesn't need
hdl's or anybody else to deliver cholesterol to it no other cell does except those
steroidogenic tissues in other words to be really clear and specific you're sloughing off endothelial
cells in your nose every day well you have to replace them the lion's share of the cholesterol
requirement is to make a cell membrane it's just it has the machinery it has the machinery within
the nucleus to produce that just as it's producing other structural proteins right so and this is what
people just translate low cholesterol plasma measurements to think you're screwing up cells
throughout the body and you're not yeah this is one of the challenges that i've never come up with
a great way to explain this idea of flux which is you do a lipid measurement at a moment in time
you're getting a snapshot of what's in the plasma at a moment in time which doesn't give you two
pieces of information how is it changing over time and what's the movement or the velocity
and secondly it gives you no insight into what's happening in the cell
or what's happening in the endothelium for that matter and instead that's the nature of
lipidology is you have to be able to extrapolate to these other things by indirect measurements
it gives you zero insight the only usability of plasma measurements are as surrogates of
lipoprotein defining whether you have apo b apo a1 particles and we know too many apo b particles
your over time at big risk at increased risk for atherosclerotic disease or events
otherwise why even measuring lipids in the plasma tells you nothing and what we're talking about you
call it influxy flux and that nails it down but it's cholesterol homeostasis or sterile homeostasis
and your body has evolved a lot of ways to do interesting too and say that a crisis is going
on adrenal needs continued it's not just hey you're you cured yourself in 12 hours overnight
you survived whatever and if that catastrophic process was ongoing HDLs eventually would run
out of cholesterol you just said your HDL cholesterol level is plummeting and it's been
documented many times so the HDL all of a sudden has to go back and start grabbing
cholesterol molecules from some other tissue and get it to the steroidogenic tissue in the number
mega place where HDLs get most of their lipidation as it goes right back to the liver and gets
lipidated or what is the biggest cholesterol storage organ in the body not the liver your
adipocytes everybody thinks adipocytes are just stirring triglycerides they're a massive
storage organ so baby HDLs that are depleted they run back to the adipocytes which express
this ABCA1 transporter that pumps out all their cholesterol to an HDL which boom right back to the
adrenal gland bounces back and forth like a ping pong ball you can find all of this information and
more at peteratiamd.com forward slash podcast there you'll find the show notes readings and
links related to this episode you can also find my blog and the nerd safari at peteratiamd.com
what's a nerd safari you ask just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more maybe
the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week email where
i'll update you on what i've been up to the most interesting papers i've read and all things related
to longevity science performance sleep etc on social you can find me on twitter instagram and
facebook all with the id peteratia md but usually twitter is the best way to reach me to share your
questions and comments now for the obligatory disclaimer this podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine nursing or other professional health
care services including the giving of medical advice and note no doctor patient relationship
is formed the use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's
own risk the content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice
for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their health care professionals
for any such conditions lastly and perhaps most importantly i take conflicts of interest very
seriously for all of my disclosures the companies i invest in and or advise please visit peteratiamd.com
forward slash about