Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Hey Ben, well, wonderful to sit with you today and talk about a subject matter that, you
know, honestly, I think five, certainly 10 years ago, nobody would have a clue what we
were talking about. And yet today we get so many requests to go back and revisit this
subject matter. So again, delighted to have you here and look forward to talking about
something that, you know, probably impacts a lot more people than, than, than most white
might appreciate. So let's take a step back and give me a sense of where your interest
in this little lipoprotein LP little A came from.
So first Peter, thank you so much for the wonderful invitation. I'm really excited about
our discussion today. So I got involved in LPA research actually during my postdoc years.
I trained here at LaValle university in, in Quebec city, did some work in the field of,
of lipids looking at LDL particle size, triglycerides, ApoB, et cetera, on cardiovascular outcomes.
So that was in 2006 to 2009. And that was really at a point where not that many people
talked about LP little A because there had been so many negative studies on, on LPA and
the risk of cardiovascular disease like MI's and stroke and so on. And it's really the
genetic association studies that have kind of resurrected the field of LPA. And these
were published in 2009 to 2011. And that was during the time I was a postdoc in Amsterdam
and I was working over there with, with John Castellan. And he was working on the treating
to new targets trial, the TNT trial, which is the trial that one of the first trial that
have that show that if you reduce low density lipoprotein levels by increasing the statin
dose, you'll get an incremental benefit in, in cardiovascular outcomes. So we were working
on a bunch of sub analysis in the, in that trial. And they had just measured a whole
panel of emerging biomarkers that they thought was associated with that could be associated
with cardiovascular events like, like CRP, anti-pro B and P other markers, inflammatory
markers, other biomarkers of insulin sensitivity and LPA. And it turned out that of a huge
list of 18 biomarkers that they had measured in thousands of individual LPA was actually the
strongest of them that, that was predicting residual cardiovascular risk. So that was,
I think the first paper I published on, on LPA in, in those years. And at the time,
we were also wondering if there was any genetic variants that could explain a statin response,
because statin work well in, in most people, but there's a huge inter individual variability
in terms of LDL lowering associated with statin. So this is, this came at a time where genome wide
association studies were increasingly used and they were used to, well, they were first used to
identify genetic variants associated with specific diseases, but they were beginning to be used in
pharmacogenetic studies. So we were part of a big genetic consortium that was called the GIST
consortium. So genomic investigation of statin therapy. And it turned out from that big analysis
that LPA was the most important genetic risk factor for that explain statin response. So we
shown that if you have high LPA, then your LDL would be, wouldn't be lowered as much as if you
didn't have a high LPA. Well, we're going to talk about that in some detail, because right now,
I think many people will not understand exactly why that's the case, because they won't necessarily
understand the relationship between LDL and LPA and why what you just described is completely
intuitive today based on all the work that's been done in the last decade. But let's take a step
back into that epidemiology so that for the people who aren't familiar with LPa, we can give them a
sense of why this is such an important topic. So we'll start with an observation, right? So we'll
start with the epidemiology, which is elevated levels of this particular lipoprotein, which
occur in about what fraction of the population. So depending on ethnicity, actually, it can be
very high as, for instance, in individuals of African ancestry who have the highest level,
and all the way down to Chinese and Japanese that probably have the lowest levels. But
we can say like in the ballpark, that about 20% of the world population has an LPA level that puts
them in a higher risk category. So if we go down in time, LPA was discovered in 1963 by a Swedish
scientist called named Kerry Berg. And he was one of the first to show in the late 70s and at the
beginning of the 80s in different European cohorts that LPA was associated with cardiovascular events.
And LPA has been measured, was measured more probably more currently at that time in these
big epidemiology studies. The thing is, however, that the assays that they were using were probably
not the best. They were certainly not as good as they are today. There was a lot of variability.
And a lot of these studies published in the 90s and in the early 2000s came out negative.
So and that really was really tough for the field because nobody talked about LPA at that moment.
Tell people what you mean about the studies came out negative and what would negative with respect
to what hypothesis and why. The hypothesis was that high LPA was associated with
cardiovascular events like myocardial infarction, stroke, etc. So the hypothesis was that people
with higher LPA levels were at the highest risk and it turned out not to be the case in many, many
of those studies. And so we realized afterwards that the assays that had been used were probably
not very good. So the assays really did not correctly identify people with high LP little
A and I think this has to be attributable to the complex structure of lipoprotein little A, which has
in the LPA genes there's a copy number variation and the antibodies that are used against that
sometimes they can bind to different epitopes of LPA. And so now we have antibodies that are
binding to LPA on other regions. So we get a much better sense of the number of LPA particles in the
bloodstream. But back in the days, the assays that were used, they were overestimating the
isoform size that was bigger and they were underestimating the small LPA isoform size,
which is associated with high LPA. So a lot of research has been done on that and now we have
better assay. We don't have optimal assays now, but most of these problems have been solved.
And you can really see in the literature the interest on LPA that actually match this effect
because the LPA gene was cloned in the 80s by the group of Angelo Scannu at the University of
Chicago. And you can see it, if you just look at the PubMed search, you would see a straight line
from the 70s to the mid 80s. And when these studies came back negative, you would see the
number of PubMed searches would go down. And they came back up in 2009 and 2010 when
genetic association studies were beginning to be published. Because the great thing about genetic
studies is that you don't necessarily need to measure lipoprotein A level. So you can look at
genetic variants, at common genetic variants that are associated with diseases. And there were three
big studies published in 2009 that have very convincingly shows that genetic variants
associated with high LPA levels were tracking with cardiovascular events. And now we can see
the PubMed searches on LPA going back up again. And they haven't been as high as they are today.
Yeah, and we should make sure people understand some of the semantics. So LPA is the gene that
codes for apo-like-the-protein little a, which then binds to an LDL and then turns an LDL from
being just a garden variety LDL into an LP little a. And I think once people understand that it
becomes easier, I think, for us to communicate in this way. So I'm going to restate that. And I
really want everyone to understand this. So there's a gene, LPA is the gene. And this gene,
everybody has this gene, but we have different variants of it. And so a subset of the population,
and it varies considerably by ethnicity. So African, East Asian, also quite high,
down to Caucasian, and as you mentioned, Chinese, Japanese, et cetera. So you're going to see
different expressions of the apo-like-the-protein little a. This apo-like-the-protein little a,
which we'll talk a lot about and what it looks like and its structure and what its heterogeneity
is all about. But it wraps onto a low-density lipoprotein. And then it becomes kind of a
supercharged low-density lipoprotein. It becomes a particularly nefarious LDL. And we're going to
talk about all the reasons why it's not responsive to the same treatments, et cetera. So would you
add anything to that? Like, I don't want to make it too complicated yet, but I want to make sure
everybody understands when we talk about the LPA gene, which is identified during the GWAS
experiments, how the genotype allows us to not know everything about the phenotype,
but we can start to get into trying to impute causal relationships. And eventually we're going
to talk, of course, about Mendelian randomization, where we can go even deeper. And anything you want
to add to sort of the basics of this? No, I think you've explained it perfectly, Peter. Maybe the
only thing I would add is that part of the genetic heterogeneity among different people is
the apolipoprotein A isoform size. So people express different LPA isoforms. Some are bigger
than the other. And that probably, well, that actually plays an important part of the
equation, explaining why some people have a higher LPA little later than others.
I'm glad you reinforced that point because, and this is going to get into a little bit of
chemistry, which I know some people will understand and some might not. One of the
big challenges here, as you've now alluded to twice, is the difficulty in measurement.
Now, when we look at something like ApoB and people who listen to this podcast a lot will
be very familiar with ApoB. We talk an awful lot about it. One of the things we talk about is that
by measuring the concentration of ApoB, you can completely and accurately measure the
concentration of the atherogenic particles, the majority of which are LDL. And the reason for
that is twofold. The first is that every LDL has one and only one ApoB 100 particle on it. The
second is that all ApoBs are the same size. Therefore, they have a molar weight. And by
knowing the mass, you know the number. Now, I always like to point out two contrasts to this,
right? The HDL particle, by contrast, has multiple ApoAs on it. And this is totally different from
ApoA. So we're not going to talk about that other than to say it's ApoA. And therefore,
you don't have a unique number. And then, of course, with LpA, you have the problem that you
raised, which creates enormous challenges. There is no molar weight for ApoA, right? This is the
fundamental problem in the assay of trying to measure this thing. Exactly. And we're really
moving in the right direction in terms of getting the LpA measurement in nanomoles per liter. And
there's more and more labs that are doing this. And this is clearly the way to go. We have to
move away from measurements in milligrams per deciliter, which is really influenced by the
isoform size of LpA. And the measurement in nanomolar will actually give you a much better
sense of the number of LpA particles in the circulation. And that's what we should be
aiming at. Now, will that require electrophoresis? How will that actually be measured? Or will it
use NMR? I mean, it's going to be measured through immunoturbidimetric assays. So not by
NMR. NMR can actually give you a pretty good estimate of LDL particle number, but you have
to use antibodies to measure LpA. Okay. So we got a little in the weeds there. I apologize. We'll
come back to that stuff later. But let's pick it up back about a decade ago when the GWAS studies
were able to distance themselves from the limitations of the assay and focus instead
on the genotype and the heterogeneity of the genotype. These GWAS studies now found a much
stronger association between the variants of this genotype that produced high copy numbers of
apolipoprotein LpA and insipid cardiovascular events, correct? Exactly. So there were,
I think, three studies that were all published in 2009. The first one was the one by Robert Clark
from the UK. They used the procardis consortium, which were, if I recall, well, there were 3,000
people with heart disease and 3,000 controls. And they've identified two SNPs in the LpA regions
that are completely different from one another. And you really saw the dose response effect of
these SNPs on LpA levels with a proportional effect on the risk of heart disease. So it was
like the kind of the first Mendelian randomization study where they nicely showed that if you had one
LpA-raising allele, you had higher LpA levels. Whereas if you had two or more LpA-rising
variants, then you had even higher LpA levels and the risk was proportionally higher. Also worth
explaining how important this type of analysis is because it really is the bridge between
observational epidemiology and clinical trials. And of course, we're going to talk about clinical
trials, many of which are ongoing. But the importance of what you just said, Benoit,
is the following. There are a handful of assumptions that make this type of Mendelian
randomization essential. One is the assumption that the sorting of these genes is random.
Right? So in other words, you know, we look at a population and we can say we can look at this as
though nature did an experiment and it randomized the population to different copy numbers of these
alleles that are going to produce different amounts of the protein. But the second important
piece of a Mendelian randomization, being able to link something causal, is the assumption
that the gene of interest is not doing something else that you're unaware of. Right? In other words,
if the LpA gene was on the one hand responsible for making Apo-like protein little a, which it is,
but on the other side, it also changed your, I'm making this up, your susceptibility
to secondhand smoke. And people who had that gene would be debilitated by secondhand smoke.
People who didn't have that gene had complete immunity to secondhand smoke. Imagine such a
gene existed. Well, all of a sudden the Mendelian randomization wouldn't be very helpful because
those people who are at an increased risk of cardiovascular disease from having more copies
of LpA, you don't know if it's that or if it's the exposure or susceptibility to secondhand smoke.
So do you have a sense? I mean, I think in the case of LpLit it's pretty straightforward
because it's a relatively simple gene. But when that type of analysis was done, was it relatively
easy to demonstrate that that gene wasn't doing anything else, both in its coding and non-coding
regions? Yeah. First, let me say that I think that a lot of genesis would disagree that LpA is a
relatively easy gene. I mean, there's like, I think 2000 different variants that are associated with
LpA and you add in the isoform and each isoform has a specific set of different variants. So that
being said, I think you really nicely explained it. And the beauty of working with LpA, but also
with most proteins in the circulation, is that you're looking at cis-acting SNPs. So cis-acting
means variants that are acting within the window of the gene that expressing their protein as in
opposition to like a transacting SNP would be, for instance, a SNP in the CTP gene, for instance,
which we know might be associated with LpA. But CTP does a lot of other things. It regulates HDL
cholesterol levels, it regulates triglycerides. So we don't use CTP genes when we do Mendelian
randomization on LpA. And the example that you mentioned, a specific gene being associated with
an intermediate phenotype that could, on the other end, influence LpA would be reverse causality. And
in the case of LpA, it's, you know, we're very, very confident that we're using the correct genetic
instruments to infer a causal relationship between LpA and a wide range of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular diseases. So to put a bow on that, we really have two independent types of analyses
now that make it very clear that LpA is playing a causal role in the development of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease independent of LDL, which you referred to earlier by commenting and using
the term residual risk, which I think people might not appreciate residual risk, meaning what is the
risk that remains in terms of ASCVD in the presence of LDL lowering. And of course,
LpA would be one such example. And those two pieces of information are now the regular
observational epidemiology, provided that the assays more accurately capture the measurement
of LpA. And now these Mendelian randomizations that effectively are nature's randomized
experiments, provided those two criteria we discussed can be met. Is that a fair synthesis
of the state of the art today in terms of our understanding? Yes, I think you can also add a
third assumption, which would be that the effect of the variance on the outcome, so the effect of
variance on cardiovascular disease are explained by higher LpA levels. And I think for LpA,
it's a fairly fair assumption to make. Okay, so let's talk about how this is done clinically today.
Over the past decade, I've seen three different types of commercial assays for measuring LpA.
I don't believe two of them are in existence anymore. One was the LpA cholesterol content.
So I assume that this was an assay that was looking at the cholesterol content of the
LpA, which means the LDLs that had apolipaprotein A on them, you just measure the cholesterol content.
So it was analogous to measuring LDL cholesterol, but for this narrow subset. Is that assay still
in existence? Well, I think there are certain labs that still use it, but it's really not the way that
the field is moving to because the cholesterol, and you can make the same argument for LDL,
the cholesterol within a certain lipoprotein does not necessarily tell you a lot of information about
the number of particles that are in the bloodstream, which is the most important thing
to measure if you want to estimate risk. So for LDL, ApoB, there's some discordance,
but for LpA, the discordance is even higher. Exactly. So what you really want to do is try to
find a lab that will give you an LpA measurement in nanomoles per liter. Right. Now, there are some
labs that have done that. I've seen a lot of those labs. So one of them was called
health diagnostics labs. I think that was the name of the lab. They no longer exist. They did
calculate an LpA in nanomole per liter. I don't know what their methodology was.
Most labs are using milligrams per deciliter. So they are simply telling you, I say simply,
they are telling you the mass of LpA. Now, just to be clear, are we in that assay looking at the
mass of the entire LpA? Are they just trying to estimate the mass of the Apo lipoprotein?
It's the mass of the particles. So it's a much better measurement than LpA cholesterol that you
just referred to. And we shouldn't let good be the enemy of perfect here. If you have an LpA
measurement in milligrams per deciliter and it puts you in a high risk range. So let's say
you're it gives you an LpA level of above 50. Then the chances of the LpA assay that will give you a
result in nanomoles per liter, it will also give you a high level. So if you have an LpA measured
in milligrams per deciliter, you can obviously try to get a second measurement in nanomoles per liter.
But if you have a LpA in a high range, both methods will give you the same information that
you have an LpA in the higher range. Now, you have to keep in mind though, that if you have an LpA,
for instance, of 50 milligrams per deciliter, the measurement in nanomoles per liter will be around
125 nanomoles per liter. So some people have measurements using both methods and they just
say, well, for some reason my LpA doubled. Well, that's not the case. The LpA didn't double and it's
remarkably stable over time. So most guidelines will probably tell you just to measure LpA once
in a lifetime and it's relatively relatively stable. Yeah, I mean, I think that's the take home
point here is unlike LDL and APO-B, which are so modifiable. And therefore it really matters that
you know what you're measuring because you're going to be measuring it over and over and over
and over again. With LpA at this point in time, this is going to be changing, but at this point
in time, it's basically something we measure to determine risk, after which point we don't really
need to measure it. We've established risk and now we need to take measures elsewhere.
So let's now kind of talk a little bit about the biology of LpA.
We'll include figures in the show notes to the podcast. So we'll be able to show people exactly
what this thing looks like and how it intersects with and binds to the LDL particle, how it's
distinct from the APO-B, et cetera. But let's talk a little bit about the production of this thing.
Is it hepatically produced? It's produced in the liver? Yes, exactly. So
all the lipoprotein A particles originate from the APO lipoprotein little a that's
pretty much only expressed in the liver. So it's not entirely clear in the literature how
or where specifically an APO lipoprotein little a will become an Lp little a. So where it will
bind to APO-B and ultimately an LDL particles. There's multiple hypotheses that have been tested.
So some people say that the APO lipoprotein little a, which is like a glycoprotein, is secreted in
the bloodstream and there it will bind to whichever LDL is closer to it to form LpA.
There's another hypothesis that suggests that it's probably at earlier after the secretion of
LpA. So not entirely in the bloodstream, but when it leaves hepatocyte in the space of this in the
liver that the binding of APO lipoprotein little a with LDL. But now I think we have
very good evidence that to suggest that this happens within liver cell, the binding of APO-A
to APO-B to eventually form LpA. So there's good evidence to suggest that as soon as the
APO-A is produced, it can form an LpA when it meets with an APO-B particle.
And for whatever reason, that just seems a bit more intuitively obvious given the mechanics of
it. You're bringing so many LDLs to the liver, you're making APO lipoprotein little a in the
liver. It seems like a more obvious place for the marriage to occur than in the periphery. But again,
it remains to be seen, although it seems like it's more likely that that is the case, correct?
Correct. And so the levels of LpA are determined by the levels of production,
by the rate of production of LpA particle and little by its catabolism. We're still
not entirely sure of how the catabolism of LpA occurs. Most of it is by the liver. There's a
little bit of catabolism by the kidney as well. But identifying the receptor at the surface of
hepatocyte that will remove LpA from the bloodstream has been challenging. So there's
some evidence suggesting that the LDL receptor might be one of them. There's some evidence for
and against that. And there's also the plasminogen receptor. And I think we're going to eventually
talk about the homology between APO lipoprotein little a and plasminogen.
So let's go back to this point, which is that it's really the production of APO lipoprotein
little a that determines the concentration of LpA. And if that weren't the case, it might be
that by simply reducing the amount of targets for it, i.e. reducing the amount of LDL,
you might reduce the amount of LpA. But in fact, that does not appear to be true,
with one notable exception that we will get to down the line.
In other words, if you give somebody a statin, which is a very potent drug to lower LDL,
the primary mechanism by which it does so is by increasing hepatic clearance of LDL.
So you have more and longer lasting LDL receptors on the liver, and they're pulling those LDL out
of circulation, which is lowering the plasma concentration. And yet that does nothing to
offset the amount of LpA, which goes back to the explanation that started your journey here,
which was why is it that some people respond really well to statins and some don't?
And obviously, it would be the higher your LpA, the worse your statin response,
because there's a subset of your LDL that are not responding to the statin.
So maybe let's start by explaining how a statin takes an LDL out of circulation,
and why this doesn't work for an LpA, which is basically just an LDL with this one other
little thing covalently bound to it. Exactly. So the statins actually reduce LDL particles
in the circulation by upregulating the LDL receptor at the surface of the hepatocytes.
So the density of the LDL receptor at the surface of the hepatocyte is super important. The more
LDL receptor you have, the higher the catabolism of APOB containing lipoproteins will be because
APOB binds to the LDL receptor. So under the assumption that LpA is catabolized by
the LDL receptor, you would think that statins would actually reduce LpA levels.
Whereas we see that there's not really a lowering effect of statins on LpA. And there's even been
more than one studies that have shown that if you put somebody on a statin, you'll even have
a small increase in LpA levels. Now that shouldn't be a reason not to put someone on a statin,
of course, because there's been trials like the heart protection study that have shown that
a treatment with statin is beneficial in patients with high LpA level, even maybe even more so
than patients with low LpA levels. So one should not prescribe a statin because you're afraid of
a small LpA level. It might be an interesting thing to do to measure LpA levels before and after the
initiation of a statin. But overall, we have so much experience with statin that we know they work
in the overwhelming majority of individuals and especially even better in patients with high LpA.
Yeah, I mean, one hypothesis for that might be that the statins are bringing a higher influx of
LDL to the site of the production of the apolipoprotein, little a, and that might possibly be why
you're seeing an increase in LpA. Again, if that were true, that would make it even more likely
the scenario that that's the source of the merger between apolipoprotein, little a, and LDL.
What's the approximate magnitude by which LDL or ApoB, let's be specific, I guess, because that's
really the metric we care about. What's the magnitude by which ApoB would go up in the
presence of a statin for an Lp, little a, pardon me, let me restate that. What's the magnitude by
which Lp, little a would go up in the context of a statin? Well, that depends on the study.
There's been a lot of studies that have shown that statins don't have an effect.
Most of the studies have shown like a 10% increment in LpA levels. If you have low LpA levels
and you're treated with a statin, you'll still remain with a low LpA level. If you have high
LpA level, then you'll obviously still remain with a high LpA level, although it's going to be
a little bit higher. It's important to say that as we move forward with LpA lowering drugs that
are being tested on top of statin therapy at the moment. We have published a paper in Patients
with Aortic Valve Stenosis at the Astronomer Trial where you can actually get, I think it
was a 20% increment in lipoprotein, little a. It might not be trivial. The signal is there,
but let me restate that statins are very effective in patients with LpA, even though
there's a small increment of LpA. Yeah, and an easy way to think about this would be
if you give a statin and let's say in the most aggressive case, the LpA goes up by 10%,
but the ApoB comes down by 60%, you'd have to make the case that an LpA is six times
more atherogenic for particle basis for that to be an equivalence maneuver.
So that begs the question, what is it about LpA that's so virulent? What is it about LpA
that makes it, I assume, more atherogenic on a particle for particle basis than its
garden variety ApoB bearing cousin? Yeah, there's no question about this, Peter. I mean,
on a per particle basis, LpA is much more atherogenic than an equivalent LDL particles.
Well, first of all, an LpA has an LDL particle on it. So by definition, it's, you know, as
atherogenic just to start with. There's also evidence that LpA might influence the rates of
thrombosis because LpA has a sequence homology with plasminogen, which plays a role in
clotting and has anti-fibrinolytic activity. But I think the most important thing is the number
of oxidized phospholipids that are transported by lipoprotein little a, which is much higher than
the amount of oxidized phospholipids that that you see on LDL particles. And oxidized phospholipids
have effects on a wide variety of cells, endothelial cells, smooth muscle cells, macrophages,
cells of the aortic valve like valvular interstitial cells. Now they're sending in
signals that will drive pro-inflammatory, maybe pro-trombotic and pro-calcifying signals to these
cells. So that is probably the most important reason why on a per particle basis LpA is more
atherogenic than LDL. So let's talk about these oxidized phospholipids. I think most people might
not be familiar with what a phospholipid is. But before we do that, let's explain to people
what an LDL looks like physically in relation to an LDL. So if an LDL is a largely spherical
compound that has on its surface a single lipoprotein called ApoB100 that wraps around it,
how does that now interact with the ApolipoproteinA to become an LpA?
Okay, so to answer this question, I'm going to tell you a little bit about the structure of
ApolipoproteinA. And to explain that, I'm going to talk about plasminogen for a minute. So
plasminogen is a gene that's expressed on chromosome 6. It has five cringles repeats.
Now a cringles is, it's called a cringles because it resembles a Danish pastry. So it's a little
round of proteins and you have five of them that are one another in the protein. Now LpA is the
gene right next to plasminogen on chromosome 6. And we have reasons to believe that along the
lines of evolution, it probably emerged from a duplication of the plasminogen gene. So LpA
which would have been very important tens and hundreds of thousands of years ago, because
trauma was such a threat to our species, much more than it is today. And of course,
trauma carries with it in the short term an immediate risk of hemorrhagic shock, blood loss.
Ultimately septic shock probably would have killed just as many people from the infection.
But anything that would have reduced your risk of hemorrhagic shock would have been a generally
positive thing up until a hundred years ago or a couple hundred years ago. So tell people exactly
how plasminogen would have played a role in that and why this is something that if a duplication
was created probably worked to an evolutionary advantage again until we lived long enough for
it not to. Yeah, there's a lot of hypotheses out there and the effect of LpA on wound healing is
certainly one of them and this is being studied ex vivo. So that might be one of the reasons why
we have high LpA levels in 20% of the population and why before that even there was the duplication
of the plasminogen gene. Now when we're talking about that duplication, it's only the
cringles four and cringles five that remain in the LpA gene and the cringles four is even separated
in 10 different subunits. So there's the cringles four type one all the way to the cringles four
type 10. Now the most important is probably the cringles four type two which is where the copy
number variation is. So one can have one cringles four type two or only a couple and you can also
have the way all up to 40 cringles four type two repeats. So this is where when we talk about LpA
isoform size it's due to variation in cringles four type two. So there's other cringles
repeats that are parts that are important. Cringles four type 10 is probably the most important for
the binding of oxidized phospholipid and to answer your question Peter about the interaction
between ApoA and ApoB you have to look at the cringles four type nine which contains cysteine
residues which are important to do a disulfid bridge with ApoB. So it's a covalent bound that's
happening because of the cysteine residues on cringles four type nine. So interesting sort of
thought experiment. And the reason I'm asking this question is not just to be difficult it's to try to
understand the pathophysiology a bit better especially as it pertains to the oxidized
phospholipid. If you could create a drug that would cleave that does that disulfide bond so it
couldn't it wouldn't lower ApoB and it wouldn't lower Apo lipoprotein little a it would just
prevent their union and therefore it would eliminate Lp little a but you still had a high
concentration of Apo lipoprotein little a floating around by itself dragging with it oxidized
phospholipids. Would you guess that it would still be problematic or would your guess be that no
because it wouldn't be able to gain residence in the tissues such as the subendothelial space
the interstitial space of the aortic valve all the places where it wreaks havoc.
Yeah I'm only going to speculate here of course there's I don't think there's solid data on the
the form of ApoA that's not bound to to LDL particles. So we know that
ApoA can still have oxidized phospholipids and we are not entirely sure how if you're talking
about LpA how it it gets inside the cells if it gets inside the cells. Now we have some evidence
and we've we've published that with a colleague of mine Patrick Mathieu here who's a who's a
heart surgeon. We've looked at the an LpA receptor in the valvular interstitial cells so these are
the types of cells that are very abundant in the in the aortic valve and just to remind our
audience LpA is also associated to a very significant extent to aortic valve stenosis
and when I'm talking about LpA receptor I'm not talking about the receptor for
lipoprotein little a I'm talking about the receptor for lysophosphatidic acid which is generated by
LpA by an enzyme called autotaxin which is actually carried by LpA in in the blood. So on top of
oxidized phospholipids ApoB LDL LpA has its specific proteome so it carries a lot of of
different proteins that have different function that makes LpA even more atrogenic. Now these
oxidized phospholipid can have a signaling effect in the in the aortic valve and that might be
totally independent from from from LDL so so we don't know I'm only speculating here but there's
some signaling effects of of oxidized phospholipids that I think are very important and they they
activate a lot of of different inflammatory processes and also osteoblastic processes
because these types of valvular insert in interstitial cells are becoming like osteoblasts
which are the cell types that that that make bones so it makes a lot of sense you know when
you're talking about aortic valve calcification that there's a bone-like process that's that's
happening within this tissue. Yeah for all of our patients that have elevated LpA one of the first
tests we do is get a baseline look at their aortic valve so typically we'll do it with an echocardiogram
if we can get a good enough view if not we'll use a cardiac MRI but it's for exactly this reason.
What's the approximate hazard ratio? How much does risk go up for aortic stenosis
in an individual with elevated LpA and how much does it depend on whether or not they have a normal
aortic valve to begin with which has three leaflets so-called tricuspid valve versus if they have a
relatively common anatomic variant with only two leaflets which is called a bicuspid valve which
even outside of LpA would increase your risk for stenosis. Exactly so there's not really good
evidence showing that LpA is associated with bicuspid aortic valve stenosis because we
we're studying genes that that are associated with bicuspid aortic valve stenosis and we don't see
really an effect of of LpA there. Now that being said it might accelerate the
the formation of aortic stenosis in patients with bicuspid aortic valve. Who are already at risk.
Exactly so LpA is probably an initiator of aortic valve stenosis and we've known that
since 2013 when George Tanesoulis and Wendy Post they published this
genome-wide association studies of aortic valve calcification in the in the charge consortium and
they've shown that LpA the with that one variant associated with high LpA level was the most
important variant associated with aortic valve disease. Now we had known for a few years that
LpA was present in the valve and in the valve it actually co-localizes with oxidized phospholipids
so we knew this but that study was really I think a game changer for our understanding of
aortic valve stenosis. Now when we're looking at the effect of high LpA on aortic valve stenosis
it really depends on the level of LpA. So if you're looking at patients that have
high ish LpA levels such as well let's say 50 milligrams per deciliter or 125 nanomolar their
risk can be increased by 50 percent to maybe 100 percent or double but when you're going into
and you look at patients that have very high LpA their risk can can increase quite
substantially. So if you have patients with with very high LpA level then what you're doing
looking at the at the aortic valve especially by echo because it's probably the most
widely available tool to investigate this. Now in our lab we performed
sodium fluoride PET CT so positron emission tomography coupled with computed tomography using
a radio tracer that's called that that's called sodium fluoride and in patients that have high
LpA levels but these were patients from the general population we can already see like a signal
before the onset of aortic valve calcification using this this this radio tracer. So this really
tells you that there's an effect of LpA on the initiation of the of the process of aortic valve.
And what is it so you're seeing before any gradient appears before any flow related metric
you're seeing a metabolic change of the valve? Yeah exactly so the the sodium fluoride will
actually bind to a chemical called hydroxyapatite which is literally the complex of calcium and
phosphorus which will eventually be involved in the petro physiology of aortic valve stenosis.
And we see that process happening very early at the earliest stage of the of the disease and we
also see an effect of LpA on the later stage of the disease. So the the data that's available so
far that have looked at the progression rates of aortic valve stenosis has shown that patients with
high LpA might even progress more rapidly than patients with who have low LpA especially with
in younger patients that have that have high LpA because when you're looking at patients you know
that are above 75 or 80 there's a lot of calcium that's already present in the valve and the
mechanism might be very different in younger patient compared to to older patient when you're
when we're investigating the progression of aortic valve stenosis. Yeah and if we're going to create
a public service announcement here for primary care physicians it's so important to identify
aortic stenosis in its earliest stages because the outcome data are quite clear that the earlier
you intervene the better the outcome. So you know I think 25 years ago we had a certain threshold
in terms of surface area of the valve and gradient of pressure across the valve at which point you
would you know replace the aortic valve. If you look at the literature today it seems that you're
getting better and better outcomes when you proceed earlier and earlier before the heart is overly
taxed based on that based on that pressure head that it faces and of course the increased risk of
spontaneous cardiac death and other things that goes up with aortic stenosis. So aortic stenosis
is a very serious problem independent of ASCVD atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease which is
what most people think of when they think of LpA assuming they know something about what we're
talking about in terms of this molecule. So let's go back to another point you raised so you and
again I think when people look at the diagram this will be much easier. We get into the anatomy
of the fourth and fifth region of these cringal repeats and which of the subunits can create this
vast heterogeneity. Why two people can have an LpA gene that over expresses Lp well LpA through
apoliproptenin little a but they can have one of them can have a molar mass that's very high one
can have a molar mass that's very low because of these number of cringal repeats. What does the
number of these repeats tell us about the pathophysiology of this? Well if you had asked me that
question 10 years ago I would have said a lot but our understanding of the pathophysiology of LpA
is increasing every every week now basically. So maybe 10 years ago there was this debate about
LpA as to whether or not it was the LpA concentration that matter or if LpA concentration
didn't matter at all because it's the apoA isoform size that that matter small isoform size being
associated with higher LpA levels and there has been some epidemiological studies that have
measured apoA isoform size either through PCR or immunoblotting etc so in the same patient you
can have LpA levels measured and you can have the apoA isoform size and using the techniques that
were available back then they did multiple adjustment adjusting LpA concentration for
the apoA isoform size and looking at the association of apoA isoform size with outcome adjusting for
LpA levels and the data back then was going all over the place basically so some studies were
saying it's the concentration some other studies were saying it's the apoA isoform size that matters
and once again these questions were ultimately resolved by looking at genetics so there's
there's one variant that's associated with small LpA isoform size but that's also associated with
a low LpA so you can see this was our way to do a discordance analysis by looking at that specific
SNP and that genetic variant was not associated with cardiovascular diseases at all and in many
studies now it's been shown that probably the best study that has investigated that is a study from
the D code cohort which is a cohort from Iceland they have they sequenced they did a whole genome
sequencing and I think it was 50,000 sorry 15,000 individuals and they've shown unequivocally that
the LpA isoform size even though you can sequence it really was not associated with
the risk of heart attacks and strokes once you take into consideration LpA level so it's really
the LpA number that matters and that's actually very positive for for the field that because
there's so many puzzles that we still need to figure out in terms of of the association between
LpA and risk so at least we can you know I think I can we can convincingly say that it's the the
the number of LpA particles that that matter and not necessarily the isoform size and that the
isoform size matters because it's associated with different levels of of LpA and not true an
independent effect. So really this for once creates a beautiful symmetry here which is it
mirrors ApoB the first second and third order factor in the in the uh in the harm caused by
an LDL particle is the number of the particles the size all of those things only factor into the
number so why is it that smaller particles are more often associated with a poor phenotype
because when you have smaller particles you generally have more of them.
So that's good to know. Do we have a sense of the complexity in why some families because again we
didn't talk about the inheritance of this so in fact before I ask this question let's go back and
explain the inheritance of this it's a very important piece of the puzzle. How is this gene
inherited and what are the implications for people who have elevated levels of this as far
as their offspring? Yeah that's a that's a very good question. So the pattern of inheritance is
true autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance so it's like any like for instance if you compare
it with a monogenic disorder let's say familial hypercholesterolemia. In in Quebec we have a very
famous mutation which is a 15 kilo base deletion in the LDL receptor so if uh if you inherit that
then if you inherit at least one copy you know you'll you'll have FH. For LPA if you inherit
a genetic variant that's associated with high LPA chances are you'll have high LPA as well
because you only need one variant and not necessarily two so you need either the allele from
your father or your mother that will rise LPA but it's a bit more complex than that because we
we cannot necessarily consider it monogenic disorders because there's
2,000 different variants in the LPA region that are associated with high LPA so your father can
have an high LPA because of a specific variant and your mother can have an an LPA variant that
lowers LPA but it depends on the combination of SNPs that you will ultimately get so it's not
it's not as clear as any monogenic disorder even though it's a dominant mode of of inheritance
it's been shown that the children you can they have a very different LPA levels than their
their mothers and fathers and you cannot really estimate it so you really have to
to measure it and for people that are asking the question at what time I should get an LPA
measurement let's say if I had a heart attack at an early age and I want to prevent that in
in my children then we know that the LPA gene is fully expressed by age two in the liver of course
and that the levels that you will get at five years old are probably going to remain
this well maybe not the same levels but if you have high levels by age five
so it'll probably increase through adulthood but very very slowly yeah so again some very
important information there right piece one of that is you cannot predict the phenotype of the
offspring from the phenotype of the parents and let's contrast this with apo-e the gene by the
way there's a lot of parallels between apo-e and LPA apo-e is a gene that today doesn't seem to
serve much of a purpose all it seems to do is increase your risk of Alzheimer's disease and
even increase your risk of cardiovascular disease independent of that there are three
isoforms the two three four type and it's this fourth type that's high risk so you can argue
how in the world does this gene exist and of course the answer is evolution wasn't really
thinking about Alzheimer's disease so therefore there must have been some benefit of it and of
course we now know there is right this this genotype was associated with protection from
parasitic infections in the brain which would have been far more to our advantage 100 000
years ago 50 000 years ago 10 000 years ago than the downside of Alzheimer's disease in your 70s
or 80s but with apo-e because you have these three discrete isoforms you only have six combinations
and therefore if you know what the parents isoforms are you can probabilistically give a
distribution for what the children will be you still would need to measure it of course
but there's a finite number of outcomes now of course there you're measuring genotype and not
phenotype we don't measure the phenotype of apo-e yet so here you have so many genes
that are associated with this thing that if the parents are both elevated the probability that
the offspring are going to be elevated seems pretty high if one parent is elevated and the
other is not there's a pretty decent chance that the offspring will not tell me about the situation
in which both parents are not elevated but yet could carry genes that or could carry variants
of LPA that when combined could elevate that is that has that been observed or does one safely say
if both of your parents are below 30 milligrams per deciliter the probability that you are going
to be north of 50 is very small i think it's very small but you still have to to measure it
peter i i i to be honest i don't think i would know the answer to that uh so that's why we we
simply suggest to measure LPA well the guidelines now most guidelines will tell you to measure it in
everybody at least once in their lifetime but and there are people guidelines suggest that that
start do the guidelines suggest doing it in adolescence when you have a long enough runway
to take action if the LP little a is elevated or do they not specify i don't think they they
specify that and the the guidelines are actually just starting to advise for for LPA measurements
so some some guidelines uh like the american heart association guidelines uh which are um probably the
less favorable for LPA measurement they'll tell you to measure i don't remember exactly but in
patients with atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease or with a family history of atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease in patients with familial hypercholesterolemia or in patients with aortic
valve stenosis so but the guidelines don't usually so in other words when measure the LP little a
once they've demonstrated that the disease that it causes is present yeah pretty much that's
fantastic advice so so so if you look at the yeah but if you look at the canadian guidelines though
they'll tell they'll tell you to measure it in everybody at least once in their in their lifetime
so there's and by the way this is where canadians also stand out over americans canadians have long
adopted the measurement of apo b as the superior measurement to quantify LDL risk and yet here in
the united states the guidelines still favor the use of LDL cholesterol which is clearly inferior
to apo b yeah absolutely so uh i i would like to comment on on that i think i think the the
canadian guidelines are are much more up to date with the with the recent literature on that there's
clearly no no doubt about it but as are the european guidelines while we're on the topic yeah the
european guidelines the canadian guidelines are in line with the available evidence and the united
states guidelines are you know just 40 years out of date but that's all yeah absolutely and the
european guidelines actually they they advise to measure lpa in everybody for a different reason
it was to identify patients who have very very high lpa levels because we realize uh throughout
the years that the having a super high lpa might be a cause for familial hypercholesterolemia
so um so and you need to measure ldl to diagnose familial hypercholesterolemia and after them after
mutation in the ldl receptor mutation or variation in the lpa gene might even be the second cause of
familial hypercholesterolemia and the reason for that is quite simple because when you measure ldl
uh you also measure lpa cholesterol so if you have a very high ldl and also a very high lpa
there's a very good chance that the high ldl cholesterol will actually be high lpa uh cholesterol
so um so yeah this is i think it's really underappreciated and and actually that's the reason why
it's in the european guidelines uh but now i think most of the guidelines that will that will be uh
put forward will just simply for whatever reason to measure lpa at least once and i don't know if
it's in the pediatric guidelines because i don't really follow that that literature but uh maybe
in children uh who have strokes at a young age many of them have high lpa so it's not as um as
clean as the literature in adults but there's been a lot of studies looking at high lpa and
stroke in children so uh if you have a family history uh or relatives that had uh stroke at
at a young age it might be a good idea to uh to to measure lpa as well yeah that's actually a
terrifying thought by the way um you know my view on these things of course is just that
the amount of energy that goes into debating it is so ridiculous compared to the relatively low
cost of simply measuring the thing the the people who debate why oh why would you spend 14 dollars on
an apo b test it's like if your life isn't worth 14 dollars we shouldn't be having this discussion
same is true for measuring lp little a so uh i think it should be done on everybody non-negotiable
certainly before your 18th birthday that would be my that would be my thinking on this um so uh
let's go back now by the way i what's the greatest that you've seen uh number of lpa to lp little a
to ldl i i had a patient once when we were measuring both in nanomole per liter who had an
lp little a of 690 nanomole per liter in the context of an ldl particle concentration of about
1800 nanomole per liter so a little over one third of his ldl were lp little a i assume you've seen
numbers even in excess of that uh yeah well um just to to be to be clear peter i don't see i
don't see patients i'm not i'm not a physician i'm a biochemist but i've seen and i've seen some
very interesting case reports uh on uh children that have uh fh and high lpa some of them even
had to have liver transplant because uh the the lipids were just so high and they were having
events in children years so uh so but those are only uh case reports of course it's it's it's not
the not mainstreaming i wouldn't want to scare anybody but this is this is as dangerous as it
can get so let's talk about other therapies that have been proposed so there was certainly a day
and sadly there are still a number of physicians that i interact with including those who
carry the uh the title of lipidologist who are recommending the use of niacin
to lower lp little a can you talk a little bit about the history of that
and at the risk of spoiling the punchline why we do not believe that is a good idea
yeah um well it was even in the latest in the last guidelines of the european atherosclerosis
society to advise niacin treatment in some patients with with high lpa and we did not have
cardio large cardiovascular outcome studies uh on uh on on literally any effect of of niacin therapy
now we know that niacin therapy will actually reduce lpa levels it will increase hdl it will
lower triglycerides so the effects on on plasma lipids are are actually pretty good um however and
and you know if you're looking at lpa the reduction the mean reduction will probably be about 20 or 30
percent with the with niacin and there are as you say some lipidologists that have seen like very
important reductions of of lpa with niacin that that actually so they've decided to keep those
patients on on niacin and i don't see any any any problem with that uh the thing is however when
you look at the actual evidence we have two large cardiovascular outcomes trials we have the aim high
trial and the heart protection study two trive trial that have shown that there's no cardiovascular
benefits in treating uh well uh anyone with uh with niacin and we see a lot of side effects as well
uh flushing being the most uh the most important side effect of of niacin so we have those risks
and we don't have that many benefits so that's why niacin is not as prescribed as it uh as it
once was there are still people that have that are using it niacin reduces the production of
of lpa but uh and an lpa still predicts the risk of events in patients treated with niacin so we
know that from the from the aim high trial so when you're looking at the cost to benefit ratio for
for niacin the evidence really isn't isn't there to support so why why do you think this is i mean
if we look at the effect of niacin on raising HDL which it does right HDL cholesterol goes up
with niacin administration at a high enough dose um but the outcome trials are very clear that that
does not translate into benefit it makes you think a little bit of the CTEP trials where you give a
CTEP inhibitor HDL cholesterol goes up in some cases you actually saw more events but usually at
best you see no effect there it's a little easier to argue why that could be happening
when you look at the complexity of HDL biology and you understand how much we don't understand
and therefore that HDL functionality is what really matters and we don't have an assay for
HDL functionality so these things that we measure like the amount of cholesterol in an HDL particle
is a pretty useless measurement in that it tells us nothing about how the HDL actually works
especially when you consider that you can have high cholesterol in an HDL particle because of all
the cholesterol that's entering it or you could have high cholesterol in an HDL particle because
not much cholesterol is leaving it those would be two completely different states of affairs
and again it makes sense why you can dismiss the notion that raising HDL cholesterol is valuable
pharmacologically in the case of LP little a it's a bit more confusing because as you said
niacin actually inhibits the production of apo lipoprotein little a and for all of the
nastiness associated with LDL and LP little a their biology is actually easier to understand
in other words the things that they're doing to hurt you are easier to understand than what HDL
is doing to help you so why do you think there is not a more clear signal between the use of
niacin and the reduction of events yeah it's a very good question and the Mendelian randomization
studies have been very clear that you will need a very large reduction in LPA to produce
cardiovascular benefits there was the first study has uh has shown that i suggested that because
it's basically only modeling right we there's no trial data so we can at best estimate the
treatment effect so it suggested that you needed a hundred milligrams per deciliter reduction in
LPA to get a benefit in a trial that would be comparable to a statin treatment like over what
period is that a five year you'd need to see that in a five year window or what yeah well that's
actually the problem because when you're looking at Mendelian randomization studies you're looking
at primary prevention and we're looking at lifelong reduction so it's very hard to estimate
oh so the MR says if you want to reduce if you want to take that mortality curve down
to the next rung it's a hundred milligram per deciliter reduction and lifetime exposure
which means in a clinical study that showed that there's other study that came out after that that
said well it's probably not a hundred it might might be around 50 milligrams per deciliter but
it's still high so you need a large effect so it's not a 20 reduction but there's a bigger point
there which is which you alluded to if that that's over the course of your life that's that yeah
well that means over five years you might have to basically obliterate it if you're going to want to
see a benefit yes and well that's what the anti-cense the anti-sensology nucleotides will do and we'll
I guess we'll come back to that later but when they compare it to LDL though they also compare
it to lifelong exposure to lower LDL so so they're not necessarily comparing lifelong reduction to
trial data that we you know with statin trials we have between two and seven years length of
treatment in patients that already have disease so you cannot really compare apple and oranges but
when you compare the lifelong effect and that's obviously a caveat of those of those studies
because you're trying to get lifelong effects to to estimate the results of a trial using lifelong
effects so so you have to you know take some and and leave some for those for those kinds of studies
but I want to come back to something that you said about CTP inhibitors because we we do have
evidence at least for the anacetrapib that it might lead to cardiovascular benefit the trial
was that the Merck one yes they stopped the trial even though it was trending in a positive direction
is that correct exactly so there's one reason for that was that they saw a lot of drug accumulation
in adipose tissue which is not something you want if you want to prescribe a lifelong treatment
and the second thing is that well the treatment effect was not spectacularly high so it was I
think it was a six percent reduction in the rate of events but because I'm saying this because you
talk about HGL and functionality and in that trial I don't remember the name of the trial it was a
revealed trial they they've shown yeah that was stopped about two years ago it was relatively
recent maybe three years ago right oh maybe a little bit more than that but it was a big trial
I think 30 000 patients so this is why we need big trials in that in that in that arena
so what they showed is that the it was the reduction in the number of apo B lipoproteins
that actually mattered it really didn't matter like the risk was not proportional to the HGL
rising effect it was proportional to the apo B lowering effect and when you're looking and if
you plot all the all the clinical trials together if you plot the apo B lowering effect to the
reduction in cardiovascular disease you can see that all these trials line perfectly on the line
and even that that specific trial with anisetrapib it fell right on the line same with
uh pc sk9 inhibitors same with isetamib any LDL lowering drug that's that that's out there will
basically well there's maybe some few a few exceptions but it will land on this line so it's
really not about HGL so much well when they developed the drug they thought it was about
HGL of course but it's really it's really funny because actually it's it just further convinced us
to hit low hit on apo B containing lipoproteins as hard as we can yeah it is kind of the silver
lining and all of this sometimes it's easy if you think about this stuff too much philosophically to
lament the fact that we even have apo B right because there's no real need for apo B you know
we could we could survive with no circulating apo B and we wouldn't have any atherosclerotic disease
so every time you get a little depressed and have that thought you can also realize how fortunate
are we that the biology of apo B is so much more well understood than that of apo A now I'm talking
apo big A and that eradicating apo B is becoming easier and easier and easier and safer and safer
and safer and it's the single most important thing that you can do in the plasma to reduce the risk
of atherosclerotic disease I mean all these things make for a very fortunate turn of events for our
species and that's why turning to this pesky LP little a is so important because of what you
described at the outset which is this residual risk in the individuals and it's interesting you
you talked about 20 percent that's higher than I that's that's higher than the number I quote my
patients I usually tell my patients it's 10 percent so I've been understating this for some time
I didn't realize it so all comers 20 percent of the population would be over 50 milligrams per
deciliter yeah depending on on ethnicity so it's certainly above 15 percent no no no doubt about
it and some population especially in populations of European ancestry they have the highest
LPA level I'm sorry of African ancestry they have the highest LPA levels and they also have the
highest LPA levels adjusted for LPA isoform size as well so in most of individuals what if you look
at the distribution of LPA in the population it's really skewed towards the null so it means that
there's a lot of patient most individuals have very low levels of of LPA and there's some
individuals as we as we mentioned 15 to 20 percent that have high LPA levels now in individuals of
African ancestry it's it's a more like a Gaussian distribution so so that's one of the reason why
they have higher LPA does that mean they have higher risk if they have a higher LPA not
necessarily because the the risk is really proportionate to to the to the level so there's
nobody within shouting distance of the of what I'm about to say I believe which is LPA little a
is hands down the most common hereditary driver of ASCVD correct I mean FH wouldn't even get within
the same zip code when you think about genetic things that are driving atherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease correct it is by far the most prevalent form of dyslipidemia so you can argue that maybe
and and we have to talk about penetrance as well so the penetrance is the proportion of
individuals with a certain genotype that will have the phenotype exactly so the penetrance is
obviously not a hundred percent right so so when I hear people say that you know LPA for the
pharmaceutical industry is a market of 1.4 billion people I say well hold on a second it's not it's
not everyone that has a high LPA that will have an event and we need to figure out what are the
the drivers of risk in patients with with high LPA and we're starting to study that then we see
that there is some residual risk effect even in patients with with high LPA so we see that for
instance if you have a high LPA but have lower CRP levels or lower like inflammation you might
be you might not have a risk that's as high as if you have high CRP so you can argue that residual
inflammation is very important but there need to be more studies on this because one can make the
case that while it might be the same for smoking or type 2 diabetes or any other cardiovascular
risk factor that you can think of but even then even if LPA is not fully penetrant it is so common
that it is by far the most important form of dyslipidemia that will explain a lot of
cardiovascular events at the population level and what I find so tragic about that statement
is the number of good physicians out there really great doctors that are working hard taking
care of patients frontline physicians family medicine physicians internists who have no idea
what it is you know you ask them about it and they look at you as though you've asked them something
in a different language I still struggle to understand that disconnect given its urgency I
wonder if that's a uniquely American phenomenon do you have any insight I know you're not a clinician
but do you have an insight as to whether or not the literacy around this in Canada and Europe is
higher I don't have any reasons to believe that the literacy in Canada or Europe is higher than
it is in in America even with your guidelines being more forward leaning oh yeah but these
guidelines are new and it will take a lot of time before they implement it sometimes it's you know
it it takes a full decade before it you know it's transmitted to younger generation of physician
and it's and people actually talk about it so that's one of the reason I'm so glad that we get to do
this this podcast hopefully this this will raise awareness for the physicians out there that no
didn't have any information about LPA and you know you can't blame them because well it it's
obviously in the guidelines but you know not all physicians and read all the lipids guidelines
there's so many guidelines out there that you can't blame them for that but I mean that's why
we have to do more education to to physicians and I think one of the reason that people are reluctant
to measure LPA is that because there's no treatment for for high LPA so sometimes
you know when you any so so any any medical procedure that you do even if it's asking for
a measurement of of any labs that you can mention it has benefits but it also have it also has
consequences so for instance you can you know you don't want to stress anybody saying hey you have
this risk factor it's super important and you don't want to do like an over diagnosis and an
overtreatment so so I used to I used to think that a lot but now you know we're in the age of shared
decision making you we can communicate the the correct information to to patient tell them tell
them what we know and even though there's no specific therapy for high LPA it doesn't mean
you can't do anything and I mean there's trial data showing that if you prescribe for instance
a statin and if you lower LDL cholesterol levels in patients that have some risk factors for
for cardiovascular disease you'll reduce their risk of events so in patients with high LPA
you need to manage LDL you need to manage LPA you need to manage lifestyle smoking cessation
and etc and we've actually shown that I I worked I've been working for more than 15 years with
investigators in in Amsterdam and Cambridge on the epic Norfolk study so the epic Norfolk study
is the European prospective investigation into cancer and nutrition and they have LPA measurement
in 18 000 individuals and we've looked in that in that population at the effect of LPA on the risk
of events but according to what the American Heart Association calls the life simple seven so
smoking having a healthy diet being physically active having low body weight LDL cholesterol
no diabetes and blood pressure that's on target and if you look at patients that have high LPA
and that manage all of these risk factors it's observational study of course but you can
if you consider it a causal relationship you could reduce your risk by by two thirds so so
that's not trivial so so we're trying to so that's one reason why we should we should measure we
should measure LPA if it's just to target the the other risk factors will have a lot of benefits
in terms of prevention of cardiovascular diseases at the population level and I think this is another
great example of the parallel with apo-e the genotype as recently as even a couple of years ago
I would have enormous arguments with physicians about patients that we were co-managing right so
this would be a patient who has both of us as their physician and the patient would say look
I want to have my apo-e genotype measured I would say I completely concur the other physician would
say that's an absolutely horrible idea what good comes of that if they discover that they have an
apo-e4 gene and their risk is higher all you've done is create anxiety to which I would argue
perhaps in some individuals sure and that's why it should be something that is done with consent but
it that assumption can assumes you can do nothing about it and while you can't change the gene
the evidence that you can modify behaviors that will lower the risk is enormous now in the case of
apo-e it's even more complicated because we now know what we didn't know a few years ago which is
there are so many other genes that will either amplify or attenuate the risk of apo-e so frankly
today knowing that you're apo-e4 positive in my opinion carries much less information that it once
did so I want to ask you about something parallel with lp little a I've had patients who have had
modest lp little a meaning 150 125 nanomole per liter 60 milligram per deciliter
who have had the most devastating ascvd that you can shake a stick at I mean six vessel disease
calcium scores of 2000 I mean these are people who are having you know coronary artery bypass
surgery in their 50s and their lp little a is you know a little elevated and by the way their LDL
and apo-b were not through the roof they're not smokers they're not hypertensive they're
they're not type 2 diabetic etc hard to explain those ones similarly I've had patients whose
family histories do not suggest advanced or premature ascvd and I told you about one of
them earlier 690 nanomole per liter lp little a now this person had a zero calcium score admittedly
they were in their 40s so at least say you know a calcium score of zero when your 40s doesn't
generally tell you anything but at least tells you that this person isn't having advanced
atherosclerosis their family history is very uninspiring and at least one of their parents
had to have an elevated level grandparents nothing and I scratch my head and I think
why is it that this person seems somewhat immune from their very elevated lp little a
whereas this other person who's elevated but not through the roof is ravaged by it
well you're describing my next grand proposal Peter so this is absolutely exactly what we're
trying to study and I alluded earlier to the penetrance of high lpa and that's exactly what
you're what you're referring to so there might be misunderstood then well I thought you were
referring to the penetrance in terms of the expression of the protein you were referring
to the penetrance of the disease yes exactly I misunderstood that so so but you know we can say
a lot about that because we actually measured so in our lab we isolated the lpa particle from the
blood of donors and patients with aortic valve stenosis so the reason being that well we're
going to study those those particles because those patients they were matched for age sex statin
therapy smoking etc so they're like the same people demographically speaking but one of them
has a disease and the other one doesn't so and they have they all have high lpa so and they were
matched for lpa levels so we thought well maybe there's something happening in the particle maybe
they have more oxidized phospholipids maybe they have different proteins so we've studied that and
we we realized that these patients might have more cell adhesion molecules that are transported
by lpa which make them more quote unquote sticky to endothelial cells or or fibrin clots or whatever
they would make them or maybe even macrophages because patients with high lpa also have
activated macrophages which can penetrate much more easier in the in the vessel wall there's
more apoptosis in the in the macrophages more cytokine production like il6, il8 etc so
there might be something that's different in the lpa particle that's just a hypothesis this was a
study of i think there were 20 patients in each in each study arm because you know it's not easy
to measure to to remove lpa from the blood and have it in a sufficient quantity that you can
actually do proteomics on it so this is it took my a phd student of mine at least one year just to
recruit the patients and isolate their and that's just because the the electrophoresis is complicated
or the isolation after the electro is it getting it out of the body that's complicated or isolating
it once it's ex vivo well once it's ex vivo you have to isolate it it's not difficult to isolate
it because you need to do ultra centrifugation but it has the same density of well i well it
probably has it has the same size as ldl and the same density as hdl so you have to do chromatography
columns to just basically separate it from ldl particles and also hdl particles so you need to
do a size exclusion chromatography and an affinity based chromatography so so it's it took a lot of
time just to set up that that technique and we worked with a great colleague of mine marles
kusinski who's at the robots research institute in london ontario and she's been doing this for
for ages but she helped us doing that and we're actually i think one of the first to actually
isolate lpa from the blood of of patients so so that might be an explanation for this different
expression of the disease in in in people that have all high lpa but some that that are lower
than others so that's just a hypothesis there's you need to look at other risk factors maybe
um there's another gene that's out there that might be might code for a receptor
of ldl there's labs that are really devoted to finding other genes uh aside lpa uh that that
might explain this and the gwah hasn't identified any because that would be your first tool before
i'd go looking for that gene or that receptor rather i i would be trying to just find out what
the association is right absolutely and those studies have been done probably the best gwah's
on on lpa levels was published i think last year by the group uh of george tenesoulis in uh at
magill uh in montreal and uh and james engert what they showed is that well obviously the biggest
hit was at the lpa locust uh but we and we had known this for a while that apo e actually uh also
regulate uh high lpa levels so that's another reason why is there concordance is there some
concordance with high with with apo e and lpa yeah so so the the apo e that will the apo e allele
that will rise the risk of heart attacks will also rise lpa levels so you have that you have
the ctp gene and and then we haven't talked about the low the lpa lowering effect of ctp inhibitors
which is actually higher than what you can get with niacin therapy so some have suggested that
uh the benefits of all the quote-unquote benefits of ctp inhibition might be too to a certain extent
to high lpa levels but the problems with with niacin trials and ctp trials is that they weren't
done particularly in in patients with high lpa so i guess they're probably underpowered
at least when it comes to trying to understand that yeah because you would have to recruit only
patients that have high lpa which would mean to get rid of 80 of the trial population so
so these trials will be will be very hard to do and when you look at the other genes you have ctp
and you also have apo h which is on another chromosome and apo h codes for beta 2 glycoproteins
and that protein might actually influence the the presence of oxidized phospholipids on apo a so
that might be interesting and i don't know uh i can't think of a study that have tried to look at
that locus with high lpa to see if it has a a modulatory effect on on outcomes but that would
be a very interesting study to do so these are these are the genes that that i can think of
interestingly the ldl receptor and also the most probably important regulator of ldl receptor
pcsk9 they did not pop up in in that gwase which is which was a little bit surprising to me
uh given the effect of of uh pcsk9 inhibitors on on lpa before we get to that i want to go back to
and really make sure we flush out this oxidized phospholipid plasminogen
basically the atherogenicity of this particle is it clear that lp little a's enter the subendithelial
space as ldl's do or is that unclear yeah well there's not as much research has been done on
lpa but you know it's if you look at um post-mortem studies uh you can see lpa in
in atherosclerotic plaques and you can and you can certainly see it on on aortic valves
because there's more easier like aortic valves are much more easier to get than atherosclerotic
plaques as you can remove the valve and then you can study it in the under the microscope so
there's there's good evidence um that the lpa can actually penetrate there usually what they do
is they will bind to uh to clots that are in the region of of the ataroma and that's one of the
reasons why they might also be present present there but and they can also send their oxidized
phospholipid through different uh through different receptors uh because we don't really
know what is the receptor for lpa in those uh in those tissue um so at the surface of
macrophages there are scavenger receptors uh toll-like receptors cd36 that might um
that might bind lpa they bind a bunch of things and but they also might bind npa which will
uh ensure that lpa get get strapped in the macrophages myloperoxidase
uh lpa sorry sorry i meant lpa but if i'm hearing you correctly then it would almost suggest that
lp little a plays less of a role in the initiation of atherosclerosis which is really initiated by
the monocyte becoming the macrophage in the sub endothelial space and engulfing the oxidized
LDL to become that foam cell that's really the initiating trigger you're saying lp little a might
not be playing a role in that or maybe it is i want to make sure i'm not misquoting you but
where it really lights things on fire is once you already have a plaque that's where the ability
to form a clot goes up potentially if you say it has more vcams on it it's attracting even more
macrophages to the site of injury so so am i capturing what you're saying correctly
absolutely uh i think it's actually both so the macrophages of patients with high lpa are already
activated and they will get uh as soon as there's and some endothelial dysfunction they'll get there
they might even cause endothelial dysfunction so lpa is is is associated it's probably a main driver
before the onset of any discernible plaque but it also has this double whammy where it's
it initiates the disease but it also is associated with the progression with the progression of the
of the disease and we see it in uh for instance i i talked to you a little bit earlier about the
pet imaging of with sodium fluoride these studies have also been done by eric strus in in amsterdam's
what they showed is that if you you don't use sodium fluoride but you use fdg so fluoro deoxy
glucose which is um basically a marker of macrophage activation and if you look at the
carotids and also the aorta of patients that have no disease but that are separated on the basis of
whether or not they have high lpa you'll see a lot of light in patients with high lpa so that tells
you that it also it's also associated with uh with inflammation with the inflammatory plaque
in uh even in patients that don't have established a disease so that's one of the reason why it's um
it it's this kind of particle is so dangerous and the association is obviously very strong for
as cvd and aortic stenosis how high is the association specifically for cerebrovascular
disease it's clearly not as high so there's there's obviously a signal if i if i would have to
rank those uh atrosterotic cardiovascular disease the first one will be aortic valve stenosis that's
it's obviously less present or prevalent than uh than mi or or or stroke but the
but there are fewer contributing factors beyond lp little a the way you have apo b
exactly exactly so the relative risk is actually higher that the absolute risk is lower because
there's not that many people that have that these might be two percent of the of the population
age above 60 but if you look at top quintile versus lower quintile uh the the biggest risk
is with aortic valve stenosis after that it depends on the study sometimes it's myocardial infarction
sometimes it's peripheral artery disease and we haven't talked about that but lpa is very strongly
associated with pad as well so it's aortic valve stenosis pad and mi then ischemic stroke
and it's important to uh make the the distinction between uh hemorrhagic and ischemic stroke because
lpa is only associated with uh with ischemic stroke um and uh yeah i think that's it it's
also associated with uh chronic kidney disease so that's it really it's only associated with
aortic stenosis mi's peripheral vascular disease ischemic cerebral strokes and kidney disease but
aside from that it really does nothing yeah there was some some literature maybe uh 15 or 20 years
ago on deep vein thrombosis and and lpa and there has been new studies published on that there's been
genome-wide association studies and we really don't see a signal for lpa being associated with
with deep vein thrombosis too so so that was part of the conversation part of the conversation for
a while but now i think it's pretty clear that it's really more closely associated with
atherosclerotic cardiovascular diseases and less with uh trombolic events
do you think i mean we do have an assay i believe for ox uh ox ldl correct yeah is that
assay picking up the oxidized phospholipid of lp little a included in that calculation no absolutely
totally different yeah yeah well there is actually an assay to measure uh oxidized
phospholipids on apo b containing is that is that sam tamekis's assay exactly exactly so they they
have an assay that measures ox pls on apo b including lpa of course and also ox pls on uh
apo lipoprotein little a so but the correlation coefficient between these two is very high and
the correlation between lpa levels and ox pl on apo b is also very high so uh of course that can
provide some information and there's been uh and obviously sam tamekis has measured uh ox pl on
apo b in all of the cohorts that that that he could put his his hands on and it's a good predictor of
all of the diseases that we've uh but is it is it a predictor beyond the level and the number of
lp little a particles no i don't think there's good evidence to suggest that it's it's a better
marker than or it predicts above and beyond lpa i think we should advise people to measure lpa
that that would be a gigantic step and then we can see if the if if at some point we have convincing
evidence that you know measuring oxidized phospholipid will bring in an added value but
i haven't seen much data that that that suggests that yeah and and i and i stopped measuring ox ldl
because i didn't see any benefit to it over apo b so it sounds like it's potentially the same thing
here and of course the whole you you'd hope that it would have benefit above and beyond so that it
would help you stratify risk further but uh interesting that it does not very complicated
to know what to make of this these these oxidized phospholipid tails that are sitting around their
wreaking havoc and potentially also forming part of this explanation for the for the for
the differential expression of the disease right yeah so so it's and it's the same for for ldl as
well so the ldl particles they get oxidized they also have oxidized phospholipids and that's one
of the reasons why ldl particle uh cause atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease but uh
the measuring them in the plasma will not it will not tell you how many oxidized ldl particles you
have in your in your plaque so uh so that's why we need to stick with uh with apo b and an lpa
because uh you'll get a you'll get a sense of all of the lipoproteins that that cause
atherosclerotic cardiovascular diseases so you alluded earlier to a pcsk9 protein which
we'll talk about um tell people before we get into the drug just tell people about the pcsk9 protein
how it works what its relationship is to the ldl receptor absolutely so pcsk9 uh it means
pro-protein convertase septilizin kexin type 9 it was discovered in 2003 by a collaboration between
nabil cedar who is at montreal and katrien bualo who is in france they had identified this family
in france that had familial hypercholesterolemia but they couldn't find a mutation in the ldl
receptor gene uh that explain the familial hypercholesterolemia so by the way before you
get into this i just want to say this is one of my absolute favorite stories in all of medicine
certainly in the modern era of medicine you know if you think the last 20 30 years this
story is remarkable so please yeah thanks for doing me the honor so so they had identified
this family that had fh without a mutation in the ldl receptor and the paper was published
in nature genetics in 2003 so you can think that they had been working on this for for a few years
so that was probably at the time where the human genome was being sequenced so that was uh during
the days of so that was pre genome-wide association studies and whole genome sequencing where
you were doing linkage analyses with satellite dna and yeah so i was an undergrad at that time
i was learning these these techniques and i wasn't in the lipids field so so i i heard that story
after but uh so so what they found is that uh they they were able to map the the gene in in that
family to a protein that was at the time called narc1 and so they they didn't know that that that
it was a pro-protein convertase so when they identified that uh that family in france they
partnered up with uh with nabil cedar who's um a world renowned scientist on uh pro-protein
convertases and they mapped it to narc1 which eventually became uh pcsk9 so the the way pcsk9
works is that it's a regulator of the ldl receptor so when the cells makes an ldl receptor
it will also make pcsk9 now pcsk9 can bind to the ldl receptor that can happen inside the cell
and when that happens uh the ldl receptor gets degraded in the lysosome that can also happen
extracellularly um when uh the ldl receptor obviously in the hepatocyte gets stuck at the
membrane but pcsk9 gets secreted so you can actually measure pcsk9 levels in the blood
but when it gets secreted it can actually bind the ldl receptor and when that happens the ldl
receptor cannot bind uh ldl particles and i told you earlier that uh ldl receptor density at the
surface of hepatocyte is super important for ldl clearance um so uh because pcsk9 can be uh can be
secreted and by the time that they had realized that they had shown that uh there were actually
families in in montreal that had a gain of function mutation in pcsk9 that had uh familial
hypercholesterolemia and then uh in 2006 the group of helen hobs at ut southwestern had shown that
there are common variants in pcsk9 that are associated with lower levels of of pcsk9 lower
levels of ldl and protection against uh cardiovascular diseases now the pharmaceutical
industry didn't need much more information to develop pcsk9 inhibitors right and and i remember
that paper like it was yesterday i mean it's hard to believe it's been yeah what is that now 16 16
years ago 16 years yeah absolutely yeah i i remember i was uh i was a master student at the
time and we were we were witnessing that and it was it was very a very exciting time um so let me
just make sure we go we synthesize that for people because it's such a big deal right so
familial hypercholesterolemia is a very heterogeneous disease there are at least 35 hundred mutations
that produce the exact same phenotype very very elevated cholesterol these are patients that have
total cholesterol typically north of 300 milligrams per deciliter ldl cholesterol by definition above
190 milligrams per deciliter of therapy and often much higher this disease is unequivocally linked
to accelerated as cvd and what was discovered in 2003 was yet another gene that was associated
with it but what made it different is most of the genes not all but most of the genes associated
with fh directly involved the ldl receptor this one didn't seem to instead they discovered that
it was this protein that wreaks havoc on the ldl receptor when it's over expressed either by
degrading the ldl receptor in the lysosome before it gets brought to the surface or frankly just
interfering with the receptor when it's at the surface does pcsk9 also degrade um ldl receptors
or increase their turnover when they are at the surface of hepatocytes yeah exactly that's that's
exactly what i was going to say that's the third mechanism through which uh pcsk9 can influence
ldl receptor density because what people don't really appreciate is that the ldl receptor when
it does its job of bringing ldl particles within the hepatocytes gets recycled at the surface of
the hepatocyte and that can happen a hundred times in the in the life of the ldl receptor because it
takes a lot of energy to the cell to make the ldl to produce the ldl receptor and once and a pcsk9
is bound to an ldl receptor then it prevents its recycling so so the cell has to make more
ldl receptor and when it does that because they're under genetic control of the srebp2
um transcription factor so then the ldl receptor gets produced and so is pcsk9 so so you can have
this uh this vicious cycle so um and it's interesting to think that if if the story had
stopped there it's not clear we'd be where we are today without the 2006 paper which showed
wow as bad as that gain of function is the loss of function is really amazing where now you found
these people who had the opposite of fh these are people who were basically missing their pcsk9 not
completely just significantly under expressed and these were people that as adults walked around
with neonate levels of ldl cholesterol 10 20 30 milligrams per deciliter yeah so so the the most
frequent um uh variant that they look at was present in two percent of the population and
they saw a very mild ldl reduction so they i don't remember this is 2006 so i'm gonna say
20 reduction in in ldl but you know it's a lifelong reduction right that's right the mr
would still suggest that that's beneficial exactly but there has been some that there has
been some studies on as you say patients or individuals that have virtually no ldl because
they have no pcsk9 really and they don't have of course atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease
because you need ldl for that but they have uh they're perfectly fit uh you know that doesn't
influence reproduction or hormones or or anything uh they have uh they don't have like
dementia no exactly no increase in the risk of other diseases so they have normal risk for cancer
alzheimer's disease every other disease and they just don't have the risk of ascvd and their ldl
cholesterol is 10 20 milligrams per deciliter very important teaching point here i think for
for the listener which is it might be tempting to say how can someone with such little cholesterol
in their plasma not have other problems when we understand the importance of cholesterol in
creating lipid bilayers of cells and being a precursor to steroidal hormones and i addressed
this in a previous podcast but i think it's worth stating this again when you look at how much
cholesterol is in the body and isolate that fraction which is in the plasma even if you take
that to zero you've maybe reduced the total body pool of cholesterol by about 10 percent so yeah
and and there's still some cholesterol in the blood right because uh deliver will secrete very
low density lipoproteins that will not necessarily be targeted by by pcsk9 and there's high density
protein as well so you still have a total cholesterol that might fall from 180 milligrams
per deciliter it might fall to 70 milligrams per deciliter or 60 milligrams per deciliter but it's
not zero you're right but you know the the point is you still have so much cholesterol in extra
like an extra apo b tissue right the this the red blood cells all of the tissue the hepatocytes
etc so yeah and we're seeing that also in the the trials because uh well obviously the industry
develop antibodies monoclonal antibodies against pcsk9 and these have been tested in two large
cardiovascular outcomes trials and they've shown that if you reduce LDL through these pcsk9 inhibitors
you get a reduction in in cardiovascular events and and now in these trials now these were all
patients that were already treated with statins and you add on to that a pcsk9 inhibitor and you
really bring LDL cholesterol levels to the floor and in postdoc analyses of these trials you can
see that the benefit was also correlated with the reduction in LDL levels so patients that have
the lowest LDL levels had the lowest risk of having a second event is i say second event
because these were these trials were done in patients with stable cad and also acute coronary
syndrome so it really tells us that there's there doesn't seem we haven't identified yet the the
level of LDL that's that's so low that it's going to harm any physiological or disease process
yeah it's such it's such an important point um and and again i think you know you're referring
to foyer and odyssey i gotta tell you this is one of those beautiful moments again where it
i i was a little worried that foyer and odyssey were not going to be positive trials especially
foyer um because you'll recall foyer the patients had an average starting LDL cholesterol in the
70s i can't remember if it was 71 or 77 i think the mean was 90 and they brought it back down to 30
milligrams what was the mean 90 i thought the mean at the beginning was in the 70s but i could be
wrong there there was not an entry level of LDL sometimes you see that in these kinds of trials
you have to bring the LDL down to a certain level uh but that was not the case so it was they were
just being treated with uh standard of care which is obviously yeah so these were on very high doses
of statins so if you're right and they were if they came in on a statin maximally and their LDL
was 90 that's still very low that still puts them at the 10th percentile i thought it was 70 so that
would have been at the fifth percentile but the point is when patients come in and they already
have such a low LDL you add a drug that lowers them to the 30s but the trial was only five years
and my thought was there's no way in five years you that's not long enough to see a benefit
when the patients are starting out so low and that turned out to be wrong so the trial was
supposed to last five years it was 4.2 but they saw a benefit at 2.2 years oh wait that's right
it was 2.2 and four years exactly and odyssey was 2.4 years or something exactly exactly so me too uh
so basically they stopped the trial when they knew they had an effect but when the trial was
published uh that was in 2017 no august of 15 i think okay well that long okay well there had been
postdoc analyses uh from from phase three trials that were uh that were very positive in the new
england journal i i don't know if you're referring to these papers but uh anyway so for your trial
uh sorry yes yes i'm referring to the fda approval which was on the earliest analysis which was
august of 15 obviously subsequent analyses came after but but i believe at that point you had the
2.2 and the 2.4 year data because basically rapatha and praluent were approved within a month of each
other if my memory serves me correctly yeah based on their LDL lowering and not necessarily on their
effect of cardiovascular disease so i was actually very surprised because in that trial the
relative risk reduction if you compare pc sk9 with placebo was only 15 so people were kind of
expecting like a 20 plus percent reduction and uh many people were kind of disappointed by by that
but i mean it happened over 2.2 years only so that's what's underappreciated i remember
i can't remember if i wrote a blog post about this and if i didn't i'm sure i wrote it in an email
to a friend and i hope i could find that email but it was a friend of mine who worked at a hedge fund
yeah so it must have been an email i don't think i wrote a blog post he said because you remember
amgen's price share price declined with those results yeah and it was i think it was because
they didn't hit the relative risk reduction it was so modest and and i said to him i said that's a
miss that's that tells me wall street doesn't understand atherosclerosis if you can hit a 15
percent relative risk reduction which ultimately turned into a bigger risk reduction in 2.2 years
on a group of patients who show up on the maximum dose of astatin whose LDL is already at the 10th
percentile you've you've changed the you've changed the field of cardiovascular medicine
yeah i i completely agree and i was saying i remember thinking this that you know if they
really wanted to make a trial to increase their stock price they they would have made make it
the full four years right because then you would have seen the biggest increase because if you look
at the cap and myer curves they're still going in opposite direction they haven't stabilized
so and i talked earlier about the cholesterol treatment trial is curve the the data from the
four year in odyssey trial they fall exactly on the same curve where you're looking at achieved
apob levels and reduction in event it's right there at the at the lower end of the curves of
the curve of course because that's that's the in that's a trial in which they they saw the the
biggest reduction in in ldl apob so let's go back and close the loop on one thing before we now talk
about pcs canine and lp little a so you've explained now why a pcs canine inhibitor the drugs we're
talking about are so effective in lowering apob because they're basically mimicking the most
extreme loss of function of this gene you're taking away that protein that does those three
things to reduce lp ldl clearance why is it remind us that statins don't lower lp little a
you would think well we know why statins get the ldl receptor to be more dense that should do it so
the the the obvious explanation here is ldl receptors don't clear lp little a but why is
that isn't an lp little a just an ldl with a little extra thing on it why is that causing
so much difficulty for the statin i told you earlier that lpa levels were determined by their
rate of production and one of the players that was an unanticipated player in in april a lpa
slash a poa production is actually pcs canine because if you uh incubate cells liver cells with
with with pcs canine you'll see the expression of a poa going up and in lipoprotein turnover studies
you also see that so if you treat people with a pcs canine inhibitor you will actually see a
reduction in the production rate of of a poa and there was a nice study that's a bit complex to
to fully appreciate by gerald watts who's in pert australia he's shown this but he also showed in
a second group that if you treat patients with a pcs canine inhibitor and the statin you see the
and that's probably what where the ldl receptor presence gets maximized at the surface of the
liver cells you can actually see clearance or increment in the fractional catabolic rate
of of lpa so there's still so much that we don't know in this in this area so and it's not totally
clear why we see this difference of pcs canine inhibitors that's depending on whether or not
you're treated with a with a statin and i think all comers we see that a pcs canine inhibitor is
lowering lp little a by is about 30 is the on average yeah and so the average is is probably
between 25 and 30 percent in all comers yeah but the variability is enormous i mean i exactly the
very the variability is is very important and it's another example where we need to study patients
that have high lpa because these are the patients that we want to provide an answer to and there's
only been one trial that had tested the effect of a pcs canine inhibitor on in patients with lpa
there there had been sub-analyses in foria and odyssey outcomes and when you look at that trial
it's called the anichco trials and all these postdoc analyses of of randomized control trials
of pcs canine inhibitors you see that in patients with high lpa the reduction is approximately 15
so it's not spectacular and in in the anichco trial what they did is that they've looked at
arterial wall inflammation using fluoro deoxy glucose this is a trial run by
zai fayed at mount sinai in new york and eric streuze in amsterdam they showed that even though
you you reduce ldl by i don't know what percentage but it was a spectacular reduction in ldl a very
small reduction in lpa of 15 you don't see any effect on arterial wall inflammation so that means
that you know there's an important residual risk that's associated with lpa because
if you lower ldl with pcs canine inhibitors you know there's no outcomes data although they did
link lpa with recurrent cardiovascular disease in this in these trials you see that the pro
inflammatory effect of lpa on the vasculature still remains so we're gonna have to go after lpa even
in patients that have very low very low levels of ldl there's no doubt about it and so is one
interpretation of the fact that pcs canine inhibitors can lower lpa by 30 but that might
not be sufficient to ameliorate the lpa risk specifically is that it's just simply not enough
it gets back to what you said earlier yeah it you're going to have to eliminate lpa and it
becomes a bit more of a step function than the gradient we see with apo b yeah i don't know if
we need to eliminate lp little a but we need to take we need to get it probably below and bring
it down yeah yeah yeah to a lower level so that brings us what they're testing yeah so that that
brings us to where we are today right so what's the state of the art today in 2022 with my patients
who have elevated lp little a i take a two two prong effect uh when it comes to lipid management
obviously there's many things we're doing outside of lipid management the first is absolutely
eradicating apo b so we're very aggressive on this because it's very clear that you can do this
safely and effectively we target an apo b of about 30 to 40 milligrams per deciliter so we target an
apo b at what we would call a physiologic level so the level that a child would have it's clear
that a child can have an apo b of 30 and have no problems with development which is the most
cholesterol demanding period of their life so there's absolutely no reason that we shouldn't
be able to take an adult there um without side effects meaning provided we can do it without
side effects from the medications but the second thing we do is we're very liberal in the use of
pcsk9 inhibitors because even though we don't know the answer yet our belief is even if it wax
it 30 which is about what we see we see on average about a 30 reduction lp little a it's worth it
until we get to antisense oligonucleotides so let's talk about antisense oligonucleotides what are
they yeah now before we get into that uh i'll tell you that i do the same thing i mean uh i'm
going to turn uh 4d this year so i decide i decided to have to have a lipid check and
have my lpa remeasured and it's very high it's at 200 nanomolars i knew that because i had my
genotype done with uh direct to consumer uh company and and they let you look at your own data so
they they send you all of your SNP information so i went and looked at my favorite SNP in lpa and i
was a carrier of one of the most famous mutations in lpa so and that's exactly what i decided to do
so my LDL was a bit higher than than average my lpa was high so i just started to uh to take a
statin and of course i've been on close to vegetarian diet for more than three years i
i'm physically active but you know at some points you have to look at at your at your labs and say
well there's i need to do more so so even i started taking a statin even though i'm not 40 yet
because i i i see those studies and i see the importance of going after LDL very early and
very aggressively now i'm not on a super high dose i need to have it to check it after three months
but um but if it doesn't go down i'll increase the dose so so and that's i think what uh people who
have high lpa should do so coming down to the uh oligo the antisense oligonucleotides against
lpa this is a very exciting time for uh for lpa research so the probably the the first horse in
the race will be uh the the compound by ionus pharmaceuticals so it is an antisense oligonucleotides
against the lpa gene well all of them all of them will be and the second one is uh the and they
just released some data on this in the in nature medicine a couple of months ago uh and it's called
all passurin it's uh it's not an oligonucleotide it's an si RNA against lpa it's the compound by
amgen and i believe they'll they'll need to do a phase three trial but with the first one with the
ionus compound there ionus is the company that used to be called isis like before exactly before it
became horrible to have the name isis it was it's a san diego based company i remember i used to swim
with a guy who worked there and he had a his his duffel bag which was from works at isis on it and
i was like yeah you're probably going to want to change that yeah you can't board a plane with that
so um so yeah so they they have they they already uh have phase two data that's been published in
2020 uh in patients with atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease a very nice dose ascending
study and they've shown that in the dose that they're going to use in their trial which is a
monthly uh injection you can get mean reduction of lpa levels of 80 even in patients with high lpa
so that's very encouraging because this is what we're going to need to uh to to prevent uh heart
attacks and and and obviously to have successful cardiovascular outcomes trial and in that study
they also showed that uh 90 of patients who were treated on that dose had lpa levels below 50
milligrams per deciliter so it's very potent it's a second generation um antisense oligonucleotide
and they have launched a trial a cardiovascular outcomes trial that's called horizon and they're
recruiting a little under 8 000 patients with stable cardiovascular diseases and they will
study the effect of lpa in of their antisense oligonucleotides in the prevention of major
atherosclerotic cardiovascular events and is this a secondary prevention trial it is a secondary
prevention trial so this is where you have to start uh you have to take the patients that have
the highest risk to have uh to have a positive trials there's uh to my knowledge there's no uh
plan for a trial in primary prevention but that will that will be the off way eventually have to
come yeah so yeah do you do you have a sense of how far they are in their enrollment because
this trial and maybe it's just because of how emotionally invested i am in this i don't i have
a normal lp little a but it's just i think i take care of enough patients that don't
this trial feels to me like the molasses rolling uphill in january trial and as a as a kibbe kwa
you can appreciate the speed with which molasses will roll uphill in january what is taking so long
this is a trial that feels like it's a year away from being completed every year for the past seven
years yeah well uh first of all uh being an investigator in a research center at times of
covid was very very difficult to bring people into the hospital for an exploratory trial so
so so that has had i i don't know for that specific trial but i can tell you for any lab
or any clinical research facility the any patient that were recruited and especially in our hospital
we're the the covid hospital for the entire region so i mean people don't want to come here
during during a pandemic so so i i'm thinking that this is probably part of the of the explanation
so we'll have the result of that trial probably in 2025 because um i told you earlier that trial
is going to be 8 000 patients when i saw that i thought well this is not enough i mean they
they need to do a big trial and this is it's it's it's kind of risky to do a trial in only 8 000
patients but the way i understand it it's that is that they're going to use the full four years of
their uh of their treatment period so even though you have less patients and for instance
foyer or odyssey outcomes that have 16 15 000 yeah exactly so they're recruiting half for the
roughly the same population so but they're they're gonna they're gonna study it for a longer period
so that might also explain why it's not going to be published uh anytime soon and we need we need
to be patients and i'm really looking forward to seeing the the results of that trial because they
hold the the fate of the entire field in their in their hands so really looking forward and also
especially for the for the for the patients really looking forward to seeing the results of that
trial and i hope that there will be other companies i know there are there's three companies
that have antisense oligonucleotides against lpa so you have ionis which is partnering with
novartis for the for the the the trial amgen has one and there's also another sirny company called
silence therapeutics that have that have an lpa inhibitor i don't think they have released
their phase one study yet but i think we'll see more and more of of these companies because
there's still there's still money to make i think in that in that area of of residual cardiovascular
risk because we can target ldl as as low as we want and there's still a an underappreciated
amount of residual risk that's associated with with with different things with triglycerides
inflammation but the first thing that comes to mind to me is is the risk associated with high lpa
it's an amazing decade we're in if in fact this study is published in in 2015 uh pardon me in
2025 you'll have exactly a decade between the approval of pcsk9 inhibitors and potentially
the approval of this antisense oligonucleotide for lp little a and you could argue that those
two things will have an outsized effect on on human health so benoit i want to thank you very
much for spending all this time with me today and by extension with all of our listeners this is
such an important topic that i think of this almost as a a public service announcement uh if
you're listening to this podcast there's a at least a 10 and maybe a 20 chance that your lp
little a is elevated you really need to demand that your physician checks this level we think
that the milligram per deciliter mass uh measurement is probably sufficient and if you're
elevated on that level at least at this moment in time the best thing that we can do is keep apo
b as low as possible and manage all of the other manageable risk factors hypertension smoking
insulin resistance etc that that traffic with atherosclerotic uh cardiovascular disease the
other thing i think we can at least i would be comfortable recommending i know you're not a
physician so you probably wouldn't be comfortable making a recommendation i would also insist that
you at least once have an echocardiogram to look for even the earliest signs of aortic stenosis
as it is imminently more treatable and the outcomes are better if it is addressed earlier
well thank you peter for having me and thank you for raising awareness on on on health da was a real
pleasure talking to you today yeah the pleasure was mine thanks benoit thank you for listening
to this week's episode of the drive if you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we
discuss we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth exclusive
content without relying on paid ads it's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price
of the subscription now to that end membership benefits include a bunch of things one totally
kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic paper person thing we discuss
on each episode the word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these monthly ama episodes or
ask me anything episodes hearing these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed
that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this the qualies which
are a super short podcast that we release every tuesday through friday highlighting the best
questions topics and tactics discussed on previous episodes of the drive this is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone
steep discounts on products that i believe in but for which i'm not getting paid to endorse
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on if you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits you can head over to peteratiamd.com
forward slash subscribe you can find me on twitter instagram and facebook all with the id
peteratiamd you can also leave us a review on apple podcast or whatever podcast player you
listen on this podcast is for general informational purposes only does not constitute the practice of
medicine nursing or other professional health care services including the giving of medical advice
no doctor patient relationship is formed the use of this information and the materials linked to
this podcast is at the user's own risk the content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute
for professional medical advice diagnosis or treatment users should not disregard or delay
in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they have and they should seek the
assistance of their health care professionals for any such conditions finally i take conflicts of
interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the companies i invest in or advise please
visit peteratiamd.com forward slash about where i keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies