Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Max, thanks so much for making time today. So wonderful to see you again. It's been a
lot of years, huh?
It's been a long time. Actually, I can't remember the last time we saw each other, but since
we kind of, we started together in medical school at Stanford, but then finished a little
bit different times. It's kind of, I think it's been a while since we saw each other.
Yeah. Well, as I was sort of joking earlier, this is, we're going to have like a whole
subset of the Drive podcast, which is based on the Stanford MSTP students between Carl,
you and Josh. So, you know, again, kind of speaks to the quality of people that, you
know, were a part of that program. So let's tell folks a little bit about kind of work
you did. So as you mentioned, obviously we started in medical school together. We have
some really funny stories from the beginning of medical school, which I think will refrain
from telling at this point in time. But they, I could have a whole podcast just on some
of that stuff. And then after the first two years of medical school, I went right off
into the clinical stuff and then you went off into the lab. Tell folks about whose lab
you went to and what it is that you started pursuing and frankly, how you even made that
decision.
As you pointed out, as part of the MD PhD program here, the way it is done in most programs,
you split the curriculum with splitting medical school in half, doing the first two more classroom
based years first, then doing the PhD work in the laboratory and then going back for
the clinical work. And so that is, there's an important transition point there when you're
finishing the classroom part of medical school and deciding what lab to work in. And I ultimately
chose to do my dissertation with Pat Brown, who is a professor of biochemistry here at
Stanford. He is no longer, a lot of your listeners may know of him though, because
he's now a CEO of Impossible Foods or was until recently, I think he just transitioned
to a slightly different role, but founder and CEO of initially of Impossible Foods.
But he was here, a faculty member. And what really attracted me to his lab was that he
had just around that time invented a technology for measuring the expression of basically
all the genes in the genome with a technique called DNA microarrays. And that at the time
was revolutionary. Before that we were always measuring everything in one or a handful of
genes at a time in experiments. And now we could measure tens of thousands in one experiment.
And it just seemed to me that this was opening up whole new fields that we would be able
to learn so much. And that's why I chose to pursue that lab.
So what did you do for your actual dissertation? What was the project that you worked on?
I had a little bit unusual dissertation that I worked on many different projects. It was
a very unique time in the lab and Pat's lab as well as in labs in general where, and I've
seen this happen since several times, but when there's a new technology that's developed
that's sort of transformative, it opens up so many doors simultaneously that you have
this new tool that no one's ever had before, a new lens through which to view biology.
And so you can just immediately think of thousands of questions that would be interesting to
ask. And so I worked on a variety of different things, but mainly two main areas. One is
immunology, the other oncology or cancer biology. And those were my two interests coming into
medical school. And so, you know, I felt fortunate I was able to do projects in some of both.
As far as, you know, maybe I just had one or two of them. One of the projects was focused
on T cells, which are a type of course of white bloods or a lymphocyte that are a critical
part of the adaptive immune system. And so we had this new tool to measure all the genes
in the human genome at one time to see how they go up and down after you perturb cells.
And so we were very interested to see what genes are turned on and off in T cells when
you activate them, when you stimulate them through their receptor, the T cell receptor,
either by itself or with a costimulatory signal.
You would look at the T cell, it's stimulated and you're, are you actually measuring protein?
Or RNA.
You're not RNA.
Yeah, the technology was a way of measuring RNA, that's what transcripts, so the intermediate
between DNA and proteins, of course. And so we could see, you know, hundreds and thousands
of genes changing as we manipulated the cells. And so building a catalog of all the genes
that are turned on or down regular turned off when you activate T cells using different
signals. And that catalog then, of course, has been very helpful for subsequent studies
in better understanding and teasing apart the mechanism of T cell activation, which
has gotten increasingly more interesting, of course, now with the advent of immunotherapy.
Yeah, so there's a lot of things there that are interesting. One of them is the instability
of RNA. This is going to become relevant as we start to talk about the differences between
cell-free DNA and RNA. But at the time, how difficult was it to basically keep all of
this RNA intact as you cataloged the generation of mRNA from DNA as this signal of gene expression?
I mean, was that one of the big technical challenges of this technique?
That for sure is a hurdle in all work that's focused on RNA, which as you mentioned, is
chemically relatively unstable, particularly when you compare it to DNA, which is much more stable.
And so one has to be very careful in any experiment, whether you measure a single RNA or where you
measure 20,000 RNAs, to really try to preserve the sample in a way such that you minimize the
potential chemical degradation of RNA. So there are, you know, relabatory methods to do that,
of course. So for example, if you're in that example of the T cell stimulation experiment,
you know, the cells are alive, the RNA, of course, is maintained. It's really once the cells die,
that the degradation issue starts happening. So you design the experiment in such a way that
you're very careful to immediately, you know, add solutions that protect the RNA after you kill the
cells at the end of the experiment so that there's no time for chemical degradation processes.
I had a, my other main project in the PhD was actually, we really struggled with this because
it was a separate project, my rotation project, which is the first project you do in a lab when
you're kind of trying to figure out if you want to go there, where we developed a method to isolate
RNA that stuck to the endoplasmic reticulum inside cells, because that is where RNAs go for genes
that are secreted from the cells or that are surface proteins in the cells. And we were
interested in cataloging those because those are interesting for diagnostic purposes and therapeutic
purposes. So we had to purify the subset of the RNA that was stuck to the, these organelles called
the endoplasmic reticulum. And to do that, there's a very long procedure where you have to build
special gradients and float, you know, gently slice the cells and then they float the membranes
that they're stuck to to various levels in a test tube. And that required a lot of work in a cold
room where, you know, you're busy, you test tubes into four degree room, but so is the experimenter.
You know, you have to wear jackets and stuff because you're working basically in a fridge,
and it's all to maintain the integrity of the RNA, as well as you can add chemicals to try to
stabilize the RNA. So this is something that was critical at the time to really try to work out
methods to stabilize the RNA.
And how much of an insight could you get into non-coding sequences of genes where they're not
making proteins, but we now know, of course, that these non-coding segments can be very important as
well. Could you gain any insights there?
So with the technique we were using at that time, we could not directly because we were focused on
measuring the coding portions of the genes, of the transcripts that code for proteins. And we had to
decide at the beginning of each experiment which genes we measured, because basically we had to
create a probe for each.
You had to have the primers and...
You had to have the primers for it. And so you had to make a decision. So at the time, we were not
focused on that. But subsequently, this approach was used in some of the early work on long
non-coding RNAs, and I was largely led by a former postdoc from Pat Brown's lab who was there while I
was a grad student named Howard Chang, who is a professor here at Stanford, as you may know.
So I think you finished your PhD in about three years, correct?
Well, yes, it took about three years. Yeah, three years, something like that.
And then you went back now and you started your clinical rotations. Did you have a sense when you
went back for the last two years of medical school that you definitely wanted to be a clinician? So
which would mean not just finishing medical school, but then doing a residency? Or because, you know,
some people in the empty PhD program, you know, just say, look, I just want to be a pure scientist, not a
physician scientist, I'm going to finish medical school and get my MD, but I'm not going to do any
clinical training. Where were you on that spectrum at the beginning of that final two years?
I was set on doing a residency. I wasn't sure yet in what, but I was set on doing it. You know,
actually, my sort of decision point was for me was made prior to med school when I was an undergrad.
Initially, I thought I was going to do graduate school and go for a PhD and focus on research for my
career. But then my father was diagnosed with lymphoma while I was junior in college. And the,
you know, the journey that he went through and interacting with the oncologist and the medical team
as part of that and really seeing how little we knew about many things and how suboptimal treatments
were really convinced me that that number one, I know, I want to be on the doctor side, not just on
the patient side with my father and be able to help people help patients at the time of their life,
what might be the worst time of their life, as well as to try to move the field forward to improve
treatments that, you know, while they worked somewhat, obviously were not good enough.
And so does that mean that even coming into medical school, not only did you know you wanted to be a
physician and a scientist, but did you already have kind of an inkling that oncology was where you
wanted to be? That's exactly right. Yes. I knew I wanted to work in one of the cancer specialties. What I
didn't realize when I was the first you met students how many options they are in that, of course, you
know, you were probably looking at it mostly through the lens of medical oncology. That's right. Whereas,
of course, you have surgical oncology, radiation oncology and other sorts of avenues. That's right.
And remind me, were you born in Germany? Were you born in the US?
No, I was born in Germany. I was born in Munich, and I didn't come to the US till I was 11 years old.
Okay. And you grew up on the East Coast?
Yes, we initially moved to South Florida. And then when I was a sophomore in high school, we moved to
Connecticut, the Northeast. And then I went to Harvard as an undergrad. So I was in the Northeast until I came
out here, but then I've never never left anywhere. And I've lived longer here than anywhere else.
Yeah, I know that feeling. So you go into the clinic, and now it's basically a decision of, you know,
medical oncology, radiation oncology, or God forbid, something like surgical oncology, though, I'm
guessing that was probably third on the list of three options.
You know, I did honestly strongly consider it. I do like the the procedural aspects of it. And that's the
one reason why I chose what I chose. So I did, you know, every surgical, my surgical change, when I had a
choice, I always chose the oncologic subspecialties and you know, did some surgeon, did some gynon surgery
rotations, but ultimately chose not to do that in large part, because I, you know, I saw that, I thought it
would be difficult to balance with with research. And of course, people do it very successfully. But but I
think it is harder in general in the surgical specialties.
So how did you ultimately decide on radiation oncology then?
Yeah, radiation oncology, as you mentioned, I was sort of leaning towards medical oncology, because that's what I'd
seen through my dad's journey. But I did a rotation in radiation oncology actually, in large part, because my
wife, who was also a medical student at Stanford, who you of course know, did a research year in the Department of
Radiation Oncology. She at the time was also interested in oncology. And so that actually is how I got exposed to the
field. While we were dating, I would often visit her in the lab. And so, you know, I kind of got exposed in that way to
the department in the field. And then so it made me want to try it as a rotation. And then I really enjoyed it. I not a
variety of things I enjoyed about it. From a patient care standpoint, the it seemed to me that the radiation
oncologist had a little more time in clinic to spend with each patient. We generally see less patients in a day than
might be seen in medical oncology. And that seemed very attractive to me. The other thing I really liked was the
technology aspects. I was always been interested in technology aspects, you know, both new technologies in the research
space, but then also, you know, technologies for treating patients with radiation oncology is very procedurally heavy.
It's, of course, a field where we do a lot of imaging to see where tumors are in the patient's body. And then we have
fancy robots that deliver the radiation very precisely. So it just seemed like a great field to combine my love of
oncology and patient care with my interests in technology development. And then lastly, I kind of saw it as a field where
they really compared to medical oncology, there wasn't as much work being done in the laboratory at the molecular level.
And it seemed like an opportunity to make a difference in a field where there weren't so many people working.
You know, one of the things I talked about with Carl was the challenge of keeping his hand in the lab during those last two
years of medical school and then during his psychiatry residency. He mentioned that he was he really found himself in a great
situation when he did his residency, where he was effectively allowed to do kind of a postdoc. And he was freed from, you
know, certain things. He didn't go to lab meetings and journal clubs and things like that. But he still got to do a little bit of
work. Were you able to do anything like that during your residency or were you really strictly focused on just the clinical
training for it? Was it four years?
Yeah, so radiation ecology is I did an internship in medicine here at Stanford and then it's four years of radiation
oncology. So five years. During internship, of course, as you I'm sure remember, there is no time to do anything else.
Although I do remember trying to write some papers in the call room, you know, finishing up work from from the PhD. But the
for the radiation oncology residency programs have a research track for individuals who are interested in laboratory based
research called the Holman pathway, which is in other fields, kind of called short tracking or fast tracking. It's a similar idea
where basically one can trade in some of the clinical training time for research time. And so that's what I did, which gave me a
postdoc time of about two years during my four years of radiation oncology residency. During that postdoc time, I had clinic
activities about half a day to a day a week. And the rest of the other days were in the lab. So it actually was a really good
preview of what, you know, my life would be like once I finished all the training and was a faculty member myself. And so that that
allowed me to kind of keep a foot in the clinic while mainly focusing on the postdoctoral research.
So when you finished your training, obviously, the first decision you had to make is do you want to stay at Stanford? I'm guessing that
between, you know, the connections you already had there, Jenny was probably by this point already out of her training and in practice, that was
probably a very high activation energy to leave. Tell me about the Department of Radiation Oncology at Stanford. Was it a natural fit for the
types of problems you wanted to solve on the research side?
Yes, I mean, the department here at Stanford has a very long history. It was actually one of the very first departments of radiation
oncology in the US. Radiation oncology grew out of radiology, which is, as you listen to part, now is a diagnostic arm of radiology where you do
imaging mainly to diagnose disease. And initially, back in the 50s, 40s, 50s, it was part of radiation culture, it was part of those
departments. But then here, our first chairman, Henry Kaplan, who is a very famous radiation oncologist and physician scientist, became the first
chair of radiation oncology and sort of led the movement to develop it as its own specialty. And then he quickly put the department on the map because of his work in
curing Hodgkin's disease with radiotherapy, which, you know, was this was in the around the 50s, where, you know, those were some of the first successes of taking
patients, young patients with a Hodgkin's disease, which is a type of lymphoma that was incurable previously, who now, you know, the majority could be
cured with radiation, made the New York Times, you know, at the time, and all that, you know, was headlines. And at the time, you know, there were articles about how now
radiation will cure all cancer and look, we're on the path, you know, that, of course, didn't turn out to be that way. We still have many, many patients we can't cure. But it sort of was one of the first
examples of this, the hype that you get at each time a new therapy comes where, you know, then think, oh, now we've really solved it. But ultimately, you know, it gets more
complicated. But that, of course, established department is one of the very leading departments in the world. And it is continued that the department here throughout its history has
had a very strong interest in laboratory based research is all thanks to Henry Kaplan, who was doing laboratory research at the time, also while seeing patients. And so there were already faculty that were
laboratory based, even just PhDs who were fully laboratory based, which wasn't the case in many radiation college departments. And so I really liked that here, that within radiation ecology, this was a place where I could see that the kind of research I wanted to do was valued. And there was already, you know, mentors that had done it successfully. And those things are important when you're a young physician scientist to have mentors that can show you, if you run into trouble, how to overcome obstacles.
At what point in your evolution did the idea of liquid biopsies start to become of interest? Obviously, that's something I really want to talk about today, because it's, it's something that I think people are just starting to hear about. I mean, it's something I've been following for about six years.
Obviously, you've been following it for a lot longer than that. But I think even in the, in the, in the sort of broader public eye, the past year, I think a lot has happened to bring this to the fore. But, but I still think for many people, it's still a bit of a black box.
So, so at what point, how many years ago did this sort of become something that landed on your screen as an area where you wanted to put focus?
Yes. So as these things often happen, I did not start my lab with the idea of focusing on liquid biopsies. I really got there by following the results we got from some experiments. And, you know, I think one of the keys to being successful scientist, whether you're a physician scientist or a laboratory, purely laboratory scientist is following the data, following the data that you generate to where it leads you.
As opposed to folk, you know, saying I have to work in one area. So I was actually going to work on a different air initially. I started this whole, this line of work in my laboratory initially out of a clinic, a clinical need I saw.
And that's in general how I run my laboratory, all the research projects we do. We start with a clinical need or a clinical area where they're suboptimal. We're doing the clinic, whether it's for diagnostic purposes or treatment purpose or whatever.
With the idea being that that, you know, that's of course one of the things that having being a physician and taking care of patients is one of the things that I spent a lot of years learning about and also what I have insights into that others might not.
And that's one way I can, you know, be a useful contributor to the field in general. And so we always start with clinical areas of clinical need. And here in this case, it was one of the main things I struggled with as a junior faculty member, which is that I decided to specialize in treating lung cancer clinically.
One day a week, once I was on faculty, I was doing clinic one day a week and I saw lung cancer patients exclusively. And I was very frustrated by the fact that after I treated patients, so I treat a lot of early stage lung cancer patients, these are patients that are stage one or two lung cancer, which means as far as we can tell, the lung cancer hasn't spread yet. It's still, it's just in the lung where it started and hasn't spread anywhere.
And with targeted high dose radiation, I can cure the majority of those patients. But there's, let's say, about 20, 25% of those patients who ultimately develop recurrence where the cancer comes back. But after I finished my treatment and that first, you know, follow up visit, let's say three months after I do the radiation, I could not tell who was going to ultimately have the cancer come back and who had been cured.
So state of the art at the time, and actually, you know, it's still state of the art today in many ways, is just to see the patient every three, six, 12 months as you get further out and to do scans and see if the cancer has come back without any way of predicting in whom it will, right?
It's really just, it's a very reactive approach and very unsatisfying. And this is something we went through with my dad also. So this was a major frustration for me.
And also, and also very difficult because of the resolution, right? I mean, give people a sense of the resolution we have with traditional imaging. So if, if I assume, where are we at on CT scanners? Are we at 256 bit? Are we, what's the, what's the resolution and speed of a CT scanner today?
There is a wide variety of that. And that, that, that you may better ask somebody who works in that specific field of building those scanners. But the, I think, I mean, to rephrase your question a little bit is, you know, what's how small of a tumor can we see?
Yeah, that's where I'm really going, which is, you know, it's, if you can see a one by one by one centimeter or a one centimeter diameter tumor, that's, you're doing pretty well, right? You can probably see a little smaller than that.
That's exactly right. So it is hard to see things much smaller than, you know, one centimeter in diameter, maybe eight millimeters. It depends a little bit on the location in the body. Some areas, of course, it's easier to see smaller things than others, but that's inherently true.
And so how many cells is that?
Yes. So that's great question. And, you know, the general sort of rule of thumb is that's about a billion cells already, which is of course, a vast number of cancer cells, you know, again, at the time when we can just barely detect it in a patient.
And I think it's important for patients to understand the non-linearity of this. So you have everything shy of a billion cells is by conventional detection methods undetectable, right?
And then, but a built, but, you know, outside of the most rare tumors, anything at a centimeter is not posing a direct threat to the organism, you know, maybe a really badly placed brain tumor at one centimeter is problematic.
But for the most part, if you talk about a lung cancer, liver cancer, pancreatic cancer, colon cancer, et cetera, breast cancer, one centimeter is irrelevant.
At what point does a tumor become in and of itself threatening to the host? I mean, you could argue by the time it's 10 centimeters by 10 centimeters by 10 centimeters, the burden of tumor itself is fatal.
And that's how many cells there roughly when you're at the point where the burden of the tumor is actually fatal.
Yeah. So the, of course, whether tumors fail or not, as you point out greatly depends on the location.
And in certain areas, one can have a ton of tumor without it being fatal. In other areas, you have very little room for that.
But, you know, obviously it's a volumetric, right? So it grows by the cube, by the radius multiplied by itself three times.
And that is, of course, non-linear. It grows much faster. The number of cells in a mass are much more, you know, than just the linear increase in the diameter of the lesion.
Yeah. And I think that's the part that's just hard to understand for because we don't we think linearly pretty well. We don't think exponentially very well.
But again, I think I want people to just anchor to this idea that from zero to a billion cells, we're pretty much flying blind.
That's exactly right. And it's actually relevant to the work, some of the work that we're now doing.
If you realize that many cancers, once they have metastasized or spread, which is really ultimately what ends up killing patients is once the usually when the cancer spreads.
The cancer is only localized. Usually a surgeon or a radiation oncologist can cure that patient. But once the cancer spread and is in many places in the body, you can't remove it all or radiate it all. Right.
So if you think about a patient who has what's called micrometastatic disease or microscopic disease that has spread elsewhere in the body, you can have dozens or even hundreds of these micrometastatic deposits that are under under half a centimeter.
And so technically tens of billions of cells and it's still undetectable. And it's still exactly right. And that is a critical issue where that that's a limitation of blind spot of our imaging methods because we can't.
This is all spread out. We can't see them all. But that is one thing that that one could potentially get a handle on if one had a test that could be measured, let's say, in the blood where one could measure contributions from all these dozens of micrometastatic deposits and that that one might get higher sensitivity.
And that exactly kind of was the motivation for the liquid biopsy work in my lab. I had no idea how I was going to do that when I started it.
Now let's hit pause for one second, Max, because I think it let's also give people a little bit of the historical context of where there are at least a couple of areas where this was sort of being done, although it wasn't great.
So maybe explain for people how PSA, CEA and CA-19-9 have been used historically, because even when we were in medical school and long before you and I got to medical school, those three biomarkers were used.
Now, you were always cautioned that at least the CEA and the CA-19-9 could never be used for screening, but they could be appropriate for following. PSA has a very complicated history, which we could go down the rabbit hole of, about how it could be used for screening, but you know, you can be misled.
But tell folks a little bit about what those things are and how effective you think they were for what they were trying to do and which elements of those you wanted to replicate for lung cancer and where you wanted to improve upon it.
Yeah, great question. And you're absolutely right. When we started thinking about, you know, developing a blood-based test for initially lung cancer, we of course thought about exactly examples you pointed out, which are the markers you mentioned, like PSA, CEA-19-9.
PSA, CEA-19-9 are protein biomarkers. So these are proteins made by the cancer cells that can be shed into the blood and that one can then measure them in a non-invasive fashion.
Now, the main or a large issue with these protein biomarkers is that they are actually not that specific for cancer, meaning that these are also proteins that normal cells can make.
Now, cancers often tend to make more of them, which is why they are potentially of interest. But the problem becomes that having low levels of any of those markers, when a patient has that, you can't know whether that means they have a little bit of cancer in the body or whether it's just that's their baseline what the normal cells are making in their body.
And that lack of specificity is what it's called, meaning you're not so sure when you see it that it's cancer or not cancer, was the major Achilles heel of the protein-based biomarkers.
And a lot of work, of course, had been done in lung cancer previously looking at similar biomarkers, including CEA, actually, which sometimes in some subset of patients can be a good biomarker if the tumor just pumps out a lot of it and the patient has a decent amount of disease, so the total level is significantly higher than what a normal patient would have.
But in most patients, that was not the case. And so that was, you know, the protein-based approaches were really state of the art, but had this major weakness of the lack of specificity.
Let's maybe use this as a moment to explain to people sensitivity and specificity, which are going to become very important as we then factor in prevalence when it comes to screening to understand positive and negative predictive value.
But I think for now, if we can just start with helping people understand what specificity and sensitivity are in terms of probabilities of false positive and false negatives.
Again, I find this stuff to be so important. And yet, if you don't, I think, explain it over and over again, it's easy for people to kind of get lost in the details.
And yet it's so important for what we're about to talk about today that we'll probably end up doing this twice, three times.
Yes. No, I agree with you. These are very important topics, words that are thrown around a lot and can be confusing.
So sensitivity is something that's also known as, or a synonym for it, is true positive rate, which is basically the likelihood of having a positive test when the patient has the actual condition.
So let's say in the example of cancer, sensitivity is out of you have 100 cancer patients, you have a new blood test out of those 100 cancer patients.
You know, how many of them is the blood test positive? So that's sensitivity. Right.
So a perfect test would obviously have 100 percent sensitivity, which means 100 out of 100 would test positive.
In reality, to give people a sense of this, and, you know, a mammography might have an 85 percent sensitivity, which means if you do a mammogram on 100 women who are known to have breast cancer, it might only tell you that 85 of those 100 do.
So it's correctly identifying 85. It's erroneously, it's giving you a false negative in 15 of the 100.
That's exactly right. Yep.
And in general, it's important to realize that there are no perfect tests, really, particularly when you start pushing the envelope to seem trying to see smaller and smaller tumor.
So while it would, of course, be great to have a test that's 100 percent sensitive, meaning it catches every cancer patient, that is really unrealistic in the vast majority, if not all cases.
I think it's something that's sometimes not understood by patients where, you know, you have a you go get your mammogram or your your CAT scan for lung cancer screening.
And, you know, you still patients sometimes still develop a cancer, even though they did all those things.
And, you know, why is that? And that can lead to a lot of frustration.
But that's because these tests, they aren't perfect and they can't they're not always going to pick up a cancer even when it's present.
My one of my former analysts, Bob Kaplan, came up with a great thought experiment to explain this to people, which was the reason you can't have perfection is if you drive something to a very, very, very high sensitivity, the specificity must go down.
And here's the silly example. And this is his example. So I don't want to take any credit for it, but it's brilliant.
If you wrote a letter, Max, to a thousand women randomly and told every one of them they had breast cancer with no additional knowledge, you technically have a test with a hundred percent sensitivity.
Because let's assume, I don't know, ten. Let's assume 50 of those women have breast cancer. You have correctly identified them all.
There are no false negatives in that group. So you have a 100 percent sensitive test.
The problem is your specificity is in the toilet. You have so many false positives that the test is utterly useless.
So you can have a hundred percent sensitivity if you really want to push that envelope, but it has no clinical utility.
So you have to. And of course, I can play the experiment the other way. You could send a thousand women a letter that says you absolutely do not have breast cancer.
And technically you have no false positives, but you clearly are going to have false negatives.
So I love that experiment because it explains that if you if you pull full throttle on sensitivity or specificity, that's fine.
But it doesn't make for a good test because you've undoubtedly compromised the other parameter.
Yep, that's absolutely right. And that's exactly. And I think I agree. That's a great example to explain how that works.
And actually that explains a lot of what happens in the in the in the research, the diagnostic research field in general, that you try to push sensitivity.
But that never is meaningful to report if you don't also report the specificity, to look at specificity, because it's kind of like a yin and yang.
If you push on one, the other, you know, usually one goes up. Most of the time, the other goes down.
That is in general how it is unless you really have a dramatic new insider, a new advance where you can just increase sensitivity without also hurting specificity.
And then I guess just to finish off, just to finish up specificity. Yeah. So that is sort of the inverse of sensitivity, which is that for a patient who does not have cancer.
So it really is a true negative where we call it and doesn't have cancer. The test reports that the patient doesn't have cancer.
So it's sort of the exact inverse of sensitivity, but for the patients who don't have cancer. And as you mentioned, they are connected and you can game it.
You can always push the sensitivity higher if you kind of ignore the specificity.
So now let's go back to your clinical problem. By the way, Max, you know, we've talked a little bit about lung cancer on the side.
We've talked a little bit about lung cancer on this podcast, but I can never resist the opportunity given the prevalence of lung cancer and the, you know, what I refer to as the loss given default, meaning the severity of the disease.
Do you want to give people just a sense of where we are today in 2022 with lung cancer? Is it the first or second leading cause of cancer deaths for men and women?
It's the number one cause of cancer death, which I think a lot of people don't realize because it doesn't get nearly as much attention, at least historically, as some of the other cancers that are maybe more common.
Because if you look just in men or just in women like breast or prostate, but we're actually outcomes are much better.
You know, we can cure a very large fraction of patients with breast and prostate cancer. Of course, not everyone in there. And that is a critical area. We still need to make more advances.
But the difference with lung cancer is that the vast majority of patients historically can't be cured. And so that's why it is the number one cause of death, of cancer related death. So it is a major problem.
Is that going down or going up or flat line? I mean, because smoking rates are coming down and about 85 percent of lung cancer by incidence, I believe, is small cell or sorry, is smoking related.
So some combination of smoking related. 15 percent is in non-smokers. So where do we what's the trend line on lung cancer mortality?
Yeah. So that's one of the good news in oncology in general is both the incidence of lung cancer has been going down in both men and women.
It initially lagged in women, but it's also coming down in women now. And this is all related to, as you mentioned, the uptake and then now decrease of smoking in the population.
So that means because there's less smoking and because smoking is such a strong risk factor for developing lung cancer, it there's less lung cancer overall.
And on top of that, our treatments have gotten much better and as has now slowly the advent of screening, we have a way of screening for lung cancer, which is relatively recent development.
So those things combined have also decreased the number of patients who die from lung cancer once they get it, even with all that said, it still is the number one cause of cancer deaths.
But the trajectory is good. It's starting to head this way. And of course, we're very eager to accelerate that slope to make it make it even less of a of a problem, a health problem or killer of patients.
I think it is important. I want to point out one other point, which is often comes up in these kind of discussions, which is that while smoking is the, you know, by and far away the largest risk factor, it is not the only risk factor.
And really, anybody who has lungs can get lung cancer. And the, you know, that can happen for reasons that related to pollution.
You know, and that has been well described that pollution or other things in environment like radon gas that, you know, people are exposed to can cause lung cancer.
And there's genetic associations also, for example, in the Asian populations, there's a much larger incidence of non-smoking individuals who get lung cancer, particularly females.
And so we're never going to get rid of lung cancer just by even if we could magically make smoking go away today, you know, across the globe, you know, make all cigarettes disappear and never make a new one.
There will still be lung cancer.
So let's go over kind of the distribution of how these things work out. You have small cell and non-small cell is the big division, correct?
And then within non-small cell, you have adenocarcinoma, you have squamous cell carcinoma, large cell and carcinoid. Are those the big ones on the large cell or in the non-small cell? I'm sorry.
That's right. Yeah. I mean, carcinoid is not considered a non-small cell lung cancer. It's its own thing. But you're right. It is one of the it's not a small cell. So that's true still.
But that's right. So and the dominant the most common lung cancer isn't the non-small cell subtype of which the the majority have adenocarcinoma, but also a significant fraction of squamous cell carcinoma.
And when a non-smoker gets lung cancer, it's usually adenocarcinoma. Is that correct?
That's correct. The vast majority of the time it can sometimes be, you know, squamous cell carcinoma or even occasionally small cell. But that is extremely rare.
And as you mentioned, being a woman, being Asian seemed to elevate risk on the on the on the in the case of women, it seems to be potentially related to differences in estrogen testosterone that's been proposed as one plausible explanation.
Do we know what genes might account for this in Asians versus non?
We do not. And that's sort of one of the big mysteries that we have not identified the main genetic drivers.
They've been. That's not for lack of trying, of course. So it strongly suggests that it's multifactorial, right, that it's one of these as as as are many, of course, of our chronic illnesses that have genetic components that have like the cardiovascular diseases, for example, right, where it's not about a single gene.
The vast majority of the time it is contributions probably from multiple genetic variants that in aggregate elevate the risk. And then there may also be, of course, on top of that, then some further environmental factors that aren't smoking that that may then interact with that genetic background.
Am I correct in saying I think you mentioned radon. We talked about that as definitely a big environmental exposure. What do we know about the sort of PM 2.5 exposure?
And, you know, I've certainly seen data that's that show that people who are in and just for folks listening. So so, you know, particulate matter less than 2.5 micron is small enough to make its way into the most distal part of the lung.
There's clearly an increase in all cause mortality associated with higher PM 2.5 exposure. Do we know if that's also true specifically for lung cancer? Is that something that we can peg to an increase in lung cancer?
Yeah, that's a great question. I mean, there are associations of that. So, you know, people have looked at individuals living in cities versus rural areas and, you know, and correlating with the particulate contamination.
And that is also associated with more lung cancer in the cities that have more of the particulate in the ambient environment. So there's definitely an association in that regard.
You know, as with epidemiological studies, to really prove it in a human is difficult, of course. But but it does seem quite strong. And there's some biological rationale for that, where that if that is causing irritation and chronic inflammation, those kind of things.
Of course, we know that those things are can be associated with developing cancer in many organs. So it all makes sense. And I think it's likely true. But there also are, of course, chemicals in, you know, in smog that, you know, sort of along the lines of what's in tobacco smoke, a similar class of chemicals that that can be direct carcinogens.
Do we have a sense of what the dose response curve is in in pack years of tobacco to relative risk increase in lung cancer? So, you know, does a person who smoked a pack a day for 10 years, so they have a 10 pack year history, relative to a non smoker, is that 2x the risk, 50% more risk?
Do we have a sense of how nonlinear that curve is as well versus, you know, the 40 40 pack year smoker, the five pack year smoker, etc.
Right. There are associations between the number of pack years and the risk of developing lung cancer. Now, a pack year is is it's not an ideal clinical variable because, of course, you can't measure it in a completely unbiased way, the way just so your patients understand what when we do.
And so, you know, we basically how we figure out, you know, how a doctor tries to figure out how many pack years a patient has smoked, meaning we basically multiply the number of years of smoking, how many years they smoke for by the number of packs per day that they smoked.
Well, how do we get that information? Well, we have to ask the patient. And the reality is, number one, patients smoke different amounts of time right over there, over their time. Number two, you know, they don't always remember perfectly.
It's not a great metric in that regard. So it's difficult to really pin it down perfectly. I have seen studies that have suggested for sure suggested there isn't, you know, increase when you go as you go from zero to higher levels.
But then around 20 or 30 pack years, some studies argue that then kind of plateau is that you kind of you may be sort of saturating. But they that's not exactly my expertise.
So I don't have the exact, you know, the slopes of those lines. I don't know the top of my head. But but it is not a perfect variable, of course, is what do the data say about secondhand smoke, which I would imagine is even harder to quantify than pack years.
But when, you know, for example, I have some patients who grew up with parents who smoked, they themselves have never smoked. And let's say those parents continue to smoke all the way until those kids now adults went to college.
Do you have a sense of how to quantify what their their smoke exposure is? And should they be treated as former smokers in terms of cancer screening, for example, with low dose CT and things like that?
Yeah, interesting question. So yeah, I agree. It's very difficult to measure. It's even harder, harder to measure than the pack years we just talked about.
And, you know, we know that certain, you know, certain professions that were exposed to a lot of smoking, like, you know, waitresses and waiters or stewards and stewardesses that there was increases, you know, epidemiologically.
Of course, there's always other things that go along with that with that issue also. So I think the link is quite clear how, you know, how to quantitate it and how to know, you know, has one had enough secondhand smoke exposure that one's risk is significantly elevated.
I think that's a major problem. Actually, an error would be very useful to have a biomarker that could be quantitatively measured to actually like measure like a clock of amount of exposure you had.
We don't have such a thing. And currently, that is not one of the criteria that would get a patient eligible for lung cancer screening by low dose CT. So secondhand smoke is not considered.
The way that we decide on those criteria for who should get this test and covered by insurance and who shouldn't is really about trying to enrich for us, you know, the highest risk population.
You know, you want at least a certain percent, half percent, a percent of risk of developing lung cancer that you're going to screen for because otherwise you will screen lots and lots of patients who will never get it.
And then the specificity becomes a problem we talked about earlier. And so that's even though there are things like, you know, exposure to pollutants, secondhand smoke that we know increase the risk.
We don't think it can be frustrating enough for patients who are who are in those categories to to know whether, you know, why can't they get access to screening? But there are, you know, sort of public health reasons for that.
Yeah, which we'll then get to something we'll talk about in a little bit, which is you can know the sensitivity and specificity of a test, but you then need to know the prevalence with the pretest probability to know how to interpret the result.
Without the prevalence, you can't impute the positive and negative predictive value, which is what tells you when you have a positive, how confident are you it's positive. And similarly, when you have a negative, how confident are you there?
Let's talk a little bit about low dose CT because I would say this has been certainly in the last 10 years one of the major changes in how we manage lung cancer. It's been about 10 years, correct, since since the data have made the case for the use of that as a screening technique.
That's right. Yeah. So that was, you know, there had been a long effort of trying to develop a screening test for lung cancer, given that it is the number one cause of cancer deaths.
And there were a lot of failures along that road. A lot of initial studies focused on doing chest X-rays when that was the main thing that was available. So a much lower resolution way of imaging the lungs where those studies were unable to show a benefit.
But then there was a landmark study called the National Lung Screening Trial that proved that if you take in that trial, they took patients that randomized them either to get a low dose CT scan, which is now a more high resolution way of looking at the lungs that can see smaller nodules.
Versus getting a chest X-ray, which was this technique that previously already we had kind of known that wasn't didn't work. And if you do that, the patients who get the low dose CT scan, the higher resolution imaging in that in that group, there was significantly lower rates of lung cancer deaths, you know, relative risk reduction of about 20 percent.
That suggest, you know, argued that that's a major win for a screening test to actually be able to decrease the number of deaths from the disease you're screening for.
Do you remember what the absolute risk reduction was?
That was small. It was in the single digit percent. I don't remember it off the top of my head.
But it was single digit percent. So you would still have an let's say it was five percent. Your NNT would be 20. So you would you could save a life for every 20 people. That still seems pretty good.
It's it's actually lower than that. Yeah. No. So maybe it was like one to two percent number.
It was like one to two percent. Yeah. It's in the hundred. I think I'd say one or two. Maybe it's point five to one percent. Okay. Now the that gets complicated also because you think doing a CT scan and then you either see a nodule.
You don't. So it should be pretty easy. But of course it's not that easy. A CT scan is a complicated thing to read. And so how you interpret the scan and what you consider a positive will, of course, affect your sensitivity and specificity and will affect the number needed to treat downstream.
So the way that we now read scans, the low to CT scans is different than what the initial study did because of a high risk of false positive. The way that they was doing the original study.
So it's not the low to CT is not my area of expertise so that I don't have all the numbers of my fingertips. But those are the sort of salient issues that are in that field.
So even though we have this test and it is great and is this major home run for screening because we can save cancer deaths. It's not a perfect test. And do you know by any chance how many millisieverts of radiation the low dose CT provides?
I'm guessing it's like shot, you know, one millisievert or less maybe. I think that's right. Yeah. I don't know that off the top of my head again because I don't do those pictures myself.
But it's significantly less than the scans that we routinely do for patients who already have cancer. And this is an important concern that patients have is that, well, you know, radiation can cause cancer. So why should I?
Is the risk worth it? Right. The risk of the lower cancer. But it's called low to CT because the amount of radiation used is much, much, much less than was historically done for a CT scan. And so therefore the risk of causing a cancer is much, much lower.
You know, the NRC says that we shouldn't be exposed to more than 50 millisieverts in a year. You know, is that sort of like saying, you know, you shouldn't drink more than, you know, 10 drinks in a day. Like, do you have a sense of, you know, what would be your personal threshold for how much radiation you would want to receive a year from imaging?
Because you're going to get radiation from, you know, being on airplanes, although that's relatively small. You know, just being at sea level is probably one to two millisieverts a year. If you live in Colorado, you probably double that.
But do you ever when do you start to think about how much radiation a patient is getting from a practical standpoint? You know, do you start to worry at 20 millisieverts in a year, which is obviously pretty easy to do with a PET CT scan, for example.
Right. So, you know, we don't routinely track that at the individual patient level. And I think that, you know, the way in more it's tracked in a less, you know, I guess, systematic way in that, you know, we don't do imaging tests unless we feel that the benefit of doing that test outweighs the known, but really low and actually very difficult to quantitate harm, right?
Because, you know, it's actually very difficult to quantitate exactly how much risk of, let's say, a second milligency there, a future milligency there is from a given protocol of a CT scan or whatnot, just because to get that data and the number of patients you need, you could never do it, randomize all those things.
Right. And so, you know, the way that medical practitioners who order imaging studies, which of course, most or many fields in many fields, they do not just radiology is the calculus is always do I need this test, right?
Will this help me manage the patient in a way that's beneficial to the patient? We absolutely should not be doing imaging if there's no point.
If no matter what the scan shows, I'm not going to change what I'm doing, then I should not be ordering that scan. And there are that does come up quite frequently that there are, you know, you're sort of the question of should I image, should I not?
And, you know, the way I and, you know, all of us, you know, in this in these areas think about it is, is it worth doing?
And so, you know, some patients who have lung cancer, particularly when they get radiation therapy, which is very high doses of radiation, they have astronomical amounts of radiation that if you were not a cancer patient, you would never want those amounts of radiation.
But the vast majority of those patients will not get a cancer from their imaging or radiation treatment. And their cancer, if we leave it untreated, will kill them, right? And so, or if we don't catch if it's going to come back, if we don't catch it early, where we still might have a chance to a second chance of cure.
So that's how we, you know, we do the calculus. It's not that there's, you know, badges, badges that patients wear that that meant to track this so that that then if you get to a certain point, you couldn't do no more imaging.
It's always a sort of a case by case basis.
So let's go back now to the clinical problem that is at the at the root of this whole situation, which is you have a patient who has either had a resection and or radiation to follow their clinically, as we would say, any D no evidence of disease.
But you know that the recurrence rate is there. It's let's say it's 25% actuarially 25% of these patients of these hundred people who are currently any D are going to have a recurrence.
And we know that the sooner we catch the recurrence, the better the odds are for treatment, the lower the tumor burden, the lower the burden of mutation in the patient, the greater the odds of therapy.
So if this was 200 years ago, we'd be hosed, right, because we'd have to wait until, you know, they had folating, fungating masses, they were coughing up blood. I mean, obviously, that would be crazy.
And we've already now just put in, you know, great detail that look, even giving high resolution CT scans, at best, we have to wait until a billion cells are cancers. That's the best case scenario.
So now we want to talk about something else. So, so walk us down the path of how you would or how you did think about going after another type of biopsy, a liquid biopsy.
As I mentioned, you know, I was frustrated by not being able to diagnose a recurrence earlier, and that was an unmet need. So I wanted to start, you know, a part of my laboratory working on that problem.
But to be able to do that, you know, there's two ways you could think about doing that. You could start with mouse models to build mouse models, let's say, you know, what they're called preclinical models in which you try to, you know, grow tumors in the animals and then see if you could, you know, have an hypothesis for what,
what might be a good biomarker, try to test that and see if it works in a mouse and then ultimately go back to the human. And as I mentioned earlier, sort of the approach that we take in my group is more very tied to the clinic, very what's called translational research.
And so for us, really, the human being is the model organism. It's the final model. Of course, it's the model we want to get the answer for. And so I thought we should do this work directly on blood samples, because if we find something, then it likely will be directly apical.
Otherwise, you'd always still have that second step where it works in the mouse, let's say, but you don't know. So so I started collecting blood samples. I actually didn't know what I was going to do with them.
And by the way, who was funding this work at the time, Max? Was this something you went to the NIH and said, you know, here, I want an R01 and this is why I want to study it or the outset, who was the who was who was bearing the risk financially?
At the outset, it was basically me. When you when your new faculty member, when you start a new lab, when you get that first job, you get what's called a startup startup funds, which is basically funds your department or university gives you provides you sort of as a to kick start you because you don't have grants at that moment.
You haven't you're just starting. You haven't had a chance to write them. And so I was using that money basically. So I was footing the bill on sort of that that pot of money. I got to start my lab.
Because as you know, and I'm sure your listeners have heard many times that one of the things with academic research and funding is that oftentimes you kind of have to show it already works before you can get funding for it.
That's a very common story because, you know, grant funding is limited. And so the organizations that fund research are often quite conservative that if the idea is sounds great, but you have no proof that it works at all, you know, they're not going to give you money. So I use money that I had for my startup funds.
So, so, yes, I just start collecting blood and then start thinking about what biomarkers might one would be good. So I read the literature on the protein biomarkers, as we talked earlier.
And sorry, did you collect blood in patients prior to resection and post resection or just post resection?
Both. I always add, you know, prior prior to resection or radiation, whatever the treatment was. And then in subsequent follow up visits, usually, you know, at the time of their follow up scans when they're coming back to see us.
And so the protein biomarkers didn't seem very useful. I then spent maybe about a year looking at something called circulating tumor cells, which is one subtype of what this field called liquid biopsy, which is actually looking for intact cancer cells that can circulate in the blood of patients.
I tried that with a couple of different techniques and quickly realized, you know, something that many others in the field have also observed, which is that while if one could really do that, it would be super powerful.
It is very complicated to actually measure those cells for a right of reasons.
Two biggest ones probably are. I mean, three big ones are there. The cells are not very abundant when they are there. There's very few of them. And they're so they're very difficult to purify, like, you know, to actually purify, you know, a good purification.
They might still only be one percent or less of the cells in your purified sample because it's just so hard to purify. It's finding a needle in a haystack.
And because it's intact cells, you have to process the samples really quickly. You have to process them basically the same day or within an hour or two of the patients having the blood sample drawn.
That makes it very difficult to build up biobanks of frozen cells, frozen samples that you could get a large cohort to actually study because you have to press them immediately.
And then the last thing was that we did some control experiments. This is critical. Obviously, you always want to ask, is the thing I'm working on really working and where we drew blood from healthy individuals who don't have cancer.
And some of these tumor, certain tumor cell methods we're using found circulating cells. Those patients don't have cancer. So they were picking up something else. So there was a lack of specificity.
They were technically complicated. It seemed like it's going to be hard to get this into the clinic anytime soon. And there was some weakness. So that's them when I went back and tried to really see what else could we do.
So let me go back to the first one. Let's just talk about the protein because that makes sense as the obvious place to start because we already kind of do that with PSA, notwithstanding the limitation that normal cells, normal prostate cells, non-cancer cells make prostate specific antigen.
Same with CEA, CA-19-9. Did you find any proteins that were made that were expressed by lung cancer cells that were unique to them?
We at the time did not. We did not do a holistic screen ourselves, but other people had, which one can do. There's techniques now called mass spectrometry where one can take a sample of proteins, let's say purified from the blood, run them through this machine.
And it basically tells you what proteins were there. And those studies had not found convincing markers that were unique to lung cancer cells. Now they found some markers that in some patients were elevated.
Actually, CEA is one of them that can be elevated in lung cancer patients. And in ones where it is, it can even be a marker for occurrence like PSA can be in prostate cancer.
But we already knew that CEA has problems with specificity, right? So that was sort of the main concern. So we didn't actually do, but the main protein work we did was to actually, I drew some CEA and a few of these other markers like C-19-9, some of the ones that had been previously reported to be markers in lung cancers in some of my patients.
Because there were some studies that claimed really great performance in the literature, but quickly realized that those studies were, you know, maybe it was an artifact of that cohort or something else was going on where we could not reproduce those results.
Yeah. Let's talk about that a little bit, Max, because that's, I think what people don't understand is how difficult it can be to reproduce results.
And so like help people understand what that process is like. You or one of your graduate students or one of your postdocs reads a paper where somebody says, hey, we've identified this protein. It seems really specific. It looks fantastic, etc, etc.
Presumably these people are collaborative. You can read the paper and get the methods. You can call the lab. They can tell you how they did it. Now you do the experiment. What do you find?
In many cases, unfortunately one finds that one can't reproduce the result.
That often that can be not that it doesn't work at all, but that just it doesn't work as well as it did in the initial study.
And that but it works so much less well that it's not going to be clinically useful. That's a very common event.
Now, do you still publish that result, Max?
The lack of validation? Yes. You mean? Yeah. Sometimes it depends. Yeah. Sometimes we do. Often people don't.
The reason is complex, of course. But one issue is that, you know, to definitively prove something doesn't work quite as well as it was initially reported.
One actually has to do very large studies so that the what are called error bars are an estimate of the sensitivity. That's what we care about is very accurate.
Right. But even though by doing a smaller cohort, you can already tell it's not going to work out, but to really ultimately prove it to the level of rigor that one would need for a publication would require another year and thousands of dollars.
And so there is these decisions one has to make is, is this really worth it? And what's the opportunity cost? Right now.
But it's interesting, right, when you think about it, because it means that we have a bias system in the publication realm that we are biased towards positive findings that are often untrue.
Because let's say one person publishes that they can make this thing work. OK. And again, we're going to throw out fraud or anything like that. But we're just going to assume that in good faith, these are people who did something, but they had an artifact.
They didn't catch it. The experiment looked like it was positive. They publish it. Let's assume that you and four other labs independently try to reproduce it and none of you can reproduce it.
But you all come to the same conclusion, which is, well, we only did it this one way and it didn't work. Technically, I would need to do it three or four other ways to be really sure.
I'm going to put those resources of time and money elsewhere and away I go. And everybody comes to the same logical conclusion.
But of course, that means that that one finding gets disproportionately propagated as a positive finding when in reality, four labs have now found it to be highly unlikely and that doesn't get published.
Of course, I'm not being critical of you or anybody, other than just the system, which is I wish there was a way that the incentive structure could be such that we prioritize negative findings as much as positive findings.
Right. And I agree with you, 100 percent. And as you laid it out, it is true and that does happen. And in general, we all have a system where one lab could know that three other labs have done the same thing.
You know, maybe eventually you find out over dinner at a conference or something. But because there is no place to go to look up to see what other people have done, there is no way to know.
So it is a problem. It would be great if we could fix it. It's a very difficult problem, of course, because of the many factors, including the economic parts of limited research resources and time.
And like even, you know, to publish such a study would take, let's say, a grad student could still take six months of their time to get that out.
But now, you know, they're not spending those six months on their main project, which is to develop the new test. Right.
So there are so many reasons why this happens. Right. And I've spoken with graduate students who will say, look, it's really going to be harder for me to get my PhD publishing negative studies.
I mean, I'm going to quickly turn my attention to where I think my committee is going to be looking at me more favorably.
So, yeah, I think I think the problem is pretty significant. But there's a selection bias for it.
It is the selection bias of the positive results is a major issue. And so this this is why reproducing positive results is so critical and something that also not everyone likes to do it because reproducing something someone else already did is not making a brand new discovery.
Right. But that is critical. That is, you know, and that's one thing I would say, particularly in the more in the medical fields, we do do quite a bit of right.
There is quite a bit of studies that sort of try to reproduce results, positive results and then publish it when the results are also positive. And that's really to really prove something works.
You know, to convince convincingly convince yourself that something is really real. It's really helpful to see multiple studies from multiple groups.
Yeah. I deal with multiple methods that find the same thing. And that's sort of how you can read read through the literature and really try to see where where is likely a robust finding.
All right. So let's go to the CTCs now. So protein out circulating tumor cells. OK, so talk to me about a patient who shows up with a big juicy stage two lung cancer prior to resection.
How many milliliters of blood do you take out of that patient preoperatively?
So that depends greatly. But you know, the these kind of tests, whether whether we're doing them for research purposes or ultimately, you know, if you were to help something for the clinic usually take somewhere between 10 to 20 mls of blood.
So a few tablespoons. So right out of the gate, how many CTCs do you see preoperatively when you should be at your highest rate? That should be your greatest circulating tumor burden.
So in stage one to two non small cell, most often zero. Oh, my God. So yeah, so that's so that and that that was what we found when we when we looked.
And so the that meant the sensitivity isn't very good. Right.
As a control, did you have positive controls of stage four patients?
We did. And we did see some patients where we saw quite a lot. So you can definitely see patients that have massive amounts. Occasionally, you can see early stage patients that have quite a lot.
And this is work not that we didn't we didn't do, but other another group in the field led by Carolyn dive from Manchester, where they actually took blood from the draining veins at the time of the surgery, the lobectomy for lung cancer, and did circling tumor cell assays and found evidence that there they could find more signal sensitivity was better in that context, because the hypothesis being that you're basically measuring the blood outflow of the tumor.
So you're going to catch more cells that way, because once they hit the systemic circulation, they're getting diluted all over the entire body. So there is some evidence along those lines.
Any findings about the differences in those early stage? So if you if you took a person with stage two cancer, who is your typical patient who has no circulating tumors, even preoperatively, but then you said there might be a some who had a reasonably high burden.
Does that predict who's going to recur, even though based on TNM staging, they're both considered identical postoperatively?
Right. And so yeah, absolutely. There's there is evidence of that. There are studies that have shown that, that when you when you do see high levels, that that is a negative prognostic marker, a bad thing. And that those patients are at higher risk of recurrence.
Now, one complication in the CTC field, the certain tumor cell field in general is that, as I mentioned, even non cancer patients can have circulating cells that look like circulating tumor cells using the markers that are generally used, which are usually when, you know, when it's looking for certain tumor cells, most assays look, use, stain the cells, meaning they look for markers on the cells.
And they want the cells to not express markers from lymphocytes from white blood cells. So there's a marker that's highly expressed on white blood cells that should not be expressed on the circulating tumor cell.
Which one do you use? CD3?
People usually use CD45 as the most common marker, which is sort of a pan white blood cell marker. And then for on the flip side, for a positive marker, what is should be expressed in the cancer cell but not the white blood cells.
They look for things like cytokarotins, which are structural proteins that that are specific to epithelial cells. But as we and others have found, healthy patients can also have cells that have cytokarotin expression, but no white blood cell marker expression in the circulation.
And other people have gone further to do single cell sequencing of those to show that their genomes are actually normal. Those cells have normal genomes. They're not mutated like the cancer cells are.
So it definitely appears that there can be epithelial cells circulating in us that are not cancer cells. And very likely, those cells can't divide forever, so they will not ever set up shop anywhere. There's not very many of them.
But that makes it complicated to look for the presence of certain tumor cells if one doesn't have a very specific way of getting, removing that signal.
Yeah, so that right away tells you this is never going to be at least that exact approach can never be a cancer screening tool.
And it makes you worry that even in patients who are without disease, but who have been resected, it might not be a great predictor of disease recurrence.
So far, the only thing that sounds somewhat promising from this approach is it might help you determine the course of adjuvant therapy in a patient. Correct?
So if you took a patient who was resected, radiated, stage two, had high circulating tumor burden versus one who didn't, you might take that former patient and say,
even though the textbook says you don't need chemotherapy, we're actually going to give you chemotherapy because we're going to treat you like you're stage three or worse.
Right. And that's absolutely where we wanted to get. That was that exact situation, one of the main motivations for starting liquid biopsy work in my lab.
And yes, with very high levels of certain tumor cells, one could have envisioned if one were to do a very large studies to definitively prove that these patients with a certain threshold, even though they're a small minority,
if that is really very highly associated with recurrence, that could work, but it would miss most patients who ultimately developed recurrence.
And so that was the negative. And again, it's not to say in the future we might not get there. There's lots of work still going on in this circulating tumor cell field.
So I don't want to be too negative about it. It's just not as far along as the thing that we ultimately settled on. We'll talk about shortly.
And more development is required if we're going to be able to use that clinically.
All right. So then where would you go? Where'd you go next? Did you look at cell free DNA?
Yes. So the next after that, we went to what's called cell free DNA, which refers to DNA molecules that are found in the circulation, but outside of cells.
So they're circulating in what's called the blood plasma, which is the noncellular liquid portion of the blood.
And it's called cell free because it's outside of cells free of cells. Of course, it comes from cells originally, but it's now circulating by itself without membranes around it.
And the reason I got interested in that was actually largely from reading about a different field, which is prenatal diagnostics, where around this time there was a lot of work being done, led by a number of individuals like Dennis Lowe in Hong Kong and Steve Quake.
It was actually here at Stanford in the engineering department, basically showing that in pregnant mothers, you can detect DNA from the fetus in the woman's blood cell free DNA again, not not inside cells, but outside of cells.
So it's pretty obvious that I mean, I wasn't the only person who had this thought that if we can do that in pregnancy, then, you know, couldn't we try to do the same thing in cancer patients.
And just to be clear, Max, when you spin this down, when you when you take a tube of blood and you spin it, you get all of the cellular matter below the buffy coat and then the plasma is above is the cell free DNA in the clear plasma and not stuck within the cellular material.
It manages to.
That's correct. So the cell free DNA is in the plasma and that's exactly where we isolated. And that's actually a critical technical aspect.
Yeah, because if it were in the cellular matter, it would be a disaster to find it.
You can't get it, right? And it actually we've thought about this idea that I think it's actually quite insightful idea you have there. Could there be more cell free DNA mixed in with the cellular compartment?
And I think it's quite likely that if you could put a gradient on that and try to somehow extract it.
Yeah, get it out that you might be able to get it out.
You can enrich your cell free.
You can enrich for it again. And that might actually be a future interesting research direction. But the problem is currently if you were to just take some of that cellular compartment, there's some vastly more DNA in the cells than there is in the cell free space that you would basically lose the signal.
You would just have all the vast, vast majority is from cells in that compartment.
So we take the aqueous part, the plasma part at the top of the tube after you spin it. And there's very low levels. It's only about on the healthy individual, about one to five nanograms per mil of cell free DNA in the plasma.
By the way, you know what's interesting? I have beta thalassemia minor. So my phenotype is normal. Well, I shouldn't say that. My hemoglobin and hematocrit are normal. But my phenotype is that I have very small RBCs.
So my MCV is in the 50s or 60s or something like that. Right. And my RBC count is very high. So that's how I have a normal hematocrit because I have a lot of small blood cells.
So our mutual classmate for med school, Matt McCormick, who is my roommate, used to always refer to me as having shite for blood. And I just learned something very recently. I've spun my blood a billion times. I've been more times than I can count.
And I've always thought, man, I must be dehydrated, man, I must be dehydrated because relative to everybody else's blood, you know, you'll get cellular matter this much, Buffy coat plasma.
They're about the same volume. And you can even estimate hematocrit by spinning in a lavender top and looking at the separation. Well, you can't do any of that in my blood because my plasma volume is tiny and my cellular fraction is enormous.
And I've and so finally I spoke to a hematologist who said, oh, the reason is because you have all those little crappy red blood cells, they're actually keeping and trapping a lot of the plasma within the cellular body at the bottom.
So it's not that you don't have a normal plasma volume. You do, but you just can't get it out of the separation, which means I'd be a lousy patient for this because I'm cutting my sample size down so much by reducing your plasma volume.
So you might have to donate larger amounts of blood to get the right amount of plasma. But I think that's a very interesting observation. I think it does suggest that this phenomenon of there potentially being trapping DNA among the cells.
Yeah, it's probably, you know, also, you know, happening. You're the exceptional outlier, but it's probably also happening in the average patient to a lesser extent.
Now, again, it's DNA. So just to make sure everybody remembers, this is a double stranded or single stranded DNA.
These are largely double stranded DNA as we think and haven't done, you know, we know there's experiments along those lines. These are a double stranded DNA molecules. They are rather short. The cell free DNA molecules.
How many there's, you know, base.
Yeah, it's about one hundred seventy basis. Okay.
One hundred sixty five hundred seventy. And that's actually exactly the length of DNA that is you would expect if the DNA were wrapped around the core histones. Histones, of course, are for your listeners are proteins that that package the DNA in our cells.
And so the DNA is sort of the scaffold and that lets the DNA, which if it were linearly stretched out, be extremely long, fit into the compact nucleus of a 10 micron cell.
It has this special packaging scaffold, which is consists of the histones. And so the DNA in the circulation is wrapped still around this core histones.
And I think that's critical because there's actually high activity of enzymes that chew up DNA in our blood and our extracellular fluid.
And so the DNA is only there temporarily and it's temporarily protected by these histones. So the DNA that's bound to the histones is present at a higher frequency in the blood than the DNA that's between the histones.
And so the DNA that's been
released from the blood is also like pearls on a string and the DNA regions that are between the between two pearls are relatively depleted from the blood because these enzymes are chewing up the DNA constantly, which is what contributes to these very low levels of DNA.
Because of course, we have lots of cell death. So you might imagine we should have higher levels of DNA in the body in our blood.
But there's we have a system to clear it out in this DNA enzyme and probably important because if you ever work with DNA, if you get to high concentrations of it, it becomes very sticky kind of a snot like substance.
Which would be very probably bad to have in your microvasculature, you know, for stroke, etc.
And so does does this cell free DNA primarily come via apoptosis or what is the predominant method by which or mechanism by which the cells are evicting their DNA?
That is very poorly understood.
That's a great question. It's still one of the mysteries. And it's a mystery because it's really difficult to study because the in a human being or even an animal.
What we know is that most, if not all tissues, contribute DNA to the cell free DNA pool.
And so there is, you know, it's coming from everywhere. So it's very difficult to to to study the release of something from everywhere.
Right. It is because it is, you know, chopped up in these small histone bound fragments.
There was historically a lot of, you know, most of the reviews and textbooks argue that largely apoptosis that does that because an apoptosis, of course, there is a laddering of the DNA or chopping up of the DNA.
Maybe tell folks tell folks what apoptosis is so they know what.
Yeah, great. Apoptosis is a mode of cell death. So how cells in our bodies can die. But is it is a controlled program cell death, meaning that there is a mechanism in our cells that is basically a suicide program that can get activated.
This is critical for the development or development because at certain points as we're developing from, you know, the fertilized egg up to a full infant.
And even then, you know, during later in life or cells sometimes have to get killed to make room for other cells.
And that's just part of our normal, normal development homeostasis. So it's something that we have evolutionarily built.
It also is critical for getting rid of sick cells because some of the cell gets sick. There has to be a way of killing it.
So apoptosis is a programmed way of cells dying. And as part of that, once that's activated, the cells chop up their proteins as well as their DNA.
Basically, it's sort of to make it sort of a tight kind of clean up after themselves in a way. But because of this chopping up the DNA that happens during apoptosis, it was long thought that that likely could be a major mechanism.
I think it still could be that the complicating factors. Now we have a much better understanding that there's also DNA just floating in the plasma that are also chopping up DNA.
So for the long chunk of DNA were released through a non apoptosis process, it would likely also become chopped up. And so, you know, we can't do just because it's chopped up assume it comes from apoptosis.
So we don't know for sure. I think that's an important area of research. We think it's likely multifactorial apoptosis necrosis, you know, basically any way that a cell can die and release some of its contents into the blood.
OK, so let's say we're talking about a normal person. You've taken 10 cc of blood. You take the plasma from them. How do you quantify how much cell free DNA you would expect to get out of that?
And then furthermore, how are you distinguishing what is potentially cell free DNA from a normal cell, which presumably is the bulk of it versus cell free DNA that is from the cell of interest, the cancer cell?
Right. So once we purify the DNA, once we have the plasma, so the noncellular compartment, there is laboratory procedures for isolating DNA that have been well worked out for over many decades that we use in all different fields of biology.
And so we apply some methods there that have been optimized for these low concentrations of DNA. That's one of the unique things about the software DNA work.
The concentration is really low. Like I said, you know, one single digit nanograms per mil.
And often when we do laboratory procedures, we like to work with at least micrograms of DNA. So there's nanograms. It's a small amount. That was one of the challenges early on in the field to try to overcome that.
So we purify the DNA and then we can quantify how much there is. There's a variety of laboratory tools we have. The most commonly used one in our lab is a fluorescent based method where you basically add a fluorescent dye to the solution.
It binds to DNA and that gives a specific fluorescence. And then you can read that out in a machine that can read that fluorescence.
So you can then have a standard curve and read off how much DNA you have. And again, like a...
So it would in-suit you to hybridization or...
No, it's this is just purely a dye based method. It's much simpler than that. You could do some you could do more complicated things.
You know, probably the next most the more complicated thing that we would do next when we do sometimes in certain situations is what was called quantitative PCR, where basically you use an enzymatic method that can amplify DNA.
And you again have a standard curve where you know how much DNA is in there and you compare how the amplification curves grow and that can let you read out how much DNA was in your sample.
But most of the time we can use this more simple method, which is just add a dye, put it in the machine, get the result. It's very fast.
And just give me some quantity. So in 10 ml of plasma, how many nanograms would you expect or how many nanograms per milliliter in any sample would you expect to have of cell free DNA?
Right. So 10 ml of plasma would be 20 ml of blood we collect because plasma in most individuals is about half. Right. So from 20 ml of blood, we get 10 ml of plasma.
Those 10 ml in healthy individuals would have somewhere between one to five nanograms per mil. So that would mean 10 to 50 nanograms of DNA at the end.
And but in some conditions, in some advanced cancer patients, patients who have trauma, have an infection, the levels can be much higher, much higher than five nanograms per mil because there's active cell death happening in the body.
And so when that happens, we sometimes see levels, you know, in the hundreds of nanograms per mil that's rare, but it can happen.
So now the big question is, how do you separate the good actor and the bad actor in that pile?
The way that we and others in the field do that is to focus on a unique molecular property of cancer cells that normal cells generally don't have. And that is the mutations that cause the cancer.
Of course, as many of your listeners will know, cancer is a disease that is caused by mutation mistakes in the DNA of a normal cell that accumulate and ultimately lead to that cell not being responsive to cues to stop growing or to or to kill itself and just to grow uncontrollably.
And so then those mutations, both the ones that cause the cancer as well as many thousands that are long for the ride in most tumors, are sort of as really exquisitely specific markers of the cancer cell because these mutations are really only present in the cancer cells, not in the patient's normal cells.
So this is a really attractive biomarker and for a variety of reasons. One is you're tracking the cause of the disease, right? You're really at the molecular cause of these is a mutation. That is what you're tracking.
What better biomarker can there be for an illness, right? You're actually tracking that. And the second thing is the specificity, particularly when you compare it to the proteins, where, as we mentioned, like PSA can be made by normal prostate cells and by prostate cancer cells.
But the mutations in a prostate cancer would not be present in the normal prostate cells. They would be present in the cancer cells. So how do we tell them if there is circulating tumor today present is that we look for mutations in these short DNA molecules.
So we look for mutant molecules. Most of the molecules in the blood come from the healthy cells of the patient and they don't have mutations, but a small subset, and that can be ranged from an advanced lung cancer patient might have 1% of the circulating DNA is from the cancer.
So still a small amount. It's still relatively small. That's high levels. In early stage patients, it's often well less than 0.01 or 0.001% of the DNA that's from the cancer cell.
So how do you even detect that without, I mean, do you have the resolution to detect 0.1% of the cell free fraction, which itself is already very small and know that you're not seeing an artifact?
Yeah, so that was the challenge in the field when we started. That's not trivial. It's actually extremely difficult, as you suggest. The reason is that the methods we use to try to detect mutations, and there's a variety of them,
but the one that we chose to use in which basically the vast majority of the field has moved to since as well is next generation sequencing, which is these high throughput molecular methods for sequencing DNA,
where you can identify the actual sequence of the bases, the AGTC bases that make up the DNA. You can get the exact sequence for hundreds of millions of molecules or billions of molecules even in parallel in one experiment.
So we use those tools because we can just read the data. It's as if we had a microscope that's so good that we can just read off the bases. It's not a microscope. It's a complex molecular biology procedure, but the end result is the same.
We get a data set of millions of DNA sequences that are all about 170 bases in length, and we can then compare those sequences to the patient's germline DNA, let's say, that we purify from a buccal swab or from the cellular compartment compartment of the blood.
And we can say the vast majority of the molecules look identical to the patient's germline, meaning they're normal healthy cell DNA, but some small proportion of the molecules have mutations.
And in many of our experiments, the way that we can be very certain that's the case is because we start by actually sequencing the tumor. So let's say, particularly for this initial problem we had of telling who is cured or not, if those patients all had treatment, they all known to have cancer, so we have a piece of their tumor.
We can sequence that and identify what mutations that tumor has compared to the patient's healthy cells. Let's say we find, in a particular panel we might be using, let's say we find 10, just for sake of example.
So 10 mutations the patient's tumor has that the healthy cells don't. We can then go look in the blood in the sequencing data set we have for those mutant molecules that carry one of those 10 mutations.
And that turns out to be exquisitely specific and sensitive for the presence of the cancer. If we see even one or a handful of molecules that carry the mutation, one of these mutations has borne out that that basically means there's still cancer cells in the body.
Now, the other thing that I want to make sure I understand here is we're talking about relatively short fragments of DNA. You said call it 150 bases, correct?
Yeah, it's 170 maybe closer to 170.
99.9% of all of that cell free DNA lines up to some segment of their germline.
But no two of those are the same either, right? So it's like if you could lay their entire germline genome out, it would, you know, span miles and miles and miles. You probably have no two segments that are the exact same.
So you have a whole bunch of 170 base segments that line up somewhere on that problem. That's a pretty interesting computational problem to me because 170 is not that big. Presumably some of that 170 also is present in the cancerous, in the mutated.
Yeah, the vast majority, the vast majority, right? The cancer.
The cancer is only going to have maybe a hundred mutations.
Yeah, so a hundred mutations in the coding regions exactly.
That's right.
A hundred mutations in the coding regions in the total genome, if you include the regions between genes, maybe, you know, 10 to 20,000 or something. It depends, of course, as a range.
But no more than 10, having more than tens of thousands of mutations in the whole genome would be unusual.
Yeah. So I guess what strikes me is almost improbable is given the few number of mutations that really exist in the cancer,
if only 0.1 percent of the entire cell free DNA, which itself are very short segments, it seems to me you could very easily just miss it, right?
You wouldn't happen to find a segment that lines up with a mutation. Right.
Presumably there must be a way to do the I mean, I feel like if you gave me an hour, I could figure out the numbers like it's just a it's just a statistics and probability problem.
But so how infrequent is that?
So that is exactly one of the major challenges in the field.
And that's actually our initial, you know, our first paper in this field that started really this whole part of my laboratory back in 2014.
We had we addressed that problem.
So what there, of course, had been some prior work in cell free DNA and cancer prior to us.
One is always building on the shoulders of former researchers when one does the next project.
You know, maybe just for brief history lesson, you know, mid of last century was the first observation that there is a cell free DNA present by a French group.
And they even said very, very insensitive methods back then, of course.
So they could only tell it, see it in some very, very advanced cancer patients.
But they even then they were already at the foresight to say, well, this could be potentially useful.
But then for the intervening, I don't know, 50, 60 years, there wasn't that much progress because of this hurdle of there being so little of it.
And the method is just not being there to measure it.
And what people had been starting to doing around, you know, sort of the mid to 2005, 2010 in that range was to actually look, use very sensitive PCR methods to look for single mutations.
Let's say, you know, the patient has a P-3 mutation, you go looking for that P-3 mutation.
And so that there weren't ever at that time then methods that could do that more sensitively.
But that ran into the problem that you mentioned, which is that, well, now you're looking for one mutation.
It's less than a cancer genome present in the blood tube.
And so you just cannot you have lots of negative samples just because that mutation isn't there.
It's not in the blood draw you took.
So the way that we overcame that was actually fairly very simple, which is just to say, well, let's use this next generation sequencing technology where we can get sequence for millions of molecules.
And instead of looking for a single mutation, that looks for dozens of mutations from the patient's cancer in parallel.
So compared to looking for one mutation, looking for 10 actually increases your sensitivity tenfold by a whole order of magnitude, because I don't have to see all ten mutations.
Now the cancer is still there.
If I have mutations are specific, I just need to see one of the ten.
And you don't care if they're coding or non-coding.
Correct. That's true.
We don't care if they're coding or non-coding and we've successfully used both.
But what is beneficial is to have what's called a truncal or clonal mutation, meaning a mutation that's present in every cancer cell.
So as cancer develops, as we talked about earlier, by acquisition of mutations, the cell starts healthy, it gets the first mutation and then ultimately gets to be a cancer which has tens of thousands of mutations.
Those happen over time, right?
Years, generally.
Many of those mutations are present, many of the ten thousand are actually present in all cells of the tumor, even though they're not driving the cancer, just because it's the history, the evolutionary memory of that cancer, right?
That the cell that ultimately was able to continuously divide has already had these ten thousand mutations from the precursor process.
And so once it then gets the final mutation that lets it divide forever, it keeps all those to other ten thousand mutations.
So we don't care. We just want the mutation to be present in all the cells.
And it's interesting because driver mutations have surprising heterogeneity, right?
I mean, I was actually talking to Steve Rosenberg about this on the podcast last year and I was amazed at the non-overlap of driver mutations.
And so, yeah, a lot of people had P53, but it wasn't necessarily the driver. So it was present.
And also, I mean, this gets it back into your other thing that you're interested in, which is the immunology is how often it was not the not a mutation that was antigen inducing.
But that was, yeah, that was immune response to this again.
So so let's now talk about is there such a thing as cell free RNA or is that just so unstable that it's not even worth thinking about and is cell free DNA the only place to be thinking about this?
No, absolutely not. There is such a thing as cell free RNA.
That field is much more nascent than the than the DNA field.
What advantages would it offer given the instability of the molecule?
I think there are some critical questions initially about what is the stability of the molecule, you know, how much of it is there and how stable is it.
And then you miss the non-coding mutations as well, right?
Well, yeah, you would there you can if you're looking for mutations, I don't think it has advantages, really.
But you can do other things. Right.
So like my vision is that ultimately we want to get to the point where we can from a blood draw determine as much as possible about a patient's cancer, ideally eventually to the point where we don't even need to biopsy it.
Now, that is science fiction currently. Right.
But if you extend the line of work decades into the future, that is where we're trying to get.
And that means we have to be able to if we want to get there, we have to be able to measure things other than mutations.
Mutations are important. They're critical. But they're only a small part of the puzzle.
Measuring RNA could tell you about which genes are on and off in the cancer theoretically.
And so that is critically important, for example, in the immunotherapy field that you mentioned.
There's some markers like PD-L1 that can be expressed in the tumor cells that can basically hide the cancer from the immune system.
That marker is that's not a mutational process in the vast majority of patients.
It is it's expressed from the promoter, like, you know, just turned on for, you know, reasons have to do with signaling, epigenetic reasons, et cetera.
And so you can't tell by looking at the sequence in DNA of PD-L1 whether the tumor is has this marker. It's not a mutation marker.
So we'd like to be able to measure something like that from the blood. We'd like to be able to tell the difference between an adenocarcinoma and a squamous cell carcinoma,
or between a lung cancer and a breast cancer from the blood. And some of those things you can do with DNA potentially, but a lot of them you can't.
And they might be better done with RNA. So it's absolutely it's a fascinating area. My group is working in this area.
We haven't published our work, but we will hopefully soon. We have some exciting premiere results.
I think I think in the future RNA will be a big part of the liquid biopsy puzzle that doesn't replace DNA.
It just it has it offers a complimentary pieces of information that you can't get from DNA.
Now, is there a difference between cell free DNA and circulating tumor DNA? Sometimes I've heard people use those interchangeably.
Are they are they interchangeable or is there a distinction?
They are different. Generally, cell free DNA refers to the total amount, the total DNA in the circulation that includes both the healthy cell derived DNA and the cancer cell derived DNA.
And circulating tumor is just the sub fraction.
Just the portion, that one percent that's from the or whatever that's from the tumor. Exactly. So that that that that's the difference in the terminology.
And then are there any other signatures that can be helpful here, for example, looking at methylation patterns on the DNA? Can that be informative at all?
Absolutely. Yep. So DNA methylation is refers to a chemical modification of the DNA molecules.
So we again, we have these about 170 base pair molecules in the circulation. And at certain of the the nucleotides, there can be chemical modifications that are put on by enzymes, particularly methylation.
A methyl group, which is a chemical chemical group. And that is put on not the same in every cell. Different cells based on largely what tissue they're from have different patterns of this methylation.
And it has to do because these methylation marks, these kind of modifications can influence which genes are turned on and off.
So you can envision that in a lung cancer that needs the genes to the lung cell that needs genes for surfactant production or making a VLI or whatever needs those genes on.
But it doesn't need the genes on that of an adipose, a fat cell to make fat because it's not doing that. So they might be methylated.
Some genes are methylated and turned on or off in different cells in different ways. So they can be more exquisite marks of the origin of the DNA.
And so there's been a lot of work in the last couple of years looking at methylation marks to do that.
And it has some potential advantages because unlike mutations, you know, they're much more stereotyped.
So a lung, the methylation of a lung cancer of two lung cancers is more similar than their mutation profile.
So in other words, you can use the mutations to identify and distinguish between tumor and non tumor and you use the methylation to hopefully zero in on tissue of origin.
You could, for example. Yes, exactly.
If you were using it as a pan screen.
For screening purposes, exactly, which is a little it's a different scenario than this initial scenario of saying I have a patient who I've treated with surgery or radiation. I want to know if they're cured.
Now, I think an important thing to recognize is that the sensitivity of the methylation based approaches is significantly inferior to that of the mutation based approaches, which.
But from a practical standpoint, the methylation approaches have some advantages for the screening question. But the sensitivity and the practicality aren't aligned because you'd I really you'd want the most sensitive assay possible for screening.
Right. Yes. Because the tumors are tiny, but that is not the current state in the field is that the mutation based methods are much more sensitive.
So we recently published a paper, a new method, a new method that's for the third generation mutation based method that's about a hundred times more sensitive than our prior methods as well as other methods in the field.
We can now get down to one part in a million. So we can detect, you know, maybe with the prior methods were kind of bottoming out at about point oh one percent.
The prime mutation based method around point one percent. So one in ten thousand. This new method can get to one in a million. So, you know, that's a two log improvement.
So that's a log improvement is a dramatic, of course, improvement in a diagnostic assay. And so with that assay, we have, you know, now with lots of patients where we had sample leftovers, we could use our first gen assay and now come to this new assay.
And we had false negatives with the first gen assay that now we can pick up with this newer method saying that it's not that they didn't have any wasn't that there was no CT DNA.
There was certain tumor. It just was not at the level that the prior generation could detect. So that one, you know, we're about a one in a million with the methylation based assays.
It's actually the data is still not very mature to know exactly what their sensitivity is. But as the put, you know, putting data, the data that's been literature as well as some of our own experiments, it's probably closer to one, one in a thousand.
It's a point one percent. Now, of course, to be clear with the mutation, the advantage, what makes the mutation based method so much more sensitive is, you know, what you're looking for.
You have the mutation a priori in the methylation method. You don't. Right. So you if you're doing a pan screen for someone who doesn't have cancer by definition, you can't know what mutations to look for.
That's right. So how does that gap get closed? Because if you look at a test like Grail, for example, so Grail is, I believe, looking at exactly this method, right? They're using I think they're looking at methylation patterns of cell free DNA.
But they're doing it as a pan screen. So it's give me 10, 20 a mile of blood. And we're just going to look for all the cell free DNA. We're going to identify if there's cancer or non cancer in there. If there is cancer in there, we're going to try to predict the tissue of origin.
How how good can that get? Because right now the sensitivity for all stages is probably 50 percent.
With a specificity of about 99 percent, it's above 99 percent. But if you look at stage one, right, if you're really trying to catch an early cancer, we're talking about a sensitivity of maybe 20 percent, right?
Right. So this gets into a very interesting part of this this diagnostic field in general, particularly this liquid biopsy field with regards to early detection, which is how results are are presented. And you put your finger on it.
We care about sensitivity and specificity. We want specificity very high. Ninety five, 99 percent, something in that ballpark. And we want high sensitivity. Now, when studies report sensitivity across stages, I have an issue with the weight that when that is done, because it is you can easily bias that by just including more stage four patients. Right.
One stage one patient and 999 stage four patients and say, I have sensitivity of blah from stage one to four. So I think what you did in this, as you laid it out, is it's important to break it down by stage.
And actually, even within stage one, it should be broken down because when you for like a lung cancer, let's say we break stage one into stage one, a stage one, B and even stage one, a one stage, one, a two stage one.
So it gets very granular and that all relates to small and smaller tumors that have better and better outcome that are the ones you want to catch. And so in lung cancer, actually, the sensitivity for stage one lung cancer in the grill that's been presented is actually five percent or less.
OK, so let's make sure people understand the math on that. If it's bigger than stage one, you don't need a liquid biopsy. You can do a low dose CT and you'll see it. Right.
But in theory, the only reason you care about a liquid biopsy is if we're talking about fewer than a billion cells.
That's true. I mean, if if you had a patient, you could do either test. That's true. There are some potential advantages of the blood based test as a way of getting more patients screened.
I think there are some practical reasons why you could argue. Let's say they were.
Yeah. If people have less access to care and access. Right. It's like it's the advantage to get the scan. Yeah. Yeah. Fair enough. OK.
But but let's just say let's I want to make sure people understand the following. If a test has and this is going to be, I think, amazing for people.
Fifty percent sensitivity. Ninety nine point five percent specificity. If you said that that was your stage one performance in an unbiased sample, I think people would be like, wow, that's pretty good.
I mean, for people who don't have cancer for who for whom we believe don't have cancer in whom we don't have any mutational information, I have a test that is fifty percent sensitive and ninety nine point five percent specific.
Do the test. OK, here's how I explain this to my patients. What is the pretest probability that you have cancer?
So if you're one of my patients and you're forty five years old and you're not a smoker and your family history is relatively normal and oh, by the way, your colonoscopy is negative.
In other words, your pretest probability is one percent. So you go and I encourage everybody to do this. And for the show notes, we're going to include my calculator.
So I built a little calculator, but there are apps that do this. I just do it in Excel. But you can download an app that will allow you to do this.
You plug in sensitivity, specificity and prevalence and it will spit out positive and negative predictive value.
Well, if you use the numbers I just gave you fifty five percent, ninety nine and a half specificity, one percent on the prevalence, if my memory serves me correctly, your negative predictive value is like, you know, goes to ninety nine point seven percent or something.
Or it goes from, you know, let's just say you put in ninety nine percent specificity. It goes to ninety nine point five percent negative predictive value.
And they say, well, that's really good, isn't it? And I say, yeah, but it's only a little bit better than what it was at the outset.
Your pretest probability was ninety nine percent negative. I just took you from ninety nine negative to ninety nine point five negative.
And by the way, your positive predictive value is forty percent. So if I get a positive test in you, it's more likely than not a false positive.
And so I don't want to be the guy that's raining on the parade because we are using these tests in our patients, but never in isolation.
And I just I guess the question that's that's a lot I loaded into that. So feel free to comment on any and all of it.
But where I want to go with this, Max, is without the mutational information that makes the type of testing you're doing in patients with known cancers so sensitive.
How can we make these things more than a parlor trick in patients who don't have cancer, at least at the surface?
Excellent point. Yeah, you you laid out some things that I often do in my my talks as I talk about these things.
This is something that's even not well understood, not just by patients, but by a lot of researchers and physicians, this issue that something that, you know, sounds great.
50 percent sensitivity, 99 percent specificity, even ignoring for the fact that the stage one sensitive is actually less than five percent.
Like just to stay on the surface, the 50 percent where it's where we're at.
That if you already basically have no risk of cancer, you know, less than one percent chance of having cancer, the test isn't moving, really moving the needle for you significantly.
And as a high risk of catching false positives, as you mentioned, because the positive predictive value isn't so good.
And that leads to lots of further testing anxiety.
Often we can't find anything, but then patients are worried for years that there's something brewing.
Is it just the next scan will show it or the next time? And so I have lots of concerns about that.
I am I'm one of the researchers that's really focusing on this field.
And I very much see these issues and I'm concerned about them.
This is why I really strongly feel that we as the field need to ultimately really do studies that prove cancer specific survival benefits of these tests.
And that is currently not really on the road map.
The commercial efforts, which there are many, are largely they're not planning on doing this large these large randomized trials like the LDC, low dose study we showed we talked about earlier.
That proved that you save lives from lung cancer. Why not?
Well, they're expensive and take years, right? And so it's not attractive from an investment standpoint.
But if we really want to be sure that we are helping our patients and we're not just adding costs to the health care system, that's what we have to do.
And we don't know if the sensitivity as of the best test as they currently are, are good enough to save lives.
And there's multiple reasons for that.
But an important reason is that it gets very complicated. But even beyond.
OK, we are said you got to look at by stage because by saying across all stages doesn't is meaningless because you can gain that even within stage one.
You got to look by stage one. A one, one, two, one, three.
But even once you're at that point, it gets even more complicated because there's actually really.
But let's say we have stage one cancer patients. There's two types of stage one cancer patients.
The stage one cancer patients where the cancer cells have not left the lung.
There's that's where they are. That's the only place they are. And the surgeon removes the tumor and the patient is cured.
That's one type of stage one lung cancer patient.
The second type of stage one cancer patient looks the same as the exact same CT scan as the same surgery, but already has microscopic cells in the liver and the brain that we don't know about.
They're stage one. We call them stage one because that's all we can see.
But so stage one is actually heterogeneous. There's two subtypes of it.
And in order for a screening test to be useful, it has to catch a significant fraction of the first type of stage one, the stage one that doesn't have micro metastases because which the surgeon can cure.
Because I think what's implicit in your comment, Max, is that the surgeon is not going to cure the second one.
Good point. Yes. So the surgeon can cure what he can see or she can see right what they can cut out.
But if there's micro metastatic metastases in the liver and the brain, the surgeon isn't cutting those areas because they don't know about them.
And so those will eventually grow back. And so that is why simply saying a test increases the number of patients diagnosed at earlier stages doesn't automatically prove that that test will save lives.
Because when you look at the very granular level and you consider this issue about that there being different kinds of stage one patients, you can envision a test that mainly catches the patient with micro metastatic disease.
And actually we have hints that the CT DNA assays preferentially catch those patients because of the things we talked about at the beginning with there being now lots of microscopic deposits spread throughout the body.
If you were to put those all in the one place and add them up, you would have many billions of cells. Therefore, overall, you have more circulating tumor DNA.
But you can detect it, but you think they're stage one because that's all you can see on the scan.
So how do we ever how do we prove that the tests are not falling into that pitfall is we have to do randomized studies.
That's the only way we can we can prove it. And so that that's something to me that's a major concern.
And there is this push and pull about, well, these are great tests. They're very promising.
And obviously I wouldn't work on it if I didn't think ultimately these will save lives. But so can we do we should we withhold them from patients.
Right. If they are from non cancer patients especially. Yeah.
From non cancer patients. Yeah. Not because we should we withhold if we are have the test.
OK. We don't know yet if they're going to save lives. But isn't it unethical to not give them because if we later find out if we ten years from now or five years from now, find out they save lives.
Now there's five years of patients who didn't have the benefit. That is an argument that's often put forward.
You know, the problem with that argument, which is why ethically it sounds, of course, very reasonable, is that if by that argument we would never test anything new that we develop in medicine because there's always a possibility that that thing could improve things.
Well, and that's, I think, why the FDA has taken the posture because right now there are only four approved liquid biopsies. Right.
Garden to three others. Yeah. Yeah. Garden. There's some academic assays as well. Like Morris on getting back from. But those are four very different things. Right. Those are four genotype.
We haven't really talked about those are for identifying what mutations are present in patients with advanced disease. That's what those tests. Yeah. So let's actually talk about that. Let's tell folks what garden does. And you know, it's an FDA approved diagnostic.
But explain to people what it's used for because I get asked this question all the time. So the garden assay.
And they're one of the first companies in this field. They use a very similar method to what we use an extra sequencing to measure circling tumor DNA. But the test that they, their initial test, the one that's approved was developed for a very specific clinical problem.
You have a patient with metastatic cancer, let's say lung cancer, you know, multiple parts of the body and you want to identify what mutations that patient has because in lung cancer, we have drugs that work for patients with certain treatments based on mutations.
Yeah, exactly. It's what we call actionable. If we know what the mutation is and if we have a drug for it, that's the first thing we should treat the patient with. Historically, we always had to do a biopsy or surgery to get the piece of the tissue to to identify the mutations.
What we've we, you know, the field garden we others have shown is that you don't many patients with advanced disease because like say one percent of the circling tumor DNA is from the cancer.
But that's enough that you can identify the mutations without needing to the biopsy. So that's potentially very useful, particularly in patients who can't have a biopsy or where they had a biopsy, but the whole all the tissue is used up.
There's lots of cases like this and or where the biopsy missed the tumor that happens a lot, as you as you know, or a certain subset of the time.
So in those cases can be super useful to have a blood test to say, oh, yeah, this patient does have an EG for mutation. So they should get on the EG for tires and kinase inhibitor. That's what those tests were developed for.
Now, that is the easiest problem in the liquid biopsy space because you're in stage four patients that are known to have cancer.
High tumor burden.
High tumor burden. And so those tests are optimized for that. They work well for that. They have good agreement. 80 high 80 percent agreement with biopsy.
They can sometimes find mutations of the biopsy misses because of technical issues with the biopsy, as I mentioned. So they have their good test for that for that problem.
They are not designed for number one early cancer screening or detection where the levels of certain tumor in a day are many logs lower.
And they're not designed for this question of is the patient cured or not after treatment begin where the levels are much lower. They are designed for this one thing. And and that's very important to recognize that we can't that test.
If you were to go to the doctor and say, you know, I want to test to see whether I'm cured or not, that those FDA approved tests don't do that.
Is that true of is it cell search and foundation one? There are a couple of the others that are approved, right?
Correct. Yeah. Yeah. Foundation has a liquid biopsy test that's basically very similar again, technology similar to what we developed in garden. And they do the same thing now.
Cell search is actually a circulating tumor cell assay that is FDA approved. Actually was that was approved before any circulating tumor DNA assay.
And we talked about certain tumor cells at the beginning. They at the very beginning of the look of biopsy field, like in the early 2000s, that was the focus.
They were everyone's focus on the cells. And so that's why that was the first test. It is FDA approved. No one really uses it because it's not doesn't provide you actionable information.
Your doctor runs that test. Whatever the result is doesn't impact how the patient has met treated. And so therefore that has grown out of favor. And there is a difference between FDA approval and actually clinical usefulness that that is important to recognize.
Now, when you look at a test like GRAIL, for example, the FDA has not approved it yet, but it is still permitted in use. Explain that distinction.
This is a complicated area in the diagnostic space in the U.S. where there's really two kinds of ways tests can be regulated by the government such that they can be used on patients.
One is the one is well known as FDA approval, which is, of course, an agency that focuses on developing, approving drugs and diagnostic tests and evaluates them carefully and then allows companies to give them approval to market them if they pass all the bar of what you need to show.
The second way is actually a much easier way to get assays out to patients. And that is by setting up the assay in a lab that is compliant with what's called the CLIA Act, which is basically an act of Congress that focuses on regulating laboratories that do diagnostic tests that's independent of the FDA.
And those way that roughly works is that the lab itself gets this designation that, yes, you guys are doing things in an appropriate way. They get inspected every year or two and to make sure they're doing things appropriately.
And then those labs have the blessing to develop any tests that they want using the procedures that they're supposed to follow with running control, those kind of things, and then offer them to patients.
So the FDA never reviews those. It's really a much less highly regulated because basically the individual tests aren't regulated. It's the laboratory that's regulated.
And that is what, you know, GARDEN did before they got their FDA clearance. That's what GRAIL is doing. That's what all the diagnostic companies, they start by building a CLIA laboratory and then building their assays in that frame because they're much less regulated.
And so you can start selling them to patients and providers long before you'd ever get FDA approval.
So from a technology standpoint, I mean, there are like 30 other companies that are out there doing this right now and not to use the word GRAIL again, but the holy GRAIL is the blood test that's going to take a patient who doesn't think they have cancer, screen them with a high enough sensitivity and specificity
And I do the blood test and it says, Peter, we're afraid that you have, you know, colon cancer. What? I had a colonoscopy two years ago. Well, it looks like you have it again.
Go get a colonoscopy next week. Low and behold, there's a tiny little adenomatous polyp there that is an early stage one.
And gosh, I need just the smallest little partial colectomy and I'm cured because that is a hundred percent curable cancer or, you know, a woman gets a blood test and it says you have breast cancer.
And she says, that can't be. I don't feel a lump. My mammography was negative six months ago. Understood. Maybe you should go get a diffusion weighted image MRI and look at that breast a little more closely.
And sure enough, there it is. What would really be amazing is if we had the confidence in these things that even if they were never showing up on imaging, you could treat them.
Right. I mean, that would be this is now we're getting back into science fiction. What's science fiction? Science fiction is in it.
In five years, you're going to have a one centimeter pancreatic adenocarcinoma. And, you know, you and I, Max, both know that even a one centimeter pancreatic adenocarcinoma has a 25 percent five year survival.
I mean, that that is a death sentence of a cancer, unfortunately, even at stage one. So, you know, waiting until you can see a billion cells on the CT or MRI is not going to be the way to remedy pancreatic cancer.
It's either going to be much earlier detection or treatments that actually work. So today we have neither of the above.
Is there a path to this sci fi world that I'm dreaming of where using the blood alone, we can actually start to develop a high enough sense of confidence that that patient does indeed have cancer, but they might be three or four years away from it being clinically detectable.
I do think I am hopeful that we could get there. It's not going to come in one step, but we are already taking steps towards that. So building building the bricks on top of each other.
And the reason I say that is that the easier application, again, is in the patients who already know deaf cancer, where we have these super sensitive tests that we can then run after and see who's cured or not.
So that we now have we have these tests that that can detect the state that's called minimal residual disease, meaning microscopic cells that are residual after your treatment and that have currently at least a very high positive predictive value, meaning that if you detect the CT DNA, the patient is very likely going to have the cancer grow back.
And is that guiding therapy? Is that immediately now sending you to adjuvant therapy right away?
That's exactly where it's going. Excellent point. So there's now studies, clinical trials underway to do that. So we've recently launched a couple here at Stanford in lung cancer where we're taking patients with early stage lung cancer.
They can have one of the trials that it's very broad. They can have radiation or surgery, whatever it is appropriate if they need chemo for their standard of care for their stage.
And we get that too. When they're done with every standard thing, they get the blood test and we do the this minerals and jewelry test. If it's positive, we give those patients immunotherapy before we can.
We can't see any cancer anywhere in the body, but we know they have microscopic cells left behind. And that is the moment in the patient's lifetime with their cancer that they will have the least number of cells they'll ever have.
And the lowest chance of having resistance. So I'm very hopeful that by doing that we will be able to cure more patients. And we already have evidence of that because we know adjuvant treatment even given the brute force way like we've done for decades where we basically give it to everybody with the same drug in adjuvant is more effective than the same drug in metastatic.
Yeah, I think this is a very important point that gets lost on the part of many people in the field, which is early detection absolutely matters. And you have to look no further than that simple point, which hasn't I've never seen it refuted.
Less tumor burden, less heterogeneity equals better outcomes. It's an axiom.
That's correct. That's absolutely true. And that's because we know that, you know, we now understand much better that why cancers are become initially respond and become resistant is because of this heterogeneous genetic heterogeneity that they already have mutation.
They're not all the same. The cancer cells actually all two, no two cells are probably the same. They're all different. They all have slightly different handful mutations that are different in between each cell. And some, the more cancer you have, the higher the chance that one of those mutations will make the cancer resistant to whatever therapy you're using.
So this idea of guiding adjuvant therapy based on CTNA MRD, I think is the first step towards what, you know, the future that you're that you're envisioning or dreaming of.
And so let's think about which cancers that's going to be relevant in. So it will not be relevant in pancreatic because everybody's going to probably need adjuvant. I mean, if you're really being honest, it certainly is relevant in your field of lung cancer.
It's certainly going to be relevant in breast cancer. It's certainly going to be relevant in colorectal cancer. I mean, you could you could potentially argue prostate, although the treatment is pretty bad.
Those that really takes care of kind of the big five right there. The common ones. Yeah. Yeah. I throw in bladder, which is what are the six most common cancer. You could, of course, some of the more rare ones.
It would be useful melanoma, of course. It's much more rare, of course. But where we also give adjuvant. I agree with you. I think the way that I think of it actually is it's going to be useful in the cases where a minority of patients develops recurrence.
If you have a situation like pancreas cancer where the vast majority of stage one patients will develop recurrence, that's not the place to start this kind of developing this kind of a test.
Because like you said, the tests aren't ever going to be 100 percent perfect. And even a perfect, you know, you already have no test gives you 75 percent chance of recurrence that it.
That's not the place to do it. It's to do it in places where there's a subset that recur. And in many cancers, actually, that maybe at certain stages you don't need it. Stage three colon cancer. Well, maybe we don't need it there.
Yeah. We know the probability of recurrence is high enough. We should just treat it accordingly.
Maybe maybe we should have treated. But stage one, too. That's a different story. Right. The minority recur there. So I think that's how I think of it of where to first focus on.
So. So. So we've talked a lot about where we are on that. Call that stage one writer. You know, program one identifying the high risk patient who needs adjuvant therapy. Great progress on lung.
What is the state of the art for that exact problem on breast, prostate and colorectal cancer?
So there are active studies underway. The colorectal cancer actually, I would argue, might be the furthest along. There actually are some Medicare approved tests using CT DNA from a company called Natera for colorectal cancer that that I believe can be reimbursed in some patients.
Actually, even though there hasn't been proof of benefit of that, that that treating based on it matters. But that's something that got approved recently. So I think in those patients, a subso that can already be done in a doctor's office.
But there are many trials going on in colorectal cancer, actually many more than in lung cancer currently. And there are trials going on in breast cancer to to also do similar things. Now, breast and prostate are actually more challenging for a couple of reasons.
But one is they have very low levels of circulating tumor DNA. It seems that there's difference between tumor types and how much circulating tumor they shed for a certain amount of volume. And they seem to have lower levels.
So it's a little more challenging. So you need to use these very, very sensitive mutation based methods and probably even the subset of mutation based methods that's most sensitive.
But there are so I know there's studies going on in in breast cancer. I'm actually not aware of prostate cancer studies in the CT DNA space because of this issue of the very low concentrations. But I wouldn't be shocked if there are now some places that are doing a few.
Yeah, prostate seems to be a very privileged site. I mean, even the Grail test, I think they say really it doesn't screen effectively for prostate because you're just not getting enough cell free DNA in the circulation.
That's correct. Or breast actually. The the the Grails and development plan initially was largely around breast, but they then pivoted because the early results were that breast also didn't do very well.
So that's then I think it would be that the next stage of patients you're interested in treating our patients who are, say, post adjuvant therapy or who were deemed low enough risk to not need adjuvant therapy, but who are still higher risk than the general population in whom you're screening for recurrence. Would that be kind of the next group you would want to develop a liquid biopsy to assess?
Yeah, I think so. I think if we can get proof of principle of that these things that this approach works in these early studies, I think that some logical next step would be exactly what you say, which is the way I view that is you can envision a future where actually maybe even you move into the more high risk patients with higher risk of recurrence where there's still a substantial number that don't recur.
But you do this test repeatedly, let's say every three months and you don't give adjuvant until you see a signal that the test is positive. So maybe even that way you minimize missing patients and you can still catch a month before they have clinical recurrence.
And I think it's very likely that that kind of an approach where you basically only give adjuvant the test is positive, but you do the test longitudinally to make sure that you don't minimize missing people, that that would very likely have equivalent outcomes to giving everybody in that group treatment.
Actually, maybe even better because you're not giving toxicity due to a big chunk of patients. So that's one. The second one, which I think is really exciting, is analogous to that basically, which is to, you know, I guess it's the same set of trials.
But I think it's looking at the other way around, which is to say that patients, you would avoid over-treating patients. So one big problem we have right now in adjuvant therapy in places like many places, but breast cancer is a good example of it.
The number you need to treat is quite high because most patients don't already cure the surgeon and don't have a micro-meter-static disease. And then the treatments aren't perfect. So the ones even that have micro-meter-static disease, the number don't benefit.
So actually we have a huge problem with over-treatment and this approach that I outlined with the repeat testing could get us away from that over-treatment situation where we only give the treatment to the patients where we have real evidence, you know, substantial evidence that they still have cancer cells in the body.
So those are three great use cases for liquid biopsies that are all going to benefit from a very important insight, which is, you know, the mutations of the cancer at the outset. So you get to pair a very important piece of information, which is tumor identification genetically with cell-free DNA.
We now need a different approach if we're going to move to the sort of panacea of cancer screening, which is every person once a year goes to their doctor, gives 10 or 20 ml of blood, and a test comes back that says, one, do you have any cancer, yes or no?
Two, if you do, it's this organ, let's go work it up, which either means in the early stages more diagnostics in the later stages means direct to treatment, right? That would be, again, what we talked about earlier.
It seems to me that one way to think about that is if you were going to try to do that based on mutation analysis, you would have to develop the world's most robust database of mutations for every given tumor.
Is that even possible?
Yeah, great question. So we, about a year and a half ago, published a paper where we developed actually a mutation-based lung cancer screening method using CT DNA. We call that method lung clip for cancer likelihood in plasma.
And it's a method that is purely based on mutations. The way it works actually is you sequence the plasma and the white blood cells of this screening patient, the sample, the patients you're trying to screen, you sequence both the CF DNA, cell-free DNA, and the leukocyte DNA.
The reason we do that is because we've learned that there, and in the older individuals, there are mutations present in the leukocytes often that have been acquired through age, through a process called clonal hematopoiesis.
So those mutations that are in the white blood cells also end up showing up in the plasma most of the time because the white blood cells die in the circulation and release their DNA and that's part of the cell-free DNA.
So those you want to get rid of because that's not coming from a lung cancer or breast cancer, right? So we do both. We subtract the things that are in the white blood cells, and then we use a machine learning algorithm that looks at the mutations that are left in the plasma and looks at things like how long is the cell-free DNA molecule?
We talked about it, but we and others have shown that the cancer-derived cell-free DNA molecules are a little bit shorter than that 170 bases. They're tiny, but a few bases shorter on average.
The reason we think is because most of the DNA in the blood comes from white blood cells. We know that's true, about 80-90% of the cell-free DNA is coming from white blood cells.
And that the other 10-20% comes from solid organs as well as cancer. And probably the DNA has to traverse longer to get into the blood, right? If you die in the tissue and then to get into the blood takes a while. And that's probably a longer time to be exposed.
That's right. So we think that's part of the problem. It may also be that some of the way the histones in the chromatin is configured may contribute to it. But for whatever reason, that is true.
So we look at is a mutation present? What gene is the mutation in? How long is the cell-free DNA fragment? Is this mutation one of the mutations that is caused by smoking? All these different things.
And put that in a machine learning model. And the machine learning model isn't just saying, have I seen this mutation before in lung cancer? But it's looking at these other properties to say, do the properties of the mutations match what you'd expect in the lung cancer?
And then the model ultimately spits out a probability that that blood sample was from a patient with lung cancer or not. And so that is, I think, the way that I would envision doing it using mutation-based approach where you're not actually doing this catalog of mutations because that won't work unfortunately because every cancer is unique and you can have a mutation in any gene, in any position.
Right. So but you're using, I assume you can use machine learning to basically predict what should be a cancer mutation versus not.
That's what we're doing. Exactly right. Yes. You basically try to use as much information as you can get beyond just the mutation being there. And now in follow-up work, we are trying to extend that by adding more such features. The more features you have that you know are cancer, that link with cancer, the better it is.
The question is, can we combine that with methylation? Maybe the combination of the two, right? You could kind of leverage the best of both worlds. Can we combine it with other analytes, other approaches? So that's how I think we're going to move forward to try to develop ultimately the best screening test.
And it very likely will be a combination of combining, you know, it's not just methylation or just mutation or just, you know, what's called fragmentomics, which is this size of the molecules or their distribution.
It likely will be a combo method. And so that's still very much in the early research phase. One has to prove which of those things combined nicely and usefully. And then once you know that, then you have to think about, okay, can I develop an assay that's, you know, affordable that no one could imagine doing on hundreds of millions of years?
And then you have to think about, you know, how do we get to the point where we're going to be able to do that? And then you have to think about, you know, how do we get to the point where we're going to be able to do that?
And then you have to think about how do we get to the point where we're going to be able to do that? And then you have to think about how do we get to the point where we're going to be able to do that?
And then you have to think about how do we get to the point where we can definitively say these patients have CTDNA and how much in stage one? So that experiment will tell us what is actually the lay of the land for the amount of circumtumidity shedding in stage one lung cancer.
And then we have that. We will know what sensitivity do we have to get to with a naive approach, meaning we don't know what the patient has cancer with this integrated approach.
And before I can say this, I need to see that data. But I'm hopeful we can push it above the 5% we talked about earlier. So in our study from a year or two ago, within stage one, we could get to about 20% sensitivity, including in stage 1A, non-small-cell lung cancer, in a validation cohort.
And what was the specificity?
The specificity was 98%, I think it was 200 in that analysis, 98%.
Which again, probably, again, I know that's early stage, it's still just not going to make sense for people whose incoming pretest probability is 1 to 2%. It's just still going to grow.
I mean, my back of the envelope math max is that if someone has a pretest probability of 1%, I mean, it sounds crazy, you're going to need 80% sensitivity and 99.5% specificity to say, this is a test that matters.
This is a test where, okay, now my positive predictive value is high enough that I can do something with this. And just as importantly, my negative predictive value means I can breathe easy.
Right. I think in the ideal world, you're absolutely right.
I mean, again, this is, do you think this is a decade away? Is it?
Yeah, I guess it's hard to, I mean, it's possible we can't get there with this approach, right? So if you had asked this question in the 50s with some of the protein biomarker work, which was exciting, people would have said, well, okay, we're not there, but maybe in 10 years we will. So I think we...
We don't know what we don't know.
We don't know, but we don't know, right? We don't know, we don't even know what the real distribution of CT DNA is because most of the experiments have used insensitive methods where most of them are negative. Well, then that doesn't, we can't see what's negative, right? So I think I'm hopeful we can get increase it significantly. I'm hopeful we can get to at least 50%, you know, 50 to 75%. Can we get to 80, 90%?
50 to 75, if it's truly early stage one, that's a big step forward.
Agreed.
If you can keep your specificity north of 99%.
Correct. So there are some liquid biopsy groups that have kind of done that by saying, okay, let's go with 80% specificity, because if you ever tested 99% specificity, that has 20% sensitivity, now you drop the specificity to 80, your sensitivity management goes up by 20%, right? Because it's just the dumb luck.
Yeah, and your negative predictive value goes out the window.
So that's the problem, right? So I think for the foreseeable future, there's going to be sort of just two sort of main areas, the way I think about applying these. One is in the cancers that have no screening tests currently, the bar is, of course, much lower.
Right. We know that mammography, even low dose CT, some they don't make me a colonoscopy is a little bit of an exception. But none of those are perfect, obviously. And yet, we do them and at least for the case of lung cancer and the colon screening for very confident they save lives, we think for breast cancer, of course, as you know, there's controversy around that.
But the, the in, in the cases where we don't have screening tests, if we can even get a test, that's kind of like that, not perfect, but can get us some that could be helpful. Like, it would be ideal in a case like pancreatic cancer, but for reasons we talked about earlier, but then we don't have the treat. Yeah, we don't know what to do.
We don't have to do with them. And I don't think that's the right place to do it. But other cancers, you know, that we don't screen for. So that there's that group. And there may be the bar is lower because we don't have a predicate, right?
In the cancers that the, that we already have screening tests for, I think it's really important how we compare, how the tests compare to the existing screening tests, obviously, if they're as good or better than what we're already doing. Well, then you could argue, well, then we should switch to those, right? Even if they're not perfect.
But, but if they're worse, which is currently the situation, the liquid biopsies aren't as good as those tests, then you really have to think hard about how you would use them. And then I think the main use has to start to be something that's more around practical considerations or health system considerations, like low dose CT, for example, we know a tiny minority of patients who are eligible are currently getting it in the US. Medicare pays for it, but the vast majority of patients who are eligible don't get it.
So why is that? Well, there's many reasons, but part of it could be, you know, this concern of radiation exposure, the difficulty of having to book another appointment to go to an imaging facility, access to the imaging facility. So if you're already a department care doctor, you're getting your PMGOM A1C tested or whatever.
It's probably easier to draw another couple tubes of blood and send those off, right? So there could be, but that's not the dream. That's helpful, but it doesn't solve the problem for us, I guess. So, so I think that's sort of, you know, I would rush and develop it.
But we still need to prove again, I think it's very important that these tests decrease cancer specific death, because I think ultimately we shouldn't, even though they're exciting technologies and we're very hopeful that they will, we shouldn't just give them a pass because they're high tech and not do the right clinical science.
Do you know of any companies out there that are actually in pursuit of what we're talking about as the dream scenario where you have a, an actual high sensitivity, high specificity test for low stage, early stage one?
I mean, I think all the companies are working to try to improve their, their tests constantly, you know, and this is one of the things with this, because they're being run in the CLIA environment, it's actually much easier to change the test than it is in the FDA and approval.
So I think people are trying hard. I haven't seen it solved, you know, I guess it's the next obvious question. And, you know, and that includes my group. We're working on it hard. We have some ideas we think are promising.
But it's too early to know how much they're going to push the bar over, you know, what we showed in that prior paper or what Grail showed in their recent paper.
How much money is the NIH putting into this?
On a global scale, that's a great question, actually. I have never seen a number of how much funding are they doing for a liquid biopsy research. I can tell you that it's increased dramatically.
So just in general, when I started working in this area, like probably 2012, you know, with our first publication 2014, when I was going to meetings around those times, I would often be the only person talking about a circulating tumor DNA.
There would be a bunch of other diagnostics, imaging, and a lot of circling tumor cell work at that time that was being presented.
Whereas now, you know, the vast majority of presentations at meetings and stuff is focused on liquid biopsy.
The same thing I've seen at the NIH in study section, you know, reviewing grants. Many of us, including myself, serve on these NIH study sections where one scores the grants that the NIH uses to fund research.
And it's a lot of work because you've got to read dozens of grants, and you know, you spend days of your week reading other people's grants and commenting on them.
But it's a service we do because, of course, otherwise the system doesn't work.
But now in the study section I sit on, which is focused on cancer biomarkers, we see lots and lots of liquid biopsy work being submitted and often scoring high.
So I think it's substantial. It's increased dramatically from 2012.
And there's a lot of interest from NCI and NIH. And these, you know, they see the value just like many of us do, and that this is an area we absolutely have to push forward and deserves more funding.
Max, this was super interesting. I mean, this is a topic I've been interested in for years, and I learned a lot today.
I really have a much better sense of the landscape and the history of how it got where it got.
So I'm positive that everybody listening to this will, even if they came in with less information, then me or more information is going to have gleaned something.
So thanks so much for making the time and setting aside, you know, a few hours of your day to talk about this and to catch up in general. It's just great.
Well, great. Yeah, it was really a pleasure chatting with you. It's great to see you again.
And, yep, thanks for all the insightful questions. I really enjoyed the conversation. I hope your listeners got something out of it.
I'm positive they will. Thanks, Max.
Thank you.