Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest today is Dr. Mike Gershon. Mike is a professor of pathology and
cell biology at Columbia University, where his research focuses on the neural control of the
gastrointestinal tract and the role of serotonin in the gut as a neurotransmitter. Mike earned his
medical degree from Cornell University, followed by a postdoctoral fellowship at Oxford. Mike has
received numerous awards and honors over the years, published hundreds of peer reviewed papers on the
nervous system, and even authored a book on the role of the brain and the GI system. This episode's
different from I think a lot of our episodes. Truthfully, I think it comes across more as a
bit of a med school lecture, which is how it felt to me. It was really interesting, but I think at
the surface, doesn't really come across as highly applicable. I think the reality of it is you just
have to get through some of the embryology, anatomy, and neurophysiology of the gut and the
brain to understand how these things coexist. I just want to be honest and set expectations.
If you're coming into this thinking that this is going to be a podcast that's about how to eat this
and not that and affect your gut biome, it's really not about that. This is a much more basic
discussion and I mean basic not in simple, but I mean basic in more elemental explanation of how
this system works. Truthfully, I learned a lot in this episode, much more than I normally do. A lot
of times I go into podcasts knowing the subject matter pretty well and maybe increasing my
knowledge by 20% or something like that, but I think this was pretty different. I think what
I would just say is rather than give you a blow by blow of everything we talked about here,
which would probably take me 20 minutes, I would say go into this assuming you're not going to know
much of what we talk about and you'll come out of this with a much greater appreciation for how your
gut and your brain are connected. Unfortunately, I think we're only now beginning to think about
how to translate that to clinical utility. In other words, I think that we don't yet have all
of the insights. I don't come away from this episode saying, oh, all you need to do is eat
this and your gut's going to be healthier and if your gut's going to be healthier, then your brain
is going to be better or vice versa. Maybe you'll come out the other end of this podcast feeling
like you've got it figured out. I certainly don't, but nevertheless, I feel like I have a much better
foundational knowledge to evaluate half of the snake oil stuff that is out there, which I mean,
I got to be honest with you, most of what's out there on this topic is utter nonsense. Commercial
tests that promise miracles that don't make any sense and supplements that just don't make any
sense and I think you'll come away from this kind of understanding how difficult it is to try to make
the claims that are out there. So without further delay, please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Mike
Pershing. Hey, Mike, thanks so much for making time to speak with me today about a subject matter
that I know very little about, but know enough to know that it probably matters and I think that's
why we're going to talk about it. Okay, I'll do my best. Let's kind of start with what is it that has
brought you so much curiosity in an area over what I'm guessing 60 years now is probably how
long you've been studying the GI system. Yes, I guess that shows you it's a very difficult
subject because I've been studying it for 60 years and there's still more to study. In other words,
I haven't gotten very far. Or as the saying goes, the further you get from shore, the deeper the
ocean gets, right? I love that. Yes, I haven't heard that before. You know, this is one of those
subjects that and I've been thinking a lot about this and trying to figure out how to frame our
discussion today, because there's just so much fundamental foundational knowledge that I think is
necessary to at least have a basic understanding of before we can get into kind of the nuanced
stuff around the GI system. So does it make sense to maybe just start with some of the real basics
of the human GI system, including frankly, its embryology, anatomy, vascular supply. And ultimately,
I think we're going to want to talk of course, about its nervous system, which is quite distinct
and unique relative to even the peripheral nervous system. Would that be a reasonable place to start?
Absolutely, it would. All right. Well, let's start with the embryology of this. So what is it that
takes place during our development as embryos that leads to the system of the gut? Well, before I
mention exactly what that is, let me just define it. Because I think that some people don't really
know what we mean by the GI system. So basically, it's a tube, it begins at the mouth, and it ends
at the anus. And as TS Eliot said, we are hollow men, and I will add, and women. So the inside of
the GI tract is really outside the body. It's internalized external space. If you bleed into
your GI tract, you lose blood. It's no longer in you, even if you can't see the blood. So one of the
major crises in medicine is hidden bleeding in the GI tract, which can be very damaging, even if
you don't see any blood. The inside of your gut is outside of your body. And as such, you can have,
and you do have inside the gut, space for the existence of a community of extra organisms that
is immense. And so the inside of your gut is dangerous and has to be kept separate from you.
So it's a major problem for the GI tract to keep a barrier and a surface to defend the body,
and yet allow food to be digested and absorbed and food stuff to come in.
So it has to maintain the communication with the lumen, which is what we call the inside of the GI
tract, and yet at the same time be protected. That's a really good point, Mike, which is that
we think about this all the time when we think about our skin, which is the other part of us
that is exposed to the outside world. And I think most people would be familiar with how many
bacteria we have colonizing our nasal passages, skin surface, et cetera. I guess most people would
probably understand that bacteremia is a bad thing when bacteria enter our body, and they can do so
through many of these pathways. It's problematic, but you're right in that the GI tract has a
particularly unique challenge, which is it must still do a lot of transmission across its surface,
obviously all of nutrients. In that sense, for example, the respiratory system only has to be
serving for gas exchange, and not to minimize that, but you could make a case that that's an easier
problem to solve to allow gases to exchange, but not to allow organisms to go through. So I think
that's a very interesting way to begin this discussion. Of course, I don't want to denigrate
the importance of the respiratory tract in an age of COVID. Let me tell you, it's important that gas
exchange be easy and proper. Anyway, to get back to the GI tract, the gut has a further problem
in that the food we eat is not ready for absorption. It doesn't come in. Food that you eat has to be
digested, so that you eat complex products, and then you have to digest it into small molecules
that can be absorbed. So that not only does the gut have to absorb a variety of things, it has to
have a particularly awful witch's brew to turn the same kind of thing that we're made of
into juice, essentially break it down without dissolving the body. The lining of the gut is
absolutely remarkable. So it's complex molecules that are not sterile as well, entering a non-sterile
environment, and somehow we have to only allow sterile nutritional building blocks to move across
the border. Yes, and those nutritional building blocks have to be made from the same kinds of
things that we're made out of, which we have to break down and digest. Without breaking down
ourselves. Correct, so we don't want to self-digest. It's a major problem, and the gut manages to solve
all that. Now you ask where it comes from. Well, during development, the body forms a disc, a flat
disc, and that disc undergoes a series of folds from head to toe and from side to side, and the
lateral or side folding produces the tube from which the gut forms, and so the flat disc folds
around to create an internal space, and that tube becomes the gut. How many weeks, can you remind me
post-fertilization, does that fold take place? The folding takes place during the first trimester,
and the gut is fully developed during the second trimester, and is between the second and the third
trimester when you're born. The gut is modeled and achieves its ability to do the kinds of thing that
we were just talking about, digest and absorb. The first part of development is called embryogenesis.
That is, the fertilized egg forms the disc, the disc folds, the organs of the body form,
and that's the embryonic period. The fetal period follows that, and the fetal period
models the organs into their final, or not necessarily final, because some development
continues to take place after birth, but appropriate development so that it becomes
functional enough to support a baby. In my recollection, which is about 26 years old now,
is that when that tube, that fold turns into the tube which will become the entire length of the
GI system from, as you said, mouth to anus. There are also these little outpouchings that come
along later that become things like the pancreas and the bile duct and things like that, which form
other things that drain into the GI system that obviously perform essential functions for digestion.
Yes, that same fold gives rise to lots of things, some of which drain into the gut,
like the pancreas, the gallbladder, which you mentioned, but it also forms the lungs,
which do not drain into the GI system, and the liver, which has a component that drains into the
gut through the bile system, but those are all derivatives of the gut. So the foregut forms the
stomach, the first part of the small intestine, the lungs, the pharynx, pancreas, gallbladder.
The midgut is the business of small intestine, and the first part of the large intestine,
and the hindgut is the end of the large intestine.
And my recollection, Mike, was that the foregut, midgut, hindgut basically tracked with the three
vessels coming off the aorta, the celiac, the superior and inferior mesenteric. Is that correct?
That is correct.
So maybe tell folks a little bit about that blood supply, what makes it unique,
which is, of course, we have a portal system, which is very important. We'll go from there
into the nervous system, which is perhaps the most complicated of the bunch.
As you've said, the foregut is defined as the part of the gut from the celiac artery.
The celiac artery is the first of the, or the most, rostral or anterior or...
Closest to the head.
Yes. I'm trying to put it into terminology that the entire world can understand. There
is also the terminology that the aficionados understand. So the celiac gives rise, or the
foregut, the celiac branch supplies the pancreas, the stomach, the first part of the duodenum,
and the liver, and the gallbladder. The superior mesenteric artery supplies the midgut,
and that's the longest part of the gut, and that goes roughly to the mid-transverse colon.
The colon has three parts. It folds. It has an ascending colon, a transverse colon going sideways,
and a descending colon, which goes down to the rectum and anus, which is out.
The inferior mesenteric supplies the end of the gut. When the celiac gives rise to the stomach
and first part of the small intestine's arterial supply, that then breaks into capillaries,
absorbs materials from the gut. Those capillaries drain into veins in the gut, and in a unique way,
those veins then form large vessels, which then move into the liver. They then break into capillaries,
small vessels within the liver called sinusoids. So the venous system that supplies the liver
is actually acting like it as if it were an artery, but it begins in the gut. And so the liver
depends for its oxygen on blood that the gut has had a first crack at. And to keep the liver going,
it gets a second arterial supply from the hepatic artery so that it gets a little bit of arterial
blood. And basically the liver is perfused with blood coming from the gut, and when it's about to
asphyxiate, a sphincter shuts that down, opens up, and it gets a breath of fresh air or fresh blood
and gets some oxygen, and then it goes back to dealing with what it gets from the gut. And the
reason it does that is the liver is the first step in the body's ability to use the nutrients
that the gut absorbs. So when the gut absorbs fatty acids, the liver turns them into
chylomicrons, which can go out and supply energy to the body. So the liver is a major center of
metabolism working on products from the gut. So it gets the first crack at what the gut has absorbed.
Now how about the nervous system of the gut? How is the gut innervated?
Well, as you've said, and I'm glad you've given your audience a warning,
it's complex and different. The gut has its own intrinsic nervous system, and I've called that
the second brain, and that's the title of the book, by the way. And the reason I called it the second
brain is that like the brain in the head, the nervous system of the gut is able to function
and control reflexes and behavior independently of any influence from the brain or spinal cord.
So it is the only nervous system of the body that can work on its own. So if you completely isolate
the gut from the brain and the spinal cord, it will function. You're not dead. Years and years ago,
in the days when peptic ulcers were thought to be psychogenic, surgeons used to cut the vagus
nerves, which are the major conduits that connect the brain and the gut. And after they cut the
vagus nerves, the gut continued to soldier on as it would have to. Unfortunately, it never did
all that much to fix peptic ulcer disease, and that turned out to be because peptic ulcer disease
is mostly an infectious illness caused by helicobacter pylori.
So you're saying before the discovery of H. pylori, it was believed that stress was driving
peptic ulcer disease. And the idea was that the central nervous system would communicate
the stress to the gut via the vagus nerve. That's correct. Now, that wasn't all wrong.
The central nervous system can communicate stress to the gut via the vagus nerve.
But that was not the cause of peptic ulcer disease. And it did help to show that the gut could,
in fact, be cut off from the brain and still work. But that observation was made long ago.
The nervous system of the gut has been known to be present for a long time.
It was discovered about the time of the American Civil War. Our back in Germany
noticed an extremely large nervous system in the human gut at that time. He didn't know what it did,
but later around the turn of the last century, that is 19th to 20th, in what I know to have been
a very cold, chilly laboratory in England. The reason I know that is I worked in England. I did
my post-doctoral training there. Laboratories were not heated. Even when I was there, we used to crack
the ice off the organ bath to get started in the morning. And I'd wear gloves with just
fingertips open so you could do experiments. Anyway, at that time, Bayless and Starling
cut all the nerves to the intestine of a dog. This is the same Starling from whom we have
Starling curves in cardiac physiology? That's the Starling. And so when they cut all the nerves to
the gut and then increased pressure inside the gut in the lumen, the gut would respond with the
stereotypic behavior of oral contraction, anal relaxation that they called the law of the
intestine, which was a name that I liked very much and sounded very poetic in a sense. 17 years later,
while armies were paralyzed during the First World War, crossed trenches that cut Europe
from the Swiss border on the way down to the English Channel in France and Belgium. Behind
the lines in Germany, another German scientist by the name of Trandellen Berg had tuberculosis.
And that kept him out of the army, even the German army at that time. But he had to keep busy.
So he strung up a loop of guinea pig intestine in vitro, that is in a test tube, on a J-shaped
tube. And he blew into the J-shaped tube, which raised the pressure inside the intestine, very
much like Bayless and Starling had done. And he found that even in a test tube, when he did that,
the gut blew back at him. And it was a very profound observation because it showed that
with nothing there but gut, the gut could respond, sense the pressure, and show a coordinated wave
of activity in response to it, indicating that the intestinal nervous system is able to function
independently of the CNS, the central nervous system. No other nervous system outside the
CNS can do that. And even the spinal cord can't do that. It works in conjunction with the brain.
How preserved is that, Mike, across other species? Is that kind of a universal finding?
Yes. It begins with a little organism called amphioxus, which undergoes metamorphosis,
turns into a vertebrate. So it's a vertebrate invention, and all vertebrates have it. You do
not find it in invertebrates. So it's a vertebrate invention, and it gets more complex as vertebrates
become more complex. So a fish has only one layer of enteric nervous system. Humans have two.
Actually, some people would say three. And the two that we have are between which layers? I guess
we didn't really finish our GI anatomy. So when you go from the lumen at the very inside all the
way out, you have a mucosal layer, a submucosa, a muscular layer. Is that where these different
bundles live? Yes. So the lining of the gut is called the mucosa. It has a superficial lining
that is in contact with the lumen called an epithelium. Underneath that is a loose nervous
system called the lamina propia, but together that's the mucosa. Below that, there's a dense
layer of connective tissue, which allows gut to be used for stringing tennis rackets,
allows gut to be used to suture material. It's tough. You can't pull it out. The next layer
is a circular layer of smooth muscle, another layer of smooth muscle, a second one called the
longitudinal layer. And then if it's in the peritoneal cavity, another layer of very thin epithelium.
The major parts of the nervous system of the gut are the submucosal plexus,
which has the epinim meister, but it's submucosal plexus. And that's in that dense layer of
connective tissue. And that's the smaller of the two. The larger one by far is the myenteric plexus,
and that is in between the two layers of smooth muscle on the outside of the gut.
The two plexuses communicate with one another, and they both really do get input from the central
nervous system and speak back to the central nervous system. So although they can function,
as I've been emphasizing, independently of control by the brain, in practice they don't.
They communicate, and there is constantly a bipolar or two-way communication between the
brain and the gut. The gut receives input from the brain and sends back information to the brain.
And in that function, bi-directional communication, the brain acts very much like a CEO.
That is, it gives general commands. The detail of what the gut actually does, that behavior,
is controlled by the bowel itself. Let me try to summarize that. You have these two muscular walls,
one of them runs longitudinally, so runs in the direction of the lumen, and one runs orthogonal
to that. It runs circularly. This is one of the things I remember from anatomy, was that you have
these things where if the circular inner layer contracts, that shrinks the lumen, and the
longitudinal one, as it contracts, shortens it along its long axis. And I think that's what permits this
remarkable, peristaltic, rhythmic contraction of the gut. Yes, I can talk to you about the behaviors
of the gut, but the behavior of the gut is not so simple as to have just one peristaltic movement.
When you look at it, it seems to be moving rhythmically, but it's much more complicated
than that. It doesn't do that all the time. Interesting. So that first part of the enteric
nervous system, which is the myenteric plexus, sits between those two layers, correct? That's correct,
yes. And then beneath those muscular layers is when you get into that very tough submucosal layer,
and it's between that circular muscular wall and the submucosa that you have, the submucosal plexus.
That's absolutely right. And then of course, inside the submucosa, you have the mucosa, and then
ultimately the lumen on the very inside with the enterocytes that form the endothelial lining of
the gut. Give me a quick sense of the epithelial turnover. What is the, I don't know, median
residence time of an epithelial cell in the gut? They vary depending on the type of epithelial cell,
but you turn the epithelium over about once a week. Interesting. And when you say it varies,
I assume you mean from, say, the proximal jejunum to the ilium to the colon? Is that
what you mean in terms of location? No. What I was talking about is that you have certain cells
in the lining of the gut, such as a cell called the paneth cell, which is in the base of the crypt,
which is getting into the weeds here, but it's a part of the folding of the lining of the gut.
But the paneth cell has two major functions. One is that it's defensive, and it puts out
a number of antibacterial proteins that keep the lining, particularly of the small intestine,
sterile or close to sterile, only a few thousand microorganisms per cubic milliliter. But the
large intestine doesn't have those, but it has cells that put out the equivalent kind of
antibacterial product that helps to fend off the bacteria from getting too close to the lining of
the gut. The other function of the paneth cell is to nurse the stem cells that turn over all of
the cells. So the paneth cell lasts perhaps three weeks. You also have in the gut endocrine cells,
these endoroendocrine cells that produce hormones that are in the lining of the gut,
and they're a little bit longer lasting. The endorocytes that you talked about
turn over very rapidly. Well, we're going to come back to those endocrine cells pretty soon,
because that's a very big part of this gut-brain connection I want to explore. I do have kind of a
random question for you though, Mike, which is, in some ways it's not surprising that the colon
is so susceptible to neoplasia, to the formation of cancer, because it has at its surface a cell
that turns over so frequently, and therefore it's turning over constantly, and as a result you
probably have more and more chances for genetic errors of replication that produce mutations that
are oncologic. I find it interesting that the small intestine, which presumably turns over at
roughly the same pace, is almost void of cancer. Do you have a thought as to why that's the case?
Well, people have speculated on that. One part of the answer is that microbiome, to which the
large intestine is exposed, is orders of magnitude larger than that of the small intestine,
and the other part of it is that the products that sit in the lumen of the large intestines
sit there for much, much longer. Small intestine digests food and it just goes by very fast.
So in terms of being exposed to environmental toxins, or toxins produced by organisms, or
toxins that are split off from what you eat, the large intestine, which acts as a sewer,
really is exposed to very much more. My recollection is most of the nutrient absorption
is taking place in the small intestine and that the large intestine is mainly reabsorbing water.
Is that right? Yes, but not quite, because what the large intestine does is conserves sodium.
So it absorbs sodium and secretes potassium and water follows the sodium as it's coming back into
the body. So the colon acquired that function and it enables organisms to live on land. When organisms
lived in the water conserving sodium and water was not such a problem, living on land makes itself.
The bulk of the water that the gut absorbs, however, is not in the large intestine. It's
done in the small intestine together with the bulk of most of what else you absorb.
Still the final 100 milliliters or so per day of what you absorb is polished off in the colon,
and it is important in maintaining the body's fluid content. If you lose it, as one does in
cholera, where cholera toxin turns sodium absorption into chloride secretion, water flows out,
and you can die of dehydration in about four hours, and people do with cholera. So it's a great plague.
Perhaps three million people a year die of cholera even today. Three million people a year
die of cholera today? Correct. I had no idea. Where is this primarily happening? Is this in
Africa and Asia? At the moment it is, but there have been major league outbreaks in our hemisphere.
One began off the coast of Peru with contaminated crab. That led to cases that were as far north as
New Jersey, as people ate contaminated crab. Haiti, of course, is the most famous one. There
was a great earthquake in Haiti. It destroyed a lot of their infrastructure. They had a group of
peacekeepers from the United Nations from Nepal that was stationed there, and they brought cholera
with them, put it into the water system of Haiti. It got into the rivers and streams, and is now
endemic in Haiti. So it reduced the population of Haiti considerably, but it is mostly in Asia and
Africa. Are there direct treatments for it, or is the only treatment supportive care to prevent
dehydration? Well, it's a very simple illness. All one has to do is keep track of the water,
so you put a patient on what is known as a cholera cot, a gurney with a hole in the middle,
for the anus to be positioned over. You put a bucket under it. The nurse puts a ruler into
that bucket periodically to see how much fluid is coming out. You replace it intravenously and orally.
The great life-saving discovery was that although cholera blocked the absorption of sodium,
it does not block the absorption of glucose in the small intestine. And so adding a little bit
of sugar to the fluid that you're using for oral rehydration has saved countless millions of lives,
just that simple thing. So antibiotics have no use at all in color, zero. Does the immune system
basically, if given enough time, fight it off, and all you're doing is just supporting the hydration
status of the person until your immune system kicks in? Correct. I want to go back to something
you said earlier. You made a point to talk about the intrinsic innervation, and I realized that
there are going to be people listening who might not know the difference between intrinsic and
extrinsic neurons. Can you explain what that means in the context of the gut, please?
So the intrinsic nervous system of the gut is a term representing the nerve cells that live within
the gut. We've described them, the two plexuses. The extrinsic innervation includes the brain,
which sends fibers to those neurons, and the sympathetic nervous system, which projects from
outside the gut into it. And it also includes the spinal cord and the ganglia associated with the
spinal cord, sensory ganglia, and dorsal root, which provide a sensory innervation of the gut.
So those are all extrinsic nerves. Intrinsic means that the cell body of the nerve cell resides
within the gut. Extrinsic means that the cell body is outside the gut, wherever.
Mike, one of the things I'm sure anybody listening to this can appreciate is the incredible pain
that one experiences with distension of the bowel. I used to be a general surgeon, so when
patients present with bowel obstructions, it can be as painful as a bowel perforation, and it's so
important to be able to put a nasogastric tube in them and decompress them. And again, even if you
haven't had a bowel obstruction, just if you're bloated or something like that, it can be incredibly
uncomfortable. So explain to people how that pain of distension in the gut is being communicated
to their brain, where they're obviously conscious of the discomfort. Let me make two points. One is
that essentially pressure of the kind that which you're speaking, whether very severe, as you've
mentioned, or much less so, the only way the gut feels pain is in response to dilatation or pressure.
You can cut the inside of the gut with impunity. So surgeons are constantly doing that, taking
biopsies from inside the gut, and that can be done without anesthesia. So it's differently
innervated from the point of view of pain than the skin, for example. The skin feels pressure, but it's
much less of a painful stimulus than cutting. The gut is exactly the reverse. Most of the fibers
that get excited when you press increased pressure are located in the dorsal root ganglia.
Those are pain fibers that relay the signal to the brain by way of the spinal cord. The vagus nerve
has some pain, but not much. Mostly the vagus nerve carries information back to the brain
that has to do with signaling what is called homeostasis, which means we don't know for
exactly what it all is, but you need it. Before we leave kind of the anatomy and
innervation of the gut, you mentioned the CNS functions kind of like the CEO providing
broad instruction, but not necessarily minutia driven operational instructions. Can you give
an example of what type of information is conveyed by the CNS and how that information is enacted
locally? Let me give you an illustration this way. One of the things we do as scientists is depend
for our funding on the NIH, and we send in grant applications in which we try to give our research
its best look. Under goes peer review, and then the government decides on the basis of the peer
review on two levels, whether to fund it or not. So when I wait to hear how my grant has done on
peer review, I become acutely aware of the kind of effect the CNS can have on my gut.
After three trips to the John, I will go and open the computer and find out.
So what I'm saying is most people can resonate with that because they felt it, this feeling of
butterflies, this feeling of tension-induced diarrhea. That is all coming by way of the CNS.
Similarly, some people when they're frightened or traveling just completely lose the ability to
defecate. They become constipated. I always assumed that that was due to the dehydration
of air travel, but it sounds like you're saying there's more to it. There may be, yes, I think
there is. Well, what it seems to come to is, for example, the sympathetic nerves can slow the gut
and make it less likely to defecate, and that is in response to, as opposed to anxiety,
to true fright. So for example, if you're fleeing a foxhole because the enemy is coming,
it's best if you don't have to stop to defecate along the way.
You've alluded now to the sympathetic and parasympathetic overtone of the CNS.
So it communicates that via acetyl-CoA and acetylcholine, things like that. But at the
local level, how does the gut receive that message? And then let's use the example of
anxiety-induced diarrhea. The actual action taken by the gut is presumably more rapid
peristalsis and less absorption? That's correct. And that's all has to do with the
enteric nervous system functioning. One theory, which I believe, is that there are nerve cells
in the gut called command neurons, and they receive the input from the CNS. So it turns
out that the number of fibers in the vagus nerve that are running to the gut are pretty small in
humans, three to five thousand. It's been estimated. And the number of nerve cells within the gut are
in over a hundred million. So the intrinsics outnumber the extrinsics by three orders of magnitude,
if not more. So that raises the question, how do these nerve cells control it? As I've said,
as a CEO, they can get to command nerve cells and start reflexes going, keep things moving more
rapidly. The gut has a number of different behaviors. It's not just propelling at all times.
If the gut were propelling, as I described it with oral contraction, anal relaxation,
as it's capable of doing, then social discourse of the kind we're having right now would become
impossible. The gut has to sometimes stop. And so one type of behavior is just essentially parisis.
The gut stops moving. A second type of behavior that the gut shows is mixing in which it allows
the enzymes that it puts out to do digestion. And anyone who's ever taken time in an organic
chemistry laboratory will tell you nothing very much happens unless it's stirred. So the gut has
a mixing process in which it just goes back and forth, back and forth, no propulsion. And then
it's able to sense what goes on. And when digestion has occurred sufficiently, it propels it on.
It can also, during night while you're sleeping, a cleaning process goes through the gut
in which a wave begins. The stomach goes down the small intestine, down the large intestine,
and cleans the gut out. Open sphincters, so the things that would ordinarily be much too big to
pass can go through. So a little kid can swallow a paperclip, a dime, sometimes an open pin. And all
those things are passed. And miraculously, I don't know how the gut manages it, but if an open safety
pin goes in, somehow it manages to propel it all the way down with the small end down and it almost
never gets stuck. So let's pivot a bit to appetite. Obviously the gut plays a very important role in
the regulation of our appetite. And this, I suspect, is an area where the gut and the brain
are in a high level of communication. Can you walk us through what that looks like?
And let's assume we're talking about this in a non-pathologic state, because obviously there's
going to be things that I assume can hijack this process. A number of factors play into it.
Distention of the stomach being one, so that as the stomach is pushed out, it tends to cause
satiety and decrease your urge to eat. Another factor is not the level of blood glucose, but the
rise of blood glucose, the ascent of it. And these factors are sensed, one by receptors within the
gut, which send signals to the brain, and the other are cells within the brain that are chemosensitive
and detect nutrients within the gut. Another factor, which you alluded to before, are the
endorheal endocrine cells within the gut, which make hormones such as cholecystokinin, which can
signal to the brain by going through the blood-brain barrier to be received by neurons
leptin within the gut. So there are a large number of hormones, hormone receptors in the brain,
that can trigger your urge to eat, as well as nutrients that you absorb, as well as
distention of the bowel itself. So that the gut has receptors in it, and the brain has signals
within it that trigger the urge to eat. So basically, mechanical and chemical are the two
big means through which this is communicated? That's correct. That summarizes it well.
So the mechanical are both in the actual stomach, but also in the small bowel? Yes, to a lesser
extent. And those are transmitted back from the gut via the vagus nerve? Correct. The glucose
rate of change, as opposed to absolute level, is that directly sensed in the CNS? Yes, it is.
And that's fine, because of course glucose easily traverses the blood-brain barrier,
so the gut doesn't need to be involved in that decision. The blood vessels that provide blood
to the brain have transporters that allow certain chemicals from the gut, such as leptin and
cholecystokinin, to be transported so that they can affect the CNS directly. Where does ghrelin
fit into this? Ghrelin is another hormone from the gut that works in the opposite way to what
we've been talking about. I've been talking about things that decrease food absorption. Ghrelin
is a gut hormone that promotes it. So what amplifies ghrelin? You mean what makes ghrelin
be secreted? Yes. Well, there are certain chemicals in food that you eat that can do that.
Mostly it's nutrients that come into the body that suppress, like amino acids and fatty acids,
can suppress ghrelin secretion. Does that mean that ghrelin's natural state is to be secreted,
and it's the presence of nutrients that simply turn that down? Yes, it's secreted at a constant
rate, and it can be upped or downed so that inhibiting it is important to prevent the
development of ghrelin effect. And what about the type of meal? So if you took, you know, and this
is the kind of stuff that's done, of course, all the time in research models. I think Rudy Leibel
and Mike Rosenbaum have done a number of these experiments where you'll take mixed meal shakes
versus solids. What are some of the differences in the way that those things would affect
satiety? And is it all done purely through change in the speed of absorption, or are there
other factors between liquids and solids that might factor into that? Well, there are a number
of factors. I just want to mention while we're on it that Rudy Leibel is just across the street.
He's a colleague over here of Bonnet, Columbia. The rate at which the stomach empties varies
tremendously depending on what you put into it. So for example, if you just eat a saline meal, the
stomach will empty much more rapidly than if there's protein in it, and even protein will empty much
more rapidly than if there's fat in it. So the stomach senses the nutrients, and the speed at which
it empties regulates the dilatation of the stomach and the signal that the stomach is sending back
to urge satiety on the brain, which means that if you're eating protein and fat, you will
reach satiety much sooner than if you're eating just salt and sugar. In terms of solids, solids
do the same. Particles can't get through the pyloric sphincter unless they're ground down
to be millimeter or less in diameter, so only tiny things can get into the small intestine.
So solids will delay gastric emptying. The stomach has a particular form of behavior,
which is amazing when you watch it, but one part of the stomach contracts massively and suddenly
and forces the bolus that's in the stomach up against the pyloric sphincter, which is the exit
of the stomach, which is shut tight, and this ramming action breaks up solids into the small
particles that can get through. At the end of it, if you still have some solids that are too big to
reach that level, they can get through, but during sleep when cleaning process operates, and then
the sphincter is open. So solids will slow the emptying of the stomach, and anything that slows
the emptying of the stomach will tend to induce satiety and reduce the length of time during which
you feel hungry and want to eat. The point here you make about the particles needing to be sub-1
millimeter to get past the pylorus is kind of remarkable and gives you a sense of how much
mechanical digestion the stomach is doing. I mean, the pH must be helping that, but really there's
just got to be a lot of mechanical shearing that goes on of food stuff, correct? Absolutely right.
The stomach doesn't get its recognition in this story. When you think about how small a sub-millimeter
particle is, and yet how big things of food that make it into your stomach are, and to think that
it does this without fine instruments, it wouldn't be hard for me to make a bunch of 1 millimeter
pieces if you gave me a knife, but it's doing this basically inside a soft reservoir using
contraction and acid. And some enzymes. It is a remarkable structure, but you can live without
the stomach. Given everything we've just learned about the stomach, let's talk about an operation
where we bypass it, right? One of the most successful operations for the treatment of
both obesity and type 2 diabetes is a gastric bypass. What happens in a patient, and this is
kind of a remarkable operation in the sense that in an instant their upper GI tract is rerouted.
It's not like they had months and months to adapt to something new. I mean, there obviously is an
adaptation post-op, but it's an immediate change. Explain to folks what's actually happening in that
procedure and how it might explain some of the benefits we see most universally in post-obesity
and post-type 2 diabetes. Well, for one thing, why does the stomach just put all those little tiny
particles through? That's because if they were to get into the small intestine, it would set up
a lot of emergency, don't do this kind of apparatus. In other words, satiety, stop eating
signals, go into high gear. And what the gastric bypass is doing is it's triggering that emergency
procedure so that you're getting that satiety signal a lot. In other words, the kind of thing
that the stomach has evolved to keep in reserve is now coming to the foreground. It's no longer
there as an emergency to stop eating because I'm getting overwhelmed with signals. Usually you get
this because people, as in the Roman Empire when they would overeat, would force the system. The
stomach would dilate so much, they just overwhelmed the body and they ignored the signals. And so
the small intestine is there to back that up and get them to stop by making eating just so
objectionable that it stops. What the gastric bypass is doing is to make eating so objectionable
that it stops sooner and you eat much, much less. That's the goal of it. Another way to do this is
to put a band on the stomach and interfere with that process of grinding the food down so large
particles do come through the banded stomach and the same thing happens. And that would explain,
Mike, why both of these procedures can fail if a patient continues to consume very high-calorie
liquids. That's right. High-calorie liquids are the way around it. One of the things I always say to
people that are trying to lose weight is a pretty obvious insight, but this provides a better
mechanistic explanation for why is try not to drink any calories. Drink water, drink tea, drink coffee,
etc., but minimize the number of calories that are coming in via liquid, which includes alcohol,
by the way. Yes, and last I saw alcohol is a liquid. Let's talk now a little bit about the role
of neurodegenerative diseases and the gut. How long have you personally been interested in this
connection between diseases of the CNS and the gut? Oh, probably about 30 years or so.
I've recently become, if I might digress for just a second, even more interested in the sense that
I've discovered with my wife that the gut is a source of infection by varicella zoster virus,
which is the virus of chickenpox and shingles. And so shingles of the gut can occur. That can
be very, very serious. So I've never heard of that. Let's give people a bit of background on
how varicella zoster remains dormant after you have chickenpox and comes back as shingles. I think
people are probably somewhat familiar with that, but maybe worth re-explaining. And then of course,
bringing in this new idea that you've just brought up. The word that is generally used is latent
rather than dormant, but people get the picture. It's because it's essentially there, but not
sleeping. It's just quiet. Anyway, so when you get chickenpox, you clear the virus
and it forms what is known as an episome in neurons and just sits there
latent without causing infection for years and years and years. And essentially all of us die
with the virus that gave us chickenpox. It just stays with you for life. For reasons
that are unknown and only be speculated upon, they reactivate. And reactivation gives rise to
the re-emergence of active virus. And it always starts in a nerve cell because it's been latent
in a nerve cell. That's the site of latency. We know the virus becomes latent when it's in dorsal
root ganglia because then it goes down the axon or the process from the dorsal root ganglia into
the skin and causes a rash. And because you have immunity, it stays just in the nerve and in the
skin and doesn't give you a systemic disease like chickenpox was because when you had chickenpox,
you had no immunity. So it stays localized. And because the nerve cells die and become extremely
active and they're pain nerve cells, it can be an extremely painful rash. In 15% of people in which
that happens, there's a condition called postherpetic neuralgia or PHN in which pain persists for years.
That is very difficult to treat. And some people are driven to suicide because of this uncontrollable pain.
Mike, is that not something that's amenable to nerve killing? You know, for example,
they can sclerosis the dorsal root ganglion from which the pain is emanating?
No, there's no good at all. It's pathological pain. And the virus isn't there. The nerve cells
are no longer causing the pain. It's coming from within the CNS. It's sort of like a phantom limb
in which people cut off a limb and people have the feeling the limb is still there, but it's not.
So it's very difficult, as I've said, to treat. There are some drugs that do some good like
gabapentin, but nothing is wonderful. What is it about the varicella zoster virus that produces
this very peculiar inability to die even after the immune system gets ahead of it? Back when I
was a kid and you were a kid, we all got chicken pox. I think today they even vaccinate kids,
don't they? Yes, my wife developed that vaccine. She's famous for that.
Oh, wow. So despite either natural immunity or vaccine induced immunity, when this virus comes
into you, it stays, as you said, and remains latent in the dorsal root ganglion. Why is that
the case? Why doesn't the immune system completely eradicate it like it does in virtually every other
virus we encounter? Because when the virus is in a nerve cell, the immune system can't see it.
I see. So this is more of an artifact of where this virus likes to spend its time
or where it retreats to maybe is a better way to describe it. Let's call it a sequestered virus,
and it sits as a piece of DNA inside of your body and your immune system can't see it because it's
not expressed on the surface of the nerve cells that have it. The immune system has a very good
look at it when it re-emerges and you attack it, kill the cells in which it re-emerges,
but pain can continue in a small number of people, even so. What we've discovered,
much to our chagrin, is that the enteric nervous system can be infected by this virus when you
have chickenpox or when you get the live virus vaccine. It can establish latency within the
intrinsic nervous system of the gut, in the enteric nervous system, and when it re-arises,
even if it gets killed by the immune system, it's killing nerve cells. And so you get diseases such
as pseudoobstruction in which the gut loses the ability to work and just becomes totally paralyzed,
or if the virus emerges and gets into the mucosa, the gut can perforate.
And what's the frequency that this happens in?
We don't know. It's just been discovered. The most shocking thing that we've just published on with
this is that it gets into the nerve cells and re-emerges in the esophagus and causes a disease
called acholasia. And the ability of the esophagus to deliver food to the stomach is lost.
The esophagus can't open, so you can't swallow it all.
And just to be clear, this can occur during primary infection or reinfection,
or is this just during reinfection?
Just during reinfection.
What triggers the reinfection? I mean, I think most people understand that...
If I could answer that question, I believe I could get an all-expenses-paid
trip to Stockholm in December.
And if not there, at a minimum, you would probably get free dinner at Red Lobster every Tuesday for
the rest of your life. That's the second prize after the Nobel Prize. Yeah, it's interesting.
I mean, we know it's a disease associated with aging, or the reactivation is associated with
aging. And we know that things like weakened immune system can see it, I think, in the early
days of HIV, we would see patients. A weakened immune system is part of it,
and that's how you get to aging. That sets the stage. It seems likely that the virus
keeps reactivating periodically throughout your life, and that when you have shingles,
just exceed a threshold because the immune system has receded just enough to let it out,
reach the clinical threshold. That's the idea.
And the current vaccine that we have, Mike, the shingric vaccine, the two-shot separated by six
months, this has been kind of a step forward, correct? That has been a giant leap forward.
That's been amazing. And the purpose of that vaccine is just to prime our immune system
to the virus once again, to either catch it more quickly if it escapes the RG or...
Even more important, the enteric dose, it's about 97% effective. Remarkable vaccine.
Yeah, I got mine early. I'm not quite 50 yet, but I was like, ah, what the heck am I waiting for?
And the other thing I'll tell you is what a kick in the chops that vaccine is. That makes you sick.
Actually, interestingly, the older you are when you get it, the less likely you are to be bothered
by the injection. I'm reaping the benefits of my young immune system as I get butchered by the
shingric shot. What about diseases like autism? Children with autism seem to have, as the severity
of their illness goes up, an increase in the prevalence of gastrointestinal illnesses.
How well acknowledged is that? Is that loosely accepted or is that now becoming more accepted?
It's so accepted. What does that tell us? Right.
What can we take from that? What does that suggest potentially?
Well, autism is a disease involving probably synaptic transmission. It occurs in the CNS,
the well-known behavioral effects. It occurs also in the enteric nervous system
with small effects on the GI tract, some of which are constipation but more frequently diarrhea.
There also seems to be a higher degree of food sensitivities and allergies, doesn't there?
Yes. That's not so well understood, but it does seem to be related to activation of mass cells.
Spoken with many parents of kids with autistic children and a lot of them are pretty convinced
that if they pay more attention to what their kids eat, they can reduce the severity of their
symptoms. This would not seem like an entirely unreasonable idea given the simple observation
of this association, correct? It wouldn't seem to be unreasonable, but having said that, I would
like to point out to you that there's no regularity to the symptoms that you can point to. It's hard
to back it up and people have been unable to produce any sort of rigorous background for that,
so that when you put controls and constant observation, you just can't document it.
There must be so much variability that it almost seems like you have to be kind of empirical in
approach and probably no hate the term, but no one size fits all here, which is stating the obvious,
I suppose. I should also point out that the area is a bit fraught because in 1991,
a British gastroenterologist by the name of Andrew Wakefield published a study
in for a large number of children, not a large numbers. Yeah, it was actually a very small number.
We actually did a podcast on this entire subject matter, Mike. Oh, did you? Yeah, yeah. But by all
means, go ahead and tell the story because not everyone will have heard that podcast with Brian
Deer. Oh, well, he knows much more about it than I do. But in any case, Wakefield associated it with
GI inflammation. And his idea was that if you ate gluten containing material, you could produce
from what you were eating, what he called endorphins. That is, you'd eat an opiate like material.
Magically, the enzymes, the digestive tract would liberate opiate like products.
You'd absorb these opiate like substances and they would go to the immature,
developing nervous system and cause autism. That is not the case. And his idea was that if you got
measles, mumps and rubella vaccine, it would cause the defect in the gut, which could lead to the
absorption of these products. That was also incorrect. You can't train an enzyme to cut
something differently than the way the genes have programmed it to. So that trypsin looks for
particular amino acids and cuts proteins there. It doesn't care what kind of endorphin is sitting
somewhere else. Nothing can ever make it cut that out. And then when it gets peptides out,
peptides are essentially not absorbed. The only thing that's absorbed are amino acids, maybe
dipeptides, tripeptides. So tiny little molecules are absorbed. Yeah, let's make sure people
understand the difference there. Amino acids are the building blocks of peptides. A peptide is a
string of amino acids, but the amino acid is the smallest functional unit that makes up a protein.
So we have these 20 amino acids and you can string them together in thousands and thousands to make
complex proteins. But small peptide of 9 to 11 amino acids, for example, would be what the immune
system recognizes. And what you're saying, Mike, is from a GI standpoint, they have to be even
smaller than an immunogenic peptide if they're only sort of single amino acids or maybe two
peptides or two amino acids joined. That's correct. That gets absorbed. But even if there was some
miracle happened and they got absorbed, they couldn't get to the blood-brain barrier. They
wouldn't, in fact, go past the liver. So I testified, actually, to Congress on that subject.
Yeah, it's funny. Now that I think about it, Mike, I think you were actually mentioned in Brian Deere's
book. I might have been. There was an exhibit at the Science Museum in London called The Autism
Files. And I had a section called Mike's Miracles. And Mike's Miracles had to do with the way I was
phrasing it when I testified to Congress. And I was threatened then by Congress.
You were threatened?
Yes. I was told that if I didn't recant my testimony, I would be charged with perjury.
I'm not sure I understand.
So I testified at the Congressional Committee on Government Oversight. And the chair of the
committee did not like my testimony in a major way. In fact, he had to be restrained from throwing
a gavel at me. And after that, when I went cringing into the cloakroom afterward,
Congressman Waxman from California came over to me and gave me a high five.
Remind me the name I've forgotten now. What was the name of the congressman who was adamant that
Wakefield was right?
You've got me. I can't believe it. I'm trying to think of the name. I was afraid you were going
to ask me that question.
Yes. Now this is all kind of coming back to me like a horrible bad dream.
His grandson had autism and he was sure he got it from his vaccine. He said he could see this
wonderful child develop autism before they even got the needle out of his arm.
I know it'll come to one of us as we continue this discussion. Let's talk about serotonin before we
go further because serotonin levels are higher in at least a subset of kids with ASD.
And most people when they think of serotonin, they associate it with a hormone in the brain
that is responsible for mood. Can you say a little bit more about serotonin and in particular the role
of serotonin in the gut?
Well, serotonin is a molecule that I've been working on since college. I did my senior thesis
on serotonin when I graduated from Cornell in 1958, probably when dinosaurs roamed the
earth when I was young. In any case, serotonin was discovered actually in the gut.
Enterochromosin cells, which are an endocrine cell of the gut, are responsible for making about
95 percent of the body serotonin. The brain produces about two to three percent of the body
serotonin. So although the brain serotonin is probably what makes life worthwhile by that is
living and is responsible for happiness among other things, in terms of amounts it's a little
afterthought of evolution. So within the gut, serotonin is made in two places. The bulk of it
is made, as I've just said, in the endroendocrine cells, which are the small endocrine cells that
are part of the GI epithelium. It's a minor component of the epithelium, but a major component
functionally of what the gut does. About 80 percent of the endocrine cells make serotonin.
The other source is serotonin containing nerve cells within the enterochromosin system.
So it is a neurotransmitter and an endocrine substance in the gut. It's very important in
feeling pain in the gut. It's very important in triggering nausea. So in sending signals
from the gut to the brain, serotonin is an important transmitting substance.
During development, serotonin is very important as a growth factor. The first nerve cells to form
in the gut make serotonin. Subsequent nerve cells depend on serotonin, triggers them to develop.
So if you knock serotonin out of the nervous system, the gut winds up with too few neurons.
It doesn't have enough and it doesn't work very well. If you knock serotonin out of the epithelium,
then there's problems signaling back to the brain. The peristalsic reflex is impaired.
It's not stopped, but it's impaired because the enteroendocrine cells in the gut can trigger
peristaltic waves that are propulsive. But if you lose that, then in order to trigger it, you have
to press harder and harder and dilate the gut and get the nervous system to do this directly.
It's highly involved within the gut and it also talks to the immune system. So it triggers
inflammation. As you might imagine from the amount of it that's in the bowel, it does everything.
It's a pan function, multifunctional molecule. Now there's a class of medication, of course,
that are used to treat the symptoms of depression and in some cases anxiety. And these medications,
SSRIs, prevent the reuptake of serotonin, this neurotransmitter in the brain, presumably leaving
more of it around to exert positive effects. What are the effects of SSRIs outside of the CNS?
Do they impact the gut specifically? Yes, they tend to cause nausea by enhancing the ability
of serotonin to talk back to the brain to trigger nausea. Drugs that are used in cancer chemotherapy
also trigger the release of serotonin within the gut and trigger that reflex. Same one.
The SSRIs also first make the gut go a little bit faster, but then when the gut keeps doing that,
the receptors, that is the molecules upon which serotonin acts, desensitize. One way they do that
is to internalize and so they can actually block the effect of serotonin and transit.
So in terms of motility, they can make the gut go faster and ultimately they stop the gut
and give rise to long-term constipation and have to be stopped. So they're nauseating,
they change motility, and during development if you give them to a mouse during fetal development
that is given to the mother during fetal development, you get an abnormal nervous
system in the mouse's nervous system because of the effect during fetal life.
Are SSRIs contraindicated in pregnancy?
They are used frequently and in large numbers, large amounts in pregnancy because pregnancy is
very often associated with depression. Fortunately, most commonly, postpartum, but even then it's a
problem because SSRIs can be communicated to the child in breast milk. But there is evidence that
a number of conditions are increased, such as irritable bowel syndrome in the offspring of
mothers who are treated with SSRIs during pregnancy. Is that understood by the physicians
that prescribe them? And obviously there were going to be scenarios where those risks are worth it.
Yeah, people worry about it. But let me tell you, depression is a potentially lethal illness.
And if you've got something in which to treat it, sometimes you just have to use it.
Yeah, I just wonder if, because there are alternatives, right? I mean SNRIs
can also be very efficacious, presumably they don't have the same effect.
They do have some of the same effects because the SNRIs, serotonin and norepinephrine,
we have taken here, but they're just less.
Less serotonin.
Not less serotonin, less selective for serotonin. They include norepinephrine as well. So that
doesn't get you anywhere. Let's talk a little bit about leaky gut. This is a term I think a lot of
people have heard of, and I think they sort of maybe get the gestalt of. But in the context of
everything we've been discussing where we now have a pretty clear sense of what these
enterocytes are up against on their one side, on the luminal side, they've got just
never-ending barrage of toxins, microorganisms, bacteria viruses, food stuff that have to be
absorbed. At the same time, they can't be digested by these things. We didn't talk about tight
junctions specifically. Do you want to maybe tell people what the tight junctions are that
sit between these things?
Epithelia are the cells that line cavities. Epithelia have three types of junctions that
hold the cells together. One type is called a desmosome or a spot weld, just very tenacious,
hard to pull out connection between the cells. Another one is called the tight junction.
Tight junction has protein in the membrane on one cell, forms an attraction to the membrane across
the cell, transmembrane, and it obliterates the space between two cells. So the function of tight
junctions is to prevent material going through the channel between two epithelial cells. It's a plug
in the bathtub. There's another junction called an adhesion junction, which is essentially like
the spot weld, but it also is contractile. But let's concentrate on the tight junction because
that's what we're now talking about. And the more of these tight junctions you have between two
epithelial cells, the less leaky or permeable that connection is between them. So anything that
interferes with tight junctions can make the channel open and allow material from the lumen
to get into the body, but at the same time allow material within the body to get into the lumen.
And material going into the lumen is very dangerous because, as I've told you,
anything going into the lumen is lost from the body. And so if you open tight junctions
in the lining of the gut, you can essentially flow out into your bowel.
And Mike, besides the obvious, which would be water or electrolytes, is there ever
scenario where nutrients that were actually absorbed now go back into the lumen?
Absolutely. And worse than that, protein from the body. It turns out that underneath the lining of
the gut, capillaries are very permeable, and there's a lot of protein in the lymph, the fluid,
underneath the lining. And so if you open the lining of the gut, that protein gets into the GI
tract, and that's a disease called exudative enteropathy. You lose protein, and people with
that disease can blow up and look like balloons because edema goes all over the body. It's a
terrible thing. So Mike, what would you say is the most common cause of leaky gut? Allergy.
Okay, so meaning there is hypersensitivity. That is, the immune system is reacting
and causing tight junctions to open. Is this an allergy in the food specifically because the
allergen is in the lumen? Not always. For example, bee sting can cause this or can be injected,
or some other way that you can get a toxin that can do this. I want to ask a question going back
to something you said earlier that I never really have thought about until now, but I've never
thought this deeply about the gut. You know when they say a shark, like great white sharks have
multiple rows of teeth so that they're kind of constantly just pushing forward so when teeth
fall off, you kind of have new ones that have already grown into place. How does this epithelial
layer replace itself while preserving the tight junction? We're talking about every week or so
these epithelial cells slough off and new ones are present. Does that mean we have
several rows of them ready to sort of spring into action already tightly bound to their neighbors?
Or how does that happen to preserve the integrity? The gut is arranged lining the small intestine
and to a lesser extent the large intestine so that the gut lining is highly folded.
And there are projections that come up from the surface of the gut that look like fingers.
These are called villi. So most absorption occurs on the surfaces of these villi.
Now between the villi there are clefts called crypts and at the base of crypts there are stem cells
and the stem cells which live next to this other cell that I mentioned earlier called the paneth
cell can give rise to each of the cells that form the villi or line the gut. And there's an
escalation of those cells. The progeny of the stem cells keep rising so as new ones form
other ones move up. In part the proliferation in the crypt produces a pressure that causes cells
to rise as they differentiate but they're also mobile so they crawl a little bit as well. And if
you wound the lining of the gut then adjacent cells can crawl over the space and cut it off.
At the tips of the villi there's a zone called the extrusion zone and so the cells are born
at the base of a crypt climb up the crypt up the villus reach the tip of the villus
die and are poofed off at that point. So they stay in contact with one another
and the tight junctions are finally lose it when the cells die or the desmosomes and they pop off.
So the mechanism of death is called apoptosis so they're programmed to die.
We talked about the importance of toxins, allergies, things like that playing a role in
leaky and inflamed gut cells. Are there any reputable assays that can identify what these
are in an individual that has otherwise vague symptoms? If somebody has a substantially leaky
gut you would guess it from making a determination of the serum protein albumin. If the gut is leaking
albumin will be low and so if you see a low albumin you can look for it. If you think it's true
you can look for an enzyme called alpha 1 antitrypsin. Tripsin is produced by the pancreas
antitrypsin blocks it, its action and it gets into the lining into the gut. It should not be
absorbed. It's a measurement that will tell you whether the gut is leaking or not. By the way
there's an alpha 1 antitrypsin deficiency disease isn't there it's a hereditary condition? Yes.
What do those patients present with? Usually vascular and lung disease because there's too
much digestive action damaging in those organs. I think I said it wrong. Alpha 1 antitrypsin is on
the luminal side, sorry, on the vascular side and if it gets into the stool that's the problem.
I see. So we shouldn't be seeing it in the stool? Correct. Do you have to see low albumin to make
the diagnosis of leaky gut? Because that's a very significant leaky gut. I mean if a person is
exuding protein to the level where it shows up in their serum albumin that would strike me as a
lot of leak correct? Correct. Are there milder leaks that don't allow something as massive as
albumin to escape but do allow toxins and microorganisms in? That is now getting onto the level
of controversy but it has probably not toxins in, at least not to a great extent.
Maybe a little bit, yes, and take it back a little bit and you can look for those by giving
various peptides or fluorescein or dyes that measure it by oral that should be excluded
from the blood and seeing if the fluorescence gets into the blood or you can measure it with
certain sugars that should not be absorbed and if the non-absolvable sugar gets into the body,
then you assume this is slightly of the kind you're talking about. And do we think that there
is a causal relationship between leaky gut and autism spectrum disorder or do we think that
these are things that move together for a similar underlying pathology? The problem in
the gut in autism spectrum disorder is a disorder of the nervous system. It has nothing to do with
leaky gut. That's part of the Wakefield hypothesis, leaky gut, no evidence that that's correct.
Let's go back and explain again now that we've talked more about serotonin. What do we think is
the relationship between, do we see more leaky gut in ASD? Not really. Let me give you an
illustration. My collaborators and I have produced a mouse called G56A. This mouse has a mutation
in the serotonin transporter. The serotonin transporter is the protein that you spoke of
before that is the target of SSRIs. It is what the SSRIs inhibit and which remove serotonin
from the circulation or from the synaptic cleft when it's a neurotransmitter. What this mutation
does though is not inhibit CERT but make it more active. So CERT becomes what I like to call the
super CERT mouse. This animal has essentially a deficiency of serotonin. It is so effective at
inactivating serotonin after its release that it doesn't have a chance to act. So that animal has
a smaller nervous system in the gut, too few neurons, and it has slow transit, and it has a
problem in the gut. In the brain, it doesn't socially interact with other mice. If you put
them in a tube, two mice convene. One with the mutation backs out and lets the other mouse through
all the time. And it has repetitive behaviors. It keeps tapping its foot, hitting its head against
the side of the cage. So it has central features that look like autism, and it has a GI tract which
is abnormal. Abdomenolity is seen in about 2% of patients with ASD. So it was the human abnormality
put into mouse. Now it's not the cause of autism, but it's a sort of test case. It's one of the many
genes that can give rise to autism. Put into a mouse shows autism and also defect in the gut.
The defect in the gut has to do with serotonin and the ability of serotonin to act as a growth
factor. So there's a deficiency in terms of numbers of nerve cells in the bowel. In a patient
with autism spectrum disorder, similar kinds of things happen. This, by the way, is exactly the
opposite effect of giving a mouse during development an SSRI. So if you give a mother SSRI, they get
too many nerve cells growing in the gut. If you knock out the transporter, you have too many nerve
cells in the gut. And if you make the transporter more active, you have too few. And remind me again
the phenotype of the former, and you have in utero exposure to an SSRI. You have too many nerve cells
in the gut, and so gut motility becomes defective. I want to talk about bacteria now. We very briefly
touched on it earlier, and I knew if I started, I wouldn't stop. And the first time it came up was
when we talked about the difference between the colon and the small intestine. And one of the many
differences between them, of course, is the flora. Can you give people a sense of how many bacteria
exist in the small intestine? And let's start maybe even divide them into three. Let's talk
about the proximal small intestine, so the jejunum, the late small intestine, you know, the ilium before
it gets to the cecum, and then the colon. What's the relative difference in bacterial colony?
The numbers of organisms descend, that is, were assent as you go down the gut, so that you have
more of them close to the colon. And it's thought in a large way that stomach acid
sterilizes, to a large extent, the food that you eat. Although there are bacteria that can be found,
even in the stomach, in the presence of one normal hydrochloric acid,
helicobacter pylori, being the prime example of an organism that can survive. But the small intestine
then neutralizes stomach acid, but benefits from that acid because very few organisms are dumped
into it. The motility of the small intestine and the fact that the smaller numbers of organs come in
contribute to keeping the number down as the gut pumps its way on down. In addition, there are
cells like paneth cells, which make antibacterial proteins, which are called defensins, which help to
keep the lumen of the gut, not sterile, but close to it. As you get closer and closer to the colon,
the mechanisms, the numbers of paneth cells decline, gut slows down, and you're getting
close to a large number of organisms which live in the colon. And they're separated by the ileocecal
sphincter from the colon. When bolus of food gets into the colon, or not just food, it's by then
kind, it's been digested. When that material is delivered to the colon, it goes into a region
where it will spend some time. And in the colon, there are huge numbers of organisms.
Now, the numbers of organisms are about equal in number to the number of cells of the body.
We're talking trillions. And you have perhaps tenfold more bacterial genes than you do
your own genes in your body. And what are the classes of bacteria? Are these all gram negative?
No. A lot of them are gram negative. What they do have in common is that they are almost all anaerobes.
That is, they live in the absence of oxygen. And most of them are very hard to culture.
And so until relatively recently, we had no idea what a teeming mass of organisms were in there.
I mean, people all knew for a long time that the colon still wasn't sterile. And they, people,
culture still. But most of the organisms are highly resistant to culture and have been detected
through molecular biology. You look for the genes.
So now that that's been done, I assume we've done the equivalent of the human genome project
for the human colon, there tend to be a few classes of these things, right? I mean,
bacteroides is pretty common. Actinobacteria, proteobacteria, I mean,
what are the broad categories of these facultative anaerobes and such?
Well, there are about 16 different classes, and I can't remember them all. One of the
largest of them is the firmicutes. But bifidobacteria and lactobacteria, those tend to be
bacteria that we think of as good. Clostridia tend to be organisms that mostly are bad,
but not entirely. Some of those bacteria are related to causing cancer. Some of those bacteria
are highly protective. And they do stuff for us. For example, one of the things we eat a lot of
is fiber, celery, for example, celery or lettuce. We don't digest that. We have no enzymes that can
digest that. But we have bacteria in our gut that live on that, and they digest that. And they make
short-chain fatty acids from that. And those short-chain fatty acids are solved by the lining
of the colon. And our colonic epithelia are dependent on the bacteria to keep going,
and they get the bulk of their energy from the bacteria in the gut. The bacteria also make
certain vitamins that we can't live without, vitamin K being the most famous of them.
So clotting of blood depends on the bacteria. And as you probably know, they also seem to regulate
things like mood and obesity. It just strikes me as one of the most poorly understood connections
for something that has such a high impact on human health at this point still. Obviously,
we know more today than we did 20 years ago, but in many ways, it still feels like this is a bit of
a black box. Is that just my ignorance? No, it's our ignorance. So why are we ignorant, you might ask.
And the answer is, I've just told you, we can't culture most of those organisms.
They are extremely difficult to study. And Mike, pardon my ignorance, I'm not a cell biologist.
How much of that difficulty is because they're anaerobic and just logistically,
it's more complicated to culture organisms in the absence of oxygen? Or is there something
that even goes beyond that? Oh, it goes well beyond that. We don't know the nutrient,
not broths and things to which they can live. It's easy enough to make an atmosphere that has
no oxygen in it. But it's not so easy to figure out what they need to live. Colon produces a great
environment and how to match it is not so easy to figure. This is a very remarkable evolutionary
tale and also perhaps the most interesting symbiosis we experience. This strikes me as a
more interesting symbiosis than the one we share with bacteria on our skin. Is that a fair statement?
I think so because the bacteria are able to get involved with the nervous system
in a way that bacteria, the skin, pretty much do not. So for example, the bacteria that are in the gut
can activate lining of the epithelial cell for enteroendocrine cells to release serotonin
or other chemicals from them. And that can signal by way of the vagus nerves to the brain.
Or chemical products that the bacteria make can also trigger nerve signals that send signals back
to the brain or even go through the blood-brain barrier to affect the brain. So that experiments
can be done for example with mice in which one can breed germ-free mice.
Germ-free notobiotic is the term for that. Germ-free animals grow up without any contact or organisms
in them. I'm not trying to understand how that's possible Mike. I mean I've heard about it but I've
never really understood it. How do you have a germ-free animal? How do you feed it? You're feeding
it sterile food into a... and they had to have been born because this would have begun gestationally.
That's right. So they're all born by caesarean section. They're fed sterile food and they live
in incubators and people handle them with gloves. What's the phenotype of that animal after two
years relative to an otherwise identical animal that's born normally and fed normally? Let's go
one year. Okay and that tells me something really changes. Yes. So for one thing, the numbers of nerve
cells in their gut, their motility, the lining of the gut, they're all different. They're very much
more primitive. They have almost no spleen. They have none of the pyre's patches that we, you know,
talking to the immune cells. So their immune system must be horrible? Yes. They have no immune system
but they have a thymus and so they can develop an immune system in a big hurry if they survive.
You take them out and expose them to bacteria. But what you can do with the organisms with the gut
is use them as vessels and recolonize the gut with organisms. So for example, if you take those
animals and colonize them with bacteria derived from a strain of mice that tend to be lean,
you get lean mice derived from those animals. If you colonize them with from a strain of
mouse that tends to be fat, those animals grow up to be fat and you can cross strains.
So that that seems to indicate that bacteria can determine obesity or lack thereof. Yeah. How do we
think this plays out in humans where it's not as extreme? We don't have Darryl humans. But your
point is, and I believe there have been some experiments done. You'll have to correct me
because I don't follow this literature, but haven't they done some fecal transplants from
lean to obese that have at least partially addressed the phenotype? Correct. And also
anxiety seems to work in its very similar fashion. But what you have to take with the human is always
everything with a grain of salt because the experiments are very difficult to do.
And they're all flawed because you can't deal with pure organisms, pure humans,
what they're retaining. Do you have any idea how many such transplants have been done
where they've done a fecal transplant from a lean to an obese individual? How many times has that
been done? Not under a controlled setting. Why do you think that type of research, while admittedly
complicated, is technically feasible and has a potential for enormous fecal transplantation
in humans? It's not without danger. For sure. Tell people how the procedure works and obviously what
the risks are because I believe the only approved use of the therapy is for C. difficile. So you've
already alluded to Clostridia before. Yeah, let me just say Clostridium difficile is a normal
component of the GI tract. Many, many people have it and it sits there. And with your organisms,
one of the major ways that you control the various bacteria is to have other bacteria.
And so the bacteria control themselves. There's a competition for how much nutrient is there when
they make toxins that affect one another. But people then take antibiotics and the major effect
on the human microbiome is an antibiotic. For the most part, we like to think antibiotics are used
effectively and appropriately when you have an infection and they're given to you to fix that.
Unfortunately, that happens not to be the case. A lot of people are exposed to antibiotics because
they're used in agriculture and they're used in agriculture because it was found probably 60 years
ago that giving antibiotics will cause animals to grow faster and get bigger faster. And so you can
give antibiotics for that reason. You can also keep pigs more safely in small quarters by giving
them antibiotics because infections are not wiping them out so badly. This profligate, if I might use
the term, use of antibiotics in agriculture, exposes the human population to antibiotics
and changes our bacteria in ways that we would never have appreciated. Just to give you an
illustration, my son who has now just turned 60 but was young once when he was a child, he got
pneumonia. Kids do. And so culture was taken, was found that it was pneumococcal pneumonia. He was
too. So he was given penicillin to treat pneumococcal pneumonia. He got an exudative
enduropathy for it, his skin peeled off, his teeth came in mottled, his hair changed, his fingernails
changed, he was taking baths in oatmeal. We nearly lost him. So he is deathly allergic to penicillin.
How the hell did he get to be allergic to penicillin at age two when he never had it?
Well, part of the answer was that my wife had a very bad infection and so he had to be bottle fed
after the first month of life. And so he had cow's milk for a long time. Nothing
wrong with that. Kids always drink cow's milk. But cow's milk is coming now with penicillin in it
because the agricultural industry treats penicillin. So he developed an allergy to penicillin.
He then got treated with it. So now he doesn't take penicillin anymore. As it turns out,
I discovered many years later, I too am allergic to penicillin. That's where he got it from. I
apologize to him, but it's a gene. But do you think he would have been less allergic to it
despite his susceptibility genetically if he had been breastfed normally? Well, if he'd been
breastfed normally, the first time he got penicillin, he would have been sensitized,
but he wouldn't already have had the allergy. He behaved as if he was exposed to penicillin
because he had been. But in a way we never knew. And lots of kids are getting it. But the major
effect of it is that it's affecting a microbiome. But let's go back and explain how a stool
transplant works for C. diff. You were also explaining how it's not a zero risk procedure,
even though in the case of C. diff, it's life-saving. What happens in C. diff is that
patients get antibiotics. It knocks out the bulk of the bacteria. C. diff is resistant,
and it emerges as dominant. It produces a toxin. The toxin causes massive diarrhea,
and that can wipe you out. Very similar to the way cholera toxin does. It works in a different way.
It works on the nervous system, but it's a bad toxin. So to cure C. diff, one takes oral
vancomycin is the first step. Vancomycin is an antibiotic to which C. diff is usually sensitive.
It hasn't become all that resistant because vancomycin isn't used that much,
and it's not absorbed. So it just goes down the gut. But if 25% of patients
don't respond to oral vancomycin or C. diff recurs after they take it,
and they can't get rid of it, in that case, the only thing that can be done is a fecal transplant.
That can be done as an enema, or it can be done as an interacoded capsule now,
so that the capsule goes down, bacteria recolonize the antibiotic, wiped out gut.
It then suppresses the C. diff. That's life-saving use, and it's approved. Now,
what's the difficulty? So you get stool for C. diff treatment that has been very carefully
looked at, and one knows that there are no organisms in it that are potentially dangerous.
You have perhaps 500 species of organism in your gut that are potentially lethal.
So one has to be careful. There used to be people were giving it husband to wife,
and people doing this kind of home bruise. We've lost a few patients that way. Not a good thing to
do. One has to be very careful when you're doing fecal transplantation. Mike, is there any potential
for using synthetic biology to create the microorganisms so that you could control exactly
what you're giving people so you could effectively capsulize the exact organisms
that people are deficient in and replace those without the risk of providing anything you don't
want to be part of the recolonization? I've already told you why that cannot be done,
because for the most part, we can't grow these organisms. If you can't grow them,
you can't produce them in such a way as to synthesize them. Knowing their genetic sequence,
you can't synthesize them if you don't have the media in which to keep them alive once you've
synthesized them. That's correct. You have to be able to not only make their DNA, but
make their food. Yeah, keep them going. How many people are working on this, Mike? This seems like
a really enormous opportunity if the code could be cracked, right? If you could figure out how to
support these bacteria in vitro, it does open the door to synthetic biology. It does open the door
to basically medicines that are bacteria, right? Well, medicines that either are bacteria or are
derived from them. So knowing what the bacteria produce and knowing how they produce it
are just as good. So there is a huge amount of modern GI biology going into study of the GI
microbiome. Over the past 10 years, it's been the growth industry of the field. One of the things
that's very common today is commercial home kits that they're going to tell you what your sequence
looks like. This seems to be a field that's really full of a lot of nonsense. So there's been outright
frauds, right? There was that company out of UCSF called UBIOM that turned out to be kind of like
the Theranos of this space. There seem to be a lot of companies that if you give them a small
stool sample, they're going to send you a lengthy report of what your gut biome is. And let's assume
that they're even able to do that accurately. Is that a fair assumption? Are they able to provide
this information? Are they able to do the sequence and tell you what makes up your gut bacteria?
What they give you is the classes of organisms and the percentage of the total bacteria each of the
classes represent. And that turns out to be remarkably unuseful. Say more. Well, you need to
know species by species at a very, very fine level before you get to be able to really do something
with it. To get this class of bacteria in proportion of it's too high in the genome, too high in the...
So far too little resolution is being provided by these tests.
Correct. You can say you can change anxiety, you can change body form with the microbiome,
but to say that you can go look at the microbiome and then determine what that is, is not yet there.
You can't just go look at somebody's stool and say what they're consistent. The best of the kits
that I know of that do this are the ones that look for cancer. So like cologuard and things like that?
Yes. Those are excellent, but even those kits... Let's remind people exactly what cologuard is
looking for. As the cells age and undergo apoptosis, this left off into the lumen. And so human DNA
is in the lumen of the gut as well as bacterial DNA. And what cologuard does is looks at stool
and you can look at the DNA in the stool and look for the genetic signatures of a number of GI
cancers. And so about 90% of GI cancer can be picked up effectively by cologuard, which means
it's wonderful and it's a great advance, but it doesn't mean you don't have to go also do
colonoscopy. Yeah, the goal of colonoscopy is to find it before it's cancer. It's to find the
polyp that's going to become cancer, not wait until you have cancer. That's a major point.
But if you do have cancer and you find it early in a colonoscopy, that's great. And the problem
with cologuard is if you're missing 10% of cancer, you don't want that to happen.
It seems to me that cologuard is really a great tool in areas where access is limited,
where there might be hesitancy for colonoscopy and things like that. But I agree with you,
it's not a substitute for a colonoscopy. So this is an interesting point, Mike, which is basically
all of these commercial tests out there that are giving you information about your gut microbiome
are not doing it yet at a resolution that's actionable. Is that kind of a fair
synthesis of what you've said? Right. And my particular quarrel with them is that because
they're not doing it at a level that is sufficiently documented and sufficiently
informative for you to be actionable on that information, they cost money abnormally and they
change what you do for reasons that are not well documented and you shouldn't be following them yet.
Yeah. And a lot of them basically are paired with supplements or probiotics or prebiotics
that are supposed to quote unquote fix the defects that are found in the test. Right. Isn't that the
RXDX model? That's what they're doing. But what they're really doing is making money.
I think they're a con. I don't know enough to draw a strong enough conclusion. I can just say,
based on a decade of looking at them in many, many patients who have been adamant about having these
tests done, I'm still looking for a great example of where it mattered. I worry also that there is
a lot of noise created without a signal. One of the most important things nutritionally that people
can do to make sure that they have the optimal flora for their gut. I want to break this into
two categories, Mike. The first is just as general health maintenance and the second is after taking
antibiotics. So like it or not, we're going to take antibiotics and they're going to save our
lives from time to time. I have found myself to be more and more reluctant to take them and I
generally tend to resist as long as possible until I have no choice. But I'm going to hold
out a long time before I take a Z-pack. If I'm sick, I'm going to really try to make it go. But
I think the last time I took antibiotics was for a dental issue where it just required something
more significant. So let's start with the general maintenance principle. You're not someone who's
taking a lot of antibiotics, but you want to do what's best for your gut. And I assume that
nutrition is one of the most important levers we have. To my way of thinking, the best kind of
diet is a balanced diet, not one that tries to be like the South Beach or one of those diets
whose way. Having a balanced diet with appropriate nutrients, including vitamin C, but not in excess,
although won't hurt you to have any excess of vitamin C, but there's no reason to do it.
And particularly fiber included is good for your body. So I would be opposed to having particular
diets. For example, a cleanse. I like to point out to people that they should consider that the
microbiome is something they live with and has evolved with human beings as long as there have
been human beings. And cleansing the inside of the gut is not a good thing to be doing.
I'm not even sure I really understand what a cleanse is. I've heard so many different variants
of it, but certainly one method in which we do some form of a cleanse is a prep for a colonoscopy.
How much does that alter the flora of the gut, even though its purpose is really to just mechanically
get rid of all stool matter so that the endoscopy can be performed with better visibility? Does that
alter the gut flora in a way that doesn't return to normal quickly? No, remarkably little. That
doesn't kill organisms or change the balance between them. What it does is just moves the
mechanical stool out. And so the gastroenterologist is doing a colonoscopy and have a clear view of
what's in you. When people do these dietary cleanses, they're usually drinking a lot of
water with pepper and presumably some nutrients, but they're kind of doing a bowel prep, aren't they?
Some of them are also supplementing it with enemas. And I worry about those people getting
into electrolyte imbalance. I see, but they shouldn't be killing the bacteria. No, they're
not killing the bacteria. But on the other hand, they're not doing their body a favor by eating
strange foods and that kind of thing. You alluded to soluble, pardon me, insoluble fiber earlier,
the things that we can't digest at all in lettuce and celery and things of that nature.
Tell me the importance again of that in the human diet, because there presumably are people who
don't eat much or any insoluble fiber and that's going to clearly change their gut bacteria.
Is there evidence that that is impacting their health negatively?
Not that much has been done on low fiber for negative impact as so much as to show that there
are health benefits of fiber. One of the benefits is that fiber can absorb toxins so that it can
decrease its thought carcinogen effects long-term. It also provides the colon something to chew down
on and is good for motility, keeping the bowel going and in shape. And it also provides
a substrate for the bacteria of the colon for them to chow down on and produce short chain fatty
acids, which are good for the lining of the gut and provide it with its energy metabolism.
By the way, do any of those short chain fatty acids, Mike, make their way into the person to
provide ATP or energy there beyond just the epithelial cells?
Less so, but the answer is yes. They are absorbed. And so to some extent, they can get into the body.
Directly through chylomicrons as regular fatty acids would?
No, no, no, they're very short and they're soluble and they tend, like acetic acid is a
short chain fatty acid. That would be a one carbon.
So fiber sounds like it's going to be the most important nutrient in terms of fueling the bacteria
of the gut, which in turn pay service back to providing energy for the epithelial cells, correct?
Not just fiber. Polysaccharides do as well. They can digest those. Everything that gets down there,
they can live on. It's just that very little of the protein that you eat will get down to the colon.
Then tell me about things like artificial sweeteners or non-nutritive additives to food.
There's been a lot of discussion that, for example, aspartame or other sweeteners that
aren't caloric may still provide some impact on the micro bacteria of the colon.
How well is that understood?
There are bacteria that can metabolize them. And so there are effects on the bacteria.
The net effect of that is I really can't speak to because that's a literature that I find
to be self-contradictory. Some people think they do things. Some people think the effect is negligible.
I haven't spent much time in that literature, but the little time I've spent in it, I've come away
without much of an understanding of how these things are potentially creating an impact.
You mentioned protein already. What do we know about the role of fatty acids in the colon? How
many of them are making their way there? Well, most of the fatty acids that get to the colon
are derived from fiber. In other words, they're not exogenous.
That's true normally, but not always. So, for example, under abnormal conditions
in which bile salts or pancreatic enzymes are deficient, then those fat can get into the colon
and one gets fatty stool. Bacteria can metabolize that. And so in celiac disease,
for example, there's a lot of fat in the stool or in biliary tract disease, there's often a lot of
fat in the stool. The stool is described as greasy and foul smelling because the bacteria do
metabolize it. What about the scenario where a person has taken antibiotics potentially for
a protected course? What can they do to appropriately repopulate their gut?
What a good question. Probably taking appropriate probiotics at the same time they're taking those
antibiotics or afterward is helpful. And what constitutes appropriate probiotics? This is a
world I know very little about. It varies. Some people think that yeast-derived saccharomyces is
good. Some people swear by lactobacilli or bifidobacteria. There is evidence that when you're
taking antibiotics, saccharomyces at the same time, trying to think of the name of the pill
that they sell, it's over the counter. And sorry, just for semantics, what's the difference between
a pro and a prebiotic? Probiotic is defined as an organism that has beneficial effects,
and a prebiotic is defined as a material that will enable the body to grow organisms that have
beneficial effect. So the difference between them is that prebiotic enables you to make your own
healthy organisms, probiotic as you eat them. So for example, I eat activity every day. Now that I've
aged, it fights the problems of aging. So fermented foods are obviously valuable probiotics.
An important point to bear in mind is not just that it's fermented. I mean, all yogurt is fermented,
but that something like activity has bifidobacter animalis in it, which actually gets through,
survives the stomach acid, goes down the GI tract, and comes out in the stool.
And just to be clear, that's anaerobic bacteria or aerobic?
It's an anaerob, but it can get down the gut and survive in the stool.
It's so interesting that we can be eating something anaerobic that it can be in our food, right?
It's added. I guess it's aerobic. It has to be aerobic.
Kind of gets to the challenge of this whole anaerobic problem, right?
Yes, but the organism that's put in, it actually goes through the GI tract and survives.
So the importance of a probiotic is not only that it be there, but that it survive and do something
in the GI tract. How can people navigate this world, Mike? Because this is another one of those
places where there's a lot of opportunity for charlatans to sell you things that, A, don't even
have the colonies that they claim they do, or if they're there, they're dead on arrival, and if
they're not, they don't survive the transit from mouth to colon. I mean, how does one kick the
tires on these things? Well, for one thing is you can trust the FTC and the FDA. So claims cannot be
made for food stuff like a probiotic that are medical unless it has been subjected to actual
tests and pass FDA muster to show efficacy and safety. Most of what they call probiotic, prebiotic,
has not done that. Food stuff then is regulated through the advertising by the FTC.
So I was interestingly called upon to testify at a hearing for a game. I consult for Danin,
and so when I mentioned activity that I take, that doesn't mean that I want to tell everybody
out there that this is better than any other. It's just one I know about. So in any case,
the FTC looked very carefully at the claims made for that product and wanted to see and carefully
evaluated all of the evidence. And in order to make the claims that Danin makes for that product,
they actually have to demonstrate to the FTC that they have the evidence that it does what they say
it does. So they say that if you eat as much as two cups a day of activity, it will cause the GI
tract to speed up. And the answer is it will. And how many colony forming units are provided
in that? I honestly don't know. I can't answer that question. But there are, I think, something
in the order of 10 to the 11th going in. And I'm trying to think of what comes out the other end,
but it's much less. But they do have evidence, at least for that product, that it survives and goes
through. When it comes to getting your GI system back and tracked after a course of antibiotics,
what are the most important elements to look for in the probiotic? Is it lactobacilli then?
Not a specific lactobacillus, just the ability to colonize the GI tract. So saccharomyces
works very well in that case. That's the one I'm trying to think of the trade name for.
We'll figure that out and link to it in our show notes.
It's well known and it's a yeast derived product.
And it's over the counter, not?
Yes, it's over the counter.
Now, by definition, does a probiotic need to be refrigerated?
It just needs to be able to survive. You can take it as a pill.
But even pills don't need to be stored in the refrigerator.
No, they don't. Not necessarily. It depends on which one. So, for example, bifidobacteria
animalus, which is in activity, has to be refrigerated. But so does the activity because
it's yogurt based.
Again, it just seems to me that the big opportunity here is going to come
with kind of the bioengineering that's necessary to grow these bacteria in culture. That seems to
be just an enormous blind spot we still have in this space, both from a diagnostic standpoint,
but also from a therapeutic standpoint.
Absolutely right. And from a point of view of really having what is sort of a fringe popular
economy to a really effective major product so that if you could make an organism and
know exactly what it does and you can make it in scale and give it to people to take it safely,
big time bucks.
Well, Mike, thank you very much for this tour of one of the most probably underappreciated systems
in the human body. We've talked a lot about its unique embryology, very unique innervation.
And of course, perhaps most importantly, its cohabitation with bacteria that basically
outnumber us. As we said, I think at the outset, I can't remember if we talked about this before
we were recording or not, but this really feels like a bit of a black box. And I guess that speaks
to why 60 years later, you're still working just as hard.
That's right. Or as you said, as you get further away from shore, the water gets deeper.
Yeah. Well, the water feels awfully deep right now, Mike. Thank you very much
for your time and your expertise today.
Thank you.
Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper
into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to bring
you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is
nobody's show notes rival these monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes hearing
these episodes completely access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything
without having to listen to spiel's like this. The qualities, which are a super short podcast
that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and
tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous
episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products
that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse and a whole bunch of other benefits
that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member
only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on
Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on
Apple podcast or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational
purposes only and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional
healthcare services, including the giving of medical advice. No doctor patient relationship
is formed. The use of this information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's
own risk. The content on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional
medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical
advice from any medical condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their
healthcare professionals for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very
seriously. For all of my disclosures and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit
PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.