Hey, Josh. Great to see you again. It's been, I don't know, I was trying to think about
this the other day. It was about three years ago, I think was the last time we saw each
other in person at that, some sort of conference in New York, a cancer metabolism conference,
I think, right? Oh, yeah. The New York Academy of Sciences,
I think. Yeah, it was great. And we somehow wound up at some kind of mediocre bar in Brooklyn. And
it might have been the dorkiest concentration of people talking about autophagy and metabolomics
and all sorts of things. Oh, yeah, yeah, that was actually the ACR Brooklyn conference. That's true.
Well, you know, it's really funny, just recently, I've interviewed a few of our classmates from
med school, Max Dean and Karl Deseroth. And I think Karl and I were reminiscing about how you,
me and Karl all started our surgical rotation together in the same day. And I, it's almost 25
years ago, and I remember it like it was yesterday when we were all sitting in the room practicing
sewing with our big goofy knots and things like that before we all got divided up into our
surgical rotations. Do you remember that? I definitely remember you. I really do not
remember Karl from those days, but I certainly remember you practicing a lot while I looked
and said, oh, I guess that's what you're supposed to be doing if you want to become a surgeon. The
thing I remember most clearly is being in surgery with you. And it was like the very end of surgery
rotation. And finally being given the bovee and immediately making a mistake. And, you know,
then I got the nice lecture, you know, we're happy to pass you on this rotation as long as
you promise never to use, you know, a knife or bovee again. So, so remind me, whose lab did you
do your PhD in? I did my PhD with Hardin McConnell, one of the great physical chemists together with
Mark Davis, the immunologist. And so tell me and tell the listeners a little bit about what project
you worked on for your thesis. My thesis was about the physical chemistry of T cell activation.
And so at that point in time, people had discovered that different antigens could activate T cells
differentially. And so I was really interested in how that happened. And so I studied the process
of antigens turning into peptides that could bind to MHC and then how the kinetics of the interaction
between the peptide antigen and the major histocompatibility complex protein MHC.
And then the interaction of that complex with the T cell receptor determined whether people
have productive or failed immune responses with the hopes you could then manipulate those processes
to promote better vaccination or disease clearance and also to potentially treat autoimmunity.
And did you also have an interest at all in cancer? Because of course, this would be one of
the hallmarks of how immunotherapy would be effective in eradicating cancer.
Shows how bad a prognosticator I am. At that point, I really felt that immunological
prosciutistic cancer didn't hold that much promise. And so I was really more focused on
infectious disease and autoimmunity. So shows you what I know. It's wonderful to say that the world
has turned out to be a lot better than I dreamed it would be on that dimension.
No, but it's such an interesting topic. I had Steve Rosenberg on the podcast last year,
and it was just a beautiful and fun recap of how the immune system works in general. But we were
talking about it obviously through the lens of cancer. And I think the part that will forever
humble anyone who tries to think about how amazing the system is, is that these things have to be,
you know, 9 to 11 amino acids long. I mean, the peptides have to be just the right size
to be presented and then to be recognized. And that just doesn't seem to leave a lot of
margin for error. I mean, it is really a tuned system. Do you have a sense of why evolution
ended up with such a narrow fragment of peptides that were recognizable,
as opposed to a broader range or as opposed to just a range that's different? Like why wasn't it
two to three or 150 to 160 amino acids? Like, is there a chemical reason? Because of your
background in chemistry, I feel like you'd be more equipped to offer a teleologic explanation
for this. Yeah. I mean, I do have an intuitive sense on this that, you know, our bodies work on
the scale of, you know, billions of immune cells and billions of immune receptors that are made
through recombination. And that naturally pairs with billions of antigens. And so you just think
about this number nine and you think about the number of amino acids, right? There are 20 amino
acids. So you're talking about 20 to the ninth power of presentable peptide antigens. And so
these things are all tuned to be on the same scale, this kind of scale of billions and-
Tens of billions in that case, yeah. Exactly. Yeah. So if you did it, if it was like a three peptide,
it's really a small number actually. There's not enough information there to,
you know, selectively respond to a virus, you know, or a bacteria. And if it was 25 peptides,
it's too much. There's too much information there. There's extra information anyway. And this system,
I think, was built to work on minimal or just the right amount of information. Yeah. That's super
interesting. So at what point during either your PhD or the end of medical school where we met up
in the clinical portion, did you make the decision that you wanted to be a full-time scientist as
opposed to a physician scientist? You know, I applied to do an internship knowing that I really
loved research, but I guess I decided as I did more and more medicine that medicine is such a
noble profession, but it involves a lot of doing the same thing right over and over again,
a lot of following the standard of care, even for the most creative physicians, and that ultimately,
like my passion is to come in and try to do something different every day to think differently
than people ever have before. And so that's what really led me to research. I love the patient
interaction part of medicine. It was the doing things right part that was challenging for me
sometimes. Yeah. No, I think those of us that chose the more medical side of things can also
speak to the frustration of how creativity can often be stifled in medicine. And that's
in large part for good reason, but I think it comes at a cost as well. And I think I'm sure
on this podcast I've told stories about how frustrating that was in surgery, at least surgery,
probably more so than most other disciplines tends to sometimes at least frown upon creativity and
novel approaches to problem solving. Now, if I remember correctly, before you joined the faculty
at Princeton where you are now, you went into industry straight from medical school. Am I
getting my facts right? Yeah. So I was fortunate to have the opportunity to work with one of the
great early biotech entrepreneurs, Alex Zaffaroni. And so he and I started a company when I was
straight out of medical school that was focused on fast drug delivery. So what could you do by
being able to deliver medications non-invasively on the time scale of giving an IV push in the
hospital? And so we did that through inhalation of small molecules kind of building on the concept,
obviously, that if you smoke something like a cigarette, you get incredibly rapid access to
the systemic circulation. And so we built that company, Lexa Pharmaceuticals still exists,
has one FDA approved drug. So that was my first job. What drugs were you targeting with that?
You know, our initial focus was migraine. Unfortunately, we never found the drug that
had the perfect combination of safety with rapid delivery and efficacy for migraine. The drug that
ultimately got approved was for acute agitation. And so there's a set of hypnotic for acute
agitation. And I'd say it's really wonderful for the patients who get it. They come in in the ER.
Something people don't always know about agitated patients is like they're agitated, they're
frustrated, but they also want to stop being agitated. They don't want to act like that. And
so they're very eager to most cases to take a puff of something and calm down in a couple minutes.
It's wonderful for them. So this is kind of an unusual path, right? I'm guessing that most
people who experience that type of success that you had would want to keep doing it over and over
again. I mean, hence the term serial entrepreneur. What made you decide to take this lateral step to
go into academics, which would have made a lot more sense if you'd done it coming straight out of
your PhD. You know, I think I was lucky to get the chance to go straight from that job into a
faculty position at Princeton. That's a rare opportunity to have. Because you didn't do a
postdoc in there unless they considered your industry as sort of a grandfathered postdoc.
Yeah, it was a very, very weird version of a postdoc. And it united me with my wonderful wife
and at Princeton on the faculty here and turned out well.
So you show up at Princeton and they put you on a tenure track position,
which means they're giving you the types of resources to now start solving whatever
problem you want. What was the first problem that you said, I want to build a lab around?
You know, one thing that I learned actually doing Alexa was about drugs because we studied
every medication in the pharmacopoeia for whether it could be a candidate for rapid delivery. Could
you make a benefit by delivering it rapidly? And one thing I noticed is that so many of the most
important medications work via metabolism. And then starting out my lab, I realized that there
were relatively few labs looking at metabolism broadly compared to other, you know, really
important areas of science like immunology or cancer or neuroscience. And so I started my lab
with a really simple question. Could we measure the classic metabolites that you read about in a
biochemistry textbook in one shot quantitatively? And so that was the starting point for my lab.
And I guess the second question that we always had in our mind is can we measure
the activities of those metabolic pathways? So how fast are those metabolites flowing? Where
are they coming from and where are they going? I had lunch or dinner actually with one of our
mutual friends, Navdeep Chandel, who was also a previous guest on the podcast three or four years
ago, maybe a week ago. And he was here in Austin for a talk. And we were talking about how in the
late 90s he said, and he was obviously studying metabolism, he said if you were to rank me,
meaning Nav was ranking himself right, he said you were to rank me and my work.
Just across the spectrum of the stuff scientists were doing, he said I'm bottom 10 percentile.
You know, I mean, nobody found metabolism interesting. It was this was sort of the,
I forget the term he used, but like this was basically the corner where the kids went that
nobody wanted to play with. If you weren't doing genomics, if you weren't doing this other sexy
stuff, immunology, you were really an uninteresting person. But he just found that interesting. And of
course today, as we're going to discover, this is where the action is. So, you know, Nav was talking
about that in the 90s. We're now in the early 2000s. Was it still a little bit of that stigma
that Nav described that he was kind of under where he was like a totally underperforming,
you know, loser in his own words? Or was that transition already starting to happen where
people saw, wait a minute, there's something going on here?
You know, Nav was so funny. And I don't think anyone who's ever met Nav thinks he's a loser.
I'll say that right off the bat first. You know, but I will say that, you know,
metabolism as an area was definitely out of favor. And it was a really strange thing because
you had the academic current that metabolism was a solved problem, right? Krebs was, you know, the
culmination of metabolism research at the same time that metabolic syndrome was becoming worse
and worse and worse in the population. And I would say when I started, it was still not a real
popular topic, metabolism. But I think two things were beginning to shift. One is the fact that
people realized that, you know, genomics as a standalone was not going to solve health problems,
that it was really going to have to be supplemented by other technologies that looked at biochemistry
broadly. And metabolomics proved to be one of those that I think has been enduring, will be enduring.
And the second is that, you know, the metabolic syndrome epidemic just kept becoming more and more
obvious. Yeah. So this is kind of where your training as a physician becomes relevant because
perhaps more so than somebody who didn't spend four years also doing medical school,
you saw the clinical problem that was sort of kicking you in the face, even if it wasn't top
of mind to a scientist. Yeah, I think it's really true. You know, I just benefited so much from the
breadth of biology and medicine that you learn in medical school. And I mean, it allowed me to start
my lab working on bacteria, which I had never worked on at all as a PhD student because, you
know, you learn bacteriology is one of the things in medical school. And that was like the perfect
starting point for building these technologies with a view all the way to metabolic syndrome and
ischemia reperfusion injury, right? These huge medical problems. But I really wanted to start
somewhere tractable where we could get, you know, firm proof of concept. So for somebody listening
to this, which let's assume that they have a greater attention span than somebody you're going
to walk into at a cocktail party, but obviously not necessarily the depth of understanding of
everything we're about to go into. How would you explain metabolism to that person?
Metabolism is the process that converts the food we eat into usable energy and the building blocks
our body needs to grow or regenerate itself as well as waste along the way.
And so now how do you layer on the omic piece of that, which is really what we're starting to talk
about when people hear the word genomics, they sort of understand what that means. But I think
when people hear the term metabolomics, it becomes a little harder to understand. So how would you
now layer in that in the context of everything that you're now beginning in your lab?
Yeah. So, you know, the bulk of activity in metabolism that makes most of our usable energy
involves something like a hundred metabolites. And so the first thing we really wanted to be
able to do was measure those hundred metabolites really well. So tell people some examples of
those, Josh, because I mean, I think we take it for granted, but like glucose would be an example
of a metabolite. What are some other metabolites that are important to understand if you're trying
to study this system? Yeah. So all the amino acids are other fundamental inputs that we get from the
diet. Like glutamine is a great example. That's a very important circulating nutrient. Other things
that come in, you know, from the diet, if you have vinegar, you have acetate or else your microbiome
can make acetate that goes in the body. Fats are obviously important input metabolites. And then
there are sets of intermediary metabolites. These are things that are like glycolytic intermediates
that people may have heard about in biochemistry. Fructose bisphosphate is a famous one of those.
Pyruvate, lactate that a lot of people hear about from exercise. Members of the Krebs cycle,
like citrate is a famous one that exists in our circulation, obviously in citrus fruits.
So these are classic examples of metabolites. And then they're the kind of more effector or
energy holding metabolites like ATP, NADH, NADPH. Got it. So I kind of interrupted you there,
but you were kind of explaining how first you begin with sort of this survey of all of these
metabolites. Yeah. So we want to be able to measure all of these. These are kind of the core
components of metabolomics. And part of the beauty of metabolism as a system is that
with some modest variation, there's almost a singular solution on earth to how metabolism
works. And so when we learn to measure the metabolites in E. coli, at the same time,
we were really learning how to measure metabolites all the way up to human. And so there are these
basic components of protein and eclaic acids, basic intermediates like fructose bisphosphate
that exist at all of these levels. And if you survey relatively comprehensively, there's on the
order of a thousand of them that have clear biological function. So it's a big problem,
but it's a problem on the scale of knowing all the kids who go to your high school,
not a problem of knowing everyone in the phone book in New York City. So it's a problem
that's right at this interface between the human scale and the computational scale.
So I wanted to ask you about that. You already kind of anticipated perhaps almost a question,
which is, do we think we have the complete solution set here? I mean, we clearly know
all of the amino acids. We clearly know all of the intermediate steps and intermediaries period
of the Krebs cycle. Do we think that that means we actually know every single
metabolomic element or is there a chance that there are others out there that we don't know
because we haven't looked for them or they're very short-lived, for example, and we haven't
stopped and looked at reactions closely enough or studied the kinetics hard enough. I mean,
this is almost a naive question in a way, but I've never actually thought about it until now.
Yeah, it's a great question. And we keep discovering new metabolites. So, you know,
groups around the world keep discovering new metabolites. I would say it's an interesting
yin and yang because there's this steady accumulation of new metabolites, but I don't
really think there's been a completely new and obviously important metabolite yet this century.
So I think at some level in terms of the metabolite finding part of the problem,
things were wrapping up around the time of Krebs, the most important part of the work anyway.
But in terms of undertowelinating how the system really works and how we can choose the right
diet to be healthy given our genotype, given the disease we're fighting, we haven't scratched the
surface yet. How many of these metabolites are really tightly regulated, a la glucose,
versus not that regulated at all? They can kind of fall to zero and they can,
meaning how many of these things can change by log orders all over the place and how many are
regulated so tightly that if you just fall a little bit out of that range, I mean, one of the
things I try to explain to people when I explain regulation and homeostasis is I love using pH as
an example because the pH spectrum runs from basically zero to 14, neutral being seven,
but anybody who's taking care of a patient in the hospital knows that 7.4 is where we live as
an organism, almost unsurvivable to have an acidosis that goes below seven or an alkalosis
that exceeds about 7.7. I mean, so for a system that runs basically zero to 14, the fact that we
can't as a species survive from outside of 7.6 or 7.7 talks about something that is so tightly
regulated. So in that field of metabolomics, which ones behave like pH and which ones don't?
Well, you know, pH is such a great example, right? And you have this giant logarithmic scale from
zero to 14, right? And so even when you talk about 7.1 to 7.4, you're talking about something
of a two to three fold change. It's about a three fold change in acid concentration. That's right.
And I think a lot of metabolites that are the important ones live typically in that two to
three fold range as being the preferred range. Some of them, there's a lot more active regulation
like glucose. Some of them, there's kind of relatively passive processes that tend to keep
them in that range. Then of course, there are all sorts of other metabolites that may be some cool
secondary metabolite that's made by a plant and some of us eat it, some of us don't eat that plant.
And so some of us may have a lot, some of us may have none. But for the big ones,
the biochemistry tech book ones, I think, you know, this kind of a few fold range in the bloodstream
is a common healthy place to be. Are there common and consistent tools that the body uses to
regulate? Are there principles that the body just adopts over and over and over again in the form of
this regulation? Yeah, I think there's one most important principle and that's when it's there,
use it up. And so, you know, in a physics speak, you could say this is a
linear consumption of circulating metabolites or in chemistry speak, people call this mass action,
just whatever mass is there, you tend to take it in. And so you eat a lot of what you eat after a
little bit of processing enters the bloodstream. And then it's the job of tissues that need these
ingredients to use them and use them at first blush in proportion to their availability in the
blood. Are there examples where that regulatory mechanism is not the preferred way to manage them?
Well, there's a lot of regulation layered over top of that in order to make the body work. And,
you know, the most important regulatory hormone in mammals, I'm pretty convinced is insulin.
Right. And, you know, there are two ways to look at insulin, I think. And there's the probably the
way that comes to mind first to you, which is insulin is a hormone that acts to control
elevations in blood sugar. And it does that at the highest level by promoting uptake of glucose
and preventing production of glucose. But there's an alternative way to look at insulin. And that's
that we've evolved mainly to be able to survive lack of nutrients. Okay. That this was the strong
selective pressure on animals and mammals and that storing fat is very precious. And that insulin
is a hormone that says you don't have to use fat right now. Okay. And so it senses that there's
enough carbohydrate around and therefore it's safe to not release free fat from your adipose tissue.
Does that mean that you think that an equally important role of insulin is not just the
disposal of glucose into muscle and the cessation of glucose production in the liver,
but you're saying it's equally important as a signal to stop lipolysis to keep your fat in its
fat stores. Meaning save this for a rainier day because you actually have the glucose here that
I'm going to deal with. Yeah. That's certainly how I look at insulin right now. And I think
there's little doubt that, you know, biochemically and medically the suppression of lipolysis is a
primary, perhaps the primary, you know, function of insulin. So kind of going back to the broad
strokes of metabolomics, you alluded to it briefly without, I think using the term, but
what do we know about the flux of these things? Because when I think back to my, even my
biochemistry 25 years ago, you know, Stryer's textbook, which is, you know, the classic textbook,
at least it was then, I imagine it's one of them still today. We really studied it in a static way.
And I'm guessing that that's one of the first questions you went after, right? Which is what's
the movement? What are the derivatives with respect to time of all of these things? So
maybe expand a little bit on this idea of the of fluxomics.
Yeah. I mean, metabolism is a system in action. And I think this kind of static view of metabolism,
which is probably never a view that Stryer ever had in his mind, but that got codified in the
textbooks is one that killed metabolism in a way as a topic of excitement. And so, you know,
metabolites are intermediates in the process of converting what we eat into usable energy
and protein biomass and these things. And so they're really, you know, relatively low in abundance,
and they're flowing very, very fast. So they're completely different than parts of our body like
neurons that are going to sit there maybe for our entire lifetime. Okay. Here, the metabolites are
meant to be made and used somewhere on the time scale, depending on the metabolite of roughly a
second to, you know, roughly an hour maybe for metabolites in the bloodstream. And so all the
action is in the flow. And so it's really understanding where things are coming from,
where they're going, where we can learn about how metabolism works.
Let's again, just use glucose because one, it's ubiquitous, everybody gets it. It's
essential for life, but it also offers, I think, a beautiful portrait in velocity.
So I just had my blood drawn yesterday. I draw my blood about every two months. And
so, you know, tube of blood comes out and let's say my glucose on that, because that's a snapshot,
right? That's in that moment outcomes, five tubes of blood, and it's going to look for a whole bunch
of things. But one of them is glucose and my glucose, because I did a finger prick at the same
time, my glucose was 89 milligrams per deciliter. Can you explain to people what that actually
means? What does it mean that my glucose at that moment in time was 89 milligrams per deciliter?
Well, I'm sure you were smiling about it. That is like it's a super healthy blood glucose in
terms of a level. But when you think of that absolute amount of glucose, right, if you took
all the glucose in your bloodstream at that level, that's a few minutes of glucose or energy.
For the body, right. So yeah, it's probably four or five grams of total glucose. Exactly. Yeah.
20 calories worth. Exactly. So that has to be constantly replenished in order to feed
your brain and the other tissues like activated immune cells that depend on glucose.
Now, this is what to me is remarkable. If I had done that same test, Josh, and I had come back,
let's make the math easy and say it was 90. We'd still say, great, you're healthy. You're
fasting glucose is 90. Now let's say I had come back and it was 180 milligrams per deciliter,
my fasting glucose. There's a disease that I would immediately now know that I have that disease is
called type 2 diabetes. What's the absolute difference in the amount of glucose in my
bloodstream? It went from being 5 grams to 10 grams. Seems like a really trivial amount.
Why is it that the body in the person without diabetes seems to be able to keep it at, you know,
80 to 100 milligrams per deciliter overnight while you're fasting, but in a disease that's going to
more than double your risk of mortality and increase your risk of cancer, Alzheimer's disease,
cardiovascular disease. I mean, it's really a problem for your health. It's only doubling
the amount of glucose in there and it's still a relatively trivial amount that needs a constant,
constant update. How can we explain this delta of that seems so trivial in the absolute amount
that could be consumed in just an extra couple of minutes, but yet the steady state is still
off by this factor. What's going on? Why? Yeah. I mean, when you think about why is that a disease
problem with only a two-fold excursion, then you think that, right, the system has been built to
have about the most circulating glucose that you can have safely, right? And I think a lot of the
really important metabolites have been kind of pushed to the edge this way, right? And so we know
that there are deleterious, you know, protein modification reactions, like oscillation reactions
that occur when glucose gets above this point. So we kind of in evolution pushed right up to the
highest and non-problematic glucose. We didn't do that for a lot of other metabolites and that's
why there's not a lot of, you know, part of why there's not a lot of other diseases like diabetes.
So that's part of the answer is that, you know, evolution didn't build a lot of wiggle room for
your glucose to safely rise because having that, you know, good amount of glucose circulating is
really valuable, right? You know, every time your heart pumps, it's sending that amount of glucose
to tissues and that's productive. On the flip side, obviously, there's a broader set of
derangements in the body to produce this two-fold excursion in glucose, right? And so, you know,
this has to do with, you know, things going wrong in fat and fat handling and so that's part of this
whole metabolic syndrome that leads to the full set of downstream health consequences.
It's so interesting that the body doesn't just, again, I think this speaks to why the flux problem
is the more interesting problem than the static problem because if you just think about this
example in the static context, you would say, okay, well, at 704 and three seconds a.m.,
your blood sugar is 190, but three minutes later, if nothing changes, meaning if your liver doesn't
put too much glucose back into circulation, you'll be fine. So the problem is not that your blood
sugar is too high in that moment. The problem is the liver assumes, I mean, in part, that that's
the right level and it continues to do it because at that moment when you're not eating, that is the
only source by which glucose is getting into the bloodstream. So we're maintaining this elevated
cycle, right? It's everything from gluconeogenesis, hepatic glucose output. I mean,
all of these things continue to stay unregulated and I think that's only really appreciated when
you think of time and the passage of time. Yeah, I think one thing that's really interesting
is that you can have, depending on the details of how processes are tuned, the same amount of
production and the same amount of consumption and these have to be balanced for your glucose to stay
anywhere close to steady, okay? So in a diabetic production and consumption or balance and a healthy
person production and consumption are balanced and they can even be the same amount of production
and consumption. But it can just be that you need a higher amount of glucose to achieve that same
balance of production and consumption in the diabetic and that reflects often, in my opinion
at least, underlying issues with how fat is handled that you either need more glucose to induce
more insulin in order to suppress lipolysis in the diabetic, right? Or more glucose to
out-compete fat to get burnt in tissues. And so ultimately I think a lot of what's setting
blood glucose is competition between glucose and fat. This is a very old idea called the Randall
hypothesis. But I think there's a lot of truth to it. We have a lot of new data that's consistent
with it and so I think a lot of these issues come back to making room for glucose to be burned by
controlling the amount of fat that's being used by tissues. So can you state for folks the Randall
hypothesis? I'd love to actually talk a little bit about the more recent data because as you said I
mean this is I mean this is over 50 years old, isn't it? You know I'm a terrible historian so I'm
going to trust you on that one but you know I think the essence of the hypothesis is that
fat is somewhere between a preferred and the preferred fuel for tissues and there's competition
between carbohydrates, classically glucose, and fat for burning and so when fat is available then
glucose tends not to be burned effectively and that's a possible cause of diabetes.
Now of course when you say fat you don't mean fat within adipose tissue, you mean
fat within you mean fat that's available for use? Fat that's available for use and so that can come
in multiple forms. The simplest way to think about it is free fatty acids that are floating in the
bloodstream and that may be the most important form of it but there's you know also adipose
stores within tissues not subcutaneous white adipose which is typically a healthy place to
store fat molecules but you can end up with what people call ectopic fat for example droplets of
fat building up in muscle and when those are there they can compete with carbohydrate for being burned
or you can have breakdown of lipoproteins from the bloodstream things like VLDL okay that we
desperately need to have broken down in order to have a good HDL and a you know a low LDL cholesterol.
Tell me about some of the more recent evidence around why that hypothesis may be more compelling
even so than when it was proposed. Yeah I mean I think we've been doing experiments that look at
you know what are things that can suppress glucose use in tissues and one thing we see is
it's just very clear that fat does this we're certainly not the only people to do this I think
there's a long history of this but it maybe hasn't been adequately appreciated just how fundamental
that result is and if you turn off lipolysis different ways then you rapidly induce glucose
consumption and if you provide other alternative fuels and we've learned that lactate is a very
important circulating fuel and so it also will compete with glucose to suppress glucose use so
the fact that you can have multiple different types of fuels either fat or lactate and any of
them will suppress glucose use really makes me believe in this kind of competitive nutrient
environment and that that plays a central role in determining whether you clear or don't clear
glucose and how high your glucose has to go basically in order to be cleared. So let's talk
a little bit about lactate because this is one of those things where I you know now given how much
I think about lactate read about lactate and we've had a number of podcasts where we get into some
detail either I was asleep through part of medical school or it just really wasn't presented in
anything other than the following. When your demand for ATP gets high enough and quick enough
you're going to basically take glucose and when you turn it into pyruvate rather than take the
efficient path of shuttling pyruvate into acetyl CoA through the Krebs cycle where you can generate
lots of ATP requiring oxygen you're going to take a quicker path that's less efficient but doesn't
require the same cellular oxygen and you'll turn pyruvate into lactate. You won't get nearly as
much ATP and you'll also tend to generate a lot of lactate which tends to gravitate with hydrogen ions
which tends to kind of poison the muscle a little bit and that's you know why it becomes
rate limiting in terms of how long you can sustain that level of output.
Maybe explain today why that's at you know the tip of the iceberg in a generous sense of the term.
Well I think it's all actually really important stuff. It's just only as you say part of the
picture and I think the other part of the picture is that mammals have been wired to use lactate as
a major circulating nutrient. It's a super super fast turnover nutrient so when you think about
that glucose and you're having you know a few minutes supply circulating in your blood lactate
you have even shorter supply than yet that. It's constantly being made released into the blood
stream and consumed and serves as an almost universal nutrient. They're transporters that
will carry it into virtually any cell in your body. These are the MCH or is it the the MCT
transporters? Yeah these are called MCT transporters or stands for monocarboxylate because
lactate has one carboxylic acid if you think of it as a chemistry perspective.
And so those transporters are ubiquitously expressed and they allow lactate basically to go
everywhere. And so it's the universally. Which by the way Josh that already differs from kind of how
we learned it in biochemistry class which was all that lactate goes back to the liver and the
Corey cycle turns lactate back into glucose and then just exports it down the glucose pathway
via hepatic glucose output. And you're saying I'd like to understand when that happens versus when
each other tissue says oh great more fuel let me take in this lactate. Yeah I think the really
important thing about lactate is that glucose penetration into tissues is actually heavily
regulated. It has to be heavily regulated so that if we go through a period of having low
carb intake there's still glucose preserved for the brain and for other cells that particularly
need it. And lactate is the universally available form of carbohydrate. And so and I give an example
like you know in a healthy heart at least in the fasted state it basically will not touch glucose.
But it will use lactate as free fatty acid. Would that be preferred fuel as free fatty acids.
It probably also gets some fatty acids from lipoproteins and it definitely uses lactate and
also things like ketone bodies. But this is like a very clear example of a tissue other than liver
that net consumes lactate just using it as a fuel to have access to carbohydrate energy.
Now lactate is a is another metabolite that I pay a lot of attention to Josh. So as regularly as I'm
checking my glucose I'm checking my lactate. And unlike glucose the range is much greater right.
Like the lowest glucose I've ever measured in myself is probably 50 milligrams per deciliter
and the highest not including the time Jerry Reven had me do an insulin suppression test at
Stanford. And I almost died actually. This is actually a ridiculous story because one of the
IVs got blown and we didn't know that they were pushing glucose because I was just getting so
hypoglycemic and I could feel it. You know you learn in medical school what hypoglycemia feels
like. And when you start sweating really profusely and this was like nothing I've ever experienced.
It felt like a bucket of water got dumped on me. So I knew oh my god I'm really and I was like
they got to push glucose and I could feel the IV was blown. Anyway to make a long story short when
they finally corrected it my glucose got up to 240 milligrams per deciliter. So like there's call
it 250 right. That's a you know a 5x range. But with lactate I mean I've measured it as low as 0.3
millimole and as high as 20 millimole. Right. So that's a 60 fold difference. Yeah that's that's a
big big range but it probably depends a lot on your physiological state. Well of course the point
three would be you know at rest and fasted. The 20 is you know kind of an all out two minute effort.
But the point here is that's a much bigger range. And is this regulated. Is there an upper limit to
how high lactate can go or is it simply how much pain you can tolerate in terms of what is necessary
to generate lactate. Like is there truly an upper limit. I'm honestly not sure. I mean you may be
you may be right on the pain side of the scale. Right. And you know this this has to do with how
fast its production and consumption are. So you can have that excursion to 20. And you know that
goes down very quickly. Cleaned up in a few minutes you know if you're actually you know completely
resting. So yeah this is a very flexible metabolite this way. When did people start to realize this
that that lactate was a fuel because I remember first reading about this in about 2011 where
people were starting to say hey neurons might like lactate besides glucose because at that point
in time there were really only two fuels that a neuron would ingest. Right. So under normal
circumstances it was exclusively glucose. And then George Cahill showed in the 60s. Yeah but if you
starve somebody you can turn up to 60 percent of that fuel stock into beta hydroxybutyrate.
I think it was BHB maybe it was acetoacetate but it was it was a ketone right. So you'd be maybe 60
40 in favor of a ketone to glucose. But that was really it. And then there were these kind of
whisperings in these you know animal studies that suggested no actually neurons all consume lactate.
Where are we today on that front. Yeah I think it's still very unclear which cell types in the brain
are the lactate consumers versus lactate producers. Certainly there's lactate use in the brain. And is
it more astrocytes neurons. Do we know. I think it's really an active area investigation. I mean
it I think I bring biases to it but I don't bring answers. You know my bias is that you know
we are a neuron centric form of thinker right. And we didn't evolve to make glucose a unique
brain fuel in order to feed astrocytes. We did it feed neurons. So I do think there's a special
neuronal dependence on glucose. But you know as a lactate goes everywhere so it probably goes into
both astrocytes and neurons as a fuel in the right circumstances and it probably can be excreted from
both as a waste depending on exactly what activities are required in the brain at that time. And that's
really the beauty of lactate is that allows you a tremendous degree of flexibility that wouldn't
exist otherwise. And this was actually you know thought about a lot by a guy named Brooks at
Berkeley who. George Brooks. Yeah recognized the you know ubiquitous potential for lactate as a fuel.
And I think you know we were able to contribute to that story by really showing it. Yes you know
using using mass spectrometry to make it crystal clear that this usage happens throughout the whole
body. So what is the evolutionary reason in your mind for why the body would allow most tissues
to love lactate as a fuel directly versus just having the liver mop it up at the same kinetic
rate turn it into glucose and shoot that glucose out. Is there is there an obvious reason for why
the current strategy is a better one. Yeah it's not an easy answer but I think there are strong
reasons. And I'll say that we've lately done experiments in yeast actually. And you know
yeast make ethanol as waste and people always I think assume that you know yeast face this
exact same choice that you talked about when you get to the level of pyruvate either do you spit
it out as redox balanced waste in humans that's done as lactate and yeast that's done as ethanol
or do you take the pyruvate into the TCA cycle. We see that going all the way back to yeast that's
a false choice. The default is to spit out the redox balanced waste. Okay and then you can always
pick the waste up and reuse it if you need energy from the TCA cycle. And so I think this goes back
to the very earliest days of eukaryotic life basically that you want to be able to run
glycolysis whenever you need to run glycolysis so use glucose whenever you need to use glucose.
That takes you to pyruvate you've created a redox problem okay because you have electrons from the
glucose that are not sitting on the pyruvate. And the first priority is always to solve that redox
problem that's achieved in our bodies by spitting out lactate. And you don't really want to hold
that problem within cells in your body you want to get that all the way under the circulation so
every cell in your body can work on this master metabolic challenge of keeping you know electrons
balanced. Then whoever needs energy okay and these electrons are super valuable sources of energy
can pick them up in the form of lactate. And so there's been kind of this false coupling of
oxidative and glycolytic metabolism in the way biochemistry is taught when really our bodies
eukaryotes all the way back to yeast are really designed to be much more flexible to allow these
two processes to happen in yeast completely independently because they really can just spit
out ethanol to the environment in us quasi independently. So independently at the level
of individual cells in our bodies so none of them faces this pressure okay and that's really good
so if you have a bout of hypoxia okay you can release lactate and elsewhere in the body the
problem can be cleaned up. Now in our bodies it has to be cleaned up within the body somewhere
okay because we don't have any master release valve for this so all of our cells together have
to solve this problem. Meaning the way that yeast can literally eject ethanol from their cell and
get it away we can't emit lactate from our body we can emit it from a cell but it's still part of
the broader system. Exactly and that's when you get into medical problems like lactic acidosis
if you have a very fundamental metabolic deficiency or if you know god forbid someone put a bag over
your head and you couldn't breathe right then then you end up in this crisis of redox imbalance but
we distribute that problem across the body through this concentrating lactate in and out of cells and
letting whatever cells that need carbohydrate energy use the lactate. The system would be way
way less flexible if you know only the liver could clean this up and it would be also way
less commensurate with effective burst exercise okay. You know the heart is super well perfused
and if muscle is making less well perfused muscle that's far from the heart okay so it's hard to get
oxygen there is making a lot of lactate. Of course it's very advantageous at that moment for the heart
which is sitting on more oxygen than it needs to use lactate rather than fatty acids which are
better long-term things to store for the future anyway so it's way way better to have the system
designed this way. And is that regulated then locally is that regulated at each cell like how
is that decision made because how does that myocyte in the heart know the energy of the entire
system so that it can make the decision that is in the short run counterintuitive? You know it's
seems medically or maybe textbook med school counterintuitive but it's physical chemistry
pure intuition. Well no no yeah yeah yeah. Lactate goes up and so it gets burned. Regardless how but
how is the decision made are you saying it's just made on mass balance? Yeah it's made on mass
it's made on mass action and availability of substrate so there's no decision okay
that this it's it's pure physics basically. Yeah okay now I see what you're saying so
it's basically a gradient problem across the board. Mm-hmm if you have too much lactate it
flows out if you are short on energy it flows in. So tell me more about lactate I'll tell you
one thing that has I've become very interested in clinically is the implication of fasting lactate
levels in the population. So if you you know measure a person's lactate level first thing in
the morning you're going to see quite a bit of variability and it seems to be proportional to
their metabolic health. The higher that number the less metabolically healthy they are.
It's not uncommon in someone who's insulin resistant to see fasting lactate levels approaching
two millimole with no activity whereas in a healthy individual it'll be below 0.5 millimole.
What do you think that tells us about fuel partitioning and this problem of metabolomics?
Yeah well I think there's a correlation between fasting glucose and fasting lactate
but lactate is the kind of maybe harder to measure but perhaps even more intimately tied
to the essence of metabolic dysfunction molecule and I think you know very much the way you said
it that you know it reads out a few things you know when lactate is high it reflects the fact
that during these times of fasting when glucose is not really supposed to be being used much
you're still using too much glucose converting too much of it to lactate and at the same time
that your lactate clearance system isn't working very well and typically that's because you're
having competition between lactate and fat to be burned and you know so this all feeds into the
syndrome of diabetes. Now there's another interesting push observation that I've made which is
I wake up in the morning check a lactate it's 0.4 millimole. I eat the biggest carbohydrate meal
I can ingest don't lift a finger other than to feed myself. I recheck my lactate in an hour it's
one millimole. Why did that happen? I mean we can understand the biochemistry right which is
I have more glucose to metabolize but this kind of gets back to your point of
med school biochemistry would suggest my lactate should not have gone up. I'm taking glucose I'm
making pyruvate I have endless cellular oxygen I should be running that pyruvate through the
Krebs cycle and I shouldn't see any uptick in lactate but that's exactly what I don't see.
Yeah I mean circulating lactate is an intermediary
mediary in glucose catabolism and that's just the way the body works it's not what we were taught in
med school. Yeah yeah and I wonder I mean do you have a sense of of how it's being taught today
do you do you get the sense that that biochemistry students at Princeton and Stanford today are being
taught what we were taught with respect to this sort of more rigid model of lactate and it's as a
as a metabolite? Well I'm probably chipping away at it at Princeton but you know I don't know how
much it's shifting at the medical education level yet probably thank god I haven't sat through those
classes at Stanford again but um I think it's something that we should see shift and and I
hope we see the next generation of biochemistry textbooks talk about circulating lactate as an
intermediary in glucose catabolism. I think that's a really fundamental thing for people who want to
just think about metabolism accurately to know and as you say it you can do this the self-experiment
very simply and see it. And I think it's a very interesting thing to consider from a prognostic
standpoint you know when you go back and look at Jerry Reven's five criteria for what was then
syndrome x and what is now metabolic syndrome fasting glucose is still one of them. You could
make a case that fasting lactate would be more telling. Yeah I wouldn't be surprised I mean I
think the challenge with lactate is that it is a metabolite that can get up and down faster and
one response to stress is to rapidly convert glucose into lactate
and so that's just part of your body activating but of course there are people who have stress
at a blood draw and because you know lactate is a little bit more fluctuating this way
they're going to be pros and cons medically in terms of using it as a biomarker. You know I
I don't think our problem with metabolic syndrome anyway is diagnosing it right
our problem is preventing it. Yeah although what I would argue is I think we treat metabolic
syndrome too discreetly and I think we come to it too late right I think we should be looking
for things far before you actually have hypertension and truncal obesity and dyslipidemia
and hyperglycemia and I do wonder with nothing other than just intuition if
lactate dysregulation for lack of a better word might be one of the earlier canaries in the coal
mine. I totally agree with that. I want to go back to something that we've talked about a couple of
times you've mentioned it in passing you and I know what it's about but I think it's such an
important part of where we're going to go in a discussion that I almost need you to go into full
prof mode and really explain two things which are obviously highly related in a moment you'll see.
The first is how the electron transport chain works. So what is what is the Krebs cycle doing
and how is that feeding into this massive generation of energy currency and specifically
can you talk about it with special attention to the concept of redox?
And I would encourage you Josh to take as much time as you need because the more the listeners
understand this the more they'll be able to understand NAD, NADP, NADPH, NR, NMN all of
these other things that people really care about but I think unfortunately they've been conditioned
into very glib understandings of these things which I think are serving no one any benefit
without actually going back to understanding the root of this problem. Now that's a great framing.
You can think of it this way fundamentally you eat three macronutrients carbs and protein and fat
and in a healthy adult first approximation every carbon atom that you eat in any of those three
forms needs to exit your body as exhaled carbon dioxide. And all of that exhaled carbon dioxide
first approximation is made in the TCA cycle and the main way that nutrients flow into the TCA
cycle to become carbon dioxide is first turning into pieces that are two carbon units in size.
And so from carbohydrate the basic flow is glucose to lactate and then lactate to pyruvate
to a two carbon piece that goes into the TCA cycle. Fat is basically composed of preassembled
two carbon pieces so they just get shopped up two carbon pieces at a time and the protein part is a
little more complicated we can probably skip it. So you end up with these two carbon units.
But we're worth just sort of noting Josh that protein really the primary role of protein is
actually the nitrogen side which we're kind of putting into these amino acids that are building
blocks. It's really less of an energy substrate but it does have that carboxylic acid on it that
still has to go through this cycle and be exhaled. But that's in other words that's why we'll skip
it for now because it's really not a significant energetic component right? Yeah I mean I think it
really depends on what kind of diet you eat right? If you're on a carnivore diet then it's probably a
different situation. Yeah it's a very interesting side discussion but ultimately you know unless
you're gaining protein mass which of course wonderful for us guys anyway when that happens
typically at least societally smiles on it you know but other than that you know whatever
amino acid carbon you take into the form of protein has to be balanced with also amino acid
catabolism. So at that level it's not that different than carbs and fat it's just a little
different in that it can enter the TCA cycle sometimes also as four carbon pieces but a lot
of amino acids are broken down into these same two carbon pieces they're just 20 of them so it's
you know no one wants to hear a discussion of how all 20 of them get chopped up. So ultimately you
end up with these two carbon pieces and then they congeal with a four carbon piece and that makes
citrate and a lot of them one of the problems with the Krebs cycle is that it has three names
okay the Krebs cycle in honor of the amazing biochemist who played a key role in figuring it out
the citric acid cycle and that's named for this condensation molecule of the four carbon and the
two carbon piece citrate or the TCA cycle and TCA is tricarboxylic acid and that's because citrate
has three carboxylic acids okay so you have this cycle that unfortunately has three names but that
it's probably three times as important as anything else in metabolism so maybe it's fair.
So ultimately as this cycle turns it's going to spit off the two carbon pieces that
came in as carbon dioxide and in so doing it's going to take the electrons that were part of
those two carbon pieces and pass them to this famous cofactor NAD to make NADH okay and that
H stands for hydrogen right and that hydrogen is really one proton and two electrons and so this
another confusing nomenclature thing that you just can think of that H even though it may sound to
those who've taken from you know freshman chemistry like H plus like acid this is an H with two
electrons stuck to it so it's really what we call hydride or electrical form of chemical energy
and so then the NADH that's made from NAD there is what feeds into the electron transport chain
and those electrons then flow through a series of proteins that sit in the inner mitochondrial
membrane the mitochondria of two membranes the outer one is kind of leaky and kind of not so
important the inner one is super tight and has a ton of regulation in it and most importantly
can be used to pump protons to one side or the other and ultimately it's the pumping of protons
out of the mitochondria that's the function of the electron transport chain and in this kind of
metabolic flux way that we talked about earlier the protons that get pumped out just flow right back
in but as they flow back in they turn a turnstile and as that turnstile turns it squeezes
ADP and inorganic phosphate physically squeezes them together to make ATP the master energy
currency that we use to power our neurons for thinking our muscles for moving and so on.
So one of the things about this system that is just so beautiful is the transition from chemical
energy to electrical energy back to chemical energy and I you know I've tried to explain this
to my daughter she's 13 she's not fully in love with it yet but I know at some point it'll be a
more fun discussion but it really is a miracle right like so much of biology just seems like
it's hard to believe it all worked out but if you were going to rank all the things that I can't
believe it worked out this has got to be in the top five right it's like let's go back to the
basics again you eat a piece of bread right you're eating glucose it has these carbon to
carbon bonds and carbon to hydrogen bonds and some carbon to oxygen bonds now refresh my memory but
carbon to oxygen is not a very energetic bond right you know this is a another thing where
you have to be careful with the nomenclature so like CO double bonds are spectacular bonds
they're super high energy but that's where life I didn't say life that's where
physics and chemistry want to flow too they want to make these high energy bonds and in making high
energy bonds you can release a lot of energy and so those are bonds that are very energetically
favorable right so they're the end state it's the CH bonds as you're alluding to that start out
energetically loaded okay they're less energetically good in and of themselves so they have
the potential to become something better yeah it's the it's the potential that I really yeah
I'm glad you're I'm glad you're adding this level of sort of chemical rigor to this so yeah the
point I want to make is that these these carbon carbon carbon hydrogen bonds have this potential
that this entire cycle with three names that's so wonderful basically liberates it basically
says we're going to take that chemical energy and we're going to liberate it through electron
transferring apparati and then at the last second using that I love the turnstile analogy right
we're basically going to quickly shunt it right back into a chemical bond which is the p binding
to the a d p to make the a t p and now we have this energy currency that is going to go and do
its own thing and it has lots of different ways that it unleashes itself so explain to people the
difference between oxidation and reduction in chemical terms because I think people have to
at least hear once what's an oxidation reaction what's a reduction reaction and then why we use
the term redox synonymously with these two right so oxidation reduction are always coupled okay and
they refer to the movement of electrons and so when electrons go from substance a to substance b
okay the one that gives up the electrons is oxidized it's subject oxidation the one that
receives the electrons is reduced okay it's the subject of reduction let's talk about redox
pairing so you've already brought up nad and nadh so talk about how oxidation reduction pairing
works with those two to facilitate the electron transfer down this lovely chain of the inner
mitochondrial memory right so this is a pair where nad is the oxidized form nadh is the electron
holding or reduced form and it normally exists in a quite biased ratio towards a lot of nad
and a small amount of nadh and the way nature works is that whenever any parakemicals is
skewed in one direction it's favorable to turn the one that's abundant into the one that's less
abundant and so this makes nad a decent electron acceptor and so it's sitting there prepared to
pick up electrons from these intermediates carbon intermediates of the tca cycle that are
coming from carbohydrate and fat and take the electrons make nadh which then can feed into
electron transport chain and that back end has to happen fast in order to keep this ratio skewed
so you have mainly nad and not too much nadh and that's really important because when that nadh
starts creeping up all sorts of things start going wrong such as well the nadh going up will
drive too many electrons into electron transport chain and going back to
nov you know he's done a spectacular job showing how that leads to production of free radicals
and so when you you need the right amount of this but this is a clear way to get toxic
amounts of free radicals if you have nadh build up secondly it just gums up metabolism if you have
too much nadh relative to nad and so then you can get into problems not having enough atp
and then it can also make signaling things go awry. Now are there clinical scenarios in which
we see that happen or are these more typically there are things that result from toxicities
where you know like you know the classic thing you learn in medical school to explain the
significance of this whole system is cyanide right you know maybe tell folks how cyanide works and
I don't know if that's too extreme an example of how this system can be hijacked but but let's see.
Yeah I know I mean obviously you know cyanide is electron transport chain
inhibitor and so that leads the whole system just backing up a bit by bit and so you can't
then transfer electrons from nadh into the electron transport chain and so nadh goes way up
nad falls to the floor and then you have no way to make atp and that unfortunately leads to rapid
mortality right. Yeah and that's that's that's an interesting point because it speaks to this
again comes back to the kinetics and the flux which is it's not like cyanide kills you in an
hour I mean it kills you in seconds it's really a sobering thought. Yeah ATP turnover via this
system is on the time scale of a second and so same for nadh and so these are things you're just
whizzing through our bodies all the time and that we're constantly dependent on. Are there are there
less extreme examples Josh of things that will put that balance in the wrong direction kind of
chronically? I think it's a really interesting question I mean and
I don't want to give the misimpression that you know the right thing is to have as much nad and
as little nadh as possible right. This is a first of all it's designed to be a dynamic
system you know if you undergo intense exercise you're going to drive nadh up and this is a very
healthy context for doing this transiently metformin of course is a super interesting
medication and it's going to probably works you know mainly by slowing the conversion of nadh
back to nadh by impairing the complex one of the electron transport chain the one that does this
initial electron offloading from nadh to make nad. How well is that understood I mean this is you'll
talk to five people who study metformin and they'll tell you five different things which
I think just tells you how much we don't know but what is your view of the I don't think it's really
disputed that metformin inhibits complex one is it I think the broader question is how much
is that the main attraction versus kind of a sideshow right. Yeah I'll say you know there are
many people who know more about this than me but one thing that we tend to do in our lab sometimes
take these kind of famous metabolic effects like metformin inhibiting complex one and just do a
quick test of it and I say when we do that about half the time they look to be true and half the
time they look to be dubious and metformin was a shining star in our hands in inhibiting complex
one it was one of the cases where I really felt like you know it may do other things but it
certainly does what it's supposed to do there it does that strongly and I think it's probably the
fact that it does it in a relatively liver specific way due to the way that metformin enters
cells of the body that leads to it first of all being safe okay there are many things that make
it safer than cyanide but it is really crazy that you know it's the maybe the world's most widely
used medication is it some level transport chain yeah yeah and it's a mechanistic analog of cyanide
right and see if like one of the most acutely lethal substances and the most widely used drug
working in a remarkably similar way and so I think the fact that there's a strong liver
specificity is probably what makes it you know net beneficial for at least a subset of people
and and what's the what's the what's the change that you saw in your lab josh between so if you
go or off metformin what's your nadh to nad ratio and then on metformin how much did it change that
it depends how much metformin you use but if you try to approximate like a you do your
best to approximate an actual clinical dose of you know say a couple grams a day
yeah I'm not sure we did this in a way that I would consider clinically applicable so but but
I'll say that it's certainly crystal clear that it goes in the right direction
and so it doesn't surprise you that metformin would raise fasting lactate levels correct
no I mean it certainly is aligned to do that right and that's just backing up further it's
just basically creating more of a roadblock into the TCA is going to give you more lactate
yeah more of a road back and electron disposal basically do you think that that's a neutral
effect or do you think that that's a potentially deleterious effect of metformin that is probably
offset in a patient with diabetes by the benefits that it has on hepatic glucose output
that's a great question I don't think I know I mean
I think having more circulating lactate can be you know a bit of a challenge for
clearing fat right because they have some sort of competition so from that perspective I think you
know being in a lower state might have some benefits but then you know lactate is a valuable
fuel as long as it's not getting too high level so I'm not sure how that all plays out in terms
of long-term health interesting yeah anything you want to say about NADP and NADPH just to round it
out so people know the full story yeah these are you know super important co-factors that personally
I'm very obsessed with that are kind of they live just on the edge of what people who take
biochemistry either in undergraduate or med school learn about or don't learn about and
they're fascinating co-factors because in terms of their intrinsic chemistry all their intrinsic
chemistry from the energy point of view is exactly the same as NAD, NADH but they have a different
handle on them chemically that allows biology to use them in a different way and then the
ratio is maintained quite different level from NAD, NADH so NAD, NADH is super biased towards NAD
this is much more of an even pairing which means that there's much more driving force to dump the
electrons off okay rather than to absorb them up and so NADPH is really to me second only to ATP
a master energetic building material and it's the building material that's used for example
to assemble fat I mean it's the most important one so as you take pieces two carbon pieces from
carbohydrate and want to put them together to make fat you keep dumping in electrical energy
in the form of NADPH and then NADPH is used in all sorts of other really interesting ways to fight
reactive oxygen species it's also used if you're trying to kill bacteria to intentionally make
reactive oxygen species so this is where biology is freaking confusing and complicated and there's
definitely the yin and yang that you have this awesome co-factor that's so important for fighting
oxidative stress and also can be used to create boatloads oxidative stress intentionally when it's
needed first of all that was a fantastic overview of how the Krebs cycle works and specifically with
attention to how electrons move through it and move through these redox factors which then brings
us to I think a part of the discussion where a lot of people have an enormous interest which is
I don't know go back seven eight years it started to become fashionable and it's only become more
fashionable to talk about supplementing with NAD I say that quote unquote we're going to talk about
why you don't actually supplement with NAD but is it safe to say that at least part of the impetus
for this was the observation that as we age cellular NAD levels decline and you've already
made a very compelling case for why NAD is important I mean I don't I almost want to avoid
the whole sirtuin side of this because I think that story keeps changing so maybe we can just
unless you feel strongly or compelled to get into sirtuins we can put those aside for the moment
yeah I love putting sirtuins aside let's let's just get to real metabolism and
yeah I you know I think the first principles in this field are great right that you know
NAD plays this super central role in energy generation that we all want to feel more
energetic whether you know you want to be a more extremely successful athlete at age 21 or whether
you want to feel at age 50 like I am or later you know like you're 21 and so you think you know if
we could just you know turn up the the burner capacity right this would be absolutely fantastic
um and then we have this data that NAD is depleted with aging although I have to say
when we do those measurements we agree that NAD is depleted with aging but it is a lot more subtle
than you know you would think uh looking at the literature and so these are really quite subtle
NAD depletions you know we were talking about these ranges earlier and you know
the kind of three-fold uh range where a lot of metabolites live on a daily basis some of them
glucose that's their worst day right and as you pointed out some of them like lactate you know
they may do the three-fold all the time and then the 60-fold when you stress them uh NAD changes
we see with aging are like you know 10 percent 20 percent oh wow I didn't realize it was that little
Josh yeah so I think um and I'm not saying that in some tissue of you know an aged human there might
not be bigger effects but I think this is the first caution I would give to people thinking
that they're going to fix everything through NAD and um so you know on one hand it's a robust
finding that this is something that changes with aging that with a central metabolic role on the
other hand it's something that happens with a fair amount of subtlety can you explain to folks how
this is done because again I mean you know we talk about measurement sometimes a little too glibly
right so pretty easy to explain how we can measure glucose and hemoglobin and lactate
at the other end of the spectrum we've talked a lot about ATP but but I but I think most people
don't understand is it's very difficult to measure ATP it comes back to what you said a moment ago
this ain't sticking around a very long time right you're using MRS and super complicated physics
to be able to measure these things where does NAD fit on that spectrum and how do you actually
measure it yeah I mean I think the good news is that NAD unlike NADH is not like one of these
super transient metabolites and so NADH measurement is wickedly difficult but you know most of this
NADH NAD pair sits as NAD and it tends to sit around for you know hour-ish time scale oh so
you don't even have to you don't necessarily have to flash freeze tissue or things like that
that's right you have you have some more flexibility in making those measurements as
long as you're not irritating the tissue in a way that leads to you know massive NAD degradation
which you know people may do sometimes by accident but I think generally it's not that
hard of a measurement NAD obviously like ATP it's a tissue metabolite not a circulating metabolite
so you need biopsy specimens to measure it I'm not a master of the literature of you know NAD
levels in human tissues but my not fully informed perspective is that there probably isn't as much
as we should have okay and that's because it's hard to get biopsies from from people and if you
if you took if you take blood if you take a whole blood and you look at PBMC can you look at NAD
levels in there with relative ease or is it too complicated because by the time you separate the
PBMC you've kind of lost your window I think it's a really good question because there is quite active
NAD metabolism in immune cells so yeah I'm not an expert in this but I bet there's a way you could
develop a good protocol I haven't followed you know how good the measurements up to now have been
so most of what you've measured has been in tissue yeah typically you know we work a lot in mouse
sometimes we measure human but more typically on the cancer side and yeah there we just take tissues
and freeze them and you know extract metabolites do mass spec you're seeing a consistent clear
decline in NAD with the aging animal or human but it's I mean it's not a fold reduction it's
a percent reduction 10 percent 20 reduction and that's that's the most common thing yeah okay so
this this generates a hypothesis the hypothesis is if you restore NAD levels in the old organism to
the level that they were in the young organism the old organism will feel and perform like the
young organism that's one hypothesis another hypothesis would be if you induce super normal
levels of NAD in any organism they will feel super normal so let's assume that both of those
hypotheses are simultaneously testable what happened five seven eight years ago NAD clinics
started popping up all over the place and they started saying if you come here we'll put IVs in
you and we'll give you NAD so let's first explain why did they do this intravenously why couldn't
they make an NAD pill yeah so NAD and its precursors are broken down in the gastrointestinal track
and so you know if you take you know NR for example so nicotinamide riboside orally
it mainly will enter the body in the form of nicotinic acid or niacin which is a healthy
substance so there's nothing wrong with it but you know it except for maybe the epithelium or
gastrointestinal track you know the body is not seeing nicotinamide riboside and NAD just to be
clear because we're going to talk about NR and NMN in a moment but NAD there's no way to orally take
it right it has to be yeah there's no known absorption route for NAD and I think it'll get
broken down probably all the way to nicotinic acid although I'm not 100% sure anyone has proven that
but I certainly don't think it would enter the body any other way than either nicotinamide
which is like you know a little bit closer to remaking NAD or or nicotinic acid. So what
happens when a person receives intravenous NAD what's the fate of that NAD because you know one
of the things in metabolism and biology is anytime you put something in a vein you bypass the liver
with something called the first pass effect which in your former life was very important because
when you had these patients in the ER that you were giving inhaled drugs to it's not just the
speed with which they were getting it it's that you didn't you could actually deliver the exact
drug you wanted not a pro drug that could be modified by the liver. So this idea of giving
intravenous NAD is at least theoretically interesting because you're putting the molecule
of interest directly into the venous system. So what's its fate? I think and you may be more up
on this than me but that you know it's going to get broken down partially right because there's
not clear uptake mechanisms known anyway to get NAD from the bloodstream into cells.
Nicotinamide mononucleotide
I think may be able to enter cells directly or nicotinamide riboside. So these are partially
broken down forms of NAD but that are nevertheless meaningfully closer to NAD than the normal things
that circulate in good amounts in our bloodstream and that does partially I would say short circuit
the route to cells making NAD. So they kind of can break down partially the NAD in the bloodstream
take these partially broken down NAD precursors into cells and rebuild NAD in a shortcut manner
that probably has a good chance to bolster NAD levels.
So in other words when you give intravenous NAD there is no transporter to take NAD into a cell
but that NAD breaks down into things like NR and NMN and in the vascular system we know that those
things can get taken up at least into some cells. Do we know which cells have the capacity to do that
or which cells don't? I don't know that I'm the best expert to ask that but I
yeah I think
I think certainly at least some important cell types in the body can take those up and
may be pretty broadly but I don't know off the top of my head. When the NR or NMN gets into this cell
is it relatively straightforward that it will be reconstituted into NAD? Like what's the
energetic cost of doing that or you know how easy is that and is that the favored reaction at that
point? Yeah I think it's the favored reaction which is the important thing and this is not a
big demand relatively speaking you know the big energy flow is through this NAD and NADH exchange
but the making of NAD itself is not an expensive process per se and so yeah you get these pieces
you can kind of think so NAD stands for nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide and so it's two
kind of nucleotide pieces put together and when you take an NR or NMN it's one of those two pieces
but the more interesting side and the other side comes from ATP and it's there all the time because
all your cells have ATP or you got much much deeper problems and so you just snap it together
and I think you end up with you know probably effective NAD supplementation when you go the
IV route. In other words taking IV NAD will probably increase into intracellular NAD levels
though not directly because there's not a transporter but it goes through this sort of
circuitous route to get there so might not be the most efficient way to do it but
this certainly corrects a statement I've made in the past which is intravenous NAD is not a good
way to get NAD because we don't have a transporter that's correct but incomplete. I think that's a fair
summary from my perspective. In other words we don't really know how much if you take a hundred
units of NAD intravenously infused we don't really know how many units ultimately make their way into
a cell but it's probably not a hundred. Yeah I'm sure there's a fair amount of loss in the process
I mean there's a very interesting protein called CD38 that's I think designed to control these
kind of pathways okay and it's a suppressor of NAD levels and it works I think by breaking down
NAD that's outside of cells and mainly there's not normally in physiology NAD in meaningful
amounts probably outside of cells but there is NMN in meaningful amounts since this is a protein
that's super good at breaking down NMN. It still leaves you with NR which is still
so it's one step further away from being NAD but it's still meaningfully closer than your typical
physiological precursor and so I think it's positioned to as you say at least some places in
the body boost NAD. Today I think the majority of efforts to increase intracellular NAD are done
through oral precursors and the two are NR and NMN which as you said are pretty similar and
are you aware of a more convincing argument for why one might be a more preferred substrate? I
haven't particularly seen arguments that one is superior than the other. I've seen some
unpublished data that suggests one can be made more temperature and moisture stable than the other
but let's put that aside for the moment. Would you consider these two a first approximation
equivalent approaches? Yeah. Okay so now talk about something else that you said that it also
kind of news to me which is what is the effect of the gastrointestinal tract on these agents?
Yeah I mean they get broken down and they get broken down all the way to the level of nicotinic
acid or niacin basically and this is the main way they enter the body. It doesn't mean that
there can't be a trickle of them entering some other way that has a physiological effect
or that there's some local effect or some effect on the microbiome of taking them. So they're
you know biology is super complicated. There are ways that these could be doing interesting health
supporting things but I don't really think they're fundamentally different than taking a physician
prescribed niacin pill from the perspective of providing NAD precursors. Now a physician
prescribed niacin pill when people used to take niacin for hyperbeta lipoproteinemia right which
is really obviously no I mean there's probably still some patients out there who take niacin
unfortunately but it wasn't uncommon to get a real flush from the medication. Now I don't remember
what doses people were taking but I feel like it was on the order of grams not telegrams.
Do you recall how much niacin you would need to give somebody for them to experience an actual
flush? I think it was a few grams I think that that's where my recollection is too. Okay so is
that the reason people don't experience a flush with NR and NMN because they're typically taking
you know 500 milligrams to one gram and that's simply not going to produce enough niacin to reach
that threshold? Yeah they're also kind of niacin prodrugs so they probably are delayed absorption
forms of niacin so that may smooth things out enough so they may be better tolerated but I
think this is how I'd fundamentally think about them is that they're niacin prodrugs.
Your lab has done some some of the flux work on this correct? What are some of the most interesting
things you've learned about how NR and how NMN when given orally end up in different tissues and
what the effect is in the liver versus the muscle versus the plasma? Yeah I think the main thing you
see is that you know these are converted to niacin they will raise niacin particularly niacin heading
to the liver out of the gastrointestinal tract so in the what we call the portal circulation that
connects you know your intestine to the liver very effectively and that you know other than
that their effect on like boosting their own circulating levels is somewhere between subtle
and vanishing. I'm still not sure which of those two it is but I think they certainly remain in the
bloodstream much less abundant than nicotinamide which is the thing the liver is normally producing
to feed NAD precursor to the tissues of the body and so there there's from what we have seen no
clear route for oral NR or oral NMN to produce circulating levels of NR or NMN that are high
enough to compete at least at a standard concentration level with nicotinamide the
physiological precursor as a way of feeding NAD precursors to tissues so basically at some level
they don't change what's happening and what most of your tissues are seeing that much if our
measurements are correct. Where do you think you could be fooled on this I mean I know that's a
question every scientist or every good scientist asks themselves that question right how can we be
fooled by our measurements. I'm sure you've thought about this where do you see this the
opportunities in this particular case to be misled. Yeah I mean it could be that you know
there are local effects of NR or NMN on like the intestine that are really important it could be
that their availability impacts the microbiome in important ways the microbiome can have big effects
on health. It could be that even though the amounts of like NR that may reach the liver or
even lower amounts that may reach you know the heart or something are really small that there's
a subset of cells there that are really NR preferring because maybe they're really deficient
in using nicotinamide and maybe getting even small amounts of NR to those cells is meaningful so I
think these are all possibilities that we're very much open to but you know my base assumption is
that often the obvious is true and here the obvious would be you know the physiological
system just isn't that impacted by this particular type of oral supplement. Do you think there's any
chance that with chronic administration you'd see something different because I'm assuming in these
experiments you're not seeing the effect of these chemicals being ingested chronically or are you?
No I think it could be I mean human can be different than mouse okay first of all it's
another important thing that I say we haven't done these experiments in human. I think someone
if they aren't already should do these experiments in human and yeah chronic versus acute so there's
a bunch of variables that could alter things. Based on what you know now if the hypothesis
is true if giving well let's not talk about the route if restoring intracellular NAD levels
at 50 to the level they were at when you were 20 would improve some measure of performance
based on what you know today what do you hypothesize would be the most efficient way
to restore NAD levels? Yeah I mean I guess you know IV is the promising way to do the restoration.
I'm not very convinced about the first hypothesis and you know I think the big history of medicine
you and I can debate it is that things are way more complicated than people can envision right
that you know hormone replacement therapy is like one of the great examples right it didn't turn out.
Although it's being overturned well but I think you know I think HRT is one that
I think if you go back and look at the women's health initiative I think it got it wrong right
I mean I think it was the randomized experiment but it was really misinterpreted.
So is this what you thought save a bit more about that? Maybe I picked up on the wrong
thread of where you were going but I assumed what you were going to say was look the epidemiology
in the 80s and 90s was that giving women hormones post menopause was a good thing
and then the women's health initiative came along and said no it's a bad thing I assume that's what
you were going to say and what I was going to say was actually no I think that's actually
misleading I think if you actually go back and look at the women's health initiative
it was just an awful example of how to misinterpret a study. I think there was no increase in the risk
of breast cancer and if there was any risk increase in the risk of breast cancer it probably had
nothing to do with the estrogen that the women were given. When you actually look for example
at the relative risk and absolute risk different in those cohorts so remember the
women's health initiative had three cohorts you had your full placebos well technically it was
two parallels right so you had the placebo versus estrogen only in women who did not have a uterus
and then you had placebo versus estrogen plus MPA the synthetic progesterone. So in the estrogen
only versus the placebo there was a non-statistical significant reduction in the risk of breast cancer
so there was a hazard ratio of about 0.8 or 0.79 or 0.81 something like that but it didn't quite
reach statistical significance but trending towards estrogen actually reduced the risk of
breast cancer. In the estrogen plus MPA group there was a barely statistical significant increase
in the risk of breast cancer I think the hazard ratio was I want to say it was about 1.24 1.25
and the p-value was exactly 0.05 or 0.049 or something like that so at the surface you'd
say gosh this is increasing the risk of breast cancer and what was talked about was it was it
was a 25 percent increase in the risk of breast cancer but the you know to talk about the relative
risk increase without talking about the absolute risk is obviously irresponsible if you look at the
absolute risk change it was 0.1 percent it was one in a thousand and that says nothing about a lot of
other methodologic issues with the study including the fact that in my opinion a more plausible
hypothesis was that the MPA was more the issue than the estrogen but the estrogen gets all the
attention right so estrogen causes breast cancer gets the attention and you know if you look at
subsequent studies I don't think we see that to be the case so so I'm gonna hypothesize or predict
that in 10 years I think that we'll look back at what happened to a generation of women which I
think is really unfair in that you know basically an entire generation of women got deprived of
hormones because of I think a really poorly interpreted study but your point notwithstanding
sometimes the obvious is not obvious sorry for the digression well I mean yeah but like no I mean
that was super interesting and I thought there was some cardiovascular risk data in that study that
was surprising but I it's you know it much better than me yeah I think on the cardiovascular front
there probably is a slight increase in risk with oral estrogen because of the hypercoagulability
I also think it speaks to understanding the use case today very few women on hormone replacement
therapy are given oral estrogen the preferred route of administration is is is a is a patch
you know something like a vivel dot where you're given topical estradiol and you get all of the
benefits of the reduction of azer motor symptoms the incredible benefits that you see on bone
health without any of the hypercoagulability and cardiovascular so now we actually see the reverse
now there's a very clear trend not just trend it's statistically significant there's a very clear
reduction in cardiovascular mortality yeah so that's a great example where you had to give by
the right route of administration right in order to get the net positive health benefit right and
I mean I think you know right and said to Advil another one right people knew they had a lot of
side effects but everybody assumed that they were kind of counterbalanced by the fact they were
reducing coagulability and that this was going to be cardio protective right and I I don't know if
you're going to tell me that you still believe that but no I don't most most people don't right
yeah and so so so really where you were going I think is you were saying look you might even
just reject the outright hypothesis like this idea that yeah we do observe a 20 percent 10 to 20
percent reduction in NAD levels as we age you haven't even bought the first hypothesis which
is even if I could magically deliver 20 percent more NAD to a 50 year old you're not you're not
sounding very convinced that that's going to improve quality or length of life yeah not at
this point in time right I mean these these things involve such complicated interplay of different
organ systems and it may turn out that you know NAD supplementation is super valuable
medically I am completely open to that and I would love that to be the case but I think if so it's
going to be because there are select cell types that are genuinely severely NAD depleted
and that we will need to figure out how to restore NAD in those cell types and then we may see big
health benefits so I think that would be fantastic and it's completely possible and it's possible
that the general intravenous supplementation is hitting those cells and doing that but I think
it's equally possible that it's having some adverse effect that's going to be net negative for people
and we don't know the science well enough and we certainly haven't done the clinical experiment
well enough to give good health guidance yet so two things first a statement I mean this is really
interesting for me because I really stand corrected and I just want to apologize to all the people
over the years that I've said intravenous NAD is not getting in your cell I stand corrected it
indirectly based on everything you're saying may actually be getting into at least some cells
the second is a question right which is how would you even begin to tackle that question
which is are there certain cell subtypes that may indeed benefit from NAD boosting
I haven't really seen a single convincing clinical study in humans using either NR or NMN
that has made me excited about this and I'm not a stranger to putting things in my body without
absolute perfect information right I mean I take rapamycin I've been taking rapamycin for four or
five years I will be the first to admit I think we have very good evidence for that it's not perfect
it's far from perfect we're never going to have a definitive human clinical trial but if I'm willing
to take rapamycin why am I not taking NR and why am I not taking NMN and the reason is I just can't
find a shred of compelling evidence to tell me to do so and I'm in the same boat you're in I'd love
it if there was because it's a pretty easy safe thing to take so what study needs to be done to
help someone like me a reluctant NAD or get on the NAD train you know I think we need to first
of all map better the basic pharmacology of NAD in animals and human I mean that's quite doable
and this is something that we as a field are doing and there are a lot of great people doing this and
but we can do more and better then we need to have the technologies to look at this at cellular
resolution rather than bulk resolution so this is like we're pushing very hard to develop the
ability to take a slice of tissue and say what's the heterogeneity across cells in NAD levels I
think that'll be very helpful because if we see that that's really scattershot and aging and
homogeneous and young then you have your answer that you know all that we need is for one in 10
cells at any time to be really NAD depleted and we view that 10% reduction not as some tiny wiggle
down but as one in 10 cells being on the road to a catastrophic outcome okay and so I think
there's going to be a really important measurement and I think the field will get there over the next
few years not instantly and then ultimately we need successful clinical experiments right and
I think there there have been some really persuasive experiments in animals you know with
for example I think there are experiments on reversing you know bad outcomes after renal
ischemia and so it'd be good if we could find niche experiments where there's a very strong
effect in animals a very quick clinical readout right you have a
ischemic renal event and you do supplementation and you get a benefit or you don't so I don't
think the right way to go about it. How is it administered in that experiment I don't think I
remember that one. You know I may not get the details of that right so but I think I would
just say conceptually we need to find the strongest animal proof of concept that can be translated
into a small but definitive clinical trial and prove that this really can do something
beneficial in the right context and then from there you can think about kind of you know
expanding the indication to general health betterment. Who's the natural owner funding wise of this
investigation I mean is NIH is this a question NIH is interested in I mean
indirectly through the ITP, Rich Miller, Randy Strong et al. have already done an NR test
in their very rigorous tried and true model as you know that failed right so NR did not extend life.
Is NIH still interested in this question enough to continue funding it do you
you know where is your funding for this level of investigation coming from?
You know we mainly try to help the real NAD expert labs by you know doing the flux studies
facilitating measurements but you know it's not the bread and butter of my life I'm probably about
an observer at the same level as you of this this field broadly speaking. I think you know there's
there's money at NIH for interesting science and so this is too central to metabolism and too
much public health interest for you know. So you're not worried that you're not worried this is not
going to run up against this? No and I think biotech is interested in this and you know there's
very interesting ways to do this pharmacologically and so we may see those mature faster you know
CD38 inhibitors obviously there's a whole different financial structure there right if you can make a
patent approved you know medicine and all that economic incentive is is great for driving first
you know science answers and then clinical answers. What are the top labs right now in your mind in
in studying NAD and its and its precursors or ways to increase it? Oh gosh I think I'm too much
of an outsider to get into naming names on that I'm gonna only get myself in trouble other than
credit other than to credit Joe Bauer for being a fantastic collaborator. Yeah you'll fail to
mention somebody fair enough fair enough. Okay let's pivot to the final thing I want to really
get into Josh which is cancer metabolism it kind of ties in so much of what we've talked about and
that's how you and I reconnected five or six years ago at a conference and then obviously number of
times since then. So you know the irony of it is right you do your PhD in the inner workings of
how the immune system works but you're not particularly interested in cancer at the time
you you you you come back to academia as a metabolomics experiment as an as a metabolomics
expert and now you've kind of wound your way back to oncology in a way. So tell me a little
bit about that journey right how did you go from this profound interest in metabolism metabolomics
and flexomics to realizing a beautiful application for this is in the field of oncology.
Yeah I think you know part of it is really the human connection and I was so fortunate to
be at Princeton which is this kind of academic bubble where I could do my experiments on E. coli
and yeast and really set up these good metabolic measurements unmolested but then you know
also we're close to Penn and at some point I got a call from the head of the Penn Cancer Center
at that point in time Craig Thompson saying he wanted to visit and he just of course I just say
yes you know it's a simple one and that was kind of a life-changing call for me because it brought
me into the world of biomedicine you know again basically in the context of working on cancer
metabolism and it was very natural because if you look at the history of cancer therapy right
you know the first great rational triumph in treating cancer was antifolates and Sydney
Farber and you know name memorialized on the Dana Farber Cancer Center right and so this is really
the origins of how cancer was rationally treated by targeting metabolism and it just got
understudied for so many years and it was a very natural re-entry point for me because cancer you
can study as isolated cells in a culture dish much as we were studying E. coli and yeast
and so that was much more comfortable to me in you know the 2008 or whatever time frame
than you know starting to work on mice and I'm delighted that we got back to mice a few years
after that. What year did Craig leave Penn to go to Memorial Sloan Kettering? Must have been shortly
after he invited you over right? Yeah a few years after I think so yeah. So people like Craig who I
have not had on the podcast but I'd love to but Lou who I have you know when you think about cancer
metabolism today I mean it's just a booming field right I mean I would argue and no disrespect to
people in different fields but that cancer metabolism and immunotherapy are really two
of the most promising and exciting areas in the field today which were two things we didn't have
a single word about in medical school right? Yeah that's absolutely true except you know maybe some
anti-metabolites for cancer hit in some way in the pharmacology book you know but yeah I think
you know one of the most exciting things going to be interface of those two fields
also and we see this with you know microbiome composition being predictive of whether
immunotherapy works amazing work from Jennifer Wargo showing that you know fiber can promote
the effectiveness of immunotherapy and so we're seeing that connection all soluble or insoluble?
TBD okay so we're very excited to work on that answer and then you know
there are different flavors of soluble fiber and so I have my pet dreams for how this may work
mechanistically but I think it's going to be an incredibly important interface. Wow so tell folks
a little bit about what it is about cancer cells that makes their metabolism distinct from their
non-cancer counterparts but within the same tissue even like if you want to compare adenocarcinoma
of the colon or breast or prostate and look at the perfectly normal non-cancer cell sitting right
next to it I mean we we typically talk about two hallmarks of cancer right we talk about the
inability to respond to cell cycles signaling so this is why these silly things just keep growing
even when they're told stop growing and then the capacity to metastasize to basically pick up leave
go grow in a new site but what is it about them metabolically that also is a piece of their
signature? Well cancers tend to be glucose users and you know once you step back and think that
you know in the fasted state in particular using glucose is a weird thing rather than a default
thing okay and that the default thing is to use fat and lactate then the fact that cancer uses
glucose is very distinctive and they do this in large part because they're programmed internally
to basically feel like they're always seeing insulin and this is through mutations and
something called the PI3 kinase pathway that Lou Cantley who you mentioned you know pioneered
and this leads to the fact they're positive on this FDG PET scan so they'll constantly take up
and phosphorylate and trap glucose or glucose analogs and this is actually the most sensitive
way to detect most types of cancer downstream from this though there's a ton of metabolic changes
in the cancer cells and you know the most fundamental of these is the fact that in order
to do the uncontrolled growth they have to do uncontrolled nucleic acid synthesis
and this is the vulnerability that was targeted initially by Farber but has been targeted by a
lot of very important medications that are you know widely used still today you know Pematrexa
is first line treatment for lung cancer and if you get these medications right you can induce
mutations through you know the metabolic stress on the nucleotide system and this can make
immunotherapy work better and so that's a very exciting part and I think that part has gotten
understudied as cancer metabolism has you know returned to the fore there's been a lot of focus
on fuel usage cutoff which is tough because like most cells in the body cancer cells can use a lot
of different types of fuels depending on what's available yeah this is an important point Josh
because a lot of people I think would hear the first part of what you're saying and their natural
conclusion would be well wait a minute if you know you do a PET scan on somebody and it lights
up with glucose that tells me cancer loves glucose ergo the way to treat cancer don't eat glucose
the problem with that logic is no matter how little glucose you eat you still have plenty
of glucose in your circulation I mean even if you're in a complete state of starvation again
going back to George Cahill 40 days of starvation they still had three millimole of glucose and
their circulation 40 days out so there is no way to eliminate glucose now an argument could be but
you're going to minimize insulin so I guess the question becomes is minimizing insulin actually
more important than minimizing glucose but the idea of starving cancer seems potentially overly
simplistic right based on everything we've already talked about yeah I think starving cancer is very
very hard and as you say getting circulating glucose to go meaningfully down below you know
the healthy 89 where you last measured yourself is very very difficult and even if you could do
that it's not going to prevent the cancers from having access to internally stored fuel for a while
in the form of glycogen and then ultimately into amino acid fuel and fat fuel and lactate fuel
ketone body fuel and we've shown very clearly that cancer can use all of those things okay so
they're they're all valid inputs they can't replace glucose in the test tube but you know
it's not easy to cut off the cancer fuel supply especially not without cutting off some other
critical fuel supply the immune cell fuel supply right which would be a disaster or the brain fuel
supply which would be an even more acute disaster this idea that there's a way to exploit
the metabolic I don't want to say limitation but I would just say quirk of cancer in a way that
also augments the immune system say a bit more about that because that's both fascinating
intellectually but also elegant in that it's mechanistically in line with a bias I have
which is cancer is really going to be hard to you know get under control so you know hoping for
a stalemate where you use multiple modes of action is probably a better strategy than hitting really
hard on one lever again it's a bias of mine but you know at least I can acknowledge it yeah well
I think we're seeing a lot of moves to try to make cancer into a chronic disease where the therapies
are not so terrible and you know certainly hitting the nucleic acid side of cancer as
line people are trying for you know maintenance therapy and I think we need to think about that
whole side of cancer metabolism fresh because I think there are targets waiting to be developed
there I think you know if they create nucleotide imbalances which is a natural thing to do when
you hit that system then nucleotide imbalances are drivers of mutations and mutations in cancer
cells are drivers of immune response to cancer so that's one very appealing avenue so in other
words interrupt their ability to synthesize DNA they will create more mutations more mutations
is more shots on goal for the immune system exactly so I think that's one really exciting
avenue another exciting avenue is to apply a very strong stress to the cancer while putting
pressure on their fuel supply and so I think it's very hard to think that you're going to put so
much pressure on the fuel supply okay that that alone is going to make the tumor slow or even more
optimistically regress or something but if you come in with chemotherapy for example that's already
targeted preferentially not perfectly right to the tumor and then you pair that with something
like ketogenic diet which is lowering insulin lowering glucose then we at least see in animal
models that this can be a very powerful combination we see that the tumors start to deplete glucose in
response to the chemotherapy whether that's because their vasculature is breaking down
or whether that's because they have heightened glucose demand because they're having mitochondrial
damage from the chemotherapy I'm not sure but we see that chemotherapy lowers glucose in the tumor
intrinsically and then if you come in with a diet that lowers glucose availability this becomes
stronger all right and then you can get to really low tumor glucose and we see pretty big
improvements in outcome in mouse experiments hopefully they'll translate to the clinic we
have a clinical trial open on this now and what's the best tool we have besides the conventional
and maybe it is simply the conventional in terms of ways to inter interfere with their nucleic acid
this is synthesis is it literally just going back to old school chemotherapeutics that do that
well for the moment right yes I mean for the moment hematrexate is probably the most successful
clinical agent but you know uh gemcytobine and uh you know other things of this sort are you know
all well used as part of the armamentarium but I think we need to think fresh I mean I'll say on
this front it's really interesting to me that when we were in medical school you know I thought we
would not see a cure in our lifetimes for hepatitis yeah and look at that and that was
mainly nucleoside analogues I mean I remember being told like there were two things that are
absolutely because I remember talking about this as why can't there be a vaccine for hep c and it's
like you you'll never be able to vaccinate a flavivirus okay well that still turns out to be true
but you'll never cure hep c and yeah lo and behold and this is just nucleoside analogues as
the centerpiece of this right and so the fact that there's clearly untapped potential there
now maybe that potential was maxed out you know 40 years ago uh you know when people were doing
this hardcore for cancer from the cancer but not hepatitis perspective but but my guess is that
that's all chemistry that's evolved a lot and that this is a ripe area for for rediscovery
well it's interesting you mentioned gemcytobine because of course that's you know one of the
first line agents for pancreatic cancer and if I if I'm not mistaken you have a particularly
keen clinical interest in pancreatic adenocarcinoma is that correct
yeah it's the cancer that I've worked on the most uh it's obviously just a horrible disease um you
know it's definitely one of the cancers that gives cancer a bad name it's um it's the fourth leading
cause of cancer death in both men and women and yet by incidence it's a fraction of that right
it's it just speaks to how lethal it is um you know the last time I looked Josh I would say that
adenocarcinoma the pancreas is 95% lethal and I've heard people argue that the 5% who don't die are
misdiagnosed almost suggesting that it's pretty much impossible to survive pancreatic adenocarcinoma
which is the worst thought in the world um so you certainly picked a tough one to study
yeah I mean I feel a very strong commitment to it because of a bunch of reasons and you know but
just the fact that it's so terrible is a motivation and I think it's you know was a disease that for
a long time people it's just so terrible we just give up and you know I don't think that's the
right attitude for terrible diseases and you know I think the one of the hardest things in
making biomedical progress is getting a clinical readout and you know the hidden positive and how
terrible this disease is is the clinical readout is just sitting there itching to be improved and so
there's the capacity to do really compelling clinical tests of any idea and it's a terrible
disease most of these uh you know clinical efforts are going to fail but they can be done
relatively fast relatively cost effectively and we're seeing progress I mean that's what's so
exciting that you know fulfurenox is progress a lot of patients tumors respond even more will
respond if you combine uh two agents that were approved uh gem cytobine and abraxane um which is
albium and balanform apaclitaxel uh with a platinum agent that triple combination
produces regressions in most patients tumors um but they're not durable I mean that's they're
not durable okay but the duration of response is terrible right now but the fact there's response
is promise okay and I think in the anyway normally from my perspective once you can start
seeing response you're on the road we have to figure out how to make the response durable I
hope that's where the metabolic part becomes important it's going to be some interface of
the metabolic part or the immune part or a yet harder hit with you know chemo radiotherapy
earlier diagnosis these are the hopes for for fixing this is there something about pancreatic
adenocarcinoma that you've observed metabolically that is distinct from other gastrointestinal
adenocarcinomas I think you know colon is also a terrible disease liver is also a terrible disease
so all the gastrointestinal you know adenocarcinomas are unfortunately really bad diseases but at least
with those stage one can be I mean certainly stage one colorectal cancer is survivable
a pedocellular is a bit tougher you know you're but you're better than a coin toss but you know
again coming back to pancreatic stage one is 80 to 85 percent not survivable I've always wondered
what is it about pancreatic adenocarcinoma that is so difficult and is it simply that its rate
of early metastasis is so early that stage one is just sort of a misnomer term it's not there's
such a thing as stage one I think that's a big part of it it's kind of a soft organ the pancreas
and you get the it's a very invasive cancer and you can have local invasions so many places from
that site plus immediate access to the portal system that's just seeding the liver constant
it's just seeding the liver and so it's anatomically a really problematic location for keeping the
cancer self-contained so I think the other thing is that you know metabolically it's a very tricky
cancer it's almost solely driven by mutations of the Ras oncogene not saying there aren't other
drivers but almost every patient has this Ras driver and this is an instruction manual for the
cancer cells not just to divide but to do a bunch of metabolic things that involve scavenging
nutrients from the environment and taking in nutrients in non-standard ways and so it actually
instructs the cancer cells to reach out arms pull in nutrients internalize them degrade
macromolecule nutrients from the environment and use this as kind of a garbage recycling form
of nutrient access that that makes them very metabolically pernicious the other thing that
we see that's really interesting in new work and mouse models of pancreatic cancer is that
they don't have to be very metabolically active in order to be horribly lethal so the pancreas
is a master protein producing organ and you may think insulin is most famous protein to come out
of the pancreas right but the bulk of the pancreas is not you know beta cells that make insulin
it's only five percent of it yeah that's right the exocrine is the real gland and the exocrine
pancreas is just making digestive enzymes like crazy it does by far the fastest protein synthesis
in the body the cancer turns that protein synthesis way down so it's not hyper metabolic
it's just that it has this huge capacity to make stuff that even when it turns it down
still has enough biosynthetic capacity to grow and divide and grow and divide
because it's turned down its main energy consuming normal function of protein synthesis it can
function with much reduced tca activity reduced atp synthesis rates and so it's amazing that it's
very efficient then very very efficient so it can turn down all these normal functions and it
still has the capacity to reproduce the cells and make these horribly invasive and metastatic cells
which are ultimately lethal of all the epithelial cancers today for which we don't have a cure which
is almost every one of them right shy of like a gist or something like that or certain testicular
cancers is there one that you're more optimistic about in terms of metabolic approaches to therapy
it's a great question
um
I mean you see pematrex said being used effectively in lung cancer right and I think you see the
cancers with mutational burdens being the ones where you're getting the good immunotherapy
responses whether they're ones that are particularly susceptible intrinsically to metabolic effects
I don't know I don't think that's going to be the standalone heart of treating any of these
cancers I think it's more going to be a key piece of the puzzle in getting enough either drug killing
by preventing their metabolic escape mechanisms or enough immune activity and those may be kind of
opposites so you may need also kind of cyclic therapies where you go through rounds of
metabolic suppression in order to keep things calm while you can and then periods of metabolic
augmentation that are really directed at augmenting the immune system and I'm a big believer that you
know there's metabolic limitations on immune response to cancer and that if we can overcome
them we will have major therapeutic benefits you know you mentioned RAS in the context of
pancreatic carcinoma RAS is rarely immunogenic in the pancreas right it's it's it's a driver
mutation but the immune system it doesn't produce back to the way we started our discussion it
doesn't give us a beautiful little 9 to 11 amino acid peptide it gets presented on an MHC class
molecule right it's a great irony of this whole thing yeah you need more shots on goal you need
more antigens do you have any sense of how many tumor infiltrating lymphocytes are typically
identified at all in resected pancreatic specimens I think it's typically quite the lymphocyte desert
there's a ton of macrophage activity in pancreatic cancer and so I think macrophage
rewiring is going to be you know a big part of allowing lymphocytes to enter
and these are areas where I think metabolism can be quite impactful well Josh this is a
super interesting I hate that we're ending on somewhat a depressing note is there
is there anything more optimistic that we want to talk about than pancreatic adenocarcinoma beyond
you know the statement that hey look you know this is why we have the smartest people working
on the hardest problems but anything else within cancer metabolism specifically that
you think boy 10 years from now like I'm really optimistic that we're going to have a new way to
you know hack into their DNA synthesis pathway in a corrupt manner that just spits out mutations
using kind of novel systems right you know I don't know if andy gets any sense all
like a nucleotide it's like just something that totally disrupts them in a selective manner
you know I think my big hope on this front is that we're going to be able to have some combination of
directed metabolic immune supplements and diet that really work with therapy to treat cancer
I mean cancer is such a discrete disease the clinical trials are so manageable and the fact
that things are metabolically messed up in the tumors so incredibly clear and they're so clearly
messed up in a way that's favoring the wrong kind of immune cells and so ultimately through either
some sort of supplement or diet we're going to be able to reverse that and we're going to make
immunotherapy work instead of for 10 percent of patients for a majority of patients so that's my
uplifting thought for you is that metabolism will be part along with you know you know better
pure immunological therapies of getting immune control of cancer over the coming decade
and besides reducing insulin which is such an obvious strategy are there other metabolic
levers to pull with the diet because really between ketogenic diets and cyclic fasting
those are kind of the two ways that you do that do you see evidence of amino acid restriction
or any other nutrient restriction that could potentially play a role I think amino acids are
you know complicated but they hold a lot of potential I think the type of fat can be important
you know the saturated unsaturated fat are really different and in cancer they're going to play you
know different roles so it's very nice work from Matt van der Heidens lab showing that you know a
higher saturated fat ketogenic diet could be more tumor suppressive in some context because
the tumors have trouble making unsaturated fat in the context of hypoxia say more about that I
wasn't aware of that so Matt I know Matt's worked very well of course is is he still at Dana Farber?
He's at the coke at MIT so he's actually head of the the coke now okay and was this in prostate
cancer this was oh I forget what cancer background he did it and I think it was in pancreatic at least
in part but I'm not 100 sure okay so that's super interesting so a ketogenic diet that was higher in
saturated fat posed a greater problem for the cancer cells because they couldn't make presumably
the essential unsaturated fats exactly so I think this is a interesting strategy I mean those
effects were relatively subtle up to now but you know it could be part of the picture you know I
think the really exciting part of the diet is also the parts that connect to the microbiome so I think
the fiber part really working that out and maybe total protein matters in ways that we don't
understand and needs to be much like you know maybe we need to not just think about cycling
fasting and feeding but cycling you know for example there's a time maybe when you want to
come in with a lot of carbs in the absence of protein and that may achieve something that
creates a particular immune milieu and then you know you need protein in the right timing after
that so there's a lot of things we can do with timing of macronutrients that can be interesting
and it seems like an eternity before we'd be ready to study this in a human clinical trial
because the permutations are so many so do you feel like we have high throughput animal models
where we can test these hypotheses and say you know hey this is one way to do this and
you know or we've looked at 10 ways to do this in animals but these are the three most promising so
we're going to kind of go ahead and do these now. Yeah I think you know the good animal models of
cancer are still not that high throughput and there's a lot of challenges converting animal
diet and human diet right and so you know we'll come out with some work showing that you know
some of the most exciting dietary combinations are absolutely effective in animals but they're not
effective through the mechanisms that people thought before and it's you know it's because the
even in animals trying to get the diets aligned so that you really isolate variables is tough
but I think the fact that we're asking these questions that haven't been asked before
is going to build momentum and we're gonna we're gonna build this interface out over the next
five-year period in animals and we'll do clinical work you know as a field in parallel with that
that has an impact and has an impact on patients lives within the five to ten-year timeline I hope.
Do you worry that the challenges of even if you came up with the right diet so let's just assume
10 years from now the answer is a cyclic ketogenic diet that has this much saturated fat this much
monounsaturated fat this much polyunsaturated fat this much glucose on this day this much protein
on that day like you the formula exists right so this is almost an impossible thing but that
it's impossible to adhere to in the way that you know a pill or a drug or an infusion is much easier
or do you think that in cancer because the stakes are so high adherence will be unlike it is in any
other field of medicine? No we have to make it simple right I mean this has to be clinically
actionable and but you know I would go much more back to the first question that we asked you asked
maybe when I first mentioned the potential of immunotherapy and fiber like is it soluble fiber
is it insoluble fiber and then there really are different flavors of soluble fiber and maybe it's
the gammish of them or maybe it's one in particular maybe it's one isolated molecule
that relates to that and then we have one isolated molecule tiny molecule that will more than double
the number of complete responses you get to immunotherapy and mice one tiny molecule smaller
than glucose okay we already have that as a as a metabolite okay and so I think we're going to get
a to it could almost be simple supplements as opposed to whole cell dietary changes.
Supplements the dietary changes maybe in a very acute way just the way the patient comes in the
hospital for you know tough about a chemotherapy or a tough surgery maybe we're going to go to a
place where we take people's glucose in the hospital almost down to zero for 12 hours you
know with a deep ketosis and some pharmacotherapy at the time that we hit them really hard with
chemo and 24 hours of that it's like night and day in terms of the overall effect but it can't
be asking patients to give up eating and giving up the joy of food or another trial that we're
starting now is a trial with sglt2 inhibitor plus a low carbohydrate but not fully ketogenic diet
to see if it can put people in ketosis and then just looking forward to would this be a convenient
way to get the benefits of ketosis in cancer patients while still allowing them to have a
little bit of you know breaking bread with the family. Last question for you is totally random
I don't know what maybe just think of this Princeton is the only ivy league school that
doesn't have a medical school correct? I think that's right. Is there I mean that there's got
to be a deliberate reason for that it has it's Princeton is fantastic in everything do you do
you know why it doesn't have a medical school and is it just the proximity to Penn or that it was
assumed that there that's where the collaborations would be? I mean Princeton doesn't have a medical
school because at its heart Princeton is a hybrid of a college and a university and it is an
institution that you know has the ultimate priority under undergraduate education it's
committed to that it's best in world in that and so I think
in assessing how to be best in world at undergraduate education the Princeton
administration many times has asked the question is having medicine on campus part of that and the
answer has always been no let's have a somewhat more pure intellectual environment and keep our
focus on doing the very best training for undergraduates and so it's a very conscious
not a business school either and I guess it's the same argument right there's no business school
there's no law school so that's Princeton it makes it very special and it's good to have special
places that are you know distinct I think that's a wonderful thing. Are you at all a fan of Richard
Feynman's work? At a very light level I guess I would say that's the best way to put it. But
there aren't places around Princeton that you go to see where you know he you know what eating
club he was in or things like that you don't you don't you don't look for the old places.
No I'm not I'm not a fan that way I guess there I read the giant biography of Oppenheimer and
they're filming the film of that on campus so Matt Damon was apparently on campus I'm guessing
he's playing Oppenheimer but I haven't checked anyway so but I guess I've become a small Oppenheimer
fan after reading reading that intensive book. I have three of Feynman's books meaning like books
that were actually his so I have his table of integrals from when he was in high school
and then two more advanced calculus books one from when he was at Princeton and then one from
when he was his first professorship professorship at Cornell and that it's just they're sacred to
me right it's like his scribblings like his notes all over these things signed Richard P. Feynman and
like what you know what his address was and things like that so yeah I've never I've never made the
pilgrimage to look for his eating club and things like that it probably doesn't even exist anymore
but I just wondered if you'd been the been on the tour. No but you should come down there definitely
have been some you know awesome Princetonians you know I guess my kids all went nursery school
in the building where von Neumann built the first computer so you know there's it is amazing the
amount of stuff that happened around here. Well Josh so great to see you again and I hope it's
not too long before I see you in person again but really appreciate first of all the amazing work
that you've done over the past 20 plus years and and sitting down to to share it with us today.
That's been fun I appreciate the opportunity.