Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
It is such a pleasure to be at least virtually sitting here with you today. As I was kind of
alluding to a moment ago, if I were to sort of look at all the people I've had on this podcast
so far and kind of ask the question, when was the first time I became familiar with their body of
work, you know, you would be pretty far up there in terms of duration. So, you know, growing up,
you know, endurance sports were always sort of something that meant the world to me. And once I
even made that decision to go to medical school, a big part of it at least was, you know, kind of
understanding physiology better. And so, you know, it's been 25 or 30 years that I've been reading
your studies. So, in some ways, it's a long time coming to finally be sitting down with you and I
hope to meet you in person one day. Peter, thanks much. And it's been great to be able to visit with
you today. Thank you for inviting me. And I'm glad somebody's been paying attention to what I've
been doing for the last 25 or 30 years. So, it's very validating. Thank you. So, let's talk a little
bit about your background. You're a physician by training. I believe you're an anesthesiologist,
correct? Correct. So, tell me a little bit about that. So, you know, you decided in medical school,
you wanted to do anesthesia. Right. But you've always had a lifelong interest in exercise and
exercise physiology. Did you just view anesthesia as the most logical conduit to better understand
human physiology? So, Peter, before I went to medical school, I actually volunteered to be a
subject in a study on the lactate threshold or anaerobic threshold when I was 19 at the University
of Arizona. And luckily there were excellent physiologists there, but a couple of younger
physicians came over from the med school and it became clear to me when I was 19 or 20 that if I
wanted to have a career as a research physiologist doing invasive studies, you know, there was
pretty catheters in people and humans, it might be wise to go to medical school. So, this was always
sort of my vision starting at about age 20 or 21. And then what happened is I was thinking of going
to cardiology or pulmonary medicine. I was working at the Tucson VA at one time doing a
surgery rotation and I saw what they did in anesthesia, which is a lot like an exercise
test. You're measuring people's breathing, you're measuring their blood pressure, their heart rate,
and you're giving them drugs that affect their autonomic nervous system. And I've certainly
done a lot of that. So, I saw it as the flip side of the same coin. And so, it just sort of happened
and it is strange though to have pursued this vision for over 40 years now.
Yeah, I remember having the same thoughts when I did my anesthesia rotation. I can't even remember
if anesthesia was a required rotation in med school. I don't think it was, but it was positioned
as sort of a very good thing to do and I agree with that. And I had a field that even though I
think by that point I knew I was going to go into surgery, but I absolutely loved it. I think as a
physiology geek, anesthesia and critical care for that matter are both two remarkable specialties
that are the tip of the spear of what physiology is. It's interesting too Peter, because
when you think about exercise or people climbing mountains or adapting to some unusual environment,
the brainstem back there has to do all sorts of incredible things to maintain what we call
homeostasis or the internal environment in a way that allows you to survive and thrive.
Well, in anesthesia and critical care, you turn those mechanisms off and the physicians and the
nurses really become the patient's brainstem as they regulate the breathing of the patient,
the blood pressure of the patient, the heart rate and so forth. So, again, it's the flip side of the
same coin. And as soon as I saw what the anesthesiologist did at the Tucson VA, it just sort of
clicked. So, where did you go on to do your residency in anesthesia? So, at the Mayo Clinic,
and so what happened is I got out of medical school in the spring or early summer of
87 and I moved here. I've been here ever since. So, 35 years in a couple of weeks. And so,
where did you grow up? Did you grow up in a warm climate? I grew up in Tucson. So, what, I mean,
obviously the Mayo Clinic's a great program, but presumably there were other great anesthesia
programs that were in the middle of a place like Rochester. No offense to those from Rochester.
So, what drew you to Mayo? Well, I'd read this paper, a review article about skeletal muscle
blood flow, the regulation of skeletal muscle blood flow. And there were a lot of new ideas
in the middle 80s about the regulation of skeletal muscle blood flow. And the world's leading expert
was a man named John Shepherd, who was a very senior member of the faculty here. And I wrote him a
letter and he, you know, it was before email and stuff. So, he was friends with the head of the
department of man named Alan Sessler and John took it over to him. And I wanted to be able to
both do my residency and spend time in the lab and I was able to work with Dr. Shepherd. And our
department and our residency program were very research friendly. So, that's really why I decided
to come to Rochester. But I thought I'd stay, you know, three or four years and go back to Tucson.
So, that obviously didn't happen. I don't see that happening. Yeah. So, let's talk about exercise,
you know. Right. People who listen to this podcast know that I'm really passionate about this idea of
longevity. Right. Think about longevity through the lens of five sort of modifiable behaviors.
Exercise, sleep, nutrition, emotional health and all the tools around distress tolerance
and then exogenous molecules. Those are the five things that as far as I can tell, mostly you can
manipulate. Correct. They can both impact your lifespan and your health span. Four of those are
kind of behavioral. Right. All right. The medications aren't really behavioral in the sense that,
you know, compliance is relatively straightforward. The other ones really require a shift in behavior
and in mindset. And of these, I just, again, maybe we all have our biases in our blind spots,
but I just think exercise is in a league of its own in terms of its potential. Both on the lifespan
axis. So, it, you know, its ability to extend life and reduce all cause mortality is well documented.
We'll talk about that. Right. But also on the health span side, it really has no rival. So,
it's for that reason, I think, that we spend a lot of time inside our practice focusing on exercise.
It is really the biggest pillar within what we do because it has the most impact and unfortunately,
or fortunately, it's also the most challenging one, I think, to get people to change their
existing behaviors around because the time commitment is significant.
So, let's start with some of the basics just for folks who maybe aren't completely up to speed.
What would you say if you're at a party and somebody came up to you and said, Mike, I understand
you're really into this exercise thing. Can you explain to me why it is that exercise helps you
live longer? I think there's a couple of things, Peter, and it's multifactorial. But the first
thing is that, you know, the risk factors that contribute to cardiovascular disease, all more
cause mortality are all influenced by exercise and physical activity. These would be blood pressure,
diabetes, to some extent, lipids and cholesterol, and also how you deal with stress. So, I think
you get the big three there. There are some other kind of new age or second wave risk factors like
endothelial function, the lining of the blood vessels in your body that improve with exercise,
the way what's called your autonomic nervous system, and people may have heard of vagal
tone or heart rate variability. That's also influenced positively by exercise. So, I think
there's five or six things, but what's interesting is when you add up each one, you know, the modest
increase in cholesterol, a modest reduction in blood pressure, those sorts of things,
when you add them up, you get X percent improvement in health, span, life expectancy,
any metric you want to use. But when you look at the epidemiology, people who do the sorts of
things you just mentioned have a much bigger benefit than just the simple sum of the other risk
factors. So, there does seem to be some sort of synergy or some sort of X factor that we don't
really understand yet. But again, yeah, go ahead. No, no, you go ahead. I was just going to say this
collection of lifestyle related factors, which are really critical. And again, the autonomic
nervous system, blood pressure, lipids, the lining of the blood vessels and diabetes would be the big
five. I want to dive into a couple of these in depth. One of the things I would say at the,
before we do so, is, you know, you've thought a lot and you've looked a lot at this literature and
one can say, look, the epidemiology is so overwhelming that it's, I mean, the hazard
ratios are sort of absurd. When we're used to looking at a field like nutrition and looking
at the hazard ratios in nutrition, they're very small. In fact, they're so small and also so
inconsistent that it becomes almost impossible to assign a mortality benefit or addition to almost
anything you can eat. I mean, literally jelly beans to bacon to kale. The hazard ratios are
trivial and they flip flop from month to month. Correct. Well, and yeah, let me tell you something.
It's really interesting. It's good you brought this up. So I'm working on a review article on
related topics. And one of the things I'm looking at is all of what you might describe as natural
experiments, where you have two groups of people that are otherwise similar exposed to different
things. And that's a long, long, long use tool in epidemiology. And people are now using it in
economics and behavioral sciences. And in fact, these natural experiments, the economists just
got a Nobel prize from a couple of years ago. But the classic one is the London bus driver bus
conductor story led by Jeremy Morris after World War II, where they showed the physically active
conductors who were walking up and down the buses all day, had much lower rates of cardiovascular
disease and the sedentary driver bus drivers. And it was about 50%. And they had similar things
with telephone operators versus people who were out walking around doing things. And what's
interesting is you look at that 50%. It's incredibly consistent, incredibly consistent.
Those studies, studies of longshoremen, studies of Harvard alumni, there's one in the last 10 or 15
years of 50,000 male and 25,000 female finishers of the Vasa Lopet 90 kilometer cross country ski
race in Sweden. And they compared them to match controls from the Swedish record system. And they
showed again, about a 50% reduction in cardiovascular and all cause mortality. There's data from the
National Cancer Institute showing the same sorts of things and showing, you know, four or five or
six year increase in life expectancy, you know, among the people who got a substantial amount of
physical activity or structured exercise, either one. Yeah. And I think the sort of take home
point for the listener is unlike nutritional epidemiology, where the risk increases and risk
reductions are very, very small and they're never consistent, right? I mean, there's some things
that are consistent and consistently small. For example, you know, vegetarians consistently have
a small reduction in mortality, which of course then gets to the next point, which is what are
the confounders? And this is where I want to kind of talk about it with exercise. And this is where
the natural experiments are much better on the exercise front than they are in the nutrition
front. You see, going back to the example you gave, which is a very famous one of the guys running up
and down the buses, the sort of conductor guys versus the drivers. That's a great natural
experiment because it's really not amenable to a choice. And you would be less likely to believe
that the bus driver who sits there is also making poor choices relative to the other guy when he's
not at work. In other words, we wouldn't really have a reason to believe that he's more likely to
be a smoker. He's more likely to eat, you know, make poor food choices, etc. Whereas when you look
at sort of the vegetarian to non-vegetarian dietary pattern in nutrition, it's pretty clear
that a vegetarian diet is very restrictive diet. And therefore, the person who's making that choice
is likely very health conscious in a number of other ways. Correct. Yeah, they have a suite of
behaviors. Yeah, exactly. Some of which are easy to measure and correct for like smoking,
but many of which are not. And that sort of makes the nutritional thing harder.
The exercise thing is pretty profound. So let's explain to people what it means
when you have a hazard ratio of 0.5, which means a 50% reduction in all-cause mortality. What's the
time frame that that's usually looking at and how does that translate to, you know, a five-year
increase in life expectancy? The way you would say it is that, you know, the relative risk of
dying of heart disease in any given period of time, whether it's year, five years, 10 years,
whatever the study is doing is 50% lower. But obviously not everybody dies of cardiovascular
disease. People die of other things. And so then you have to translate that into sort of years of
life gained. And typically the years of life gained are somewhere on the order, if you account
for smoking of three to five years, something like that. And then if you look at the concept
of health span, you know, you may get six or eight years of improved health span. So health
span, as you know, Peter, is how long you can, you know, how disability free you are. And so you
have, you know, four or five-year increase in life expectancy and a four or five-year additional
increase in health span. And the idea, you know, is to live a long time and then die quickly
with minimal disability. So kind of one of the ways we try to get around this idea of the sort
of vagueness of freedom from disease and disability is to make it very, very granular. And we do this
by creating this model we have called the centenarian decathlon, which says, if you go out to your
marginal decade, and we define the marginal decade as the last decade of your life. So again, we don't
know when that is, but let's just make the math easy and say, oh, that's going to be 79 to 89 or
81 to 91. You're in your marginal decade. What are sort of the athletic events and the activities
of daily living that you want to be able to do? But we do it by making people cross off things they
do not want to do. So we make this a you have to opt out of things. Right. And they're very
specific, right? So it's like walking three miles in one hour, you know, being able to climb
X number of stairs, you know, 60 stairs that are eight inches in one minute, being able to carry
20 pounds of groceries a certain distance, being able to get up off the floor with at most one hand
of support. So it's very specific stuff. And I think for most people, the initial reaction is
well, that's really easy. Like I can do most of these things today. But, you know, when you're a
45 year old reading that, I hope that's easy. I don't think they appreciate the precipitous decline
that will occur without deliberate training. And it's for that reason that I think exercise has
more potential to offset all of those things than anything else. Sleep, nutrition, certainly any
medication. And so that to me, that's really what health span comes down to. It's right. It's not
just I'm not disabled, but it's I'm really thriving. Yeah, I'm engaged. I can engage in what
I want to engage in. Yeah. And I think Peter, you've hit the nail on the head. And I think that
what we see in those decades, there's what's really instructive is if you look at the decline
in performance in age group, swimming, running, cycling, rowing, really any sport where there's
pretty good record keeping is people can start to decline at age 30 without training. You can push
that back to age 40 with training. In other words, if you work out every day intentionally and
relatively hard. But then something happens to people in their middle seventies where there seems
to be a, you know, kind of a more steeper rise. And what's interesting about that steeper rise is
it seems to shift from sort of a cardiopulmonary limitation to sort of a skeletal muscle strength
slash frailty situation. And what you described in terms of getting up off the floor, it makes
up like 70 year, 70 percent of 70 year olds can't get off the floor, not one hand, two hands just
can't get off the floor. And you start looking at, and we both know from, from being doctors,
if you look at what happens when a person in that age group falls, it's just no fun.
So, so if you look at it, what really takes people out, it's things like falls, it's inability to,
to, to, to do things. And so what happens is, is, is, you know, walking three miles in an hour
takes some cardiopulmonary capability, but not a ton, just some. But whereas being able to go,
you know, the stairs takes more being able to get off the floor takes more.
So I think one of the things that people have to think about, especially as they get into their
40s and 50s is, is adding strength or some sort of circuit training and agility training to their
program. And so I think you've hit the nail on the head. And one of the things I do is, is I'm 63,
I'm almost 64, is I have the jump rope my mother gave to me when I was 14. She gave me a beautiful
boxer's jump rope, leather with ball bearings in the works, you know, and I carry it with me when
I travel because you can always jump rope, even if it's out in the parking lot of a hotel, you can,
people think you're nuts, but it's a, you know, but it works. It's a terrific, terrific exercise.
It actually is for a number of reasons, including foot reactivity, which is also one of those things
that can control, you know, the lack of foot reactivity is something that can contribute to the
fall. So you're, you're getting the cardio benefit, the coordination benefit, and also this, this,
this gentle foot reactivity without, and it depends if you know how to skip like a boxer,
you don't have to really pound your knees as well. Correct. And the other thing is you do that with
some body weight, you know, some, some things as simple as pushups or, or planks, since there's a
place to do some pull ups, you're good to go. Yeah. There's so many things you said there,
Mike, that I want to go back on and just make sure people really capture, because it's so important.
There's, and I will probably find the study and I'll link to it, but there's an amazing study that
demonstrates like muscle mass changes, strength changes, activity changes in men and women as they
age. And it's one of those things where you don't actually need to understand the statistics to be
able to see the figure. And it's exactly as you describe it at the age of 75, there is a cliff
that is so violent, you can't believe what you're watching. And it's at that cliff where physical
activity level declines like this. It just goes boom. Muscle mass goes boom, strength, boom, same
thing. And, you know, of course it begs the age old question, right? Is the patient losing strength
because they are no longer active or are they no longer active because they have lost strength?
My view is it's both. I think these things feed off each other. Which one's the first insult?
I suspect it's probably the loss of strength that contributes to the loss of activity. But then I
think those feedback and accelerates this thing. You really get into a death spiral. And I think
that's why it becomes important to keep exercising relatively hard as you get over at least a few days
a week to slow this decline. And there are remarkable examples. There are some Swedish
cross-country skiers, men who were world and Olympic champions in the 40s and 50s.
Who remained active as many of them were woodsmen and lived in the countryside. Remained very active
skiing and so forth. They were studied in their 80s. Now you could argue that there was something
special about these guys to begin with or they would not have become champion athletes. But their
rates of decline were quite modest. And more importantly, their fitness levels were similar
to what you would see in people in very early middle age. The other interesting thing about
that is the classic studies from the 1960s. These fighter pilots, Navy and Marine and Air Force fighter
pilots were sitting in the outer space. These were incredibly fit guys. They'd go up for a week and
come back completely atrophy. Couldn't stand up. And really in bad shape. And in 66, NASA commissioned
folks at the University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center in Dallas to put five college-age
males, two athletes, at bedrest. And they had tremendous reductions in their fitness over just
three weeks of bedrest. And interestingly, Ben Levine and his group in Dallas, along with the
late Jerry Mitchell, brought these same men back 30 years later. So now they were early 50s. And
it's incredible, but three weeks of bedrest caused losses of physiological function associated with
30 years of aging. So it's an incredible study. And that's one of the things that is instructive.
Those sorts of small studies. And that's why it's so important to just avoid inactivity
of any type. And whether it's low grade physical activity, whether it's walking the dog,
whether it's gardening, whether it's taking a flight of stairs once in a while, or intentional
working out, it's really the way to go. And as you point out, really, in those lifestyle factors,
you mentioned really sort of overwhelms things. Over overwhelms almost everything else.
Yeah. You mentioned and alluded to the danger of a fall in later life. And this is something we've
been doing a lot of research on internally, given our concern around bone mineral density and the
population. The mortality, when you look at 65 year olds and up who suffer a fall that results
in the fracture of any part of the hip or femur at one year, depending on the study, it can be
as low as 25% as high as 60%. Yeah, the magic number is usually around 40, 50. Yeah. Again,
I want people to understand what we just said. You take all the 65 year olds and you look at
those who fall and the fall results in a broken hip or femur. And you ask the question, how many
of those people will be alive in 12 months? The answer is half of them. Correct. Correct. And the
other half, it's not like the other half are... Yeah, they're not back to themselves necessarily.
No, exactly. And that's exactly right. So you want to avoid a major health like that for sure.
The other thing, Peter, there's a couple other things that have really hit me
as we've talked. One is this man named Lester Breslow, who was this very famous epidemiologist
who died in his late 90s, was at UCLA for many years. And he studied people in Oakland in the
late 50s and early 60s who made it to 90. And the sorts of four or five things you talked about,
he identified the people in Oakland who made it to 90 and they were non-smokers. They weren't
obese. They remained physically active. They ate modestly. They stayed engaged in life. And there
were just five or six things that they did. And the same is true in the Honolulu Heart Project,
when they've looked at a huge number of Japanese American males, same exact stuff that you mentioned.
Not so they weren't as focused on the small molecules, but exactly what you've described.
And then I think about, we've talked about natural experiments. At the Cooper Clinic,
they've looked at people's fitness levels. Now that's not exactly the same as physical activity,
but in general, the fittest people are also the most active. And they divided people into three
or four groups of fitness and then had them look at a so-called healthy eating index. So, you know,
were you a junk food junkie to eat okay, or were you really conscious of your diet? And the healthy
eating index in people that weren't particularly fit did have something to do with all cosmortality.
But among the fittest people, there was very little impact of diet on the outcomes,
which is sort of interesting. And it always brings me back to the famous quote in a book about
distance running called Once a Runner, where somebody said, yeah, if the furnace is hot
enough, you can burn anything even big max. Now you have to take that with a grain of salt, but,
or I guess we're worried about diet, maybe not a grain of salt, but I think it does kind of give
you the take home message. But just about what a powerful thing exercise is.
I completely agree. And I know it's very, there's a very common mantra that says, oh,
you can't outrun a bad diet. And I would argue that's probably not true. I think you can outrun
a diet, but it's pretty hard to do. And most people don't understand the amount of running
that's needed to do it. That's great because, you know, again, I'm looking up these studies.
So I've looked at these classic studies like that. And so, so there's this incredible study
from the fifties of people who worked at a jute plant in India, and they categorize people on
incredibly physically active, you know, doing manual labor, hacking away on jute to make,
I think, linen or rope. They're going to make rope with this stuff all the way to office workers.
And as you got more and more physically active, people got lighter, you got more inactive,
they got heavier. But what was interesting is, is people that were in the middle, middle kind of
rung of occupational physical activity also had slightly lower caloric consumption remain very
trim. So certainly, you know, if people are physically active enough, if you read the old
papers about what lumberjacks were eating, you know, when they were chopping wood all day long,
I mean, it's five, six thousand calories a day. The old order Amish who walk around and do manual
labor all day long and don't have, you know, don't have tractors and stuff like that, they eat an
awfully lot and very few of them are obese. So, so I think you can't outrun a bad diet or can't
out exercise a bad diet in a modern high calorie, low physical activity world, I think is the caveat
that has to go to that one. Yeah. And yet when you look at athletes that are doing insane amounts
of exercise, most of them have a hard time keeping on weight. Well, there's, yeah, there's terrific
study about the Tour de France, you know, where they get done every day and they're just handing
them food. And, you know, these people are eating ad lib, except when they're on the bike and even
when they are on the bike and they have a hard time and they're eating 6,000 calories a day,
they weigh about 150 pounds. Yeah. And they have a hard time keeping their weight. Yeah.
They are catabolic throughout the Tour. Correct. They finish in pretty bad shape.
Correct. They look like, you know, you know, well, not, not death camp survivors, but people who
certainly haven't had a lot to eat for a few weeks. So let's go back to something you said at the
outset, which was the impact of exercise on the autonomic nervous system. Correct. Explain to folks
what the autonomic nervous system is, how it differs from the sympathetic nervous system
and why it plays such an important role in our health. And of course, how exercise impacts it.
When we think about the nervous system, normally we think about our brain, our eyes, our ears,
and in our senses, and also our ability to grab things, move our muscles, that sort of thing.
And, you know, feel pain or feel heat or cold or, or, or, or sense the environment. But your autonomic
nervous system is what controls your internal environment. And, and that's called the, you know,
the Malou internal or whatever is, is from the French a long, long time ago. And it's called
homeostasis. So, so, you know, we can increase our metabolism 10 or 20 fold with exercise,
but our, our body temperature only rises a degree or two. And so this happens due to the actions of
the autonomic nervous system. Now there are two branches of the autonomic nervous system. There's
this sympathetic nerves and the parasympathetic nerves. And these used to be kind of categorized
as fight or flight. And you would either, you know, activate, especially the sympathetic nerves,
if you needed to fight, fight or fly, run away. And whereas the parasympathetic nerves were seen
as what happened when you were asleep, when you're digesting your food, so on and so forth.
But it turns out there's kind of more of a balance in the yin and yang between the two that happen
all the time. But the parasympathetic nerves, and the most notable one is the vagus, they control
part of your heart rate, make your heart rate slower. They also tend to lower blood pressure
and they're critical to digest your food. And that's one side. The other side is the autonomic
nervous system nerves that increase your heart rate, stimulate your blood vessels to constrict,
help your muscles contract harder, and also do things like make you sweat. And so that's,
that's really the difference between the autonomic or the parasympathetic and sympathetic
branches of the autonomic nervous system. And the key thing to remember is that they help you
regulate the internal environment. And that exercise really keeps these things tuned up.
And by having your autonomic nervous system a bit better tuned up, it can do a better job
regulating your internal environment. The classic example being for example, your blood pressure.
Now, of course, what everybody knows, and we're going to talk in a moment about VO2 max testing
and how that's done, because I want to get into the weeds on that. But when we have our patients
tested, you know, we have a protocol, we look at their blood pressure before, and then we look at
their blood pressure throughout. And then we want to look where they are percentile wise,
at the max exertion, what's their blood pressure. And without exception, a person's blood pressure
goes up when we do a VO2 max test. So you take somebody whose blood pressure is 115 over 75,
at the outset, they'll easily be 160 over 95 or 100. And that's completely normal and healthy.
Even higher if you measured it while they're weightlifting.
Yeah, exactly. So explain to folks why it is that during exercise, nothing looks good, right? Blood
pressure is high, heart rate is high, heart rate variability is low. What is it about the recovery
phase from exercise that produces a net positive effect, even though in the moment exercise,
presumably is doing things that are not necessarily in our body's best interest in that moment?
I would say they are in their best interest because what happens Peter is the system
shifts a little bit to kind of meet the demands of the skeletal muscle.
You got to be able to contract the muscles to exercise. And again, that's sort of consistent
with the fight or flight thing. If you're going to run away or be in a fight, you want to be able
to contract your muscles. And so to do that, you need to send more blood flow to those muscles.
And one of the ways you do that is by increasing your blood pressure, more blood pressure equals
more flow. And the other thing you got to do is increase the pumping function of your heart.
At rest, people's heart is beating about five liters or a little over a gallon a minute.
During moderate exercise, it can be 10 liters a minute. During heavy exercise, 15 or 20.
And elite athletes who are very trained and have very large hearts, it can be 30 or 40 liters a
minute. So what happens is you're pumping all that blood out against these blood vessels. And so your
blood pressure rises. So it's a completely normal thing to think about and to generate that large
cardiac output. Cardiac output is heart rate times stroke volume. That's the amount with each
squeeze of the heart. And so naturally, you're going to want to increase your heart rate.
So that's what happens. But then when you stop, as you mentioned, heart rate falls, blood pressure
falls, and things look probably better than they did in somebody who is untrained and hasn't
exercised. What do we know about the rate of recovery? Like there's something called heart
rate recovery, HRR, that is a pretty interesting metric. Tell us what we know about HRR.
So people do a maximum exercise test and their heart rates 150, 160, 180, whatever their age is.
220 minus your age is an interesting number, but there's a lot of patient to patient or person to
person variability. So what happens is how fast does your heart rate go back down to some number?
How fast does it get to under 100? How fast it goes back to baseline? Whatever.
So the faster it goes down, the faster it goes down, the better the action of your
vagal nerve, the nerve that slows your heart rate. The vagus nerve is also responsible mostly for
your heart rate variability. And that means that, and this nerve also suppresses funny heartbeats
and is protective when it's in good shape against arrhythmias and ventricular tachycardia,
ventricular fibrillation, sudden death, all of those things. And so heart rate recovery,
heart rate variability, all of those things are indirect markers of what we call vagal tone or
vagal activity. And that's a good thing. Now heart rate variability can be quite genetic, right Mike?
The absolute number in milliseconds between any two individuals can be quite distinct. And it
seems to be not nearly as modifiable as some other factors. Have you found that to be the case?
You know, I would say, again, it depends on what sorts of training people have been doing,
what they've been exposed to. But in general, most people can get a nice training-braided
cardia, which again is vagal tone. And most people if they're trained can go from slow
heart rate recovery to faster heart rate recovery and also have more heart rate variability. So I
think worrying about the differences in the initial baseline period while interesting and
what they might be attributable to is probably less important than the fact that they're
modifiable as you mentioned very early, you know, as they say at the top of the show.
Yeah. So let's talk about this VO2 max test because we're going to talk about what it means
and, you know, how predictive it might be of an individual's mortality. So let's just start by
explaining to people what you do when a person comes into the lab.
Right. So what you do is you get them on a bike or a treadmill, you put some EKG electrodes on them
and they either run on the treadmill or ride a bike and they have a nose clip on if you're
going to measure it directly and either a face mask or a mouthpiece that they breathe.
And that allows us to measure how much oxygen they breathe in or air they breathe in,
how much air they breathe out. We know that the air has 21% oxygen coming in. If we measure the
amount of oxygen in the expired air, we can make an estimate of how much oxygen has been consumed.
And so what happens is when people start to exercise, they go from using about
three and a half mls per kg per minute. So think about, you know, or maybe 250 mls or 300 mls,
so like 10 or 12 ounces of oxygen per minute. Right. And an unfit, you know, person in their
30s or 40s can typically increase that about eight or tenfold to say, to say 30 or 35.
Yeah. To 30 or that would be, that would be 30 or 35 or about three liters a minute.
Right. And with training, most people can increase things at least 10 or 20%.
And if you have some ability and or you train very hard, some people can almost double it.
And so what happens is that once your VO2 max goes up again, just like physical activity,
it's a measure of physical fitness and it's also linked to all cause mortality. So people,
the fitter you are, the lower your chance of dying in the next year or two years, five years,
ten years. And it's it for many years, they thought that things sort of plateaued at what they call
about 10 or 12 met. So met mean you're resting metabolic rate. So you had to be able to get 10
10 mats and 10 mats is being able to run one mile in about 10 minutes, roughly for the average
person. And now people have shown a group in Henry Ford in Detroit have shown that that continues
to rise even up to 1516 met. So people that are quite fit continue to gain, you know, benefit in
terms of all cause mortality. I mentioned the cross country skiers earlier. And while they didn't
do VO2 max tests in those people, the people who had completed the most races and done the races
the fastest. So people who had both been active for the longest period of time and probably were
the fittest also had lower lower all cause mortality than people who had not not compared
to sedentary peers, but compared to people who've done a few races a little bit slower.
So yeah, peak fitness matters. Yeah, when we look at that, that there's a paper in JAMA that I think
is by far the most compelling description of this phenomenon. A couple things are noteworthy about
it. I've talked about this on a previous AMA, because it's it's really one of the I would
consider it one of the 10 most influential papers that I have read in terms of changing how I think
about, you know, health span and lifespan. As you said, the relationship is monotonic,
and it does not plateau. So it's that's that's an important thing to to appreciate, which is,
this is a more is better phenomenon. And very few things in physiology are more is better. Yeah,
usually physiology behaves in use and upside down use or maybe J's and things like that.
Or, or, or, you know, a shake or whatever. Correct. Exactly. Sigmoid curves. But this is not the
case here. This study that we're talking about put people into the bottom 25th percentile,
you know, 25th to 50th percentile, 50th to 75th. And then the last group, it basically divided into,
you know, 75th to 97 and a half. And then they had that little sliver of people that they called
elite that were at the top two and a half percentile. And all cause mortality just went lower and lower
and lower. Correct. And if you looked at the hazard ratio the other way, because we often think about
hazard ratios and risk reduction. But if you look about it in risk increase, when you compared
the people in the top two and a half percent of the VO two max to the bottom 25 percent,
the hazard ratio moving in that direction was five point zero four. My memory serves correctly.
That means there's a five fold increase in all cause mortality between the fittest two and a half
percent and the least correct 25 percent. And even when you took something less extreme, I believe
if you looked at the least fit 25 percent to the third quartile. So the 50th to the 75th percentile,
the hazard ratio was still about just just below three. I think it was two point seven five ish,
which was kind of right on par with the increase in mortality that you would see from having end
stage renal disease, which is by the way greater than the hazard ratio associated with smoking.
Yeah. No, no. Being unfit is an incredible risk factor. You know, and people like Frank Booth
have argued that it should be, you know, for lack of a better word, the risk factor. And Jill Barnes,
one of my fellows at the time, she's now at the University of Wisconsin, a faculty member, she and
I wrote a editorial for Mayo Clinic Proceedings that maybe five, ten years ago where we said,
look, if people had, you know, twelve, thirteen, fourteen met peak exercise capacity other than
doing cancer screening, you could probably just ignore everything else. You know, I mean, and
that's a little bit I don't think anybody's ready to go there. The sorts of people who do health
screening and that sort of thing. But if you screen people for physical fitness and again,
just did the routine kind of cancer screening and you can even argue that you could probably cut
back on the routine cancer screening for most things, except for skin cancers because fit people
tend to be outside of it more. You can make that argument. Yeah. Make it with a straight face and
the data is there to support it. And I would belt and suspenders it and say, but look, I'd still do
the cancer screening. I'd still consider aggressive lipid management and things like that. But
you're absolutely right. I mean, there's really no intervention that we have that's going to rival it.
Well, and I think, I think you mentioned limpets, Peter, and I think there's a couple of things
you got to remember. One, especially for people who pick it up late in life, you know, exercise
is not a vaccine. And one of the most incredible studies ever done, again, we're talking about
these sort of one in of one experiment of nature sorts of things is there was a man named Clarence
DeMar. He won the Boston marathon seven times. He was born, I think in 1888 or 1890. Also won
a medal in the 24 Olympics, got a bronze medal in the marathon. And he really is almost like master
athlete number one. So he kept training his whole life, ended up dying, I think, of stomach cancer
at about age 70. So he didn't live to be a gazillion. But remember, he was born in, in, in
1888 or 1890. Anyways, Paul Dudley White, a famous cardiologist, we know him from something
called the Wolf Parkinson White syndrome, a weird kind of funny heart people get. He did an
autopsy on DeMar. And he'd run really until very late in life. And he had some plaque or, you know,
fatty builds up and calcium buildup in his coronary arteries. But his coronary arteries were huge,
were just massive. And subsequent to that, a man named Bill Hasglout at Stanford in the middle 90s
studied a bunch of ultra people who've done ultra marathons and they did the same thing,
except this time they put catheters in injected drugs to make the blood vessels expand. And they
showed the blood vessels were bigger and they expanded more. So, so again, while you could still
have some blockages, even if you exercise, and there are people with horrible lipids who do,
in fact, get heart disease in spite of exercise. So it's not a complete, you know, complete vaccine,
but it's overall protective effect is quite large, both in terms of what it does to people's
lipids, but the fact that the blood vessels get so much bigger and the linings of the blood vessels
are healthier. Mike, one of the things that we've looked at a lot internally is the literature that
argues a different point, the literature that argues that in fact, there's a J curve here.
And we all agree that a person who doesn't do anything is at the highest risk. The
literature is so unambiguous there, it doesn't warrant any further discussion. But now let's
now look at the addition of work. Now you and I, I just want to make sure that the listener
understands the way we're going to talk about this. Let's talk about these in met hours per week.
So you've already done a great job explaining. A weird, a weird.
Oh, I've actually had to convert my own training into a met hour per week spreadsheet so that I
can interpret what I do in the context of all the literature. A weird metric for sure. Totally
weird. But let's explain to people what is. So you've told us what a met is. One met is the
metabolic expenditure of sitting at rest, which corresponds to about 3.5 milliliters per minute
per kilogram of minute ventilation. So, or actually VO2, so oxygen ventilation, not pulpit
Okay. So then let's talk about how that ramps up, right? So if you, if, how many
Mets is it, Mike, to walk three miles in an hour? That's, that's probably four, five, six,
something like that. I don't know. Okay. I would have guessed. It may, it may be,
because, because remember, remember a 10 minute mile is, is, is 10 Mets. Okay.
Seven mile, six miles in an hour. Yeah. And that's pretty nonlinear. So yeah, yeah,
yeah, you're right. It's probably about three or three to four Mets. I would guess would be
something like that. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. And then of course, as you noted to run a tent to run a six,
six miles in an hour would be 10 Mets. So let's say you did that. So you, you went out and ran,
you ran six miles in an hour for an energy expenditure of 10 Mets. So that would be 10
Met hours. You did 10 Mets times one hour. And if you did that four times a week,
and that was anything you did, you'd be at 40 Met hours per week. Correct. Of activity.
So I do this for my training. So I, I spend how much time am I on the bike at this many Watts,
at this many Watts and in the room and, you know, carrying my rucksack and, you know, I'm sort of in
the hundred met hours per week category. Correct. So if you look at the literature,
the epidemiology on this, it would say my mortality risk might be higher. That would be the headline
than someone who's doing 40 Met hours per week. In other words, it's a J curve. So it sort of starts
up here highest mortality at nothing mortality comes down sort of naders, depending on the study
between 50 and 75 met hours per week. And then the mortality tends to climb. Now, you know, I won't go
into this in great detail other than we've, we've looked at every one of these papers and we find
significant fault in each of them. What do you see? Not all of them, not all of them say that,
not all of them say that in the sense that some, yeah, the big NCI study was 650,000 patients
or subjects didn't say that. And again, you know, what I really like is that, that, that cross
country ski paper that I mentioned from Scandinavia and, and these, you know, if somebody's going to
ski 90 kilometers and if they're going to do it year after year and they're going to do it fast,
they're going to have to be trained a lot. You're going to have to be training a lot. You're going
to be training year around. You almost are certainly getting all sorts of met hours.
And, and, and training pretty hard. Now the one caveat in all this is, is that,
and I agree with you completely. I don't think the evidence for a J curve is particularly good.
The other thing is in many of these studies, the number of people that are way out there is very
small. So even one decimited gets hit by a car or something. It can make a difference. That's
certainly one of the problems with a study from Mike Copenhagen, as I recall, or Norway,
but one of the Scandinavian capitals. And, and again, so I really think that the dispositive
study here is the real world data from, from the Vaselopet story. Now the one thing that does happen
is, is that people do have at least an apparent increase in risk of atrial fibrillation.
And now there's two, there's two, a couple of caveats to that. The first thing is they do not
have any increased risk of fatal arrhythmias. I mean, atrial fib is no fun, but it, but it certainly
can, you know, lead to medical problems, but not typically to kill you. The sorts of things that
kill you ventricular arrhythmias, these are not seen in any, to any greater extent in these people
that are, you know, really heavy exercises for their entire life. So then the question becomes,
do these people actually have more atrial fibrillation or is it just that they're exercising
and notice it? And, and that's the controversy. I think, I think you would probably have to say
that people who, who train the way you're talking about for, for their entire life have some
increased risk of atrial fib compared to people that are just super healthy otherwise and, and
physically active at that 50 to 70 met hour per week thing you're talking about or level you're
talking about, but your risk of atrial fibrillation is still probably lower than people who are
sedentary, hypertensive, obese, diabetic, and so forth. And there are good treatments for atrial
fibrillation and you continue to be protected against fatally arrhythmias. So, so I think that,
that that's the one caveat. I think that where there, the evidence is, is, is better than marginal
this atrial fib story. And what do you think about sort of myocardial fibrosis? There's,
there's been some talk about that. Do we, do we, do we see compelling evidence to suggest?
No, I think in fact, you see, you see the opposite. If you look at people who've been,
if you look at, you get the data from a Ben Levine's group down in Dallas where they've
done a bunch of echoes and loaded the heart and done all kinds of things. And they show that,
that, that young fit, young people have very flexible, compliant heart muscles. And they
show that that declines with age, but, but doesn't decline nearly so fast in people that are either
habitual exercises or people who remain master athletes or remain highly competitive. So again,
I think that you can, you can talk yourself into these sorts of things through a case report here,
a case report there. But when you look at the sort of data that came from Ben's lab
and, and other things, you see that, that, that this sort of training keeps the ventricles
compliant, flexible, and, and able to handle the, the, the, you know, the increased demands and
pumping demands of exercise. So I think the fibrosis argument's a little spurious. I think
we've, we've talked a little bit earlier about the large coronary arteries in people that are
habitually physically active. We've talked that those arteries vasodilate better. They probably
are less likely to generate a clot. And then we've just simply said, and you're protected against
fatal arrhythmias. We've just simply said there may be a subtle increased risk in atrial fibrillation,
but again, good treatments for atrial fib. And so, so I think, I think you're in good shape. I think
in that regard, doing as much as you do Peter. And I think then the other thing to remember is that,
that, you know, it's not, it's not a, an absolute vaccine or an absolute, you know, you work out
an hour a day, you're never going to get, have heart disease, but, but I think your risk is going
to be dramatically reduced as, as we've discussed throughout the visit so far. The other thing I
think that argues in favor of, sorry, argues against the J curve is the VO2 max data that we
just discussed, which is an enormous cohort, probably the largest cohort after Copenhagen
cohort and far more balanced in terms of the number of people in each group. And has been
repeated in other populations. Yeah. And so, so there you have to ask the question, how is it
that people in the top 2.3% of the population for VO2 max have the lowest mortality by a wrong shot
if they're not training significantly? Correct. Because I, you know, I, if you, I look at,
I know those numbers very well. I mean, we, we, we put all of our patients up against that template
and we show them where they are and where we want them to be. And we actually hold them to an even
higher standard, Mike, we kind of want our patients to be at the elite level for a decade below where
they are actually are age wise. Correct. And I'll tell you in a moment why we do that. I want to see
if you agree with my logic, but I just, you know, having been training my whole life, I can tell you,
I don't see how you're going to get there doing 40 met hours per week. Like you can't achieve a VO2
max of that level, just doing a little bit of, you know, maintenance stuff here and there. I mean,
you have to be training. Yeah, you have to be training. You have to be doing some high intensity
training. So I agree with you. And, and the other thing is if you look at some classic studies by
people like Bob Hickson and more recently, Wisloff's group up in Norway, you know, people who do some
longer intervals three or four times a week can get a lot of bang for their buck in terms of VO2 max.
Well, I'm going to, I'm going to come back to that, Mike, because I want to talk very
specifically about the different modalities for training. Before I do, I want to see if you can
check my logic on this. Okay, sure. A big part of where we come up with the reason you want to have
a high VO2 max when you're young is we want to be able to prepare for the inevitability of decline.
So I want to start by just asking you, what is the most up to date understanding of how much
peak VO2 declines in, and let's do it in a non-training individual and a training individual.
So, so if you look at, if you look at it this way, so, so in general, people think VO2 max declines
about 10% per decade, starting in the fourth decade. So sometime in your thirties, you know,
some people say nine, some people say 12, some people say eight, but roughly 10%. All right.
A lot of that is driven by a age-related decline in heart rate, but in people that are not training,
it's driven just because their heart can't pump as much blood and their muscles can't use it.
So among people who are training, you start at a higher level. And then if people continue to
train, you probably don't see a big decline until your late thirties or early forties. And we see
that among athletes because there are world-class endurance athletes in the early forties. And then
you can reduce the rate of decline by about half up to certainly up to your seventies probably.
Now, not everybody keeps training hard. And if people stop training, their VO2 max falls
precipitously. Dr. Dave Costell, really one of the founders of exercise physiology in the United
States, studied a lot of elite athletes in the sixties and seventies. He brought them back to
his lab when these guys in the nineties, 1990s, when they were in their late forties and fifties.
And about a third of them had continued to train very hard and had minimal reductions in their VO2
max. A third had become sort of joggers, had some reduction. And there was a third that had just
stopped doing anything and they looked like regular sedentary people. So you do have to stay at it.
So I think that, and there's a group of master athletes in, out in the LA area were studied,
same sorts of things. People declined and their VO2 max declined. But among the people who, who
continued to train intensely. And in the case of the men do some strength training,
their VO2 max declined at a much lower rate. So, so, so you have a situation where it's 10%
if you do nothing, you know, somewhere in, and if you really work at it and stay,
stay with it at a really high level, it's, it's, you know, maybe five or 6% per decade.
But most people who've been super competitive can't quite keep doing that their entire life.
So they drop off a little bit. But even if they drop off 10% per decade, they started a much higher
baseline. So if your baseline is 60 versus 35 and you lose 10% per decade, you're still going to be
way, way, way ahead, way ahead. And at age 60 or 70, you're going to have a VO2 max value higher,
higher than, you know, 30 year old. So the reason we push so hard, Mike, for our patients to have
as high a VO2 max possible as possible when they're in their forties and fifties is based
on this inevitability of decline and with the hopes that we're extending life by a decade. So that,
hey, even though actuarially you might only be expected to live to 81, we're kind of hoping
you're going to get to 91. Correct. And if you say you want to be active, then we have to reverse
engineer what that means. So what do you think is the VO2 max above which you have absolutely no
limitation on any normal person's activities? In other words, if you said to me, hey, look,
when I'm in my eighties, I want to be able to do pretty much anything reasonable. I don't have to
run a five minute mile. But what I do want to be able to do is I want to go on a hard hike.
And if that means I got to climb 100 feet in half a mile, so be it. Well, Peter, that's a
great question. It goes back to one of your earlier comments about, you know, your scale versus the
traditional kind of anti frailty scale. And what do you want to not be able to do when you're 85 or
whatever the magic number is? So if you look at it, 14 Mets, which is which is 14, a VO2 of 14
mls per kg per minute or four Mets, four Mets is required from an oxygen consumption sort of
perspective for people to do their activities of daily living, which means an occasional somewhat
brisk walk for a few minutes and be able to kind of get around the house, go to the supermarket and
be quote, independent, whatever that means. And now if you want to be able to run, you know,
10 a mile in 10 minutes, that would be 35 VO2 max. Yeah. Yeah. 35 or 10 Mets. Now, so somewhere
between those two are the magic numbers. And so so I would say that, you know, if somebody in their
80s had a max in their in their 20s or or lower 30s, that'd be terrific. Well, that's so funny
what you say. We have arrived at 30 to 31 as the magic number. That would be a rough guess. And
what's interesting that you mentioned that is those Scandinavian elite skiers I mentioned,
had values in the very high 30s or low 40s in their 80s. Now, but remember, they would any
any sort of biological gifts or genetic gifts that those men had and or the fact that they started to
train, you know, probably be very physically active as youngsters and really were maximally
physically active from age, you know, 13, 14 to probably 30. Yeah, that would account for that.
Yeah. So so so I think I think 30 be a terrific goal. But I think the other thing too is is,
you know, how many push ups do you want to be able to do and how many sorts of body weight type of
things do you want to be able to do? You know, what sort of agility maneuvers do you want to
be able to do? And I think, you know, we have to kind of factor in factor in, you know,
orthopedic problems and that sort of thing. But but again, we have good treatment for those now.
And orthopedic surgeons can fix a lot of things that other otherwise would have made people very
difficult for them to walk and move around. Well, and we, yeah, we think a lot about those things.
And we think that strength and stability need to be trained in parallel and as hard as we're
training from a cardio standpoint. But I do think this idea that, hey, if you're trying to reverse
engineer ending your life with a VO two max in the mid 20s to high 30s, the good news is you are
never going to not be able to do something that you want to do. Correct. If you're in the airport
and the escalator isn't working. Yeah, I don't care. Which is which and I think the thing you have
to ask people and this really resonates is, you know, do you want to be able to play with your
grandchildren? That's one question for people. The escalator question, that's a terrific question.
A terrific question. Yeah, I was just in the airport last week, escalator down, you got to
be able to care and it's a long one of those really long ones. Yeah, right. You got your carry-on bag
plus your backpack and you got to get up the escalator. Now, I'm sure somewhere out there there
was an elevator. But the point is, do you want to be able to do this stuff? And if you do, then you
have to do the math. You have to work to agree. You got to do the math. And what's interesting
too is if you see a few people around here in rural Minnesota who, you know, grew up on
less than fully mechanized farms and remain, you know, active milking cows and doing these
sorts of things, doing a whole lot of chores. And it's remarkable the muscle mass that some of these
men and women have, you know, that some have. And I think that that is something to keep in mind
too, if you look at these people in these, well, if you look at in Japan, for example, in a couple
places, you know, the hilliest parts of Japan and some of the hilliest parts of Italy and Greece are
where the longevity is the highest. And people have argued it's because people have to walk up and down
the hills. And also, and so they keep their balance and keep their glute strength. They don't
fall, that sort of thing, Peter. And also that they're, you know, living a more rustic lifestyle
is probably getting them some de facto strength training on a daily basis. So yeah, so I agree with
you. Let's talk a little bit about VO2 max again in terms of like, what is actually driving it? So
let's go through all the variables, right? So you've got sort of gas exchange,
you've got sort of gas exchange in the lung. In the lung, correct. And then you've got gas
exchange in, or sorry, then you have pump efficiency, right? So we went through the mechanics
of that again, but just so people understand what we talk about, you've got stroke volume,
contractility, of course, afterload and preload and all those things that determine basically
the efficacy of the pump to move the medium to the capillary bed. And then you have capillary
exchange in the muscle bed. Right. So broadly speaking, let's just say those are three
variables, right? You've got the gas exchange at the source, you've got the pump, and then you've
got the gas exchange at the destination. Is that, I know that's overly simplistic. Yeah,
it's a way to look at it. So let's just think you got air to lung, lung to blood,
blood from the heart to the tissues and oxygen from the blood to the tissues, right? So there's
four or five steps like that and you enumerated the three big ones. And so in general, oxygen
uptake is cardiac output, how much blood you're pumping per minute times arterial venous oxygen
difference, how much blood you're extracting, or oxygen you're extracting out of the blood.
And it turns out that if you look at all the studies and all the people fit, unfit, trained,
untrained, in general, the biggest issue is how much blood can you pump? And so what is that heart
rate times stroke volume equation? Where does that leave us? Now, when you train, you get so you can
extract more. And if you're at high altitude or if you've got problems with your lungs, maybe the
lungs don't work as well. But in general, I like to tell people you cannot extract what has not been
delivered. So the key is delivery. And that's heart rate times stroke volume. And interestingly,
Peter, as you I'm sure you've seen, is some of your fittest people actually have slightly lower
peak heart rates. And one of the reasons is because their stroke volume is so high. One of the really
interesting again, experiment of nature patients is our subjects is a man called Eskeld Ebison,
who won gold medals in five Olympics and rowing for Denmark. And they have serial VO2 max date
on him from the time he was 18 or 19 till his early 40s. And his VO2 max stayed around, you know,
5.6 liters per minute, which is quite high. And he weighed about 70 kilos. I believe he was a
lightweight rower. And anyways, but his peak heart rate dropped from about 190 to 150 over that period
of time, which all that means is for he was able to pump the same amount of blood, but he had to do
more with each beat. And that's, that's sort of an interesting example. But that's an insane example,
actually. Yeah. Yeah. And again, these are the sorts of things you see. So, so that is really the
key. And so in other words, in the individual as they age, we think that the majority of the
reduction VO2 max is coming from cardiac output reduction. But right. And the majority is probably
coming from a reduction in peak heart rate, which can be buffered to some extent, if you have a nice
compliant ventricle, like we talked about. I mean, I'll tell you, I'm not quite yet 50. And I am just
saddened by the reduction in my peak heart rate. It is really breaking my heart. I mean, I was never
very high anyway, and I don't worry about it, you know, but I'm 63. So I stopped worrying about it.
I just I worry about what my workload is. Yeah, yeah, no, I just, but it is a may, I remember
thinking like, there will never be a day where I can't get my heart rate above X. But, but actually,
I'll tell you, for me, it fell quite precipitously in my 20s. So as a teenager, when I was training
obscenely hard, inappropriately hard, a heart rate of 200 was was an everyday occurrence. There was
never a day in high school that my heart rate didn't hit 200 to 205 beats per minute. Right.
And then by the time I was in medical school, so 24, 25 years old, all of a sudden it dropped
immediately to about 180. It became very difficult to get over 180, which by the way,
was far lower than the 220 minus your age prediction. So Peter, I was in a study, I was in
two famous studies as a subject. One is this lactate threshold study when I was 19. And then
a few years later, I went and worked one summer at Washington University in St. Louis, and I stopped
training. I just run, you know, finished my last year of track and field at the University of Arizona
and run 10,000 meters in 3048 and didn't double on the packed ends, which was fast. Well, I was
good enough to get labbed by the world record holders, like what is what I like to tell people.
But anyways, what happened is my peak heart rate was like 185 or 188. I can't remember. And over
the period of 12 weeks of detraining, it went up to about 10 beats a minute. Yeah. So which would
have been, you know, in the high one nineties, which would have been quote 220 minus by age,
at the time. But but again, and there are all sorts of examples, there's a bunch of data on
elite athletes showing that that some of them have peak heart rates similar to 220 minus their age,
but many are lower than that. And they're like Escald Ebesen, there are some people that have
been world record holders, Olympic champions that had peak heart rates in the 150s. Yeah, mine's if
I hit 170 today, it's a it's a great, yeah, that's a good, which is about 220 minus my age. But you
know, my my guess is I'd be hard, I'd press to get to 140. I was talking with Lance Armstrong on a
had him on the podcast, many actually, but maybe about a little less than a year ago, actually.
And we were talking about back in the in the heyday of his tours, they weren't really looking
at their power meters when they were competing. So they trained with the power meter. But when
it was when it was race day for the time trial, yeah, you just went off heart rate. And I was just
blown away. I mean, so you got to think Lance was winning the tours between 28 and 35. Right. He was
still holding 200 beats per minute for the entire time. Yeah, right. So so 45 minutes at 200 beats
per minute when you're 30 plus years old is and on the other example, there'll be a man named Bob
Schul, who is an American who won the 5000 in 1964, who did interval training all day and all night.
It was incredible how he trained in his peak area. I have the data someplace was like 154 156. It's
it's was not particularly Jim Ryan's was not the great miler was not particularly high in his 20s.
Yeah, so just incredible stroke volume. Correct. Correct, correct, correct. Big heart, big pumps.
All right. So let's talk a little bit about the training. So so let's let's start with something
that we haven't talked about, which, you know, when you look at the best, you know, high output
endurance athletes today, you know, it's one thing to talk about their peak engine performance,
but it's easy to overlook what they're doing at the low end. You know, I've had Inigo San
Milan on a podcast twice and we've talked at length about Tadeep Pagachar. And it's it's amazing
to talk about high hit how high his FTP is his functional threshold power. We can talk about his
VO two max, but equally amazing to that is how much power he can put out while keeping lactate
below two millimole. Right, right, right, right. And, you know, I think he's at four. He's over
four watts per kilo while keeping lactate before below two millimole. Right. And why that's amazing
for someone who doesn't ride a bike is you if you took an average fit person off the street and said
hold four watts per kilo, they could maybe do it for a minute. Most people can do it for a minute.
And this guy can do it for four hours. Correct. So so so that low end aerobic efficiency,
I always try to explain to my patients, if your VO two max represents the height or peak of your
pyramid, the wider your base, the higher your your peak. Do you agree with that sentiment?
So what I would simply say, Peter, you know, as we think about performance, you think about these
elites, we think obviously about their VO two max and you start thinking about, you know,
whether lactate threshold, which would be sort of the FTP and they're all sort of related anaerobic
threshold. There's a lot of terminology here. You can get arguments with people about the details.
But what fraction of your VO two max can you perform at for, you know, minutes to hours?
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. And so, you know, and typically, it's about 60 percent and untrained
kind of young to middle age people lower and people that are really untrained.
But just just sort of sedentary people that are very fit. It can be 75, 80, 85, even 90 percent of
the two max and some older athletes close to 100. So so that's exactly what you describe.
Somebody like that probably has a, you know, a peak work rate that they could sustain for 10
or 20 minutes of six, seven watts per kilo. So the fact that they can do four watts per
kilo forever shouldn't surprise anybody. And that's just like you look at somebody like Mr.
Kip Jogi, you know, he's running 440 miles at a pace that doesn't really probably cause much
of an increase in his blood, like the data levels at all. Did they ever reveal any of those metrics?
Yeah, that data is that data has been published. Tell me what was his lactate level at the
completion of the two hour of the just under two hour. Well, remember, remember at the end of the
race, you wouldn't have a lot of carbohydrate on board, but I would just simply say he can run
440 miles or over 12 miles an hour at at at, you know, at levels that barely nudges, lactic acid
levels barely nudged. But but remember, too, but his video. But what's interesting is is when I
first started thinking about this and making models of performance, I thought the the highest
number was 85 percent of max. And it's probably closer to 90 for somebody like him. But but but
the other interests. So the one you were talking about FDP for one minute. The other interesting
thing about that, Peter, is, you know, the Kip Jogi challenge, people have gone and, you know,
put treadmills at 12 and a half miles an hour to see how long somebody can last on the treadmill.
They're getting spit off in 30 seconds back. Yeah, less than that, you know, so. So yeah,
so same sort of thing. So so so I think that that sort of training, you know,
and these people are training two, three, four hours a day. If you look in terms of the runners,
running is limited to some extent because of the there's almost, you know, orthopedic
issues become becomes a problem impact, right. And so it's really difficult for people to run
more than about 120 or 130 miles a week and ever run do hard training for prolonged periods of time.
Now, there are a few people who can do it. And if you look at what Kip Jogi does, it's almost
identical, even day for day, what Bill Rogers and Frank Shorter did, does it at altitude. But but
there's a lot of medium eight and 10 and 12 miles of runs, a couple of hard interval sessions per week
and, you know, long run. And that's so, you know, that gets them to 120 miles a week, you know,
week in and week out. Now, the cyclists can do more because you don't have that issue. But
remember, though, with cycling, you know, you're going up and you're going down and you have always
a chance to take a break here and there. The swimmers do a ton as well, you know, and again,
because swimming is very forgiving in terms of not beating people up, provided your shoulders,
you know, don't get a bunch of tendonitis. So so but what's amazing is, is that if you look at what
the elite of the elite are doing, does not really change that much for 50 or 60 years.
You have better equipment, you have better races, you got better this, better that. But in terms of
if you look at the data on the elite of the elite from the late 60s and early 70s, it's not like
Kip Jogi's VO2 Max was 90. It was high 70s, just as what you'd anticipate and so forth. So so I
think a lot of what's happened in terms of at the very edge of things has been better races,
people that have longer careers, they don't stop when they're 25 or 26.
Sports medicine is better. So if they get injured, they can recover. We saw this in last night with
Clay Thompson. He had two injuries at 3040 years ago would have been, you know, basically career
engine, and he's come back from a combination of an ACL issue and Achilles, especially used to just
destroy people. He's playing very well. So I think those sorts of things, the races are much
better, you know, and they used to run the Boston Marathon at noon whenever so often you'd get a,
you know, a really hot day. So I think that's what's happened. So most of the improved performance
can be equipment, these sort of social factors. Unfortunately, in the case of Mr. Armstrong,
people, you know, bending the rules and so forth and so on. But yeah.
So let's talk about kind of the intensity levels that needs to be training at. So again, let's,
I mean, we could pick the most extreme example and talk about Kipchoge. So how many hours per week
is Kipchoge running? Because I know he also does a ton of other strength training and body weight
training. My guess is that the total amount of time he's running is somewhere between 14 and 18
or 20 hours a week. Okay. But remember, he can, you know, he's covering a much greater ground,
of course. Right. So he can do that. And my, again, you know, if you looked at it in terms
of the lactate threshold or the equivalent of critical power on the bike, probably 60, 70% of
that is, is, you know, fast, but not that fast. They typically start off their group run sort of
jogging and then they pick it up over time. Also remember that he's doing this at, you know,
seven, 8,000 feet. And then my understanding in reading his training program is that, you know,
a couple of days a week, he goes to a track and they run, you know, multiple 400 meters,
let's say 200 meter jog or multiple kilometers with a 200 or 400 meter jog,
like 10 times a kilometer very fast. So the total amount of time he's running faster than race pace
might just be 10 miles per week. So he's probably running about 60 or 70% of his stuff,
some of it quite slow, but most of it, you know, medium fast, but certainly not, you know, where
he's can't talk to you where he's short of breath. Then he's probably spending about 20% of his time
where, where, you know, he can still talk to you, but he's pushing it a little bit and probably 10%
of his time where he's pushing it a lot. Yeah. I mean, that's exactly my impression. And it's
the same impression I have of elite cyclists and elite swimmers. Yeah. No. And, and, and that
would be true for that, that, that, that those sorts of breakdowns, kind of the,
you know, 60, 70, 20, 30, 10 are pretty typical. Now what's interesting is that's really emerged,
the last say 20 years. If you look at people who've looked at the history of training and they have
gotten training logs from people. And I told you, we have lab data on people. That's quite good,
starting in the 19 some even in the 1930s, but certainly by the fifties and sixties,
we've got plenty of good data. And if you look at what these individuals who have tremendous
treadmill values, tremendous DO2 max values, ran very fast times on like dirt tracks and muddy
conditions, that sort of thing, or, or, you know, kind of what we'd describe as a kind of a
kludgy bike now, it's certainly no aero bars or, you know, look at the swimsuits people were
racing. So if you look at what those people were doing, they were doing all kinds of things.
There are people, uh, runners in the sixties, there were, there were people like, again,
like Bob Shule, a fancy, a fascinating man who's still alive, who his morning workout would be 40
times a hundred meters with a short jog in between. And his afternoon workout might be 20
times 400 meters. And he rarely ran continuously at all except in races, you know, and, and, and it
would be a fast interval slow. And there are other people who, who ran, you know, up to 200
miles a week and hardly ever ran fast again, except in races and some strides. And then, then
there were already people doing the sort of mixed training I described a minute ago. So what is
interesting is the extent to which things have sort of converged on this 60, 70, 20, 30, 10 sort of
model. Yeah. And it really, I mean, it, it makes sense if you've ever done it yourself, right? I can,
I can understand why there is a benefit to just the mitochondrial efficiency that comes from,
Yeah, right. You made more money. Sure.
That you'd miss out on if you were just doing the short bursts. And similarly,
Unless you do a whole lot of them.
Yeah. Well, it depends what short is. I mean, again, if you're moving to 400s into 800s,
And the recovery is a jog. Yeah. That's, that's, yeah. Because these guys aren't walking.
That's right. Yeah. Yeah. Um, so, so do you think there's a, a sort of training benefit? I know
there's a health benefit, but a training benefit in the lowest zone. So, so we kind of think about
zone two as where Kipchoge is probably spending 60 to 70% of his time. He can still talk.
Yeah. Probably right, right at the edge of two or three.
Yep. And then, um, and then obviously he's in zone three, four for, you know, kind of race pace.
Yeah. And then, and then he's like four, five, 10% of his mileage, which is really stretching himself.
Now is Kipchoge or other athletes deliberately putting time into zone one,
which is truly a recovery pace or. Yeah. They do that when they're recovering,
you know, between intervals. And, and you would be amazed at how, uh, I mean,
cause I did it many, many years ago, you know, getting started. So the first mile or two can be
very slow. I mean, it can be just almost a walk jog, and then they kind of drift into it. Uh,
and I think, but, but thinking about the listeners who are just trying to improve their health,
that where you, that's where you come back to physical activity versus intentional training.
So, you know, you start looking at the health benefits of just kind of, uh,
less than brisk walking, you know, purposeful, but not really brisk walking. They're substantial.
Yeah. So, so I think, you know, people at zone one, two, you know, you know, parking your car,
uh, farther out in the parking lot and strolling in, I think, you know, walking the dog.
And that can mean all sorts of things, depending on what kind of talk you have
and who's in the neighborhood, uh, you know, can, can help. I mean, the data on gardening,
uh, you know, and again, you could be out there, uh, hacking away weeds with a, with a machete or,
but most of us think about gardening as relatively light exercise. So the, the health benefits of,
of light physical activity, light exercise, I mean, are substantial. And remember,
you're, you're correct in the sense that it, that at least from our perspective, there is no J curve
and things, you know, things are, are go up, but it's not completely linear. And, and, you know,
the biggest benefit people get health wise is the first 10 or 15 minutes a day.
And why do you think that is?
Well, I think that if you, if you, if you look at what 10 or 15 minutes does, I mean,
I think it begins to do things in your scalable muscle that improve your insulin sensitivity and
help you fight against diabetes. I think just a tiny bit of additional physical activities,
at least some buffer against weight gain. I think that there's some, uh, improvement in your,
the lining of your blood vessels and, and probably some improvement in your autonomic function.
Is your, is your heart going to get bigger? Are you going to get a more efficient cardiac pump?
Probably not, but are you going to begin to do some of the things, uh, and the answer is yes.
So Mike, should those of us who really kind of care about this and care about using as many metrics
as we can to understand this and, you know, should we be looking at heart rate recovery and adding
that to our kind of repertoire of something we track in ourselves as we train?
So, you know, I think that, that, that, and you see it more among the cyclists and you do it again
among the runners. Uh, and, and, and is, is, I think that there are people that are, you know,
really into tech and monitoring and then they're sort of tech nudies. I'm a, I'm a tech nudie. And,
and part of the reason is, is, is there wasn't as much around him when I started.
And I mean, we just were getting digital watches and they weren't even stop watches.
And, and the other reason is, is that, that at the time, one of the big innovations was rating of
perceived exertion, uh, you know, the six to 20 scale or some people use a one to 10 scale
about how hard you're working. And I think that what's been shown is cause you know,
you can have a good day and a bad day in terms of the metrics. So I think what's been shown is,
is that, that they're all sort of parallel. And if you learn to read your own body via the,
via, you know, the rating of perceived exertion and, or, or metrics, you know, find one you like,
and then just focus on sort of big picture things. So I would not get too hung up on heart rate
recovery and too hung up on, on, um, on, uh, heart rate variability. I would just more say,
are you, how much are you doing? You know, uh, 30, 40, 60, a hundred, you know,
180 minutes a week. Are you also doing other forms or not a week a day? Are you also doing
other forms of, of activity, you know, like taking the stairs, as you mentioned, and what sort of
combination are you doing? How much time are you spending where you're really short of breath?
How much time are you spending where you're a little bit short of breath and how much time
is it, you know, kind of a pleasant sort of pace. So I think that that sort of information can get
you as, as much as you need. And I think the main thing then Peter is to make sure that, that, um,
you have some accountability, whether it's, you know, with a training partner,
maybe with a device or a diary, maybe, you know, with just how far did I run today?
That sort of thing. So, so what is your current exercise regimen? I mean,
you sort of downplayed it a minute, but 30 minutes and 40 seconds for a 10 K.
So here's what I do is, I don't think people understand how fast that is. I mean,
yeah, no, and I once ran a 225 marathon, but, but you know, the older I get the better I was,
right? So here's what I do. Here's what I do, Peter. And is, is it that
like, I'm a big believer in what's called hard easy, hard day, easy day. And, and I think that,
that, that, and so what, what I, what I'll do, uh, like tomorrow will be a hard day.
So I'll get on, on, uh, uh, you know, a stationary bike in my, in my, uh, workout room and, and,
and on the bike and the rowing machine, do some sort of warm up for 10 to 15 minutes.
Then I will do a circuit that starts with, um, uh, 15, uh, or really kind of 25 squat
thrust, a minute of jumping rope, static wall set to failure. And then some drop sets where you go
down, you know, where you, you go down the weight stack drop set, then, then, then drop sets with,
with, uh, incline flies, then drop sets with leg extensions and drop sets with a combination of,
of, uh, pull ups and lat pull downs and military press. Then some additional stuff for my legs.
Then some, uh, uh, pushups, bar dips in upright rows, followed by something else for my legs. So
I alternate arms and legs and I work my way through this with no rest drop sets on each
thing for all large major, major muscle masses. And that takes about 22 minutes. And it's, it's,
it's, it's, uh, 22 minutes for one circuit, one circuit. Then, then I'll do a,
then, then I get on the bike, right. And, and I'll do, uh, like eight times, uh,
three minutes of a ladder where you start, you know, unloaded, go up a notch, go up a notch,
go up a notch. And I get to maybe about 350 Watts for the last 30 seconds, come back down to about
a hundred Watts, 350 Watts, do that times eight. And sorry, how long do you take to ladder? Three
minutes, three minutes. So, so you go like a hundred Watts for something like a hundred
Watts for 30 seconds, 150 for 30, 200 for 200 for 30, 250 for 30, 300 for 30, 350 for 30,
come back down times eight. And that, you know, and that takes about an hour in between your
three minute sets. No, you just go up and come right back down. Okay. So you're right. So the
recovery is exactly. And, and that takes about, that takes about an hour and that'll fix your
wagon for a while. So you'll do, that'll be your hard day tomorrow. That'll be my hard day. And,
and I'll do that basically every other day or every third day. My easy days will be something
like, you know, like this morning, I, and I gotta, I want to go do 20 more minutes, not because I
need to do 20 minutes. I want to, because I wanted to watch the first bit of Obi-Wan Kenobi.
So my easy days are built around what, what documentary or, or, you know, how many times
can you watch the Mandalorian? How many Clint Eastwood movies can you watch that? And this
started during lockdown, right? So my easy days are 30 to 40 minutes of, of light cycling,
transitioning to rowing back and forth of around 30 to 40 minutes. Sometimes I do one, sometimes if
I come home from work and I do another one, but the goal there is, is, is an old concept called
active rest. So I'm not trying to get a real training effect. I'm trying to loosen up from
the day before it's worked out. Cause I'm sore that, you know, if you do what I describe,
you know, you warm up for 10 or 15 minutes, do, do 20 minutes of drop sets and,
and that type of intervals at the end, you will be sore, right? And so then, then what happens is,
is, is, you know, so you have to recover the next day. Now I'll do this for about six months and
then probably when it gets, starts getting dark again, I'll do what I did like last year, where,
where I start just doing kind of maintenance circuits in terms of the strength. So not,
not quite as, it may be only twice a week and I'll start doing longer rides. We have a Peloton and,
and I don't do any of the classes, but, but I started doing this hour of truth
to see how many Watts I could average for an hour.
Okay. What are you at?
It's who my best is. And I think, I think my best during lockdown last year was 360 average,
360 Watts for an hour.
Wow. Do you, do you think, do you, I mean, that's, that's obscenely high.
Well, and the things are calibrated pretty well. So, and I have, I have a Wattbike,
I got a lot of equipment. I got a Wattbike and I think they're pretty close. And if you,
if you look online, they claim they're close, right? And, and, and I know how, and I think
that, I think it's consistent with what I think my, I haven't measured my VO2 max in a while.
So I want to see if I get like 320 Watts next year.
What do you, what do you, what do you think your VO2 max is right now?
You know, well, I'll tell you, back when I was quite young, it was 5.4 liters a minute,
right? My guess is it's, my, my weight then was probably between 75, close to 80 kilos.
Okay.
So I was right at under 70.
I think my weight is now is probably about 95 kilos. Because I've actually made an effort
to gain some weight. And I think my max is probably 4.5 liters a minute would be my guess.
Something like that.
Yeah. I mean, that's still an amazing wattage under any circumstance.
Well, yeah, assuming the machine is okay. But I think it is because,
and remember when I'm doing those ladders that I was telling you about, those pyramids,
that's after I've done a heavy leg workout, you know, so my legs are pretty fatigued. I've done that.
But remember, I have some ability to because, you know, I'm a pretty good,
yeah, I became a pretty good, I didn't really start running until my senior high school.
So I started late. And I'm 6'4". And I tell people if, you know, if I come back in the
next life, I'll be a swimmer or rower because I used to show up with these tidy people.
Yeah.
So I was, I was, I'm the world's largest relatively good distance runner.
What's on your easy recovery day, Mike? Are you just paying attention to RPE?
Or are you looking at a split time on the rowing machine or as a low-rodded?
It's just all RPE. It's really just active rest, which is a lost concept.
Do you have a sense of what your heart rate is as a percentage of your max body?
No, I don't even measure it. No, I have no, and I get, I think it's probably based on the,
on the, you know, the hour of truth ride. And my wife got me a Peloton shirt that she had
printed hour of truth on it, which was kind of cool. But anyways, I think, I think Peter, my,
it's probably about 140 is my peak heart rate. That would be my guess. But, but again, I go with RPE,
I go to life suffer. And, and it's, but remember, it's unusual and, and, and, you know, it's unusual
to be able to do intervals on your own and really push it. Not everybody can do it. And that's why
you need a class or you need a coach or you need a group and so forth. But, but I'm lucky enough to
be able, able to do it in, in, yeah. So my training is really polarized. I mean, like really polarized.
So let's talk about folks who are listening to this who want to boost their VO2 max. Let's talk
about the different protocols that exist. I'll tell you what we typically tell patients to do,
which is kind of in my experience, one of the most efficient ways that you can do it,
but I'm curious as to what other ways. So we typically talk about a four by four, four on four.
Yeah, no, you're right there. So, so we'll tell people, and again, the easiest way that I
personally can do this is on a bike, on an incline. And it can't be a very steep incline. It's got to
be like 6% grade. I want to stay in the saddle and, but I never want the resistance to go away.
And I basically want to be in the saddle climbing against resistance for four minutes. And I use a
power meter and a heart rate. So I just want to keep the power as steady as I can. Invariably,
it dips in about the third minute, and then I can recover it in the fourth minute psychologically.
And then the recovery is four minutes of literally doing nothing, but rolling back to the starting
line. And then it's basically just repeat that. So, so, yeah, no, no, I'm with you. What I tell
people, for example, that have come and say, I want to run a faster marathon. I want to do this.
I want to do that, you know, and they're running a lot of miles. They need to get their VO2 max up.
And I tell them exactly what you've described. Sometimes I tell them five minutes and three
minutes rest, sometimes whatever. And people that are fitter sometimes only take, like I would only
take two minutes of rest. And that's just, but four times four is terrific. So you would do
something if you were thinking about running, I would tell people to do something that would be
right at their sort of 5k race pace, maybe a little faster, or, or you would do the first one
a little slower than your 5k race pace. The next one, you know, a little faster than that,
the next one, a little faster than the next one faster than your 5k race pace. And depending on
how fast you're running, if you're going pretty fast, then you would just jog in between. And if
you were, were not going so fast, you walked in between. So that would be the sort of thing that,
that I would describe to people. And the classic training, you know, among elite runners is,
is mile repeats, you know, people doing, you know, four or five times one mile. And then they
jog at a quarter mile or half mile in between. And I personally have seen really good runners.
I mean, it's, I've seen people's, you know, do, you know, four 30, four 25, four 20, four 15,
four 10, four Oh five, which is, but I mean, these were people getting ready for the Olympics, you
know? So, so, so, but, but those sorts of things, but sort of for the average person, right?
You know, the, the hard part that I think requires a little bit of coaching upfront is it's,
you know, you and I have done this our whole lives. So we sort of know what four minutes all
out feels like. Yeah, right. Exactly. And 30 seconds in, you shouldn't be hurting too much.
If you've gone out too hard. So it's, it takes a little bit of work to understand what, what
you're going for is a constant four minutes, but the, but the suffering is disproportionately in
the last 90 seconds. And Peter, you're, you're, you're exactly right. So I describe it as you,
when you're done, when you get done with the last one, the fourth one, you do not want to be bending
over you. If you'd gone a little bit of faster, you'd want to be bending over. So I call it the
no bend over rule. Interesting. And then what people have to recognize both for the four times
four minutes and within the four minutes is a good interval workout. And this sounds, you know,
completely masochistic is like putting your hand in warm water and then slowly increasing the
temperature in the water to where you can barely stand it anymore and then leave it in for a while.
And then you turn it down and let your hand cool off and do it again. And that's really
what you described. And, and, you know, one of the things I think we've learned from the
Cyclist is a terrific phrase called manage your suffering. You know, you need to learn to manage
your suffering. And, and, and, and I think that's the other interesting thing about this type of
training in, in, is, is to the extent, you know, people can have these sort of religious experiences
exercising, this sort of interval training is one way to get them. That's what I would tell you.
No, I completely agree. I mean, obviously we're cut from the same cloth in this way, but, but I think
that there really is something wonderful about experiencing your limits and understanding that
level of discomfort. And if you're able to maintain your rhythm and tempo, Peter, while you do it,
that's when you can have these sorts of experiences. And, and, you know, I mean, one of the most
beautiful things ever, and it wasn't a total endurance athlete, you know, even it was a little
bit shorter, a couple of minutes, but to watch Michael Phelps win the butterfly and watch his
stroke. He was a tree. He was good at everything, but he was especially good at the butterfly.
And to watch, you know, most people stroke has fallen apart and they end up taking more
strokes the last 50 of a 200 meter butterfly. And, you know, his stroke count, the second,
third, and fourth lap didn't change because he had that rhythm, that tempo. And if you listen
to the old school coaches talk about interval training, they're constantly talking about tempo.
What is your rhythm? What is your tempo? And, and why you're doing it, why you're suffering,
Peter, why you're pushing it while, while, while it's hurting, while it's burning.
The goal was to not lose your form and not lose your tempo.
You know, it's funny, I used to, I used to watch Michael Phelps train because before he kind of
broke out in the early 2000s, I lived in Baltimore because I did my residency at Hopkins and he used
to train at a place called North Baltimore Aquatic. Yeah, right. So, so watching now,
Michael, of course, within the swimming world was already an unbelievable prodigy because he,
he had gone to the Olympics in Sydney, placed 15 or something, which is quite young for a man.
That's right. He was actually the youngest, he became the youngest male to ever set a world
record in a time sport in early 01. Correct. When he set the record for the 15. Yeah.
Set the record for the 200 fly. So, so watching this 16 year old swimming at North Baltimore
Aquatic and BAC, which his signature event of course was the 200 fly. Now it's 200 long course
butterfly. I would put that up there with the 200 breast and the 400 IM as the three worst races in
all of swimming. To me, it's like doing an 800 meteor intermediate hurdles on the track that
event doesn't exist. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's just, it's just, it's pure, it's insane suffer.
But here's the thing, Mike, his training was almost never, you never once saw him do a 200
fly. It was lots of 75s, lots of 75s. And his coach, Bob Bowman was really adamant about perfect
form because if I were correct, Michael had an unusual rhythm, which is that he breathed on
every stroke. And usually like when I swam butterfly, when most people swam butterfly,
it was every other you would, you were head underwater for one stroke, head up for one,
down for one. And, and Michael, I'm pretty sure he would breathe every stroke. But as you pointed out,
no one's form could rival his. And that's why he, he was usually the last guy to hit the wall at the
50 and, and, and yet would come back and just devour everybody. Well, and you see that with
Edwin Moses, 13 steps between hurdles and the 400 hurdles in the late seventies with that innovation.
And again, you see these people, you sell with Kim Chok, you're doing it for two hours,
their ability to maintain this form and tempo. And as you watch it, as you watch it, Peter, you,
you are awed by this sense of great effort and simultaneous relaxation. It's really,
it's a real paradox. And, and, and when, and you, again, you see that, you see that in other sports
too, you see it when the golfers get hot, how far they hit the ball, but it's, it's both violent and
relaxed at the same time. You, you certainly, you know, you sit there and watch Steph Curry
or Clay Thompson start launching balls. And, and, and, and it's just incredible, the tempo, the rhythm,
the form, and, and, and, but, and the effort, but again, just how relaxed they are. It's just wild
to think about even. Now, going back to our very, very recreational person who's never trained in
their life. We, we don't even, we don't use lactate testing on people at that level. We basically do
the whole thing off RPE and we try to get 80% of their time, which might start out at two to three
hours per week as we want you to be able to talk, but not enjoy it. Right. I don't want you to be any,
I don't want you to be any higher than that. Right. And then once we build up a bit of a reserve
in that, after maybe six months of that kind of training, we're sort of ready to move them to that
next phase of, Hey, once a week, I want you to do kind of four on four off four rounds. Do you think
that once a week doing those four hard intervals is sufficient to boost VO two max? It will increase
it for sure. Yeah. In that vast majority of people, especially if they're doing the other stuff you're
talking about. And I think that, that what I really liked about what you describe and what people
don't realize, especially when you're going to advocate relatively hard training for citizens,
is that sometimes you have to train before you can really train. Yeah. That's right. You got to train
to train. Yeah. Yeah. You got to get, and you certainly have seen that in some, some studies
with older people that are really, you know, 60, 70 years old is that they almost have to do three
or four or six months of sort of pre-training before they are fit enough to train hard. So I think
you're spot on there. And I, my guess is after they they've been able to do it for, you know,
once a week for a while, you build them up to two times per week. I think the one thing that
people need to recognize, and this comes from a man named Stan James, who I think is still
practicing medicine. He's in his nineties was a, one of the pioneers of sports medicine,
orthopedic surgery, and he's not operating anymore, but he, the last I checked, he was alive
and well out in Eugene, Oregon. And he, he worked with coach Bill Bowerman, you know, the, the
great organ coach, found one of the founders of Nike, the waffle shoe guy, you know, and they got
into this hard, easy thing, which is, is sort of what I do. And I, and, and, uh, you know, Dr.
James would tell you that once people start doing more than about five or six hard, hard sessions
every two weeks, you're beginning to ask for some sort of load management issue, whether it's
orthopedics, whether it's just your fatigue, whether it's this, whether it's that. So I do think
that, that, um, you know, you want to do something literally. I mean, I can't remember the last day
I didn't do anything. It's probably been, you know, years, but, but, but my guess is the,
the number of times I do something hard is, you know, 120, 130 times per year. And I, and my
guess is I never go more than a week without doing something relatively intense. When you think about,
about these sort of exceptional elite athletes, the Chokis of the world, do you believe they have
a finite number of exceptional performances in them? You know, I, I think people used to sort
of think that, but I think what's happened now is that, um, uh, you know, people used to drift into
the, into the, into the world rankings and they'd last, you know, maybe, uh, two Olympics. So they'd
last, uh, you know, uh, six, seven years. So they'd come in, kind of emerge right before one Olympiad,
do well, do well on the next one and kind of fade. But I think there's, there's, there's, uh,
two, two things that have really changed. The first is, is that, that again, sports medicine is better.
So people do get injured. They can do things about it. I think the second thing is just,
it's been, it's become so professionalized is, is people can, that are really, really good can
now make enough money to make it worth their while to continue. And, and, you know, you see this in
terms of the age of Olympians where, where, you know, you used to have, uh, you know, used to be
very unusual to have women over age 20 and swimming. There was no college swimming. There was none of
this. There was none of that. So it was a lot of teenagers. Now you see that drifting up and you
see people like Katie O'Deckie having extended careers, you know, uh, Phelps going 2000, 2004,
eight, 12, and going to five Olympics. Yeah. That would have been inconceivable previously for
swimmers, you know, because people, you know, people hung around and, and maybe stayed for one
additional Olympics. And when they got done after college, sometimes too, but, but eventually they,
they had to go do get a job. But, but again, among the most elite who can now monetize this
people can last longer. And you see it also in, in quote, the major unquote professional sports,
you know, before orthopedic surgery was good and, and so forth. And, and every knee surgery was an
adventure. You know, somebody like Tom Brady, Brady, his career would have been over in 2009
and, and why keep, or, or it would have been attenuated. And, and the other thing, Peter,
is why keep, you know, if you're making a hundred thousand dollars a year, why keep playing?
If you're making, you know, 20, 30 million or whatever, 30, whatever the number is,
you know, why not keep playing? And you look at, you look at, at, you know, again, uh,
in, in sports like running, swimming, cycling, you know, there, there's less of a kind of a
journeyman group. But if you look at, at, at, you know, the NBA, the NFL, major league baseball,
the salary scales are pretty good. And if, if people can play another couple of years,
you know, this can be millions of dollars, millions of dollars for them. So they're very
motivated in, uh, uh, to do this, you know, so if you can be the eighth man on an NBA team and
give people 15, 20 quality minutes a game, you know, you're going to have a job for a long time.
And again, if you're LeBron, you know, who apparently spent some huge amount of money on
training and, uh, cook and all that other stuff is, is, uh, is, you know, I mean, if you start
thinking about spending X per year for a, you know, a 40 X paycheck, why not? Why stop?
So where do you think we are today, Mike, in, um, performance enhancing drugs in sports? So,
so cycling is probably the sport I would follow the closest of the major sports. I mean, I guess
I follow swimming, uh, as well, though not nearly as much as I did for sort of 15 years prior. Um,
but, but you know, I think when you go back and look at the cycling data, and I love the way Lance
talks about this, right? You know, I think he's very open, right? To say, look, as long as there
has been a tour de France, there has been a graying of the line, right? But there is a difference
between the kind of high octane cheating that was done in Lance's era and sort of the low octane
cheating that was done in Eddie Merck's era when they were, you know, using a little bit of upset.
Here's what I would say about where we are with doping. So the testing has gotten better,
both in terms of the frequency of testing and the, uh, you know, the actual chemistry of the
testing of the machines, the analytics. Yeah. The ability to detect. Yeah. Yeah. Um, if you
look at the way, what's called an abnormal test is called, it's not like what we call
an abnormal test or an out of range test in clinical medicine. There, there are typically
many standard deviations above average for these things. And they're typically designed. So there's
not a lot of false, false positives. They don't want to have any false positives. So that gives
people a room, some room to micro dose. And that's why you have relatively few positive tests,
but occasionally they'll be people, you know, caught through investigations, judicial mechanisms,
the police, and historically many of the biggest busts have been the police. So I think what I
would simply say is that the era of industrial strength doping is over, you know, people,
people doing like the East Germans did and androgenizing females to the extent that they
really look like men. So I think that that is, is done. So I think there is still.
But sorry, Mike, you say that even in light of what the Russians did as recently as less than
a decade ago. And I think, I think what the Russians did was again, relatively low dose
by comparison. So I think there's plenty of room for microdosing and plenty of room for the kinds
of manipulation, systemic manipulation, if there's a motivated government to do it. And there's plenty
of room, you know, for other forms of corruption. So, so, but I do think that the industrial strength
doping has largely been quote, stop permitted. I think there are probably a bunch of novel compounds
that are out there, you know, small peptides that cause this to be released or that to be released,
which would be very, very difficult to detect. They'd have vanishingly short half-lives and so
forth. And they would just boost your endogenous production of hormone X, Y or Z, you know,
something like a growth hormone releasing factor or, or some sort of, you know, something that
caused testosterone levels to go up or so forth. So, so I think that, that, that it's a cat and
mouse game. And you're always going to, I think, I think for the kind of the big three amphetamines,
EPO slash blood doping in anabolic steroids slash growth hormone, I think that, that the testing has
gotten better and industrial strength doping is over. I think we, we don't know what we don't know
about these novel compounds. And I think what we learned from the ball code situation is that
there are all sorts of, you know, clever bathtub chemists who can make all sorts of things,
you know, at home in the garage, wherever it is in, in, in, in a very unregulated environment.
And the barrier to entry for that kind of a do it yourself sort of stuff is quite low.
You can buy, you know, all sorts of laboratory equipment and reagents
and all sorts of things. So you don't have to be, you know, a big pharma house to make,
make interesting things. Like that's why I'd say we are with doping.
How familiar are you with, with Balco and the, and the agency?
Balco and Patrick Arnold.
You know Patrick?
I don't know Patrick, but I know who he is. And the tragedy of Patrick Arnold, this tremendous,
you know, kind of a guy with a master's degree, I believe in organic chemistry,
you know, tragic tragedy of Patrick Arnold, he wasn't working for, wasn't working for
one of the big pharma companies making anti aging and isochromania compounds. That's the,
you know, where he had, he had been, was making, you know, unusual,
you know, chemical chemically modified androgens.
Yeah. I actually, I've met Patrick a number of times, I've spent a lot of time speaking with him
and in a very unemotional way and just a very frank way he can explain in great detail exactly
how he modified these androgens.
No. And the guy has encyclopedic knowledge, apparently, of everything that's ever been
synthesized in the androgen field and what it does in terms of half-life and that metabolism
and that sort of thing. And then I think if you think about Victor Conte Jr., you know, a refugee
from the tower of power, junior college educated rock slash jazz musician, who's one of the great
auto didex ever out there. And, you know, so I think with both of these individuals, step back
from the legal ethical ramifications and say, what do they know? And try to be a little bit
objective about that. And then, you know, with doping, you get into all sorts of other sort of
areas, you know, you know, what was in the in the in the in the cultures those people were operating
in, what was considered the cultural norm? I mean, you know, and Lance was not the only person doing
industrial strength doping. Was he doing it better than other people if there were six ways to dope
and and person X was doing two and you were doing three, was Lance doing all six, that sort of thing.
And so I think that that the other thing people have to recognize about doping
is that you're always going to in these incredibly competitive situations with these
incredibly competitive people with competitive organizations or people that have, you know,
foreign policy, you know, our country is better than yours because we want more medals,
is that there's always going to be some sort of arms race mentality. And you see it with training,
you know, if you're in there lifting an hour a day, I'm going to go lift an hour and 10 minutes a day.
And so where does it stop? Do you still think that growth hormone, human growth hormone,
which is, of course, not something that can readily be tested for, is still one of the more
utilized agents, probably even today for performance enhancement? You know, I think there's
probably some of it going on. You know, I think that my guess is people are probably have drifted
back to more short acting androgens, low dose, short acting androgens and hope for the best.
And that would be my guess. The same would be true with low dose EPO and or, and or, you know,
sort of related compounds or other factors. You know, but again, when you when you when you learn
about growth hormone is typically because person X says that they're sending FedEx package, you
know, trainer X or source exit has been sending FedEx packages to athlete Y, you know, that kind
of thing. Yeah. So as opposed to. Yeah. And I think that's that's really the bottom line is it's so
much of this is is, you know, and again, again, like the Russian, so much of this has a judicial,
judicial slash, you know, investigatory element to it when you when you get to the big scandals.
Why do you think some sports seem more effective than others? So, for example,
swimming as a general rule seems less impacted than than than, say, cycling or even running,
even though the demands are still pretty high. Hard to know. And how cultures had one way or the
next is is, you know, I lead, you know, is I feel like that's bones, Dr. Bones in Star Trek.
I'm a doctor, not a, you know what I mean? I'm a doctor, not a sociologist, Peter. And I think,
you know, in groups, out groups and the things that those folks, a sociologist and tribalism,
the people who think about, you know, tribalistic behaviors, what's normal, what's not normal,
and so forth. I think that that's really, really, really, really key to understanding that sort of
thing. Key to understanding that sort of thing. So we started this discussion, Mike, by talking
about the miracles of exercise. Correct. We went through all of these things that exercise is doing
physiologically, and how the net impact of these things is so profound. Correct. On the length of
your life and the quality of your life. There's no shortage of pharma companies out there that are
trying to understand how can those benefits be put into a pill? Exercise pill, sure. Exactly.
What is your level of optimism around the idea that some of the benefits of exercise could be
basically captured by a pharmaceutical strategy? So there's a couple things there,
Peter. One is the efforts for exercise mimetics so far have been primarily things that increase
mitochondrial biosynthesis. And that appears like it at least works in animal models. And then you
always, how do you translate it from one to the next? But as I pointed out, exercise, sure, it
makes your mitochondria better or makes more of them. But making your mitochondria better isn't
going to make your autonomic nervous system better, isn't going to make your blood pressure better.
Isn't going to necessarily make the lining of your blood vessels better, so on and so forth. So it's
not going to make your heart bigger, so on and so forth. So I think at least so far, at least so far,
these have been sort of one trick ponies. And while you might be able to get some benefits
for people that are wheelchair bound or whatever, although even those folks, I mean people that are
quadriplegics, let's put it that way, wheelchair bound or can exercise for some of the reasons that
may be helpful. I think the jury is really still out. And I think that I'm not particularly
enthusiastic about it. I don't think you're ever going to get one that does any more than a little
bit. I think more interestingly, I like to tell people at some level there's already an exercise
medic out there. It's called the poly pill. If you look at the data on people who get
a combination one pill a day of low dose statins, low dose blood pressure meds, and maybe one or two
other other components, it causes pretty nice reductions in risk factors in most people.
Because the doses are low, the side effects tend to be low and so forth. But again, none of this
is patentable. There's no market for it. But if people don't want to exercise, can exercise,
or whatever, I think a better choice than trying to find some mythical exercise of a medic is to
use a poly pill, which would do the same thing. You give them a statin, their cholesterol goes
down. And maybe their endothelial function gets better. You do a tiny bit of metformin,
maybe their glucose tolerance gets better. You do a bit of beta blockers, their heart rate is lower.
So again, I'm not advocating this. But there's all sorts of data out there that a poly pill
is a legitimate, whatever that means, potential public health strategy for lifestyle diseases.
I would encourage people to exercise and do the sorts of things you're talking about.
But I think poly pills have been understudied.
So, Mike, what is it you're most excited about right now? What is the question you're most
interested in trying to answer?
I'm excited about a lot of things. So we've got some interesting data with Sarah Baker
on sex differences in blood pressure regulation. I'm quite interested in human performance.
As you know, Peter, the first thing they teach in medical school is that a right shift in the
oxygen hemoglobin dissociation curve is good for you at altitude. Well, all animals that are
genetically adapted over centuries, millennia, to high altitude, llamas, the birds that fly
over Mount Everest and so forth, are left shifted. We've been doing some really cool hypoxia studies
and people with rare left shifted hemoglobin. I'm super interested in that just as sort of
a physiological question.
Can you explain to folks what the right and left shift looks like on the hemoglobin dissociation
curve?
A right shift, you know, think of a curvilinear situation or an S-shaped curve,
kind of an italicized curve. And so the idea is that if you shift it to the right,
the red stuff, the hemoglobin in your blood doesn't hold on to the oxygen. So it releases it and can
give the oxygen to the tissue. And that's great if it's hypoxic. Now, the problem with that
is it's harder for that kind of hemoglobin to get the oxygen out of the lung.
And animals like llamas and like these incredible athletes called the bar-headed goose that fly
over Mount Everest. Yeah. And without acclimation, they're living in the plains of Mongolia. One day
they just fly over Mount Everest and go to India. They're left shifted because they prefer to make
sure that they can pick up the oxygen out of the air in their lungs at very high altitude.
So we have a family of people and some other subjects that we've studied that are left
shifted. And it's very interesting. Meaning there is a family of people who genetically shift left
instead of shift right. Right. Correct. And there's all sorts of rare hemoglobin variants.
And these just are not, you know, they're not like sickle cell or anything like that.
So what's interesting, it's very interesting Peter to be sitting in the lab, having somebody
breathing 10% oxygen talking to you. These left shifted people do that. It's crazy. It's just wild.
What is the FiO2 at the top of Everest, by the way, just for comparison.
The FiO2 at the top of Everest is well, the barometric pressure is about 250. So the 21%
of 250. So roughly about 50. So once you get into your lung, I think arterial is about in the 30s.
Wow.
Yeah. And so 10% would be, and certainly at 15%, which is 3000 meters, these people exercise like,
like, no, you know, they do fine. So I'm very interested in that. And then as I mentioned,
you know, before we went on is through a weird collection of events. When the pandemic struck
in March and early April of 2020, I somehow became the principal investigator of the US
convalescent plasma program, a program that was initially designed to facilitate in 5,000 patients
compassionate use of convalescent plasma plasma from recovered antibody rich plasma from recovered
COVID patients that we would give to give to people who had disease and hopefully the
antibodies would help them. And they're through all sorts of twists and turns. We ended up doing
over a hundred thousand people. We found evidence. If we gave people a whole lot of antibody early
in the course of disease, we made them better. We also found some evidence that it was probably very
helpful in people that were immune suppressed. And that has been the gift that keeps giving. So at age
60, you know, one 62 63, I kept kind of a new career in immunology and infectious disease.
And so we're pursuing that and we're especially interested in that Peter, because whenever
COVID sort of finally winds down, about two to 3% of the population is what we call B cell
deficient. So B cells are the cells in your body that make antibodies help you respond to fight
the virus or respond to the vaccine. And about two or 3% of the people don't have any or don't have
very many. And those people continue will continue to get COVID and other forms of infectious disease.
And antibody therapy is essential to help those folks. And I was telling you,
you know, I'm very happy that we've published papers in high profile journals. But
we just learned yesterday from People magazine of all places that the actor Jeff Bridges,
you know, the dude from the big Lebowski he, dude himself, the dude himself had gotten lymphoma,
gotten drugs that that depleted his B cells, which is typical for lymphoma patients,
got COVID, he could not clear the COVID and responded to convalescent plasma.
What's the total volume of plasma you need to give a patient in that setting?
If you get really high, tighter stuff, two to 400 mls.
That's a one time treatment?
Yeah, typically. Sometimes we give people more. And what's been helpful Peter is that
we now have people that have been both vaccinated and they've had a breakthrough infection,
or they've had an infection and been vaccinated, right? So they have hybrid immunity. And those
people make, you know, really, really, their plasma has a whole, whole lot of antibodies in them.
And they're broad spectrum. So they cover all the variants. And they almost anticipate future
variants because of the way the immune system works. And as a sort of a sloppy replicator.
And so they cover a lot of the variants that cover potential future variants and as monoclonal
antibodies, which have been super helpful during the pandemic, as those get less effective due to
escape variants, this very high, tighter plasma is still available. So, so we're back doing exercise
studies. We're back writing papers about exercise and doing our regular physiology. But I think,
yeah, this antibody therapy has really got, you know, took a bite out of me. And it's, it's,
it's like what Jim Bowden said, the great pitcher, you know, you spend your life
gripping the ball and thinking about your grip on the ball. And in reality,
it was the other way around the ball had a grip on you. So, you know, I've been thinking a lot
about antibodies and maybe antibodies have been thinking about me because it's really hard to
stop thinking about it because it's so interesting. And, and we get reports back to us from, you know,
not famous patients that are very similar to what we've heard of Mr. Bridges. So we're
quite excited to pursue these solutions for our immune suppressed patients. And I'm especially,
you know, when I started medical school in 1982, those sorts of patients, you know,
their life expectancy was quite low. And now our patients with hemolygmacy, multiple myeloma,
lymphoma, leukemias, a lot of those people live a long, long time.
And so how long after a person is infected and recovers from infection,
are they a suitable plasma donor? Within about two to three weeks.
And how long? And then like, when does that window close?
Certainly, it goes on for three or four months, you know, probably up to six months.
And it would probably reopen if they got boosted, that sort of thing.
But it only, you only get sufficient antibodies from people who have had the actual infection,
not from people who just go get a booster. What's happened is, is that that's been initially
because there were no vaccines, we only had people that had the normal normal infection.
Since the vaccines have become widely available in the last almost 18 months now, or 15, 16 months,
we've now been able to get people who've had both. And those people, the people that have had both
are really the super donors, you know, and we can work with those people to come back in and get
multiple units. We collect our own blood at Mayo. We have a terrific blood bank here locally, but
but they're using it at Hopkins, they're using it at Harvard, using it at Einstein,
a lot of other big places. We're working with the societies, the Food and Drug Administration,
and others like the Lymphoma and Leukemia Lymphoma Society, the CLL Group, Infectious Disease,
or excuse me, Immune Deficiency Foundation, to make sure that we have this available for their,
for those sorts of patients. They're doing this at scale in France to about 50 patients a week,
which would be about 300 a week in the US if you account for, you know, population differences.
So that's one of the things we're quite interested in. This is something people can donate. It's a
way for people to give back. Are you able to find sufficient donors? Are there enough donors?
Yeah, yeah, there's sufficient there. Again, because there's so many people who've been
both infected and broken through, there's a, you know, there's always logistical issues
in terms of getting a person to the blood collecting center, getting it here, getting it
there, but availability should be pretty high. So, and with plasma, do you still have to do a type
and cross? Yeah, you still got, it's got to still be typed and crossed and people are subject to,
they have to be eligible to otherwise donate blood. Yeah. Okay. But during that, during the
peak of plasma use prior to the vaccines and prior to the monofamals, you know, 20, 30, 40,000 units
a week were being used in the country. And in the weeks when more plasma was being used, the death
rate two weeks later was lower. So there's a pretty nice correlation between that. So that's
been, but, but again, I think, you know, we've talked about training, we've talked about, you
know, a little bit about coaching, we've talked about, you know, participation in support and so
forth. But I think one of the things that really helped me, you know, work with the government and
work with our team to, to instead of do a 5,000 person demonstration project, do a, do a, really
a treatment registry and over a hundred thousand or a hundred thousand patients was the organizational
skills I learned from my coaches who, and I, and I used to joke with the, uh, higher ups in the food
and drug administration. They'd say, well, how did you do that? I'd say I'm a recovering physical
educator. And that was always, uh, always got, I was always good for a laughter and at least a few
dark hours. Last, last question, Mike, given your long standing history in athletics, both personally
and professionally, are you optimistic or pessimistic about the future of Americans based
on the level of physical activity that we, we see? Uh, we need to do something. We need to do
something. And I think it really reflects our society in general. I think that you have,
you know, for lack of a better word, upper middle-class kids who have access to superb coaching,
to superb facilities and to programmatic things. I think we've got a tremendous problem with play
and unstructured play. And I think we've got a whole lot of people that are, are things that,
when I was growing up in the sixties and seventies that were done through the park,
park district and the school school district, I think a lot of those opportunities are, uh,
are, uh, have followed by the wayside. I mean, we used to have, you know, the kids who were
college athletes used to come back and have open gym all over Tucson when I was a kid. And there's
no open gym at the high schools in Rochester, Minnesota, a rich community in the summer. And,
and I mean, the, and the advantage of open gym was, Hey, you know, you got people off the street and
they were doing things and, and, um, you got better athletes and, and, and, uh, and, and, you know,
even the, and the police knew where we were, uh, which, which, which they're always very pleased
about, you know, if they know that they, if they know that all the high energy boys are in one place,
it makes their life a little easier as well. So, so I think, uh, yeah, I think it's a real problem.
So, so I think we'll have these incredible performances by the kids who have access,
but I think that, that what we're doing in the rest of the world is, is, is problematic. And,
and, and, you know, if I could, I guess if I could do anything, uh, I'd start a national open gym
movement, uh, you know, uh, winter, summer, whatever. Cause a lot of, we have a lot of
nice facilities that are used just to, you know, a limited number of times per day.
Yeah. Could you imagine if you were Czar and you could sort of do anything and you just said,
no matter what it, no matter what your lot is in life, right? If you're a school child, if you're
correct, a person who works in an office, if you're a person who works in,
we somehow rearrange the day such that every person has a mandatory one hour activity.
Right. You, you could make it exercise, right? You could make it, you, you, you can go to the gym for
an hour, but, but it could also be, look at a minimum, you got to go out and walk.
Well, you know, it's interesting you mentioned that because, uh, in our department, uh,
with, with, uh, remote work and so forth, this has broken element, but we had a number of
secretaries, uh, uh, terrific, you know, all of them, they were all women, middle aged women.
And we have this huge sort of, uh, you know, deep bunker system with the bowels of the hospital
with these huge hallways. And it's about a mile around the place. And, and these, uh, these,
these folks would go down and walk at lunch and they're literally, you know, they'd bring,
bring their tennis shoes to work and they, they would meet up with their pals and, uh,
you know, they'd go do 30, 40 minutes a day of, of laps at lunchtime, uh, with the secretaries
all over the hospital. And it was, uh, I think terrific for them. Uh, yeah, I think it was a
social event for them. And, and I think that they solved a lot of problems too. And they actually
made them way more productive. I believe it. Well, like, as I said at the outset, I've enjoyed reading
the papers for, yeah, for more than two decades and I'll continue to do so. And it's
it's been great to chat and hopefully we can meet in person at some point and do a workout together.
What do you live now? Austin or someplace? Yeah, I live in Austin. Yeah. Now Eddie Coyle at the
University of Texas is a good friend of mine. So yeah, I look forward to it. Yeah. Well, it's funny.
I, I have been meaning to, to get ahold of him and I'd like to have him on the podcast as well.
Because Eddie's quite a guy. Yep. Eddie's quite a guy. Yeah, exactly. All right, Peter. Thanks
much. Yep. All right. Thanks. Bye-bye.