Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Shereen. It's great to finally meet you. Not in person, but better than being on the
phone, I guess.
Yes, same here.
So, you know, people on this podcast have probably heard me in a couple of episodes
reference this thing called DBT. I've never really gone into much detail about it, but
it's something I've wanted to obviously have a dedicated podcast around, and now we're
finally going to get to do that. So, I mean, I guess maybe we can just start by kind of
defining what it is a little bit before we get into its history, its founder, your involvement,
and things like that. So, if you were at a party and somebody said, Shereen, I heard
that you're a DBT therapist and a practitioner. Can you tell me what that is? What would you say?
Sure. So, DBT stands for Dialectical Behavior Therapy, abbreviated DBT, and it's a form of
therapy or a form of talk therapy that is largely inspired by cognitive behavioral therapy,
also abbreviated as CBT. So, we often say that DBT is a form of cognitive behavioral therapy
that was designed for individuals that have complex mental health problems and originally
designed for individuals that are suicidal or self-harming and who may meet criteria for a
disorder called borderline personality disorder. So, at its simplest, I would say it's a form of
cognitive behavioral therapy that was designed for more complex people or presentations. But then,
of course, there's a lot more nuance beyond that. Yeah, which we'll certainly get into.
Maybe give people a bit of background on what cognitive behavioral therapy is. I mean, that
term I've heard a lot, but truthfully, I don't know much about CBT outside of CBT-I,
which is cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia, which we have referred, I would say,
over the past five or six years, probably a dozen of our patients to CBT-I practitioners.
And I think I can say without exception, it has always proved to be incredibly valuable,
not just incrementally valuable, but incredibly valuable. But that's the very limited experience
that I have with CBT is through that one narrow lens. Is there something more broadly we can say
about CBT that then allows us to contrast it with DBT? Yeah, so CBT refers to maybe a class of
talk therapy and could often be used to contrast with other kinds of talk therapy. But some of the
distinguishing features of cognitive behavioral therapy is that it's present focused, so focused
on what's happening for people right now in terms of the problems they're experiencing, and less
focused on one's history, one's childhood, less focused on the sorts of things that have led to
the person experiencing the problems that they're experiencing. So it's present focused, and it's,
as the name implied, it's focused on working with thoughts and behaviors that go along with the
problems that people experience. So in CBT-I, for example, it would be, you know, what are the
thoughts that are contributing to your insomnia? And how do we work on modifying or changing those
thoughts that you're having in order to increase the likelihood that you fall asleep, or stay asleep?
What are the behaviors that you do that promote sleep? What are the behaviors that you do that
get in the way of sleep? And how do we modify that? So at its most concrete level, it really is
working with thoughts and behaviors that, in the present, that are contributing to your problems
right now. So it's very much an active problem-solving approach. And I think what is, with people who
don't have a lot of experience with therapy or receiving mental health treatment, they might have
an idea, based on the media or TV or movies, that the best therapy is one where you just go in and
talk about whatever is on your mind. And CBT and similarly, DBT is much more structured and guided
than that. And the other distinguishing feature I will say about CBT and DBT is that
it's evidence-based, meaning that we construct treatments in a way that we could measure
its effectiveness. And if we find that something is not effective for people, then it's not likely
to stay in the therapy. That's our goal, anyway, is to be as empirical and scientific in our approach
as possible. So how long has CBT been around as a discipline? I would say it emerged, you know,
probably the figure that is associated with the beginning of CBT is a man named Aaron Beck,
who died last year, I believe, at the age of 100. And so he, or something like that number,
I would say it was probably the 60s in which he first started developing his form of cognitive
therapy. He was trained as a psychoanalyst and was seeing that it wasn't all that useful for a lot of
the patients that he was treating in psychiatry. And so he started developing an approach that was
much more about changing the way people thought about themselves and others.
So let's talk about Marcia, who is obviously Marcia Lindhen, who's, you know,
I think it's safe to say really the creator and founder of DBT, is that a fair statement?
Yes, for sure.
So tell me about her journey. Presumably, she had tried CBT both as a patient and maybe even
as a therapist before realizing that there was a way that it could be improved upon for at least
a subset of patients and or a subset of problems. Would that be kind of a fair statement?
Yeah, so the origin story of DBT was that originally Marcia set out to apply what might
be considered standard CBT to folks who were chronically suicidal. And this was, you know,
and this was, you know, perhaps beginning in the 70s. She was receiving advanced training at
Stony Brook in New York. At that time, Stony Brook was considered one of the premier places to
learn and apply behavior therapy. And back in the days of the 70s, 80s, there was really the heyday
of behaviorism. And the idea was, in some ways, in many ways oversimplified. But the idea was that
we could treat any mental health problem with behavior therapy in very few sessions just by
applying these, you know, standard principles of what we know about behavior change.
By the way, can you give me an example of what that would be? So does that mean that if
if a person was clinically depressed and came in and they were suicidal, what would the CBT
approach have been in the 70s or 80s to address that concern?
Well, I might if I can come back to depression and suicide in a minute, but I might start with
anxiety disorders, because this is actually what behavior therapy and CBT was probably most
prolific about in those days. And the idea was that you could have somebody who came into
treatment with a fear of something, a phobia, it could be something like a fear of heights,
or a fear of spiders, or it could be a fear of social situations, social anxiety, and the
behavior therapy approach to this or the cognitive behavioral therapy approach to this would be
to teach people competing thoughts. So rather than thinking this thing will kill me,
I can learn to have thoughts like, I can tolerate this, this might be difficult, but I can
handle it, or even have thoughts like this is not going to kill me. But those thoughts
were only one part of it. The other piece of it was the more behavioral piece, which is
exposure, basically saying that how you're going to get over your fear of spiders is not to talk
about it every week for an hour with somebody, but it's actually going to be coming into contact
with spiders repeatedly, over and over again, so that you learn that you can handle it. But you
also learn that the fear outcome is not going to occur. So that was some of those...
Change your thoughts and get exposure, change your thoughts, get exposure.
Exactly. And the getting exposure is changing your behavior because you want to run away or avoid,
and instead it's saying come into contact with approach, something that you want to avoid.
Right. And so what they were finding in these early days of applying CBT is saying
people may have gone to psychoanalysis, which was the dominant paradigm of therapy in those days.
And by the way, this is almost exclusively a rich white person issue when I'm talking about
who was receiving treatment for mental health problems. That's what I'm talking about back in
those days, largely. And so people could go to a psychoanalysis, a psychoanalyst, and talk about
their fears for months and years and not necessarily do better with them. And so CBT comes along and
says, actually, we could do this sometimes, depending on what the fear is in one session.
There were people who would do like a three hour session to, quote unquote, cure somebody of a
phobia. And they were finding that it worked. And so then you say, okay, how do we take those
principles to something like depression? And this is what Aaron Beck started to do with cognitive
therapy more, was noticing that people who have depression tend to think in very particular ways.
They have negative interpretations of almost everything, right? And also about themselves,
about their future, about others. And so a cognitive behavioral approach to depression
would be about working on changing those thoughts to be more balanced and evidence-based. And then
also the behavior change that goes along with depression is usually about getting active.
So when somebody is depressed, the tendency is to retreat, shut down, avoid. And the behavioral
treatments for depression would be to get people activated and to solve the problems that are
causing the depression, whether it's unhappiness with a job, unhappiness with a relationship,
and work on targeting the problems that are causing depression in a systematic way.
How successful was it? You mentioned earlier that evidence is a very important part of this.
How were they able to tally the results and determine if their intervention
was in fact better than the standard of care at the time?
Right. So the history of psychotherapy trials is largely based on a paradigm known as randomized
clinical trials, where you would recruit individuals who meet certain inclusion criteria,
say somebody meets the diagnosis for depression, and then you would randomize them to either, say,
receive 12 weeks of cognitive behavioral therapy or receive nothing. And then you would
nothing or receive treatment as usual or standard of care and then evaluate outcomes over time.
And with things like depression and anxiety disorders, there are these standard measures
that are popular within our field, where we have developed benchmarks for what we're trying to get
to, what might be considered a success. And I would say that in general, the trials for CBT
for things like depression and anxiety are overwhelmingly positive, meaning that most of
the trials, especially in the early days when you were comparing CBT to nothing or treatment as usual,
found very large effects for CBT in those settings. Now, I think where we see or where
we'll come back to Marsha emerging is recognizing that, of course, none of these treatments were
100% successful for everybody. And more than that is that when you look at these studies and you see
who were these studies done with, the inclusion criteria, meaning what allowed somebody to be
in the study, were often quite narrow. For example, with a depression study, the person
might have to meet the criteria for a diagnosis of depression, but not have suicidal behavior.
So people with suicidal behavior may be excluded from a lot of those studies, which makes sense
from a research point of view in some contexts. But in other contexts, doesn't make sense because
of course we know that a lot of people who experience depression are also suicidal. So
if you're removing suicidal people or not allowing suicidal people to be part of this research,
then we don't know ultimately if the treatments work for those populations.
So when did, I mean Marsha as a young girl, I think was diagnosed with schizophrenia,
is that correct? And was treated with electroconvulsive therapy and all sorts of things that
are still used today, but probably not as frequently and probably with a bit more
particular attention to the use case, probably used more liberally than I'm guessing.
So Marsha was a teenager, I believe, at the time that she was receiving
a lot of treatment. And this was in the late 60s, if I'm, no, wait, if I'm remembering correctly,
what, when she was born now that I'm thinking about it. But it was before CBT was really in
the picture. And she was sent away, hospitalized for being suicidal and chronic, and she was
chronically self-injuring, doing a number of things to cause physical harm to herself as a way
of relieving emotional intensity and overwhelming emotions. And so at the time, there was not
a lot of treatment options that were available. And the medical model was to treat with really
strong meds, you know, antipsychotic meds at the time, or to use something like electroconvulsive
therapy. And so those were the treatments that she was exposed to from a very young age,
in addition to therapy. But the types of therapy that she was receiving at that time
were unlikely to be, you know, anything like the cognitive behavioral treatment we know today.
So how did she find her way from being almost institutionalized to eventually, you know,
getting an education and herself becoming a therapist? What was that journey that went from
that teenage girl to kind of the person who created DBT?
Yeah, so she has written about this in a memoir as well as described it in a piece in which she,
in the New York Times, which was a piece where she kind of came out to the world as having
been someone who experienced her own struggles, significant struggles with mental health. And I
say that as a preface because for that article in the New York Times came out, I believe in 2010,
2011. So for most of her career, she was not forthcoming about this, her own personal
struggles. She would tell people that were close to her new, her students, I was one of them,
knew about this experience, but she wasn't public about it. And she would long say that the reason
for that is because she wanted DBT to be judged on its merit empirically. She did not want
DBT to be judged on her personal story alone. She wanted this to be a scientific treatment that
lives and dies by its outcome, she would say. So when she would talk about how DBT developed
to the public, she would talk about it in leaving out this earlier part of her own history. So the
earlier part of her own history that she describes is that she had a spiritual moment when she was in
one of these institutions. And the spiritual moment was that she describes experiencing
God in a very dark moment of her own life. And in that moment, she realized that she could,
she felt the love of God and felt that she could serve this purpose in life, which is
to get out of hell, her own experience, and then to work her entire life to get other people out of
hell. And that was how she took this spiritual experience and developed her life's work based on
that. Now another reason why she did it. How old was she, Shereen at that time? I would say
I would say as best I remember in her early late teens or early twenties.
Kind of profound to follow through on something that you could argue,
well, God, you were still so young when that was happening. And was she at some point here
diagnosed as having a borderline personality disorder as well? Or is that something that
is more retrospective where it's sort of like looking back, she was probably misdiagnosed as
having schizophrenia. I mean, what was the state of understanding of her actual condition?
So I believe that she was probably, you still see this today, but when people are unclear about how
to explain someone's problems, they get given almost every diagnosis in the book. And now this
would have been before the criteria that we now know is borderline personality disorder being
defined in the way it is most well known would have started in the third edition of the DSM,
which came out in about 1980. So the criteria that we have now to define borderline personality
disorder was not the same as when she was receiving treatment. So I believe that she
had a number of diagnoses attributed to her. I can't remember, it's quite possible that
borderline personality disorder was one of them, because of course, that's also the diagnosis that
they give people when they don't know how to treat them. And so it wouldn't surprise me.
And what are the criteria? Tell folks what borderline personality disorder is today. What
do we know today? Yeah, so borderline personality disorder is considered a complex mental health
disorder that is defined as meeting. There are nine criteria of borderline personality disorder
as defined by the DSM. And in order to meet criteria or to have the condition, you have to
endorse five of the nine, which actually means that ultimately, it's a really heterogeneous
disorder, because there's all these different combinations and different ways in which one
can meet criteria. One of the things that Marsha did was to restructure the different criteria
of borderline personality disorder in a way that perhaps is more understandable and also makes more
cohesive sense. And to say that it's a disorder of dysregulation across a number of different
domains. So the core domain of dysregulation that we see in borderline personality disorder is what
we refer to as emotion dysregulation. And this is largely defined by people's experience of emotions
as feeling like they have very intense emotions, they don't feel like they can control their
emotions very well, their emotions change very rapidly. So that's referred to as affective
lability, that the emotions will go from set intense sadness to intense shame to fear to joy,
you know, very quickly and seemingly without a lot of reason. So emotion dysregulation is part
and considered core to the disorder of borderline personality disorder. And then these other domains
of dysregulation stem from emotion dysregulation and include behavior dysregulation. So not having
control over or feeling like you don't have control over your behaviors. This is associated
with a lot of impulsivity and behaviors that go along with impulsivity. So substance use,
reckless spending, impulsive sexual behavior, impulsive driving, you know, behaviors that are
experienced as impulsive and potentially could cause problems for the person. Impulsive eating
is another domain. I mean, it sounds like there's quite an overlap, at least in some of those with
bipolar disorder, right? Bipolar one, where you could sort of see, I don't know about the
affective lability, but certainly the mania side of it sounds like it might be consistent with some
of that dysregulation. I'm guessing that's what makes psychiatry so difficult is you don't have
biomarkers, you don't have imaging scans that give you diagnoses, right? Right. We don't. And so there
is, you're right, a lot of overlap and actually probably the ones, the overlap that is more
consistent or difficult to discriminate as bipolar two, because bipolar one is associated with
the depression, longer, longer lengths of either a pure manic state or a pure depressed state. Bipolar
two might have manic states, but it is shorter in duration or might not be, you know, super manic,
right, as high. And so that's often really hard to discriminate from somebody who has borderline
personality disorder. And generally what we're talking about with BPD as opposed to bipolar is
that we actually see the mood changes happening more frequently within BPD than with bipolar two.
But I'm probably oversimplifying, but that's what I would be looking for if I was trying to
assess the difference between the two. A person with BPD, what are the challenges that they face
in the world, right? If this is a, let's just assume this is a person of totally normal intelligence
and other, all physical capabilities are fine. And this is sort of the one issue, this one
psychological issue. How does it manifest itself for that person when they're in school, when they're
in college, if they get married, if they have kids, like help us understand how this condition
makes life more difficult for the individual and those around them. Yes. So one thing I'll say is
that you rarely will see this condition in isolation of anything else. And again, this speaks to one
of the complexities of trying to study psychiatry that I think on average people who meet criteria
for BPD have three to four other mental health problems at the same time. So they'll also meet
criteria for depression or an anxiety disorder or a substance use disorder or an eating disorder.
And those things aren't stemming from the BPD. These things are, we believe independently there
as well. Well, I think it depends on who you ask because I would say as somebody who is trained
mostly behaviorally, I would say the diagnosis matters less than how we conceptualize these
problems. And to that point, I would agree with you. We could say emotion dysregulation is central
to all of those things, but the diagnostic system as we currently have it does not allow for that.
So they would say, if somebody meets criteria for these other disorders, they also have these other
disorders. So how somebody with borderline personality disorder lives their lives, I would
say it's complicated because on the one end of the continuum, we see people who have severe problems
associated with BPD such that they struggle to hold on to a job so they don't work and they're
on disability or receiving social security. They can't maintain relationships. So they're very
isolated. And why is that? Why are relationships blowing up and why are they not able to hold down
a job? What's the fundamental issue or fundamental issues that are impairing them?
From a DBT perspective, we would say that it all comes back to difficulty regulating emotions.
So that if I experience intense emotions that I feel like I can't control, when I get angry,
I lash out. When I get scared, I run away or avoid. Or I have emotion dys... One of the
criteria that goes along with BPD that you could see as tied with emotion dysregulation problems
is what's referred to as fears of abandonment. So a person with BPD often will have a lot of fear
that a person that they love or are close to will leave them. And if I am in a relationship
where I am afraid that the other person is going to leave me all the time, that may cause me to
behave in ways that are frantic, chaotic, and actually paradoxically have the effect of causing
the other person to be more likely to leave. Texting the person, calling the person relentlessly.
If a person doesn't come home or call at the time that they say they will, having the experience of
feeling like I'm losing it because I don't know where that person is or perhaps they've left me.
As a result, if I have BPD, I experience intense fear, intense shame, intense sadness, and now I
don't know what to do with this intense behavior. And I may self-injure as a way of leaving that
emotional intensity. Or I may threaten suicide as a way of getting the person to come back to me.
And maybe I'm doing this without even having awareness that that's the effect of my behavior.
I just know that in this moment, I don't know what to do. I feel entirely out of control,
and I need to do something to fix it in this moment. What is the
mortality of BPD? I was very surprised to learn recently that anorexia nervosa has probably the
highest mortality of any psychiatric condition. I would have guessed depression, presumably.
But where does BPD stand in terms of mortality, either through self-harm and neglect potentially,
or obviously suicide? I sometimes get into the weeds a little bit about this. And when,
as an academic and psychologist, what I find, and someone who studies suicide,
I review a lot of manuscripts and grant proposals, and I am always saddened and amused
when I see people write about a disorder and say, this disorder has one of the highest rates of
suicide. Because if you look at it, it seems like every disorder has one of the highest rates of
suicide. And I think it's because we don't know how to study this very well, honestly. We don't know
how to determine of the people who die by suicide what are the mental health conditions
that they had, and what is the relative risk according to these different disorders.
Especially when you overlap, because as you said earlier, if a person with BPD also suffers
significant depression, if they commit suicide, are we attributing that to depression?
So, no, I think my question more broadly is knowing that one could never tease that out,
how risky is it for an individual understanding all of the comorbidities that tend to cluster with it?
I will say it's very high. And one way in which I can answer this is that another criteria for
for BPD is repeated or chronic self-injury or suicide attempts. And upwards more than 75%
of people, and in some studies 90 to 95% of people who meet criteria for borderline personality
disorder, engage in self-injury or have made more than one suicide attempt in their lives.
And this tells us a couple of things. One is that on its own is considered a very high risk
behavior because people who engage in self-injury, even if they don't intend to die,
there could be accidental death as a result of self-injury.
What are some examples, I mean, people probably think of the most common examples of people
cutting themselves or burning themselves. What are some other examples of self-injurious behavior
that people engage in? Head banging or punching or hitting oneself. There are multiple forms of
cutting that include different objects to cut, but could also be people really intensely scratching
themselves to the point where they draw blood. There's overdosing is considered a form of
self-injury, especially if it's or you have to determine is this with intent to die or not,
but there are people who overdose without intent to die as a way of hurting themselves.
There's also more rare, but other forms of self-injury may involve ingesting toxic substances,
et cetera. So this has also, I think, evolved over time, or we didn't know how to study it
very well over the years because even in my career, I feel like 20 years ago when we were
talking about self-injury, we were talking much more about things like cutting or burning.
I feel like as there have been more people interested in studying self-injury,
we're also finding out about other ways in which people cause harm to themselves. Then there's all
sorts of debates about whether this is considered self-injury or not because some people might say,
I have binge eating or I overeat and I do that intentionally even though I know it's causing
harm to myself. Whether we classify that diagnostically as self-harm or not is one
question, but whether a person considers themselves actively doing harm to themselves,
that's another question. What's the male-female split in BPD?
Yeah. So that's another thing that's changed over time. It was long thought to be a female
disorder and there's all sorts of reasons for that. A lot of them are sexist. Now we
see more studies that indicate that there are roughly equivalent rates among men and women.
However, there's still a diagnostic bias for tending to diagnose women more often as BPD
intending not to diagnose men with BPD. So does that mean underdiagnosing men over diagnosing
women potentially? I think so. I think the underdiagnosing of men has been shown in a number of
studies and it appears that men have to be more severe in order to receive the diagnosis
than women. Whether women are over diagnosed, I'm not sure, but I think it's very rare that you would
see a psychiatrist or a medical professional do a diagnostic assessment. I think it's much more
likely that they base that diagnosis on is this person difficult in some way. So when you look at
the twin concordant studies of things ranging from autism to depression, you see a very strong
genetic component to these things. Do you have a sense of how strong the genetic link is for BPD,
presumably based on these identical twin discordant studies, identical twins raised separately and
looking at the prevalence. How much of this is genetic and then how much of this is environmental
where life events trigger a susceptible individual to manifest the traits?
So I don't know the data off the top of my head about the twin concordants, but I would say there's
a general understanding that there is of course a genetic component to this disorder.
And I would say that the DBT framework is one that has a model for explaining how BPD
develops, which we can probably get into, but that speaks to the fact that there is both a
genetic and an environmental component to the development of the disorder.
So let's go back to Marcia in her journey. So she has this, you know, literally come to Jesus,
right? So she has this kind of epiphany in her late teens or early twenties,
which it sounds like, you know, puts her on a different path, potentially saves her life.
It's still a long way from there to where we are today. So walk us through that journey.
Right. So this is where it picks up in terms of the story that is part of the development of
DBT story. So now leaving out her own personal history, you know, Marcia went on to get a degree
in, I mean, I should also point out that I think one of the factors that led to Marcia being able
to do this is that I think she's hands down a genius. And so that was probably despite her
really difficult experiences. She had this amazing capacity for, you know, thought that helped her,
I'm sure, in numerous ways, including developing this treatment. But so she went on to get a degree
in social psychology, a social psychology PhD, which is a little known fact about her that she's
not a clinic. She doesn't have a degree in clinical psychology, but she got her social
psychology degree, but then decided that she wanted to get clinical training. And that's what
led her to this training experience at Stony Brook, which is where they were doing a lot of work
on theory and treatment related to cognitive behavioral treatments for a range of disorders.
And at that time, nobody was studying cognitive behavioral treatment for suicidal populations.
And so Marcia decided, I want to take what we know about CBT that seems to be hugely effective
for all of these disorders. And I want to take all that we know about CBT and just plop it into
treating chronically suicidal individuals. The way she reports it is saying she wasn't interested at
that time in diagnosis, she just wanted to work with people who chronically experienced urges to
die. And so that's what she attempted to do. And by her accounts, this quickly blew up.
And just for timing, this is kind of, I'm guessing this is now the early 80s?
Yes. Late 70s, early 80s when she did her fellowship there.
And do we have a sense of how she is treating herself at this point? In other words, how is
she regulating her own emotions? Are the tools of CBT things that she is finding helpful for her own
self-care? This is a great question. And I'm not sure I know what the answer is. And what's
interesting is that I think that what Marcia did was she took a lot of her own experiences,
and then she was able to translate that into cognitive behavioral terms, which led to the
development of a lot of the skills in the in DBT that she developed for people. Whether she was
thinking at the time about applying CBT to herself, I don't know. But I think that that's
what she ended up doing by developing these. So she sort of became the index case, right?
She was sort of not necessarily thinking it this way, but she was working out the tools of how do
you transition. I sort of liken that to what Bruce Lee did. I don't know how familiar you are
with Bruce Lee, but most people sort of know him as kind of a movie star in martial arts. But he
was far more relevant in creating a system of martial arts called Jeet Kune Do, which took from
over 30 different other styles of martial arts and in his words, took what was useful and discarded
what was useless and sort of created a new system with a very particular goal, by the way.
So he had a very clear objective in what Jeet Kune Do was to be about. And in some ways,
it's almost like that's what Marcia was doing on herself, right? Yes, on herself and also in her
treatment development work, which is a very iterative process like, let me try this. Does
this work? I'll keep it. Does it not work? I'll throw it out. If it works, what is it? How do I
define it? How do I write about it in a way that other people can do it? And put it all together
in a package. Again, I think this speaks to how brilliant I think she is that she could do it,
but it does align with what you're describing, which is really, and what's I think really
exciting about treatment development work is this whole process of figuring it out as you go
and then trying to replicate it and really using the client's experience to say,
is this having the intended effect? So I interrupted you, but let's go back to Marcia
at Stony Brook and finding out that CBT in its current form is not helping suicidal patients,
at least not to a level that she's feeling is successful, right? Right. So what she,
again, this is secondhand, so I just tell the story as though I'm her, but what she would
report is, okay, I go into my session with somebody and I ask them about what are all
the problems that you're experiencing that is causing you to feel suicidal. And the person would
say, I hate my job, you know, I hate my relationships, I don't have any pleasure in my life, whatever
those things are. And Marcia with the CBT lens would say, no problem. We can figure this all out.
We'll just, you know, take all of your problems. We'll put them on the list. We'll systematically
go through each of your problem one by one, which we'll solve. And we'll figure this out in no time.
And the way she reports it is that she did that feeling all the hope in the world and the reaction
that she got was totally unexpected, which is people saying, you have no idea. You have no idea
how bad my problems are. If you thought that these are things that are easy to solve,
you are sorely misunderstanding the depths of my problem. You clearly don't understand anything
about me or my situation if you think that these are things that could be easily solved.
And more than that, if these were easily solved, I would have solved them a long time ago. You have
no idea how much I'm suffering. You don't get it. So this iterative process was like, okay,
this blew up, right? Clearly, this isn't working the way I intended. And so the next piece of her
story is she would say, okay, that's not working. I need to figure out what's going to work. And she
said, she took kind of the other perspective and she said, okay, what they're telling me is that I
don't understand the depths of their problems. And maybe that's true. And so what I need to do now
is tell them and work with them to completely understand. And so she would go into her sessions
with, again, people who are chronically suicidal and say, you're right, your problems
are too difficult. You've had long standing experiences with trauma. You've been treated
terribly your whole life. You have a number of obstacles that may prevent you from getting the
job that you want or the relationship that you want. And perhaps what we need to do is work on
accepting your life as it is and finding joy in that, but accepting the life as you have it and
let go of trying to solve all these problems. And so that was her next step.
So this is the epiphany that of course, anyone who's done DBT knows is radical acceptance.
Well, it wasn't quite labeled that yet.
No, no, no. Yeah. But was this kind of the precursor of what we would now describe as that?
Yes. I think it could be the precursor, but it was missing something because what she would say is
this is the acceptance piece. But when she tried it thinking, oh, this is what people want,
they're saying I can't solve their problems. And so clearly if I communicate that I understand
how difficult things are and we can work on accepting it, the reaction she got then was,
what? There's no hope.
How can you say that I should just accept this? My life is miserable as it currently is.
If I accept this, there's no hope. I should just die. Again, you don't possibly understand
everything. And this was the, DBT stands for dialectical behavior therapy. We can talk about
dialectics. But this is what turned into the idea of this primary dialectic in this treatment,
which is the dialectic between change and acceptance and figuring out how do I as a therapist,
as a treatment provider, straddle this line, synthesize this because both of these are
important. We need to work on solving the problems in your life that are causing you such distress
and misery. And we also need to work on accepting your life as it is and accepting the things that
we can't change about our lives. But how do we do that in a way that is palatable to the person on
the other end, and in a way that conveys hope that things could change? And so it's about
synthesizing those two elements. And I think it's the synthesis of those elements that lead to
things like radical acceptance and other components of the treatment.
So this is probably a great time to double click on what dialectical means because it is,
I don't know, I'm not sure if it's innate to us, right? I think it requires some practice.
Yeah, I was listening to some interview the other day where somebody just simply said,
humans don't like contradiction. And I think that that's true. We don't like contradiction.
And so dialectics is really the, at least I'm, by the way, I'm no expert in dialectical philosophy
as, you know, as Marx initially wrote about it. I'm more a student of dialectics as it informs,
you know, my life and my practice. But dialectics is this understanding that there is contradiction
and opposition and tension in everything. And therefore, we can't avoid it. And the more we
try to avoid conflict and tension, the more likely it is that we're going to see conflict and tension.
And so dialectics is at least, again, in the practice of DBT is the practice of recognizing
tensions as they exist, polarization as it comes up, and then striving to find
what is valid about both sides, or both sides of the tension and seeking to find a synthesis,
some new argument or new statement that recognizes and adopts the validity in the two opposing sides.
This might be a reasonable time to jump forward. And then I want to come back because I love this
sort of story. But if you've, if a person listening to this or watching this has ever kind of gone
through DBT, then they're familiar with the workbook, right? You're doing this in a very
structured way. And one of the first images in the workbook is the two intersecting circles of
wise mind and emotional mind. Do you? Emotional mind and reasonable.
Sorry, reasonable mind. Yeah. Wise mind being the intersection. Yeah. So maybe use, you want,
can we use that as an example of dialectical synthesis where you have those two minds
intersecting and then that union or intersection of them being the wise mind and how do we find
those? But again, contrasting it with sort of emotional and reasonable mind.
Yeah. So I think you, that's exactly right. That is an illustration, a key illustration
of dialectics at play is this notion of wise mind and the way we, and wise mind being a skill in the
workbook that we teach people as something that we are striving to access wise mind more often
in our lives and that accessing wise mind involves synthesizing these two tensions
potentially or polarizations known as emotion mind and reasonable mind. So we emotion mind is
the idea that a state in which we are completely controlled by our emotions.
So when we're angry, it could be lashing out at somebody. It could be engaging in physical
violence. It could be threatening physical violence. It could be slamming doors. It could
be quitting things, you know, all the things that we might do when we're, when we're being controlled
by the anger we're experiencing. Reasonable mind on the other hand is when we're controlled kind
of by facts and logic and emotions aren't really, we're not aware of or experiencing any strong
emotion and you could, you could imagine or you can envision the tension that exists between these
two. If you've ever been in emotion mind having an argument with somebody in reasonable mind
or vice versa because that happens a lot. I think it has happened in my marriage. It probably happens
a lot across many people's marriages where one person is in emotion mind, the other person is
in reasonable mind and that's a recipe for you know really strong conflict. So wise mind is saying
okay what can I, what's valid about the emotion that I'm experiencing here? What's valid about
reasonable mind that I'm experiencing here and what's a synthesis? So a silly story that we
might tell to illustrate wise mind or emotion mind is you're walking down the street and you
pass by a pet store and in the window are a dozen puppies or if you're a cat person imagine
a dozen kittens okay. Emotion mind takes over and says get them all. I want all the puppies,
every single one of them because this one is cute for this reason, this one is cute for this other
reason. Oh my god they would be so happy together and I would be so happy if I had all these puppies
in my life I want them. So emotion mind says get all the puppies. Reasonable mind says oh my gosh
dogs are so much work. You have to walk them three times a day. They're expensive. You have to get
all this equipment. You have to get a veterinarian. You have to restructure your time so that you
spend more time with the dogs or not. You have to you know reimagine your whole life around that.
So reasonable mind might say no puppies. Puppies are never for you right. So what does wise mind
say? Well what's great about even teaching this as an idea is that wise mind is not a synthesis,
a dialectical synthesis, is not a compromise. It's not a halfway point because if I were to say that
then wise mind would say get six of the puppies if there are 12 right. And that makes no sense
as a compromise or as a synthesis because it's not seeing the validity in both sides. So what would
wise mind be? That would vary depending on the person because for some people a wise mind decision
would be to bring home a puppy. For other people a wise mind decision would be to say now is not
the right time for me to have a puppy but I am going to do x, y, and z in order to increase
the likelihood that I can have a puppy in the future. Wise mind might be I have the perfect
scenario now I can bring home two puppies and we will live happily ever after. So it's going to
vary but the idea of finding this synthesis is about seeing what's valid and true about both ends
of the or both of the sides and then trying to figure out what a synthesis could be.
Does that make sense? It does it really does of course and I think one of the things I'm struck
by when I look at the notebook, the workbook that we use in dbt is how much is in it. And
to think that this is sort of the work of largely one individual and obviously it's been iterated on
but it's really kind of remarkable. So can we kind of go back to the story of some of the earliest
insights she had treating some of the most in need patients and how she basically then realized
she couldn't do what she was doing under the umbrella of cbt and needed to make this change
from the cognitive to the dialectical and create another form of behavioral therapy which again is
it's really a kind of remarkable thing to realize given how relatively recent this is. I mean this
is something that's happened in the last 30 or 40 years. Agreed yeah so I think you know getting back
to where she was in terms of realizing that you know if I push for change too hard disaster happens,
if I push for acceptance too hard disaster happens, what can I do to you know find the middle,
how do I balance these two things. And again part of the the lore of the story of dbt was that she
was writing about this idea of balancing change and acceptance and these were the days where she
would you know write up notes either handwritten or on a typewriter and hand them over to a
secretary who would you know type them up or revise them and her story is that the person her
her assistant that was working on typing this all up came to her one day and said my husband is a
graduate student in philosophy and we were looking at this and we think that what you're describing
actually is something that he he studies and is called dialectics. So according to Marcia she
didn't know anything about dialectical philosophy as she was iterating this treatment and this was
one of those happenstance moments that that came to her and then of course she sought out readings
descriptions of dialectical philosophy and saw yes that is exactly what she's thinking and that
dialectical philosophy informs a lot of science and scientific thought and so actually worked
well within the the paradigm of you know the development of of cognitive behavioral treatments.
So so that's where you know dbt started to take form however if if you're familiar with her books
you know that her original treatment manual that was published in 1993 including the and and also
the original skills workbook that was published in 1993 says on the cover cognitive behavioral
therapy for born personality disorder yeah the the newer edition says dialectical because she
was told at the time by the publishers that nobody will know what this means and nobody will want it
and I think that may be true it's it's possible that if it was called dialectical behavior therapy
on the cover of the book back then it would not have actually been as popular as it is now. Now
of course we can put dialectical behavior therapy on the cover of any book and and people will see
the value in it but I don't think that was true then. When did she develop kind of her own sort
of interest in zen philosophy and the practice of mindfulness which also is a very important
muscle that one kind of develops as they move along their dbt journey was this something that
had been more long-standing with her? So I think that this was all happening around at the same
time that she was her own interest in you know Marcia grew up in a catholic family identified as a
very religious person identified as saying that at one point she thought she was going to become a
nun and so this was a large part of her upbringing when and also was part of that spiritual
experience that she had personally but I think she also realized that and another reason by the
way that she didn't want to come public with her story early on is that she didn't want the lesson
to be oh if you want to get better you also have to have a spiritual experience. Instead what she
wanted to figure out was how do I operationalize for lack of a better word this spiritual experience
so that other people could experience it as well and so I think that was going on in her mind
at the same time that she was interested in her own spiritual development and learned more about
Zen and became a student of Zen Buddhism and saw that they all connected and came together because
ultimately how she translated that personal experience is into this idea that you mentioned
earlier of radical acceptance can you radically accept this moment the situation yourself exactly
as it is and if you can experience that radical and complete and total acceptance you can experience
joy you can crack open the moment of joy she would say. Yeah I mean there are some things where
Shireen that's I get it right like you're stuck in traffic right so you're supposed to be going
somewhere and let's pretend it's someplace that matters right it's not just like a dinner
reservation let's say it's your kids sporting event or you go into the airport and it's a
flight and if you miss it it's going to really wreck things up and there's nothing you can do
about it you're stuck in traffic there's an accident a mile ahead and that this is the way
it's going to be walk me through what you would say you know your your patient now is in the car
and you're sitting with them in the car and they're understandably getting very flustered at the
situation walk me through radical acceptance in that situation how are you helping that person
go through the you know can you fix this problem are you accepting this problem can you change like
going through all of those layers for that specific type of problem yes and I've been in
that problem myself so I understand yeah so you know um what I would say as a precursor is that
when we're experiencing suffering however you define that suffering if you were to look at it
more deeply you would say the vast majority of the time that we're experiencing suffering
it's because we're thinking about something that has already happened ruminating um wishing it
hadn't happened mulling something over whatever it might be or you're thinking about something
that may happen in the future and that actually if you just experience this one moment
uh and let go of the past and the future that alone might reduce your suffering a ton
but we could say you might experience pain in this moment because this moment might be painful
but we're not adding on we're not adding on all of these things that actually increase our suffering
so in this moment when you are stuck in traffic you can't undo the decisions that you made that
got you to this point right because of course we're saying things like oh if only I had taken
this other road or if only I had left 15 minutes early or we think all these stupid people on the
road if only they had done something different right so that's those are all fantasy thoughts
because they're all not reality of this moment so I would say how do we reduce our suffering in this
moment is to say I can't change any of that for today in this moment this is what it is
um and what happens you'll see actually I'm holding my palms up right now as I'm talking
because I associate holding my palms up with this idea of willingly accepting this moment which is
uh this is the moment that I'm in yeah it's sort of a surrender posture yeah yeah in a way it's
the surrendering willing this is the moment I'm in and what happens if I just just as though it's
easy but what happens if I accept that right now there is nothing I can do to change this
right now I think the other piece to this is and this is why it's not just about acceptance
because I would say if this is something that happens a lot right if you often find yourself
in situations whether it's traffic or something running late or something like that then we
absolutely want to figure out how to prevent this from happening as much in the future but in this
moment when you're there you can't do that so in other words in the moment of crisis you don't
really want to be problem solving around how can I avoid this the next time how do I avoid this
crisis again in the future when I'm at a 100 or a 90 of distress I'm not going to be able to
effectively do that now obviously so much of what you're saying sounds very familiar to anybody who
has practiced mindfulness or vipassana or one of its derivatives in forms of meditation
we've had a couple of podcasts that have sort of gone into that and
you know when the goal of the practice is to help you identify thoughts and to separate you from
these thoughts and so in this individual I mean there's probably nothing as you say in this exact
moment that is particularly unbearable but the thoughts are unbearable if you're if you let them
go right which is I'm gonna get to the airport I'm gonna miss my flight then I'm gonna have to wait
for another flight and I'm probably gonna miss that too or they're not gonna be a good seat or
whatever and then I'm gonna not get to where I'm going and maybe the whole trip's gonna da da da
and and so what is what do you say to the person who says okay Shireen I understand that those
thoughts which are all future are not happening to me now and I can just sit here right now in
this car and frankly I could turn on music and enjoy the music for the moment but that doesn't
change the fact that that's going to happen it doesn't change the fact that in an hour I am going
to get to the airport I am going to have missed my flight what do you say to the person when they
they acknowledge that I could probably take myself down from 100 to 50 by being present in the moment
but will I get back to 100 when I get to the airport when I realized that I now have to deal
with this mess possibly but that's a new moment now now you're in a new moment and a new situation
so part of it depends on well what's your what's your goal so when you're experiencing distress
in that moment of being stuck in traffic and not having any control about that what's your goal
if it's to get to the airport in two minutes sorry that's not a realistic goal we're gonna have to
let that one go if it's to problem solve what will happen when you get to the airport is there
something that you can do while you're in the car you know possibly but if your goal is to how do I
make this moment more bearable because I can't undo anything then I think we have some other
options available to us which could be distracting you know doing something like music or
or some other forms of distraction that you could safely do in the context of your car
okay so now let's look at kind of the other end of the spectrum where I think it becomes even
harder to do this so I'll think of two examples I think of an individual who receives a terminal
diagnosis so they're they're diagnosed with a cancer for example that and let's let's make this
even more tragic right I think anybody dying of cancer is tragic but now it's someone your age
or my age who's you know dying decades too soon but they're basically told and and it's accurate
that look in six months you're not going to be alive so in that sense they're they're you know
there's they're mourning the loss of their life and who they're going to be away from and then
there's another example which is very fresh in my mind right now because you know a very close
friend of my wife's daughter drowned a year ago and and because we're coming up to the one-year
anniversary of that it's it's all you know she's reliving a lot of this so you know it's hard for
me to imagine what she's going through and what her husband is going through but they can't there's
no there's there's nothing that will undo that there so so maybe use those two examples as two
of the the most difficult examples of how can radical acceptance allow the a this this person
who's who's going to die far too soon to come to grips with that and maybe have a chance at
having the best six months that they can have versus not you know you know and then perhaps
even more tragically the you know a parent losing a child is you would sort of hold that up as about
as tragic as anything can go where nothing is ever going to bring that child back and yes
cognitively you can say look you still have other children and you have to be a great parent for
them you can't allow yourself to you know you can go through all of that stuff but like I don't know
how I would cope with that I don't think I could I'm not I'm not sure so yeah now let's go from the
sort of banal of traffic to the the really heavy stuff of life yeah easy right so uh I mean one
I've thought about both of these things um a lot or both of these circumstances a lot and I think
one of the um misunderstandings about acceptance is somehow this idea that it if you accept
something you don't experience pain and so I want to differentiate that uh life is full of pain no
matter how zen and mindful you are you're going to experience pain and a lot of pain and we're not
trying to eradicate pain because actually without pain and I don't mean you know physical pain I
mean emotional pain but it could be both but without that we would have other problems right
if we did not experience um pain as you hear about your friend's daughter that would be a
problem for you in a different way so we need to understand that that pain is going to be a part
of our lives and actually we cause a lot of problems for ourselves when we try to escape
the experience of pain so that's one thing about um reality radical acceptance that I want to talk
about but the other is when when you ask questions like that like how can we ask somebody to radically
accept this I would answer in part by saying what's the alternative the alternative is refusing to
accept how how does that work how how do you do that um how and how long can you sustain that for
so I would actually argue that the refusal to accept or the putting your head in the sand
or the denying reality actually ends up taking a lot more mental resource and ultimately causing
more problems for you in the long run and that said from a dbt perspective when we when we talk
about practicing the skill of radical acceptance we have another expression called turning the mind
which is referring to the fact that um practicing radical acceptance involves a very active process
of continuously turning your mind towards acceptance the the metaphor is that you're at
a fork in the road and one road is acceptance and another road is is refusal to accept you're going
to come across the fork in the road possibly multiple times a minute and what does it look
like for you to say I'm going to actively and willingly choose the road of radical acceptance
how can I turn my mind my body my soul towards acceptance and for me a lot of it is actually
asking myself that question of what's the alternative what other choices do I have
and recognizing that more suffering comes from refusing to accept more often the fact that it's
referred to as radical acceptance versus acceptance I think kind of highlights that that it it's not
easy it's not it's not a decision it's not like you would sit down with my wife's friend have this
discussion once say what's the alternative I know this is awful but in the long run this is going to
produce more happiness for you and your family and for her to say yep I think that's right thanks
like it's no it's not it's to your point every minute of every day for god knows how many
months and years you're confronted with that and if I speak for myself there's a lot of uh what's
the what's the term uh backsliding right there's a lot of no I don't want to accept this today
like I'm not I don't accept this this is I'm angry about this I want to pout and have a little
pity party about this um and then maybe I experienced that and I realized that wasn't
very productive because now I feel actually worse and so um you know one of the things about dbt
that so I you know we were introduced through Andy White which is who I work with and I just I just
think the world of Andy one of the things about dbt that for me makes it a wonderful system
is that you do work like you you have you you you write you do you have homework you
you you have to talk you know write out your emotions and your decisions and the
the trees like you know if you feel this do you do this and I don't know I how deliberate was that
in in Marsha's mind as a system I've never done cbt so I don't know if cbt has a similar workbook
and she's just modifying it is that is that something that's been modified from other systems
certainly cbt is associated with doing homework doing work in between sessions
more standard cognitive therapy is associated with doing worksheets about your thoughts what
thoughts you have what the evidence for your thoughts are that sort of thing and so I think
doing work during worksheets not shying away from the term homework as part of the treatment
is very consistent with the cbt model now what I will say is um
you just reminded me about this based on something you said is that one of the
assumptions about borderline personality disorder from the dbt lens is that this is uh we use a
skills deficit model which is to say that we believe that people who end up with the constellation
of problems associated with borderline personality disorder have an absence of certain skills and
skillful behavior in their lives and that absence could be a result of never having been taught it
in the first place or having had effective behaviors been punished out of them by their
environment this is the environmental piece that we're talking about but they they don't have
we all you know have certain deficits in in some air in some skillful areas and so the work
another one i would just add to that it's so yeah the skills have never been modeled for you
you've done them correctly and been punished for them i think a bigger one might be you've done
them incorrectly and never been corrected yeah that's a good one too yeah absolutely so you
built all the muscle memory doing it wrong your whole life and you didn't have parents there to
sort of say hey that's not how you do it this do it this way yeah and it's a lot harder to unlearn
a behavior than it is to learn a new behavior uh and that we know that as a phenomenon so
so marcia developed this you know this workbook what we refer to as the skills training manual
that's part of of the treatment of dbt and perhaps what dbt is probably most known for
more broadly speaking are the skills that are part of it but that these skills deficits are
thought to exist in in four different domains or five different domains actually mindfulness
so when we say someone has a deficit in mindfulness it's not that we're referring to anybody who
doesn't practice zen as having a mindfulness deficit but it's a deficit in excuse me a deficit
in the capacity to be aware of the present moment basically another domain in which people have
deficits is interpersonal effectiveness as i go through this you'll see everybody has deficits in
in all of these areas at different times and i think again that's that's part of the beauty of dbt
is that it can help so many people so interpersonal effectiveness which could mean conflict with others
but also could mean deficits in in knowing how to ask for something effectively how to say no
effectively emotion regulation deficits is the third domain so deficits in knowing how to label
your emotions what to do with emotions when you have them how to prevent having intense and extreme
emotions how to change emotions can't remember if i said that uh and then a fourth domain is is
deficits in distress tolerance how do you tolerate really stressful and distressing situations without
doing anything that to make the situation worse and then the fifth area that is not talked about
as much though i can certainly talk about it if that'd be helpful is this idea of self-management
deficits and self-management which has to do with um being able to do things you don't want to do
you know broadly speaking you know how some people can get up every morning at six o'clock
and go exercise and eat a healthy breakfast uh and you know go to work while other people
snooze their alarm eight to twelve times you know haphazardly eat breakfast sometimes um
get to work late you know those are sorts of things that we might uh say fall into this kind
of self-management domain and so dbt is designed as a treatment package to teach people the skills
to overcome deficits in these different domain so i actually wasn't aware of the fifth i was
really only aware of the four is that fifth one um is it kind of a more recent addition
so it actually is in the original treatment manual in the 1993 um text that she put out but
her thinking was i don't need to create a whole other skills module for self-management because
dbt therapists are going to infuse this throughout their entire treatment and i think this might have
been at the time a little bit of a missed opportunity because i don't think she realized
that actually a lot of clinicians don't know how to do that um very well marcia was thinking that
actually this is where behaviorism comes in it's teaching people principles of of behaviorism so
you don't see it in the original skills manual and you don't necessarily see it in the new skills
manual or what i refer to as the new skills manual unless you look because where you would see it now
is in the set of skills that are referred to as the walking the middle path skills which are
which actually came out of um the first adaptation of dbt for adolescents and their families um and
jill rathis and alec miller who along with marcia created the adolescent version of dbt
took a lot of these principles of the self-management skills and created this fifth module
of dbt skills called walking the middle path in which they teach adolescents and their caregivers
their parents these skills about how to how to manage your behaviors how to learn behaviors um
and to be more effective more broadly you know just kind of going back to the origin of dbt
around basically um a modified tool to help some of the people who are suffering the absolute most
right if you think somewhere in the back of marcia's mind it probably wasn't just how do i
make cbt better to handle the most recalcitrant depression suicidal patients perhaps on some level
it was also bpd right which we didn't we kind of glossed over this but i'm guessing that cbt has
historically not been very successful for borderline personality disorder is that a fair statement
well i would say at the time that marcia was was doing this treatment development we didn't know
and i think the the general thought and they're actually there have been more studies that have
looked at whether the presence of borderline personality disorder interfered with
um outcomes for standard cbt and there's kind of mixed data on that and that some studies
showed that the presence of bpd did uh lead to worse outcomes in in some studies but what i
was going to say is that marcia didn't know one the reason that she gives for her pivot to borderline
personality disorder as a population of interest is that when she was first seeking research dollars
research grants to study the development of dbt and the you know to start to do randomized clinical
trials of dbt rather back in those days you could only get research grants from nih if you identified
a disorder of interest the way she tells it as oversimplified is that you know she was interested
in suicide and suicidal behaviors and at the time she thought her choices based on that behavior
was either depression or bpd and she said at the time she didn't want to do depression because
there were already so many um smart people doing depression research she wanted to do
go into an area where there weren't already a lot of people doing research in this area and that's
why she chose bpd again this is the story but of course i think there's more to it than that
because i think the you know her own experiences uh would lead one to assume that she also had
specific interest in a motion dysregulation piece that goes along with bpd and doesn't
necessarily go along with with more standard depression yeah i mean so what would you say i
know what i would say but what would you say to somebody who doesn't have bpd doesn't it's not
depressed who says you know peter shireen this is all very interesting but what would there ever be
any benefit in me doing dbt given that this program was really built around people with real pathology
of which i have none if you i went through the dsm five last week nothing in there i don't meet
the criteria for anything fully um would i have any would there be any value to me in in this
type of practice i think that's part of what's so fascinating about this treatment because you're
exactly right this was the treatment that was developed for what could have been termed the
worst of the worst at the at the time and it's a treatment that is actually for all of us i have
yet to meet a person who could not benefit from at least learning some of the skills nor have i
met a person who i've yet to meet a person who hasn't identified the skills as being something
that could be relevant for them now whether they're always willing to use them or apply them
or want to do them that's a different issue but when i talk about here's what the skills are for
i get universal agreement that those skills could be useful to learn yeah the way i kind of describe
it i you don't know this about me but i love cars and race cars and all sorts of things like that
and a lot of people say like i don't really understand how there's any value in you know
a company like mercedes or you know any of these companies participating in you know building race
cars you know it's such an expensive proposition it seems so gratuitous but the trickle-down effect
for what the impact of that is on street cars is remarkable in terms of fuel efficiency power
safety all of these things you know it's true if you want to build a formula one car it's you know
it's basically a 400 million dollar a year operation to build and operate those things
but those things are functioning at the absolute limit and if you you know where every gram matters
and the stakes are so high and if you take everything that you learn there and bring it
down to the rest of us who aren't driving formula one cars the benefit is actually enormous
and i think of it as sort of similar right which is this is a system that was conceived and
um validated on a sample set of people with real difficulties in regulating their emotions
and you know when i go through the list of the dbt you know skills pillars it's like i mean check
check check check check right i mean i can i might not meet the diagnostic criteria for something in
the dsm-5 but i mean i have enormous problems with all of these things i have staggering deficits
of skills i mean one of the first exercises that really illustrated that was something as simple as
identification of emotion you know it was any emotion that i wouldn't say that that's simple
necessarily yeah yeah yeah but but it was like i couldn't really identify an emotion that wasn't
anger it was very difficult to go beyond anger to helplessness sadness hurt fear all of these
other things so that i mean i don't know andy and i must have spent three months with my homework
just being okay you're going to get angry 16 times a day 16 times a day pull out this sheet
and go through and figure out what else is going on you know that's that sounds maybe simple but
that's learning a new language as well what what made you want to do that why not just stick with
your experience of anger yeah i mean look it's it's a it's exactly what you said earlier it's
like what's the alternative all the alternative is you're really you know alienating a lot of people
um and i think watching my kids get older and realizing i don't want them to see me always
angry i mean you know i think i was just angry 24 seven i don't think i really experienced
anything that wasn't anger um so yeah i think it was just uh it was it was sort of just saying like
i have to sort of break this cycle because it's you know my kids will if every time i get cut off
on the road i'm screaming so much at the person who cut me off that you can see the droplets of
my spit on the windshield even if i'm not yelling at them it's not like i was actually yelling at my
kids but it doesn't matter i don't you know as i've learned since i don't think kids can appreciate
the difference a five-year-old doesn't understand that just because daddy is yelling at the guy that
cut him off he's not mad at me so i think once i came to realize that i realized no this i i don't
want to do this yeah i think these skills are for i just totally agree i mean i've been so i don't
actually have my own experiences with borderline personality disorder or psychopathology in that way
and i learned dbt as a grad student uh in you know my early 20s and it's been a long time now
that i've been using and applying dbt and i will still go in my head like when i have a difficult
interpersonal situation happening where i will walk through the steps in my mind of the the dear
man skill of how to ask for something and be effective let's go through dear man in a moment
finish your story but i would love to go well i was just gonna say like it's been 25 years and
i'll still be writing an email and then i'll say wait pause edit am i following the dear structure
what what can i take out what am i adding on what judgments are in here so i feel like i you know
i've been a pretty skillful person for most of my life and i still need to i still benefit from
actively thinking about uh using these skills in my daily life so i mean i'm still so early in my
journey i would say i'm you know if if if 10 out of 10 is having all the skills and always employing
them one out of 10 is not even knowing what a skill is you know i'm in the sort of three to
four out of ten range which is i know them and i don't know maybe half the time i reach for them
correctly um but let's talk about dear man um because everything in dbt is really built
around being highly accessible it's not it's not really at least to me it doesn't come across as
having errors right like this is you know it's it's funny acronyms it's like little diagrams it's
there's nobody that can't do this right so um tell everybody what dear man is and what the acronym
is is really used to walk you through as a thought process right i think sometimes people actually
have a negative reaction to all the acronyms in in dbt and i think that's a fair criticism but
acronyms are you know meant as mnemonics to help us remember um maybe because i went to medical
school we just you do so much through that yeah yeah yeah yeah though i will say i was training
dbt somewhere where was i i think it was iceland was it iceland where they don't do acronyms
um like it's just not part of their language uh to use acronyms and so that isn't added
difficulty but in in the u.s and canada and we can talk about these acronyms so dear man is a skill
that's in the interpersonal effectiveness module so this these are the skills that are designed to
help you be more effective with other people in your life and dear man is specifically the skill
to uh on how to ask for something in a way that gets another person to give it to you
or how to say no to something in a way that gets the other person to accept your no or increases
the likelihood i should say because nothing is going to be 100 effective so dear man walks you
through these seven kind of sub skills to help you do that so it stands for describe express assert
reinforce that's the the dear part that's that's basically what you say um or write uh to ask for
something and then the man stands for mindful appear confident and negotiate or be willing
to negotiate so that when you're in a situation so i don't know do you have a situation that is
coming up for you where you need to ask for something or say no to something yeah i do
actually um i don't think i can talk about it publicly unfortunately it's such it's a very good
one but i probably can't talk about it publicly let me think of one where i could um without
embarrassing someone uh okay this is going to embarrass the hell out of her but let's try it
my daughter wants to get a third earring so she's got two piercings in her ears and she really wants
to now get a third and i'm not sure maybe this isn't a great example but i'm hoping to talk her
out of it for a little longer how's that i i'm like why don't you wait till you're a little bit older
i just have this fear that she's going to you know damage her ears and have so many things hanging
that it will stretch her ear lobes out and she'll be 50 years old like me one day and regret it
potentially a totally irrational fear but that's the fear i have so the ask that you want to say is
will you postpone this decision for a while or will you take this off the table for a period of time
right and the reason because someone listening to this might say what kind of lousy parent or you
just assert it but um but but her mom is not opposed to it her mom's like i think it's
reasonable for her to get it so so now it's become kind of more of a negotiation and how old is she
uh she's 13 yeah so i would say the more you tell somebody a 13 year old not to do something
that's pretty much the recipe for for going out and doing it so uh so if you were to practice the
dear man the first step would be to describe the situation without adding on any interpretations
or judgments so uh if i were your daughter you would say to me um olivia i understand that you
want to now get a third hearing great so often this means exactly what you did which is to
keep it short because sometimes we have a tendency to go on and on and on about all of our reasons
for something but actually the more we do that the more we lose the other person's interest
uh and then express would be to express your feelings about it i have some fear about you
getting a third earring because i worry that it would damage your ears and this would be
something that would bother you many years from now right so you know we could work on on
simplifying or shortening or saying i i fear i have fears that you would regret this if you did it
whatever it might be to get the express but that was also really nice because you didn't add on
judgments you didn't say you shouldn't do this right these are all just describe the facts and
then express your feelings about it now assert is where you ask for that's the a where you ask
for directly what it is that you want olivia would you be fine if we could postpone this
decision until you're older maybe even out of high school so you may think about prior to doing it
what is it specifically that you're asking for so if you want to start out by asking i'd like you
know would you be willing to postpone this decision until after high school might be a more direct
assert but it could be there's other factors that might contribute to you asking it more tentatively
or more firmly but making a direct ask now what we often say about this you didn't illustrate this
but what we often say about this a part the assert is that a lot of the time we don't actually
assert we just want somebody else to read our minds or do what we want and i think this is
especially a problem for uh not to over generalize but i think women have more trouble with this on
average than men loads of reasons for that but actually asking directly for what it is that you
want is is really challenging for people and so what instead you would see people doing is just
doing the describe and express and then expecting the other person to just know what it is they want
and do it so we're trying to get people to to learn how to be more comfortable with
asking and stating directly what it is that you're that you want and then the r is stands for
reinforce uh which is to say you want to say explicitly what's what's in it for the other
person what reward could come their way by by giving into your request or giving you what you
want which in a second we can talk about whether or not this is manipulation but in the moment uh
in your dialogue with olivia what's in it what's something that you could imagine uh reinforcing
so here's where i could go into many directions right one direction is
you know you play volleyball you're really good at volleyball you're you're playing year round now
and the more jewelry you have on the greater your risk of injury you get hit in the head with a ball
that's one more thing that could hurt this is just one less thing to worry about right that would be
one sort of very narrow niche approach probably my preferred way would be something like
optionality is a great thing and by not doing it now it doesn't mean that you can't do it tomorrow
you always have that option but you can't undo it once you have it now she'll argue
yes you can you can just take it out so i don't know maybe she's right but um
that's probably those would be the the things i would reinforce which is
i'm not saying no i'm just saying not now and that really isn't taking anything away it's just
potentially delaying something yeah so what i would say is that i agree with you about all of
those points what you're doing is you're providing more evidence in favor of what it is that you're
asking for but if i were to think about about uh reinforcing in the sense of what reward
could she expect if she were to say yes dad i won't get a another piercing so is this something
like where i could literally just say and if you don't do this like i give you know is it literally
like you're bribing your kid is that potentially what's in there well it could be uh but i wouldn't
necessarily i mean it would be bribery but bribery is what we do all the time right if you mean would
it be something like you know and if you don't do this i mean we could go shopping in those new
converse shoes you love let's get those instead it could be okay yeah i never thought of it that
way right i've always thought of it in more sort of theoretical reinforcement which i think um
can work sometimes with some people but i think uh more often than not
it needs to be a tangible connection to to this now what we often say is a good good fall back
you know to asking somebody for something um at work or interpersonally is to say if you do this
i would really appreciate it right my appreciation of you and your behavior is a reinforcer
right you might feel good by the fact that i appreciate it when i see something like what
you're describing your daughter wants her dad's appreciation of not high on the list of things
exactly right so you have to think about the person that you're asking and what is most likely
to work now and and you also have to think about it to a certain extent how important is it for you
to get this thing that you're asking for and if it's really important for you to get it
then you might say oh i don't like you know buying her sneakers instead but if that's what
worked then we would say you know be effective like in this situation if this was something
that was really important to you well and i think it illustrates this i'm glad we did this example
which is kind of like i thought of it as well sort of glib but it illustrates another point which is
um there's sort of there's a meta thing here which is i'm teaching her by my behavior
and my interaction what is a more emotionally regulated way to handle this because
i think if the old version of me would have just said no like i'm the parent you're doing what i
say like this is non-negotiable and you know if i was a kid and argued this i would have got the
back of the hand to my face so just be lucky you're not getting that for even pushing and provoking
this discussion you know i mean like so so that would have been the old way to have dealt with
this and and so i get to at least they would have run out and gotten the earring and just right
right so now instead we get to model something better and i i think that that's the other i
assume that that also factors into the dbt for adolescence which i actually haven't maybe it's
time that i sort of look at that as well but i i haven't really spent any time looking at that work
but i would imagine that it's as much about helping the kids as showing the kids how the
parents can change as well well what what is an amazing adaptation for dbt so in standard dbt for
adults in uh what we do we haven't really explained like what the therapy looks like but in general
what would happen if somebody were receiving dbt treatment is that they would be coming to a skills
training group once a week or receiving skills training individually where they meet with the
therapist who teaches them these specific skills they practice that they come back report on their
practice um and get feedback and coaching etc in skills training group you might have a number of
adults all together and you teach them all together and you assign homework and you all talk about the
practice and use of skills what was an amazing i mean i just think it's so brilliant adaptation
for dbt for adolescents is that in your skills group you have now multi they're called multi-family
skills groups where you have the adolescents in the skills groups but you also have the
adolescent adolescents parents or caretakers in the skills group at the same time and everybody
is learning the skills all together and the way these groups are designed it's not overall learning
these skills so that you all can you know help your adolescent apply them of course that's part
of it but we're framing the groups as saying we're teaching everybody the skills because the parents
need the skills as much as the adolescents need the skills and therefore the parents have been
caregivers have to practice the skills on themselves not just for their adolescents
i mean do you do you do you find it's do you find it's harder for the parents because
you know you said something earlier which i completely agree with
it would almost be easier to come to dbt with no skills positive or negative and then just learn
the positive skills um it's it's harder to come in when you have decades of reinforced negative
skills anti-skills and you have to unlearn anti-skills and then build positive skills so
do you see that it's easier for the kids sometimes to pick this up than their parents
i think there's um sometimes easier to pick up but there's different levels of willingness
and willfulness yeah so with adolescents a lot of the times adolescents not not necessarily there
by choice i'm guessing sometimes yes so a lot of the times it's their parents or their schools
that say they have to do this and so there's always a question of how much they're there because they
want to be there at a less i mean of course with adults in certain contexts and situations they
don't want there to be there easy uh either but there's generally more willingness um let's talk
about the structure of the therapy i've jumped around a lot because there's just so many interesting
frameworks and i want to make sure we get to them but um let's assume that you know a person comes
to you now um and they're there by their own choice this is an adult and they don't meet the
criteria for any of the dsm-5s so this is just someone who's having difficulty interpersonally
um you know one of the things that i think i sort of realized was so much dysregulation stems from
interpersonal interactions gone bad with your spouse with your child with your co-worker with
the person who cuts you off on the street i mean it's generally an interpersonal interaction
that doesn't meet your expectations whether those are reasonable or not reasonable that then leads
to sort of an emotional regulation or dysregulation thoughts that then feed into those emotional
dysregulations and then you create this awful feed forward loop that can lead to bad behaviors i mean
that is that it's sort of a safe way to talk about it from interpersonal to thoughts uh emotion
emotions thoughts feeding off each other and then behaviors i mean that's kind of like the pathway
of how this all seems to go wrong for people and i mean there are some people out there who just i
seem who seem just wonderful and they don't seem to suffer from these issues but but most people if
we're being really honest with ourselves even if you're not as extreme as as me i think most people
realize that this isn't always going well especially as we're under more external stress you know
there i i love the idea of distress tolerance and i i think that's just one of the most
interesting concepts is a window and that's the sort of image that i have of it right so
i mean this entire year my distress tolerance window is about this thick and it's all my own
fault i've put way too many things on my plate and so there's no buffer there's no margin for
error one thing even before this podcast was recorded i was getting upset about some stupid
video i had to record that i was like yeah but i had to record it twice it was supposed to be two
minutes the first time i did it it took two minutes and 20 seconds like like something so
like something so dumb that shouldn't even bother me bothered me because i'm out of time so so
something like external factors will change your distress tolerance window and and for me it's
always being too close to the top where it's getting upset but for some people it's being
too close to the bottom and it's getting you know sort of dysthymic or depressive versus getting
irritable and during good times like people imagine being on vacation where for two weeks
like you don't have to worry about email nothing is going on you know nothing really seems to
bother you doesn't you know you go to a restaurant and they forgot your reservation you're like yeah
no problem we'll go to the next one like it just you know i think people can resonate with this
idea so one of the skills is how do you make that distress tolerance window higher how do you make
it wider there's nobody that's not going to benefit from this so it's a it's a long rambling
question but really where i'm going is you get somebody that comes in where do you start
well i will say that one of the when when you just said that what i was reminded of is
what is learning what makes us more vulnerable to negative emotions or stress or distress and
that is another key skill in dbt is to identify and understand what our vulnerability factors are
and then to address because sometimes we could actually solve our you know target or treat our
vulnerability factors and our lives just go much more smoothly you know when we sleep decently you
know when we remove some things from our list so that we're not so stressed all the time like that
could actually solve a number of problems but where i start with by the way that's i want to
that's i'm glad you brought that up because i i i should have mentioned that's actually one of the
first things andy asks me every i i work with andy once a week so we every you know i've been
working with him for two years now it's always once a week um but that's one of the first
questions he always asks which is tell me what's going on physically right so are you in pain
are you sleeping uh what are the other vulnerabilities and i think out of the
gate he's trying to gauge what state i'm in as a function of how many things are pressing me
and what uh and i mean i can't speak for what andy's doing but uh and how um in those moments how
able are you to receive info like if you're at you know a 90 on a scale zero to 100 you're not
taking in a lot you're not learning a lot right so we if you're at that level that we need to figure
out how do we get you regulated enough so that you could learn uh learn to do something differently
and i think that that's great that he asked those questions i think for myself when i'm in physical
pain i i just can't do much of anything and it makes me admire yeah yeah or sleep deprived as you
said i think i think uh he he's he's had me pay much more attention to those things like if you
haven't slept well in two nights you can't and you shouldn't assume that you're at your best
in terms of your ability to receive both information and tolerate things um physical
pain is a very interesting one i agree with you completely um i'd love for you to share an example
of your own life i have so many of where i've been in pain and it's made me more irritable
what what have you noticed and what do you do about it specifically well what i was going to
i just admire people so much who have chronic pain conditions and and function in their lives
because i have been fortunate to not i mean i've had pain um but to not have a chronic pain
condition uh because i think uh that would be a challenge um for me to learn how to navigate that
but i do think that when i'm experiencing pain and whether it's you know a transient headache
that i know will pass or um i hurt my back you know exercising and now i feel it you know every
which way i i personally recognize that as a huge vulnerability factor for me because it makes me
more irritable um in general and makes me much more likely to to snap at people um or to have
less patience for things so for me what that means is recognizing kind of similar to what you
said like okay this is going on for me right now i have to accept this is going on for me right now
because i can't just will away physical pain as much as i want to and know that this is a
vulnerable time for me so given that it's a vulnerable vulnerable time for me is there a
way that i can reduce demands on myself in other ways or is there a way that i can treat myself
kindly in other ways to kind of offset the the pain that i'm experiencing and sometimes it's
for me it's also um learning to be more explicit and vocal as it relates to kind of this
interpersonal effectiveness uh because when we experience pain it's often entirely um experienced
within our bodies other people may not uh even know that this is happening for us so learning to
say out loud and you know granted it helps as your kids get older you can say things when they're
younger you can't say as easily mommy has a headache so you know but they get older and you could say
um i'm really suffering right now from this headache so i need to have a little bit of space
you know from this conversation or this situation so learning to recognize this as a vulnerability
factor and then figuring out how can i act more skillfully within this context to prevent
the lashing out to prevent irritability because i don't know if this is your experience peter but
mine is that whenever i do act out of anger i almost always regret it and almost always feel
worse about myself um afterwards and so it's almost a selfish process it's it's to help the
other person by saying i'm not going to get irritable with my kids it's to protect them but
it's also to help me not feel so bad afterwards uh because my kids will recover i'll recover but
i don't like how it makes me feel yeah the the cycle of of anger and shame and isolation is is a
is a pretty frequent i know the path well um you know before we leave the pain thing one thing
i've observed in myself is not all pain is created equal and expected pain seems to be far less
destabilizing to me than unexpected pain so i had shoulder surgery recently um i don't know why i
hadn't been told how much it would hurt but and i so i didn't really want to take any of the
narcotics and things like that i mean for a week it was i mean for two days the pain was so bad i
couldn't sleep i mean literally i was just sitting up in a chair not sleeping for two nights but even
for that week the pain was excruciating interestingly it didn't uh negatively impact me in terms of
interactions like it didn't i would have guessed look knowing what i know about how much pain can
destabilize distress tolerance um capacity i would have thought well that would have thrown me over
the edge but it didn't because it was like look i had six trocars in my shoulder i just had a an
enormous operation this is kind of what it's going to feel like whereas i've had headaches that have
lasted for three days at a time due to you know some awful tension and no amount of tylenol can
make it go away and it ostensibly it's not as bad as my shoulder was hurting but one i don't
expect it i don't know why i have it it i find that far more destabilizing to me from an emotional
regulation standpoint i don't know if you've ever observed that and by the way i think people with
chronic pain that must be the most frustrating and difficult thing because a lot of those patients
are told by physicians like either a there's nothing we can do or b this is in your head and
really you should just kind of ignore this i 100 agree with you personally and professionally
what i noticed and what you said is that you actually um engage in a lot of self-validation
with regard to the shoulder surgery basically saying of course i feel this way it's okay to
feel this way and i think with the other pain that we experience sometimes we might not realize that
we're doing this so explicitly but we're actually invalidating ourselves we're saying
why am i feeling this way what's wrong with me how could this be happening right and so we're
rejecting it and and i have my own personal example i'm i'm tapering off a medication right now
and i didn't realize when i was prescribed this medication how difficult it it's known to be a
medication that's difficult to get off and had i known that um it was sort of a moment of weakness
that i was prescribed this i decided to take it had i known how horrible it would feel to go off
it i never would have gone on it um but now i'm i'm trying to wean myself off of it i'm i'm really
going kind of nuts with how much i'm like microtosing myself on this medication because i start to
feel this this withdrawal symptom and i'm realizing exactly to this point that you made is that part
of the suffering that i'm experiencing about this is my thoughts like oh what if this goes on
forever what if this doesn't end and and even when i realize okay it's not going to last forever the
subsequent thought is but can i tolerate this for two weeks you know why can't it just go away and
so this is the way in which we do have some control over the suffering that we experience because
we're adding on all of these thoughts and so one of the one of the mindfulness tricks that i really
love when i hear it is i think i heard it as it relates to like learning to be mindful and
accepting of your emotions is just to say to yourself it's okay to feel this and it seems so
simple but just say those words it's okay to feel this no matter what the this is is can be a really
powerful experience and i think even with the pain we could say it's it's okay to feel this
and just notice what effect that has on us so going back to kind of the beginning of the
interaction with the clinician and the patient you start with this idea of what are the vulnerabilities
so once you sort of establish that and i suspect a lot of that is you'll see it quicker than the
patient will like a lot of times people probably don't appreciate what the vulnerabilities are
until they're kind of pointed out which is no like these are again it's a form of validation
these are really clear things that are going to make it more challenging for you to be understanding
of others to be understanding of yourself to regulate your emotion to control your thoughts
and ultimately to control your behaviors so once you establish that i imagine it's somewhat
liberating for people it's it's kind of a nice first way to have you validate things for them
is that usually received that way so i think for a lot of people understanding the vulnerability
factors and determining ways to reduce their vulnerability is really critical and you ask me
like what i would typically do with somebody who first came in and i think that is something i
mean i'm used to working only with people who meet criteria for bpd and are unusually on that more
severe end of the continuum so i don't have a lot of people i don't have experience with you know
people that are not as extreme usually so i think that for a lot of people learning about
vulnerability factors is really important but i put vulnerability factors in the context of
something that we do in dbt called a chain analysis which is a way of assessing problem
behaviors that people have that they want to change as a way of assessing it in order to figure out
how to change it going forward so vulnerability factors is an element of that chain analysis so
for example you know you were in treatment with me and one of the things we were working on is
this target behavior of you exploding in anger at you know various points we would identify
what a recent occasion in which that happened and then we would do an assessment of what were all
the factors events thoughts behaviors that led up to that behavior and then what were the consequences
of that behavior that would be the chain that we assess as a way of identifying okay well what can
we modify in this chain going forward to make it less likely that that problem behavior is going
to show up again and i think what we've been talking about is addressing what happens actually
very early on in the chain that vulnerability factor and for some people and in some situations
working on the vulnerability factor changes everything that follows but there's other events
and circumstances where it's not about the vulnerability factor or the vulnerability
factor is just one element but something happens in the environment a prompting event we would call
it perhaps that sets off the chain and it doesn't matter whether you got sleep or not the night
before because no matter what that whenever that prompting event happens you're going to explode in
anger right so we want to work on vulnerability factors but we also want to identify well what
are some other critical elements along the path towards the problem behavior that we can address
and and uh behaviorally manipulate yeah i mean when you say it that way it's really obvious because
you know even using myself as an example which is probably a more extreme example nothing ever
occurs in isolation like i've yet to come up with one example in my life where i can say yeah i
flew off the handle and it was only because of what was happening in that moment i mean it's just
not the case it's if i flew off the handle this is a situation where i would have barely got upset
a day ago or a week from now it was the literally the six things that had happened and maybe yeah
maybe maybe i didn't have a great sleep that's not what caused it of course but that made me more
susceptible and maybe this other thing happened and i didn't deal with it you know i didn't
confront the person who said such a thing that upset me and i just sort of buried it and went on
and maybe i you know read something on social media and i didn't even acknowledge that that
was very upsetting to me somebody attacked me and i sort of ignored it and then i find myself
in this situation and um i liken it to sort of the the challenger blowing up you remember when
the space shuttle challenger blew up this is you know god almost uh 40 years ago now um
it's so interesting and i'm an engineer by training so i i really have a keen interest in
in kind of the ins and outs of that that type of scenario and what you realize is like there was
nothing sudden about that horrible tragedy nothing about that was remotely sudden and
unexpected when you actually peel back the layers of the onion and go through the entire chain
analysis for not just the challenger but all the previous space shuttles and you realize
how inevitable this was and on that day this was almost a foregone conclusion um and yet at the
surface it just you know again now imagine watching that as a spectator oh my gosh how
could that happen well it it ties into the you would get an a on your dbt test because it ties
into the dialectical philosophy of everything is caused right and everything has multiple causes
um and that is very hard to accept sometimes and it's also very hard to experience especially in
our dominant culture that wants us to believe that there are simple answers uh and there's one person
to blame or one root cause that's that's what the dominant culture is trying to tell us about
everything and anything because that's simple and it's more complex than that uh that there's
always multiple determinants um of anything and that we could dissect
any behavior any problem and see the thousands or millions of causes that led up to that behavior
i have one of the pages in front of me that i've copied from my skills book that has so many of my
notes in it um and it you probably remember the page it's um sort of what makes it hard to regulate
your emotions and i've all this is probably one of the 10 you know this is a 350 page 400 page workbook
but this would be there's probably 30 or 40 pages that i have stickies in and this would be one of
the 10 most important and it's just this great reminder so just for the person listening to this
so what makes it hard to regulate your emotions biology let's just acknowledge there are
biological differences between us our brains are different um i won't go into some of the details
there but but you know anybody who has many kids more than one will recognize that they are simply
different even if they're raised identically um one that we already talked about lack of skill
right so lack of skill because skills were not taught because good skills were pushed away or
because bad skills were reinforced i think this comes from it which is reinforcement of emotional
behavior so kind of going back to childhood this one's very interesting right moodiness right
your your mood in the moment will alter your ability to regulate emotion um this one i can
relate to a ton which is emotional overload so the more pressure you have on you whether
self-imposed or otherwise the more difficult it is and then one that i love which is emotional myths
so mistaken beliefs about these things and i just may i have my own notes here one of them says when
i can't regulate it is almost always the case that at least one and typically three of these
are happening um so it's very interesting you know again three of these really pegged to
childhood right the biology the reinforcement of emotional behavior plus or minus skill and the
emotional myths yes i definitely think that they um a lot of them are long-standing patterns and
some of them are are current and also contextual so for example there might be a person in your life
just one of many that actually when you um uh display anger gives in to everything you're asking
right and that this could be totally outside of your awareness but that means that you're more
likely to have that anger response with that person in that context uh in the future i had
a while you know before my husband uh ex-boyfriend at one point who um when we would argue if i started
to cry he would immediately back down and this was outside of my awareness that this was happening
but i realized over time i found myself crying a lot more than i ever had before um and crying is
i'm not saying crying is good or bad but i just noticed that that was what was happening because
in that context with that person that behavior was was being reinforced and i feel like this could
happen so subtly and um it's so contextual that how we and why we're sometimes different with
different people um is because of that this is often at least as it relates to bpd is is like
pathologized oh if a person if you're different with different people there's something wrong
with you you have no core sense of identity or something but i would say it's actually pretty
normal we're all different with different people um because the context you know often call for that
and it's adaptive to be that way so is it essential for everybody who's practicing dbt to also be
practicing mindfulness meditation given the importance of that first step which is
recognizing the thought it is uh well we might have to disentangle what we mean by mindfulness
meditation because i would say mindfulness as a skill is central to everything yeah sorry let me
rephrase the question given the importance of mindfulness as a central tenet to this entire
practice is it also suggested that people use a form of meditation that practices the
skill you know you you know typically focusing on something like the breath or an object and
you know bringing their attention back to that every time it wanders as kind of one form yeah
we have actually debated this uh within dbt and i remember actually there was a while that
marcia was when i was a student of hers and therefore seeing her every day when she was on
this this kick for lack of a better word saying that we need to get all the therapists to practice
seated meditation like you're describing for at least 20 minutes every day and actually there's a
form of cognitive behavioral therapy called mindfulness-based stress reduction mbsr you
may have heard of it for depression in which they they teach people who are in the treatment
to work up to that seated meditation and they also require that therapists who
do mbsr also practice it that way and so marcia was thinking do i need to require this and i remember
even way back when arguing against it at the time because i thought that's that's not actually
practical for everybody always i think about a working mom who a single mom with three kids and
to say you need to find 20 minutes a day to do seated meditation is is um impractical um there
have been many times in my life where that was impractical as well so uh she and part of this was
to try to figure out like how do we define a dbt therapist how do we know when somebody is doing
dbt um so we she never ended up requiring or saying that therapists have to do this but what
she would say is that therapists who practice dbt have to have a mindfulness practice but that
practice could be anything um under the umbrella of mindfulness so you do yoga that's uh
could be your mindfulness practice or you do mind you know you do mindful walking or you do
mindful participating in various things and i would say that that is something when it comes to
clients who are in dbt we want them to strengthen their mindfulness muscle absolutely and if i have
clients who are interested in learning to do seated meditation that's amazing and i would
support that entirely i think for a lot of the clients that we work with at my clinic
that would be too big a jump um and why marcia doesn't doesn't say that clients need to do this
because lots for a lot of people who are in dbt who might be at that more severe end of the
continuum just sitting with themselves and their thoughts and their minds without doing anything
to change it for a minute could be excruciating um so we're trying to build that that tolerance
of course but the mindfulness skills in dbt are much more concrete and practical and designed to
be used in any moment rather than um designed to facilitate a more formal practice you know obviously
we can't cover dbt in any comprehensive manner there's so much but there are a couple things
i'd love to just highlight that i have found very helpful and i'd love to kind of hear your
you expand on them one is opposite action which is um you know for anybody who's done dbt you'll
grin when you just or grimace depending on because how hard it can be sometimes right
do you want to explain to people what opposite action is and when we use it i think you know
what's the use case for this yeah i did my dissertation on opposite oh i didn't know that
action i did okay so opposite action is a skill that falls into the emotion regulation module
and it's a skill for changing an emotion that you don't want to have
and it's simple in concept and hard to execute because uh simply put it's engaging in the opposite
of what your urges are telling you to do so we know and that's why it's called opposite action
so we know that from emotion science from our own experiences that our experience of emotions
are associated with an urge to act in particular ways so when we feel sad we have an urge to retreat
or withdraw when we experience anger we have an urge to lash out when we experience shame it's to
hide fear it's to fight or flight and so what opposite action says is that when your emotion
does not fit the facts of the situation or is too intense for the situation and you want to change
it a way to change it is to act opposite to your urges so when i'm sad instead of withdrawing i
activate when i'm fearful instead of running away i approach kind of like the exposure we were
talking about earlier when i'm experiencing shame rather than hide i actually confront or disclose
and and so on so it is really hard to do but you get better at it over time i will say that if you
practice i don't know if that's been your experience it has been and i but what i want
to tell you and i guess you'll appreciate this given your background especially is
you know i mentioned earlier anger being a profound emotion that i'm very familiar with
the other one is is um i don't know what the underlying emotion is i haven't really figured
it out yet um i don't think it's sadness but it produces a phenotype of needing to isolate
so there's a uh just a desire to completely isolate so these are two areas where opposite
action becomes very helpful right so with you know one of the really interesting things that
if you told me this five years ago i would have never believed it but it's remarkable is the use
of cold water to calm uh the nervous system in in moments of high fight or flight mode so that's
part of the opposite action effect there i feel angry i'm going to go and do something that's
really calming which is take an ice shower or jump in the cold pool this is nice in the winter
here in austin because we still have pools open and they're you know really cold in the winter
where i have but that's harder those are harder to do it's as you probably can imagine when you're
when you're at nine out of ten activation and your desire is to scream or break something
to then walk yourself back from that is harder where i have found um opposite action to be
remarkably helpful and helpful to the point where it's now the norm this this might be my biggest
win so far is when all i want to do is isolate forcing myself to go and play with my kids
and i remember the very first time this happened it was about a year and a half ago
and for reasons i didn't understand it was a sunday morning and i just didn't want you know
i wanted to sit in the office and do work and exercise and just do my own thing and be my own
thing and my wife said hey we're gonna go to barton creek and you know play on the rocks and
throw rocks in the water and stuff and again that's the sort of thing i would have said
absolutely not i'm too busy i just i'm overwhelmed i need to just do this thing
and she would have accepted it she would have been upset and she would have accepted it and she
would laugh and i was like okay let's go now i didn't want to go at all shireen i mean the
thought of not getting my work done and missing a workout potentially and then going to some place
where it's totally unstructured and there's going to be other kids potentially and it's going to be
loud like that everything about that was unappealing and we had this amazing time doing
nothing literally playing games like who could get across the creek without getting the most water
in their shoes and you know exactly what you'd expect and then on the way home we stopped and
got a burger and fries like the last thing i'd want to do right like we did everything i would
never want to do and i got home and i felt great and i didn't get as much work done and you know
and now that's become kind of the real is like you do that enough times that you realize this
really works this is the key for me this is important when i don't want to engage with anybody
go and engage with my family because that's by that's the drug to get out of this so yeah i
think opposite action is really a remarkable tool even the think of a simpler one smiling when you're
furious and meaning it right so uh what marcia talks about is this opposite action all the way
because we all know what a fake smile is and a fake smile while you're also in your mind thinking
oh what a asshole i hate this person you know like that's not opposite action because that's
what we might say half-assed opposite action it's not going to work because your mind is
still going to be angry but what's going to happen really what we're talking about with
opposite action is if we act opposite to our urges we're sending the feedback back to our brain
to to feel a different way right so approaching i think for a lot of people relate to the idea
of doing opposite action like what you said but also with when you're feeling socially anxious
like you want to avoid going to the party or speaking up in class or at work because you're
anxious and maybe you have a long history of avoiding saying anything or doing anything
because you're anxious so opposite action would be to say throw yourself into that go to that party
even though you don't want to and then throw yourself into the party which is what you
described with your family like you could have gone along physically but all the while been thinking
i could have been sitting there on my phone or goofing off yeah yeah or thinking this is stupid
or whatever but you threw yourself into it when you were there and i think that that's the the
critical piece it's not just the the moving your body there it's throwing your mind into it as well
so what else do you think would be really interesting for a person who's never heard
of dbt to kind of understand as they themselves contemplate hey is this something is this a new
skill i should learn right it's it's no different than saying i'd like to learn tennis because i know
that as i age full court basketball might be hard for me but tennis is something that i'll be able
to play for longer therefore i want to go and learn this skill i'm gonna need to coach i'm
gonna need to practice and a year from now i'll be better than i am today but i mean is that do
you think that's a good way to think about dbt well i do with with some caveats so you know
anybody who reads any news or is living their lives right now knows that what we're hearing
about is the idea that we're in a mental health crisis or that there's endless mental health
crises right now and what we know is that there are just simply not enough mental health providers
to treat all the need that's out there and what that has meant on a practical level is that there
are huge long waiting lists for treatment everywhere for most people and and i don't think
that we don't want that to deter people from seeking out help when they need it but the point
i want to make as it relates to that is that i don't think everybody needs full-on dbt and
and we don't yet have the science really this is actually an area of research that i'm interested
in is trying to figure out who does need the full package of dbt versus who can benefit from a
lighter touch a lower dose you know whatever word you want to use there because we want to be
efficient in our mental health delivery we also want people to learn to reduce suffering of people
on a on a mass level so is dbt something this sort of interrupt but just to kind of this will fit
into what you're saying is dbt something that can be done somewhat effectively on your own
meaning with manuals with books with videos online versus the way you would work with
you know people who are much sicker where you have to be working with them directly in person
so this is what we don't know yet i think we have some assumptions about this
but i don't even know if our assumptions are that valid but i think you know the assumption was
always for example that if somebody is experiencing suicidal thoughts they absolutely need you know
some form of treatment and it needs to be in person and it needs you know to be x y and z
and i think covid actually threw us into this new world that we weren't expecting because we had to
start treating people who were suicidal virtually for example and we were able to realize that this
idea that we had to see people in person was a myth that we believed and there were reasons why
we believed it but but there doesn't seem to be any as far as we know so far any added risk of
seeing somebody through telehealth when they're suicidal so i think a lot of our assumptions about
what people need are our assumptions that we don't actually know a lot about so one of an area of
research that i'm interested in and that i actually applied for some funding to do is to do kind of a
stepped care model of dbt to start everybody with what we might call a low dose intervention like
videos of skills and see what percentage of people benefit from that and from that alone
versus what percentage of people don't benefit enough need something else and then what can we
add to that that would be a slightly step up like maybe some phone coaching you get a call with
somebody once a week about how to apply the skills in your daily life then then test it again right
and then if you're not responding to that maybe then you get offered the full package of dbt
or something else and we basically can identify through that kind of study what are the sequences
of care that are going to be most effective that will help the most people and can be disseminable
so that's that's an area of research that i would love to do we don't have a lot of knowledge about
that so i'll but i'll say and i think we spoke about this very early on is that i honestly
believe that anybody could benefit from learning dbt skills and so to that end i would say yes i
think there is a value to your listeners to say expose yourself to some of these skills see if
and there are videos there are books there are things that you could do to learn more about them
um see if you resonate with them see if you can apply them on your own and if you want to know
more or you're struggling to apply it in your life then that might be where you could reach out for
for help and find a dbt therapist now speaking of that step shireen how does a person know when
they find the dbt therapist how can they verify that they're you know well trained i mean you're
probably an exception in that you trained directly with marcia um there are obviously a number of
people who train directly with her but you know that's not scalable so at some point you're going
to meet a potentially wonderful therapist who doesn't have that that lineage so how how is um
how is the field of dbt self-regulated or self-policed so it's been a long-standing process
to try to figure this out um and you know mental health is really screwing in this way because
there are so many ways in which a person can provide can become a therapist hang a shingle as
either window and practice therapy and um and that person can call themselves a dbt therapist
or a cbt therapist or any kind of therapist and and may not have the credentials or training to
back that up so i would i always tell people to kind of proceed with caution and to do your
research when you're looking into finding a mental health provider um so we marcia was against this
for a long time she was against this idea of um certifying dbt therapists she she didn't want
to have a regulatory role she wanted people to learn dbt and to just sort of get dbt out there
but then she was hearing more and more stories as we all have now of people saying that they
received dbt and it didn't work and then you ask them what happened in their treatment and you hear
details about their treatment that were clearly not dbt and so there's and and you know the worst
case scenario is somebody dies by suicide or you know has a terrible outcome thinking that they're
getting dbt when they're not so a few years ago she started the linnahan board of certification
lbc which has started a certification process for dbt therapists so what i will say is that
what's the logic here that i'm finding the hard time describing it but so all people that are
certified by lbc to be dbt clinicians are likely good clinicians good dbt clinicians because
they've met all of these standards but not all people who are not certified are bad dbt therapists
right because there's a number of dbt therapists who have just elected not to go through the
process of certification so if you're first starting to to think seriously about dbt you
might start by looking up certified dbt therapists but recognizing that that's not the only criteria
to use are there any other questions that a person can ask to determine if the pedigree of the person
who's going to be conducting their therapy is truly in line with the principles of dbt as opposed to
you know something that's been bastardized and and sort of misused so i'll share another
marcia anecdote in response to that question because relatively early on sort of after the
initial trials of dbt were put out showing that dbt was effective insurance companies started
getting interested and wanted to pay for dbt but didn't want to pay for non-dbt and so they would
call marcia up and they would say this person says they're doing dbt how do we know if they're really
doing dbt so that we can reimburse for the service and she thought about it and ultimately
said ask them if they're ask the dbt provider if they're on a consultation team now i think
that this is oversimplified by far but i'll explain that one of the aspects of dbt or one
of the components of the full package of dbt in addition to individual therapy and skills training
is that the dbt therapist him or herself attends a weekly consultation team meeting
with other dbt therapists and the consultation team meeting is a place where dbt therapists talk
about their experiences delivering dbt with an aim towards improving their own adherence to the
model and their motivation it's often called therapy for the therapist and and i think marcia's
response to that question was important because in many places somebody might say i want to learn
dbt and i can a provider might say oh i've learned the dbt skills and i can teach my clients dbt
skills and i'll just you know pick and choose what i want to do out of dbt and the first thing
they elect to drop is the consultation team meeting because it's time right it's time and effort and
it's and it's centered on you improving yourself as a therapist so i think it's i think it holds
up though as a reasonable question to know to what extent is the person that you're that you're
looking into adhering to dbt principles is to ask whether they're part of a dbt consultation team
that's a that's a great litmus test actually i really like that i don't know how many people
yeah i mean i don't it'd be interesting i mean it's funny because i hear andy talk about his
not surprisingly but i never really thought of it as a great litmus test as well so yeah shireen
this was fantastic and i know we're going to get to meet in person in about six weeks so i'm really
looking forward to that but thank you so much for your for your time uh today and i think you know
this is a hard topic because it's so big and it's so big to get your arms around it all and i i want
people to come away from this not at all thinking that they know what dbt is necessarily from this
but i hope we've piqued someone's curiosity such that they go out they they watch some videos they
maybe pick up a book or a skills book and decide hey is there something in here for me and and
maybe for some it means going as far as you know someone like me has gone and and saying i'm going
to make this a regular part of my training yeah great it was really fun talking to you so thank you
thanks shireen