Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Welcome everybody to episode three of the week of day spring.
In this episode, we talk about reverse cholesterol transport.
We talk about lipid transportation.
We talk about apolipoproteins and we talk about CTEP inhibitors and HDL.
Of all the things we talk about here, the thing that I think is the most interesting
is the discussion on HDL, which I think most people today would agree is far from being
understood and is probably far more complicated than LDL biology.
I would say that of all of the things that Tom and I discussed over this seven hours,
I learned the most personally in our HDL discussion and our discussion of the CTEP inhibitors.
I was very familiar with all of the trials here, but Tom brought a level of nuance to
this that actually sharpened my understanding of this and for that I am of course eternally
grateful.
So welcome to episode three.
Let's define now direct versus indirect RCT.
All right.
So if we're talking about the cholesterol, it's in lipoproteins.
So at the end of the day, you have perfect cholesterol homeostasis.
For some reason, there's some cholesterol excess in your body.
It's going to wind up in your artery wall or if you're lucky, it's going to wind up
in your stool.
That would be the preference way.
So the body clearly had nose.
Beyond a certain point, we don't want cholesterol.
We've talked about that at a bit of length so far.
So now how can the body get rid of cholesterol that's already inside, is made by cells, the
motion of the joint.
And everybody thinks the liver makes most of the cholesterol.
We're not talking about the brain now.
That's separate.
Of your rest of your cholesterol in your body, the liver makes 20% of it.
The rest is made in your peripheral cells.
So the bulk of your cholesterol that's in your body, if your peripheral cells are making
too much, it's got to get out or that cell will die.
So the cells through even beyond ABCA1 efflux that we've talked about, they can free diffuse
out of there.
ABC transported a compound cholesterol out and it gets in a lipoprotein or it binds to
albumin or binds to a red blood cell and it can be taken elsewhere.
So classically we were taught that, aha, the HDL particles are definitely a substrate that
a cell can efflux cholesterol out into, especially an empty HDL, APOA1, the protein itself, that's
unlipidated or a real baby HDL particle, very small HDL particle, is a great cholesterol
acceptor.
And we have membrane transporters that can give them free cholesterol.
All right.
So now the HDL has cholesterol and what were we taught?
Well, of course, the HDL just brings it right back to the liver and the liver then will,
if it has a need for cholesterol, it'll use it up and then it'll put it in your bile.
It'll go down and go right out your rear end.
Or your liver can actually change it to a bile cell, which it sends down the bile and
your bile cell could be excreted in the stool.
So in fact, that's a way, it's a major way of getting rid of cholesterol, but our ilium
doesn't cooperate.
Our ilium typically reabsorbs about 90 to 95% of the bile salts and reuses them.
So it's not the best way.
Unless you can make sure that bile cell is being excreted and we have a drug, the bile
cell questions that make sure that happens, then you would deplete internal cholesterol.
So that's so simple.
So our VLDLs and LDLs and colomicrons bring cholesterol to the tissues.
And if for some reason there's too much cholesterol, the HDLs bring it back to the liver and it
goes bye-bye.
If you're talking to a second grader or physician at one point in our careers, that made great
sense.
That's plausible.
That's perfect.
That's why HDLs are not delivering cholesterol to the artery wall.
They're bringing it back to an organ that's going to get rid of it or use it properly.
Perfect.
And if the other, the VLDLs, kylos and LDLs are bringing cholesterol to the tissues,
they never colded that, but I would say, well, that's forward cholesterol transport.
And if the HDLs are bringing it back, that's reverse.
Perfect.
And if we have a great balance between forward and reverse cholesterol transport, that's
good cholesterol homeostasis.
You're not going to get in trouble.
And then we made the mistake of, aha, our metrics of these pathways are going to be
LDL cholesterol, maybe total cholesterol or HDL cholesterol.
And that's where the whole thing falls apart because those metrics have zero to do with
describing the complex flux and trafficking of all these pools of cholesterol or so.
Zero.
There is no cholesterol measurement in the plasma that tells you anything about that
movement.
Are you in, are yourselves building up too much cholesterol or are they not?
Or God, you have great reverse cholesterol transport.
So it made such perfect sense and we were all stupid in medical school.
We're never going to contradict a professor or even give it two seconds worth of thought
if somebody told us something that the higher your HDL cholesterol, you got great reverse
cholesterol transport because that HDL is going to take it to the liver.
At a certain point in my studying of lipid understanding this stuff, and I knew, God,
what is it about not everybody with high HDL cholesterol is protected.
There are people with low HDL cholesterol who don't get disease.
But if what HDLs do is reverse cholesterol transport and they're bringing cholesterol
back to the liver, shouldn't your HDL cholesterol go down?
Why would HDL cholesterol go up if it was bringing it back to the liver and being internalized
or delipidated?
That made no sense to me.
So I knew there was more to the study.
And of course, guys like Dan Rader, who I alluded to before, and Brian Brewer and John
Chapman, our HDL experts in this world have figured this out pretty much by now.
So I know it's a, this lipid transportation system is way more complex than an HDL bringing
it back.
And in those, we give that a different name now.
So HDLs indeed are capable of bringing cholesterol back to the liver itself.
There is a receptor that will delipidated cholesterol S there from an HDL.
That's called the scavenger receptor B1 and SRB1.
There is a holoparticle receptor that can internalize large HDL particles and bring them into the
liver.
But free diffusion can also occur.
A big HDL can abut against a hepatocyte and cholesterol just diffuses from the HDL membrane
into the liver.
So there are at least three pathways of cholesterol getting back to the liver.
Hey, that same thing we now know happens at the intestine also.
So HDLs don't even have to go anywhere near the liver.
They can go get rid of some cholesterol at the intestine.
Remember that TICE pathway, Transintestinal Cholesterol Leaf Lux?
Right now we are boggled our minds and there are great papers on this.
Red blood cells carry way more cholesterol than deliproproteins.
They're so much bigger.
Now granted, the cholesterol is all in their surface, but they have a ton of cell membrane
surface.
So there's free cholesterol.
Albumin at least per albumin molecule can attach to 17 molecules of cholesterol.
So we now know to variable degrees both red blood cells and albumin can just abut against
any cell in your body and accept free cholesterol by free diffusion.
And LDL particle can abut against the cell and accept cholesterol by free diffusion from
a cell.
So now LDLs have another way of acquiring cholesterol.
It's interesting.
This would be a great question for someone like Josh Knowles who's such an expert on
FH.
Has anybody looked at red blood cell cholesterol membrane concentration or even size in FH
patients?
Because one hypothesis would be they will, especially the FH patients who have FH as
a result of LDL receptor deficiencies in some sort, you'd think that there'd be more free
diffusion of cholesterol from their LDL into their red blood cell.
Yeah.
And whether anybody's ever looked at that.
I mean, it might not be the case at all, but that would be a question.
Theoretically, free diffusion can occur between any two membrane surfaces.
So do their red blood cells, I would imagine at a certain degree it would cause red blood
cell irregularities.
Well, yeah, there might be too much noise, but you'd look at the MCV or something like
that and you'd say, have you increased or decreased the mean corpuscular volume of these
things?
Is there anything happening?
I don't know.
You're changing certainly the membrane structure if that process is occurring in those people,
whether that would affect red blood cell functionality.
Remember when you start putting phytosterols into red blood cell membranes, you get hemolytic
anemias and stuff.
Cytostrolemia, phytosterolemia, that's part of their pathology because the red blood cells
looking for cholesterol to stay healthy, not phytosterols.
I didn't know that, so I didn't realize that that's one of the hallmarks.
It's part of the phenotypic picture of cytostrolemia, red blood cell hemolytic anemias, or crazy
red blood cell structure, spherocytes and things like that.
So it's one way that the early investigators will, this person has an only phytosol, what's
this red blood cell problem going on this person too?
So this is interesting.
The HDL story is one where the more time goes on, the less I know.
I mean, there are a few things in lipidology that humble me more than my complete and utter
buffoonery and ignorance when it comes to understanding high density lipoproteins.
It's true of all of us, and that's why I don't want you reading my 2002 lipid hall.
It's anonymous.
You're embarrassed.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, God, I would criticize somebody with spout net stuff today.
So only if you read it with that in mind and you would see how things change.
Can we use a very specific example to explain this?
Let's talk about the first failed CTEP inhibitor trial, which was Pfizer's back in the mid-2000.
So let me give the background, and then I want you to explain why this may have failed.
Maybe I just want to explain a little more about the lipid transportation system.
Yeah, yeah, that's a good idea.
So you know what CTEP is.
So remember I talked about the early on view with forward cholesterol transport, even though
they didn't call it.
That's the ApoB family bringing cholesterol to tissues and the HDL family bringing it
back.
And here's why that's just such an absurd theory.
Because when the intestine pumps out colomicrons that have a lot of your absorbed cholesterol
in it and your liver, certainly when it manufactures a VLDL particle whose primary purpose,
and everybody please listen to this, the VLDL has two purposes, one of which is not to deliver
cholesterol anywhere.
The liver is to develop transport triglycerides energy to cells that either store or utilize
any fatty acids for energy and to transport phospholipids.
All right, so that's what your VLDLs and colomicrons do.
So they're part of the forward cholesterol transportation system.
So the liver or the intestine excretes them and then they're floating around.
So what do they do?
They go to adipocytes or they go to muscle cells, their triglycerides are extracted,
and then their phospholipids break off and are utilized by cells.
So what are you left with when a chylomicron loses surface phospholipids and core triglycerides?
You're left with a smaller VLDL or a smaller chylomicron.
Any lipoprotein that goes from a bigger size to a smaller size, but it's still within the
density of a VLDL or chylomicron is called a remnant.
It's a smaller.
Hey, if Peter just amputated my right arm now, I'd be a remnant of my former self because
I'd have one less arm.
So the VLDLs and colos have lost their core triglycerides and they've lost their core
phospholipids and a few proteins have broken off too.
So now what happens to those remnant VLDLs and colos?
They're virtually instantly cleared by receptors that exist in the liver primarily.
How do those receptors clear these VLDL particles and these chylomicron particles that have
accomplished their mission and delivered triglycerides?
They bind to either the Apo-B100 that's on the VLDL, but LDL receptors won't bind to
Apo-B48 and the chylomicron, but they bind to Apo-E.
And chylos and VLDLs typically, if you're lucky, have multiple copies of VLDLs.
So as soon as the chylos or VLDLs deliver your energy, deliver your phospholipids,
they are cleared, which is why the chylomicron half-life is minutes and the VLDL half-life
is a couple of hours.
Don't ever confuse half-life with plasma residence time.
That's a little bit longer, but that's only a few particles that are persisting beyond
those average half-life or so.
So now any of the VLDLs that are not totally cleared by the liver keep getting smaller.
They become smaller remnants, but then they change densities to a certain different degree
density range.
So you can't call it a VLDL anymore.
You call it an intermediate density lipoprotein.
The same thing, that's got a half-life of an hour.
That's also clear because IDLs have a lot of Apo-E on it.
But at the liver, as they're being cleared, there's another enzyme that transforms some
of your IDLs into a smaller.
It's an IDL remnant called, well, you'd be entering a new specific density boundary,
and it would be called the low-density lipoprotein.
So technically, you can say, yes, some VLDLs do become IDLs, do become LDLs, and in the
LDLs, we'll hang around forever until the LDL receptor clears in LDL by binding to Apo-B.
The reason Chylos, VLDLs, and IDLs get cleared so much more quickly than LDLs is the Apo-E
content, which is a mega ligand for the LDL receptor.
The LDL receptor is really an Apo-B, Apo-E receptor, and there are other Apo-E receptors,
too.
So that's why those particles don't last long.
And just to interrupt you for a sec, Apo-E greatly amplifies the efficacy of that ligand,
the Apo-B ligand?
It just is a preferred ligand for either an LDL receptor or other, they're called LDL
receptor-related receptors.
I'm sorry, I want to come right back to what you're saying, but I know I'll forget to ask,
what percentage of LDL particles also co-express Apo-E?
Yeah, so if you are lucky enough to have that genetic gift, and your LDL happens to contain
an A-B, it's half-life is pretty much the same as an IDL.
They're gone.
So if they're gone, guess where they came and wind up?
You have enhanced clearance, your Apo-B, your LDL particle level will be much lower, and
you don't get heart disease.
And in average population, it's about 3 to 4%.
But I guarantee you, depending on genes you've inherited, some people probably have a lot
of Apo-E on their LDLs, and of course I would bet if they were studying genetic drugs, they
don't get heart disease, you know, because it's being cleared, all those particles.
And we'll talk about it later, there are other Apo proteins that can retard clearance of
VLDLs, IDLs, and even LDLs.
I'll just mention its name now, it's Apo-Liproprotein C3.
You got that on your particles, you're going to have seriously increased plasma residence
time of all those things, and LDL with Apo-C3 on it is intensely more atherogenic than in
LDL that only has Apo-B100 on it.
You once told me, this was probably a couple months ago, we were just shooting the breeze
one day by phone, and I remember you saying that if you could add one clinical assay to
the arsenal of lipidologists, it would be an Apo-C3 assay, is that still true?
It would be, because I think that's going to be the way we really are going to smartly
identify remnant lipoproteins that are the VLDLs that are potentially causing trouble.
Most VLDLs are not troublemakers, they're cleared rapidly, or the LDLs that are number
one in a list as to what's going in your arterial wall.
Apo-C3, as you know, Peter, is over expressing insulin resistance situations.
I have no doubt that one day that would be a cool test, unless maybe we can just measure
your genetic, the genes that give you Apo-C3.
Except that insulin sensitivity and insulin resistance impact it, which would suggest that
if you took two people with the same lipid profile at the lipoprotein level, but one
had higher Apo-C3 than the other, that person's at higher risk.
And I think we got enough data now, it shows that, and to show you, pharma believes that
there's a major ongoing now with an Apo-C3 inhibitor that's coming, because it'll be
the way to get rid of these extremely epigenic problems.
Is this ISIS doing this?
Yeah, I believe so, yeah.
Oh, sorry, just for the listener.
ISIS, I'm not referring to, yeah, yeah, yeah.
This is ISIS, there's a pharma company, it's in San Diego, they're actually based out of
San Diego, because that's where Sam Tamekis is, but it is ISIS.
Yeah, it's one of these new...
Yeah, and they're looking at oligonucleotide...
Oligonucleotide, yeah, they're looking at oligosense.
...an anti-sense thing, so keep your fingers crossed.
So we should come back and talk about that, because the anti-C3 and the anti-sense oligonucleotide
against Apo-Lipoprotein little a, those are hugely interesting.
Yeah, they're going to probably be great therapeutic avenues for us if we need it.
So yeah, I think there will be utility for measuring this right now before a third party
payer is ever going to pay some lab for doing that, it's going to need a little more proof
than what we have so far and everything.
But back to our lipid transportation system, so please understand, and there are just too
many people out there who think every VLDL becomes an LDL, it's not even close.
And in fact, if you are not insulin resistant and you don't have a, however you define a
triglyceride issue, which I might define as a trig above 1.30 or so anyway, I think
40% of the ApoB particles coming out of your liver, they're not VLDLs, they're LDLs.
And the VLDLs that are coming out are not big, because they're not carrying extra triglycerides
because you don't have them.
They're just carrying some degree of cholesterol and a little bit of triglycerides to supply
the energy you really need.
And that's why if you are measuring some VLDL metric, big VLDLs occur only in triglyceride-rich
lipoprotein pathologies by far the most common of which is insulin resistance.
And clearly because that VLDL would come out, and I guarantee it's probably got ApoC3 on
it, it doesn't have a half-life of a few hours, its plasma residence time is much longer,
there is more conversion of that VLDL particle into LDL particles, which would be triglyceride-rich.
Through some transformation they become the small LDLs, which are even less rapidly cleared.
So your ApoB particle number, your LDL particle number goes through the roof.
Now yes, part of those ApoB are the remnants, but I've posted enough slides on Twitter right
now, I'm pretty sure it's in Peter's package here.
Even when you take these type 2 diabetics with severe insulin resistance, or insulin
resistance just proved by an insulin clamp study, their ApoB level, their particle levels
are going up, but the LDL particles go up astronomically, and the VLDL maybe doubles
or triples, it goes from 30 to 90, whereas the VLDL particles go from 1,000 to 3,000.
The LDL, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
That's an important distinction.
So a lot of people will say when you're insulin resistant, all of that net difference is,
we see, because there's no disputing, the more insulin resistance you get, the more
discordant you get between your LDL-P and your LDL-C. And all things equal, the LDL-P
is just going up and up and up as you become more insulin resistant.
So people will say, it's all the VLDL.
Furthermore, they'll confuse a percentage increase that's relative with an absolute
increase.
So as you pointed out, if you're referring to the Garvey paper, I think, so in that paper,
you might see VLDL particle number, I'm making this up, so someone will see the numbers and
decide for themselves, but it might go from 30 to 60.
Yeah, or 150.
An animal per liter.
And you think, well, God, that's a much bigger relative increase.
And it is.
But if anybody's read our lengthy treaties on relative versus absolute risk, you cannot
evaluate a relative change without understanding its absolute change.
And so even though the relative change on the LDL-P is smaller, it's starting from such
a high base that it might add 300 to 400 nanomole per liter, which might only be a 30 or 40%
increase, but that absolutely dominates the lion's share of the increase, not the extra
30 to 50 nanomole per liter you might get on the VLDL.
This is a really important point if you want to be a lipid geek.
It is.
And this is one reason why non-HDL cholesterol has become in vogue, because remember, non-HDL
cholesterol, we told you, you calculated by subtracting HDL cholesterol from total cholesterol,
but you could really add directly measured LDL cholesterol to a VLDL cholesterol.
Your cholesterol is not in your HDL particles, theoretically, potentially, atherogenic cholesterol.
And hey, that's a free calculation, too.
So they use non-HDL cholesterol as a marker of remnants.
Okay.
And there's no doubt some of those VLDL particles would be remnants, but we'll get into this
later, I hope.
I'll make the case that a lot of those VLDL particles are not remnants and they're not
going into your heart.
Yeah, it's funny.
I used to always sit a patient down, and the very first time we reviewed a blood test,
I would say, look, there's four things we're going to talk about from a lipid standpoint.
We got to know your LP little A. We have to know your LDL P. I'd like to know how many
of those are small, because it's a proxy for some other stuff, and I want to know your
VLDL remnant.
Well, I can't measure that, so I'm going to approximate it with VLDLC.
Well, I don't say that anymore, because I've come to realize...
That's a very crude, crude estimation that's almost useless.
I wouldn't call it useless, because...
I use the word almost in front of it.
Yeah, okay, yeah.
And I'll get all my lipid colleagues real mad at me if I start saying that, because
I get into this in a lot of the papers.
And we still target.
I mean, I still say to patients, I want your VLDL cholesterol less than 15 milligrams per
deciliter.
And the odds are good in an insulin resistant patient.
You have other ways of knowing whose insulin resistance who's not.
If that marker is up, remnant lipoproteins are part of their pathology.
But the exact same therapy I'm going to give you to get rid of the real troublemaker, your
LDL particles, is going to get rid of the remnants too.
So at the end of the day, it's I got to normalize APOB, your LDL particle number, and there
is significant discordance.
Alan Snyderman has published it many times.
As good as non-HCl cholesterol, meaning better than LDL cholesterol, is a metric of APOB.
There's a lot of discordance between APOB, your LDL particle number, and non-HCl cholesterol.
So I understand it's a free calculation.
Please and people who you really are worried about or you think, Aris, you've got to use
particle numbers to make the proper clinical decisions.
This reminds me, I need an excuse to go to Montreal so I can interview Alan.
If you can get him on a podcast, I'll be your first listener.
Nothing comes out of his mouth that you don't want to write down.
If you don't make anything up.
Alan is sounds a special guy.
Alan is not afraid to call a spade a spade, so to speak.
He will just tell you.
And that's why I love him.
I don't mind Alan telling me I'm an idiot.
No time you're wrong.
I know here's the way it is.
Again, you learn some guys like that or not afraid to put you in your place.
Alan, if you're listening to this, why don't you come up with an excuse to come to New
York or San Diego?
And if I do have an excuse to come to Montreal, I will.
Let's get back to our lipid transportation system now.
So we have our theoretical forward delivering particles, the APOB particles, and I tell
you how they transform into one another, how they deliver their cholesterol.
By the way, no VLDL or IDL or Kylo is delivering cholesterol to your peripheral cells.
They don't need it.
They're making all they need.
So just restate that, please, for the courts transcript.
So tell me again what Kylo's are doing are not doing what you walked out of this.
I was in the room to do so when I was explaining what Kyle is in VLDL.
Tom just outed me.
I went to go take a leak a minute ago.
So I explicitly went over that the purpose, the functional purpose of Kylo microns in
VLDL is to deliver energy in a form of triglycerides, the adipocytes and myocytes and phospholipids
not to deliver cholesterol to any darn cell in your body.
So spend your time reading on it.
That's what they do.
You could even make the case that if they're not delivering cholesterol, why is cholesterol
even in their particles?
And it goes back to something what Peter said.
These particles have to be spherical.
So when a VLDL or an anthracite is starting to lipidate APOB48 or especially liver APOB100,
if you put cholesterol in that and we have proteins that do that, microsomal triglyceride
transfer and other cellular lipid transport proteins, by putting cholesterol on the APOB,
it becomes a spherical particle.
So all primordial VLDLs and Kylo microns are first just very cholesterol rich spherical
particles.
They don't have the triglycerides yet.
Then when they're spherical particle, they can really fill up with their triglycerides.
So the cholesterol is in there for a structural property to make them spherical particles
so that they can carry more triglycerides.
And that's why when they go out, they become smaller spherical particles that are triglyceride
depleted and they just bring their cholesterol back to the liver or the intestine and they
do whatever they do with it.
So that's why cholesterol is in there.
They're not bringing cholesterol to my nose or your kidney or any place else because those
cells need cholesterol.
Those cells will make it or they'll get it by some free diffusion if they really need
it or absolutely virtually any cell of it absolutely needed cholesterol because for
some reason the synthesis was broken.
Any cell could ultimately up regulate an LDL receptor, but most of them don't.
So because they have no need for the cholesterol that's in an LDL.
The liver up regulates most your LDL receptors because that's involved with clearance of
these particles.
That's where your LDL receptors are heavily expressed.
But now you do have these particles that have certain half-lives or plasma residence times,
VLDLs even for a few hours or LDLs for at least a day in some instances more, HDLs for
a few days.
So are they stagnant particles that never change?
No, guess what?
They're living, breathing particles.
So I used to have nice animated diagrams of this.
Every second of every minute of every day, your particles are having sex with one another.
They're transferring bodily fluids.
They exchange from their core.
Every lipoprotein in your body has some degree in its core of triglycerides and cholesterol
ester.
Every particle from an HDL to a cholomicron to a VLDL, IDL and LDL.
And we actually have a protein that's pretty much carried on HDLs.
It was originally called apoprotein or apolipoprotein D as in DORG, capital D. And in my dirty New
Jersey mind, think of an HDL particle which carries most of the APOD.
Men carry something between their legs that if it got erect, it's sticking up and it can
penetrate something else.
So if HDLs are carrying this APOD and it suddenly sticks up, it can penetrate another
particle, be it another HDL or an APOB particle.
And that's a phospholipid sort of tunnel.
It's like a little tunnel that can connect two circulating lipoproteins.
And therefore, the core lipids can exchange.
And this is HDL to HDL or can it be HDL to LDL?
The HDL to HDL, in which case it's called a homotypic transfer because it's like particles
exchange in their bodily fluids or a heterotypic where APOA particles exchange their core lipids
with APOB particles.
What is hardly known out there is two APOB particles can exchange their lipids.
A VLDL can exchange its core lipids with an LDL.
And I'm going to tell you, that's where remnants get a lot of their cholesterol.
So that would be homotypic exchange of cholesterol and triglycerides between two different APOB
containing particles.
So a lot of it is between HDLs and APOB particles.
And why?
Why would we even be given that lipid transfer protein?
Because HDL's job is to be a great cholesterol acceptor.
It is very important in delipidation, helping cells efflux the cholesterol they don't want.
So when an HDL acquires that free cholesterol from a cell, what does it do?
Well, HDL carries that ACAT enzyme I talk about it, except it's called LCAT because
it's an lipoprotein.
It starifies the cholesterol to cholesterol ester, goes to the core of the particle, the
HDL becomes bigger.
Then the HDL transfers its cholesterol ester to, let's say, an APOB particle, 95% of which
are LDL particles.
So here's where the joke comes in.
So I know you're all calling the cholesterol in an HDL.
That's good cholesterol.
But what do you call that cholesterol molecule the second an HDL transfers it to an LDL?
Does it instantly become bad?
Oh, it's bad now.
If I looked at it, it's still the same exact cholesterol molecule.
So if you want to use those darn adjectives with a patient, I guess what's going to determine
what's good or bad cholesterol is, what is that lipoprotein going to do with its cholesterol?
It's a cholesterol molecule.
If it's an HDL and it's an LDL and it's bringing it back to the liver or the intestine, well,
that's not bad.
I don't think, because those organs know how to get rid of cholesterol.
So I don't know, maybe that's a good cholesterol pathway, but I don't think you can apply that
to the cholesterol molecule itself.
But follow me here.
What if that HDL pulled cholesterol out of your cell because it was overproducing too
much and he gave it to an LDL and said, buddy, take off.
The liver's got that LDL receptor.
It's going to clear you.
And that LDL particle raced back to the liver.
And for some reason, there was no LDL receptors, so there weren't enough of them there.
Where's that LDL going?
He might wind his way back into circulation.
He will, because he's not going to be clear.
He might wind his way back to endothelium.
All of a sudden, your good cholesterol is in the macrophage in your arterial wall.
So spare me the nonsense.
Stop using its absurd term.
It has no meaning.
You're mis-educating patients, if you tell them it's good cholesterol, because they use
that because they're measuring HDL cholesterol and blood is a marker that I'm in good shape
or not.
And trust me, virtually all of the early trials that showed low HDL cholesterol was bad news,
were never ever adjusted for ApoB or LDL particle counts.
Because I'm going to tell you right now.
And that includes Framingham, which I alluded to earlier.
Yes.
A lot of people like to hang their hat on the fact that Framingham, because most people
forget what Framingham is.
They throw the term around.
So let me just spend one minute explaining this.
Framingham started out as a five geography, a five city or five region observational study,
purely observational, of which Framingham was one.
And I used to know them all.
No, Framingham is only Framingham, Massachusetts.
No, no, no, but the original cohort of that study from NIH was Framingham, Puerto Rico,
San Francisco, Hallelujah.
Where did Framingham evolve from?
That's right.
Then there was a five city group here.
And that's where they gathered the information.
That's where they made the observation.
So there was a purely retrospective assessment of five cities.
And I'm blanking on the fit, but I think one was Puerto Rico, Honolulu.
I'm pretty sure Stanford might have been one.
But anyway, the point, but the prospective work was then concentrated in Framingham, Massachusetts.
But the point is, a lot of people like to point out that LDL is irrelevant because the
LDL cholesterol, which by the way, was calculated, not measured directly.
So you've introduced a variability.
Years later, not in the first 20 years.
Correct.
It turned out to be less predictive than the ratio, not the ratio, I'm sorry, the absolute
level of HDLC and triglyceride.
And a lot of people like to stop at that and say, well, look, that means LDL doesn't matter.
What they don't realize is those are two enormous proxies for APOB.
That's all they are.
And virtually all of your insulin resistant patients are getting atherosclerotic disease.
It's APOB.
It's LDL particle mediated because everybody who's not on a drug or a serious diet who
had a triglyceride HDL cholesterol axis abnormality has astronomical APOB.
So if you go back for all this cited forever epidemiologic data, that low HDL cholesterol
is such an important risk factor, do me a favor, pal, adjust it for APOB or LDL-P, which
has never done and can't be done in those studies now, it would disappear as an independent
risk factor or low HDL cholesterol.
Well that's certainly the hypothesis.
I mean, I guess the question is, does Mesa still have enough blood kicking around to
measure that or Framingham offspring?
It does.
Mesa has certainly shown in the discordant people where there's the discordance with
APOB and LDL cholesterol or, and people have low HDL cholesterol, APOB, LDL particle is
your most important metric.
So Mesa has shown-
And Mesa, when we're saying this, by the way, folks, we're not talking Mesa, Arizona.
We're talking about the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis, which is abbreviated Mesa.
So we'll often, you'll often hear people refer to Mesa and Framingham and what they're referring
to are enormous studies of atherosclerosis that still have biobanks that are available
to do these retrospective analyses on prospectively collected samples.
Yeah.
And that is much more contemporary and multi-ethnic.
So it's-
Yeah, because I've got another criticism of Framingham is you've taught me a lot about
middle-class white people in-
Boston, right.
... the Northeast.
But what have you told me about African-American, Hispanic, et cetera?
All information is always good.
There's always weaknesses with all information or shortcomings or so, but we build stepwise
on it.
So before you declare, make any statements based on an HDL metric, please make sure you
have an LDL particle or APL B metric in front of you also, and pretty much base what you're
going to advise a patient on risk and assessment based on-
So one of the most amazing papers you've ever sent me, and this was actually kind of recent.
I feel like this was a year ago, maybe a year and a half ago, was a case study of a woman
who had an HDL cholesterol of about 130 to 140 milligrams per deciliter.
So for the listener, you just never see levels of HDL like that unless you work in the lipid
community or you're a lipidologist, which means I don't see them because I'm not a lipidologist.
I just pretend to be one.
But the average person, the average female might walk around with an HDL cholesterol
of 60 milligrams per deciliter.
So this woman is showing up at two and a half times normal.
And interestingly, I don't even know you remember this case study, Tom, but if not,
I think I remember enough of the details, she had very accelerated atherosclerosis.
She did not, by the way, to my recollection, have particularly elevated LDL cholesterol.
Her LDL cholesterol was probably about 110 milligrams per deciliter, slightly below her
HDL cholesterol.
And of course, the question was, why did this woman have elevated atherosclerosis when
she had normal amounts of quote unquote the bad cholesterol and two and a half to three
times normal good cholesterol?
Do you remember this case?
Not per se, but it's been well explained.
And this is a rare genetic thing where this cholesterol trafficking pattern is disrupted
in certain ways.
Something's wrong with that pathway because that HDL should be getting rid of its cholesterol
and it should be bringing blood back someplace.
So this person would have to have incredibly massive HDL particles that are carrying way
more cholesterol particles per HDL particle than it should be.
And it turns out, and they're not being cleared as much as they should.
So this is going to turn out to be cholesterol rich HDL particles that don't have a protein
that's very integral with clearing HDLs and say PoE again.
So if you don't have a PoE on your HDLs, they might become very cholesterol rich.
Your HDL cholesterol is through the roof.
Those are incredibly dysfunctional HDLs.
And part of their dysfunction is they're probably carrying the wrong type of phospholipids and
are not carrying the type of protective proteins that an HDL should be carrying.
Because when you have a surface area that's that big, the proteins that should be binding
to it no longer bind because it's not, they're looking for the molecules they're supposed
to covalently bind to and they can't find it or so.
So that's a circumstance of very dysfunctional HDL.
And now I remember the context, which was a really good friend of mine from med school
sent me a friend of a friend's blood and the numbers were like that.
And I remember reaching out to you saying, this is odd, Tom, what do you make of this?
You sent me the case study.
There's really nothing to do to treat these people except lower APOB, right?
You just have to chase.
It's sort of like, what do we do for LP little A nowadays?
You chase every other identifiable cardiovascular risk factor.
And I remember saying, nobody would do it to her, but there is a product that induces
a receptor in the liver that pulls cholesterol out of HDL particles.
It's a, was I called probucal.
I don't know if it's even still available by prescription.
It induces the scavenger receptor drastically lowers HDL, but it's a powerful antioxidant.
And there were some early arteriographic studies that suggested this is good.
Studies at least on an arterial imaging look better.
So say, saw or Milan.
I'm sorry, just to be clear, the reason why, I mean, again, there's a 217 ways to be fooled
by an angiogram.
It's about as crude a way to assess this process as anything that said, if you believe that
this is improving, you believe it's basically increasing the throughput of HDL to D lipidate.
Yeah.
So the theory would be, uh-huh.
This is the case where, hey, remember I espoused the theory before that if HDLs are really
delivering cholesterol back to the liver, shouldn't HDL cholesterol be going down?
Well, here's a drug that depletes HDL cholesterol and at least arteriographically people look
better.
We now have identified a gene that regulates the functioning of the scavenger receptor.
So if you have an inactivity of that scavenger receptor, you have very big HDL particles,
high HDL cholesterol and coronary atherosclerosis.
This is a nice transition.
So let's summarize that.
This is, again, overly simplistic.
This is a zeroth order analysis.
So we're just going to put our fourth grade hats on, which is acceptable for limited periods
of time.
If you have low HDLC, you cannot infer if it's low because you're failing to quote unquote
pick up cholesterol or because you're delivering it quickly.
You don't know.
Conversely, or similarly, I should say, if you have high HDLC, it is not clear if it
is high because you pick up a lot, which in theory would be quote unquote good, or because
you're deficient at dropping it off, which would be quote unquote bad.
And therein lies perhaps one of the most interesting or certainly top five interesting drug stories,
which are the CTEP inhibitors.
Right.
And again, I'm just going to do it because I just want to finish this whole.
So I told you HDL has this-
APOD.
But APOD is better known as cholesterol ester transfer protein.
It really ought to be called cholesterol ester triglyceride transfer protein.
C E T P.
So we're going to talk about a CTEP inhibitor in a moment because it's going to stop that
process.
The lipoproteins can't exchange the particles anymore.
Now wait a minute.
If you're following me so far, and HDL, which is pulling cholesterol out of cells, it's
really good at that, is then transferring a lot of that cholesterol to LDLs.
Here's something that's going to shock you.
In an average person, anywhere from 30 to 60% of the cholesterol in that LDL particle
arrived via an HDL particle.
So if that LDL particle will accept that cholesterol from an HDL and race it back to the liver,
thank you LDL.
It's like the HDL was a quarterback, it passed it to the tight end, we ran it across the
goal line.
Who gets the credit, the quarterback or the tight end or both of them?
So in the lipid transportation system, they work harmoniously together if everything works,
including the lipid transfer proteins.
We're not going to talk about it today, but God also gave us lipid inhibitory transfer
proteins, apolipoprotein, FAPO, C1.
So everything is tightly regulated in our homeostatic system.
But we'll leave that for another day.
Yeah, so if this is the master's class on lipid, that will be the whatever falls above
a master.
So it's always more complicated.
So now just to finish up the definitions of a reverse cholesterol transport, all day is
HDL back to the liver.
Nowadays it's HDL gets cholesterol from wherever.
If things go right, it could bring it back to either the liver or the small intestine
or an adrenal gland or an ovary or a testis.
So that's going to be called direct because the HDL is doing it.
And we're saying he's the primary factor here because he does pull cholesterol out of the
cells.
But we now also know that HDL can give its cholesterol to an LDL, to a VLDL, to a chylomicron,
to an IDL.
It's most of them are LDLs.
It's giving most of it to an LDL.
And they can bring that cholesterol.
They're going to be cleared at the liver if you have the proper number of LDL receptors.
Hey, so if an HDL gives its cholesterol to an APOB particle, it brings it back to the
liver.
That is called indirect reverse cholesterol transport.
We're still debating can an LDL bring it back to the small intestine also for a while.
That was yes.
That was probably not.
Now it's back to a probably yes again.
But if an LDL brings it back to the liver for sure and the intestine, then that's indirect
cholesterol, reverse cholesterol transport if you still need the reverse adjective put
in there or so.
But part of that pathway is it's not the liver.
It's the intestine, the trans-intestinal cholesterol efflux.
So if you want to talk about total reverse cholesterol transport, I would rather just
talk about lipid transport.
It's every particle is part of the system.
But if you want to stick with reverse cholesterol transport, total RCT is the sum of indirect
plus direct.
And both direct and indirect involve the liver and the intestine.
And a serum HDL cholesterol tells you nada about that process.
Yeah, we may or may not have time to get into this, but yesterday over dinner we talked
about the futility or the challenges maybe is a better way of saying it to be a little
more optimistic.
But the challenges in coming up with HDL functional assays because once you get deep enough into
this topic, as we're getting now, you very quickly start to realize that to measure HDL
cholesterol or even HDL particle number is so crude in terms of providing an insight
into its functional status.
The best we can do today is we measure HDL cholesterol, HDL particle number, and HDL
particle size.
And we try to triangulate just as we used to when we could look at LPa mass and LPa
cholesterol.
We could sort of triangulate if we were in the zone.
But that's still not the answer.
I mean, that just doesn't tell us how well these things function.
We just need more specific biomarkers nowadays to take it to the next level and the types
of therapies that are coming along.
And I think that's even important knowledge to know when you're going to prescribe a
specific nutritional therapy also that all these things come into play.
So very important to understand this stuff, but I hope you can see how this world has
changed and we ought to stop using even the term reverse cholesterol transport.
It's idiotic.
It's so immensely complex.
You don't know what you're talking about and you have no biomarker that you can evaluate
that on the given patient.
And the functionality of these particles, like do they really participate in these pathways
or not, are determined in large part by their phospholipid content in the proteins that
are on these surfaces apart from just the APOD we talked about.
And with HDLs, just briefly, I think there is probably hundreds of HDL subpopulations.
HDLs carry an immense number of proteins, way more than LDLs or VLDLs ever can.
But they all can carry one or two proteins.
They can't carry 200 proteins that have been identified as coming from HDLs.
So it's probably the protein signature of an HDL or even the phospholipid makeup, the
lipidome of an HDL.
We have just like, you know, I love fire departments.
Fire departments have hoke and ladder trucks.
They have pumper trucks.
They have hazmat trucks.
They got a variety of rescue vehicles nowadays.
They got ambulances, rescue trucks, and they don't all show up at every fire.
The dispatch sends the trucks that are needed to specific types of fires.
Well, your HDL subpopulations show up where they're needed and they know where they're
needed because the cells that need them recognize the proteins or the phospholipids that are
on their surface and pull them in.
So I don't know when it's going to come down to lipidomic or proteomic analysis of these
particles.
I think that maybe will take us to the next level and wouldn't hold your breath on that
anytime soon.
All right.
So let's go back to this idea of, because I want to start talking a little bit about
some drugs, but rather than start chronologically, which I want to do after we get to this question,
but just because while we're on HDL, there are really two drugs that have been discussed
as ways to quote unquote raise HDL, one being niacin, which we'll come to later on, but
the other being these CTEP inhibitors, which are relatively recent.
It was 2006 when the first CTEP trial, or at least when the first data became available,
and they weren't promising.
So first of all, why would inhibition of CTEP been thought to be an optimal strategy?
And two, why do you think it didn't turn out that way?
Because we don't know what we're doing with HDLs and especially using metrics to analyze
them.
And the story starts a lot longer than that in Italy, that little section up on Northeastern
Italy where ApoA1 Milano was discovered, and these were people who had HDL cholesterol
levels of five and 10, and yet had longevity.
And how could that possibly be?
Because Framingham has taught us low HDL cholesterol, you're out of here.
And yet here's where people with longevity.
And it turns out they had a very functional ApoA1 that really did the flux system very
quickly or had other properties that didn't matter how much cholesterol was in the HDL.
The HDL was unbelievably functional.
Do you know anything about their ApoBs?
I think even if they have high ApoB, they don't get, I don't know that, they're probably
out there, I can't answer that often.
Maybe we'll look that up if we can.
But their high functioning ApoA seems to protect them.
I doubt if ApoB matters because some of them probably would.
Although their role on that Mediterranean died and stuff, so maybe they don't have that
for a general part.
So I can't answer that.
So that led pharma to, hey, let's just invent either synthesized ApoA1 or a truncated ApoA1
and commercialize that.
At least for people who had acute coronary syndromes, we'll infuse that into them.
It'll de-lipidate their plaque and home free.
Every single trial failed, including a very recent trial.
So there's one where they got a specially protective type of HDL, but they couldn't
reproduce it, whatever it is.
So that failed.
So there were people in the past that Peter talked about, he gave a case where a woman
had very high HDL cholesterol but had coronary atherosclerosis.
But there is a bunch of people out there with very high HDL cholesterol who don't have
coronary, I'm going to theorize in retrospect, maybe ApoE's got something to do with that,
but I don't know that because that would enhance their clearing.
But what is one of the genetic conditions that would give you high HDL cholesterol?
Remember I just taught you what ApoD is, CETP, CETEP.
It takes the cholesterol out of your HDL and gives it to an ApoB particle.
So theoretically that would lower your HDL cholesterol.
But if I inhibited CETEP, your HDL would get the key ball, it's cholesterol.
What would go through the roof?
Your HDL cholesterol.
And the genetic model was at least some people with certain CETP variants had very high HDL
cholesterol and they didn't seem to get much heart disease.
Although what I'm confused by, Tom, is that in 2011-ish, didn't a Mendelian randomization
look at this and conclude?
Now this was long after these drugs were in the pipeline, but didn't the MR suggest that
those people were not better off?
It's a nature paper and we'll pull it.
CETP and the investigation of these drugs were long before the Mendelian randomization.
Absolutely, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So they didn't have that data that Mendelian randomization shows not necessarily so that
with high HDL cholesterol you're protected, whereas nowadays most of that data would show
it's not.
Yeah, yeah.
My recollection is that the MR came out in 2010-2011 and it basically validated what
had at the time been seen in two trials, which was, wow, inhibit CETEP, things don't get
better.
Well, yeah.
So I think Mendelian randomization, had they had that data first, they would have never
investigated these drugs, which is why they did chase PCSK9 inhibitors because the genetic
model told them this can't fail unless there's a downside to the drug that we don't know
about.
That's always a problem with a drug that's going to change a gene.
It may do good to a marker and do bad to some other marker you're not smart enough to know
about yet.
Oh, I can't wait until we're going to talk about PCSK9.
So let's inhibit CETP, the HDLs get to keep all their cholesterol, HDL cholesterol straight
on the roof.
That's good, epidemiologically, right?
Except on first principles, it doesn't even make sense in light of what you just told
us.
No, but they didn't know that then either.
Remember, this whole HDL story has evolved too.
Oh, wait.
So that's interesting.
I don't think I understood that.
And so I should give them more credit.
Are you saying that it absolutely was not known?
No, there was theories on it.
Guys like Dan Rader was always talking about it, but you don't know how much you're interrupting
the system with that and everything.
You know, they're so heavily focused on basic lipid biomarkers like LDL cholesterol and
HDL cholesterol.
And HDL, HDL, good.
And it's the same denisin story.
How could it not work?
It raises HDL cholesterol and turns out nisin doesn't work if you want to take legitimate
trials to show it works.
And is there a price for using niacin even if you don't believe the legitimate trials?
So that's another story which we'll probably get into.
We will definitely get into that because this is one area where your peers will argue with
you.
But many will not.
Other than all rights, I've tried everything else.
Nothing else has worked.
Let me, and look, I'm a guy who took niacin myself for a bunch of years.
So before I knew what I knew now, and it didn't unfortunately work for me anyway.
So this CETP, it's going to raise HDL cholesterol.
But how much it raises, it really depends on the potency of the CETP inhibitor.
And there are different degrees of CETP inhibition.
We have weak inhibitors and we have super strong inhibitors.
The first one that came out, Pfizer had developed a drug that inhibited, thought it was going
to be a multi-billion dollar drug because it raised HDL cholesterol.
Pfizer and many other companies already proved lowering APL, LDL cholesterol works.
It really works well.
Imagine if we can take those people with residual risk because their HDL cholesterol is still
low and we could raise their HDL cholesterol.
That niacin angiographic trial would really support doing that.
Okay.
So they said, let's inhibit CETP and raise HDL cholesterol.
So Pfizer went to market.
Many people were buying that stock in its infancy, thought they'd make a zillion dollars.
I remember where I was standing the moment those results were announced.
And it's interesting because I was not at all a lipid guy, but at the time I was working
at McKinsey, I was in San Francisco.
It was on a September day, a beautiful September day in San Francisco, 2006.
I took it as a fait accompli that this drug would work and Pfizer stock was going to skyrocket.
Look, we all knew the company of Sperion who developed that.
We knew their guys.
We had heard them lecture many times.
Many the top.
Everybody was banking on that.
Boy, this is real.
I mean, you never know in a clinical trial, but it looked like a slam dunk.
It really did.
And I remember whenever I found out, I forget the weather that day, but it was late at night.
And I think the internet was even.
And I saw a little thing and was like eleven thirty at night.
I don't even know why I saw it.
That Pfizer terminates Torcetropib trial.
Well, in fairness, you were actually seeing it in real time.
I saw it the next morning.
Right.
So and look, there was no Twitter and I could call up every lipidologist.
I know I emailed a few close buddies.
Look at what I just saw.
And so they stopped the trial, not because it was harming people.
And as it turns out, it looks like that drug had some other properties that screwed up
certain electrolytes and other hormonal levels that, OK, no wonder.
So we raising H.L. cholesterol, if it's going to bring a downside to the table, goodbye.
So Pfizer lost a lot of money in that.
But that didn't stop research on the drug.
As they developed these other toxicities that maybe were specifically related to that CTEP
inhibitor, let's develop better CTEPs inhibitors and go with them.
So they did.
They came up with a very weak one called Dalcetropib.
Who made that?
It wasn't Merck because Merck is the third one.
So there's someone in between.
I keep forgetting.
Yeah.
Anyway, OK, so we can figure that out.
I was confused all these things.
I was certainly a bit consulting with them back to and then two other companies.
Again, it was Merck and Lilly had super potent CTP inhibitors, but they did all the tests
and it didn't have this other toxicity with electrolytes and renin-angiotensin levels
and things like that.
So maybe this would work.
And of course, the stronger your CTEP inhibition, the more you would raise HDL cholesterol.
So Dalcetropib raised it 20 to 30 percent, whereas the stronger ones raised it 80, 100
percent HDL cholesterol.
So the Dalcetropib, they enrolled in acute coronary syndrome, a humongous population,
and were doing a randomized trial.
And after a few years, they didn't see any downside.
They weren't telling anybody or.
There was no superiority, no inferiority.
Those are very expensive trials.
So the bean counters said, it's a futile trial.
Forget about it.
So Dalcetropib.
I think that those trials combined with the MR have put an end to this approach to lipid
modulation.
They did.
And the two other companies, though, said, well, it's a weak CTEP inhibitor.
We're potent.
So we're going to continue.
Our trials are well on their way, too.
So with anacetropib and evacetropib, the remaining things, they did them.
And sooner or later, Lilly just bailed on their trial.
More futility.
They weren't going to take it up.
Merck continued their trial.
So Lilly, with a potent evacetropib, was seeing not only drastic raisings in HDL cholesterol
but LDL cholesterol.
But PCSK9 inhibitors are starting to appear.
But nobody's going to ever prescribe this drug based on what it does to LDL cholesterol.
And we're not so convinced that raising HDL cholesterol matters anymore.
And they're really thinking with some futility.
So they bailed on their trial, too.
People think they should have.
Some people wish they would have continued that trial.
But Merck did continue.
And Merck did hit its endpoint.
It did reduce coronary events.
It did drastically raise HDL cholesterol.
But it dramatically lowered APOB also.
So the theory came to be what a CTEP inhibitor does to the metric HDL cholesterol has nothing
to do with anything.
But if it can lower APOB, it works.
And the trial was, it worked.
But they're not going to bring it to market because it stays in the human body for years.
And they just are afraid of that.
They have no idea what might show up before.
Well, especially when there's no upside relative to what you can do anyway.
So we got other things that will give you that type of APOB lowering that seem to be
safe and been around.
So Merck is not going to commercialize that product, even though it has a successful trial.
So if you want to definitively say CTEP inhibition doesn't reduce atherosclerosis, well, it did.
But at what price and at what benefit?
And we just can do it with some other LDL lowering things coming to the market.
It still seems too crude, is the point.
It's not entirely clear why one of those drugs is working and why one is not.
Because the inhibition of CTEP is, it's interrupting a transfer, but it doesn't actually tell you
what happens after the transfer.
And that becomes the problem.
No, it doesn't tell you.
I know some of the primitive HDL function studies they did on it didn't look like they
were screwing up the HDL, but there's immense numbers of HDL function.
You don't know what you're doing.
And if that protein is going to stay in your body forever, what other consequences might
there be long term screwing up of other biological systems or something?
So it couldn't risk that.
Yeah.
Well, kudos to Merck because I think the FDA would have approved it, don't you?
Not with the tissue residual.
So you think the FDA would have denied it based on the...
They had that fear.
And even if they thought they could get it by, their lawyers probably told them...
Well Merck, it's funny, a lot of people don't remember what happened to Merck with the Vioxx.
Sure.
The failure of the black box warning.
And actually, I got to tell you that, that to me is one example of an overreaction too
late versus an appropriate reaction sooner.
So not that I'm a pharma guy and know much about pharma, but Vioxx was an amazing drug.
I mean, 10 times better than the Celebrex ever was.
For the listener who's wondering what we're talking about, Celebrex and Vioxx were the
first two versions of these things called selective COX-2 inhibitors, which were potent
and much more selective anti-inflammatory drugs.
So for people with orthopedic issues, joint pains, things like that, but they don't have
some of the drawbacks you have with using just non-selective inhibitors of cyclooxygenase
such as Advil or Aleve or things like that.
Anyway, to make a long story short, it was about 2001 when they saw a small subset of
patients and turned out those, I think that were hypertensive were having a higher risk
of MI taking Vioxx.
The drug got immediately yanked.
I think it was the best anti-inflammatory COX inhibitor ever out there.
And in reality, I think what emerged after the fact was, hey, the guys at Merck sort
of knew this earlier on.
There was data that suggested there was something going on and instead they should have partitioned
it and said, hey, maybe there's a subset of patients in whom we don't let this drug be
taken because I think a lot of patients got deprived of an amazing drug on the basis of
a few.
So anyway, my guess is Merck's highly sensitive to that stuff.
Sure.
In today's medical legal world, that stuff comes back to haunt those companies.
One person goes south and it's a zillion dollar lawsuit, so it is very, very tough.
And look, it goes back to my young days where we couldn't do anything for MI but suppress
ventricular arrhythmias with any number of grave and all we did was kill people.
Yeah, those things were the most toxic drugs imaginable.
But the VPCs disappeared.
And so today, you got to be careful.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast.
There you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode.
You can also find my blog and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com.
That's a nerd safari you ask.
Just click on the link at the top of the site to learn more.
Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my subjectively non-lame once a week
email where I'll update you on what I've been up to, the most interesting papers I've
read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance, sleep, etc.
On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD.
But usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare
services, including the giving of medical advice.
And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own
risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical
advice, diagnoses, or treatment.
Patients should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice for any medical condition
they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such
conditions.
Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest very seriously.
For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash about.