Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Celia. Thanks for making time on a Friday evening to sit down and talk about ketamine
and perhaps a few other things, but great to meet you.
You too. Thanks. It's my pleasure.
Let's talk a little bit about your background because I know that you ... I think you finished
your graduate training in the UK, but then you did a stint here in the US at Yale, if
I'm not mistaken, correct?
Yeah. I did my undergraduate in psychology with pharmacology and astrophysics for a bit,
but then I went ... I did a PhD program at University College London, but as part of
that I spent some time at Yale and I'd got a scholarship to do a little bit of research
out there in the US.
What did you focus on during your PhD?
My PhD was largely focused on the effects of ketamine. Back then, that makes me feel
quite old, but nearly 20 years ago we were looking ... both had the acute effects of
ketamine as a model of psychosis. At the time people were using ketamine with the idea that
would help us understand the neurobiological underpinnings of psychosis because actually
from the outside ketamine looks quite a little bit similar to people who are psychotic.
We were using that to map the cognitive processes altered by ketamine, but I was also simultaneously
looking at people who take ketamine recreationally because at the time that was quite a big problem
in the UK. Yeah, I had this dual focus. When I went to the US it was to work on, again,
neuroimaging studies looking at ketamine as a model for psychosis. It was before it
really became established as an antidepressant.
Let's talk a little bit about the history of ketamine. It was synthesized in the 60s,
I believe, correct?
Yeah. It was synthesized as an anesthetic by Parker Davies who ... it was synthesized
as a replacement for PCP or Fence-like LeDine because obviously people know PCP as Angel
Dust and this is folklore around it of people running at the police and being shot down
and keeping running. Really, the problems with it had this protracted psychosis-like
effects that lasted for a really long time following anesthesia. It was still a good
analgesic anesthetic. It synthesized ketamine as a similar molecule. It still worked on
the same receptor in the brain, the NMDA receptor, but it was 10 times less potent. It was synthesized
back in the 60s. The drug company that synthesized it were initially really impressed by its
analgesic and anesthetic effects. Then with increasing clinical experience, it was noticed
that people were coming around from ketamine anesthesia reporting a variety of quite weird
effects, say things like hallucinations and out-of-body experiences. That's what's really
limited its routine clinical use, but it's still one of the most widely used anesthetics
in the world today. It's on the World Health Organization list of essential medicines.
Yeah, I mean, one of the things that I remember from my clinical training was that one of
the perks of ketamine was that you didn't have the respiratory depression. Most things
that we use as anesthetic agents have this problem where if you overshoot them, and that's
not an issue if you're doing general anesthesia because you have an endotracheal tube in the
bronchus and the main stem bronchus, so you're breathing for the patient. When you start to
think about conscious sedation, respiratory depression starts to become a very frightening
consequence that must be managed closely. With ketamine, you didn't have that. Now,
is my memory correct that kids were less susceptible to the hallucinogenic effects?
I literally, this is because I didn't do much in pediatrics, but I can't recall if there was more
flexibility in using it with kids or am I making that up?
No, I think, I mean, it is used more with children. I don't know. That's the thing. We
tried to do a study actually, which never really came off, but I don't know if it's that people
haven't asked kids if they're hallucinating or maybe they're just more open.
It seems less foreign to them if they are.
Yeah, exactly. They're tripping all the time, but no, maybe not that. But they're more open to
changes in consciousness. So yeah, I think they certainly seem to, I mean, it's used
routinely. I'm really interested and I don't think anyone's really actually asked children
about their experiences. But yeah, it's definitely, I think it's used because it's so safe. So
in pediatrics and geriatrics, also in battlefield medicine, it was the most widely used anesthetic
in the Vietnam War, for instance. So it's used, yeah, as you said, it's really safe
physiologically as an anesthetic because it doesn't slow your breathing or your heart rate.
So when you've lost a lot of blood, it's good as well because it actually even vaguely increases
your blood pressure. So yeah, I think that's why it's a widely used anesthetic. It's a really good
question about kids though. And I don't think, I mean, I know there's some people trialing,
get them in, in its antidepressant use now with adolescents. So I'm sure we'll come on to that later.
Yeah. And I'm glad you made that other point, by the way, it doesn't lower blood pressure. So now
you talk about it being the perfect anesthetic in trauma and shock where those patients are
hypovolemic, their blood pressure is already going down. You give them an agent that if anything
slightly acts like a vasopressor raises blood pressure without the respiratory depression. I
mean, in that setting, you can understand why it sort of became, you know, a turning point in the
field medicine in Vietnam. Yeah, absolutely. I mean, the acute experience must be really unusual
when you're in that setting, but I guess the dissociation. So like, I think there's an interesting
study about looking at the interaction between those acute subjective effects when you're on a
battlefield. But I mean, yeah, also, as you mentioned, not having to intubate people, that's
why it's really popular in developing countries, where you've got limited access, you know, to,
or ability to intubate patients, you know, so it's a really important medicine, you know,
anesthesia still. And I think that's something people forget with all the new developments with
the use of ketamine. Yeah, it's really interesting when you go and imagine what surgery was like
before ether. And, you know, I mean, when you, I mean, that's just ridiculous. And to think that
anesthesia is something we've only had for about 140 years. Yeah, it's a pretty crazy thing to
imagine. That fascinating, that fascinating concept anyway, like when you lose consciousness
and how you measure that, you know, there's different things on it. And you could just use
there's an index, which will realize on some EEG to look at how your consciousness drops. But I
still don't think we really know, you know, what turns it on and off. But yeah, that's probably
another podcast. So you mentioned that ketamine is kind of an analog, is it safe to say it's an
analog of PCP? Yeah, so they're all under the class of arrow cyclohexamines. And so I think
Edward Domino coined the term dissociative anesthetics to describe PCP and ketamine. And
also people include nitrous oxide in that category, laterally, so I think based on the fact that they
kind of dissociate you from your body and are characterized by these out of body experiences.
Which can be quite helpful again, I think in anesthetic use. Yeah, so they are related compounds
with similar their main action is on the NMDA receptor. So let's talk a little bit about that.
Let's assume that folks don't know what the NMDA receptor is. They don't know what glutamate is.
They don't know GAP. Like, let's just assume people are coming at this from a standpoint of not being
completely up to speed on excitatory or inhibitory neurotransmitters. Explain in some detail
exactly how these neurotransmitters work and how other neurons can amplify or attenuate
the response of those and where ketamine fits into that. Sure. So I guess, well, do you jump in as
well if I'm either going too slowly or too quickly. But yeah, so glutamate is the major excitatory
neurotransmitter in the brain and it's prevalent all across the brain. And one of the receptors
that glutamate works out is the NMDA receptor and the NMDA receptor, the N-methyl-despartate receptor,
which are really important in a lot of our higher cognitive functions. So it's the kind of the
fundaments of learning and memory, particularly a process in learning called long-term potentiation,
which is where neurons that or brain cells that activate at the same time are more like then if
they both activate, then they're more likely to activate in future. So it's characterized by this
term that someone said neurons that fire together, wire together. And glutamate is really important
in that and other excitatory functions in the brain. And GABA is an inhibitory neurotransmitters
so it shuts down the flow of electric impulses across the brain. What ketamine does is.
And before we do that, so just to give some people some examples, right. So
glutamate is excitatory, GABA is inhibitory. We can give people a sense of like alcohol.
You and I were talking before we started about, you know, GABA analogs that are meant to mimic
alcohol. I mean, what are they doing? Why do people feel relaxed when they drink? It's the
GABA potentiation. When you look at things like benzodiazepines, they're working at GABA.
Right. Yeah. So yeah. Yeah. Okay. So, so, and then are there things that we can examples we can give
people that work at glutamate that are amplifying glutamate? We tend to focus more on the opposite,
right? Yeah. So like the mocha genes, the drugs used in seizures tend to reduce the flow of
glutamate in the brain, particularly in the prefrontal cortex. I'm trying to think of examples.
So good question, Peter. Do you know of any? No, I can't think of anything off my head that
would do that. Because again, we normally are thinking of the opposite side of that.
So alcohol increases GABA in the brain and that has the effect of kind of
dumping down your brain activity and reducing things like anxiety and slowing your motor
function and generally inhibiting the flow of electrical impulses across your brain.
And then it's part of the reason why we get the symptoms you get when you stop drinking,
your brain kind of goes into a more hyper. It's like a see-saw, I guess. So the alcohol is being
pushing down on that side and keeping it dampened down. And then you release that and you go into
kind of a more excitatory state. And so you get things like, and, you know, I work a lot with
alcoholics, things from alcohol withdrawals, you can get seizures and the shakes and that's all
down to this kind of increase in excitation. So that's why withdrawal from strong GABA
promoters like benzos and ethanol can be fatal if not managed directly. You can't, you know,
it's sort of funny. I think people intuitively sort of know this, right? Like you can stop
opioids immediately and it might be the most painful thing in the world, but it won't be fatal.
Whereas if you take a person who's on a high dose of benzodiazepines or a person who drinks
a lot of alcohol and you stop that abruptly, it actually can be fatal.
And they are the drugs you can die from withdrawal in because of these huge, then increase in
excitation. Cause they get a bit of, you know, repeated alcohol. Your brain gets used to having
all this GABA on boards and then you get adaptation and your brain kind of regulates
to counteract that. And then when you remove it, yeah, you can die from withdrawal. So the people
I work with, you know, severe alcoholics, it's unsafe for them to stop straight away. So they
have to cut down and use things like benzodiazepines and withdrawals. So yeah, it's something that I
think people do think about opiate withdrawal potentially as a really difficult thing. But as
you say, you wouldn't die from that. It's only from withdrawal from these inhibitory substances
like alcohol and benzodiazepines. So, so, so then, so, so, okay. So we have excitatory and
inhibitory neurons and the inhibitory neurons, are they the ones where you have like an NMDA receptor
that is sort of globbed on to say a glutamate receptor? Yeah. That's, that's one of the theories
of how ketamine works basically. Well, we were just talking about the neurons.
But you're right. Yes. I'm going exactly to now like different ideas. Cause I think
it's not a hundred percent clear exactly how ketamine works, correct?
No, no. And so there's a couple of theories that either ketamine blocks directly, the NMDA receptors
on the glutamate, surging neurons. And then this triggers a kind of downstream cascade or I mean,
there's some evidence and maybe it's a combination of the two. And this was, you know, is that the
ketamine blocks NMDA receptors on these, they're called gabber, jacinta neurons. So they're,
who are gabber receptor neurons that synapse onto your glutamate ones. So they,
they put the brakes on your excitation. So they, they, so if you block an NMDA receptor and a
GABA, urging into neuron, then you're going to have a net effect of increasing glutamate flow
in your presynaptic cells. So they're presynaptic. So yeah, it's not quite clear and it probably is
a combination of the two. It's, I think increasingly people have become interested
in the downstream mechanisms really, and potentially in the therapeutic effects of
ketamine, but I expect we'll get to that later. Yeah. So, so again, ketamine is one of these
drugs where the dose kind of makes the poison. I mean, I think that's true of most drugs, but
it really has different effects on an individual based on how much they're getting, right? And,
you know, anything from kind of like mild hypnosis to some dissociation to complete,
you know, complete anesthesia. Yeah, absolutely. No, and low doses as well. People, you know,
I worked quite a lot with people who take ketamine non-medically or recreationally and they,
low doses, it's got kind of stimulant properties. And then as the dose increases, you get kind of
just perceptual distortions and illusions and kind of a mild melting. People talk about floating
higher doses. Still you get kind of much more profound, maybe not hallucination, but changes
in the perception of reality and the highest dose you're completely sort of catatonic,
but people are experiencing inside these really, really profound hallucinations. And that's, I
mean, it's, there's really high doses from my work with, you know, non-medical ketamine users that
were actually really dangerous. A couple of people died from taking ketamine, you know,
and then having a bath and they're completely dissociated from reality and they drowned. And
it's like the saddest thing. And it makes you, I think as a user, the ketamine users are very
vulnerable to accidents at these higher doses because you are not completely dissociated from
reality really. Wow. So that's sort of like LSD in the sense where it really has no LD50, meaning
you can't, there's no amount of LSD that you're going to take that is going to create some
physiologic process that kills you the way, for example, Tylenol, acetaminophen, you know,
would, you know, poison your liver at a certain dose. But it's not to say that LSD is completely
safe because you can alter your behavior in a way that is so altered from reality that you put
yourself in harm's way. And you're saying basically, is that the same with ketamine? That if you look
at it from a purely pharmacology standpoint, there's no LD50, given that it doesn't have
respiratory depression and all these other things that we worry about, or how do you think about
that? Yeah, no. I mean, I think there's very few, yeah, it's much the cases I'm not aware of anyone
are getting to like a toxic dose of ketamine. And there are problems with, you know, repeatedly
taking high doses of ketamine, and which have been uncovered in work with abusers, but yeah,
and physiological problems, that ketamine has a direct toxicity on the epithelial, so like the
lining of your bladder, which is really interesting as something that only emerged really with people
using really high doses. But yeah, there's no LD50, like you say, I think it's more how, and much
more so probably even than LSD, where a lot more of your kind of top down higher cognitive functions
are preserved with ketamine, they're not, and you are completely, you know, catatonic, people will
be kind of collapsed anesthetized really in a cataleptic state, so much more vulnerable to
accidents and yeah, through that. The drowning in a bathtub example, that seems tragic, and to
imagine how dissociated you would have to be to slip into a bathtub, inhale water, and not respond.
Yeah, exactly. You are completely dissociated, and it's really sad, it's someone that I was
working with, and that is not the only example I know of a few case studies or examples of people
who that's happened to, various different accidents. So yes, it's really tragic, as you say.
While we're on the pharmacology, let's talk about the different routes of administration. I assume
that most of the time when it's used medically, it's intravenous?
Yeah, that's most of the studies, certainly in the depression field, and when it's used in
anesthesia, I think people would give it intravenously. It's the best availability
in the most well-characterized route, but yeah, or out, as you say in American.
But there are other ways of administering it, which I think have been increasingly used.
Intramuscular has got quite good availability in the blood, and then there's people starting to
use things like sublingual administrations, they're putting under the tongue. Intranasal,
obviously, is the route popularized by first the drug users themselves, but then patented by
the pharmaceutical company, Janssen, have now used that for their licensed form of ketamine
and depression. Yeah, and those are the main ones, and oral dosing, although that's not as
great in terms of bioavailability, it's obviously an easy way to get a drug over and across into
the system. But yeah, you're right. I think- And there's no liver toxicity with, I know you're
going to have a bad first pass effect, which is why you prefer to put it under your tongue as
opposed to swallow it, but there's no toxicity. It just means you need a higher dose if you're
going to take it orally, presumably. Yeah, I think, I mean, it's not that well
characterized, I don't know whether. I assume people are doing detoxicity studies at the moment,
because I know there's some pharmaceutical companies looking at oral dosing as a potential.
But I think for the purpose of our discussion, we're really thinking about what has been learned
through intravenous and intramuscular and perhaps most recently intranasal.
Yeah, and that's where I made the bulk of the research, is for sure.
Okay. So in the 1970s, when this drug was being used pretty liberally as an anesthetic,
was it unscheduled in the United States? I know now it's a schedule three, so it's a
much more regulated compound. But is that- Yeah, I think it only came, when was it in the US,
I think maybe 1996? Yeah, I think it was the late 90s.
It was relatively recent. Yeah, late 90s. 2003, Putin banned it in Russia.
Just banned it altogether. Yeah, even for using humans. And quite an interesting story,
Bridget Bardot, obviously the very attractive French actress, petitioned him to use it in
animals, because it's obviously widely used in veterinary anesthesia. So he removed the
ban for animals, but kept the ban in place for humans, which is pretty horrendous,
considering what an amazing anesthetic is. In the UK, it became, it was 2006. So yeah.
In the UK, it mirrors basically the US regulation around our equivalent of C3.
Yeah, ours is class B, ketamine. So yeah, it's under the misuse of drugs scheduling,
but it's obviously what we could, we scheduled two drugs they use for medical use. But
unlike, I mean, maybe it's something we'll get into, whether you consider ketamine to be a
psychedelic drug, but there's not any other drugs with these kind of type of effects that can be
used medically that are legal. That's right. So in the United States, the other psychedelics,
LSD, psilocybin, and even MDMA, which is not a psychedelic or schedule one, which means
they are not even used, they have no medical use at all. Yeah. And that's, I mean, it's interesting
drug policy wise, right? Because ketamine is the most likely to be abused, I would say, of all of
those compounds. But it's the one that's, you know, legal for medical use. I mean, it has,
as we've said, got an amazing number of medical use ends, but you don't consider MDMA psychedelic.
I mean, I don't think I'm an expert to say, but no, I don't consider MDMA a psychedelic personally.
I sort of put it in the category of an empathogen and, because you don't really have any dissociation
with it, right? You know, it's not altering perception in the way that LSD or psilocybin
would. And your point is an interesting one, right? Which is, you know, schedule one typically
implies no medical use, high potential for addiction. Well, certainly, I think there's
medical use for psilocybin and MDMA, as you said, pretty low potential for abuse. And interestingly,
while ketamine clearly has a high medical use, I want to talk to you about the potential for abuse
as well. I've heard mixed things on this, but what are the data say? How addictive is ketamine
in terms of other things for which we have benchmarks, like, for example, benzodiazepines
and opioids, where we really have a clear sense of the addictive potential of those molecules.
Where does ketamine stack up? Well, I don't know if we have really good data on that,
but I would say, I mean, in terms of physical withdrawals symptoms, I mean, it turns out you
assess the addictive properties, right? So there's the initial high, there's, yeah, and how you
really categorize that. Because I guess I would say, I struggle with things being addictive,
people become addicted to things, but they're also, you know, multifunctional. Coffee's addictive or
whatever. Yeah. But I would say, I mean, we did a study of people that use ketamine, so they're
probably at higher potential for abuse. I've found, I say people who use ketamine non-medically,
it's as in what you would say, recreationally. I think about 9% of them had symptoms of some
sort of dependence or craving. 9%. 9% of a group of like recreational users of drugs. So I'm finding
that hard to benchmark that against opioids and benzase. I mean, that's, that actually is a bit
lower. So I'll tell you, I mean, the last time I looked at the opioid data and someone listening
to this will probably say, no, that's wrong because I'm going by memory. My memory was about 20%
of opioid users became addicted, but that was prescription based opioid painkillers, right?
That doesn't include heroin where that number might be higher. But of course, you're also pre-selecting
a different subgroup of the population. So it's not really an apples to apples comparison. In other
words, what I'm saying is of 20% of patients who would be prescribed opioids for medical use,
could become addicted, which is a staggering number, right? One in five people who gets an
opioid prescription could go on to abuse them later. So I don't know how much faith to put
in that number because it seems so absurdly high, but it's plausible. And I guess, so the only way
we would really know this, I suppose on an apples to apples basis is you took patients who were
being treated with ketamine for another indication, such as recalcitrant depression. And you ask the
question, how many of those patients would go on to experience dependency, pharmacologic, physiologic
dependency? Yeah, yeah. And that we know is, I mean, so far the data suggests is pretty low,
like what's not really seen at all. So we know that a little bit from the trials that have gone
on so far, but it's a really early stage. And I guess if you're doing apples to apples, opioids
is that daily, like, or benzos, I don't know, like frequency, obviously how you're defining addiction
is quite hard because if it's physical withdrawal symptoms, or is it impacting on your everyday
functioning, or is it seeking beyond your prescription, day, sesculation? Yes, it's
a tricky one. I mean, I know from having worked with ketamine, people who are addicted to ketamine,
that's a small proportion of people do become addicted. And for those, you know, as we mentioned,
it has these really serious physical consequences of having toxicity on your bladder. You know,
I was working with people, 16 year old girls who've had their bladders have to have a
cystectomy. So you have your bladder removed, and then they're, you know, having to wear a
colostomy bag, really dire consequences. And I think that's quite rare. I was thinking about
other drugs that have got like a direct physiological. So just to make sure I understand,
so these are 16 year old girls that were not using ketamine for medical indications, such as
depression, they became addicted to it recreationally. Yeah. And this was kind of an
epidemic in the UK in the 90s, early 2000s, when we were researching it, because people didn't really
know anything about ketamine. So the nickname was, I mean, I was in medical school in the 90s,
and we learned about it as Special K, right? That's what it was referred to. So now that,
I don't know if that was the San Francisco name, because that's sort of where I was going to school.
And I don't know if it was it called Special K in the UK also? Yeah, I think people called it that.
Some people, you know, it was very, so these people that I was working with were very constrained
subcultures. So we have kind of these travelers, they're like people who live itinerant lives.
I don't know if you have something equivalent in the US. So it was amongst those groups. Some of
them called it kiddie smack, basically saying it's like an addictive drug. It was basically like heroin
for kids. I see. So it's kind of the JV or junior version of heroin, not quite as bad. Yeah. For
those people, but there was zero information about it at the time. And they were not taking
the drug the way it's given, you know, for depression. They were taking grams and grams
of it every day. So these serious, something important to say. And what would they experience?
I mean, grams of this, I will come back and do the math on what that means. But if they're taking
high doses of this stuff daily, were they taking it and then basically passing out in their
apartments for hours and just associating on trips? And no, I mean, they would be a dose that
would render someone completely catatonic or septic, which they would just tolerate it.
Because it is the tachyflaxes, it's like a rapidly developing tolerance. And if you do administer
ketamine repeatedly in a short time window, you do need to give higher and higher doses.
I think that's what we felt like with these people, they were going, they were functioning, you know,
walking around on doses that yeah, would floor an elephant or certainly a horse. So yeah,
it's pretty, it's pretty extraordinary. And I think, I do feel, yeah.
So with opioids, we kind of have a sense of what that high is that the person using it is
experiencing, right? The mu receptor, when it is, you know, agonized, it produces a very deep high.
What is the feeling that that person is getting from those escalating doses of ketamine, even
once they're tachyflactic? What do they say that they're experiencing that is bringing them back to
it? Yeah, it's a really good question. I think it's not one thing. We actually did some research on
this. I think we spoke to about 120 ketamine users doing some interviews of why they took it.
And some of them did. So some of them said very pragmatic things, I think, because it's very cheap.
So things like it's cheap, it gets me really off my head. I think at the escapism of it, you know,
but there is, I mean, there's some mu receptor, there's some slight opioid actions of ketamine,
maybe come on to that, talking about the different isomers of ketamine. But yeah,
so some people are taking it just for the escapism. Some people talk more as we'd see them kind of
psychonauts, but almost addicted to chasing the consciousness and the insights they felt they were
getting. And they were just taking more and more to try and get more insights. I mean, there's some
really high profile examples of that. I don't know if you've heard of John Lilly, who was the
kind of neuroscientist based in California. And the film Altered States is about him. And he
did quite a lot of unusual research, you know, giving out acetidolphins. He invented flotation
tanks, I think. And he writes in his book, The Scientist, clearly documents becoming completely
addicted to ketamine, to the extent that he was having an intravenous drip of ketamine, you know,
pretty much 24 hours a day. So he really heavily escalated his days and became kind of psychotic,
I think. And we had these revelations and went to tell the president of the, the president of the USA,
about the world being taken over by computers. But yeah, so I mean, it's a really fascinating
book if you're interested in reading an account of ketamine addiction.
And how did that story end for him? What is the?
Well, I think he managed, did he manage to get off of ketamine in the end? I'm trying to remember
this. It's a really good question. I can't remember the end of it. I know there's some sad ends. There
was another book called Journey to the Bright World by someone called Marsha Moore. I think
she was an heiress to some, her husband, some kind of fortune. And her husband was an anesthetist and
she experimented with ketamine. So actually quite interesting. They are very different
subjective experiences. They're generally these ones, very machine state, and he's experiencing
these nations very related to being in a computer and hers were very soft and round and going back
to the earth. But she sadly, I think, froze to death. She took some ketamine outside. And again,
that thing where you are completely dissociated in your, yeah, from your body. And she'd gone
outside one evening and actually froze to death. That's really sad. I mean, they were people taking
really high intravenous doses of ketamine. But yes, it's got a rapidly developing tolerance.
And why is it different? So PCP, I'm trying to think, I don't really think I took care of any
patients that were strung out on PCP, but I certainly remember the lore of the drug. And it
struck me as a much more aggressive drug. People that were on PCP, as you alluded to earlier,
they seemed almost bulletproof, right? They'd punch their hand through a glass window,
be unfazed by the fact that they just broke every bone in their hand.
Given that these drugs have such a similarity, why did PCP seem to produce that phenotype? Or
is that just lore and that really wasn't what was happening? Yeah, I think that's lore. I mean,
I think it produced a protracted psychotic state, but some people have likened it. I think they
gave the police nets even to catch people on PCP. There was a lot of kind of police brutality,
these special PCP nets, police brutality associated with PCP and maybe the people taking PCP. Some
people have suggested kind of a degree of racism or against kind of people in poverty. So yeah,
I don't, I've been looked for examples of this kind of bulletproof phenomena and I can't find any
in the literature, certainly. There's definitely examples of people having a protracted sort of
psychotic like symptoms, having hallucinations, having to be hospitalized, but this whole running
up piece and the kind of violence aspect, I find hard to imagine. And is PCP still being used? Is
it still a street drug? It's certainly not, it's never really been a street drug in the UK. I'm
not aware there's many reports in the US either. So it's interesting. And it's interesting in the
context of the new use of all these substances. Nobody's really thinking about using PCP, but
maybe that would be something to investigate. So speaking of kind of the resurgence of these
drugs, how would you contrast ketamine with psilocybin and LSD? So psilocybin and LSD of course
are much more similar to each other. How does ketamine differ? I mean, obviously it differs in
use case, but do you have other senses of how it produces a different experience? Yeah. I mean,
obviously it has to come to a different action where they work on the 5-HT2A receptor and
ketamine, as we were talking about, works on these kinds of glutamatergic receptors. And there
are some similarities in the acute experience, which is one of kind of people talk about EO
dissolution and ketamine causes that quite profoundly. So you lose your sense of self.
And that happens to a degree as well on psilocybin, psilocybin mushrooms and LSD. I think you get
much that you can think more clearly on LSD and psilocybin. Ketamine
impairs some of your higher cognitive functions and causes that kind of analgesia, which is
associated with ketamine's got an anxiolytic effect. So even at higher doses, people don't
report anxiety. Whereas, I mean, they can describe things, so some of our patients describe things
that sound scary, but they don't feel the kind of physiological anxiety. Whereas, you know,
drugs like LSD, psilocybin, people can report being absolutely terrified by the experience.
And I think maybe that's the dissociation that happens more on drugs like ketamine,
where you really have the sense of being separate and everything's kind of emotionally
numb, as I guess you'd think with it being an analgesic or an anesthetic.
And that might be due to the greater inhibitory effect potentially of ketamine is probably why
you maybe can short circuit some of the anxiety that can definitely happen with LSD and psilocybin
if the setting is a brighter, if the dose is too high.
Yeah. And so that, I mean, it's, and that's probably when you're, we were talking before
about the, you know, the P's potential, maybe why it's got higher B's potential because.
That's right. It has less of a negative feedback loop. I think anybody who's tried the other
psychedelics will say, look, if you go back to the well too many times, you can get stung.
Yeah, yeah, exactly. It's unpredictable in that sense. Whereas, ketamine, and that,
if you're looking for kind of escapism, you don't want to escape into absolute terror.
Well, so, all right. So let's, let's talk about depression because I think this is where
people are really becoming interested in ketamine. It's certainly how it came to my attention,
seven, eight, maybe nine years ago was, God, I'm trying to think how it was, it was a physician,
friend of mine saying, Hey, I, you know, he was saying he's been prescribing intranasal ketamine
to some of his patients for depression. And I thought, none of this makes sense. Please say
more. And he said, yeah, no, this is, it's perfectly legal. We, you know, I have a compounding
pharmacy and these are the instructions that we give the pharmacy and they give him an intro,
you know, they give the patient an intranasal spray and they use this spray. I forget the
frequency with which it was like one, they were doing it once a week or something was the,
the use case. And at the time, again, this is maybe 10 years ago, I couldn't find a lot of
literature on it. And, and, you know, I found some, and I found some interesting case reports and I
found, I remember there was one study I found based in India that looked pretty interesting.
But then I sort of forgot about it until maybe four years ago. And, and I think what brought it
back to my attention was frankly the epidemic for lack of a better word of ketamine clinics,
which, which, you know, basically are almost as ubiquitous as Starbucks now. So before we get
into kind of the business of ketamine clinics, I want to just kind of understand where the,
where the idea came from. How was this something that people even thought was, you know,
worth pursuing clinically? And then how does it work? Who does it work in? Who does it not work in?
You know, let's just go down the depression rabbit hole. Sure. Yeah. I mean, that's quite
where it came from is probably either was an early early study in Iran, I think. I mean,
it might even date back to some quite dodgy work by Salvador Bocce. I'm not sure if you've heard of
him. Yeah. He was, he was a, I do want, I do want to compliment you on the use of dodgy. That word
cannot ever be overused. So any, anytime you want to just throw in that that's a dodgy scam or
that's just dodgy work, please, please feel free to insert that. Thank you. It's not a very scientific
word, but it belongs here. It belongs here. Okay. Yeah. And he definitely was a dodgy guy.
So there we go. He was a, he was working for the Mexican government actually, I think interrogating
people and he took some of the techniques from that, I think, and tried to, he's a psychoanalyst,
kind of psychotherapeutic practice. And he was giving ketamine with other psychedelics to try
and produce changes in people's brain state. But I guess that's probably the first documented cases
of people using ketamine in a kind of psychiatric therapy sense. And this is what, this is in the
80s or 90s? No, that was back in the 60s. And yeah, so way back, maybe the 70s, there was this
study out of Iran. But really, yeah, the work that's kind of caused this whole explosion in
ketamine depression research, because I don't think anyone was really watching those areas of
research came out of a group at Yale and a guy called Robert Berman, who did an early study in 2000,
giving ketamine, a single ketamine infusion to patients with treatment resistant depression.
And they showed this thing, which was kind of groundbreaking and that's,
was that you could get this rapid reduction in depressive symptoms, not as traditional SSRIs,
you know, your Prozac's and your traditional antidepressant drugs have got a delayed onset
of action. And it was just kind of accepted that they take two weeks to work. And you know,
there's various ideas of why, but this, these ketamine works immediately. And then people with
treatment resistant depression, this is a mild depression. And tell me how it was administered in
those early studies. Was this, it, that was, yeah, sorry. So that was intravenously.
Intravenous. Okay. And what kind of doses were they using?
That was 0.5 milligrams per kilogram. Yeah. So,
okay. So an 80 kilogram person is getting 40 milligrams intravenous.
Over 40 minutes. Yeah.
Over 40 minutes. So not an IV push, but a pretty quick drip.
Yeah. So pretty quick, like mild dissociation, I would say, from my experience of using different
doses and some kind of peripheral subjective changes. So yeah, we've used that dose in acute
studies. And then just for reference, what would a recreational drug user who's not completely
habituated. So they're not way up the tachyflaxis curve. But if, if, if a recreational person went
to their drug dealer and said, I want some ketamine, cause I want to blast off, what dose
would they be given? That's really variable, I'd say, but maybe more on like at least a hundred,
if not 200 milligrams, I would say. Got it. So they're going to be given two and a half to
five times the dose that, and they would blast off with that. They would probably take that.
Yeah. That would be a blast. Yeah.
No, people with intranasal, I think is the typical route for.
Okay. And is the bioavailability similar? I'm sure the onset is different with intranasal versus
intravenous versus intramuscular, but does the same amount of drug basically get to you
with each of those routes? Yeah, slightly less than intravenous, obviously the optimal
rate for that. But yeah, it's pretty good way to get it across, which is why it's now been
taken forward as a treatment and depression, I guess. Okay. So, so the, so going back to this
patient that's getting 40 milligrams. It was a higher dose, I would say.
That's a dose that they know something is happening. They're not getting a placebo,
but it's, they're not being blown out of the water. No. I mean, I think it's really variable
through all my work. I guess I must have given them hundreds of people get them in, in research
studies and it is, the response is really variable and not necessarily predicted. So we wait, adjust
all of our doses. So give me the range. What's the, what's the sort of interquartile range? So
there are, are there some people that literally feel nothing at 0.5 Migs per gig?
I don't know that anyone would feel nothing, but maybe feel more like slightly drunk and feel a
bit disoriented. You know, that kind of feeling like intoxicated basically and slightly dissociated.
And at the other end of the spectrum, are there people that are just tripping?
People who are going, you know, people have gone down a canoe in their mother's eardrum,
like doing really weird stuff, like having fine calisthenations basically, like really extreme
responses. And I think, I mean, we can talk about that in a bit. We've found that a little
about what predicts that I think now. Tell me, yeah, I'm very curious because I just know myself
with any single agent that I've ever ingested in my life, anything that ranges from alcohol to
acetaminophen to, to a psychedelic agent. I'm, I need like three times what anybody else needs
to feel it. And I've always been curious as to why. That's incredibly hard to beat.
Now I think, so the things that we, the things that we found out from our research is that people
with a family history of alcohol problems, would they have a greater acute response to ketamine?
They're more sensitive to it.
Yeah. Well, they have a greater, sorry, they're great to response to the therapeutic effects.
They've actually got less of a response to the acute. Sorry, I said that completely wrong.
And what are the other things BMI, which is kind of obvious, I suppose is so higher BMI
body mass index is, um, predictive of a higher acute effect.
Because they're, but that's because they're getting a higher dose.
Yeah. Well, in a way, but then I guess the BMI is, is slightly different. And I
suppose maybe that's something to consider it similar with alcohol, right? Like your
lean muscle versus your fat.
That's not surprising, right? Because it would, because BMI really speaks to how much lean mass
and non lean mass you have. It doesn't really speak to your organs and it certainly doesn't
speak to your brain.
No, no, it doesn't speak to your brain. So no, these are really obvious things. I mean,
this is why we haven't got very far in predicting how people respond. And therapeutically, we know
with depression, the more suicide attempts, people have a better response. So they're more
likely to respond, which probably maybe means they're more severe, I guess. Um, but yeah,
we know not very much at all. Really. There's some kind of,
But so let me ask another question. Does the acute response that you are watching
during the call it two or three hours that they're in your chair being administered the
drug, right? Cause it's a 40 minute infusion, presumably it's another couple of hours while
they're under the effect of the drug. We call that the acute response. Is that predictive
of what you're really after, which is the, um, the abatement of depression?
Yeah, that's a really good question. I think the field is pretty divided.
So the way that the acute effects have typically been measured is with a scale called the clinician
administered dissociative state scale, which basically looks at dissociation, but it was
designed to look at dissociation from people having flashbacks from traumatic experiences.
And so it asked some questions that are relevant for ketamine, but some
than not. So it's like, are things moving into the emotion? Have colors changed? Um,
do you have a sense of forgetting chunks of what have happened? A lot of it is relevant, but
people have looked at other aspects of the acute experience. So with these dissociative effects,
some studies, I'd say about 25% find they predict, predict the therapeutic effects.
We've actually done a systematic review on this, um, but the others don't. And so I think there's a,
this is maybe, but I think in general psychiatry, there's a feeling that these
acute effects are a nuisance and that we need to find, there's a whole, you know,
research effort has been devoted to finding drugs that don't have these acute effects, um,
with kind of limited success. Um, so I don't know. I think, and actually when you look into the data,
people who use a bit more nuanced ways of looking at the acute effects. So there's some scales that
look at some of the bit more, I guess you'd say trippy effects and things like mystical
experiences in the sense that you can't explain the experience that's gone on. And those do seem
to predict. So it's quite interesting. Wow. First of all, I mean, to just try to unpack that
it's not crystal clear that the person who's sitting there feeling slightly drunk is going
to have a lesser outcome or a greater outcome than the person who's on the canoe in their mum's,
you know, station tube, right? So the second point I would extract from what you said is
we're probably using too crude an instrument to try to tease out exactly what effects in the
acute phase matter. And it's either because we don't know what questions to ask them in that
window, or we're not doing our analysis on a fine enough gradation of symptoms. Is that
a fair assessment? Yeah. Yeah. That's what I'm saying. Basically, I think we need,
you know, maybe a finer, more nuanced understanding of the effects. So we're doing some stuff now,
just recording what people say and getting them to describe it and then using artificial
intelligence kind of machine learning algorithms to find patterns in that to see if that might
predict it. Because I mean, that seems like a, you know, a bit of a no brainer now that we've got
quite a long way with just using natural language to predict outcomes. By the way, does ketamine
produce amnesia? Yeah, it's got some amnesia, but people can't remember the experience. It's not
as, so you might forget aspects of what's happened and it's an impairs your episodic memory, but
people do remember the experience. So we do interviews with people about the salient points
of the experience they'll remember. But I guess it's through a bit more of a fuzzy haze than maybe
your classic psychedelics. So a bit less accessible, I would say. The patient then,
let's say after you've done this, the patient wakes up and it's three hours later or wakes
up as the wrong word, but the patient sort of returns back to their baseline state. Do they
immediately feel the alleviation of the depression? Is that how quickly it can onset? People can feel
just, yeah, quite considerably better. A colleague of mine, we put McChane, he set up the first NHS
treatment resistant depression clinic here in the UK and he likened it to the film Awakenings,
which is actually about Parkinson's. But these people are really severely depressed, they often
can't get off bed and that they suddenly come alive. Some people, not everyone responds to it,
but yeah, that is pretty rapid and people just feel a kind of sense of clarity, a bit more
interest in the world, I would say. Almost like you're able to detect novelty where you went before
you know your attention. Yeah, it's quite a great thing to see. What is the mean and median duration
of how long that lasts? Well, yeah, that's again a really good question. Is around, I think people say,
I mean, and again, it's really variable and obviously some people don't respond at all,
so it's important to say that. What fraction do not respond at all? I don't think we have a good
handle on it basically. We need more real world data because if you look at people in trials,
it's often very different. I think it's around maybe I would say like 50, 50, 60%. Oh my god,
I had no clue it was that high. So you're saying just call it 50%, half the people that go through,
so half the people that show up with completely treatment resistant depression
and go through this experience under the well controlled setting of the lab in a clinical trial.
Have no benefit from it. Yeah, I think that's what's happened over time. So the early studies,
like Carlos Arrate study, you know, it was 75% and this typically happens with any new treatment,
I think. As more and more studies come out, the rates of response reduce. So yeah,
I would say, I mean, maybe I'm being overly conservative. So I should probably have that
figure to hand. But I will say, I think the duration is probably about, you know, two days
to a week often. And some people have longer will have two weeks. But that's the bit where my
research comes in really, because we've been looking at how you might extend that response.
And that's something that does seem to be coming out now. If you give it alongside psychological
therapy of some kind, you can really extend the response of the to ketamine and the antidepressant
effects, as well as the my child's been looking at ketamine in the treatment of alcohol. But we found
still reductions in drinking six months following just three infusions. So
how far did you space those three infusions? Oh, they were between either a week or kind of up to
two weeks, probably on average between them with seven sessions of psychological therapy. So quite
a limited treatment program, really. So let's go back to this, because this is sort of interesting,
right? So we would say, let's say 50% of people that show up and let's define treatment resistant
depression for somebody. It's not defined by duration, is it? No, it's not responding to it.
So and it's very nice to tricky one, because it's defined differently depending on different trials,
often we would define it as not responding to two conventional antidepressants
in the current depressive episode, or having had multiple different treatments. But yeah,
so it's not defined as treatment. But there have been some people taking more conservative definition
of that to have maybe three failed responses. So it is pretty variable in the trials.
And depression requires at least two weeks of the set of symptoms that we typically associate
with depression. And would it be classified as depression if there is an obvious externality? So
loss of a child, you know, if your child died, and a month later, you can't get out of bed,
is that considered depression? I mean, what I mean by that is like, how does that get classified,
given that there's such a clear explanation for the why? Yeah, I think, I mean, if that continues
for a really prolonged period of time, but then even that in itself is maybe contentious, because I
guess, but yeah, there's a clear boundary between, you know, grief, what's your anticipate from grief
and natural sadness, and then depression. So let's keep this one sort of simple and say that this is
not something that's clearly associated to a trigger such as grief, but instead, less
obvious to explain form of depression. It's been going on for at least a couple of weeks, let's
make it interesting and say it's been going on for months, so that this person has gone through
one SSRI, they've taken it to a therapeutic dose, they've had no benefit. They've then progressed
and moved to a different SSRI or a different class of drug in SNRI or something like that.
And similarly, they're just not getting the benefit. Does it matter if, do we sort of assess
how much psychotherapy they've been doing at the same time? It depends on the, I mean, I'm just
thinking about the clinical trials, all the reasons we give for prescribing off label
ketamine here in the UK. And typically, it would be the antidepressants, like not responding to
antidepressants. But yeah, you could say failed response to CBT. I mean, that's happened in,
in a lot of the trials, they would have non-responders to CBT. I know particularly some
of the psilocybin studies, but that's cognitive behavioral therapy. Yeah. Okay. So, so now the
person comes in and again, we've just said 50% of those people are not going to respond.
And that's pretty sad. So what are we saying to those 50% of people? It's, we, we, we're going to
go back to trying more and more conventional therapies, or do we say we should try this again
and maybe the second time we use a higher dose or something like that? Yeah, because some people,
there's some evidence that people take maybe three, this is in depression. Maybe we'll take,
might not respond to actually three ketamine doses, but maybe the fourth one,
they, there's some evidence that having an extra beyond three doses might increase the response.
I mean, certainly the unlabeled ketamine, which is this bravato, this is the Janssen
version of ketamine, which is intranasal. And that's indicated, you know, for repeated dosing.
So you start out twice, weekly, I think it's for a month and then move to weekly.
And what they're finding with the long-term studies is that people are staying on the dose.
I think it was an idea that people might, you know, progress off or drop down to,
I think they dropped down to fortnightly, but they're staying on it for a number of years now,
I think is the kind of long-term data. So it is a maintenance.
So the plan is to keep people on ketamine or like, let's go back to somebody who responded.
So let's go back to a patient whose depression is profound and they've been through all the
treatments and nothing's worked. They do their first ketamine infusion and they feel remarkably
better and it lasts four days. And then all of a sudden the depression sets back in.
Is the thinking that we're going to repeat this treatment and get longer and longer periods of
benefit, during which time we can work more on psychotherapy to try to, you know,
wean off the need for ketamine?
Yeah. I mean, that would be my thinking and that some people's thinking, I think,
is that targeting the therapy during that time is really important if you don't want to keep
someone on ketamine as a maintenance dose.
By the way, do patients need to stop their traditional antidepressants when they are
coming to these trials? So if the patients, because most of them are probably on SSRIs
and not doing well, do you at least get to keep them on that?
Yeah. I mean, we, in our trial, we were our funding buddy, which is the like,
the UK state didn't want us to include people on SSRIs, but actually most of the studies,
the depression studies, people are still on them and there's no interaction. So it's not like some
of the other novel substances like psilocybin where you'd, because it's working in a completely
different way in the brain. So there's no sense.
So why wouldn't this work?
You probably wouldn't be responding to them, I guess. Sorry.
What do you think is the mechanism of action?
Oh yeah. So I mean, that's where I think potentially the therapy and targeting the
therapy is really important. I mean, people have talked about ketamine and
indeed the other psychedelics, the psychopathic gens. I'm not sure about the term, but maybe the
idea that they provoked this kind of cascade and the study showing they increase synaptic
plasticity in the prefrontal cortex was certainly ketamine does. So increases the growth of new
synapses and dendrites on, so basically the ability of the brain to form new connections.
And that is correlated with the antidepressant effect. And so we kind of want to, we're doing
some work at the moment to sort of chart the time cause of that in humans by looking at EEG. So
that's kind of electrical signals from the brain and trying to target the window of this synaptic
plasticity. Because we know from animal studies, this might be kind of starting four hours following
the ketamine dose peaking about 24 hours. So it just sort of track the antidepressant effects,
which is quite interesting. I think the idea, you know, from me as a psychologist is that you could
time your psychological therapy when your brain is most plastic and is able to learn new things.
And we know actually, you know, this kind of plasticity is impaired across a whole range of
like sort of psychiatric disorders. So not just depression, but also an alcohol
and addiction and trauma. So actually still be able to stimulate the brain. So it's kind of
learn new things that, well, it's really plastic than actually giving some psychological therapy
that uses that process because we know that's what we're asking people to do really in psychological
therapy is to think definitely about things, learn new ways of thinking about old problems.
So yeah, that's, that's to me, it seems like an intuitively appealing mechanism. I mean,
there's some problems with it and that neuroplasticity happens from all sorts of things.
So some might argue, you know, is this like specific enough as a process? Other drugs
produce neuroplasticity that we wouldn't say were necessarily potential treatments for mental
health problems and psychiatric disorders. So you need to find out more about it. Well,
like cocaine. So people say the neuroplasticity produced from cocaine is used, is why it becomes
addictive. Like there's this kind of stimulation of that from an acute cocaine dose. So I don't
think we need to find out a bit more about it. And maybe it's down to something really specific
and neurobiological. So I leave that to my kind of preclinical researchers. But yeah, it's
fascinating. Now, when you think about, when you think about things like MDMA and psilocybin,
the real, a lot of the therapy takes place well under the influence of the drug,
whether it be for PTSD or depression. Is that happening also with ketamine when that patient is
in the aftermath of the infusion? Or is that, are they basically just left alone during that
period of time and the psychotherapy takes place immediately following, you know, the next day and
the next day and the next day trying to take advantage of them being less dysthymic?
Yeah. I mean, in our work, certainly, we wouldn't be trying to do any therapy
under the influence of ketamine. I think people would see the associated, you know,
the memory impaired. To me, that's, I know there are some ketamine therapists who do use this,
what's called kind of psycholytic approach, to where you use mild doses to be able to
do some therapeutic process. There's a really interesting study actually from a guy, where is
he? In Texas, I think, like in one of the VAs, I would have some correspondence with him. He's
actually looking at complex PTSD, which is, you know, really severe multiple traumas. And he was
treating complex regional pains and drain on top of that. So these are really traumatized people
who've got like really severe pain. And he was giving continuous, quite low dose. I can't exactly
have my fingertips, the dose, but ketamine over 96 hours. So continuous infusion. And he was doing
very kind of basic psychological therapy during that time and found massive reductions in, you
know, CAPS score, which is a long measure of PTSD symptoms. I mean, it was a really small study,
but I thought that was quite interesting approach. But no, to answer your question,
we do the therapy outside of that. And I think most people with ketamine do do that. I think
really with psilocybin as well, even people would argue what you're doing in that, when they're
having the acute experience is really just supporting them. Yeah. Yeah. That's fair. And
then it's the integration afterwards where we see it. Yeah. Well, there's a very little
research on what integration is or what the key fundamental is kind of accepted that this thing
that you have to do, but I don't know. We're kind of lacking research from that side. And what do
we know about the brain under the influence of ketamine? I mean, have people done FMRI or FDG
PET and kind of looked at either the metabolic state of the brain or the activity of the brain?
I mean, you've obviously mentioned the prefrontal cortex, but can we get even more granular than
that? Are there certain sections of the PFC that are more active than others? Yeah. There's quite
a lot of very interesting work. So there's the kind of, I guess, as you'd imagine, the default
mode network, which is, you know, being the- Tell folks what the default mode network is.
It's very important. It's basically what happens in your brain when you're not doing
anything active. So when you're in a scanner and we don't give anyone anything to do, then that's a
resting state scan. And you look at how the brain networks connect. So people say it's kind of,
yeah, the task, the kind of background activity of the brain and have likened it to things like
rumination, which we know are important in depression, which is like where you repetitively
think about something. You can have positive rumination as well. Repetitively think about
something good, but repetitively thinking about something bad or kind of mind wandering. So that's
where the default mode network has been kind of shown to be disrupted following psychedelics.
So this kind of background, normal kind of chatter of your brain and also similarly with things like
mindfulness. So there's been studies looking at that. We mentioned the prefrontal cortex. There's
some really interesting studies looking at prediction error signaling. So the idea that your
brain is basically like making predictions all the time about the world. And that's how we
understand everything perception. We know that there's like whatever behind your computer screen,
there's a world behind that. I would predict that if I put my laptop screen down and found there was
a gap in reality, then I'd have like a massive shock of surprise because that would signal to
my brain that I had to learn something new. So every time a prediction that we make based on our
learning is violated, then you get this increase in learning and attention and activity in your brain.
And there's some work that Ketamine basically disrupts. There's a bit of the
towards the lateral prefrontal cortex, those sort of in your prefrontal cortex, but a bit back and a
bit to the side. And that's really associated with this prediction error processing. And that's
disrupted with Ketamine. So things that aren't surprising become surprising. The things that
shouldn't be surprising and are completely predictable and things that aren't predictable
are no longer surprising. So basically kind of noisy signal that I think it's just quite an
interesting way of understanding maybe the subjective experiences from a lot of these
drugs that you turn off some of that kind of forward prediction from the brain and make a kind
of a noisier signal. So I think that's quite interesting way to think about the subjective
experiences. But yeah, I mean, there's quite a lot of neuroimaging work being done. Yeah,
we've done some of it as well, looking at kind of hippocampal function.
And is the brain hypermetabolic under the influence of Ketamine?
I think the idea is that there's more kind of more hypo in some ways. So get an increase in
sort of prefrontal glutamate. And we know that as well, because you get attenuated. So
and an increase in kind of prefrontal function. But then there's, yeah, so I don't know that that's
particularly clear, I guess. And the neuroimaging, as I've done it as a as a method in the past,
is not my area of expertise. So yeah. How many patients do you think, when relieved of their
depression during these Ketamine trips, will need to stay on Ketamine as a long term treatment? And
if so, at what frequency? Yeah, so I think that's what's really frustrating in a way is that there's
all of these Ketamine clinics, as you mentioned, that sprung up all across the US. We don't really
have that in the UK because we have a state health care system. So in the UK, any patient who is
receiving Ketamine for depression is doing it through the NHS. It's paid for by the NHS.
There's a couple of private clinics now that have sprung up, giving Ketamine. I'm involved with one
actually. But there's, it's mainly there's five centers prescribing on the NHS, but it's all
off label. Because our state health care regulator have not recommended yet Spravato, which is the
kind of intranasal Ketamine for use. And so there's no licensed Ketamine for depression.
So it's all prescribed for treatment resistant depression.
But if the physician prescribes it off label, is it paid for still by NHS?
Yeah, in some of these clinics, yeah, that have sprung up. Yeah, so there's maybe five of those
at the moment. But yeah, I think potentially there's a lot of data out there that we could
be looking at, but we don't have a good registry of all the patients. So we don't, I think in
answer to your question, yeah, there'll be a number of people that probably might respond.
And we don't know what, in all of these clinics, my sense is that not everyone has treatment
resistant depression, I think, particularly in the US has been given for a wide range of indications.
I mean, my guess in looking at the way it's being done in the US is there is no indication.
The only indication is, do you want to pay for it?
Yeah. And that's really, I mean, that's a bit, I guess there's kind of worrying signs there.
Although, but yeah, I mean, that's why I think it would be amazing if we could have a kind of
international registry way and we could look at, and then we could look up this data. We'd have
the data to be able to say, you know, with this presentation, how long someone would likely be on
ketamine. Because speaking from the trials data is one thing, but actually it's already being given
out there, you know, for like you say, for all manner of things. So it's a shame, because I think
those data would be really helpful. And also it would add a level of kind of safety potentially
for the patients and for the clinicians. I know there's a couple of case reports of people
going across state lines, ketamine seeking. I don't think it's a huge problem because,
I mean, but we don't know, right? So we must be mindful of the potential of these things.
I've seen some slightly worrying trends recently, but I'll organize a ketamine conference with some
colleagues, some of them from the US. And we had a few pharmaceutical companies coming in and
developing ketamine for all daily dosing. And to me, that's a bit of a worry having worked,
you know, for 10 years researching ketamine users, because I feel like even if you're using very low
all daily dosing, you're going to have to dose escalate, right? So where's the end point? And
if you aren't giving it in a sport of therapy, because the idea that people are just on ketamine
all the time, I don't know, to me it seems a bit worrying. Maybe there's something I'm missing
about the drug development pathway there, but. No, no, I don't. I mean, I'm going to just take
the skeptics point of view on that. I don't think you're missing anything. I think it's a land grab
for a greater profit motive without enormous consideration for the downside. You know, so,
so I mean, I would, I would share your, I don't know what it is about ketamine that has me
sort of cautious. And maybe it's just the anecdotes and that's a bad, that's a bad frame. But
you know, it just, do you, is there, this is going to sound really silly, but do you, do you have a
sense, have you ever seen people with these sort of ketamine eyes, like these sort of sunken,
distant, like this person has taken too much ketamine in their life and their brain doesn't work
as well anymore? And I think you can have that with, I'm sure there are lots of different drugs
that can produce that phenotype. I'm sure somebody that's taken far too much cocaine can experience
something, but, but, but it, I think it has, it's something that you see more commonly, I would
assume with ketamine than you would with LSD or psilocybin, because as you said, the frequency of
use is much harder with those other drugs. Like no one is going to, I mean, I shouldn't say no one.
Someone can do anything, but it's far less likely that a person is going to take heroic doses
of LSD or psilocybin over and over and over again. Whereas you could get down that path with ketamine.
And again, it's just anecdotal, but you know, you see some of these people where
you, you get the concern. It's not just the bladder. I mean, the cystitis is a very obvious
and tangible objective side effect that can be devastating. This is much more subtle. It's just,
something's changed in that person's brain and it's not for the better. So am I just sort of
making this up and it's possible I am and that I'm just over extrapolating from something else,
but have you, you've been around this more than almost anyone. Do you have a concern around that?
Yeah, no, we've done a lot of studies on that as well. And I guess maybe, I don't know,
we haven't studied that, sunken eyes. But we have lids and brains.
Yeah. And it's not, I mean, it sounds silly to say it. It's not physically sunken, right? Like,
like you would with hypothyroidism. It's just, it's a vacancy is more what I'm describing.
Yeah. I kind of dullness. And I mean, I guess like any addiction, one thing I noticed,
and again, anecdotally, it was just like a lack of, you know, when people lose their sense of humor
and that seems to be like a thing in addiction, it's like the spark has gone out of life,
which is odd, right? Because what we're giving ketamine for, this is quite a paradoxical drug
in depression is to like put the spark back. But then it makes sense you do it too much. And maybe
that spark has gone. And we found that, you know, cognitively, we found cognitive impairments and
with planning. And we found actually reductions in, you know, your hippocampus, which is involved in
processing novelty and encoding memories. And that's the function of that is reduced in some
of our brain imaging studies with people who, these are people who take daily heavy doses of
ketamine. So I'm not saying even your non-medical recreational user, which show this kind of symptoms
to people who take it occasionally, but yeah, really, really, really heavy doses. I think that's
possible. I don't know because seeing the way that it's administered in clinics, I mean, originally
it was not never really the idea of it as a rapid acting antidepressant. And I think the promise
was that it's not a maintenance medication, you know, and how empowering that is for patients
to not be on a daily medication. And that's why I feel a bit sad that there's not more research
effort going into looking at enhancing the antidepressant effect with therapy. So we don't
have to give people hundreds of doses of ketamine. And maybe some people will just need that. And
that's a cost benefit analysis, I guess, you make when you're prescribing any drug, you know,
because these, some of these people, you know, this is life threatening, right? Like people who
are really heavily suicide or say, has anyone done that study where you, because that's the closest
way to get to a quality adjusted life year analysis, which is going to be that cost benefit
analysis. Has anyone taken that group of patients who are the most treatment resistant and randomize
them to continuing to try to treat even though it's resistant versus ketamine and looking at
really hard outcomes like differences in suicide rate? These people have definitely done work with
patients with suicidal ideation. Yeah. And you get reduced mortality with ketamine. So I guess,
and they have randomized people, which is, I mean, these are tough studies to do, right?
Yeah, of course. They're ethically difficult as well when you know that you have a treatment.
Yeah, really, really difficult. And so just, you know, amazing. Just, yeah, amazing. And all of the
researchers doing that work because it's so important. So what does your intuition say is
probably the sweet spot for what the intermittent, you know, call it transient but fixed use of
ketamine is as a bridge to go from completely treatment resistant to depression to treatable
depression. Well, yeah, I mean, I guess my work's been with people with addictions. So maybe I
could talk about that because I feel, you know, more able to speak just from our data. But there
we used, as I was saying, like these three doses and seven. Three doses separated by seven days
each? Yeah, seven days to two weeks. And then that was a 0.8 milligrams per kilogram. So it's
quite a slightly higher dose than in depression because you get a sort of cross tolerance with
alcohol. Because alcohol also works on the same receptors ketamine at high doses so that, you know,
when people get really intoxicated and feel like they're spinning out, that's kind of your alcohol
working on your NMD receptors. So yeah, we use that three doses. And these, I mean, people with
alcohol problems have depression as well and can be quite severely treatment resistant. What we found,
I think is interesting, is we were still seeing impacts on like reductions in rumination,
which are meant that repetitive negative thinking and reductions in anhedonia, which is a hallmark
of depression, but also across multiple disorders. And that's an inability to experience pleasure in
the world. And so we saw reductions in that at three months, but they were back to baseline at
six months, whereas they were still showing reductions in drinking, which is, I thought,
is really interesting. So they might suggest like, certainly in depression, that maybe that
would be the time, you know, so you have maybe weekly or fortnightly days.
Yeah, because to me, that model makes a bit more sense. If you could say, look,
this is a treatment that, you know, you need to do once a quarter, you know, every three months,
you know, so you have a loading phase where you do the infusion weekly for three or four weeks,
and then you're on to kind of a quarterly schedule. That to me is very interesting.
What's less interesting to me, and what I'm seeing certain people do, is
twice a week ketamine infusion for life. I mean, that strikes me as, you know, I just worry about
the toxicity of the drug. And B, it would have to really have an enormous efficacy to justify, it
seems. And I look at the short term studies where they're comparing ketamine to Versed,
like it's not that much better, not that Versed is a good option, by the way, but, you know,
when you're using Versed as a control, and you're seeing, well, basically that's telling you there's
a pretty big placebo effect from doing this as well.
No, exactly. I think it was put on. Well, I mean, that's my intuition as well, is that
this is a positive thing if we're maintaining people on this twice weekly, you know, for life.
So tell me why you think it's working in addiction, and do you primarily work in alcohol addiction,
or do you also look at opioid addiction? We want to look at opioid addiction as well. And actually,
there's some other work going on in the US looking at opioid addiction. And this work dates back to
some work by a Russian psychiatrist of Jenny Kropitsky, who did work with heronatics and found
a similar, you know, dosing regime, which was just three infusions with this psychological
therapy around it, produced reductions in herone use at 12 months, you know, quite significant.
Do you know how much? How much of a reduction?
I know in alcohols, there's a 40% reduction in relapse rate.
At 12 months?
In these Russian, at 12 months, yeah.
And what's the control group, which I assume is doing, is the control group
doing pharmacotherapy or behavioral therapy, such as 12 step program?
I mean, for context, this is in the 80s in Russia, they were inpatient alcoholics.
And so they were in lock towards. So I remember saying to have Jenny, did anyone drop out?
So they can't drop out. They're locked in. So I think it wasn't in the normal consent and ethics
process as we have now. But still, a really important study in both groups had 100 people in.
And so and it wasn't, you know, it wasn't a randomized control trial.
He asked people if they wanted to be in this ketamine and psychotherapy group.
So I'm sorry, I'm just trying to understand the trial. You have an inpatient trial,
where all the patients are given trial, in quotes. This would constitute a dodgy trial.
Yeah, this is dodgy.
So it's inpatient and they're all given unlimited access to alcohol.
But they're no, no, no, no, no, no, they're not.
So how do we know how do we know what the relapse rate is?
So they do they had to do their detox. They get given their ketamine treatment,
they're discharged. And then when followed up at.
Oh, I see. So they're out. They behave as outpatients, but they're not allowed to drop out.
In other words, if you drop out the KGB, bring you back.
Yeah, they can drop out of the treatment. I was what I was asking him about was like,
do people tolerate the treatment? Well, they just did the treatment.
Yeah, I got it.
Sorry, no. They didn't get like shot by the KGB. No.
Yeah.
Yeah. So they're really important studies. So yeah, I've only asked people if they wanted to have this.
It was kind of like groups, like a dynamics, like therapy with just three infusions of
ketamine. He was using higher doses. So around an intramuscular to one to two milligrams per
kilogram. So yeah, quite strong.
So but we haven't done the head to head of ketamine plus behavioral therapy versus
pharmacologic plus behavioral therapy for alcohol.
No, we haven't. I've done Katzman plus therapy plus compared to Katzman with a kind of therapy
control. Yes. Compared to placebo and therapy compared to placebo. So I did a four arm trial.
Okay. So tell us about that. Tell us about that trial.
Oh, yes. That's the one that I mean, it's been so yeah, what we found, I mean, which was great,
because that's what we hypothesized. And that's quite rare. I wasn't expecting to get what we
hoped for was that we saw the strongest, greatest reductions in drinking and and greatest abstinence
in our ketamine and therapy group. It's 86% abstinent at rates at six months. And then
the second best effect was in our ketamine and education controls. We wanted to look at the
effects of therapy, ketamine within and without therapy, but there's really non-specific effects
of just spending hours with a therapist. Yes. It's quite nice. So we would put the kind of we
concocted this. I mean, it's a bit like medication management, which is used in a lot of the US trials.
So tell me about what that's a that's a very elegant trial design, because you get away from
what's called the performance bias of the therapy, right? The therapy itself, you have to make sure
you're you're controlling for just the fact that an hour, three times a week, they have to go talk
to somebody. And so the question is, what so tell me what they do in the education arm of that?
Yeah, so we wanted so that we wanted it to be I mean, it's not blind, right? I think for most
people, but some people thought they'd had the therapy. So that's quite positive. Because you
can't that's another issue is that you can't be blind. It's like therapy. But
and people were doing kind of calculations about alcohol, talking about how alcohol affects the
body. And we did some relaxation. But just as we thought as a bare minimum of what we wanted to do
with people going into like a ketamine session, you know, a ketamine infusion was to have a bit
of a relaxation and control. So I think maybe the relaxation helps with the blinding. But yeah,
no, we were pleased with the design. I mean, and then did for the non ketamine group, did they get
Versed or what type of control do they get? What's the placebo?
The same. So they were they got no, they got they just got saline basically.
Also no dissociative effects.
No, I know, which is a bit of a shame. In retrospect, we should have used something
like midazolam or the DIO of you know, but we just use the saline placebo. So it's I mean, we
never the last.
So it's a it's a but it's still a very elegant two by two study, perhaps only limited by the
fact that the control didn't get some sort of active substance. Yeah. But nevertheless, at 12
months or sorry, at six months, you said that the double positive group double positive meaning
ketamine plus actual psychotherapy dedicated towards alcohol reduction. Did you say 86%
were still alcohol free at six months?
Abstinence rates. Yeah, which is good really. I mean, we were really impressed. And then there was
and then what about the other three groups?
The response were quite good in all of the groups, but it was statistically significantly
different. So that's, you know, what we care about. So there was a small, I mean, it was 96
patients. It didn't feel like a small trial. It was only 24 patients per arm. So we weren't
powered for the really for the full interaction. But actually, we're taking it forward now into
phase three with 280 patients. So that's good. Again, funded by the UK state, which is great.
So we get to run it in NHS settings and hopefully see it as a medicine, you know, in those in those
contexts, because one thing, I mean, I don't know what you think of the psychedelics world, but and
I think some of the therapies are amazing. But for our state healthcare system, those things are
not ever going to happen. You're never going to have two therapists for 40 hours, you know.
So I wanted to come up with a therapy that was deliverable in our state healthcare system,
because, you know, I mean, there's certainly it's a great idea that you could do have that kind of
system. But we've got we have had we've got these kind of slightly lower level trained therapists,
and there's a lot of them in the NHS here. And so we designed our therapy to be quite
manualized so that they could deliver it. And it take a short amount of time.
So how much therapy how much therapy were they getting in the active?
They get about only about in total about 11 hours.
In six months?
Yeah, so they just get they get it for the treatment part. And I do think that, you know,
like, so just in those in those first three weeks or two weeks when they're getting
it's three doses separated by seven days.
Yeah, for a total so they have a therapy session before their infusion immediately before. And so
if they were in the therapy group, they would be doing kind of mindfulness practice. And then
in the education group, there's some relaxation, and then they have the ketamine session.
And then they just recover, you know, as you went from an anesthetic, and they go home,
come back the next day where we think the peak of that,
and the kind of synaptic plasticity effects are and they have another note. So these are
longer sessions of an hour and a half therapy. And they so it's kind of a ketamine infusion
sandwich between two therapy sessions. And they repeat that three times.
What is the therapist talking about? I don't really know much about alcohol addiction. But
so so when like in particular, when that patient comes in the day after their first ketamine
infusion, when they're, as you said, at their maximum neuroplasticity, what I mean, I assume
the therapist has a very clear playbook for how they want to work with that patient in that
90 minute block, what what's in that playbook?
And think some of it's very pragmatic, you know, things like what are your most risky
situations for drinking, like trying to preempt situations where they might relax, but some of it's
more about how you want to live your life and the values you want to embody.
So trying to think about, give out your life without alcohol, how would you structure that?
And there's some yeah, things about thinking about your thinking around drinking, which is
more kind of cognitive behavioral therapy based, what are your thinking biases, let's identify
those and then planning. So they have quite a lot of activities to do in the week or weeks in between
the sessions, you know, what I guess like standard homeworks, but planning their days, generally
keeping track of those things, we teach kind of mindfulness techniques to enable people to deal
with cravings and to get a bit more of a space between them and their kind of addictive impulses.
See, there's a whole range of stuff really, we through the book of the evidence based therapies
out there. And so it's very, oh, sorry, go ahead. Yeah, no, no, no, no, you go ahead.
No, no, I was just gonna ask you, tell me about the inclusion criteria. I mean, obviously,
you're dealing with a patient who's motivated who says I want to stop drinking. And then they
actually come and do a pre infusion therapy session. Is there anything that in that session,
the therapist says, we're not going to include this patient? Like, is there is there another
decision that's made of a go no go based on that pre infusion session?
Well, the go no goes normally made before that. So they had to go through like a number of
screenings basically to get as is with a clinical trial, which is kind of a problem with clinical
trials that we end up with quite pure populations. But we needed people to be abstinent when they
started. As we were talking about right at the beginning, you know, with a lot of people who
are drinking, they can't stop straight away. So they either need to go through a medical detox,
in most cases, or, you know, supervised, most of those are in the community now. So you can
work with people's health care providers to support them as they're doing that. So we keep
checking in with them until they're ready to start. So normally, maybe two weeks after if
they've done a full detox, if someone's drinking really heavily, but we're at levels that we think,
you know, we can help them support them cut down over a four week period, we would do that. So
there'd normally be a kind of pre screening where we check all the medical contraindications for
people and psychiatric ones. So we don't include people with psychosis or psychosis in a first
degree relative. People with uncontrolled blood pressure because of ketamine increasing,
your like, so uncontrolled hypertension, because ketamine increases your blood pressure and a
variety of other things. We would exclude people from the study. And then we have to access kind
of their medical notes. And so yeah, it's quite a process. But the main bit is getting people
abstinent. And so when so this all the therapy is all around like, you know, supporting people
with a new life and giving using the ketamine experience really, to get that perspective,
perspective they might not have had for a while, that kind of new perspective, to think about
their life in a new way, and try and focus on how they want to go forward, really. So it's really
using the ketamine as a catalyst for the therapy, rather than purely focusing on the pharmacological
properties of it. And remind me how much does blood pressure go up in that type of a therapy
when you're at 0.8 megs per Kig? What's the increase in systolic and diasolic blood pressure?
I don't know. It really varies. So some people are really minimal. Some people like goes up about 10,
I guess. I'm trying to think. As a psychologist, I guess, we have an eutectist there for the whole
thing. So they're probably checking that. And there was someone, we had to stop the infusion
because it went above, I think it went over 180. So, but that was, that's pretty rare. And that's,
you know, why we do exclude people. But they're my eutectist colleagues say, you know, if we're
people in theatre, we just give them ketamine, the perspective of this. They're quite, you know,
I guess, because of the way, an eutectist are the people that kill you, right? Ultimately,
if all of the medical professionals do want to, they're quite, yeah, desensitized, I guess,
to risk. Whereas we're like, oh. Right. So again, tell me what the response rate was in the double
negative group. So the group that didn't get the ketamine and only got the education, but without
therapy, what was their six month? And was like, still, I mean, really high, so about six, just
68%, I think. What do you attribute that to? So that means there's a 20% difference between the
two extremes, which is still great. But how do you attribute a 68% non-drink or an abstinence rate
in people that didn't get ketamine and didn't really even get therapy? They just
sat down and talked with somebody about alcohol, biochemistry. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, and it is not,
I think that was pretty extraordinary for any good child. And we did have a really lovely team,
so I partly put it down to that. I think, you know, it's something you see in clinical trials,
people just do better. A, because they've gone through this whole rigmarole process with this
really strong intention to stop, you know, so they've been through quite a lot of hurdles that
the trial was pretty demanding. So, you know, if you start with it, we also had things which I
had mentioned, like, we had a SCRAM. I don't know if you've ever seen them. They're using criminal
justice. More Lindsay Lohan had to wear one when she had some DUIs. It's basically like a tag that
you put around your ankle that measures your alcohol through transdermally because you're
excrete about 1% of alcohol and sweat. So there were things that we were using to measure alcohol
that might have actually acted as an intervention on their own. And you know, the fact that you have
to go over, it wasn't, now we're using a much more discreet wearable, right? But then this really
clunky thing, you know, you had to say, you're not going to do swimming for six months, you know,
all these things. I think that in itself was an intervention. Yeah. But also just be, you know,
a lot of these people don't have a lot of social connections. Some of them did. But the fact of
having people looking after them, checking in on them all the time, you know, repeatedly measuring,
like people just showing you general human kindness, I think can have obviously a really
positive effect in a group that might be quite isolated. Yeah. I mean, that's amazing. I mean,
I think these are really kind of staggering insights because you have everything from the
monitoring of compliance to just the interaction. I don't say any of this to diminish the
fascination I have in both two components of this, one being the effect of the ketamine and
therapy producing 88% abstinence at six months, but also just looking at the control group and
realizing it didn't take much to move the needle. And what can we learn from that sort of more big
picture? It's a bit of a sad statement. It really is. Yeah. I think alcohol services here in the UK
are just so dysfunctional at the moment. You have to, you know, people by the time they get to any
sort of treatment, people that are really seriously complexly, you know, with multiple
health problems, well, people have been through multiple treatments and they've not worked. I
don't know. And it's really hard to access therapists. It's like multiple things. It's
like, oh yeah, it's really sad. It doesn't actually take that much to shift something
that's pretty entrenched, you know? Well, the other thing too is it makes me wonder about
less responsive cohorts down the line where you would expect the response rate to be lower. But
let's say you took an individual who's less interested in not drinking. You know, I mean,
I don't think you could treat someone who says I'm going to keep drinking, but someone who maybe
hasn't fully hit rock bottom but says, you know, yeah, maybe I'm drinking too much. And yeah,
I probably meet the criteria for being an alcoholic, but I haven't destroyed my life yet.
You know, I just sort of wonder if you have these places for earlier intervention as someone is
on the path towards, you know, really destructive alcoholism. So a lot's here. So in the phase three,
obviously you said 200 plus patients, so that's going to be great. You're still going to do the
same four arms? Well, actually, I mean, it's funded by the NIH at the department for health
here. So we've gone down to take the two most extreme arms. Ideally, I mean, in an ideal world
of infinite resource, I would definitely have the four arms because I really like that design. And
I think something that's really missing from the broader psychedelics world is teasing apart the
impact of the therapy and the drug. But I think we felt speaking to clinicians, so we've got like a
patient advocacy group involved from the start that actually given potentially the, you know,
some of the risks with ketamine that we wouldn't really want to give it without a therapeutic
container. So having found these promising effects for this efficacy study, which is more
of a definitive study, then we would just take the most extreme arms. But yeah, so we're looking
just with the therapy and then, you know, the various other more discrete variables compared to
our placebo, but we're using a low dose ketamine this time instead to manage expectancy.
So what will that low dose be? Will the high dose still be 0.8 mg per kilogram?
Yeah. And the low dose is low, like 0.05. We're sort of working out with some piloting.
But. And why is that? Because at point, at not 0.5, they will, or 0.05, actually, they'll
experience nothing. I mean, they shouldn't feel anything. Yeah. Not really anything. We've done
some other studies and studies with morphine and childhood trauma, say looking at people's,
you know, I mean, it's a completely different area of research, but looking at how childhood
trauma seems to sensitize the brain to the, to respond to opiates. And there we found actually
using a very low dose morphine was kind of a better control than another drug. So I think it
is actually helpful in expectancy. So you tell people you're getting it, you're getting the drug.
Then also because we had patients actually drop out because well, because they thought, you know,
they knew that they hadn't got the ketamine and they hadn't got the active. So we're saying you're
getting one of two doses of ketamine. It's kind of easier to maintain people in that.
The other thing is you might be able to recruit some KGB officers to help with that,
that dropout rate. Exactly. No one drops out. So we're not doing any dodgy stuff.
This is not, this is a non dodgy trial. So what's your, what's your, there's one other thing I want
to talk about before we, we, we, we, we wrap this up. So I want to, but I want to sort of put a bow
on the ketamine story. What would you say to people here in the U S right? So we're, we're
ketamine clinics are ubiquitous. And as far as I can tell, I think you can just walk into them.
I don't think you need a referral. I don't think you need a medical referral to go to a ketamine
clinic. Although I think there are therapists who do make referrals and say, look, this is a
reputable clinic. And I'm sure that there are many reputable clinics and, you know, your
depression is recalcitrant or, you know, you're having this problem in your life and I think it
could get better here. So, so I suspect that there's a really good conduit of therapists
sending patients appropriately to good ketamine clinics, but let's also posit that anybody can
walk into a ketamine clinic, which I really do believe is true. And sort of tell the persons
there, Hey, I'm having this issue. I want to do it. But there's a bit of a conflict in that model
because when you walk into the clinic, they're in sort of incentivized to do what they do, right?
When you're a hammer, everything's a nail. When you're a ketamine clinic, you're incentivized to
give ketamine. How would you caution people around ketamine use liberally in that context?
I suppose I'd say that it's the evidence, you know, that we've gathered and not just us. There's
another group at Yale, Sam Wilkinson has looked at, you know, therapy and ketamine. And there's
another trial starting in depression is that actually it's a bit of a waste. If you just,
if you just do the ketamine, you should certainly try it embedded within therapy and you probably
don't need, you know, all of those doses. I think interrogating what you're trying to get out of that
experience and that actually, you know, I think it's, it's, that's great to hear that therapists
refer people to ketamine clinics, like we've got so far with therapy, then we're going to use this
as a boost so we can continue the therapy. To me, that just seems much more appealing model
because really do people want to, I don't think people want to be kind of stuck on a drug, even
if you're not, you know, addicted, but you're going in twice a week or even once a week, like
that's so disempowering for patients. We know that, right? And speaking to patients, one of the things
they said was great about there are treatment approaches, you know, rather than being on daily
meds, things like other treatments in alcohol, like the campus that you have to take three times a
day, they feel pretty liberated, you know, and they know they're doing the healing themselves,
which I think is a really important part of the process. So I'd say, yeah, get kind of,
get a therapist, think about using a really minimal number of doses. I mean, I do,
yeah, it's, it's worrying. There's some really worrying practices that you hear about, you know,
some mail order ketamine clinics. I don't really worry about them from the abuse side. Maybe I'm
wrong not to, but just because it's so expensive, I think, unless you're, you know, you have to have
a lot of money to be able to afford that ketamine. But I just think it works unsafe because if it's
certain, you don't take ketamine at home when you're not supervised, you know, this drug makes
you completely dissociated from your environment. If you, if something happens, there's a fire or,
and all sorts of things could happen. You can't take it unsupervised, but I think that's a lack of
kind of clinical care and supervision in some of these models. Yeah, I find that really worrying,
but it's expensive as well. So you sort of answered what my next question was going to be,
which was not at all to say, do you condone the use of, of, of non-medical or recreational ketamine,
but more to say if someone is going to use ketamine recreationally, what, what is the,
what is the instruction set you provide them to make sure that they don't harm themselves
psychologically and physically? So one of them is, if I'm just going to extrapolate, it's like,
if people are going to do ketamine recreationally, there really needs to be somebody around watching
them, right? You can't, you can't trust yourself to be under the influence of this drug, at least
at a high dose, which I'm guessing based on what we've said is, you know, depending on your size,
a hundred to 200 milligrams would be considered a high dose. Yeah, really high. And I think, you
know, start with any small doses and I guess is the advice that you would always give to people
with any non-medical use of a drug. Yeah. And do it in a, you know, a safe place with someone who's
not under the influence of any substances and start with a small dose. But yeah, I mean,
it's not, I don't know so much them in the US. You rarely get ketamine, particularly cut with
other things, but it can happen. So there's something to be careful of as well.
Wow. That's interesting. What would it typically be cut with?
I don't know. I mean, there are ketamine analogs, which people have shown. So there's a drug
methyl acetamin. So they're the kind of research chemicals that have come out of labs in China,
Israel. So it's an analog of ketamine, but it's got studies of shame, more toxicity of the bladder
and slightly maybe higher abuse potential. But yeah, typically, I mean, I, yeah, I don't,
I don't think it's, it's normally particularly cut with things, but it's something to be mindful of
and why it's really important to take a small dose, you know, but ideally, yeah, obviously,
I think caution may not medically use. Well, Celia, that's, I mean, this is super interesting.
I mean, this is, I've sort of been deliberately sort of ignorant of ketamine. I don't know why
I've sort of gone down the rabbit hole and trying to understand as much as possible about these other
agents, which ironically are tend to be the one that are schedule one and therefore not really
readily available for clinical use outside of trials. We do have many clinical trials here
in the United States looking at in particular, the use of psilocybin and MDMA.
But, but ketamine has been a bit of a black box to me and yet it's the one that I probably have
seen the most people use because of course it can be used legally. So I found this discussion
very helpful. I found this discussion really insightful and it sort of clarified for me
a lot of the use case, the neurobiology, the risks and perhaps most importantly, what the
promise of this agent is. So I want to thank you for your time. And again, I know it's late there
in the UK at the moment and more importantly, I think thank you for the work you're doing. This is
really fascinating and I kind of love the model. Oh, thanks for having me, Peter.