Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast, my
website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content if you want to take your knowledge of this space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are, or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now, without further delay, here's
today's episode. Welcome to another episode of the Drive. As we've released so many episodes over
the past four years, we realized we've covered a lot of topics in detail. Sometimes it can be
hard to keep up and try to piece it together. We also realized that there are listeners today who
weren't exactly listeners a year ago or three years ago or four years ago. We did a test of
this idea back in May of 2022 where we did an episode that pulled a variety of clips from
previous podcasts, but all on one topic, which was exercise. The feedback we received from that
episode was overwhelmingly positive and people asked for more. This week, we're going to do it
again. Of course, we're going to pick a different topic. This topic is going to be sleep, probably
something we get just as many questions on as frankly anything else. We put these clips in the
order of what we think is the best way to listen from top to bottom, but in between some of the
clips, I'm going to provide a little bit of commentary to set the stage. Our hope is that
this will not only allow you to understand the topic of sleep better, but also help identify
some of the previous episodes in case you actually want to go back and listen to those in more detail.
In each of these clips, I'm going to be joined by sleep expert Matt Walker. Matt has been on the
podcast several times, including three AMAs. One thing to note is that some of these clips
are from AMAs. So if you're not a subscriber, you'll actually get a sense of what we cover
during those episodes. This is still a new concept and this is only our second time doing this. So
we really do want the feedback. If you like this, tell us we'll keep doing it. If you don't,
we'll scrap it. So without further delay, I hope you'll enjoy this special episode of The Drive.
Firstly, it took Mother Nature 3.6 million years to put this eight hour thing called a
night of sleep in place. And within the space of 70 years, if you look at the data, we've
lopped off almost 20 to 25% of that. Imagine coming along and saying, in the next hundred years,
I think what I'm going to do is for the entirety of human society, I'm going to reduce that.
Oxygen saturation by about 20 to 25%. Do you think that's a good idea? And the answer is no.
No, it's such a great example. I'll pause for a moment just to tell a funny story that you and
I have talked about off mic, which is up until about 2012, I was in the I'll sleep when I'm
dead camp. And I know what led to that. It wasn't that there was a very deliberate decision at the
end of medical school when a good friend of mine with all the best intentions who was a year ahead
of me. So he was now in at the end of his internship as I was about to begin my he said,
and this is in the days when we didn't have the 80 hour work week requirement in residency. So we
averaged, I think about 114 hours a week in the hospital. So he said to me, look, Peter, you're
signing up for, you know, whatever five, seven years of this thing. If you spent every moment
outside of the hospital sleeping, you would still be tired. The only difference is you wouldn't
have any fun. So make sure you live every moment that you're not in the hospital to the fullest.
And so for me, that basically meant if I wasn't in the hospital, I was swimming, I was going out
with my friends, I was trying to meet girls like and I was doing anything, everything, such that
during that period of my life, I, I just know because I was pretty adamant about recording how
much time like I was very wed to this idea. There's 168 hours in a week, if I'm spending,
you know, 114 of them here, and I spend this many driving, I spend this many getting groceries,
and I spend this many swimming and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. I think I was about 28 hours a week
of sleep. So it wasn't for every night because you'd have none, and then six, and then three,
and then eight, like you could binge sleep from time to time. But it was pretty much 28 a week.
I'll come back to some of the implications of that. But fast forward a few years, I'm talking
to a good friend of mine who's a physician who like you is adamant about, you know, the importance
of sleep. And we're having dinner one night. And he says, he's challenging me on this. And he says,
so let me get this straight. You've just decided that you're going to sleep half of what is
evolutionarily programmed. And I said, yeah. Because does it strike you as odd that evolution
would have designed us to spend a third of our life not mating, not watching out for predators,
not hunting for food, but doing this thing for some other purpose? Do you think that thing must
have been important? And it was such an obvious argument, but it really overnight changed the way
I thought about this, which was evolution went to great lengths to do this. And superficially at
great cost to us, right? I mean, you could argue, well, imagine you didn't need to sleep and you
could spend 24 hours a day foraging for food or a mate or some other thing, but it didn't.
So it's sort of, it's sort of like, there's probably a reason we are not anaerobic.
To your point about reducing oxygen saturation by 25%.
You know, if you were to think about that, you know, during sleep, just as you said,
you're not eating, you're not finding food, you're not finding a mate, you're not reproducing,
you're not caring for your young, you're vulnerable to predation on any one of those grounds,
but especially all of them put together as a collective, completely anti evolutionary.
It sounds like the dumbest thing. And, you know, often said, and it has been said before,
if sleep doesn't serve an absolutely vital set of functions, it's the biggest mistake that the
evolutionary process has ever made. And we now realize from this constellation of evidence that
mother nature did not make a spectacular blunder in putting this thing called an eight hour
sort of need of sleep in place. It is the greatest life support system that you could
ever wish for. It is a remarkable health insurance policy. And what's great is that
it's largely democratic. It's mostly free. And in terms of a prescription from a doctor,
it's largely painless. So I almost wanted to title the book, consciousness is overrated,
or just sometimes dot dot dot consciousness is overrated. But when you really look at the
evidence in terms of risk derisking just about every disease that is killing us in the developed
world, it's very hard to look no further than sleep. And that's why I don't want to trivialize
diet. And I don't want to trivialize movement and activity. But what I would say is that if you want
to put sleep up against either one of those two and kind of play the whole head to head game,
which I don't think we need to do here, I would simply say that sleep is the foundation on which
those two other things sit. It's not the third pillar of good health. I think it is the foundation.
That's a really interesting way to think about it, because I typically describe four pillars,
or five, if you include all of the exogenous molecules that you could lump together. But
another way to think about it, which again, I don't think is necessarily the right way to
think about it. But sometimes it makes the point. If you deprive yourself of food, how long can you
survive? Well, we have one person up to 382 days, even someone who's as lean as you could survive
30 days with no food. How long could you survive without water depends greatly on the temperature,
etc. But you could make the case that deprivation of sleep would result in the quickest reduction of
health, certainly more than not eating or not exercising for a period of time.
And those studies have been done in rats.
Yeah. And actually, we know some of this from humans who have been trying to... In fact,
didn't the Guinness Book of World Records, I can't remember if I read this in your work,
they've actually banned attempts at longest period of sleep deprivation.
So I mentioned this. Yeah.
Yeah, you might leave it in the book.
But there was a time when you could still try and beat the world record of sleep deprivation,
and it got up to about sort of, I think the last true effort was about 24 days.
But I think it was debatable, that one. But based on the weight of the scientific data,
the relationship between sleep loss and mental health, sleep loss and cancer,
sleep loss, cardiovascular disease, sleep loss and metabolic syndrome, Guinness started to feel
very, very uncomfortable. And then when suicide came on the table, it pulled it.
So in other words, think about this, there was a gentleman, Felix Baumgardner, I think his name was,
who sponsored by Red Bull, went up in a capsule in a hot air balloon to the outer surface of our
planet. This was about four years ago.
Four years ago.
This was remarkable.
He opened the door and then he jumped out and he fell back down to earth at over a thousand
kilometers an hour using his body alone. He broke the sound barrier and he successfully
came back. And now Guinness says for that, just fine. However, to sleep deprive yourself, no,
much more unsafe. We're not going to let it happen.
You are allowed just to put it in context.
You're allowed up to 12 jumps off Niagara Falls.
Basically.
But that's okay. But no, no, you're not going to. That's such a great point.
So let's shift gears just a little bit and go back to the polysom. Let's explain to people,
because we're going to eventually have to talk about tracking these things. And I want to bring
up some of the sort of commercially available ways that people do that, which I think by definition
are still not accurate enough for people to compare them to their polysom. But if I came
into your lab tonight and I was willing to go to sleep there and you would hook me up to an EEG,
what are the different patterns of brainwaves and how would you morphologically describe them and
then bucket them by these stages you've already sort of touched on a little bit as deep REM,
deep REM, deep non-REM, et cetera.
Yeah. So upon falling asleep, human beings and in fact, all mammals will experience two different
stages of sleep. One of them is called non-rapid eye movement sleep. The other is rapid eye movement
sleep. Non-REM sleep has been further subdivided into four separate stages, which are unimaginatively
called stages one through four. Thank God. Yeah, I know. Yeah. I think that's all that the sleep
deprived people who are, you know, experimenting could come up at that time. So increasing in their
depth of sleep sleep. So stages three and four of non-REM sleep are the really deep restorative
stages of sleep. Stages one and two are the lighter stages of sleep. And then on the other
hand, we have rapid eye movement sleep or REM sleep, which is named not after the popular Michael
Stipe pop band, but because of these bizarre horizontal shuttling eye movements that occur
during this stage of sleep, these rapid eye movements. So you have these two different types
of sleep and they will essentially, as you fall asleep here in at the sleep center at Berkeley,
they will go into essentially a battle for brain domination throughout the night.
And that cerebral war between non-REM and REM is going to be won and lost every 90 minutes and then
replayed every 90 minutes to create what we call a standard cycling architecture of sleep,
or what we call a hypnogram of sleep. And so what you will see is that upon falling asleep,
you'll go into the light stages of non-REM stages one and two.
Before we do that, let's say before I fall asleep, when I'm just laying in the bed,
how would you describe my brainwaves under the wakeful condition?
So at that point, what we typically see is that when you close your eyes,
the back of the brain goes into what's called an alpha rhythm. So when you're awake, your brain
shows this remarkably frenetic, high frequency electrical activity. In other words, your brain
is going in terms of its brainwaves, it's going up and down many, many times a second. And
the amplitude is?
And the amplitude is very small, which kind of is paradoxically to think,
if I'm awake, then my brain is active. And so the size of those brainwaves should be big.
It's not, it's actually very small. And here's the reason. Different parts of your brain are
doing different things at different times. So those brainwaves sort of are all canceling each
other out. So the analogy would be, if I were to dangle a microphone above a sports stadium,
what I'm picking up is the signal from the crowd of a hundred thousand individual neurons that sit
underneath it. That's how an EEG electrode is. Now, before the game starts, that's wakefulness.
And at that point, the hundred thousand people in the stadium, the hundred thousand brain cells,
they're all speaking to each other at different moments in time.
So there's a lot of cancellation.
So there's a lot of cancellation. They're not all coordinated, but it's very fast and
frenetic. So I just get this signal that is very desynchronized and it's not synchronous.
So they're not summing their power together. So the size of that brainwave is not very big,
but the frequency is high, meaning that you're sort of going up and down maybe 50, 60 times per
second. Now, as you start to fall asleep or actually even before you start to fall asleep,
as you're lying in bed awake, the back of the brain is the first part of the brain that really
starts to settle down. It goes into what we call alpha rhythm when you close your eyes.
And I assume that's just because the occipital cortex is in the back and you've closed your eyes.
Brilliant. So the back of the brain, visual brain, if you close your eyes, that part of the brain
essentially stops processing the outside world and it goes into its sort of default state. When it's
awake of slow frequency, it drops down from maybe 50 times per second down to about, let's say,
10 cycles per second. But still relatively low amplitude? But still relatively low amplitude.
Then once you start to actually transition, when you make that bridge from the world of wakefulness
to sleep, as you sort of cross through that window from one of those worlds to the next,
something bizarre happens. And if anyone out there is lucky enough to be listening to this
and they have a bed partner, you can actually see this. Just look at their eyelids as they're
falling asleep. And what you'll see is that their eyeballs start to roll in their sockets
and they're called slow rolling eye movements. Now we don't know why the eyes roll in the sockets
like that, but it's the first sign that you're making the transition from the world of wakefulness
into sleep. We use it as almost an indicator of the transition into sleep. Now, by the way,
if your partner wakes up, sometimes people will wake up from that state and they see you just
looking over them in bed, staring at their eyelids. If you're in early in a relationship,
it's usually the end of the relationship. Just a point of note, please don't blame me. Usually
wait till you're married and then start to do that one. The divorce usually is harder to come by.
Then you start to go down into the light stages of non-REM sleep, stages one and two. Then after
about 20 or so minutes, you'll go down deep into stages three and four non-REM sleep.
And in one and two, have we transitioned out of that alpha wave? Where do we start to see the
thetas and... Theta already happening in stage one. In stage two, you actually go into theta
activity, which is now down from 50 cycles per second, maybe down to just six or seven cycles
per second. The amplitude's getting a bit bigger, is it? It is getting a bit bigger, yeah. Then every
now and again during stage two, the way that I know that you're in this lighter stage of non-REM
sleep, stage two, is that you'll get these synchronous bursts of electrical activity that
we call sleep spindles. That's the K-spindle. That's where you get this... Actually, you get
a nice big slow wave, almost like a single slow wave, and then you get this burst of a sleep
spindle. We actually did this great project here at the Sleep Center where we did the sonification
of sleep. We extracted brainwaves from human beings, and then we smoothed them a little bit
with some audio software, and then you can play them back. It's beautiful because when you hear
these sleep spindles, they are these short synchronous bursts of electrical activity that
last for about a second and a half, and they go up to about 10 or 15 cycles per second.
It's almost like that beautiful rolling R in the Hindi language, like a cat pairing.
You get these big slow waves, and then you get this ripple of a spindle. When you hear it on the
speakers, it's just sensational. You get this...
Every time I hear it, this is spine-tingling stuff when you realize this is going on right now,
physiologically, in someone's brain. Then from there, you start to go down to the really deep
stages of non-rheum sleep, stages 3 and 4. At that point, the brain goes into this incredible
synchronous mantra chant of these slow waves. The brainwaves slow down. You go down to maybe just
one or two cycles per second. Very, very slow brainwave activity, but the size of those waves,
crashing on the beach of the cortex, as it were, they are huge. The reason is this. Go back to the
sports stadium analogy. Let's say that we're here at Berkeley and we're playing Stanford arch rivals.
Hopefully, you're going to kick their butt. Fingers crossed.
Just make sure there's no band anywhere to be found.
It always does. It's a terrible disservice. At that point, they're chanting in unison.
They're all chanting in unison. It's louder, but they're now making the same sound together.
You can actually hear what's being said. Exactly. Now, in that single microphone,
you can hear Stanford sucks. Stanford sucks. All of a sudden, for reasons that we are only now
starting to understand, the brain coordinates hundreds of thousands of neurons, unlike it does
at any moment elsewhere in the 24-hour period. Hundreds of thousands of brain cells all decide
to join hands, as it were, physiologically, metaphorically. They all fire together,
and then they all go silent. They all fire together, and then they all go silent.
What I find amazing about that, by the way, is how slow that frequency is. This could be only
happening once a second, right? That's right. That's why it got a terrible rap for 20 or 30
years, because it actually looked not dissimilar to some aspects of coma. That's how slow those
brainwaves were. Sleep scientists were understandably fooled into thinking that deep
sleep was a time when the brain essentially was just doing nothing. Now, we realize the exact
opposite is true, because it's during that deep sleep that you get, essentially, information
transfer within the brain. It's a file transfer mechanism. The way to think about this is,
let's say it's like longwave radio. If you're in the city, you tune into FM, which is shortwave
radio. You can pick up a bunch of signals. Then the further you drive out into the desert,
let's say here in California, you just lose those channels, because the range from the tower
is so short that you just lose that range. But if you go onto the longwave radio stations,
you can still pick up stations for hundreds of miles. Why? Because the carrier frequency
of those radio waves is much slower. The distance over which you can transfer information
is much further. Deep sleep is a brain state of long distance information transfer.
ALICE Is there morphologically a difference
that you can see between stages three and four, which are obviously both delta waves,
but how do you distinguish those two?
JONATHAN Technically, no. The way it's defined is that what proportion of a 30-second period of time,
and that's the way that we score sleep, I'll have you sleep for eight hours, then I'll chop up that
eight hours into 30-second bits of information. For each 30 seconds, you'll get a sleep score,
and then we add them all up. What differentiates stage three of deep non-REM sleep from the very
deeper stage, which is stage four non-REM sleep, is simply what proportion of that 30 seconds
is consumed by that deep slow brainwave activity. If it's less than 50%, then it's stage three. If
it's more than 50%, stage four. Morphologically, no. Although, if you really look at it morphologically,
on average, yes. The waves are typically larger in amplitude and slower in frequency in stage four
than they are in stage three.
ALICE Do people always progress
monotonically through these, or do sometimes people go one, two, four, three REM, for example?
You have to go through three to get to four.
ALICE You have to go to three to get to four. You have to go from two to get to three to get to four.
With the exception of probably, let's see, two examples. One is pathological. If you suffer from
narcolepsy, one of the things that typically happens is that you go from being awake straight
into REM sleep. To finish the 90-minute cycle, and this will make sense, you go stage one to stage
two, stage two, three, three, four. Then after about 70 minutes, you'll rise back up into stage
two, and then finally you'll pop up into REM sleep. Then you'll have a short REM sleep period,
and then you'll go back down again, down into non-REM sleep, up into REM, down into non-REM sleep,
up into REM. You do that, as I said, every 90 minutes. However, what changes is the ratio
of non-REM to REM within that 90-minute period as you move across the night, such that in the
first half of the night, the majority of your 90-minute sleep cycles are comprised of lots of deep
non-REM sleep and very little REM sleep. But as you push through to the second half of the night,
now the seesaw balance changes, and the majority of those sleep cycles are comprised much more of
rapid eye movement sleep and almost no deep sleep. That's why it's always dangerous when
people say, I'm one of those who survives on six, six and a half hours of sleep at night. I wake up
five, five, 30 to get a jumpstart on the day. You can ask, well, let's say you're getting six hours
of sleep. How much sleep are you losing? They will say, well, according to your definition of eight
hours of sleep, well, I'm 25% off because I lose two hours at the end of an eight-hour night of
sleep, so I'm losing 25%. Yes and no, because yes, you're losing 25% of total sleep, but you could
be losing up to 70% of all of your REM sleep because it's the REM sleep rich phase that you
are shortchanging to get a jumpstart on the day. So you've got to be very careful when you try to
think of your sleep dynamics. But to come back to your point, sorry, yes, you always have to go
through that linear progression. Norecolepsy is a standout case there. You'll usually go from
wakefulness sometimes immediately into REM sleep. Very frightening. Most people don't experience
logical, rational waking consciousness and then go immediately into irrational,
hallucinogenic consciousness, which is what REM sleep is. It's very disturbing when you speak to
these patients. The other is if you are horrifically REM sleep deprived or chronically sleep deprived,
occasionally you can make the transition straight into REM sleep. We see this in people who are
abusing alcohol heavily, who are alcoholics. Alcohol will come onto this, blocks your REM sleep.
You can build up such a hunger for REM sleep that the brain says, well, tonight I'm going to forego
the non-REM sleep. I'm just going to go and feast on REM sleep straight away. There's hysteresis in
the system, maladaptively so. That's a bad sign when you get hysteresis like that, that type of pressure.
Matt, last time we sat down, you talked briefly about the sleep chronotypes. I've found this
interesting for basically two reasons. One is just observing probably a migration in my own
daughter's chronotype, which is she's getting older. She's sleeping in longer in the mornings
and going to bed later and later. I know that as she gets closer and closer to being a teenager,
that's probably going to increase. But also just more cognizant, I think, of other people.
You've alluded to it briefly earlier, which is like there are just people who are going to go to
bed later and wake up later. It doesn't mean that there's anything wrong with that or there's
anything wrong with the reverse, which is people who go to bed early and wake up really early.
Kind of wondering if there's a way to actually know what chronotype you are
beyond just observation because is it possible that the observation is not your optimal state?
In other words, if you have somebody who's sleeping a certain way because their job is
imposing it, but it's not the way that they're ideally meant to do it. Let me give a better
example. A student in college could easily drift into a later chronotype because everybody in their
dorm room is, even though they may actually be more suited to be earlier. How can one figure
this out? There are genetic tests that will give you a stronger sense of your chronotype.
Chronotype simply means, yeah, are you a morning person? Are you an evening person or are you
somewhere in between? Somewhere between 25 to 30 percent of the population are morning types,
25 to 30 percent are evening types, and then the rest of us are somewhere in between.
Sleep science has then gone a little bit further. We split it into five categories sometimes,
which is extreme morning types, morning types, middle evening types, and extreme evening types.
We know that it is under strong genetic control for two reasons. First, there is a significant
degree of heritability. If you are a morning type, it's more than likely that one or both of your
parents were morning types. Secondly, we now know that there are a collection of genes that will
determine to a degree your chronotype. This is why companies like 23andMe will tell you what type you
are or they will give you a probabilistic estimation of what type you are. Last count, I think, from
data from 23andMe and this data from the UK Biobank, there are about nine different genes that
we know of right now that will contribute to your chronotype. Most of them are what we call
clock genes. This refers to the fact that these genes control the rhythm of your circadian cycle.
Those genes don't control necessarily the size of your circadian rhythm, in other words, how
it's kind of strongly active and awake you are during the day and how deeply down you go at night.
These genes do something different. These genes control when that sinusoidal wave of your circadian
cycle arrives on the clock face. What I mean by that is, if you have a certain type of gene
complement that makes you a morning type, your activation peak, your peak alertness, is going to
arrive earlier in the day and your awesome downstroke of your circadian rhythm will arrive
earlier in the evening. Whereas if you have a different combination of these gene composites,
then you could be an evening type. In other words, your circadian rhythm looks very similar in its
sinusoidal pattern, but when the peak and the trough of that circadian rhythm arrive on the
24-hour clock face is very different to a morning type. We know that there is a complement of genes
that you are given at birth that will determine on average once you're an adult, are you a morning
type or are you an evening type? What you alluded to, however, for your daughter was something
different, which is that no matter what chronotype you are, that innate chronotype rhythm that you
have gifted by your genes will change as you develop from a young child to an adolescent teen
to an adult to an older adult. In other words, you go from being much more of a morning type when
you're a kid, even though you want to stay awake longer, you're found on the couch and you're
carried to bed and you're fast asleep, to then being a teen where your chronotype fast forwards
in time. This is a problem for early school start times where you're putting kids to bed at 9pm and
saying you've got to go to bed because you have to wake up at 5 o'clock in the morning to catch a 530
bus for a 715 start time. Well, there's no point in saying that. It's not their fault that they're
now in bed and it's 1030 an hour and a half later and they can't fall asleep as a 15-year-old
because their chronotype has moved forward in time. They want to go to bed later and wake up later.
Nothing they can do about it. It's biology. And then once they become an adult, it starts to
shuttle back a little bit once they become sort of, you know, moderate age 30 or 40. And then as we
start to get older, we regress. That's why in Florida there's something called the early bird
special where people are going out for dinner at, you know, 4pm or 5pm because their chronotype has
regressed back and they're in bed by, you know, 8pm. So there are genetic tests to come back to
your question. However, you don't need to do a genetic test to get close to understanding what
you are. There is a pencil and paper method that sleep scientists have developed and you can Google
it. It's called the MEQ test and maybe I'll send you the link and we can put it in the show notes.
Yeah, we'll put it in the show notes.
And it's a very simple link that you just click and it's a test. It probably takes about five or
six minutes to fill out. And it's called the MEQ test, the morning eveningness questioner test.
And you go through, you answer a list of questions and at the end you add up your score and it will
tell you what flavor of chronotype you are. And what's nice is that then they've pattern matched
this test and validated it against these genes, these genetic tests. And there's a pretty good
correlation. It's not too far off. So this is the poor man's version of the 23andMe test if you want
it. And we'll do a link in the show notes and you can take it. And that's a cheaper way,
pencil and paper method or an online method. So the bigger question is, Matt, what do we do with
this information? I mean, you've, I think we did talk about this previously at one point that
you have a couple who have different chronotypes that can be really difficult. They're going to
bed and waking up at different times. You've already alluded to the problem of children who
are, I think being subjected to potentially too much early school when in reality they probably
would do better with later school. Is this the kind of thing that should factor into decisions
people make about when they pick classes in college? Like, I mean, it seems like there seems
to be, this seems to be one of those things where there might be a bunch of people that
go through life kind of miserable when they don't have control over their schedule,
as opposed to knowing this. And so would knowing this by itself provide a benefit to folks?
I think it would. I think it would explain a lot about why you struggle so much where other people
seem to be just these energizer bunnies and they've even got time to go to the gym for an hour before
they sit down at their office desk at 7am in the morning. And you're still on your fourth cup of
coffee desperately trying to wake up and you're struggling to make it in by 7.15, having woken up
20 minutes before. And I think the second thing that it helps with is realizing that you're not
culpable. It's sort of non-mere culpa. It's not your fault. You can understand that this is
genetic because a lot of night hours have gone throughout life being chastised and thinking,
well, if only I could get my act together and get to bed earlier and stop being what people tell me
I am, which is slothful or lazy. I could hold down a better job. And again, I think society
needs to be much more understanding of it and also then modifying itself in response to
accommodate it. And neither of those things I see in full serving scoop sizes in society right now.
That should change. And I think COVID is interesting because if there's some positive
upside to it, it may have given us the chance for people to understand how much better they can
sleep when they're closer in harmony with their own chronotype rather than trying to work against
it. Because when you fight biology, you normally lose. And the way you know you've lost is often
through disease and sickness. And I think there is a version of that going on here.
I also think it can sometimes explain incorrect insomnia. Often I'll hear someone tell me if I'm
sort of out in the public, they'll say, well, I suffer from insomnia, I get into bed, and I can't
fall asleep. And I'm wide awake for the first hour and a half. And I need to take some sleeping pills.
And then I'll, I'll say, you know, first thing, I'm not a doctor. But let me just ask you a question.
If you were on a desert island with no responsibilities, nobody to wake up for,
nothing to do. And you could just sleep whenever you want to get up whenever you want. What time
would you normally go to bed? And they would say, well, I would actually like to go to bed at
midnight and wake up around eight o'clock in the morning in truth. But I have to get up for my job,
I have to wake up at six, I'm getting in bed at 10. But I still have this terrible insomnia.
And I say, well, you know, I don't know this, but it's possible that what you could have is not
insomnia, but a mismatch between your chronotype and your working life schedule. And you may want
to explore some of this. And there's a test and meq test and I tell them about this, and then go
and speak to your doctor. So that's the second implication that I think comes from the question
that you asked about how it impacts society. Once you know it, what do we do about it? And what
should we be doing about it? Those are some of the ramifications, I think. I forgot to say in
the episodes before, and I'd love to say it now is about sleep opportunity versus duration. We've
constantly been speaking about in our discussions, how much sleep does a person need? What's the
optimal amount? And we're speaking about somewhere between seven to nine hours. When I say that,
I'm talking about seven to nine hours of sleep. Not time in bed where you might lose 10 to 15%
of it. Right. And this is the reason that when I think people who say, well, surely you can get by
on six and a half hours of sleep or seven hours of sleep, you've got to be very careful because
that's a dangerous statement. This comes to something that we call sleep efficiency. Now,
if you are in your forties, you will probably have, if you're healthy, you'll probably have
a sleep efficiency of what we call 90%. In other words, of the time that you're in bed,
90% of that time is asleep and 10% of the time is awake. So let's take an eight hour sleep period
and you think, well, I'm in bed for eight hours, so I'm good. I'm getting my eight hours of sleep.
That's not true. Eight hours of sleep is what? That's 480 minutes if my math is correct.
If you get a 10% loss of efficiency, it's like a heating system, you lose 10% of it.
You're down to 712.
You're down to 712. So in other words, for you as a 40 year old with a healthy sleep efficiency of
90% for you to get eight hours of sleep, you need to be in bed for eight hours and 48 minutes.
Even a bit longer, actually.
Yeah, or even a bit longer. So you've got to be very careful. That's why I constantly speak about
a sleep opportunity of eight to nine hours in bed to get your seven to eight hours of
total sleep, if that makes sense.
And this is where I think devices like the Oura Ring are very helpful because
that's where they're very good. They're very good at telling you you were in bed this long,
but you're actually only asleep this long. And that's the number we want the patients to fixate
on. We don't even look at time in bed when we give our patients feedback. We're talking about
total sleep time and efficiency. So if there's a problem with total sleep time and efficiency
is low, you have to improve the quality. If total sleep time is low and efficiency is high,
you need more time in bed. And it's getting people to understand that distinction. That's
very important.
And the caveat that comes for people with insomnia, though, that I'm here saying you need to increase
your time in bed, your sleep opportunity, as I call it, to make sure that you get the right
total amount of sleep and you have to accept there is inefficiency in the system and you need
to extend your time in bed to overcome that slight inefficiency. So again, sort of eight
hours and 15 minutes to get your eight hours total sleep. The only time I would say that you should
not be thinking about longer time in bed is if you're someone who is struggling with insomnia
and you're lying in bed awake a lot of the time.
Reprogramming.
We actually do the opposite, which is we actually shorten your sleep opportunity.
We crunch that down. It's one of the tools that we have in the CBTI toolbox.
That's right. So you want to drive the efficiency up by taking the denominator out.
People have lost their confidence in going into the bedroom and sleeping constantly soundly
throughout the night. So what we end up doing is actually constraining them maybe down to just six
hours of sleep opportunity. We put them on a diet of sleep opportunity rather than an extension.
And very quickly what happens. So it's ironic. You come to me and you say, I'm not sleeping well.
And I say, great, I'm going to have you sleep less. And you say ridiculous. It's not what you
do is by compressing that window down, you're sleeping less and you're building up more of
that sleep pressure because as a consequence of the reduction of sleep opportunity time,
you're going to be awake during the day longer, the longer that you're awake, the more of that
sleep pressure you build up. So firstly, you're coming into the following night with even more
sort of sleepiness on your shoulders. And then secondly, I'm teaching the brain,
unlike it's been given luxury time to just be awake as long as it wants to at night and maybe
sleep some. And that's that phenotype of insomnia, awake time at night. By constraining that time,
I start to force your brain to realize, I'm sorry, you no longer have the luxury of having
all of this time to sort of be awake and be asleep. And very quickly, the brain starts to realize and
learn that in fact, it only has this tiny opportunity at the dinner table called sleep that is six hours.
And now you start to brute force efficiency. The brain starts to realize, my goodness,
I've only got six hours. I need to get my sleep into that six hours. So efficiency markedly
increases when you constrain total amount of time in bed. So it's this ironic way that we help treat
insomnia. We constrain total sleep time, you brute force efficiency and a brute force response from
the brain. And all of a sudden, something magical happens. Now that we've set the stage for what
sleep is and why it's so important, the next set of clips will really look at ways in which we can
improve sleep. These clips will look at the pros and cons of napping, proper sleep hygiene, and an
ideal wind down routine, optimal temperature for sleep and how Matt changed his thinking on blue
light. The question now comes down to one of napping, which we did touch on in our previous
episode, but I want to revisit it. Lots of times patients come to me and say, Peter, you have no
idea what a 20 minute nap does for me between two and four o'clock in the afternoon. And my
historical response to that has been, gosh, you really shouldn't need a nap. I mean, if you're
sleeping correctly, isn't that actually a negative thing because it's depleting some of that
adenosine based pressure and wouldn't you be better off letting the pressure cook or cook,
driving you into a deeper sleep when you first take your sleep? So what are your thoughts on
that type of a nap? That sort of short 20 minute, late afternoon, pre-dinner nap?
Naps really are a double edged sword. And we've done lots of studies where we use naps to study
the functions of sleep and we see benefits from naps. Even naps as short as 17 minutes can produce
learning and memory benefits. So there does seem to be some enhancement that you get. And you can
see that from cardiovascular benefits as well. The downside of naps is that it can take away just
what you described, which is sleep pressure. And so the typical recommendation that we have
is the following. If you are struggling with sleep at night, avoid naps during the day. Because what
you want to do if you are already having problems either falling asleep, which is what we call sleep
onset insomnia, or you can fall asleep but you can't stay asleep, which is what we call sleep
maintenance insomnia. You want to build up as much sleep pressure, as much sleepiness as you possibly
can during the day. If you are struggling with your sleep at night, do not nap during the day.
And the pressure cooker analogy is beautiful. Keep building up all of that healthy sleepiness
pressure. Because when you nap, it's like having the valve on the cooker open up and you just
release some of that healthy sleepiness. And now when it comes time to go to bed, you're not going
to feel as sleepy anymore. However, on the flip side, if you are not struggling with your sleep
and you can nap regularly during the day, the advice is naps can be just fine. Because in fact,
if you take a step back from an evolutionary perspective and you study hunter gatherer tribes
whose way of life hasn't changed for thousands of years, they don't necessarily sleep the way that
we do in modernity. In fact, particularly during the summer months, they will typically have an
afternoon nap right in the time zone that you just described. And this is the very much the
Mediterranean siesta like behavior. And in fact, if I stick an electrode on both of our heads
throughout the day, and I monitor our physiological brainwave activity, it'll stick much better to my
head, by the way, than you. Well, yeah, right now, especially because I've got this terrible COVID
hairdo, which I look like I should be out of book Rogers and anybody who remembers that
television show. But anyway, what we will see is that somewhere between about two to four p.m.,
both you and I will have this kind of drop in our physiological alertness, in our physiological
level of brain activity. In other words, as if as a species, we're almost pre-programmed
to have this enforced dip in our alertness. And so many people see this, you know, in the afternoon
meetings around the boardroom table or wherever you sort of get these ugly head nods that start
to happen. It's not people listening to good music. It's just that people have this sort of
they're falling asleep, the falling prey to this what seems to be a genetically hardwired pre-programmed
drop in our alertness, as if maybe we should be what's called biphasically sleeping as a species
at times during the year, rather than monophasically sleeping, which is how we do in most
first world nations. In other words, one single bout of sleep at night versus two bouts of sleep,
which is how those hunt together a tribe sleep, especially during the summer.
And so Matt, would they sleep long enough in that two to four window that they would get a full 90
minutes, say, and get through a full cycle? And then if so, did that mean when they did their
nighttime sleep, presumably they would stay up later and get maybe six hours in the evening
instead of, you know, because people always talk about how well hunter gatherer studies have always
suggested that, you know, seven and a half to nine is the species required amount of sleep on average.
But you're saying it was potentially broken into two chunks. Was that afternoon daytime chunk
or daylight chunk call it about 90 minutes?
No, it wasn't. It was actually typically shorter than that on that basis. But you're right. They
typically are not sleeping. What we currently recommend for monophasic sleep, which is the
average adult should get somewhere between seven to nine hours. That's the recommended range that
we all provide. But what they would typically do is they would maybe sleep just six, six and a half
hours at night. And then they would make the rest up and they would get into that exact same sort
of territory by way of the nap. So they would take it in these two chunks. Now, I should note,
this is very different to something else that's been described in the literature, which is first
sleep and second sleep. That activity does seem to have occurred during our historical past. It
seemed to have emerged in the sort of Dickensian era. That was different, though. That was where
people would sleep for the first four hours. Then they would wake up in the middle of the night.
They would write. They would drink. They would play music. They would make love. And then they
would go back for another four hours of sleep. Did that happen? Yes, it seems to have based on
historical writings. But is that the way our physiology and our circadian rhythms are designed?
No, it doesn't seem to be. There's usually one study that's cited that suggests maybe we should
do that. But overall, the physiology that we know of for human beings doesn't seem to suggest that
that was more sociologically driven rather than biologically driven. Biologically, we may be
biphasic, but very differently, according to this Hunt Together, a sort of tri-pipothesis. By the
way, the other thing that's interesting in those Hunt Together is, and it comes on to what I think
we described before, which is this concept of midnight. Most of us don't think of what the term
means. But in those individuals, it means what the word states, which is, it's the middle of the
night for them, midnight, because they usually go to bed maybe two hours after sundown. And they're
asleep by, let's say, 9pm in the evening or 8.30. And then they're awake just a little bit before
dawn. In fact, what's interesting, and maybe we'll get on to this in later discussions, but
what seems to wake them up is not necessarily daylight. It's the change in temperature,
because there's a rise in temperature that seems to happen before daylight starts to break. And it
seems to be it's the temperature change that they are much more buckled to in terms of regulation
of their sleep weight rhythm. And so the way in which the structure of their sleep by phasing is
different to ours in modernity. And the timing of their sleep is different to some of our timing.
For many people, midnight is the time that you think, well, I should just check Facebook one
last time, or send my last text. That's what midnight means. But normally for a couple of
thousand years, or hundreds of thousands of years, it probably meant that was the middle
of your solar cycle, and it was the middle of your sleep cycle.
I'm glad I'm closer to our ancestors. If I could go to bed at eight o'clock every
night and wake up at four, that is a perfect night of sleep for me.
Matt, and on previous episodes, obviously, we went into some pretty good depth on
tricks, tips, etc. Inside our practice, we have a whole sleep hygiene protocol. And
we sort of run patients through it relatively early, especially if they're having any sleep issues. But
do you mind just sort of going through where you are now and how you think about this? And again,
I'll caveat this by saying, you're not a sleep physician. So it is not your practice to be out
there treating any one individual with respect to their sleep. But also, you're infinitely more
qualified than virtually anybody to help people start to think through what the parameters are
that factor into sleep. And that's the way we kind of explain it, which is, look, here are these five
or six levers of sleep. And here's how you could move each of them in your control. But I kind of
want to hear how you think of it. Yeah, so I think in our past episodes, we've gone through
sort of the fine five main sort of sleep hygiene tips. And I'll just quickly go through them here,
because we've dealt with them before, which is regularity going to bed at the same time,
waking up at the same time, getting lots of darkness at night, because we are a dark deprived
society. And I actually think I've done a bad job of describing to the public the importance
of the opposite, which is making sure you get daylight during the first half of the day,
I think that's just as important. Then temperature, we've spoken about that a little bit,
you need to get cool to get to sleep. And it's the reason that you will always find it easier to
fall asleep in a room that's too cold than too hot. You shouldn't stay in bed awake. That trains
your brain to be triggered by your bed and force you awake because you have a learned association.
So if you've been awake for 20 minutes, then get up, go and do something else, and only come back
to bed when you're sleepy is the general rule. And then finally, you know, trying to avoid alcohol
and caffeine in the afternoon and for alcohol in the evenings, as we've said. So those are the
sort of typical tips. But I think if I were to add a few others, the other one that's absolutely
critical that I probably haven't espoused enough is a wind down routine. Because many people in
society expect sleep to be like a light switch, that we should just jump into bed, and we should
just turn off the light and the brain should do something similar and go straight into sleep.
Sleep as a physiological process, if you study it, it's just not like that. Sleep is much more like
trying to land a plane. It takes time to gradually descend down onto that hard foundation of this
thing that we call a stable night of sleep. So give yourself some wind down, opportunity time,
build it into your routine. For some people, it's 15 minutes, others, it's 30 minutes. Light
stretches, meditation, putting all of your phones and your gadgets away, staying clear of any
inbound in the last 30 minutes, whatever it takes, set it up, and then maintain it. Because
if you have kids, you'll know all about this, you know, you have a routine for the kids, and
you've got to try and stick to it. If you break the routine, bad things usually happen with sleep.
We're the same as adults, there's no difference. So I think that's the first thing I would say.
The second, probably, tweak is, if you are struggling with sleep, remove all clock faces
from your bedroom. It's not going to help you to know that it's now 2.35am in the morning,
and you've still not been able to fall asleep. It's only going to trigger more anxiety.
And there's been a nice study here from UC Berkeley, not from my center, but from another
sleep researcher, Alison Harvey, who looked at this in people who were poor sleepers with insomnia.
Removing clock faces can certainly help. The next thing I would say is that try to keep,
of course, all of your technology outside of the bedroom. And if you can, don't make it the first
thing that you check in the morning. Because for most of us, the first thing that we do when we
wake up is that we swipe right, and this flood of anxiety just washes onto us like a tsunami.
And that's problematic, not just because it's a bad way to start your day, but because you train
your brain in this Pavlovian way that every morning, as you're taking yourself into bed at
night, every morning, what's coming to you when you wake up is this jag of what we call anticipatory
anxiety. And it lightens your sleep throughout the night because of that expectation. So try to
avoid that. If you absolutely have to, and again, trying not to be puritanical, take your phone into
the bedroom. One of the other problems is that it causes what we call sleep procrastination,
which is that you're sitting there in bed, you've got your device and you think, well,
I'll just check Amazon and order that thing. I'll just check Facebook and I'll send that last email
and you look up and now it's 40 minutes later. The rule of thumb that a friend, a colleague of
mine, Michael Gradner said, I love this. If you're going to have your phone in your bedroom,
the rule is that you can only use it if you're standing up. And after standing up for about five
or 10 minutes of phone use, you just think, I just want to sit down. I just want to get into bed.
And at that point, the rule is you've got to put your phone away. So those would be sort of three
additional things that I would advise that can really help. I like that a lot. I would actually
add just from a personal standpoint, I've maybe three months ago instituted a little policy for
myself that I've really enjoyed, which is not looking at my phone for an hour when I wake up.
Yes. Luckily, I don't sleep with my phone in my room. So that's not an issue, but it used to
certainly be the first thing I'd go and grab when I got up. And if I get up at five, I won't look at
it till usually after 6am. And that's interesting. I didn't realize that the effect that that could
have on my brain as I'm coming into consciousness, knowing that I'm not going to be flooded with
information, especially the type of information I don't like, which is generally all the information
on my phone. Yeah, I'll just take two additional pins in that. The first is, I think any
everyone has had this experience in the extremities, where you know you've got to wake up the next day
for an interview, or you've got to wake up for a flight that you have to catch. You know for a fact
that firstly, your sleep is going to be shallow, it's not going to be particularly deep. And
secondly, you almost wake up two minutes before the alarm because you're that on edge. Well, imagine
a diluted version of that. But every single day, that's what bringing your phone into the bedroom
and opening it up first thing is all about. The second thing I would say is you're right,
and set manageable goals, I really enjoy the work of a guy called BJ Fogg, who's a researcher at
Stanford who looks at behavioral change. And it's all about incremental. So if you're trying to get
someone to floss their teeth for the first time for dental hygiene, don't say, okay, here's how you
floss, you need to floss before you go to bed. You say all you're allowed to do for the first week is
floss your front two teeth, and you cannot do any more. That's it. And then we say then's the
next, then add two more teeth for the next week, and then two more. The same with sleep. If you are
accustomed to doing this with your phone, which is so understandable for all of the pressures that
we understand from society and social media, start by saying, I'm going to give myself five minutes,
I'm going to firstly not check my phone, I'm just going to wake up, brush my teeth, and make whatever
drink that I have in the morning. And when I sit down, that's when I am gifted the opportunity to
look at my phone, and then try to push it to 10 minutes, and then try to see if you can get
changed, have your shower, wash yourself up, whatever you do in the morning, and only then
open up your phone and keep pushing it longer and longer, make it a manageable goal. Otherwise,
don't set yourself up for failure, do it for success. Yeah, I think the same advice is great
for something like meditation, where for many people saying, hey, why don't you commit to 20
minutes of meditation a day? I mean, that's almost impossible out of the gate. But if it's,
hey, meditate every day, and if you do a three-minute meditation, you're better off doing three
minutes a day than 20 minutes once a week. I think it's the same sort of idea, which I agree,
I think it becomes a lot easier. The last thing I would say is that none of these tips that we've
spoken about, which are typically sleep hygiene tips, are going to work if you actually have a
sleep disorder. So the analogy here, again, from a colleague, if I'm an athletic sports coach,
and I'm giving you all of these tips for improving your performance, but you've got a broken ankle,
none of them are going to make any difference to your performance until we actually get you to a
doctor and fix the broken ankle. It's the same with a sleep disorder. If you have insomnia,
or if you have sleep apnea, none of these things that I've been talking about are going to help
you. If you suspect that you have either one of those, definitely go and see your doctor,
see if you can get some kind of sleep intervention. Okay, let's shift on to temperature. We have a
ton of questions on this, including one of my patients who has specifically asked me to ask
you a bunch of questions on this. So I'm looking at all these questions, of which there are so
many, and I want to start at the top rather than... So I'm going to kind of mix up the order a little
bit on these. And this question in particular, I think is a great foray into the discussion.
The question is, did our ancestors get better quality sleep during certain times of the year
and or in certain climates? So for example, Death Valley in the summer, and I don't know how many of
our ancestors were spending that much time there, hopefully not too many, but presumably there are
hot places, cold places, et cetera. So I think what this question is obviously getting at is there's
a general belief that we sleep better when we're colder. There must have been a number of times
when our ancestors were either in places that were not cold or in places where at least during
a season it was warm. What can we infer or impute about sleep quality and temperature from that?
So the best taste that we have right now, again, comes back to some of these hunter-gatherer tribes.
Some of them live at different latitudes. And the best data that we have are folks who are very
close to the equator. And at that point you think, well, how is this going to answer the question?
Temperature variation where they're at is still quite significant from summer to winter. It turns
out it's just more about sort of, yes, rainy season and dry season, but the temperature does
fluctuate by some degrees too. And you can look at other communities that are a little bit further
out. But here's what we find in the summer. Typically, yes, they actually sleep less when
it's hotter, which is going against what needs to happen to your core body temperature to get good
sleep. It needs to drop and it needs to get cold. During the hotter seasons, they typically sleep
less at night. And then they seem to try and do some recovery by doing a short afternoon siesta.
But when they switch over to the winter season where it's cooler, it's a little bit darker,
but not that much. But it's really the temperature when they get cooler, then they sleep longer at
night. And the frequency with which they have daytime naps actually decreases. So I think that's
the best evidence that we have right now from just sort of going back to basics, homo sapiens,
what was going on in terms of temperature, the seasons give us the experiment, and the data
favors coldness for longer sleep. When you now bring that question to a laboratory,
where presumably you can take and someone has done this, I'm sure where they've taken subjects
and basically develop the optimization curve of all things equal but temperature,
there must be an optimization. There's probably temperatures at which you reduce latency. So
it's easier to get to bed, but maybe temperatures where it's harder to stay asleep. For example,
using myself as an example, I actually like to be really cold when I get in bed. And if I am,
it might take me a little longer to fall asleep a minute or two, but it almost guarantees I'll
sleep in a more uninterrupted fashion throughout the evening. There are times when I get into bed,
and this is again, not true at home because I can control the temperature in my home, I have
more difficulty controlling it here, for example, like we're in Bakersfield, it's hot as Hades,
the last two nights, and again, it could be the excitement of racing. But I also feel like I've
been waking up a little warm and I don't have my chili pad, I don't have that little cooling pad
on my blanket. I've had no issues with latency, but I'm waking up early. So if you run through
all the permutations and combinations of this, can one say there is an optimal room temperature
or air temperature or skin temperature or something that we should be driving towards?
So right now, the data that we have is somewhere around about 65 to 67 degrees is optimal for the
sleep of most people. Now there's going to be variability there for sure. And we know this,
we can see this in the data too. But it's actually even a little bit more complex than that.
And there've been studies that people have done where they almost strap in what looks like a
wetsuit, but it's got all of these veins that run throughout them. And we can calculate this water.
I think we've spoken a little bit about this before, where you can exquisitely control the
temperature hot or cold at any part of the body. And I'll summarize the findings as the following
in terms of temperature. It's a three-part story. For your extremities, you need to warm up to cool
down to fall asleep. Then you need to get cold to stay asleep, and then you need to warm up to wake
up. And so the reason that you may be finding latency easier here, but quality of sleep thereafter
worse is because it's counterintuitive. How do I drop your core body temperature? I'm going to tell
you, I'm going to warm you up. But the reason is because if you take a hot bath or a shower,
all of the blood is charmed to the surface of your skin and it radiates the heat out of the
core of your body. So in fact, your core body temperature plummets. It's the reason that hot
bath is great, not because you're toasty in bed. It's because your core body temperature is
plummeting once you get out. So this is why sometimes having a cold room but socks on,
or a cold room with a hot water bottle at the end of your bed, just to warm the feet, because it's
the feet and the hands that need to get a little bit warm to bring the blood, because they are the
best radiators of heat out of your body. So when we warm the pores of rats, for example, they fall
asleep faster because you're charming the heat out of the core of the body. So the answer to the
question really is a little bit more complex. Keep the room cool, warm yourself up a little bit
inside of bed to radiate that heat out and get you to sleep quicker. That will make the latency.
You fall asleep faster, in other words. Then the ambient temperature will keep your body cold
throughout that middle section and later section of sleep. And then if you have a sort of a smart
thermostat, you can rise that temperature, I would say actually quite late in the game, in the perhaps
in the last 20 minutes or the last 15 minutes. And that will try to rocket your temperature out
and bring you, you will wake up easier and feel less groggy if that temperature is higher. Now
it's hard because the ambient may not necessarily change much of what's going on under the covers,
but it's the reason that most people when they wake up, they would like a hot drink, even sometimes
in the summer, because the hot drink for the most parts, and people are just using caffeine and
that's what they think keeps them awake. But some of that benefit of the caffeine is actually not
caffeine. It's just the hot drink itself that is helping bring back up the core body temperature
that makes you feel more awake. So can we quantify the following? Someone comes to you and they say,
Matt, I'm doing all of these things off my checklist, but currently I sleep at a room
temperature of 75 degrees. How much better would you predict I would sleep if my room temperature
went from 75 to 65? So I think the hard part of this equation, and some people may face this too,
if they look at their data from sleep trackers, you're going to be sleeping better. We know
this is using population statistics for an individual, so this is always dangerous. And
I never want to sort of fall into that fallacy, but let's go with it. On average, people are more
likely to sleep considerably better at 65 than 75. Do you say that in terms of duration or stage
quality or what metric? So that's where the devil is in the details, because some people will see
it in terms of quantity, particularly the quantity of deep sleep. So when we do these studies, that's
where you see some of the greatest benefits for the cooling down throughout the night. That's where
sort of the thermal gradient can be beneficial. But what's not told is that the largest effect
size is not really in quantity, which is minutes, which is what your sleep tracker, your wristwatch,
or your ring will tell you. And you have to be very careful to judge the efficacy of that
experimental change on the basis of quantity and minutes. Because if anything, when you look at the
data, where you really see the effect is less so in minutes, which is quantity. Instead, it's in
quality, which is measured by the electrical brainwave signature. Now your wristwatch or your ring
is not going to be giving you that detail. So if you assume that the drop in temperature
has given you a nominal percentage benefit in terms of your deep sleep time, and therefore you
don't think it's worthwhile, I think you may want to sort of just second check that logic, because
there we're seeing it's qualitative that's more beneficial. And you as an individual, it's very
difficult for you to sense that qualitative change because you're non-conscious, of course. And
there's no good trackers out there right now that you can work typically on your periphery
that will tell you that metric. So with that said, it's not necessarily that hard of a question,
because I'm constantly trying to run these calculations about all of my scientific sleep
beliefs and think about these three buckets. I think the thing that I've probably changed
my mind on most or had a reversal on is the effects of blue light on our sleep. And in fact,
in the book, I spoke about a study at the time that had been done out of Harvard, which I still
think is valid, where they'd used an iPad, where you read on an iPad for an hour versus you read a
book under dim light. And they showed that that iPad had this detrimental effect on sleep, it had
delayed the release of melatonin, it had caused a reduction in REM sleep. And even when they stop
reading the iPad, it had a blast radius to it where the sleep quality was still bad for a couple
of days afterwards. And it was a compelling study and published in a good journal. But over the
years, I think there's been some research that's pushed back on that. And there's been some great
work from a university in Australia called Flinders University. And Michael Gradsdorf has done some
just great work on this at Flinders. He has changed my mind. I'm less bullish now about the idea that
these devices that we use are sleep disruptive because of the blue light. I still think that
has an effect. But what I think he's shown in some elegant work is that it's less about the light,
it's more about the fact that these devices are just so activating, that these devices are designed
to trigger alertness, and what we call physiological arousal in the brain. And in other words, what
happens when we use these devices, the reason that they're so disruptive to our sleep is less
about their blue light. It's more the fact that we are masking our sleepiness with this overriding
artificial activation from the devices. In other words, let's say that all of a sudden, it's 10pm
and you think, I'm wide awake, I'm on my computer, I'm working, I've got my phone next to me, I'm
checking it, it's pinging, it's dinging. All of a sudden, all of the lights go out, there's a massive
electromagnetic pulse that curses across your environment. It knocks out all of the devices,
you've got no phone, no iPad, no electricity. I suspect that within about 15 or 20 minutes,
you'd start to feel sleepy. And it's not because of the blue light effects, it's the fact that you
are, and you were all along, sleepy. But these devices, because they're so activating,
was creating a competing force that hit the mute button on the sleepiness, and it activated you.
So I've actually down-regulated my belief in the effects of blue light. And I've introduced this
new mental framework regarding the effects of the invasion of technology into our evening lives and
our bedrooms. And I'm much more now in our world with this idea that they are mentally stimulating
rather than blue light emitting. Forgive my ignorance for this question, but has the experiment
not been done where you've taken groups of subjects and you've subjected one group to just a blue light?
So an actual blue light that's hitting, I forget how many nanometers that is, but the actual...
Right, and the shorter that wavelength, yeah. Yeah. And then you have another group that is
just being blasted with red light, and then you have another group that is just being blasted with
a regular LED and white light. So you're getting the same intensity of light,
but you're moving the wavelength, and therefore you're nullifying the stimulatory effect of what's
being read or looked at. I mean, to me, that experiment would eloquently demonstrate whether
or not blue light per se is the problem. Has that not been done? It has. So people have played around
with the wavelength of the light, and what we believed is that it's the cooler blues, the shorter
wavelength light that are most detrimental. And the reason that screens were blamed is because
they are LED based, which is enriched in the lower visible light spectrum, the shorter wavelength,
in other words, the cool blues. And that's why the blame came because it was stamping the brakes on
melatonin, especially powerfully. And those studies were done. They were done by Chuck Seisler and
Steve Lockley from Harvard years ago, and that led to this sort of belief. And I still think
there's good validity in that. And by the way, there was a couple of studies that came out in
animals that were now suggesting at least, I think it was in rats or mice, I could be wrong,
or if it was in fruit flies, I apologize, where they actually found the opposite, where they found
that the warmer color lights had stronger blocking effects on melatonin. It began this sort of
controversy, had we got it wrong about blue light. And then this work from Flinders University,
from Michael, was coming online regarding this cognitive component. And it really sort of made
me shift my belief system. So yes, those studies have been done. And they principally looked at
melatonin. I think they studied less a full night of sleep with polysomnography and really asked the
downstream consequences. They were just simply saying, how does it affect your melatonin,
which is maybe one step short of saying, how does it then affect as a consequence of that change in
melatonin, your subsequent sleep, without necessarily doing a much more sophisticated
study, which I think are now being done, where you do the coke Pepsi challenge of
same amount of light stimulation. So light is standardized, right? Light becomes the variable
that's the only independent variable. That's right. And then you start measuring independent
variable at polysomn and melatonin for what it's worth and do everything.
ALICE And then you do a second round of studies where light actually becomes the constant
stimulus where you maintain the same light exposure. But in one condition, you're doing
something cognitively activating, like building a Facebook account or checking that versus you're
simply just there in front of the blue light. But there's no cognitive stimulation to really do the
two by two disambiguation of that. I think those studies are coming, but that's one of the things
where I've definitely changed my mind, I think, and I felt compelled to now speak more about that
and less about the blue light. The last set of clips will shift our focus to look at the effect
that caffeine can have on our sleep and the dangers of sleeping pills. If you found yourself enjoying
these clips and want more content, we have seven episodes with Matt, including three AMAs. These are
great pieces of content to go back to and listen to if you want to scratch this itch a little bit more.
ALICE The other place where I think I've changed my mind and maybe even some of my behavior
is around coffee and caffeine. The evidence has continued to mount and it's un-ignorable.
And now, again, these are mostly associational epidemiological studies, which both you and I
know are problematic for lots of different reasons. But they're so consistent that if you look at
coffee drinkers, they reliably de-risk a whole constellation of diseases that you want to avoid.
And yes, there is a dose dependency to it where once you get past three or four cups,
then things go in bad directions or the opposite direction at least. But for the most part,
there seems to be this set of very clear associations between low-to-moderate caffeine
consumption and de-risking health disease conditions. How on earth does this square with
Matt Walker's espousing of caffeine's impact on sleep and the fact that a lack of sleep seems
to be associated with many of those same conditions? The go-between here is that caffeine,
of course, can disrupt your sleep. So I've kind of modified my beliefs a little bit.
I think caffeine consumption is actually not only just fine, but maybe to be encouraged if there is
more causal evidence. I think you and Tim Ferriss would speak about this idea that the dose makes
the poison. And that is true with caffeine. But I also think there's a second variable here,
the dose and the timing make the poison when it comes to caffeine. If you're drinking it later in
the day, then I don't think we would see those same health benefits. We would see health detriments
and we don't have the data to help to find that. But then I've added a layer of complexity to that
after listening to a good friend of mine and a writer here in Berkeley, Michael Pollan,
who wrote a book on Audible that you can hear called Caffeine. And it goes into great depths.
And we spoke about this. He interviewed me for the book. He believes that the health benefits,
which are very hard to deny of caffeine, are not really due to a cup of coffee. It's actually the
fact that the coffee bean itself carries with it lots of antioxidants. And in fact, the reason
that you get these health benefits is because the antioxidants take a joy ride on the good bus of
this thing called caffeine. And his belief is that for Americans, for many Americans who don't get a
balanced diet, coffee in the morning may be one of the only primary sources of antioxidant consumption.
And that's why you see the health associations. And in fact, I looked at a fantastic review from
2017. And what they found was that in fact, decaffeinated coffee, which carries the same
antioxidant load, but without the caffeine, has many health benefit associations with it,
which then started to make it all a bit more nuanced that perhaps it's more about the antioxidant
benefit rather than necessarily the caffeine benefit. But there is certainly an association
with coffee that I think makes me more likely to tell people it's fine to be drinking a couple of
cups of coffee in the morning. Please do that. In fact, if anything, there seems to be some health
benefits. I think it's probably because of the antioxidant benefits, but I've changed my mind
that too. I think I've become more relaxed. And in fact, I've now started to drink decaffeinated
coffee in the mornings. And is the reason you're not drinking caffeinated coffee because it just
activates you too much or because you still fear it will, and because you fear it will impact your
sleep negatively? Yeah, it's because I still fear that it impacts my sleep negatively. There was a
study by a good colleague of mine at the University of Surrey in England called Dirk Jandayk published
many years ago. And they were actually dosing people with caffeine at seven o'clock in the morning.
And they could still pick up in the signal of subsequent deep electrical sleep that following
night, a reduction in the quality of that deep sleep. So I think again, it depends on who you
are. There are genetic differences in how quickly people metabolize caffeine. And I think I'm someone
who may be on the moderate end of the sensitivity spectrum. So I typically stay away from it. But
other people I think probably don't have that same sensitivity in morning coffee consumption.
Caffeine is fine.
Well, thank you, Orrin Hatch, for the supplement industry. We owe you a debt of gratitude. And I
hope you can hear the sarcasm in my voice. I think most people now are wise to it. And we certainly
spoke about it at length in the original episodes about the real downside of things like Ambien,
Lunesta, these drugs. In fact, very recently, I just saw something in the news that tried to tally
up the number of deaths that could actually be attributed to these things. So I mean, I feel very
comfortable telling patients that I would rather you stick your genitals in a grinder than you take
Ambien or Lunesta.
There's always the point in taping a podcast with P. Sretir where it just comes to one of these
wonderful crescendos, the things that I think about, but I have no bravery to say. And he just
comes out and says them. And this is part of the reason I adore him as a friendly colleague.
Yes, I really hate these drugs. I really hate them. By full disclosure, I still prescribe them
on occasion to patients who really insist on having them as a safety net. I would not let
any patient have those and I can monitor by prescription. There's no patient I'm going to
take those drugs every night. And maybe if they needed a couple of nights a month as they're
traveling and such, we work really hard to get them off it. But let's talk about sort of the
softer things that people often rely on consistently for sleep aids. What about things like Benadryl
or Advil PM? I get a lot of questions about that here. I don't think we would argue that those are
good for sleep. I think that maybe we could frame the question as how bad are they for sleep?
Yeah. So firstly, to come back to Ambien and sort of its collection, Lunesta, all of those classic,
what we call the sedative hypnotics. In fact, you're right. I think it was nine days ago from
the point that we're speaking right now, the FDA updated its mortality risk warnings regarding
those sleeping pills because of this increased risk of death, both acutely for a number of reasons,
but also this data are just chronically in terms of far greater cancer. We also see in part, I think
it's probably because of a weakening of the immune system. And I think we spoke about this before.
The irony is that sleep is incredibly powerful in boosting the whole collection of weaponry
in your immune system. Yet when you sleep and sleep longer with those sleeping pills,
you would imagine your immune system gets even better. The opposite seems to be true. It gets
worse. And the reason we know this is because there's higher rates of infection in those patients
who are taking sleeping pills scales with the degree of use and dosage. So I would say trying
to use those as a very last resort. Now, there are some patients for whom alternatives don't
seem to work. And for a short period of time, that seems to be recommended right now by the
medical community. But I should also note that in 2016, the American College of Physicians made a
landmark recommendation that they said based on the health risks and the concerns together with
the nominal benefit of those sleeping pills above and beyond placebo, sleeping pills must no longer
be the first line recommendation for insomnia. It has to be something else called cognitive
behavioral therapy for insomnia or CBT, which we can come back to in a second, which I've had
three patients go through formal CBT with great success. It's a non-pharmacological, it's a
psychological method. You work with a therapist and they try to understand where your sleep
problems are at and create a bespoke solution for you, the individual. So there's lots of tools in
the CBT box that we can use to try and help people sleep better. And because everyone who has sleep
problems is usually a little different from one person to the next, you have to create a more
Savile Row tailored suit for that person in terms of that sleep prescription, quote unquote. But
it's just as efficacious as sleeping pills in the short term. But what's better is that when you
start working with your therapist, those benefits can last. Now, I think the last report was maybe
somewhere between up to five years that you can maintain that benefit, unlike sleeping pills,
where when you stop them, you not only go back to the bad sleep that you had,
it's usually even worse. It's called sleep rebound insomnia.
How do you recommend people find good CBT eye therapists? Because like all things therapy wise,
the practitioner matters. Now I've been very fortunate because we work with this amazing sleep
doc named Vic Jane in Chicago and wherever my patients are, if it's San Francisco, New York,
he knows the best therapist and he just makes that introduction, plugs us directly in. But if
you're listening to this and you're thinking, I live in St. Louis and boy, would I really benefit
from this? How can a person listening figure out there's a just trial and error. You just have to
go through people until you find someone who's really clicking with you. So one of the things
that we can do, maybe in post in the show notes, there is a website that comes out of the American
Academy of sleep medicine. And there is one page, it's not that easy to find, but I know the link,
so I'll send it out. And you go to that link and you insert your zip code into this website. So
this is of course, just for people in America. And it will return the closest certified centers
by the American Academy of sleep medicine for sleep disorders, including CBT eye. And you can
give it a radius and you can give it a distance. Tell me where's close. And they will give you the
sleep centers to contact, contact them. And you can go from there. And what should you look for
in terms of, cause we know that all doctors are not created equal. All mechanics are not created
equal. All lawyers are not created equal. How does a person evaluate their own individual or is it
simply through the results? I mean, right now it's going to be in part trial and error. And I would
say have a conversation with two or three potential CPTI therapists and just try them on
for size and see how they work. If you can get any referrals right now, sometimes you can even go
onto places like Yelp or other places where you can get some reviews to some people. If they're
motivated to write, it's usually because they had a bad experience. So keep that bias in mind. But I
would say, if you can get a referral from a friend or a colleague, that's a fantastic way to go to,
and then speak to these people and ask them about their success rates and ask them also,
where have you found problems with your patients? Which patients have you typically had the hardest
difficulty with in terms of the profile of sleep problems? And if they sound like you,
then maybe you want to look elsewhere as well. But CPTI over sleeping pills for sure. In terms of
things like Tylenol PM or Benadryl is, Benadryl is typically used. There is a little bit of evidence
that Benadryl induced sleep also has some of the risks associated with it that sleeping pills have.
It's less potent in terms of that bad consequence and outcome to sleep, but the bad consequence and
outcome remains statistically significant in those reports. So I would shy away from things
like Benadryl as well. Tylenol PM, I just don't think there's good enough data yet to suggest
that it's either good or bad. And what about low doses or intermittent use of benzodiazepines,
either short acting ones like Ativan or longer acting ones, Xanax or longer acting ones like
Valium? I talk about this in my jet lag protocol when I'm doing heroic bursts of jet lag, 12 hour
time zone difference. And I have to put myself to sleep. We talked about the entire routine around
exercise and caffeine and going to sleep immediately, getting on the plane. And I use
phosphatidylserine and I use the Kirk Parsley stuff. And I'll also use Valium to just make sure
I am out. And what are your thoughts on the short term use of benzos, again, paired with these other
agents around jet lag? I don't think anyone's really advocating they be used in any ongoing
manner either. Certainly not. Yeah. Infrequent use, I suppose it depends on how infrequent in
one of the studies by a guy called Dan Kripke, who is actually emeritus here in San Diego.
He just looked at not only whether use of sleeping pills was detrimental to mortality. He looked at
the frequency of how often you were taking those. And what he was finding is that even anywhere
between three to 18 pills per year carried a statistically significant increase in mortality
risk. And did he put benzos in the same category as the Ativan Lunestas? He did, yeah. So he sort
of has broken some of that stuff down and broken it out too. I would say in truth, see how far you
can really get with all of the other kaleidoscope of possibilities of sleep enhancing possibilities
that we've discussed. And if those fail, then I think you can think about less resources, but
those drugs typically just are not producing natural sleep. So I would think of those
medications like that box on the wall that says break glass in terms of emergency. If you're in
that situation and you're really struggling, then it's possible that that's the time to break glass.
But those shattered shards can sometimes still be. You can still cut you. What about GHB or Zirim
Irem as a precursor? This is a drug that is incredibly potent in patients with narcolepsy.
Zirim is available by prescription. Of course, unless you have narcolepsy, you're going to pay
an unbelievable amount. It's one of the funniest sort of economic incentives imaginable. But
several listeners have asked, and several of my patients actually have asked about
does Zirim actually produce appropriate sleep staging? What's the data on that?
So the data, if you look at it, almost looks like Zirim is a great drug or GHB is a great
drug for increasing the amount of deep sleep that you have, mostly because it puts your brain into
a more sort of sedated slow rhythm, which a sleep technician, if they didn't know that you were on
Zirim, would look at it and say, that looks not dissimilar to deep slow wave sleep. So I'm going
to score it as I'm sort of scoring these eight hour sleep records. I'm going to score it as deep
sleep. So overall, in terms of total amount of sleep, GHB or Zirim does seem to actually
increase the amount of slow wave sleep time that is scored by a technician. And I'm being very
technical in my language because I want to be precise in this regard. However, if you look at
the electrical signature of that sleep, which is now independent, so when a sleep technician scores
a trace, they have a set of criteria that they use to define which stage of sleep each 30 second
epoch of time, each 30 second window of time there is throughout that eight hour period. And they
scroll through it 30 second page by 30 seconds and they score each of those. They add them all up.
That's what gives your sleep profile and sleep score. So using the criteria that we've had now
for about 60 or 70 years, they will score more of your sleep as being quote unquote slow wave sleep
when you are on GHB because it seems to produce what looks like slow brainwave activity. And by
that criteria, they have to score it as such. But if you unbuckle yourself from this kind of
standard sleep scoring criteria and a human and you just let an algorithm process the electrical
signature of that sleep, it now does not look like naturalistic sleep. And in fact, if there's
anything that we've seen that Xyrem seems to be detrimental to, it's actually these things called
sleep spindles. Now sleep spindles are these short synchronous bursts of electrical activity that
happen during non REM sleep. They last for about a minute or a minute and a half. And we know from
the work that we've done and other people have done, they are critical for things like learning
memory and brain plasticity. And what we found is that when you take GHB or Xyrem, the amount of
sleep spindle activity is decreased often. This shows up sort of at the end of as you're
transitioning from theta to delta, does this typically occur? Actually, what happens is usually
sleep, sleep spindles at the end of a deep slow wave. So you've got all of these slow waves that
happen during deep non REM sleep. And typically what happens is that sort of once you've hit the
peak of that slow wave, you will often have a little bit of a spindle burst. And in fact,
those two things couple, it's called phase amplitude coupling. So at the peak of the
deep slow wave on its awesome rise up, that's the burst. That's when you get the burst additionally
of the sleep spindle. So if I could convert it to a sound, which we've done, you would get these slow
waves, which would sort of sound like, and then often riding on top of those slow waves, you'll
have a sleep spindle. So you'll sort of have like, and that is the sleep spindle. It's this burst of
faster frequency activity. And the coupling of those two seems to be critical in terms of things
like long term memory transfer, shifting memories from short term to long term. So you protect them
and make them safe. Those spindles also seem to have a role in terms of triggering the strengthening
of connections between brain cells, something that we call brain plasticity or long term
potentiation within the brain. And when you are blocking those sleep spindles, the idea would be
that you're preventing typical memory and brain plasticity events that occur. So once again, you
can see that. So it's kind of a lesser of two evils. It's you take a patient who's got narcolepsy,
if the alternative is they're constantly falling asleep at the point where they can't function
normally. Well, maybe we have to give up something. But again, what I'm hearing you say is if you're
an individual whose sleep is not fully optimized, assuming you can afford xyrem, which pretty much
no human being can afford it, that's just not the solution either. We don't have deep sleep in a pill.
That's right. Your analogy is a good one. No one would say chemotherapy is good for a healthy
individual. But when you're suffering from cancer, it's the lesser of two evils. The same is true
in narcolepsy. Yes, you sort of the cost reward equation that is in the favor of taking the
medication. Thank you for listening to this week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in
diving deeper into any topics we discuss, we've created a membership program that allows us to
bring you more in-depth, exclusive content without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure
members get back much more than the price of the subscription. Now to that end, membership
benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally kick ass comprehensive podcast show notes that
detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's
show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or ask me anything episodes, hearing these episodes
completely. Access to our private podcast feed that allows you to hear everything without having
to listen to spiel's like this. The Qualies, which are a super short podcast that we release
every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on
previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great way to catch up on previous episodes without having
to go back and necessarily listen to everyone. Steep discounts on products that I believe in,
but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse, and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue
to trickle in as time goes on. If you want to learn more and access these member-only benefits,
you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter,
Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts
or whatever podcast player you listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only
and does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this
information and the materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content
on this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or
treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical
condition they have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures
and the companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.