Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Matt, it's great to finally be able to do one of these in person with you. We've done a lot of
these remotely. We're taking advantage of the fact that you're in Texas for filming a documentary
about aging, which is pretty awesome. So when we knew that this was going to happen, we said,
well, let's take advantage of you being here and let's come up with something that we both talk
about so much over email, which is to say, I don't think a week goes by that we aren't exchanging
an email about some aspect of the relationship or the interspace between nutrition and longevity.
Does that speak to our ignorance? Does that speak to the ubiquity of such content? I don't know.
What does that say about us?
Yeah. I mean, well, I think it's an area that a lot of people are really interested in, and it
certainly intersects with popular culture. So having been in the aging field for a long time,
I certainly recognize how complicated that biology is. And I think the biology of nutrition is equally
complicated. And when you get at the interface of those two, it's really hard, I think, sometimes
to draw a definitive conclusion. So a new paper will come out, and you usually read the papers
before I do, and you're like, hey, what do you think about this? And then we throw it back and
forth. But I think it's hard sometimes to get to concrete answers. So certainly we'll try to do
that today. But I also think this will be a little bit of a theme that there are many things we don't
understand yet about optimal nutrition and how that intersects with optimal health span.
Yeah. And you and I have spent so much time on the podcast speaking about the molecules,
the molecules, right? Of course, our favorite being rapamycin, but all sorts of them, right?
We recently talked about NMN, NR, NAD, we've talked about metformin. And basically, it's easier
almost to ask the questions from the standpoint of geoprotective molecules, because the
intervention is much cleaner. Yeah, absolutely.
Like, are you taking this drug, yes or no? And of course, what's interesting about that, and I think
it speaks to what we're going to talk about today, think about the one drug among those that stands
out, which is rapamycin. Even within that, just I think yesterday or two days ago, you and me and
David Sabatini had a back and forth about timing of the dose, frequency within the dosing schedule,
the dose itself. I mean, even with a drug, it's still very complicated to say, well, what about
during this fate? Because the study I think we were talking about was looking at mice and it was
asking the question of early exposure of rapamycin later in life, constant dosing, intermittent dosing.
That's for a drug and we're still struggling to piece it together. Now imagine trying to ask
that question of your food. Yeah, and I mean, I think we'll obviously talk a lot as well about
the animal models and what they can tell us about what might affect human aging, but the big piece
that gets lost with the animal models on top of all that complexity is the environment, right? So,
we keep these mice in a well-controlled environment, usually relatively pathogen-free, and they live
in that same environment their entire life. Now you think about the human experience where our
environment is extremely complicated. We're constantly getting bombarded with all sorts of
challenges and infectious agents, and our environment changes dramatically throughout
our lives. In fact, maybe this is something we want to touch on. A lot of the epidemiological
studies on optimal nutrition are from 20, 30, 40 years ago, right? The average human environment is
very different today than it was when those studies were done. And how does that potentially
change the interaction between nutrition and health outcomes? I think it's a really interesting
but challenging question to address to anybody's satisfaction, honestly. Yeah, that's actually a
great point. And I made a similar point on a totally different topic, which was all of the studies
that talk about cancer screening are very backwards looking by definition, right? You
have to look at controlled trials that were done in the past, but the technology of radiology is
changing so much. Radiology is a very physics-based field of medicine. And so when you read a study
that talked about mammography for screening, well, and it was a 15-year study, right? So,
it's a great study. Well, by definition, it was done sort of based on 30 to 20-year-old technology
that by the time the study has been completed, you have the follow-up data, you write up the paper,
it doesn't necessarily represent what's happening today. And that's a huge
challenge of evaluating that type of data. Yeah. And in people, because we age so slowly,
there's really not a lot you can do about that if you want to try to do correlative longitudinal
studies of aging, right? Because people age so slowly, the people who are in their
70s today were in their 30s 40 years ago. And so the environment that they were in
is probably quite different than the environment that 30-year-olds are in today. So, there's not
a great way around that. I think the key is to recognize that limitation and be potentially even
more careful about assuming causation from correlation over many decades. Yeah.
So, as a bit of a mea culpa on the topic of nutrition, which is really my least favorite
topic despite the fact that it keeps coming up on this podcast and it's unavoidable,
as I reflect back on my own understanding of this topic, the strength with which I held
convictions over the past more than decade, I would say I've gone in reverse, right? I have looser
and looser convictions as time goes on and I view fewer and fewer things with certainty as time goes
on. And when I think about this problem clinically, I have what I would consider to be an incredibly
simple framework, which is if I'm looking at a patient, I'm asking a question, are you over
nourished or under nourished? Are you under muscled or adequately muscled? And then on... So,
that's a two by two, right? And then are you metabolically healthy or not? That's sort of my
first order question. Now, one of those spaces doesn't really have too many people in it. The
adequately muscled, under nourished, metabolically unhealthy bucket doesn't really exist. So,
it's not... People aren't uniformly distributed in those buckets, but it's a pretty good way to sort
people. And you can't sort someone by looking at them into that bucket, but by looking at them,
doing some functional testing, looking at their biomarkers, and that might include also doing
things like a DEXA scan where you can actually get some objective data, you can pretty quickly
figure that out. And the reason we think that's important is it helps us understand,
do you need an energy deficit? Do you need an energy surplus? What's your protein intake need
to be to achieve that in combination with your calorie needs? And the hardest of those to treat
by far is over nutrition, under muscled. And unfortunately, that's a very common phenotype.
That's a lot of people these days. Yeah. No, I mean, I think that as a general approach,
first order approach, that makes a ton of sense. And I think one of the things that that allows
you to recognize, right, is that the optimal strategy is... There's no one size fits all,
I guess would be the way I'd say it, right? Different people are going to have different needs
nutritionally, and what works really well for one person, may not work at all for another person.
And so I think kind of looking at that level allows you to not have to try to say,
everybody should be doing X, right? So I think that is pretty similar to the way I think about
it. Obviously, I don't practice medicine, and I try not to make recommendations for what people
should do. But in my own life, that's generally the way that I try to approach it as well, and I
hope I'm doing okay. You haven't tested me yet, so you can't tell me which bucket I'm in. But I
think I'm doing okay for my age with my nutritional strategies. And the other thing that I sort of have
realized, similar to what I think you were saying before, is that it's an ongoing learning process.
And so I think it's really important that we be willing to change our beliefs about
nutrition and other aspects of health as more data comes in. So I think if you take that strategy,
then you can be open to the possibility that what you believed 10 years ago,
might not have been exactly right. And maybe we need to tweak it a little bit.
My personal view on nutrition, I'll be honest, I have real trust problems with nutritionists.
And I think it, in part, it stems from, I remember very vividly when I was,
I think it was probably in my early 20s. And I read one of these diet guru books, and it was
the theme, this was, I'm going to date myself, but this was early 90s, I guess.
The theme back then was, you could eat anything you wanted as long as you cut out the fat.
You could have this really high, simple carbohydrate diet, just keep it low fat,
and you'll be fine. And we now know that's exactly wrong. So I think I can't help but
look at a lot of what people, you know, the what I would put sort of on the fad diet side,
the diet gurus, what they're saying today, how do we know 10 years from now, we're not going to look
back on that. And again, be like, that just makes no sense. I think some of us today can look at
some of what's out there and say, that just makes no sense. But, you know, I think, again, this gets
back to the, to what I was saying before, it's not that I, it's not that I would say nutrition
sciences across the board, low quality, I think they're actually really good scientists doing
really good work in this area. It's just a really hard problem. And I do think to some extent,
the biology of aging, and the biology of nutrition do share that, and that they are these are
extremely complicated biological systems that we're, we're trying to understand in the, in the
context of sort of this, this changing environment over time, right? And so, so I don't, I don't
blame the scientists, I just think we have to be really careful to recognize what the limitations
are and not draw really strong conclusions. Like everybody should eat, you know, a low protein
diet, right? That's kind of one of the fads that are out there today. I think that's, that's a
mistake to recommend across the board, you know, nutritional strategies for everyone. I guess the
last thing, sorry, I'm talking a long time here, but I guess the last thing that what you said,
you know, makes, makes me think of as well. And I think this is really important because people
lose sight of this is, you know, exactly what you said, if you can be, you know, somewhere close to
optimal nutritional intake, right? We just say total calories, regardless of composition,
body composition is somewhere close to where it should be. That's, that's a big chunk of what you
need to give yourself the best chance of being healthy going forward, right? You don't have to
optimize every single thing. Now, I know you're all into optimization, and I respect that about
you. I think if you can do that, that's great. But you don't have to to get most of the benefits. And
so I think starting from that big picture perspective, allows you to get most people,
most of the way there. And then when they're most of the way there, you can focus on how do we get
that last 10, 20, 30%, whatever it is. Actually, I couldn't agree with you more, Matt, and I would
argue, and I do argue now in a very different way from where I used to be a few years ago.
You know, there are most things in my life where I don't like the 80 20 principle, you know, my good
friend Tim Ferriss, like he's the king of this, right? He's the king of how can I get 80% of the
learning with 20% of the time. And I've never seen anybody who can do it like Tim, like the guy can
learn a language in a month, he can be 80% proficient in a language in a month, right? I'm
the opposite. I'm the guy who loves the tail. I love the asymptote. I love the perfection of
something. I would say in nutrition, that is exactly not where my interest lies. I agree
that you can just get 80% of this right by focusing on, you know, exactly what we've talked
about and the details, the complete optimization are not worth it. And it's instead better to put
that effort into exercise. That's where I think if you're going to really go down the rabbit hole
and put more of your mental energy, more of your time and more of your focus into something,
you have far more of an ROI on the exercise front than eking out incremental value on the
nutrition front. And I've joked about this before, other guests on the podcast, Lane Norton and I
have had riffs on this back and forth. The people who sit there on Twitter, which I realize is not
a representative sampling of the world. It's simply an annoying vocal group of people
who will waste endless hours debating the finer points of their dietary pet peeves,
who can't do 10 pull ups is amazing. I mean, there should be a rule that says, if you can't deadlift
twice your body weight and do 15 pull ups, you shouldn't be allowed to pontificate endlessly.
You're not allowed to be on Twitter.
About the finer points of nutrition.
You know, we can talk to Elon about that. Maybe that can be a new rule.
Okay, so let's look, I think we've established nutrition matters here. I mean,
but I think at the same time, you know, I think David Allison said it once to me.
It's amazing how little we know about this subject matter, kind of rehashing what we said.
We know that too much and too little are bad. And for most of our existence, we were worried
about the too little problem. The too much problem has become a relatively recent phenomenon.
And they're bad in different ways, like acutely, chronically, they have different limitations.
We know that certain things are toxic, right? Cutely or chronically. Not a lot. We know,
I mean, with definitive clarity, there's not a lot we know beyond those things.
So one thing that seems to be true is, at least from the animal literature,
caloric restriction seems to reproducibly improve lifespan. And so let's kind of talk
about how that came to be as an understanding. Sure. Yeah. So I mean, this area of research is
actually quite old. So that's a hundred years ago. Yeah. The first experiments were published
in the early to mid 1930s, right? Which means they were probably started in the 1920s, right?
So almost a hundred years ago, people were going down this line of thinking of asking,
you know, what is the effect of significant restriction of calories on the aging process
in mammals? So the early studies were all done in rats. And actually, if I remember correctly,
these studies were originally designed from a developmental perspective. So they were really
thinking about malnutrition and its effects on development. And as a byproduct made the observation
that, yes, when you restrict calories in a rat early on in life, they have a smaller body size.
But then if you let them live out their entire lives, this is in the laboratory. And I think
that's really important to keep in mind. You know, they live 40, 50% longer. So we're talking really
significant increases in lifespan. And then the other thing that was appreciated pretty quickly
was not only are they living longer, but they seem to be healthier as they're living longer. So,
you know, this concept of health span and the period of life that is, you know, spent in good
health, free from disease and disability, it seemed as if caloric restriction was not only
increasing lifespan, but also extending health span. So, you know, that led to obviously a large
body of literature since then studying the effect of caloric restriction in not just rodents,
rats and mice, but also all sorts of simpler organisms, invertebrates like fruit flies and
C. elegans and yeast. And the common theme seems to be that, again, starting from laboratory
conditions, if you restrict nutrients by a whole variety of different methods, you can increase
lifespan and apparently increase health span proportionally, at least proportionally. So
there's a lot of nuance there, a lot that we can dive into and to unpack. But I think that's
generally the take home, right? Is that over and over and over again across, you know, the
evolutionary distance we're talking about is much, much greater than the evolutionary distance between
rodents and humans, right? So, over a very wide evolutionary distance in pretty much every
organism where it's ever been studied, you can find evidence that caloric restriction slows aging.
Again, there are cases where that didn't happen, where lifespan wasn't extended, where lifespan
was shortened. Maybe we want to talk about this at some point, the interaction between genetics and
environment and caloric restriction. But in general, that is the take home message is caloric
restriction can slow aging in laboratory animals pretty much everywhere where it's been studied.
The one, I think, question that some people have is whether that's true in non-human primates.
Yeah, so I was just about to say, I was going to say before we get to NIA Wisconsin, which is
perhaps the single greatest experiment that's ever been done to test this hypothesis,
both in terms of its duration, level of control and proximity to our genome.
Let's spend a moment on that. Before we do, any things that come up from the rodent studies that
are worth talking about. So, for example, one of the things that I think is always important to
point out is there's a very particular death that tends to fall on laboratory mice. They have,
you know, if you look at the death bars for humans, there's much more heterogeneity.
But the leading cause is atherosclerosis. Now, that's true in the United States.
It's true across the globe. So, when you mix in, develop and undevelop, it doesn't matter.
Laboratory mice aren't that way. They die of pretty much one thing and one thing alone.
Actually, it's euthanasia, but I know where you're going.
Cancer, right?
Yeah, cancer. They all die of cancer.
Certainly, every old mouse at time of death will have cancer. And again, because of the way animal
studies are done, usually you have defined endpoints where when a mouse reaches that
endpoint, they have to be euthanized. But the expectation is that if they hadn't been euthanized,
they would have died from the cancer. So, I think you're absolutely right.
Yeah, they're not dying from atherosclerotic. When you look at their arteries, they're not
littered with plaques the way ours are.
At least the commonly used inbred mouse strains. That is definitely true for it. There are,
you know, this is maybe getting in the weeds a little bit, but there are certainly
mouse strains that have been designed either transgenically or through selection
to develop other pathologies that will shorten their lifespan. But if you let a typical mouse
strain in the lab live out its natural life, it will have a very high tumor burden at the end of
life. And most likely, you know, I guess I should know this. I don't know exactly. I'm guessing 80%
of the animals would die from cancer. So, it's different from humans in that way.
And I actually think this is, you know, this is a legitimate criticism to some extent of the
interpretation of the caloric restriction literature that is, could it be the case
that really what caloric restriction is doing is preventing cancer. And that's why you see these
big increases in lifespan. And I think that's really difficult to definitively answer one way
or the other. What I would say is, you know, mice do develop functional declines in every tissue
and organ as they age, very much like people do. So, you know, a person may die from cardiovascular
disease, but at the same time, if they're in their 80s, their kidney isn't functioning as well,
their heart isn't functioning as well, their brain probably isn't functioning as well.
That's right.
So, mice show all of those same declines in function with age and caloric restriction
seems to delay or outright prevent those declines as well. So, yeah, maybe the lifespan effect is
primarily due to cancer, but caloric restriction is having an effect apparently on the underlying
biological aging process in all sorts of different ways. And I really like the functional measures.
A lot of people in the field these days are really enamored with, you know, the aging clocks,
epigenetic clocks, biochemical markers. I think those are all useful and important.
But from my perspective, what really gets my attention is if somebody shows that the heart
is still functioning like a young heart or the immune system is still functioning.
I wasn't planning to go down that rabbit hole, but since you brought it up,
can you convince me of the utility of the clocks absent the type of data that would actually
demonstrate longitudinally their benefit, which to my knowledge, we really don't have yet?
Yeah. So, I would say a couple things on that. I think we need to be precise in what we mean when
we talk about the clocks because there's lots of flavors of clocks, right? Most people these days,
if you just say aging clock, what they really mean are the epigenetic clocks that are showing,
you know, the characteristic changes in the epigenome, epigenetic marks that are seen with
age. Again, in every organism where it's really been studied, you do see these characteristic
changes in the epigenome with age. And so, I would say one place where their utility is clear,
at least to me, is as a chronological measure, right? Now, you might ask, okay, why would I ever
want to use an epigenetic clock to tell my chronological age? I know how old I am, right?
But forensics, for example, might be a place where that's useful. Their crime has been committed. They
want to know with some level of precision how old the perpetrator is. You could use an epigenetic
clock for that reason. In my world, as part of the dog aging project, there are many dogs
that are rescued, an owner might want to know their age. So, I think that is a real use,
and clearly the clocks will work for that. I think really what you're asking, though, is
can I convince you that the epigenetic clocks and potentially other types of clocks are actually
measuring biological aging, right? And that's a harder, in my mind, that's a harder thing to
prove. And personally, I have no interest in convincing you of that because I'm not convinced,
right? So, I think this is an area where the field is in flux a little bit. And there are certainly
scientists who I respect a lot in the field who believe at their core that these epigenetic clocks
tell us about biological aging or can be used to tell us about biological aging.
Then there are people like me who want to see the proof. And I think that the proof is really
being able to show at an individual level, that could be in a mouse, could be in a person,
could be in a dog. At an individual level, you can predict someone's biological age at some point in
their life and with some level of precision, predict what's going to happen in the future.
What are their future health outcomes? How long are they going to live? Nobody has done that yet.
What they've done comes close, I guess. So, what has been done is to look at longitudinal studies
in people where we have samples from people 10, 20, 30 years ago, measure the epigenetic profiles
of those people 10, 20, 30 years ago and ask how well does that correlate with mortality outcomes,
for example, in the future. And they do work to some extent. I think people will debate how
well they work. Are they any better than other markers you could look at in predicting mortality?
I think that's unclear, but there is some correlation there. So, again, I think it really
depends to some extent maybe on how skeptical you are. I'm a skeptic by nature and I want to actually
see the proof. I guess the last thing I would say about this, I'm talking mostly about the
epigenetic clocks. Maybe it's worth talking about other types of clocks that people can make.
The other thing I want to caution people on though is assuming that the epigenetic clocks
are the only important thing about aging. There is, again, a small number of very vocal and popular
people in the field who talk as if changing the epigenome is going to change everything about
aging. We have no data to support that. I just have to say it, that is not true at this point.
We have no data to support it. What we know about the biology of aging is that epigenetic changes
are one of, depending on how you categorize things, eight or nine or 10 molecular processes
that seem to contribute, that the field has reached consensus on. It's only one of those
things. Is it possible that it is sort of in a hierarchy the most important and drives a lot of
those other changes? Yes, that's possible. We don't have any data to support it. So, this idea that
reversing the epigenome is reversing aging is at best an exaggeration, at worst an outright lie.
I mean, it's just not true. How could that be? What a set of experiments technology-wise would
you need to be able to do to even test that hypothesis in a mouse, right? We're close.
Well, maybe close. I guess I should qualify that a little bit. Conceptually, we're close. So,
there have been these factors called the Yamanaka factors that can reprogram the epigenome. So,
this has been done in cells. So, if you take cells in culture, in a laboratory, and you passage them
many, many times, you can see changes in the epigenome, just like you might see changes in
the epigenome in an animal, in tissues. And you can put these reprogramming factors into the cells
and turn them on. Now, there are four Yamanaka factors? There are four Yamanaka factors, but
people are trying different cocktails, adding some other stuff in, taking some stuff out. But yes,
there are the four classic Yamanaka factors. And what those factors do is they basically
wipe clean the epigenetic changes that have happened over time. And also, what's amazing
is that they restore those cells back to a, if you take it far enough, back to a pluripotent state.
So, essentially, you get virgin new cells that could differentiate into any cell type in the body,
right? So, this has been known for many years. What is relatively more recent over the last
eight or nine years are people are trying to express these reprogramming factors in an animal.
So, instead of doing it in cells in the laboratory, do it in an animal. And I think the most compelling
work is work in a premature aging model of mice, so it's called a progeroid model,
where they're very short-lived, they're very sick. But these reprogramming factors can extend lifespan
by, I don't remember what the exact numbers are, but a significant amount, maybe 40, 50%,
which seems like a lot, except you have to recognize these mice live maybe 25% of the length
of a normal mouse, right? So, they're very sick. But there are impressive changes that happen that
are consistent with the idea that you fixed or made something better. So, the experiment to do
would be to express these reprogramming factors in an old mouse and make that mouse young again.
And this is where I think the exaggeration, I'll use the nice word, has gotten ahead of the actual
data. So, what has been done is showing that in one or two, maybe three tissues, you can see an
improvement in function. The most impressive, I think, is work from David Sinclair's lab, where
they use this optic degeneration model. So, degeneration of the eye showed that they could
reverse that with these reprogramming factors and then tried to do the same thing in an old mouse.
And there was at least, the data was mixed, but I think pretty compelling that you could,
to some extent, regenerate the optic nerve in an old mouse. So, that's certainly impressive, I think,
exciting. But nobody has ever taken an old mouse and turned it into a young mouse. So,
when people start talking about reversing aging, that implies that you have taken an old
animal or person and, to some extent, biologically made them young again. That hasn't happened.
So, what I would say needs to happen, to really convince me, there are two things. So, I would be
convinced that this is useful, potentially therapeutically and important. I'm actually
already convinced it could be useful therapeutically. But I would become really excited if somebody
could do as good as rapamycin in a mouse. So, I'm not asking for much, in my view, right?
We know rapamycin can extend lifespan 25%, at least. Again, a dose hasn't been optimized,
but 25%, let's stick with that. And you can reverse functional declines in many tissues, right?
So, show me you can do that with reprogramming and I'll be excited. Nobody's done even that yet.
Show me you can take a two and a half year old mouse, make it look like a one year old mouse,
and then it lives to be five years old. I'll be really excited. Look, I'll be all on board.
I might even come on your show and apologize for saying that people were exaggerating,
although they are exaggerating now. But I think the enthusiasm has just gotten so far ahead of
where the science is. Let's go back to the maybe help folks understand what the Yamanaka factors
are doing and how one can be sure that even if you fix the aging problem, you don't create a new
problem. So, if the objective is I want to take the DNA as I had it when I was young, right? So,
when I was 20, this is what my DNA looked like. Now that I'm 50, it looks different. It has
literally these methyl groups that are sitting directly on the cysteine residues. It's literally
on my DNA. Okay. We want to take those off. Maybe? Well, so first of all, it's important to understand
why that's even a problem, right? Why is my 50 year old crappy DNA not as good as my 20 year old DNA?
So, again, this is taking a step back to sort of basic biology, right? So, the DNA is where all the
information is, but then that DNA has to get turned into RNA. That's called transcription or gene
expression, we'll just call it gene expression. And then that RNA has to get turned into protein.
In general, it's the protein that does the work, right? So, what these epigenetic changes,
the methyl groups that you were talking about do primarily we think is affect expression of the
genes. So, basically what you're seeing with aging, we think, is a shift in the epigenome that
leads to certain genes being expressed that shouldn't be and certain genes not being
expressed that should be. And I think there's a little bit of a debate about which is more
important right now, but it probably doesn't really matter, right? So, the idea is you're
getting things turned on and turned off inappropriately as we get older. So, there's a
loss of regulation, which probably contributes to a loss of homeostasis. And homeostasis is,
I think, a really useful way to think about aging, right? If you're healthy, your body is
generally in homeostasis, right? And what happens as we get older is it becomes harder and harder
for our body to maintain homeostasis. When you get out of homeostasis, if your defense mechanisms
are working right, you can get back in, right? So, you get COVID, for example, your immune system
works, you're out of homeostasis, but you come back in and then you're okay again. I think as
we get older, it gets harder to come back into homeostasis and that's why we start to see
pathology and mortality. So, let me differentiate two states of pathology. My five-year-old son
was on his scooter two weeks ago going down the steepest hill in the world, which I had no idea
how I didn't see that he was about to do that, like face planted. And when he came up,
all I could think is how quickly can we get to the hospital? I mean, it was a blood bath.
Yeah.
I'm not making this up, Matt. Six days later, there was one little tiny scar, eight or nine days later,
you would have had no idea this kid ripped his face off on pavement. He's five. I get a cut,
it's like nine months until the scar is gone. So, there's a very clear distinction between a
five-year-old's DNA and a 50-year-old's DNA in terms of how he can literally make new proteins
that are better than my proteins.
Yeah. Let me stop you there just for a second because I think this is actually the crux of the
question, right? You said it's a difference in your DNA.
Well, I'm asking. I think what I'm trying to get at is, yeah, how much of... Because that's a clear
case of the protein that he makes is better than my protein, right? He's making much better protein.
Certainly functions better.
Yes.
Absolutely. Yeah. So, I guess what I was getting at though is the question... One question I think
that's really important here is there can be changes to the DNA to the sequence, right? So,
the sequence of the DNA is the information, right? Those are called mutations and those accumulate
as we age and that's honestly what drives a lot of cancer, right? So, we've known this for a long
time. The epigenetic changes are sort of on top of that, right?
Yeah. And while it more regulates expression, I'm wondering how much that factors into the
example I just gave. Does it?
It's a good question. I'm sure it does to some extent. Absolutely.
Like what else explains why his collagen is so much better than mine? What are the other
factors that go into that?
I mean, I think there are probably many reasons why healing declines with... Our ability to heal
declines with age. I actually, again, I mean, I know we've talked about this before. I think
inflammation is a huge driver of our loss of ability to recover as we get older. So,
all sorts of things go wrong if you have a high level of sterile inflammation in your body,
including the ability of stem cells to function. And a lot of injuries require stem cells to
function to build back what's been broken. So, it's complicated, I guess I would say.
But the question is...
Yeah, it could be that I have more senescent cells and more senescent cell
factors that are impairing the ability of cells to heal.
Just to throw a wrench in that though, there's actually a body of thought that senescent cells
actually promote wound healing. So, it's again, this is where the biology is so complicated.
But I think the crux of the question we started from is, if you only fix the epigenome,
do you fix everything?
How do you know you fix all these things?
Do you fix everything? And nobody knows, I think is the fair answer. I think I would be
shocked if that was the case, that epigenetic changes drive all of aging. But it's possible.
I think we have to be open to that idea that epigenetic changes sit on top of or upstream of
the other hallmarks of aging. First of all, let me say one thing. It won't fix everything.
You will not fix mutations by fixing the epigenome. The question is, do mutations,
do they happen with enough frequency to be a major contributor to functional declines that
go along with aging? Certainly cancer, you can point to.
Cancer for sure. But let's now talk about something else, which is near and dear to your
heart, no pun intended, but ejection fraction. Again, because you study dogs.
Not only is cancer a big problem, but so is heart failure. So, now we're dealing with a muscle,
a set of cells that really aren't being turned over the way skin is. So, when we think about the
example of my son, when you think about your gut epithelium being sloughed off when you get sick,
when you think about your fingernails and your hair, boy, it's really easy to think about those
things as rapidly being turned over. But neurons, cardiac myocytes, these things don't get turned
over a whole heck of a lot. So, what is it about reprogramming that we think is going to fix
an aging neuron or an aging cardiac myocyte? Yeah. So, I mean, again, I think, again,
this is an area where the biology of what's really happening, at least to my knowledge,
is so poorly understood that I think the real answer is we don't completely know.
I'm going to give a very simplistic answer, which is that what people are trying to do
is not reprogram all the way back to the pluripotent state. So, it's called partial reprogramming.
Right. Which would be pretty dangerous.
Well, that's what I was going to say. If you're a single-celled organism, no problem going back
to the pluripotent state, right? You can then start over. In a complicated animal, if we
reprogram you back to the pluripotent state, that's not going to end well for you.
No.
Right? So, I think the idea is to go back far enough that you restore the epigenome to its
pristine state, young state, and then hope that when you do that, you restore gene expression
to where it's supposed to be. Maybe one way to think about it is you restore the homeostatic
mechanisms to a more youthful state where then the homeostatic mechanisms that all of
our cells have can basically clean up the rest of the mess. Right? Because we know as we get older,
for example, we all accumulate damaged mitochondria. Right? Changing the epigenome,
which is the nuclear genome, isn't going to fix anything that's wrong with your mitochondria
directly. But maybe by fixing the epigenome, you restore the homeostatic mechanisms that then
maintain mitochondria in a healthy state, and you can fix the damage to the mitochondria. Right?
So, that's the concept. And again, I would say the evidence is suggestive that if you do it just
right, you can improve function in at least some aged tissues and organs by partial reprogramming.
I've yet to see anything that convinces me that anybody has made an old heart into a young heart
in an old animal with partial reprogramming in the heart. But you can't improve function. I
would also say the same thing is true with rapamycin. Right? I would not argue we see that
short-term treatment with rapamycin in mice makes an old heart function functionally to some extent,
more like a young heart. I would never argue that we have taken that heart and now it's young. It's
just in an old body. We don't know that, and that's hard to prove. But I think you can see some
evidence that it should be possible with partial reprogramming to do that. And the question is,
will it work everywhere? Will it work in some tissues and organs and not in others? We don't
really know. The brain is the one. So, let's just say 10, 20 years from now, people have figured
out a lot of the complexity. We're starting to move these things into the clinic. Maybe we will see
really large effects on lifespan and healthspan in mice. What I've yet to hear anybody give a
convincing explanation of is how you do that in the brain. Because so much of who we are and what
we are comes from our experiences and our memories. And so, how do you ensure that you can reprogram
somebody's brain in a way that isn't going to change that? And I just think that's going to
be a really hard problem to overcome. But maybe somebody will figure it out. There are tons of
really smart people working in this area. Lots of resources going into this area. So, I think it's
exciting. Again, my big concern is that we don't mislead people into thinking that we're close to
reversing aging. And I think it's a problem from the perspective of the general public. I think it's
a problem from the perspective of the scientific community. Other scientists look at that and
they're like, this is snake oil. This is just not true. Yeah. And my concern with it is actually
in terms of the impact it has on people, which are, hey, this is awesome. This thing's going to
get worked out. I can do whatever I want. I can do whatever. I mean, literally, it's like, I can
sort of do what I want because in 10 years they're going to reprogram me. And my view on that is,
even if that is true, or even if you have a high degree of confidence that that is true,
how would you not hedge? Right? Again, hedging is such an important part of how companies manage
risk. So, the difference between good companies and bad companies when it comes to risk management
is everything. That's why some companies do really well in economic downturns and others don't.
It's basically about risk management. And a very important part of risk management is indeed hedging.
So, if we think of ourselves each as little companies, so if you're the CEO of Matco,
I'm the CEO of Peatco, I can't think of a more important asset within my company to manage
than my own life. Yeah. Right? Like, sure, do I have enough money yet? Do I have enough fun? Yeah,
those are all important assets, but existing would be the number one asset. And to not take
a risk management approach of hedging to that is insane. And yet what I see is so many grand
promises of this stuff and nobody's sort of paying attention to what they eat or how much exercise
they do because I don't need to, this is going to be worked out. So, the thing that I always find
amazing is some of the most vocal advocates for this stuff, like don't have an ounce of muscle on
them, don't have their overweight or whatever, like they don't look healthy. And I'm like, guys,
you can do both, right? You can believe that in 10 years we're going to fix this problem,
but you could still actually care about your health. Yeah. Now, I think that's a really
important point. And having, again, been in this field for a long time now, I think you can just
look back over the last 20, 30 years and look at predictions people made on how fast these things
were going to come along and get into the clinic. And none of that has happened, right? So, I totally
agree with you. I guess also being in the center of it, I take a view of, again, pretty strong
skepticism when people say this is going to happen in 10, 15 years. I honestly have not appreciated
that there are maybe a lot of people out there looking at what they read in the New York Times
or on CNN and thinking to themselves, oh, I don't have to worry about this. This is going to get
worked out. So, my advice would be don't expect major changes in treatments to improve lifespan
and health span in the next 20 years. And that doesn't mean I'm not optimistic. I think there are
opportunities there. It would not surprise me if we do see some of these things get into the clinic,
but I certainly wouldn't expect it because there are so many barriers that we don't yet appreciate.
There are lots of barriers just in moving something through the clinical trial process.
I think the reprogramming stuff is a perfect example. So, you actually alluded to this earlier,
right? Are there potential side effects, right? Absolutely. You push it too far, right? You
reprogram too far, you're gone. We know that certain types of cancers are a side effect of
this partial reprogramming in mice. Again, it doesn't mean it can't be worked out, but there
are really reasons, I think, to be concerned that this is going to be hard to implement
therapeutically. The other thing I would say, even if those things can be worked out, the FDA
is going to be extremely skeptical of this kind of approach. So, as people move these through the
clinical trial process, they are going to have to show with really rock solid compelling data that
these reprogramming strategies are not going to cause significant side effects. So, I think it's
a long road before we have reprogramming strategies that get into the clinic. Maybe somebody will
identify a small molecule that can do some of this, and I know people are working on that. Maybe
that'll be an easier path, but for now, I think it's going to take a while. That's the best case
scenario. That's if we really can partially. I'm going to say partially reverse aging, reverse
aspects of aging. It's still going to be a long road. I wonder if the first wins are going to be
things like what David Sinclair has done where you've got one very niche application. I think
another one that would be amazing would be osteoarthritis. If you could figure out a way
to regenerate human cartilage without joint replacements, those are huge wins that seem
at least a little more feasible. But again, I agree with you. I think this stuff takes
four times as long and costs four times as much as we think. Like building a house.
You and I are, honestly, we're pretty lucky because we know about a lot of this stuff. We
actually can start practicing some of this stuff like rapamycin before it gets out there. Again,
I'm not recommending anybody take rapamycin necessarily without talking to your physician
first, but we know this stuff and we, I think, have at least a pretty good idea of the relative
risk reward. But before it gets out to where it hits the mainstream from a clinical perspective,
it's a really long path. I totally agree with what you said though about specific indications
where you can target it very precisely, hopefully, and where there's no other solution currently.
I think those are opportunities. That's exactly the strategy that people have tried to take with
Cenalytics, these molecules that will clear senescent cells. Even that's been hard. Unity
is the largest company in this space and their first clinical trial for osteoarthritis failed.
Now they're looking at the eye because again, it's a nice indication where for some of these eye
diseases, there isn't any solution and you can, in principle, target it quite precisely to the eye.
I think that is exactly the strategy that people will be taking and hopefully it'll be successful.
I want this stuff to work. I try to be a realist at the same time.
I guess the way I would describe this to people is if you want to bring it back to a financial
analogy, it's a lottery ticket. If your entire financial planning system is based on winning
the lottery, the odds that you're going to win are pretty low. Instead, if you're going to play
the lottery, play it in the context of an otherwise great saving and investing strategy.
I guess the other thing I would add to that is that, and this is what we talked about before,
you don't have to do everything right. Get 80% of the way there, which nutritionally,
I don't think is, for some people, it's very challenging, but I think most people could do
that. Exercise, you don't have to optimize your physical activity. Do something and that'll get
you most of the way there. The exercise curve, which we've covered a lot in previous podcasts,
you get most of the benefit going from, I would say literally 50% of the benefit based on at least
the so-so epidemiologic data, about 50% of the full benefit of exercise is captured going from
nothing to about 15 met hours per week. That would be depending on, 15 met times one hour would
be one way to get there, but in reality, that's no one who's that unfit is going to do 15 met,
but that would be like three hours a week of five met to put that in perspective. Five met
is like a very, very brisk walk or a slow jog, something to that effect. You get a sense of like
15 met hours per week is by extension, I do about 100 met hours per week of exercise. I think of
everything in terms of met hours, but the point is that you can get, depending on the study, 30 to
50% of the benefit going from being completely sedentary to 15 met hours per week is pretty
amazing. Which is a big benefit. Again, it's remarkable that that information isn't out there.
Most people in the general public don't know that. I don't know what the solution is. I think you're
obviously doing a great public service by trying to get that information out there, but it's
unfortunate because I think again, if most people understood how much benefit they could get
from just getting out and moving a little bit, maybe a lot, maybe three hours a week is a lot
for some people. But the magnitude of the benefit compared to the effort that you put in,
I think most people just don't know that and it's unfortunate.
Let's go back to the CR stuff. What do we know about the effect of CR in the laboratory animals
on the immune system? It's a little bit complicated. First of all, laboratory animals
in the laboratory are kept in what's called a specific pathogen-free environment. That doesn't
mean there's no pathogens, but it's a relatively low pathogen environment where they are not
obligated to really use their immune systems against all the challenges that we would face
in the real world. One question has come up. Are animals that are on calorie restriction immune
compromised? Again, I think the data is a little bit mixed, but certainly there have been studies
where people have done pathogen challenges on CR animals and they respond better. At least the
old animals respond better than age matched ad libitum fed control. Ad libitum just means eat as
much as you want. But then for certain types of challenges, the caloric restriction clearly
causes a deficit. Yeah, the sepsis experiments are pretty clear. The CR animals compared to
controls, when you induce sepsis in them, the CR animals die much more quickly. Right. Of course,
the obvious implication of that is that maybe CR would impair immune function in people and lead
to higher risk of all sorts of infectious diseases. This gets additionally complicated
though by the question of CR with optimal nutrition. You might sometimes just see this
CRON, C-R-O-N, caloric restriction with optimal nutrition, or CRAN, caloric restriction with
adequate nutrition. That can be done in a mouse. We can control all of that so we make sure that
they get all the micronutrients and vitamins that they need when they're on this CR diet.
When you move into the real world and people start practicing caloric restriction, that all goes out
the window. Right. Like I wouldn't, if I wanted to do caloric restriction off the top of my head,
I wouldn't even know what to do to make sure that I'm getting optimal nutrition. Right.
And so in that state where you are CR without optimal nutrition, I think that's where I really
become worried about the side effects, particularly as you raised immune deficits, because
you may not be getting the nutrient value or the specific micronutrients and vitamins that you need
to maintain a functioning immune system. Sure. You may affect some aspects of the biology of aging
in a way that you're aging biologically more slowly. That doesn't matter if you get influenza
and die. Right. So again, I think that's an additional complication that comes into play.
When we start talking about, we haven't talked about all the other anti-aging nutritional
strategies. When we start talking about recommending those nutritional strategies to the general public,
based on solely on mouse studies, I get really concerned because of this environmental complexity
that humans live in. And we haven't even talked about the genetic complexity. Right. So there's
all sorts of things that are just different about laboratory animals compared to people living in
the real world. And then what- Can we say about frailty, sarcopenia as it changes in an animal,
in a CR environment, and can that be extrapolated also? Yeah. So I think it's pretty clear, I think,
that much like rapamycin, most functional measures of aging seem to be preserved in
calorically restricted animals, including measures of frailty and measures of sarcopenia.
And the same thing, again, is true with rapamycin. This actually surprised a lot of people when the
first studies were done because the expectation was because mTOR plays such a big role in muscle
synthesis, that if you inhibit mTOR with rapamycin or caloric restriction, which is a potent
inhibitor of mTOR, that you would actually see accelerated sarcopenia. And that just isn't the
observation in laboratory animals. Again, we have to be careful not to extrapolate to people,
but it doesn't seem to be the case that you lose muscle mass and function in the way that people
would define sarcopenia. I think the important complication here is that all of the caloric
restriction studies that I'm aware of, when they look at muscle function, normalize the body weight.
And the calorically restricted mice weigh substantially less than the ad libitum fed
mice. Usually, I think it's on the order of 30, 35% less. So it's usually grip strength normalized
to weight. Right. So what you're actually seeing is that the calorically restricted mice have
maintained muscle function proportionate to their body weight. And I don't know the answer to this,
but it's something that I thought of when we were talking about this show. Let's just say you did
that in a person. So you would be able to answer this. I'm sure you've got a 60-year-old person who
needs to lose 30% of their body weight. But of course, you want to maintain their muscle mass,
their muscle function. Would you view it as a good thing or a bad thing if they lost 30% of their
body weight? And 30% of their muscle. And 30% of their strength? No. I don't think we would. And I
don't think we would view it as a good thing if that... Because again, if you're telling me that
someone needs to lose 30% of their body weight, presumably their body composition isn't great to
begin with. So no, I think you would view that as maybe a better thing than where they started,
but not optimal either. Optimal might be you would lose 30% of your body weight,
but it would disproportionately be adipose tissue. And you might only lose 10% of your strength or
none at all. Right. So again, this is just... Depending on the change in lean body mass.
This is just a complication of the CR studies. And again, it's hard for me sometimes. It takes me
20, 30 minutes of trying to dig through the paper to really figure out
what normalization did they do to look at metabolic rate or muscle mass or lean mass
or fat mass or muscle function. But usually these studies will be normalized to body weight. This
actually comes up also in some of the intermittent fasting studies where the question sometimes in
these studies is, are they isocholoric or are they calorically restricted when they're put on
intermittent fasting? And people will claim they're isocholoric, but the mice lose weight.
And what they really are is isocholoric when normalized to body weight. So they're really
calorically restricted, but you have to dig to get how the normalizations were done to really
understand. Now, when we think about what we know in humans, there was a study that looked at
the difference in bone mineral density in people who underwent equal amounts of weight loss,
one driven by a caloric restriction strategy, one driven by an exercise driven strategy.
And the exercise driven weight loss group did not experience a reduction in BMD, but the CR group
did. Yeah. So, you know, that's interesting. That's yet another thing that makes you think there's a
little more nuance to this, which is not to say CR from a weight loss perspective isn't valuable,
but it begs the question, you know, is CR the right tool for longevity? Once you've achieved
optimal weight, is additional CR beneficial? That makes the assumption we know what optimal
weight is. I mean, I think that's kind of the crux of the question, right? We're asking,
does CR impact longevity positively? We know if you go on CR, you're going to lose weight. So if
the answer to that is yes, then by definition, optimal weight is lower than what we think.
Right. I know, but we don't, I would say we still don't really know what optimal weight is. So,
so again, this I think just reflects the challenges in coming to definitive answers. And I mean,
I think maybe the way I think about it more so is, you know, what are the concept? So, so what are the,
what are the downsides potentially to caloric restriction? And if we don't know that caloric
restriction has big benefits in terms of health span and perhaps lifespan, what are the downsides
and do those downsides outweigh the uncertainty we have about whether caloric restriction is
beneficial? And unfortunately, I think this is something that not very many people in this field
pay attention to, right? People are, you know, we all expect if you do a clinical trial of a drug,
you're going to report adverse events and, and you're going to look at side effects. Very rarely
do people think about that before they write a book recommending that people should do diet X,
right? Even in the clinical trials, some of the nutritional clinical trials,
they don't really carefully monitor adverse events. And I think it's just, again, it's a bias
in the way we think about interventions. We feel like nutritional interventions are by their very
nature safe. And I think, you know, certainly for extreme nutritional interventions, that's clearly
not true. So I think we should be thinking about what are the risks associated with significant
caloric restriction in people as a therapeutic strategy.
Let's go back to the sort of the study that will never be done again, right? The
NIA Wisconsin Rhesus monkeys. So boy, if I can get my facts straight on this one,
I want to say that this study started in the late 80s.
Ah, it sounds about right. It might have even been, might have, which would have been probably
the early 80s. I think. Wow. Okay. So we're talking Rhesus monkeys. You know, these are
animals that are going to live what, 30 years potentially? Yeah. 40. I think the average was
close, maybe closer to 40. Yeah. So let's talk about the experiment, end all experiments with
respect to caloric restriction, which is the very famous one we alluded to earlier at the University
of Wisconsin and the NIA. So, and I, I've read this study a thousand times. If I can get the
details right once I'll be happy, but between the two of us, I hope we can do this. You had two
groups of animals, one at the University of Wisconsin and one directly in Bethesda, Maryland.
This was obviously a huge NIH funded effort. It ran for a couple of decades given the lifespan
of Rhesus monkeys. The Wisconsin animals were fed, the controls and the treatment,
CR animals were fed a very processed diet. Right. At least after the fact, the examiner,
the investigators there suggested they wanted to more mimic a standard American diet. Of note,
I recall the amount of sugar, pure sucrose in their diet was 28 and a half percent of total calories.
So this is, this is, this is a high quality diet facetiously. The CR animals, the calorically
restricted animals were fed 25% of what the control animals were fed. And in that experiment,
we found a benefit to caloric restriction. That's right. CR animals outlived the control animals.
And they had fewer age related diseases. So I think if you, if you go back to that original
2009 paper, you know, the lifespan effect is compelling and it looks real, but, but what,
again, you know, is I think really indicative of, of, of that it might be having an effect on
biological aging is that they saw reduced rates of cancer. Again, not surprisingly,
as we talked about in mice, but also heart disease and metabolic disease. So, you know,
it's consistent with the idea that in that cohort of monkeys, again, given what you mentioned about
the dietary composition, caloric restriction was in fact having a beneficial impact on the aging
process. And those animals all came in at about the same age. Right. So that was sort of an apples
to apples comparison. Now we go down the road to Bethesda, we have a totally different experiment
in a way. And I don't know how much of this was deliberate and how much of it was not.
The diets were different. So that's, that's maybe a good contrast. These animals were actually fed
the closest diet that could mimic their real diet. So it didn't have any, you know, sugar in it,
really, I think it was like about 3% sucrose. You know, it was almost kind of like a, you know,
a vegetarian pescatarian sort of diet. Fish was the dominant source of protein, but it, you know,
it was a high quality diet relative to the Wisconsin. Higher quality for sure. Yep. The
complicating factor here was the animals didn't come in at all the same age. So you had some animals
that came in young, some animals that came in old. The net result of the study was there was no
difference. The CR animals did not outlive. And so while the Wisconsin study was first published in
2009 and it said, CR works, the 2012 publication for NIA said, CR doesn't work. At least that's
the lay press interpretation of it. So how do you kind of reconcile these findings? Yeah. So one,
I think one thing to add to that is the, the NIA study at Bethesda in their paper, at least they
did show some evidence for improvements in at least some health span metrics. So if you read that
paper closely, you know, what they're, I think what they're really saying is CR didn't extend
lifespan, but it did have what appeared to be some beneficial effects on health span metrics. So
it wasn't a complete failure in that sense. So, I mean, I think it's interesting because since
then the, you know, when that, I remember when the, the, the 2011 paper came out, the Wisconsin people
were pretty upset, understandably. So I think since then they've had sort of a reconciliation
paper and where they try to figure out what does it mean that we got these different results? And
I think, you know, their conclusion, which certainly is plausible is that a lot of it comes
down to the difference in diets. And if you look at the actual body weights of the animals and how
much food they ate, not just the composition, but actually how much they ate, you know, you could
make an argument that the Bethesda monkeys were somewhat slightly calorically restricted. Again,
the controls, the controls. That's right. Yes. The controls at Bethesda ate less than the controls
in Wisconsin. Right. And that would have narrowed the gap between them and the treatment animals.
And so then I think as you, as you also alluded to the fact that the Bethesda study was a little
bit less controlled for age of onset. And I should, I don't remember the details exactly. There were
also some genetic differences in there. So there's a combination of factors that make it a little bit
difficult to conclude that it all is about the diet, right? So the, the monkeys in the Bethesda
study came in at different ages. There was at least a hint, I think that the, the monkeys that
came in at older ages started CR at older ages, maybe got a somewhat of a benefit. Whereas the
ones that started early didn't get any benefit. So it's, it's complicated to interpret. And,
you know, it's interesting because we see this a lot of times in the basic biology of age, aging,
basic science studies where different labs will get different results in, in what seems to be the
same exact experiment. And then you start to dig into it and yeah, there's all these differences
in the way it was done. It's really hard to know which of those differences contributed to the
different outcomes in this particular case, because it was a, you know, 30, 40 year experiment,
we're never going to find out, right? Yeah, I just won't be repeated both because of how long it
takes. And also because again, the, the view on primate research, these are Rhesus macaques,
right? The view on primate research publicly has changed, right? So I just don't think we'll ever
see that experiment done again. My gut feeling is that, that the Wisconsin study to some extent
probably does mirror what is closer to a typical American situation, at least these days. I do not
believe that they started with that intention, but where we're at today, it probably is relatively,
you know, as close as you can get for a controlled laboratory study. The question though, in my mind
is, between these two studies, do they suggest that caloric restriction, you know, slows aging,
and let's just start relative to the typical American diet, right? Somebody is moderately
obese, and they're eating terrible. Is it caloric restriction? Or is it just returning to, I think,
maybe what you would call like an optimal body weight, right? Optimal body mass. And I don't
think we know the answer, right? I think from these studies, you can't draw many conclusions.
I think the one thing you can do, and, and, and, uh, Roz Anderson, who's still at Wisconsin,
has really, I think, been a leader in this, is you can study the molecular signatures of
caloric restriction in the monkeys and ask, does it look similar to the molecular signatures of
caloric restriction in rodents? And you might ask, well, why would you do that? It seems obvious. But
again, a lot of the questions that people have around caloric restriction studies in mice
is will the, will, will it work the same way in people? And obviously,
Rhesus macaques are much closer evolutionarily to people than mice are. So if you see the same
molecular changes, it's suggestive that caloric restriction is having the same
molecular changes in people, certainly in primates. And in fact, that seems to be the case. A lot of
what we see in terms of, you know, changes in mTOR signaling and mitochondrial function and,
and other metabolic pathways is in fact shared between mice and monkeys. So I think that's a,
that is one important outcome from these studies that we can, we can definitely say is rock solid.
But I tend to believe that the pretty dramatic declines in age related disease
seen in the Wisconsin studies are telling us something. But again, is it just telling us that
not being obese reduces your risk for a lot of these diseases? And, and, you know, we kind of
already know that from the, from the human literature as well. Exactly. The other thing
that isn't entirely clear given that the NIA study didn't find a difference is we don't know how much
of this was the CR versus the DR, the dietary restriction. In other words, what the Wisconsin
experiment suggests is if you have an awful diet, reducing the amount of awful food you eat is a good
thing. Right. What the NIA experiment doesn't tell us is the contra positive. It doesn't suggest
that if you have a good diet, eating less of that will help you live longer. It might, but it isn't
definitive. Well, and it's not, we don't know, right? If the Wisconsin animals lived longer,
simply because they lost weight or because they lost weight and they were eating less processed
food. Right. Right. And I think the other thing to add to that is the NIA monkeys, which were eating,
you know, what we'll call a superior diet to the Wisconsin monkeys also ate less than the Wisconsin
monkeys. So yeah. So in other words, if you ate more of a good diet, would that be detrimental? We
also don't know that it's an, it's an interesting question actually. And, and, um, it's, it's too
bad. We don't know the answer to that. But I think if they had been body weight matched or caloric
consumption matched, that would have been an interesting comparison to be able to see,
are there differences there? And the other thing that just kind of gets off into weeds that we
don't need to necessarily go into is really have a great understanding of even how we differ from
the, the Reese's monkeys. So, you know, I recently read Herman Ponser's book where he,
I don't have you read it by the way. So he kind of goes into the ecology and evolution of, of
humans as a species and how different we are even from our closest evolutionary cousins.
And one of the fundamental differences are incredible capacity to store excess energy.
So our metabolic rate, so this is, you know, he documents this through lots of assessments
of doubly labeled water on not just ourselves, but also kind of, you know, hunter-gatherers
that are still around today. And then of course, all the primates is, you know, we're really kind
of unique in our energy expenditure. Our, our energy needs are far greater than anything else.
And people like that would argue, Hey, that was kind of an advantage that we took to allow our
development, including our brain development. So there's kind of a reason we're at the top of the
food chain, which is we have a much greater brain and the price we pay for that is higher energy
expenditure. And the price we pay for that is we better be able to store energy because we will
have a much harder time tolerating a low energy environment. And so he talks about how even when
you put these animals in captivity and you overfeed them, they're not getting that much fatter,
right? They're, they're actually putting on lean mass. Now they, you know, I think what you could
argue, and he doesn't talk about this, but knowing what we know about human biology,
you might argue that they're still getting metabolically sick. Right. Just as humans,
when you're overfed, the real metabolic sickness comes not with the inflation of your subcutaneous
fat. It's when that spills out into the viscera, into the liver, into the peripancreatic space,
into the perinephric space, into the pericardial space. It's that fat that escapes the normal depot
of sub-q fat that is truly inflammatory and truly metabolically disturbing. So I throw all that in
there just to say like, it's just one more confounding variable that makes it difficult
to compare us even to an organism as complex as a rhesus monkey. Yeah. Yeah. And I mean, people
certainly have made that criticism of the caloric restriction literature, you know, writ large, not
even taking into account the monkey studies, but the mouse studies, right? That there are,
you know, all sorts of differences between people and mice and the metabolic state that people have
evolved to fill is just completely different. Having said that, you're absolutely right that
even mice in the laboratory as they get older will show metabolic syndrome, right? You will see
many of the same changes insulin resistance, for example, that you see in people. And I don't-
And do you see it absent the adiposity? Can you see it-
Well, mice gain adiposity with age. They do in fact, become obese with age, right? On a,
again, on a pretty crappy diet, right? At a standard, well, I don't know if it's crappy or
not, the standard mouse diets, right? So, and I don't remember what the number is you made,
but in the Wisconsin study, right? A significant fraction of the control fed monkeys developed
diabetes, right? So- Yes. I want to say like a quarter of the controls were pre-diabetic by the
end of the study, again, which probably speaks to even though they weren't overweight, when they
get a, when you get 28 and a half percent of your calories from sugar, it's probably going to impair
your metabolism. Yeah. So, I think though the other, you know, the other point that's maybe worth at
least just mentioning here, because I hear people, you know, talk about how certain diets are better
for humans because it more mimics, you know, what we evolved to eat, right? I don't know whether
that's true or not. You could argue both sides of that. I don't see any particularly compelling
reason to think that that was the optimal longevity diet that, you know, humans ate.
I think that argument is illogical on several fronts. The first is,
and I don't know who coined this phrase, but it's so ubiquitous that it's obvious, like
by necessity, we had to be opportunistic omnivores. Right. Like there's simply no way
about it. Like to even suggest that our hunter gatherer forefathers were sitting around pontificating
about what they were and were not going to eat. What they should eat. Yeah. I mean, it's just the
dumbest thing I've ever heard, right? Like of course, I mean, I don't think people are actually
arguing that. But my point is it, the argument becomes so nonsensical when you realize
our evolution necessitated the most flexibility from a nutritional standpoint. Yes. And therefore,
we ate anything and everything. And I think because we never probably existed in an environment where
food abundance was so great that we could reach the level of over nutrition,
it gave us even more flexibility with what we could eat. Right. And kind of where I was going
with this, and I mean, it's interesting to think about is that maybe part of the reason why humans
seem to be fairly robust towards eating really, really crappy diets. I mean, certainly, obviously,
we have an obesity epidemic and all of that stuff happening. But people seem to be able to
tolerate a wide variety of different diets, some of which are pretty darn bad for them for many,
many years before you start to really see the significant consequences. So maybe that metabolic
flexibility. I was going to make a totally different point that's almost orthogonal to that,
which is you can make a case that people can survive in really remarkable health with diets
that look nothing like one another. In other words, you can look at somebody eating a really
well formulated, strict vegan diet where they're not getting any animal protein, which clearly our
ancestors all had animal protein whenever they could. They're often protein, a little protein
malnourished, but they're very healthy. Yeah. And similarly, look at the opposite end of that
spectrum. You can look at somebody on a ketogenic diet who, you know, the only thing they would
have in common between that other person is probably a lot of leafy vegetables. But other
than that, it's a much higher fat, higher protein diet. They can be very healthy. That, to me, speaks
to the resilience of our genome in terms of its interaction with nutrition. Yeah. And that's sort
of where I started, which is that there's no reason to think that the ancestral diet is best.
There's no reason to think that. But the other thing that I was thinking about when I started
down this path is that like many other things, our as a species, our dietary options and the
typical diet is evolving rapidly now, right? The quality of the food, the stuff that's in it,
the preservatives, you know, is dramatically different than it was 50 years ago, right? Both
in caloric content and nutritional content. And so in many ways, humans, you know,
taste. It tastes right. Absolutely. Which contributes to why a lot of people
want to eat more, right? So high calorie, really good tasting food that's often cheap.
But so the environment that we evolved into, obviously, is completely different than it is
today. But our environment is changing at an accelerating pace, I think. And that makes it
really, again, complicated to try to get into the minutia of what is optimal. Maybe we should be
thinking about what's good enough first, right? Because I think it's going to be really hard. And
again, this is where I struggle with the data that comes from epidemiological studies of people 20
years ago. The environment, the food quality is just very different for most people today.
Well, this is where the grandmother test comes in, right? And this is where when I watch like
the extremists on both sides argue, I say two things. The first is, look, there are really good
and really bad ways to do your respective diet, right? So I don't want to hear somebody tell me
that everybody on a vegan diet is doing well because I watched a lot of those kids in college,
and they literally were going to kill themselves eating ramen noodles and crackers and cookies all
day. So you can be vegan and eat pure garbage. You could be keto and eat pure garbage. The second
thing I would say is if you're eating those diets well, and I'm being a little subjective
when I say well, you're all shopping on the outer part of the perimeter of the grocery store.
It doesn't matter if you're carnivore, vegan, keto, low carb, paleo, whatever. If you're doing
those diets in the way that they were at least thought to exist, you aren't going down any aisles
of the grocery store. And that's kind of this grandmother test. If your great grandmother
didn't recognize what you're eating, it doesn't mean it's not good. I don't want to say that a
protein bar is not a good thing to eat. You just have to acknowledge there's a little more risk
there, right? Eating a carrot is inherently less risky than eating a protein bar with 14 ingredients
in it. That's just a fact. I think this is what you're getting at. Just a little bit of humility
around what is known, what is not known. And as we push the envelope of convenience,
of nutrient density, of economics, price, shareability, portability, the ability to
preserve things, we're going to take some risks. Yeah. I think that's exactly right.
Let's talk about more broadly a paper you wrote. How long has it been? Two years?
Well, we probably wrote it longer than two years ago. I think it came out at the end of 2021.
So it's fairly recent. You're talking about the science paper.
Yeah. And I'd read it before. So I was trying.
Maybe November, 2021 or so.
All right. So talk about the impetus for that paper, which I thought was a great paper and
we should discuss it in some detail. Yeah. So I was asked by one of the editors at Science to write
a review, I think on mTOR actually. And I was like, well, lots of people have written reviews
on mTOR. I've been thinking a lot about caloric restriction and particularly other nutritional
strategies that people have been studying in the field, like ketogenic diet, protein restriction,
time restricted feeding, intermittent fasting. And what do we actually know about those diets
and their effects on aging? Because I was of the, before I started to really dive into it. And this
isn't something that my lab researches directly. So we've previously done work on caloric restriction
in vertebrates and C. elegans, but we never really have done a lot of dietary interventions in mice.
And so, before I kind of dove into the literature, I had this impression that all of these diets were
similar in some ways and had maybe comparable effects on lifespan. At least that's the way it
gets portrayed if you read some of these reviews. And I don't even like to call them reviews because
I don't think honestly, much of what gets into the literature as review articles are actually
reviews. It's more one person's opinion piece on their specific thing that they study,
which is unfortunate. But if you read most of the reviews on caloric restriction and other dietary
interventions, they're very one-sided and they usually have phrases like fasting is known to
have all of these fantastic benefits and slows aging in every place where it's been looked at.
And you can see that for all these different dietary strategies. So I proposed to the editor
that maybe we should do a critical review of this space and think about what do we know?
What do we don't know? Are they equivalent? And to the extent possible, can we gain any insights
into whether or not these nutritional strategies, whether there's evidence that they have an
impact on the aging process in people? So that's kind of where we started. And I knew it was an
ambitious thing to tackle when I said it. And I'm not sure I really appreciated exactly how
challenging that was going to be because it's a huge area of literature. And it turns out,
maybe not shockingly, that there are many more questions than there are answers when you really
dive into it. So we really just started. So what was your process? Yeah. So we really just start,
the first step was, and I should say I had a fantastic set of co-authors, all really great
early career scientists who really helped me with this and did a lot of the legwork. I just
want to mention them by name. Please do. So Alessandro Bito, who was a postdoc with me,
Mitchell Lee, who was a former graduate student with me, and Crystal Hill, who's at the Pennington
Biomedical Research Institute. And she works on FGF21 and protein restriction. So those three were
co-authors on this paper with me, all just really fantastic early career scientists. So we started
by asking ourselves, OK, what are the different popular dietary interventions that people have
claimed have an effect on aging? And we came up with, I don't know, six or seven. And they were
the ones I've already mentioned. So there's true caloric restriction, which is pretty straightforward.
That really just means limiting the overall caloric intake that an animal gets by somewhere
between 20 towards the low end. And the most I've ever seen is 65% of calories. You were doing this
in animals and humans, or were you trying to start? We were mostly focusing on mice. We narrowed it
pretty quickly when we realized the scope of what we had undertaken. So we could have tried to do it
and fruit flies, worms, and all that stuff. We said, let's start with mice, see what's known,
and then try to look into humans and ask, are there parallels? So caloric restriction,
pretty straightforward. We actually don't go very deep into caloric restriction because that
literature is huge. And other people, I think, have done a pretty good job of reviewing true
caloric restriction. But there are some points there that we probably want to touch on that are
important. And then there are variants of caloric restriction, which include intermittent fasting,
time restricted feeding. How did you differentiate those two? I have a definition,
but I want to make sure yours is clear. So in mice, I think, well, so first of all,
the first differentiator we need to put across all of these things is, is it isocaloric or is it
a flavor of caloric restriction? Because it turns out, I would say the vast majority of studies in
mice of all of the things that we're going to talk about are flavors of caloric restriction. And what
I mean by that is the experimental group ate less calories than the control group.
Right. So it's time restricted feeding, but it's really caloric restriction in a narrower window.
Intermittent caloric restriction, maybe is the way you want to think of it. And there's actually
some nuance there that we can get to. But right. So how am I differentiating between time restricted
feeding and intermittent fasting? So I would say to my view, the easiest differentiator is time
restricted feeding is limiting the number of hours in any 24 hour period that the animal or person
eats. Right. And there are obviously, you're aware of this, there are flavors of time restricted
feeding and people where the window can be anywhere from 12 to six, sometimes even more
extreme than that. Right. But you limit the hours per day that the animal or the person eats.
Intermittent fasting, I would put in a 24 hour or more fast. Right. I think that's a reasonable
definition. That's actually the definition I use basically. Intermittent fast is a fast that occurs
at a frequency of greater than once a day. Right. Exactly. Yeah. The other thing I would say though
is the time restricted feeding gets even more complicated than that. Because there's evidence
that it's not only about how big the window is, but where in the day the window is. And that's
actually one of the things that came out of our review of the literature is there is this
clear connection between how much we eat and when we eat that ties into circadian rhythms.
And that circadian biology, even since this review came out, there have been papers that have come
out that re-emphasize the importance of when we eat and what we eat. I don't think it's either.
I think it's both. That suggests that that's probably going to be significant in terms of the
consequences of the long-term health effects. Right. I'm hoping I'm going to remember to come
back to that, but let's keep going. Okay. So then there's what people call fasting mimicking diets,
which are diets that I've been engineered to some extent to induce the same metabolic changes as
caloric restriction, usually very low sugar, relatively low protein, high fat, but also very
low calorie. So that clearly goes in the bucket of a flavor of caloric restriction. There's
ketogenic diets is another one. And then there's protein restriction. I think that's the.
Isocaloric protein restriction.
Both. So again, you really have to look, you have to take each paper one by one and figure out,
is it isocaloric or isn't it? And that's in some cases just not simply not possible because the
data is just not there, but you have to look closely. So there are examples of both.
I guess one way to think about it is, is it ad lib or not is one way to sort of think about it.
In other words, an ad lib ketogenic diet might end up restricting energy that non-deliberately.
That's one way to think about it, but I don't, I don't know that that answers the question of
whether the benefit comes from caloric restriction. So that's the complication, but I agree with you.
It's different. And you know, we don't think about this much in mice, but certainly in people,
it's true. If you are not ad lib, there are psychological consequences to not eating when
you want to being hungry all the time. Good, bad, indifferent, but there are, those are, those,
those have biological consequences as well. So they are different. Absolutely.
Let's go back to the circadian one. I want to kind of get the insights there. How do,
so first of all, let's talk about what you know in mice and then let's figure out if there's any
extrapolation. So, so when we wrote the paper, there wasn't much on this. I mean, people were
thinking about it, particularly in the context of time restricted feeding, right? That, that there
might be differences in the window of time restricted feeding for, for in humans, right?
Early in the day, late in the day. There's been a couple of papers that have come out
since we wrote the review in mice that I think make a pretty compelling case that the lifespan
benefit from say a 30% caloric restriction diet is a combination of when the animals are eating
and how much they're eating. Most of the benefit seems to come from the calories. So, you know,
let's just say this may not be exactly right, but I think it's close. Let's just say that you get a
30% lifespan extension from 30% caloric restriction that the two thirds of that benefit comes from
the calories. But one third of the benefit actually comes from the fact that those mice
eat all their food in a short window and are fasted essentially the rest of that 24 hour
period. And if you force them to, I mean, and I say force, cause if you give a calorically
restricted mouse, it's food, it's going to eat it right away. So if you force them to eat little
bits throughout the day, you lose a portion of that lifespan benefit, which is really interesting.
Now a mouse eating in an hour and then going 23 hours without food,
what would we even compare that to? I don't know. Yeah. I mean, this is, I really don't
don't feel comfortable even speculating. So, I mean, I think that, you know, the first simplistic
approach would be to say, well, a mouse lives about three years, a human lives about, you know,
I was thinking more of like, how long does a mouse take before it dies from starvation?
So that's where I was going to go next. I think that sort of length of lifespan is not the approach
you take when it comes to metabolism. So I would say that, and this is total back of the envelope
calculation, but a one day, maybe it's like a one to four ratio. So a one day mouse fast might be a
four or five day fast in people, but that's not even perfectly true because a mouse, you know,
a mouse will go into ketosis relatively quickly within 24 hours, right? Sure. And a human can go
into ketosis that quickly, depending a little bit on their incoming diet. Yeah, exactly. Right. So,
so it's not a, it's not a perfect equivalency, but maybe one to four or five. I hope I'm not
saying something totally stupid here, but I think that's probably pretty close. So yeah. So again,
it's very different, potentially these kinds of studies in mice. The other thing that I think
most people don't appreciate unless they've actually done these caloric restriction
experiments is that if you go back to the, you know, the classic experiments of Rick Weindrach
and Roy Walford, those mice are fed a calorically restricted diet. They're also fed three times a
week. So they are in fact, you know, fasting. It's insane. It's like they're basically doing a
two week fast between their meals. Yeah. And so what you see, even in 24 hours in a fasted mouse,
you see pretty dramatic reductions in organ size, right? And so, you know, if the mice are being
fed three times a week, they're going through this, you know, reduction in organ size and then this
huge expansion. Right. So, and you can see that, that sort of decrease in organ size and then
rapid, rapid increase even on some of the fasting mimicking diet work that Walter Longo has done. So
again, you know, I think this just, has anybody done their reverse experiment where you try to
actually mimic the way humans eat and you take two groups of mice and the controls are fed
whatever, a hundred percent of the nutrient, but they're fed every two hours over the course of
the day. And the CR group are given, you know, 70% of that, but they're fed at the same time
intervals constantly throughout the day. In other words, you make it purely a calorie thing and you
really take out the fasting except when they're sleeping. Yeah. Yeah. In fact, I think at least
one of these two studies that I was referring to did that, right? Oh, so that's how they were able
to identify that two thirds of the benefit came from the reduction in calories and a third of it
came from the additional fast. Right. Right. Exactly. So, and in my mind, I think this is
really important because this is one of the, this is one of the points that we made in our review
is if you look at the vast majority of the literature around intermittent fasting and
time restricted feeding and fasting mimicking diets, they're calorically restricted. So there,
there's a fasting period and a caloric restriction component. And none of the prior studies really,
really teased that out in a way that allowed us to have an understanding of how much is calories
and how much is fasting and maybe how much is when you're fasted. That's still, I think,
is an open question. Okay. So what else can we say about early fruit feeding versus late feeding?
What do we know about early in life? No, early in day versus late in day.
Yeah. I mean, this is an area I'll admit I'm not, I'm not an expert in. So I don't honestly have
an opinion about which is better. And again, this is where I think mice are not going to be a good
model for humans. So I think that we really, those studies need to be done in people. And again,
that gets- Now some have suggested that an early feeding window versus a late feeding window
produces better pairing of our insulin sensitivity to our nutrient arrival. I think that makes sense.
Most people would agree that particularly if you're eating something that causes your blood
sugar to spike, that doing that right before you go to bed, it probably suboptimal. So I think
maybe that can explain most of that, the observation that has been made that it might be better to do.
If you're going to do a time restricted feeding, it might be better early or somewhere, at least
not right before bedtime, I guess I would say. But again, I think these kinds of questions are
really complicated in humans because you could ask what benefit are we looking at? So if you're
looking at overnight blood glucose levels, sure. Makes no difference. Of course. If you're looking
at sleep quality, maybe it's going to be different. Or maybe it's going to be different in different
people. If you're looking at other biomarkers, again, it could be different. So I think it's,
again, in my mind at least, maybe you have a different opinion on this. In my mind at least,
it's not even really clear how we evaluate what is better and what is suboptimal.
It may depend on what your endpoint is, what you're actually interested in optimizing.
I mean, clinically we see in people who wear CGM that early feeding produces an overall lower
average glucose for sure. Because even if you get the same spike, let's say, if you're doing
the same meal early in the day versus late in the day, there's something about how long it takes to
come down at night versus in the morning. Now that could be you're more insulin sensitive in
the morning and therefore it comes down quicker. It could be something to do with pairing sleep
with the nutrition that is tweaking this and that there's a feedback loop where the excess glucose
creates a little more cortisol. You get a little more hepatic glucose up. But again,
I don't really know if that makes sense. I mean, I've heard people argue that, but at the same time,
you theoretically should have the lowest cortisol at night anyway. So that really shouldn't be an
issue. I don't really know what it is other than just to say I've observed it empirically.
Yeah. And it generally doesn't produce a great quality of sleep. But again, to me, this starts
to get into, which I want to hear more about, but this gets into the minutia of like, at some point,
you just got to focus more on other things. But I want to go down this rabbit hole just for the
sake of completeness. Yeah, sure. So I mean, again, I think to some extent that's almost where we
ended up, right? Was that it's, I guess, let me give the big picture answer for why I think
this is important. So I think these nutritional intervention studies in mice are very powerful
for dissecting the biological mechanisms that underlie the effects that they have.
And some of these diets clearly have effects on aging, right? I'm very, very hesitant to
suggest that people should adopt any of these diets based on the rodent literature where it's
at today. And I think there are a whole variety of reasons for that. But that's kind of where I
ended up, right? I think they're super useful for understanding the biology. I'm really not sure
that they're going to work the same way in humans. What did you learn about the protein restriction
in the ketogenic diet mechanistically in the mice? Yeah. So again, a couple things to say about that,
the ketogenic diet studies, there have really only been two that I'm aware of that looked at lifespan
and health span in mice. They were slightly different, but in mice, you have to go to really,
really low sugar to actually get the mice to go into ketosis. Yeah. I mean, these are essentially
1% or less carbohydrate diets. So again, that's a difference from people. One of the studies that
fed a ketogenic diet lifelong saw no effect on lifespan, but they did an intermittent ketogenic
diet. I don't remember the exact protocol, but it was something like every other day or maybe once
every three days or something. And there there was about a, I think a 15% increase in lifespan.
And I'm sorry, what did they do on the other days, the animals?
Regular diet. Sorry, regular diet. So it was just back and forth between the control diet and the
ketogenic diet. Yeah. And that didn't result in caloric restriction. That's the thing, the mice
were calorically restricted. So in some ways it's a intermittent caloric restriction, right? And this
is what I would say. It's also interesting because the fasting mimicking diet papers are intermittent
ketogenic diets. So, so I think that, you know, maybe that's one thing to agree on is that
intermittent ketogenic diets in mice can increase lifespan and seem to have benefits for health span.
But, but the ketogenic, the effects aren't huge, right? Again, that's the other take home,
I would say from, from our study. There are two nutritional interventions that
relatively consistently give big effects on lifespan. One is caloric restriction
and one is protein restriction. And they, you know, again, caloric restriction,
the, the most extreme study that I've seen is 65% restriction. And that gave about a 65%
increase in lifespan. So these are big, big, big sizes. I wasn't aware of that. Yeah. That's this
Wahlford and Weindrich and Wahlford paper. Okay. And when did they start that? And how long did
that restriction last? That's a good question. I don't remember. It was probably six or nine
months. I think most of their studies were, you know, early onset caloric restriction. And they,
this study was really interesting because they did, you know, a graded response from,
you know, 90%, 80%, 60%, 50%, 40% of ad lib. And you get essentially a graded response in lifespan
and it's roughly linear. So, so I think, you know, that's why I said about 60%
So 90% animals, 90%? No, but they didn't go that far. They didn't go beyond 60 or 65%.
And I also think this is an interesting study because I don't think you could do that study
today because the animal care wouldn't allow you to restrict by 60, 65%.
And an element that we don't think about enough, which is what were those, what did those mice
feel like? Like think about how angry those mice would have been on a third of their normal caloric
intake. I mean, you know, again, I haven't done these kind of mouse caloric restrictions studies
myself. I've obviously talked to a lot of people who did. I think to really appreciate that you've
got to probably be in the animal room, you know, feeding them, seeing them, right? Certainly,
activity goes up quite dramatically. That's one of the remarkable things about caloric restriction
in mice is that they are more active throughout life than ad lib fed mice are. And maybe it's a
sort of, you know, foraging response, evolutionarily selected foraging response, but but they are
definitely you give them a running wheel and they'll just run and run and run and run. So yeah,
there are behavioral changes for sure, in mice that are calorically restricted. And this is
actually one of my real concerns about caloric restriction in people. I mean, I think first of
all, you know, we should we should be realistic and recognize you're never going to get a significant
fraction of the population to calorically restrict, right? It's hard enough to get people to calorically
restrict down to a healthy weight. To get them to go 30% beyond that is just not going to happen.
But of the people I know who and I mean, being in this field, I know people who have done every
possible, you know, anti aging intervention you could imagine. And of the people I know,
I know a lot of people who've dabbled in various forms of caloric restriction.
Certainly true caloric restriction has real psychological consequences. And I and I really
would be concerned, I have been concerned for some of the people I know who've done this.
If a lot of you know, if we if we started trying to do this in in the general public, right, I mean,
there are there's social isolation that you get when you're calorically restricting, but then
there's, you know, the biological changes in the brain and you're hungry all the time. So again,
I just think we you know, we often don't appreciate those aspects of some of these nutritional
interventions. But in the mice, I think it's hard to know what their psychological consequences
are. What do we know about caloric restriction later in life in the mice versus earlier? I mean,
the sort of traditional thinking is you have a window in which you can do it early. And beyond
that, it's not as effective. I think we're going to talk about some data that counter that. And then
of course, you have the NIA experiment we talked about earlier in the monkeys where the early fast
didn't improve longevity, the late fast appears to have although that was sort of a subgroup
analysis. Hard to hard to draw causation there. Yeah. So so what I would say about the mice is
that for a long time, the sort of dogma was that caloric restriction didn't work if you started it,
you know, past, I don't know, 15 months of age, which is maybe the mouse equivalent of a
4050 year old person. So most of the early caloric restriction studies were done,
like I said, starting sometimes pre development, the early rat studies were pre development,
and then sometimes, you know, six, nine months of age. So that was sort of when I first started in
the field, that's kind of what I was told, like this is a settled question. Late more recent
studies that have been done in some ways more carefully, different diets, certainly. If you do
a graded onset of caloric restriction, in other words, don't go right from ad lib to 40% restriction
the next day, you do sort of a graded onset, you can get lifespan benefits from caloric restriction
you know, 20, 22 months of age. So whether it's as good as starting early, I think the consensus
is still that the answer is no, you're never going to get the same magnitude of benefit from
caloric restriction starting late as you do starting early. But that could be wrong. So I would say
that's the consensus. But I don't think we know we know for sure whether it's possible if you did
it just right, that you could get, you know, most or all of the benefits from starting late in life.
So Matt, on this topic of CR and mice, you know, again, the dogma has generally been,
and I've been victim of this just sort of blindly assuming it to be the case that, you know, CR and
mice only works early in life. Again, is that how applicable is that to humans? I don't know.
But, you know, a listener of the podcast actually pointed out that, you know, in fact, there are
some data that try to get at this question elsewhere. So there's this Hahn study 2019,
which we'll link to that looked at 800 female mice. Now, this is a pretty elegant experiment,
right? So for the first three months, they ran these mice out on an ad libitum diet. And then
at three months, they were split randomized to I believe a 40% calorie restriction versus ad lib.
They ran that out until 24 months. And then each of those groups was further split ad lib versus
continued on. So you had one group that was, everybody's the same till three months, one
group that spent the rest of their life on dietary restriction, one group that spent the rest of their
life ad lib, and then you had the middle groups. 21 months calorie restricted, then to ad lib,
21 months ad lib to then calorie restricted. Okay, so the ends of this were not interesting,
right? Meaning the ad lib group lived the shortest. We were looking at the figure earlier
today 1200 days, roughly, going back to a maximum lifespan. Yeah, maximum lifespan. That's right.
Median lifespan would have been looking at the graph about 900 days, which is pretty good.
So I was gonna say, how does that stack up with what we talked about on the last podcast about
length of life of control? That's a reasonable lifespan for control. I think if I remember
correctly, this was also done not in C57 black six, but in a little bit longer lived hybrid.
That's right, F1 hybrid. Yeah, so it's reasonable lifespan. Yeah. Okay. Looking at the all CR all
day mice, looks like they had a maximum lifespan of just below, they have to call it 1400 in chain
with a median that I'm going to say was about 1150. Yeah, so it's good, good lifespan extension.
Okay. So now what's interesting is the middle groups, which is really try, so I'm going to just
give you my little iPad so you can look at that table, which we'll link to. It's okay, I got it
right here. You got it right here? All right. I just love the picture. I remember the take-home
message. You do? Okay. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So what happened to the two middle groups? Right. So I
mean, the interesting thing, well, the one thing I would say is I think this is a pretty early onset
of CR. It really is three months. Yeah, this gets back to what I was talking about before that,
it seems likely from the early studies that were done in rats where they got some of these really,
really large effects that some of the benefits of CR come from actually being restricted during
development itself. So I think that's useful to put into context. So then the big question here is
what happens if you start caloric restriction late in life or what this study did that I'm not
really aware of anybody doing previously is kind of the flip. It's almost like a crossover.
That's right. Yeah, totally is. Yeah. So in this case, when they started CR late in life,
there is a significant but not huge effect. The magnitude of the lifespan extension is
much less than in the mice that were on CR from three months of age. That makes sense. That fits
with what else is in the literature. There were earlier studies. I think Steve Spindler did one,
not too many years, maybe four or five years before this one that did sort of a similar sort of
approach that starting around 15 months of age. And they saw a significant but not as large benefit
from starting late in life. So that seems to be the consensus. The thing that's really interesting
here is what happens if you're CR'd for an earlier period in life and then back on AL?
Do you lose the benefit? And it seems like the answer is no. Those animals actually were longer
lived than the mice that went on CR late in life. So you could ask some questions about is it about
the total amount of your life that you're restricted? Is it about when you go on and when you come off?
And I think in mice, this is still an open question. We don't really know what the mechanisms are.
Although the early in life mice had a longer median. The median life expectancy was longer.
The ones that were on CR and then switched to ad lib. Yes, that's right.
So they lived a little bit longer, but the bigger difference was the median life expectancy was
higher than the flipped group. Yes, although I think we have a little bit difference in
definitions. I tend to think first about median. You seem to think first about maximum. But yeah,
I think what you're saying is right. The median lifespan is quite different in those two groups.
That's right. It is the difference. The maximum is very trivial. That's right. So I think, again,
the real question here is, well, aside from what does this mean for humans, which I would say,
we can't draw too many conclusions from humans from this, but what is the underlying mechanism?
Is it really just about the total amount of time that you've been on CR? Or is there an interaction
with how old you are, the developmental process, and then what happens at the end of life, which is
mostly the degenerative process and when you go on CR? I think maybe one thing that's worth adding
to this too is it's an interesting comparison to what we know about mTOR and rapamycin. So with
rapamycin, the data are pretty clear that you can start rapamycin certainly well into middle age
and maybe even into very old age and get most of the benefit. So if you compare the curve here,
where they started the mice on CR at 22 or 24 months, whatever it is, the effect is pretty small
compared to CR. With rapamycin, you get almost exactly the same benefit starting at 20, 22,
24 months as you do starting early in life. So that might tell us that there's a difference.
There's a different mechanism potentially as well. It could be that rap is doing something different
or it's a different dose effect relative to it. Yeah, exactly. So that's an open question
exactly why it's different, but it seems to be different. I'm really glad you brought that up
because we talked about that with Rich Miller on his podcast, which was a fortuitous accident
basically because they couldn't get the formulation of rapamycin. My favorite story in
science. One of my favorite stories in science. Yeah, tell people that story. Yeah, right. So
take a step back. The NIA started this program called the Interventions Testing Program. It must
have been the early 90s and the idea here was maybe it was early 2000s. Sorry, I'm dating myself
again, losing my decades. So early 2000s. And the idea here was I think really smart. The idea was
that we could create a tool where the scientific community could nominate interventions for
lifespan testing in mice and it was set up so that it would be done in triplicate. So there are
three sites. There still are three sites for the ITP. So anybody in the community can nominate
any intervention. There's a selection committee that selects them every year. And if an intervention
is selected, then the intervention testing program sites start the cohorts of mice on that
intervention in whatever year it was selected for. So sometime back in the early 2000s, Dave Sharp
nominated rapamycin. And in some ways he was ahead of his time because this was, I think when he
nominated rapamycin, it was even before the first invertebrate studies on mTOR and rapamycin. It was
right around the same time they were being published. So he I think was thinking about
it from a cancer perspective primarily. In any case, he nominated rapamycin, it got selected,
it went into the cohort and they typically test five or six interventions or drugs each year.
So they have a huge number of animals at each of these three sites that are destined for these
interventions to be tested in and rapamycin was one of them. And Randy Strong, who's one of the
PIs on the high TP, who's also got a strong biochemistry background, I think recognized
pretty quickly that the rapamycin wasn't stable in the food. We could actually come back to this if
you want to, because this is relevant for people as well. And it gets broken down in the pH of the
gut. So basically, if they just put the powder in the food, there's no bioavailability. It doesn't
get taken up by the mice. And so they recognized that right when they were supposed to start the
experiment. And you know, of course, they were like, crap, what do we do? You know, we could just
not test rapamycin. And I don't know if it was Randy or who somebody said, well, I think I can
figure out a way to stabilize the rapamycin, put it in the food so that we can give it to the mice
and we can do the lifespan experiment. I think what they didn't recognize was that it was going
to take 18 months or so to figure this out. So once they finally developed this in what they call
e-RAPA, encapsulated rapamycin, it's basically designed so that it won't break down in the
gastric pH. Once they developed that, they were now 18 months into this lifespan experiment.
Before this, everybody, I think everybody, myself included in the field, thought you had to start
early in life or you weren't going to get much of a benefit. There was really almost no chance a drug
was going to increase lifespan starting that late in life. But fortunately, they went ahead with the
experiment starting at 20 months of age. And what they found was that they got this robust lifespan
extension from starting with rapamycin treatment at 20 months of age. And just to give some context,
that's about the mouse equivalent of a 60 or 65 year old person. And I love the experiment.
I love the outcome obviously, because, you know, first of all, nobody thought it was going to work,
except maybe Rich Miller, maybe I'll give Rich credit, maybe he thought it was going to work.
And it was really the first time anybody had convincingly shown that you could start an
intervention in middle age in a mouse and get robust lifespan extension. And for me,
honestly, I reviewed that paper. And when I first time I saw that result, I'm like,
this changes everything. We actually have a chance for translational geroscience, because
you might be able to intervene late in the aging process and have significant impact.
So honestly, that was 2009 when the paper came out. So in the 13 years since then,
the whole paradigm in the field has changed, right? Most people who are studying interventions today
are studying things that they test for efficacy late in life, because that's what we need to do
in people. So it was a super important result for the field for that reason. And it all came
about by an accident. Nobody would have designed that study that way beforehand, right? So yeah,
it's fortuitous for sure. Now you were going to make a point about the bioavailability of
rapa as well. This is something that's only recently come across my radar, but I've heard
several results now that convinced me that it's true. So I mentioned the reason why they had to
make this e-rapa is because rapamycin isn't stable at the gastric pH of mice. Same thing seems to be
true in people. So there are people who are getting their rapamycin from the rapamune,
which is the brand name generic or the brand name cerolimus that comes in these triangle-shaped
pills. There are also people who are getting it from compounding pharmacies. And I've heard of
several cases now where the bioavailability is much lower in the compounded rapamycin in a capsule
than in the actual rapamein. The white and yellow triangle. Yeah. So it's just something for people
to be aware of. And I don't think most physicians are aware of it. I don't think most compounding
pharmacies are aware of it. We've never had it compounded. So we've only prescribed
cerolimus or rapamune. And it's not a cheap drug. So I can understand why there's a desire to
compound it because it's got to be like five, six bucks a milligram. Yeah. I think that's about
right. So Matt, obviously one of the other things that came out of that review article in the animal
stuff was, as you said, the protein restriction. And I think of all the topics in nutrition,
this is the one I'm most interested in. I really don't care that much about fat and carbs. Don't
tell anybody. But I care an awful lot about protein. In fact, when you came over today,
you probably saw me chasing down what was left of a protein shake. And I think I was mentioning to
you or my wife, that's the only part of nutrition that is kind of, I don't want to say a chore,
but it's a very deliberate part of how I go about the day, which is I really have to think about it.
And the reason is I'm trying to eat a gram of protein per pound of body weight spread out into
four buckets. Right. Right. Because if you, you know, I think there's reasonable evidence to
suggest that if you consume too much protein in one sitting, and it's typically more than about
0.25 grams per pound is the general thinking you're going to end up oxidizing some of that protein.
So it's not that it's harmful. It's just that you're not getting the amino acids you need for
muscle protein synthesis, which is of course our objective. So that means I'm kind of walking
around trying to get 40 grams here, 40 grams there, 40 grams here, 40 grams there. And truthfully,
that's not trivial if you're not willing to consume a whole bunch of crap with it. I mean,
if you're really just trying to focus on the protein quality. So look, the RDA says I'm crazy,
right? The recommended daily allowance of protein is 0.8 grams per kilogram. Right. Which is less
than half of what I would consume. Why, where do you see the, and by the way, it's not just that
I'm making up the amount that I'm consuming. I'm doing it on the basis of other data that suggests
that this is the amount of protein consumption you need for optimal muscle protein synthesis.
Right. So where does this disconnect? Yeah. So I mean, I think first of all,
we can talk about the rodent studies, right, which is in the biology of aging. I think the RDA
question, you know, that there, that that's a different question. It's my understanding that
that actually was developed to be a protein balance for 95% of the population when sedentary.
Right. So I think what that means, first of all, that's a minimum amount, not necessarily the
optimal amount. And it probably very much depends on lifestyle. Right.
And lean body mass to begin with, even though it's sort of normalized too.
So I think, I think, and the reason why I bring this up is I think there's a lot, again, a lot of
confusion among the general public about what the RDA means. And it's not, it's not necessarily a
bad thing to be above the RDA in some areas, right? Maybe a lot of areas. So I think that's just
worth, worth, you know, expanding on just, just a little bit.
Yeah, I think I agree completely. I, I sort of jokingly think of the RDA for protein as what
you need to not waste away and wither up and die.
Right. Exactly. Yeah. So right. So you're not losing muscle mass. Yeah. So, so then the question
of what is the relationship between protein and aging, I think is a really important one. And
it's gotten a lot of attention in the field. And like I think a lot of other things, there's a lack
of clarity about what we actually know and what we should be recommending to people. So let's take a
step back and start with the animal studies that the mouse studies. I think there it's pretty clear
that you can extend lifespan through protein restriction. And there are actually, again,
a couple of flavors of protein restriction. You can restrict all protein down to, you know, some,
some percentage, some low percentage, or you can restrict specific amino acids, particularly
branched chains, tryptophan, methionine, or branched chain amino acids are the ones that have been
studied. And, and again, I make that distinction because it's not really clear that the mechanisms
are the same across these different flavors of protein restriction. The common mechanism
that, that does seem to potentially underlie all of these forms of protein restriction is inhibition
of mTOR. And again, that's partly why this becomes complicated when we, especially when we start
talking about extrapolation to human, you and I both recognize that inhibition of mTOR can have
beneficial effects in the context of aging and health span, certainly in mice, almost certainly
in people, I would say. And protein is an activator of mTOR. And we know a fair amount about the
biochemistry of that, that, that particularly branched chain amino acids can directly activate
mTOR through cestrines. And that's sort of all worked out. And so it seems counter, it seems
intuitive that protein restriction would be beneficial by turning down mTOR. It seems counter
intuitive that that what you were just talking about would be beneficial because you might be
hyperactivating mTOR. So we can dive into that. But I think that that's kind of the, that's the,
that's the simplest possible mechanism I can think of for why protein restriction, especially
branched chain amino acid restriction would be having an impact on lifespan and health span
in mice. The other player that seems to be important, particularly in total protein restriction
is a protein called FGF21, fibroblast growth factor 21, that is secreted in response to a
low protein diet, and then has effects on liver metabolism and also inhibition of mTOR reduction
of IGF-1. So that seems to be required for the lifespan extension that is seen from protein
restriction in mice, potentially partially upstream of mTOR and, and liver metabolism.
The interesting thing there is FGF21 overexpression by itself has also been reported to be sufficient
to extend lifespan in mice. So, so it kind of fits that that, that could be part of the story.
So the question then, one question is, is protein restriction always beneficial in mice? And can we
separate it from caloric restriction? And so this is where you really have to look closely at the
studies and determine, you know, did the mice on protein restriction eat less, eat the same amount
and eat more? And it's interesting because you can actually find examples of all of those. And
honestly, I don't really understand why that's the case, except it's something about the different
compositions of the diet. What does seem to be the case is that when you restrict for certain
amino acids, you're, if you're deficient for a methionine, for example, or tryptophan, the mice
absolutely will eat more and they don't gain weight. And they do seem to live a little bit longer.
So that could be a somewhat distinct mechanism there that we don't really understand.
So tell me what was the most compelling evidence you saw when you tried to tease apart the
relationship between protein and total intake? So again, I think the branched chain amino acid
and methionine restriction studies are pretty clear that those animals are consuming more
calories, more calories than certainly if you matched a weight, then they add libitum mice
and they're living longer. And what do we think is the route or mechanism through which methionine
exerts this effect? I don't know that that's still really being worked out. There are lots
of mechanisms that have been proposed. I suspect mTOR plays a role. People have thought about,
so of course, methylation, methyl donors are important for a bunch of different epigenetic
modifications. So there may be a role there going back to the epigenome that we talked about.
Methionine is the first amino acid in every protein. So there could be effects on protein
synthesis. There's evidence linking methionine restriction to sulfur amino acid biology,
which has been implicated in aging. So it's hard to know and maybe it's not one thing.
And those all sound like potentially just a substrate reduction problem, right? Like less
sulfur cross bridging, less protein synthesis. Right. Well, yeah. And again, if you look back
in the literature in the invertebrates, inhibition of protein synthesis in some cases is enough to
extend lifespan. And of course, mTOR is a primary regulator of protein synthesis. So when you inhibit
mTOR, you can also inhibit protein synthesis. So that's part of the challenge here is this network
is so interconnected that when you tweak one part of it, you have effects throughout the network. And
it's really hard to know which of those effects are causal. So let's talk about time course, right?
So when you consume a protein rich meal, do we have a sense of how long mTOR is being activated
in response to that set of amino acids? I'm sure somebody does. I don't know the answer to that. I
mean, I think again, almost certainly it's going to depend on what you eat in combination with
the protein when you eat. Yeah, exactly. Like how active you are. I remember talking to David
Sabatini about this through the lens of BCAA drinks. Yeah. So if you're going to pound
branched amino acids during a workout because you want as much anabolic signal as possible.
And this is a couple of years ago. So maybe things have changed. But based on that work,
I think Bobby Sutton had done the work in his lab from getting his name right. Was it Bobby?
Sutton was the guy who did that science paper that looked at the leucine sensor on mTOR.
Right. The answer was it didn't stay on long at all. Yeah. Free amino acids were so short in
their ability to turn on mTOR that unless you had an intravenous drip of this stuff, it was going
to be very difficult. So much so that the idea of using BCAA analogs to treat sarcopenia was going to
require drugs that could stay on much longer. Is that kind of within your frame of thinking?
I think so. And I think it also makes sense in a biological context. I mean, cells and tissues,
again, this gets back to the whole homeostasis concept. Cells and tissues have evolved to
maintain metabolites and amino acids are metabolites. They're involved in many different
metabolic reactions within certain levels. And there are all sorts of mechanisms to ensure that
at a metabolite, it's outside of that range that we soak it up. We do something else with it. So
I think it makes sense that you're probably not going to have a persistent increase in
branched-chain amino acids far outside the normal range. What I would say though, is that slightly
elevated branched-chain amino acids chronically can have big effects on the downstream processes.
And there are some inborn diseases of childhood where you have elevated levels of branched-chain
amino acids. We know that there are consequences to even having somewhat modest increases in
hyperactivation of mTOR signaling chronically. So again, I think the context really matters.
But yes, it's my intuition that it's probably hard to get very large, persistent increases in mTOR
simply from taking a branched-chain amino acid supplement. Doesn't mean you couldn't have some
effect on muscle building right after a workout. But I suspect it's hard to have long-term
persistent effects on the initial. I mean, the anabolic data suggests it's not necessary.
It's just, again, muscle protein synthesis window is open long enough that simply delivering a great
source of whey protein in the hours after a workout seems sufficient to not restrict
muscle potential growth. I think the other thing though that is also important to appreciate,
and this is true with rapamycin as well. I think a lot of people get confused about this,
is it's not only about how high mTOR gets turned on or how low it gets turned down.
It's also about where that happens. And this is, again, people for a long time thought that
rapamycin would cause muscle loss. We don't see that. We just don't see it in mice and we don't
see it in people. And I think it's probably because- I'm guessing you're not seeing in dogs.
We have not seen anything to suggest that in dogs. So I'm guessing that has as much to do with how
much, maybe more to do with where mTOR is being affected than how much we're inhibiting mTOR,
when we're inhibiting mTOR. And so I think the same thing's probably-
And do we know where the selectivity of rapamycin is? I mean, is it more selective in hepatocytes?
Is it more selective in adipose tissue? I mean-
I don't know of any good studies that have really carefully looked at this. There have been a few
studies in mice that tried to look at tissue mTOR signaling in the context of rapamycin.
Again, this is-
It's a very technically challenging problem.
Well, and this is what I was just going to say, it gets even more complicated because even in a
mouse where you can essentially control almost everything, right? What the mice are eating and
when they last eight has, if anything, as big, maybe bigger effect on mTOR signaling than
rapamycin, right? So there have been, like I said, a couple studies that looked at this and
I'm not sure, and they got different answers and I'm not sure who to believe because I don't think-
The only way I could imagine doing this is you have to be able to do subtractive studies where
you have to be able to do it in the context of a whole bunch of different diets first,
get kind of a baseline that you then pull out of potentially what you're seeing.
Yeah, it just gets complicated.
It's complicated. And again, that's why I often will gravitate back towards what are the
functional consequences we can actually measure, right? Sure, I get it. You think that treating a
mouse with rapamycin is going to cause sarcopenia? Let's do the experiment and find out. The answer
is no, it doesn't, right? So that tells us it's at least not as simple as we thought it was going to
be. We certainly don't understand all of it.
Now, what about the flip side of that is more protein versus less protein activating
mTOR in a way that is counterproductive?
I think it can. I think there are certainly cases where it can. Again, I don't know that
anybody has really carefully done that study in mice. There was a study, it's a really interesting
study by Steve Simpson and colleagues where they did this nutritional geometry work where they
basically looked at different compositions of carbohydrates, fats.
Steve Simpson, he's in Australia.
Yeah, exactly. And looked at, I don't remember how many diets, there's a whole range of diets,
different compositions of the three macronutrients. Tried to control for caloric intake, which is
hard as you can imagine, but I think they did a pretty good job. And then asked, what does it
look like in terms of metabolism, energy expenditure, lifespan? So the lifespan studies, I think, are
pretty clear that most of the diets where the mice lived the longest were towards the low end
in protein. But there were some things that I think called into question exactly what was going
on there because it wasn't the case that the diets that were energetically lowest gave the
longest lifespan, as you might expect from caloric restriction. And the diet that actually
gave the absolute longest lifespan had like, I don't know, it was like a 40% protein in it.
So the way I interpret that is that there are many ways to get to-
And how calorie restricted was that?
They were not calorically restricted at all.
So you're saying that a diet that was ad lib with 40% protein had the best outcome?
The best absolute lifespan, yes.
Again, how do we even reconcile this body of literature?
Yeah, and this is sort of where I was just going is I think that my view is there are
probably multiple paths to longevity. And we really don't understand the inner relationships
of these macronutrients in the diet with enough sophistication to get beyond sort of broad
general predictions. And again, I sort of- This is an area where I really- I believe,
like I can't prove it, but my intuition from the data that I've seen and just my observations
of people is that in humans, it's probably very- this relationship between protein and
health during aging is probably very different than it is in mice. I think mice are able to tolerate
a very low protein diet without some of the consequences that we see in people. That's my
intuition. I don't know that that's true. That's my intuition.
I mean, it's my intuition as well because clinically what we see in what I call the
death bars. The death bars is our internal nomenclature for how people die. We just
constantly look at death bars and we double click and double click and double click all the way
to try to tease out everything that is reducing lifespan and health span. And the problems that
occur in humans when they are under muscled are insane. And it ranges from the metabolic
consequences of being under muscled. Our muscles are a sink for glucose. They are the single most
important sink we have for glucose and our ability to tolerate glucose and maintain glucose
homeostasis in the presence of larger, more metabolically healthy muscles is the difference
between having diabetes and not having diabetes. Furthermore, when you think about sarcopenia and
when you think about osteoporosis, which again, I just don't think we're talking about how these
things impact animals. Like we don't study any animal, including primates in a setting where
sarcopenia and osteoporosis are problematic. And yet I would ask anyone to consider the entire
population that they know over the age of 75. And I would ask you take every person that is
alive today that's over 75 and tell me how many of them are not suffering at least some consequence
of one or both of those phenomenon. And if somebody did that analysis, I would be shocked
if we didn't find at least 80% of people over the age of 75 are experiencing this. And if you look
at the activity, just monitor the activity level of people over the once they hit 75,
they fall off a cliff. So muscle mass dramatically plummets activity levels dramatically plummet.
Difficult to say which one's feeding which. But there's no question that something is happening
to our species at about the age of 75. That is a structural problem. And none of this other stuff
matters if that sucks, right? Like I don't care if I live to 100 and don't have cancer if I'm
an invalid for the last 25 years and I can't play with my grandkids and throw a ball. Like for me
personally, I'm not saying that's a, that's not a view that everyone should take in the world.
I'm just saying that's my view. Yeah. Yeah. And I mean, I think that's absolutely correct. I guess
the question, and I think this is still where some of the confusion comes from is
how important is dietary protein in that maintenance of muscle or loss of muscle in people who are
going to go the wrong direction? And I think the data is that it is quite important. I mean,
there are lots of studies that have compared the RDA versus kind of the double RDA standard. And
it's a significant difference. Protein makes a very big difference, following obviously
the training that is necessary to stimulate muscle protein synthesis. So I think those have
to be coupled to some extent. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah. I believe there are data, and I hate when
I have to say this, because I just, I'm going to say something and it's going to be wrong and 20
people are going to respond. It's okay. I do it all the time. In anticipation of the fact that
there are data that I've read and I don't have the memory I once had, I believe there are data
that show just the protein difference alone can make some difference, but it's not nearly the
difference you get when you pair it with hypertrophy training. Yeah. That's my recollection as well,
right? Which brings us to the interesting question then, why is it that there is a camp? And in my
field, it's a pretty vocal camp in the aging field, right? That would argue that low protein is the
best nutritional strategy for aging and health span in people. And this gets back to the point
I started with, which is that you can find the answer you want for almost any question in this
area that intersects with nutrition and aging. There will be a study, right? That will fit your
belief. So I think you really have to be careful, or I try at least to take a global view and try to
understand what is the totality of the data say, right? But there are epidemiological studies and
one in the field that most people will point to when they go to humans and they talk about
low protein. And it was this study that Walter Longo was, I think the senior author on and Morgan
Levine was the first author on where they looked at protein consumption and all-cause mortality
as a function of age in people. There were some studies in, I think they had some yeast studies
in there as well, maybe some cell culture studies, but they looked at the take-home message was that
low protein is beneficial up to about 65 years of age. And then once you get above 65 years of age,
it kind of flips and people who ate a higher protein diet have lower all-cause mortality.
It should be clear when I say beneficial, we're talking specifically about all-cause mortality.
Which at the end of the day is a very important metric.
Sure, you want to be alive.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It's not the most important metric necessarily. You could argue it's equally
important to the health span metrics, but it might, I mean, that's, that's a, okay. So let's make sure
people understand what that means. That means below the age of 65, the epidemiologic data in
this study suggested people eating less protein had lower mortality in all-cause mortality. And
above 65, you saw that reverse.
That's right. Yeah.
Now, did that paper make any attempt to quantify the net impact on mortality? Because the very
misleading thing about an assessment like that is when you look at mortality adjusted by population,
before the age of 65, it's relatively low. Above the age of 65, it goes up very non-linearly.
So when we do our death bar analysis, it's like, you know, this is the death per 100,000 people.
If you're 40, 50, 60, 70, 80, 90, like, you know what I mean? It just, it becomes insane.
So you could argue through that analysis that you're much better off with a high protein strategy,
even if it's throughout life, because the absolute reduction in mortality would unquestionably be
lower as a result of the benefit you would have later in life.
So I would, I absolutely agree with conceptually with what you said, right? The impact of a change
in mortality late in life is going to usually swamp the impact, certainly swamp the impact,
the same impact on mortality early in life. I think the question here is what are the relative
effects, right? And so they did try, they did model this a little bit. And it is in their model,
which I couldn't get the data for, like, I don't know, I can't evaluate exactly what they did.
But in their model, the relative risk crossed somewhere, you know, in the 60s, right? In other
words, you know, your, your total mortality benefit was lower eating a high protein diet,
I think it was starting somewhere in the 60s. And that actually surprised me, because, because for
exactly the reason you said the relative impact of the high protein diet early in life would have to
be an order of magnitude greater than the relative impact of the. So I'm sorry, say what they're
finding was again, at the age of my, I don't remember the exact number. It's in the paper,
right? You can see the curves, you can see the curves crossed. It was much later than I thought
it would be, given that 65 was the point that they kind of pick. I see. I would have thought maybe in
your 50s. So I actually tried to do my own modeling of this off of the data that I that I could find
on, you know, relative risk for low and high protein. Again, where you what you define low,
what you define high, you know, there, and you're trying to ask the question, when should you switch
the diet? Or maybe more formally, at what age do they does the risk equal out? Yeah, right. What's
the crossover? Yeah. Yeah. And what did you find? So mine was closer to like 50. Yep. That that's,
that's the point where once you get past 50, they're the benefit of a high protein diet
on mortality seems to outweigh any detriment that you would get from. So that's odd to me,
because whether it's 50 or 60, Matt, it's a benefit on mortality, which is really, I think,
we're more of the argument is there's can't be any benefit on health span. From low protein? No,
from high protein. Early in life or late? Why? Why can't there be a benefit? Oh, late in life,
I'm saying. Why not? Well, I'm saying like, if your protein restricted late in life, I mean,
I think low protein has no benefit on. Yeah, well, I mean, again, unless so I would agree with you,
intuitively, but I also exclude special cases. So I'm not talking about people who have renal
insufficiency for whom they have to, you know, yeah, I agree with you conceptually. The only
thing that makes me hesitate a little bit is I've just seen like I was talking about the mouse
rapamycin experiments where everybody who knew anything about muscle said that if you gave a
mouse rapamycin throughout life, it was going to get sarcopenia. That just didn't happen. So,
but I'm saying we have clinical data that suggests that when people over the age of 65
are protein deficient versus protein significant, there's a huge difference in muscle mass,
which we know is going to be associated with frailty and poor outcomes. I would totally agree
with that. I mean, I think that it's very likely to be true. I think what we don't, again,
I don't know, do we have controlled studies where people were eating low protein and doing
resistance training late in life? I mean, they're nuance here that could complicate.
But I think in general, you're probably. I think the other area where this gets very
complicated is the, I don't want to say by necessity, but just by convention, we use IGF-1
as a biomarker for protein intake. Yeah. And it's certainly associated with protein intake, but
you want to tell people what IGF-1 is, you know, a little bit of background of, you know,
where it comes from and what it's a proxy for. Sure. So IGF-1 is insulin like growth factor one.
It's a hormone that's in the growth hormone pathway. So, you can think of it as a growth
promoting hormone. Sort of part of this central pathway that promotes growth in many, many
different tissues. So, if you have high growth hormone levels, you'll have high IGF-1 levels
and that, and high mTOR, right? So, this is a part of the mTOR pathway as well, upstream of mTOR.
So, the reason why people have been really interested in IGF-1 in the field of aging
biology, it comes, you know, from studies again in the very simple laboratory model systems. So,
the most famous and one of the first genes that was shown to clearly from a mechanistic perspective
affect aging is it comes from Cynthia Canyon and even Tom Johnson a little bit before her,
which is the insulin like receptor in C. elegans called DAF2. And Cynthia published a classic
paper showing that if you make a mutation in DAF2, you could double the lifespan of worms and they
seem to be healthier about twice as long. And what that mutation does is it turns down
signaling through this pathway. Now, it's a little bit more complicated in worms because it's called
the insulin IGF-1 like signaling pathway. So, it's not identical. And so, there's one pathway in
worms that kind of takes the place of both IGF-1 signaling and insulin signaling. But you can kind
of think of them as equivalent. And then there are a whole bunch of studies in mice for mostly
mutations in the growth hormone upstream signaling, upstream of IGF-1 that lead to increased lifespan.
So, this means GH does not activate the production of more IGF-1. That's right. So, you have
through a variety of mechanisms. You have high GH, low IGF-1 animals. Well, low GH signaling, right?
Yeah, but they probably are high in IGF. Oftentimes, it's the receptor that's mutated.
That's right. Yeah. So, those animals tend to be very long-lived. They rival caloric restriction
in terms of the magnitude of lifespan extension. And there are several different mutations in that
pathway. The mutations in IGF-1, I guess I should know the current state of that literature a little
bit better. It's complicated. And there have been some controversies in the field about the different
mutations that directly affect IGF-1 itself and the effects on lifespan. So, I'm not going to
wade into that because I think it still hasn't been resolved. But there's no question that
mutations that reduce growth hormone signaling in mice extend lifespan. Now, it's important to
understand though that with one exception, those studies are all cases where the animals are growth
hormone signaling deficient through development. So, they are very, very small animals. And then
they have constitutively low levels of signaling through that pathway for the rest of their life.
There's one study that I think it used a monoclonal antibody to the IGF-1 receptor in mice. This is
from Nir Barzilai and Haseko. Where they treated mice with this antibody late in life and they got
a reasonably sized lifespan extension. I think it was, I don't know, 14, 15% median lifespan.
That was an antibody that did not penetrate the CNS, if I recall. I remember Nir talking about
this and saying you would get all the benefits of IGF in the brain without the potential harm of IGF
in the periphery. Right. Yeah. And that's another complication, right? Where the effects of IGF in
the brain might be fundamental on for health span and cognitive function might be fundamentally
different than IGF-1 in the periphery. So, that study I think is the best evidence in mice that
you can get some benefit specifically from reducing IGF-1 signaling in middle age.
And this is such an important question I get asked all the time. I have a lot of patients that are
asking to be put on growth hormone. Yeah. And we just don't do it. And the reason is I just
am not comfortable with, I don't see enough data in humans to suggest that it's necessarily safe.
Conversely, I don't really see evidence to suggest it's not. Yeah. This is sort of the weird thing
with growth hormone. Like if you buy hook, line and sinker, the argument that more growth hormone
equals more IGF equals more mortality, and you look at how much growth hormone is being used.
I mean, it is hands down the most abused drug in sports. It's like it's first, second, third,
nobody's even within the zip code. Yeah. And this is going back 35, maybe 40 years,
probably to the early 80s. Where are the bodies? Yeah. Like there need to be more bodies. So,
I'm stuck with, like I don't see where the bodies are, but at the same time, it's still a bit of a
leap for me. And I don't have the luxury of rapamycin data where I can at least point to
all of the humans who have taken rapamycin for 23 years. And we know what that looks like. And then
even though it's not for zero protection, and then all of the mechanistic stuff that is consistently
pointing the right way. So, you know, there's going to be some patient of mine listening to this
saying, Peter, you almost talked me into taking growth hormone based on your discussion. And it's
like, no, I can't. You know, it's funny. I even took it for a week after my shoulder surgery.
I had sort of looked at some literature using GH and anabolic steroids to help with recovery.
And it could have been true true and unrelated, but like I felt the worst I've ever felt after
a week of growth hormone and androlone. And I was like, yeah, I'm done. I just abandoned it. Now,
again, I think it was I was I happened to be sick as well. But my blood pressure went up,
my blood sugar went up. I felt like crap. I couldn't sleep. Again, a lot of confounding
factors, shoulder surgery and a nasty virus. So again, it could all be irrelevant. But I think I
think the point you made is actually a really important one. So first of all, you know,
obviously, I've never given growth hormone to anyone. I've never taken growth hormone. My,
you know, I'm not an expert in the human application of growth hormone. But I've certainly
tried to follow that literature, you know, because based on the mouse studies, you would have
predicted, right, that growth hormone therapy should be the most toxic therapy you could give
a human. Yeah, certainly should should cause increased risk for a bunch of different diseases,
including cancer, mostly cancer. Yeah. Yeah. And my understanding of the literature here is that,
like you said, it's not clear that there are significant benefits, particularly for strength,
I think, I think there's some evidence that muscle mass may increase, but but strength doesn't.
But it's also not clear that there's any real detriment, right, that there's any significant
risk, which is a little bit surprising. It is surprising. And I do have a couple of patients
who have taken it. Usually other doctors were prescribing it or, you know, they came in under
the care of somebody else. And they all seem to claim they feel infinitely better on it.
There may be something to that, right? It might be that in 20 years, we have enough data to say,
you know what, by the time you're 60, you should just be on a slow amount of growth hormone for
all of these reasons. I'd love to see somebody do this study. Because again, it's, it's a very
important question to be asked. And I also think we have enough data to suggest that such a study
is not unethical, right? In other words, we don't have an abundance of data. In fact, we have a
paucity of data suggesting its harm, that it would justify ethically doing a study like this.
So anyway, that's, that's sort of a hope I would have because I, I really find this to be one of
the most confusing questions in this space. Yeah, I agree. And again, I think, you know,
this is sort of why I've, I personally have settled around the idea for now, at least that,
that that IGF one particularly is, is probably not that informative in people, particularly,
you know, once you get past 50 years, 50 years is arbitrary, but that's kind of where I would,
I would put the number. Obviously, again, IGF one itself is complicated because you don't really
know what that means in terms of IGF one signaling and downstream activity. But yeah,
important, I guess, for people to understand that just like testosterone is mostly bound
to sex and binding globulin, there's only a small amount of testosterone that's free.
It's the same with IGF one, it has these IGF BPs or binding proteins that bind most of it.
And therefore, total IGF is not really completely informative as to what's happening,
even in terms of the quantity that's there for signaling, because it's not the unbound portion
of it. So some people look at things like IGF to IGF BP ratio, the bigger that number is, in theory,
the more IGF signaling you would have. But, you know, this gets to now when you look at sort of
the epidemiologic curves, which on the x-axis would show in, you know, deciles or quartiles or
whatever buckets IGF levels rising, and then on the y-axis would show you mortality. I've never
seen one of those curves that just goes up. Yeah. Right. They're sometimes they're U-shaped,
sometimes they're downsloped, sometimes they're flat, and it depends on the indication. Yeah.
But the story seems much more complicated than IGF is bad. I agree. And again, I think, you know,
going back to the Levine paper that we were talking about, again, I think it's an important
paper, it's a well done paper. You really have to recognize that the population you're looking in
might make a big difference as well, right? So we, you know, if you're talking about a population
of people where 30% of them are obese, some high percentage have metabolic disease or diabetes,
you know, having high IGF-1 in that context might be very different than somebody who is,
you know, appropriate rate, exercising, eating a high protein diet, right? And again, that those
kinds of things don't typically come out in these epidemiological studies. The other thing I'll say
is, you know, in kind of thinking about what we might talk about today, you know, I went and tried
to look through the literature and see what other studies have shown, you know, that that same
relationship and they're all over the place. You can find studies that really don't show
any for protein, protein consumption, particularly, you can find studies epidemiological that really
don't show any downside to eating a high protein diet in people. So it's hard to, it's hard for me
to draw too much confidence that high protein is significantly detrimental when you're younger than
50. And I feel pretty confident that a higher, at least certainly higher than the RDA level of
dietary protein intake when you're above 50 is beneficial, particularly if you're exercising. I
mean, that's where I would be a little bit concerned. If you've got somebody who's overweight,
obese, diabetic, sedentary, so high calorie plus high protein could be problematic.
Totally agree. Yeah. Yeah. I think that's a, and by the way, I frankly think a lot of the epidemiology
is tainted by that. Yeah. It's high protein in the context of high calorie. Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
The other thing that I think is also potentially interesting to think about in human are these
people who have mutations in the growth hormone pathway, right? So this is now maybe more akin
to these mouse models where they have low growth hormone signaling, you know, from development,
even in utero potentially, they go through their entire lives. There have been a couple of studies,
again, Walter Longo, obviously prolific in this area, had a study on these, the little people of
Ecuador, right? There have been several studies, but the most- The La Ron Dwarfs. Yeah, that's
right. The La Ron syndrome. Yeah. The most famous study is one that was published in Science where
they looked at lifespan and age related health outcomes in the people with low growth hormone
signaling versus controls in their same- Environment.
Environment. Yeah. It's a really fascinating study. Yeah, it is. So I mean, I think that,
again, the interesting things are there's no difference in lifespan,
but the people with low levels of growth hormone signaling, the reduction in cancer risk is
profound. I mean, I don't remember the exact numbers, but I think it was zero. Like I think
they did not have any- Maybe there was one person in their cohort who developed a cancer. I don't
remember what it was and she was treated and then she lived the rest of her life, but none of them
died from cancer. And the rate of diabetes was lower in the little people, but Ecuador,
at least that part of Ecuador at that time, had a very low diabetes rate to begin with,
something 5%. So it's a little bit harder to say, but certainly cancer, dramatic reduction in risk
of cancer. So why didn't they live longer? Yeah, why didn't they live longer? And it's a little bit
ambiguous. They don't really say, but they say that there is a much higher rate of alcoholism,
liver failure, and accidents. And so this gets back to sort of what I've alluded to in passing
a couple of times, which is the social and psychological consequences in humans that are
just different than we have in mice. The growth hormone deficient mice aren't going to be subject,
well, it might be probably not subject to the same social pressures that somebody has very low growth
hormone signaling in people is subjected to, which may contribute to other things later on,
like alcoholism. So anyways, fascinating though, biology, which is consistent with the idea,
I think, that you can impact at least a subset of age-related biology by being
constitutively low in growth hormone through your entire life. What would happen if you did that in
bursts, like post-developmentally just after puberty, say from your 20s and 30s, who knows?
There are no naturally occurring examples of that, or very few that we could look at and actually
evaluate. By the way, do we have examples, is there enough data to look at people with
acromegaly during different periods of their life to see if that's had the exact,
do we see a higher incidence of cancer? I don't know the answer to that. Those populations would
be relatively small, but yeah, maybe it's possible. Yeah, it seems like, I imagine somebody's looked
at that, the incidence of cancer in people with adult onset acromegaly or something to that effect.
The other thing I would say on the IGF thing before we leave that is the interplay with insulin.
And so, high insulin, high IGF, low insulin, low IGF, low insulin, high IGF, these are very
different physiologic states. Absolutely. It's very difficult to think that we're teasing those
out when we look at broad swaths. Yeah, and again, I think this just comes back to the fact that
these, especially these epidemiological studies are a mixture of normal people typically, right?
And so, the lifestyles that most people are living, right, are what gets weighted in those
types of analyses. And that may be very different, as we talked about, if you are normal weight,
high protein, maybe high calorie because you're extremely active, right? Then if you're overweight,
sedentary, and eating a high calorie diet, I really think that's underappreciated and
and probably really important. And thinking about the cancer risk, again,
this is going to be some pure speculation on my part though, right? But there's no question,
I don't think, that high growth hormone signaling and high IGF-1 signaling, everything else being
equal in a person leads to a higher risk of developing cancer. You don't? I think that's true.
Oh, you do think that's true? Okay. I believe that that's true. Everything else being equal,
of course, everything isn't going to be equal. But if we just look at that, though, that one
variable signaling through that pathway, higher signaling, higher risk of cancer. So then,
if it's the case, which I think you could, you know, we could make an argument that
that doesn't seem to be the case, at least in certain populations of people that high
growth hormone signaling or treating with growth hormone dramatically increases the cancer
incidence. So why is that? Or in people who are... And by the way, we should also differentiate
between high causes it versus low removes it. In other words, just because we have a genetic
example of where not having it creates a deficiency of cancer, it doesn't mean... So going from sort
of 100 to 30 decreases cancer doesn't mean going from 100 to 130 increases cancer. 100 to 130
increases cancer. That's right. No, that's absolutely true. I mean, we don't know. We could.
Yeah. And actually, I mean, I think the word you use there is interesting because you said removes
it. And I know this isn't what you meant, but this is, I think, something that is also
important to appreciate. So to go from, you know, pre-initiation of cancer, right, to cancer, to
metastasis, to, you know, somebody dying from it, there's steps that have to happen there, right?
And there are different defense mechanisms that have acted at each of those steps.
My guess is growth hormone and IGF-1 is primarily acting at the very early steps, right? Where we
know that if you promote cell division, that that is a sort of a permissive early environment for
mutations to happen and cancers to get a foothold. But in most cases, it seems to be the case that
those early cancers are detected and wiped out by our immune system, right? And one of the reasons
why I think a lot of cancers become more prevalent as we get older is because the immune,
the function of the immune system to detect and clear those cancers declines. There's obviously
other stuff going on, accumulation of senescent cells, which contributes to this process. But
if you are, say, I shouldn't even say this because I bother people about the biological clocks. Let's
just say, though, theoretically, you know, you're a 60 year old person, but biologically, because you
are exercising, eating an appropriate diet, biologically, you're 40 years old, at least your
immune system is functioning like a 40 year old, you might have a little bit higher IGF-1, you might
have a little bit higher of that early cancer risk, but you have a much lower total risk of developing
cancer because your immune system has a much better chance of catching it and getting rid of it.
And those are things we don't even think about. Yeah, that's so complicated.
Well, Matt, I don't know that we settled anything today. It's pretty safe to say. We've probably,
for the listener, created more questions than answers. No, I'm sure we've done some good.
Yeah, I mean, I think, again, it's a complicated question. And, you know, we actually did not dive
into the genetic interaction with caloric restriction. So, I mean, I think the take-home
there is that even in mice where we can control everything else, if you look across genotypes,
you get different results from the same diet and the effect of caloric restriction on lifespan. So,
you know, maybe we can't answer the big detailed questions. I guess the take-homes I would have are,
again, we've learned a ton from these nutritional studies in laboratory animals about the biological
mechanisms. We've learned a lot about which proteins and pathways are important. And that
has led us to things like rapamycin, right, which might be a more effective intervention in humans.
So, they have value for that. And I think, you know, the other take-home that we've talked about is
you don't have to worry about every little detail, right? I think, again, most people
can get a big chunk of the way there by eating a relatively healthy diet. Don't worry so much about
how much protein, how much carbs, how much fat. Eat good foods, right? Don't overeat and be active,
right? Exercise. And I do worry a little bit that we, you know, society does this, but scientists do
it sometimes too when we start, you know, really getting into the weeds and making recommendations
to people that we overthink things a little bit, right? And give people anxiety about worrying
about am I eating a low enough protein diet or am I on, you know, am I still in ketosis?
What should my fasting window be? Should it be 16 hours versus 18 hours? Yeah.
So, the questions are out there to what extent do any of these things have big benefits? I think you
can get most of the benefits without worrying about a lot of that. Yeah, I agree. Well, Matt,
glad we finally got to do one of these in person. Yeah, it's been a pleasure.
Maybe the next one should be in person as well. Absolutely.
Bye.