Hey, everyone. Welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
Hey, Don. Thank you so much for making time to sit down today. I've heard a lot about
you over the past couple of years from our mutual friend, Lane Norton, who suggested
that we sit down and go even deeper down this nutrition pathway. What you may not know about
me is nutrition is my least favorite subject, but I think I say that only because I'm so
tired of the religious aspect of nutrition. I enjoy talking about nutrition through the
lens of biochemistry, but thereafter, my patience for it has dwindled over the past decade. I have
a feeling we'll get along just fine because your entire background is based on nutritional
biochemistry as opposed to nutrition religion. First of all, it's great to meet you, Peter,
and even electronically. My interest was a little sort of the opposite. I was interested in
biochemistry first, and studying organic chemistry just seemed so boring and esoteric that nutrition,
I could actually apply my biochemistry to things people were interested in. I kind of like that
split, but I totally get your aspect of the zealot ends of the spectrum. You grew up on a farm,
if I'm not mistaken, correct, in Illinois? Yes, that's correct. Before we started recording
this, you mentioned to me that your parents, your dad lived to 97, your mom to 102. You're at the
midpoint of your life right now, essentially, based on your good genes. What was it like growing up
on a farm 70 years ago? It was a great experience. Back in the 50s, when I was born,
agriculture was very poor in the United States, and so you sort of grew up in that background.
But I think some of the things I learned was I learned about animal growth, I learned about
reproduction, I learned about growing corn and soybeans, I learned about life cycle. I just got
an interest in food. We were growing it, we had it there on the farm, and so it just made me
interested in it. Combined with that, I always had an interest in science and sort of evolved to be
a kind of a natural marriage, I guess. When you're going to college, did you study biochemistry and
organic chemistry first? That was your undergrad? Yeah, the background, the serendipity of how I
got into nutrition, it certainly wasn't anything I knew about. I was in a small town, went to a
school that had like 400 people in it, and so it certainly wasn't anything I knew about. But I knew
I liked science, so I went to first Illinois State University to study chemistry, and I pretty quickly
realized I had no aptitude for inorganic chemistry, but I sort of understood biochemistry pretty well.
I got to the end of it, and it was actually during the Vietnam War, and I was scheduled to go into
the military, and so I was totally unemployable, and the university said, hey, you're doing really
good at this chemistry stuff, we'll give you graduate assistantship, and you go when you go, and
all of a sudden I ended up with a deferment getting a master's degree in biochemistry,
and my mentor at that time says, you really have a knack for this nutrition part of it,
why don't you do a PhD? And I sort of said, oh, really? And so I ended up at University of
Minnesota doing a PhD in nutritional biochemistry and fell in love with all of it, so it certainly
was no grand plan, but it kind of fit my background of agriculture, food, sports nutrition.
I fell into a group that was doing muscle metabolism, and it just kind of all felt
together for me. Now, was Ansel Keys at the University of Minnesota at that time?
He was not. He had left, but his legacy was there with George Blackburn and Ivan France and some of
those individuals, so I certainly got that background while I was there, and certainly
invested a lot of how my early thinking of nutrition, and I think Lane Norton, who you've
talked with before, has talked about how our thinking of nutrition evolves. My certainly has
evolved. Well, tell me a little bit about what, at least as far as you can remember,
what was your underlying philosophy of nutrition circa 1975, which is probably when you were doing
your PhD, I'm guessing? Yeah, I think sort of one of my earliest sort of thinking about nutrition,
again, it sort of dates to my interest in animal growth, but also sports nutrition.
I very early developed the philosophy that nutrition was really about two tissues, the brain
and skeletal muscle. If those two tissues were healthy, you were going to live a pretty good life.
Everything else is regulatory, the liver, the heart, the kidney, the gut, everything else
adapts to your environment, but you have to focus on those two, and I think if you tailor your
nutritional requirements around that thinking, you end up with a much more sensible approach, and I
sort of coined the concept that my colleague Dr. Gabrielle Lyon and I always use of muscle-centric
nutrition, and if you keep muscle healthy, you've got a good shot at avoiding obesity, avoiding
diabetes, avoiding cancer, etc., etc. Well, let's go into that a little bit. I mean, I want to get
into some weeds on a whole bunch of other really nuanced stuff, but let's follow this thread for
a moment. So when you say that, I assume you're at least in part referring to the following two
facts. One, muscle is the largest sink for glucose. So, you know, 75 to 80 percent of our glucose
storage capacity exists within skeletal muscle, and then there's another factor of muscle which is
it's a very early depot for excess adipose tissue. So once we start to let little droplets of fat
accumulate within muscle cells, it leads to this process of insulin resistance that then creates a
problem for the first point that I made, which is you now make it harder for your carbohydrate storage
unit to accept carbohydrates, and of course that leads to hyperglycemia and ultimately diabetes.
Is that part of why that formulated your thesis or is there more to it?
More to it. I mean, I think what you stated is correct, but I do think about it differently.
I think about muscle really serves two functions. One, the obvious one is mobility.
Most people get to the age of 65. Beyond that, most people actually die from some form of
immobility. Falls, breaking something, hospitalization. So functional mobility is critical.
But the other aspect is metabolism, and muscle is a primary site for insulin activity. You mentioned
glucose storage. I look at it more as an issue of glucose utilization and also fat utilization.
So basically your blood glucose and your blood lipids are heavily, I mean obviously the amount
you eat makes a difference, but the actual level is heavily dependent on your muscle metabolism.
You sort of commented about insulin resistance being associated with fat. Actually insulin causes
insulin resistance. So if you chronically elevate insulin too long, that is the definition
of type 2 diabetes is that basically insulin causes insulin resistance.
Well, say more about that. I mean, it's hard to untangle some of the causality here. I mean,
I spoke with Jerry Shulman, God probably it's been two years ago. In his paradigm,
you have the accumulation of diacylglycerides within the actual myocyte. So not interstitially,
or not between them, but it's the actual accumulation of lipid within.
It's funny, I'm blanking on which enzyme now that inhibits, but it's basically down the PI3K pathway,
the PI3 kinase pathway, where you basically render the muscle cell less sensitive to
the signal of insulin telling the glute IV transporter to come up.
This hyperinsulinemia is effectively the first way that you can externally measure
insulin resistance. Is that sort of in line with what you're saying?
Yes and no. So Jerry Shulman is great. I definitely followed his research a lot.
And the thing to understand about the biochemistry is you can create the models
to give you a negative feedback. So he's absolutely correct that
that diacylglycerol or ceramides will feed back to the insulin receptor, the glute IV transport
and the insulin receptor and cause insulin resistance. So that's true. So that is a
philosophy of fat centric that fat causes all the problems. On the other hand, you can do the exact
same thing with glucose. Too much glucose will also inhibit the insulin receptor and cause that
same exact feedback. It doesn't accumulate the ceramides or the diacylglycerol. I did some
research with diacylglycerol. And if you sort of do it in the issues of high carb, low carb,
you won't find those effects. So the question then becomes which one's more likely to be
physiological because people are eating 350 grams of carbs per day or because they're eating 90
grams of fat per day, which one's likely to cause it? Bob Wolf, there's a philosophy called the
Randall hypothesis. I don't know if you've heard of it, but basically the philosophy is the Randall
hypothesis was that fatty acids, the diacylglycerol, cause all the problems. And what Bob Wolf did was
basically run that experiment with stable isotopes. And he showed us actually the reverse, that fatty
acids are not inherently toxic, but glucose is. It has its own disease. We call it diabetes. And so
when you eat excess carbs, you must get rid of them. You absolutely have to dispose of them in
the next two hours or fat basically can hang around for much longer. It's just simply not that
toxic to the body. In fact, the body always wants a certain level of free fatty acids in the blood
because that's the fuel for the heart. Okay. So it's always high. Now, basically the issue is the
balance. Yeah, what about the ability that that excess, the ability to turn that excess glucose
into fatty acid via de novo lipogenesis? Are you saying that that doesn't happen quickly enough
to alleviate some of the toxicity of acute hyperglycemia? It doesn't happen super quick.
I mean, that's a great question. There's a lot of people who argue how much de novo lipogenesis
actually occurs, but basically when you get into requiring high amounts of de novo lipogenesis,
now we start talking about fatty liver. And so now you start seeing triglyceride problems.
And so people who are actually doing a lot of de novo lipogenesis typically have elevated
triglycerides. So that's one of the first signs that you're disrupting that flow. Triglycerides
in general are there to recycle free fatty acids. So the bottom, the blood's all the adipose is
always dumping free fatty acids out for the heart and other tissues. The problem comes in
is when you start blending that with too many carbs and too many fats. So, first and foremost,
calories are always the problem, but when you have excess calories and then you start rebalancing
these macronutrients is when you get into trouble. Yeah. You're obviously intimately familiar with
this, maybe even some of the listeners are, but there's a very famous paper by Mark Hellerstein,
you know, it's kind of circa mid 90s, 94, 95 that demonstrated really a very small amount of de
novo lipogenesis taking place with carbohydrate feeding. I absolutely believe the results of
that paper, but I also think it's a very narrow context and it's not necessarily the context of
an overfed individual. And therefore I think our capacity for de novo lipogenesis depends heavily
on total energy content or total energy balance. And therefore I think there is a scenario where
in the Hellerstein paper, you can feed a high carbohydrate diet, but within the overall
composition of a low energy diet or a balanced energy diet and DNL is actually quite low.
Conversely, you can feed a high carbohydrate diet in the context of a high energy diet. And I think
we would probably see a much greater amount of DNL. Yeah, totally. And so yeah, I think the context
matters. You're exactly right. And I do think that the first, if we were describing this as a
polynomial, right? Like the first order term is energy. The first order term is how many calories
are coming in. And that probably matters more than the ratio of carb to fat. Yeah. Go back to that
Randall hypothesis or Wolf discussion. You always want to think about it as that carbohydrates,
excess glucose is toxic. If the blood level is high, you'll damage basically every tissue from
your eyes to your toes. And so you have to dispose of the glucose. So Hellerstein's,
what he showed was that if you have a diet that say, say the American diet, 50% carbs,
35% fat, and you take in a thousand calorie meal or 800 calorie meal, which one are you going to
put into fat quickest? You're going to put in the easiest one, the one that's already fat. And so
the carbohydrates going to get burned and the fats going to go to fat. It's just simply the body is
selecting the easiest pathway. But if you switch that and Jules Hirsch did it and then, and then
Jeff Volek did it later, if you switch that to a 80% carb 10%, then you'll see that de novo liposynthesis.
And one of the interesting things out of it is when the body makes fat, the only thing it can
make is saturated fat. So we have a lot of saturated fat in the blood that actually doesn't
come from eating fat. It comes from eating carbs. Yeah. Again, in the context of how much we're
eating, right? Yeah, exactly. All right. So taking it back. It's important to realize, it's important
for people to realize we burn around a hundred calories per hour. That would be 2,400 calories
per day. So a hundred calories per hour, uh, in a two hour period, you're only burning 200 calories.
So everything else has to be stored. Average American meal is 400 to a thousand calories.
That means you have to store all of that. Yeah. Interesting. Is that an argument you think for
spreading out calories more over the course of the day? That takes us into a protein discussion.
And I would say absolutely not. Um, the two, two angles to that. One was there was a theory back
when I was early in my career, back in the mid eighties by Gil Lavelle, and he was arguing that
lots of small meals was good for, uh, less fat deposition. And it was an artifact of how he did
the study. We ran, he did it with animals and basically showed that when you made the adaptation
to lots of small meals, uh, the animals didn't gain as much as if you, uh, adapted them to like
two meals per day. But the artifact was when you adapt an animal to two meals per day, they go
through a starvation period because they'd have to learn to do it. And when you come out of a
starvation period, you're making more fat. So we redid it with a longer adaptation period. And what
we found was that, um, reducing the number of meals per day actually is thermogenically
advantageous. You actually waste more calories. So we actually redid that and published it.
The other aspect we can get into is protein. Protein needs to be distributed at specific meals.
The distribution needs to be high and eating lots of small meals, uh, is a really bad choice for a
lot of reasons. And we can get into that. But anyway, well, I, yeah. And I definitely want to
get into that because if there's, if there's one area I really want to double click on today,
it's everything from protein timing, protein type versus plant protein efficiency, amino acid
variability, all that kind of stuff. We're going to, we're going to go deep on that, but let's go pick
it up back in university of Minnesota. You've got the legacy and I'm guessing at the time, you know,
keys is really famous for two things in the mid seventies, right? I think by that point, he's
probably already published his seven country study and the hypothesis now is a very fat centric view
of, you know, the negative consequences of dietary fat, specifically dietary saturated fat
in the American diet, especially as it pertains to ASCVD. And then I suspect the second thing
that he's probably still famous for is the starvation experiments, um, that were, I'm
guessing done in the 1950s. I mean, these were done on conscientious objectors. So they're
probably in the forties or fifties, right? Yeah, I can't exactly date that, but you're
exactly right. So those were, I mean, we learned a lot about starvation at that point for obvious
reasons. We can't do experiments like that before, but we learned a lot about body composition and
how the body star. So those were good, but certainly the legacy was there. And when I got
to Minnesota, you know, I sort of bought into the cholesterol and the saturated fat and total fat.
And you know, I sort of, okay, this is what everybody's teaching. And you know, that's what
I was forced to learn. That's what they were teaching. Uh, and so I bought into it, but,
you know, as I slowly started doing experiments and early in my career, we did a lot of fasting
type of experiments with animals to look at composition changes. And I did malnutrition
work in Northern Africa. And I sort of got into all of that and I, I started realizing, you know,
I don't really believe that. And one seminar I will always remember at Minnesota was individual
by their name of Fred Kumburrow came to Minnesota and gave a seminar about the dangers of cooking
oils and specifically trans fats. And Blackburn and France just ridiculed him, basically said,
this is the craziest thing we've ever heard. All these plant oils are great. Uh, and basically,
you know, 20 years later, we banned trans fats from foods literally as the most dangerous fat
that you can encounter. So I, I always remember that just sort of thinking, well, you know,
people who have bought into this dogma aren't necessarily right. And we need to keep questioning
it. Speaking of France, um, obviously in 1973, he completes a study, the minute Minnesota
coronary experiment. Um, I actually find this to be one of the most difficult studies to interpret,
not so much the one that he published 16 years later, by the way, in 1989, but the one that
Chris Ramsden republished just a couple of years ago, based on all of the data from France's study,
plus data he never published. This to me is one of the most complicated stories. And I, I will tell
you, I have posed this question to every friend of mine who is more steeped in nutrition than I am.
And, um, I still don't have a great sense of how to explain these results. So I'll explain it for the,
for the listener and the viewer. And I'm curious to your thoughts. So the experiment was done, um,
in basically institutionalized patients. So again, maybe not a study that could be done easily again
today for ethical reasons, but had the advantage of being so well controlled. You, you basically
had patients that were randomized into two groups. Their total energy was identical. Their total split
of macronutrients was identical. The only thing that differed was that in one group, it was high
saturated fat. And in the other group, it was high polyunsaturated fat. The hypothesis being tested
was is saturated fat intake leading to increased major adverse cardiac events, heart attacks and
strokes. The experiment that completed in, I think it ran, I can't remember exactly, I think it ran
about five years in 1973 showed no difference. There was no difference in cardiac events,
despite the fact that the group that was on the higher polyunsaturated fat group did indeed have
much lower cholesterol levels. Now this was this predated the sub fractionation. So they weren't
measuring LDL and HDL. They were just measuring total cholesterol. And at the time there was some
correlation between cardiovascular disease and total cholesterol levels at the extremes. That
was certainly true. Again, because I didn't think we'd be talking about this, I don't have the
numbers all in my mind, but we'll link to it all. But directionally, I believe that the higher PUFA
group relative to the saturated fat group was about 30 milligrams per deciliter lower in total
cholesterol. And based on everything we know today, we would assume that much of that was in LDL
cholesterol indeed being lower and non HDL cholesterol. And yet there was no difference
in events. And of course, it's become a very famous and unfortunate story in nutrition research and
that Franz chose not to publish it because he didn't like the results. It didn't match his hypothesis,
which was that the group on lower saturated fat would have fewer events. Ramsden went and
published all of these data plus a whole bunch of sub data. As I said just a few years ago,
I believe in the British medical journal and actually found something that was that threw
a wrench in my initial hypothesis. My initial view of the Minnesota coronary experiment was
it probably wasn't a long enough intervention. It might be that five years was not long enough
to appreciate a difference. And so it was underpowered or too short in a duration to see
a benefit if there was a benefit. But in Ramsden's analysis, you actually saw the opposite because he
now looked at some subgroups and you actually saw a higher incidence of coronary events in some of
the people that were consuming the high polyunsaturated fat diet. And I can't remember what
the dominant oil was. I'm blanking on it. I don't remember if it was canola or safflower. I think it
was safflower. So how much of that do you remember, Don, from your time there? And can you
shed any light on this or do you have any thoughts on how to interpret that experiment?
Well, first of all, I am definitely not a lipid expert. So I sort of remember the study,
but I can't put any more numbers to it than you did. I actually did some research with Ivan
France and Penny Cruz-Etherton when I was at Minnesota. So I sort of was in the loop at the
time, but that's been a couple of years ago. Yeah, I think if one really looks at the literature
on saturated fat and is fair about all of those studies, you find a very mixed bag,
the Women's Health Initiative and all of those kinds of things. And unfortunately,
the people who believe the hypothesis have either delayed publishing it or said, well,
it couldn't have been wrong and tried to, you know, it could have been wrong and they tried to find
all kinds of excuses as opposed to just believing it. You know, there's an old theory in science
that, you know, if the theory is correct, it will get stronger over time. And if it's not,
it gets weaker. And I think one would have to realize that, A, the cholesterol theory,
the total cholesterol theory has definitely gotten weaker and the saturated fat hasn't held
up very well. You know, we still believe it, but your comment a little bit ago, it's first and
foremost calories. If you put excess saturated fat on top of too many calories, that's probably a
problem. But if you're at or below your calorie needs, I don't see any data that suggests it is.
So, you know, my sort of joke or comment all the time is that if you're committed to being
obese, you probably ought to pay attention to the quality of your fats. But if your goal,
if your goal is to be lean and healthy calories is what you're paying attention to. And the macro
distribution is sort of your personal preference. So let's talk a little bit now about how your
interest in protein came about because, you know, of all macronutrients, this is the one I have to
pay the most attention to. And it's honestly the one where I feel like I fall the shortest. You
know, I feel like I have some days when I nail it and I have too many days when I come up short.
I never go overboard. I never go to bed at night thinking, God, I ate too much protein today. But
I do go to bed sometimes thinking I don't think I ate enough for my goals. Right. My goals are to
sort of maximize muscle protein synthesis. My goals are to preserve lean tissue as long as I can. And
frankly, that's the goal for my patients. So how did this become a strong interest of yours?
Well, the real interest started in my master's degree because I got interested in studying
protein turnover, protein synthesis. And I was working with Arlen Richardson, who was an expert
in aging. And we were studying age related changes in protein synthesis. And we actually
discovered the changes in mRNA over time that the poly A tails on mRNA get shorter. Your ability to
put ribosomes on the message goes down and you have lower synthesis. So that efficiency of change
of protein synthesis over time is a theme that runs through all of my research. And we'll get
into efficiency and adults and things like that. So that was sort of the beginning when I went to
Minnesota, then I sort of got a muscle focus on it. And one of the first things I learned in graduate
school is we don't really have a protein requirement. We have a requirement for nine essential amino
acids and organic nitrogen, organic amines, which all translates into the fact that we can make 11
of amino acids and nine we have to have in the diet. And one of my favorite quips I use when I'm
talking to groups on stage is that, you know, protein we should think of as a vitamin pill.
We don't have a daily requirement for a vitamin pill. We have a requirement for 12 vitamins inside
the pill. We don't actually have a daily requirement for protein. We have a requirement for
nine or 20 amino acids inside of it. And so it's talking about a protein requirement
just to reflect ignorance. We have specific requirements for nine essential amino acids.
And that gets into the complexity then because these amino acids are essential for building
blocks for new protein, but every one of them has a metabolic role like leucine and mTOR or arginine
and nitric oxide or lysine and carnitine or cysteine and glutathione. And all of those roles
are vastly above the minimum that is detected for nitrogen balance for the RDA. And so that's where
people fall apart is that we think about vitamin C and we know there's a minimum RDA to prevent
scurvy, but people will take five or 10 times that during COVID for immune response. But we
resist thinking that way about amino acids and it's exactly the same.
You know, that's a great point, Don. Maybe we should spend a minute helping people understand
what an amino acid is because, you know, I took biochemistry, I have my little cue cards, I can
draw every one of the amino acids. Not anymore, by the way. I can't. Yeah, I was gonna say not anymore.
But there was a day when I could draw all nine of them. But let's help people understand. I think
most people understand what glucose looks like. If you've listened to this podcast, you're no
stranger to the idea that glucose is a six carbon ring and each one has a couple hydrogens on them.
And one of them's got an oxygen and a hydrogen on it as well. I think most people who have listened
to this podcast have a decent sense of what a fatty acid looks like. Long stretch of carbons.
If it's saturated, there's no double bond. So it's just littered with either two or three hydrogens,
depending on where it sits in the chain. And then, of course, you store them by putting three of those
onto a nice little three carbon glycerol backbone. But I actually think most people
understandably have less clarity around what an amino acid is. And you've already alluded to the
fact that there were 20 of them and nine of them we can't even make. I mean, we're if we were
deprived of these things, we'd be dead. So we got to eat them. But can you give folks a sense of
the nomenclature? What is an amino acid? What do these things look like? Yeah. So a little bit like
a fatty acid, an amino acid has a carboxy end connected with a carbon and then it has a nitrogen
end. And when the body is making so when we eat protein, we get these amino acids in some sort
of a string, but we totally digest them down to probably individual amino acids, maybe di or
tripeptides, and we absorb them that way. They get to the blood as single amino acids for the most
part. And then the body begins to reconnect them based like on the messenger RNAs. Our DNA tells
us how to reconnect them. And so we connect a carbon to a nitrogen and we string them together.
Of these 20 amino acids though, they all have that that acid and nitrogen part, but they also
have a side chain ranging from very simple one like glycine with just a hydrogen to ones like
tryptophan that have a big aromatic part to them. And so all of these are different and they go into
proteins in different structures. The DNA tells us how we put them together and proteins can be
simple like insulin with 51 amino acids, or they could be like myosin with thousands.
And so they're all and then every protein in the body has a different turnover rate. Some of them
like insulin might last 15 minutes and some of them like myosin or let's say collagen might last
250 days. And so they turn over at different rates. So that's sort of what they are.
But beyond that building block structure, then every amino acid has other kinds of structures.
It might be like lysine where part of it becomes the molecule known as
carnitine, which is for fatty acid metabolism, or it might be the nitrogen off arginine that
goes to nitric oxide for vasorestriction, or it might be cysteine which goes to part of
creatinine or glutathione. So we can get the leucine, which is sort of my favorite, which is
a signal which really got me interested in protein and metabolism is a signal for muscle protein
synthesis. So again, they all have this building block structure. They get strung together
in different links. But they also have other metabolic functions. And that's what people
don't recognize when they're talking about protein requirements.
So let's talk about that RDA, right? Because when we look at our patients and evaluate them from an
nutritional standpoint, almost without exception, we come to the conclusion that they are not getting
enough amino acids based on how much protein they're consuming. Now, I don't know how much of
that is the nature by which food is prepared these days, the nature by which, you know, protein makes
up a certain amount of the caloric intake based on various types of, you know, prepared foods and
things like that. And how much of that just based is based on a belief system of what people need,
perhaps coming back to the RDA. So how what's the first of all, let's tell people what the
actual RDA is and, and how it came to be. So the RDA is a recommended dietary allowance. So it's
some people think it's a daily, but it's a dietary allowance. So it's sort of a generic number.
And the argument is that for all our DAs, we sort of test the population and come up with an average
number. And then for a safety factor, which average would be 50 percent would be deficient.
And so we add a safety factor of two standard deviations, which supposedly 97.5 percent of the
people would be adequate to prevent any, any signs of inadequacy at that point. But that also means
2.5 percent of the people are actually deficient at that point. So that that's sort of the definition.
Where does the RDA come from? I think it's useful to go back in history just a little bit then on
protein. How did we begin to evaluate protein needs? Well, it all came out of animal sciences.
Back in the early 1900s, before we even knew the essential, all the essential amino acids,
farmers were trying to say, how do I get animals to grow best, you know, and different kinds of
proteins and things like that. And they develop protein quality scores and things like that. So
how much growth did I get for what I fed? How much nitrogen did I deposit for how much I fed?
So these are all rapidly growing animals. And we developed this concept really of nitrogen retention.
That basically, we've now translated into what's called nitrogen balance. And
that's how we determine the protein requirement. Basically, what's important in all of that
discussion, that long-winded explanation is that all of the concepts were developed for growth,
where nitrogen balance was positive. You could measure a change over time. And as we've now
tried to start applying that to non-growing adults, it gets a lot more vague. So it's important to
recognize that what we think about protein requirements is a, develop from nitrogen balance,
where you measure all of the nitrogen you're eating, which you can do pretty good, but then
you have to measure all of the nitrogen you're losing, which we're really bad at. And we call
that nitrogen balance. Can you explain how that's done? Don, this is, I think we're going to talk
so much about it that I think it's worth getting into the details of how nitrogen balance is
calculated. And let's do it in a human. So if I came into your lab, how would you do this?
So let's start with the front end. Let's start with nitrogen in. So that's basically, you just take
a bunch of food and you do a chemical analysis and you measure the nitrogen and you multiply it by a
factor of 6.25. So A, you're measuring nitrogen. It's not really protein. It could be nucleic acids.
It could be anything with nitrogen. You're calling it protein. And then you're multiplying
it by 6.25, which says, I believe that protein contains 16% nitrogen, which also isn't always
true. So now we've got this error on the front end and now on the back end, we're going to try and
measure losses. So the primary loss of nitrogen in the body is in the urine, urea. So that's pretty
easy to measure. You can collect that. Second would be the stool. So you can collect that,
but then you get into things like sweat and skin loss and hair loss and respiratory nitrogen
ammonia in the breath. And those are all incredibly vague. So everyone who knows nitrogen
balance says that nitrogen balance underestimates requirement. Everybody, uniformly. But that is
where the RDA comes from. And when you do short-term studies, what you find is most people
young and again, all these studies were done with college age students. So they're kind of right at
the end of their growth. And basically in a short-term seven day study, they look okay. So that's
where we're at. In the last 20 years, those of us who studied protein have gone beyond that and said,
well, nitrogen balance is one outcome, but it like the vitamin C argument, there are other outcomes
based on amino acid metabolism that may be more important than minimum nitrogen balance. And we
now know that protein handling goes down, the efficiency goes down as we get older. So now we
have much higher requirements that we, that most of us talk about for adults. So just to be clear,
Don, going back to something you said, the reason we all agree that that standard nitrogen balance
underestimates the requirement is it's easier to measure the sum of the ins than the sum of the
outs. Yeah, exactly. And the chances are you're significantly underestimating the outs. Yeah.
Especially if you do, I mean, when I was a surgical resident, there were times we did
nitrogen balance on patients who were on long-term TPN, total parenteral nutrition in the ICU. These
were patients that it wasn't clear how long it would take for their guts to start working again.
So they had to be fed all of their nutrition through a central line, which is very complicated
feeding to do. And when we would have the nutrition team come and do a consult and do a nitrogen
balance, I mean, they literally had to put a tent over that patient. They were doing the best that
they could in the ICU to basically create a laboratory environment to calculate nitrogen
balance, which turns out, you're not surprised, very important for a critically ill patient.
Right? I mean, that is a hyper hyper catabolic state. And if you're trying to create an
anabolic state in that person to keep them alive, it's imperative that you understand how much
nitrogen they have or how much money they require. So the simple idea of I'm just going to tell you
how much protein you're eating and I'm going to measure the nitrogen in that's coming out in your
urea, that's just not going to cut it. That's just too simple. Yeah. And currently a lot of those
studies are simply done with a factor. So they don't put them in tents or buildings or whatever.
They just measure urea in the urine and everything else is just sort of, well, we think it's a
one point. Yeah, exactly. Exactly. And so obviously we're perpetuating an error based on ignorance.
So then let's go one step further, Don. How do you use isotopes to now really get into what's
happening, not just on the boundaries, but like how that nitrogen and by the way, I think there's
one point we should make for the listener who might be still lost as to why we're talking about
nitrogen. Proteins have nitrogen. Amino acids all have nitrogen. Carbs and fats don't. So this is
where we can really speak to the source of the nitrogen, right? And now, as you mentioned,
anything with a nucleic acid is going to have nitrogen as well. But the majority of the
nucleic acids come in proteins. Come in. Would be found in the foods. Yeah. Would be found in protein
based foods. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Right. Yeah. You're exactly right. I mean,
car, I mean, fats and for the most part, annoying essential fatty acids, carbs and fats are basically
energy sources. They're carbon carbon bonds that provide energy where amino acids have a very
different purpose and structure. And that nitrogen is part of what makes them different.
Yeah. In other words, we consume carbohydrates virtually exclusively for their energy content,
fat mostly for its energy content. There is some structural importance that comes with fat and
cholesterol. But really you don't want to be consuming protein for energy. Right. I mean,
the only caveat I would say to that is that there might be reasons that people are
hypersensitive to carbohydrates where taking in more protein beyond what you might actually need
for protein metabolism might be a substitution for carb calories. And we can get into that
conversion and things like that. But, you know, I talk with people and they say, how well,
how much protein, what's your high end? And I sort of give them one number and I say, but, you know,
the caveat is you might want to take more if you're really trying to struggle with a carbohydrate
issue. So anyway, but you're right. So now let's talk about that measurement of what's actually
happening with those amino acids. Actually, only this question I want to ask you even before that.
Let's think about the normal. When people think of protein, they think of meat, right? That's going
to be a great source of protein. Obviously there's protein and most foods have some protein in them.
But if you if you were eating a piece of steak, how many of those 20 amino acids are in there? Are
they virtually all in there? If you're looking at animal source proteins, whether it's meat or eggs
or milk, basically all of the amino acids that a human would need are in those because they're
basically, you know, obviously a chicken's not a mammal, but the others are mammals and basically
we have the same amino acids, the same protein. So they're all there. Meat is a good example
because they're all pretty much in the right balances. But every protein has a little different
balance of essential amino acids. You can look at dairy proteins and dairy proteins are something
we can fractionate because they're all water soluble. So we know a lot about alpha-lactobumen
versus lactoferrin and lactoglobulin, etc., etc. So we know that a lot of differences about amino
acid compositions of individual proteins. And so going back to what you just said,
then animal protein, we typically think of as sort of meat, mammals, right? You know, beef,
pig, stuff like that. And then of course you've got sort of bird protein, mostly chicken for folks,
and then fish protein. And then you have eggs, dairy. We're saying based-
So the first three, the first three are exactly the same for protein. So whether it comes from a cow
or a pig or a chicken or a fish, muscle protein is still muscle protein.
And how do we think objectively about the quality of a protein? This is a topic that you've talked
about extensively. And there's a way, there's a numerical way to talk about that. Isn't there
an efficiency of that protein versus tofu versus soybean versus rice, all the way down to sort of
lower and lower protein density foods? Yeah. Protein quality is something that I think a lot
about. And I'm actually working with a group now to sort of reinvent how we think about that. But
I think you're referring to protein quality in a sense of PD-Cas or dia or something like that.
Basically we realized that when you look at a protein, there are two factors. One is what's
the composition of the, there's nine essential amino acids. And the other is what's its bio
availability? How well do we digest it and absorb it? With animal proteins and most isolated proteins,
even soy protein isolates, the digestion absorption is pretty close to a hundred. It's
usually 95% or higher for all animal proteins. For plant proteins though, it gets into, you need
to realize that in a plant, the protein is there for the purpose of the plant. And so a lot of it
is attached to fibers, it's a structures. Plants have proteins attached to the leaves and the stems
and the roots and the flowers and the seeds. And when you start to isolate that, if you just eat
it in a raw form, it may only be 60, 70% available because we can't digest the fiber.
So those are the two factors. We can put those two together and we can do that.
We can put those two together and get a protein quality score and we can determine that a whey
protein isolate because of its essential amino acids is 20% better than a soy protein isolate
just because of the amino acids. Or we can compare a wheat protein, a wheat brand, and we realize that
it's only 40% available. So if you look at wheat brand on a cereal box and say it was a wheat
flower and it says there's four grams per serving, there's actually less than two that you can
actually absorb. And so that's how we look at it. In my opinion, some of the problems with those
right now is it's hard to compare across foods and it's hard to build a meal that way. We can say
that whey is better than soy. And so if you're only eating those two things, that's okay. But
what happens when you start putting them together? And so I am working with a group trying to build
a protein quality score that really based on three amino acids, lysine, methionine, and leucine,
which in my opinion are the key markers for adult health. And so we're trying to re-score it
differently. But that, again, long-winded story about protein quality, but that's how it's
measured. No, that's very interesting, Don. So what you're saying is, if I'm understanding you
correctly, you could brute force your way through life by looking at every single thing you eat
and trying to figure out the dias score for its protein. So, okay, I'm about to have a ribeye.
That's going to be about a 96% dias. I'm going to have my soybeans over here. That's about an 80%
dias. I'm going to have my whey isolate. That's a hundred percent dias. I'm going to have my
shredded wheats. That's a 40% dias. That's a tough way to go through life
because you can't just add up the protein. And they're not truly additive. You can't
really figure that out. And the average person doesn't even have that data. I mean, if you go
into the USDA database with whatever, 7,000 foods, there are 4,000 that actually have amino
acid scores. And of those, there's probably less than 300 that have dias scores. And so you can't
put it together. There's no way. And so we're trying to develop a system that allows people
to get better than that. If you look on a label on a package and you see, again, a wheat cereal
that says it has four grams of protein, well, again, that's a nitrogen analysis
times 6.25 for all the problems I've said. And then if you look over at another column,
it'll say daily value. Yeah, exactly. And there almost no label have daily values for protein
because that would require a PD cast or dias score and nobody has them. And so that four grams really
would translate into less than two, but nobody's being told that. That's right. And by the way,
just for folks who are hearing us use the term dias as digestible, indispensable amino
acid score, correct? Right. Okay. So, and I have a big problem that the digestibility is where a
lot of people have been focusing, but I have a big problem with the amino acid scores because
they're incredibly low. They're way too low. And so we have, they're established by the World Health
Organization, by the FAO, which is really designed to prevent malnutrition in Africa,
where we know from our Institute of Medicine that the essential amino acid scores are much
higher than that should be. You mentioned stable isotopes, a little bettigo or tracers. We know
from stable isotope studies that all those FAO amino acid scores are too low. And so that's
part of the equation that we're not telling people either. I want to come right back to that,
but I'll finish this one point, which is what you're offering as an alternative to people
living in spreadsheets to calculate how much actual indispensable amino acid they're getting
is, hey, what if we make this easier and you focus on the actual content of three amino acids?
So we're going to take a subset of essential amino acids. And if I recall, I remember Lucene
was clearly one of them. Lysene was one of them. Was methionine the other one?
Methionine is the other one, yeah.
We're going to take methionine, leucine, lysine. And we just want you, Peter, to walk around
and make sure you get enough of those with each meal. And if you do that, the rest will take care
of itself. Is that effectively what you're saying? That's exactly what I'm saying. If you look at
dia scores right now, the amino acid is scoring, A, I've already said it's too low. But if you look
at how they're scored, they're not scoring apples and apples, they're scoring apples and oranges.
So if you look at the soy deficiency, all legumes like soy or pea are limiting or deficient in
methionine. And you score that against whey, what you end up is the limiting amino acid in whey is
considered histidine. And no one has ever shown histidine to actually be a limiting amino acid
in an adult. It's a limiting amino acid in children and babies. So now we're comparing
apples and oranges. They're not fair. So if you compare methionine to methionine,
it's not 20% higher. It's 250% better in soy comparing soy and whey. So we need to compare
apples and apples. We need to compare them across the three essential amino acids that are actually
likely to be limiting. Whereas histidine, phenylalanine, to my knowledge, no one has
ever shown those to be limiting in an adult. So why do we consider them limiting?
All right. So you've already mentioned the importance of leucine and listeners of this
podcast are no stranger to leucine because we've had David Sabatini on, we've had Matt
Caberlein on. I mean, we've gone deep in the weeds on mTOR. And in fact, it was one of David's post
docs that actually discovered the leucine sensor on mTOR. So we know now pretty unambiguously,
leucine is an amazing trigger for mTOR. Of course, there's going to be a subset of people
listening to this who are confused, but wait a minute, Peter, if rapamycin is good and rapamycin
inhibits mTOR, how can leucine be good if leucine turns it on? And of course, they're forgetting
the chronicity of the state. Sometimes you need mTOR off. Sometimes you want mTOR off. Sometimes
you want it on, sometimes you want it off. But when we're talking about eating, we want it on,
right? We want to be able to turn mTOR on for muscle protein synthesis, right?
So let's circle back to our earlier comment about how often you eat. So now we've got an issue of
mTOR and whether it needs to cycle on and off. And not only does leucine turn it on, but so does
insulin. And so probably the worst case scenario, and you can use a lot of animal studies to back
this up, would be people who eat a lot of small carbohydrate meals that continuously activate
mTOR. What we want to do is use specific meals with the right amount of insulin to activate
muscle-centric mTOR. mTOR is in every tissue. And what you don't want to do is continuously
activate it in liver or some other tissue. And so that's where the confusion gets into it,
is people ignore the fact that insulin is just the biggest trigger in other tissues,
where leucines are very unique trigger in muscle.
Yep. So now let's go back to the practical application of this. So we know why leucine
matters. Can you say a bit more about methionine and lysine and why raising them to the level of
leucine becomes a great proxy for overall protein load?
So if you look at limiting amino acids actually in food, lysine is always limiting in grains.
And that has been shown in animal science over the years. That's a major limitation
in how you feed, what the minimum amount. So that one is probably limiting for protein synthesis.
It's also in carnitine and some other things, but lysine is probably mostly for protein synthesis.
Methionine is one of the least... So if we look at the amounts we need, we need about 3.4 grams
of lysine per day. We need probably a little less than one gram of methionine. So they're not in
the same proportion either. But the methionine is what we call part of the one carbon pool.
And so basically for the body to make and repair DNA, to make and repair RNA, to make taurine
downstream, to make the non-essential amino acid cysteine, to make glutathione the oxidant,
methionine is the key to all of those pathways. And so methionine is one of the most limiting,
and it's limiting in all legumes. So we think of soy and pee and a lot of, you know, and
lentils and things of that nature is higher quality protein. They are, but they're still limiting in
methionine. What are some of the natural sources of food that are high in methionine?
The classic one of, quote, sulfur amino acids is eggs. Eggs, yeah. Eggs are quite high in the sulfur
amino acids, which are methionine and cysteine. But all animal products are adequate in them.
And basically all plant products are pretty low in them.
So, Don, you grew up on a farm, right? So, you know, we look at animals like cows,
which are quite muscular, eating basically just hay and grass. For them to be able to be as
catabolic as they are and produce so much muscle, does that just speak to the incredible volume of
that plant that they have to chew to make sure they're getting enough methionine, enough lysine,
and enough leucine? I think you meant anabolic, not catabolic. Yeah, sorry, sorry, anabolic.
In such an anabolic state. I mean, what volume of total protein in the form of grass and hay and
things like that, do they need to get a sufficient amount of those muscle building amino acids?
That sort of wanders us into a sustainability argument, which I really love to wade into. But
cattle, ruminant animals are a very important part of the food chain because of their stomach,
which is full of bacteria. One of the things to think about for essential amino acids
is really the only place they come from in life is bacteria. Nothing else can make them.
And so our primary source of them in nature is the bacteria on roots of plants.
So the bacteria on the roots will take the nitrogen. Why do we fertilize our garden?
Is nitrogen. The bacteria will take that inorganic nitrogen and form organic amines
with it. And those organic amines then can be made into proteins in the plants.
But as I said earlier, the problem with plants is that they don't have the same
balance as we need. They have the plants to make roots and tree, you know, limbs and
roots and flowers and things like that. The beauty of a ruminant is they can take that
plant and they can digest it. And the bacteria then will rebalance all of the amino acids.
They'll capture inorganic nitrogen and they make the essential amino acids that mammals need
and they concentrate it for us. So basically humans, one of the arguments is humans evolved
by being able to use more concentrated protein. You know, if we just ate, you know, if we just
ate plants, it's hard to get enough. But if the ruminant animal can actually digest all of that,
form it into appropriate amino acids. So basically for every 60 grams of protein an animal eat,
they'll make a hundred grams of essential amino acid, you know, balanced protein.
Wait a minute. Say that again.
So they're basically upside.
Yeah, say that again.
So for every 60 grams of plant-based proteins and nitrogen that they'll take in,
they can upcycle that to a hundred grams of amino acid balanced protein. So ruminants are
called upcyclers. So whether it's in dairy or meats or, you know, also, you know, goats and,
and sheep and, and, and deer, all of those ruminant animals upcycle by eating grasses,
they produce great quality protein. No other animal, no other animal can do that.
And just to make sure I understand the mass balance of that,
the bacteria are obviously the engine of that upcycle, but you can't make nitrogen out of
nothing. So you're saying the other four.
But they're making, they're making protein out of nitrogen.
That's right. That's what I was going to say. So they're getting the nitrogen from the fertilizer
that went into the grass.
Not quite. They're getting nitrogen that's inorganic in the plants, but it's not actually in
protein forms. And so it's in the fibers and other kinds of things. So they're able to upcycle that.
They're able to increase the value of non-amino acid nitrogen. Plus they capture all of those
other nitrogens.
So first of all, that's fine. I had no idea that was happening. I had,
I had never heard of that phenomenon. So that's incredibly fascinating.
Secondly, are they also disproportionately creating amino acids that weren't necessarily
there in the plant? So in other words, if you use the example you gave earlier,
which is, you know, you eat a hundred grams of cow protein, you're going to probably get
quite an amount of methionine, lysine and leucine. Is it true that that amount of amino
acid was not even present in the 60 grams of grass protein that they consumed?
Exactly. That's exactly what's happening. So the bacteria, if you look at the flora
in the cow, they have certain bacteria that will produce methionine or a lysine. So they can
basically take a non, you know, an amine nitrogen, or they can take glycine, a non-essential amino
acid, and they can make it into, into amino acids. One of the, one of the supplements that you can
actually feed a cow is urea. So a human waste product type of thing, we, we excrete nitrogen
waste as urea in the urine. You can actually feed urea, a nitrogen source to a cow, and they can
make it into methionine or leucine or lysine. Unbelievable. So the, it's an interesting argument,
because you, you know, this gets, now we're not, now we're, now we're venturing from nutrition
into religion, but right, there's certainly a group of people who would argue that we should
not be eating any animal protein whatsoever. We shouldn't eat, you know, we shouldn't eat meat,
we shouldn't eat eggs, we shouldn't eat dairy, et cetera. A counter argument to that would be,
it's awfully difficult without these animals to get adequate amino acids, especially if you stop
thinking of it in terms of an RDA and start thinking of it in terms of essential amino acids.
I try and stay away from the religious argument of it. That's a, that's a, you know, that's a
personal preference. As you said, I grew up on a farm where we raised cattle and pigs, we raised
corn and soybeans. And so, you know, I saw it as a life cycle type of thing. I think of it as a
biochemist, and there's just no question that ruminant animals play a very important role in
our food system. And one we can't really replace. We can't just idle millions of acres of grassland
and pretend that we can grow avocados on them or broccoli. You know, cattle basically spend a year
of their life on basically nothing but grass. And that is an amazing, you know, and that's an,
and sheep are, you know, sheep and goats the same, but those are amazing contributions to our food
system. Yeah. Again, I was completely unaware of this capacity to concentrate and, you know, almost
up produce, both in quantity and quality of amino acid. That's, that's a very interesting finding.
So where were we before we went down that path? Because I was just trying to understand how it
happened. So, so also didn't appreciate the role of the bacteria. I think we were about to get into,
oh, I know where we can go back to. You mentioned that you have spent some time studying the
difference between, call it 20 year olds and 60 year olds in terms of the efficiency of muscle
protein synthesis. So, and this is where you probably have to get into the isotopes, right?
Now you're getting into sort of nuanced stuff, but what do we know about a 20 year old versus
a 60 year old who's under, who puts their muscle under a progressive overload. So they're, they're
now asking, you know, they're, they're, they're doing resistance training. They're being provided
with adequate amino acids. And let's assume they're being provided with not just the right
quantity, but the right quality of amino acid. What do we know about the assimilation of that
amino acid into new muscle tissue across and pick any age you want. I just use 20 and 60,
but I, I know you've studied this at very specific age points.
Piece of background before we get into that is important to recognize that whether you're 16 or
65 year body needs to make nearly 300 grams of new protein per day. So there's a protein turnover.
Every, every tissue in the body is turning over. Some as fast as liver enzymes,
we replace every hour muscle proteins, we replace with half-lives of around 15 to 16 days. So
every 30 days, collagen turns over at about half-life of a hundred days, which is why if you
hurt your knee, it takes so long to repair it. But basically if you put that into thinking,
the body replaces literally every protein in it about four times a year.
That's a pretty remarkable number. And then if you think of we have to make 300 grams of new protein
per day, the average American intake is around 80 grams or less, women 70, men 90. That means that
there's a recycling thing going on. So of every new protein that's getting made in the body,
about six out of seven amino acids are getting recycled. All of that sort of feeds into this
process of protein synthesis, protein turnover. And what, remember I said what I was doing with
my master's degree, we were studying the age-related changes. What we now know is that as you get older,
the efficiency of that protein turnover goes down. So where a 16 year old, you give them a certain
amount of protein, they'll have a very good response. If 65 year old will have maybe no
response at all or 10% or something. But what we have learned sort of with the study of leucine and
initiation factors and all of that, is that if you give an enriched source of essential amino acids
more protein, you can actually make the adult look just like the 16 year old. So what we know
is that the efficiency goes down, but the capacity to respond doesn't. And so what we're
now thinking is that what we now know is that if you have a requirement, it's about twice the
minimum RDA. So instead of 0.8, it's 1.6 grams per kg. We can get the adult, the 65 year old,
to respond just the same as the 20 year old as far as muscle protein synthesis.
Now, you know, a moment ago, Don, we talked about how it's a slippery slope if you just focus on
total protein. So when you say 1.6 grams per kilogram, does this assume it's from a way like
product and an animal based product? And if that person says, hey, I'm 65 years old and I'm on a
plant based diet, are you going to say that number is going to need to be higher? So that's a great
question and a great way to ask it. What we know is that most people who go to a plant-based diet,
a vegetarian diet, decrease both the quantity and the quality. So your point is exactly right. If
you're on a plant-based diet, you'll need more protein and that means you'll have to have more
calories. But what's the threshold for that? What we would probably argue is that if you have 120
grams of protein per day, it probably doesn't matter the distribution between animal and plant
because you probably have enough to cover it. Okay. If you're only eating 50 grams of protein
per day, then it makes a big difference. You'll never catch up to your essential amino acid needs.
So somewhere between 50 and 120, it depends on what you choose, you know. So, you know, if you're
going to be plant-based, you know, have 125 grams of protein per day and you're probably fine.
But if you're going to be vegetarian and you think you're going to get along with 56 grams per day,
you're going to get in trouble. Going back to this difference earlier about the, you know, call it
anabolic resistance, right? Between the 65 year old and the 16 year old. The obvious thing that
comes to mind is there's a huge difference in androgen level between those two.
Right. What are the other things that might explain this anabolic resistance that I think,
by the way, I think it's very interesting that you can overcome that by a higher amount of protein. But
prior to that work around, what else do you think explains anabolic resistance?
Clearly the hormone issues are first and foremost. So, you know, I always make the comment that
when you're growing hormones are your friend, they're sort of driving it. And you look at
malnutrition in Africa and children will grow on really lousy diets. They may not grow as healthy,
they may not live as long, but there's a survival reproduction nature to that.
Now we switch to talking about healthy aging and I want to live to where my parents, you know,
I want to get to that century mark. Now we talk about healthy aging and now we sort of change the,
we change the criteria that we're looking for. Let's just think about mTOR for a second and
try and put that in framework. There are four different signals that regulate mTOR. We've
mentioned leucine. We also mentioned insulin. An enzyme, a factor known as AMP kinase, which is
carbohydrate sensitive, is energy sensitive. And then another molecule known as red one,
which is stress sensitive, particularly resistance exercise. So there are four different things,
the individual balances. When you're young and growing, insulin and IGF-1 dominates that. And
insulin first and foremost is a growth hormone. And when you stop growing at 25, it ceases to
have an effect on protein synthesis and muscle. And so now the shift, the whole thing shifts to
protein quality. Protein quality is not nearly as important when the system's dominated by hormones.
And so now what we know is as we get older, we can buffer that loss of the hormones
by higher quality protein, mostly leucine and resistance exercise. Those two factors will
balance out the growth issue that young people have, the benefit of the growth part. So that's
the way you have to think about the change in efficiency with aging.
Speaking of aging, at the front end of what you just said, I want to go into that a little bit
more. And I think most people will recognize that this is an enormous problem in the developed world.
And we should talk about it through that lens, because I think that's where it's most stark.
But I'm curious as to whether or not you think this could become a problem or even plays a role
in childhood obesity rates. So let's talk about what happens to a child that is protein deficient
at the beginning of their life. What is the implication of that later in life?
So when I got into protein, John Waterlow and Joel Millward and Peter Garlic and Vernon Young
were sort of the godfathers out there that I learned from. And I got involved with some
international malnutrition with the US Agency for International Development USAID project in Morocco.
And so we looked at that, and that led us to doing some animal studies. And basically,
we used the animals to look at malnutrition and recovery. And what we found was that
malnutrition, starvation insults early in life would stunt muscle development, basically
limited the DNA development, limited the cellular development, and basically stunted lean mass in
the children and in the animals. And if that was stunted, basically what happened is the
individual as an adult was always predestined to have low lean body mass and high body fat.
Obesity. And that was really the origins of how we started thinking about muscle-centric health.
If muscle didn't develop right, if it wasn't metabolically correct, you were predestined to
some of these other things. And I mentioned Dr. Gabrielle Lyon, and that's sort of how we
put that concept together is muscle-centric health, we've got to have the correct development,
and we have to have the correct protection as adults, because that's kind of where
both your mobility and your metabolic health start.
Don, what's the mechanism? Do we have a sense of why, for example, maybe people are aware of this,
but when you look at children in places like Africa who are really malnourished,
at first glance, you almost pause and think, well, why are their bellies so big
if they're malnourished? And yet they don't realize that's an extreme, and I don't even
remember, was Quasi-Orcor, was that the name of the- Exactly. Yeah. And what's the pathophysiology
of that? Why does the extreme malnourishment lead to that protruded abdomen and things like that?
So there's sort of two terms, two directions that childhood malnutrition goes. One is called
marasmus, which is sort of the skin and bones look, and the other is Quasi-Orcor, which is that
kind of inflated belly looking. The belief of those two differences is that in Quasi-Orcor,
there's disproportionately poor protein, and that leads to changes in water balance and edema.
People have argued, is it cortisol based? Is it stress based? But it appears to be an imbalance
in the protein to energy relationship, where in marasmus, they're just short of total calories and
total protein and everything, but in Quasi-Orcor, it appears that the quality of the protein,
they're eating these starchy porridges and things like that, totally deficient, probably in lysine
and methionine, and that leads to water imbalances and other things. And what is it about this
critical window of development where this protein deficiency makes it very difficult
for them to put on lean mass later in life and creates a propensity for adiposity?
So again, we actually did some of that original research, and this was stuff we did way back in
the late 70s, early 80s. Muscle is a very unique cell structure. We have what are called muscle
fibers, and unlike a liver cell, which has a DNA, a nucleus in each cell, muscle cells are
multinucleated. They have what are called satellite cells around them, and so as the original fiber
begins to develop, the satellite cells will put DNA, these nuclei into it, and what we determined
was that each DNA has a certain amount of protein it can handle, and so what the DNA ultimately
determines how big your muscle can get. And so what we determined was that late in pregnancy,
early in lactation, if the insult occurs during that, you stunt these satellite cells and you
don't develop enough DNA, so the muscle is always limited in its potential size.
Wow. I was aware of the propensity for adiposity later was not aware of the limitation in lean
growth, so this is really the double whammy, right? It's effectively lifetime sarcobesity.
Yeah, so basically you're decreasing your lean mass, you're decreasing your metabolically active
tissue, and so you're sort of stuck with minimal calories with deposit fat.
Now look, in the US it would be hard to imagine a child developing quasiorcor, but clearly there
are kids in the United States that are disadvantaged enough that they're not going to be exposed to high
enough protein in either quality or quantity. Do you think that there's to a lesser extent
some of this problem that's going to happen in developed nations like the US?
I think it's possible. Frankly, these are the kinds of things I worry about with the advocates
of plant-based diets. We're starting to see New York City taking animal proteins out of school
lunch. I mean, what is that really going to do? We're conducting a public health experiment
without actually having any knowledge of that. I think that's frightening, and the issue is
public school lunches, nursing homes, daycares, these are all under these federal guidelines
where we're diluting out the quantity and quality of protein at the same time with no knowledge of
what that's really going to mean. I think that's pretty frightening to be doing that kind of public
health experiment without knowledge of it. Yeah, I hadn't even considered it through that lens,
actually. Let's talk about something else that we alluded to briefly, but now I want to get back to,
which is maximum protein usability or assimilation in a given sitting. I'll tell you where I come at
this. One of the challenges that I've observed in taking care of patients is when they get into a
very heavy regimen of time-restricted feeding. You're probably aware of this, Don, but there
are ideas that say, look, if you can just limit the amount of time that you eat, but not place
any limits on what you eat or how much you eat or what you're eating from into this sort of intermittent
fasting window, it produces some health benefits. It's certainly an effective way to reduce calories.
If the goal of the exercise is to reduce total energy expenditure and you create a narrow enough
window, you will indeed do that. But what we've seen repeatedly is people who, after, say, six
months of adopting a very narrow feeding window, say one meal a day, will lose weight, but
disproportionately will lose lean tissue. And so the diagnosis here is pretty straightforward,
they clearly reduced energy intake, but they probably reduced protein intake too much.
And so body composition actually got worse despite the fact that weight went down,
which then gets to a point, which is, well, can't you just eat all of your protein in one meal? So
if a person says, I'm just going to eat one meal a day, and let's just say this is a very active
person, so they're going to eat 3000 calories in one sitting, which I will raise my hand to saying,
I can do that quite easily, I'm quite a glutton. Even if I was able to eat 150 grams of protein in
one sitting, is it clear that my body will get the benefit from that, that it would if I ate 50
grams three times a day? Yeah, it's quite clear that you won't get a benefit, that there is a limit.
So now we need to think about the body as muscle versus everything else. So we're going back to the
muscle-centric view that I like. Yeah, you're probably sensing a theme with me at this point.
The muscle, there's a lot of data now that muscle can handle protein meals for an optimum
anabolic response between about 25 and maybe 60 grams. So then you start getting into distribution.
If you think you're going to have 150 grams per day, how should you distribute it?
One of my pet peeves in nutrition, I'm slightly getting off track here, is people refer to protein
as a percentage of calories. Protein is not a percentage of calories, protein is an absolute
number. You need to decide on what you're going to build your diet around. So right now we're
building it on 150. The issue with protein is being an absolute number, if your calories go down,
say you're now a 75-year-old woman and your calories per day is now 1200 calories, you still
have 100 grams per day protein requirement. So now your protein needs are 35 to 40% of your calories.
If people are doing weight loss, it's an absolute number. So people should never talk about
percentage of calories. That's basically people who don't think protein is important and say,
well, fat should be 30%, carbohydrates should be 50%, and that leaves 15%. I mean, you have to think
about protein first. So that was the issue. As far as distribution, from my research, one of the
things that we believe is that the most critical meal of the day is the first meal of the day.
When you have had an overnight fast, your protein synthesis is down and that mTOR signal molecule
is down regulated. It's inhibited. And until you have enough leucine around three grams,
which translates to about 30 grams of protein for most people, until you have a meal that has
30 or more grams of protein, your muscle stays catabolic. So you're continually breaking down
protein. We think that's a significant aspect of aging, that people have lower and lower protein,
they don't eat protein at breakfast. And we know the efficiency is going down in the first place.
So we want a front load protein in the day. So we want at least two meals that are well above 30
grams of protein. So I always have people shooting for 40, 45 at the first meal, another 45, 45 at
their last meal. And then in between, again, if we're talking with people who are, say, an elderly
woman trying to maintain minimal muscle, I'll concentrate on those two meals. If I'm talking
with somebody who's trying to do weight loss, I'll concentrate on three because I don't want
them getting hungry. If I'm talking with someone who's trying to be hypertrophy, a muscle builder,
I'll concentrate on four. So how many meals per day do I make anabolic and muscle? And by anabolic,
I'm thinking 35 grams or more. And the data that we know for absolute certain is the first and last
meal are absolutely important. The middle meal, I'd be hard pressed to show you a single study
that where anybody's ever looked at lunch. And so the reason that you're saying for the anabolic
person, we need four meals is we just simply need, we know we need it for positive nitrogen balance.
We're just going to have to get the, yeah. Right. So there's two, there's two aspects. There's one
is mTOR signaling muscle protein synthesis, leucine effects, and the other is total protein per day.
So those two lead say, well, if I need more protein and I max out at 50 grams, I need another meal.
And what about timing? So let's just talk about someone who's doing their strength training
in the morning. So let's say someone's going to do strength training from 8 a.m. to 10 a.m.
Do you want them having that first bolus of protein before the workout?
There's some debate about that. You'll find some people and trainers who believe that. We did some
studies and most of them were with animals where we looked at different timing. And we find that
exhaustive exercise is catabolic no matter what. So having protein ahead of it doesn't make it.
So we find the benefit is after the exercise when the system is now finally tuned, we've
stimulated red, actually we've inhibited red one, the system mTOR is ready to go. So we find
the benefit is after exercise, not before. And just to be clear, what you're saying is, look,
you can take all those amino acids before, but it's not going to prevent you from becoming
catabolic during exercise because, again, exhaustive exercise is a catabolic activity.
So you are going to be breaking down muscle no matter how many amino acids are on board
while lifting. It's more important after the lift that you have a good meal.
You'll find some disagreement in that in the literature, but I strongly believe that what you
just said is correct. And my research supports that. And talk about the efficiency or the window
in time post a workout in which you want to make sure you're getting that first big meal of protein.
Is it one of those things? I'll tell you a funny story. So my youngest son, who's now five,
but when he was like three, I mean, I don't know, for whatever reason, he just fixated on protein,
probably because we kept telling him to eat this and eat that because there was protein in it.
Hey, eat your salmon. It's got protein. Eat this because it's got protein. And basically, he has
become the protein police of the preschool. So he just he walks around and he looks at kids' snacks
and he's like, that doesn't have protein. That granola bar does not have protein. That has protein.
And you can imagine what these people who work at the preschool say to my wife when she drops him
off and picks him up. She's like, are you a nutritionist? And she says, no. Oh, OK. It's just,
you know, your son really fixates on everybody's protein consumption. So we joke about how he's
going to be like that, like one of those bro protein guys who's just going to be all obsessed
with his protein and when he's eating it and stuff like that. So I've lost our train of thought here
for a minute. But just to focus on the children for a moment. So we're talking about
adult protein needs. And I don't want everybody to walk away thinking,
gee, I need to get 50 grams of protein in my kid. Children, children will be very efficient at
maintaining growth with small snacks of eight to 10 grams of protein where that will have virtually
no impact for an older adult. So, you know, a protein bar that had 10 grams of protein is
a perfectly legitimate snack for a child where essentially the only thing it would do is probably
increase liver enzymes at a 70 year old. So don't want all the mothers think that they're doing a
bad thing by giving their child a 10 gram protein snack. OK. I want to go into, I remember what we
were going to come back to. So I'll take us back there. But let's talk about that a bit more. So
because that's actually news to me. I didn't realize that there was
minimal benefit in smaller quantities of protein. So this is another argument for don't dribble out
your protein. Commit to it's binary. You eat it when you eat it and you don't when you don't.
Yeah. So again, children versus adults and the adult. If we have every meal of the day,
let's say we have 100 grams of protein, but we take it in and very small meals, 15 grams
trickled in all day long. You will never stimulate muscle protein synthesis, but your liver will be
perfectly fine. Your gut will respond to that amount of protein, your gut, your liver, your heart,
your kidney. All of those organs will respond to the net protein per day, no matter when you
ate it. But muscle doesn't. Muscle is specific. Muscle is such an energy. As you mentioned earlier,
there's so much mass to muscle muscle isn't triggered unless the diet is exactly right.
And we could get into teleological arguments about losing at this point,
branch chain amino acid. Why does the muscle sense that? But basically the muscle senses energy,
insulin, protein before it triggers. And if all of those aren't balanced, it won't trigger,
but your liver will. Yeah. I mean, I guess to your point, teleologically, you might make the case
that the liver has more concern for the brain than the skeletal muscle. And maybe it gets priority
over being happy because it has to maintain glucose homeostasis. And without glucose
homeostasis, the brain would literally die within 20 minutes. So yeah, I guess. Likewise,
you know, your liver, your heart, those have to function, you know, middle of the night, your
liver still has to be making protein, but your muscle doesn't. While you're laying there in bed,
your muscle is catabolic and it's supplying amino acids. So all those other organs work.
So while I argue about muscle centric health, the reality is moment, the moment it's organ based.
Yeah. But long term, your overall health is determined on keeping the muscle healthy
because it keeps everything else healthy. And just because I want to keep talking about this
before we go back to where we were before I distracted us, is the reason that it's okay
for kids to be, you know, eaten little bit, much smaller amounts of protein. Is it simply just the
mass that, you know, like, I mean, my youngest weighs 25 kilograms. So is it basically just saying,
look, he probably doesn't need more than 40 grams of protein a day. So for him to have a 10
grams serving is 25% of his protein. That's like me having 40 grams.
And plus his protein synthesis, as we mentioned earlier, is driven by hormones where yours isn't.
So his growth, his growth is highly efficient. It's driven by hormones and he he'll, he'll
accommodate it in small doses. And you're right. He probably only needs 45 for the day anyway.
So I'll take you back to where we were before I sidetracked us. It was now asking about
how big a window you have to refeed to maximize muscle growth.
So, so we actually did that first experiment in rats. So Josh Anthony and Tracy Anthony were in
my lab. Uh, I was just before Lane came. Uh, and what we were looking at was exhaustive exercise,
again, erodins. We were looking at this catabolic state. We were trying to look at how to muscle
regulated recovery. And so we were looking at what we're called initiation factors. And we discovered
the link between leucine and an initiation factor called EIF4. That is sort of the downstream
effect of mTOR. mTOR is a regulator and it stimulates EIF4 and S6 and other initiation
factors. And so what we found was that when you came out of an exhaustive exercise,
muscle is catabolic until you took in enough leucine to reverse it. And so we started looking
at feeding right after exercise and Stu Phillips and a number, you know, Doug Patton Jones and
Luke Van Lee, a lot of people sort of picked up on that. Um, okay. So now the caveats, um,
the biggest effect of feeding right afterwards is about a two hour window,
but that's in untrained individuals. Um, if you begin to look longer, you can have a ballot of
resistance exercise and you'll detect the difference. You'll begin to make them, you'll
start regulating that red one protein factor and you'll see an anabolic effect the next day,
24 hours, 36 hours later. So when does your protein effect, well, it makes it more effective
all the time. Um, the more trained you get, the less you're going to see a post exercise effect.
So if you're beginning training near in the first four weeks, post exercise protein probably makes
sense. If you're well trained, you basically training the same way and you've been doing it
for six months, I don't see any effect difference between having protein within two hours after
exercise versus just having your three or four meals per day. You won't see any difference in
either mass or strength. Yeah. I remember having this discussion with Lane as well and being very
surprised by that, right? Being pleasantly surprised by the way, because it says, Hey,
look, once you get to a point where you're well trained enough, you don't have to be so maniacal
about meal timing. You can just focus on the big picture, which is total protein, protein quality,
and spreading it out such that you don't exceed the metabolizable fraction of it at anyone sitting.
Right. Exactly. And people, you'll hear trainers take that last statement, metabolizable energy,
and you'll hear trainers say, well, you can't use more than 30 grams at a meal. You won't digest
it or whatever. That's not true. I mean, you'll digest and absorb a hundred grams of protein at
a meal, but muscle in particular only has a window of around 25 to 60, depending on protein
quality where it can use it. The liver will use all of it. I mean, it doesn't matter. We have what
is known as first pass metabolism of protein, which confuses the issue even more.
When you eat a meal of protein, approximately 50% of the protein is degraded to nitrogen and carbon
before it ever gets to the blood, almost 50%. The one exception, the exception of that are the
branch chain amino acids, leucine, isoleucine, valine, and over almost 75, 80% of those get
into the blood. And we're back to that teleological argument. Why did muscle learn to sense that?
Because that basically shows up in the blood in direct proportion to the meal. And the muscle
learned to sense that as a meal quality. It says, oh wow, this meal has adequate quality for me to
trigger this very expensive process of protein synthesis, protein turnover. And until it sees
that signal, it won't do it. While we're on the topic of muscle done, another thing I've learned
somewhat recently that surprised me was the importance of leucine in fatty acid oxidation
by the muscle. So one of the things that is such an important pillar of our practice is
kind of low end aerobic training. We call it zone two. So zone two, mitochondrial efficiency. So this
is basically pushing your muscles to the maximum point at which you can keep lactate below two
millimole. And in a very fit individual, that you can generate a lot of power while still keeping
lactate below two millimole. I mean, the best in the world can produce more than four watts per
kilo while still keeping lactate below two millimole. And they're doing so virtually exclusively with
fatty acid. So we will pair this type of analysis with CPET testing and we will look at fat oxidation
rates. And again, you will see the fittest of the fit have insanely high fat oxidation rates.
They're over a gram or roughly a gram per minute. So tell me, so another point of that is, look,
a really good muscle doesn't just rely on glucose. A really good muscle can oxidize fats
very effectively. What role does leucine play in that? That's a great question. And
I don't think it's been researched well enough, but there's no question. So leucine, I mentioned
earlier, we're talking about amino acids and every amino acid has a different side chain.
Well, leucine is one that's referred to as a branch chain amino acid and its side chain is purely
carbons. It's a carbon chain that looks a lot like a fatty acid. And so leucine is one of
really two amino acids that are ketogenic. It is metabolized as a fatty acid. And what we know
is that leucine will also activate the CPT-1 enzyme, the carnityl palmitin
transphrase enzyme, which is the link of bringing fatty acids into the mitochondria for oxidation.
So there's a benefit there. It gets even more complicated in that when you have higher leucine,
it also begins to inhibit pyruvate from going into the mitochondria. So when you oxidize a leucine,
the nitrogen that comes off of it is put onto pyruvate generating an alanine. And so the body
begins to recycle glucose. So it becomes kind of steady state on glucose and emphasizes fat
oxidation. So back when you were talking about Schulman studies early, if you overload all of that,
basically you can make the leucine inhibit carbohydrate oxidation. So if you have huge
amounts of carbs coming in, and then you overload the system with leucine, you'll inhibit pyruvate
oxidation. And so that could look like insulin resistance. But if you look at the physiology
of how it's supposed to work under conditions where you'd be burning fat, like you just described,
leucine actually stimulates fat oxidation and spares glucose for the brain and other tissues.
So again, you really have to think about how the experiment's set up and what's getting inhibited
and what's getting pushed. Now you've recently actually taken an interest in weight loss, right?
So the dietary interventions that can be efficacious for weight loss and treating
things like metabolic syndrome. So let's build off this idea a little bit, but how do you incorporate
the strategy around reducing energy intake? Because this is sort of how I think about weight
loss, right? Like you got to reduce the intake, but I think of three broad ways that you can
approach that. So three strategies, right? One is you just reduce calories and that becomes the only
focus. So you pay attention to the total energy content of food without thinking about the timing
of food or the macro distribution of food. The next approach is you spend less time thinking
about the total number of calories, spend more time thinking about the macro nutrients, create,
I described it as sort of create a boogeyman in the diet, some things that you avoid
and the restriction of certain things becomes a roundabout way to restrict total energy.
And then we talked about time restriction as well as another strategy. So how do you think
about manipulating that middle bucket of changing macros to achieve energy deficit?
So I totally agree. Weight management is a calorie issue and it's not the same for every
individual. Everybody's got a little different efficiency. So we understand it's not,
you can't be an accountant and expect to just count calories all the time. But
let me build it as a story of how we thought about it. Back in the late 90s,
the keto, you know, Atkins and the keto diet were out there and Barry Sears and protein,
you know, the zone diet and Michael Eads and the protein power. And I was looking at all of those
things and we were doing those leucine experiments and we had discovered this effect of leucine on
muscle protein turnover and some of these metabolic things with fat metabolism. And I basically
took the leap of faith and said, you know, I think the underpinning of all of these diets is really
the protein carb ratio. And how can we manipulate that? And so I started thinking, well, you know,
if we're going to create diets, one, we know that from a satiety standpoint, protein is probably the
most satiating, you know, lures fat would be next carbohydrate, the least. We were concerned
about big insulin swings. So we wanted to sort of balance out our carbs per meal. We know that if
people are overweight, they tend to have big post-carb, post-meal carbohydrate and insulin swings
where they get two hours later, they'll have insulin low carbohydrate lows. And so we started
trying to think about that and we said, okay, so we think the first meal after an overnight fast
is critical. So we're going to correct that. So we basically started saying, how much protein do you
need 30, 40 grams of protein to get most satiety protein synthesis effects? We knew that protein
had a higher thermogenic effect, burns more calories, more heat than either carb or fat.
So we wanted to front load that effect. People have argued that, well, that's because protein
or the nitrogen, it's harder to digest and absorb. We don't think that's true at all. We think the
thermogenic effect is stimulating muscle protein synthesis. We know that that is a massive ATP
expenditure. And so what we want to do is maximize that at every meal. So our first meal, we wanted
to be 40 grams of protein. We wanted to have a carb level that would not overstimulate insulin.
We kept that under around 30 grams for what we created a carbohydrate threshold concept.
We could go into and then fat sort of around out the calories. And we basically developed three
meals a day to distribute like that. We basically increased the protein to about 1.6 grams per kg.
And we ran the study comparing it to the food guide pyramid with 0.8. So as far as we could tell,
we did three different studies. One, a total feeding study where we fed everyone. A second
study would diet and exercise that was four months. And a third study was multi-centered
with 120 subjects that lasted 16 months. And so we did three studies and what we saw-
The last two were free living where they were responsible for the food, but the first one,
they were fed?
The first one, we fed them in the lab so we knew exactly what they were eating.
The second one, we actually fed them for the first two weeks for a few meals so they really
saw what it would look like. And the last one was totally free living based on the diets and
manuals that we developed.
And each of these was two arms where the only difference was protein?
So in the first one, it was two arms, food guide pyramid, high carb, low protein versus
higher protein, low carb. The second one was two by two. So we basically had the diet treatment
and then we had a resistance exercise treatment. So high protein, low exercise, high protein,
et cetera. And then the last one was diet with a generic recommendation for exercise, but just
a two treatments.
So what did the first experiment show, the really well controlled one?
So the well controlled one, what we found was that with the higher protein and as far as we
could measure exactly the same calorie intake, the people on the higher protein, low carb,
lost more total weight, more total fat and less lean. And that stabilized their insulin and
glycemic regulations and lowered their triglycerides across the board.
And do you remember what the difference was in weight and fat mass? And was it all explained
by the thermodynamics of the Delt difference in protein?
It was close. We found that based on, if you just, if you assume that body fat is
3,500 calories and you can make that calculation, we figured out that the people on the higher
protein diet were getting a better fit of, I think it was around 170 calories a day,
eating the same calories. So that could be about the thermodynamic effect.
So in other words, that amount spread out over the duration of the study explained the difference
in weight loss.
Right. So both groups lost weight. They were both on weight loss diets, but the protein people lost,
and I didn't look those numbers up, but they lost around eight pounds more and almost all of,
you know, something like, you know, six and a half of it was fat.
And did they also complain less of hunger or was there a difference subjectively between the groups?
Yeah. We did, we did a satiety check in that really just a,
using an analog scale. We just asked them to rate how they felt and stuff. And one of the things that
the dietitians who were running the study always came back as they said that the, the protein
people were never talking about food and snacks, but the people on the high carb diet were always
talking about being hungry and snacking. And so yeah, there's definitely a different satiety
and compliance issue to it. And the fat was longer in that study in the longer term studies in the
first study, which was only 12 weeks, basically all subjects in both groups finished the study
and the longer studies would got into four months and longer. We found much higher dropout rates in
the high carb group too. So did the results of all three studies point in the same direction,
which was a higher protein weight loss. So a protein sparing weight loss diet,
which gets back to your point earlier, stop thinking about protein as a percent of total
calories. Protein should always be absolute. And if you want to think about it that way,
it's actually, it should, as, as you reduce calories, protein should increase the total
fraction of calories. Right. Is going to preserve lean tissue better, maintain satiety better. And
plus there's potentially this bonus of the thermogenic effect of protein. Right. It definitely
partitions the weight loss toward fat, protects muscle, malign tissue, definitely has higher
satiety. You know, and one of the things we know, and in fact, for a long time, there was a lot of
debate whether people over 60 should ever try practice weight loss because they would lose too
much muscle and they can't gain it back. Um, you know, they're Doug Patton Jones had the theory that
sarcopenic aging isn't a gradual decline. It's a series of acute effects that you injure yourself.
You're in bed. You're, you have a surgery, whatever you acutely lose lean mass and you
can never gain it back. So we were concerned about that. We want, we want weight loss,
but we don't want people to lose any lean mass, especially if they're adults. If you're a 20 year
old, it probably doesn't matter so much. But if you're older, you know, if you're beyond 40,
it does matter. It's a scary thought, Don, if you think about it, right? I mean,
that 40 40 is not that old. And yet, um, you know, I recently had shoulder surgery. Uh, so as with
the time that we're recording this, I'm probably about five months out from that shoulder surgery.
And, um, I still have not gained back all of the, the, the muscle mass. Now I think I will gain it
back. Um, but I look at how difficult it has been and how acutely I lost it. I mean, within three
weeks, I was 10 pounds lighter. I lost 10 pounds of body weight. And it's obviously not just from
the shoulder. It's when you don't have an arm, you can't squat, you can't deadlift, you can't
do all of these other things. So I would bet that, you know, obviously some of that was water weight,
but look, I think seven of those 10 pounds was lean tissue that I lost in, in a span of three weeks.
There's some tremendous research by my colleague, Doug Patton Jones, who unfortunately passed away
this last year, um, who did a lot of that kind of bed rest sort of study and looking at older adults
versus younger. And in the same period of time, an older adult in bed rest will lose four times as
much muscle as a younger adult. It's, it's frightening how fast you can lose it. And you
know, to your point, if you're diligent and do weight training, you can begin to gain it back,
but it's hard to ever get back to ground zero if you lose it in aging. And people will ask me, well,
all this losing stuff, when does it really come into play? You know, is it as, it's not as important
for a 20 year old as it is for 60, but where's the middle ground? You know, where does it change?
And I think it's a little like bone health. I think once you're, once you're 40, you're sort of
on the back end of that and you need to be much more careful. Doug and I ran a study, which,
you know, everybody quotes now where we took 90 grams of protein and looked at it distributed
as three meals per day, 30, 30, 30 versus 10, 20, 60. Uh, and we found that with the same amount
of protein, the same overall diet, uh, you would have higher net protein synthesis with the
distribution to breakfast. So that's kind of where all the distribution data came from was that
study. And, uh, we ran that study in 37 year olds. The average age was 37. So we think that by mid
thirties, you can detect the distribution effects. And just to be clear, Don, do you think that the
reason 30, 30, 30 was better than 10, 20, 60 because you started the day at 30 or because you
had three meals where you cleared the hepatic threshold? That's a great question. And one that
I wish the Twitter world would understand. I think the effect is moving at the breakfast,
the first meal. I think that frankly, we'd have been better off if we ran this. You should have
done it 60, 20, 10 as the other arm, right? That would be there. No, I think it should, I think it
should have been, I think it should have been 40. What's the math? 40, 10, 40. I think the first
and last meals are the key. Okay. The, and I'll give you the reason for that. We've done a number
of studies in animals. Uh, other people, Mike Renee and, and, uh, Phil Atherton have done it in humans,
but when you trigger mTOR at that first meal, we know that it's still stimulated five hours later.
So why do you need lucine for mTOR at lunch? If it's still stimulated, you don't. So there's,
nobody has actually studied that at this point. Unless you're the person who just is so big,
you know, like your lane, right? Like if your lane and your weight, 200 pounds and you're a body
builder. But the key to what you just said is now you're talking total protein per day, not a
lucine effect. Yes, exactly. It's no, it's not a lucine and mTOR effect. It's total substrate.
It's okay. Lane needs 250 grams of protein per day. He'd be better off putting that in four or
five meals than putting it in two. So that's the difference that people need to understand is that
distributing across all the meals, if it's for weight loss and appetite, that's great,
but it's not an mTOR effect. So Don, this kind of brings me to sort of, you know, something we've
talked about before, which is, you know, so much of this research that you've done has been funded
by industry. And a lot of people are going to say, well, we're going to discount everything Don just
said, because, you know, so give us the names of some of the organizations that have funded your
work over the last four decades. So, so let me backdrop that for you. So I had the lucine concept
that lucine was going to be key to protein synthesis and muscle. We ran a study in the early 80s
where we realized it was initiation effect. And so we then started to realize we started looking
for what those initiation factors were going to be and it's EIF4. So we sent that as a proposal
to NIH, National Institute of Health for 10 years. And basically it was continuously turned down
and they said, well, we only study disease and we don't know of any deficiencies of protein. So it's
not a priority to us. And so basically I was left with what turned out to be a revolutionary idea
of reinventing protein that NIH wouldn't fund. And basically I finally went to Kraft Foods,
the National Cattlemen's Beef Association, the National Dairy Association, the American Egg Board,
and some of the other groups who were inherently interested in protein and they fund and we had
some from the USDA, I was at a land grant university. So those were the funding sources
that basically unlocked all of this knowledge about protein for adults, lucine, mTOR, muscle
centric health, all of that was unlocked simply because we could get funding from Kraft and Beef.
And, you know, am I biased? You know, everybody who eats is biased in some way. And, you know, if you
look at research, and I think maybe Lane said this with you, I never believe research when I read it
until I see it in three more labs. So I don't mind if people look at my research and say, I don't
believe it, but my research has been out there, very clear theories for 20 years now and every test
makes it stronger. And so that's how you believe it. The fact that Kraft or Beef funded it's
irrelevant. The issue is everybody who's ever run the study after me shows the exactly same thing.
Do you think NIH has, or have you seen, I know you've been, you know, semi-retired now,
you're kind of not really retired, but you're retired from the grant cycle.
Exactly.
But do you have colleagues that are still in it or do you see any evidence that NIH has taken a
broader purview to health? If nothing else, they should be able to look at the fact that
two thirds of Americans are, you know, have metabolic syndrome. And that should at least
give pause to think we might need to revisit the way we're approaching nutrition. And therefore,
maybe we should be funding, quote, unquote, non-diseased research in nutrition.
I think they definitely have. Chris Lynch, who's director of nutrition at NIH now,
that position didn't even exist.
And where does that, within NIDDK, where does that sit?
That's a great question. I think it's across multiple institutes. So which one actually funds
the most? I think NIDDK might be the one. The Cancer Institute, I think his unit actually
goes across multiple institutes. But again, that didn't exist back in the late 80s, early 90s.
So, you know, I think it may be a little broader, but there is a general philosophy still at NIH
that NIH does not do applied food research, that industry should fund it. So that becomes a cash 22.
You know, if we're going to study the difference between whey and soy,
unless you can say, well, that's going to cure heart disease, they're not going to fund it.
And so you have to then go to the dairy council and say, I want to do this study. And then people
say, well, you were funded by the dairy council, or I'd go to the soy board or whatever.
So it's a catch 22. But basically the alternative is we put our head in the sand and we don't do the
research. So basically, I look at people in nutrition right now. And literally, I don't know
anybody in nutrition who doesn't get industry funding. I just simply how you have to get funded.
Yeah. One of the things I would also point out in this whole issue of bias,
it's important to recognize that the animal commodities are all under the USDA supervision
because they are animal commodities and they have check off boards. So that means everything
they say in advertising has to be screened, where the grain industry has big companies like Kellogg's
and Pillsbury and Coke and Pepsi. And they can literally go out and say anything they want.
And so you'll see a product out there that pretends to be an egg. And they'll claim that
there's better than eggs, but egg can't come back and refute it. They can't say, so you've got two
different playing fields, one that's highly restricted and supervised and the other which
is fair game, you know, for, you know, First Amendment, I can say anything I want.
On that topic, Don, how closely have you paid attention to kind of both the plant-based meat
and the synthetic meats? I've paid a little bit of attention because obviously there's two companies
that are pretty popular. I can never remember their names. I think it's Beyond Meat and Impossible
Meat or something like that. Exactly. Got it. And they're plant-based meats, right? So they're making
meat out of plant. And then you have a whole host of companies, none of whom I can remember the names
of, that are actually trying to make synthetic meat. The little bit that I've read about that,
which really amounts to reading like two scientific articles, left me with the impression that that
will not be technically feasible. That just from an energetics cost, mass balance,
sanitation, GMP standpoint, that's not going to happen. So that's my way of saying either I'll
be proven wrong or that will turn out to be one of the biggest boondoggles of industry in some time.
Do you have thoughts on either of those two, including kind of nutritional composition and
how it feeds into an amino acid perspective? First, as an overview, I think that as the world
continues to expand in population, we're probably going to need additional protein sources. We may
be near our capacity for animal-based proteins. I mean, we may not be able, I don't think we can
double it again. So we may be near, so we're going to need other sources. So I accept that
plant-based proteins are important to us. I totally agree with your comment about synthetic
proteins. I don't think that will ever be economically or environmentally feasible.
I don't think that's true. Then we get into sort of the popular versions of plant-based
Beyond Burgers and things like that. And the reality is it looks like a flash in a pan. I
mean, people tried it. And basically, if you go to a Burger King and look, basically, they had
good sales for a few months. And basically, and you track that, it was all people who don't
normally go to Burger King. It was people who were interested in a plant-based burger. They went
and tried it once and never came back. So basically, we know the stock has fallen through
the bottom now. We know that nobody's using it. The problem with it is, let's take Beyond Burger,
basically, it's a P protein that's produced in Canada. It's shipped to China because we can't
process it in the United States. There's no processing for the most part. They're beginning
to develop it. But when it came out, there was none. Shipped to China. China processes protein,
ships us back to the US. We know transportation is the number one cause of greenhouse gas in the
world. And so now we've shipped it all over the country, comes back to the US and they process it
into something with like 25 ingredients, probably five or six of them are not FDA approved.
I wasn't aware of that. Why so?
They have multiple products. They have multiple components and synthetics that have never really
been studied and they're not FDA approved. So they're basically relying on safety without ever
proving it. Will that ever come back to haunt them? I don't know. But in the spirit of having
natural foods, there's certainly not anything natural about them. So anyway, I think that
plant-based proteins have been around a long time. I think trying to pretend that it's meat
or calling soy drink milk or almond drink milk, I think those are travesties. I think those are
standards of identity. Almond milk has what? One gram of protein per eight ounces where
cow's milk has eight. Calling that milk is pure deception.
You know what my wife, I love cashew milk by the way. That's how I make all my soybeans and stuff.
My wife calls it nut juice. She's like, you're going to have some of your nut juice.
I mean, and I'm not against using them, but I think the nomenclature needs to be correct.
Right. I mean, if you look at one of the examples I like to use is that if you look at a wheat
cereal, we won't pick any, but take a wheat cereal that has four grams of protein per serving. We
always said that's only two probably on the label. It says you mix it with a three fourths of a cup
of milk. So now we have 10 grams. And if you look at the lysine balance of that, it's exactly
balanced. But if you go to soy milk, a soy milk only has six grams per eight ounce per cup instead
of eight. So now you already have less protein and it's also deficient in lysine. So it takes
almost a quart of milk. It takes almost 30 ounces of milk to balance that cereal. So if you're a
mother feeding this to your child and thinking, well, I'm doing a plant based thing and I'm feeding
them a totally deficient diet with, you know, six ounces of soy milk for breakfast. I'm feeding
them a totally deficient diet. How many mothers know that? Yeah. Yeah. I look, if I don't know
that, I'm guessing a lot of mothers don't know that. And so those are the kinds of things that
we think need to come out about protein quality. We want a system where we can show people an
additive value and that at the end of it, and I put that meal together and this, this is a company
called wise code that I'm working with. We think that we can show with using QR codes and your
phone will simply add them up and you can tell what your total meal looks like. Yeah. That would be
incredibly helpful. I mean, I, again, as I alluded to earlier, still something I trouble, I have
trouble with is, is, is doing it especially on days when I don't have access to as much meat. And
what it comes down to for me is just how much did I have from leftovers the night before. So, you know,
I've got a meat based meal, which is my dinner. You know, wild game is sort of our, our routine,
right? So elk and venison and stuff like that. And if I'm smart enough and thoughtful enough to make
a lot extra, then I get, I can basically have it for breakfast and lunch the next day, but sometimes
I'm not. And then I'm, you know, I'm making protein shakes. I'm, I'm, you know, eating a venison bar
here and there, but it gets a lot harder. And yeah, I've never even, I'm having a hard enough time
just making sure I hit the total grams per day of protein. And it's, it's, there's no attention on my
end going into, Hey, how much methionine is here? How much leucine is here? How much lysine is here?
And if, you know, as I said a while ago, if, if you've got 125 grams of protein in your diet
per day, chances are you'll hit those numbers. And where, where leucine is a meal to meal number,
lysine is a daily number. It doesn't matter meal to meal. It's a total. And I guess for me,
that's probably okay. But then I think about it for my wife or my female patients where it,
I mean, it's like, it's hard to get them up to 120 grams per day.
Yeah. We struggled with all of the adult women we had in our studies and, you know, we had whatever,
three, 400. It's a real struggle to keep a female at a hundred grams of protein per day. It's just a
struggle. And that then quality becomes an issue. And, you know, that's my, my concern with the whole
plant-based movement is that do people have the resources to make that, you know, can you make
that healthy? Sure you can, but you a need a lot of knowledge. You need a lot of food skills and
you're going to have to eat synthetic products because you can't get it from eating, you know,
be, you know, lentils and rice. You just can't eat enough of them. And so you're going to have
to have shakes or supplements or something to get to that kind of level. Otherwise the track
record says that vegetarians will end up around somewhere in the sixties for their protein per day.
And quality does make a difference at that level. Well, Don, this has been really interesting. I'm,
I'm so glad that we were introduced and I can talk about protein all day because it's an eternal
interest of mine personally, but also in terms of helping as many of my patients as I can. I think
this is perhaps the, you know, it's not the macronutrient that gets the most debated on Twitter.
That's reserved for carbs and fat, but this is, this is the one that I think we need to be paying
more attention to. So I'm grateful for the work you've done and for the attention you brought to
it today in our discussion. Yeah, I appreciate the opportunity to do that. And I, you know,
maybe one thought thought I'd leave you with that we haven't touched on is people talk about high
protein. And I think it's important to try and come to grips with what that means. If you look
at all of the epidemiology, which I think is pretty bad science, the definition of high protein is
about 1.2 grams per kg and low protein is actually below 0.8. And so a lot of them will express it as
percentage of calories and they'll say less than 10%. And so when you look at the epidemiology,
you need to realize they're talking about very narrow ranges of protein intake. And, and it
really isn't the protein that's making a difference. It's the calories and the other things that are
going with it. And I'll just, one last thought when I was for four years, I was director of research
for the American egg board. So I funded all of the research that basically got the cholesterol
direction eliminated from our guidelines. One of the things we funded though, was there was a lot
of research suggesting that eggs had a high correlation with obesity and diabetes and heart
disease. And so we funded some research with, with Teresa Nichols and Vic Vergoni who are experts
in the NHANES data. And what they looked at was that in the epidemiology, the difference between
the first quartile and the last quartile for egg consumption was three to three and a half.
So they were basically saying that a half an egg per week or per week, yeah, per day,
I'm sorry, per week, half an egg per week was a difference in causing obesity, heart disease,
and diabetes. And so what they did was they went into the NHANES data and they factored out all of
the eggs that were eaten at fast food versus the eggs that were just eaten at home in a quote,
good nutrition setting. And what they found is in every case, eggs now became a positive.
They reduced obesity, they reduced. So basically it's not the egg, it's the egg in the company it
keeps and you can make anything a bad diet. Yeah. And I think to your point, it's when we talk about
epidemiology pointing at high protein being a problem, you realize anybody who's tried to
actually consume high protein realizes it ain't high protein, it's high calorie that's the problem.
And the protein is along for the ride because again, 1.2 grams per kilo is actually kind of
low protein in the context of a high calorie diet. If you look at epidemiology and you do any food
surveys, what you realize right away is that the data for protein is pretty good. If I ask you how
many eggs you ate yesterday, you'd give me the number. If I ask you how many ounces of milk or
how many grams of meat, you'd give because we sell those by ounces and weights. But if I ask most
people how many carbs they ate yesterday, they'd miss it by 200 grams. And so that's the problem
with epidemiology is that the errors are not homogeneous. They're not equal. So anyway, I
ramble on, but a great pleasure to chat with you, Peter. Thank you, Don. This was fantastic.