Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Michael, so awesome to be sitting with you here today. I have been looking forward to
this podcast for probably about three or four months. And I appreciate you making the trek
out here to do this in person.
Absolutely. Likewise, Peter, I've been looking forward to this one. It should be fun.
My wife, by the way, I just want you to know called me like an hour ago to give me a ton
of crap for the fact that we're not recording this outside in the hundred and seven degrees
here today. She's like, you guys talking about the comfort crisis in your air conditioned
studio here. What? So she's kind of called us out on the fact called me out on this fact.
Well she's not wrong. Yeah. I did think about that. I would like it might be interesting
if we actually did this while rocking, but here we are. We'll rock afterwards. It'll
be fine. And she was like, I mean, she wants to rock with us later today, which we will.
She was mostly like, really, you should at least be just sitting outside doing this in
the sweltering heat and, you know, all that stuff. And so maybe she's right. I mean, we're
definitely way too comfortable right now.
There's going to be a weight penalty for our behavior with the rucks. If we were planning
40 now, it's now 50, 55. So that's how we'll compensate. We'll all check out in the end.
So look, people have heard me kind of talk a little bit about your book on previous
podcasts. People have also heard me allude to this obsession of mine in rucking.
Certainly anybody who knows me personally is it's they're they're they're either
converted or sick and tired of me and my daughter who just got back from her first
sleep away camp in Colorado and Wyoming. So she was first time in 13, gone away for two
weeks. And, you know, this was a hard camp. You know, we sent her to a place deliberately
because of how hard this place was. And it's basically a camp where you go to work. So
they're, you know, taking care of animals, you know, doing a bunch of hard stuff. And so
in prep for this, we said, look, Olivia, you really ought to just rock with me all the
time because it will make it easier for you to go. And she just didn't really want to.
I mean, I think when you're a 13 year old kid, the idea of going for a heavy weighted
backpack walk with your dad at five o'clock in the sweltering Austin heat is not that
appealing. The whole time she's there, you know, they have no electronics. You get one
time to speak with them. You get a 10 minute call at the middle of the thing. So the first
thing she said on that middle of the thing, she goes, Dad, I'm like the fastest hiker here.
All that rucking totally paid off.
I love this. Yeah, I could not love this anymore.
This is so cool to hear because they were like 10 to 12000 feet. So they're at altitude.
And, you know, I was having her out there with 25 to 30 pounds in her pack.
Very cool. And we have a lot of hills here, as you'll see later today. So it was it was
good for her. I also love that you sent her to a camp where she's doing hard things outside.
It's a theme that runs through my book, as you know, that is so valuable for kids today.
I mean, so I teach at UNLV and seeing a lot of the students that come in where they're at
psychologically and sort of how embedded they are in, I would say, digital worlds and in their own
head and how things that I think most people would consider maybe minor inconveniences in life can be
so easily blown up. I think that ties back to a lot of what I'm talking about in the book.
And I think the antidote to that is sending kids out when they are younger, trying to introduce
hard things into their life. And there's obviously a lot of different ways to do that.
But it sounds like what you did is a is a really cool thing.
I mean, it's certainly one way to do it. And we had friends that recommended this place when we
reached out to friends who had older kids to say, hey, where are places you can send kids?
I mean, our actual initial hope was to send her to kind of a missionary camp where you could really
sort of see something challenging in Africa and things like that. A lot of times they just, you
know, for kids this age, we're not necessarily looking for that. But let's take a step back and
kind of, you know, just help folks understand a little bit about you. Remind me where you grew up.
I grew up in Northern Utah. So a little town called Bountiful just outside of Salt Lake City.
Okay. Were you a skier? What was your main?
I like to say that snowboarding got me into college because when I was in high school, I was not a
great student. I liked to go out. I liked the party. I was into girls. I was into cars. I was
into all that kind of thing. Didn't really care about schoolwork. Now, would never do homework,
did okay in school. But with Park City Mountain Resort, they would sell you a season pass for
$99 if you got on the honor roll. That is the only thing that incentivized me to do any good at
school. So thank you, Park City ski resort. That is what got you into college. Yeah.
So you mentioned your, did your parents split when you were young?
They did. So my, well, I wasn't even born yet. So my mother was pregnant, five months pregnant,
and my dad took off. So their backstory, which I think is relevant to understanding the context,
is that my dad was always a heavy drinker, heavy drug user. When my parents met, my mom was into
that lifestyle too. So eventually my dad realizes, you know, maybe I'm a little too into this world.
So he goes to rehab. Now as part of his rehab, sorry, this is after you've been after you're
born. This is before I'm born. Okay. Yeah. So they were married at the time. They'd been married a few
years. So as part of his rehab, they give my mother the book that he is supposed to read in
rehab. And they say you read this so you understand what he's going through. Is it 12 step? It was.
Okay. Yep. So she, she goes, okay. And one night as she explains it, she goes, so I'm sitting in
the tub one night and I'm drinking a gin and tonic. And I get to this line in this book and it says,
try to drink and stop, try it twice. And she goes, Oh yeah, I couldn't do that. So she realizes that
she has a problem too. And she manages to get sober. So that's, that's the joke is my dad went
to rehab and my mom got sober. And so they got back together. He stayed sober for a little while,
you know, a little bit, just enough for her to get pregnant. And once she got pregnant,
it was, you know, there's, you don't have a drinking buddy anymore. The funds over. And I
think he wasn't quite ready for that. So he took off and my mom raised me, always been raised by a
single parent. Do you have a relationship with your dad today? I do not. I haven't heard from him for,
oh man, since I was like eight or something like that. Yeah. So given, you know, you,
how much of this history of your parents drinking did you know as you got into high school and stuff?
I knew my mom didn't drink and I knew the reason why she didn't drink. Now she was very respectful
of my dad. She wasn't going to give me any sort of details, but I was left to assume that the reason
that he was not in my life is because he didn't ever stop drinking. So that was sort of the context
around that. So when you get to high school and most kids are, even though not, you know,
sort of legally allowed to drink, but obviously that's when kids are most experimenting with
alcohol. Did your mom have any advice for you or did you have any thoughts about, you know, I,
I'm born from two parents who both have probably suffered a little bit from this. I could certainly
have a genetic predisposition. Yeah. So when I was a kid, my plan was I'm never going to drink
because of that genetic predisposition. And I read books, it was kind of a nerdy kid. And then you
turn into a teenager and your brain starts changing and you look for excitement and risk and all of a
sudden the pull of social things becomes so much more rewarding than it ever was that I drank. And
when that happened, my response was why the hell would you not do this? Right. That was the answer
because the town that I grew up in, uh, I was, it was all one religion except all Mormon, presumably
all Mormon. Yes. And we were not Mormon, um, single parent. So a little bit of an outcast in that sense,
you know, it didn't have a dad around. And so I think you kind of, you're kind of trying to
figure it out. You know, you're, you're uncomfortable in these situations around people just,
just generally. And then you have a drink and all of a sudden that goes away. So it becomes this sort
of learned thing where you associate this with, with good things. All of a sudden I could talk
to anyone. I could talk to girls. I could say funnier things. It was a lot more clever, right?
So you get all this positive feedback and why would you not drink? Right? Now that eventually
worked for me until it stopped working. That's sort of the classic story. So today I'm, you know,
I'm sober and there's a good reason for that. And I'm glad I am saved my life. Yeah. So talk to me
about the, um, the, the kind of realization that this isn't working for me. Um, you know, they talk
about how change happens really slowly and then really quickly. Um, and, and so what was the slow
descent into the quick realization and how many, how many, not everybody just has a one realization
where they hit rock bottom and they switch. Sometimes you have to bounce a little bit on
the bottom. 100%. I would say that I would, uh, I'd always noticed that I probably drank a little
more than other people. At the same time, there were no real repercussions for that until I was
maybe 23 or 24. I was living in New York city. I was going to grad school. I was living alone
and I had no one watching me and I had bars that closed at 4 AM and that's a potent combination.
And I think that was when I started to realize, Oh, like maybe this isn't good. And I remember,
I remember exactly when I sort of realized it as I went, uh, went on the internet like you do
consulted Dr. Google and you know, signs you have a drinking problem and it's like these
10 questions or whatever it was. It's like, I'm going yes to that one. No to that one. Yes,
to that one. No, to that one. Yes. Yes. And I go, Oh, five or six out of 10, I should be fine.
It gets to the bottom. If you have answered yes to one or more of the, I just go, uh, oh.
So that's when it gets on your radar. And I think I told myself,
well, I'll just quit when it gets bad enough. Once I reach eight out of 10, then I'm stopping.
Yes, exactly. So then you just start racking them up over the years. And for me, you know,
I had tried to stop drinking probably probably started trying to stop when I was about 25 in
different ways and it never worked. Just never worked. And why, why is that? I mean, I'm sure
you are not the first person to come to that realization of just willpower alone without
maybe a broader system or structure or awareness is tough. Why do you think that's the case?
I think there's a lot of things behind it. I think some of them are developmental. Most people tend
to get sub out half of people will end up getting sober around age 30. So I think certain things,
the same things that are happening in the brain that draw a teenager towards alcohol and make it
this great association, they start to kind of shake out over time, right? You take on responsibility,
you have all these other things in your life that all of a sudden make that you start to realize
maybe this isn't as good for me. I also think that eventually the balance just tips where
the short term relief just doesn't isn't as good as what this long term thing could be. And I think
that coming to that realization takes a long time. Like you said, a lot of bouncing. And for me,
it was just one morning I woke up, I was living in Pennsylvania. I was working at a magazine that
was based out of there. We had an office in New York, but her editorial office was in Pennsylvania.
And I woke up and my house is a mess. I'm a mess. I'd had mornings. How old? I was 28 years old.
And I'd had mornings like that before. And for whatever reason this morning, it was like,
you could kind of see where this path was going. And it was very clear to me that if I were to
continue this drinking, I was going to die early. Now, whether it was 35, 55, 75, I didn't know,
I just knew that it was going to be earlier. And tell me about your relationship with your
mom at this point. Does she understand how much you're drinking? Is she? No. So I always hit that
from her. We've always been very close. You know, we were always a team. Yeah. And so I kept that
away from her. She would travel when I was a kid and in high school. So I would even only drink
when she was out of town, she was gone about a third of the year. So even things like behaviors
like that, I just didn't want her to know. And sort of, and it's interesting when you kind of
contemplated getting sober, did it occur to you that your mom could be the most important ally in
that given that she knew what it was like as well? Well, I think that so the morning where things
became more clear to me, she was the first person I called, right? I had told people. So now you're
telling her two things, which is I'm getting sober, the implication of which is I'm an alcoholic.
Yeah. Which you didn't know that. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. That was a phone call. She didn't want
to take, but was happy to take. Right. And I could also see that. So I could see this one path would
lead in an early death probably. And more importantly, it was like, you're going to lose
everything in the process. You know, at the time I had a girlfriend who I really loved and I was
starting to realize like, Oh, this is a, this is a really good person for me. We're now married.
What did she think of your drinking? She aware of it fully or? Yeah. Yeah. She was like, you got,
like, you got to get a handle on this. She basically put it, you're a really good,
cool dude when you're sober, but you start drinking and you're obnoxious.
And I was, you know, and I knew it too. But once you get in that cycle, it's like, if you're, if
you drink like I did, it was, well, if one's good, two's better, three's even better. Four's even,
but just keep stacking them on, you know? And so once you start drinking, something happens in your
brain where all of a sudden just your entire thinking and universe. I mean, this is, you know,
I have such empathy for someone who's gone through this, but I can't actually relate to it because,
you know, we are all wired kind of differently, right? And I don't have that chemistry in my
brain. Alcohol doesn't do it for me, which is not to say I don't like to drink. I love certain types
of tequila and wine and there's even one beer I like. But I can never recall like feeling what
you're feeling, though intellectually I can understand what you're saying and I can only
imagine how difficult that is because it becomes a reinforcement loop and those can be very
difficult to break. Yeah. The problem is the solution is the problem is the solution. Yeah.
Right. So that becomes a challenge. And where was I? Well, basically the other path is that I could
see, you know, this is going to be hard. It's going to be very uncomfortable. I'm going to have
to relearn everything. I don't know if I can do it, but I'm going to try this thing. And, you know,
I'd gone through stints where maybe I wouldn't drink for a few weeks, but I was like, I'm going
to take action and taking action was picking up the phone and calling my mom. And then did your
mom suggest the 12 step program? She suggested that I talk to people who were similar to us. Yeah.
So I started becoming active and just meeting other people who were sober, you know, and
having to a big part of it for me, which I think is one of the reasons why this book came about
is that I had to realize like, I don't have to be comfortable all the time, you know, because
alcohol is the ultimate comfort blanket for me. If I had stress from work, it became this really
learned behavior where if I just had a drink, then problems gone. But that ultimately was backfiring
on me over time, like in a very severe way. How many of your friendships were sort of predicated
around alcohol consumption? And therefore, once alcohol was gone, those friendships didn't make
a lot of sense. That's a great question. There's a few that they stuck around. I have some really
good friends who I remember I got sober, I got sober on December 15th. And I had planned to hang
out with a friend on New Year's Eve who was kind of my drinking buddy. And I had to call him and
be like, Hey, man, like, not drinking this weekend. He's like, Oh, I don't care. We can just go golf
or something. And it was just like, Oh, what a relief. Like, yeah, like that dude, I owe him a lot.
But then some, it's like, you just realize you don't have as much in common with them after the
it's not so much the drinking as it is, you only have this one thing in common. And so once that
thing goes away, it's like, Oh, well, cool. This was fun hanging out. We're probably not going to
call each other again. And that's okay. To me, that's like the subtle part of this that's really
complicated. And I may have told the story previously on a podcast, but I can't recall.
And when I was doing my residency in Baltimore, you know, at the time, it was certainly the heroin
capital of the United States. Now, I don't know if that's still the case. And, you know, opioids
have expanded far beyond heroin. But we definitely took care of, I mean, just it's almost like
everybody that walked in the ER with an abscess in their arm or something like that was addicted
to heroin. And, you know, the best advice I could ever offer, though it was not particularly helpful.
I mean, it was it was intellectually true. But like, I don't know how you act on it was,
listen, you're going to die from this. Like, it didn't kill you this time. You had a huge abscess
that I cut open and drained and pulled old needles out of. And you're really lucky to be alive. And
you're going to be on IV antibiotics for a few days and then oral antibiotics for a lot longer.
You only get a few more of these. And that's going to be the last one.
But I realize you can't just leave here and go back to the row home you're living in with all
the people that are doing that same thing and expect to stop. Yeah. So if you want to quit
heroin, you need a whole new group of people to be with. That's just such a devastating thing to
contemplate when your entire life is centered around this block of Baltimore where everybody
is using. And, you know, some doc is saying, look, this is going to kill you. But it's not just that
you need to stop this thing that is the ultimate comfort blanket. It's that you need a whole new
social, you need a whole new social group. You need to be around people that don't do this.
Yeah, exactly. And that I mean, that plays out.
Just devastating. Yeah. And it plays out in the research. You look at research on
alcoholics and I think there was a group that tracked alcoholics who, you know, at day one of
the recovery for a year and the people who still stuck around their normal friend group, only 15
percent of them were still sober after a year. I'm amazed it's that high. Truthfully, the group
that got a totally like stopped hanging out with those people, started hanging out with different
people. 60 percent of them were sober after a year. So it seems to me that your wife being sober
is a, I mean, I don't know. She doesn't know like she became sober in the sense that she was,
but the fact that your wife was not a big drinker. Yeah. Is probably the single biggest factor in your
life. I'm guessing. Super helpful. Yeah. Very helpful. I mean, I know it's definitely harder
for people who have a significant other who is continuing to drink heavily. A lot harder because
you're around that all the time. Probably the conditions that maybe led to some of your
drinking haven't changed at all. And, you know, it almost becomes an illogical decision not to drink
sometimes in the short term, you know, because for someone who has an addiction,
using the substance is a relatively rational decision in the short term. Totally. You know,
yeah, but it's just completely adaptive. Not only maladaptive in the long term. Yeah. So,
you know, how did you think about that issue, which was, okay, I have this adaptation that
serves me well in the short term, not serving me in the long term. But what's the adaptation for,
you know, how much of this is related to your abandonment as a child by your father. And did,
you know, because one could say that that's the potential root of this coupled with the
genetic predisposition, right? So you have these, which is kind of the way things work in life,
right? You have sort of an environmental and a, you know, genetic component to something. Did you
at the time think I should also probably figure out like how much of this is driven by that feeling
or that, that, that, that vacancy? I would say early on, you're just trying to figure it out
day to day. You're just trying to not drink. You're just trying to make the next right decision.
I think you start to unpeel that onion over time. And it's something that takes a long time,
you know, and everyone has their own onion, whatever it is that needs that unpeeling. And
just like with a real onion, sometimes you cry during it, but it's the right thing to do.
Yeah. So the magazine you're working at at that time, what do you, what's your, what's the,
what are the kinds of stuff you're writing about? So I was mainly in fitness and nutrition and
performance. I did some mental health stuff. So all kinds of different articles I was running,
basically all the fitness coverage for mental health is what magazine was. And I was,
which is how we met originally, wasn't it? I think it was. I feel like you interviewed me a couple of
years ago on, on something that was related like a men's health piece. I don't remember what it was
about. Yeah. I think Bill Gifford introduced us, right? Yeah. I think it was him. Cause he,
his background is with men's health, right? Yep. So Bill introduced us and yeah, I worked there for
six or seven years and that's where I was working at, at the time. So where did you get this idea
that we are in a crisis of comfort? Few things happen. So one is that working at that magazine,
I noticed that every single thing that I was writing about, cause I mainly am working on
lifestyle, health, performance, fitness, nutrition, that kind of stuff, mental health.
I noticed that anything that I'm writing about, you have to go through a short term discomfort
in order to improve. If you want to get fit, you're going to have to exercise
harder than you are now. If you're not, if you want to lose weight, you're probably going to be
hungry at some point. If you want to improve your mental health, just like I experienced,
you might have to ask yourself some hard questions about why do I feel this way? What's happening?
What's the underlying behavior and motivation? And that's not always comfortable. So I make that
observation. Then I get sober, which is the ultimate. Yeah. That was really, really hard.
What year was this? December of 2014. Yeah. 2014.
That was exceedingly hard, but after things sort of started to settle,
after you're done with the white knuckling, how long is the white knuckling? For me,
I would say there were times it was probably shorter than for some people. Cause I think
I was just done psychologically. Like it was sort of like, okay. But part of the white knuckling,
I'm sure is also just the physiology, right? You're really giving up something that. Yeah.
So you're having to relearn all these behaviors, which is really tough and
figure out how to deal with things. Um, but soon, like literally everything in my life
got better. Everything you could measure got better. Your performance got better at work.
Performance got better. My writing got better. My finances got better.
I lost weight, all these things. Uh, but more importantly, I would say internally is where
the change really was. I mean, I was just like, wow, like things have changed. Let's keep this
energy going. And I got that from being willing to sort of step into the fire to enter the cave
that was the one that I feared. Right. So that sets the stage for this idea that,
okay, going through discomfort often leads to something really good. And in the long term,
it's a necessary buy-in for change. And I kind of start thinking about this idea of comfort and
make some observations like, well, wow, you know, life is pretty comfortable in a lot of different
ways now. And then what sort of really brought the idea that would ultimately become the book
together as I do this back country hunt with Donnie Vincent, who's this back country bow hunter
filmmaker, and I profiled him for men's health magazine. So we go on this elk hunt. He was up
there for maybe two weeks. We're in Nevada up in the mountains. And I was only with him for maybe
five days or something like that. But you know, it's a backpack hunt. So, and what led you to want
to do the profile on Donnie? I came across a YouTube video of his and it's called who we are.
And I think that I had always been interested in the outdoors somewhat. I'd always had, I'd kind
of been interested in hunting. And I think part of that goes back to maybe my father. So his
profession is a hunting and fishing guide. So I just kind of had this interest in it, you know,
it's like a thing that was on my radar because of that. But I had never really come across material
around hunting that really spoke to me. You know, when you turn on the Sportsman's channel,
it is, if you've ever watched the Sportsman's channel, it's the Sportsman's channel, right?
And Donnie talks about hunting. Totally different way. Totally different way.
It was, I mean, he, I like to describe him as being part locavore, part naturalist,
part environmentalist, part conservationist, part ultra athlete. And which is funny, because that's
the way I was introduced to it. So that's the only thing I can relate to, which is why I don't think
I know what's happening on the Sportsman's channel or whatever it's called. Like I, you know,
for better or worse, like I just, my only exposure to hunting, it sounds like came about through the
same way that Donnie, I've read, you know, what you've written about him. So, so I thought that
was interesting. And I thought that he was talking about it in an interesting way. And I thought that
there was a lot of things, you know, knowing what I knew in the health space, I thought there's a lot
of different things that are probably happening around this that are good. So I joined him on this
hunt and we backpack in up to like 11,000 feet. And I'm freezing cold. This is in Elkhun. So this
is September, October, September. And I'd come from Vegas where it was a hundred something and
we get up to these super high peaks and it's freezing cold at night. And I didn't pack well
enough. Let's just say that I'm sleeping in the dirt, starving the entire time because you're on
public land. We're on public land. We're only packing in so much food because you don't want
to carry that around. Getting water requires that we hike down to this stream, hoof it up.
Sitting in the afternoon sort of glassing is very boring. Yeah. Because most people don't understand
that you're, you really only can shoot the elk at dawn and dusk. Yeah. The rest of the day, you're
just doing recon. I had no idea. Had I known that I might've brought up crossword puzzle, but instead
I'm just sitting there going, Hmm. You know, looking around and it's like, Oh, all of a sudden
I'm bored again. Um, on and on. And during the five days, did he get an elk? He got one right
after I left. So I didn't get to see that, but also the, the underlying census, we got really close
to one. It was just a little too young for him. So we got within, oh, like 40 yards and this thing
didn't see us. And it was just like, I mean, I was just saucer ride. Oh my God, that thing is huge.
You know, they're, they're magnificent creature. It was unbelievable to see it that close and in
the wild. And what ended up happening is we, we got in really close and a coyote came in because
he's waiting for Don, like he understands, Oh, this guy's going to kill it. I'm going to have dinner
too. Um, so that elk spooks and takes off, but I get back home to Las Vegas and I feel great.
Like, man, I haven't felt this good since I was like, just got sober when you're riding that
pink cloud off into the sunset, man. You know, and it occurred to me, you kind of have this moment
where you're like, man, the world I'm in now is so different than the world I was in up there.
And it's different because this is comfortable in every way. And that has,
it was uncomfortable in almost every way. And yet that, yeah. Why did that feel better? Right?
That doesn't make sense. Right. And yet that world is the one that humans lived in
for pretty much all of time. 99.9996% of our genetic evolution. Yes. So you go,
whoa. Well, that's interesting. Now we've had this very, very rapid tip into comfort. So you start
to look at, start to look at all the things that most impact my daily life. I couldn't live in
Las Vegas. We're not for air conditioning. I drive to work as I stream entertainment from my XM radio.
Right. Uh, I don't have to be alone with my thoughts. I have this easy, you don't have to
hunt or gather any of your food. No, I don't have to work for any of my food. My food is also
exceedingly calorie dense. If I want it to be, I can eat it anytime. There's an abundance of it
on and on and on. And so I just wonder, okay, well, how are all these other comforts affecting us?
Right. Have we almost become too comfortable? And what happens if you sort of push back against this?
And I guess what are the key types of discomfort that we evolved to face and do those still help
us today? So there's the question. And that ultimately led to me going, well, that's a,
a lot of material. This doesn't sound like a magazine article. It sounds like a book.
So you write the book proposal and we shopped it out. And it's funny because this whole process,
uh, you know, you have a book agent and stuff and they're going, well, this is a really good idea.
And I think I'd like to read it, but I don't, I don't know what the hell it is. Like what,
what section does it go in? Right. Because when you read the way that I tell the book,
which we'll get into as I did this 33 day trip in the Alaskan Arctic, and that is the overarching
narrative of the book. And as I'm facing these important discomforts that humans used to face
in the past that can still be beneficial to us. Now that our world is comfortable, I spend chapters
on those. So I'm kind of weaving the stories in and out. And it was kind of a confusing thing
for them to wrap their heads around. They're going, is this in the adventure section? Is it
self-help? Is it like, what is it? But we took it out and luckily someone was like, well, I think
I can probably do something with it too. So I, I love the way it's written. Um, and as you know,
I gave it to my daughter and I love that. Yeah, nothing makes me happier. Yeah. So, um, of all the
we'll, and we're going to go into each of these in some depth, but I'll tell you the one that
nagged at me the most, because most of these discomforts I've thought a lot about, right. And
I've, um, but the one that I don't think I'd really given its due to was boredom. In some ways,
that's the most insidious comfort we've cured. Yes. Um, I love the way you talk about it,
right? Cause it basically we, you know, I think you say sort of like in the 1950s television,
no, no, no. So it's go back 1920s radio, right? So that's the first time you've got this
external source of input that you can kind of numb your boredom with, um, which is passive
rather than active. I think that's a part of it as well, right? So you could have read before then,
but reading is not really boring, you know, uh, reading is not necessarily the same type of a
remedy. Um, and then we talk about televisions in the 1950s and the 1960s, but I love what you
describe is what is it June 29th, 2007 is the death of boredom. Yes. The advent of the iPhone.
And I think that that shifts. So if you sort of back up and look at how much time people spend
engaged with digital media today, when I wrote the book, the average was 11 hours and six minutes.
It's now past 12 hours. Yeah. So, so I had my team look at this because I'm like, this can't be right.
Like I said, first of all, that must include working at the computer, right? Does it,
I think it might. And I've always, that's been a question in my mind as well. Yeah. But when you
look at cell phone usage, it's up to like three average hours television, television. I will say
this television is the most dominant at capturing our attention. And how much of that is the TV is
while I'm cooking, but I'm not watching it because when I go through these numbers,
there's one of two possibilities. One is I am so out of touch with how the world lives
or it's capturing things that aren't direct, right? Like, cause I've seen that I've looked at
these data where it's like 12 hours and yeah, TV's the biggest chunk and smartphone and computer and
and stuff like that. And I'm thinking like, if I could watch six hours of TV in a week,
that would be a big week of TV. And that's only during a week when there's a Formula One race.
Right. Right. Like it's not, it's, it wouldn't be on a regular or a non F1 week.
So how is the average person watching four hours of TV a day or whatever it is?
I think it's definitely possible because think about the data from Netflix
when they release a new series, something like a thousand upon thousands of people will binge
12 episodes in a weekend. I mean, that's so I guess you're right. I just, so Netflix,
they like, I binge watched Ozark. Yeah. Cause you know, and I was, I'm lucky I was able to do that
because it can't, you know how they, they missed a couple of years. Like that would have driven me
nuts. I liked that. I could just kind of watch it. You did it right. I did it right. But I don't
think I ever watched more than two episodes in a day. And there were lots of days I didn't watch
it. So when I say binged, I meaning I took like three months to watch it, but that felt like a lot
when Netflix released. So Netflix went all in, when they were trying to go to streaming,
they went all in, um, financing house of cards and sort of as a random thing, the decision that
gets made and who the hell made it. And they don't know why they go, you know, let's just put it all
up at once. Some crazy number of people binged the show, all of it, all of it. And they go,
Oh, what's this about? That's when binging, that's when binging show starts. So it's kind of this
random decision made by someone, probably just kind of a coin flip. Yeah. And I guess let's just
put it all up at once. The thing that I've been paying most attention to is the phone. And what
I've realized is like, if I compare myself to now versus pre Blackberry. So, um, I didn't get the
first gen iPhone in 2007, or I got it and then I returned it after a week because I thought it
sucked. But I only cared about email, right? So I was like kind of in the work mode of like email
and the email wasn't that good. And the phone wasn't that good. Like it wasn't actually a
good telephone. It dropped calls like the Blackberry was still the gold standard. But when I think about
what life was like before that, and I'm old enough to remember, there's a lot of time when you just
like you wouldn't, you wouldn't think to be sitting on the toilet looking at your phone,
right? Whereas now it's like, yeah, I'm pretty much always reading the news. Yeah, yeah, guilty
as well. And it's like, that is so weird. How if you think about something as silly as sitting on
the toilet, right? Like you're not there for that long. Do you really need to be doing anything else?
Right. So I started thinking about the idea of boredom from hunting, as we talked about that
it's a lot of sitting on a hill and looking for animals. So when we're when we are in the
people don't understand how sparse animals are. I think people have this view of like,
hunting is getting out of the back of a truck into a pen of animals and shooting them. Like,
they can't fathom what it actually means to scour 20,000 acres for an animal. Yeah.
And I think people think it's action packed that you're always like, you're always on the move and
running. It's like, no, it is 99.9999% extreme boredom and 1.00001% pure panic. Yes, exactly.
That's a great way to describe it. So we would sit on the, these hills because we're timing our hunt
to the caribou migration. We're hunting caribou. So we're waiting for the, so you're now in the
Alaska. So we're in Alaska now. Yeah. And so we're waiting for these animals to come through.
Now this just wasn't happening. So five days in a row, not seeing anything going, well,
they should be coming through here. It's not happening. And I didn't bring a cell phone,
of course. I'm not bringing books, magazines, all that stuff. And it's like,
I love the stuff that you read. Oh, dude. So to entertain ourselves,
we read the labels on our food. So I can tell you a cliff bar has 250 calories, six grams of fat,
49 carbs, 10 grams of protein, right? Like these are the things you're getting into. And you know
what kind of carbs too. Yes. You're reading all the labels. I'm coming up with, you know,
who made your clothing, right? Wasn't it Hong? Yeah. Some guy named Hong. Yeah. Yeah. My
Kefaru bag, some guy named Hong. And I'm coming up with Christmas shopping lists
for like the next six years. Did you bring a journal? I brought one of the,
right in the rain notebooks that I bring on any journalistic assignment. Yeah. So that also led
to, okay, well, you know, each thing becomes boring eventually. Cliff bar reading becomes boring.
Learning about Hong becomes boring. So then I go, okay, well, I'll come up with some ideas for the
magazines I write for and come up with like 17 different ideas. And they're all like very good.
I start writing some of the book. So this leads me to sort of a point about boredom,
which is that boredom is an evolutionary discomfort that basically tells us whatever
you're doing with your time, the return on your time invested has worn thin. So if you and I
are, you know, it's a million years ago, you and I are hunting, we need food or else we're,
we're going to die. We're going to starve for hunting and no animals are coming through.
Boredom is going to kick on and it's going to tell us go do something else. And then we might go
pick potatoes or pick berries, whatever it might be. Right. So boredom tells us do something.
And in the past that something that used to be productive, it used to often move our lives
forward in a way. Well, now when we feel this evolutionary discomfort of boredom, we have
very easy, very effortless escapes from it, right? You just pull out your cell phone. We have like
the ultimate vehicle for stimulation and attention capture on our persons at all time. Right. So it
has really put a big dent in boredom and boredom does come with benefits. So there's these really
interesting studies around boredom and creativity and they're like totally hilarious too, is that
they'll take one group of people and they'll let them do, you know, whatever they want, put them
in a room and like people bought their cell phones or whatever. They'll take another group and they
will, they'll bore the hell out of these people and then they'll give them a creativity test.
And the board group always comes up with more, more creative answers than the non board group.
And I think it also gives your brain time to sort of process information in the background,
let things sort of happen. So when you think about the sort of cliche of you get your best
ideas in the shower, well, it's a cliche for a reason. It's because when we're focused outwardly
on the outside world, like in a screen, our phone, Netflix, even this conversation, your brain's
working hard to process that information. So it's kind of a work mode. When you have these moments
of boredom, you tend to go inside for a little while as you figure out what to do. You kind of
have some weird funky thoughts and that's kind of more like a rest mode for your brain. I call it
unfocused mode in the book. And that tends to sort of give your brain a little bit of time to rest.
And from that seems to come good things. And one of the researchers I talked to, he goes,
look, boredom is neither good nor bad. It really isn't. It's, it's how you, it's what you do with
it. And so what we do with it now, I think is increasingly becoming something that maybe isn't
moving our lives forward. So what I'm arguing in the book is I'm not saying, you know, burn your
cell phone and, you know, go back to a flip phone or any of that. But I am saying that I think we
need to think about putting more boredom back into our lives. Because a lot of times there's so much
talk around how we need to reduce our phone screen time, like reduce your phone screen time, reduce
your phone screen time. And I think that's a good thing. But what tends to happen to people
is they go, okay, I took an hour off my iPhone screen time. Well, now what do I do? So they
watch an hour on Netflix. Well, your brain doesn't know the difference. Right. So I think it's, it's
better to have time where you're just sort of unstimulated. So if something that I'll do in my
own life is just go for a walk every day, at least 20 minutes and just don't take your phone and just
kind of let your mind do what it needs to do. That also gets you out into nature, which has its own
benefits. I'm sure we'll get into and well, that's, that's, you know, we're going to talk about rucking
a lot. And so this will be the, you know, one of many, but some of something that I really, and I
always talk about this, one of my friends, when I'm getting them into it, it's like, Oh, and by the way,
you don't bring your phone, you're not listening to a podcast and you're not listening to music.
Like the whole key to this thing is going without the phone so that all you're hearing, you know,
we're lucky here, we get to do it and we're not hearing, like we're not on a road that's busy
with a bunch of cars going past it. So you're mostly just kind of listening to the wind.
But, you know, wherever you are, you're, you, you have to get into that zone of not being with the
phone, which for me was also like, I'm the king of efficiency. Yes. You know, I'm always listening
to an audio book or a podcast or I'm on a phone call. Like if I'm moving, those things are
happening. Yes. There is never a time when one of those three things is not happening. I was totally
the same way. And I started digging into this research and it really changed how I thought
about it. And I do think that I tend to get a lot better ideas. My mind goes to more interesting
places that it maybe needs to go when I am disconnected and don't bring that phone along.
That's ultimately going to sort of capture more attention. Going back to the hunting thing,
I find it takes two days for me on a hunt to find my senses. We were talking a little bit about this
before we started the podcast. You know, one of the reasons I like AccessDeer so much, not only is
it, you know, just from an environmental standpoint, it's, you know, you're doing something very
positive for the environment. The meat itself is incredibly healthy, tastes great. But the
challenge of hunting that animal is so high, right? It's just, you know, if you can shoot an AccessDeer
with a bow, you have earned that animal. And the reason for that is they have really good senses,
like their sense of hearing, their sense of smell. It's insane. And so if you try to go and hunt them
in a clumsy way where your senses aren't heightened, it's a joke. It's like they're
toying with you, right? Like they'll smell you a mile away. They'll see you a mile away. They'll
hear you a mile away. You're not going to get within their zip code. You can only get up on them
if you become as attuned to the wind, as attuned visually to what's going on, as attuned to every
sound you're making. And again, I'm sure a guy like Donnie can get in that zone in one second.
I need like a day or two. And again, I like you don't have your phone with you. You know,
you're not listening. You don't have earbuds in as you're making this move. And I remember each,
you know, on almost every hunt I've been on, I remember kind of what that transition feels like.
And getting there is hard. Like it is, it is boring as hell. It's totally boring. But you
have to kind of go through that for your senses to wake up, at least for me. Yeah. I mean, I think
two things. One that's short and one that's long. I think that that's kind of a metaphor for the
book as a whole is you have to go through that to get that benefit. And I think there's a lot of
different things that we've removed from our lives that going through can benefit us. The second thing
is that what you're saying, it totally jives with not only my experience, but there's this concept
called the three day effect. And it basically shows that after three days in nature, a lot of
good things tend to happen to people. So in the modern world, your brain tends to ride what are
called beta waves, frenetic sort of go, go, go associated with sort of stress, burnout,
this sort of thing. After your third day in nature, brain tends to start to ride what are
called alpha waves. And these are found in experienced meditators. They're like calm,
more focused, more aware. And you just feel like, I'm sure you felt it when you're out there. When
you first get into nature, you're kind of to your point, you're like, what's going on? You don't
really feel in tune. You're worried. Like, did I put the garage down? Is this my, you know,
my daughter have a ride to school, that sort of thing. Once you get to day three, it's like
focus centered, like you just feel like, like a Zen monk or something. Right. And I think there's
a good reason for that. There's a lot of things that are happening. And this is why, one reason
why some researchers are thinking of extended time in nature as a way to help help people with PTSC,
specifically veterans, because the benefits don't seem to wash off immediately. So this idea of the
three day effect, it's at the top of this concept that I write about in the book called the nature
pyramid. And it basically prescribes different amounts of time you should spend in different
types of nature. So this idea of three days and sort of more back country removed nature is at the
pinnacle of this. And it basically says we should try and hit that at least once a year.
You know, I never really thought of it that way, but that's, you know, as you know, if you go on
a hunting trip, that's another thing people don't understand. Like, if you're going out there to try
to, you know, kill an elk or a deer, like it's going to take you a week. And like my first elk hunt,
seven days later, I didn't have an elk. Yeah. Like that's not uncommon. Yeah, not uncommon at all. And
I would, I think most, I mean, the success, I don't know what the success rate is. It's maybe like
20%, I would say for the average. You know, it depends obviously, but in public land, it's really
got to be pretty low. Yeah. You know, you have to be like, you have to be an exceptional hunter to,
to get an elk on public land. Yeah. And I think another thing that people sometimes don't
realize about hunting is that you're not hanging out on a trail and going on the, you know,
the trotted ground. Like you are embedded in the wilderness. You are bushwhacking the entire time.
You're completely, you can be completely off the grid. Like you are in it. And I think that that's
what makes hunting compelling to me is that rather than becoming sort of a observer of nature,
you become a participant in it. And I wasn't sure how I would feel about that, to be honest. So
the first time I ever hunted big game was for this book. And I definitely had my reservations.
But Donnie told me, you know, I think you'd understand why we go out there and do this thing
if you were to actually hunt. And so I trusted them on that. And I can see the appeal.
Yeah, it's funny. My, my daughter again brought this up when she got back. I've taken my daughter
on one hunt with me when she was 10 or 11. And, you know, in retrospect, I'm really glad I did.
And I don't know what I was thinking at the same time, because like, it's hard to see an animal die.
There's there's no way there's no getting around that. Like, I don't know, maybe if you've done it,
you get numb to that. But I don't think so. Even the most experienced hunters I know have a have a
real respect for life. And for you know, what I describe as the carbon cycle, like we're part of
it, too, right? Like we're, you know, we're going to die and our carbon is going to go back into
the earth and our nitrogen and it's going to fertilize something around us. So and of course,
the one axis to your she sees me shoot, it's a disaster because I forgot literally, I forgot
my front stabilizer. So, you know, we're booking it in at four in the morning, right? Because you've
got to be in position to try to see deer by like five thirty to get a shot by, you know, five forty
five or whatever. And I stupidly like just took the front stabilizer off my bow the night before,
something I would never do. And I forgot to put it back on. And we're an hour in and I realize I
don't have it and I don't have a choice. If we go back, we're done for that morning. So I'm like,
I'm going to be shooting this thing without a front stabilizer. I've never done that before.
It's doable, but I've never done it before. So to make a long story short, I get a 47
yard shot at this axis deer and I don't I don't hit my sweet spot, which is like you're on an
axis deer. It's not that big. It's only about that big. You've got to be able to get how much
the way the biggest ones in Hawaii are 200 to 220 pounds. This one was probably 150 pounds.
This one was not a monster. And instead, I hit him in the neck, but it hits his spinal cord because
he just dropped immediately. He was paralyzed. So now we've got to run up and stick a knife into
his heart to immediately kill him because, you know, on the one hand, you could say, well, he
doesn't feel anything, but you could argue psychologically this is pretty traumatic.
So it's not just like she sees a clean kill like she actually sees a very messy kill.
How did she handle that?
Amazingly well, she got a little nauseous when I because every time I shoot an animal,
I also want to take its insides apart. And so you're taking the meat off is one thing,
but I like to see the organs because I do think it really helps me to understand the anatomy well.
And I really like to see every detail of their anatomy over and over and over again. Plus,
we also eat the heart and some of the organs as well. So I think when I when we got into me taking
out the heart and doing all that stuff, she was like, I'm going to stand back here for a minute.
But otherwise, she did great. And then, of course, what did we do? Like we took that deer back to our
hotel because we were staying on another part of Maui and ate it and like shared it with everyone
who worked at the hotel. Cool. So we befriended the chef. And these are all people local to Hawaii
who know about what access do you do to their community, how they destroy their farms and stuff
like that. And many of them had never even eaten an access deer. And I was like, well, you're in for
a treat tonight. And so the chef prepared it for us and for the whole staff like fed like 50 people.
I love that. So it was it was it was really fantastic. And again, the point was the point
I was going with this. I had a point. Oh, I know. So my daughter is at this camp that she just
got back from. And she's talking all about she's like, well, you know, this counselor, that counselor.
And she's like, you know, one of the counselors there was a vegan. So for like a week, I went vegan
too. And I was like, Oh, what was that like? And she's like, Well, you know, it was all right. But
you know, probably not for me. And I was like, well, and I was like, so did the counselor tell you why
she was vegan? And because I've sort of explained to my daughter that there are generally three
reasons that people would associate with being vegan, right? There's sort of the like the animal
rights reason sort of like, and then there's a kind of the environmental reason vis-a-vis kind
of climate change. And then there's kind of like the perceived health reason. And I've talked to
my daughter in detail about each of these, right? And and I just wanted to kind of understand, I
said, So what was the rationale of the counselor who you were in? And she's like, you know, really,
for her, it was around the treatment of animals. And I was like, Yeah, I mean, I said, like, I
really respect that. And there's, there's almost a part of me that thinks you shouldn't be able to eat
meat unless you can kill it. That doesn't mean you have to kill everything you're eating. I'm not
suggesting that because that gets pretty complicated. But if you can't actually kill an animal
psychologically, maybe you should question whether you should be eating it. That would be at least a
discussion to have, right? And that's part of why I wanted my daughter to be able to see this so early
in her life, which was, look, anytime we're eating an animal, you have to understand like, that thing
was alive. What does that mean? Yeah. And so she, my daughter was sharing with this counselor,
like her experience, which is we eat elk and access to your like, most days. And she was like,
Yeah, the, you know, this counselor was super impressed. And I was like, that's a great sign,
like when when your vegan camp counselor is like, very impressed that you're eating wild game.
And, you know, Olivia was able to kind of explain the manner in which these things are killed, I
thought, you know, that's that's really cool to me. Yeah. And it gets back to your point, which is
it totally changes the dynamic of how you think about food. 100%. And it also makes you realize
how easy is it to be able to use a sophisticated weapon like this? And think about what our
ancestors had to do. Think about what we were doing just 1000 years ago. Yes. Like, I don't
know if you can see it, but right over there, we won't be able to show it on screen that you see
that bow on the wall. Oh, yeah. Yeah. So that a good friend of mine, Darren Aronofsky was doing
some filming for a documentary he was producing. And this is I think these are some hunters in
Papua New Guinea. And that's what they hunt with like that is there. So he actually brought me back
their act one of their actual bows and their actual arrows. And, you know, out to 10 or 20 yards,
they'll kill an animal with that. I was just in the Bolivian Amazon with the Chamane tribe. And
that's what they hunt with. They do a lot of fishing. They like okay, so how do you, you know,
kill to peer what a tapper I don't know how you pronounce it some sort of yeah,
they're just standing there and throwing like spears at them. Yeah. And they've got,
they've got bows like that. It's like, Oh my god. And here we are. So you realize like,
whatever I will ever do, or you will ever do or Donnie will ever do, it's still an enormous step
forward in technology to be able to use a bow an actual compound. Yes. Or something like that.
100%. And it, you know, it's fascinating because when I, when I kind of had my hesitations.
And was your hesitation around the act of taking a life?
I think that's ultimately what it was. Now my, I told myself is because we're journalists and
journalists don't get involved in the story. So you're just there to cover it. And I think that
was kind of a mental workaround for me to not have to, you know, I wasn't sure how I felt about it.
But I don't know. I mean, that seems like a reasonable point of view as well. Do you not
think that I could see that argument? I can see the argument. But I think ultimately it was just
a different experience. I don't think one's better than the other. I just think like you could have
been there watching Donnie do it. Yeah. And what was the other guy's name? William, right? Yeah.
Alternatively, by doing it now you're, you're writing about your experience.
I think that the, I'm glad I trusted Donnie. Let's just say that. I think that the,
the book ended up better. I think specifically the section where I talk about death is a lot
richer because of that. I mean, I feel like it is internally. The experience of actually hunting
the animal is, you know, I, I told him, even when I said, okay, to Donnie, I was like, I don't have
to do it. I don't have to pull the trigger. And he was, he kind of told me that too. He's like,
just plan on it, but you don't have to. And he wasn't pushing me either direction, but you know,
you buy a, buy a tag, which in Alaska, you can buy a caribou tag over the counter and go all the way
out there carrying the rifle around for a couple of weeks. And we finally get in a position where
we're on this hill and there's a herd on the other side of this valley on a hill and you know, Donnie
says, you know, if they keep eating their way down this hill, they're going to probably come over this
knoll. So if we can get on the other side of the knoll, we're going to be in a good position. So
when that happens, we just, we're on the move, right? We're kind of up and over the knoll.
We start cranking through the grass and the tundra, and eventually we kind of get into an army crawl,
you know, planning that these, this herd is going to come over the hill. And so we get in position
and you know, it was, it's like something out of planet earth where you're kind of watching this
hill. And then all of a sudden it's like the first thing you see are these antlers, these gigantic
antlers that first, and then it's like, there's one and two, and then eventually there are 30 and
they're all kind of coming. And we're looking at them because we're only wanting to shoot something
that's old. And we had, you know, from the spotting to help, we had thought, okay, there's probably
two older ones in there, but you know, you want to be sure. Cause we're super far away when we
made that call. How far were you when you guys made the first spot? It was pretty far. I mean,
maybe a mile. I mean, it's a big valley. And we eventually see in this herd that there's this
really old bull that's, that's limping. And so still at that moment, I'm going,
I got the rifle, I'm in position. I don't have to pull the trigger. But when we saw that limping
bull, it was like, okay, it felt right. And it was a tough process to get the shot off because
they're going in and out of the herd and you want a clean shot. And you know, Donnie at one point,
cause they were maybe within 150 yards of us was going to be the closest point. And I couldn't get
them in the scope and they kind of kept going. And Donnie kind of looked at me and goes, look,
if you don't have to take, if you don't want to take the shot, don't take the shot. But if you're
going to take the shot, you got to do it right. This is when you got to do it. You got to do it
soon. And right after that, it's like the herd sort of parted. It was right there. Just perfect
shot. Pulled the trigger, pulled it again. Herd ran bull fell. And my initial reaction was,
oh my God, like what have you done? There's, it was immediate regret, to be honest.
And sadness. We come up on the animal. That didn't help things. And
what was really interesting though, I had a lot of emotions around that.
And remind me what day of the hunt this was. This was probably a couple of weeks in. Yeah. So
we start breaking in town and all of a sudden that shifts the relationship there because you
kind of go, well, wait a minute. That's, that's me. You know, Donnie's like, yeah,
that's why we're doing this. That's why we're doing this. But you don't really understand that
until you experience it. And then it kind of occurs to me, dude, you eat meat all the time.
Dude, you eat meat all the time. And never, never questioned it. Never questioned it. You've
never felt one iota of emotion. And here you are now with this, like a mess. And not only that,
this animal that you just shot died more humanely and suffered less than anything you've ever eaten
to your, to date in your life. A hundred percent. It's not even a comparison. You lived a beautiful
traumatic life in nature, which is what it is. Let's not romanticize nature.
But wasn't in a corral, wasn't force fed antibiotics. And, you know, one of the things
that I really love about this project we're doing in Hawaii is, and we've only, I never appreciated
this until I met Jake Muse was the stress that an animal is in, in the final hours of its life
impacts the food quality. And even if you're eating the most she, she grass fed, organic
cow, make no mistake about it, the final hour or two of that animal's life is very stressful.
As it goes through the process.
As it goes through the process. Yeah.
I believe it.
And it's totally different when an animal gets, you know, a bullet through it and dies within,
you know, again, and we're trying to make sure it's an instant death for the, for that meat
process. There's, there's no cortisol surging through it. There's no lactic acid surging through
it. So yeah, what you did is actually about the most humane thing you could have offered that
animal relative to anything you've eaten, but also given to what its natural history is.
Like that's the other thing people have to understand. Like these old animals don't go
to old animal folks homes. No, they don't have graceful exits either. No, he's going to get,
he's going to get killed by wolves. He's going to drown crossing rivers because when they make this
migration, they have to do a bunch of river crossings. It's going to freeze to death. They
have a harder time. They have a harder time getting food as they age. So he's going to starve
to death. Or he's going to be killed by another caribou. Yeah. So it was really this, really just
a deep appreciation set in after that and sort of gratitude where you go, you're very thankful for
that meat, but also the fact that all meat, you know, I wish that our meat system, um, had some
changes to it, but you become grateful for all the other meat that we have. Cause you're like, wow,
like look at the buy-in that goes into this. You see that it is a life, you know? And so I think
it made me realize you kind of have this like very intense realization that for one life to go on,
another has to die to your point about the carbon cycle. And then the next step is, wait a minute,
I'm not left out of that. Am I right? Yep. And so this eventually gets me thinking about
about death in general and how, you know, I'm going to die. You're going to die. We're all going to
die. And if you think about that, like if you think about right now, we're just sitting here
having a moment very soon in their future, you're going to be having a moment. And then all of a
sudden there won't be a moment anymore. That is an uncomfortable thought. Right.
So I start thinking about that and this idea of, you know, death is the most uncomfortable thing
that we can, that we can think about. Really. When you do it right, you will ball up like a child.
But when I started practicing that, I found that it improved my life because it improved my behavior,
changed my behavior. When you realize you're going to die, all of a sudden you don't
pop off in traffic. Someone cut you off. You start to make decisions about work and what you're going
to do with your time that are better. It improves your interactions with other people, everyone from
my wife to the lady at the 7-Eleven. And the thing is that in the US, we don't think about death. We
sort of want to ignore it if you look at our structures. So we've talked about our food system.
Our food system is based around meat that you don't really know that it's come from an animal,
the way that it's processed. We even have euphemisms for different cuts of meat instead of
saying, you know, the muscles, the muscles that they are. And it's also in our funeral system.
Whereas after someone passes away, what do we do? We dress them up to look as alive and youthful as
possible. We have a viewing and then we're told to take our mind off it. It sounds like take your
mind off it. Don't worry about it. Don't think about it. And I just wondered what some of the
repercussions of that are. And it got me also thinking about, well, are there other ways that
places do this? And so this leads me to this trip to Bhutan that I take. So Bhutan is a very
fascinating place. I believe. And I mean, you know, you have a whole chapter on it, which is amazing.
And I want to hear all about it. Were there other candidate places you looked at besides Bhutan?
Bhutan came on the radar and it kind of became that. I think that's a place I should know.
No, it's an amazing discussion about the contrast. Yeah. So how do they die?
Well, I mean, first of all, what's so fascinating about them is they're
on if you measure it by GDP, they're 160 something out of like 184 or something. Yeah.
They just don't dirt poor. Yeah. But in a lot of happiness measurements, they rank in the top 20.
So they punch way above their weight and death, this idea of death and how they approach it,
I think factors in. There's a lot of things going on, but I think their relationship with death
does factor into this. And in Bhutan, it's they just take it into their life. So the Bhutanese
are told to think about death three times a day. It's kind of a cultural practice. Death is woven
into a lot of the art and the cultural dances and heritage. And there's even these little clay
pyramids called sasa. So this is mud mixed with ashes of cremated people. And they're all over
the country, all over the country. You take a turn, like an abandoned road and there might be
300 of them. They're in the window seals in the city. I mean, they're everywhere. So there's
this constant reminder and it flows in with this idea of impermanence and Buddhism. And I think
that Bhutan is a country really plays that up. So I traveled there to learn more about this.
And this was after the hunt. This was after the hunt.
Because it grew out of this understanding of, yeah.
And I met with three different people there. The first was a guy whose name is
Dachokarma Urra. And a Dachau is like secretary in the US. Like we have secretary of state.
Secretary of happiness.
Secretary of happiness. Yes. So I meet with him and he just does these happiness
measures all around the country. And he finds that I think 92% of Bhutanese say that they are
happy or less. They have different variations. They say, I think they have narrowly happy,
sort of like kind of baseline happy. Yeah. Very happy or like I'm extremely happy.
92% say they're at least some form of happy. And what by contrast, do we know what that is in the
US? I don't know. Although I know that some of our numbers there are dropping for sure. We're,
I mean, we're definitely not 92%. I want 40 comes into my mind, but definitely don't quote me on that.
So he does all these really fascinating.
It's hard for people to kind of wrap their head around some of this stuff, Michael. I'm quite
familiar with this research. I've talked a lot about it with Arthur Brooks, who also studies
this. And it's just, it's so perplexing until you actually go and experience places away from what
we do. Like I don't think one can cognitively appreciate what you're saying. If your only
exposure is what we are doing here, you sort of have to, you don't necessarily have to go to
Bhutan, but you have to see other parts of the world. You know, I, I, several years ago interviewed
this amazing physician named Tom Katana, who's like a missionary physician in Sudan. And he's in,
you know, one of the worst parts of Sudan, at least it was, it's, it's getting a little bit better now,
but it's in the Nuba mountains. There's about a million people there with no access to healthcare
who are being bombed by their government. So he's kind of running the hospital that takes care of
these people who are getting shrapnel and plus all the normal things that come up, you know,
infections and things like that. And, you know, one of the things we talked about in our discussion
was like the fact that nobody's depressed and there's only been one case of suicide that he's
ever seen. And it was probably related to a brain tumor that completely altered the person's brain.
I'm thinking to myself, Tom, the circumstances that you're describing sound so miserable.
How are people not just in a state of pure misery? And it turns out there's an amazing
sense of community, which we're going to talk about in Bhutan, right? Like there's,
there is no place you go to die that isn't around here. The oldest person, the youngest person,
everybody's together. And they're not, they don't seem to be any less happy, which again, it's
mind boggling that that can be the case. Yeah. And I think that there's generally more
economic equality too. I think that can affect it. I think there's a, the place definitely feels
slower, like much slower than the pace of life here. They have more exposure to nature, more time
in nature. Also they have no debt. I think that's, yeah, you mentioned everyone there, how do they
own their own homes? Obviously they're modest homes, but how, I just think it's inexpensive enough.
It's so inexpensive. Yeah. And there's, it's all universal healthcare. And the guy that I spoke to
is Dasha. He goes, look, our healthcare isn't perfect, but if you have a, you have something
that needs to be treated that is beyond what we're capable of treating, the country will pay for you
to the flight of India somewhere else. And just that's fully taken care of and fly you back.
So people generally don't have debt. And yeah, there is a big sense of community. So the what's
another, of course, there's so much healthier too. Is the other thing you said there's obesity rate
is 6%. 6%. Yeah. So that is one of the things that factors into it as well. They're generally
healthier. There's the entire country does not have a stoplight. Like what? Right.
There's no McDonald's or Starbucks or Burger King. I'm not saying those things are bad,
but I think what they've tried to do is really change the influence of or prevent the influence
of other places from coming in and sort of let Bhutan kind of figure itself out without other
places intervening. I don't know if intervening is the right way influencing that. And so that
seems to factor into it as well. I think most people, so I think the city of, I think the whole
country is maybe 3 million people. 600,000 live in Timpu, which is the capital. And then most
other people live sort of in the countryside and mountainsides and small communities of maybe 200
people. The stress thing is an interesting one. As I mentioned, we just kind of got back from
Italy. And the thing that I spent the most time thinking about while we're there is why is there
life expectancy four or five years greater than ours, despite the fact that they smoke nonstop?
Because this is the part I couldn't wrap my head around. And again, it's like I've been to Europe
many times. I've been to Italy once before. So it's not like this was the first time I was seeing it.
It was just the first time I really, really thought about it. I was like,
like smoking is the national pastime here. It's, and by the way, it didn't bug me, which is weird.
Like in the United States, when I smell cigarette smoke, it's like I have an allergic reaction. I
hate it so much. Somehow being in Italy smelling their smoke, I was like, look, it still smells
disgusting to me. But it just felt so culturally appropriate that I was like, you know, it is what
it is. I'm not going to be that American who's going to open my mouth and complain about smoke
in their country. But I'm like, their life expectancy, it's like four or five times,
four or five years greater than ours, despite the fact that they're participating in the single
most damaging thing you can do to your health. Well, of course, what I came to realize after
contemplating this for two weeks was everything else they're doing is so much better. Right. Like
they're eating a fraction of what we eat. And I mean, by the way, they're still eating pasta,
gelato. It's just the serving sizes are like this tiny. Yeah. They're much more active.
But the thing that really blows my mind is, and it's not surprising, is the pace. The pace is just
so much lower. It's just I really would believe and I don't know what metrics we have to measure
this, but I can't imagine they are under the stress that we put ourselves under. Now, the
flip side of that is because I've also thought a lot about this and talked a lot about this with
people. Maybe there's a reason the US is the world's biggest economy and maybe there's a reason
that most of the innovations are coming out of here and not Italy for that matter or pick, you
know, Bhutan for that reason. So I don't want to sound so naive to suggest that, you know, we should
all be like that. But you start to appreciate the trade off. Yes. Like we are paying a price
to be the world's leaders in innovation. We are paying a price to have unlimited access to food
and comfort that that, you know, when we were in Tuscany in the middle of nowhere, like you there
was no you know, the home we were staying in in Tuscany had no heat and no air conditioning.
So in the winter, it is freezing. And in the summer, it is basically just a sauna. It's a sauna
with with clay walls. Right. It's interesting. I mean, when I started to look at a lot of what
kills us now, it's all things linked to pace and comfort. Yeah, it's over nutrition, under movement,
under movement, too much stress. Yeah. And, you know, one thing that I learned, as I did this,
when it when it comes with stress, it's the question becomes, what is causing our stress?
A lot of it is manufactured, right? No one causes your stress, you cause your stress. Amen.
There's this concept in the book I talked about called prevalence induced concept change. And
that's kind of a nerdy way of saying basically problem creep. So these scientists at Harvard,
they did this kind of fun study. And they noticed this, by the way, they're waiting in line for TSA,
they're going to a conference. And they're looking at TSA, they're going, you know, a lot of people
who are clearly not that threatening get patted down, you know, it's like, grandma's getting the
full body pat down, because she had a half filled bottle of hairspray in her purse. And, you know,
they just pulled out my banana thinking that it was a Beretta or something. So they start to
wonder, you know, if all of a sudden, everyone just followed the rules, would they let everyone
flow through and, you know, just go on to your flight, or would they start looking for
successively smaller things, and they thought it would probably be the latter.
And I bet the reverse is true. If, if every fourth person coming through actually had a gun,
would the other three of us who have never carried a gun or threatening thing to an airport never get
patted down again, right? So they do this study. And there's two different studies they did where
they had people look at 800 different faces, and the people had to deem whether the face was
threatening or non threatening to them. So the people are going non threatening, non threatening,
threatening, threatening, non threatening, non threatening. What they did is about midway
through, they started showing the people successively fewer threatening faces. The other one they did
was very similar, except they're having them read these research proposals. So you would have to say
whether the research proposal is ethical or unethical. And again, somewhere in the middle,
they started feeding them fewer unethical ones. So you would think that people would just start saying,
threatening fewer times, they would start finding fewer things unethical, because it's like a person
either threatens you or they don't, right? And something either crosses this moral line you have
in the sand or it doesn't. Right, which you've already established through the first half of the
study. Well, it did. What ended up happening is they said that they said threatening the same
amount of times, same ratio times they found the same amount of studies. What word am I looking
for now? How many ethical, unethical? Yes. And so what their takeaway was, is that as we experience
fewer and fewer problems, we don't actually perceive this, we simply go out and look for
other problems. We don't become more satisfied. But the thing is, is that as the world improves
over time, and I think we can agree that even though things aren't perfect right now, everyone knows it.
There's never been a better time to be a human being with respect to the benefits we have. Yes.
You're less likely, you know, compared to 100 years ago, you're more likely to be literate,
educated, you're less likely to die at any moment, on and on and on. But when you pull people, only
something like 12% of people think the world is improving. It's because we're always moving the
goalposts. And I think this makes evolutionary sense because in the past, when the world was hard,
when you did have serious life threatening problems, if you were always identifying the next problem,
okay, that's going to give you a survival advantage. If you're always, okay, we got to fix
this thing, this thing, okay, this is a problem, fix that, fix that. But in today's age, as things
become successively better, we look for problems where they maybe don't exist, or our problems
become more hollow. I agree with that completely. I think there's another issue at play here, and
I've thought about this so much. You know, the first time I started thinking about this problem
was 10 years ago when I read Guns, Germs, and Steel, Jared Diamond's book, which I'm sure you've read,
and if people haven't read it, it's a great read. I suspect some of it is now dated, and there's,
you know, I don't know if he's written an updated version of it, but what it got me thinking about
a lot was how awful life was. I mean, there's just no other way to put it. Like, it's, it's,
we can sit here and talk about romanticizing some elements of a world with no iPhone.
The reality of it is, like, I wouldn't want to be one of the Hadza right now.
Even if you look at the Hadza today, which are one of the last tribes of hunter-gatherers,
so that's kind of our, one of our final windows into what people were doing 10,000 years ago.
There's, like, literally not a second of that that I think of as desirable outside of a vacation.
And by vacation, I mean, like, a hard experience you would go through for a couple of weeks
to make you more appreciative of what you have when you're back in plush Austin, Texas.
Yes.
But I can honestly say, like, I would never want to exist back in that world. It was awful. It was
so awful that I can't believe we survived it.
Yes.
I just can't believe I am tied to the genetics of people who managed to survive that.
It's unbelievable. And especially after we start to establish cities. Because then all of a sudden
you have one king and you're out in the field for 12 hours a day.
In service of that king.
In service of that king and you're starving the whole time and you have, you know,
you have all these problems with malnutrition. You're living in with, like, no sanitary.
It's just totally terrible.
Did you ever see that movie, The Duel, with Matt Damon and Adam Driver?
No.
So it's sort of it's loosely a true story based on the last time there was a duel,
the last time the King of France authorized a duel. And I believe it's sort of, I don't know,
I want to say 16th century, maybe 15th century. So call it like 500 years ago directionally.
Really good movie. I really quite liked it. But again, I'm like looking at the movie through
a different lens, which I'm always doing when I'm watching movies. And the lens I'm looking at it
through is this is a movie about the most privileged people in France, like the kings,
the knights, the most privileged. And at the time, France and England were the most privileged in the
world. So you're looking at the most privileged people in a society that is the most privileged
society on the planet. And this is only 500 years ago, which might sound like a long time, but
when we start talking about what 1159 33 means, people will understand how not long that is.
And I'm thinking I would rather be homeless today than the King of France 500 years ago.
Like it is unbelievable abject misery they lived in.
It's yeah, it's it's very crazy. And to your point, what you said earlier,
a lot of it gets romanticized and it's oh, yeah, you should you should check it out.
Go back there. See if you can. It's terrible. So it's a life is amazing to me.
I mean, yeah, yeah. So so yeah, I mean, that to me is the is the is the thing that you you're
constantly weighing, which is we have this incredible privilege today to be alive.
And all we need to do is to me, this is how I read the book, right? I don't read the book as saying
we need to go back and be hunter gatherers. No, it's sort of like saying, look, you have this
incredible. It's like a it's like an Uncle Ben moment with Spiderman, right? It's like with great
power comes great responsibility. We have this great power today. We have processed food, which
by the way, and the guy that you talk about in your book, I think does a great job of
explaining to you out of the gate. Hey, don't think processed means bad.
Processed is actually what allows us to like not get poisoned every time we eat food. Yeah.
So you have all of these things that allow you so much latitude. Do more with it. Right. That's
that's to me what really what it comes down to is we have the ability to help more people. Right.
You know, if you if you think about what it was like 500 years ago, if a person had mental illness
500 years ago, like I don't know how many other people were bending over backwards to try to make
their lives better because you were just too busy trying to survive. Yeah. Whereas today, like you
can help somebody else. Yes. That's the that's the responsibility that comes with the privilege
of having so much. You can afford to try to feed other people that aren't being fed. Yeah. And again,
in a world of over nutrition, it seems almost absurd that anybody would go without. Yeah.
Yeah. I think the argument that I'm making is that in a way, we've come become victims of our own
success. And if we don't have times that push back against what we have and sort of reframe
how lucky we are in the grand scheme of time and space and give us insight into these things are
all wonderful. But if I use them all the time, it seems like bad things tend to happen. Yep. Processed
food. Great. Keeps us all alive. It's why there's nearly eight billion people on the planet. The same
time if that is who don't have to move around. Like, yeah, think about this. Like we get to sit in
the same place. Yeah. Yeah. But if you're always eating the most comforting food all the time,
you're going to have some problems. It's great that you don't don't have to quote unquote exercise
or physically work for your food every day. It's great. But at the same time, if you never
reinsert exercise into your life to make up for that, you're going to have some problems.
It's great that I can, if I feel bored, I can go on Instagram and watch the most entertaining 15
seconds of my life and probably laugh my ass off for a week because I've found something so funny.
Which is hard to imagine. Like that couldn't have been done a hundred years ago. Yeah.
And here we are. But if you're always doing that, then it's like that comes with problems. So the
argument that I'm making in the book is that we need sort of moments that push back at us and
reframe things. If the entire history of this universe were laid out in a calendar year,
can you give some milestones? I love, I love where did you read about this or learn about this?
I was, I was driving to work in my truck 29 and it was on a podcast. Someone walks through it and
I just started bawling like, you know, I'm driving past like a Chipotle, just this, you know, kind
of fitness bro. Like, Oh my God, that's so much time, you know. Why? Okay. Well, so tell, give,
give the answer. And then I want to talk about why that, what that meant to you emotionally. Yeah.
So the answer is that the big bang happens. The big bang happens on January 1st.
I believe that our galaxy forms, I might get the months like September, September,
earth forms in November, dinosaurs die off on December 25th. After appearing on December 20th
or something. Yeah. Yeah. They were around for, you know, five days on this calendar. Yeah. Yeah.
That's right. The 20, 25th to the 29th or something, right? Of December. Of December.
All of human history that we have written down happens New Year's Eve, 11 59 starting
at 33, 33 seconds, 33 seconds in that is all of recorded human history.
That is how little time we've been here. It's crazy.
It is unbelievable. All of recorded human history is 27 seconds. The last 27 seconds of a year.
Yes. So for me, that was one of the things too, that, you know, I started thinking about
just that you're, it makes you realize you're not that damn important in the grand scheme of time
and space. Now that sounds like it's kind of, you're being hard on yourself, but at the same time,
I would go one step further. It's that you are completely unimportant. I mean, it's like,
you couldn't be less relevant. Yeah. And so that, you know, that can be unnerving at first,
but at the same time, I need to do the calculation of what an average human lifespan is.
Cause it's milliseconds on that scale. Yeah. Yeah. Definitely. And once you have that
realization, I think that it can change your behavior in a positive way.
Cause we're all here. We're all going to die. Right. Yeah. And so going back to this,
and again, it's just fresh on my mind. Cause I just kind of got back. So we're staying with
this friend in, in, in this place and in Tuscany and it's, uh, you know, it's like a 400 acre
farm that has been built up over years. So the first thing that was built on that farm was 500
years old, was like an old church and, and then like, you know, three, you know, and then 50 years
later, this other house got built. And then a hundred years later, this other thing got built and
then a hundred years. So the newest thing on this farm is 300 years old. The oldest thing is probably
five, 600 years old. That's your, that's your timeframe. And I had this sense that came over
me while I was there, which was, I felt so good being in a place where I knew so many people had
lived and died. Why do you think that was for the exact reason that you just said, which is it
really made me feel appropriately irrelevant. And I said to my friend, um,
so some of my friends in American, but he lives there like three months out of the year.
I said, did I not being facetious? So you can say no. But if I know, if I, if, if my death is
reasonably inevitable, like I have cancer or something like that, um, would you be cool if
I came and died here and, and was buried here? And he's like, yeah, man, that would be fantastic.
Because I feel like I would really like to kind of die in a place where I'm just a, you know,
I'm just an irrelevant piece of the long, beautiful history of our species. And then
I've never liked the idea of these, you know, funerals and things like that, but I'd like,
I'd like, could I just be buried there, right? By the olive trees so that my carbon and my nitrogen
become a part of an olive tree that someone will drink olive oil from, you know, 25 years later.
Um, and I don't know how to describe it. Like I just, I'm sure there are some places in the US
where you might find that feeling, but again, certainly nothing here that's 300 years old,
let alone 500 years old, let alone a couple thousand years old. Um, and I just, I think
that as morbid as it is to think like that, I don't know. I feel like I'm excited about the
possibility of, Hey, will I be fortunate enough to have enough of a warning when I'm going to die
that I could go and die there? Yeah. It's so when I was getting sober, a phrase I learned is
rule 62. Don't, don't take yourself so damn seriously. And that reinforces that for me.
Right. It's like, I think people have a tendency to take themselves and the things in their life
so seriously. And once you realize it's things aren't that big of a deal, like you got one ride,
you don't have to always ride the gas all the time. You know, like you can slow down sometimes.
That's been relatively freeing for me. And also I think improved, I mean, if we want to talk about
improving performance at work and in life, like that's kind of a life hack because once you kind
of let off yourself, it's like, you're free to kind of do the things I think you want to do and
let your mind go where it needs to go, especially for me doing creative work. You know, if I don't
put all this pressure on myself, I'm like, fuck, no one's going to read this book in 200 years,
100 years, 20 years, like who knows, right? Just make it good. Like, it's a ride. You know,
I remember watching this documentary about the Grateful Dead, one of my favorite bands. They are
my favorite band. Oh, really? And I think it was maybe it was 67 when they're kind of coming up
and they take a bunch of acid as the Grateful Dead do living in San Francisco. And how big
was the band at that point in time? So they started by they, they rose by playing the original acid
tests that Ken Kesey would do that eventually got written about in the electric Kool-Aid acid test.
And so this would have been down three years after that, they're kind of starting to come up there in
LA and there's this big LA tower thing that this guy had like built over years and years and years.
And Garcia talks about, you know, people, tourists would come to see this big tower
this guy had built. He looks at it and he's like, you know, I want to just create things that live
and explode in the moment and just have fun, like in this moment. And that ultimately guided them as
a band forever. And that's, you can see that in their music, that every song is like its own
exploding moment. And that's kind of what we are as humans, right? No one's going to remember you.
You're not going to have this big monument to you. It's like, man,
ride this thing out. Like give yourself some space and just like, enjoy it, you know.
So what's Misogi? Misogi. So I learned about this concept from a guy whose name is Marcus Elliott.
He went to Harvard med school, but decided he didn't want to be a traditional doctor.
He decided that he wanted to get into sports science. He wants to revolutionize sports.
And he kind of ends up doing it in a way. He's the first guy to really bring
AI and movement tracking into pro sports. And by using this data, he can basically tell people,
the way that your knee caves in, as you do this, you might have a 60% chance of injury based on all
the other cases we've seen of men of your size in the NBA, whatever. So he's kind of all about these
numbers and data and figures that can improve performance. But he also believes that what
improves performance and potential, it can always be measured in a way. There's intangibles that some
people have. And so to get to these, he does this idea called Misogi. Now the setup, the backup for
this is why it's important is that if you think about how humans evolved, we used to have to do
hard things all the time. No safety net. This could be from a big hunt, moving from summering to
wintering grounds, tiger lurking in the bushes, all these different things. So we were challenged
all the time. And if we failed, we would die. But each time we would take on one of these challenges,
you would inevitably learn what your potential was, right? You would really have to dig deep,
push, and you would come out of that. Assuming it went well, made it out the other side, knowing
what you were capable of. But now in modern life, you start to see a shift where you can live a
decent life and you're never really challenged, especially physically in a way that sort of
almost blends mind, body, spirit. You know, you'll have your running water, you'll have your food,
you'll have your home, you'll have your family, and it's really great. But, you know, he argues, and I
I'm with him on this, that if you think of human potential is like a really big circle. It's like
most people are kind of in this little dinner plate size thing right here because we never explore
those edges, really what we're capable of. So enter Misogi. And this is this idea that once a year,
you're gonna go out into nature, you're gonna do something really hard. Some challenging tasks.
So there are only two rules of Misogi. Rule number one is that it has to be really hard.
So he defines this by saying you have a 50-50 shot at finishing whatever it is, this Misogi task that
you decided to take on. And it has to be true 50-50 because now I think when people take on challenges,
especially when there's a physical element, they pick things that they know they will finish that
are within their capabilities. So if you look at how marathoners approach running a marathon,
it's not, I don't know if I'm gonna be able to finish this marathon.
Right. I don't know if I'm gonna be able to finish this marathon in under three hours or whatever.
Yeah. The second rule of Misogi. Which I like as much as the first rule.
So you can't die. Don't die. That is kind of a tongue-in-cheek way of basically saying,
be safe on this thing. So to give examples. Wait, isn't there also a third sort of rule of Misogi?
There's guidelines. Well, oh, I thought there was a, we don't talk about Misogi. Like you don't go and
like your Misogi doesn't get up on Instagram. Yes. So that is, then there's two guidelines.
The two guidelines are one, you don't talk about Misogi publicly. You can talk about it with
friends with your, with your wife and close ones, but you don't put it on Instagram and Facebook
and Twitter. And the reason for that is so many times now this rule, this guideline was a guideline
before social media, but so much stuff that people do today is often for the gram.
You want to do something so you can post it. And by removing this, all of a sudden you have
this question of if you're doing something really hard and you want to quit, are you going to keep
going for you knowing that it's not going to be for a pat on the back, some sort of social with
social implications. The second guideline is that the Misogi should be somewhat quirky, make something
up. The reason for that is because once you were removed sort of artificial metrics, that changes
the game, right? If you're doing a marathon, all of a sudden you're thinking about your time. You're
thinking about all these different things that are kind of socially constructed. Whereas if you
just pick some random task, it's like, well, let's just see if we can do it. We have no, we have no
framework for this. And that kind of opens up the door for some interesting experiences. So some of
the Misogis that this guy has done is one year, him and a few guys, they got an 85 pound boulder
and they walked it underneath the Santa Barbara channel. I think it was five miles. So one guy
would dive down, pick up the boulder, walk 10 yards, drop it, go up. The next guy would dive down,
rinse and repeat till you're at point B. But there's also simpler things like, here's this mountain
that we see every day. Let's see if we can get up there in a single day, things like that. Now,
the point of these, there's two big reasons for doing something like this. One is that it teaches
you that you chronically undersell your potential. So if you choose an appropriately hard task,
you are going to have a moment where you go, I'm done. I got to quit. I've reached my edge.
There's, there's no going back from this. But if you can keep putting one foot in front of the
other, then you get this other moment that's much more important. And that's where you look back and
go, well, wait a minute. I thought my edge was back there, but I am clearly past it now. And that
suggests that I'm selling myself short. And the more important question that comes from that is,
okay, where else in my life am I selling myself short? So you see that you're capable of more.
The second thing that comes from this is that it can reframe fear for people because we're wired
to avoid failure at all costs because failure in the past used to mean death. So of course,
we would want to not fail, but today failure isn't death. It's, I don't know, mistyping in an email
misspeak when you're speaking to a group of people, something like that.
Yet we still fear those kinds of things like their death. So sort of
dancing on the edge of failure, you can realize that it's not that big of a deal.
Now, when I first learned about this concept, it sounded cool. It sounded intriguing. The same time
I'm like, okay, it's kind of quirky, just like some made up thing. And then I started really
researching what was happening here. And we used to call things like this rites of passage. So when
we had a young person who was at point A in their life, and we needed to get them to point B, where
they were more confident, competent, a better contributor to the tribe, what would we do? We
would send them out into nature to do something really hard. Right. And along the way, they would
struggle, they would battle, they would have moments of doubt, but they would ultimately come
out on the other side realizing that they were capable of a lot more. And they could bring that
back into society and improve the tribe as a whole. And you saw these, what's interesting is you see
these across cultures. This is, this wasn't that one tribe said, Hey, we're doing this thing. It's
pretty cool. You should try it too. And that tribe put the word out. Oh, these just pop up.
This arose independently throughout, throughout culture.
They just, it just arises. And it's also in mythology. So if you look at the work of Joseph
Campbell and the hero's journey, it's the hero exits the comfort of home. He or she goes into
a trying middle ground, they're faced with battles. They have to go inward and they have to physically
strive. And then they come back into society with the treasure or the talisman or whatever it is.
Well, what is the treasure of the talisman? It's not the actual physical object. It's the way that
person has changed and that change that they can bring back into society. And you're, you've seen
a falling away of traditional rites of passage like this, which is why when you were talking about
sending your daughter to that camp, I got so excited because I think kids really would benefit
adults too. But kids in particular really benefit from having times where they get pushed to their
edges and they have those moments where of doubt that they're not sure what they're capable of,
but then they cross it and realize, Oh, I've got more on board than I really ever imagined.
Because like you look at what people can accomplish when the conditions are a survive
condition. It's incredible what people can do. And it also makes evolutionary sense to undersell
yourself. Yeah. Keeps you safe. Keeps you safe. Yeah. You don't want to be the hold my beer guy.
Right. That person dies. So it's a practice that I do in my own life. And as I said, it's when I
first kind of heard about it, I go, yeah, sounds kind of fun. Also kind of like, yeah, quirky. And
then when you start to learn more, it goes, Oh, wow, this is actually a powerful thing. And when
you look at research on challenges in people's lives, the people who have the worst rates of
mental health are the people who have had a ton of challenges, like an overwhelming amount of
challenges and traumas. But on the opposite end of the spectrum are people who have no challenge in
their life and no traumas. They have equally poor rates of mental health. So it's kind of a U-shaped
curve where having enough challenge in your life that you learn that you're what you're capable of,
that you can persist through things that you've got this seems to be healthy for people.
So speaking of challenges, right, one of my favorite challenges now that we get to talk about,
even though it would never rise to the level of a Misogi, but as a daily practice is rucking. So
why is it that people like you and I have taken to this thing? And maybe we could start by just
kind of defining what is rucking. Rucking is carrying weight for the sake of weight in a backpack.
So the word grew out of military circles. So in the military, rucking is just a standard fitness
practice. It is the main fitness tool that the US military and militaries all around the world going
back hundreds and hundreds of years you use to build fitness for soldiers. It is just carrying
weight on your back in a backpack. And it's interesting because this is again kind of a
feature that is unique to our species. Yes. I started thinking about this when I was hunting,
because once you kill the animal and you have the meat, you have to pack it out. So if you look at
why the human body is built the way it is and what we're physically good at, we're good at two things.
The first is running long distances in the heat. So if you've read Born to Run or that was spawned
from a 2004 paper in nature by Dan Lieberman. And we have all these adaptations that make us
good at running long distances slowly in the heat. And we would use that to hunt on hot days.
It's not even running. I mean, like over 24 hours, we could walk further in a day than an animal could
go at whatever pace it chose. Yes. Yeah, absolutely. We don't have to be running. We can just simply be
walking three miles in an hour. Yeah. We'll walk 75 miles in a day. We're unbelievable at covering
ground. And animals on a hot day, four legged animals, they're not efficient at cooling
themselves. We are. That's one of our adaptations. So we sweat our noses are really complex nasal
cavities, a cool air, all these different things. And so we would chase animals down until they
essentially toppled over from heat exhaustion and we would spear them. And then this leads to
the second thing that we're good at, which is we would then have to carry that animal back to camp.
And we also have adaptations that make us really good at carrying. And we are in fact, the only
animal that can carry. Yeah, I was really surprised to learn how lousy primates are at carrying.
They're terrible, very terrible. So we will still be more efficient. I think we can hold up to 33% of
our body weight and still be more efficient at covering ground than most other primates.
With no weight. With no weight. Yeah. Just on their own. They have this sort of tipsy,
weird gate. There's a technical term for it. I forget it, but it's not efficient at all.
And arguably, yeah, which I completely like, I, I weigh 180. I could easily carry a 60 pound
kettlebell in one hand. It's easier if I could make it a 30 and a 30, but even a 60 in one hand,
it's like nothing. Yeah, most people can. Yeah. Yeah. And to think that that's more efficient
than a primate is with nothing. With nothing. Yeah. Yeah. And it definitely shaped us. And
the experience of carrying out meat is really what made, had me starting to think that because
I had been familiar with the Lieberman work and all that. And it was in my mind and thinking about
how, you know, it's linked this, this running's link to hunting and, but then you carry and you're
like, Oh, they would have had to do this too. Like we also seem to be the only species that can really
do this well. And, you know, arguably we carried a lot more as early humans than we would have run
because running is mostly reserved for hunts. Whereas you look at what is gathering. So you
go pick up some stuff and carry it around as you get more stuff and then you carry it back to camp.
And so I actually went to Harvard to meet with Lieberman and that was a really fun meeting.
He's a fascinating guy. I enjoyed talking to him. But so I argue in the book that when you look at
running is obviously popular jogging is a thing, right? Or is it yogging? I can't remember.
Jogging.
But carrying is not as a form of fitness and activity. And I ultimately ended up traveling to
go Ruck HQ. And this is a, the tribe, I argue that has really adopted
carrying is the military through rucking. That's like the only group who's really putting this at
scale. And go Ruck is a company that makes backpacks that are specific for rocking and their
founder, whose name is Jason McCarthy. He is, he sort of leaned into rucking as a, as a form
of fitness. As I started to really look at the research on it, it's really great for us because
you're working your cardiovascular system, but you're also working your strength system to a
degree. So you're not going to get that with, you know, running or cycling something that is a pure
endurance act. Whereas with rucking, you're getting the endurance, but also you've got
load on your body. And so that is stimulating your muscles to a greater degree. And there's some
really fascinating studies on backcountry hunters who will carry in loads, you know,
into deep into the mountains and they'll test their body fat before and after. And those hunters
across, I think it was a 10 day study, a small study. There's, you know, there's only so many
weirdos like that. They lost 14% of their body fat and they actually stayed with same amount of
muscle. Some actually gained like an ounce or two of muscle. So it's really good at melting fat
and preserving muscle. And the other thing I think that's for me, something I really enjoy about it
is, you know, most of my cardio is done on a bike. But as you said, there's no load on a bike.
And I used to run a lot growing up. That was sort of my thing. And I'm really, I feel pretty
fortunate that despite 60 mile weeks growing up, I still have perfectly fine knees and hips. But I
also realize as much as I would love to go back to running, I don't want to poke the bear. I just,
I dodged a bullet in life being able to run so much without hurting myself. But as I'm older,
I don't, I just don't think that's the case. And I think when you look at, I think it's about eight
times your body weight is the force experienced by your knees with every step when you run.
Obviously weight matters and the lighter you are, the better. And it's not a surprise that the best
runners are, you know, feather light for obvious reasons. But with walking, it's only about three
times your weight. So when you're rocking, you're walking, not running. And yes, you're adding more
weight. So let's say you increase your body weight by a factor of 30 percent. The 30 percent increase
at a three X multiple of force is much less than your body weight at eight times the force. If
you're running, in other words, as hard as rucking is with all that extra weight, it's still much
easier on your knees than running. Yes. And you're still getting, I mean, yesterday was the first day
I had rucked in two weeks. We just got back from vacation and I'd been walking nonstop while we were
there, but it wasn't the same. Holy cow. Like much harder. Even just taking two weeks off. It's really
like a type of workout. My heart rate hit like 165. I was in the 150s and 160s, which is totally
uncommon for me when rucking. I'm normally in the 130s, 140s, but I guess because I was sort of
deconditioned for not because all my walking in Europe was, you know, without load. Yeah. So it
really made a difference. It really showed me just how demanding it is. It is. And
the injury data is really interesting to your point. When you look at studies on
people in the military, what tends to injure soldiers is running that has, I mean, when
they'll even throw people into, they'll do studies where they look at injury rates across something
like a selection, which is, you know, a long process where these guys are being just hammered
and they're all getting injured by running. That's not to say that some people don't get injured by
rucking, but it's like very, very small numbers comparatively. And so for that reason, I think
it's a lot safer, but it sort of also gives you to your point, your ability to get a higher heart
rate than you would from walking and also preserve muscle. Yeah. The thing that I've got my daughter
really embracing is the hills because on the uphill, you're just obliterating your heart and
lungs, but also, and my daughter might be the only 13 year old to really be able to explain to
you the difference between eccentric and concentric strength because all the times we're walking
down hills, I'm explaining to her how this is working her eccentric strength and her quads.
And this is where you get your breaks from. But I mean, I love the walking downhill as well.
And, you know, really trying to be as deliberate about it as possible and really making sure
because in life, that's where people fail. Right. So when you get older, you know, never mind
running, it's like, can you walk downstairs without collapsing? Can you take a can you walk off a step
and not hurt yourself? Well, if the answer is I don't know how to decelerate, the answer is no,
you're hosed. Right. And there's no better way to learn to decelerate than with a big load on your
back walking downhill. Yes. That will teach you how to decelerate. And that's not something you
get easily in the gym. No, it's it's not something you get easily running. It's you just don't get
that skill any other way that I'm aware of. And if you do fall, you're going to be better off
if you've been rocking because it also is rather good at improving bone density. Really interesting
studies on women where it improves bone density better than weightlifting alone, better than,
you know, cardio alone. And that becomes so important as women age. You look at
women in sort of hunter gatherer societies that are always carrying things. I mean,
they stay strong and vital their entire lives and they just don't get hip fractures.
Yeah, I you stated in the book and we sort of loosely described it here, but I just think,
you know, if the if you if if if McDougall argues we're born to run, I would argue we're born to
carry. That is my argument. We are born to carry. If you look at what people what people in hunter
gatherer societies actually spend their time doing physically, no one runs like you even look at the
tar. Humara, they very rarely run and it's not for fun. It's for ceremonial purposes. You know,
but work life is caring. Yeah. And, you know, a reasonably well trained person, we can get most
of our patients to the point where they can carry their body weight. Now, again, you're not going to
start out there if you're not well trained, but like a reasonably fit person could for a minute,
carry their body weight in their hands. Yeah. Yes. You could carry it longer on your back. But
but even the fact that we have the grip strength, the limb strength to carry our body weight
is just fantastic. I mean, we one of the metrics we use with with female patients who obviously
have less upper body strength is seventy five percent of your body weight carried for a minute
is one of like our multiple. You know, we have many sort of strength metrics we put people through.
That's a great one. Then that's that's you know, think about that for a moment. That's like that's
pretty impressive, especially in light of what you said earlier. So so what are kind of some of the
so so by the way, you know, I didn't even know what rucking was when I was kind of doing it in
training for hunts. But I realized, you know, what I do now is so much better because then I was just
using a weight vest. All right. So you'll see later our backyard is really, really steep. And
so I would you know, in the weeks leading up to hunts, I would put on a 50 pound weight vest
and just go up and down, up and down, up and down, up and down the hill. But why is it that a rucksack
we would agree and argue is better than a weight vest? What is it? What is it offering over a weight
vest? It tends to pull your spine into a better position. So most people today since we work
in front of desks, we're slumped over all the time, we're naturally slumped. When you put weight on
your back, it sort of puts your spine in a safer position. And that can actually seems to relieve
and prevent back pain. So that is according to I spoke with Stu Miguel, who's the back expert up
in Canada. And he's a huge fan of rucking. He's a very careful person when it comes to exercise.
In my experience with him, I mean, he's very nuanced. And he's a person I trust because of that.
And he said, you know, rucking is a great way to add some durability to people in a way that's safe.
The other thing I think about rucking, and I also own, you know, several rucksacks from Go Ruck now as
well. The belt really makes a difference when you get that belt on your hips, because, you know,
I had shoulder surgery four months ago. And one of the things I was super stressed about was not
being able to ruck because, you know, I've got my shoulder operated on. And amazingly, I was
probably rucking three weeks after surgery, and I couldn't do much else. Let's be clear.
But how was I able to do that? Well, first of all, you know, you've got really well placed straps
on your shoulders that are not, you know, it's not putting my joint at risk. And more importantly,
the majority of the weight, because you control where the load is by how you adjust it. But I
basically just said, I'm going to put all the load on my hips and I'll cook my legs a bit more, but
I will spare my shoulder. Yeah. So that's kind of to me, the other thing about the rucksack that
really, really beats the weight vest is that you have the distribution to load posteriorly,
but you also can really distribute the load on your hips, which anyone who's hunted or done any
backcountry stuff knows, like a really, it's so important to have your pack fit well on your hips.
Otherwise you could simply couldn't carry 100 pounds on your shoulders for very long. Yeah.
When I was in the Arctic and we were packing out caribou, we were heavy. I mean, over a hundred
pounds, you know, maybe 110, who knows 20. It was nice to have the hip belt because I would sort of
spend most of my time with the weight on the hips, but eventually that just starts to burn and you
need to wash that out. So you pop it your shoulders for a while and you can just kind of go back and
forth. I love that back and forth on, off, on, off. Yeah. Yeah. Just trying to find something that
isn't absolutely awful for a moment. It's good burn though. It's funny when my wife started rucking
with me and my wife is like, I think she's a super tough chick. She has, I think she's a very
high pain tolerance. The first time she ever did a dead hang, she went three minutes and eight
seconds. Oh, wow. Which is like insane. Yeah. And she's gone longer since, but the first couple
times she did it, she was like, does this ever stop hurting? And I was like, no, I wouldn't say
it ever really stops hurting. I mean, you can lighten the load, but you know, I was like, no,
it's, it's, it's, it's uncomfortable. Like I'm not going to lie to you. This is not something that
ever, if you're doing it the way we're doing it, which is, you know, we're, we're about a third of
our body weight and we're walking as quickly as we can while walking. No, this is just uncomfortable.
There's no two ways about it. It will be uncomfortable. And, but the upside is, is that,
you know, I'll even take rucking meetings where I'll toss in 20 pounds or something and I'll just
walk around while on this. I know I'm going to have to be on this phone call. I could sit in my
desk and office in the dark, or I could go outside and have a light load and get it all
taken care of there and sneak in a bunch of steps with some weight on my back. I mean,
it's very easy to flow into life. And it's like, if you were, if you know, you're already going to
be walking the dogs, we'll just toss on a pack. And all of a sudden that becomes a lot more
effective. I've got so many friends, uh, uh, and I don't get any kickbacks. I don't know,
I don't know anybody at go ruck. So I, but I, I've sent so many people there. Um, I think we will,
at some point, hopefully do a subscriber discount with, with them because I, you know, I just would
love to get more and more people doing this. Yeah. They, I've tried a handful of packs for
rucking specifically, and they definitely are my favorite sweater in the book and they've thought
about it deeply. Yeah. They've got some great content as well. Some great videos and stuff we'll
link to. So, I mean, look, I think this has been such an interesting journey. I, um, as, as I said
too many times before, I think this is just on some level, it's such an obvious thing, right? Like
it's one of those books where you read it and you're like, yeah, of course. But if, if you're,
if it's not pointed out to you, it's really easy to miss how this has happened. Comfort has become
so ubiquitous that I don't think we're aware of it anymore. It's kind of like the David Foster
Wallace, this is water thing that the ubiquity of the water of course creates the irony of the
fish not knowing what water is. And I kind of feel like that's what comfort has become for at least
those of us in the developed world. Yeah, I think so. And I, I also think that sometimes
even if you're pressing against it in one way, there's probably a lot of other ways that you're
not pressing it against it. I have friends that can run 25 miles now if you, if I asked them to,
but if I said, Hey, why don't you sit in silence for 10 minutes? It's like, what? I couldn't handle
that. So there's all these things that we've removed from our lives over time that I think
have a benefit and it is figuring out, well, what are those things, which is why I'm trying to
present in the book. And then how do I intelligently leave them in my life? Because we talked about
earlier, I'm not trying to suggest in any way that we go back to living as hunter gatherers,
like no way. Life today is amazing, but it's how can we use some of those things from the past to
build a better future? Yep, I agree. And it's part of its hunger. You know, I used to do a lot of
fasting. I don't fast as much anymore. But one of the things I loved about fasting was how much I
learned what I could do when I was hungry. You know, I would do sort of seven up to 10 day water
only fasts. Wow. But I'd keep working out hard throughout. And the first couple of times it almost
killed me. I mean, the first, I remember the first time I tried to put myself through serious workouts
during a seven day fast. I mean, I thought I was going to die. Wow. And it's not to suggest that
during those fasts, I was as strong or, you know, my performance was what it was normally. It wasn't,
it never was. But, you know, I just kept, I just couldn't imagine and other things like I remember
going to bed so hungry sometimes thinking I'll never be able to sleep. But yet I did. And you
realize like, of course you did this. There's no way our species would be here if we couldn't figure
out how to do these things when we're hungry, you know, be it sleep or go out and hunt or do
something like that. So, yeah, when you think of all of these forms of discomfort, it can be hunger,
it can be boredom, it can be a physical challenge. Time in nature. Yeah. It's, to me, that's the
take home is we have we have this incredible privilege and it just comes with a little
responsibility, which is just make sure on a daily basis you are inserting brief windows of
discomfort so that you're never too far from realizing that you're in the water. Yeah.
You said it. In other words, if you're the fish, just make sure you jump out of the water a few
times a day so that you never lose sight of the water you're in. Amen. Yes, sir. Well, you know
what we get to do now? Are we going to go rock? We sure are. Yes. Michael, thanks very much for
coming. I've enjoyed talking about this a lot and I hope everybody picks up the book because
it's fantastic. Yeah. Thanks a lot, Peter. I really enjoyed the conversation and now we get a rock
and suffer a little bit. And for dinner, elk and access to your awesome. Perfect day.