Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Well, Arthur, this is a first in that we're doing a repeat podcast. Although unfortunately,
this time we're not in person. The last time we did a wonderful podcast, we were in person and
I enjoy that even more. You want to tell everybody what happened?
Yeah, for sure. Hi, Peter. Nice to see you again. And I wish I were down in Austin where all the
cool kids live with you too. Showing up at your podcast studio last time, we had a great conversation
for a couple of hours and then learned afterward that we hadn't turned the sound on, which it
turns out you need for podcasting. People can just stare at two bald guys for two hours looking like
they're talking, but that turns out to be not the most interesting programming. So we had a great
we had a great time together and now we're doing the parts here.
Yeah. And then we did have a great video from that first podcast. And we actually were able to get
some people who could sort of sign it. And we even contemplated releasing it with subtitles.
But in the end we decided, eh, what the heck, let's just do it again, even though it won't look as
good because we'll be on video. The good news, I think for the listener is though I have a pretty
good memory. I have an awful memory for podcasts. So, um, when I record a podcast, if you asked me
two months later, what did we talk about? If I remember two things, that's a lot. So it's almost
like we're doing this from the beginning, at least for me, because I don't really remember what we
talked about. And I hope that that allows us to reproduce the, uh, what I recall Gestalt wise or
valence wise was a pretty positive discussion and a really enjoyable one. Yeah, me too. I agree. And
I don't remember exactly what we talked about, except it had to do with happiness and longevity
and living a prosperous, flourishing life. I see it by the way, also that when we were together
last year, turn me onto Gia, which is, and you're drinking it right there. And I've been drinking
ever since too, by the way, I've been on a constant diet of it. It's the best. It's really nice to be
able to talk about things where the company has no idea you're promoting it because, you know,
I'm paying full retail for this stuff, which is, uh, enjoyable. And yeah, I make no money off it,
have no affiliation with it, but, but do love it. And I always love when I can get somebody
turned on to Gia. Oh, it's so great. No, I completely agree. So I think for folks who
might not be familiar with you at all, um, to understand the arc of what we want to talk about,
which, um, I think there are a lot of sort of things to talk about, but the biggest arc is sort
of accepting the transitions that are inevitable in life. I mean, if I were to sort of put my finger
on one thing that resonates the most, and by the way, I went back and reread your book, uh,
because I, you know, I'd read it months ago when we did the thing. And I was like, you know, the best
thing for me to do to prepare, just to be reread it. That was really the part that stood out to me,
especially when we get to the, uh, sort of four stages of life that you talk about, as I think
about personally transitioning from the second to the third. But, um, you've lived many lives. And I,
I think for people to understand kind of that first life, which happens to be a life that has
a short half life, had you stuck with it indefinitely. So talk a little bit about
the background, uh, as a, uh, as a musician. Yeah. I mean, I'm, as a social scientist,
you don't usually dig into the background of a guy who teaches behavioral social science and,
and find classical music, but that's actually where I started. And that's where I intended to finish.
I intended to be a one act guy and to be, I wanted to be the greatest French horn player in the world,
which is a pretty weird ambition for most of the people listening, I would imagine. Um, but that
was also my parents ambition for me. For some reason, I started on violin at four piano at five
and I took up the French horn when I was eight and I was really good at it or I had a natural ability
in it at least. And so I did it a lot. I did it to the exclusion of nearly everything else. As a
matter of fact, and, and when it came time to go to college, I had one successful run at a year in
college and then went pro because that's really what I wanted to do. So at 19 I dropped out or,
you know, dropped out, kicked out, splitting hairs out of college. And, and, and I went on the road
as a classical musician. I played chamber music for six years, um, all over the United States,
all over the world. And then, uh, then I, then I went to Barcelona where I was in the symphony
orchestra. And then my plan was to become a French horn soloist, um, you know, playing these great
concerti of the greatest composers. And it just didn't work out that way. And so by my late twenties,
actually by my, my, my mid twenties, I was in decline as a, as a performer. My, my technique
was getting worse. It's, it's not entirely clear why that was happening at this point,
but I had to make a plan to exit to do the next thing. And so by my late twenties, I was in college
by correspondence, which I finished a month before my 30th birthday. Then did my master's degree at
night, finished up my horn career at 31, started my PhD. And that was the new, the new phase,
the next phase, which was becoming a social scientist. So, so before we kind of exit that
first phase, I want, I want to sort of dig into that a little bit because again, as you said,
it's very foreign. I certainly can't really appreciate what you're speaking about. And I
suspect a lot of people listening can't either. Um, what is the arc of a French horn player and
how many exceptional, uh, French horn player talents can be consumed by the world? So for
example, we were talking about baseball, you know, you know, there are hundreds of people who can be
good enough to make a living. Uh, what is it with French horn players? Well, classical music is
musicians in general, there's about a 95% unemployment or underemployment rate in the
classical music industry. It's an absolute superstar industry. Now that's not like professional sports
insofar as the people are not getting rich. I mean, the great soloists, the great opera singers,
the great conductors are pretty wealthy, but orchestra musicians are earning a kind of a
middle-class upper middle-class income, but they're not really very money motivated. So they're,
they, they want to do this to almost the exclusion of anything else. And so what you find is that
there are a few, let's say, uh, probably about a hundred really great orchestras in the world,
each one of which has a principal French horn player and then four other French horn positions
in those orchestras. And then a few other people, a handful of other people are making a serious
living in playing chamber music. And they're usually about one or two French horn soloists
in the world at any given time. So they're not that many people making a living at it.
And there are a lot of people who are trying. So it's weird, you know, most people are listening
to us, they're like French horn player, what an exotic thing to want to do. And yet there are
plenty of people who are trying to do that. We're really motivated by the idea of making that kind
of music and are good at it and are taking every audition that they can. And what kind of commitment
was necessary to get to that level? How many hours a day were you practicing as a teenager,
for example? I was all in, I was practicing five, six hours a day, plus playing in every ensemble I
could possibly find. I was basically doing it to the exclusion of almost everything else in my life.
It was like being a gymnast. It was like being an athlete where you practice as much as you can
without doing damage to the musculature. So there's not just diminishing returns for athletes,
there's negative returns if you over train. And that's the same thing that happens in classical
music. You can get all kinds of repetitive stress injuries, et cetera, et cetera, if you do that.
But then the time that you're not actually actively practicing, you're listening to music,
you're learning the repertoire, you're thinking about what your craft actually is. So the result
of it is that it's almost every hour of the day is what you're doing. You're thinking about your
future, you're thinking about what you want to do, you're trying to get better in your mind as much
as in your lips and in your fingers to the craft. So it's very much like a sports career, just that
it's more fine motor skills as opposed to gross motor skills. What distinguishes the best French
horn player in the world from the hundredth best? Which I'm guessing I wouldn't be able to
distinguish them, but for the discerning ear, what is it that separates those two people?
It largely has to do with accuracy. So the French horn has a problem of physics,
insofar as that the mouthpiece is smaller than a trumpet mouthpiece, but it has a very long,
the tube is as long as the tuba, which is the largest brass instrument. So by physics,
it should actually play in the low register, but by mouthpiece, it should actually play in the high
register. And the result of that is for anybody who knows that any of the physics of these,
of the harmonic structure of these instruments, that harmonics are very close together, meaning
it's very easy to miss notes. That's the reason for a guy who will like classical music, and they go
to the orchestra, the principal French horn, notwithstanding the fact that she or he is one
of the best in the world is missing a lot of notes. It's just really, really hard to be accurate.
The greatest, greatest, greatest, greatest, they have some uncanny ability. It's sort of like
Nolan Ryan, who was able to hit a postage stamp at 98 miles an hour, the fastball when he's 40.
That's the kind of difference that you get the freakish microscopic differences. Now, yeah,
you probably wouldn't notice the difference if you're not a big classical music buzz,
and especially if you're not really into the French horn. But if I went to an orchestra
now and I heard the best French horn player in the world versus the hundredth, I would notice
the difference in a big hurry. You mentioned in your mid twenties, that if I sort of remember
what you said correctly, you felt you were in decline, or at least you'd peaked and you were
now on the way down. Two thoughts on that are two questions. The first is, is that the typical age
at which a French horn player peaks? And secondly, what is it you noticed that was changing?
Yeah, so the answer is I was peaking and declining early. The average age, now I've done this
research subsequently as a social scientist, not as a French horn player. I kind of knew casually
that brass players, the classical musicians in general, they tend to peak in terms of
their physical qualities, their ability to dominate the instrument in their late thirties.
And you start to see a little bit of drop off in their forties and fifties. The greatest players
in the world, the greatest piano soloists will still be touring and playing beautifully in the
seventies, but they're not what they once were. I mean, you find that, I mean, even in rock and roll,
you find that the great guitar players can shred at 40 very differently than they can at,
now these days, the great rock and rollers are all like a hundred at this point. The rolling
stones are still on tour, but you heard Mick Jagger saying recently, and it's, yeah, it's
he's reminding you of what he was doing 57 years ago when I can't get no satisfaction was released
and was number one of his charts. So it's usually late thirties, early forties where the peak happens,
then it's a slow decline. I was declining much earlier than that. And it's almost certainly
having to do with a microscopic terror in, in one of the lips, an injury. And that wasn't well
known at the time, but there actually are surgeries that brass players will get at this point to
repair that. And had I been 25 years younger, I certainly had a much longer career in music and
much to my own detriment because I wound up going on to something that's touching a lot more people,
I think, in which I actually have more possibility of doing something positive in the world. So
within every, what seems like a tragedy at the time is, is there's all kinds of opportunity.
Now, I've heard you say in the past that when you started going back to night school for college and
ultimately for your bachelor's and master's degree, you were a little bit ashamed. You're
kind of doing this in secret, right? Why is that? Classical musicians think nothing else matters.
It's one of these, it's a cult, basically. It's not, it's not a profession. It's more like a cult.
So it's like a lot of, my son would, my oldest son would have Princeton and my younger son is in
the Marines. Those are cults too, right? And so if you basically say to someone, your friends in the
Marines, you know, I'm getting out, but I think I'm gonna, I think I'm gonna, I'm gonna re-up,
but in the Navy, they'll laugh you out. I mean, that's just like, that's, you just wouldn't do
that. Well, that's what it's like in classical music that I remember one time I was hanging
around with this group of brass players and I was probably 28 years old or something. And it was,
I knew the writing was on the wall and I wasn't telling anybody. I was actually studying at night
serendipitously. And this woman who hangs out with us, she's also a French horn player. She,
you know, says, I got an announcement. We're like, hey, what, what happened? You went and auditioned,
man? She says, nah, I decided I'm going to leave the business. I just got a full scholarship at the
University of Miami. I'm going to become a, to the medical school. I'm going to become a surgeon.
And, and then, and, and she leaves, you know, after a little while, we're all sitting around going,
see, she didn't have it. It's like, she's going to become a surgeon. I mean, this is,
that's a big deal, but it wasn't to us. It was just like, obviously she didn't have it. So she
had to quit her crummy, low paying French horn playing career to settle for becoming a, you know,
a lifesaving doctor like you, Peter. So what did you study for your bachelor's? Economics. And I
didn't intend to do that. I actually intended to get my, you know, my bachelor's degree in some,
you know, some area of the humanities or maybe even composition. I was a pretty avid composer.
And I thought that that's what I would do, but I took an economics class and it just opened my
eyes. I mean, just the, I statistically based social sciences, it felt like I had a magic wand
or some actually more like a, you know, crystal ball. That's a better metaphor. I mean, I could
see things about the world. And furthermore, I could actually analyze behavior in ways that I
never, I didn't even think was possible. I felt like I was, you know, those whole world of
information to be able to generate information was being open to me. I was just, my mind was
blown. I was completely hooked and I wanted to become, becoming an economist, you know,
talk about the sublime to the dismal. And then did you go straight from bachelor's to master's?
At what point did you formally hang up your French horn and say, I'm going to pursue the PhD. Where
did, where did that occur in the timeline? So I finished my bachelor's degree completely
by correspondence. And in those days I was faxing in my assignments and buying course materials,
you know, over the phone from the, from the bookstores of these universities that offered
these correspondence school courses. And I was banking the credits at this state college in New
Jersey at the time that I never visited. I never saw the place until I went there. They gave me an
honorary doctorate 20 years later and I went and gave the graduation speech. I mean, what's the
graduation for correspondence school? Is it like 10 guys around a conference table? It turns out
there was 3000 people in the Trenton ice rink. It was, it was fun. I was wild. I mean, it was
mostly first-generation college graduates, a lot of active military men. I was very proud that day
to be among that group, you know, of, of really sort of American life entrepreneurs. It made me
very proud. And then I went on to the state, the local state university, and at night did my master's
degree, a one-year master's degree. And at that point, I mean, it was Fisher cut bait. And so I,
I left music at that point after that, and, and, and went away residentially and more traditionally
started my PhD and over the next four years finished my PhD. And what was the focus of your
PhD? My PhD was in quantitative policy analysis. So I was doing mathematical modeling and applied
microeconomics for public policy. I was working at the same time as a military operations research
analyst for the Rand corporation. I was doing theater level combat modeling for the air force.
So I was doing, you know, large scale, early artificial intelligence algorithms to link
computers up together to simulate battle situations across a lot of scenarios. So I was
learning a lot of math modeling. And that was a real weakness for me was my mathematics and
statistics. So working in that area was critically important for me to beef that up and, and, and
become a well-rounded scholar in the area where I had previously had weakness. And what did you do
right after that? You went, you became a professor, if I'm not mistaken, before you went to AI, right?
No, no, I was, I was 10 years as a professor then. So I graduated when I was 34 for my PhD. And I
went to Georgia state university in Atlanta for three years. And then I went to, I was able to
secure a position at Syracuse, which for public policy is the best school in the country. That was,
that was a really great opportunity. I will always be grateful to that place for giving me that
opportunity. And I moved to Syracuse and we spent the next seven years at Syracuse. And I, you know,
I did what academics do, you know, I was writing academic journal articles, refereed 14 readers,
highly technical writing papers that were mathematically so complex that now at age 58,
I can't read them. I actually don't know what I was talking about at 35, which speaks to a lot
of what I do now, which is the changing structure of the prefrontal cortex and our ability to learn
and perform at different phases of life. What are we good at then? And what are we good at now?
So I want to come back to that. Cause of course that's really the important hook here, but I just
want to go to this next chapter. Cause I want to understand when you understood this shift in
intelligence. So from Syracuse, you then went to AEI. You were the CEO for about a decade,
if I'm not mistaken, almost 11 years. Yeah. Before leaving to join the faculty at Harvard,
where you are today. At what point during this journey, did you begin to understand
what it is that you've now written about in strength to strength? So when I was, I went to
AEI and for those who don't know the American enterprise Institute is a think tank in Washington,
DC. It's a think tank is like a university without students. It's completely dedicated to
high quality academic research, but in, in, in the service of better public policy. So it's in the
middle of Washington, DC. It's one of the oldest think tanks in the world. It started in 1938 during
the great recession, the great depression to poll the United States and the world. They thought
out of the great depression using the tools of the American free enterprise system, but they had
to bring together the greatest economists and later foreign policy experts in health and education
experts. So I had 300 employees. I had to raise about $50 million a year in philanthropy. You
know, my job was like running for the Senate and never getting elected. And I did that, you know,
for 10 years, it was, it was, you know, it was actually kind of a slog. I mean, there's an 80
hour a week CEO job. And I noticed about halfway through that my skills were kind of changing. I
was getting worse at certain things and I was getting better at other things. I didn't actually
understand why that was. I found that I was, I was getting worse at thinking up brand spanking,
new, clever ideas. And I was getting much better at explaining things. I was becoming effectively
a better teacher, a better instructor, but I was worse as a classic innovator. When I had first
come to AEI, I was developing new programs. I was coming up with these new big policy and
research ideas. And about halfway through, I was noticing that what I was really good at was
synthesizing everybody else's ideas and putting them together into a relatively compelling argument
about how we should do things, which was interesting to me. But it also occurred to me that it was
probably more to it than that. And I got to work on what, where this was going to lead in my own
life such that I could exploit my own strengths optimally. And I started looking at the research
on different forms of intelligence as people get older. What it led me to conclude based on the
work of a lot of social psychologists that were doing intelligence work in the 1960s and 70s,
actually, it was older work out of the UK, primarily the work of Raymond Cattell, is that early on we
have a fluid intelligence, which is largely our innovative capacity based on working memory,
where we can do a lot of things alone and come up with brand new ideas based on kind of limited
background. Later on, we're less good at that, but we're much better at synthesizing ideas. We have
a vast library, much less working memory, but a much better vocabulary, pattern recognition,
and ability to synthesize ideas of other people, which is called crystallized intelligence.
Now, what we find is that fluid intelligence tends to peak in the late 30s, which is, by the way,
why a lot of classical musicians are picking in their late 30s is because fluid intelligence is
not just about writing mathematical formulas. It's about doing a lot of things that make you great
with your 10,000 hours of practice and your mastery, et cetera, et cetera. And then it
declines in your 40s and 50s, but your crystallized intelligence, your teaching capacity,
your explaining capacity, your pattern recognition, your management of other people, that those things
get better through your 40s and 50s and 60s and stay high in your 70s and 80s. When I saw that,
I thought, hmm, what am I going to do? What's my plan so that I can exploit that for the rest
of my career? And that's actually what led me to quit my CEO job and to do what I do now,
which is writing and speaking and teaching, really using my creative capacities to mix
ideas together about happiness, which is my main area of focus and research.
Now, these terms, fluid and crystallized intelligence, the first time I ever encountered them,
I think is about four years ago in an Atlantic piece that you wrote. I think it was in the
Atlantic. Obviously, this was a precursor to the book. Does that sound about right?
That's exactly right. That was in July of 2019. And that was when I first wrote that piece,
I was doing this research for myself. It was me search, Peter, which is what we all do. I mean,
it's like, you know, people think, ah, Peter Attia, the great longevity doctor. Well, Peter
Attia wants to live a long time with good lifespan and health span and happiness span.
And so that's why he's doing this work. And that's exactly why I was doing that work as well.
And it was so I found that it was so useful to audiences that I wrote it up for the Atlantic.
And if you know this, how to go from strength to strength in your life, that article was one of the
50 most read articles of the entire year of all publications in the world. And I thought,
it turns out I'm not the only one who's thinking about this. And so I wrote it up in a book over
the next couple of years and published it in February of 2022.
Now, what I don't recall, though, I'm sure you explained it in the article, are those
terms, fluid and crystallized terms you came up with or are those in the literature and you're
simply bringing them to our attention? Those are in the literature that that was they were coined
by Raymond Cattell, the social psychologist I talked about later. And his findings were
replicated. And and of course, the social psychology then expanded into the neuroscience
literature. This is the way that the world is going. I mean, social psychology was kind of
the whole show through the 50s and 60s and 70s. And since about the 90s and especially this
century, neuroscience is really getting into the game. So the neuroscientists have started to
replicate these these two curves and finding the strength and some of the neurophysiological
reasons for these strengths that are occurring as well. In the in your book, you open, I think you
open with this story about being on an airplane sitting in front of an older gentleman who's
well, I'll let you tell the story because I want to I want to hear the story. And I'm also curious
where that experience occurred in your personal evolution of this. Yeah, I was thinking halfway
through my time as a CEO, you know, where kind of where does it go? I mean, it's it's crazy. I mean,
you run a company, I mean, you know what it means to actually run a business. But sometimes you
think, you know, I'm going to turn my I'm going to do my homework and turn it in and things are
going to get better. And then it's going to stop. Well, when and under what circumstances and what
does that mean? What is the end goal? What is my intention with all that is very funny. It's
mean, that's a I remember feeling a kind of an existential crisis about that. And I was thinking
about it a lot. And around that time, I was doing what I always did, which was sit on a plane and
with my laptop. And I was coming back on a long cross country flight from LA to to DC is this
flight that leaves LA at five o'clock in the afternoon, gets in about one o'clock in the
morning into the into Dulles. And I took it a lot. And and one night I was listening to this guy
telling his wife that he might as well be dead. And his wife was consoling, he was very
disconsolute. I couldn't quite make out his words, but her words were very penetrating. So I was just
hearing the answers. Oh, don't say it would be better if you were dead. And then it's not true.
Nobody remembers you or cares about you or loves you anymore. It's just it was just awful. And,
I thought, you know, this guy is, you know, somebody who's not Peter Attia. I mean, this is
somebody who, you know, he hasn't lived up to his own personal standards. He hasn't had the
opportunities. He hasn't pursued the education and started the business. And and now it's kind
of near the end. I could tell by their voices that they were in. They were elderly. And at the end
of the flight, I was kind of curious just to give a little look. And the lights went on. I
stood up and I turned around. It was one of the most famous men in the world. This is somebody who
is not controversial. He's not some, you know, actor or politician. This is somebody who's
justifiably considered a hero by many millions of people for his his, you know, his achievements,
his accomplishments in the in the 1970s, 1980s and and before that as well. And and and he evidently
is living a real life of regret because those times are long past. And I got this window onto
his soul. Now, when we were leaving the plane, the pilots like, you know, thanks for flying
United folks like that was doing. And he looks through me like a pane of glass. I mean, why
wouldn't he? He sees the guy behind me and he recognizes him and he says, sir, you've been my
hero since I was a little boy. And I turned around and he's beaming with pride and joy. And I thought
to myself, which is the real guy? And then I had a selfish thought, which is how can I be not that
first guy? How can I structure? Look, I'm trying to I'm not going to be the hero on the plane, Peter,
but I'm trying to do a lot with my life. You know, I'm trying to live to the max to create
to have a contribution to achieve a lot. And which has some pathologies attached to it as well. I
write about this in my research now about the success addiction and the workaholism that's
attendant to that. And then and the neuroscience behind those addictions as well. But what can I
do so that the rug is not pulled out from under me? And I'm telling my long suffering wife, Esther,
on a plane in 30 years that I might as well be dead. And and that's what really led to this
research project that led to the book. Let's define happiness. I don't think I understand
what it really is. And given that it's your business effectively, it's what you teach,
it's what you write about. It's the thing you think about as much as I think about, you know,
sort of the longevity component of biology. I'm sure you get asked this question all the time.
And I'm sure you've got a 30 second answer. And I'm sure you've got a three hour answer.
Take it in any direction you like. Yeah, I've got a semester long answer,
which is the class I teach at the Harvard Business School, which is what is it and how do you get it?
And the reason for that is that by the time my students reach me, my graduate students at Harvard
reach me, a lot of them are realizing that the world's promises are empty, that, you know,
the money, power, pleasure and fame that are supposed to bring you undying happiness are
false promises. They're a bill of goods. They couldn't be instrumental to getting what you
want, but they can't intrinsically give you the satisfaction you desire. So I start in the first
day of class and say, OK, guys, I mean, you you spent all your all your elective points getting
into the class because they have a competitive system to get these electives. And the class
fills in like nine seconds its happiness after all, who are the free candy kids. And there's
hundreds of people on the waiting list for this class. I say, OK, you you made a commitment to
getting this class. You must know what happiness is. As I go around, I cold call what's happiness?
They'll say, it's that feeling I get on Thanksgiving and, you know, yada, yada, yada, feelings, feelings
that are wrong. Happiness is not a feeling any more than your Thanksgiving dinner is the smell
of the turkey. The feeling of happiness is evidence of happiness. Now, we measure happiness
in all sorts of very complicated and very simple ways. And one of the things that we know is that
all of the people who are really happy, who have a lot of happy feelings, but also have a lot of
satisfaction content with their lives, they're basically they're they're getting abundance
and balance across three dimensions. And so this is the the definition of happiness. I'll think about
this like if I were to say, hey, Peter, what is the Thanksgiving dinner? You'd say, well, carbohydrates,
proteins and fat, you know, you'd say there's the three macronutrients of all food. And, you know,
we're always trying to get our macros in order. Right. And so and so you talk about forget lifespan,
let's talk about health span. And I say, let's take it even farther to happiness span. So let's
get our literal macronutrients in order for health span, let's get our happiness span in order with
the macronutrients of happiness. They are enjoyment, satisfaction and purpose. Those are the three
macronutrients of happiness. If you don't have those things in balance and abundance, you will
not report being a happy person. Now, this is different than unhappiness, which is another
entire subject, believe it or not. Happiness and unhappiness are not opposites. They're different
phenomena. So we're just talking about happiness here to be a truly happy person. You need to enjoy
your life. And that requires not pleasure. It's it's pleasure plus elevation is pleasure plus,
plus metacognition. And so, you know, Thanksgiving dinner fills your belly and tastes good. That's
pleasure. But the the experience that you have of consuming the Thanksgiving dinner with other
people and having a memory that you can last forever, that's enjoyment. And so it's a much
more elevated experience than pleasure. Satisfaction, which is super fleeting and troublesome. And,
you know, as Mick Jagger saying, I can't get no satisfaction. The truth is, you can't keep
no satisfaction. There's an entire research literature on that that I've participated in on
the problem with satisfaction, but it's the joy and reward for a job well done and a goal met,
you know, that elation from actually meeting a goal. And last but not least, is purpose,
is meaning in life. You know, I talk an awful lot about the coherence, the significance, the
direction, these are the the meaning of meaning. And it gets back to a lot of the great philosophy,
but we can also measure it. And I can even have a few diagnostic questions that I asked for the
clients who come to me and they'd lack purpose in their life. The questions I asked are why,
why were you born and for what are you willing to die? And if you can't answer one or both of those
questions, you're going to give a serious meaning problem. We got to dig in and actually solve that
particular problem. But that's it. I mean, these are the three macronutrients, the protein,
carbohydrates and fat of happiness or enjoyment, satisfaction and purpose.
There's so much I want to touch on there. I'll start with the latter. I have to be honest with
you and I've thought about this a lot. In terms of purpose, I literally can only think of one
thing. And I suspect a lot of people will think of this, which is kids. I think that's probably
the only thing I'm I would say I have a real purpose for that I would die for in a second and
think nothing of. Is it bad that I don't have a higher purpose than that? Well, it sort of
depends on what the higher purpose means. One of the things that you find is that the one of the
habits of the happiest people is and this is different than the micro maybe think of this
as the dishes and the happiness meals, as opposed to the mic, the macronutrients and happiness meal,
the happiest people, they all have a transcendental understanding of life, which is that it's just to
say that they have an understanding of life bigger than themselves. But the most miserable people,
the people who lack happiness and have a lot of unhappiness, they're focusing on me, me, me,
me, me, the philosophers talk about the I self and the me self and the I self is outward looking.
It's observational, it's sort of Zen. The me self is reflective of the outside world. It has a lot
to do with social comparison. It has a lot to do with the micro circumstances, you know, like
my job, my money, my career, my friends, my house, my mortgage, my commute, me, me, it's just so boring.
And a transcendental understanding of life is key to a happy life because you need peace.
You need perspective. You need to zoom out. When the Dalai Lama says, you're one in seven billion,
what he's saying is not that you're insignificant or you're the speck. What he's saying is that you
need to stop focusing on yourself so you can actually get some relief for once in a while.
So that might be the higher purpose, but it's just a transcendental purpose and understanding
of something bigger than yourself. So that's another thing. And I know you have that. I know
you think about things that are bigger than you. And part of that is your family and part of that's
your kids. But part of that is an understanding of the universe. Yeah, I guess it's interesting. I
mean, coming back to the kids thing, I think one of my greatest fears of aging is less about the
physical changes of aging and more about kids being out of the house. And again, I think a lot
of parents probably feel that way, which is it's so enjoyable to have young kids around, even though
it's hard, right? It's like a two-edged sword. But I can't imagine how quiet a house would be without
them. And I don't know, sometimes I think like I'm not really sure how enjoyable life would be
when they're gone. Because when they're gone, they're gone. You know, recently I posted something
on Instagram that I found really depressing, which was a chart of the fraction of time that people
spend with others in their life over the course of their life. So it's kind of like the x-axis is time
and the y-axis is percent spent with each entity and its various curves. And the one that just
depressed the hell out of me was time with your kids, which basically corresponds to once they
turn 18, it just plummets. Now you've got kids that are all, you have three kids, right? Yeah,
my three kids have grown up. My youngest is 19 and in Spain in college. So yeah, so I know all
about how the empty nest works. And there were times, I mean, like I've been in your house and
there's a lot of Legos on the ground. And it's, I mean, there's a lot of chaos that comes from
little kids. And I remember that and my wife and I, we said, you know, what's it going to be like
when actually, you know, they grow up and move out. And it is very different and it's very
disconcerting. And it's kind of new to us quite frankly. But the key is, and this is one of the
most important things for a happy life is, is a partnership with somebody who will be the last
person on whom you lay your eyes as you take your dying breath. That's really, really important. A
companion that love that is your wife. That's all that turns out to be much more indicative
of your happiness than actually getting the, you know, developing and having a relationship
with your kids because your kids are turning into different people every single year.
I mean, that's super fun and that's super interesting, but that's actually not the key.
The people who suffer the most from empty nest syndrome is not the empty nest. It's the fact
that they're only with one other bird and they don't really like that bird very much. That's the
real problem is when it comes in. And that's one of the things that I talk about with my students.
And by the way, I'm doing lots of executive teaching these days. And it's what I'm talking
about with people our age too, is the goal of your marriage is not passion, it's friendship.
This is the goal. You must be close friends, ideally best friends with your spouse such that
your kids, they grow up and they move away. And then you have your grandkids. I'm probably going
to have grandkids with them. My oldest son is Mary and you know, they're going to have kids
quick. I bet. I mean, I don't know. I mean, you can tell that I'm projecting and praying about
this, but, but you know, then I'll have grandkids and it'll be a different experience, but I'm going
to be with my wife Esther and until, you know, death do us part. So that has to be the juice of,
you know, who, who of the relationship or, or the love that actually makes true happiness and
love truly is the great secret of happiness. Yeah. I mean, that, that, that's the one saving
grace is, as I feel very fortunate that my, my wife and I are, we joke that we're the best
roommates in the world. Right. And so, um, there, I think we'll have a lot to enjoy in, in, in that
transition is the implication of that though, Arthur, that, cause I don't think it is, but how,
how do we reconcile then a person who chooses not to have a partner? Yeah. So the key is with,
there are some people who do really, really well on their own. They're, they, you know,
introverts who like to live alone, for example, and loneliness is not the same thing as solitude.
Isolation and solitude are very, very different phenomena, but they're, by the way, they're
neurocognitively different phenomena. They affect the brain in different ways. And, and, and so
isolation is always bad, but, but solitude is not, as a matter of fact, we all need it. We need it in
different levels. That's point one point two. And actually this is based on the Harvard study of
adults. And, and sorry, just to interrupt for a sec, Arthur, you can be lonely in a relationship.
Oh, for sure. And you can be in solitude and not be lonely. Absolutely. One of the greatest
predictors of divorce is, is partners who are lonely while living together. And this is the
big, and this gets back to the big danger of the empty nest syndrome is that the only thing you
have in common is your kids. And that one point of commonality disappears and you're sitting across
the table blinking at each other during dinner, not talking, because you literally don't have anything
to talk about. That's, that's really, that's metastatically awful for a relationship. And so
that's why it's critically important that couples have something in common besides their kids,
that they're practicing their religion together. They're practicing interest together. They're
reading the same things. They're on the same philosophical journey together. I mean, one of
the things that I talk about with, with couples is that they should develop philosophical interests
in common. They're talking about deep things. And, and, you know, so it, the, the gold standards
that your kids are like, ah, mom and dad are talking about Kierkegaard again, or whatever.
I mean, it's got to be something that's bigger than digit change is diaper, because, you know,
that, that's not going to be something you have in common forever. And you're going to be lonely
inside your relationship. The second big point, however, is that whereas most of the truly happy
people, as they get older, they do have a spousal partner where that's companion in terms of his love,
which also has some passion, but the companionate part is ascendant throughout, you know, the,
throughout your marriage, whereas the passion part is not as high as it used to be. And that's
completely okay. That's healthy, normal, and actually advisable because it's more sustainable
over the long run. But some people are very happy and don't have that. What do they have in common?
Very, very close, personal, lifelong friends. So here's the key. If you don't have a spouse,
you need real friends. These are people who know your secrets, who would take your 2am phone call
and that you talk to a lot. Now, that doesn't mean that if you're married, you don't need that.
Because, you know, when I talk to, especially men, men are horrible at real friendships. They're the
worst. You know, they got lots of deal friends, but no real friends a lot of the time, especially if
they're really successful in business. And so we'll say, okay, name two guys or whoever,
who are real friends beside your spouse. And they're like, yeah, so and so and so and so and so.
So what was the last time you talked to him? It's like, I don't know, four months ago,
not a close friend. That's just the case. And so you got to work on these things for sure,
for a lot of reasons, besides the fact that it's just healthy and good. You also might at some
point be left alone if you're if you're widowed. And you don't want to be alone in the world under
those circumstances. That's really corrosive. That's one of the reasons that men do so poorly
when they lose their wives to death. Because a lot of them don't have real friendships to backfill
any of this need in their souls. Why? Well, actually, before I ask you that the gender
differences there, can you give me a few other characteristics or features that differentiate
deal friends from real friends? Yeah, so this is actually an Aristotelian notion, believe it or
not. And we do a lot of this stuff in our, you know, mathematical social sciences as well. But
all the things that we do in behavioral social sciences now, all we're doing is we're just
exposing the ancients to empirical scrutiny. And, you know, we're just testing whether or not
Aristotle was right, which he always is. So Aristotle wrote a lot about friendships. And
he talked about these, these escalating levels of friendship in terms of the satisfaction they bring
and the virtue that they bring to our lives at the lowest level is the friendships of transaction.
So these are, you know, friendships where people work together, and they're really, you know,
you're a shirt manufacturer, and you've got a guy who sells you cloth. And your friends like, you
know, you probably really are. I mean, you like him, he likes you, you're really friendly with
each other, you take care not to offend each other. But if you stop making shirts, you're probably
not going to continue that relationship. Above that are relationships of admiration or beauty,
where you admire each other, you know, and that's a really good thing too. But that's dependent on
a particular quality. The perfect friendship or the friendship of virtue is just inherently
satisfying. You'll like being together, frequently, it'll revolve around a third kind of useless thing
like baseball, right? It'll be, it'll be that thing. This is what guys do. It's like, I don't
know, what do you guys do together? I don't know, we build birdhouses or whatever it happens to be.
And it's that third thing that is the kind of the focus. But what you're doing in parallel is
developing a very beautiful friendship of that's a very positive link. And that's what these real
friendships have in common. They're intrinsically satisfying, and they're frequently focused on the
cosmic therapy. It doesn't have to be useless, by the way. I mean, I have a very close friend,
one of my very closest friends is he's in Atlanta, and we have the same religion. And we talk about
that a lot. And our discussions about that are quite deep. And he also wants to know what's going
on with my marriage and my kids. And he knows my secrets is the bottom line.
You alluded to something that I think most people intuitively would appreciate. But I'm curious as
to why. What is it about men that makes it harder for us to have those really deep friendships?
Again, if I were to consider my parents, you know, I don't think my father has one
such friendship. I think my mother has many. I mean, really many. She's rich in friendship.
Maybe they're an extreme example. Why do you think that is?
Well, there's some generational differences between men and women, and there are probably
some intrinsic differences as well. The generational differences largely have to do with the fact that
in conventional family setups, I mean, I'm going to guess that your dad was super hardworking.
He probably was busting his pick all the way through your childhood. He put you through
college. He did all that stuff. And he knew that he was gone all day. And that if he went
out to goof around with his buddies after work, he was stealing from his family. And so he came
home. The truth was that his intimate relationships were in his family and his business
relationships were at work. And there was a firewall between the two such that he could afford
to spend adequate time where he had adequate time to spend with his family. And so it was a very
traditional situation. Meanwhile, your mom was making sure that you kids were, you know,
properly brought up and you had friends and she knew your friends' mothers. And the result was
that she was reinforcing friendship relationships and therefore getting better at them. Now, the
distressing thing is that friendship is a skill that requires practice. It's like a muscle. And
it will atrophy. You can get worse and worse at friendships. And so I'll meet these 60-year-old
guys. Guys who are a little older than me, and they'll be like, what do you want me to do? Call
up some other dude and ask for a play date? I mean, how does one do this? I don't know how to do this.
I haven't had a real friend since I was in college. And ever since then, then I got married and,
you know, had my family and I worked really, really hard and now I'm lonely. And so what do
you expect me to do? And the answer is you have to actually learn how to make and maintain friends,
real friendships. And that's a skill that a lot of men lose because of our traditional social
circumstances. So what do you say to that guy? So the 60-year-old guy comes to you and let's make
this a dramatic case. He and his wife have divorced or she's died. His kids are grown up.
And using the example you said, I mean, this is a guy who hasn't had an intimate friendship
with somebody in 40 years. And let's say he's bought into what you're saying, which is
a crucial part of his happiness for the remainder of his life is going to be
intimacy through friendships. And maybe some of those are not platonic, right? Maybe he meets
another woman, but let's focus on the platonic side of that. Yeah. So the truth is, it's not
an easy nut to crack, but you have to do the work like anything else. You can, we know that there's
enough plasticity in the brain and there's enough emotional plasticity as well that we can learn
all kinds of new skills. I mean, people can learn lots of skills. They can't be as good playing the
cello starting at 70 as if they started at seven. We know that to be a fact, but you can get plenty
good at stuff. And that includes social skills, but you have to be committed to doing the work.
What a lot of guys want is like, okay, I just thought great. That's a good advice, professor.
You know, I'm going to go out and get some help me get some friends. Like you, it's going to take
time. It took your wife years and years and years and years to build up her friend group.
It's going to take you some time as well, but you actually have to start putting into work.
That has to do with actually making yourself available and vulnerable to other people. That
means actually hanging out with other people and saying, and taking the time. A lot of guys will
be like, I don't want to go have dinner with some guy. Well, you got to go have dinner with some guy.
Furthermore, you actually have to ask that other guy questions about his kids and be interested in
that other person. That sounds so obvious, but these are skills that a lot of men have lost or
never really cultivated over the course of their lives. So you can go through these basic social
skills and they're sort of mystifying to a lot of guys. But once they do it, I've seen case after
case, because I've been coaching people on this now for a couple of years since this research has
started to get some prominence and I've seen amazing progress from people who are older than me.
Let's go back to the three components of happiness. The one that we didn't really touch on is
satisfaction. You've obviously alluded to the Rolling Stones tune, which speaks to how fleeting
it is. I wonder then why it's included, because whenever I think of satisfaction,
I echo that sentiment, right? Which is like, I'll have some goal. And I mean, I think of,
I can't think of a single goal I've had, including ones that took me years to achieve,
where the moment I achieved it, I mean, I don't think I'm being facetious to say within five
minutes. I'm thinking about the next one. And I mean, that's a very depressing thought. So
given the sort of fleeting nature of satisfaction, why is it even a component of happiness?
Well, you're not a typical case, Peter. And part of the reason is because you're doing an unusual
and unusually difficult success oriented thing. Not only are you working for your own success,
you're working for your client's success. And so you're an addict for your success,
you're an addict for other people's success. Now let's talk about a more typical profile.
Most people are not going through life thinking, I'm going to get this great big thing, and then
running for the next great big thing and next great big thing after that. Most people are not
thinking about their achievements in exactly the same way or the same scale as you. Most people
have sources of satisfaction, which is a reward for getting to the end of the day, a reward that
feels like a real reward to get through the week and to get to Saturday and to be able to relax.
And those are real sources of satisfaction. Now you can blow that up. You can bloat that
to the point where your version of Saturday is some huge business milestone. Your podcast now
has 200,000 weekly downloads. This is just so out of proportion to the ordinary experience.
Now that doesn't mean that the ordinary person can master satisfaction and get it in a reliable
way either. We all fall prey to the problem of I can't get none. Actually, I can't keep none. And
there's a reason for this. Now it is extremely joyful to be rewarded, to achieve a goal, even
a little goal. I mean, we're made. Our brains light up like Christmas trees. We all know,
I mean, you've talked on your show many times. I'm a regular listener to your show and I've heard
this many times and I've heard you on Huberman and all the other kind of parallel shows that people
listen to in this suite of how can we improve our lives podcasts and shows that we all have to
understand dopamine these days. And dopamine, of course, is a neural modulator, not a pleasure,
but of anticipation of reward. And what it does is it says you're going to get satisfaction if you
get this thing and you're going to get it forever. Dopa means a liar. Mother nature is a liar. She's
horrible. Mother nature basically says if you're getting that new car smell, it's going to last
forever. Right. And you always believe it, which is why we do what we social science call get on
the hedonic treadmill. Hedonic means feeling and the treadmill is obviously a metaphor. So we can
run and run and run and run, but it moves against us. We think we're going to get satisfaction and
we're going to keep it. And we actually don't. So we run for the next one. Now, fortunately,
ordinary people get a next Friday and a next Friday and the next Friday. But if you're doing
this and your main objective is, you know, the next big financial milestone, something out of
proportion to the ordinary human experience, then it becomes quite tyrannical. You know,
then it becomes something that you really can't keep up with. Now there's a reason that mother
nature does this. There's, you know, bringing coals to Newcastle by telling Peter Attia about
homeostasis. But every biological and even emotional process is subject to homeostasis in
which we go always back to our baseline. You know, if you're on the treadmill this morning for good
cardiovascular health and you want your pulse to be at 135 or 140, you don't want it to be there a
week from now because you die. Homeostasis 15 minutes or 30 minutes after you get off the treadmill
takes you back to your baseline pulse rate. That's for good and proper health. And the same
thing happens emotionally. If you get elation from a job well done, it's going to leave so that you
can be ready. It's going to go away very quickly. So you can be ready for the next set of circumstances.
That's why you can't keep no satisfaction is so that you won't be just staring at the delicious
berries on the bush with joy in the Pleistocene while the saber-toothed tiger is sneaking up
behind you and you're not aware of it. You need to be ready for the next circumstantial, you know,
whatever is going on in your life. And that's how homeostasis works. That's why it happens and that's
why you can't keep no satisfaction. That notwithstanding a life without those moments
of satisfaction is dull and it's gray. And that's one of the key parts of major
depressive disorders called anhedonia. You know, anhedonia means the inability to get this feeling
of satisfaction and the anticipation of the reward. So you need it, but the paradox is you
can't keep it. And so one of the things that I talk about is for people like you who have this
outsized understanding of what satisfaction is going to be, how you can how you can crack that
code, how you can dominate the matrix in a different way. And the answer is basically this,
you need to stop managing your haves and start managing your wants. In other words, your
satisfaction is what you have divided by what you want. And you need to manage the denominator of
your satisfaction fraction as opposed to the numerator. And serious, full on wants management
can be a game changer for a guy like you, for anybody for that matter. But it's a less serious
issue for a lot of people. But for a guy like you, you need a wants management strategy or you're
going to be running from thing to thing to thing. And as your haves go up, your wants will go up by
more and paradoxically your satisfaction will decline, which pulls down your overall happiness.
A lot to unpack there. So let's start with how much of the want deals with comparison versus
intrinsic needs to one up yourself. So I'll give you an example. A great source of satisfaction
in my life has historically come not anymore, but certainly historically has come through sort of
athletic achievements. So when I was a cyclist, it was certain milestones I wanted to be able to
hit when it was a marathon swimmer, it was certain swims I wanted to be able to do.
And I mean, believe it or not, there's less comparison to others in some of those things
depending on how you define your metrics. Like you might say, like, I want to be able to climb
Mount Palomar, which is a long climb 20 miles or something. I want to be able to climb it in a
certain amount of time or I want to be able to swim across this sliver of the ocean or things
like that. So those don't feel like they're heavily dependent on comparison to others,
but yet there are a number of other things where I think it's almost exclusively about you can't
ignore what's happening to others, right? You mentioned income or some other measure of
professional success. You know, we joked about the idea like you could literally be worth 100
million dollars, but if your peer group is worth a billion, you might actually find yourself feeling
poor, which is like a loser. Yeah, it makes no sense to those of us that are, you know,
miles beneath that. But so how do you sort of untangle those two types of objects of satisfaction,
one that is purely intrinsic, one that is pure comparator and yet both of whom could easily put
you on a hedonic treadmill? Is there a difference? Well, yeah, there is, but they're kind of in a
hierarchy of what will bring you enduring satisfaction. And the one you're talking
about where you're comparing Peter with Peter, Peter times zero with Peter time one, that's
still a tyranny. It's just not as bad a tyranny as comparing yourself with somebody else, you know,
counting your social media followers or your, you know, it's like, I don't care if I have 200,000
downloads, as long as I have more than Huberman, you know, that's a real tyranny.
That'll never happen. And to be clear, I wasn't suggesting that the former was less insidious than
the latter. I just wonder what the difference is because the problem with the former is whether
it's playing something on the French horn or swimming, you're, you know, those tend to rely on
going back to fluid intelligence. Well, we've just established that that's probably going to peak in
your 30s. So, you know, your, whether it be athletic achievements or whatever, they're probably going
to start going down. For sure. Now, the biggest problem with social comparison, however, there's
nothing good about social comparison. We do it because we have to. And part of the reason is we
have to understand what we're doing. We have to understand who we are and where we're going. And
that means, and we're part of a society. So there's a natural fabric of comparisons that are happening
all the time. But, but actually trying to understand your own self-worth in comparison to other people
is, is, I mean, that's really the worst tyranny that leads to envy. Envy is the only, you know,
it's like Joe Epstein, who's the, you know, the great essayist says that, that, that envy is the
only deadly sin that's not even fun. Right. I mean, it's just misery because it's like, my dad,
my dad was a really funny guy. He used to joke that it's not enough to win, son. Your friends have
to lose too. Right. It's like, it's, it's horrible because it actually tears other people down.
You can feel awful about yourself notwithstanding the fact that you're creating real value.
I mean, that's the, in Dante, you know, down to the bottom of Mount Purgatory, that he finds
Satan and Satan at the worst of the deadly sins is actually half frozen in a block of ice. Keep,
and, and, and, and twisting in agony in this ice. And he's keeping the ice solid because of the wind
from his wings where he's, he's fruitlessly trying to get away. And it's in such agony, he doesn't even
notice the, the narrator of the inferno going down to the bottom of Mount Purgatory. This is analogy.
It's not envy isn't fire. It's, it's, it's your, your, your frozen is awful. There's two commandments
against it. It's so bad is the whole idea. Okay. So when you're comparing yourself with yourself,
that's just looking for progress. And, and mathematicians will say that all of happiness
is in the first derivative progress off the baseline. That's what you want is progress.
And that's really good. The problem is that's insidious too, because that's also on the
treadmill. The true master, you know, will be getting intrinsic enjoyment from the thing that
she or he is doing. That's what the true master actually gets. And, and that's the goal that we
should all be going for. And the way to do that is to have this idea of wants management or, or,
you know, there are other ways to put it. There's other ways to actually get at this as well.
You know, I like the metaphor of instead of adding brushstrokes to your, the canvas of your life,
start thinking of your life as a sculpture where you have to chip away until you find the,
you know, the true Peter. Yeah. Tell, tell that story. Actually,
you wrote about that in the book. I believe you were in a museum in, was it in Taiwan?
Yeah. And the national palace museum in Taiwan, which is the greatest collection of Chinese art
and artifacts in the world from the paleolithic into the present. And I was asking this, I,
I actually, when you go to a museum, never go by yourself because you'll, you'll remember nothing
except the, like the snack bar. You got to go with somebody who will show you 10 things. So hire,
get a guy, as they say in the vernacular and say, I want to understand deeply 10 things. That's the
way to go to any museum. And so I hired a guy and he was a philosopher and an expert in both
Eastern and Western art. And, and I said, what's, you know, I was looking at this block of jade
that was carved a two ton block of jade carved intricately into a village, a village scene.
I said, even if I'd never seen any Chinese art in person, and I were not in Taiwan,
if I were in Dayton right now, I'd know this is Chinese how he says, oh, it's just that the whole
philosophy is different between Western and Eastern art. And I said, what is it? He said,
well, Western art is, is uses the metaphor of starting with nothing and then creating something.
The Eastern art uses it. The idea is starting with everything there and chipping away until
you reveal it. Now this is true in music too. You'll find in Eastern classical art traditions,
you have studied, uh, Hindustani classical music, you know, Raga, for example, I studied tableau,
which is the North Indian classical drumming. And you know, the, the, the ensemble will be as small
as it needs to be such that nothing is extraneous. Whereas in a Western orchestra, a symphony orchestra
is 85 people cranking in a hundred decibels such that in the East they'll say, I can't even hear
the music of a symphony orchestra because there's too much going on. It's the same kind of metaphor.
Well, your life in the first part is usually a canvas. By the time you're 45, if you're a
successful person, that canvas is full, man. It's like Jackson Pollock, you know, add one more brush
stroke and it adds nothing that you can possibly, it probably gets worse. It's just dense and dark
at that particular time. You got to move to the metaphor of the, of the block of Jade that you
chip away until you actually find the beautiful thing that's in you. And the goal for the second
half of life, certainly after 45 years old is each year having less each year, getting rid of more
relationships that are extraneous, more possessions, more ambitions, more experiences. And the way that
I do that, I actually have a practical way of doing it. You know, when I was a, I was a young guy,
like everybody else had a bucket list. I'm a very ambitious guy. I've gone from career to career,
try to do a lot with my life and I had a bucket list, you know, all the things that I wanted,
all it did make me feel like a loser, you know, it's like all these things that are unfulfilled
and it kept me fired up to be sure. But now I have a reverse bucket list where I make a list of all
of my worldly cravings and ambitions and I might get them and I might not. What I'm not is I make a,
a conscious metacognitive commitment to not be attached to the things on that reverse bucket
list. I'm not attached to my opinions in the same way that I was. My political views, I'm not
attached to the ambitions that will show me that I'm Mr. Big along the way. It might happen. It
might not happen. But when I make a commitment consciously to detach myself from those things,
it's like chipping away and I'm telling you, Peter, it is very, very effective for helping you with a
wants management strategy such that you can have a big fulfilling life that's enviable by any outward
standard, but at the same time not be chained to it in this, this insidious kind of success addiction
that brings so many successful people so much unhappiness. Say more about this want management.
I mean, I think I intellectually kind of understand, I certainly understand the equation, right? Why
we want the want in the denominator to go down, which therefore, you know, raises the value of the
fraction. But what's the practical set of tools that one, so let's just say I'm sitting here saying,
Arthur, I just don't think I can be happy until I, and I don't want to use myself as an example
because people are sick and tired of hearing about me. So let's just say I'm a normal guy.
And until I get this promotion, I just got to get to VP. Until I'm a VP, it's just not, you know,
but once I get there, I swear it's going to be great. And I just want to pay the mortgage off,
like I, you know, because right now it's just, it's a bit of a chain. And once the mortgage is
paid off, like we are absolutely going to be able to take a month off every summer and go anywhere.
And so there's a list of all of these things that all seem pretty reasonable in terms of aspirations,
in terms of, you know, career success, etc, etc. So how would you explain to that guy? Well,
let's skip the first part. The first part is you're going to tell him that, by the way,
when you get all those things, you're not going to feel that much different for very long. But
more importantly, how would you spare him the agony of spending the next five years pursuing that,
only to find out he'll be right where he is now? Yeah. So I actually started, I have an exercise
that I do with my students when they're in their late twenties. My MBA students are on average 27,
28 years old. And it's the same thing that I, the same exercise that I do with people who are my age,
I'm 58. And it basically starts like this. Imagine yourself, you're 49 or 50, I can't remember.
49. Yeah. Okay. I'm not trying to give you an extra year, Peter. So imagine yourself in five
years, you're 54 years old. Okay, totally imaginable at this point, you're going to be in,
you know, really good health, you're going to be working really hard. Okay, now,
imagine that you're happy. And we've talked about what that means, but you know what it means when
you're happy. You know how it feels when you're happy. So you don't even have to describe that.
Put in order the five things in your life that explain it, why you're most happy in order,
right? And think about it carefully. Don't, you know, it's not the stuff that you wish would make
you happy, the things that might make you happy, the things that never have, but could somewhere.
The things you really know, really realistically, 54 years old that are making Peter Attia happier
than he is today in order. I guarantee you that one, two, and three are going to be about your
relationships. And the only, the bottom of the list is going to be about human achievements.
That's just the way it's going to be. And then the next thing I'm going to ask you is what's
your strategic plan for aggressively managing one, two, and three, as opposed to leaving them off to
chance? How much of your time are you spending on four and five and even things that are not on the
list as opposed to one, two, and three? What is your strategic plan for fortifying your friendships,
your marriage, your spiritual walk, the relationships with your children,
your relationships with your parents, all that stuff. Those are the biggies. And that's how you
think about it. And you say, okay, you got to promotion. Congratulations. You've got extra
money. I might say that's a good way for me to have better relationships because I'll be able
to go out of town with my family. Do you really think that that month away is going to be the
game changer for you to have the perfect marriage? Or should you be thinking, great, if you get the
promotion, more power to you, but do you think you should be thinking more aggressively and
strategically about how to improve your marriage today? How can you improve your marriage today?
And probably has a lot more to do with paying attention to your wife. It probably has a lot
more to do with actually trying to, to get interested in many of the things that she's
interested in. And, and, you know, it's not rocket science. We actually know how to do this,
but if it turns out to be that mystifying, maybe get some help, but manage the things that really
will be what you know, will bring you the greatest happiness. Don't leave those things up a chance.
I love that exercise, Arthur. My, my question, I guess, is what fraction of people do you think
have enough, maybe awareness or introspection is the word that they could come up with that list?
Because I think you're absolutely correct. I think if you really think about this from the right spot,
one, two, and three have to do with your physical and emotional health. And if your physical and
emotional health are out of order, I don't think anything else really matters. Do you get the sense
that when you pose this question to your students, that all of them are able to arrive at that
conclusion? Yeah, so it sort of depends on how deeply they take or how seriously they take the,
the question. So if you ask it in a kind of a breezy way, a pretty informal way, half the
students will have these extrinsic motivations about money, power, pleasure, and fame,
and half of them will have intrinsic motivations about relationships and love. But if you ask them
to think very, very deeply about it, almost all of them wind up in the intrinsic category of love
and relationships, usually the top, especially for people in their late twenties of the romantic
lives. They want to have that on point. The second is their family and friends is the second big
category. And the third is that they want to have children. Most of them really actually want to
have children. They don't know when and they don't know how, but that's really, that's something that
they want. And so we say, okay, well, we need to be focusing strategically on, on, on treating your
romantic life the way that you would a startup, you know, we need to have the same seriousness.
You need to be putting in the time you need to be putting in the work. And we talk about actually
how to do that with the barriers typically are. There's a lot of science and there's a lot of
good practices behind that. And they tend to, when you ask them to do the work, they will focus in on
those three areas. Now, if you say, why weren't you paying attention to those things? They'll say,
I don't know how to manage those things. I came to the Harvard business school to learn how to
be successful in my career. I didn't learn how to be successful in dating. So professor, how do I do
that? And then it turns out that there are ways to do that, but you have to take it seriously and
put it to work. We spoke about the four idols, right? So what is it? Money, power, pleasure,
pleasure, and fame. Fame. Fame is really a funny one though. Because most people listening to us
are like, I don't want to be famous. Yeah. But you want to be admired by others and you want to have
some prestige. And that's localized fame. That's to be known and admired by the right people. It's
exactly the same phenomenon philosophically and psychologically. So let's explore those a little
bit more. Is it necessarily the case that we are hardwired to have preferences along that spectrum?
Or how much of that, well, I suspect it's both nurture and nature, right? I can imagine that
the circumstances by which you grow up would heavily influence that. But how much of that
do you think is sort of hardwired versus developed as a result of circumstances?
So there's a lot of research on that. And what most of the philosophy would suggest, and even
the evolutionary psychologists would suggest that we're hardwired to be looking for money,
power, pleasure, and fame because that gives us fitness in the mating market. Who gets mates?
Somebody who's got a bigger cave, more flints, more animal skins, more buffalo jerky piled up
in the corner. And it was actually known by more troglodytes than troglodytes that he or she knows.
This gives you mating fitness. And so the result is this would become an imperative. It would become
a hardwired imperative. And then you have all kinds of evidence of this. You actually find that when
people are kind of at their base nature, when they're being distracted, they will go for these
particular rewards over much more intrinsic, more satisfying rewards having to do with love. They
will go for these types of rewards all day long. We see this in our consumer patterns. We even see
some of the really interesting neuroscience research talks about how it will illuminate
our brains, how it will stimulate the most dopamine. The most dopamine comes from these
not very satisfying rewards, but nonetheless, the ones that we're supposed to go for. Now,
here's the key thing to keep in mind. Mother Nature wants you to pass on your genes. Mother
Nature wants Peter and Tina have like a hundred kids. But of course, you don't want that. You want
three and you want to have a lifelong partnership with one wife. And that means that you can't
live the hippie motto of if it feels good, do it. That is the motto of useful idiots.
Now, by the way, there's other stupid mottos like if it feels terrible, treat it and make it go away
because suffering is really important in a full life too, it turns out. But the key thing to keep
in mind is that Mother Nature, she doesn't care if you're happy. She doesn't care. That's not Mother
Nature. We don't select on happiness. We select on biological fitness to mate, to pass on our genes.
And so the result is if you follow, if it feels good, do it. You're going to be chasing a whole
lot of very fleeting rewards for what you think is enduring satisfaction. And you're going to have
your hedonic treadmill speeding at a terrifying velocity and you won't even know how to get off
it. You need to get in charge of your own life is the bottom line. You wrote something,
God, I want to say it's been in the last couple of months in the Atlantic about
happiness and success and noting that the happiest people weren't necessarily the most successful.
If I'm remembering that correctly, I think you wrote this in maybe April, it might have been June,
but it looked at some data that suggested actually a little bit of sacrifice in happiness led to
greater success. Am I remembering that sort of correctly? Yeah, that's right. And part of the
reason is because people who are tremendously successful in worldly terms, when I'm talking
about success, we can define it in different ways, right? I mean, having a lifelong marriage
where you're in love with your spouse, that's unbelievably successful. Believing like you have
found spiritual transcendence, that's unbelievably successful. Living for the good of other people,
tremendously successful, but that's not what we're talking about. We're talking about worldly
success, money, power, fame, the admiration of other people. So these particular metrics of
success, people who are remarkably successful along those worldly metrics, they're making cost
benefit calculations systematically that are not in their own happiness favor. Typically they're
making sacrifices of their own happiness for some reason. And this is one of the things that
I've looked at in my own research. Why? Why? Why? Why? And I was talking to a woman, one of the things
that I do as a social scientist, I'm not just cranking data, I go out and talk to the humans,
which I find is a really beneficial thing to do. And I was interviewing this unbelievably successful
woman on Wall Street. I mean, billionaire business or epic success after success and very well known.
And she was confessing to me that she was missing decisions, that people were doubting it,
that at the same time that she and her husband were just kind of roommates, that she had a
cordial relationship with her adult kids, that she was starting to get bad blood work back for her
doctor. She thinks that she was probably drinking too much. She couldn't sleep right. And the whole
thing, she said, what are you doing? I said, you don't need a nerd from Harvard to tell you what to
do. You told me you're a billionaire, step back from your company, take a souvenir in it,
go on to the board, whatever. Get to know your husband, re-establish a relationship with your
kids, start to take care of your drinking problem, become a client of Peter Attia. I don't know. You
know what I'm talking about here. And I say, why don't you do these things? And she said,
she thought about it. She said, you know, I think I, I guess I'd prefer to be special than happy.
And I thought, she, that, that is the hallmark of addiction. You know, I've met, you know,
I used to be a musician. I've met a lot of addicts. I've met a lot of alcoholics in my life.
And they will confess that before they got clean and sober, that they preferred to be high than
happy. They all said that. They knew that they'd be happier when they were finally beyond this
thing. But let's just get high one more time. Just the feel of that pipe on my lips one more time,
just the burning of the alcohol in my throat one more time. Just the, what did, what did William
Burroughs call the, the, the, the red that of the blood in the hypodermic needle before you actually
put down the plunger. And it gives incredible pleasure to people. And they say just one more
time, just one more time. And that's what that lady was saying to me. That's a success addiction. And
that is a, that is absolutely implicated in the dopamine system. And that is like any other
behavioral addiction that a lot of very worldly successful people fall prey to. A lot of people
listening to us and I'm glad they're listening to us right now because they want an edge, but you
got to ask yourself, I have to, Arthur has to ask himself and Peter has to ask himself and all the
people listening to them have to ask themselves, is this a pathology that, that I'm actually feeding
by, by actually trying to get this edge. And I hope it's not, and I hope it's not for me,
but I know a lot of people where it is. And, and you know, they'll thought we talk about work
holism. There's a lot of literature on work holism. Work holism is an ancillary addiction to
success addiction. You know, people work really, really hard. The payoff, the cookie that you get,
you know, that the dopamine is just driving you to is the promotion is the raise is the dollar is
the compliment is the adulation on social media. That's where the real addiction is coming in. And
those are the people that are going to be sacrificing their own happiness decisions for these
success metrics. Do we have a sense of, I mean, this is an unanswerable question, so I'll rephrase
it in kind of a more theoretical way. What would the world look like today if no one was pursuing
being special over being happy? Like how, what year would we be living in? Right? Would it,
would it be 1842 right now? Like I, in other words, what I'm really getting at is how much of the
modern marvels of this world do we owe to the backs of people who sacrificed their own happiness
for the, the innovation that allows us to be doing what we're doing right now?
It's such a smart question. And I consider this myself for me to say,
you and I should break our success addiction. Therefore, the world would be better if nobody
has a success addiction is the fallacy of composition. You know, it's to basically say,
since I get home faster, if I go a hundred miles an hour on the freeway, it would be better if
everybody drove a hundred miles an hour on the freeway. Now you live in Texas, you're like, yeah,
actually that would be better. But anyway, but it's that, that is really, really relevant because
what you find is that the, many of the greatest innovators, composers, creative intellects, these
were people who are, that absolutely sacrificed their happiness, that were deeply, deeply unhappy.
Look, there's a huge literature that shows the, I mean, what is it? The ventral lateral prefrontal
cortex is stimulated by, in, in, in depressives in a way that makes them highly creative.
I mean, we actually have good brain science at this point that shows the people who are suffering
from mood disorders, they tend to be disproportionately creative and they do a lot.
This is, I mean, it's not, you know, Van Gogh was not the outlier. It turns out there's a lot
of weird people in Silicon Valley that have a lot of pretty untreated maladies and they're doing a
lot. Now you might say in Silicon Valley, a lot of them are doing a lot of harm for society as well.
But the point is that, that it is true that the world has been propelled by a lot of unusual
people with unusual goals. And so I don't know how I would, if I were the, if I were the divine,
how I would create the universe, I don't know how I would designate people in society. I don't know
whether I would make people sacrifice their happiness for the greater good of the whole.
I'm just not sure whether there's a kind of a success martyrdom that's going on here.
Yeah, I think about this a lot. I mean, my,
two cents having none of the data and none of the insights that you do is that we are,
we are probably a lot better off for people who have made enormous sacrifices. And I,
and I'm not just talking about like what we think about in Silicon Valley. I mean,
I'm talking about Newton and Gauss and Euler and like the great physicists, the great mathematicians.
I feel like these people made untold sacrifices in terms of the pain that they endured as a result
of their genius. I think you're right, Peter. I think, I think that's actually right. But there's
one thing that I want to emphasize, which is that the misery is not inevitable. You can actually,
and this is the, one of the reasons I've done my work. I'm not asking people to not be successful.
I'm not asking people to be not ambitious, to not work hard. I'm asking them to dominate it such
that you're not playing to your, your, your, your most innate drives so that you can be successful
and happy. And that's a small quadrant of the happy, unhappy, successful, unsuccessful,
the successful and happy, really, really successful and really, really happy. It's a pretty small group
of people, but it's not, it's not not populated. I mean, I write in my book about the case of
Johann Sebastian Bach, the greatest composer who ever lived, who died surrounded by the people who
loved him and who revered him. And the reason is because he got on his second curve because he
would, he dedicated his work to, to other people. He didn't say, you know, forget it. I'm not going
to write any more music. He said, I'm going to write music and, and I'm just going to detach
myself from the ego of having this enormous audience of people who will say that I'm the
greatest composer ever, and I'm going to do it for humanity and for the glorify God and to refresh
the soul of other people. And, and if it's really successful in commercial terms, it is. And if it
isn't, that's okay too. In other words, be, be really ambitious, but detach yourself from the
worldly idols and think about how you can use your success in service of other people. And that's the
hack. That's the workaround. That's actually the glitch in the, in the success unhappiness matrix
is when you become other focused, you can be a success machine and also happy.
I agree with all of that. I was going to actually make a slightly different point, which was
just because that's what got us here today as a civilization, doesn't speak to the individual
choice that we all have. Right. Right. I mean, it's sort of like how I, I'll give you an example
in my world is my thinking on cancer screening for an individual is based solely on the individual.
If I were in charge of creating a cancer screening program for everyone in the country or in the
world, it's a totally different question. Right. Right. Because the former is really all about
individual risk, individual cost, and what the reward potentially is. When you start to talk
about that at a societal trade-off level, it's a much more complicated problem. Now you have to
look at quality adjusted life years and all these other metrics. And, you know, you have to balance
a budget to basically do this. Right. And so, yeah, my takeaway from this is that just because
everything we said is probably true, it doesn't mean that any one individual doesn't have the
potential to make a choice to live in less misery or to be happier. Absolutely. Absolutely. And part
of it is, I believe you don't even have to sacrifice the success, but you do have to go against your
worldly urges in a very big way, not against your worldly urge for success, but against your
worldly urge to pursue the success for a particularly idolatrous reason. And that's a really big
distinction as it turns out. Now, this is the point that's made by, you know, philosophers and
theologians forever, that when you do things in service of others to lift other people up, to bring
other people together, then you can become unbelievably successful. You can become the
Dalai Lama, you can become Desmond Tutu, Mother Teresa, you can do, you know, you can do what
they, you know, the Albert Schweitzer, what are all those people have in common? I mean,
they were world famous, but they were doing this in the service of their fellow women and men.
And that was the key distinction that allowed them to wiggle their way into the both happy
and successful quadrant. You wrote about this also very recently. You're the only reason I
subscribed to The Atlantic, by the way. So The Atlantic should know that. Thank you, Peter.
You wrote about the mortality paradox, right? We can't conceive of not being here. I have been
thinking about this so much. I'll sit there on my bike and I was thinking about it yesterday and I
was really sitting there thinking, you know, how difficult is it for us to imagine the world with
us not in it? Because every experience we have is only through our eyes, only through our senses.
Say more about that, because I just find this to be such a fascinating topic.
Yeah, the more the important mortality paradoxes is has to do with the fact that we're as big brained
mammals, we're able to understand that we're going to die intellectually. But what we can't conceive
of, because our brain isn't that big, is the idea of not existing. So I know I'm going to die,
but I can't imagine not existing. Those are two different phenomena, the two different cognitions.
And one, I can really understand the other that I can't. And the fact that those two things are
intention creates a lot of fear. It creates a lot of uncertainty, real discomfort, real cognitive
dissonance and discomfort in people. And so the result is they're trying to work through that
their whole lives. Either they'll say, okay, well, I'll just resolve it on the first time. I won't
die. You know, well, good luck with that. I mean, it's like, you're the longevity guy. And I heard
you say, you know, I was listening to you today and you said like, the one thing we all know is
that we're going to die. So Peter Attia says, I'm going to die. I'm going to die. Right. Okay.
Or they try to resolve it on the other side, which is to either understand, to apprehend
the concept of not existing or to say, I will always exist, notwithstanding the fact that I'm
going to die. And there's lots of philosophies and religions and look, I'm a traditional Catholic.
And so I've resolved it in a particular way. But the result is that of all of this is that this is
a lot of what leads to people's fears. You know, people talk to me a lot about what they're most
afraid of. I ask people about that a lot. And part of the reason is because my main focus of my
happiness work is love and love and fear are opposites. Love and hatred are not opposites.
Hatred is downstream from fear. And this is a philosophical principle from Lao Tzu and Saint
John the Apostle, but it's also a neurocognitive regularity where you find that, you know, how the
brain works, you know, that you tend to find that love neutralizes fear and fear can turn off love
and every other, every other feeling like a switch because of the way that the brain is designed.
The main focus of my work and happiness is the subject of love. And part of the reason is because
love is the nuclear fuel rods of happiness. If you want to know one thing about how to be happy,
happiness is love full stop. And there's a ton of longitudinal data that shows this.
There's a ton of data that shows, you know, people who are in their 80s and 90s who are really happy.
If you look back in their 20s and 30s and 40s and 50s, what they all have in common is strong
relationships that they were cultivating and working on real love relationships in terms of
romance and family and real friends, not just the old friends. Now, the interesting thing is when
you're studying love is you also have to study its opposite and the opposite of love is fear.
That's a philosophical truism. You know, Lao Tzu talked about the fact that fear and love are
opposite Saint John the Apostle, but also we find this in modern neuroscience in the way that
emotions are processed in the human brain. Psychology shows this abundantly that love
and hatred are opposite. Hatred is downstream from fear. So if you want to understand what turns off
love in your life, when people come to me and say, I don't have enough love, I'll say, well,
tell me about what you're afraid of. And when people come to me and they say they have too much
fear in their life, we'll say, well, we need more relationships. We need more love to neutralize the
fear. So the big fears that I ask people about, one of the things that I find is that everybody has
a death fear. This is an interesting thing. You know, most people say I'm not afraid of dying and
I'm not afraid of dying. I mean, like Peter, you and I are like, you know, it's like the reaper comes
tomorrow. It's like, okay, it's, you know, I lived right. I'm actually not afraid of that. It's,
but I do have a death fear. Everybody does. And it has to do with the extinction of how you
understand yourself. And that gets back to the mortality paradox. The idea of not existing has
some manifestation almost everybody's life, whether it's I'm really afraid of becoming irrelevant.
I'm really afraid of being forgotten. That's your mortality problem. That's your death fear. You know,
for me, it's like, I think about it. The one thing about my health I'm most worried about
is dementia. I'm just, you know, my mother was demented, was in early stage dementia,
which was my age. She was mid 50s. She was in early stage dementia and she lived for another 15
years. And it was, man, it was really, really bad. It was really a bad ending. And for me, I mean,
my whole living is inside my head because these are my ideas. This is how I make a living. This
is how I support my family. Furthermore, it's how, it's how it's everything I love to do is,
is it has to do with my, my ability to think clearly and to think creatively. So for me,
my death fear is my cognitive decline. Everybody has something like this, whether it's really
ego related or has to do with skill related. Everybody's got their, their mortality terror.
And so this is one of the things that we need to dominate if we want to be happy.
And, and I have an exercise, believe it or not, Peter, that I give my students on how to do that.
Number one is you have to figure out what it is. You have to do some serious reflection of what
your death fear is. And for most of my students at Harvard is fear of failure. You know, these are
super high performing. I mean, this was you, I mean, you went to Stanford and then, I mean,
and you did all of this, you know, fancy college stuff. And so my guess is that you never had any
academic failure and you were perhaps pre-afraid of academic failure because you'd never experienced
it. And because it would have been problematic in your family if you had started to fail some
classes in college, I was going to guess, right? But I'm a bit confused because what you spoke
about earlier makes a lot of sense as a death failure because I see a cognitive decline being
tied to physical death because it's an end of life thing. I'm a bit confused about what the
students, these 29 year olds are equating failure in life, for example, starting a business and
having it fail with actual death. Yeah. So it's basically, I am a success machine. Most of my
students start off as very objectified by their parents, where their parents say, you're the
special one, you're successful, you always get A's, you're a hard worker, you know, get it done.
And they start to see themselves as kind of homo economicus. They see themselves as
highly, you know, high performers. And they're very bright and they're very hardworking and
the result is they don't experience any failure in school. I mean, for me, these are absurd things,
you got to be on an exam who cares, right? You know, I've flunked out of college. I mean,
it's like, man, I know failure, but for them, they've never experienced these things. So it
feels like a mortal threat, because it's a threat to who they think they are, which is a successful
person, somebody who never fails, and is very foreign territory to them. So whether their
their death fears failure or cognitive decline, or being forgotten, or being irrelevant, or actually
dying, the technique for getting beyond this is really all the same. And it comes from that I
found very successful is to do what is called a Theravada Buddhism, the marinasati meditation,
this is the nine part death meditation that Theravada Buddhist monks in Sri Lanka and Thailand
and Vietnam, what they will they will undertake in which often they'll contemplate corpses,
photos of corpses in various states of decay. And they'll say, I that is me and that is me. And
they have a nine for this marinasati is a meditation in which they they imagine themselves
decaying, dying, and then, you know, a rotting bloated corpse. And then it's so graphic is
super graphic. It's unbelievable. And that's the point, right? And super accurate, like it really
is how a human corpse decays. Just unbelievable. And so, and what you're trying to do is what
psychologists would call exposure therapy, you're exposing yourself to the inevitable truth. Like,
I heard you say, Peter, I'm gonna die. Okay, fine, fine, fine. No, think about it. Think about it.
Why? Because that it loses its terror when it becomes familiar. So what I make my students do
is a nine part meditation on their own failure, catastrophic failure by their own terms, which is
not necessarily human catastrophic failure. But there'll be I remember the first time I did this,
I put the steps in because they didn't know how to do it. And the first one is,
I'm falling behind my colleagues at school. I graduate, but just barely. I'm not getting the
jobs that my friends are getting, and the people thought I was going to get. I'm finding a really
my career is not what I thought it was going to be. And then I get to this one point, I threw this
in just for a little bit of pathos. And I said, there's one point I say, I think my parents feel
sorry for me. And a student starts crying. Because that's the nerve, man. That's the nerve. There's
always this point in the deaf meditation. So figure out what death means for you, where this mortality
paradox, it really has teeth, and then actually put together the exposure therapy of walking
yourself through the the experience, the emotional experience of this failure, and you will be free.
This is the one thing that I guarantee that you'll be free of that. Now you got to think and do it
just once. You have to do it again and again and again, because what your fear is has very
as deeply rooted in a lot of your experience. But once you're exposing yourself to that,
again and again, it has an incredible therapeutic impact.
So the exercise is obviously first taking some time to really be thoughtful about what these fears
are. And by the way, I'm guessing some people have more than one. I mean, you have this sort of the
fear of actual death, perhaps the fear of failure along the way. So you might be doing this exercise
twice, right? Yeah, for sure. For sure. You know, like, we probably all have multiple versions and
they change throughout life. You know, when I was 20 years old, I wasn't afraid of cognitive decline.
I'm 58 years old and I want to keep the party going, is the law of life. And the party's not
going to keep going. I might not be demented. I might be hit by a bus tomorrow. I might be,
you know, my mother-in-law died last month and she was talking about a good death. She was 93.
She had her marbles to the last minute and she died at home, right? I mean, not bad, not bad,
you know, chapeau. I mean, that's like, that's really, really good, but everybody goes.
And so you can't keep these things unless you're comfortable with this inevitability,
the mortality paradox, this inability to process these two competing ideas,
it'll terrorize you. It'll paralyze you. It'll be a problem.
What's the optimal dose of exposure? So if I was an arachnophobic and I came to you and said,
you know, we came to the understanding that I need to be exposed to spiders, how often would we need
to do this? That's a good question. And actually, there are psychologists and psychotherapists who
deal with this with different kinds of phobias and they find that different people have to be
exposed, have to have an exposure that's had more or less frequent and you have to re-up it or you
don't. Some people are just, they solve a problem. I mean, my little girl, she's 19 when she was a
baby, we adopted her from China and she had, you know, she had never been held and, you know, she
was undernourished. And so when she came to live with us, she was afraid of a lot of stuff. And one
of the things she was really, really afraid of was dogs. She would see a dog outside, she would
scream and, you know, she would want to be. So we wanted to solve this and we did it by getting a dog,
right? But we didn't just like throw the dog in the room with her in the crib. You know, we
held, we kept the dog apart and it turns out there was about three days. And after about three days,
she was not afraid of the dog anymore. And after about six weeks, she loved all dogs. And that was
it forever. She's so crazy about all dogs. She's 19 years old. She has pictures of the dog that
was that dog sadly passed away, but lives in blessed memory at this point because it was her
cognitive therapy, death meditation dog or something like that. But other people who have
lived with these phobias all their lives, including people who have these stresses about their own
mortality, it requires a, I think a more strenuous and thorough intervention and one that's more
frequent. And so how, how do you suggest somebody go about doing this exposure? In the case of the
monastery, they literally have pictures of nine stages of decaying corpses. I assume that the
monks come there and look at these pictures and meditate. Yeah. Yeah. They stand in front of each
one of the pictures each day and they say, that is me while staring at the photograph. And they
want it, what they want it to become is actually completely trivial and familiar. That's what they
want. So for all of us, um, again, that's a good one to do by the way, but because we're all going
to die and you know, no, he's like, Hey, can't wait. You know, they're there. Um, but the thing that
really is your bugaboo, you know, the thing that really is holding you back, your version of the
death meditation, think about it, contemplate it, write it out and expose yourself to it as much as
you need to. And you'll, you know, you know, when you're getting the benefit, it's hard at first.
And that could literally just be, I could just be reading it out every day. Yeah. I actually ask my
students to contemplate each step for two minutes. Um, and to do that each day for three weeks. Because
one of the things that I found is by the end of three weeks is like, yeah, yeah, I'm gonna fail.
Wow. So not a big commitment. Look, it's 20 minutes a day for three weeks, basically.
Totally. Yeah. And again, you know, maybe a psychotherapist would be like, Hey, you're
kidding yourself. If it's a really entrenched problem, it's going to take a lot longer than
that. Plus cognitive behavioral therapy plus drugs. I know. But one of the things that I found
is that my students are afraid of failure and we can get over it pretty quick.
You visited India. You're, you're, I think you describe yourself as an India file.
Yeah. I'd love it. Um, by the way, when you were here, did I make you Curry? I can't remember.
You did. And it was delicious. Oh yeah. Yeah. I know we talked about it. I couldn't remember
what we ended up doing. Yeah, we did. It was delicious with tofu and, um, and with non-fat
Greek unflavored Greek yogurt that you actually pointed out for consistency and thickness.
Yeah. Yeah. Really good. So, um, talk about the four ashrams and how we can kind of,
I know they're divided into sort of 25 year chunks, but I'm, I'm, I find this very interesting what
those four stages are. And especially, I guess, as you pointed out, I'm about to be 50. So
I'm really under entering enter, ending the second one about to enter the third. Yeah.
And it's really the second one. That's the hardest one I think to leave, isn't it?
Yeah. So these are called ashramas, which are, which means what, what it means is the quarters
of a perfect life in, in Vedic philosophy. So really ancient Indian wisdom. Um, these ideas
are probably 5,000 years old. I mean, this is, this is, you know, it's funny. You know,
when I talk to, I, I, I have studied with a lot of these very deep Hindu masters in Southern
India. When every time I go to India, I try to sit at the feet of one of these masters and they'll
say, you're Christian, right? And he says, you think all these things that we used to think 4,000
years ago. And it's a, and, but the, I went to India specifically to study the ashramas with a,
with a wonderful guru in a place called Palakkad in Southern India, um, on the border between
Kerala and Tamil Nadu, which is these two Southern states. And his name is Sri Nochir Venkatarama. And
I asked him about these ashramas, which are the four quarters of a, a well balanced and perfect
life, ideally 25 years each. Now the odds of getting to a hundred are one in 6,000 in the
United States today and a lot lower than that in India. So the point is not to be dogmatic about
turning 50 Peter. What we're really talking about is just these, these chunks of life. The first
phase of life is called brahmacarya, which is the student life. And all that means is not
necessarily literally a student. It means the time when you're learning, when you're absorbing,
when you are a sponge for human capital and, and, and ideas that then around age 25 is when you
enter Grihastha, which is typically when a man, for example, would, would get married and start a
household. And that's called the householder phase. And that's career and marriage and children and
success and sexual relationships and all of these kinds of worldly rewards of money, power,
pleasure, and fame. You know, that's when you get addicted to those worldly rewards of money,
power, pleasure, and fame. And, and it's fun and it's good and it's hard and it's tiring, etc, etc.
Then whereas in the West we talk about that one hard transition from kid to adult from brahmacarya
to Grihastha. And India, they talked about the difficulty of the second adolescence,
which is passing out of Grihastha into the third phase around 50, which is called Vanaprastha.
That's 50 to 75. And that's a really critical and very interesting phase. It's hard to get into
because it requires wanting less. It requires chipping away. It requires a reverse bucket list.
What it requires, it's in Vanaprastha comes from two Sanskrit words, Van and Prastha, where it
means to retire into the forest. Obviously, not a foric. I mean, I'm not, I'm not going to go live
in the forest and neither you. The whole point is to retire away from a lot of the parts of Grihastha.
You're still going to work. You're still going to do your thing, but you're going to have a different
focus. You're going to be focused on teaching. You're going to be focused on other people.
This is very second curve. This is where it all comes together. And this is what I try to do with
my work. As I take Eastern or Western philosophy and wisdom, I mix it up with neuroscience,
with historical regularity, and with modern experimental social science. And it all has
to be consistent. If it's not all consistent, and there's one part of that that's not quite right,
then I'm onto the wrong comprehensive story. So how this hangs together is you're passing
into your second curve, which is also Vanaprastha as one of the ashramas retiring into the forest
where you are the teacher. You are becoming less involved in your own success, but more involved
in the success of other people. Now that might carry you to great glory, but that's not primarily
for that. If you're going to be in the happy, successful quadrant. And here's the twist. There's
another goal ahead of you, a big goal, which is the last ash or the last quarter, the last ashrama,
which is 75 and beyond, which is called sannyasa. Now, a lot of people who studied Eastern philosophy
or, you know, Hindu thought, they know what a sannyasi, a sannyasi is somebody who's an enlightened
one. And in a lot of religious cults, they talk about sannyasis and all that. But basically all
that means is somebody in this ashram of sannyasa. And that is where you're really dedicated fully to
spiritual and spiritual enlightenment. And in ancient times, Hindu men of some means at age 75
would take leave of their families and go to the Himalayas and sit at the foot of their master until
death. Now I'm not suggesting that right. That doesn't sound so great to me because I want to
death to do us part with my wife. But the whole point is once again, not that to take it literally,
but rather to say, look, I mean, the fruit of my old age requires a lot of training. The intellectual
and philosophical and spiritual transcendental fruit of my life requires this elite training,
which is vana prastha. You can't show up to the Olympics, 60 pounds overweight, expect to swim
the backstroke, having not swum in months. It can't be done. You have to train for it. It takes,
according to the Hindu philosophers, 25 years of elite spiritual and intellectual and
transcendental training to get to that point later in life. Arthur, if you go back in time to that
plane ride from LA to DC, and let's just imagine you've somehow found yourself alone with this
gentleman once you figured out who he was and processed all he had to say, what would you say
to him? Well, I wouldn't intrude on his privacy to begin with because I was overhearing a conversation
about the most intimate things in his life with his wife, which is one of the reasons I haven't
divulged to a single soul and the identity of that man of the plane because it's not important. It
could be anyone of, you know, could be anybody practically under very similar circumstances.
But if you're asking me for particular advice, I would talk about the one thing that he's
really missing, which he's evidently really missing. And by the way, I have Googled him
since then. I've been following him since then. He divorced that woman already, and it's not his
first wife. You know, and so the whole point is what he's been hungering after, panting after,
lusting after is what he had in Grihastha, what he had on his first curve, what he had in his
idols of money, power, pleasure, and honor. That's what he wanted. That's what he wants back. And
the fruit of his life should be his enlightenment based on love, on faith, and family, and friendship,
and service to other people. Those are the habits of the happiest people. Those are the people who
are maximizing their happy span. I made up that word being as hot as awful, but I'm just trying
to, you know, I'm talking to Peter and Tia here. So I got a, you know, saying in the theme,
that's what I would talk about is like, you're going for the wrong thing. Your ambition to go
back in time is going to lead you to misery. You need to move forward into the bonds of love that
are your, that should be your, your rightful claim as a person later in life. And I did the research
so that I could give the advice to myself and other people on exactly how to do it.
Well, Arthur, I won't even ask if this gentleman is still alive, but if he is, I hope he's listening
as I think we all are. And I think we all benefit from this. It's a lot to think about. I think this
is, I think this is a harder thing to fix than a lot of the things that I talk about. And I'm not
sure why, you know, I, I, because you would think, well, gosh, it must be really hard to
take somebody who's sleeping six hours a night in a fragmented way and, you know, help them get to
eight hours a night of great sleep or someone who's sitting on the couch all day and get them
to exercise or someone who's living on McDonald's and get the meat happy. All of those things are
difficult, but they're not as difficult. I think as taking somebody who lives on a hedonic treadmill
and getting them to adjust that to decrease wants to make the type of strategic changes that are in
keeping with what ultimately will bring them happiness. I guess my final question for you is,
why do you think, well, first of all, I guess, do you agree with me? But assuming that you would
agree that this is very difficult, why do you think it is? I've contemplated that an awful lot.
And I mean, I'll answer that actually in a weird way. When I was doing work for the Rand Corporation
on, on combat modeling, using, you know, huge computer systems to look at unbelievable number
of simulations and contingencies. What I found was that, that, you know, all of the easiest
problems to solve, which can be very hard, but they're solvable, are what mathematicians call
complicated problems. Those are problems that they're, they take a lot of computational
horsepower, but once you solve the problem, you can, you can replicate the solution over and over
again with great accuracy, like creating a jet engine where every single jet flies and almost
none of them ever crash or fail. That's a complicated problem. Now it took a long time to do
that. That's what we call that the toaster problem. It wasn't that long ago that there were no toasters
and I recommend that you don't try to build your own. You probably burn your house down,
but now you can get a $20 toaster in the last two for many, many years and it makes really great
toast. That's a complicated problem. But the bigger problems, the problems that really
bedevil us, the problems of human life and the essence of human life are mostly complex problems.
Those are the problems where we, we understand the nature of what winning means very easily,
but there's a so many inconceivably high number of permutations that they can't be solved.
Those are not toaster problems. Those are cat problems. Cats are complex, not complicated.
You know what they want, scratches and warmth and kibble and a box to poop in, but you don't know
what they're going to do next ever. And all of life's really interesting things that make life
life. They're complex problems. Love is a complex problem. Love is a cat, not a toaster. The problem
that we have in our life today, you know, and the problem with what we're getting from tech,
for example, is that they're trying to solve our complex problems of love using complicated
engineering solutions. You know, you're lonely. Here's Facebook. That's like saying you want a
cat, here's a toaster. So that's the problem is that these complex issues, they're insoluble,
actually. And so we're looking for a simulacrum for a solution to these particular problems. And
when it comes down to saying just love more, it's insufficient. And that's why it's so hard.
And so what I'll do when I can't get my cat is I'll just try to be contented with a toaster.
It's like, I don't know, I can't find a mate. So I guess I'll buy a boat. I guess I'll try to be
more successful. I guess I'll try to make more money and it doesn't work. And that's what leads
to a lot of the heartbreak of ordinary life. Arthur, I think that's literally one of the most
remarkable explanations I've heard for, I mean, certainly I'm familiar with complex and complicated
problems, but this application of it is probably one of the most helpful I've heard. So I appreciate
that. And I appreciate your patience and sitting down with me a second time. What a pleasure. Are
you kidding? I was like, that's great. That's awesome. I get to talk to Peter twice.
Well, we'll do it a third time at some point, it'll be in person and we'll come up with something
great to eat as well. Thank you, Peter. Thank you for what you do. I love your show and all of the
things that you do, you make my life a lot better. Well, I can say the same to you, Arthur. Thank you
so much.