Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Holly, thanks so much for making time to sit down today. I look forward to talking about a lot of
things. My wife has already peppered me with a hundred questions for you today.
I'm really excited to be here. Thank you so much for having me on the show.
So tell us a little bit about yourself. I know you grew up in Australia and I know that you,
I think you ran track growing up.
Yes, I did. So yeah, I grew up in Tasmania, Australia. So for those that may not be
geographic of that, where that is, it's the little island that sits just south of the mainland. So
it's a pretty small place. And I think part of the evolution of me now being where I am in Florida,
was just having such a big open mind and I didn't want to stay there. So I moved away
to do college. So I moved over to Melbourne Deakin University, where I did an undergraduate
in nutrition science, food science, nutrition, and then a master's in dietetics.
So how, I know Tasmania by landmass looks pretty big, but what's, is it a tiny population?
It's tiny. I think at the moment it's probably like 500,000. Where I grew up specifically,
when I was living there, the population of Lompsiston was about 90,000. So pretty small.
So in high school, you ran track or in college?
All the way through. So I started track at about age eight and I went right through till age 18.
So I finished by the time I got to like second or third year of university. I guess at that point,
that was when I could either go for a sporting career or choose academics. So I ended up choosing
academics because unfortunately in Australia for females, it just isn't a whole lot of opportunity
to have a successful career in sport. For males, it's a little bit different. We have Aussie Rules
football, which is incredibly popular and absolutely can make a killing. And I think
perhaps now that social media has grown to be where it is, maybe some female females have an
opportunity to have a good career in sport. But yeah, academics was kind of the only option really
for me at that time. What did you run in track? So I was a sprinter, 100 meters long jump,
triple jump. And if someone dare ask me to do a relay or a 400, I might do that. So lots of fast
twitch, anything explosive and powerful and short. And did you lift weights in high school? Was that
your exposure to it? So not in high school. I actually only started lifting weights probably
in year 11. So we call that college at home. So grade 11, I started or introduced lifting weights.
And that was when I was part of the Tasmanian Institute of Sports. So my coach at the time,
Peter Fortune was also Olympic 400 meter runner, Kathy Freeman. So she won the gold medal in the
2000 Olympics and everybody loved her. So I worked with him. And yeah, that's where I kind of had a
lot of my, I guess, experience in track sprinting. So why did you choose nutrition in college?
Good question. So I think most people would probably say, Oh, you know, I'm really passionate
about sport and da, da, da, da, da, da. But my reasoning was probably not a good one. I got into
the sport purely because of my, I guess, desire for control of my nutrition. And it probably begs
the question, you know, what's that all about? So I have only very recently overcome a 15 year
long eating disorder. I struggled with anorexia for a short period of time. And that went on to
become a binge eating disorder in bulimia. So before I even thought about going off to college,
I was already in the depths of that disorder. I was also struggling a lot with depression.
At age 16, I had already attempted suicide twice. And I was hospitalized for a good part of my year
11 schooling, which looking back at that now, like it's, it's really sad actually. And I just
didn't have the supports. I didn't have the mentors or people in my life that really helped me to feel
what I needed to feel. And I think experience as a child and it kind of escalated into my adulthood
and really very recently have I only started to work on my mental health. And I think that's where
a lot of my advances have come, especially as it relates to like feeling like I have a sense of
purpose in life and really ultimately finding my happiness. So, um, so are you the, you have one
sibling? Yes. Older, younger. Younger sibling. A sister. Yes. So, um, when, when did the eating
disorder start and did that sort of, uh, uh, proceed the, what you described as depression or do you
think the two are kind of hand in hand and intertwined? They, uh, kind of came on simultaneously,
I think, um, for multiple reasons. So, um, I don't want to, you know, say negative things about my
family and my parents or how they raised me because gosh, my mother was just an incredible woman. She
basically raised us as a single mom. Uh, I did have a father in my life, but, uh, he was a very
hard worker, uh, very disciplined and so career focused that, you know, we were kind of invisible
to him. So my mom, uh, I think she had grown up in a similar situation where her mother, um, was
completely absent. She was a single mom. So I think her life experiences where she didn't have
somebody that even cared about her, that take her to do anything, do sports, you know, she had to do
it all herself. She'd catch the bus to afterschool trainees. She'd take herself, you know, to
athletics on the weekends. So, um, my mother was a wonderful woman, but she, she did what she did
based on her own personal experiences. So it probably wasn't the best thing looking back at it,
but you know, we all have our flaws, but our relationship was really strained. Um, I think
she wanted to control me, um, to protect me. I think, um, you know, and that kind of put a lot
of friction between us. So I felt like I had no control in my life. Uh, I think up until like year
10, I wasn't even allowed to have like a sleepover at a friends without there being like serious
like arguments. And there was just a lot of hostility and confrontation growing up. So,
so your 10 is about 15. Yes. And so give me a little bit more of an understanding of that. So
was the focus before that age, was it sort of a heavy emphasis on your academics and on your
sports? And that was it? Absolutely. Yes. So we were doing, uh, dancing, like tap jazz, ballet,
uh, piano music, guitar, like drums. Um, then we were in basketball and athletics. So we did a lot
of, um, you know, activities. Um, and I think the only kind of praise and recognition or like you
felt like you were cared for or loved was when you excelled at something. So, you know, if I came
home and I did really well in my grades at school, that was about the only time that I would get,
you know, Oh wow. You know, we really love you or well done. Um, and I know my mom loves me. Like
it's, it's just how people communicate is so important. Um, so yeah, I really kind of grew
up with this idea that unless I was the best at something or did everything and I excelled at
everything, I didn't really have value as a human. So that's kind of one aspect, um, I think of where
all that depression and the eating disorder started. Um, but sadly I also, um, experienced
some sexual trauma around that age. And I think that there were two instances and it happened
with people that I really respected that I trusted. Um, and that coupled with this toxic,
you know, home environment where you can't really even go to your parents because there's this,
you know, a fear of being judged, you know, from the community. Um, you know, everything was about
keeping up with appearances. So it wouldn't be, you know, are you okay? Talk to me. Let's, let's
have a discussion about this. It was, well, what, what, what did you do to deserve that? Well, what
were you wearing? How are you dressed? What, what kind of makeup did you have on? Like you're asking
for this, you know? So yeah, you didn't, you didn't disclose any of this to your parents.
Uh, I spoke to my mother about it. Um, but that was kind of the feedback that, that I got. Um,
she didn't know how to, to support me and she did granted, you know, try to look for therapy, um, at
the time. But, uh, I think at that point I was so far down like the rabbit hole of depression.
Um, and just feeling like I was a lost cause that like nothing even, nothing worked. Certainly the
behavioral therapy that I did, um, at that time was ineffective and the medication that I had
actually, um, made it worse, significantly worse, um, for a period. So I consequently came off that.
And so, um, help me understand a little bit more about how one, um,
sort of, cause I, I think that eating disorders are probably a lot more common than we are led to
believe. Um, I don't actually, this is not something I know a lot of the statistics about.
We've actually been trying to find an expert on eating disorders for the podcast because I think
it is a very important topic. So I don't know if you are familiar with these statistics, but I'm
not. Uh, but do you have a sense of, of, um, how often they afflict young women versus young men?
So the prevalence is a lot greater in females than men, but it's actually increasing over the last
10 years, uh, in young boys as well. Um, I hope I don't butcher the statistics I did actually,
there was a couple of studies that I'd like to reference, but I don't have them with me.
But I believe 60% of, um, high school students in US, um, females have reported to struggle with,
um, low confidence, uh, negative, um, sense of self and body image, um, prevalence of eating
disorders. Uh, I guess it's a little bit lower, but I wouldn't know the exact statistics, but
it is scarily high. And we can also then look into some of the, the younger studies in children.
Um, and it is higher than it should be. Absolutely.
And so when you think back to how this started in you, I think you mentioned that it started
first with anorexia before binging and purging. Um, did you gain a sense of control by limiting
what you were eating? Did it, did it in the short term satisfy something that was inside you?
You know what it did, but I think because I was so athletic, I was so heavily involved in sport
that, you know, my energy demands, like I think back to the amount of training that I was doing,
you know, you've got your in-school sports and then after school and it was hours of practice
and six days a week for the most part, maybe training on Sunday. Um, I, I couldn't sustain
the restriction. I might like, I was so, um, famished and hungry and like that frustrated
me. It really did. Like I didn't connect the dots. Like, you know, why can't I control,
you know, what I put in my body? Like, you know, but little that I know anything about,
you know, your appetite regulating hormones at that point and the requirements for energy
for the sport that I was doing. So, um, I would, uh, I guess I would act out these behaviors of
binge eating, um, and then purging. And it was just constant. It became a point where
it was probably every day of the week for, I would say five years, which is terrifying to think about
considering the risks. So that means from high school all the way into university.
Yep. Um, it definitely slowed down when I got to university and I think it was just because of
the requirements for study and like I had to work three jobs and, um, you know, to make everything
work. So there was just less opportunity for me to do that if I wanted to excel in my studies.
So, um, yeah, it was horrific. I just remember feeling like I wanted to be able to control
things, but at the same token, I had no control because my body was doing what it's meant to do,
which is to protect you from starvation, essentially. Now, some of the complications
that people experience with bulimia, of course, you know, the constant flow of acidity up and
down the esophagus, did you have any of the issues with your teeth, the electrolyte abnormalities?
So interestingly, no. Um, I can't speak to the electrolyte abnormalities because I never had,
um, you know, routine blood work back then. It was, that was definitely not something I was going to,
to prioritize as a young, uh, naive student. But, um, I can say now, like thankfully, um, you know,
I never had any of the esophageal erosion from that acidic acid. I think, um, that, you know,
plays a strong risk in developing cancers of the throat and the olfactory. So I do wonder about
that, um, because of the frequency of purging, um, and what that says for me in the future,
because now that I have, you know, made, got that under control, um, it's a scary thought because
I'm in, you know, cancer's a, uh, it's a scary thing. So how did this progress? So you, you're
in university, you're doing an undergraduate degree, then you do a master's degree right after. Um,
what's happening? Does anybody in your life kind of recognize that this is going on, be it your
sister, your mom or friends? No. So I think one of the challenges, and it's, I think been exacerbated
by moving away, um, was my family weren't in the same state. Um, and they didn't travel, uh,
to see me very often. And it's kind of been, been that way since I've moved away. Um,
so I didn't have the family support. Uh, I've never had a close relationship with my sister,
though I would love to. It's just, we've just gone in different directions, I think with life.
Um, and yeah, my, I don't, didn't have any kind of relationship with my father. So, um,
I didn't have anyone to go to for guidance. Uh, so I was kind of in and out of, you know,
dating when you were at school, college and, uh, you know,
But none of your boyfriends knew that this was happening.
No, I may have communicated it to one. And I think part of that was out of shame. I think,
think about the stigma that's associated with mental health issues, depression for one. Um,
but then to have an eating disorder and me being the perfectionist, high achiever,
um, you know, driven woman that I was, there was no way I wanted to share this weakness.
And especially given that I was, you know, educated, I've done a bachelor's in food science
and now I've got a master's degree in nutrition. I should be able to control this, you know,
in that is that word control. So I, I was terrified to tell anybody. Um, so I was
suffering in silence and it probably went that way for 10 years.
And during that 10 years, this pattern of behavior was still continuing. Um,
we're going to talk a lot about training. We're going to talk a lot about, you know,
bodybuilding and stuff that you've done more recently, but kind of helped me understand,
like, what did you physically look like at the time? Did you look as fit as you look today?
Did you, did you have more of a sort of slender build? Were you more muscular? I mean, I,
it, I think there's a, I think part of the issue, and I know this isn't true, but I think it's part
of the stereotype is when we think of somebody with an eating disorder, we picture an individual
probably in different extremes. You know, I think when we think of someone with anorexia,
we think of someone that's incredibly thin and, and you know, they appear unhealthy and how thin
they look. Conversely, I think when we picture somebody with bulimia, we usually think of
somebody that's a little overweight. Um, were you sort of somewhere on that spectrum?
I was right in the middle. Um, I think again, because of the amount of activity that I was
doing, um, that prevented me from being in this state or a mental state of anorexia. So I never
got to the point where I was dangerously low body weight. Um, but I, I was a healthy body weight and
I was still, you know, sprinting track training. Uh, I would say I was above average muscularity.
I was, that was kind of when I just started getting into, uh, you know, do you remember the
Les Mules, um, like classes that they would have at the gyms where there's, um, like combat class or,
uh, kickboxing or a body pump. So I was doing, you know, some light resistance training. Um,
my actual like interest in bodybuilding didn't start until, uh, much later after college. So
yeah, I was, I was healthy body weight, but I think like, if we look at, you know, the research for
people that do suffer with binge eating disorder and bulimia, they tend to be normal weight too,
you know, above, above normal weight. So yeah, I was right in the normal, no one would have known.
And you mentioned also, I think that you had a suicide attempt when you were six, was it 16?
Yes. And was that, I mean, I don't want to ask the obvious question. How was that not a wake up
call to your parents? It was, um, one of the things that was really disappointing and I think
it just enhanced the sadness. I get a little bit upset than emotional thinking about it. But,
um, again, just to kind of outline just how incapable like my father was of communicating.
And it's not that he's a bad person. It's just, his backstory is incredible. Like lost his mom at
age 13 through breast cancer was raised by an alcoholic father, four brothers, like beaten,
you know, really, really sad. He didn't know how to communicate. And I remember at that point, um,
my mom was very upset when that happened. And I think my dad came into my room and was like,
you're a fucking idiot. And he walked out, you know, sorry to have that from like somebody that
you're like, wow, I thought like you loved and cared about me. It was, he was never somebody
that would have had a clue where to start. Um, my mother on the other hand was like overbearing
and that was the problem. Like she didn't, I knew that she was trying to help, but part of the reason
that I'd gotten to this, uh, space anyway, in combination with the sexual assaults, uh, and
then some of the things that my coach had said about, um, my training, which led to the ED disorder as
well, um, was that she was just way too controlling, wanted to just do everything for me, whether it
was live vicariously through our sports, which I understand. And I've forgiven my mother for that.
And you know, she's just doing what she knew, but, um, yeah, she tried to get me in touch with the
right health professionals. Um, but I think just lack of, you know, knowledge resources, um, not
having good connections herself. Um, and she worked in the medical industry, um, as like
administration for years before she became a stay at home mom. So even not like even through her
networks, she just didn't have the tools. And it was right about the time where I was ready to
bounce and go to college and I had to fly and move away, uh, essentially. So the ability for her to
kind of control and manage, um, you know, what I did with my health and now I'm kind of becoming an
adult. Um, it was a lot harder. So I think in some ways I'm really grateful that I stepped away from
Tasmania and, you know, took on other opportunities that didn't require her support because I think,
you know, if you get, um, I guess, babied for your, you know, young teenage years, uh, and enabled,
I, I would never have had the life skills to, you know, be the person that I am today to
know what it's like to step out and take risks and, you know, fear. I don't have any fear of failure.
Um, and I think part of that was developed from me just moving away and stepping out from that control.
I want to kind of go back to still the understanding the eating disorder a little bit more. Um,
did you, did your, um, self image of your body seem sort of, um, inaccurate with what you now
look back at as reality. In other words, does, does everyone with an eating disorder necessarily
also have a skewed view of their body image or can, can that be uncoupled and the eating disorder
is simply a control tool that can be unrelated to, um, a misbelief, a misguided belief about body
image? I don't think dysfunctional thoughts. Yeah. So I think it really depends on the individual.
Um, I don't, uh, I couldn't recall all of the exact criteria, um, or like characteristics, behaviors
that, um, you know, clinically define, um, anorexia or binge eating disorder or the like,
cause they are all slightly different in their own way. Um, but for me, at least I can say that
initially it wasn't, um, my body image that I was concerned about. It was control. Um, and I think
that's kind of then developed into like obsessive compulsive for some things. It was like anytime I
felt stressed, uh, anxious, dropping whatever emotion, um, as I grew that, um, control, the
desire to control came back and I kind of crafted this little environment where when I lived on my
own at school, uh, and then, um, post-school past postmasters, when I went off and started my career,
um, my environment was built in such a way that I basically shielded myself from stresses,
potential triggers, whether it was food, environmental, social, um, so that I could
live in control and that gave me comfort. So reality check, when you become an adult and you
have to be flexible and nimble and pivot and, you know, learn to adapt under stress, which
my goodness, I feel like my life was extremely stressful for a lot of different reasons, but I
just had no coping skills. So I didn't, it didn't start as a negative body image. It was simply,
um, the desire for control. However, as I kind of found myself, you know, more and more involved
in sport and as my physique did change, um, and as I started to connect the dots with my
train, uh, athletic performance with superior physique, low body fat, more muscle, uh, and then
the praise that I would get externally from people that then became the obsession. It was, you know,
it's how I look. And that was where I found myself worth. That was where I, uh, felt valued and
appreciated and, you know, people respect me and for a good part of my life, I think it became my
identity and it was impossible to break and that just fueled the disorder. Yeah. So I can only
imagine which then leads to the inevitable question of how do you break that cycle? Um,
oh, through a lot of hard work. And this is one of the practices, I guess, that I've incorporated
only very recently into my own like nutrition coaching, um, and with our team as well. And
that is really, um, working in collaboration with allied health, um, particularly mental health
experts. So for me, until I actually started having regular therapy and I'm not talking like
once every six weeks for review, which is kind of the expectation, I guess, in the clinical world,
I know for me as a dietician, um, we would see our patients, um, you know, maybe you do a four
up for a four week review or a six week review. Um, so it was really infrequent, but that's kind
of how I had been exposed to it with my parents when mom had gotten me into therapy. When was that?
That was when I was about 16 when I was living in Tasmania. Yes. Yeah. They put you into kind
of an infrequent therapy. Yeah. So I would have to travel to Hobart. I saw a specialist down there,
um, who, you know, worked with females, predominantly any women's health issues,
but eating disorders and, uh, nutrition. So, um, it was infrequent, but I remember loving those
little trips because it was like the one time that I was like, Oh, my mom cares. Wow. We get to go and
stay in Hobart and we get to go and spend time together. And she cares about me. And it was just
like, it's a sick relationship to think like that was so exciting for me, but that was what was fuel.
It was almost like that attention was good attention because I never felt like anyone cared
like about me outside of like your credentials and that kind of thing. Now, as you think about
sort of the post college life, um, did you think that you had things under control or did you think
that this is a dirty little secret that is totally out of control? I think it kind of came in
waves. Um, and I think like any kind of condition, you know, it's all works along a spectrum. So
I definitely had periods where I felt like, um, I was managing the symptoms, um, and the feelings,
the emotions that kind of came along with that disorder. Uh, okay. Um, but as soon as things got
a little bit stressful or I had it, you know, extra assignments due, or if I needed to like
from a financial perspective, you know, I need to do two full weekends of work back to back. And
that's the only way that you're going to be able to have groceries next week or put gas in your car.
Um, you know, when anything extra kind of came into my life, I just lost it. It was, um, like
extreme, um, you know, binging purging, secret eating, um, was really something that I struggled
with. Um, you know, I would go out for dinner with friends and I would try to like enjoy myself
and like partake in the food, but because I would restrict so aggressively, um, you know,
anytime that I did get outside my four walls of like comfort foods and things that were on my list
of, you know, these are okay to eat. Um, I was terrified. No one would know it on the outside,
but like I'd go out for dinner and it was just this uncontrolled, like it was like I had no
control to slow down my eating. So I ate so extremely fast. Um, and so many of my friends
as adults, like I have said to me, yeah, you really eat fast, but I've noticed a massive change,
you know, for the last few years, this is certainly for like longer term friends,
but you know, that habit stuck around. So I'd eat extremely quickly and I would almost binge eat.
And then I would usually order something else and take it home with the idea that I was going
to have it, you know, tomorrow. Um, and I'll, you know, portion it out appropriately. Um, but again,
because of that extreme restrictive behavior, it just meant I'd go home and then binge eat more.
And it was absolutely spiraled out of control. And I think again, my stress response at that
time, the only way I knew how to manage stress was to eat. And it completely, um, countered like
the goals that I had for my sport and my training. So yeah, it was hard. So how were you, um, able,
well, actually there's, let me start with a different question. What was the wake up call?
What was the, um, event or set of events that led you to think I have to do something different. And
it's, it sounds like I'm going to have to take therapy very seriously. Yeah, absolutely. So
it wasn't until I got to probably about age 25 at that point, I had moved from, um,
state. So I finished my schooling in, uh, Melbourne, moved to Gold Coast where I opened my own
business. So I actually already had my business in Melbourne, but you know, I basically was starting
from scratch. So a new clinical practice. Um, and then also, uh, working, I guess 50% of my work week
was also in-person training. Um, cause at that point I'd discovered like the love for resistance
training and I wanted to be able to incorporate those two things together. So, um, my business
was going crazy, like busy, busy, busy, busy. Um, I just had some success in the bodybuilding space
and I got to the point where my anxiety was so hard and I, I didn't even know what anxiety was.
Like I'd never had, I didn't, wasn't able to identify or put a word with the feeling that I
had just like, it sounds so silly to think about it now because of course it was anxiety,
but like I couldn't even open my laptop. Um, because I was so stressed at the amount of work
that I knew I had to do. So I actually got to a point in business where I was experiencing
some burnout and I took myself to a therapist at that point. Um, so that kind of started it. And
then I ended up having to, uh, admit myself to like a rehab. So I traveled to back to Melbourne
to a very well-known like rehabilitation therapies, uh, location in like country Victoria.
And it was, um, I guess incorporated, um, I guess, counseling, uh, yoga practices, different
relaxation, um, type techniques. And then, um, one of the owners, I guess would kind of come and
work through just different nutrition things with you. And this was specifically for people
with eating disorders. Yes. And how long did you commit to go to this place? So I, I was there for
seven days. Um, so it was pretty short, but it was very intense. Like you had a schedule mapped out
from the minute you woke up to the moment you went to bed. So, and how difficult was that for you to
make the decision to shut down work for seven days? Terrifying. Um, I, I remember calling my mom
actually, and she was bawling. And I, I, we rarely spoke, um, not because, you know, we didn't have
a better relationship as adults, but I think we just kind of grew apart. So calling her and, uh,
I guess she knows like, if I'm going to ring my mom, there's probably something wrong. Um, yeah,
I was just mortified because I was so stressed about like losing hours work. Cause I was so
passionate about, you know, I put my clients, but you know, I just couldn't bring myself to do it.
But you know, she said, look, financially you're going to be okay. Like just take, just take a week.
You know, it doesn't have to be exorbitant. The therapy was quite expensive, but, um, it was very
well worth it. I'm going through this, you know, I haven't really resolved my eating disorder.
I'm at business burnout stress. So it was just, to me, it was like overwhelming. And I think at that
point again was the second time in my life where I felt, um, some of those suicidal thoughts. I don't
think that, um, I kind of talked with my therapist and she'd said, well, do we need to bake, correct you?
And I was like, no, no, I think I'll work through this, but it's the first time that I felt this,
um, like hopeless. So how much of an impact did that seven day, um, inpatient, uh, rehab have on you?
Not as much as I would have hoped. Um, I think to think that any, anything, you know, that that's,
that's that short in duration is going to cure you is very foolish, but it opened my eyes to
the benefits of, um, you know, relaxation, meditation, um, and the value of communication
and being transparent and open. And that was not a behavior that I was moved at. Um, for that 10
year period prior, I was very closed off, very reserved, didn't share very many things at all.
I was very private. Um, so I think I saw the value in, you know, what it's like to kind of
work through issues rather than suppress them. Um, and once I finally moved to America, uh,
I got myself straight into weekly therapy. So I have had therapy sessions every week since 2016.
I've probably missed, I dunno, maybe 20 weeks just through travel and business. So it got me on
the right path. And then what were sort of the breakthroughs that occurred with that type of
much more consistent therapy? So I think number one, it made me accountable and it made me speak,
made me talk, um, and helped me kind of reflect back on, you know, my past, which I'd never done.
I had never given two thoughts about my upbringing. Um, I feel like now it's all I talk about,
it all I think about, but so much of what I experienced was bottled up in, you know,
the past traumas and, uh, those, those different styles of communication. So I think gaining an
appreciation and understanding for why I felt the way that I did was incredibly valuable. It was
like, Oh, I've now got some data. At least it made sense to me. And then I think we started kind
of discussing, you know, where are the dysfunctions in these beliefs? Let's start picking up these,
um, you know, different sets of thoughts that you have, um, and let's deconstruct them and how might
these look different for a healthy mind. And through so much self-development reading,
also finding myself spiritually, which is another major part of this piece, uh, the story, um,
it really helped me to understand that I was enough as a human, despite my, um, accolades
in sporting accomplishments and that like I'm loved and I don't need to keep proving myself
to, you know, all the people in my life. And it was like this huge weight to lift it off my shoulders.
Part of that was, um, one of our staff, um, invited me to go to church one day and I'd only been to
church once when I was young, uh, with a boyfriend. His family were a Christian. So my experience with
like religion was not negative. I'd say I grew up like, um, agnostic. So I don't think my parents were
anti, you know, religion, but they certainly didn't hold any beliefs of their own and it was not
something we discussed. So going to church and this was a non-denominational church, very progressive.
The pastor was just like incredible. And every message every week I kept going back. Um, and I
was like, wow, this is so relatable. There's so many things out of the Bible that like, it's just
so good. It's like such a good information. It was like, this is what I've been missing my whole life
because I felt for a long time that I didn't have purpose. And part of my decision to keep moving
and traveling was to feel like what's missing. Maybe it'll be here or maybe if I go to this
country, you know, the people will be different and I'll resonate with them better. Um, but it
was something in here that was missing and yeah, going to church and reading it just, that was
probably the one thing that changed my life. Um, and since then I have never been happier. Sorry.
So I think there's sort of two things that are interesting in the story that I think are, are
important and illustrative for, for anybody struggling with anything. And one is that the
improvements didn't happen quickly and that it's kind of nonlinear. So, you know, you, I, I'm
actually struck by the fact that, uh, you know, you said, look, I did this seven day intensive
thing and it helped, but it didn't help as much as maybe I wanted it to. Um, but I think the
encouraging point is here, uh, you kept sort of at it, right? You know, it was, you know,
it would be years before you would find yourself in daily or weekly therapy. Um, I guess the other
thing is, uh, when I think of my, uh, addictions and struggles, I think like any addict, um,
let's just pick alcohol cause it's an easy one for people to identify with externally.
You know, they say that an alcoholic is always an alcoholic. It's just a question of,
if you're in recovery or not, but if, if, if an alcoholic commits to no longer drinking,
they still need to be mindful of their behaviors and still need to be cognizant of the fact that
they can slip back into drinking. Yes. And that doesn't mean they can't be around people who are
drinking, but they have to understand themselves and understand those limits. Um, that's certainly
going to be true for me for the rest of my life. I know what my addictions are and I, and I, I know
how they need to be managed and they're always there. So do you feel that way as well?
Absolutely. So I think there is this idea that you can completely recover and I don't think that
anybody truly recovers. Like you said, once an addict, always an addict, you're in recovery,
you were not recovered. Yes. Now I think with something like that, you know, there's the
physiological, you know, symptoms that you need to manage as you come out of that, you know, you've
got a chemical dependence, but for something that is psychological, um, you know, there's
obviously chemical imbalances in some, um, in some of these conditions, but I think there's also
a strong need for your desire to, to change and to improve. So I think it wasn't until like I had
kind of committed to myself and said, you are never going to purge again. And I remember,
and I actually have started writing a book about this actually, uh, which will be hopefully very
helpful for a lot of people that are going through the same kind of thing. But yeah, I remember
sitting on my bathroom floor one day, um, balling, just like emotionally exhausted, physically
exhausted. And it was during a contest prep. Um, you know, the, the most difficult thing that one
could probably ever attempt to do, um, which is get extremely lean and try and control your body,
which wants to control you essentially. Um, and I remember just saying like, you're not going to
do this anymore. And I think as soon as I really believed that, like I didn't want to purge anymore.
I was exhausted. Um, that's when things started to change. And I think the more I talked about
that with my therapist, um, where I no longer had a compensatory mechanism, I wasn't going to let my
do myself do that. And I also wasn't going to try and overcompensate with activity because that was
something else that I would do. If I didn't purge, I would feel so restless and anxious and guilty if
I didn't go and do a, you know, a 10 kilometer run because I'd work out, I came, well, I probably
ate this many calories in that purge. And then really I've got no idea because I threw some of
it up. And it was just this horrible, like sickening feeling. Um, it's hard to talk about really. It's
kind of gross, but you know, once, once I kind of didn't have these outlets anymore, it forced me to
get real with my intention for eating. It forced me to become mindful. It forced me to slow down
and you know, become present with my meals and to really like listen to what my body was saying.
And that was really hard because, you know, of course, if you've restrained from, you know,
certain food, alcohol, drugs for a long period of time, all you do is think about that thing.
Right. So for me, like I'd restricted, like I would allow myself a little bit of ice cream,
um, until I learned about flexible dining, of course. And then that, that changes a lot of
things, but that's another story. But like, you know, I'd restricted cookies and you know,
just nice fun cereals, like normal foods. And I just couldn't control myself around them anymore.
So that was so difficult because I just felt like I was going crazy. I'm like,
what is wrong with me? I remember saying to my therapist, like couple of years into therapy,
why do I still want to eat the entire type of ice cream? I feel like I can't just make myself
one serving. I want to eat the whole thing. And she's like, well, Holly, like you've restricted
this for 10 years. Like why, what makes you think that you're going to cure this, um, desire
overnight when it's been something that you've built a habit that's ingrained over, you know,
your lifetime with this disorder. So I think once I started having a little bit more compassion
for myself and, you know, forgiveness and reducing the amount of judgment that I had
for myself as a human, like you're, you're a screw up. You're what's wrong with you. You know,
once I started to be kinder to mess myself, that was when I started to make a little bit more
progress. And I hated the outcome at that initial, like going through that initial trans, um,
transformation, because it meant I gained so much weight, so much weight. And at this point,
I hadn't really tackled the underlying cause either. Like the, the why, which was, I felt like
my body need, that was the thing that would give me value. So I'm trying to do this just to stop
the binging and the purging. So for me to see my body weight, you know, exceed like 70 kilograms,
like right now I sit at about 63 kilos. Um, so to get to like 75 kilos at the peak of my recovery
was the most uncomfortable I think I've ever been. And I think anybody that struggled with body weight,
you know, weight gain, uh, can appreciate that feeling. And I just had to do it. Um,
So meaning like, was the, was the therapeutic instruction, like you need to sit in the
discomfort of this weight gain? Yep. Um, that was one of the first strategies that I had to work
through for my anxiety. At this point, I'd also developed a social anxiety. It was, it was just
like this, the lid had been taken off and all these things were like, you know, immersing themselves
in front of me and I, I had no idea how to manage them. So yeah, learning to sit with that discomfort,
um, and be okay with that. So now like part of that process was discussing the feelings
and that was really when we started to identify, okay, what are the feelings that you have now
that you've gained weight? And it of course led to, uh, I feel horrible. I'm disgusting. This is
so unhealthy. Um, you know, I hate myself, like just such horrible words, um, to describe myself.
And you know, I think one of the things that at the time the therapist had said was,
what would you say to a client? Cause at this time, like I'm practicing dietitian. I've been
a dietitian for like 10 plus years. So, you know, I really had to go, okay, what would I say to my
clients if they said that? So I had to start treating myself like I would my clients and
yeah, there was a big shift then in, you know, just that, like I said, compassion, um, that I
had for myself. So yeah, I think. So how did that work? I think that's a wonderful test. I call it
the Rick Elias test. He's a friend of mine who describes it, uh, even one step further, which is
what would you say to your best friend if they were saying these things, if they were in this
situation and it's amazing how much it totally changes and softens the tone. It really does.
Yeah. I think, um, you know, the first thing that springs to mind was, um, but what about your
physical appearance? Um, well, what does our friendship have to do with your physical appearance
if it was a friend and nothing, it, it was like, I don't have any like logical reasoning for believing
this to be true. Um, and so many people like clients would say, Oh, you know, I've got this
holiday, um, catching up with some friends that I haven't seen in a long time. We've got this,
you know, it's always a wedding or some kind of, you know, special event where
they feel the need to look a certain way. And I said, do you think you would have been invited
if you were, um, you know, 10 kilos heavier and like people are like, yeah, of course. I'm like,
those relationships aren't built on your aesthetic. It is built on your, you know, your character.
There's obviously something admirable that people like about you that has nothing to do with your,
you know, appearance. Uh, it's a common interest, you know, the ability to connect over things and,
maybe your sense of humor, like, you know, insert whatever characteristic it is.
And I think when I started kind of talking to myself in that way, I was like, Oh yeah,
I actually still can have fun on the weekends. Um, and it has nothing to do with my,
the weight on the scale or my body fat percentage. So
part of what is so interesting about your story makes it so hard to reconcile, which is,
um, everything we just talked about, which then co-exists with one of your passions,
which is bodybuilding, which, you know, seems to me to be this single activity that would most
raise the risk of the one thing you're trying to prevent. Right. I mean, I guess if you were a jockey,
or a gymnast that might be close on the list as well, but, but even those entities wear more
clothing than a bikini. So, so you've, you've chosen to have this hobby outside of your job,
but it's really related to your job, right? I mean, it's in many ways, it's the pinnacle of exercise
and nutrition as it pertains to aesthetics. And you've also chosen to do it in the drug free
category. So you, you don't get to rely on any additional biochemistry. You have to do this
just through training and nutrition. Um, there's an, I don't know if irony is the word, but, but,
but there's something in there that's worth exploring. And I, I imagine this has come up
repeatedly with your therapist. Absolutely. So yeah, it's, um, it's been a really long journey.
And there was a point just a few years ago where I really questioned my decisions to remain a coach
and to be in the, you know, nutrition and exercise space, um, because of the hypocrisy that I felt
with, you know, what I was coaching on. So again, I think I can say that for the first 10 years of my
practice, I had no desire to change my beliefs. I believed truly, um, from the bottom of my heart,
that in order for me to be successful in business, to, um, you know, support others the best that I
possibly could and to be taken seriously in an industry that is largely, you know, dominated by
males. Um, I needed to not only talk the talk, but walk the walk. So I never addressed that belief.
I believe that I needed to be lean. So I never did anything about it. I felt uncomfortable that
whole time. Like the psychological stress that I had. Can you by the way, give me some examples on
this for, I mean, I don't, what body fat are you at when you're on stage? Um, it depends. So I
compete in, I have competed in figure for IFBB, which is, um, a non drug tested Federation. Um,
and I have since moved away from that. Um, but for those girls, you're probably looking at just on 10%
body fat. They're extremely lean. Um, and now that the division that I competed in, which is the
fitness category and it's for a different Federation, it's a slightly, um, smaller body,
but still very, um, muscular and very lean. Um, I probably get down to about, you know,
10 or 11% body fat. And just to make sure I understand at 10 to 11% body fat, does your
menstrual cycle still continue? So for majority of my competition history and competing life,
yes, it would completely stop. Uh, in fact, for about five years, I did not have a period.
And that was even with the return of, you know, calories back to a normal amount,
even with the return of body fat, you know, back to, you know, normal healthy levels. Um,
I think it was just the years of, uh, you know, binging and purging.
I mean, think about just from an evolutionary standpoint, what that's telling you that is
telling you that again, evolution has one purpose for you and it's saying you are not even fit
enough to do this. Yep. Yeah. And I mean, a lot of people ask like, is it a healthy sport and is it,
you know, dangerous to get that, that lean? And I would say, well, it kind of depends because,
you know, I know there are a lot of females that particularly in that, you know, line of work,
if you're going to call yourself a professional in the bodybuilding space, they don't have the desire
for, you know, families. So fertility isn't even an issue. Yeah. No. And I'm making no judgment
about that. I'm just thinking about it from an evolutionary standpoint. Absolutely. It's
basically saying the one thing you were put on this earth to do evolution is putting the brakes
on because it's basically saying you don't have enough excess energy to care for another life,
to carry another life to term. Absolutely. Um, it's, it's really scary. So you, you, there's,
there's no, no doubts about it. Um, it's not a great thing for our, you know, for females to
be that lean, we're not meant to be that lean. Um, and I think unfortunately, you know, it's
just something that has grown with, you know, the changes in times, society shift. I think there's
been a lot of segue and improvements with, you know, the ideals for females. I think it used to
be extremely slim. You know, you think about the really tall models, you know, runway models that
used to be like the, the look that everyone wanted to go for. And I'm actually really happy
that I think we're seeing a shift just with the general population to, um, you know, empowering
females with resistance training and strength training. Um, because to me, that is far more
beneficial than, you know, starving and, you know, being a bean bean pole. So I think there's,
that's promising, but for whatever reason, we seem to kind of find ourselves back at this
extremism, um, you know, ideal and, you know, extra extremely lean women are simply not healthy.
Now, do all women lose their menstrual cycle when they compete? Um, no, I've had probably a 50 50,
um, with the competitors that I've worked with that still have normal, um, menstrual cycle, or
it may not stop, but it becomes, you know, irregular. It's, um, all over the place. In fact,
my last competition, I was actually getting a cycle like every two weeks for about eight,
probably 16 weeks of a contest prep, which was really bizarre. Um, but that was after also not
having had a period. So it took me a few years to recover my period, um, through, you know, the,
the process of reverse dieting, the recovery diet, um, and allowing myself to gain some body fat and
have an off season where I, you know, got an adequate amount of calories and was able to fuel
my body to a point where, you know, my hormones are working and functioning as they should. Um,
but yeah, then the other 50% of people do completely lose it. So how do you,
how do you now think about this? Right? If you, if you could go back in time and talk to yourself,
uh, when you were 18 years old, would you, would you say to Holly, then, you know,
just stay away from the fitness industry, stay away from bodybuilding, uh, get your degree in,
you know, economics or business, you know, something like that. Like, do you think that
even though where you've ended up now seems like you're on a path to recovery.
Do you feel that you were just flying too close to the sun all of this time?
Yeah. So I have asked myself this question a lot. Um, and people will say, you know,
what would you do differently? I think that if you spend an equal amount of time working on
your mental health and that is, you know, coupled with, you know, diet and exercise,
I believe because I'm in this place right now where, wherever I am, uh, along the spectrum
of body fat, um, wherever I am, you know, in my competition on season off season, um,
I could truly say that I am good, like with myself, wherever I am, the things that will limit me from,
you know, getting to the point like, like obesity or like an unhealthy body weight, um, would
probably be like, again, extreme habits, like taking anything to the, um, to the limits where,
you know, you're just completely careless with your food and careless with exercise and you
just don't have any interest. So I don't think I would ever like allow myself to get to that place
because it just wouldn't feel good anymore. Like I try to really, uh, be conscious of, okay, what,
what leads to you, you know, number one, feeling happy. Um, and then also what's good for your body.
How do you feel best? Where do you perform best? Um, how do I think and function best? So,
you know, outside of that, I just, I feel like you can be in this space, but I know a lot of people
are not doing the work that is required to, um, shift their why. Because I think that's really
important for people that are moving into the bodybuilding space. So I want to just kind of walk
through, let's say your most recent contest. You just had a contest a couple of weeks ago, right?
Um, so I want to walk through the training and the nutrition for the entire prep. So let's just
say six months leading up to the contest. So kind of a bulking building phase and then a cutting
phase and then a post phase or a recovery diet phase. Um, and even though in your case,
the stakes are really high, it's a professional bodybuilding competition at the highest level,
right? It's a world Federation, but for someone listening to this, it could be like their wedding.
Right. It's like, you know, a woman who wants to look her best at her wedding, um, and might
acknowledge that like she, it's going to not be the most sustainable she can be, but wants to do
it in a way that's not harmful. So, um, let's go back as far as we need to six months, nine months
a year. What is the training? How do you periodize it? What are the principles of nutrition? Um,
and everything I want to understand what the cutting phase looks like. And I want to know
what this, this, cause my wife was telling me, cause you guys were talking about this,
the, the recovery phase is also very important. How you come out of the competition without doing
what would be natural, given that you're starving is just to go, you know, go wild. So let's go back
to the beginning. Uh, it's time to start adding muscle and, uh, and bulking up.
Yeah. So I think, well, first and foremost, I'd say majority of the people that, you know,
our team work with are just gen pop. You know, they're not, not quite as, uh, extreme or high
up in like the professional athletes status status that I am. Um, but the wonderful thing is that
the processes are honestly no different. The only true difference between somebody that is,
you know, a professional athlete, um, versus your stay at home mom who wants to, you know,
look good for, you know, they've got a girl's trip coming up or something, you know, next year or
wedding, like you said, um, would be the extreme or the, the degree to which we take these processes.
So for most people, when we first start, um, I kind of want to have an idea about like,
what's their goal? Uh, what do you like ideally want to look like, or sometimes there's health,
you know, health, um, goals as well. But I will say the majority of people that come to us are
also looking to, or primarily wanting to change their physique. So we need to get a good
understanding of what, what that looks like, because a lot of, a lot of women will say,
Hey, you know, I'm down for this resistance training that you're talking about, but I'm
terrified of getting, you know, too bulky. Um, and that is going like how we approach this whole
thing comes down to the individual's definition of like, what's bulky look like to you. Yeah.
What percentage of clients that you guys have look at you and say, I don't want to look like you.
That's too much muscle. So I would say that, uh, most of my clients, 90% of my clients,
um, like this ideal, I think most people would say, yeah, I am not too bulky. Holly, you look great.
I have had some people like, Nope, your quads are way too big. Nope. I want to fit in my jeans or,
you know, something like that. But for the most part, um, like my physique, like that fitness
looking fitness model physique is something that most women, um, I might be generalizing, um, but
aspire to, but again, it depends, you know, if I'm talking to an endurance athlete versus somebody
that, um, you know, has come from a sporty background and they're trying to do something
that's very, you know, anaerobic might be a different, um, uh, physique ideal. Cause that
would not be beneficial for their sport. But, um, we want to, we want to identify that first. So we
go through, you know, it's very unlikely that women will get to the point where they look like a
female bodybuilder. Like these things don't happen naturally. Like that, those bodybuilders,
like that, that physique, that look, um, is not obtained without performance enhancing drugs.
Um, my physique and great genetics and it's extreme training, personality,
perfect nutrition. Yeah. We call it the myth of accidental muscle. Yeah. And I still, you still
have to admire those people to spite them being on, it's not easy. Like it's still not easy, but
you know, they've got some support. So for me, like if someone was looking to make change their
physique to, um, you know, this level of muscularity, um, that's still taken me like seven years of
very consistent nutrition and training. Um, where, you know, I've, I have probably missed less than,
you know, 10 weeks a year of training. Like, and I have been like that for 10 years.
So you're not going to accidentally grow muscle like this, even without, you know,
some serious consistency. And how do you help them identify the actual goals? I think this is
an important state. So when a, when a, when a client, and I just want to, I'm going to use
a female example here and focus that. So, so if, if she comes in and says, look, I'm getting
married next summer and I want to look my best, is that not specific enough, right? You want to say,
well, right now you weigh this much and your body fat is this a year from now. Do you want to weigh
this much and have your body fat be this? I mean, what degree of granularity do you need to set the
goal to, to, to set the path? Absolutely. So I am pretty granular compared to some of even our other
coaches. I think all of our processes are slightly different. I guess the principles at the end of
the day are the same. Um, but I'll often say like, is there somebody that you follow on social media
or that you've seen in magazines that you like really like their physique just to help me get
a better understanding? Um, because it does really vary. And sometimes I've been very shocked. I'm
like, Oh, okay. All right. I actually don't really need to do a whole lot of, you know, building for
this individual, um, you know, based on where they currently are. So that building phase may not even,
you know, be part of the equation. So, uh, that we also have a look at their scale weight and their
current body fat percentages, which will, um, preferentially have them send us through DEXA.
We take a look at all their biomarkers, that type of thing. Um, and then from there, I kind of plot
a bit of a trajectory. So if they do need to gain, you know, a significant amount of muscle in that
12 months time, um, I will basically map out, um, you know, week for week using some equations,
like, okay, this is basically how many weeks of building we would need to do as a natural,
like drug-free person. And tell me what you believe the limits are for women. So, uh, it's going to be
a little bit lower than males. And part of that is just, you know, due to their ability to, you know,
build more muscle mass and, um, I guess, sex differences and that type of thing. But we can
still do a lot of, like a lot of positive work in an off season. So in an eight week period,
I was actually looking at a study very recently, um, for natural athletes, we're able to acquire
somewhere just under the amount of one kilogram of fat free mass. So fat free mass isn't just
skeletal tissue. We've got to take into consideration, you know, the increases in, um, you know, water
mass increases in all of these other things. So that's my record, by the way, in the one year I
dedicated to the most improvement was 13 pounds in 12 months of fat free mass. So it's about
a kilo per eight weeks. Yep. That sounds, that sounds dead on. And you're saying that's true
for men and women. Yeah. Well, again, it depends on, you know, the individual, how, how much time
are they willing to invest in this goal? Where is it on their priority list? You know, it really
comes down to their training volumes. How well are you going to adhere to your diet? How are you
going to adhere to these other variables that all impact, you know, your rates of muscle gain? So do
you know what the largest amount of lean mass you've put on in a year has been? So I haven't done it
over 12 months. Um, but I do know that between two competitions, one at the beginning of the year,
uh, one towards the end or last quarter, uh, I put on about six kilograms. So that's more,
that's like 14 pounds of lean tissue. So it was a lot. And that was me going into the
university of South Florida. We were doing my, um, uh, BMR testing. I did muscle thickness testing.
So this was all, you know, fairly, um, accurate methods of determining like hypertrophy. So that
was, that blew my mind. But again, I would say I've put on muscle very easily, like, um, which,
you know, maybe there's a genetic component to that, but I'm also very like regimented with my
training and the period of time when that happened, I was very, very fluffy. I was very
fluffy. I allowed myself to put on a lot of body fat. Um, Oh yeah. So I want to ask you about that.
So in the, with the six kilos of lean tissue, how much fat tissue came with it? Um, six kilos,
like for me, in that particular episode for you. Oh goodness. Um, it was probably about, uh,
oh, 30% on top of. So yeah, if I had six pounds, so two pounds, two kilos, two kilos of fat. Exactly.
Okay. Yep. So basically your body fat probably went up a little bit. Yeah. As you put on a lot
more lean mass. I'd say I probably went up by about 30%. So if I started this build, um, at,
you know, 12% after a show, I got up to 19%. So actually it's more than that. I remember being
19% body fat at the end of that build. So yeah, that's, that's kind of amazing Holly that, that
to me, if a guy made that change, that would be considered impressive drug-free so that a woman
could do that. Um, and again, let's just posit that you have great genetics, but it gives, it gives us,
it gives us a range that there are women with lesser genetics who might be able to do half of
that in a year. They might be able to put on three kilos in a year, which is still seven pounds.
And I think I also have to be very, you know, transparent about this. So I was in a position
too, where my ability to kind of step back from my other obligations and priorities, um, has been
like fair, I'm not going to say easily facilitated, but you're doing this as your job. Yes. Right. So,
you know, I remember and recall through that training block I had programmed,
you know, progressively overloading, like my first week of a, um, as a cycle might've been
three working sets of everything on my list. And I might've had six or seven exercises by that
sixth week of training, I would be pushing like five working hard sets, high training,
intensity, you know, RPEs eight nines of like my first three exercises and then four of everything
else. Like the volume I was getting up to was insane. So talk to me about hours in gym per day
in the beginning of the build phase versus the end of the build phase. I hit it hard
pretty quick, pretty early. Um, I also had a bit more of a reactive style to deloads. Normally I
would plan intentional deloads. The whole purpose of that build was to get as much muscle on me as
I could in a very short timeframe. So, um, the volume probably went up by about 50% within the
first, you know, 12 weeks. Um, and then it just continued to grow. So, uh, the time that it would
take me varied from maybe 90 minutes in like the earlier part of that build phase, um, all the way
up to two, two and a half hours daily. And I was doing five sessions a week at that point. So it
was a big commitment. And then were you doing any cardio at that time? Minimal. I would just hit a
daily step target, um, with about 10,000 steps and cardio was not even part of the equation. Got it.
So averaging to up to two and a half hours a day in the gym, five days a week. So again, we're
talking about good genetics coupled with 15 hours, a lot of training. Um, some of the people
listening to this podcast, I'm guessing will be more women than men. Uh, won't be as familiar with
RPE. Do you mind explaining to people what that is? Cause it's going to be an important concept as
we talk about resistance training. Yeah, absolutely. So RPE, uh, is or stands for a rate of perceived
exertion. So it's a measure of training intensity and training intensity is one of the principles
that need to be, uh, increased over your, um, training lifespan in order to facilitate hypertrophy.
So, uh, I guess I can reflect back on my early training days and I didn't even have a training
RPE. There was no training intensity. Um, you know, there's, I guess another one that we can
refer to, which we use on our workout builder programs is the RIR, which is repetitions in
reserve. So you're basically an IRR, RIR of three would mean that you've got three repetitions in
reserve all the way up to an IRR of zero, you're hitting failure. So whatever weight or load you
select for your lift, you are going to your drop essentially. So my training, when I first started
lifting, um, incorrectly, um, was so low, like I never challenged myself. Uh, and again, I know that
we wanted to talk today about our bodybuilding versus powerlifting and how they may be beneficial
for, you know, females. Um, I am so grateful for the time that I spent powerlifting because
that style of training, um, kind of threw me into understanding training intensity and what my true
strength was. So there was a lot of carryover to, you know, how quickly I was able to, um, you know,
select weights for my bodybuilding style of workouts. Um, and that advanced me so quickly.
So just to make sure I understand you're saying when you were younger and you were doing fitness
training and even training for track and field, you were never pushing yourself in the weight room.
Your art, your, your RPE was below five. Your RIR was above five. Yep, absolutely. Yeah. We,
and we were never even given a training intensity. It was just do three sets of 12.
Yeah. So right now, when you say in these, in this building phase, when you say RPE eight,
meaning you stopped and you had two in the tank, um, you could have potentially squeezed out two
more. And you said, so if you're doing RPE eight to nine, these are near failure sets all the way
through. Yep, absolutely. Focus on, uh, how would you split those five days? Was it a leg day,
a push pull day? How are you splitting those days? Yeah. So look, I think, um, if we all look at how
I kind of set up a training program, there are so many ways that you can go about this. Um, and,
but they all do need to follow, you know, the principles of hypertrophy. And I guess number
one is, you know, exercise specificity. We need to make making sure that we're training in such a
way or a modality that he's going to have the desired outcome. So obviously building muscle
and then choosing muscle groups that you want to build during that timeframe. So for me, that
looks like a group, glute hypertrophy. Um, that's kind of the main area that most women, or at least
those that I'm experienced in working with, uh, really want to improve, um, because that has a
lot of benefits for many things from normal day-to-day activities, bending down, squatting, um,
through to, you know, improve strength across all sports, jumping, da, da, da, da, da, da. You know,
there's so many benefits. So, um, glute hypertrophy took up a big part of my training volume. Um,
shoulder hypertrophy was another one that I really, uh, focused a lot of my training volume on to kind
of create the, um, you know, the capped shoulders and the illusion of a narrower rate for waste.
Um, so thinking back to that build, most of the training that I was doing was lower body. So I
actually did four lower body sessions, believe it or not per week. And then one upper body session.
So it sounds crazy. Yeah. It does sound crazy. And those four lower body sessions,
were you still dividing the legs up or were you hitting the same muscles of the legs four days?
So, uh, I think my programs are varied and again, I would kind of triage, um, to kind of give my body
the recovery that it needed. And again, it was very reactive style of deload. So I would start by,
I guess Monday might be spread out by doing quad hamstring, glute, carve, um, quad hamstring.
And then that might be that workout. Uh, I may have a second day, which looks like, uh, glute
hamstring quad, or I would prioritize again, the muscle groups that I knew I wanted to build.
So, uh, then I would have a rest day because back to back two days of leg days, pretty intense.
Um, and then I would probably incorporate an upper body session to again, a second day of
complete rest from my legs. And then I would finish out the week by doing like a Thursday session,
lower body two days off, come back in train on a Sunday, another lower body session. So
there was a lot of training volume. And I just want to say that I would never do that for somebody
that was brand new to training. Um, that volume would be radically reduced. Okay. So what would
it look like for a person who has some exercise background, like they, they go to, you know,
orange theory fitness twice a week and they, you know, they're, they're a relatively active person,
but they don't have any powerlifting experience and they've, they don't know the difference between
RPE nine and RPE five. Right. So they're not, they're not there. How would you, but they still
have this ambition of building. They want to put on five pounds of muscle in the next year
and lose three pounds of fat. Like that's the physique goal.
Yeah. So first and foremost, I would say like, again, if this is like literal, literal, literal
practical takeaways, I would say number one, find somebody that's evidence-based first and foremost,
ideally find somebody that can also that's evidence-based, be with you in a gym setting.
They do one-on-one training because there is so much value and knowledge to be learned just one-on-one
spending time with someone that's got more knowledge than you in that space, um, developing
optimal training techniques, developing the right movement pathways. And boy, I have seen some doozies,
you know, clients are being trained in the gym by someone that has no idea how to squat or deadlift.
So another little plus if you can find somebody that does powerlifting or has done
bodybuilding and powerlifting. Um, I think that is like a little golden egg. They, there's not
a lot of these people out there, but, um, incorporating that evidence-based approach with,
um, experience with women and powerlifting and bodybuilding. That's like the perfect ideal.
And experience with women because of what difference specifically? Is it anatomic
differences in movements or is it just the assumption that women are coming in with lower
training volume? No, I think, look, there's plenty of men out there that can do that as well,
but I think you've got to connect with the person that you're working with. And I think
now if you've got a male that's extremely experienced, um, you know, in all of those
things, then of course, I may, I may all can be great, but I think, um, having gone through
different body image issues, having that understanding and appreciation for maybe
body dysmorphia, uh, having an appreciation for menstrual cycle, you know, I think men that are in
fitness industry, and I don't want to generalize because I know there's a lot of really intelligent
guys out there, but there isn't a lot of work like just the general personal trainer, um, and the
amount of time that they spend, you know, learning about the reproductive system and how
that can impact strength and, you know, subj- subjective performance and, um, you know,
the implications that that can have on your mood, your psychological state, and just the plethora of
like what being a woman encompasses. I just think that women tend to do better with female trainers,
but again, it's, it's harder to come by. So that's what I mean by that. So what would you
design for a client in that situation? So let's just make the, I'm just gonna make it even harder.
This is a woman who wants to gain five pounds of muscle and lose five pounds of fat in a year.
In other words, they want to weigh, they're not, they're fine weighing the same amount next year,
but the change in body composition is going to be dramatic. Yeah, absolutely. Okay. So first and
foremost, I would be looking at, okay, what realistically can we gain in, you know, an
eight month timeframe? So that's the period of time you want to build up. Yes, absolutely. So
first off from a program design standpoint, we would want to start with a fairly low training
volume if this is somebody that has not, um, you know, done a whole lot of resistance training.
So we would start by selecting the muscle groups and the exercises that target the areas they want
to build. Um, and we would progressively overload that, um, training. So it might start with, you
know, one working set for every exercise in week one. That little. Yep. That little. So, uh, typically
I would start with a program that is like 40 minutes maximum, 30 or 40 minutes maximum.
How many warmup sets to get to that working set? Typically, probably one or two. Um, and part of
that would also be just helping with the demonstration of technique and kind of getting
that movement pattern. And what would be the RPE of the one working set? Starting off like an RPE
six or seven in a week one set of 10, but weighted to an RPE of six or seven. Yep, exactly. Which
again, just for the person listening means you're going to do 10 reps of this thing. But if, if
your life depended on it, you could get 13 or 14. Exactly. Yep. And just one set. Yep. So you
might start with three days a week. It's, and again, we've got to incorporate the, uh, person's,
uh, ability to sacrifice time for their training. So, and so the other thing I'm taking away from
this Holly, cause I wouldn't have thought of this. So I'm glad I'm asking this question.
It's better that she does one set of leg extension, one set of leg curl, one set of
single leg RDL, one set of leg press, do, do, do, do, do, do, instead of just five sets of leg press.
Yep. Yeah. And I think part of that as well, um, it's teaching her enough. It's giving her
the education on this so that you can now build on that. Yeah, absolutely. Well, you're learning
what muscle, uh, what exercises target certain muscle groups and you're also minimuming the,
minimizing the risk of them, uh, getting injured or ending up with extreme, you know, delayed onset
muscle soreness. Um, the last thing that you want to do is put together a program that is
too difficult and the next day they can't even walk. Like how, how well is somebody going to,
um, or likely to comply with that program? You know, thereafter, they've had that level of pain,
um, from a session, it's going to be really low. So we want to have good adherence from the get-go.
So, and it's also, I guess more interesting, like it's sort of the diversity of the program.
Exercise diversity. And I think women, um, definitely, well, men and women as well,
but I think males are probably happy to do a lot more repetitive type training, um, you know,
to get to the end result. Females, we like a little bit of diversity. So how many days a week are you
doing this and are you mixing upper and lower body on the same day at the beginning? It doesn't really
matter again, the primary driver of what, um, or how I would put together that workout would really
be like training volumes. So whether or not you do, you know, lower body and an upper body or whether
you do a full body training session, it doesn't really matter. Um, I would probably be deferring
to what's your history like, what's your experience? What do you like doing? Because on paper, it
probably doesn't really matter that much. What's more important is that I can get you to stick to
this. So, so how many weeks are you in that phase? Yep. So typically I will write a mesocycle for
somewhere between four and six weeks. So again, my decision for four weeks versus six weeks is
the person's ability to adhere to the same program for that amount of time.
I know for me, when I first started, I, if I had to do the same program for more than two or three
weeks, I was like, this is so boring. Like as if it's even working, let's change it up. So again,
there's a lot of personal preference, you know, when it comes to putting those programs together.
So I personally write my programs for six weeks. I can handle anything for six weeks. It's repetitive,
but you've got, you know, maybe three or four, maybe five programs again, depending on the levels
of the individual's experience levels. So you've got quite a bit of exercise diversity, you know,
within a seven day period. So tell me some of the lower body exercises you would have
a relative newbie, but not a total novice do you would cycle through what for lower body?
I think my favorites for compound lists are always going to be your typical power lifting
movement. So I always try to incorporate some kind of squat or hinging variation or deadlift.
So the degree of flexibility just with those two exercises alone is enormous. Like you can do
heels, elevated squats, spiff machine squats, box squats, pause squats, and as in squats,
like there's so many variations, but what do you, so if you have a woman who's never done anything,
basics, and that's what you're going to start with like a goblet squat or a back squat to a box or
yep, absolutely. Body weight squat would be actually the first thing. So I'm just looking
at movement pattern to begin with. Um, and then we start to add loads and I typically start with
a barbell and my preference is low bar squatting. I like to teach, well, actually it depends on the
person's anatomical makeup because high bar squatting might be better suited to, uh, an individual
that's got very short femurs compared to somebody that has extremely long femurs like I do,
low bar squatting. And I'm basically leaning over, looking at the ground when I squat just
to clear my hips or to be able to clear my hips. So, um, keeping it basic. And when you say low,
high, you mean the position on the track position of on, on the, on the back. Yeah, absolutely. So,
there are advantages, I guess, of having a low bar squat in that it, um, if you think about
like the moment arm, if you hold a weight plate, um, right in front of you, that's 20 pounds,
you can probably do it for a long period of time. If we extend their arms out, how long do you think
you're going to hold that 20 pound weight? Too long. Not very long. So similar, um, hypothesis
is that when we put the squat bar lower to our center of gravity, um, we tend to have a little
bit more strength and power. And that was a big difference for me as somebody that had crazy long
levers. Um, I was a terrible high bar squatter. Um, my strength went up like 50% by shifting to
that low bar position. So again, you asked about that. But is that only because your femurs are so
long? Correct. Yes. And there's other reasons as well. I think spine length as well. I have a long
spine, very long torso. So again, I want to bring that, um, barbell back into closer to the center
of gravity. So I'm very low on the back. Um, and I realized I'm totally deviating from what you
asked me, but keeping it simple with the squats. Are there any women that you look at and you just
say, you know what, it's not worth, you're never going to be a power lifter. It's not worth the
risk. I don't want you squatting. Um, I would say, uh, anybody that's got, um, some serious
like injuries, like a history of, um, hip injury knee injuries. Um, but again, my area of expertise,
um, isn't in like a rehabilitation. So I'm normally working in conjunction with, you know,
a physical therapist or chiropractor or something like that. Are women, do you find women who have
never done this kind of intimidated by the idea of that big 45 pound Olympic bar going on their back?
Heck yes. Absolutely. It is intimidating. I can't imagine. I mean, it's, I think if you've not done
that before, it looks really scary. Terrifying. And I think people's like fear is that the bar's
going to come down on, on top of them. It's going to turn them into a pancake. Yeah, absolutely. So
first of all, when you're first starting, you're not going to be loading the bar that heavy, but I
think, um, I work with like the catch bars on. So, um, a technique that I would do and incorporate
into a new person's program. If I was training one-on-one would be the Anderson squat. So you
basically start with the bar on the catches. So you position them at a high. You start in a low
position. Yeah. Yeah. So you're finding the, uh, clients, um, I guess, uh, horizontal position at
the bottom of the squat and that's where you start. So the, the thighs are parallel to the ground. Yep.
You start in that position and the rep is up, down. Yeah, absolutely. So that's a really, um,
empowering exercise that I think helps build confidence. So I'll do that in conjunction with
other squat variations, um, because it is, you know, it's such a big movement you're using. It's
like multi-joint, uh, big muscle groups. So it's also going to help contribute positively to energy
expenditure compared to just doing, you know, isolation exercises like triceps and biceps.
In fact, I rarely program arms for women anymore because at the point where, and again, it depends
on their goals, you know, if they're a kayaker or something, they need arm strength. I'm going to
probably do that. But for aesthetic reasons alone, most women, once we get rid of the body fat,
they've got great arms because just by way of the, you know, muscle engagement during these big
compound lifts, um, you're using those muscles anyway. Okay. What's your preferred deadlift if
you had to choose or how do you think about navigating trap bar versus traditional versus
sumo? Anatomical like structure of an individual. Um, so people that have exceptionally long arms
are extremely good deadlifters typically, um, because they basically don't have to lean
forwards very far to have a bar in their hands. Um, my arms are like T-Rex arms. Like they are
disproportionately shorter than everything else, but also is great and creates the illusion that
I have massive arms when I don't really. So for me, um, like I am not any way, shape or form,
like built to be a good deadlifter. So you might be more of a trap bar deadlifter.
Whereas he's more of a sumo deadlifter. Yeah. But when I do deadlift, I, for that reason,
I do sumo because by widening my stance, I can now get lower to the bar and then I don't have to be
so horizontal to get down to reach. Yeah. Yeah. The traditional would be very painful for you.
Oh, it is my spine and I've also extremely long spine. So for my, my, um, my deadlift is so ugly.
It's very tech, like it's technically it looks disgusting, but I'm doing all the right things.
Like we know that a little bit of spinal curvature in a deadlift is okay. If you are
activating, you know, your core and you're keeping tight. Um, so yeah, I have a hunchback of notred
arm looking, um, conventional deadlift, which is feet together. Um, but sumo deadlift is my
preference because it enables me to get closer to the bar. And I just feel like I'm in a better
position to execute. So interesting, right out of the gate, we're going to take, uh, you know,
a woman who's never done these things before, and we're going to program in some, some getting to
know the squat, getting to know the deadlift. Um, you're going to also include isolation exercises
and I assume they follow in the workout. So you'll start with the prime movers and the combined hip
hinges, and then you'll move to leg extensions, leg curls. Um, what about, uh, where do, where
do split squatting and lunging fit in? Yeah. So typically I will, uh, incorporate, you know,
at max, you know, to cut large compound multi-joint exercises. Typically they are like the first,
you know, six to eight sets are your best sets. There are like working sets. And then
what we tend to see is that any volume that's accrued, you know, after those eight first
working sets tend to, you start to have like diminishing returns. So big movers first,
isolation, accessory exercises, seconds. So again, the way that I would structure in something like
lunges or leg extensions or a hamstring curls or calf raises, it depends on what that person is
wanting to build. Truly. That's, that's all it is. So again, if we look at the, um, I guess,
minimum dose for a hypertrophy, when we look at like total set number, we want to be shooting for
somewhere around, you know, probably the 10 to 15 range per muscle group. Um, there are a lot of-
When you say per muscle group, you're counting quads distinct from hamstrings, distinct from
glutes, distinct from calves. The trouble is, and I guess a lot of people have a difficulty,
um, you know, trying to write their own program is that certain movements are hitting multiple.
So I will often just give us, you know, yep, that counts as this exercise and that muscle group.
And it counts as that. A dead lift is going to triple everything. It's hitting everything. But
when you do the leg extension, it only counts for quads. Leg curl only counts for hamstring.
Exactly. Okay. So you're going to, you're saying we want, by the end of this workout,
we want to have 10 to 15 boxes checked for each of those muscle groups. So let's just go through
some of them. So your, your favorites for glutes, obviously a squat and a dead lift. Yep. Absolutely.
That single leg RDL. Uh, interestingly, I actually was looking at a systematic review, uh, on glute
hypertrophy recently. Um, and I guess they were using, um, muscle activation as opposed to true
muscle thickness testing or some of those other more accurate methods of, um,
hypertrophy. Um, but step ups were actually as good as our glute activation as some of your,
you know, hip thrusts and, you know, squats, um, particularly some of the horizontal style
step ups or lunges where you're coming across the body. So like a cross bench step up where
you're taking the foot down one side and then coming back up, uh, where there's a lot of stretch,
uh, and lengthening taking place in the, in the glute. So yeah, for, for, for glute hypertrophy,
uh, there's always, you know, a hip thrust, a hinge of some sort or a bridge, um, usually some
kind of abduction. Um, an abduction is basically, uh, taking your knees out, um, as opposed to
adduction, which is bringing them together. So I'll find, um, different machines that, uh,
enable that. I can also do those on the cables as well with like an ankle attachment. Um, so they're
the primary ones that I would use for, for glutes. Those are great. Okay. So deadlifts, squats, hip
thrusters, step ups and abduction. Yep. That's a lot. So you got a lot to choose from there to just,
you got to get 10. So you don't have to be doing all of them every time. Yep. And to be honest,
like as, as that individual progresses, um, over, uh, I guess a seven day training block,
like we may be working up to, um, you know, 30 sets on, um, you know, each individual muscle group,
if they're able to, to execute that, um, over a seven day period because of their training
frequency, obviously, you know, a beginner, we're probably going to be looking, you know, over a
seven day period, they may get, you know, 10 to 15 sets, um, with their three or four training
sessions, but someone that's more advanced really maybe pushing like up to 30 sets, uh, maybe even
more. But again, there's a point where we have like diminishing returns where, uh, the inflammatory
response to that training, um, just makes it impossible to continue making progress in which
case we have the D load. Okay. So then for quads, obviously a lot of what you mentioned is going to
hit quads, certainly the squat to some extent, the deadlift, depending on how they do it,
the step up, certainly, uh, RDL won't, uh, abduction won't. So then you add some dedicated
stuff like leg extensions. Yep. So leg extensions are a really simple one. Obviously minimal, uh,
set up straight on the machine, but I also like a different leg press variations, uh, and different
squat variations that get our knee into a position where there's far more forward knee travel. I know
there's a lot of, uh, contradictions. I used to hear that all the time. Like don't put your knee
over your toe. You know, it's dangerous for your knee. Now, if someone's had a history of knee
injuries, that's something that you would want to take very slowly, um, very progressively. Um,
but anything where we can get the knee traveling past the toes. So by elevating your heels in
something like a barbell squat, my preference is honestly on a Smith machine because it really
controls the movement pattern. Um, and you only go forward. Sorry. And so people know the Smith
machine is the squat bar that has the hooks on it. That's in tracks, right? So the part, the path is
vertical on its control. Yeah, it's completely fixed. So, uh, I love that, that exercise. I think
targeting my quads, that's been a huge help. Uh, and then also foot positioning on the leg press. So
again, you're looking, uh, to have at the bottom of the movement, um, where your, uh, quads are in a,
uh, lengthened position. Um, you want to have lots of forward knee travel and I won't be specific in
where you should put your feet because feet placement honestly depends on the machine that
you've got access to because I've had some, I've had to put my feet up quite high because of the
movement plane. So it's less where the feet go and it's more where the knees and toes are in
relation to each other in the bottom position. Yes, exactly. Yep. So that's kind of the,
so are you saying to the, to the, to the client, um, we want you to work to your level of comfort
in getting knees over your toes in the leg press and that's going to maximize quad development. And
obviously you're going to work the back of the leg in the opposite position. Yep, exactly. So,
and then also there's a lot of benefits to doing like single leg work to, um, so many of us. And
I was honestly disgusted at my own, uh, imbalances. When I tested it the other day, I was doing some
single leg squats, um, you know, from a, just a sitting to a box, then, uh, standing on the box
to going to the floor only. Um, and it's very easy, you know, with lots of repeat training and
lots of repeating the same movements, um, where we have a bit of a discrepancy. So I really like to
incorporate at least one single leg exercise, um, for every session. If we start to add too many
single, um, all leg movements, your program end up, you know, it's extremely long. So that's,
that's a real consideration. You know, not everybody has three hours to train. So we want
to be concise and to the point. Okay. What are some of your favorite hamstring hits?
So, um, my favorite is a seated hamstring curl. And the reason for that is, um, it is better
able to isolate your hamstrings than say a prone hamstring curl where you're in the, uh, you're
laying on your stomach and you're kind of curling the machine in towards your hamstrings. And part
of that is just because of the position of the movement. Um, when you're in a seated hamstring
machine, you've already got tension on the hamstrings because we're sitting in this kind of,
you know, upright position. Um, so it's a lot more tension on the hamstrings. And if you're in a
prone position where your hips are far more open, um, we, we don't get the same kind of, um,
shortening of the hamstrings. So my preference is to do a lot more volume on a seated machine.
Uh, and then I'm not saying you don't do any, you know, prone work, um, but I'll do less of that
exercise. The other exercise that I really love for hamstrings and glutes, particularly the
hamstring time, which I think a lot of women, you know, you'll see the bikini competitors
specifically have these incredibly like tight, um, you know, hamstring attachments, um, to their
glutes. Um, a lot of that is conditioning, which basically just means getting rid of all the body
fat. You will see that. Um, but, uh, arteals and banded, uh, arteals. So tell folks what an
arteal is. So a Romanian deadlift, uh, I guess you are, it's a hinging exercise and you're shifting
your hips back to lengthen the hamstrings. So you were loading the hamstrings in that exercise.
You can do, we'll, we'll link to videos of all these things that people can see.
Awesome. Cool. So, um, you can do that with dumbbells. You can do it with barbell. Uh,
you can do it with kettlebells if you don't have access to those.
And do you prefer to do these single leg?
So I'll do both. Um, again, I, for a compound movement, if I'm trying to hammer my hamstrings,
I probably will start with an RDL because it's a big movement. You know, we're talking multi joint.
And when you do it two legs, you're loading on your back.
No, in front of me. So the barbell hangs in front of the dumbbells.
So, you know, for, for me, when I first started, it's crazy how quickly you can progress if you
work at it. I remember picking up 20, 25 pound dumbbells to do my first set of RDLs for sets of,
you know, 12 and now I'm all the way up at 90 pounds dumbbells for a set of 12 RDLs, which
you're holding to 90s in each hand. Yeah. So I would never have thought that I could do that.
And again, credit to my time in powerlifting to help me identify what I was really capable of.
Yeah. So what impresses me is not your hamstring strength to do that, but your grip strength to do
that. Most men cannot hold two 90 pound dumbbells. Really? Absolutely.
Look, I gotta be honest, I get a little bit of help. So again, there's benefits to...
Oh, are you using a grip? Are you using a wrap?
Grips. Absolutely. So, and again, I, people will say, oh, that's cheating. Like I don't
want to use something that cheats, like use your raw grip strength. If the point of the exercise...
Yeah, the point of exercise is to hit your hamstrings.
To hit your hamstrings, what's going to be the limiting factor? So,
grips are like a no brainer for me. Now, when you do single leg, do you do
contralateral weight or ipsilateral weight? In other words, if your left leg is on the ground,
are you going to hold the weight left hand or right hand?
So again, for a beginner, I would do opposing because you're going to have greater stability.
As you become more advanced, then same leg, same arm. Absolutely. I think it just challenges you
with different ways. It calls upon different muscle groups to help with stabilizing. So
for the client that we were discussing before, that's, you know, kind of has some experience
once the game muscle. I'd probably over the course of that six week mesocycle, sorry, over
the course of maybe their second or third training mesocycles, I might incorporate, you know, the more
advanced variation of a single leg RDL. It might start, you know, opposing to leg and then as they
advance, I would move it to a single leg over, you know, that 18 week, 24 week period. Yeah.
Okay. So, and then calves, what are you doing for calves?
A combination of both. I originally wasn't doing any calf work because from an aesthetic perspective,
it's not something that you see a whole lot of, I guess, but probably, you know, six sets per week.
I'd probably start again for someone that's brand new, like three sets. And then maybe in the week
two. Of what? Standing toe presses? Seated? Seated or standing? I believe based on the research,
seated tends to be a little bit better for hypertrophy outcomes. Don't ask me the mechanics,
this is not my area of expertise, but a study that I did a post on very recently was looking at the
different feet positions. And I used to be, first to put my hand up and throw myself under the bus,
do the toes in, like pigeon toes, calf raise. Pointless doesn't really yield, you know,
any meaningful results. Neutral stance and toes facing out tend to be better for optimizing
hypertrophy of, you know, I guess different aspects of your calf. On their upper body day,
how do you focus? Now I know you, I mean, I'm still surprised to hear that you're not doing
a lot of upper body for a woman. And what you're saying is the most important thing is taking the
fat off to let the muscles show. Yeah. But in that one day, what are they going to do for
for chest, for back, for shoulders and arms? Yeah. So I think one of the main things again,
that does differ between men and women's training programs is chest volume. So men typically want
to have Jack biceps, Jack triceps, big chest. There's less of an emphasis on that. So the women
in even in the fitness categories seem to be judged a lot on glutes, hams, shoulders, quads.
Back is so like, it's less important. They want to see a conditioned back, but it's not really
where a lot of the judging and time is spent. Unlike, you know, traditional bodybuilders where
like you look at your chi greens where it's just got lat on lat on lat. So I will incorporate,
I guess, different back exercises, more predominantly in a program that I would for chest.
I defer back to the client. Do you want to do chest training? I love bench press. Like again,
I've done powerlifting. So to me, like that's so empowering, like trying to hit a one-rip max
on a bench. I love that, but I'm not everybody. So again, I defer to the person that I'm working with.
And let's assume that she has no interest in her strength on a bench. It's really coming down to
how she's going to look in the dress. Aesthetic. Some people really need, you know, a lot of chest
training or conversely, they need a lot of back training due to their posture. So that's a big
consideration. But if a woman is sort of hunched forward. Yeah. They're really kyphotic. They've got
that rounding. They probably have extremely tight pectorals and weak back masslature. So in that case,
I would do a lot more volume on back and I probably wouldn't spend any time on any chest work. So,
you know, for that final one training session, I might be looking to hit, you know, 15 sets of back
and no chest at all. And what types of exercises would you do? So I would target the wide back,
mid back. So we're looking at our lats to get the lat, the width of the back. And that can help,
I guess, from an aesthetic perspective to create the illusion of a really small waist. So our wide
grip pull downs, wide grip pull ups, assisted pull ups for somebody that's just beginning and then
progressing to bodyweight pull ups and then weighted pull ups. So again, through, you know,
the course of somebody training consistently over, you know, nine months, say there's a very
good chance they could go from doing no bodyweight pull ups to weighted pull ups. Now, most women
can't do a single pull up unassisted, correct? I'd say that probably 90% of females would not
be able to do a single bodyweight pull up. And how many can you do? I think my last AMRAP was like 20.
20? Yeah. Okay. So you're at the point where you would use weight.
Yeah, I had some weight, but not a whole lot. But, you know, Beth Lewis, who you met briefly
the other day, you know, Beth is convinced that you can get any human being to do a bodyweight
pull up. Absolutely. Absolutely. There'd have to be something, you know, like from a neurological
standpoint that would inhibit someone from being able to. It was a lot of work. I was that
person. I could never do a pull up. I remember like when I first like got into lifting, I started
with bands, like the thickest green band possible with my feet in to help me. And I could do about
five reps with that. So yeah, the thing that really facilitated my strength in pull ups,
I program those every single program for years, every program. And it was always the most
intimidating exercise. I hated it, but I'd always put it first. So I'd always been nervous going to
training. Um, if I knew I had an upper body day, cause I had to do like pull ups, but yeah, I went
from not being able to do like any body weight to being able to do 20 body weight over the span of
like five years. But I can tell you now, uh, there was probably maybe three or four programs
over that entire timeframe that I did not program specifically put ups. And was the progression using
less and less and less resistance on the bands, but always sort of targeting a certain rep number.
Yeah. So I would pick, you know, somewhere in the hypertrophy rep range. So that's typically
anywhere from eight to 12. Um, and yeah, once I could do, you know, 12, um, reps with a certain
band, I would progress to the next like lighter resistance. And I just kept going. Once I got to
12 body weight pull ups, I was like, Oh, okay. Now we added like the weight belt with a little,
you know, two, two and a half pound kettlebell kettlebell or something. And, you know,
progressed that way. How much are you varying your hand position for both yourself and then
obviously for the client in this situation? So for me, I, again, and this was primarily because of the
aesthetic goal, which was to widen my lats. I would do a lot more, um, like prone grip. Um,
I guess I kind of targeted my rhomboids a little bit more, um, which would be a close grip pull up.
Um, but I, I don't know why I didn't, I didn't really do a whole lot of those. Sometimes I would,
change up my variations. So if I had three sets programmed to failure, say, um, my first set to
failure, I would do wide because that was the muscle group that I wanted to work the most.
Then I would switch to a neutral grip and then I might switch to an underhand grip.
And how much time do you need between sets to failure on pullups?
A long time. You do not want to rush that. Um, sometimes it would take five minutes between
sets. And I think that's where a lot of people find themselves, um, not being able to make
progress and not just with pullups, but for training in general, they go way too fast. And
then the consequences, they're not recovered when they start the next working set. Um, and because
they're still fatigued, they're not able to execute the next working set with, um, to the same number
of reps because they're not recovered. So they may have to drop those weights and pick up something
lighter. Um, I used to do that. And as a trainer, I'd be on the floor, you know, you'd have 60
minutes for the client and you want to rush. But the reality is if you can slow down your workouts
and take as much time as you need. And my rule of thumb is when your heart rate is back below 100
beats per minute. Uh, for me, it probably is a little bit lower for men. I think males tend to
have slightly lower heart rate than females. Um, so once my heart rate is back under a hundred,
that's when I know I'm like, okay, yeah, I can probably think about doing my next set.
Okay. Interesting. I'm glad you mentioned that. I was going to ask about your rest phase. Um,
okay. So anything you want to say about arms before we move on to the next metaphase?
If you like arms, do arms. If you don't like arms, don't worry about it.
Wow. This is, this is so paradoxical. I would guess looking at you that it's like,
I haven't done a bicep curl or tricep extension in 12 months.
So those arms that you have are simply the result of all of the stuff you carry.
Yes.
The heavy things you're lifting with your hands like deadlifts and RDLs,
and coupled with obviously getting rid of, you know, fat.
Absolutely. I think especially for something like pull-ups, you do actually get better at pull-ups,
uh, the less body fat you have and the lighter you get. Um, there's a, you know,
there's a point where it crosses if you lose too much muscle, but, um,
again, this is a very interesting point, right? Which is you can, we can joke and say, look,
biceps and triceps are not the most functional muscles in the world, but being able to do a
pull-up, being able to do a deadlift, that confers great benefit to life skills.
Oh, absolutely. Yes.
And so, so in some ways your bodybuilding training much more mirrors functional training
than what I would have expected.
Yeah, absolutely. But I mean, I think
Now let me just play devil's advocate for a moment. How much of that is your genetics?
Do you just genetically think you have big muscles in your arms and that's why you can get away with
this?
Look, I think if I was to look at my parents, like my dad is freakishly muscular for somebody that
doesn't do anything in the gym. He like grew up, I guess, being in very like laborist type jobs.
So like he's always been extremely lean. Uh, and I think he has short, um, humorous like I do. So I
guess it kind of creates this illusion of more muscle. It's easier to grow. It looks, you know,
if you think about a long muscle, it's a lot more muscle you've got to grow to make it look big.
So, um, I think just my, the way that I'm put together probably has assisted in some ways,
but that's not to say that it's not possible for other people as well.
Do you do some deltoid stuff?
Lots of training for shoulders.
So what are your, what are your sort of hits on deltoid?
Um, my favorites are probably scrape the rack shoulder press. I don't know if you've ever done
those, but essentially you're up against a squat rack, um, with a barbell on, you can do it kneeling
or standing. I like kneeling because it eliminates, um, the ability to cheat when you're standing.
You can use a bit of momentum to keep pushing. So kneeling, scrape the rack press, and you're
basically driving that barbell into the rack.
And what angle, what's the humoral angle at the top?
Um, well, you're pretty basically extended pretty vertically.
Wow.
Yeah. So you have to have good range of motion and mobility for your shoulders. Um,
one that I don't do with everybody, but I do, because I do have a lot of mobility with my
shoulders behind the neck shoulder pressing on a Smith machine. No, I only do it in on the
Smith machine because it keeps me in a very safe, uh, fixed plane. Like it's not allowed.
I'm not using dumbbells where I'm swerving everywhere or a free barbell. So I really
like that because it's, I had some shoulder injuries.
What about for somebody who can't put, who can't really press overhead due to shoulder
injuries or impingements and things like that?
Yeah. So again, I would, my area of expertise isn't specifically on like rehabilitation,
but I would be working with a specialist with that, but lateral raises is probably another thing
that people can do, um, to improve their, um, like medial shoulder, uh, and also then re-adults.
So you can do like a reverse pec fly where you're kind of pushing away. If you've got access to
cables, you can do a cable crossover, um, to hit your re-adults and, um, what else? Just face
pulls, those types of exercises.
Okay. So let's say we've progressed the intensity of all of this, uh, which means we've, we've
overloaded. So we've added sets, we've added reps, we've added intensity. We're eight months in
and let's assume we've hit our hypertrophy goals. Uh, you do another DEXA and remember
the initial goal was gain five pounds of muscle, lose five pounds of fat. If she has met her
hypertrophy goal and gained five pounds of muscle, how much fat do you think has changed at that
point? Do you think she's up neutral?
Absolutely. Uh, it depends on their dietary intake, to be honest. So, um, I think we can
go through a, you know, a period of progressive overload with an intentional building phase,
and do all the right things when it comes to the resistance training. But the other key piece to
the success of that build is diet. So how much was the client able to adhere to their
dietary requirements during that time? Um, you know, it's probably like 50% of the, the outcomes.
So I think going back to the beginning, if, um, I'm going to just create a stereotype, which is
she was sort of reasonable in total energy intake, but protein deficient relative to your goals. So
what would be your protein goals for her? Yeah. So it's honestly exactly the same as it is, um,
males to females. Um, the only difference is going to be the absolute total target that we
have for a female, because our body lean body mass is a little bit lower. So the required, um,
or the, the protein reference ranges to optimize, um, hypertrophy are anywhere from say 1.8 grams
of protein per kilogram of lean body mass, uh, all the way up to three grams of protein per kilogram
of lean body mass. So, um, based on the individual's dietary preferences, um, and what foods they like,
some people love protein. I've had clients that can't stand it. And it's a real struggle with them
too, which blows my mind. Cause I would probably live on meat if I had to pick one food group that
I'd have to survive on meat for the rest of time. But, um, I would pick something that is realistic
for them within that range. So, you know, for some, you ate that whole 16 ounce steak yesterday by
yourself. I was hoping you were gonna, something there's gonna be a little piece left over for me.
I told you, I do enjoy protein. So, but yeah, I think it really comes down to, um,
their preferences and there isn't one number that's better than another. Um, but consistency
is important. So we don't want to be chopping and changing your protein and, you know, bouncing all
over the place, um, for a couple of reasons. And that is that you can potentially, um, reduce or
limit your potential. Um, but it also impacts your energy balance because protein, um, has a far
higher thermogenic effect of food than, you know, carbohydrate and or fat. So if that's bouncing
around, you're effectively moving and shifting your energy balance. So, you know, that, that would
not be favorable for somebody that is trying to gain muscle and, you know, 90% of their protein
their dietary calories are now coming from protein. Um, you know, it's actually might be
shifting their energy balance in a negative direction. And if she was starting out, let's
just, I'm making math up, but she's 140 pounds and she's okay being 140 pounds at the end,
but that 10 pounds swap in body comp is important. Um, do you basically, and let's assume she's
weight stable coming into this exercise. Do you, um, basically keep her calorie stable and just
switch the macros around to increase protein? Yeah, initially, absolutely. I would have a
look at what her current dietary intake would be. And, um, if it was below the recommended reference
range, I'd pick a number that, you know, aligned with her lean body mass and her ability to nail
that number consistently. Then progressively throughout that building phase, we would want
to be, you know, slowly adding in calories. Um, if we look at the, um, overfeeding studies,
which unfortunately there is not as much, um, information available to us as there are like
weight loss studies, but of those that we do have, if we were to compare, um, somebody being in a,
like a surplus of say 20% above their maintenance calories versus 40% versus 60%, um, what we tend
to see is that the best results, and I should quantify what I mean by best, um, the most amount
of muscle mass that would be gained during a given timeframe would be optimal at about that 20% mark.
If we go up to 40 or up to 60, what we just end up seeing is excess 40 fat gain. It doesn't like
continue to get better the more you eat. So do let's just, again, let's making this up. She's at
2000 K cal coming in. Does that mean you're actually going to put her at a surplus, even though
you don't want her to gain weight. You just want her to gain lean mass. Well, I think to begin with
just for the initial week, I like to, if someone can tell me that they're eating a certain number
of calories, I want to see the data. Let's assume that you did that. Let's assume you did a food
log and she comes in at 2000 weight stable. Yep. So if that's her maintenance calories, um, that's
not optimal. We want to go to a small, you take it to 2400. Yeah. Well, it might be a, yeah, it might
be a 10 to 20% surplus. And again, part of that decision is also based on the individual's
comfort with adding body fat. And for females, that is the hardest group of people that I work
with to encourage to gain body fat. So usually I'm working within a far more restrictive
calorie surplus. And I would, if I'm working with a male client, they're a lot more open to gaining
some body fat to facilitate their gains. So if I'm being real optimal would be 20%,
most women will not adhere to that. So I'm probably going to prescribe something that's
more likely going to reflect the reality. And that is like a 10% increase above their maintenance.
And how would this change if she said she's 140 pounds, she wants to weigh 130 next year. So she
wants to lose 10 pounds, but wants it to all be fat loss. So this will also improve body composition
because she's going to just lose 10 pounds of fat, but wants to lose no muscle, which still
functionally means putting on some muscle to offset the fat loss. Would you then not put her
in a calorie surplus during the building phase? No, I still would because her ability to acquire
that new tissue is going to be. It's energetically demanding. Yeah. You need surplus energy to come
from somewhere. Now, if somebody is starting with a higher body fat percentage, now we've got somebody
that has, you know, they have an energy reserve and we can petition that stored body fat. And
that's the whole concept behind, you know, body re-composition. So for some individuals, if they
do have body fat, I may not need to put them in a major surplus. So it's so client dependent, you
know, I have to look at them and the complete pictures. So, um, it might not be a massive
surplus at all. If they were, you know, 20% body fat, it might just be, let's nail these calories
for the next six months. And over time, we will see some positive changes because you've got
enough body fat available to help with the building and the foundations of that new skeletal tissue.
Okay. So now it's eight months in. Yep. We're two thirds of the way to our goal.
She's on target for lean mass. She's also, of course, added a little bit of fat mass.
You now have four months to get that fat off and keep the lean tissue on. What changes in nutrition
and then what changes in the gym? Yeah. So changes in the gym initially are negligible. I think
there's a misconception that suddenly everything changes when you start dieting. The goal for
dieting is truly to be able to keep you on as higher calories as possible with as little
increase in activity as possible, whilst still achieving a targeted rate of weekly weight loss.
So to begin with, their training may say exactly the same. It might make, we might make a couple
of tweaks because they're bored and they need to change up. But the concept, the principles of that
training program and the structure does not change unless suddenly they decided that they
no longer want those giant glutes and we put back in, you know, chest training. But, you know,
the principles say the same. From a diet perspective, that is again, we kind of look at,
okay, now that we've acquired a little bit of body fat, we want to get all of that off, you know,
in time for this, the wedding or whatever the event is, I basically do a back calculation.
So, and I pick a targeted weekly rate of weight loss that does not exceed more than 1.5% of their
body weight. So. Per what unit? Week? Per week. Yeah. If we, again, if you look at the. That still
sounds like a lot. It is, it is. It can be a lot. And some people may not have the. That could be
two pounds a week. Yeah. Again, but it would be relative to the individual. So, you know,
200 pound male, that's a lot. But even this 140 pound woman. Yeah. 1.4 pounds. That's 1%. So,
we're looking at close to two pounds. So, again, we've got to be realistic with how much can be
achieved in a seven day period for that person. So, choosing that percentage rate of loss is
important. Why it's important is because we, when we see extreme dietary interventions carried out,
continuous diet interventions that push weight loss beyond those numbers, we are increasing
the risk of metabolic adaptation. So now we're starting to look at, you know, more, I guess,
adaptive mechanisms, a greater response to dieting or our self-defense system really, you know,
ramps up. We become far more efficient. So, we want to keep the rate at that, that level.
And that will help to keep your BMR, your basal metabolic rate nice and high. And it's protective
of your muscle mass beyond that one and a half percent. That's when we really start to see people
actually losing a greater percent of muscle mass and lean tissues as opposed to fat loss. So,
you know, I think a lot of people will argue with me in the first few weeks when we,
you know, put together a program for them. They're like, that just doesn't seem like enough weight
loss. I'm used to seeing, you know, two kilos a week. And I'd say to you, so if you're worried
about the number on the scale, if that's all you're worried about, what have I said to you
that that two kilos, you lost not a single bit of fat, it was mostly lean tissue. Is that still okay?
And they're like, Oh, okay. So, you know, we've got to be realistic with what you can do in a week
and how it might impact muscle loss. And then determining what calorie deficit that actually
requires. So, we have a really wonderful, I guess, calculation in one of our books,
The Complete Contes Brett Guide. And I believe it's also in Fat Loss Forever.
And that outlines what amount of calories is required to lose a certain amount of body weight
in grams. So it's a really neat little equation. And we can calculate very accurately for the
average person that doesn't have crazy, you know, a really fast metabolism or really slow
metabolism, what the deficit is that they need to lose that one and a half percent or whatever
number it might be. So, it's really neat. I can pretty much forecast exactly what someone
has. How does a person do this practically? So there's, on the one hand, there's the calculation,
which let's just say it comes out and says, okay, we're going to reduce your intake from what was
2400 now down to, you know, 1875 calories. But then there's the application of that, right?
Which is, you know, if this person doesn't have a chef that can prepare every meal that they're
going to eat with a scale, how do they go about doing that? I mean, this can be really difficult
stuff to go weighing everything. And I don't see how you could reach that level of precision
without a scale, right? Yeah. So it is really tough. And I think one of the things that I will
say to people that I've worked with is there is so much value in giving or I guess dedicating a
set amount of time to weigh your food, to get familiar, to calibrate and learn, you know, what
what a four ounce piece of chicken looks like, what, you know, ex food weighs on the scale. I
think having that knowledge and an understanding of what it represents from a caloric perspective
and from its macronutrient, like the constituents of that food, knowledge is power. And I really
struggle with people that like don't want to invest that time because that is a lifelong skill that
once you know how to do it, and it might take you six months to get the hang of it. But like for me
now, I can, and I've been doing this for over 12 years, is I can estimate anything and eyeball it.
So you get really good. So there is a lot of, I guess, accountability coaching, homework tasks,
I think getting them like practical tools and resources to learn how to do that,
which is kind of what's involved in that whole, you know, weekly check-in and that coaching process.
So as she gets closer and closer to, you know, this, this event, again, let's just use it as
this wedding example. So she's four weeks out and, you know, do you have a sense of where she
would need to be a month out on those goals to hit the target? Yeah, absolutely. I think when we get
to probably within three to 5% of their, their goal body fat percentage, like that's when I can
start to tell. So there's a lot of, I guess, photo exchange. So we have so much data that we collect
for a client and that can be super helpful to make, you know, accurate analysis, but there's
so many benefits to also having that supplemented with, you know, an actual physical picture.
And if we're not always looking at somebody's DEXA scan, you know, every six weeks as they're
going, which is not always feasible for every client, depends on the clientele that you're
working with, but we don't always have that data available. So it really does come down to looking
at their, you know, macro tracking, watching their weight trends, and then coupling that with
their pictures to be able to see, you know, body fat loss is actually happening. And the situation
I described 130 or 140 pound woman who's going to be the same weight a year later, but have a
five pound switch. How visibly different is that? Probably not as much as you would think. Okay. So
maybe that goal wasn't ambitious enough. No, but if that was, and again, you have to look at what
is required for somebody to, you know, develop the muscularity of like a, an elite fitness
professional. That's like a 10 year process for some people. So I think again, that, that five
pounds is realistic for somebody to add, but how notable is that going to be? You know, it depends
on what they're starting with too. It really does. It really does. And I think how lean they get at
the end too. And sometimes the first attempt at fat loss, it doesn't get you to the goal and it
takes multiple attempts of coming out of this diet process through recovery diets and then fat
loss again, and then another recovery diet before we really start to kind of achieve the ideal that
that client is wanting. So let's talk about that. So she hits her goal, which is five and five,
and she's pleased in that she hit her goal. She looks better in her wedding dress than she would
of a year sooner. But to your point, she's like, I have greater ambitions here. I would like to be
even leaner a year from now. And I like this process, but I don't feel like being as restrictive
right now. So I'm about to go on my honeymoon to Italy. Sounds amazing. How do I recover from this
without doing, without undoing all the good I did in the last year? Yeah. And I think, you know,
again, looking at the research that we have and, you know, some of these longitudinal studies
that show us what happens with fat loss and, you know, the success, the success rates of fat loss,
you know, over a dietary intervention, people don't necessarily have a difficult time losing
the weight. It is this inability to keep it off. And a lot of that is actually, I guess,
the reasons that it occurs is because typically outside, you know, good governance of a good coach,
people do things in such extremes. So they've done everything wrong during their diet phase.
And the consequences, they've lost a lot of muscle mass during that fat loss that negatively impacts
their basal metabolic rates. And now their metabolism is, you know, their body's requirements
are a lot less. They're coming up against hormonal changes that impact their appetite
regulating hormones. So most people, you know, post diet experience some talk, some form of
hypophagia, which for people that don't know what that is, it's just like that excessive extreme
desire to eat more than what is physiologically required by their bodies. So if they aren't
conscious of that happening, and they're not aware that there are these hormonal changes,
the natural inclination post diet is to go back to what you were doing before, especially if you
haven't chosen a dietary approach that works for your food preferences. And this is where we see a
lot of people struggling with, oh, I've tried this diet. It didn't work. Tried this one. It didn't
work. And then they end up going back to what they like. So if you can slowly reintroduce your
calories post diet, um, and unfortunately that means that that whole process still feels like
the diet. And I can say like, as somebody that has, you know, just a few weeks ago, finished my
competition, I didn't get as lean. So the hunger response was not as severe as it's been in the
past, but it's still there. It is really hard to continue to regulate when the goal is now
out of sight, or at least the goal that you were getting close to is leaving because doing a reverse
diet there, you're not getting that positive visual response. This is intrinsic and you can't
see your metabolism improving. The only data or evidence that you have when you're reversing
is seeing the small little increases in calories. Like, oh cool, I get to eat a hundred more calories
this week. You know, so it takes a good number of weeks to be able to get your calories back up to
a point where it's like, oh, it's me. It's made a meaningful difference to my life. You know, I can
have, you know, a couple of glasses of wine now with, you know, my friends and I've been able to
incorporate my dessert again. So it's a really difficult, um, process. And a lot of people-
And how many weeks does that last?
It depends. And again, for a lot of folks, you're trying to get them
initially rule number one for setting a reverse diet after you've finished
being in a deficit is just finding your new maintenance calories. Um, and you can assess
that by looking at how much weight you have lost over, you know, the weeks, the final couple of
weeks in your, um, fat loss phase. So we can go back and predict what they are for our time.
So for this woman, technically, if her maintenance was 2000 coming in,
it's probably going to be a lot lower.
It's probably going to be, oh, I was going to say a little bit higher because even though
her weight is the same, she has more muscle.
She may have more muscle mass, but it depends how lean she wants to get because-
Oh yeah, yeah. But this is saying, um, you're, you're saying if she wants to continue to get
leaner, not, I'm saying if she's happy to stay at that 140 for another six months before she
begins her next cycle, she might actually come in at 2100 to 2200 calories before you then say,
okay, now the time is we're going to take off another five pounds of fat.
So I completely understand what you're saying. However, the problem is even if she has added
five pounds of muscle mass, which we know in theory, you know, muscle is very energetically
demanding tissue. It requires more calories. So you would expect there to be a shift,
a positive shift in their BMI. Yes. When she did that at the end of the build, yes.
But that fat loss phase that someone did to get the weight back down, again, depending how long
it took, how extreme we had to go, um, and how, uh, equipped they were to execute the deficit we
needed. And what I mean by that is, did we need to do a whole lot more cardio to create the deficit?
What was the intensity of that cardio like? She could have lost some of that muscle during
the fat loss phase. And evidently you will lose muscle anyway. Like it's, you will always lose
muscle mass when you attempt to fat loss phase. Um, but how the leaner you get the greater the
risk of that muscle losses because you no longer have that caloric cushioning to, um, support that.
So, um, her metabolism, even when we go back to her new maintenance calories, after she's added
more muscles, so physically she's going to look better, she still may be lower at the start of
that reverse diet, which is really interesting to think. So there may be some work that's needed
to be done reversing just to get her back to maybe that 2000 calories that she was on.
She may not be able to go straight back to that. It takes weeks. So the way that you do that is
slow and incremental increases week by week. Um, and you observe the weight gain and then you
adjust, respond accordingly. So I guess before we wrap, um, are there any other specific differences
in sort of male and female training that we could shed light on? Yeah. So I think, you know,
outside like the specificity of like putting together an actual program and targeting certain
muscles, muscle groups, rather, um, people may have actually heard, um, somewhere along their
fitness journey that women tend to do better with higher rep ranges and males do better with, uh,
lower rep ranges. And traditionally I think there's, there's a reason why we tend to see that,
that style of programming, um, you know, more prominent, you know, in the gym scene.
And part of that is due to, I guess some of the differences in sex hormones. Um, and that kind
of has an impact on our muscle fiber type. So females actually have a greater percentage of type
one muscle fibers than do males. Um, and the positive consequence of that, um, difference
there for females is that it means that we're better able to transport nutrients, uh, into the
tissues and also clear, um, different metabolites, um, you know, during activities. So the benefit
there is that women tend to be less fatigable, um, when it comes to training. And, uh, another
thing that kind of coincides really nicely with that is that women, um, again, in both the fed
and the fasted state tend to do better at utilizing, um, fatty acids. So again, it means that we're
less reliant upon some of those glycolytic, um, you know, pathways or anaerobic processes. So,
um, we do better, um, in, as when it comes to recovery from, um, different types of training.
So when it comes to building out that training program, again, I'm being pretty meticulous here,
but men, I would often opt for a little bit more strength specific training. Um, and I guess if you
look at the definitions of strength training, it's the rep ranges between one to six. Um,
then you've got your moderate rep ranges, or we call that the hypertrophy rep range. Um,
I'll have more of that with females and then the,
Which is about eight to 12.
Eight to 12, eight to 15. And then we've got our endurance strength training, which is,
you know, your 15 to 20 reps. So some like women will, um, say that they, uh, enjoy that type of
training and they're able to tolerate it better, um, more so than some of the strength based
training. But I would, I would still argue that females, when you're, you know, put in the right
hands with a good qualified coach, um, that they could equally enjoy that style of training too.
But again, that's thinking about like the actual differences, you know, that muscle fiber type and
part of that's due to, I believe it's estrogen. Um, you know, women having a higher level of
estrogen, we've got more estrogen receptors, I believe on our escalatal tissues. And that's
one of the benefits, um, for, you know, the nutrient transport. So.
That's interesting. Wouldn't that also suggest that women would have an easier time
training without ingestion of glucose, right? Um, at least in theory. And yet I feel like maybe
it's just looking at my wife, she does not like to train on an empty stomach. She needs something to,
you know, she needs to be drinking or eating something beforehand. Yeah. But I think you
mentioned you like to train on an empty stomach. I'm the opposite. So again, I think it's really
subjective. Um, we can, the science can always say certain things, but we've also then got to
take into the, into account, I think the individual's, you know, perception and often it's, you know,
it is very subjective. Sorry for me as somebody that has struggled with like irritable bowel
syndrome for, you know, the last 10 years of life, I can't think of anything worse than trying to
train with anything in my stomach. I might have a couple of coffees in the morning, um, but I'm
keeping, you know, pretty low gut irritant type foods, because the minute I feel some kind of,
you know, distension or, you know, pain in my stomach, I cannot train. I would rather train
hungry with a rumbling stomach than try to have to execute with a full stomach. So, but again,
endurance training, very different to, you know, more anaerobic training, like the resistance
training that I do is probably more, um, you know, anaerobic. So it might be just due to the
differences in, um, you know, exercise type. Any other differences that we should be aware of
as far as female and male, uh, either through response to nutrient or load? Um, I think,
again, speaking to sex hormones, I think the menstrual cycle is probably the only other thing
that kind of springs to mind. And, um, there's been a lot more, um, information becoming available on,
um, that topic as it relates to, um, hypertrophy outcomes and strength training. And again,
there's probably four studies, um, that are, you know, high quality at the moment that I can think
of that, um, again, tend to be kind of on the fence. Um, half of them show that, um, you know,
during the second phase, the luteal phase of your menstrual cycle, um, when progesterone is high and
uh, estrogen is low, that subjectively, uh, strength decreases for females during training.
Um, and then during the earlier parts of training, when progesterone is low, um, you know, people
report to feel a lot better with their training, their performance is better, the strength is
improved. But again, it's like, it's a 50 50 for clients. So when it comes to female programming,
I as a default, and if it's, it doesn't seem to impact them, that's great, but I will default to
setting deloads, um, on or around their menstrual cycle. So you might go two weeks on two weeks,
like you could upload two weeks, download two weeks. Yep. Wow. Yeah. It might be in the middle
of a mesocycle, but again, it, it depends on how serious they are about their progression, but
guessing that's something a lot of male trainers don't think about. No, probably not at all.
Absolutely. And like just ability to be adherent and like your energy mood, sleep, you know, all of
those things can be impacted around your cycle. Um, constipation is another prevalent symptom of,
um, you know, mentioned men's ease. So, you know, that, that absolutely impacts people's energy
levels and like motivation to train. So yeah. How many times have you found yourself training
clients post pregnancy and in menopause? Do you, do you have a high number of clients in those two
categories? Yeah, actually, uh, more recently, my clientele has shifted more to middle age. I'd say
majority of my clients now are probably 35 to 65. Um, and yeah, I think that transition going from,
you know, uh, high levels or higher levels of normal levels of testosterone for females to low
level, uh, during menopause and the changes in estrogen, it's really hard on females. Um, and
a funny story. My mom did not even know, um, that there was like symptoms that came along with,
um, you know, menopause. She was like, Oh, I just, I knew women couldn't, you know, have children
anymore, but she's not, you know, super scientific in any ways. She didn't know she was going to have
hot flashes. No, she had no idea about any of these symptoms. And you know, for her, she was
so upset and like just frustrated that she didn't have any energy or she didn't want to go for walks
anymore or go to a Pilates classes, whatever she was doing. And, um, yeah, I said to like,
there's so much benefit to number one, like going and getting those levels tested. Um, I believe
you're a big advocate of hormone replacement therapy. Yes. Yeah. Um, just the, just putting
somebody back into those normal reference ranges in the benefit that that has not just on like
seeing a number move on, you know, their biomarkers, but what that does for their, you know, quality of
life and how much more motivated people might then be to be active, you know, as we age and stay,
you know, involved in sport. It's, it's crazy. And so do you see this difference than in clients where
you have menopausal women who are not on hormone replacement therapy versus those who are,
and do you see a fundamental difference both in body composition and work and work tolerance?
Absolutely. And I would say, unfortunately for the women that aren't proactive and aren't on
some kind of hormone replacement therapy, we tend to see those women coming in with extremely low
calorie intakes and extreme exercise output. So it's like they're burning the candle at both
ends and they're feeling frustrated because they're like, I already eat nothing. You know,
I'm training multiple times a day. I'm doing all this cardio and I just, I can't lose fat or, and
I've only gotten fatter, you know, during this process, which is likely to happen because if
you've been dealing with those negative symptoms for a long period of time, like naturally, if
you're not motivated and you don't feel good, you're not going to train. So, you know, people's
quality of exercise goes down. Now they're losing lean body mass and they're probably,
as I've experienced, aging tends to lend more towards the finer things in life. And, you know,
you're gravitating towards, you know, more indulgent type foods and a different lifestyle
that keeps you less active, unless you're very proactive about it. So people gain a lot of weight
during that timeframe. So yeah, we obviously defer out to the experts for the hormonal
replacement therapy and then integrate with our, I guess, interventions, the reverse diet, to get
their calories back up to something that feels manageable. Now they're enjoying, you know, all
their favorite foods again, they have a social life again, and they just feel so much better
with that extra energy. And then the hormones returning to normal. And then what about women
after having kids? You know, it's a lot of women will say, it's just not the same,
speaking about their body, right? So, and body composition. So, is there anything that you've
noticed in clients where you think we have to do something a little bit different? You know,
there's the 40 year old woman who's never had kids, and then there's the 40 year old woman who's had
three kids and both of them are still premenopausal. But do you notice anything different between them?
Yeah, I think the first one that's pretty smart is just the available time that they have for their
goals. That is such a huge like consideration for all of this. I can think very distinctly of a
couple of clients that I have that did not, or they've either had children and they've now grown
up and moved out. So they have, you know, all the time in the world to, you know, do what they want
to do with their hobbies and their physique goals or health goals. But for people that have children,
it is really hard. And again, I think it comes back to managing expectations. I am the coach that
will turn people away if they, you know, use the goal that I want to achieve Holly, you know, 50
pounds, I've got to do it, but they've also got three kids. You know, they only have a very
limited amount of time that they can apply to, you know, meal preparation. Maybe they have a limited
income and they can't have a chef, you know, like we do that comes in and helps out during, you know,
those really busy times. They don't have a nanny full time to come and support them. So
there are major differences in what can be achieved realistically. And I think, you know,
kind of looking at someone's lifestyle, it is so important. And I think women don't give themselves
enough credit for the amount of time that they are taking in these other obligations.
But from the standpoint of that woman who's say 40, mom of three, who's got 10 pounds,
she simply cannot shed. Can you guess whether most of that is going to come from
dietary restriction versus increased activity versus what combination? Do you have a sense
just hormonally which one is pestering her? Because, you know, one of the things in our
practice that really we don't put emphasis on due to the sheer ignorance around it is,
you know, body composition, right? I mean, we will say to that woman, look, we're interested in
making you as metabolically healthy as possible. That won't necessarily come with the improvement
in body composition you had. It won't necessarily take you to your pre-pregnancy weight. But as you
said, a lot of people are coming to you and that's their primary thing, right? They're, yes, I'd like
to be healthier, but, you know, quite frankly, I want to be able to fit into the clothes that I was
wearing two years ago. Yeah, that's a tough one. I have said multiple times to women, you need to
get a new wardrobe. Like as simple as that, like it's the easiest thing or easiest way to instantly
feel better about yourself. Now you've got a pair of clothes that are more flattering for your now
physique. It's going to improve your mental health first and foremost, but it's not constantly like
you're not pulling and tugging on the clothing that like it makes you think about your body. And
if you're already in an unhappy place, like that's a bad place to begin with. But is it realistic for
somebody to get back to their pre-pregnancy body weight? Maybe, but for a lot of women, if you have
partaken in some kind of exercise, you know, whether it's running or swimming or cycling,
if there's anything that's applying some kind of like load and resistance, you've probably added a
lot of muscle since you were pregnant, you know, however many years ago too. So to expect that
you're going to see the same number on the scale, often that's not realistic because they've built
so much muscle over the course of their life that they would never be that way to get, and they'd
have to lose all this muscle and some to get back to that. So I really wish that I could give you a
better answer here. Do I see any differences like even from a hormonal perspective? No, not really.
I think that with proper nutrition intervention and that is like optimizing somebody's metabolism
through the process of reverse dieting. So we want to sit right on the edge of like every week,
we're trying to positively adapt and get their metabolism to move up. And that can be done
without any changes in lean body mass. Like there is a true adaptation that takes place.
So yeah, we're trying to optimize their dietary interventions and get them, you know, doing what
we know to be adequate from a training standpoint. Like that is what will help that person get to
this end goal. And it just means it's going to take a lot longer for a mum of three, just because
they don't have the ability to do it. Where do you think this goes from here for you? Do you plan
to continue bodybuilding? I don't know. I think that part of me feels really compelled to stay
in the industry and keep showing up maybe on a yearly basis to be an advocate for the people
that are still suffering in silence. I think that there's so many people that have difficulties,
you know, sharing their struggles, you know, reaching out for help, gaining, getting support.
And I've seen a massive shift in the type of work that I'm doing and the education that I'm sharing
now, because it's a really hard life to live and it can be very unrewarding. It can feel like,
what's the point if you can't keep, you know, making progress and or if you never really
if you never really work on the psychological dysfunction that might be happening, like what's
the why? So I feel a little bit conflicted coming back and staying because I don't have the same,
I guess the same feeling towards competing anymore. I don't, I no longer desire the leanness.
I really don't. I don't, I can do the process now. And I was really worried about my last
competition because I thought now that I don't have this eating disorder, am I going to have
what it takes to execute? Like, or was that previously just driven by a psychological
condition? So that was, it was nerve wracking, but I was able to do it, but I'm no longer attached
to the body. So I want to be somebody that can be an advocate to help people realize that if you do
the work, you can do these together. They don't, they don't exist, you know, exclusive to each other.
I think you can do a bodybuilding show and not have some kind of eating disorder, but also
recognize that it's, it's an extreme sport. It's an extreme sport and it requires a lot of sacrifice.
And personally right now I'm so passionate about mental health and the idea of potentially stepping
back from everything that I do, the fitness industry and going back and doing a PhD in
the area of neuropsychology or mental health and eating disorders that it may not be something
that I have in my foreseeable future. I just don't know, but I want to, I want to help people.
I know that there is so many women that would benefit from learning that, Hey, I struggled
with all of these feelings and, you know, low self confidence and low self esteem.
And that there's another way aside from calorie restriction and dietary restriction that can
lead me to the same positive, you know, outcomes and value as a human. So how do you think about
aging yourself? I mean, how do you think about being 50, being 60, not looking like you do today?
Yeah. Given the, the journey you've been on and the struggle you've been through and how closely
those have been intertwined. My approach is all about longevity. I think, um, if you had
asked me that two years ago, I would still be, I'm still going to look amazing, but I think my
perception or my ideals about what my life should be, um, in order to truly, you know, be happy. Um,
it doesn't look like me slaving away in the gym anymore. It doesn't look like me being a lifelong
competitor. That doesn't mean that I want to let myself go and, you know, not have any interest in
exercise at all. But I think I would like to remain, and I hate using this word, like functionally fit.
But I want my body to be able to move. Like I want to be able to, if someone says to me,
Hey, let's go for a 5k run. Like I want to be able to do that. If I, you know, need to be fast
and agile for something. So I think my training is probably going to gravitate a little bit more
away from the gym, um, and incorporates just some more hobbies and things that keep me active and
functioning well. Um, but I will always lift because I know the benefits, um, that resistance
training can have on your body. But you're okay with the changes that are going to come,
which is, you know, you're not going to be 12% body fat. Yeah, absolutely. And I think even in
like six weeks, I will no longer even look like I do now. Like I'm very content with the idea that,
um, I can still be healthy at a much higher body fat percentage. Um, and as long as I have the
muscle mass underneath that body fat, I know that that is protective in so many ways. You know,
I'm thinking about, you know, reducing my risk of like bone degenerative conditions,
like osteoporosis when I get old, like resistance training, anything that applies, you know,
tension and stress on the bone, you know, those little bone creating cells, you know,
they ramp up and now I've got greater bone density. Like I think about that. My dad struggles
severely with osteoporosis and arthritis. Your dad. Yeah, very much so. He's, he needs a double
shoulder reconstruction. He went to it, but yeah, I think that's, that's kind of the message we,
we give to our patients, both men and women, but I think it's more important for women to hear
because I think, um, sometimes women are a little bit more governed by the scale than by what's,
what's underneath. And again, that's a stereotype, but I see it. But it's real. It's real. And what
we say is I'm much more concerned with how much muscle mass we can put on you and how much we can
increase the density of your bones as you age. And even if we never take an ounce of fat off you,
which by the way would mean you'd potentially even gain weight a little bit as you age.
But if that weight is predominantly lean tissue and we're maintaining the integrity of your
skeletal structure, you're going to live a better life. You are. And I think the first thing that
women have to do, and again, I don't want to stereotype, but ladies, this is just the reality
of how we are wired, uh, in today's day and age, but letting go of some of that, um, identity,
um, and this belief that we need to look a certain way. Um, there's one thing to being,
you know, feeling comfortable and confident. Um, but let's focus on the important things of life.
And I think, you know, to me, after having gone through all of this and recovered, um, or actively
and always will be a recovering, uh, person with an eating disorder, but you know, there's so many
other things now to me that are so much more important. And, you know, my long-term health
is important. Um, I do want to make sure that I've got good bone health. I don't want to have,
you know, bone diseases. I want to be able to live my life to the best. And, um, you know, I think
mentally as well, I'm probably going to stay active because of all the benefits that we know
for mental health, like anxiety, um, depression, depressive-like symptoms. Um, I want to optimize
like my health and staying so fixated on the scale and body fat and cellulite. Ah, it's like the least
of my concerns right now, which is a really weird thing for me to say as someone that like used to
feel like unless I was stage-leaning around, I was not a worthy human. So yeah, I think there needs
to be a big shift in what we're delivering to our, like, to our patients and to our clients, because
if we look at social media, it's really easy to get, you know, engrossed in, you know, social
medias, thin ideals and filters. And I think the best step that I ever took was just unfollow,
like all the accounts that are only focused on the aesthetic. I just, nope, I don't look at them
anymore. I don't, like I read about the things that I want to learn more about. If I want to feel
happy, gosh, I've got like a hundred books that I've read that are all on, you know, how to change
your mind, how to be happy, what is life's purpose, um, how to break habits. Like that's where I spend
my time now. I'm looking to optimize myself as a human. And yeah, it means that there's less need
for all that aesthetic stuff. Well, Holly, thank you so much for sharing both the insights and also
obviously the really deeply personal stuff that actually I think will probably resonate with many
people, both men and women. Thank you very much. Thank you for having me. It's been awesome.