Hey everyone, welcome to the Peter Attia drive.
I'm your host, Peter Attia.
The drive is a result of my hunger for optimizing performance, health, longevity, critical thinking,
along with a few other obsessions along the way.
I've spent the last several years working with some of the most successful top performing
individuals in the world.
And this podcast is my attempt to synthesize what I've learned along the way to help you
live a higher quality, more fulfilling life.
If you enjoy this podcast, you can find more information on today's episode and other topics
at PeterAttiaMD.com.
Hi everyone, welcome to episode four of the week of day spring.
In this episode, we cover a lot of drugs.
We talk about statins, we talk about cholesterol regulation, we talk about a zetimibe, also
known as Zettia, and we talk about the most recent class of drugs introduced to this field,
a drug, a class known as the PCSK9 inhibitors.
There are two such drugs on the market today.
We talk about fibrates and we also talk about the use of fish oil, niacin or niacin span,
which has fallen out of favor.
This came up a little bit on the discussion I had with Ron Kraus several months ago and
we get re revisited here.
Tom has a very different point of view on this from Ron.
So you will be able to determine which of those views that you favor, which camp you're
going to be in on the niacin side.
We talk about the role of cholesterol, statins and brain health.
And another thing that I learned was about the futility of using CKs and LFTs to address
statin response or ill response.
So again, another great example of how I'm doing these shows, but I'm learning along
the way and so I'm confident that any physician listening to this is going to learn something
and that hopefully this becomes kind of a part of your ongoing medical education.
So sit back and get ready for episode four.
So while we're on that topic, let's go back and talk about the drugs.
So we just finished with kind of one very niche story, but when it became pretty clear
that there was an association, a strong association, frankly, between cholesterol and heart disease,
you now had another target because as you said, if we went back in time 50, 60 years,
if you were astute enough, you would have your patients stop smoking.
You would manage their blood pressure.
What was the first drug that was specifically brought to market to target cholesterol?
Well, niacin has been used that infinitum forever without a lot of data, but they knew
it changed certain metrics.
They were measuring total cholesterol, HDL cholesterol.
And the only form of niacin available back then was immediate release of pretty much
intolerable drug for most people, but you could find some people who could take the
massive doses needed for that.
So that was around, believe it or not, when I was coming up and total cholesterol was
the only measurable thing and they knew that if it was 400 or something, you were probably
in trouble.
They gave neomycin to those people.
Neomycin, the antibiotic.
Which interrupted the hepatobiliary circulation of cholesterol and it lowered cholesterol
anywhere, no outcome evidence with it.
But along came the bile acid sequestrants, which we hinted on will make you excrete bile
acids, which therefore you have to use up your endogenous cholesterol to make new bile
acids.
So you will lower your cholesterol metrics that you're looking at.
And in a crazy long outcome trial, it did seem to work.
They pudged a lot of statistics, I think, in retrospect on and didn't have the type
of statistics.
This is the LRC.
Yes.
So there was a little proof that not only what Framingham said is true, cholesterol
is a risk marker, a risk factor, depending on how you want to label it, but lowering
it does reduce clinical events.
To me, the tragedy of that is for the next 20 to 30 years, the only thing that the pharmacological
industry focused on was cholesterol as their metric of, that's all we got to do.
We got to find stuff that lowers cholesterol metrics or improves cholesterol metrics in
one or the other direction.
And by the way, questions do raise HDL cholesterol in milligram or two milligrams per cent, which
turns out to have some statistical significance.
Potentially without any physiologic significance.
Correct.
And it's a minuscule thing, so who knows.
So that led to just investigation of everything else.
And all of a sudden, this guy discovers a fungus that has got a property that lowers
really potently cholesterol.
And that was the statin group, Akira Uendo, a mycologist over there in Japan, who unbelievably
has not gotten a Nobel Prize yet.
And there'd be no statins without him bringing it to the table and stuff.
We wound statins, lower LDL cholesterol dramatically, pretty low doses.
They seem to be safe.
After LRC, the FDA needed it was if you got a product that didn't harm anybody and it's
lowering LDL cholesterol, welcome aboard.
So several statins got approved starting in 1987 with the lowest statin, Mevacor being
the first and came on the market.
Mevacor's like me who are well into believing, yes, lowering LDL cholesterol, though the
only metric we have now, and that's good, people seem to do better, became very aggressive
statin people.
And that story told early where we used to see MIs like crazy in our heyday, we stopped
seeing them anymore.
So we had at least anecdotal belief that these things were working.
And lo and behold, pharma knew ultimately they were going to have to do serious outcome
trials.
And the first group of people they studied were Swedish guys who survived an MI and had
an LDL cholesterol of 190.
So these patients had FH?
In retrospect, they're FH patients, who's got an LDL cholesterol, one of the definitions
of FH.
And giving them a dose of Simvastatin got your 25% reduction in clinical events.
So outcome data, bingo, great drug.
And right behind them was Bristol-Myers Squibb, who had the much weaker statin, Pravastatin,
sold originally as the branded Pravacol.
Let's study Irishmen who have not had a clinical event, but also their LDL cholesterol is 180,
190, some more FH Irishmen.
So you're going from secondary prevention FH, basically to primary prevention FH.
And lo and behold, reduced virtually every atheros
to
takes
super cholesterol rich. The liver can pull cholesterol back effluxate so to speak from
the bile back into the liver. Why? Because what is also expressive to hepatobiliary surface,
the neem and pixi one like protein. So, azetomibe has two areas where it acts. It blocks the intestine
from internalizing cholesterol, but it prevents the liver from internalizing cholesterol from a
biliary source. Put them both together, you're depleting the liver of more cholesterol and the
liver needs cholesterol. There's a sterile sensor, the sterile regulatory element binding protein,
a nuclear transcription factor that turns on your genes that make LDL receptors.
So this is interesting, Tom. I mean, the beauty of doing these podcasts is I'm also learning as
we're doing them, right? And this is an enormous insight to me that I now remember you once telling
me about this, but it was just one of those things where I was like drinking from a fire hose and
clearly this detail left me. I'm generally not a huge Zetia fan, Zetia or zetomibe. I just generally
think it's kind of too impotent for real curiosity and sort of reserve it for situations where
patients can't really tolerate statins much and can't afford PCS, can't end inhibitors and all these
things. Historically, the way I've decided on who's a great Zetia candidate or not is looking at
phytosterols or looking at other proxies of absorption. And I've argued, by the way,
that the trials that suggested Zetia were not that valuable in monotherapy. It's never been shown to
reduce. No, they never did a monotherapy clinical trial. But they didn't even do a monotherapy.
It would work if you picked the right person. Well, that was always my argument, which was
it might have been a mistake in patient selection. You didn't select hyper absorbers. But what you're
saying would suggest that that would dilute my argument. Because if it only worked at the
Neiman-Pixie one-like-one transporter, the argument would be target your hyper absorbers.
But if it also works at biliary cholesterol, that shouldn't matter that much. No, but yeah,
no, that's part of hyper absorption. Because remember, if you're pulling it back into the
liver, you're depleting the cholesterol of a pool of cholesterol. But is the liver also then going
to be a dominant source of where we'll see cytosterol, campaignsterol, et cetera?
The final body preservation way, God forbid, phytosterols make it into your column microns
or your HDLs. And I can make the case that if they ever get into a cell, they're going to
injure that cell. But most of the column microns are going to deliver to the liver first before
it goes out in a VODL. So the liver will, if you're over absorbing phytosterols, a lot of them
do make their ways back to the liver. And the liver recognize them instantly is using your analogy,
that stupid bouncer in the intestine let you in. That Neiman-Pek in the ABC let you in.
We're getting ready. We're the backup police.
So you're the VIP lounge bouncer.
Yeah, right. So boom, out you go again. Now I realize those dopes may let you in again,
but you're going to come right back here and I'm getting you out again. So great analogy here,
the VIP bouncer. So who's to say? Zetomime is taken out or reducing the functioning of the Neiman,
and I think it's in both areas. Merck knows this. Merck didn't want to, that's too much education to
give. Let's just tell them it blocks cholesterol absorption. The gut would make sense to most
people. Most people, including lipidologists, don't even know the liver's involved in the process.
So it was like advanced lipid study and stuff. We don't have to confuse people with that. I've
written a number of articles on it. Zetom, Peter Toth and I think did one of our oral class articles
on the mechanisms of it and stuff. Yeah, what year was that? We just got to make sure we linked to
that one. I've come back with my years, but it's probably, I don't know, 2010, 2008,
but it's really with great diagrams, of course, showing you and explaining where Neiman Pick is.
And that's Toth, T-O-T-H. Yeah, Peter is one of the key and certainly mentors in my life. And
of course, Peter and my Deversons had me write the chapter in the book, Therapeutic Lipidology
on Phytosterolimia. And Davidson's at Northwestern, right? He's at University of Chicago. And look,
very early on, probably because I was just such a good educator on lipids, lipoproteins, and statin
mechanosuction, I was in very early in Merck's investigation of cholesterol absorption and
became a very effective educator on that too. And therefore, I had great contact with a lot of the
Merck scientists, the Swedes who all invented all these absorption markers and stuff and really
became subspecialties in lipidology and sterols as one of them. Why do you think that the Zetia
combination, synvastatin trials, so the main trial with Zetia was with and without synvastatin,
correct? No. Or sort of synvastatin with and without synvastatin. The reason why Zetia,
my mistake in so many damn hits is Merck's poor thinking of the type of trials that let's bring
to market to show that this is a great drug. And instead of just doing the damn outcome,
daddy, even doing a solid outcome trial in the right person, primary prevention, as well as,
of course, do your secondary prevention trials, even do that first if you want to. And if that
fails, you're not going to do anything with it. But let's, they wanted to just get so much to
market. What's the easiest thing to do? IMT. So let's take people with a lot of lipid abnormalities,
carotid intimal thickening, which is an ultrasound measurement of the thickness of your carotid
artery, which has some correlation with subclinical atherosclerosis and clinical events.
And that's unarguable. And therefore they're at risk. They have lipid abnormalities. Let's give
them as they're, you know, they're on a statin because we have to give them statins if they're
LDL is that a metric? Is that a whack? Let's give them one half of the group is that a mibe
in the other half placebo is that a mibe and let's follow their IMTs. We only have to do that for a
year or two and we'll see IMT progression in one arm and no IMT progression in the other.
Only did that virtually every lipid parameter, including APO big got better. Every inflammatory
mark has got better. Any IMT didn't change whatsoever. Meaning Simvastatin had the same
IMT as Simvastatin plus a satin. In a short time. And of course we now know that what happens to
IMT with any drug has virtually no relationship to clinical outcomes. So that's not a tool you should
be using to follow up and saying, look at it's like the coronary calcium score. It's not the
tool you should be using to demonstrate the efficacy. They should have looked at, but look
at this APO B reduction beyond what Simvastatin can do. Look at the triglyceride reduction. Look
at the CRP reduction beyond what Simvastatin can do. Or ox LDL or any of these things. At least say
that doesn't mean anything, but they had already polluted the minds that IMT was the best way to
check the drugs. Obviously nothing trumps a hard outcome. If you can reduce MACE, that's the way
to go. Sorry, major adverse cardiac event. But they picked the wrong shortcut is basically what
it comes down to. There were better shortcuts you could take. And who did that turn off big time?
The images of the world, the cardiologist who instantly dismissed the Zetimib as the world's
most useless drug. Most cardiologists don't even know what APO B is. And nevermind that. Look at
this as a potent thing. I hinted to you, I was very much involved with the Reloxifin, the first
CERN that came to the market. As good an APO B lowering drug as Zetimib is, which might have
portended great cardiovascular benefit to the CERN-Reloxin, which I believe it still has. In fact,
we have some. They did a big cardiovascular outcome trial where it was no, didn't hurt anybody,
but it didn't reduce events. But if you looked at the primary prevention people in that trial,
it did lower events. Now post-Hawk hypothesis generating data, but an 8%, a 5% lowering of
APO B mattered. And I think the right trial done with Zetimib and outcomes, it would matter.
But we're never going to know, and this gets to a really interesting point when it comes to
pharma's challenge of studying atherosclerosis today. The industry is now going to always be a
victim of the success of statins. It is unethical to take high risk patients and take them off
statins, despite what the internet wants to tell you that statins are evil and all that nonsense,
which I don't want to get into. But if you actually have any modest understanding of how these drugs
work, they absolutely save lives, especially when directed at the right patients at the right
times. What that means is you want to study another drug, you're adding it to a statin.
You are not doing it in mono. You don't get to do the study of Zetia versus placebo. It's not
ethical. No, but if you've picked the right patient. You think of a reason it would be ethical to do
such a trial. Yes. You take a bunch of highly, highly statin intolerant patients. So that would
be one which they're never going to do for a variety of reasons. But here's another, and
Merck did two big outcome trials where they could use. You didn't necessarily have to give a patient
a statin. They took people with significant aortic stenosis and of the belief, because
calcium and there's cholesterol in those aortic valves that if we could lower cholesterol and
people with aortic stenosis, we'd reduce morbidity related to that. And we don't have to give them a
statin because statins failed to reduce outcomes in people with aortics. Those trials were already
done. So they took the C's trial, aortic stenosis, zetimibe, and lowered it. And guess what? Did
nothing to end points related to, because they're enrolling people who need surgery for God's sake.
Yeah. I mean, again, that just, I mean, that kind of stuff just, it breaks my heart. It doesn't
anger me. It breaks my heart. But again, post hoc analysis, they did reduce the
ischemic events in that trial with zetimibe. So MI's went down and JYNA went down, but that's post
hoc analysis. And they got lucky. They didn't power for that. No. They may or may not be legit.
Correct. So you'd have to do another whole trial to do it again. And so, but they were hoping to
sneak by without doing. And the next thing they did was statins had failed to reduce clinical
events in people with chronic renal failure. Statins didn't work. So let's give them a statin
plus zetimibe. So you had the sharp trial renal, they had pretty bad GFRs. So everybody, two groups
got a statin, but the one group got a statin and zetimibe and the statin zetimibe group reduced
events. Whereas it's statin zetimibe works. So, and then of course they really had to wait for
the acute coronary syndrome, entirely improve it trial to really convince the cardiologist that,
yes, a little bit of extra B lowering, at least in that type of horrendously risky people matters.
And we now have had that replicated with the PCSK9 in it. And a great point you made up lately.
I mean, cost them God knows how long the money to do that, improve it trial. And they really had
extended a couple of extra years to reach statistical significance, which turns somebody's
loud mouse on the internet dismiss it because of that now. But it's a miracle and people that are
aggressively treated with statin, that you've reduced their LDLC to way, way down that just
by lowering it a little bit more, you can get extra event reduction. And I would never downplay that.
I think it's miraculous that it worked. And I think it's why it's miraculous PCSK9 inhibitors
work in trials where they're enrolling you where your LDLC is 70 for God's sakes, because you're on
a statin or statin-a-zetimibe. So that to me is one of the single most impressive things. And again,
we don't know if this is going to be true in 10 years. Again, all facts have a half life,
but from the moment we are sitting here today having this discussion, the fact that the Fourier
trial could take patients who had an average LDLC of 92 milligrams per deciliter on statins,
that means they are at the 10th percentile of the Framingham population on a statin. You are
going to add either a placebo or a PCSK9 inhibitor. In that case, it was Rapatha. You're going to
study them for less than two and a half years and you're going to even have the nerve to suggest
that might reduce an event and oh, it did. And if it doesn't, you've just wasted billions of dollars
of our money. What bean counter allowed that trial to proceed? I had been following this story even
before I became interested in lipids just out of interest in the novelty of you see a natural
experiment, which is PCSK9 hyperfunctionings, PCSK9 hypofunctionings, MR drug. It just became a
beautiful, elegant model. And then I remember-
The problem with real life takes decades to express itself.
That's right. And this all took a decade. And I remember thinking, especially once I got
interested in lipids, on the one hand being excited and the other hand thinking, there's
no goddamn way this trial can work. You could not reduce events in 2.2 years. And they did. And of
course, this is how naive I am. And this is why whenever people ask me for advice, friends will
say, Hey, should I invest in this company or that company? My advice to them is don't listen to a
single thing I say because you're asking a question, will the market value something which I have no
input on? I can provide you plenty of input on whether it makes scientific sense, but you have
to talk to somebody with a different skillset to understand if that's an investible thesis.
And so I remember Amgen kind of got hammered when the trial came out because people thought,
that wasn't enough of an improvement, which I thought it's amazing. And in reality, in fairness
to the market, I think what the market was basically saying is if you did the math based
on that trial under those circumstances, it would be a million dollars or more to save a life.
Well, that's a fair question for the market to assess. But if you look at it from a scientific
standpoint, that you could take that patient population and achieve that outcome, I think
it's one of the most remarkable things in cardiovascular medicine. And to your point,
it doesn't even speak to the patients that I have on PCSK9 inhibitors. My patients who take PCSK9
inhibitors are patients whom prior to this drug, we were flailing with what? Maybe some niacin,
maybe some monotherapy, Zettia, maybe the smallest dose of Livoloe that a human could tolerate and
getting woefully inadequate coverage. As you know, you're doing that off FDA label because they would
want to try. And they're paying out of pocket for it. So people who can afford it, but it's certainly
the genetic model tells them you're doing smart there. And what are your option is to, and I would
say, as you know, there are certain nutritional therapies that can send your LDL particle count
off the roof. And people are dismissing that as a meaningless biomarker now, because if you do this
biomarkers X, Y, and Z, and maybe even your waistline looks better, but APOB, LDL-P, doesn't matter in
them. Every single thing that's ever been done genetically or properly done clinical trial shows,
it does matter. And an individual, can I say, yes, it matters in you, it does not know. But if I want
to follow the bulk of the data, it matters over time. So maybe if I send your LDL-P off the chart
for two years, it doesn't matter. But do I want to do this for the next 15 years? If you're a young
person on a type of nutritional program that sends that through the roof, is that wise? How are you
going to be mad at me in 20 years or 15 years? Because I put you in the CCU. I don't know.
Yeah. How many Nobel prizes have been awarded within the field of lipid science? At least three,
right? Well, certainly you got the LDL receptor and you got two for cholesterol. And I'm guaranteed
on other lipid things or might be a Nobel historian. No, but it's interesting, right? I
mean, I think this is one of the things that, I guess there are a handful of discussions I have
with patients that I find frustrating. Some of them are frustrating because I have the same
discussion over and over again, and I've written about the topic and the patient just won't read
what I've at least written or at least take the time to read or listen to a lecture to then come
back and ask a question. So that's sort of frustrating for a different reason. But few things
frustrate me more than having to discuss things where the patient's baseline of knowledge is the
internet, which obviously you have all the signal can be found there, but the noise of course is so
great that you just don't know. But it's these discussions around cholesterol and statins that
I find most disturbing because in some ways it's partly the fault of the pharma industry, I think.
They have to take some responsibility for this, which is in an effort to get these drugs into the
majority of people who need them, there's been a need to simplify the message. And when you simplify
things, especially things as complicated as this field, you will undoubtedly make mistakes. You will
undoubtedly create confusion. And so now we have a system where most physicians don't understand
enough to actually explain to their patients why they are putting them on statins and which patients
may or may not even be good statin candidates, something I want to come back to because you
brought it up and I think it's worthy of its own sort of thread that will go down, which is this
whole brain issue. It's a totally separate issue, but it's this idea of failing to educate patients
and physicians has allowed basically a, I don't know, call it a militia of internet
noise that is just completely ungrounded in science. I mean, it's just completely ungrounded,
it's completely disconnected. And you already mentioned one example,
there's several others where a drug has come to market and then some harm would develop it. So
therefore you castigate every drug that's ever been invented as aha. Even though we just,
even though we just illustrated, right, you can take two drugs that inhibit two enzymes
and get different results and get completely different results. Same result, same result,
biomarker, but different outcomes. And so I always try to tell patients, although I don't know,
that probably falls on deaf ears, but you got to think of every drug like you think of a tool,
right? If you had a general contractor and he had a hammer, a screwdriver, a drill, a level,
a nail, a screw, et cetera, you would want to have the most tools in the tool belt. That's the first
condition. And the second condition is you'd want to know when to use each tool and what its
limitation was. And in that sense, the one view, which is statins should be in the drinking water,
and then the other view, which is statins cause everything from diabetes, Alzheimer's disease,
to global warming. Both of those views are so idiotic that I just, it's very difficult for
me to process that. And I've basically stopped engaging on Twitter with any of that discussion.
You can't either extreme. You got to get rid of those people very quickly, or you just get annoyed
all day long. And this is why it ultimately comes down to, and it's the way you practice.
So you got to individualize everything. So anybody who says statins belong in the drinking water,
that's no public health solution to anything, or nobody should ever take that's absurd.
Statins have tons of proof that you got to pick and choose your patients properly. And this is why
in the latter part of my career, I've developed so much more into biomarkers and other
risk assessment tools, because the better we can define an individual's
risk to any disease that he might be prone to, we can attack that disease through many mechanisms.
Part of an atherosclerosis is you got to attack APOB. If you don't, good luck. But the more you
understand, and that's where biomarkers and really not understanding the only understanding is
pathogen, he talked about a lot more clinical chemistry. The average clinician has no clue how
a laboratory reports a given concentration of anything to him. I'd like to go into triglycerides
because everybody thinks the whole world... People have no clue how laboratories assay triglycerides,
and maybe later we can talk about that. Well, one of the things that I've been pleased with
is once I got back into medicine, I realized I didn't know that stuff. And I have been really
fortunate every lab I have reached out to, to come and actually come to the lab and see how it works,
including THD. They've all opened the doors and said, come on in, Peter.
Oder, what the happier?
And they overdo it. I love it. They literally will walk me from every station to every... This is
where the specimen arrives. So you can see where the FedEx box dumps off the specimen. This is how
we take it out. This is how it's handled. This is boom, boom, boom, all the way to here are the
magnets where we're doing the NMR. And I've got precision analytics has also been great. I went
up and spent two days with them a few years ago. And I agree. I mean, again, not every physician,
I think has the luxury of time because they're clinically so much busier than I am. So I
certainly don't fault physicians for not doing that. But I do wish there was a way to make that
sort of experience more available to physicians because the more you understand how these tests
are done, the more you understand what your blind spots can be.
Yeah. And I was doing that for a while when I had more of a net presence with full lectures,
which I don't do anymore or they're not available on the net anymore. But just one other thing,
like I told you, most people are clueless that labs don't measure triglycerides. They measure
glycerol in your blood and they calculate that into triglycerides. But when you get an LDL
cholesterol or a total, let's talk about LDL cholesterol. The assay that's analyzing the
sterol in that particle has no difference. Does it know whether it's cytostral,
campestral, desmostral, cholesterol? No. All it knows is it's a sterol.
So it just knows it's not a stanol.
When you get LDL, it'll measure a stanol too, but they would likely be a small part of it.
So LDL cholesterol is really LDL cholesterol plus LDL cytostrul plus LDL-
Plus LDL desmostral.
And the other 48, then a little bit of whatever, stanols may have made their way into your body
too. So they don't know that. So in a person with phytosterolemia, a large part of that
LDL cholesterol value is a-
Is the phytosterol.
Yeah. But they don't realize. So they don't even know,
could a zetimibe have a better- If phytosterols are injurious, and I can make that case,
if I did a one hour lecture to using proper slides, you would be pretty convinced,
I want phytosterols not in my body. Zetimibe is the only way to keep them out there.
And wherever you're going next, my final word on a zetimibe would be,
if you're a big believer in this reverse cholesterol transport process,
which I've certainly expounded on now, what is the number one pharmacologic agent
that increases the amount of cholesterol that's winding up in your toilet bowl,
because it's in your stool?
That would be the best reverse cholesterol transport,
because the final common pathway to reverse cholesterol transport is,
it's out of the body. Zetimibe by far.
So I can make the case that if I wanted a lipid lowering drug,
and the drinking water is first line, it would be a zetimibe, not a statin.
So very interesting.
And very controversial.
Yeah. And the FDA would put me in a lunatic asylum,
and so would these so-called evidence-based guys.
But if you're analyzing this from cholesterol homeostatic pathways, it's a great drug.
Yeah. Well, we'll come back to all drugs.
I guess the next place-
Most of the time, we do have to lower APOB a lot more than a zetimibe could ever do by itself.
So the one that we've left out before we get,
I want to come back to niacin from a trials perspective,
but let's take a break right now, and then we'll come back and we'll pick it up with,
I want to talk about the fibrates, and then obviously I want to talk about niacin through
a clinical trial standpoint, and then we'll get into the PCSK9.
So we'll take a break right now, and we will come back.
Okay, guys. So we are now back.
We're going to slice this beginning into where we finished off.
So we had sort of more or less finished talking about zetimibe, also known as Zetia.
So we use this as an opportunity to go into the next drug.
So, all right. So Tom, that was pretty insightful stuff on Zetia, also known as zetimibe.
Let's move to another class of drugs that doesn't get a lot of use.
I can probably count on two hands the number of times I've prescribed it,
which is phenofibrate, or more broadly, it's class of fibrates.
What the heck are these drugs? How do they work, and when should we use them?
Well, if you practice in the United States, you do have two choices.
You have phenofibrate, and you have gemfibrazole, and they're both out there.
They're both can be attained generically nowadays.
So probably phenofibrate still comes in branded form.
That's the trilimbrics.
But you don't have to, that's one of them.
There are other branded forms available out there.
Gemfibrazole is a pro-drug. It has to be converted into the active fibric acid,
whereas phenofibrate is the active form right away.
So it's a little bit more bioavailable than it.
It's kind of interesting for the purists of the world.
Gemfibrazole has a monotherapy outcome trial given to veterans with coronary artery disease
who had low HDL cholesterol and high triglycerides,
and it reduced events as much as the statin did in any trial.
So there's outcome evidence.
Was it independent of triglyceride level?
Yeah, it was independent, although they enrolled people.
But many of the men, the triglyceride levels were certainly not at super high levels or so.
But it was mostly low HDL cholesterol,
and virtually all of those people have some degree of triglyceride elevation.
But they tried to recruit people with what at the time was considered a normal LDL cholesterol also.
Which trial was this?
It's called the Veterans Affairs High Density Lipoprotein trial.
VA hit.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I didn't realize that was VA hit.
Yeah, and that was Gemfibrazole.
And remember, Gemfibrazole already had outcome data from the Helsinki Heart trial too.
So this would be the second trial.
Now, phenofibrate did come along with a couple of big trials,
but it missed the primary outcome but hit some secondary outcomes
for a whole lot of reasons, enrolling the wrong people, heavy concomitant use of statins.
Nobody in any Gemfibrazole trial was ever polluted by people sneaking in statins with it at the same
time. And clearly, whatever fibrates do, they do it differently than statins.
And the question is, can it contribute to a statin?
But those trials weren't designed to do that, but they were so polluted by statin use.
And I just want to clarify what you mean.
I know what you mean, but I want the listener to understand.
When you say polluted by, what we're talking about is statins are so potent
that when you include them in trials, you are making it much harder for a new drug or compound
that's being investigated to show its effect because you've effectively raised the bar
much higher for what needs to be done.
Sure. You've taken out one path. You're trying to prove with a certain class of drug that
via these mechanisms, very different works. And then all of a sudden, you're getting rid of all
the ApoB particles via the statins. And the statin is not given in a randomized fashion here.
Somebody takes it, somebody don't. Some doctors, you take this, don't take it.
Yeah. So that's the bigger problem scientifically. Of course, the counter-argument is, look,
ethically, we don't want someone getting randomized to no medication. And then the second issue is,
if the statin is the standard of care and therefore in the community, quote unquote,
that's the way these drugs are going to be used is with or without statins,
that's the way they should be tested. So it's all of these are fair points.
But when you ask a true efficacy question versus an effectiveness question,
the cleaner you can ask that question, the better. And there's no cleaner way to ask it
than to not have another drug involved. Sure. And by the way, when those trials were done,
it was not standard of care that you had to be on a statin.
No.
So they were legitimate trials that were ethical.
Whereas with the PCSK9 trials, it was statin.
You couldn't do it.
You couldn't have a no statin arm in those trials.
Right. That being said, these are all factors that go into the post-hoc, at least interpretation of
some of these trials. But anyway, so gemfribrazole worked. And it's kind of interesting. You couldn't
explain the benefit of gemfribrazole in the VA HIT trial. But even though it did raise HDL cholesterol,
it was like a milligram and a half increase and it lowered triglycerides, but not to a significant
extent. So why did it work? Or were there other pleiotrophic type effects of fibrates or doing
something that we weren't measuring with any biomarker or so on? I mean, some of that is
probably true. But then they did at least in a cohort of it, they did a post-hoc analysis
using NMR. And this was Jim Ockfos who did this. And he found out that the benefit of the gemfribrazole
in the VA HIT trial could be easily explained by what it did to LDL particle count, which
fibrates do lower in certain patients, depending on the causator. And it raised the HDL particles,
which had a statistically significant tie-in to the clinical endpoint. And that was the first
trial showing anything that raising an HDL metric in a clinical trial. Maybe if you want to do an
HDL metric, it's HDL particle count. So can we make sense of that in light of what we spoke about,
I don't know, 20, 30 minutes ago, which was raising HDL cholesterol without paying any attention to
particle number or particle size is so noisy and at least as likely to be counterproductive as it is
productive. Here you had two pieces of information, of the three at least, which is you had more
particles, you didn't change the cholesterol content in total, so you could make some inference,
again, not necessarily correct, but you could at least have a better guess that you could make
about the clearance of cholesterol through HDL. But of course, then you have to make an
assumption about the size of the particle, correct? Yeah, but very interesting in that NMR analysis,
whereas HDL particle went up, it was almost all small HDL particles. And for years, people have
been running around saying the small HDLs are bad and the big HDLs are good and there was
serious evidence that boy, what BS that is. So, fibrates help to dilipidate HDL particles. So,
if you're in the old school of, hey, you're increasing reverse cholesterol transport because
the fibrates upregulate the scavenger receptor B1, which would dilipinate your HDL. So of course,
your HDLs would become smaller and then the small HDLs could theoretically traverse back into the
arterial wall, pull cholesterol out of your sterile laden foam cells, the histopathologic
mark or the plaque atherogenesis. And by the way, and aside from that, when we talked about the
complexities of the reverse cholesterol transport process, one pathway I didn't mention, it's a sub
sub pathway, something called Dan Rader coined this term years ago, macrophage reverse cholesterol
transport. And he used to make the case, the only aspect of the RCT that matters as far as
atherosclerotic clinical outcomes is dilipidating the foam cells in your artery wall of cholesterol.
And that's really the job of an HDL. It can get into the artery wall very easily.
There's another ABC that facilitates that.
There's a couple of them. There's ABCA1, which will lipidate small lipid poor HDL particles,
but there's ABCG1, which will lipidate big mature HDL particles. So you have two ABC
sterile efflux transporters in the surface of macrophages that can pull cholesterol,
efflux cholesterol out of the macrophage into a big or a small HDL, which can then return to the
plasma and the small one to sturifies it becomes a mature one and gives it to LDL, which returns it
to the liver. So macrophage RCT, which is certainly an incredibly functional aspect of what HDL does
has absolutely no relationships to the serum HDL cholesterol level. So again, how do I know?
I can't use HDL C as a metric to tell me I'm dilipidating plaque in your artery wall,
but I can have some confidence that if I'm using a fiber, that's one of the things I'm doing. If
you do have plaque in your artery wall, and who doesn't? Now, so why do you think the fibrates
work best in patients with a higher triglyceride level? Because their main mechanism of that,
yeah, look, so they modulate HDL particles, but triglycerides and there's a lot to do with HDL
remodeling too, but fibrates mostly stop the synthesis of VLDL particles, triglyceride rich
LDL particles in the liver by depleting triglyceride pools in the liver. Remember
what determines the lipidation of ApoB in your liver. All humans make two tons more of ApoB than
they ever have a prayer of lipidating and changing into an ApoB particle. The vast majority of your
ApoB gets catabolized because it's unused. So people always, Oh, what produces increase ApoB?
Nothing. You, your liver makes way more ApoB than any human can ever use. Why do we think that is?
I don't know. People just assume, Hey, if you're making too much of something, you got to be
increasing the components. Except the one component we make too much of and never use is ApoB.
Yeah. I just, I wonder why that teleologically would be the case that we would make orders of
magnitude more ApoB than we could ever want to export. Well, remember, A beta-lipoproteinemia is
death. So you have to make ApoB particles. They transport energy. They transport phospholipids.
They transport fat soluble vitamins, the big particles. So you can't not have
ApoB particles in your glass. So you think it's just a margin of safety that is so big. It's not
even. Well, yeah, they just make far more than we ever use. So, and it's very easily catabolized.
So you have a lot of it, but what determines the creation of the VLDL particle in the liver? It's
the lipid pools, how much lipid is available to attach to ApoB and create a circular spherical
particle that's going to be ejected by the liver. And that comes down to the cholesterol pool and
the triglyceride pool that's in that triglyceride. It's the stored energy in your liver and
cholesterol esters, the stored cholesterol in your liver. Cholesterol, I think I mentioned before,
binds to the cholesterol ester binds to the, or free cholesterol binds to the ApoB first.
Some of the cholesterol will be esterified even in the circulation. Some in the liver via that
ACAT enzyme. And so then once you get the little primordial spherical VLDL, then triglycerides
are transferred in using MTP, microsomal triglyceride transfer protein. And now you
got a real VLDL ready to be shipped out. Other, as it passes through something called the space
of this, which is a little space between hepatocytes and the plasma, other Apo proteins join there.
But believe it or not, many of them, as soon as that nascent VLDL or whatever you want to call it,
enters plasma, a ton of the Apo proteins just leave your HDL particles. One of the functions of
HDLs, remember I told you to transport proteins, they transport a ton of these proteins that are
involved with lipoprotein catabolism. So C2 jumps off of HDLs, E jumps off of HDLs and goes right
onto the surface of a VLDL if it was not put there as it passed through the space of this. So
and they all determine the catabolic fate of that VLDL particle. So fibrates through several
mechanisms. One you get is an enzyme involved with the synthesis of triglycerides. You know,
it's adding fatty acids to glycerol. Fibrates are a potent inhibitor of that. So you just stop
triglyceride production with fibrates. Omega 3 fatty acids work in a similar way. So they
deplete the hepatic pool of triglycerides and you're going to make less VLDL particles. Remember,
a fiber is not going to blow away your LDL P like a statin does, but it's going to blow
a 10, 15% reduction in part, depending on the triglyceride richness, not the serum triglyceride
level, but the triglyceride richness of the core. So that's one of the. Now where's the backup of
free fatty acids? Because at some point, if you're not synthesizing as much triglyceride,
but you still have enough fatty acid, you're absorbing fatty acid, you're adipocyte storm.
But is there a hepatic backup of fatty acids? Or de novo synthesis. So in other words,
this would not decrease naphyl D if you had a patient, because at first blush, you'd think,
well, a fibrate should be able to reduce fatty acid to reduce fatty liver.
It was thought that for years, but it's just never been proven in a trial that that alone would do
it. Whereas actually, a Zetimibe has more data on reducing fatty liver than a fibrate still.
And most people all blame fatty liver on triglycerides. It's a
sterols that really cause a large part of the lipotoxicity that results in injury to the cells
in your liver. And there's a lot of animal data on the Zetimibe eradicating fatty liver because
they deplete the cholesterol pool in the liver. So it's not all fatty acids and triglycerides
that are causing fatty liver sounds like it is, but it's a toxic disease to the list, a lipotoxic
disease, and it's not all fatty acids. Although the fatty acids must play a significant role when
you look at, I shouldn't say must, but would suggest it because when you look at some of
the preliminary data now that's coming out with fructose elimination, meaning without restricting
any other macro or micro, it doesn't matter about, it seems that glucose is not that relevant,
even fatty acid composition, not that relevant if you completely restrict fructose.
Well, fructose is a major stimulus for synthesis of the triglyceride.
The triglyceride, but not to my knowledge. I don't know where it would fit into the
cholesterol synthetic pathway, right?
But look, it's a lipotoxic disease, but one of the major lipids that's causing
hepatocellular toxicity is cholesterol. It's just not all fatty acids. I don't know,
not implying or no role of fatty acids or fatty acid synthesis, triglyceride synthesis related
to fructose, but it's not all just somehow ignore cholesterol and you're going to get rid of fatty
liver. And you can't even separate the two because if you have a lot of triglyceride,
you're going to have a lot of ApoB particles that are part of the cause of that sterile toxicity.
Yeah, that's probably the bigger issue. It's very difficult to disaggregate them once
triglycerides are elevated. So really the ideal candidate for phenofibrate is going to be someone
with an elevated ApoB and an elevated triglyceride.
So if you look at, even if you take the two positive gemfibers all trials and the failure
of phenofibrate in a couple of trials, easily explained if you look at things,
but if you do look in the, and basically they enroll people that didn't have insulin resistance
or triglyceride rich lipoproteins and gave them a fibrate. So they designed a clinical trial where
nobody in their right mind would ever give that person a fibrate for a bunch of reasons. Hey,
but they were diabetic, but that was their field trial is 100% diabetics. And so they figured it's
a no brainer fibrates because of so many things that they do will improve outcomes. And then
maybe they would have, but the field trial was so polluted by statin, unauthorized use of statins,
inappropriate use of statins. Remember you're in a clinical trial. You've got the trialists watching
you, but you're going to your own private doctor. He can, and they were nervous at the time because
the statin data was coming in and it was almost, it was getting to the point where you're a bad
doctor if you don't give a statin to somebody with a lipid disorder. So they said, I know you're in
a trial. We don't know what you're getting, but I'm sorry. I'm not happy with your LDL cholesterol.
Take a statin. So it can Tammany, you know, we can always guess if we could have kept it as a pure
trial of fiber, but it worked in diabetics, but you know, that's just opinion. They didn't work,
but it did work in everybody who had an increase in triglycerides and low HDL cholesterol. It worked
in, that's where the outcome reduction was very interesting, which no other lipid drug has ever
done. It reduced several microvascular endpoints in those trials to retinopathy, amputations,
peripheral neuropathy, renal disease, even though phenofibrate can raise creatinine a little bit,
GFR improved and renal outcomes improved. So what other drug you got, you can give a person that
relessons his chance of a diabetic retinopathy if he's a diabetic, nothing. Now it's post-hoc,
it's secondary. Well, that wasn't put, that was secondary outcomes. So the trials weren't designed
to prove that. So they were hypothesis. You'd have to theoretically go back and do that before
the FDA would ever give you approval, but kind of interesting data. So, you know, I always made
the case, what? Fibrates reduce amputations, neuropathic ulcers, improve renal disease,
save your eyes. Why the hell are you not on a fibrate if you're a diabetic? You know? So again,
using that type of data and people use drugs for far less data than that. These are big, huge trials
and all of those endpoints have published their analysis of those secondary endpoints and everything.
What are the main side effects of Phenofibrate? Not a heck of a lot. You know, it's a pretty
well tolerated drug. Anybody can get any number of any side effects with it or so. People used to be
afraid of the increasing creatinine until in the field trial, there and a large number of patients
were doing creatinine clearance and that didn't go. So there was a muscular buildup of creatinine
had nothing to do with GFR or renal clearance of it. But there's nothing much. There are some drug
drug interactions. I mean, the Phenofibrate, Zetimide, I mean, they're both very well tolerated,
certainly more tolerated than statins. They really are. And you can make the case, at least in a
diabetic, which is probably going to be, especially with what we know now, the patient who's going to
wind up on a fibroid. Now most lipidologists wouldn't use it until you statinize somebody or
statinize them and zetimize them, got their ApoB as good as you can get. It's still not there.
Or triglycerides, which is what they're looking at too bad in my mind, but they look at that and
it's still high. That is the persons that were helped as at least in post hoc analysis of every
single fibroid trial, including the VA hit there and all the Phenofibrate trials. So that's pretty
much where it's reserved to people with these identified by hyper triglyceridemia patients or
so. And we're not talking about people with triglycerides of 400 or 4,000 where pancreatitis
comes into play. We'd probably all use a fibrate and a lot of other stuff there like Omega 3s there
on hopefulness that it would reduce the incidence of pancreatitis, not proven yet, but you would
attack that degree of hyper triglyceridemia. But the real world is people with triglycerides
between 130 and 300 that insulin resistant world, which we've already clearly defined as an ApoB
disorder. So that's why your statinizetimibe is your first line drugs there. But if you didn't
normalize that with your statinizetimibe or indeed triglycerides were still high. So you're
presuming there still are triglyceride rich lipoproteins, whatever they may be, they might be
remnants. They could be LDLs that are triglyceride rich, especially in the lipidology community who
are way more familiar with fibrates. Although it's sadly a disappearing drug that even younger
lipidologists come on board have never been taught anything about middle go back and Rudy. So it's
the older guys like me who grew up through all those trials have lectured on have written on them
really have a better understanding of it than a younger lipidologist. And that's unfortunate
because we're going to have a potentially effective drug for a certain amount of people
is just not going to be used anymore. They're apt to use a fish oil instead, which because it lowers
triglycerides and it's so easy to tell somebody to take a fish oil, they're not going to go home
and read potentially scary stuff on the internet where they might with a fibrate or so.
They're going to still read it.
I guess on everything you're going to read some crazy stuff on the internet. So tragically to me,
because I don't believe there's when you say fish oil, is it more the EPA that's having the
effect on triglyceride or EPA would have more an effect on Apo B, but DHA is the triglyceride.
These are some recent brand new data published on that. Because DHA is just more potent on C3 than
is EPA. So I personally think you ought to give both if the primary reason you're going to throw
a fish oil, a prescription fish oil product at somebody is I need extra Apo B lowering.
Yeah. Then I would give high dose EPA, but I monitor omega three levels in everybody. So
not everybody can convert EPA to DHA. DHA is just as crucial for a lot of reasons. Your brain
sure wants it. So I will measure, Oh my God, I'm giving you a lot of EPA, but you're one of the
people who can't convert it to DHA. So then I would give you some DHA or you take the high
strength EPA and you throw in a lesser strength EPA, DHA combo tablet, which is how you get it.
As far as I know, there's no DHA only tablet. Where is EPA only tablets, certainly in the
prescription realm. So, you know, fine. If you want to lower Apo B, you can stick with your
Apo B, but I don't have, where's my evidence that if I use whatever fish oil therapy you
want to use, I'm happy. I'm improving microvascular disease. I have pretty serious evidence that I'm
doing that at least with phenofibrate. And the other thing, although they're both available
generically, sometimes these old drug companies, they'll force Genfibrasol on you. The real reason
when you ask me, are there any side effects about fibrates? And I did say the word drug
interactions. Phenofibrate has a serious drug interaction with Coumadin. So you have to lessen
the Coumadin dose there. We're using a lot less Coumadin. We're using much more eloquence these days.
Yeah. So that's becoming less of a big worry, but God forbid somebody's on Coumadin and you didn't
know that you threw big dose phenofibrate out on them. They caught you up with a lot of bruises
because you know, you potentiate the anticoagulant effect. Genfibrasol though, has her
raises statin levels through the roof. So there's much more incidence of myositis and rhabdomyolysis
when you use Genfibrasol with a statin and there's none of it with phenofibrate.
So if you want to use a fibrate, I strongly encourage you because it is generic nowadays
to use phenofibrate because you're going to be using it with a statin in the vast majority of
cases. So you don't have that worry, the muscular worry or so. So those are the two big things you
better know about fibrates you don't. And so most of the lipidologists released were somewhat
schooled on fibrates are going to use it in people where the triglyceride parameter is still high
because they're assuming, I think if we had better metrics of triglyceride rich lipoproteins,
maybe VLDL remnants or people who have high LDL triglyceride levels and they would likely be
people who have ApoC3 on their LDLs, we have some other evidence that I want to fibrate on board you
or so. So that's where that's going to get used, but that's not your average person who walks into
and if he walks into the average doctor, doc's going to be chasing LDL cholesterol or non-HL
cholesterol if they're a little more astute and they're going to stop there.
I want to come back to, I made a note here to come back to VLDL remnants. So I got another
question on that, but I do want to finish our tour of drugs. So the next drug to then get into,
we've already kind of talked about a little bit, but I want to come back to it because I know you
have a strong point of view on it and I got to be honest, I'm a little bit ambivalent. I don't know
the last time I prescribed this drug, but just from an intellectual standpoint, I'm always
interested in these drugs for people who can't go down a mainstream route and that drug of course
is niacin. So I don't think there's anybody out there that says, Hey, niacin is first line. I don't
think anybody would argue that. I think the question is you take a statin intolerant patient
who's got normal triglycerides, who maybe doesn't respond particularly well to monotherapy Zetia,
who can't afford a PCSK9 inhibitor and doesn't meet the regs for approval.
Are these patients who should be on niacin? So I'll go back to where we were earlier.
Niacin exists in an immediate release in a time release form.
Oh, two types of time release forms.
Oh, I didn't even realize that.
Intermediate release and sustained release.
So Niacin span, the Abbott version is.
That's intermediate release.
That's a prescription only product, which you're not going to get covered by any.
No, no, no, no. I learned that the hard way because I had a patient that was on it a few
years ago and he got a bill for like they wanted $3,000.
I didn't know what's that high.
It's ridiculous.
But if you want to, you somehow believe in niacin and want to give it a trial,
immediate release and you got to give it three or four times a day at massive doses,
you'll flush your brains out. Most people you're going to make the case you're not
flushing nice and isn't working in you. So let's talk about what the sustained
release is cheap. You can get sustained release.
But the biggest problem was in clinical trials, niacin being the toxic drug it is,
there's way more hepatotoxicity with sustained release niacin than there is with the short
release or the extended release where there's no hepatotoxicity.
So first of all, niacin became interesting as you talked about because it's known,
it's been known for a long period of time. It lowers cholesterol, lowered LDL cholesterol.
Yeah. And better yet, raise HDL cholesterol. That's what everybody always focus on.
Everybody since low HDL cholesterol is a risk factor. We now know April B related,
but whatever. Therefore, if low HDL cholesterol is bad, raising HDL cholesterol has to be good.
And niacin is the best product you had at the time. And then so trials were done with niacin.
And it's kind of funny because I listened to the podcast you and Ron Kraus did. And it was kind of
cool because you made the case a little bit for niacin, Ron Dick. But at the end, as you just said,
you're ambivalent to it. And even Ron says, I don't use it much anymore. And then you maybe
wind up, okay, it's a fourth line drug if everything else has failed. All right. I'm not
going to smack you around too much if you say that. And you can't prescribe a PCSK9 inhibitor
because of cost. All right. But I think at the end of your go back and listen to you,
you both said, you don't use the darn drug anymore.
I think the difference is, and this is where I'd love to hear your take. I think Ron's point of
view was the niacin trials may have failed for the same reason that we would see the discussions
we talked about earlier, which was overly statinized patients. Now you kind of had a different point
of view on that, right? No, because there was never, they weren't statinized in any, certainly
the big, niacin has one trial designed to use niacin as a monotherapy. It was that big
coronary drug project, which was a multi-prong therapeutic trial where they randomized people
to a bunch of drugs. One group was given solely thyroid hormone. Thyroid hormone lowers LDL
cholesterol. And all they did was kill people by with coronary disease, you give them thyroid
hormone. They're not, you make them hyperthyroid, not exactly good if you have coronary. So that
drug failed. They used a primitive fibrate, clofibrate. And there was some question of a
mortality adversity there. So that was hit number one on the whole foot. Nobody in America uses
clofibrate anymore. It's probably still available in Europe. I don't think anybody uses it.
So fibrate arm of that trial failed and they used estrogen given to men because, hey, women don't
get heart disease because they have high estrogen levels. If we just gave estrogen to men, they
wouldn't get heart attacks and they had immediately stopped the trial by precipitating heart attacks
in men by prescribing estrogen. So, uh, the only thing that would make that funnier was please
tell me they gave it orally. They did. Oh, yeah. That's the only form they had anyway. So yes.
And then they had a niacin immediate release niacin arm. And now you know, in a clinical trial
world, if you go down to the FDA and you just put a drug through a clinical trial, you better be
empowered or better not have been much toxicity and you better come in and have hit your primary
end point. Cause what will the FDA never ever allow you to discuss a secondary end point? If
you fail the primary end point, you've ever failed drug. All you've done by improving some secondary
end point is generated a new hypothesis. Let's go back and do a trial on those people. So what was
the primary end point in the coronary drug project? Favorite end point that people today love,
mortality and guess what? Niacin did to mortality. It worsened it not statistically, but it,
you could say it was no, but it was certainly going in the wrong direction.
So did I care when they did the secondary analysis that, but wait a minute, myocardial infarctions
were down. It was like me telling you in that aortic stenosis trial, but Hey, Zetia reduced
myocardial infarctions, but it didn't reduce the order. But in fairness, was the trial powered
for mortality or was it powered for, um, no, it was powered mortality was the end. The only end
point and all the arms that are trials, that's what they were looking back at. Then all cause
mortality or coronary mortality? No, it was all cause mortality. I don't know if it's kind of
amazing because I mean, that's very unusual. You're talking about a trial in the 1960s, you know,
early trials, you know what, how they picked end points and stuff, but niacin. So don't come
and preach to me that it hit secondary end points. Wait a second. Wait a second. Why is it that
niacin failed this trial in the sixties? And it was only three or four years ago that the,
basically the payer said we're no longer paying for it. Well, because we've had a lot of other
trial data that's come down since then where other types of niacin and probably better designed
trials also failed to reduce any end points. So the evidence became overwhelming. Show me a damn
trial where it works and then maybe we'll give you a, we'll pay for it. At least the FDA would
never give it an indication without primary end point that or so. Then the other thing they did
with that coronary drug project is they published like a 10, 12 years later, the most ridiculous
post-hoc analysis done on questionnaire sent to people who they could round up, who they
discovered you were in the original trial, small number and low and behold mortality was improved
in that group of people, coronary mortality. So there we have evidence that niacin improves
coronary mortality. But it's still, it's still a worst. It wouldn't even be published today. It
would be laughed at if you ever submitted it to a journal. The, the coronary drug project might,
I don't think a drug company would even send the coronary drug project to a journal nowadays. I
mean, they almost have to nowadays. No trials. They tried to hide them in the end, but you know,
that population, thank God it did. So we learned a lot about a lot of drugs in that trial. So there
was no evidence in a trial designed to prove niacin reduces coronary heart disease, at least the
level one evidence. Then of course guys said, well, angiography got introduced and it could
start doing regular angiograms. It's uncor quantitative angiogram where you're basically
looking at the lumen of an artery and seeing how much plaque may be extruding into the lumen.
You're doing nothing to what plaque made existing in the coronary artery walls. And in that trial,
using quantitative angiography, they did see a statistically significant improvement in the
lumen of arteries in people with coronary heart disease who took niacin. That's the Hatch trial.
It's a small, well under a hundred people given niacin, no statins or anything. And
they come to this inclusion was a 90% event reduction. Not only did we see a fraction of
a millimeter increase in the lumen, and by the way, at that rate, it would have taken you 200
years to open up the artery seriously to hemodynamic blood flow. But in this small
cohort and a trial absolutely not empowered to look at clinical outcomes, there were less
coronary events in this trial. And that got extrapolated through a lot of disingenuous
marketing of people saying, oh, look at this. Nothing ever gives you that type of outcome
reduction in niacin, 90% event reduction. And there are a bunch of-
I'm sorry, just to make sure I understand that. I'm actually not even familiar with the Hatch trial.
So this had a hundred subjects in it? Yeah. So it's a 50 in each arm. It was a one-to-one
randomization? No, I think they just did the angiograms of people and they put them on niacin
and they did a repeat angiogram. Also a hundred people with a crossover. Basically you were your
own control. Yeah. Your baseline arteriogram was in your follow-up. Right. So I don't want to get
into a lecture on shitty science, but I can't help myself. To be clear, there's no placebo group here.
Right. In other words, you've completely eliminated the-
You're looking at angiographic changes from a drug.
No, understood. But there's a performance bias here. Every patient in that trial knows that
they are being given a compound that is supposed to make them better.
Yeah. And they're given other advice too. But-
But the point is you have no idea of knowing if they've changed any other behavior that may or
may not contribute to an improvement. Notwithstanding the bigger issue I would have with that trial,
which is that the millimeter change of an angiogram doesn't actually tell us anything-
We now know it's meaningless. Yeah.
About the vulnerability of plaque or true events.
No. And you certainly can't use that type of numbers of people to generate outcome data. They
did it. It was disingenuous for them to do it. It's absurd for anybody to ever talk about it,
but they did it. Because look, we were in our infancy on these drugs. We're learning as we go
along. It's easy for us to say that now and everything. And there were three or four other
nice and angiographic trials that sort of indicate, boy, the images look better when we follow up on
these people. And HDL cholesterol is going up, so what else could it be? And that HDL, that
HATCH trial was so impressive to people that they said, the only way we really can prove this is to
do a giant randomized perspective blinded trial where we give niacin, add it to whatever else,
get this HDL raising on top of we're already given drugs that lower LDL cholesterol.
Was this aim high?
So aim high was the first. So there'd been no aim high if there wasn't this HATCH angiographic
trial. First, that was the whole premise to let's spend money on the aim high trial because now we
are in the statin era where you do have to give everybody a statin. So we'll make everybody's LDL
cholesterol perfect. And by the way, if a statin doesn't do it, we'll add a zetimide to it also.
So we will get LDL C perfect, but HLC is still going to be low. So we're now going to add niacin.
And this, I think, is Ron's real point, which is when you look at that trial,
which was really then using niacin to increase HDL C in an already optimized LDL patient,
you missed an opportunity to actually add.
You didn't miss it because here's what happened in that trial. Niacin made the APO B go lower
than statin and zetimide did by themselves. So you got additional serious APO B lowering
and no outcome reduction.
So how much lower did it get?
Another 10, 15%. So here is a drug that is drastically further lowering APO B,
atherogenic particles. It's raising that, as I know, called a stupid metric, HDL cholesterol,
but it's not working. Well, I just told you, Reloxifen, I believe, works because it lowers APO B.
Why didn't niacin? Because it's got to be doing something bad that's aggravating your arteries.
And you give me a drug that causes acanthosis nigricans in human beings,
pathognomonic of insulin resistance. Why would I ever give that drug to a human being?
So niacin causes worsens. And the only person who you're probably going to wind up giving
niacin to is probably insulin resistant, identified by triglyceride HDL abnormalities.
You're giving niacin.
And it makes them worse.
I could read off 15 other well-known side effects with niacin.
Well, I don't think anybody would dispute that.
And so why did it fail, even though it lowered APO B, beyond what a statin is that a margin?
That's a very interesting point, right? And I guess the only, if I could wave a magic one,
the only other question I'd have, which is purely intellectual, again, I don't really
think niacin has a place anymore, is could the wash on mortality, despite the reduction in APO B,
be explained by the worsening of insulin resistance?
Can you explain by something?
Yeah. No, but I'm saying like that would actually be an interesting thing to try to quantify.
It could be explained by GI bleeding above an acute niacin, well-known to do that.
It could be explained by all sorts of hematologic parameters, disruption, platelet reactivity with
niacin, well-known, and a bunch of other things that niacin has been implicated in.
So to me, every time you use a drug, you're using trial data benefits versus risk.
And I see some benefits to niacin. I don't think the A-chill is a benefit, but lowering APO B,
I'm going to always consider that a good benefit. But if it's nothing is happening,
there's something adverse going on, which I don't understand.
Look, they took that extended release product off the market in Europe based on this trial.
In the United States, it's still here, but you just made it unaffordable.
So they don't want you using it. Immediate release niacin is you're basically
prescribing a vitamin at a mega dose. One other little aside, because I noticed people who take
niacin, remember these trials were done with massive pharmacological doses of niacin.
They didn't tell, take a multivitamin with niacin in it, which has nothing to lipids or lipoproteins.
So if you want to be a niacin player, will you in the coronary drug project,
immediate release niacin was four grams a day. Try that. Sustain release niacin.
Wait, so those patients took one gram four times a day.
Yeah. Oh, they worked their way up to it. You know, so because many can just,
hey, if this is as much it can take, that's what you, but they got them in pretty high doses.
I will say, you know, stay is kudos to the docs in those trials and everything.
Extra number of people.
Kudos to the patients for tolerating it.
Yeah. Listen, if you get not only flushing, but massive paritis can occur when you use
immediate release. It's a scary phenomenon to a layman who experiences that, who hasn't been
worn. I remember a call I got early in my practice, like at two in the morning, the guy thought he was
going to die. He had dialed 911 because he just had an extensive, periodic reaction and he felt
his whole body was on fire. If he'd had a swimming pool, he would have jumped into it. But he called,
cause he just thought his body was burning up. And I just said, you're going to think I'm crazy.
Chew two aspirins and just call me back in an hour. It'll be gone. And I forget whether he
did wind up in the ER or not. Now that's an extreme reaction, but it occurs. So, and look,
I took an eyes in a couple of years on myself on some of the beliefs before we knew a lot of this
because I could not tolerate a statin or statin is that a mime and I had an APO B issue and I
hadn't learned about intermittent fasting or follow the low carb diet at that time. So
unfortunately, nice and didn't even lower the APO B and me did nothing, but I tolerated it
for whatever reason, but did nothing. And who knows what it did to my insulin resistance,
you know, for me, nice and sort of grew out of favor with patients even before the final trial.
I think just the exacerbation of insulin resistance became sort of problematic. And by the way,
the last trial, they did another trial cause it was a branded product. They took that extended
release nice and, but they combined it with an anti itch compound and aha. So everybody's
can tolerate nice and now, and they added it to a statin. That was the heart protection study thrive.
And it was basically a duplication of the aim high trial, nice increase in HDL cholesterol,
further reduction in APO B and zero outcome change. And a lot of toxicity,
much of the toxicity is glucose extubations. You're going to aggravate glucose. So Europe decided
that's it. So they took that combo pill off the market. I'm sure you can still get immediate
release nice in Europe if you want it, you know, it's a vitamin for God's sakes, a mega dose. So I
just don't like people out there who want to extol nice and fine, but don't start telling nice and
has a lot of data. It's got zero data. And these are the same people who bash vibrates, who do have
two large randomized, destructive trials, Helsinki and VA hit with vibrates. And yet
they never consider a vibrate. They always tell you nice and it's the better drug. And at least
in the field trial, nice or phenofibrate had all these microvascular. There's no prayer, nice and
reduces diabetic and retinopathy, amputations, kidney disease. But yet there was that battle.
People bashed vibrates, hold them to the high standard of you got to hit your primary end point
and they never held nice. And, and to be honest with you, the same, that's what Ron Krauss did in
that study. So I understand what he's talking about. There is some data if you want to extol it,
but it's not the type of data you and I use anymore. So we'll go from the step child to the
poster child, which we've already kind of alluded to, which are Rapatha and Praluent, these two
PCSK9 inhibitors. And I'll just give a little bit of background, obviously. What's the name of the
fellow up in Toronto who actually discovered this? Oh, I thought it was in Texas. Hobbs,
Helen Hobbs was the first person who discovered the PCSK9 expression.
No, I mean the actual family of PCS, the PCS family.
Yeah. Look, there's at least 10 members in the family. They've been around forever.
Yeah. And I think it's, I don't know who discovered number nine.
I think because I grew up in Toronto, I have a fondness for remembering anything that anyone
from Toronto did, but we'll figure it out in the show notes. I could be making all this up.
But I do think there was, there's a guy in Toronto who actually discovered this family
of proteins, but you're right. Then the genetic evaluation, genetics, gain of function,
loss of function, explains how the gain of functions were discovered first. Correct?
Yeah. So I'll explain this really quickly and briefly. You can expand upon it. PCSK9
degrades LDL receptors. So if you have a gain of function, you are more rapidly degrading LDL
receptors on the liver. You're going to have a decrease in your clearance of LDL. You will have
a higher LDL. These patients had very high events. In fact, these patients are makeup, what, five to
10% of what we would diffusely refer to as familial hypercholesterolemia. That's correct.
It's one of the many, and I think in one of your podcasts, people don't understand FH could be a
thousand different disorders. FH is a phenotype in my GFR. And they're not all autosomal dominant.
Some are heterozygous disorders of various genes, but the phenotype is an LDL cholesterol above 190.
And then you fast forward to about 2004, 2005, maybe it was 2006, but even I remember this.
And again, this was before I became kind of a lipid wannabe, but I would still read the New
England Journal of Medicine just because it's sort of interesting. And there was the discovery of the
hypo-functioning PCSK9 folks. And I really do remember this, and I'm surprised I remember it.
Actually, I discovered an African-Americans first. I believe in a Jackson trial down there.
That's exactly right. Yeah. And these were folks that were walking around with an LDL cholesterol
between 10 and 30 milligrams per deciliter, and they were completely event-free. And of course,
the first 100%, but significant reductions. Dramatic reduction. And the reductions,
I believe we actually went back and did a calculation to see if their reductions,
how congruent they were with some of the more recent Mendelian randomizations.
And they're very similar. And it's not surprising because that's effectively how you would model
a reduction, a lifetime exposure reduction. The thing that interested me, because I remember at
the time, like many people, I'm sure, I sort of had this concern, which is, well, God, if
cholesterol levels, I mean, I now realize I was being naive. But my concern was, God,
if your LDL is low, that must mean you can't make hormones. It must mean that you're going to
get some other awful disease. And so the interesting thing to me was those people
didn't have any of these other phenotypes. They didn't seem to have deficiencies or deficits as
a result of that. And of course, I think that trial is what was the catalyst for Amgen,
Sanofi, and these other companies to start working on these drugs.
Yeah. So by the way, they've since studied in these people where they've blown away LDL
cholesterol at 10 and 15, there's been zero effect on reproductive hormones or
adrenal cortical hormones. It goes back to what I just told you. Those glands synthesize all the
cholesterol they need. They get it from HDL. So none of them are waiting for an LDL to show up with
cholesterol to keep them functioning. So it's all the nonsense you get when you go to a health food
store or a gym where the guy tells you, you got to raise your HDL cholesterol or something. You're
helping your testosterone level in the blood. It has nothing to do with it. Or if you deplete
testosterone, because God forbid you're actually taking a stat and you're screwing up your
testicular function, you're not having nothing to do with it.
Yeah. Yeah. There doesn't seem to be any evidence of that.
So that put into perspective, yes. But so the genetic model is if you got an LDL cholesterol
of 10 and 20, nothing's going to be wrong with you. And you're certainly going to have far less
coronary heart disease. And when we talk about loss of function, that means your LDL receptor
half-life is much longer. We didn't get into it before. We told you the liver makes LDL receptors.
Theoretically, any cell could. If your liver expresses an LDL receptor, how long does it stay
there for? Two, three days. And it grabs your ApoB particle. It brings it into an endosome.
But then the LDL receptor travels back to the surface, grabs another one. I used to, those of
you old enough to use to watch the Addams family on TV, it's like things hand coming out of a box.
It's the LDL receptor, grabs something, pulls it in, but things arm comes right back out again.
But if in some people that LDL receptor might be catabolized in the lysosome endosome, then it
can't go back to the surface. And PCSK9 is a major determinant of how quickly you recycle your LDL
receptor. You do not recycle it. So by putzing with the expression of that enzyme, we can give
you much further expression of your LDL receptor and as you said, enhance clearance of your ApoB
particles, including not only your LDLs, which are 90 to 95%, but you're clearing remnants also.
So for those who believe, oh, remnants are the bad guys. That's not a reason not to use the PCSK9,
but I'll get rid of them also. Now, we're going to come back to this because I want to talk a
little bit about the brain and you alluded to it earlier, but I don't want to derail us now. So I'm
saying this just as much to remind me is to remind you. You can come up with multiple ways to lower
LDL. When I say LDL, I'm talking the actual particle number. You can inhibit the synthesis of
cholesterol, which in turn also activates the clearance, or you can just go directly after the
clearance. So the former would be how a statin works. The latter would be how a PCSK9 would have
better work. You can also make the evidence that if you're depleting the cholesterol pool in the
liver, you'll make a few less either LDL particles or VLDL precursors, which would contribute to a
lowering of ApoB. And that is a small part of both the zetimides and the statins. In fact,
most of it is clearance, but you are producing less particles too. But this is an area where I
do probably have a slightly different view from the mainstream lipid world, which is certainly
there's a favorable hypothesis that's the zero LDL hypothesis, this idea that-
Well, you can't make LDL.
Well, not only can you. I think let me rephrase that. What they're basically arguing is the lower
you drive LDL, the better. And I do take a little bit of issue with that because I think it depends
how you lower it. And it also depends on what you define as better or worse. If you're talking
about lowering LDL reduces the risk of atherosclerosis, I think that's pretty clear. But
at some point, my concern has always been if you lower LDL through cholesterol synthesis inhibition
a lot, do you impact other organs, namely the brain?
Well, you don't know. Remember when you're measuring whatever LDL metric, it's what's
floating around your plasma. The only place I'll make that's irrelevant. You're not measuring
cellular cholesterol based on an LDL cholesterol. So you tell me what your LDL cholesterol level is.
I have really no clue are your cells synthesizing or not synthesizing, exporting, effluxing or
whatever to particles that carry cholesterol. But as I think we indicated earlier in our talk today,
look, it is integral. Cells do have to make cholesterol. So you certainly wouldn't want to
stop cholesterol synthesis in probably any cell on your body because the cell membranes, if nothing
else requires it. And we talked about the brain certainly, it's the only way it has cholesterol
as it makes it. So if we did know we were inhibiting cholesterol synthesis in the brain,
would you be really that comfortable with that? And if you were, is there certain limits where,
I wouldn't mind reducing it a little bit, but how much? Because that brain really needs it.
And the brain has no other source of cholesterol. Now, nowadays, with the exception of patients who
have been on a statin for a long, long period of time, when it comes to patients that are relatively
new to statins, they're really only a handful we're really looking at today, right? Lipitor
and Crestor are doing the lion's share of the work. For some patients who are very sensitive,
we'll use Livoloe or we'll use Pravastatin, but we're not really doing much in the way of
Simvastatin or any of these older drugs, correct? No, if you're following guidelines, what you're
doing is prescribing high potency statins or at least moderate intensity statins. So if you want
to follow the guidelines, the only choices you have are Resuvastatin or a Torvastatin,
Lipitor or Crestor at a 40 milligram or above dose for a Torv or a 20 milligram or above dose for
Resuva. If you're stuck, they would allow you to sneak Simva 40 milligrams into there, but that's
at best a moderate dose statin. 80 milligrams of Simva has been taken off the market.
Yeah, the side effects are quite high with Simva.
Well, Simva, because of a variety of pharmacokinetic reasons, has a ton of drug-drug
interactions and we're in a polypharmacy world, whereas there's far less with a Torv and infinitely
less with Resuvastatin and the Pravastatin you mentioned, Livoloe or so. But I would make the
case that if you want the statin has the most data that you're going to do good, it would be
Pravastatin. And Pravastatin, very cheap, it's almost free if you go to a drug store for it.
It's just not that potent, right? Even at 80 milligrams.
You know, but if you use the outcome trials, they got the exact same 25% reduction as any
a Torv or Resuva trial ever did. So again, Bristol used to explain that to magical mystery
pleiotropic effects of Pravastatin. But I would make the case that, all right, if APOB, LELP is your goal.
I would also argue though patients are sicker today. I think patients are more metabolically
ill today than they were, meaning I think the Crestor trials have a higher bar to cross than
the Pravastar trials. But that again, that's just my bullshit speculation.
Oh, I think the lipid level enrollments with the West of Scotland were twice as horrific as any
Resuvastatin trials.
Yeah, they were, but they had FH. So these are patients who weren't necessarily
metabolically ill.
Yeah, I understand what you're saying. So the end of this discussion comes, I got a lower APOB.
So yeah, unless somebody is incredibly statin sensitive and there are ways of predicting
statin the responsiveness or hypo responsiveness, if you want to just routinely pick for a Resuvastatin
and go down that path, I'm all free.
So what do we know about CNS penetration of these statins?
Well, we're good today. And look, I jumped on Resuvastatin bandwagon, because of being a giant
Pravastatin guy, because it's one of the, what I would call hepatoselective statins. It's
hydrophilic. It goes right into the liver. It doesn't need transporters. So you don't need much
of a drug to get in the liver and hit the cholesterol synthesis and upregulate LDL receptors.
So Resuvastatin, five milligrams is all out of people. You don't need 40. They want you to use
40 because in a trial, that's the dose they use where they got heart attack reduction. But
since it all comes back to APOB reduction, use whatever it takes to get your APOB down. In my
mind, you know, that's not how the guidelines exactly figure out how to do it. They like to
give level one star rated evidence or so. Mine would be a lesser degree of evidence.
So you pick, so they get in the other drugs are not as hydrophilic. So the only way they get into
the liver is various receptors, pull them in. There's a whole variety of transporters that pull
molecules into the liver, but they're subject to interference with a ton of other drugs that may be
in your system or other molecules. So you don't have the clean pharmacokinetics like you do with
Pravastatin or Resuvastatin. That being said, we you're talking, you want to introduce the brain
into the discussion. Now, all statins can get into the brain. They can cross the blood-brain barrier,
but the statins that cross it much easily are the lipophilic statins because they have to pass a
lipid membrane, a blood-brain barrier. So atorvastatin, simvastatin get into the brain more easily than
do lovastatin, simvastatin, and atorvastatin. Wait, say that again. The most lipophilic one.
The lipophilic statin's easier to cross the blood-brain barrier. Yeah, which is atorvastatin and simvastatin
are the two biggest. And lovastatin would probably be the worst. Whereas Pravastatin would be far
less, Edward would Resuvastatin. You have that fluvastatin, sort of a water-solubastatin is probably
more in the class of Resuvin travels. And what about Livolo? So Livolo would be the same. It's a
non-lipophilic statin. So if you're worried about statins getting into the brain, you might want
to choose the hydrophilic ones or so. But the only concern I might have is, well, if those statins
are getting into the brain, it's great to read those cholesterol synthesis in a liver. I'm going
to upregulate LDL receptors. I don't know that I want to do it in every cell in the body, but I'm
probably not. I know I'm not with any of them. Totally inhibiting cellular synthesis cholesterol.
But the brain, it's way more dependent on cholesterol. And then we have studies of people
with Alzheimer's disease and other cognitive, their brains need to be depleted of cholesterol
to variable degrees. Now, Tom, I'm just going to stop you right here, because if I had a dollar
for every time I had a brutal argument with a cardiologist about this point, because up until
this point in the discussion, if you're a card-carrying lipidologist or a cardiologist who really
understands lipids, you're kind of on board. You're in the camp of let's lower LDL. But I do get
patients from time to time who are more than at their LDL goal, meaning their LDL cholesterol is
40 milligrams per deciliter. Their LDL particle number is 500 nanomole per liter. These are people
in primary prevention, but let's assume they have a calcium score of 800 or something. I mean,
they're very high risk. But I look at that and I say, well, gosh, their desmosterol level is
unmeasurable. Well, you're advancing the discussion here. So let me continue down this pathway.
So if cholesterol synthesis is so crucial for the brain, man, I need a biomarker of brain
cholesterol synthesis. Now, very interesting. We talked about two pathways of cholesterol synthesis.
One is the desmosterol, a block pathway, and the other is the leftosterol, the Candage-Russell
pathway. Well, it turns out the block pathway predominates in the brain. So would,
should I do spinal taps and measure CSF desmosterol in these people?
I'm going to go with no.
Yeah, be a tough, by the way, don't leave. I'm going to come back and just do a quick
spinal tap on you today.
Hang on, just wait there in the waiting room.
I imagine even trying to do a clinical trial where that was what you're trying to prove
and enrolling people into that. And also it's going to happen. But so people know we can measure
desmosterol in the blood and there's lots of articles correlating that with cholesterol
synthesis as there is with the leftosterol. And you can make the case in peripheral cells,
maybe even the leftosterol is a more dominant pathway. They're probably both at play, but also
the desmosterol pathway is much more important in younger newborns and youth rather than older
people. So.
I didn't know that.
Yeah. So maybe that's a critical patient if you for whatever reason want to give a statin to
a really young FH, a homozygous FH patient.
I've been involved in one of those cases.
So my desmosterol be money. So here's what we know. So when people with these cognitive
myocardial impairment or various dementias have low cholesterol when you wind up autopsy in their
brains, they do have low desmosterol in their cerebral spinal fluid, suggesting that they do
part of their impairment or cholesterol depletion in the brain is their, their brains aren't
synthesizing as much cholesterol and nice trial where they done this, they car, they did do spinal
taps on the people in the trial measured CSF desmosterol and they measured serum desmosterol.
What was the correlation?
Identical. The R that is very high in there. So now all of a sudden a serum
desmosterol level becomes a biomarker of brain synthesis of cholesterol. And there are what is
by far, it's not even close. The biggest reason that a brain has suppressed as most
of cholesterol synthesis, it's statin use. Yeah. So I would make the case.
So I'm going to pause here because I know what you're going to say and I agree,
but I'm going to give you the counterpoint before you even start. So you can color your commentary.
The heterogeneous population based data say statins reduce Alzheimer's disease.
Nothing serious against that. I mean, yeah, you want to start looking at crazy,
which is not to say that the trials are using that as an outcome. It's just that we're not
seeing an increase in Alzheimer's disease in the statin trial.
Dementia is a multifactorial disease. A lot of things that contribute to dementia. So in general,
the vast majority of people take statins, wind up demented. No, absolutely not. There's not any
evidence that is shown at least from the cumulative statin trials or so. But are there certain
individuals where that is? And by the way, in these trials where they measured low, both serum
and CSF desmosterol, guess what? There was a significantly increased incidence of Alzheimer's
disease and mild cognitive impairment. So yes, this is all at the hypothesis level. It's looking
at a biomarker, not clinical endpoint trials, but that's enough evidence to me to say,
if I'm going to give you a statin, I'm going to push it to, for a variety of reasons, much rather
give you a baby statin plus a zetimibe. And by the way, baby statin plus a zetimibe gives you
the exact same ApoB reduction as does the gorilla statin, the mega dose of it. But I think with a
lot of other additional benefits a zetimibe brings and certainly less potential side effects and
certainly less cholesterol synthesis suppression, including the brain. So if I were giving you
massive doses of your favorite gorilla statin per guidelines, and I simply measured serum desmosterol
on your next visit, and it was low, that tells me I've over, I've stopped the synthesis of
cholesterol too much. So Tom, you are the only other person in this space who will entertain
this discussion with me. I mean, I just can't tell you how many times I get into debates with
other lipid folks who say that is complete and utter nonsense. And they point to the absence of
a huge upsurge in Alzheimer's disease in the statin trials. Now, to which I say the following,
one, I am sympathetic to what you were saying, because I realize that all of the anti-statin
rhetoric out there is so illogical and they throw everything in the sink, right? Like,
but, you know, oh my God, it causes, you know, diabetes, does it? Well, yeah. And a small,
small subset of the population, we're going to see a slight uptick in the risk of diabetes,
especially with a torvostatin. Does that mean statins cause diabetes and it needs to be avoided
as a result of that? No. Does it, you know, do a subset of patients end up getting, you know,
muscular pain? Of course, it's probably five to 10%. It might be even a bit higher depending on
the nature of the trial. But what I think is really going on here, this is my hypothesis.
Alzheimer's disease, as you said a second ago, is multiple diseases. It is not a disease, right?
I'm talking cognitive impairment.
Yeah. But even if you talk about Alzheimer's disease, even if there is a final common pathway
or a set of pathognomonic features that define the disease, I think there are several ways to
get there. There is a metabolic way that people get there that is probably explained by the
increased incidence we see in cognitive impairment and Alzheimer's disease in patients with diabetes
and insulin resistance. But there's also a vascular component that I don't think gets nearly enough
attention. There's a guy named Jack Delator who I, you know, it's funny, I reached out to him
recently to interview him for my book and he's on a research sabbatical in Spain for two years. So
I'll probably interview him by telephone, but I would like to eventually have him on the podcast.
But he's done some of the most impressive work on looking at this sort of vascular hypothesis of
Alzheimer's disease. My hypothesis is this. On average, you take a group of patients with
terrible dyslipidemia, you give them a stat and you improve their vascular complications,
which include atherosclerosis, and you're probably actually reducing Alzheimer's disease
in those patients. In other words, all things coming, are you better at being at the 90th
percentile or the 10th percentile of ApoB with respect to Alzheimer's disease? You're better off
being at the 10th percentile. However, I think to your point, there's going to be a subset of
patients in which you go too far. These are patients who don't synthesize a boatload of
cholesterol. They're probably hypo synthesizers to begin with. And you statinize the hell out of them
and you are increasing their susceptibility. Now, again, that's the problem with everything I just
said is it takes more than a tweet. And for anybody who throws it in your face, there's no evidence of
that in any statin trial. Say, oh my God, I've read the FDA package in sort of every single statin
that's on the market and cognitive impairment is listed as a potential side effect of every
single statin. Did the FDA just make that up? No, it's been seen in clinical trials.
Now, did the FDA make this link? Because I'm talking about papers. There are actually papers
that show, and we will absolutely link to this because I think this is one of the better papers.
It's about six years old, but it looks at desmostrol as a continuous variable. So in the same way that
you might look at PSA as a continuous variable, it can be anything and try to decide the question,
at what cutoff does having a high PSA suggest that you have a high enough risk of prostate cancer?
But using desmostrol as a continuous variable and using a statistical technique called receiver
operating characteristic curve production, they showed that once desmostrol fell below 0.5,
the AUC, the area under the curve of the receiver operating characteristic, was somewhere between
0.8 and 0.87, depending on the study and depending on gender. And again, maybe it's more detailed than
people want, but the higher that number, which varies basically between 0.5 and 1, one is a
perfect study. One, there's no such thing as a diagnostic test with a one. Five is a coin toss.
When you get into the 0.8 territory, that's a very powerful predictor. Correct. So I think it's
careless to dismiss that as a potential player. We've given you a lot of the plausibility and
there's even more. If you tell me you are a doctor who has prescribed a lot of statins and
look, I was in practice 37 years, 20 of which I was writing as much statins as anybody. If you tell
me you've never seen cognitive impairment in a patient, you start on a statin, you're a liar or
you're a fool, or you're not questioning your patients when they come back because it does occur.
I don't know what a lot of reasons it could occur. And look, who doesn't have a day where you wake up
thinking I'm a little foggy today for sun and it's nothing to do, but it happens. So we've now got a
plausible explanation why it happens. If the real reason you're prescribing a statin is APOB
reductions, I got a lot of ways of getting your APOB to go without maximizing a statin. So in my
mind, if desmostrol is below a certain population percentile cut point, I've inhibited cholesterol
synthesis. I probably get no bang for the buck on further LDL or particle lowering, APOB lowering,
by having you continue to take that. I can clear APOB furthers by stopping cholesterol absorption
back into the liver and the intestine with a zetimide that does nothing to cholesterol synthesis,
a PCSK9 inhibitor. So with most people, baby statin and a zetimide will give you the exact same APOB
reduction of your gorilla statin. And we have outcome evidence in the improve it trial that
is zetimide and statin for the guys, I got to see outcome data, you got it. So therefore I use it as
a tool to monitor statin therapy. Most people and they also these people would argue you I will bet
as much money as I have in my bank account days never. They couldn't even tell you what desmostrol
is. They've never read anything about the cholesterol synthetic pathway and they don't know what they're
talking about. Yeah, I mean, look, in the end, I think this is such a contentious topic because
we're getting so nuanced on something now and the world has lost its appetite for nuance. People want
to know statins are good or statins are bad. And everything we've just said says it depends.
It depends on how you use them. You can give too much of these things. That doesn't mean they're
bad because what we've also done, I realize, and I've been very deliberate about this because I
think it's important to show both sides of this. We've also given the statin deniers and the statin,
you know, the statin conspiracy theorists a great ammo, which is aha. If Dayspring and Attia are
sitting there bashing statins and talking about mild cognitive impairment and they take that to
discussion out of context, they're going to say, well, statins should be outlawed. Yeah. But of
course, any reasonable doctor, if a patient came in complaining of statin or a cognitive impairment,
they'd pretty much stop all drugs because that's the first explanation a drug is causing it. So
it's not like I'd continue to force you to take this statin if you were cognitively there. I mean,
if the listener is sort of saying, what the hell is the takeaway from this? I think it's a couple
things. One is statins are not bad. Statins are still the mainstay backbone of anti lipid therapy.
Be thoughtful about which ones you use. You know, Tom, I have moved more to Crestor over Lipitor,
though I still use Lipitor quite a bit. And in many ways, I'm sort of slowly migrating patients
who seem to have no difficulty from Lipitor to Crestor. Two, I'm actually going back and using
Prevostatin much more than I used to. I'm surprised at how much I find myself reaching
for Prevostatin in a patient who doesn't tolerate, who has a slight CK bump, even if they're not
complaining of pain, if they're getting a CK bump that, you know, their CK goes from a baseline of
50 to 300, even if they're asymptomatic, I don't like it. So I'm going to switch that. By the way,
I would chip in at CK elevation has nothing to do with statin toxicity or stansosis, silly
biomarker. Totally. And evidence with total. Well, I know it doesn't correlate that well with my
site. First of all, before you ever do that, make sure you have a baseline. Yes, of course. A lot
of people working out. Not even working out. They just have high CK levels, African-Americans. So,
but I didn't realize that. And you know, when you should stop a statin when it's like a 10,000 fold
elevation of CK, then you might start to worry. So CK, there's any number of guidelines issued on
it's not a biomarker that is of any use to you. And all you do by doing CK is when somebody goes
from 50 to 300, they get the bejesus scared out of them and they stop their statin when there's no
reason. The reason you should stop a statin is if they're having myopathic symptoms, aches or
weakness, then I don't care what their CK. I did not realize that. I'll get some info to you on that.
So stop monitoring CK. And if they come in and tell you, hey, Peter, I'm feeling pain or you
somehow are doing some muscular strength testing, or they tell you, I don't get out of the chair as
much proximal muscle weakness, stop the darn statin. Yeah, well, those are the easy cases.
But don't use CKs to dictate your statin therapy. I think the point here is I can't imagine giving
any lipid lowering therapy without being able to measure phytosterols, stanols, and desmostrol.
Some with you there, most lipidologists would not be, but they just have not studied the data like
they should. And even if what we're just talking about is pure hypothesis, what harm would you be
doing by lessening the dose of a statin and substituting a little azetimibe, or if they
could afford it? You can make the case if it was free as Pravastatin, let's just use PCSK9 inhibitors
for God's sakes. Because, you know, whatever other minor side effects of statins, I don't
think we've seen much with PCSK9. No, I mean, of course, more time to go. I was just about to say
that the skeptic will counter that Tom and say, but we only have three and a half years of data
with these drugs. So right now, we're not going to use that except for people who can afford it or
our nightmare patients where a third party will finally pay further. So, so it's not like docs
are going to run out tomorrow and start injecting everybody with a PCSK9 inhibitor. They're not
because there's handcuffs on them, but there's no handcuffs on you using generic azetimibe to a
baby statin. As you have to buy onto, LDLC is not your best surrogate of atherogenic lipoproteins,
ApoB or LDL particle count is. And if that's your real goal of therapy, then you got a lot of options
available to you. Now, the one thing I used to use the combo lowest dose statin possible coupled
with is that a my if there was some evidence of even mild elevation of phytosterol and stanel,
one thing I've noticed and I can I've just been a little delinquent. I don't think I've gone back
and looked at the trials. Did the trials show an increase in transaminases with that combo?
No. And I think the only trial it would show you'd have to look back at sees where
improve where they use the Simba statin and is that a my improve it? Yeah. And there was nothing
more than I don't know what it is. I don't know what it is. I keep seeing these. And again,
I will tell you there's not a package insert in the world that tells you you should even be
following aminase to judge statin or anything going on in the liver as a result of a statin.
There's no correlation whatsoever. So I'm repeating them and all the time because maybe
it's a biomarker of fatty liver or something else, but not a statin toxicity. It's not.
You know, so don't ever let a patient stop because they've doubled their AST,
whatever aminase you're measuring level on the statin, not related to anything. You've got great
medical legal safety because that's what the guidelines are telling you to do. There's not
a statin in the world that they're all out of the package insert that you should be following liver
function tests. Yeah. Again, I think part of the problem is like you, I'm going to follow liver
function tests regardless. I have a very different view of how these things should be.
I mean, yeah, so they have other use and who's not going to do it's part of your chemistry
profile that you're probably doing on every patient every time. So you're going to see them,
but you don't necessarily have, but be prepared when the patient calls you up in a panic. That's
not in your differential diagnosis of why the aminases are changing. Yeah. I don't know, Tom.
I still, I'm going to go back and look at this entire documents where they've analyzed all the
data in the world on aminase and statin therapy, it's in consequential. But I mean, I'll give you
a silly example, which is I have seen the following at least four times. You take a patient, you make
they're on a statin, there's no other change. And the only thing you do is you add Zetia.
And then their next blood test, their transaminases have doubled. And then the only thing you do is
stop the Zetia and it returns to baseline. All right. So something is happening, but is it
doubling of a transaminase of that etiology of any concern to you? So fine. If you want to stop
it and see, go ahead. And if that's going to occasionally limit how much Zetimibe you're
going to use in a patient, okay, figure out how else to lower EBOB. So fine. I understand there
are things that'll come into play in an individual patient where the data doesn't support it, but
you're making an individual decision. Sure. That's my point. Of course. That's my point.
You've got to be able to make an individual decision, which is what we're saying with the
dysmosterol level. Again, I think most patients, again, if someone's listening to this and they're
freaking out because they're like, what the hell are these guys talking about? We are not saying
that statins are causing dementia. What we're saying is, at least what I'm saying, I'll let Tom
clarify for himself. There are going to be a subset of patients whose risk of dementia does
go up with a statin. And it's our job if we're prescribing those drugs to know exactly who those
patients are. And to the best of my reading of the literature, plus understanding the nature
of the biology, it's probably the patients in whom we overly suppress synthesis for whom they
don't make that much to begin with. Suppress cellular synthesis, which has nothing to do with
the amount of cholesterol you measure in the blood. Great point. And cholesterol synthesis is not
affected per se by PCSK9 inhibitors. Isetimibe is interesting. If you go with isetimibe monotherapy,
you'll actually get a little reflex increase in cholesterol synthesis. Yes. And vice versa.
So if you go with statin monotherapy, a hyperabsorbed statin. So there's a little bit of
physiologic homeostasis going on. And this is like that's not changing levels to these toxic levels.
And that, believe it or not, has become one of the times when I like using Zetia,
is if I've got a patient who really needs a statin because when you just look at their
numbers, you get the sense that this is an LDL clearance deficiency. But you want to boost their
synthesis a little bit. You do it concomitant with the Zetia and you'll sometimes get that reflex.
And I argue with clinicians too, who they are doing sterile testing. So I identify my
hyperabsorbers and I surely make sure isetimibe is on board my APOB lowering therapy in that patient.
But I'll make the case for you. Even if you do those markers and you're a normal absorber of
cholesterol, but you have an APOB problem, even by taking a normal absorber of cholesterol and
making them a hypo absorber, the genetic model is they live longer if they have genetic
loss of function of anemone pixi when they're protein. So even in a patient who's not
hyperabsorbing cholesterol, you do get additional APOB lowering, maybe not at the same magnitude,
but you get it. And you're changing them into the genetic model of longevity, maybe,
you're certainly keeping phytosterols out of them.
You can find all of this information and more at PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash podcast. There
you'll find the show notes, readings, and links related to this episode. You can also find my blog
and the nerd safari at PeterAttiaMD.com. What's a nerd safari you ask? Just click on the link
at the top of the site to learn more. Maybe the simplest thing to do is to sign up for my
subjectively non-lame once a week email where I'll update you on what I've been up to,
the most interesting papers I've read, and all things related to longevity, science, performance,
sleep, etc. On social, you can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID PeterAttiaMD.com.
But usually Twitter is the best way to reach me to share your questions and comments.
Now for the obligatory disclaimer, this podcast is for general informational purposes only and
does not constitute the practice of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services,
including the giving of medical advice. And note, no doctor-patient relationship is formed.
The use of this information and the materials linked to the podcast is at the user's own risk.
The content of this podcast is not intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice,
diagnosis, or treatment. Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice
for any medical condition they have and should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals
for any such conditions. Lastly, and perhaps most importantly, I take conflicts of interest
very seriously. For all of my disclosures, the companies I invest in and or advise,
please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about.