Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia. This podcast,
my website, and my weekly newsletter all focus on the goal of translating the science of
longevity into something accessible for everyone. Our goal is to provide the best content in
health and wellness, full stop, and we've assembled a great team of analysts to make
this happen. If you enjoy this podcast, we've created a membership program that brings you
far more in-depth content. If you want to take your knowledge of the space to the next level.
At the end of this episode, I'll explain what those benefits are. Or if you want to learn more now,
head over to PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash subscribe. Now without further delay, here's
today's episode. My guest this week is Erin Mikos. Erin is an internationally known leader
in preventative cardiology, women's cardiovascular health, and cardiobstetrics. She's an associate
professor of medicine in the division of cardiology at Johns Hopkins School of Medicine,
the joint appointment in the department of epidemiology at the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg
School of Public Health. She's also the director of women's cardiovascular health and the associate
director of preventative cardiology with the Johns Hopkins Center of Prevention of Cardiovascular
Disease. This is an episode that covers a topic that is obviously valuable to understand given
that atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease is the number one cause of death worldwide. And while
as the topic we've covered in detail in the podcast before, I think it's an important episode
because we focus this conversation around cardiovascular disease and lipids specifically
through the lens of female biology. We discussed the prevalence of ASCVD in females as they age,
the importance of making interventions early in life, the risk of ASCVD over the course of lifetime,
as opposed to the traditional view, which is to only really consider 10 year risk. We then probe
the ins and outs of CVD, lipids, and various lipid lowering medications across a female's lifetime,
including the premenopausal state changes during the perimenopausal state, pregnancy, and menopause
and beyond. We also touch on a number of other subjects that affect a female's risk of ASCVD,
specifically polycystic ovarian syndrome, contraceptives, GLP1 agonist nutrition, metabolic
health, familial hypercholesterolemia, statins, stress, HRT, and more. So without further delay,
please enjoy my conversation with Dr. Erin Mikos. Thanks so much for making time, Erin. Look forward
to this discussion. We have a lot to talk about, but before we do it, there's one thing I wanted
to just check. Going through your bio, I realize when did you do your residency in medicine? Because
you also did that at Hopkins, correct? Yes. So I've been at Hopkins 22 years. I did residency 2000
to 2003, and then stayed on for cardiology fellowship and then joined the faculty. So I've
been on faculty over 15 years now. I did my general surgery there. I was there from 01 to 06,
which made me realize the probability we haven't passed each other somewhere in the emergency room
during residency is exceedingly low, right? I'm sure we must have interacted because I was there
all during that time, overlapped with my residency and my fellowship. I always am amazed when I run
into people who I know I was there with. And there are certain medicine residents I remember
very well, but just by coincidence, you're always in the ER together, but obviously it's a huge
program. So when you went into medicine, did you know you wanted to do cardiology? When I went into
medicine, I did in college, actually didn't know that I was going to go into medicine. You know,
there's no doctors in my family. So I'm the first one. So I didn't really know what a career in
medicine would be about. So I started out my undergrad studies at Northwestern as a molecular
biology major. Through that I interacted with so many pre-med students who are my classmates. And
their enthusiasm about entering the field was really contagious. And I was doing a lot of bench
science, which is really a good experience. I think anybody entering science and medicine should have
some bench lab work experience. But I began to long for more direct clinical research with direct
patient exposure. So kind of late, I switched to being pre-med kind of my last year of undergrad
and applied actually to both the PhD and medical programs. And then when I started medical school,
I really fell in love with cardiology, even as a medical student before medicine residency.
I have a real interest in diet and nutrition and exercise and lifestyle. And we think that over
90% of cardiovascular disease is due to preventable, modifiable risk factors. And there's, you know,
so much we can do for prevention. And this is why I really love being a preventive cardiologist.
So when I entered medicine residency, I already had my eye towards cardiology fellowship.
You did the full three years of medicine and then you did three years of cards.
I did four years of cards.
Oh, you did?
So no, I was on the slow track.
You were on the slow track.
I did three years of residency, which is standard. And then our cardiology fellowship program was
four years because we emphasize research. So I did two years of research on a T32 program
and cardiovascular epidemiology. And that's where I got my master's in health science.
You said something at the outset that I completely agree with. And I feel like sometimes I'm banging
my head against the wall trying to make this point. You said, correct me if I misquote you,
but something to the effect of 90% of cardiovascular disease is preventable when you consider
modifiable risk factors. Was that kind of the gist of what you said?
Yeah, that's the data from the inner heart study that 90% of mild cardiomyvarction risk was due to
preventable risk factors. One of the things I tell my patients is that both in the United States and
globally, ASCVD is the leading cause of death. In fact, I was surprised somewhat recently,
like in the last year, to realize how much bigger the gap is between ASCVD and cancer
globally than in the US. It's number one in both. But when you look at the entire world,
I believe it's about 18 and a half to 19 million deaths attributed to ASCVD versus about 10 or 11
million to cancer. It's almost 2x delta. And when you take into account what you just said,
that between smoking, hypertension, and controlling APO-B, you could basically turn
that into a disease that would barely rank on the top 10. Does it surprise you that this doesn't
get more attention? Yeah, it surprises me. And I'm also really concerned that we're reversing
these trends. The first statin, lobostatin, was approved in 1987. After that, along with
efforts in smoking cessation and blood pressure treatment, there was a significant decline in
cardiovascular disease mortality in men. During this time, unfortunately, CBD mortality was rising
in women till around the year 2000 when this came to attention that we need to prevent cardiovascular
disease in women as well. And after that time, there was dramatic decline in cardiovascular
disease mortality in women and continued decline in men. But unfortunately, in recent years,
we are no longer making these strides in progress anymore. In fact, we're no longer even stagnated.
There's been a frank uptick in cardiovascular disease mortality in both men and women
due to the epidemics of obesity and diabetes and cardiometabolic diseases. In fact,
cardiovascular disease mortality is on the rise in younger women. And when you look at rates of
change, the fastest growing heart disease death rate is in middle-aged women age 45 to 64. So,
this is a particular group that needs more focused attention. So, we really need to double down on our
preventive efforts. And it's really disheartening to see that we're no longer making the progress
that we used to. So, if these trends are not overturned, you know, heart disease is set to
overtake cancer as the leading cause of death in younger women as well. I'm really glad you
made that point because when you look at what these things called in our practice, we have these
things called death bars, which is just an analysis that shows mortality sliced and diced in different
ways. But, you know, sometimes a graph just says things in a way that it's harder to describe in
words. And one of the things that does emerge from this analysis is that in middle-aged cancer
is still the biggest killer. And, of course, overall cardiovascular disease is, and in old age
cardiovascular disease and neurodegenerative disease dominate. But what you said is very
distressing if indeed now cardiovascular disease would eclipse cancer in even middle age.
So, overall, and focus on women's health, so cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of
death in women. You know, women more often fear breast cancer, which is a terrible disease. My
mother had breast cancer, but far more women are likely to die of cardiovascular disease than
cancer. But notably, you know, in younger individuals under the age of 65, cancer is
still the leading cause of death in women. But one of my studies that we published in the European
Heart Journal, we track death rates in younger women under the age of 65 in the US looking at
CDC wonder data over a 20-year period from 1999 to 2019. And we showed during this time that
actually cancer mortality has been declining in younger women, which is a good thing. But since
2010, heart disease mortality is no longer declining and is factually rising in these
younger women at 0.5% per year. So, it's actually narrowing the gap between cancer deaths and heart
disease deaths in the younger female population as well. So, if these trends are not overturned,
as I mentioned, you know, heart disease is set to overtake cancer as the leading cause of death in
younger women, which is really discouraging considering that we have so many more tools now
for prevention. And what was also really disheartening, I don't know if you saw this American Heart
Association survey that was published in 2021, but the American Heart Association has sent out
surveys over the years to women about their awareness of heart disease being the leading
cause of death in women. And back in 2009, you know, 65% of women reported that they knew that
heart disease was the leading cause of death. But in 2019, the more recent data, 10 years later,
only 44% of women reported that heart disease was the leading cause of death in women. They were
more likely to report cancer as the leading cause of death. So, this lack of awareness is worrisome,
and it was particularly prominent among non-Hispanic black women and among Hispanic women,
and also among the younger women demographic that we're talking about, who arguably we can do the
most for primordial prevention would be most effective if started earlier. I also think
there's kind of an emotional thing to this, which is even if you don't pose the question directly,
like a multiple choice question, I just find in speaking with my female patients, so young female
patients, I think there's a greater fear of breast cancer than ASCVD, even though the mortality from
heart disease is somewhere between eight and 10 times greater than that of breast cancer. It's
amazing to think that they would be more afraid of something that has a log lower difference in
mortality. What do you think explains that? And again, you can answer this both through a personal
lens through the experience with your mother, but also professionally given what you study.
I think there's still this lingering notion that somehow heart disease is a man's disease.
The problem is, women have historically been under enrolled in randomized clinical trials.
So, we previously had limited data on efficacy and safety of therapies in women. So, both women
think that they're at lower risk than they really are, but also clinicians. So, clinicians, even when
given the same 10-year estimated risk or burden or risk factors, clinicians are more likely
to perceive women to being at lower risk, and this leads to under treatment. And particularly,
I see this with women who have FH, amylo-hypokalestralemia, who are under treated,
because on average in the non-FH population, women tend to develop cardiovascular disease about 10
years later than men, somehow thought that premenopausal women of reproductive years are
somehow protected. But we don't see this in FH. FH affects 1 in 250 individuals. It's autosomal
dominant, which means women are equally affected as men, and it's associated with a 20-fold increased
risk of CBD. Women with FH have an earlier onset of ASCVD about 20 to 30 years earlier than women
without FH, and they continue to be under treated. But notably, in the FH population, women have the
same age, early age of onset, as CBD as men do. So, they are not protected. They don't have this
premenopausal advantage, and it's still really disheartening to me to see that these women who
have very high genetic risk are not being treated because of concerns about pregnancy, which you can
talk about our management around there. But it's better to even have short interruptions in treatment
than to let these women who have genetically high, very high LDLs be marinating in this
atherogenesis for decades and decades untreated, which, you know, dooms them to earlier onset
morbidity and mortality if not treated. Let's put some of these numbers to folks. I don't know if
these are still the correct data, but the last time I looked, this was sort of a directionally
correct. We use 65 as the dividing line between quote-unquote young and old, and the data basically
suggested that if you consider all the people who are going to suffer a major adverse cardiac
event in their life, and you consider men and ask the question, what fraction of men will experience
their first event? Of the men who experience a major adverse cardiac event in life, what fraction
will experience it before the age of 65? The answer was fully half. Again, this is to dispel the notion
that cardiovascular disease is an old person disease, because I don't think most people would
consider someone who's 60 years old to be old by today's standards. And even in women, to your point,
who have this time shift of about one decade, still one third of women who will experience a major
adverse cardiac event in their life will do so before the age of 65. Those were the data about
five or six years ago. Do you believe that that is still the case? Yes, unfortunately. You know,
women of reproductive age are still at risk for ASCBD. They may be lower risk on average,
but they're still at risk, and they're less likely to be treated. You know, when you look at the data
from like the YUMMI, Young Myocardial Infarction cohort, before the onset of their myocardial
infarction, you know, women were less likely to have been treated and perceived to be at lower risk.
So this is really concerning about the under treatment of women and this presumption that
they're lower risk. We know that smoking and diabetes, in addition to the FH, as I mentioned,
also eliminate any premenopausal advantage. It's not only really the magnitude of LDL elevation,
but it's the duration of exposure. So even exposure to mild or moderately elevated LDL
for a sufficient number of years has increased the risk of ASCBD to an earlier onset compared to
individuals who have had lifetime low LDL. And so by waiting to treat individuals until later of life,
you know, you've left atherosclerosis propagate unchecked during this time. It's never too late
to implement prevention, but prevention is better implemented when started earlier.
Yeah, there's two ways I try to explain this to patients, and usually at least one of them works.
So sometimes patients will come in with some recollection of calculus, and you can remind them
about the area under the curve and the integral, and you can sort of explain that an enormous
driver of atherosclerosis is indeed exposure to APO-B. On my podcast, the listeners are very
astute. They understand that we're really talking about APO-B, which includes of course LDL, but also
VLDL, et cetera. And we say, look, it's really the time is the X axis and APO-B concentration is the
Y axis. You want to minimize the area under that curve. And to your point, that means starting
earlier and lowering APO-B or LDL cholesterol more. And the longer you wait, the more it puts
the burden on you to really lower that APO-B. So if that doesn't resonate, I think the other
way that resonates with people is to think about saving for retirement, which is in an
ideal world, you'd start saving in your twenties and you wouldn't have to save an enormous amount
if you were saving in your twenties, but you'd be chipping away at it and building up your coffers
and generating a slow and steady incremental return and letting the effective compounding
take its toll. Of course, if you wait until you're 40 or 50, you're going to have to be more
aggressive in your savings and you're going to also require a higher rate of compounded return
if you want to have the same amount when you retire. And of course, if you wait until you're
60, it doesn't mean that you can't have some sort of financial independence in your seventies, but boy,
you've got to really sock away a lot of money and you've got to really hope for some
pretty impressive returns in the stock market. And so usually somewhere between those two
explanations, people start to understand what you're saying and what people like Peter Libby
have said, which is it's time exposure to APO-B. Do you get the sense that it also works that way
with blood pressure and some of the other really clear causative agents for ASCVD?
Yes. You know, you wouldn't take someone who has a younger adult who has a systolic blood pressure
of 160 and say, oh, you know, your 10 year risk is low in the next 10 years because you're only
30. So, you know, we're not going to treat you. We're going to let this high blood pressure continue
on and damage your arteries and cause, you know, silent vascular damage. No, you would treat a 30
year old who have elevated blood pressure. So this problem with these 10 year risk in younger adults
is that, yes, younger adults are going to have a lower short term risk over the next 10 years,
but they have a high lifetime risk and that we do them a disservice by ignoring these high values
because they haven't crossed some kind of theoretical 10 year threshold with the exception
of guidelines say, well, FH, we treat if it's above 190, but a lot of patients have mild to moderate
elevated cholesterol in younger age years that is not being treated. You know, I tell my patients,
I'm not just concerned about preventing a heart attack in the next 10 years. I want to prevent
them from having a heart attack over the next 40 years. And so this is where we need to have much
more focus on prevention. And this does emphasize the role of lifestyle as well and healthy dietary
changes and really healthy lifestyle should really begin in utero. You just took a real page out of
Alan Snyderman's JAMA paper from a few years ago where he really just took aim at this ridiculous
notion of 10 year risk being remotely helpful in young people. One of the exercises I like to do
with patients is take them to the Mesa risk calculator page and basically demonstrate for
them how much it's driven by age. If you go to the lowest end of that calculator, which I think is 40
or 45, there's almost no variable you can put in there that gets you to a high enough 10 year risk
that you would trigger treatment. Five percent 10 year risk. Okay, now we need to act. Conversely,
at a high enough age, there's almost no variable you can put in there for which the risk is low
enough. In other words, age is the biggest driver of risk. How do you think we got here? Because
you've clearly, I think, identified the jugular issue, which is the time horizon of risk.
And yet somehow when it comes to lipids, we stick to it. And yet when it comes to smoking and blood
pressure, we don't. We treat the causative agent when we're dealing with blood pressure and smoking,
and yet we somehow ignore the causative agent of APO-B when we're talking about lipids and focus
instead on time horizon. Well, I think part of the problem is randomized clinical trials do serve as
our primary evidence base for guideline recommendations. And they're very, very important.
But randomized clinical trials are expensive. And so you run them over generally a short time
period, five years, and you want to enroll high risk people that are going to have events over
the next five years. You really can't feasibly do a randomized clinical trial for decades and decades.
And so by nature, these lower risk individuals in younger adults are not included in these trials.
And then it comes down to the fact that we don't have data specifically for treatment in this
population. But I definitely hone down on lifestyle changes, particularly in younger adults. And I
think we're going to get into women's specific factors a little bit later and talk about
pregnancy. But high adverse lipid panel, elevated triglycerides, elevated total cholesterol,
and chronic hypertension and obesity, these cardiometabolic risk factors.
If women are entering pregnancy in poor cardiometabolic health, which the data shows that
there's been an increase in this, they're more likely to have these adverse pregnancy outcomes
like preeclampsia and gestational diabetes that not only increase their risk of short term
complications at delivery, but also impact their risk even decade or more after their index pregnancy.
Really, we need a shift improvement in cardiometabolic health earlier in life,
which means in young adults and women of reproductive age.
I agree with that completely. And I want to come back to it in more detail. But I still feel like
there is a double standard going back to what we talked about earlier in that we don't have a study
that says not smoking if you're aged 30 to 40 is going to reduce your risk of cardiovascular
disease. But yet there's not a physician out there that doesn't recommend smoking cessation
to a person the minute they pick up a cigarette. Why? It's because we've identified causality.
Once you identify causality, that's all that matters. The same is true with blood pressure.
We don't have a hypertensive study that looked at people aged 25 to 35 or 35 to 45, where we
reduced blood pressure and showed a dramatic reduction in events because they probably weren't
going to have the events in the time horizon of the study. And so the reason it's very easy for
any physician to treat hypertension in a 35 year old is because they're treating the causal agent.
And that's where I'm frustrated, Aaron, is we have the same level of causality for APO-B.
There is no ambiguity about this. And yet we somehow have this double standard where we
ignore the causal agent. I agree with you. We have overwhelming evidence that LDL is a causal factor
in atherosclerosis. We have data from observational studies, from genetic studies, from
interventional trials. It meets all the criteria for a causal factor. You just asked me to speculate
I'm not sure why that there hasn't been a greater uptick about treating in younger ages. And this
focus on 10 year risk scores, I'll point out though in randomized clinical trials, none of the
randomized clinical trials enrolled people on the basis of a 10 year cut point. The pooled cohort
equation has never been tested in a randomized clinical fashion about treating people based on
a full cohort equation cut point versus another cut point that was never been tested. The trials
have specific enrollment criteria and they really weren't based on 10 year risk scores. They were
based on other factors. And so this over-reliance on 10 year risk scores. But I will say that we
have made some progress. And I was really pleased. I was a co-author on the 2019 ACCAJ primary
prevention guidelines. We do acknowledge the limitations of these 10 year risk scores. They
can both overestimate risk in certain populations, such as older adults and those with higher
socioeconomic status. And they can underestimate risk in other populations, such as those with more
social deprivation and these other unique risk factors that are not captured in these 10 year risk
score. And so they acknowledge this, they still feel like you should do some kind of risk assessment
as a starting point and very low risk individuals, less than 5% 10 year risk lifestyle may be enough
and high risk individuals above 20% 10 year risk. You don't want to use your high intensity stat in
the lower LDL by 50% or more. But they do allow more room now for the borderline intermediate risk
to consider these risk enhancing factors of which April B and like portal A are some of them. But I
also was really pleased that they've acknowledged these female specific factors that we'll talk
more about early menopause and adverse pregnancy outcomes like preeclampsia. And so the presence of
these risk enhancers and those of borderline intermediate risk would favor the initiation of
statins. And then if there is still uncertainty about risk, even after you estimate 10 year risk
and consider those risk enhancing factors, you can get a coronary artery calcium score
to help refine risk a little bit better and guide shared decision making. So my practice, I use a
lot of coronary calcium scoring and particularly for elevated score, I'll even treat individuals
similar to secondary prevention population. But we know that even that doesn't work very well in
the younger population that we're talking about less than 40 because it takes time for plaque to
calcify. And so a zero calcium score, a young adult isn't as reassuring as a zero score in an
older adult. You know, they get they might be at low risk the short term for sure, but they may
still have a lifetime risk. We've gone back and forth in our practice about how to use calcium
scores and I think come to the same conclusion you have, right? Which is that in a young patient,
frankly, I would say younger than 50 truthfully, I don't know that a zero calcium score tells me
much. First of all, we know that 15% of zero calcium scores are false negatives. Anyway,
if you do a CTA, a CT angiogram listener, you're going to see a calcification that was missed
because the CTA has much finer slices than the CAC, or you're going to see soft plaque. In fact,
one series found that I think almost 2% of zero scores on CACs actually had hemodynamically
significant lesions on CTA. Even if you put aside the false positives or the false negatives,
rather, to your point, the physiology of the disease tells us that's the wrong metric to
care about. It's more interesting, I suppose, when you have perfectly clean CTAs in 70 year olds with
hyperlipidemia to which you can say, well, look, clearly this person has other factors that are
protective. We might not understand what they are and this is a patient in whom aggressive
treatment probably isn't necessary, especially if they don't feel that if the patient themselves
doesn't want it. Let's now talk about this thing that you've brought up on two occasions, which I
think is really important if I'm understanding you correctly, which is if we think about the lack of
progress or the regression in progress, I guess, that's been made over the past decade.
Am I understanding you correctly that it has been less about a reduction in treatment
for the preventative measures of ASCVD and more about the increase in the background
metabolic dysfunction or have both of these things been happening together?
Both of these things have been happening together. In terms of treatment, individuals are still
undertreated. We see this over and over again in registries. If you look at even the highest risk
patients, that's just those with ASCVD from the gold registry in the US and the Santorini
registry in Europe, patients are not at goal with their LDL and they're undertreated. In the gold
registry of US patients with ASCVD, more than two-thirds remained with an LDL above 70. We can
argue that maybe they should have been up there. LDL is as low as 55, but we even use a threshold
of 70 as the goal for initiating a non-statin therapy to a statin. Two-thirds were above this
goal and over a two-year period, only 17% had their lipid lowering therapy intensified.
There's this credible inertia. Patients are not at goal. The use of combination therapy,
including PCS-canine inhibitors, is very underutilized. There's something like 6% in this cohort.
We're certainly not treating with the tools that we have, which is really disheartening.
But also on the backdrop of this, we've all seen the US maps about the epidemic of obesity.
Along with that comes diabetes and other disorders related to insulin resistance,
including worrisome trends with increasing maternal mortality, rising rates of gestational
diabetes, which is increasing worldwide. The cardio metabolic health of the US population
is getting worse over time. We're shifting more morbidity to younger and younger age groups,
which is not a good thing at all and likely going to affect anticipated life expectancy trends to
reverse. Aaron, obviously, these trends that you're observing, the increase in obesity,
the increase in insulin resistance, the increase in type 2 diabetes,
although you didn't state it, it's embedded within here, the increase in naphthal D and
NASH, the increase, as you said, in gestational diabetes. I mean, all of these things are
basically growing out of metabolic syndrome. You could argue now, I don't know the latest stats,
but do you know what fraction of people in the United States now have metabolic syndrome?
I don't know. I've had my head for metabolic syndrome, but it's huge. We know that diabetes
rates are certainly going up with over one in 10 US adults having diabetes. And many with diabetes
don't even know that they have it. So there's a latency and diagnosis. So this is all really
alarming trends, especially when we have a lot of therapies we can do for prevention.
But of course, one of the most important prevention therapies I can prescribe for my patients is
lifestyle changes. Even modest weight loss can have a pretty significant impact on proglycerides
and blood pressure reduction. So it's always important that we can talk about all the new
exciting therapies we have for weight loss, like the GLP1 receptor agonist and the dual agonist,
but really still emphasizing healthy lifestyle from childhood is still such an important
strategy for prevention. So we know it's multifaceted. I don't think any serious
commentator on this will point to one thing and say that's the culprit for why we're seeing this
epidemic. But how do you rank order these things? So what is the causative driver in your mind for
weight loss? How much of that do you think lies at the feet of lower exercise levels versus
food availability, hyperpallatability, specific elements within the diet? How do you start to
disentangle this? Because I think without some level of granularity there, it becomes difficult
to say lose weight. An overweight person shows up and you tell them to lose weight. That's not a
particularly helpful insight. So in other words, to prescribe something insightful, we have to have
some sense of what the etiology is. So how do you think about that? First of all, I'm trying to
prevent or reverse the trends of obesity on a population basis. And so we put too much
blame on the individual, but we have major societal and population problems with the
easy access to poor quality food, these highly processed foods that are extremely palatable,
but contain a lot of saturated fats and other additives and sugars. The way our jobs are
structured to be more sedentary and long commute times, having access to safe places to exercise
and having time to do so and the increased stress levels in life. I mean, there's so many social
determinants of health that have led to this problem. And there's huge parts of the country
where there's food deserts, where there's not access to fruits and vegetables or food swamps
that are just really only available, cheap and easy foods are these highly processed packaged foods.
So as individuals, we do have some responsibility for our own life choices. Larger issues should be
placed in regulation and policy on a population level. And then, you know, once an individual is
already obese, it's much harder than to lose weight. We certainly talk about lifestyle changes,
but obesity is far more complicated. There is all kinds of hormonal regulations, and it's not just
as easy as calories in, calories out. The good news for these individuals is that at least now,
we do have some new pharmacological agents that are beneficial in weight loss that do not have
cardiovascular harm, like some of the older weight loss drugs, and may actually be
cardiovascularly beneficial. We know the GLP1 receptor agonist, at least in patients with type
2 diabetes, you know, reduces the risk of major adverse cardiovascular events and stroke.
And so while we do have an outcome trial ongoing right now in persons who were overweight and
obese, but without diabetes with the GLP1 receptor agonist, I'm anticipating this will also be
beneficial for cardiovascular disease. So we have new options to treat obesity, but really trying to
focus on prevention of obesity in the first place, because it's certainly not feasible to treat
two thirds of US adults are overweight and obese. The statistics are astronomical,
they're astounding. So we really need to focus on population interventions.
Which GLP1 agonist are we looking at now? Is it semiglutide or trisepatide?
So they're different. So semiglutide is a GLP1 receptor agonist, at least in patients in type
2 diabetes. We have cardiovascular outcome data for the injectable, the subcutaneous dose.
There is an outcome data ongoing for the oral formulation, but we don't have that data yet.
So usually I prescribe the injectable form. Now, so receptor bide is a new kid on the block.
It's a dual agonist, a GIP, GLP1 receptor agonist. This has been approved also for
diabetes, although the outcome trial for diabetes is ongoing, the CIRM-out outcome trial.
But it also has been evaluated for weight loss and really showed dramatic weight loss,
up to 50 pounds in the highest dose, which is really remarkable. We can't compare trials
head to head because they were not compared head to head, but in the STEP trials with
semiglutide, there was about a 30 or so pound weight loss. So triseptebide is not yet FDA
approved for weight management, although it will likely have this indication soon, but it was,
it is approved for type 2 diabetes. Semiglutide is approved for both type 2 diabetes for reduction
in major adverse cardiovascular events, but it also has a separate weight loss indication
for persons who are obese with BMI above 30 or overweight with a BMI over 27 in the setting of
one or more obesity related cardiovascular risk factors who need additional weight management
after diet and lifestyle attempts. So we have new agents now, which is really exciting, but getting
back to we need to do in a larger population to reverse the overall trends of obesity.
Before we leave the GLP1 agonist and the dual receptor agonist, what is your best guess as to
the mechanism by which they also reduce cardiac events if it indeed is beyond weight loss? In
other words, do you think it's all due to the benefits of weight loss, which of course bring
with it an improvement in metabolic health, or do you think there's something specific there
that's going on? And I would ask the same question eventually, although we don't have to discuss it
now with SGLT2 inhibitors. The GLP1 receptor agonist, I don't know that we fully understand
all of the benefits on the mechanisms for benefits, but we know that the benefits of
reducing major adverse cardiovascular events are independent of its A1C lowering. These are
interesting agents that in persons with elevated glucose, such as diabetes, they lower blood
glucose. But in persons who don't have elevated glucose, such as those with who are overweight
obese who don't have diabetes, GLP1s don't cause hypoglycemia solo agents. So they only lower blood
glucose in a glucose dependent fashion. But the benefit on base reduction, which has been shown
to persons with type 2 diabetes, is independent of A1C lowering. It may in part be related to
favorable changes and other risk factors, such as reduction in blood pressure and weight loss.
There's improvement in the lipid panel. It's being investigated also in NAFLD as well. There
may be anti-inflammatory effects. There may be anti-atherescrotic effects. There also may be some
effects in the kidney. We do see a reduction in albinuria with these agents as well. So there
really an interesting class of drugs. So let's now turn our attention to specifically the physiology
of women as it pertains to lipids and ASCVD. So I think we should maybe to make it easier,
at least start with premenopausal women. What's happening in a woman's body when she's 25,
that's different from a man's body when he's 25 as it pertains to sex hormones and the interaction,
therefore with lipids and other factors that impact the simmering process of ASCVD?
Sure. First, I just wanted to give a broad statement. I'm glad that we're having this
discussion about lipids in women and ASCVD in women because there are differences. Women are
not smaller men or have unique risk factors. Even among traditional risk factors, diabetes and
smoking confer a greater relative risk in women than in men. And then women have unique risk factors
that we'll talk more about throughout their lifespan that men do not related to menarchy
when earlier late and polycystic ovary syndrome and infertility, spontaneous pregnancy loss,
parity, adverse pregnancy outcomes like preeclampsia, lack of breastfeeding and early menopause.
And in addition, chronic inflammatory conditions like rheumatoid arthritis and lupus are more
prevalent in women. So women have these unique risk factors that are female specific or female
predominant. And cardiovascular disease also can be different in women, which is why we need more
trials in women. Women are more likely to have ischemia with non obstructive coronary disease
from coronary microvascular dysfunction or coronary vasospasm. They're more likely to have
SCAD, spontaneous coronary artery dissection and more likely to have stress cardiomyopathy than men.
So we really need more data about treating cardiovascular disease in women.
But let's talk about the life cycle that you alluded to in the beginning with your question.
Estradiol is the predominant female sex hormone in women of reproductive age that seems to have
the beneficial effects with lowering LDL and conferring some cardiovascular protective properties.
But I should mention there's actually three types of estrogen. So estradiol, which is the predominant
one in women in childbearing age, and this is the most potent form of estrogen. So estradiol is E2.
So estriol E3 is the main estrogen produced during pregnancy. And then estrone E1 is the only estrogen
produced after menopause. It's also the weakest estrogen. So you know, starting with puberty,
puberty is a process that starts in the brain. So the hypothalamus in the brain suddenly begins
secreting gonadotropin releasing hormone or GNRH. FSH and LH levels gradually increase during puberty,
which stimulate the follicle maturation and estrogen production and the ovaries,
and also the secondary sex characteristics like breast changes and changes in body composition.
This gets to the point where then there's the onset of menarche or the first men's
yeast. And so this is typically, you know, around age 12. And it's important to note that, you know,
I treat adult patients, but why I even ask adult women about the onset of menarche
is because both early menarche before the age of 11 and also late menarche after the age of 17 has
been associated with increased cardiovascular disease risk later in life. And there's likely
hormonal and adipokine and cardiometabolic imprinting that's related to this. There's
lots of factors related to the onset of menarche, but both socioeconomic and environmental factors
as well as genetic factors. But elevated BMI is a risk factor for early onset menarche, which is why
again, it's so important that we think about healthy lifestyle starting in childhood.
And I'll talk a little bit now about the menstrual cycle, because many people don't know, but the
lipids do change throughout the menstrual cycle difference in little cholesterol, you know, as
much as 10 to 12 milligrams or deciliter difference. And so while most women are reproductive age who
have lower LDL, this is not probably clinically significant in terms of atherogenesis. It does
matter when thinking about the timing of measuring a lipid panel during the menstrual cycle. I think
that's important to note. So during the menstrual cycle, you have the hypothalamus is releasing GNRH,
which causes the pituitary gland to release FSH. So FSH is acting on the ovaries to mature the
follicles. And that the follicles of the ovaries is what secretes estradiol. And so estradiol causes
the maturation of the egg and the thickening of the uterus lining and preparation for a fertilized
egg implant. And then the increased estradiol triggers the release of LH, which induces ovulation
and release of the egg. And so ovulation ends the follicular phase. And then after ovulation,
you're in the luteal phase where estradiol with progestin prepare the womb for implantation. But
if the egg isn't fertilized, the corpus luteum, which is secreting the progesterone breaks down.
So this leads to a drop in progesterone level in the beginning of the menstrual period. What does
this mean for lipids? So after menses, you know, total cholesterol and LDL increase rapidly after
menses. And so they really peak during this follicular phase. And then this is followed by
a decline in the luteal phase, which corresponds to the rise in the peak concentration of estrogen
and progesterone. So when estradiol is the highest in the menstrual cycle, this leads to the fall in
total cholesterol and LDL. HDL is highest around ovulation. Triglycerides didn't really have a
consistent pattern during the menstrual cycle. So there isn't specific guidance. And so just to
make sure I understood that, Erin, the difference between the peak and nadir of LDL cholesterol
is about 10 to 12 milligrams per deciliter, or is that total cholesterol?
That was total cholesterol, but it mirrors the difference in LDL as well. So this was a study that
published on average, total cholesterol may go from 158 to 168, where LDL on average went from
97 to 102. So, you know, they're not dramatic changes, which is why we don't worry about this
too much in women of reproductive ages who don't have a lipid disorder. But it's, you know,
interesting to note. But if a woman is very high risk, like has ASCBD, and we're trying to target
these really intensive thresholds, like LDL is less than 70 or even lower, it's useful to know
that they do change throughout the menstrual cycle. So while there's no specific guidance around this,
you know, I generally recommend clinicians measure the lipid panel during the menses so that it's
ideally measured, monitored and compared at the same time during the menstrual cycle. So usually
the menses is easiest to benchmark to. We do that when we're concerned with, as women become
perimenopausal and we want to start getting a sense of what's happening, we always use day five.
So if the initiation of menses, even if it's spotting is day one, but we always just pick day
five. And that way we have a really consistent view specifically of FSH and estradiol, progesterone
is zero at that time. But the FSH and the estradiol really give us a sense of how close she's
probably getting to menopause. And then we correlate that with symptoms to sort of start
to think about initiating HRT, but as a whole other topic, which I'm sure we'll get to.
You know, in terms of lipid panel, it's good to be measuring around the same time each month. So if
you're following the serial lipid panels in a woman for a reason, so timing it around day five,
especially if you're measuring other hormones. But yeah, so FSH would be at the highest during
the early follicular page and then declines after ovulation where LH is low during the early
follicular phase and then peaks around an ovulation, which stimulates the egg to be released.
At this point in a woman's life, she still enjoys this for all intents and purposes,
decade advantage over men in terms of ASCBD risk. So a 40 year old woman who is still
ovulating is at a cardiovascular standpoint is a 30 year old man. Is that directionally what we
would say prior to menopause? Yeah, I mean, on average, and again, people are not averages,
people are individuals, but on average, there is a about 10 year offset of ASCBD in women
developing it later than men. And this may be because we'll talk about when we get to menopause,
you know, with the loss of estradiol after menopause, LDL levels rise after menopause.
And so that women may have higher LDLs a little bit later in life. You know, many women's tell me,
oh, you know, I've always had good lipid levels. And now they're higher, you know, after menopause.
And so when we get back to what we started with about the integration of duration of LDL exposure
in terms of cholesterol years, they may have had lower number of cholesterol years during their
childbearing years and then higher levels later in life. And that might be why they have this
offset. But again, you don't see this in FH, and we don't see this as well in diabetes. And so each
person is an individual. And so we do women a disservice when we presume that all women somehow
are lower risk or protected during their menopausal years, because we started out this podcast talking
about that we absolutely see myocardial events, not just things like SCAD, but we see actual
atherosclerotic myocardial infarction events in younger women too. So they're at lower risk,
but not zero risk. And so we take each person as an individual. And then there are things we need
to consider related to contraception and PCOS that can also affect the lipid profile as well.
Let's take each of those then, because I think they're both incredibly fascinating and highly
prevalent. So let's start with PCOS. Tell folks what it is, maybe what the prevalence is, what we
think the etiology is, and of course, what the impact is on metabolic health and ultimately lipids.
So polycystic ovary syndrome or PCOS is the most common endocrine abnormality of women of
reproductive age. Estimates are about 5% to 13% of women in the general population. And it does
affect women of all race ethnicities. It's categorized sort of by this triad of hyperandrogenism,
ovulatory dysfunction, so irregular menses or anovulatory cycles, and polycystic ovary
morphology. So just having cysts in the ovary in itself is not enough for the diagnosis. You need
to have these other criteria. It is a heterogeneous disorder in that there are differences in risk
with PCOS. But really, if you talk about the classical PCOS that has the hyperandrogen form,
this seems to be the one that is the most strongly linked with cardiovascular risk and the
cardiometabolic phenotype. So we really think that insulin resistance is hallmarking under the
pathogenesis of this, that there is molecular defects and insulin activities and PCOS that
leads to impaired glucose tolerance and glucose insulin resistance and hyperinsulinemia.
Studies have shown that about 95% of obese women with PCOS and about 75% of lean women with PCOS
has insulin resistance. So there is a lean PCOS phenotype. While most women with PCOS do have an
elevated body mass index, not all women have an elevated body mass index. But this insulin
resistance is probably driving a lot of the cardiometabolic complications, so elevations
in blood pressure and dyslipidemia patterns. So we see this, the triad of dyslipidemia with the
elevated LDL, elevated triglycerides, and low HDL, this metabolic syndrome pattern. PCOS is
associated with hypertension and insulin hypertension, and this is actually independent of BMI,
but obesity increases the risk and makes the risk greater. And there is an association not only with
increased subclinical atherosclerosis. I recently published a meta-analysis where we showed that
women with PCOS were twofold more likely to have coronary calcium. They're also more likely to have
parotid plaque, but they're also associated with increased cardiovascular disease later in life.
And the variable estimates have varied across studies, and this is likely because how PCOS was
defined and how cardiovascular disease was defined. And so they're not quite consistent across every
study, but on average about 30 to 50% increased risk that we saw in an umbrella review of a
meta-analysis of future cardiovascular risk. Now there's a little bit of debate about whether PCOS
is causally related to CVD. This excess risk that we see seems to be more of women during reproductive
age. Once women's already after menopause, having a prior history of PCOS doesn't seem to confer the
same level of risk, and likely because of all of the increased risk after the menopause transition
with the low estradiol and the more androgen phenotype after menopause probably outweighs or
overshadows any prior risk related to PCOS. But there does seem to be this long-term risk, but when
you look at Mendelian randomization studies, that does suggest that the elevated testosterone,
the hyperandrogen, the obesity, the higher insulin levels, insulin resistance, and lower levels of
sexual rebinding globulin do appear to have a causal relationship with PCOS based on genetics.
And so it may be that these are the mediating factors that link PCOS with future cardiovascular
disease risk. Obviously there's an enormous impact on fertility. Are multiple pregnancies
associated with an increased risk of ASCVD or decreased risk based on the estrogen? PCOS
is associated with infertility, and this is one of the mainstay of treatment of women PCOS who are
not wanting to become pregnant, of course, is oral contraceptives to kind of reduce the
hyperandrogenism. We recently published, though, a study looking at national data of pregnancies
at delivery, and we did show that women, you know, with PCOS who did become pregnant, you know, they
were at greater risk for preeclampsia and many gestational diabetes and many cardiovascular
complications compared to women with PCOS. So it's important to, you know, note that not only are
they at increased risk, have decreased fertility and trouble getting pregnant, but once they do
become pregnant, they are at increased risk of cardiovascular complications and delivery.
So it's really important with PCOS, again, that we optimize healthier lifestyle and weight
management may be really important to mitigate some of the cardiometabolic risk. I'm interested,
you know, in women who are not trying to become pregnant or not pregnant, GLP1 receptor agonists
may be promising to help with the weight management and the insulin resistance, you know,
we talked about that class of drugs, and even statin therapy may reduce some of the testosterone
or the androgen associated risk. So that's what PCOS, but I think that you asked about parity in
general. So when you look at parity or the number of live births, there does seem to be a J point,
J shape relationship with higher parity, particularly more than four or five live births,
being associated with subsequent risk of cardiovascular disease. The reason for this
is not quite known. I showed in the MESA study that women who had a histogram multiparty, you know,
were much more likely to be in poor cardiovascular health later in life, middle aged, older age,
compared to less parous women. You know, women tend to gain weight with each pregnancy,
but there may be also dysregulation of adipokines that sets the stage for later
cardiometabolic complications. And so this is why it's really important that we try to optimize
women's cardiometabolic health before pregnancy and enter pregnancy between pregnancies to try
to prevent these long term complications. So I mean, I wouldn't tell a woman that they can't
become pregnant a certain number of times, but I would really try to work with them to try to
optimize their cardiometabolic health. I feel like your intuition is right there,
Aaron. I've always found the epidemiology on number of pregnancies and disease X to be
completely full of confounders, such to the point that I think the epi provides no insight.
Whereas I think the confounder you mentioned is the most obvious one, right? Which is the more
pregnancies a woman has, the more likely you could believe that she's having difficulty getting back
to her pre never pregnant state of metabolic health, not just weight, but overall metabolic
health. And that would strike me as a greater risk factor. Again, I, one can't know this without
randomization. We're obviously not going to have that. So it probably shouldn't factor into
decision making. I will mention that there are a couple of studies. So the problem is most
epidemiology studies don't ask men the parody history. They don't ask men these questions,
you know, they only ask them of women, but there were a couple of studies where they assess
number of children and men and parody is actually a risk factor for CBD and men too.
So this likely gets to your point about compounding by social economic factors and cultural factors,
education factors that might lead a family to have more children rather than less. But the risk does
seem to be a little greater in women suggesting that there may be some true biological effects,
maybe weight mediated beyond just confounding my social economic and cultural factors.
Let's talk about the impact of oral contraceptives, even outside of the case of PCOS. So if you have
a young woman who wants to use OCs as a form of birth control, what is the impact that that,
if any, has on her lifelong risk of a CVD via the, let's just say she's going to go on it for a
decade, age 25 to 35, and then have kids 35 to 40, and then goes through menopause at 50.
Is there some impact that that decade being on an OCP has on her down the line?
You know, women of reproductive age may be initiated on contraception for various reasons.
So it's not just pregnancy prevention, but maybe for treatment of menstrual cycle disorders, PCOS,
acne, there's lots of reasons why they might start oral contraceptive therapy.
The risk likely depends so much based on formulation and type. So we can't link
all contraceptives in one bin. Oral combined hormonal contraceptives, the older formulations
had much higher doses of estrogen. And so estrogen can increase triglyceride levels.
It can lower LDL, which is a good thing, but it can increase triglyceride levels.
What's the net effect, Aaron, on ApoB? Because certainly the analysis I've seen suggest that
once you correct for ApoB, triglycerides below 400 milligrams per deciliter really don't mean
anything. Obviously above that level, you have to start worrying about pancreatitis, but that
ApoB was capturing that risk. And it's interesting, of course, if you're only looking at LDL-C and
triglyceride, it's possible that a rise in triglyceride is problematic because that could
actually raise ApoB as you now have to obviously increase the potential number of both cholesterol
and triglyceride trafficking particles. I'm guessing that analysis isn't done, but do you
have an intuition around it? No, I mean, of course, pregnancy also increases triglyceride levels a lot
too, as we'll talk about. So preventing an unwanted pregnancy outweighs any slight change,
risk for these lipid changes with oral combined contraceptives. I think the changes are relatively
modest, especially since we're using typically now the lower estrogen formulations because it's
really the more estrogen that a combined hormonal contraceptive contains has the greater impact of
increased triglycerides. So I don't have that number for you because it really depends on the
formulation. It's unlikely to have much impact in most women, but women who already have high
baseline triglycerides to begin with, it can trigger severe hypertaglyceridemia above 500.
So this probably would not be the agent you'd want to use if your patient already had high
triglycerides. Now, the transdermal combined oral hormonal contraceptives, the patch, is less likely
to cause clinically relevant elevations and triglycerides. There's, of course, other types
of contraceptives, and very high risk women with established cardiovascular disease or women who
have FH, who have very high LDL levels. These tier one methods, the long acting reversible methods
like the IUD and the implant are safe and effective for most women who even have high
risk, who have established cardiovascular conditions. The progesterone based ones like the
Marina with the progesterone releasing IUD system, they can marginally, associated with lower HDL,
but usually these revert back to pre-insertion levels by one year. Most of the time for the IUDs,
the triglycerides and LDL and the cholesterol ratios remain pretty stable. So I really don't
think that the lipid changes are so much impacted by that, and that's why we do tend to recommend
the IUD for women who have FH or cardiovascular disease that are high at risk.
Let's talk a little bit about pregnancy. I guess there's two things I want to chat about. The first
is obviously what's happening to a woman during pregnancy. So probably share a little bit more
than my wife wishes I would, but I sort of use myself and my wife as a guinea pig from time to
time and just love checking labs all the time. During, I don't know, one of the pregnancies,
maybe it was our second child, I probably checked her, you know, did a very thorough
look at her lipids and lipoproteins and everything all the way through her pregnancy.
I was shocked at how much her lipids rose during pregnancy. My wife is sort of one of those people
who genetically has very low burden of APO B. So her baseline LDL cholesterol is probably 60 to 70
milligrams per deciliter or HDL cholesterol might be 80, 90 milligrams per deciliter. So triglycerides
of 40 milligrams per deciliter, right? So from a lipid lipoprotein standpoint, she's pretty
uninteresting. And I want to say by the third end of second, beginning of third trimester,
you know, she looked like she had metabolic syndrome without the triglycerides. But just
from the standpoint of some of the other stuff, tell me what, and I know we hate talking about
averages, but can you give me just sort of a general sense of what's directionally happening
to a woman during pregnancy with respect to her lipids and lipoproteins?
Yeah, so absolutely, there's changes in lipid panel, which is why women with known lipid
disorders are recommended to have consultation with a lipid specialist prior to pregnancy.
But you know, even at normal pregnancies, serum total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL cholesterol,
lipoprotein A and HDL cholesterol levels all gradually increase. And as pregnancy proceeds,
you know, they peak during the third trimester. So you can have about a 25 to 50% increase in total
cholesterol can be as much as 150 to 300% increase in triglycerides, probably, you know, relative
increase the most, and LDL increased by 66%. And so this is normal physiologic changes because
it's designed to promote accumulation of maternal fat stores, that's going to be a source of calories
for the mother and the fetus during later stages of pregnancy and lactation. You know,
the cholesterol increase is needed for utero placental vascularization, placental steroid
synthesis, placental transport function. These are important physiological effects. But these
changes when someone like your wife who started out, so it's such low cholesterol levels,
these are generally felt to be non-athrogenic because they really do fall precipitatively to
pre pregnancy levels following delivery. So pregnancy is not a good time really to get a
baseline lipid panel because it's not going to be representative of what a woman's typical lipid
panel is. But in women who have concern for lipid disorder, having a baseline lipid panel before
pregnancy is helpful so that you can know what to expect. In women with FH, you know, they have the
same relative increases, but they're starting with such a high baseline level that the magnitude of
elevation is even greater. You know, I realize I've been delinquent in letting us talk shop a
bit too much. We haven't defined FH other than to note that it's familial hypercholesterolemia.
We also noted, I think the incidence or prevalence of about 1 in 200, but we've been a bit delinquent
in giving people the magnitude of what it is. Can you just tell folks a little bit about how high
a total cholesterol or LDL cholesterol, a person with familial hypercholesterolemia typically has
and what the lifetime risk of AOCVD is in that population? I think we mentioned at the beginning
that it's about 1 in 250, 1 in 250 people have FH and it's being autosomal dominant that women are
equally affected as men. So the FH phenotype LDL above 190, you know, there are different scoring
systems that you can look with additional criteria based on family, personal family history of AOCVD
and genetic tests are available when there's apps that you can download to determine the
likelihood that your patient has, you know, a definite or probable FH. Just even having the
phenotype of having an LDL above 190, which is not all monogenic FH, that is still associated
with increased lifetime risk with a 20 to 30 year earlier onset of AOCVD in females. But if they have
the genetic mutation, you know, having the monogenic mutation, their increased risk is even greater than
their LDL value. So that's why genetic testing is really helpful, not only for cascade effects for
determining the risk of their first degree relatives and their offspring, but also because
they have a greater risk even beyond their absolute LDL value. But so 30% of women with an untreated
FH will have a mild cardiomyfarction before the age of 60. And this is why it's so important that
we can't ignore FH. We need to know FH, we need to screen for FH and we need to treat FH. Women
get the same onset as men, they don't have the female advantage. And probably because they're
losing many years of statin therapy, because this concern about pregnancy, women with FH are
undertreated. I should note that women with FH don't have an increased risk of congenital
malformations or pre-clampsia, which is good. They may have a slight increased risk, greater risk
from aacronal infarction. So we can talk about shared decision making about treatment during
pregnancy versus withholding for a short period of time during pregnancy and lactation. But
interestingly, in some countries, you can actually test for the mutation in cord blood and lipid
levels in children with FH are similar, whether they inherited the gene from their mother or the
father. But for contraception, because of their increased risk for atherosclerosis, we would want
to avoid any higher estrogen compounds, either use low dose estrogen, oral contraceptives, or preferably
IUDs or barrier techniques, especially if they're over the age of 35 to kind of avoid the estrogen
oral agents, even low dose and consider the IUD for contraception. So of course, most people with
FH, we don't really know the genetic cause of this. You know, last I checked, there were probably
more than 2,500 different genetic mutations that produce that phenotype. So this is an interesting
point that there's still value in looking. In other words, just having that phenotype,
how many of the genetic drivers of FH do we know and contribute to that very interesting point you
made, which is identifying that specific genetic driver carries with it even greater risk than is
embedded within the LDL. When I see patients clinically for evaluation of FH, I do send them,
they're willing for genetic testing, trying to discern whether they have the monogenic FH
from a mutation in the LDL receptor or APOB or PCSK9. Of course, polygenetic risk can have a similar
phenotype to FH. We certainly want to reduce their lipids. So this comes up, because we were talking
about pregnancy and there had been so concerned for so long about avoiding statins in pregnancy.
For a while, I had that category X. And so this actually led to overabundance of caution with just
not treating women of reproductive age with statins at all because of fear that they might
accidentally become pregnant. And we really, of course, do them a disservice of a third of them
are going to be at risk for an MI before the age of 60 if they have FH and we don't treat, especially
because now we have more data suggesting studies of women who did become pregnant while on statins
that did not show the teratogenic effects. And so statins are probably not teratogenic.
You know, we don't have a ton of data here, which is why we still have some caution, which
most women who are planning a pregnancy, you know, we do generally still stop the statins
during conception, during pregnancy, and during breastfeeding as shorter term interruptions
is better than, you know, not treating them for decades and decades. But with the removal of the
frongus warning label by the FDA, this does give us some more flexible options. So in patients at
very high risk, such as women who've had a recent acute coronary syndrome, as part of shared
decision making, we could consider using statins during pregnancy. But you know, we still have
less data. So for most women, we're still stopping the statins. But if they do become pregnant, you
know, I usually reassure them and we just stop the statin once pregnancy has become aware. But I think
there's a really interesting body of work now about whether statins can actually prevent
preeclampsia. So in the setting of preeclampsia, there is this abnormal trophoblast invasion,
and this leads to impaired spiral artery remodeling. So essentially what's happening
is there's placenta ischemia, and this sets off a whole cascade of adverse hormonal and
anti-inflammatory markers. So we have this increase in S-flip 1 and a decrease in placental
growth factor. There's, you know, this increased sensitivity to angiotension 2. There's other
inflammatory and oxidative stress. And this sets the stage not only for complications during the
pregnancy like preeclampsia, but also is likely contributing to vascular damage that increase
a woman's risk, you know, long-term after delivery. So statins are being, you know, investigated for
preeclampsia prevention because we know in animal studies, they can decrease S-flip 1,
they can improve endothelial function, they can decrease inflammation and oxidative stress.
So they seem promising. There was one study that was published where they gave women who were
pregnant who are increased risk of preeclampsia, paravastatin starting at 35 weeks gestation
and didn't show any benefit in preventing preeclampsia. But this isn't really surprising
because it was just given way too late. You know, if you know anything about the pathogenesis of
preeclampsia, you know, preeclampsia can generally start after 20 weeks of gestation. So you likely
would have to intervene, you know, much earlier in the process. So there is a randomized clinical
trial ongoing now enrolling about 1,500 women who are high risk because of a prior history of
preeclampsia. And they're starting the statin, paravastatin versus placebo earlier around 12
weeks of gestation. So right after the first trimester, the primary outcome is going to be
proportion that develop preeclampsia or retinal loss and maternal death. And they're looking at
other things like preterm delivery. So it'll be really interesting to see those results. We don't
have those results yet, but it may be a whole pendulum switch from this absolute avoidance
of statins during pregnancy to maybe actually using statins for preeclampsia prevention if
this trial is successful. Do you think broadly we're seeing a greater trend towards statin?
I don't know, phobia for lack of a better word. Well, yes, even in sort of the non-pregnant state.
I meant even more broad. Yeah, exactly. I meant just across all of your patients.
First of all, I think there's some misconceptions out there that I still hear people cite this
false statement that statins don't work in women in primary prevention. And that's completely not
true. In the older studies, they just didn't enroll enough women in trials. And in primary
prevention, they're at lower risk, so they're less likely to have events during the short
terms of the trials. But now we have enough trials, the data's in, and meta-analysis that included
over 18 randomized clinical trials, over 40,000 women have shown that statins benefit women in
both primary and secondary prevention without interaction by sex. So meaning in similar risk
individuals, women benefit from statins just as much as men in both primary prevention,
where there was a 15% reduction in major adverse cardiovascular events, as well as for every one
millimole per liter or 39 milligrams per deciliter lowering of LDL. And in secondary prevention,
at a little bit greater, 22% reduction, as well as all cause mortality was lower in women with
statins. So women benefit from statins. What's the NNT on both of those, Erin? I would have to
get back to you from the meta-analysis, I don't know offhand, but of course, the NNT is going to
depend on primary prevention versus secondary prevention. And of course, the women that were
enrolled in these trials were at higher risk. But the important thing is that they benefited
similarly to men with no effect interaction. That's what I was kind of getting at. Was it
in the ballpark of men where your primary preventions could be anywhere from 60 to 100,
and your secondary preventions might be 30 to 50? Does that sort of... Those numbers kind of ring a
bell to me. That sounds about right. I just don't have that data right in front of me, but that
sounds about right. I can look that up for you. But despite the evidence clearly showing that they
benefit, to get back to your original question, women are less likely to be offered a statin.
We saw this from the Palm Registry. And if offered, women are more likely to decline or
discontinue. In the usage registry, women were 30 to 50% more likely to report statin-associated
muscle symptoms and stop statins for this reason. Even in secondary prevention, studies of individuals
who have post-mile cardiomyfarction, young women under the age of 55 were significantly less likely
than men to be on a statin two months after their MI. And these are the highest risk individuals,
the recent MI, and women are still less likely to be on a statin. One of my own studies,
using nationally representative data from the medical expenditure panel survey,
it's weighted to represent US adults with ASCBD. So it's weighted to represent 11 million women
with ASCBD. Women were 45% less likely to be treated on a statin than with men. So we know
there's lots of... And Aaron, how much of that do you think is on the shoulders of the physician
for either being ignorant or just, I guess, ignorant would be the only excuse,
not offering the statin versus how often is the physician doing the right thing and the patient,
as a woman specifically, is saying, you know what, this is not the right thing for me?
So the Palm Registry shows women are less likely to be offered. And so this is on the physician
side. We see this across all kinds of subgroups, both in primary prevention, secondary prevention,
and also whether they're treated by a cardiologist or primary care, women are less likely to be
on a statin. But if offered, if the clinicians do the right thing and offer, women are more likely
to decline or discontinue. This is a combination of things. Women may still perceive themselves
to be lower risk. Women may be more fear adverse. They also, women are report more likely to have
statin-associated muscle symptoms. And so this gets down to how much is real versus the nocebo effect.
Is it biological differences related to women's smaller body size,
influenza hormones, or is it that maybe women are more socialized to report symptoms or
read these warning labels or a possible symptom that could happen or be more concerned? I mean,
we have overwhelming data about the safety of statins. Serious muscle injury is one in 100,000.
In randomized clinical trials, there's no difference of muscle symptoms between treated
and placebo. We know in real world practice, up to 30% of statin-treated patients report
muscle symptoms. So there's this tremendous nocebo effect in trials like the SAMHSA trial,
up to 90% of statin-associated symptoms was elicited by the placebo too. So patients were
having symptoms on the statins, but 90% of those symptoms were also elicited on the placebo. So it
really wasn't as more the act of taking the medication compared to the medication itself.
So we know the nocebo effect is real, but the problem is that this can be challenging to
counsel. There's a lot of medical misinformation out there. And when an individual, the symptoms
are real to them, and if they're convinced they're having these symptoms, it can be hard to break
that mindset. My practice is all about building trust and we build a relationship over time. And
sometimes I start slow or do alternative doses every other day or three times a week and trying
to get individuals back on their statin and show that they tolerate them and have them take a muscle
symptom survey and show that a lot of the aches and pains that they have, you know,
were unrelated to the statin. But the good news at least is that we're releasing an error
that we have more options than we did before. Though all individuals who have report statin
associated muscle symptoms or statin intolerance, you know, really should be given a re-challenge
for our highest risk patients. We have other things. Zetimine, we have the PCSK9 inhibitors,
we have clizarin, mepidobic acid, and more things in the pipeline. So we have ways to get to LDL goal
if patients are willing to work with us. And, you know, while these other therapies are meant to be
as an adjunct to diet and lifestyle and maximally tolerated statins, for some patients, the maximally
tolerated statin is zero statin. And so sometimes we have to move to some of these other agents to
get their LDL under control. Aaron, what's your statin workflow? How do you work through a patient
with a statin? So my behavior on this front has evolved a little bit in part just due to experience,
but also in part due to the arrival of these other agents that you mentioned, the big three being
zetimide, PCSK9 inhibitors, and most recently, pepidobic acid. But these days I really find myself
only fiddling with about three statins truthfully. And this excludes patients who show up on one
already that they inherit. So a torvostatin or something like that. But in terms of a naive
patient, I would say it's really mostly two. It's really resuvastatin and then pitavastatin with
occasional pravastatin. You can imagine obviously the order in which we do that based on symptoms
and need. Walk me through your thinking specifically for women. So woman comes in, doesn't have FH,
family history is notable for atherosclerosis, but nothing incredibly premature before the age
of 60. Her APO B is the 70th percentile concordant with her LDL C. And after months of being your
patient, she says, you know, okay, I sort of buy this thesis, which is I'm 40 years old, my LDL is
only going to go up from here. So let's start to take preventative measurements. So this is
true primary prevention in a relatively low 10 year risk patient. And you have no reason to
be concerned with anything else. So what's your first line agent? What dose and how do you proceed
if there was issues? The highest risk patients, we'll get back to your primary prevention patients,
highest risk patients with ASCVD, you know, we want to get as low as possible as quickly as
possible, lower for longer for faster. And so we do a lot of disservice by starting these really
low dose statins, and they don't come back for six months to a year, and then they never get
intensified and patients don't get to goal. So in the highest risk patients, starting with a high
intensity statin, if you start up front, that's more likely the dose that they'll stay on,
and use of combination therapy early. So you know, just like blood pressure, if it's above 160,
you know, we're thinking combination therapy for blood pressure. And I have the same approach
really for lipids, or very high risk patients, such as the ones with a recent coronary syndrome,
that you know, we know what their starting LDL is and where we want to go. And I always try to aim
for at least less than 55 optimal LDL is probably, you know, around 30 or lower these patients,
you know, if where you need to go high intensity statins will lower the LDL by about 50%. But if
you need a greater reduction, thinking about combination therapy up early, we have some data
now about the safety of giving PCSQ9 inhibitors even in the hospital setting after an acute
myocardial infarction can have important changes in plaque stabilization and plaque reduction. So
being very intensive about those treatments. I want to make the plug about using combination
earlier and more aggressively. And your lower risk primary prevention patient that you started with,
the modern intensity statin would be fine. I mean, it depends on their age. If it's a man over 40 or
women over 50, get a coronary calcium score. You know, if they're above the 75th percentile,
also thinking high intensity statin and aiming for an LDL less than 70, which is also consideration
of PCSQ9 inhibitors, even in primary prevention patients, if they have significant plaque,
you know, very high calcium scores above 300. But you know, in a lower risk person where we're just
trying to shift them some lower. And sorry, just going back to that, Aaron, I know it wasn't my
question, but since you brought it up, is your preferred two line out of the gate,
resouvastatin and azetamide? Is that your typical starting one, two punch?
I mean, again, it depends where they are and where we start with. They're very high risk. They have
ASCVD and they're very high risk. You're going to go PCSQ9 plus. Yeah, especially if they have
elevated liporatidyl A because statins, azetamide, bimpedoic acid don't lower liporatyl A. So if they
had an ASCVD event, it used to be to get the PCSQ9 and prove that you had a beyond statin and azetamide
before you could get the PCSQ9 approved. So I used to use both just knowing that I'm going to move
to PCSQ9. Now it's a little bit easier to get the PCSQ9 approved, even if you don't have azetamide
on board. So these very high risk patients, because azetamide, you know, you can lower LDL
by about, you know, 16 milligram per deciliter, but you want to really get the LDL way down in
these very high risk patients. I'm moving pretty quickly to PCSQ9 inhibitors, but in lower risk.
Do you have a preference by the way between Praglutin and Rapatha?
You know, so they were never compared head to head. So they have a lock a map and all
rock a map had a similar 15% reduction in major adverse cardiovascular events in their respective
trials, the four year at Odyssey trials, and they had similar reduction of liporatidyl A as well.
I tend to use, I mean, I use whatever one I can get approved. So it often depends on the patient's
insurance. Mostly if all things being equal, either one being approved, I probably tend to
use more of a lock a map because you don't have to do the dose adjustment. The short click pattern
is really easy. We have our nurse and our clinic teaches patients and I have lots of patients on
all rock a map as well. Closer in, you know, we're just starting getting experience with onboarding.
Tell folks what that is. So the PCSQ9 inhibitors that we were talking about, the eva lock a map
and all rock a map are monoclonal antibodies. So PCSQ9 is a hepatic protein that's involved with
LDL receptor degradation. And this was really interesting how quickly we moved from understanding
from genetic studies, all the way to translational studies and the bedside, you know, we know that
individuals with PCSQ9 genetic mutations that were loss of function, these individuals had very
low LDLs and very low risk of cardiovascular disease of a lifetime, were gain of function
PCSQ9 at high LDLs and increased CBD risk. So by inhibiting this protein, by inhibiting the PCSQ9,
it prevents the LDL receptor degradation so that there is an upper regulation of LDL receptors on
the surface of the hepatocyte, which leads to greater clearance of LDL out of circulation.
Those were the monoclonal antibodies and we have not only do they lower LDL by about 50 to 60%,
they also have some modest lipo-bertal A lowering around 25%. But we have two outcome trials,
Fourier and Odyssey, Fourier being in stable ASCVD and Odyssey in patients with recent acute
coronary syndrome that show that they also reduce major adverse cardiovascular events,
as we would anticipate. And we now have longer term data for follow up, which shows even after
these trials end that earlier exposure to a Velocimab to exposure to a lower LDL has a legacy
effect with continued lower risk of events. So I think that the trials were pretty short,
around two years and the curves were just starting to separate. So I think with longer
treatment, you would have had even a greater reduction. As we're talking about women,
I will just mention, unfortunately, both of these trials, women were only about 25% of participants.
Women start out with higher LDLs for various reasons. After menopause, women tend to have
higher LDLs compared to men, but that they had a similar reduction in LDL with PCSQ9 inhibitor
therapy. In terms of mace reduction, there was no interaction by sex, meaning that women benefited,
these high risk women who either have ASCVD or recent acute coronary syndrome,
benefited to a similar degree as men did. There was no major adverse event difference between
the sexes, although women are more likely to report injection site reactions. So those have
been available for a while and they're in the guidelines now as an add on to statins in high
risk patients with ASCVD or heterozygous FH who need additional LDL lowering. I also use them in
high risk primary prevention, such as those with high calcium scores who need LDL lowering. But
in closer is the new kid on the block. So this inhibits PCSQ9, but through a different mechanism.
It's a small interfering RNA, so it prevents the translation of the PCSQ9 protein from being made.
We have data from the Orion 9, 10, and 11 trials, which was looking at LDL lowering,
showing that, again, women had higher LDLs at baseline, but they had similar reduction
within closer in. Notably, the mechanism of this little difference is that it's a subcutaneous
injection, but after the first baseline in three months, it's given every six months. So it's
designed to be given in a clinic setting as opposed to the monoclonal antibodies, which people give it
home. And the frequency of every six months may be attractive for adherence because you give it in
the clinic only one more time a year than a flu shot, and you can lower LDL by about 50%. So it
may be helpful for adherence. It has been approved for LDL lowering, and we're starting to onboard it
throughout the country in our clinics. But it should be noted that we don't yet have the outcome data.
The Orion 4 is the cardiovascular outcome trial that's ongoing. I anticipate with a 50% reduction
in LDL that this will certainly translate into a reduction of major adverse cardiovascular events,
but we don't have that data yet. But these are all potential options for patients that need
more intensive LDL lowering. You can also mention bempedoic acid to round out the new drugs that are
available. This one also might be interesting in women. So bempedoic acid is an oral drug,
and so it blocks ATP citrase lyase, which is an enzyme in the cholesterol synthesis pathway. So
it's upstream of HMG-Coase reductase, which statins inhibit. Kind of works like in the pathway where
statins work, where it blocks cholesterol synthesis. And so by blocking cholesterol synthesis, this
leads to upregulation of the LDL receptor on the surface of the liver and more clearance of LDL
out of circulation. But what's notable about this is that prodrug, the enzyme to activate it,
it's only in the liver, not in the muscle. So it does not have the same reported muscle symptoms
that have been seen with statins. And also interestingly, it doesn't seem to have the
risk of new onset diabetes or the increase in glucose that we see with high intensity statins.
So alone, bempedoic acid lowers LDL about 18%. So kind of in your range of azetamide,
a little bit more lowering if it's used as monotherapy without statins, about 21% in statin
intolerant patients. It does come as a fixed dose combination with azetamide. And together with
azetamide, you see kind of greater, about 36% reduction in LDL. So you're kind of getting in
the range of your moderate to high intensity statins. Notably actually in pooled analyses
from the clear studies, which were the studies looking at the LDL lowering effects of bempedoic
acid, we see that in ASEVD and FH patients that women seem to actually have a little bit even
greater LDL lowering with bempedoic acid than men. And they were more likely to achieve a 30%
reduction in LDL with bempedoic acid than men. Since women are more likely to have statin
associated muscle symptoms, and this agent doesn't cause that, this may be a good choice
as an oral therapy for women who can't get their LDL control on a statin or don't tolerate a statin.
So just for the audience, we don't have outcome data yet for this either. It's been approved for
LDL lowering, but the big cardiovascular outcome trial clear outcomes enrolled a population with
statin intolerance. And I was really pleased that nearly 50% of trial participants were women,
likely because women are more likely to have statin tolerance. So this has been closed out
and we're anticipating we may hear the results maybe in March of 2023, hopefully.
Is this secondary prevention, Erin? No, this is high risk patients that have statin intolerance.
So high risk primary prevention, statin intolerance. Yes. And secondary prevention patients with statin
intolerance. I got you completely off topic from our original question, which was low to moderate
risk, low to moderate short-term risk. Obviously long-term risk, everybody is high risk. It's
important to say that long time horizon, we're all high risk. Everybody gets atherosclerosis if you
live long enough. But we've got our woman whose LDL cholesterol is 130 to 140 milligrams per
deciliter and she's in her 30s. She gets it, right? She says, look, nothing's going to happen to me in
the next decade, but I'm playing the long game here. I don't want to have atherosclerosis in my 80s.
What's your algorithm for statin choice out of the gate? I tend to use one of the high intensity
statins that can, you know, a bit more potent LDL lowering like a Torva or Resuva. So if they don't
have CKD, because it's important to note that Resuva does need to be dose suggested if patients
have chronic kidney disease, but assuming, you know, otherwise healthy individuals. Yeah, say she
doesn't. I use a lot of Resuva. In my experience, they tend to have a little bit less muscle
associated symptoms. Psychologically, the doses, if you do five, 10, 20, you know, patients feel
like they're taking a lower dose when compared to the Adorva, you know, 20, 40, 80, you tell
patients you can't compare milligrams from one agent to another agent because they're completely
different drugs. People think they're taking lower drugs, so lower doses. So sometimes there's a lot
of buy-in and I have a lot of patients refer to me because if they're a little bit statin reluctant
or statin hesitant. So again, this is all in a background of lifestyle changes, but if they are
concerned at all, sometimes I use just Resuva 5. It's more about buying their trust and getting
them used to the idea of taking a statin and we know even in statin intolerant patients, even if
we do Resuva 5 milligrams, three times a week, we still can have if again LDL lowering compared to
no statin at all. So for patients that have been statin intolerant, statin reluctant, just getting
them to take a low dose and then seeing a little bit as believing. And so when we got getting their
numbers back and making progress, often then we can adjust up there based on how things are going.
You know, high-risk patients, you know, I started the highest dose right out the bat. Sometimes
patients kind of check vitamin D and thyroid levels and hit coenzyme q10. There really isn't
very good data that coenzyme q10 prevents statin-sociative muscle symptoms, but if my patients
want to take that because it makes them feel better with the concept of taking a statin,
I don't object to it, but I don't actively prescribe it because it really isn't good data
that it really blocks this. The same thing with vitamin D. There really isn't good data that
taking a vitamin D supplement can prevent statin-associated muscle symptoms, but many patients,
you know, want to take that. And you know, my philosophy is if I could get them on the statin
and get their LDL lowering, you know, I'm willing to work with them on some of these other things,
really trying to get their buy-in to get them on a therapy that will lower their LDL.
And it's really important that I do refer them to our, we have a preventocardiology
nurse who discussed this nutrition because I don't want them to think that I don't value
diet and lifestyle. You know, we know that a lot of lipids is predominantly genetically determined,
but there is influence in diet. And I want to emphasize to my patients that this is really a
combination approach and that I do take diet and lifestyle, you know, very seriously as well.
What type of an impact do you think you can see with manipulating diet, presumably mostly through
the types of fats they're consuming, but more broadly, is there how aggressively can you use
dietary manipulation, especially in a woman who for whatever reason, be it pregnancy or just
reluctance, is hoping to minimize, if not avoid the use of lipid lowering medication?
No, about three fourths or 80% of LDL is synthesized by the liver. So there's, you know,
is a strong genetic component. I have lots of patients that are strict vegan and do everything
right. And they still have high cholesterol and they get so frustrated. And I, you know,
this is genetically determined. And if they had a bad diet, their numbers would be so much worse.
And so it's important to note all the good things that they're doing for the diet, but also
acknowledge that sometimes they're going to need a little help with pharmacotherapy because of the
strong genetic determination. But, you know, around the other 20% is influenced by diet. So diet
does matter, particularly in younger adults. We're thinking about adolescents in young adults,
you know, especially wanting to start earlier in life. If we can shift everybody a little bit lower
in their LDL by following a healthy diet, really, since, you know, early childhood, if we can shift
everybody lower on LDL, this will reduce the total burden of years with LDL elevation. So, you know,
we counsel about reduction in saturated fats and focusing on the healthier fats, the polyunsaturated
and the monounsaturated fats, increasing fiber, fruits, vegetables, whole grains into their diet,
really trying to avoid processed foods, which are the worst, especially processed meats.
There's some patients that have already have a CBD and they don't want to take a medicine. And,
you know, at this point, it's like too late, you know, diets important, but you already have plaque
in your arteries, you're pretty far along in the process. And we need to do everything to
prevent further progression and even reverse. And we know from, you know, the IBIS studies that
high intensity statins and significant LDL lowering can cause atheroma volume regression.
So it's really a combination of pharmacotherapy and lifestyle changes. But for a very low risk
young adult, I push as hard as we can with healthier lifestyle changes.
You know, it's sort of funny, I've gone back and forth on this stuff so much,
Aaron, and I probably sound like a heretic at the moment, but I just sort of went through and
reviewed as many of the Cochrane collaboration meta-analyses as I could sort of stomach on all
of the different fatty acid impacts on cardiovascular disease. So if you look at the Cochrane
collaboration in 2019, that looks at the role of PUFA's and then the one in 2020 that looks at
the SFA substitution with PUFA and MUFA. And if I came away from this with anything, it's that I
don't know how much any of that stuff matters once you're in energy balance. In other words,
in the context of over-nutrition, I think it all is bad. In the context of adequate nutrition,
the ambiguity in these data were enormous. And, you know, I was left basically thinking,
look, on the basis of PREDIMED and the LION heart study, in addition to some epidemiology,
MUFA is probably the most important fatty acid, and therefore, let's just call it 50% of your fat
intake should probably be MUFA. And, you know, probably after that, looks like PUFA is a little
bit better than SFA, but I certainly couldn't find a shred of evidence to suggest that aggressive
restriction of SFA was in any way protective. Now, of course, the opposite, which was you do see
people that are consuming massive amounts of saturated fat and who have incredible hyperbeta
lipoproteinemia, you know, I think that's a clear problem. But, you know, when I think about all of
the lifestyle factors, I wonder if the one that gets the least attention that has the greatest
impact is stress. You know, because we don't have a pill for it. We can offset the harm of
nutrition so much easier with pharmacotherapy. And yet, a person walking around with simmering
hypercordicillemia and the effect that that's having on their endothelium and, you know, their
sympathetic nervous system, I feel like that's the one that I wish we had a better handle on as far
as how to help people. Because again, we don't have a pill right outside of blood pressure
management. We don't really have a pill for that. What are your thoughts on the role of
stress? It's such a dumb buzzword that I hate it, but I really think physiologically it's problematic.
Well, first of all, I didn't say about aggressively low saturated fat diet. The guidelines,
the HAACC guidelines really are talking more of a moderate fat intake diet. And really,
a Mediterranean style pattern, as you alluded to, is what I recommend to my patients. You know,
maybe I'm biased because I'm half Italian, I'm married to a Greek, but we do have both
observational data and clinical trial data. A Mediterranean style diet is pretty palatable,
and it's pretty easy to follow without getting too crazy. And it's, you know, generally low
unsaturated fats and generally higher in the unsaturated fats, lots of fruits and vegetables,
but it's also the Mediterranean lifestyle with increased physical activity, more social
connection and reduced stress. And I'll add in there the importance of physical activity,
although exercise maybe has less impact on lipids per se than diet, it has significant
impact on overall cardiovascular risk with both helping with weight maintenance, but also
increased levels of fitness is being more fit is one of the strongest favorable factors for lower
cardiovascular risk. So I definitely encourage regular physical activity as well. So I do think
mental health is very important that we also address. You can't talk about cardiovascular
health without talking about mental health. And I was a coauthor on the American Heart Association
statement that came out last year about the mind heart body connection. We really talk about
both positive psychological factors and negative psychological factors, both influence cardiovascular
health, both in indirect ways and direct ways. So what do I mean? So in indirect ways, so
individuals with more negative psychological factors like anxiety, stress, depression, anger,
you know, they might be more likely to have poor coping habits, such as they might be eating more
poorly and not getting physical activity and having more smoking or more alcohol intake,
you know, and less follow up with preventive interventions. So sort of the indirect mechanisms
where the positive psychological factors as individuals may be more likely if they have a
sense of purpose and more optimism to be, you know, eat healthy and exercise and take their
medications apart with preventive visits. But there also may be direct mechanisms as well,
that stress leads to activation of the sympathetic nervous system, increasing heart rate, increasing
blood pressure, increasing release of stress hormones like cortisol that can lead to more
insulin resistance, more fat deposition and the visceral cavities, and more low grade chronic
inflammation. And we know that inflammation can also be a trigger for plaque rupture. So I do
think it's important that we think about the whole person and, you know, we can make all these
recommendations about managing their lipids and things, but if we don't take into account some of
the challenges that they have in their personal lives and social determinants of health, you know,
we may not be able to effectively deliver preventive interventions. Completely agree with
everything you said. And sorry, didn't mean to apply that you were suggesting a low saturated
fat diet. I was sort of saying that more just as broadly you kind of hear these extreme views.
I guess what I'm getting at building on what you would say is when I think of the five pillars
through which we can impact a person's health, so nutrition, exercise, sleep, emotional and mental
health and pharmacotherapy, the lowest impact in my view on cardiovascular disease is through
nutrition. I think the other four trumpet all day, every day and twice on Sundays. I don't even think
it's close. And the reason I mention this and the reason I'm on my soapbox about this is I think
the general public seems to think that nutrition is the most important lever in controlling
cardiovascular disease risk. I see this a lot, right? I see the person who ostensibly is eating
quote unquote, a healthy diet. And yet they still have these biomarkers that are horrible and or
they even have evidence of clinical disease. They have a calcification on their calcium score. They
have soft plaque on their CTA. And they sort of say, but look, doctor, I eat this, I'm on this
diet or that diet and clearly I've got it under control. And I sort of want to say to them, no,
you don't even have it close to under control and your diet's not even remotely helpful at
controlling this. And if it is, it's rearranging the deck chairs on the Titanic at this point.
Those other four things are going to move the needle far more in different amounts,
in different people. There are some people for whom I think the stress thing doesn't play a role.
And there are other people for whom I think it plays an enormous role. And every time I'm in
Europe, I come to the same conclusion you do, which is especially in amazing places like Italy,
which is hands down my favorite place in Europe. They're way more active, they eat less,
and they just don't give a damn. Like there's just a sense of it's all okay. They're not so
wound up the way we are. And I think that counts for, I don't know. I think that's 90% of it right
there. Let's shift gears for a second. Let's talk about LP little a it's come up a number of times.
And obviously the listeners on this podcast know the ins and outs of LP little a, we've had a number
of guests talk about it, but we've never spoken about it through two lenses. One is specifically
through the lens of women versus men, anything we need to know. And also I want to now talk about
the role of LP little a you already alluded to it in pregnancy, you know, it is an acute phase
reactant in a way. So you wouldn't surprise me that LP little a goes up during pregnancy,
but I also want to talk about what happens after menopause, if anything.
Sure. I'll talk about that. And then I do want to talk more about menopause. Cause I think we
talked about menstrual cycles and pre menopause and PCOS and pregnancy. And then we didn't get to
really dive into menopause. So yes, I want to go back. That's where I want to go next. So yeah,
I want to go from this directly into menopause and then HRT as well, but I wanted to just close
the loop on LP little a so lipoprotein little a. So I know you've talked about this a lot, but just
in case there's any new listeners, I'll just briefly recap. It's an LDL like particle that's
comprised both of an Apo B, which is, you know, Marker, the bad moieties. So it shares protein
with other atherogenic lipoproteins. And then it also has an Apo lipoprotein A moiety. And that's
what distinguished lipoprotein A from LDL. And this Apo A is kind of unique cause it has these
10 subdomains of these Kringle four domains and the Kringle four two can expand two to 40 times.
And so that's leads to a lot of heterogeneity in the population. You know, 80% or more of
individuals actually carry two different isoforms of Apo A, you know, one inherited from each parent.
And so it's important to recognize this heterogeneity in the multiple isoforms. Cause this
accounts for some of the differences in cardiovascular risk that we see by race, ethnicity,
with higher lipoprotein A levels being seen in black and South Asian individuals compared to
white individuals. But in terms of women, there are sex differences. So lipoprotein A
generally is five to 10% higher in women than in men, but there's changes over the life course
where lipoprotein A is relatively constant in men, where in women it tends to increase after menopause.
So it does increase during pregnancy, normal pregnancy between 10 to 35 weeks with about a
doubling of the value during pregnancy. And we think since the levels fall back to their
pre-pregnancy baseline after delivery, that the short increase is probably not atherogenic,
but it does rise during pregnancy. So why don't we care about lipoprotein A? Well,
it's pro-atherogenic, pro-inflammatory, and pro-thrombotic, and it's associated with
cardiovascular risk. And as likely from Mendelian randomization studies, you know,
causally related to both ASCBD as well as calcific aortic stenosis. And even in individuals
who have LDLs less than 70, like in the Copenhagen general population study, lipoprotein A above 50
milligrams per deciliter is still associated with risk of cardiovascular events. So it's still
associated with risk even when the LDL is low. And you really need to, you know, measure it because,
you know, if you think your LDL is low, you may be missing some residual risk depending on,
you know, whether lipoprotein A is making up a significant component of that. And so Mendelian
randomization studies do suggest that it is causally associated with cardiovascular risk in women,
but the impact of therapies in lower lipoprotein A and what that translates into actually lowering
cardiovascular risk, you know, is a little bit uncertain. And right now we have apheresis for
an option for patients with very high lipoprotein A who have progressive cardiovascular disease.
And we mentioned the monoclonal antibodies of allocumab and alloracumab as well as encloserin
can lower lipoprotein A about 20 to 25%. And it seems that actually in those trials that
individuals who had the higher lipoprotein A levels actually
derive the greatest benefit from those therapies. So it is something that, you know, if somebody's
elevated lipoprotein A, I kind of think about moving quickly to PCSK9 if they have another
indication such as elevated LDL. And the reason, you know, why to measure it, we talked about it
being a risk enhancer, but also because of these exciting new therapies that are being studied
right now in trials, the pellicarcin, which is an antisense oligonucleotide targeting lipoprotein A
and opusarin, which is a small interfering RNA also targeting the synthesis of lipoprotein A.
And there's some other ones being studied as well, another small interfering RNA. So we'll have to
see, you know, there's a cardiovascular outcome trial I'm going right now for pellicarcin,
the horizon trial to determine how much does lowering lipoprotein A actually translate into
reduction in MACE. And that one trial is enrolling high risk secondary prevention population with
elevated lipoprotein A. Any concern that we're going to see a rebound increase in LDL with an
antisense oligonucleotide? So when you knock out LP little a, all of those additional LDLs that
would have been LP little a has just become LPL. So your APO concentration stays the same,
even though you've shifted the distribution from between LP little a and LDL.
I mean, I think this is why we need the trials. So with LDL, there's a pretty linear relationship
that we can anticipate with the degree of LDL lowering, you know, by one millimole per liter or
30 milligrams or deciliter with reduction in major adverse cardiovascular events being 20 to 30%.
And this is why therapies like bempedoic acid and clisarine got approved based on their LDL
lowering properties, even without outcome data, because we have a pretty good sense of what
lowering LDL is associated with reduced events. We really don't have that data for lipoprotein A
other than modeling data. Certainly it's associated with increased risk. But you know,
some modeling data says, you know, you might need to reduce lipoprotein A as much as 50 to 100
milligrams or deciliter to have a meaningful reduction in ASD in the short term. And other
therapies, for example, you know, niacin lowers lipoprotein A, but was not shown to have clinical
benefit in two outcome studies, albeit those studies didn't, you know, enroll based on lipoprotein A.
But you know, we're not using niacin. Same thing with hormone replacement therapy,
estrogen therapy or hormone replacement therapy does lower is associated with lower lipoprotein
A levels. But we're not recommending it for the sole purpose of lipoprotein A because particularly
in high risk individuals with ASCVD or who multiple risk factors or many years out from
the menopause transition, this therapy has been associated with increased cardiovascular risk.
So, you know, we really need the data. We know that these agents, pelocarcin and
alphacirin can reduce lipoprotein A by, you know, 80 to 90%, which is remarkable considering,
you know, statins, bempedoic acid, azetamide, you know, don't lower it at all. Statins may even
increase it. You know, PCSK9 is only lowered by 25%. So that's remarkable that we now have therapies
that work in terms of lowering lipoprotein A. But what does that mean in terms of vet reduction?
And I think we've been burned from other studies like the CTIP inhibitor and other studies that
biomarker data is sometimes not enough and that you actually have to show that it can meaningfully
actually reduce risk. And so maybe offsetting some of the LDL increase, maybe offset any reduction
in benefit. The other thing I think which warrants further study is in epidemiology studies of very
low lipoprotein A levels may be associated with increased risk of diabetes. So what does that mean
if you lower it to very low lipoprotein A level? I don't know. So we really need the trial data.
Super interesting. I feel like Tom Dayspring recently sent me an analysis of Odyssey,
which demonstrated that the greater the reduction in LP little A through the use of
praluent, the greater the reduction in mace. Am I remembering that correctly?
Yeah. So both in Fourier and Odyssey, individuals who experience the greatest reduction in lipoprotein
A had greater relative and absolute reduction in mace, major adverse cardiovascular events. So it
seems to be that lowering lipoprotein A may in part be an important mediator in the benefits that we
see with these agents. And it may just not be all due to their LDL lowering effects, but maybe also
due to lipoprotein A lowering effects. So that's very encouraging when we think about these new
agents. But you know, this is modeling post hoc analysis from these trials and the PCSK9 inhibitors
also lowered LDL. So when you now think about agents that really only target lipoprotein A,
is that going to be sufficient enough to have a meaningful, significant reduction in major
adverse cardiovascular events? I mean, I'm hopeful. I'm really hopeful because I think it's causal.
We know it's associated with risk. I'm really excited about the therapies in this area,
but I've got to show me the data. I've got to see the outcome data results.
Well, let's talk about menopause. You know, I'm amazed it's taken us this long into a podcast
to get to it because it's such an important issue. It plays such a huge role in women's health,
whether it be dementia, sarcopenia, osteopenia, you name it. But I don't think I've done a dedicated
podcast where we look at the effects of menopause on ASCVD. We've certainly danced around it today
and we've shown our hands a little bit here, which is this is an accelerator of risk. Can you
say a little bit more about why? Is there anything more to it than simply the loss of estradiol
leading to an increase in LDL? And if so, what's the actual mechanism by which that's happening?
You know, we started off the program talking about hormone levels. So estrogen levels start
dropping during perimenopause. And perimenopause can actually last several years before menopause.
Menopause is one of those things you don't really know it's happened until it's after it's happened
because it is officially sort of diagnosed when you haven't had a menstrual cycle for 12 months,
which usually happens around age 51. But earlier onset of menopause before the age of 45 or before
the age of 40 is associated with increased cardiovascular risk. You know, with the primary
estrogen of women of reproductive age, estradiol drops dramatically. And then there's the change
to estrone E1, which is the weakest type of estrogen formed in the adrenal glands and other adipose tissues.
By the way, Aaron, am I remembering my biochemistry correctly? Estrone exists in three variants or it
can be converted into four hydroxy, eight hydroxy and 16 hydroxy or two, four and eight, 16 hydroxy
estrone. Does that ring a bell at all? And the reason I only bring it up is I feel like one of
those was more thought to be involved in the creation of breast cancer. I'm not sure I can
speak on that. I'm mostly familiar with just the three major subtypes, the E2 estradiol, the E1 and
the E3 among estrone types. I apologize. I don't know that data except that it's no worries. Okay.
It's a very weak type of estrogen. And so essentially, you know, women after menopause
really have very low levels of estrogen. In fact, women have lower after menopause have lower levels
of estrogen than men do. Men have higher estrogen levels because of they have much higher testosterone
levels and they have increased peripheral conversion of testosterone estradiol. Actually,
men have higher estradiol levels than women after menopause. Do you know my other favorite stat?
That's a great one, by the way. The other favorite stat of mine is that even pre-menopause,
women have higher testosterone than estrogen if you actually convert the units to the same units.
I think some people think after menopause, the ovaries are just not active anymore. But that's
not true, actually. After menopause, the ovaries continue to just don't make a survival, but they
continue to produce androcynone and testosterone. So they keep making androgens really up to
significant amounts until age 80. And these androgens are what get converted in fat and muscle tissue
into estrone. So I mentioned this because a lot of my research has been about sex hormone levels
after menopause. And we've previously shown that postmenopausal women who have higher androgen
levels, who have higher testosterone to estrogen ratios, had a more male-like pattern. They had
greater risk of developing ASCVD and heart failure over the next 12 years. And this was even after
we adjusted for risk factors like blood pressure and lipids and diabetes. And we did a number of
studies as well in the MESA study, the multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis. But we also showed
that women with higher androgens had more coronary artery calcium progression. They had
worse endothelial reactivity. They had increase in concentric remodeling, all this adverse
cardiovascular phenotype. And also, as I mentioned, we started out talking about PCOS earlier,
but in PCOS, the riskier phenotype is the hyperandrogenism state and testosterone
and androstenone in higher LH levels in PCOS as a marker PCOS. So getting back to menopause,
a lot of things happen related to these hormonal changes. You have more visceral fat deposition in
the abdomen and more insulin resistance. And this leads to this dyslipidemia pattern of increased
triglycerides, increased LDL, and decreased HDL. There's more endothelial dysfunction,
increased blood pressure, increased sympathetic tone. So where a lot of cardiovascular risk in
women is more linear with aging, so for the most part, blood pressure and diabetes risk tends to
be more of an aging effect rather than an ovary effect. Lipids is one thing that really seems to
be an ovary effect that we do see relatively acute changes in the lipid panel following the final
menstrual period with this rise in total cholesterol and LDL. I think we alluded to earlier that it's
maybe one of the reasons that women tend to have risk a little bit later in life and after menopause
is because they tend to have this more dyslipidemia pattern a little bit later in life. Now this
pattern, this increased risk, you know, had led this whole body of work about, well, these changes
are harmful. Maybe giving menopause hormone therapy would be beneficial. And of course, you know,
we did this for years. My mother used to be in hormone therapy. This is all, you know, well before
the women's health initiative study, because we just felt that, you know, oh, well, you must give
these hormones back. There are favorable and unfavorable changes that we see with hormone
therapy, especially this combined therapy. So some of the favorable therapy changes, if you do give
women estrogen, you will lower their LDL and it can increase the HDL and estrogen can have.
And are you talking about oral estrogen or topical estrogen?
Systemic estrogen, which is oral and to some degree transdermal, vaginal estrogens don't have
much systemic absorption. So they're a really good option for women. You know, I'll talk about
which women to use hormone therapy in, but for women who just have the genital urinary symptoms,
even a women with cardiovascular disease or history of stroke, or you can use vaginal estrogens
safely. And sometimes I think there's this concern about using them in high risk women,
but you can use the vaginal estrogen. So I'm really talking about oral estrogens here.
They dilate the blood vessels through a nitric oxide effect, which, you know,
may be all cardio protective, but keep in mind, estrogens also have unfavorable properties. So
we know that estrogens can increase CRP. So women have higher CRP levels and estrogens are prothrombotic.
I mean, this is why there is some increased risk with oral contraceptives, particularly in women
who are older of reproductive age and combined with smoking and also during pregnancy,
that estrogens can increase prothrombin decrease anti-thrombin three. And we also talked about the
estrogen effects with triglycerides. Same thing with oral contraceptives, which have higher estrogen
levels, hormone therapy, all code increased triglycerides. So in higher risk women,
particularly those that are farther out from the menopause transition or those with established
cardiovascular disease, these adverse changes, you know, may outweigh any favorable benefits.
And that's why probably the women's health initiative who had the mean age of 63,
most of these women were quite far from the menopause transition. And the women's health
initiative also used an oral conjugated equine estrogen with progestin formulation that we saw,
you know, an increased risk, including a twofold increased risk of venous thromboembolism.
So this is why, you know, the guidelines all changed and we don't recommend hormone therapy
for the sole purpose of cardiovascular disease prevention, because we have many other things we
can use for prevention like statins. But you know, the pendulum doesn't have to swing so far away
that you look at sub-analyses of these trials of women that were closer to the menopause transition,
younger women, we didn't see this excess harm. And so while a lot of women are quite symptomatic at
menopause, you know, vasomotor symptoms can be very disabling for many women with the hot flashes
and the brain fog. In fact, vasomotor symptoms end up themselves when frequent or persistent
are associated with cardiovascular risk. And so for symptomatic women who are under the age of 60
or within 10 years of menopause who have symptomatic menopausal hot flashes or night sweats,
you know, consider hormone therapy. Women who go through menopause early, if they don't have other
contraindications, menopausal hormone therapy is recommended to at least the natural age of
menopause or age 51. But generally, we're not recommending it if a woman's more than 10 years
out from menopause or over age 65. This is where the increased risks are emerging in these trials.
And we want to avoid oral estrogens in women with a history of cardiovascular disease, blood clots,
hydroglycerides, gallbladder disease, or prior breast and inter-metrial cancer,
particularly the oral estrogens. There's probably a little bit less risk with
transdermal estrogens, which are still systemic, but they don't have the first pass effect.
But I, you know, very work really closely with our menopause clinic as part of doing
cardiovascular risk assessment prior to use of menopausal hormone therapy. So when risk is
uncertain, you know, I get a coronary calcium score to make sure that they don't have any
calcified plaque, their score is zero. I feel pretty comfortable with using hormone therapy in
them for treatment of their vasomotor symptoms. But if they have significant atherosclerotic
disease, you know, I tend to not recommend it. And again, if they're only having genital urinary
symptoms, topical estrogen is fine. You know, the risk, it really probably depends on a lot of
factors. It depends on when you start the hormone replacement, you know, your age and initiation,
how many years you've been since menopause, your menopause age, how long you take the therapy,
the duration, the type of therapy, the dose, and the route of administration.
And probably your incoming health. The other thing I'm hearing here,
Aaron, is this is another reason for young women, women who are in their 30s, for whom menopause
isn't even on the radar. This is another reason to be as healthy as possible and to do as much
preventative work as possible. Because if for no other reason, it gives you more optionality in
menopause. My calculus on this is looking at a few things. And, you know, obviously quality of
life is one bone health is another muscle mass, brain health is a huge one. So I'm kind of looking
at it as heart health is not even on the radar. Because to your point, we have so many better
tools to reduce the risk of ASCVD that we don't need to rely on estradiol as one of those tools.
It's basically a pea shooter in a bazooka fight when we have big, big guns to reduce the risk of
cardiovascular disease. So while we're really asking of HRT is to not hurt somebody, while we let it
do its bazooka like work, which is going to be on the brain, bone health, vasomotor symptoms,
eventually vaginal atrophy and things like that, for which we don't have alternatives. And so to
your point, the difference between a 50 year old woman who shows up with a beautiful CTA that's
crystal clear, where we're going to have no ambiguity about this line of treatment, versus
a woman who shows up with a worrisome CTA. And yeah, maybe even if we go to transdermal, there's
going to be more hesitation, there's going to be more concern. And maybe that slight increase in
risk if it exists, is something we now have to weigh in the balance. Again, it all comes back,
in my mind, listening to you to prevention is the key. It's just start early and be aggressive.
And all you do is give yourself more options later in life.
Yeah, absolutely. The risk is in women with established cardiovascular disease. So trying
to prevent that plaque in the first place, if there's no atherosclerosis, then the
vase of dilatory effects and the lowering of LDL may be helpful in preventing the
initiation of atherosclerosis. But a woman who already has disease and the slight increase in
inflammatory markers and a pro-pharmatic effect may tip them over to having a vascular event.
So all in favorable about improving cardiovascular health earlier in life. Really, how we live the
first half of our lives really influences our freedom for morbidity and mortality the second
half of our lives. Any relationship with progesterone and lipids once we get into that
menopausal state, obviously women who are on estrogen need to either take oral progesterone.
Usually these days it's done micronized or we're even seeing them use progesterone-coated IUDs if
they can't. But let's just talk about this systemic progesterone. Does that have any bearing
positive or negative? Yes. I mean, we have to use progesterone if they have an intact uterus. This
may influence some of the, again, we're not using these for cardiovascular benefit, but whether
it offsets the benefit that we see from the estrogen. You mentioned, again, something at
the outset of the podcast, which I think is an enormous problem in all of medicine, which is the
disproportionate shortcoming or shortfall rather of women in clinical trials, women as subjects.
You said something funny earlier that's only funny because it's not true, which is women are not
little men. Do you see that changing? I guess I'd just ask you to sort of think about it in your
field. I don't expect you to speak about it in terms of fields in oncology or things like that.
When you think about cardiovascular medicine, be it on the lipid side, the hypertensive side,
all fronts of cardiovascular medicine, are we seeing a more equal, i.e. 50-50 distribution
of patients into clinical trials today? Or are we still seeing it be more male focused and therefore
more underpowered to understand the effect of interventions on women? For background, women
are historically under enrolled in cardiovascular clinical trials, usually only 25 to 30 percent of
trials. I previously published analysis where we reviewed the literature of lipid-lowering trials
between 1990 and 2018. This was just through 2018, so it doesn't reflect the more recent trials.
We showed the overall representation of women was only 29 percent in those trials.
Now, for some things like acute coronary syndrome, the prevalence is less common in women than in men.
We benchmarked it to something called a participation to prevalence ratio, where a ratio of one would
be adequately representation to their prevalence of the disease in the population. We showed that
women were underrepresented with a prevalence to participation ratio, generally 0.5 or less,
meaning that even though if they had lower burden of disease, they were still under enrolled in
trials related to this. We showed also another analysis looking at cardiometabolic drugs through
2017 that had gotten FDA approval for new molecular entities, and again, showed women
only made up like 36 percent of those trials. In an editorial we wrote, we looked at all kinds of
different things, stroke, acute coronary syndrome, heart failure, hypertension, and women throughout
all these disease entities were under enrolled in trials. Some things are getting better. I mean,
there are, you know, I mentioned clear outcomes, which is nearly half the participants are women.
I think this is because it's enrolling a statin intolerant population. There was some of the
GLP-1 studies like REWIND, which studied de-laglotide. That was largely a primary
prevention trial that had like 46 percent women, so those were encouraging. So I think there's
some examples of some improvement, but women still, for the most part, you know, we still see trial
after trial being published presented at ESC or AHA ACC, and we're like, where are the women? Why
are women continually to be under enrolled? And one of the things I'm passionate about is I think
that there's unfortunately under involvement of clinical trial leadership. These steering
committees to these trials have a dearth of women cardiovascular investigators. There was a paper a
couple years ago that looked at major cardiovascular trials, you know, published in the leading
journals, New England Journal, JAMA, Lancet. You know, only 10 percent of trial leaderships,
committees, were women, and more than half, about 56 percent of these trial leadership
committees had no female representation on the trial. One of the trial steering committee were
women investigators, and less than 10 percent had a woman in the first or last author position,
which would indicate a senior leadership position. We know from other studies that
the likelihood that a study will report a sex and gender specific analysis actually has, you know,
increased when there's more women authors of the study and more first and last authors women. I
think women tend to publish more about science related to women. So I do think it matters. There
is some data from my work and some other work from other authors that have shown a modest correlation.
It's not perfect, but a correlation between the proportion of women authors, the trial steering
committees, and enrollment of women participants in trials. For example, we did this for AFib,
and we showed that for every one percent increase in women authors, there was a 19 percent higher
enrollment of women participants in the trials. I mean, there's a lot that we can do to tackle this.
One of them is having more representation in by diversifying study team and investigators.
I think also we need to include more patients in trial designs, include more women in trial designs,
patient centered designs. You know, we hear that women are approached, but often are declined
participating in trials. And I think women tend to be a little bit more risk adverse. And this is
where it's really important to provide education, dispel misconceptions, emphasize the benefits.
Even if we don't know if a drug is going to be beneficial or not, there's a lot of benefits with
being part of a trial because you have more access to gold standard care and more access to study
investigators. And it's really important to include women in the design and try to understand
some of these design issues, which may be not so obvious, you know, such as making sure there's
no hidden costs that often people are paid for the drug or device. But there can be things related
to transportation or time off work or providing, you know, for childcare or other responsibilities
by having more flexible follow up, more pragmatic trials or having a follow up being online or by
phone or by PCP that may get over some of the barriers to enrolling women in the trials, which
I think can be really helpful. And making sure that the study designs are not so restrictive in
terms of the inclusion exclusion criteria that we shouldn't just exclude women of childbearing age,
if they have a plan for preventing pregnancy, have an adequate contraception, you know, women should
be eligible for these trials. Not to mention, we actually need more trials in pregnant women too.
It's just so important to understand what works and what's safe. And so there's a lot of barriers
to overcome. And this barriers need to be both with trial teams and trial designs with the funding
agencies, institutions, and even the journals that publish these trials should be questioning
why there's not enough women in the trial. So we all need to do better. As a randomized clinical
trials is our largest evidence base. And we want to make sure that something is efficacious, but
safe in women and that women benefit to a similar degree as men do. Karen, you've run how many
marathons? Oh, slowly. I'm not very talented at it, but I've done like 38 marathons and I was trying
to do one in every state as a goal. I'm really slow at running. So my only goal for these is just
finishing as an accomplishment in and of itself. Are those 38 in 38 different states? I've done
about 36 states. And then there was a couple of states like Maryland, where I live that I've
repeated more than once. Is that still a goal? You still want those other 14 states? Yeah. So
unfortunately I had taken a little bit, you know, I set back during the COVID. I had four marathons
planned for 2020 and they all got canceled due to COVID. And without a marathon on the calendar,
I got a little bit out of the habit of running with these long distances because I didn't really
run by myself. I do it for the social support with my running groups. And so without people
or groups to run with. And then in 2021, you know, the marathon I registered for was canceled as well.
And so I've gotten sort of out of it for a while, but I... It's really good that we're canceling
outdoor exercise during COVID because I can't... Well, it's back now. So events are back. So I am
registered for a marathon in October next month. It'll be my first marathon again in three years.
So I'm hoping to get state 37. Which state? It's New Jersey and most of the East Coast,
but this one I haven't done yet. And I've been back doing other races. I just did a 12 miler
here in Baltimore on Saturday last weekend. So races are back and they're fun. And I just like
participating. You know, you don't have to be good at a hobby to enjoy it. So I'll never have any age
groups or probably never qualify for Boston, but you know, sometimes it's just the act of doing
something and setting goals for yourself. And I love it. It's just, it's fun. That's fantastic.
Well, I have such fond memories of Baltimore. My wife is from there, so there's an additional
fondness to it, but I guess more than anything, it's the time I spent there. It's great to catch
up with you and it brings back memories by proxy at a minimum. I want to thank you for your time,
Aaron. This was really insightful. I learned a lot. I think this is a podcast where obviously
women will have learned a lot, but hopefully men as well, because if you're a man listening to this,
you certainly know a woman and therefore you should be just as concerned with her risk of
cardiovascular disease as your own. Thank you very much for this input, making the time and
your continued work. Thank you for having me on your podcast. Thank you for listening to this
week's episode of The Drive. If you're interested in diving deeper into any topics we discuss,
we've created a membership program that allows us to bring you more in-depth, exclusive content
without relying on paid ads. It's our goal to ensure members get back much more than the price
of the subscription. Now to that end, membership benefits include a bunch of things. One, totally
kick-ass comprehensive podcast show notes that detail every topic, paper, person, thing we discuss
on each episode. The word on the street is nobody's show notes rival these. Monthly AMA episodes or
Ask Me Anything episodes, hearing these episodes completely. Access to our private podcast feed
that allows you to hear everything without having to listen to spiel's like this. The Qwally's,
which are a super short podcast that we release every Tuesday through Friday, highlighting the
best questions, topics, and tactics discussed on previous episodes of The Drive. This is a great
way to catch up on previous episodes without having to go back and necessarily listen to everyone.
Steep discounts on products that I believe in, but for which I'm not getting paid to endorse,
and a whole bunch of other benefits that we continue to trickle in as time goes on. If you
want to learn more and access these member-only benefits, you can head over to PeterAttiaMD.com
forward slash subscribe. You can find me on Twitter, Instagram, and Facebook, all with the ID
PeterAttiaMD. You can also leave us a review on Apple Podcasts or whatever podcast player you
listen on. This podcast is for general informational purposes only and does not constitute the practice
of medicine, nursing, or other professional healthcare services, including the giving of
medical advice. No doctor-patient relationship is formed. The use of this information and the
materials linked to this podcast is at the user's own risk. The content on this podcast is not
intended to be a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment.
Users should not disregard or delay in obtaining medical advice from any medical condition they
have, and they should seek the assistance of their healthcare professionals for any such conditions.
Finally, I take conflicts of interest very seriously for all of my disclosures and the
companies I invest in or advise, please visit PeterAttiaMD.com forward slash about
where I keep an up-to-date and active list of such companies.
Thank you.