Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Alton, so great to finally be sitting down with you. We talked about this even before you operated
on me, which is at the time of this recording, I think we're coming up on seven months. But this
is a topic that I just, I can't tell you how many times I get asked about this by my patients. And
I don't know, in some ways medicine is so siloed. You think, well, I did general surgery, surely I
know something about orthopedics, but the reality of it is outside of trauma, and even in the most
basic sense, I know very little about orthopedics. And I think that's probably true for a lot of
doctors, primary care and otherwise. And then how much more is that true for patients? So it's a
pretty broad and specialized field at the same time, huh?
Yeah, I think that's a great point. I mean, I always have told people who've asked about medical
school, well, don't you know all these things? And we only do a subset of rotations. So I know
nothing about urology, I know nothing about brain surgery, right? It just depends on the luck of the
draw and what you get exposed to. And so I wholeheartedly agree. And then we just narrow ourselves
down like a funnel in terms of knowledge, because there's been such a knowledge explosion for the
last, really the last two decades, in terms of research, in terms of new science, a lot of which
you've talked about and do talk about routinely and know a lot more about than me. But as it
applies to orthopedics, even there are subsets of orthopedics. And then there are subsets of
shoulder surgery that involves just research versus just clinical practice. And all of that
is just an explosion of information. And, you know, my well informed patients often ask me about
things. And I know hopefully a lot of it, but I don't know all of it. And they know that is
sometimes fine because they're very good now at looking at true scientific articles, and they
approach it and approach me with new articles. So I'm learning every week from my patients,
actually, about shoulder surgery. Now, when you went to med school, did you think you wanted to be
an orthopedic surgeon? I didn't know. I barely went to medical school. I only went, I just had
a very circuitous path, but I was an engineer at UT here in Austin. And I don't think I really,
I'm an engineer as well. I don't think I knew that. What kind of engineer were you? I did mechanical
and biomedical. Okay. Yeah. And so I didn't know anything about it. My dad was an engineer. And so
I just, it just went that way. And, but as, at the end, I was, I was a little edgy about going into
industry. And so, on a last whim, because I had two uncles that were dentists, I went to dental
school for a year. And I actually didn't like that at all. But I loved the science, what was going on
with the biomaterials. They dentistry has been at the forefront of biomaterials, right? And so I left
after a year, but I was exposed to the entire anatomical body because the anatomy instructor
for head and neck was actually an MD, PhD. And she said, when I confided in her that was leaving,
she said, you know, you ought to try medical school. And so then I went back, came back to Austin,
painted houses for a year and then, then applied to medical school and went and still didn't know.
And so you go there, you don't know what you're going to do, not even if you're going to do
surgery or medicine. Right. Right. And I liked it all. I loved invasive cardiology, right? So,
I mean, just, just all the aspects of the physiology and the electricity really going on in our bodies.
And, but then I was exposed to orthopedics, fortunately. And it was like,
I knew all this stuff. I didn't know it all, but it felt so natural putting things together,
piecing them back together, the jigsaw puzzles. And it's so, it just, it felt all
in perfect line with my engineering background. In the time when you went through orthopedics,
was it common for people to also do a fellowship after the five years of residency?
It was, I think at our time, we had a big, I went to Tulane and there at that time they had eight,
this was pre-Katrina, they had eight residents per year. So it was a big program. And at that time,
about four, we're going to general practice. So fellowships were not ubiquitous. Now they're
almost mandatory, really just, just because you need to have a, I wouldn't call it a gimmick,
but you need to have a special interest because the groups that you'd be applying to work for
or the hospitals kind of want you to have some subspecialty. Yeah. I mean, I think that's,
that's the case in medicine, right? It's really, even if you did something like general surgery
and didn't do a fellowship after like vascular plastics, cardiac, et cetera, you'd be hard pressed
to go even into the community and kind of do everything. You probably tend to focus on one
part of the body. Exactly. So what, where did you do your fellowship? Obviously upper extremity.
Yeah. So I did my shoulder fellowship at Columbia in New York. And then I did my hand fellowship
in New York at Roosevelt hospital. It's two separate fellowships. Yeah. And, and most people
didn't do that at the time, but I just really liked both very much. And so, and I, it just
evolved into that. I dabbled with spine during residency. And I think the reason I evolved into
wanting to do upper extremity is because there's nothing cookie cutter about it. And I don't,
I'm not by any means demeaning any part of orthopedics, but for me, there, there were no,
there were very few jigs, cutting jigs, very few, um, linear, um, things that you had to just,
there's so much variability in the upper limb, both anatomy and also the specific pathology
that you just have to be all over the place. And it was more creative for me, frankly.
What would have been some of the sort of big steps forward? Let's go back to,
so what year did you finish your training? In 90, 96. I started practice in 96. Okay.
So at that time, what was the state of the art in terms of what was being done? So when, for example,
there was a day when, if you look at the surgery I had, that would have been done with a big open
incision. Right. When did minimally invasive orthopedic surgery take over the joint space?
It's crazy. It's such a cool question. I'm glad you asked it. Really don't get to speak about
it very much, but there was knee arthroscopy was the first big arthroscopic realm to develop. And,
and a fellow that most of my younger residents don't even know now, Dick Kaspari was, was hugely
innovative in that space. And so it shoulder arthroscopy by the time I was in residency was
primitive. We had the basic equipment to get into the shoulder, but we couldn't do much. Right. So
by the time I graduated, all we were doing arthroscopically, by the time I even finished
my shoulder fellowship, we were doing open shoulder arthroplasty. And I was at one of the
meccas of shoulder surgery. So everything advanced was being done there at the level that it could
be done. But it was open shoulder arthroplasty, which is still open, but smaller incisions. It was
open instability repairs, open labor repairs, but we didn't even appreciate what, for instance,
the slap tear. We knew they existed, but we didn't know the impact. And what we started seeing there
was, and there were certainly no arthroscopic repairs of, of, of the labrum, except these
early, early devices where you'd kind of get in there, see it, and you just mallet in, drill a
little hole and mallet in this big broad tack that was just now so primitive and they would fall out.
They had a high failure rate and it was just, that was the state of the art at that time.
So, and was any of this being done in clinical trials or was it kind of like patients are saying,
look, we have the tried and true way that we do this. The downside is you're going to have a big
scar and we're going to have to tear a bunch of muscle and your recovery is going to be longer.
But once we get in there, we know what to do versus we've got this minimally invasive way
that has all of these advantages, but the drawback is high failure rate. Right. So that was exactly
discussions. And there were, there was not a lot of, there was a little bit of FDA going on,
approval at that time, but not a lot in terms of using these sort of hemeri humanitarian devices
and so forth where you could go ahead and try it and the patients had to sign a release
and it was all fine. They were trusted surgeons that were doing it. So the, I wouldn't say there
were clinical trials. There were a lot of retrospective analyses going on. Oh yeah,
we did this in 107 patients and 47% failed. Yeah. And so in my early years of that, we were
actually just still doing mostly open and then kind of waiting for the devices for the science
or for the, for the industry to catch up with some better devices. And some of my colleagues
and occasionally me, uh, were, were adding little bitty innovative aspects of these,
whether they're application devices or the style of implants. So we've gone from today,
we've gone from, we went from purely metal to now often purely, um, braided polyester
as an actual anchor device, which is super cool because there's no metal in your body.
And then we, but in the transition through that was plastic and that plastic could be
either hard plastic, which stays in your body, but it's still benign or, um, or a bioabsorbable tax,
which I have my own issues with, um, because it does create an inflammatory response in the body
and creates a little cavity in the bone and so forth. So, uh, those are, that's kind of the
spectrum. So now we are using tiny drills, tiny suture anchors, and you can put many in and that's
what's nice about if you have to do a revision of some failed repair, you've got plenty of real
estate to work with and it's nice, but one other aspect, which I think shows so much how we change
and, and I was right at that inflection point, not by choice, just by happenstance was the slap tears
were not appreciated as a clinically relevant entity, but a slap tear, which meaning, um,
so we'll have to tell people what the labrum is in a second, what a slap is, meaning it was
they just were viewed as just another type of labral tear. Yes, but one that was benign that
didn't matter. I see. And people were coming in, a lot of overhead athletes were coming in with
secondary problems as a result of that. And the secondary problems were being treated without
treating the underlying and they were having recurrent pain. So this is probably a good
pivot for us to back up and make sure people understand the anatomy. You know, sometimes when
I'm explaining to my patients, um, which exposes my own naivete, I sort of say, look, I don't know
a lot about orthopedics, but to understand and appreciate the complexity of the upper extremity,
you have to appreciate what we did during evolution, right? And when we stood up,
you know, that became an enormous force multiplier. You know, if you think about this through the
lens of like warfare, you know, people talk about, you know, having night vision is a force multiplier
in war. Well, for us to be able to stand and walk with amazing efficiency on two legs was a few,
a force multiplier. And then also to have these incredible upper extremities, but you got to pay
a price for it. So the price, the way I describe it and feel free to correct me or make this more
nuanced, the price was stability, right? We paid an enormous price in these joints. So they're not,
you know, not as strong, not as stable. Would you agree with that? Is that, is that a fair assessment?
A hundred percent, a hundred percent. And you're spot on on that. And frankly,
that shows you do know something about orthopedics. But the fact is that, yeah,
we went from the ball and socket joints or the very stable, simple hinge joints to these,
these cup and saucer type joints, right? Specifically the shoulder, which is intrinsically
very unstable. And just, and also our opposable thumb, our opposable thumb is the base of it,
the basal joint is terribly unstable. It's just a, it's, we call it a by concave saddle,
but it's barely that there's really no intrinsic bony stability. And similar to the shoulder,
I mean, we use an analogy that's slightly off, but a golf ball on a tee. It's the tee is a little
bigger, a little bigger, but that's what it is. It's very flat and shallow. And so we can talk
about the anatomy. So let's do that in whatever way you think makes the most sense. Let's assume
the audience doesn't know the names of any of the bones, let alone what they look like. Doesn't
know the vasculature, the musculature, the innervation. What would be a reasonable way? And
we, I know you and I spoke, we were going to do this with models. In the end, you thought you
could probably do an easier job sketching for folks. So maybe let's have you explain slash
sketch through any of these things. That'd be perfect. That'd be great. And we're prepared
for that. We have some diagrams in it. So I'm going to take it off the visual and draw some
quick pictures. And this is what I do, frankly, for all my patients that I don't like the models
because well, they're just, they're just models. So I'm not saying I'm a great artist, but if we
just look at just the Glenoid, that's the socket. That's the golf tee, if you will. And then you add
a humeral head to it. And that is the humeral head. This portion
to the right of the dotted line is, is what's covered by cartilage. So that's the nice, smooth
Teflon cartilage and this space. So just to orient folks, what you're looking at is head on to a person
if you're looking straight out, then this is the right head and that little space we're going to
talk about the Glenoid fossa is that flat end of part of the scapula, which is a real complex
looking triangular bone with a big ridge on it. And it, the collarbone attaches to it and all that
crazy stuff. But the, the, the, the, the high level point here is in the hip, you have the
acetabulum, which creates a true socket for a big ball. And here the, the heavy lifting really is
done by soft tissue, not bones. Right. You've got a joint that's completely contained like that in
the hip joint versus a shallow one that just can slip and slide all over the place. So you, you've
pointed out it's a great, it's the best way to describe the shoulder joint being a delicate
balance of, of mobility and stability. And it's very easy to get out of whack because it is
biomechanically so complicated. So I'm going to add a few more things here, but this space that
we see between here is not a space. It's the, it's the space radiographically when you're
looking, that's occupied by the cartilage. So you have a thick, nice layer of cartilage on both sides.
I've left a little gap just to be able to see it, but it's the articular cartilage effectively there.
So there's a layer of nice thick cartilage there that, and when we have arthritis, of course,
that gets worn down, shipped away, and begins to, to fissure and, and then actually develop full
thickness loss to the point where then at some point it's not really functioning very well,
and it's very painful. So if we have this basic bony cartilage structure here, it's just,
it would just fall off if, if we were just left there, let's say you had a, well, if you had no
ligaments, no, what we're going to call the labrum, which are some additional structure,
stabilizing structures, or if we had, if we have the muscle tendon units that supply,
that support it. So I'm going to draw in a few more of that, of those.
And while you're doing that, we'll just remind people that ligaments and tendons are not the same.
Tendons are the connective tissue that connects muscle to bone.
Ligaments are connective tissue that connect bone to bone. Is labrum connect considered a ligament,
or is it kind of considered its own entity? It's kind of its own entity. Yeah. It's a,
it's a, it's a, it has a transition zone between fibrous tissue to ossius bone tissue. So it's a
fibrous ossius structure. And I liken it to, to calamari. That's the best. And it's rubbery,
just like that. And it, and that's the best analogy that people seem to get. So I've drawn
on two of the four rotator cuff muscles here. This is the one up above and this is the one in front.
And this is the big muscle that allows us to reach behind our back and pull our hand away
from our back. And this is also the one that helps us along with the pectoralis in front to
pull things together, like doing flies and so forth. The supraspinatus is the primary muscle
that initiates elevation of the shoulder. So it's very, very important. It also, so what we see here
is this zone and from here and about through here is where the muscle transitions into tendon. Yeah.
And then it becomes pure tendon. And it just so happens that this tendon, the supraspinatus tendon,
which is so commonly torn is actually, um, there's some physiologic downsides to its location where
it can be rung out. It doesn't have a great blood supply. The key is it gets, let me put here
where those two arrows are is essentially where the tendon tears most of the time.
And those two, and that is the part that's attached to the bone. It gets blood supply from
that bone. It gets blood supply, it gets nutrients, it gets growth factors. So our goal, and this is
jumping ahead a little bit, our goal is to get that reattached to that bone so it can get
all of those growth factors and that new healing back. And it absolutely can heal back, but there
are certain limitations to that. So, so let's, there's two other muscles, right? So we've got
the supraspinatus and the subscapularis there. There's two other muscles that make up the rotator
cuff. And I think everyone's heard of the rotator cuff. Yes. And yet it's probably not obvious to
people that it's, it's really four muscles that are doing this. What are the other two? So the other
two are the infraspinatus and the teres minor. And if you, you can kind of superimpose them over the
subscapularis, but they're on the backside of the joint and they are very important. They are the
external rotators that they give us our backhand and tennis. They give us a lot of stability for
the shoulder itself. And especially whether you're playing golf or lifting weights, they're a dynamic
stabilizer. They're very important doing bench press, pushups, all sorts of activities like that.
Archery.
Archery. Yes. Very important. So, so when a person quote unquote tears their rotator cuff,
that can be a very heterogeneous diagnosis. I mean, technically that diagnosis would apply to
a tear in any of those four muscles, which could be in the muscle, could be at the junction between
the muscle and the tendon. And could it also be just a complete separation of the tendon from the
osteostructure of the bone? Yes. So, and that's, that's critical to identify what that is. And
you can somewhat predict it based on the age of the person and their physiology and the mechanism
of the trauma. So we have, and we do broadly cast classify these into degenerative tears
and traumatic tears. So younger people, it's rare to see a young person really under the age of 40
to tear the rotator cuff. It's pretty proportionally rare, but it happens and it happens
traumatically. One of the, I had a young fellow who worked as a merchant Marine years ago,
and he was doing something with the anchor and the massive chain and his glove got caught in that.
And it basically, it almost ripped his arm off, right? But he was, he was okay, except that he
had torn traumatically as a, as a young 20, I think he was 26 or so. It ripped off three of his
four muscles and it just, you know, they had to be repaired, but he was okay. But it's, it's that
rare, dramatic circumstance that leads to traumatic tears in young people. And someone that young,
where's the weak link? Does it tear at the muscle itself or does it tear more at the tendon? That's
a great question. That's a great question because the younger you are, the stronger that linkage of
the tendon to the bone. So you often pull off some bone. And so, um, in the case of, you know,
a skier's thumb, just a common injury in the hand from skiers, the younger you are, the more likely
it is to pull off with a piece of bone. And, and that's actually great because bone heals to bone
itself much better than tendon to bone. I see. If you can get away with that, there are fractures
that occur that involve this area. There's, and I'll draw a picture here, draw a squiggly line
to represent a fracture and then I'll show it coming off. Uh, and that's a, that's a common
fracture. So right here, what I've drawn is this chunk of bone coming off right here.
That's the greater tuberosity. It's a prominence of the bone that the two, the biggest portion of
the rotator cuff attaches the super spinetis and the infraspinatus that you referenced that pulls
off. And so I would rather have that than a big, I would rather pull that off and have a good
quality repair of that than have my two tendons. And tell me the type of athlete or person that
presents with the, the fracture that you've depicted. So these are generally that isolated
greater tuberosity is generally a fractured dislocation. So you have a pretty violent injury,
you're rock climbing, you fall off, you, maybe you hit it directly, your arm is wrenched back,
or you have, let's say a football player who, who has a traumatic dislocation. They're hidden just
the right way mechanically. And it shears that off. And then, um, so it's, it's often most often
associated with the dislocation as well. The dislocation goes back, but the, but the two
drops dislocation, meaning a subluxation of the shoulder. Yeah. And let's explain to folks what
that is, how that happens. I didn't realize that we could use the word dislocation and subluxation
interchangeably. Well, technically we don't. Oh, technically a subluxation is an incomplete
dislocation. It's the shoulder coming out, but it pops back in easily. Got it. So dislocation is
usually, it comes out and it needs to be put back in most often, unless it's recurrent, the more
dislocations one has, uh, or subluxations, the more stretchy and compliant the tissues become sort of
like mine. Yes. And so then it can kind of slip and slide back in and out, uh, with, with regularity.
Let me draw a different picture. Yeah. What I've done here is taken the, the humeral head away. So
we're just looking at the socket and we're looking at it on FOS. Okay. So if you're looking at me,
you took my humorous away and now you are looking directly at the socket of this glenohumeral. Yes.
Uh, yes. Perfect. So yes. And so this, the central circle front of the person is to the front. That's
interior. We speak about that in posteriors to the back. Yeah. Superior is up above. Inferior is
down below. So the classic, um, oh, and so importantly around the outside, that second circle
is the, the outline of the labrum. So from here to here is the labrum. And that's a rubbery
calamari like structure. I love that. I love that. And it, I mean, it, it's sort of, you get some bad
calamari that's really chewy. That's kind of what I haven't chewed on labor myself, but it's what it,
I imagine it would be behaved by. And it's very strong. It's very strong. And what it does,
it has an amazing, you were talking about the evolution when it became bipeds. It's super
cool because it effectively developed as a way to decrease the depth of the socket, not by very
much, but it truly works like a suction cup. If you take a non arthritic cadaver specimen and dissect
away all of the muscle, all the ligaments, and you stick it on the humeral head on the labrum, it'll
sit there. It's crazy. It's fascinating. But just like a thermometer on a window, if you lift,
get your finger, break that seal up, break it, seal it, it falls away. But that's what happens here.
So we get a lot of static stability in our shoulder from this, the superior inferior anterior and
posterior labrum. And just to be clear, in a non-pathologic state, when you have that, you know,
that young person who has yet to be, you know, experiencing any trauma of the shoulder,
is that a contained space of fluid that is between those two cartilaginous surfaces of the
glenoid fossa, the humeral head, fully contained? Because usually to have a suction you want,
there has to be a fluid that sort of contains it or air that's incompressible, which is technically
fluid. But I assume there is an aqueous fluid that's normally in there? Absolutely. Yeah. You
have a nice viscous joint fluid in all of our joints like that. That's a great question. And
yes, you couldn't have that suction. As soon as you poke a hole in that, you lose that.
So when a person has a subluxation, it doesn't necessarily tear the labrum, does it?
Correct. And that's another huge point that will, it factors into our treatment recommendations and
mechanisms of injury. If you are a young woman playing soccer, generally young women have
looser joints. Women in general have looser joints, which is part of our difference in
physiology. But, and actually because of the weird nature of the shoulders, there are men as well who
have super loose shoulders at baseline born that way. But in general, if you think of someone,
whether male or female, who has super loose joints, then they can sublux out in and out without
tearing anything. They just ride up over that because it's just loosey goosey. So the tighter
the shoulder is, the more you have to lose. What happens to the fluid when they sublux? Nothing,
because they have just a more- Okay. It stays- They have a more- It's just expansive. It's the ligaments.
The ligaments are stretchy and they're bigger. It's more like a balloon that you've
keep blowing up repeatedly. So, but if you have someone who has a basically a pretty stable joint,
not loosey goosey, and then they sublux, the only way you can do that is either tearing the ligaments,
but usually you're also tear the labrum. And what I mean by tearing the labrum is you separate the
labrum, the inner arc, from its hard bony cartilaginous, perfectly fused attachment. Very strong.
It takes a massive force to, to dislocate the shoulder. It actually does, or perfect mechanics.
And so if you, if you have the classic, you're reaching up to get a rebound and someone grabs
your arm and jerks it backwards, that's a leverage, an unnatural leverage that makes the head tend to
go out this direction anteriorly, inferiorly like this. So the head is going to go down this way.
Yeah. It just, it just leverages it out.
And that's also a vulnerability based on where the muscles attach, right?
Yes. Yes. Very much so. And we'll get to that as the dynamic stabilizers, but man, this,
this labrum is tough, but it tears off. This is the classic location where you tear the labrum
there. Okay. And it takes either a small tear that then is repetitively increased in size just from
aggressive, but repetitive use, or it takes a one time significant dislocation.
The attachments of the four rotator cuffs are basically behind, above, like it's, it's basically
like you've got a big one there kind of at nine o'clock. Right. That's a great question. You ask
perfect questions that I forget to cover.
So these are kind of the cross sections of the muscles that are just outside. So these
encompass and in, and in shroud, the joint, and this is the cross sectional muscle bellies. And
this is where they, and then as they, as you come further out toward the head, which is out here,
they taper down and form the tendons. Yeah. Yeah. And that's so important because no shoulder can be
stable alone just by these static stabilizers, the labrum and the ligaments. And the ligaments
kind of lie in between the labrum and the rotator cuff in here. So the, when you're referring to a
slap tear, you know, obviously slap stands for superior, labral, anterior, posterior. Yes, exactly.
And that is up here. That is the super, and that's a odd injury that we,
um, um, the first person that really taught this well to us was a fellow named Steve Snyder in,
in Northern California. And he really kind of categorized these and started identifying these
as really actually clinically relevant entities, not for everybody, but certainly for younger,
very athletic people, uh, overhead athletes, weight lifters, people doing CrossFit, people doing,
um, all manner of, um, a more aggressive, uh, sports. And so unlike, and if you have a tear here
and you're active, you're going to keep re-dislocating at least subluxating. That was me.
Correct. I was kind of all the way around, but big, big, anterior, uh, inferior. Right. So I don't
know what your first injury was. I mean, maybe, so we've, you've talked about this. I believe
it was a subluxation in boxing when I was probably 17. Um, it's, so there's two injuries I remember
having in high school. I can't remember which one was first. You might have a sense. One was doing
absurdly heavy military press. I think that was the second one. Truthfully. I think the first
subluxation was boxing and just bad timing. Pun, hard punch thrown, guy gets out of the way,
probably smacked my arm on the way and out it came. And I believe that would have been followed
up six months later. I'm doing very heavy weight for me overhead. And I just remember, boom,
it just popped out and down. Yeah. And then from that point on, it was a vicious cycle of
never ending subluxations with each couple of years having a really bad one. Another
really bad one I had was in an open water swim race. I was, you know, we're swimming freestyle,
right? So I'm in the reach phase with right arm in front and the swimmer in front of me
kick down on that arm, which is not, I mean, that's a bit of force, but not absurd, but just
the down kick of that arm took me out. Yeah. Um, so it's so funny. I mean, you were describing
so many great, I'm sorry, you had suffered from them all, but, but so many great and differing
types of mechanisms that happen. I agree with you that it probably was the boxing. I've seen a lot
of those, the recoil, and especially if you don't hit something, your, your body is anticipating
and it's tightened up and it is ready for contact and it doesn't have the contact. It's no different
than, you know, you, there's an extra step in front of you that you don't know about and you step
and you go, whoa. And then you feel like it shutters your whole body. It's the same concept.
Your body unconsciously knows what it needs to do. And so you probably did have a posture
subluxation. I mean, I will say, and you know this, and this was why it was so important for you is
you had a tear going all the way from posture all the way around to there. So you had about a
240 degree tear and that's, you don't get that from one injury. It's almost impossible.
So it basically became looser and looser over time. And then it just now had too much laxity.
It could basically move in any direction. Exactly. And you were, you were compensating
well for most of the time because you're, you're very fit. You're doing all the right
upper body, specifically shoulder strengthening exercises. So you are using your dynamic
stabilizers to compensate for the loss of the static stability. And that's a critical,
critical problem. And it fits too with your weightlifting. So yeah, you had, you had a tear,
you weightlifting, you were fine. But what happens is if you're going kind of maxing out
and you're doing it repetitively, the dynamic stabilizers fatigue. And I see this,
one of the most common scenarios is the young, more often female than male, but both swimmers.
Right. So they're competing and they have a little bit of, they need the stability,
especially if they're doing fly and backstroke. They really need that. And they acquire all this
laxity in their shoulder and they're so strong dynamically that they're, they're fine. And it
gives them that extra pull, that extra inch or two. But when they fatigue, but they start out
fine on a Friday, if they have a, you know, a weekend long match and they have eight events
in three days, um, the first two days they're fine. Maybe they have a little pain at the end
of the second day, by the third day they're fatigued. And so then they start subluxing and
then they get all this secondary inflammation and pain. And that's when the damage occurs
and they have to sit out. And then we have to restrengthen rehab, sometimes even tighten up
the capsule when they get so loose. Now, one of the things I, uh, we're going to, you know,
talk about here is of course the physical exam on this, because the other thing we haven't talked
about on this diagram is that little pesky biceps head. Yes. And that tendon, um, boy,
if anybody who's experienced tendinosis there, uh, I mean, that's, that can be incredibly painful.
And I think to an average person, it's not entirely clear where that pain is coming from.
If they feel pain here, right? Right. That's a great point. And so yes, the biceps, which is a
weird structure and it's absolute part of that weird evolution that we have, the biceps is
one muscle in our arm, but, but it's two tendons at the, at the origin, which in the shoulder,
one of the tendons. So starts down here, single, single point of attachment in the, in the, in the
forearm, actually crosses the joint as one muscle and then kind of splits into two bellies with.
Exactly. And it has the long head, which is the one that so often gets inflamed and you're
absolutely right. It can be quite painful. I mean, and it can just affect every day life with that.
And the second tendon peels off over here and it goes outside the joint and attaches to a bony
prominence in that weird scapula that you talked about, which is such a weird looking bone. Um,
and it attaches there. That never tears. It literally never tears. Uh, so, but people often
do tear the other, this biceps and it can be from wear and tear. It can be acute dramatically,
but it leads to a classic Popeye muscle kind of half their muscle is, is balled up and that looks
weird. It's not really that much of a functional consequence. Usually it stops hurting when it
ruptures. And if I'm not mistaken, I mean, this has been, um, uh, in the orthopedic sort of, uh,
anecdotes for a long time was, um, great quarterback, um, from Denver, um, John Elway. John Elway.
He was having shoulder pain and was even thinking about retiring as far as I know his ruptured pain
went away and then he won another Super Bowl. So yeah, so it's not, it's a, it's a structure that's
not necessary, but it's, but, and there's a lot of argument in orthopedics and I don't need to go
into it about how important it really is. But the fact is it is anchored right up here at the superior
labrum. So when you tear that super labrum, that biceps does funky things. It becomes unstable and
it, and it gets more inflamed often. And then that you get all that secondary pain. So some people,
I'm not one of them, some people who fix a lot of these will automatically just snip that biceps and,
and reattach it in the front. So it's not no longer a pain generator. So that's the tendinesis. Yes,
that's the tendinesis, but I don't do that. I do that only when I see tearing, splitting,
something structurally wrong with the biceps. I know that I can get a good repair as any,
any good surgeon can a good repair of the superior labrum. Once that's stable, the biceps is fine
again. It's not, it's no longer symptomatic and I'm not going to worry about it. I haven't had to
go back and tend to tease anyone who I had just repaired and left it intact. As long as I got a
good superior labral repair. So because we've got the beautiful anatomy here, let's go a little
deeper into this because I feel like the torn labrum is to the MRI with the disc herniation.
There is to the shoulder with the disc herniation is to the back, right? You know, we tell our
patients, I almost wish when I give you an MRI for another reason, I could ask the radiologist
not to show me your spine. In other words, you take somebody who's not having no spine issues
and you stick them in the spanner. There's nothing that bugs me more than having to sit there and
go through all of these asymptomatic herniations, which mean nothing. And I suspect the shoulder
with its labral tear has to be the same. Yes. You're absolutely spot on. And it is such a point
of frustration. The radiologists are doing their job. Of course. They're just reading everything.
The problem is that most of us walking around have, especially for my age, have plenty of
positive findings, but they're asymptomatic. I mean, I've never had a spine or originated symptom.
And so that's your, it's a very double edged sword to get those MRIs. Same thing in the labrum.
The labrum will naturally degenerate just by using it. So will the cartilage. And look,
every, we know there's a genetic predisposition to arthritis and by arthritis, I mean,
not just inflammation of the joint, but a true loss of the cartilage integrity. And that's kind
of those two terms are used interchangeably by different people in different subspecialties. But
for our purposes as an orthopedic surgeon, it's when the joint is degenerating and the cartilage
surfaces are no longer pristine, just like you're chipping the paint on your car.
And does that occur preferentially on the humeral head or in the glenoid fossa, or is it basically
one of those things where the second you get one chip, it's going to start happening on both sides?
Yeah, that's a great question too. You know, it's, we don't have a good natural history of that. We
know that, I mean, I've operated on, done total shoulders on people who had no cartilage left on
their humeral head. It was perfectly round and smooth. There was no cartilage left.
It was just a bony, just pure soft, I mean, pure hard ivory type bone with no cartilage on it.
Whereas the glenoid still had cartilage on it. Now that's a case where to your point, the loss
on the humerus was smooth enough and gradual enough to where it didn't dig in and, and sort of
eat away at the glen, the socket. It doesn't matter. You still have to replace the socket,
but we do for our younger athletic people who have a humeral head that's been damaged
and they have a big chunk, maybe a quarter size, maybe a 50 cent piece size of cartilage,
full cartilage loss. That's not great because that man, that just keeps sloughing off cartilage.
They keep getting inflamed. They're on the young side. You don't want to do a shoulder
replacement on them. So we will do just a humeral head resurfacing. They have a, get a nice new,
smooth metal head, but we leave the car, the, the glenoid intact and, and they have good cartilage
there. So it's, it's metal on natural cartilage. Yeah. What kind of metal is that by the way?
It's cobalt chromium alloys. So it's just like the hips. Yeah. And, and the nice thing about those
is if you can get five years, I have some people that have been, had those in 10 years and they're
fine and they're, they're keep their act, they can be much more aggressive with their activities.
And if it ever, if it ever does wear down the, the glenoid side, then you just go back in and
revise it and put a plastic cup for the glenoid. Yeah. So let's now talk about when you look at the
MRI finding and what you're looking for in the MRI and then how you're looking to contrast that
with what you see on the physical exam. And in a moment I'll have you examine me so you can,
and we'll do this for all of the pathology we talk about so that we can get a sense of this.
Cause I remember the very first time I saw you after having sent many patients to you,
it was probably a year before I had my surgery. I said, look, you know, Alton, I know I've got this
labrum. It's been torn to shreds for years. I really don't want to have surgery unless I need
to. You examine me and said, yeah, you're not ready yet. So yeah, walk through how you start to test
the surrounding structures to elicit sort of feedback on the labrum. Right. So I will preface
that by saying, I'm so glad you brought that up because we, one should never make their clinical,
especially surgical decision-making on just an MRI. And I've written a couple of book chapters on
that included a very complete examination of the shoulder, the basic exam, the provocative maneuvers
and so forth. And one of the things I've always stayed, I've never done this study. I've always
wanted to, but I believe that a good history and that involves the mechanics of injury
and the mechanics of use, whether you're, you're shooting a bow and arrow, whether you're driving
a race car, whether you're playing basketball, whether you're just lifting weights, a combination
of the mechanism, but also their symptoms when they have them and then their examination. And I
think if you do those compulsively and well, you will be 95% accurate on your, without any MRI.
I remember one of the things that had changed, because for me, remember, archery, the day before
I'm having surgery, I'm out there taking a hundred shots. That was never the issue. But in the months
leading up to surgery, I couldn't serve a volleyball with my daughter. I couldn't shoot one basket.
Like we, you know, I could not do that. And then I could pull a 75 pound bow back. Yeah.
Doesn't make sense. It doesn't. And it's just the mechanics of each individual. And that's where the
MRI does come in. I use MRIs more to corroborate. I would say, and I don't think I'm, maybe I'm
a little more into sort of the concept of making an accurate diagnosis before the MRI.
Kind of the old school. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. To kind of prove a point. But, but I, I always use it to
corroborate because there are things that can be there and especially even just the difference
between a partial thickness rotator cuff tear and a full thickness or a full thickness small
and a full thickness large. And, and those are variable based again on the patient's activities.
Some, we know from good studies done with ultrasound and MRI that walking down the street,
the half the people age 60 have rotator cuff tears. Half the people over 60 have an asymptomatic torn
rotator cuff. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I'll be big, but it can be. I've seen people. I mean, I don't doubt
it just based on what we see of herniations in the C spine and the L spine. And that's where,
to your point, it comes in. It's so important that yes, we don't want something. We don't want
to ignore something that can get much worse and make their treatment or recovery much more
difficult. But at the same time, we need to be more circumspect about who we're operating and who
we're not operating on. Are there ever situations where, I'll give you an example, right? So I mean,
I'm asking, I'm going to ask this question obviously on the shoulder, but if a patient
came in and had a totally asymptomatic aortic aneurysm of six centimeters, everybody agrees
you would operate because the mortality of a rupture is enormous. And frankly, you don't want
to wait until somebody's symptomatic that can be lethal. So there are certainly indications where
we operate on asymptomatic things. Are there any such indications in the shoulder? Oh, that's a,
that's a great, great question. I would say in general, no, unless you have obviously a tumor.
Not including oncology. Just the standard garden variety,
structural injuries that can occur. There are very few except if you've had someone who had,
well, I'll give you a good example. That's very personal to me. My dad, who he passed away at
95, we were swimming in Lake Travis when he was 94 and a half. He's really vigorous, mentally fit,
physically fit. And, but he did end up having pancreatic cancer and that's what killed him at
95. Great life. No, no complaints with anybody. But at 86, being a guy who could still do pull-ups,
who was still swimming in the lake, who does guys, my hero, all his own yard work, everything. And he
was running to get out of the way of the sprinkler, did a banana peel that had a dislocation of his
shoulder, ripped off two and a half of his four tendons. And remember one of them never tears. So
almost his complete functional rotator cuff. He was planning to come up to New York to visit.
And we did a little FaceTime and he couldn't lift his arm. It was like this. And I, and he's 86,
but healthy, never took a medication, so forth. So I said, dad, you need to come up early. We're
going to need to fix this. So we'll get an MRI, come up here. And so my partner and I fixed him.
And regional anesthesia, they didn't even give him much sedation. He was like talking to us during
the surgery. Got a good six anchor repair. He had great tissue to the point that you've,
you've just helped so many of us understand, but got a good solid repair at 95 and 94. You couldn't
tell he ever had a tear. He healed it back. He was, he went back to doing everything.
And what would have been the natural history, because I think a lot of doctors might have
left him alone. What would, how would he have evolved? Thank you. That's, that was the point.
If I, he would have been miserable for the next nine years of his life because he couldn't lift
his arm. It might not even have been that painful, but he wouldn't have been able to do everything
he wanted to do that kept him so far. So in other words, pain is not a pain, shouldn't be the only
symptom we look for. We have to look for function. No. And so what I would tell someone who came in,
let's say someone had a bad traumatic, a motor vehicle accident, and they tore their rotator cuff
at a badly and there were 60, 65. Would I tell them you absolutely have to have repaired? No,
but I would also tell them, look, if you don't repair this, those muscles have lost their
muscle tendon connection. So they're going to atrophy. And later, if you, I know you're not
painful now, but if you want to still do the things you're doing and the way you do them
before this accident, they need to have a repair. So this is effectively the discussion you had with
one of the patients I sent you six months ago who tore a rotator cuff playing tennis many years ago.
And basically once this patient stopped playing tennis, they had no more pain. So today they do
yoga and Pilates with no pain, but they can never pick up a racket again. I sent the person to you
and that's basically what you said was you don't have to have this fixed, but you will see a
continued diminution of your function as you age. Right. Exactly. And the second caveat,
which I'll tell them is, you may start having symptoms in six months, even doing those other
things. And if you do come back, don't ignore them. If you start having symptoms when you've
been asymptomatic, something has changed anatomically, physiologically, or something,
let's reassess. It's not a dynamic state over a long period of time. And so
you need to be flexible in that and as a clinician. So when a patient typically comes in,
basically they're just saying, Doc, my shoulder hurts. So again, on the exam, absent even an MRI,
we're going to show people how you can just based on where I'm weak or strong and what hurts.
You probably have a pretty good sense of this person has an intact cuff versus they don't.
This person has a labral instability versus they don't. This may actually just be bicep
tendon injury versus not. What else is on your differential diagnosis in the exam? You don't
have the MRI yet. The guy just says he's got shoulder pain. That's great. I'm going to draw
another picture. Okay. So I've drawn the shoulder again. I've added on a couple of things. I've
added on the clavicle, the collarbone, and I've added on this other structure up here, which is
the bony structure. If you tap on the top of your shoulder, that's the bony roof of the shoulder.
That's the acromion and yet another part of that super weird scapula. Okay. So the, the joint that
when you hear about someone separating their shoulder, it's this joint right here, which is
the acromioclavicular joint. And that is just a, it, it only rotates about 20 degrees. It's just a,
the way I liken this, especially being in Texas, you can talk about it because there's a lot of
car lovers and you know about it as a major car lover driver is it effectively is a McPherson
strut on, on a car. So it's a stabilizer bar. If you don't have those and there are people that
are born without, um, collarbones, they can bring their shoulders completely together right here in
the center, just like this. It's kind of super cool. Um, but it, it holds those out. So that's why,
you know, it's the one most commonly injured in cyclists who, who, who wipe out because they
fracture here because they land on the outside of their shoulder. But the AC joint, the acromioclavicular
joint is what happens when people separate their shoulders, which is also different from a
dislocation, different from dislocation. That's usually from a force coming down from the top.
So we're pitched forward. We land on the point of our shoulder and it jams it down. And we can talk
about that later. It's super interesting, but this acromion again is the bony roof and under that
roof is where the rotator cuff glides. And let me draw this. So I'm just drawing the arrows back
and forth arrows here. So as the head rotates back and forth around, the rotator cuff is attached
here and it goes back and forth here. So it's rubbing or moving underneath this. Any place in
our body that there's two structures and uh, anatomically in the limbs that move differentially
with one another, there's usually a bursa that forms in between. And so that bursa is here,
I'll draw it in green. That bursa lives right in there. And so it's just the thin filmy structure
that can thicken up and become very inflamed and become bursitis. And that's very painful.
So that's a common common diagnosis. Because otherwise the purpose of that is to allow these
things to glide past each other frictionless. Yes. Perfect. Yes, exactly. And then some of us
are born with an extra kind of down sloping of that acromion or a bone spur, or we acquire it
from repetitive athletic use. There are multiple reasons. If you have a big though bird beak coming
down and pointing into that, you can imagine if this is running back and forth there, it's
irritating the bursa creating bursitis. And it's also frictionally rubbing against the rotator cuff
tendon and you can get bursal sided upper part rotator cuff tears from that alone. I know because
I had, wow, I had a big spur like that in my shoulder. So to be clear, the spur occurred
because you were genetically predisposed to it based on the shape of the bursa. Yes. That's
really great that you said that you know, you should have been an orthopedic surgeon.
You can have a type one, a type two or a type three acromion. Type one is totally flat. That's
the majority of people. Type two, the second most common in type three is about, I don't remember
the exact numbers, but certainly it's not rare. I, 30% of people. And that's the one that really
predisposed you if, but only if you're an overhead athlete or lifting weights overhead or doing all
sorts of, you know, aggressive things. If you're sedentary, actuary who doesn't exercise, then
you'll never have a problem because you're just not repetitively loading it enough to wear down
or cause a tear. This is so, so interesting because you know, you'll often hear people talk about,
um, you know, well I can do so and so, and I've never had an issue, therefore it's okay. Right.
So if you're, if you have the top acromion there, you can probably get away with a lot more overhead
activity. And you might look at somebody who's in category three, every time they do excessive
overhead activity gets injured and you might be saying, well, like there's something wrong with
you. The round of it is it would be interesting if we sort of knew these things in advance and we
could maybe modify and temper our activity around our genetics effectively. Absolutely.
It's a super cool concept. I've always thought about that, that, that stuff, the predisposition,
and I'm not talking about a genetic predisposition to arthritis. I'm, you're talking about this is
anatomics, the mechanics and anatomy. And you're absolutely right. It's so important.
I'll give you another example of it. I know just from having MRIs for other reasons, I have a very
congenitally narrow C-spine. So I just don't have any wiggle room. And as a result of that,
I take my sort of tech neck protocol very seriously. Yes. You know, I also know that
I already have two small herniations. Now luckily they aren't doing anything to me, but
I know that nobody's going to go in and remove one without doing the other, which means they'd fuse
me out of the gate. Right. So, you know, I think knowing that is very helpful because what it tells
me to do is you're going to do a lot of sort of rehabilitative exercises even before having the
injury. Yes. And you know, I actually think it's very fortunate that I'm no longer a surgeon. Yeah.
Because I think a lot of my colleagues from surgery have ended up having neck surgery.
Oh yes. Because you're in this position all the time. Yes.
So yeah, I do. I think this is a very interesting idea. I'd never thought about it
in the orthopedic context, in the joint context that is. Yeah. And, you know, the other thing I
thought of when you said that is that when you have a, but this has been studied in the spine a
little bit, right? So if you have a congenitally narrow asthenotic spine and you're playing
football, you're way more at risk for catastrophic spinal cord injury. Yeah. Blunt, blunt, blunt cord injury.
So if you've had, that's why when we were, I was team doctor for almost 15 years at a college up in
New York and you know, you, everybody doesn't screen these guys, but if you have your first
stinger, then you need to be, need to be screened and see if you are. And if you are, then you have
a very serious discussion about what you're subjecting your neck to. There are a lot of,
a lot of sports to play and you don't necessarily have to be, you know, butting heads at high
velocity, you know? So, so that's exactly true there, but you're right. It hasn't been done in
the shoulder and yeah, it'd be a simple, easy screen and say, Oh, you know, I mean, I don't.
Well, especially I think when you take about, when you talk about kids who have lots of
athletic potential and they're 11 years old and you know, maybe there is a decision to be made.
Are you going to be a pitcher? Are you going to be a tennis player? Are you going to be a basketball
player? Are you going to play lacrosse? You're going to swim. If you knew you'd have a longer
shelf life in one over the other, would that at least weigh into the decision-making process?
That's fascinating. I love the way your mind works because yes, there are plenty of multi-sport
athletes who have ability and, and, and you could do an assessment. For instance, if you are,
yeah, if you're a, if you have super loose joints, then you're going to need to pick the ones that
you can keep dynamically stabilized, but are not going to be subjected directly to unnecessary
forces. Yeah. Yeah. It's great concept. So I'm guessing Alton, you drew this to expand our
understanding of the anatomy to then appreciate the shoulder pain that somebody shows up with.
Yes. So all these things that I've drawn on here can be pain generators. And another one,
which is exactly to the point we're talking about is this, this right here, the AC joint,
almost everybody through wear and tear middle age and beyond has arthritis in the AC joint.
And like we were talking about in the neck, it's almost always asymptomatic, but it can be
symptomatic. If it's, sorry, just to be clear, the little red structure you've drawn on there,
that ligament that is connecting the clavicle to the acromion, there's no fluid within that space.
Tiny amount. Any place there's cartilage, there's a tiny amount of fluid, but there's very little,
but it can expand. And it can, and so if it's arthritic, you can get more fluid. If you have,
you know, young weight lifters like you were, can, I'll draw it here, can develop in the end of the
clavicle from that repetitive, but not doing heavy bench and other types of activities can develop
distal clavicle osteolysis, that repetitive jamming or bruising of the bone and cartilage
causes the cartilage to disintegrate and the bone to lose its integrity. And it starts to kind of
get very soft and it gets very inflamed. As soon as you start breaking up cartilage,
all the macrophages from the body come in there and then you get a big inflammatory response. You
get a lot of extra fluid and a lot of pain. So from a chronic perspective, are you going to see
that more in somebody doing bench press or military press or which direction? Both, but you'll also
get it. I don't do these. I don't recommend it. My patients do them, but the people who love to do
heavy lat raises, that just jams up. It's just so much leverage on that, that joint. And if you
are to do it, I recall you, you're sort of more in favor of, if you're going to do it, thumbs are up,
not down. Yeah. And not directly lateral. More in the natural plane of the scapula. Exactly. That
minimizes stresses. The other thing about it is that joint, you can imagine it's like you under,
you're understanding the biomechanics. You lie directly on the point of your shoulder and it
jams that against. So they have a lot of pain there. That pain comes right down the front,
kind of follows the biceps. So you have to differentiate that between the two. Then you
look at an x-ray without an MRI or anything. And you see these spurs that are down there. Well,
those spurs aren't ever going to tear the rotator cuff because that's that tendon is out there. It
never gets that far, but it rubs you. We see it as an indentation in the muscle. So, you know,
every time you're working out, you know, you hypertrophy your muscles. And so if you have that
constantly rubbing there and then you hypertrophy around it, it's a true.
So that's an athlete who complains that when they're lifting, it hurts more.
Exactly. Exactly. And that's a crystal clear when they're, when they're relaxed,
they haven't been exercising, they have rock solid strength. If you get them after,
if you get them up into positions or if they've been working out, you test them,
they'll actually be weak. Not because they're truly weak, but because their brain is saying,
no, I'm not going to give you that. It's going to hurt me. It's going to hurt my body. So I'm not
going to give you enough electrical current to give you a full strength there.
Wow. You know, this reminds me when I was in medical school, once I decided I was going to
go into surgery, I read a book and I wish I could remember the name of it, but it was a book written
by a general surgeon who had long since passed away, but the entire book was based on diagnosing
appendicitis. And, you know, this was, this guy wrote, cope. Yes. Appendice. That's right.
That's early diagnosis of appendicitis. And I thought this was the most fascinating thing
in the world because you had this old school, old school general surgeon who said, you know,
this is before anyone was using a CT, but he was like, this is 100% a clinical diagnosis.
And you wouldn't, nobody today training would ever dream you could waste an entire book
to diagnose something that, by the way, incredibly prevalent. It's the single most prevalent condition
in general surgery when you just shove everybody in the scanner and get the answer today.
But the reality of it is this, this makes me think of copes appendicitis. A, this is more
complicated. And two, I don't think there'll ever be a substitute for the nuance of the exam.
And this the history, both the history of the injury and the history of what causes pain.
Yeah. Yeah. It's fascinating. I love that. And we're going to come up with Barron's, you know,
well, the guy that, that was my cope was our professor of cardiology at Tulane. He was super
old when he was teaching us, he was in his eighties at that time. That's not super old,
but back then, yes. And he had had, he had had, he had had thyroid cancer. So he, he spoke in a,
in a very hushed tone. His name was C Thorpe Ray and he was a cardiologist. He could diagnose,
he could tell you exactly what was wrong with which valve just by listening to with his
testico with his hand. Sometimes he just put his ear up there and exactly he could tell by the
nature of the subtle variations in the heart murmurs, what the diagnosis, what I just,
Yeah. This is a little off topic, but I do sort of lament the fact that that's a dying art.
And look, you know, the reality of it is I'm sure that today with echo and stuff were better. And he
was probably such an outlier that most people could never rise to that level, just like most
people could have never attained the clinical acumen of, of code. But it is a little bit sad
to think that, you know, we can't have both, right? It would be, you have to think it would
be great to have both. So it's interesting to think that in orthopedics, it might be one of those
specialties where this judgment of the exam is still really, really relevant.
Right. That's right. I mean, obviously you get pinpoint diagnoses with the various tests.
And in orthopedics, there's plenty of things you find that aren't symptomatic, but still thinking
back to, I do lament that as well about the loss of the clinical acumen that, that comes with all
the advanced imaging. And, but I think that if you knew, if you have both, we don't, and I don't say
this self-servingly in the sense of I want to keep doing what I do as long as I can, because I love
it. But we, our patients need us to be able to still diagnose, listen to them, hear what they're
saying, because I mean, I don't know anything about general surgery, but there's got to be
things that come up positive that you don't necessarily have to have surgery on. Right.
Absolutely. And so you want to still be hearing and perhaps examining, but certainly hearing the
patient's story and knowing what's really going on to determine whether they need surgical or
non-surgical care or what kind of care they need. I feel like that was something that was,
if you were paying attention in residency, I think that was a very important message. I think
when you start residency, you're just so preoccupied with mastering the technical side of
things. I mean, there's so much to learn. It's, it's, it's like learning to master an instrument
and learn a new language at the same time. And you've only got five years to do it. But I
definitely remember the wisdom that was sort of spoken down to us, which is the single most
important thing that you will learn is when to operate and when not to operate.
Yes, that's true. That's true.
And, and, and, you know, I don't know how long that takes.
My guess is it's well after you finish your residency.
But unfortunately, and I don't want to go down this rabbit hole too much, but unfortunately,
there's. And there's some people who don't learn that.
Some people don't learn it or ignore it. And there are plenty of people who will operate
on any MRI, whether it's orthopedics or probably general surgery. I don't know whether it's.
We had one surgeon who the joke was if you rubbed betadine on the wall, he would operate on the wall.
Just, just don't, don't, don't let betadine near the wall. Right.
Because he'll start cutting it.
Yeah. Yeah, that's true. And that's, that's a perfect way to say it without being too pejorative.
And yeah, and there are economic incentives. There are even, and these are a version of
economic incentive, but there is even incentives in big institutions where it's an RV, RV, RVU,
RVU concept where you're going to do more because that's how you get your promotion and so forth.
And it makes it, I have to just suppress that information because it makes me too cynical.
And sad, but it's actually happens. And I'm sure you did when you were doing surgery. And I
certainly do now. I see patients that walk in with their MRI all the time and say, I'm scheduled for
this surgery in my shoulder or my elbow. And I'm scheduled for this by just my friend said,
I should just come get one more opinion. And I say, look, I'm looking at you, I examine them,
I do everything I go through. And I say, look, I wasn't there at the time of your examination.
So I can't speak for what that person saw and what their, their statement is. But today,
based on your MRI, your history and your physical exam, which I've done, I will not operate on you.
And if your friend said you should come to me because I have decent operative skills,
that's, I'm sorry, but I won't, I can't in good conscience operate on you. Maybe someday,
but not now. And I feel like I've sent you patients where that's been the patients that
have come from out of the country. And it's been a, I know that this surgeon is saying,
so I just want all to have a second look. Yeah. And you know, and that's,
I've never met a patient who didn't appreciate that, by the way. I mean, sometimes it creates
more confusion. Right. But, and I say that, I say, look, I'm sorry if this confused you. I'm sorry
if this is complicating your, your trajectory of what you you're planning for, but that's just
the truth. And yeah, the thing you always have to remember as a patient. And I think of this
myself is once you commit to doing something, it's the inertia to do it is huge. Right. And you can
always just say, look, there's an asymmetry in this decision to not have surgery doesn't remove
any options. You get to have surgery again later if it was the right thing to do. Yes.
Once you have surgery, it's not that you can't have surgery again, but the operative field never
looks the same a second time. That's a very good point. And so you want to keep in mind the asymmetry
of a pause. Yeah, that's very true. Very true. Right. So let's go back to our shoulder pain
patient. I think one thing we've established so far is a patient that has shoulder pain
can have so many things going on. Their AC joint can be the problem. They could have bursitis.
They could have a rotator cuff injury. They could have a labral injury. They could have
bicep tendon inflammation. And let's just leave it at that. They could have arthritis. We've got
all of these things that are going on. Now arthritis would usually be accompanied by one
of these other things that predisposed it. Okay. So we're going to go through an exam
and you're going to basically run me through these are the things you do. And this is what you look
to see on the MRI to basically correlate your findings and give you a set of confidence as you
go into the operating room. You named the bulk of them. I want to add two things to that before we
do our exam. And one of them I've drawn just kind of a red arc down there. And what I'm showing
there is the capsule. That's the best place to see the capsule when you're looking at an MRI
because it's thicker there and it's more distinct. There's not other structures obscuring it.
Normally if you have a super loose joint, you can have a very capacious capsule like that that
allows it to flop down and even sublux or dislocate. When it's very high and tight and
thick there, that can be representative of something called adhesive capsulitis. And the
reason I say that is because that's so common, one, and two, it can conflate all sorts of diagnoses.
And the frozen shoulder is the layman term for adhesive capsulitis. We don't know why this
happens. It's super common. I see probably two or three new cases every week in my office. It's
that common. But it's multifactorial. It's worse like many things are if you have diabetes,
but you don't get it with more frequency if you have diabetes. But it is and it's a full spectrum
and there's a lot of misinformation about it because the original old literature said that,
oh, all of these just get better with time. Well, they don't all. We know they don't all. And
even a subset of them, in my practice, about only one out of five actually ever need surgery. And
we never do that at the beginning. And it's just a simple little 30 minute release of the capsule
and a reduction in the inflammation. And then they're so happy. But that's the exception.
80% do not need any surgery. They need some way to control the inflammation. They need really good
physical therapy and a home program and some teams for mostly mobility. Yes. For mobility.
That's why I'm saying that is because you can get a stiff shoulder if you have impingement,
if you have a big bone spur, because your brain says, I'm not going to let you live there. And
then it just gradually stiffens up. That's a secondary stiffness or adhesive capsulitis.
It's not the weird primary adhesive capsulitis that could happen to you or me just suddenly.
And it just happens. It's a spontaneous, intense inflammation in the lining, inner lining. If you
take a little camera and stick it in there and just look, you see it's beat red. Normally,
everything when you're an arthroscopy, everything's kind of off white. And, but in the case of it's
just beat red and it's crazy. And we, and people have done all sorts of, of laboratory tests,
biopsies, evaluations have happened over a long period of time. I mentioned to you, there's a
colleague of mine in Northern California that wants to talk to you because you're so smart in this
about frozen shoulder because that maybe thinks some of the things you've said
might overlap with that biochemically. Yeah. So I was going to say, what are the,
I mean, do these respond to NSAIDs or is this a part of the body that doesn't have enough of a
vascular supply in the capsule that you don't get enough penetration? It has a rich vascular
supply, but I think in this case, I give NSAIDs when people want them and they're afraid of an
injection, but I think you, because it's that inner lining and it's so robust, I mean, if you
look at it microscopically, it's just these angry red fronds. And, and I think it's just not strong
enough. So I like to put a small dose of cortisone into the joint where you inject one time. I always
inject from the back for two reasons. One, this part is more richly supplied by the brachial
plexus. So it's more sensitive and two people kind of see you coming at them with a needle. So I
always go in the back and I never use an ultrasound. That's a whole other thing that a lot of
clinicians use the ultrasound just to see, but you can feel where you're going. You just get it in
there. And what's super cool about this is people come in with a lot of stiffness and a lot of pain
and then you inject them and put local anesthetic as well in there. They're free in 10 seconds. Oh,
my gosh. They walk out. They're saying, Oh my gosh, it's amazing. They still probably need physical
therapy, but the fact that they got such dramatic relief is such a simple treatment is so. So do you
recommend that a patient with frozen shoulder air on the side of earlier intervention with a
cortisone shot to then allow them to do more rehab sooner? Or do you say, I don't want to do a
cortisone shot till you've done three months of rehab. It's purely based again on their exam.
Well, and they're examining their history, how long they've had it and how acutely symptomatic
it is when I'm examining them. If I can stretch them and they start kind of saying, Oh, that hurts
a little bit at the end, but they've got decent motion. They're tight. Then go back and do the rehab.
Go to good PT who will really stretch you out. You don't need anything. You don't even need
insets. But if you, if I can't get them to move and they're just, they're screaming, you're not,
they're not going to get anywhere in PT because it's going to hurt you much to do it. So I'll
inject them, then send them to PT. And I always see them back at about six weeks. Most of them
are dramatically better, but not all of them. Very rarely they need a second shot. And then,
and then some of them are just recalcitrant and they just stay stiff. And then, then I'll do the
little procedure on them. So there was one other thing you wanted to mention. Yeah. What was that?
Oh yes. A big source of neck pain, which you and I have discussed multiple times is
referred pain from the spine, from the neck. And so we'll include that in our exam because it's so
important because you at least have to rule that out. Well, especially because someone comes in
with shoulder pain and I see that, you know, I take care of a lot of professional musicians
and their, their necks are doing all sorts of crazy things from all the violinists and the
philharmonic or et cetera, just all types of musical instruments that cause that lead to having to
maintain these certain postures that sometimes are very counterproductive to their overall
musculoskeletal health. But they'll come in with shoulder pain, going down their arm, maybe even
down to their hand and they'll have already gotten a shoulder MRI and they're 55 and they have four
findings on their MRI, but it's not coming from their shoulder. It's coming from their neck.
And so we have to make sure and differentiate that. And because the worst thing I could do,
the worst thing I could do to them is have them take time off from music to fix what doesn't need
to be fixed in their shoulder. And then it's, and they still have the pain. And they still have the pain.
And in that situation, is there something you see on exam that makes you think we better go look at
your neck first with the MRI because the symptoms fit as something I'm expecting to see. And then
you look and you see, well, I do see that. So now that's, yes, exactly. So that is so important. So
intrinsic shoulder pathology, whether it's a rotator cuff, whether it's impingement, whether
it's arthritis, almost never does the pain radiate down below the elbow. Whereas neck origin,
whether it's a pinched nerves at, you know, any, the lower cervical spine where it's more common to
have pathology almost always goes down below the elbow and into the hand. Now a low, the one odd
ball is C seven. And I learned this not that long ago from some really great cervical spine surgeons.
Is that if you have a deep posterior pain under your scapula, that can be C seven. And that's
right where it goes. And so I've had two musicians whom you know recently, both with that diagnosis.
Yeah, it's funny. The only time I've ever had a complaint of a neck issue, what turned out to be
a neck issue was not, didn't present as neck pain. So I, and this was several years ago. Now, again,
in the back of my mind, I've always known I'm susceptible. I'm susceptible. I'm susceptible.
And I woke up one morning and my left trap felt like it was in spasm. Interesting. And I kind of
ignored it. I was like, Oh, I slept over it. You know, whatever. This is super uncomfortable.
You know, the next day it was still in spasm. I just sort of ignored it. I might've taken some,
you know, NSAIDs and cup. This went on for like two weeks and maybe not two weeks. It might've
gone on week at that point. And at this point I'm thinking I've never had a muscle that's
this tense for this long. And in about that time, very abruptly, I started to notice a loss of tricep
strength. Wow. And yes, you know, I noticed it in the gym because it was subtle at first because I
was doing, you know, skull crushers where you have two dumbbells. So now the right arm can't
compensate for the left because using two dumbbells. And all of a sudden I couldn't move the weight
with this arm. So I, that's weird. I can move it this way. So I, and then it got to the, and then
it progressed so rapidly that within about two days I couldn't pull my bow back because this arm
couldn't support here. Wow. Yes. Yeah. So at that point I was kind of freaking out. I'm now down to,
you know, only being able to do a couple pounds. So I know, Hey, once you have those motors in,
but here's the thing, zero pain. Yeah. Not a lick of pain. Nope. Nope. No numbness tingly. No
parasthesias anywhere. Nothing. My neck doesn't feel a thing. I just have this trap on fire.
Make a long story short, you know, I see a person who says, look, you know, we could operate on you,
but unfortunately this is a surgeon who shares your ethos. And she said, look,
um, let's rehab the heck out of this. I think if you want, we could do an injection. I wasn't
excited about it because it was an anterior injection. And I said, no way I'd rather do
prednisone and traction. Yes. And so we did prednisone traction and sure enough within three
months, the strength was back. It's never returned, but that was a real wake up call to me that I had
a cervical symptom that didn't present with any neck pain. Yeah. That's great. That's a great
story. It's so instructive and you're absolutely spot on. I mean, and, and yeah, I mean, I see,
when I see, especially the musicians, as long as you don't have, you did have some. So you were,
you were absolutely right. Getting more deeply studied to make sure, because you had triceps,
but if you have no weakness, but maybe you do have a little tingling or something, but I know,
I just know it's coming from the neck. I won't lurch in and get MRIs in the neck, x-rays and
MRIs in the neck. I'll often just give them a one very low dose of prednisone and it usually goes
away. I mean, it's, it's, and then they don't have to worry about it and they don't have to get,
go down the rabbit hole of worry and anxiety about that.
So as we were talking about a minute ago about the shoulder, I think that with a good history,
interactive history and certain questions and a good physical exam, I can be about 95% accurate
in making a diagnosis without an MRI, without a CT scan or without even the x-rays. And so I think
that conserves resources and also it just gets the information because those little tidbits are
what are critical, including to knowing what's going to make you the best, whether it's going
to be an injection, PT, surgery, maybe, et cetera. So the first thing I look at is, you know,
it's nice that you're fit so I can see any true abnormalities. I can look for atrophy. I can look
for asymmetry. Somebody who's had a shoulder, a separated shoulder will have a big bump on one
side. Yours are equal. I can look at the pecs and see, you know, some of the nerve problems we talked
about, the Parsonage-Turner, for instance, the mixed brachial plexopathy. I'll see someone with a very
indented pectoralis. I had a patient the other day who's a rock and roll guitarist and he was
lifting weights and ruptured his pectoralis tendon. And so I could look and see right away
he had bruising down the arm, not the chest wall. That means he tore the tendon from the bone here
instead of the muscle tendon unit here, which a lot of weightlifters will tear. But I could also see
gross asymmetry. So those are the kind of things you're looking for. And I also even care about
the sloping of the shoulders because that can potentially be posturally if it's an issue with
posture and so forth. Okay, so looking at your shoulder, I see nothing asymmetric. I just then,
so I'm looking at the asymmetry. I haven't checked motion yet. I'm just going to palpate.
So I can palpate the AC joint and see that those are tender or non-tender. I can palpate the front
of the shoulder. Now this area is always tender. It's where the brachial plexus is passing through.
So this is one of the most tender areas in the shoulder. So I don't press too hard and I'm kind
of looking for asymmetry, not pressing hard. I want to look at the pecs. I want to look at the folds
of the pecs and see if there's any asymmetry there. I want to look at the contour of the deltoid.
And then I want to palpate back here your acromium, the roof, the bony roof of the shoulder. And I
want to palpate that and see if there's any tenderness along that perimeter because the whole
deltoid originates all around there. So you can tear, especially weightlifters, especially very
active athletes, can tear a little portion of that origin. It ends up healing, but it can be
very much of a nuisance for six or eight weeks. And then I look at the upper trapezius, right?
I want to see if there's any asymmetry. If you've had neck surgery and had an injury to that nerve,
then you can get atrophy there and it'll be very asymmetric. And then I want to look in the back.
I want to look and palpate people who are working out a lot or texting a lot and have bad posture
or bad ergonomics and get a lot of strain here in the rhomboid minor, the rhomboid major, and the
levator up here. And so those are the things I'm looking at. So I don't see any abnormalities here,
but if I did, that would help with the diagnosis. Then we want to look at range of motion. So I'm
going to ask you just lift your arms straight up in the air. So you have great motion and I'm looking
for any subtle asymmetry. Sometimes an arm will be maybe just that far. That last bit, then I push
it up. You go, oh, that hurts. That means your shoulder is a little stiff. Why is it? Well, we'll
get to that, but that's your forward elevation. Yours is nice and fluid and equal. Then we look
at external rotation. You have beautiful external rotation. That's about 75 degrees. Everybody varies.
I only go out about 50 degrees. It's fine. Now, if you're a thrower, you're going to have, let's say
you're a left-handed thrower, you're going to acquire external rotation to get more of that
we talked about that angular velocity. So this arm would come out externally more in a thrower,
in a left-handed thrower. Whereas if I come up here and measure internal rotation, that would be
decreased. You've acquired that from a lifetime of throwing. So that's what we look for. And that's
normal variation based on your activity pattern. So we've done that. Then I look, we've done
external rotation. We've done a modification of internal rotation, which is here in full
abduction, seeing how far you internally rotate, locking that up, trying not to rotate the scapula
too much because that's a, we know that a lot of people with stiff shoulders can compensate. You
were talking about that before with all that scapula thoracic motion. Okay. The other way to
measure that is just having you reach behind your back, but that's often more painful and it's easy
to deduce. If you have a frozen shoulder, let's say you have a frozen shoulder on this side, it's
going to look completely normal to look at. You have pain, you have stiffness, you can't do all
the things you want to do. And I look here and I see that this one's 70 and I look here and it goes
only goes to 30 and it starts to hurt when I do that. That's that adhesive capsulitis in there
that's blocking motion. Abduction, which is this movement here. So we always test abduction and I
see this mistake made. You can abduct way up, but that's all secondary to, not all, but a lot of it's
from your scapula thoracic. So I hold your scapula down. I know it's there and I see how far your
glenohumeral, your shoulder joint proper can come up. You come up perfectly to 90 degrees. So that's
a really important distinction. If you have frozen shoulder, it's going to be stuck. If you have a
chronic rotator cuff, it's going to be stiff. And so those are the kind of things that we start to
put together. So we've tested range of motion. Now let's test strength. So we're isolating the
rotator cuff and then we can also check the deltoid. So there's two components to shoulder motion
primarily. That's the deltoid, which gives us so much flexion, extension and abduction. But we also
have the rotator cuff, which we had talked about before. So here in neutral with your elbows at your
side, push out to the outside. Super strong. Now someone who has a big rotator cuff to you, that's
going to go, oh, it's just going to give way. And then we know that something significant is going on.
Now we do internal rotation, pushing in. Now that you can see how your pecs fired.
Internal rotation is a composite of both the pec pulling across very strong and compensating for
maybe a rotator cuff problem. The subscapularis in the front. So we can't really test the subscapularis
that way. So we had to do it a different way. Put your hands on your abdomen this way,
push your elbow out against me. And that is all subscap. That is all subscap. So if you have a little
even partial tear, that's going to hurt. If you have a complete subscap off, this elbow will, when
you do that maneuver, will fall back. It'll just fall away. You literally can't maintain that
position. So that's a nice good way. Okay. We did, we did external rotation. We did internal rotation.
Now we isolate the supraspinatus, that, that, that elevator of the shoulder. It's so important.
And so here we push straight up hard, you're rock solid, and that isolates the supraspinatus. Then,
but your deltoid is a little part of that. So that's how we can then check. Okay, let's check
the anterior deltoid. Push against me here. And I'm just resisting so I can stabilize it. Okay.
Then push back against me so that you've got a great posterior deltoid, anterior deltoid, and now
the lateral deltoid pushed straight out. That's a composite of the deltoid. We can see that firing,
but also the supraspinatus because that initiates abduction. So, so we've got good. We've checked now
the, the, for the shoulder, we've checked the strength, range of motion, and palpation, and
look for any asymmetry. Now we're going to do some provocation. We have to do provocative maneuvers
to get to more pinpoint diagnoses. So in the case of a rotator cuff tear, we can check strength there.
It's not really a provocation, but if you, if I abject you here and then externally rotate from
there, that's all rotator cuff. And if that's weak as it is, then you likely have a rotator cuff tear.
It can be the supraspinatus. It can also be the infraspinatus. And so that's one. Then if I'm up
in this position and I just wrote this relax and I rotate you down and I hear crepitus in there,
that would indicate bursitis. If I cause pain there, that's the impingement sign. And that would
imply that you're bringing the head up and rotating it and irritating that inflamed bursa. That's
impingement where you might have a spur. That's that. Now a variation on that theme is when we
come straight ahead, elbows fully up like this, keeping you up high and then push up against me.
That is your biceps. That isolates the long head of the biceps that we talked about because the
short head never comes into play and never tears and never gets irritated. So that tests the long
head of the biceps up there. Now we will cross over in one way. We'll cross over into the elbow
is by checking your other biceps, which is the distal biceps. And we kind of, we know that that
can be, if you have a normal distal biceps and a very inflamed long head in your shoulder, this will
hurt. This is the speeds where you're turning your palm up. Go ahead, supinate. You see that
really fires your biceps there. Good, strong. And I can, you're, you're being kind. I can,
I cannot break you and you can break me. So we test that that would hurt and you'd give way if
you had, and you, but you'd say it doesn't hurt here. It hurts here. So it's tugging on that bicep.
So that's a good, good indicator for that. Then we want to look at your labrum. That's a
common tearing thing that, that entity that can manifest. So the superior labrum, we have a good
provocative maneuver for that. It's called the active compression test. And we call it the SLAP
test, which stands for superior labrum anterior posterior. It's a funky, weird position. You're
across the body, it's thumb way down and then you push up against it. And that is rock solid. Now,
if you had a super superior labral tear, one, that maneuver would just hurt, but then it would just
give way. It would just fall away. And you know the firsthand about that. Okay. So that's the
superior labrum. Now, if we're looking for the anterior posterior labrum, we won't do that because
we don't have a, I would normally lie you down and then shuck your shoulder back and forth. But I can
get approximate with that. If you were sitting, I can stabilize your shoulder and scapula by
grabbing that. And then I can push, enter a posterior. Someone who's very loose, I can move
them excessively, posterior or anterior. And then I can even pull down on your arm and feel that head
go whoop, whoop. If you have that big capacious capsule, where it's inferiorly translatable,
then I can easily feel that from this position and I'll feel it just open up and go down.
So those are really the core parts of the almost full shoulder exam. And you can,
that's going to be about 95% corroborative and accurate based on what you've been telling me
in terms of your history and why you have shoulder pain.
All right, Alton. So now we have a sense of how complicated a nuance the exam is. So now let's
assume we have the diagnosis. Okay. So let's walk through some of the surgical treatments here.
Okay. So again, let's start with the operation I have. So a labral repair and
is the approach significantly different, whether it's a slap versus a complete tear like mine?
I assume it's just a number of ports or how does it?
Yeah, it's just a little more technically, right, to do. And you need a few more little,
and we do most of these now, as I was talking about the technology earlier, that we can do these
percutaneously. So we don't need five big, big, I mean, these are only a centimeter and a half.
The biggest ones are only about a centimeter, a centimeter and a half, but the others, they can be
percutaneous, tiny little holes that we use a little cannulas through and then put the drill
through and so forth. So, so that's, that's right. It's, it's more just adding a little time, you know,
it takes 10 minutes to do each anchor sort of thing. And so you just add on and you needed a bunch.
But it's also...
It's like the first thing, if I recall, that exam under anesthesia is crucial, right?
Yes. Oh, I'm glad you mentioned that. Yes. So even with a good exam, remember that a dynamic exam
you've got your, your brain has been dealing with this problem for a long time. You're naturally,
well, not naturally you work, but you're muscular, you have good muscle tones. So if I'm examining
you, I probably can't sublux your shoulder. I mean, you have to kind of, I have to kind of jump
up on top of it to do it. The rare case is somebody who's had such long standing instability that
their body's no longer responding to it. And usually I can get one or two subluxations,
but then they, they tense up, but I can usually get one or two. So that's one subset. But so yes,
so the great thing about an exam under anesthesia is once you're in your position where you're going
to have the surgery, you've got a regional block where your arm is super numb and you're sedated
so that you're relaxed and you can't control anything. And then I can just, it's as if your
muscles aren't really there. I mean, they have a little effect on it, but mainly I'm testing the
static stabilizers. In your case, I could take it pretty far out back and way I could completely
dislocate your shoulder out front. So, and that wasn't, still hurts for me to watch that video.
Yeah, right. It's super cool. And so then, you know, then that tells me, okay, I need to be
careful when I'm looking on the inside, I need to assess not just the labrum, which I know is torn.
I need to, in the case of the anterior, you've been like the balloon, you're blowing up repeatedly.
You've been also stretching out your capsule. You're still compensating, well, less well and
less well with the muscles, but you are compensating. So if that is stretched down the front,
I need to know that in addition to just repairing the labrum itself, I need to gather up some of the,
this capsule, which has become too capacious and, and do what we call a capsularophy, which is to
gather and tighten that up too. And that's kind of a judgment call. When you've done a lot of them,
you kind of know how much to gather. You don't want to gather too much because then it tightens
them up too much. To that point, and this is a caveat about not, well, yeah, unnecessary surgery,
had a lovely violinist, professional violinist who I treated her whole family. They're all violinists.
And she had been up in Vermont, farther enough away to where when she had a frozen shoulder
or shoulder pain, she got an MRI, saw a sports doctor who saw, and again, she's 60 at that time,
62, 63, and had some degenerative labral tearing. Well, he said she needed to have a repair
of that, which, and then she presented with what pain? Just pain, a little stiffness. Okay. So just
read the MRI. It said labral tearing didn't really have anything else. So said you need a repair of
your labrum. Did a repair of the labrum. She came to me about six months later in tears, had not
been playing for six months, had the stiffest shoulder I think I've ever seen, basically didn't
move. So he tightened the hell out of the capsule. Right. And did a labral repair that in a 62 year
old, who's not an athlete, would never be necessary. It's just sort of universally true. And so I had
to go in and scope her. It was really hard because it was so tight. Had to just bit by bit, release
everything that had been done and release the capsule that was all crunched up and tightened
up. Even had to take some of the sutures out to free up her shoulder. Do you have a sense of what
her initial injury was even caused by? I mean, do you think it was just capsular? I think she just
had a stiff capsule. Just had a stiff capsule. Wow. So someone that should have had PT plus or minus
at most a single injection to reduce the inflammation has the exact opposite. They
get a complete tightening of the capsule. And there's a school of thought and orthopedics that
says, we just don't like repairing labrams and doing capsule repairs in older people because
that's the outcome you get. Yes. And that's completely valid. I mean, it's completely valid.
I remember some people that I spoke with who said, wow, at your age, Peter, you're basically 50,
you're having a labral repair. Are you crazy? Now, of course, in my case, I think I don't,
I haven't lost any mobility, which is kind of remarkable. No, no. And in fact, you know,
you and I discussed that some, right? Yeah, that was one of my biggest fears. Yeah. And so one has
to pay extra attention to that. For me, if we want to be specific about your case as just a case
example, I don't think we had a choice because you, you're subluxation, you're so active,
you're subluxation with all the different activities. We already had some arthritis,
you're already wearing down some cartilage. I mean, it's, it's going to be, it's either that
or the inevitability of having a shoulder replacement in another 10 years. Right.
Yeah. I mean, I think when I saw the, a little bit of arthritis there, I kind of wished I'd done it
sooner. Sure. Knowing what I know today, I almost wish I had more pain, you know, sooner.
Because I really had a ton of pain 10 or 15 years ago, but with a lot of good tissue work and a lot
of training, I kind of got out of it. Yeah. And I made some modifications, like there were certain
things I just decided I couldn't do. But that's right. Yeah. But, but, but, but I think that's
interesting. So, okay. But another component of that is, especially now, people are so much
younger mainly because they're all rucking now. No, but they're people are so much younger
physiologically in better condition. And we know that from whether it's cancer treatments and
everything else and the advancements of science that a 50 year old now that would have applied
to that data that we have, you know, 20 years ago is misleading. So I base it on, I mean, you're,
you're, we're kind of an outlier. Yeah. You base it on biological age, biological age. And even
look, there are some people that have, I'll, I'll scope them. They'll, I'll say, look,
I don't have any other way than looking and seeing what's there. And in some cases they have
better cartilage than what the MRI is indicating or the, and then I can go ahead and do a repair.
And some of them are, I've done a couple, I mean, maybe I shouldn't say this on air. I've done a
couple of like 58 year olds, 60 year olds, but their joint was pristine. I mean, it looked as
good as a 25 year old. They just had a discreet, yeah, labor care. No, to me, look, this is what I,
this is to me an extension of what I think of as precision medicine, which is we use evidence-based
medicine, which is incredibly heterogeneous to make population-based assertions and general
broad recommendations. But ultimately the only patient that really matters for most doctors is
the one right in front of them. Exactly. And therefore you have to be able to make evidence
informed decisions based on the appropriate physiology that you see. And it's also a
conversation. It's a conversation with that patient, not a unilateral decision. It's, it's,
okay, what do you want to do? What do you know about this? Here's what I know about this. Here's
what I'm seeing with you. And we need to say, here are the possibilities and what do you want to do?
So how often when you go in for, and let's just, I guess, just explain to people. So the biggest
port puts the camera and do you have how many, and then you have like a few working ports, obviously.
Yeah. So typically, typically since more of the pathology is superior and anterior,
although you had some in the back, you, if you're working in the superior in the front,
you go in through the back with the camera. So you just have a good panoramic view of everything.
We have two different kinds of angled lenses. So we can see around corners if we need to,
usually don't need them for most things. But then I can see the superior labrum.
You know, in general surgery, we insufflate with carbon dioxide, right? So you're shooting
carbon dioxide to blow everything up. I assume you're using saline to do the same thing. So
you're making that capsule bigger. And that's a good point. So I don't use,
I mean, I've done a lot of these, I don't use high pressure. Some people use around 50 millimeters
of mercury pressure. I use 35. And that means less postoperative pain. It's less, it's less,
yes. Distention of the whole shoulder and so forth. So that's what I do. And, and you can
still put in little retractors, kind of pull tissue out of the way and so forth. So that's
just a technique. I actually, that's more of an extension of what I do in the elbow,
because there's a lot more peril because of the nerves. But, but in, so then usually you need two
working portals in the front, which are just cannulas that are just basically canals to get
in with instruments that are long enough to fit through the, through the, and do the work. And
then in the case of, for instance, a superior labrum, we use a percutaneous right through the top,
just underneath the kind of right here actually, where that red arrow is going. And that just
gets you to the superior labrum. So that's a little percutaneous. You make a tiny little hole
in the rotator cuff, kind of muscle tendon junction. It just spreads the fibers apart.
So it doesn't do any damage to that. And then you've got a perfect bird's eye direction for
the drilling and putting in those few anchors in the top. And then that's, that's really it.
And explain how that works. So you drill a little hole in the glenoid fossa. What's the diameter of
that hole? Yeah. So it depends on what kind of anchor you're doing. Usually roughly not more
than three millimeters. And now we're down to 1.8. Okay. Even three seems big.
Three seems big, but that's what you fit the plastic or the absorbable anchor in that you
just kind of tap in with the mallet. All of them you tap in with the mallet and you're drilling
into the bone. You're drilling around here, kind of this angle here.
And you have to get the angle right. It's a very three dimensional, but you put them in so that
you're drilling into hard bone and then the anchor inserts through that. And so they're
not circumferential. No, they're just straight in. Correct. We used to, if we did them open,
we used to do them even with like a suture drill holes and a suture going through circumferential.
So what holds the anchor in? Is it just the pressure you're putting an anchor in that is
bigger than the hole? And so is there like a nail? Yes, exactly. And or a tense,
not a screw, but they're not a screw. There were historically some that we screw in, but not anymore.
And now the ones that are purely basically braided polyester, those go in as a, as just a,
the suture goes in. And then as you carefully pull it back out, the way they're designed,
they ball up and it creates a, I mean, they're super strong. You can lift the shoulder off the
table. So it's super cool to use those. Wow. That's so interesting. So you have a lot of confidence
in the integrity of that repair. Yes. Yes. I know that if I tug on it multiple times,
it's not going to come out. And I mean, it would take a fully traumatic force to do that. Yeah.
So before you do this, I assume you do an exam of the cuff while you're in there.
Absolutely. So you go through and do a survey of the joint. You look at the cartilage surfaces from
the nooks and crannies cartilage surface. You look at the rotator cuff inserting on the bone from
inside out, and you can see that being smooth. If it's frayed, if it's notably frayed, you can
probe it and you can see, oh, that actually has also, and I occasionally see that because they're
athletes, a small, almost full thickness tear. Then I may put a sitch or two in that to fix that.
You look at the biceps, you can pull the kind of the biceps into the joint and see a pretty good
segment of it and see if it's inflamed, torn, something abnormal there. And you can see the
tendon of the bicep really well to see, obviously, is it frayed? Yes. So how much damage do you need
to see to do the tendinesis? Not a lot. If I see a combination of a modest amount of fraying and a
lot of inflammation around it, and when I pull it in the joint, that extends further out, then I'll
tendinesis. It's interesting. I think for people to understand how much your eyes are helpful here,
right? As you said, when you look at these images, and we'll link to some images in the show notes
of what these pictures look like. In fact, we can include my pictures and just other pictures we'll
find online. It is just a very plain, banal, gray, white normal thing. And to think that
inflammation just shows up is like, wow, that's really red. Yeah, exactly. And for me, some people
don't like to waste the time, but I get a little electrocardi wand and I paint the internal and
get rid of all that pink because it's inflammatory. It hurts. That's part of one of the big pain
generators. So I just do that automatically. Now, theoretically, if you fix everything,
that's going to go away anyway, but it helps them. I think early post-op, a recent patient I had,
I did a pretty significant repair on and he, after five days said, I haven't had any pain. What's
going on? It just, did you do anything to my shoulder? So I said, yeah, I did repair it, but
yeah, but I think part of it is just getting rid of that inflammation and so forth.
Okay. So now contrast that with the pure rotator cuff repair. Right. So let's do two examples.
Let's talk about a patient who, what is the most common athlete's tear? Which one is it going,
did we say it's going to be a subscapularis or a supraspinatus? Well, so it depends. It depends on
if it was, if they're an overhead athlete, then it's going to be supraspinatus almost always.
And sometimes it can be the infraspinatus. Right. So if a guy just has a straight up
supraspinatus tear, you don't even need to enter the capsule necessarily, depending on how close it
is. No, you do because you want to, first of all, you want to see everything. You want to make sure
that you're not missing anything, which is common in the athletes. There's a couple of interesting
various, I'm going to draw some pictures. Okay. So here I've drawn three sequential
axillary views, which are a bird's eye view, looking straight down on the top of your shoulder
if I were sitting on top, looking straight down. So we've got the glenoid, the socket here toward
the head. And we've got the ball out here toward the outside where the deltoid lives. And then you
I've drawn the, this is the supraspinatus I've drawn in here on the top in the back, as we talked
about before, that's the infraspinatus. And then in the front is the subscapularis. So these are the,
and those are the three, the Terry's minor, which is the fourth muscle, the rotator cuff. It's not
really a relevant player in the pathology. Very true. Yeah. It almost never tears. Okay.
This is actually really a cool way to look at it. It's not normal that we usually look at them from
front and back, but the bird's eye view is what allows you to see how the subscapularis and the
infraspinatus are stabilizing the front and the back while the supraspinatus is coming in over
the top. Yes. Yes. Is the supraspinatus that wide, relatively speaking? Yeah, it's pretty wide.
Wow. It's so interesting. Maybe more about here. Here it is, let, do it a little wide there.
Okay. But that's interesting. Again, in anatomic diagrams, because you're looking at it from the
front, it looks like a tiny little muscle. Yes, but it's broad. It has three dimensionality in it.
That's about three, roughly three, three and a half centimeters of width going front to back. Yeah.
Wow. Okay. Great. And so, um, there's three different views. The most common one is the
middle one. And that's because that's anterior, the biceps is here. That's an anterior superior
tear. That's the one that the overhead athletes get a lot, non-throwing athletes, but tennis
players, um, volleyball players, um, and weight lifters. Um, and that is, is one of the critical
zones where it can get rung out and not have good blood supply. And that's where they tear. That's
where I had my little tears, um, on both shoulders, but that's the garden variety one. That's also the
one that can be caused by the, the, the spur pushing down on it. And, and I've drawn a little,
a little, um, arc because that's kind of the tear off and then they'll form a little arc of
smooth tissue and you, you freshen that up, freshen up the bone and then put the sutures in that
leading edge of the tendon and put it back just like you'd put a tarp with a tent stake back in.
And that's how you repair it. You get it back to the good bony bed and you get that good biologic
healing. And that's a small tear that I've drawn there and they can be bigger and bigger if you
imagine in more chronic. Now the one down below shows the subscapularis in the front. And that is
the one that can tear in young people or older people, uh, based on mechanism. So if you have a
linebacker who has, he's going forward at full velocity to make, and then somebody is knocked
into him and shoots him across, he's got his arms out there ready to go. And he gets eccentrically
loaded into external rotation like that. That's how you can tear the subscapularis. The other way
is people falling downstairs and grabbing the banister and wrenching back that way. That's the
common, it's commonly torn with ease, an abnormal weird stretch where they're contracting and then
it's just torqued on him. Now this upper one is very interesting because we were talking about
throwing athletes. So when you, the throwing athletes, baseball players and football players,
they externally rotate dramatically. That's how they get their extra angular velocity to really
get that, that, that zip on the ball. So they, they acquire external rotation starting at a young age.
They, so their arms are very asymmetric, their shoulders. One side will externally rotate to 90,
the other one will go back another 45 degrees. And that's how they get that whip. One of the
consequences of that in a subset of them is that as this rotates and follows this area around,
that area of the rotator cuff, which is at the junction of the infraspinatus and the superspinatus,
abuts up against the hard bony rim of the glenoid and they get an internal impingement,
ultimately get small partial thickness or even full thickness tears there. So we have to be super
cautious with those. We have to repair those, but you have to be really careful because if they lose
10 or 15 degrees of extra rotation, they lose, they lose. So where does the Tommy John fit into this?
Yes. So that's the elbow. That's the elbow. But it does know as maybe that was just intuitive
because since you are a good orthopedic surgeon is actually, it fits in because a lot of people
add torque on their elbow because they have shoulder pathology.
I see. So they transfer, they gain the external. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So that's where they end up.
If they have a little weakness or something going on on their shoulder, they will overthrow
with their forearm and their flexor pronator mass. They'll overthrow with the torque and then they'll
tear their medial collateral ligament of their elbow. It's crazy, but true. And vice versa,
if they have a weak, if they have a partially torn, uh, medial collateral ligament that hasn't yet been
identified, they can overthrow with their shoulder to compensate, to get more angular velocity on
that because they can't, uh, muster it through the elbow. And so, uh, how many years ago would it
have been the case that a torn rotator cuff was the end of a pitcher's career or a quarterback's
career at the professional level? Great question. I would say easily, uh, not more than 20 years ago,
probably even not, uh, 15 years ago, probably 15. And today that's not the case. No, no, no. What has
been the advance that has changed? Because I can't think of anything that could be possibly more
stressful. I mean, to me, throwing a baseball seems even more stressful than throwing a football
because you do it more times in a game. Right. So what has changed that has made the, what's
changed this earlier diagnosis. If people now, and certainly at the, at the, the division one collegiate
level and the professional level, there's any pain is evaluate kind of over-evaluated and that can be
good for them. I mean, it's, you know, it uses a lot of resources, but it, it identifies these very early.
So that's one way. So you get to them earlier. So in other words, quarterback pitcher says,
you know what, starting to hurt a little bit, you see a very small tear in the cuff.
You're saying it's better to go in and repair that than let it become a bigger tear.
Yes and no, it depends. You, you'd certainly watch it carefully, right. And you correlate the symptoms
with, and that's why, you know, you should sometimes it's not the tear. It's just some
inflammation that's related to it. If you can cool that down, the tear is not biomechanically
significant yet. So, but there are, I've said this to many people, I have full thickness tears
in people that are minimally symptomatic and partial thickness tears that are very symptomatic.
It kind of depends on what you're doing. And I think one thing that's kind of missing from this
picture in the subscapularis in the infraspinatus is how long they are. So we're looking at the top,
but these muscles cover the scapula. Totally. So when you say a full thickness tear,
you know, I want to make sure people understand the size of the tear. Yes. So when I say full
thickness, I mean like when we were looking on that other view, let me draw that again.
Oh, actually I can just go back to the previous.
So when I've drawn the supraspinatus tendon, that perpendicular distance through there is the
thickness, the full thickness. And it's, it varies depending on the size of the patient, but,
but it could be across the entire four centimeters. It could be a whole four centimeters by
half a centimeter. Yes. So you could have, but when we talk typically about, when we speak
typically about full thickness, we mean the, the depth of it this way so that you can have a
partial thickness tear. That's maybe half the tendon there or full thickness. Now, if you have
half the tendon torn, you've lost enough biomechanics that if you're a high level throwing athlete,
no way. Yeah. No way. So. Whereas a partial thickness tear off the tendon. Yes. Could easily
be ignored. Correct. Exactly. So, so then when we talk about this, that yes, those muscle bellies
are huge. Now, the reason you jog my, my thinking about that is you can have, if you, especially if
you have these guys are so strong, like the football players and so forth, sometimes they
have that wrenching injury. They don't rip the tendon off the bone, but they interstitially tear
at the muscular tendon disjunction. And they have that, and they have a tremendous amount of edema,
weakness, pain, but that will heal. That will heal without any intervention, just some tincture of
time and some anti-inflammatory and just time to heal. What role do stem cells or PRP play in any of
this? Certainly anecdotally, there are a lot of people saying, look, you know, stem cells aren't
going to replace a labrum. They're not, you know, they're not going to work there, but you have a
tear in the muscle. Stem cells can be valuable. Now I'm not really aware of RCTs that have looked
at this, but I also haven't scoured the literature on the rotator cuff data. Are there people running
clinical trials on stem cells in that indication? So I think so. I don't know that literature as
well as maybe I should, but it's, I tend to, you know, I go to all the meetings and I stay fairly
abreast. There is obviously a lot of activity going on, but there's a lot of terribly designed
studies all around that are being used to justify using whether PRP or stem cells. So one has to be
careful to extrapolate it to your individual practice. And there's a lot of money involved
in it too. I mean, I have patients routinely that fly to various places, including Germany,
including, and I'm not pillaring. I'm not by any means because that they exist everywhere. I just
happened to know a couple that just got back and they pay a lot of money to get stem cells injected
for things that we've been talking about. And there's no data. I'm not talking about the
musculotendinous. That's different. I want to talk about that. But I mean, let's say just a
garden variety, small rotator cuff tear. There is no data ever. There are some, a few anecdotal
reports where people say, look, there was a tear there on that MRI. I injected PRP and it's healed.
It's gone. I don't know what to make of those. They're just one-offs. Well, also, do we know
what the natural history of that injury would have been without the PRP? Of course not. Do we know?
No, we don't. So we don't have enough of a series to say, if you took a thousand people that had
that tear and you did nothing and came back and surveyed them two years later, this many,
you wouldn't see the tear again. Correct. Do we not know that? We don't know that. Okay.
And I have one of my best scientific things that I can relate that it goes down to the elbow,
but I think it's important for this part of the conversation is I was speaking right before COVID
at the AOSSM, the American Association of Sports Medicine. These are non-surgical general medicine
doctors who do sports medicine and they're great. They're really knowledgeable. They do tons of
studies and I was speaking, I was waiting to speak and the two papers presented before me were back
to back. Really well done. Large numbers, over a thousand patients, double-blind, randomized
studies comparing for tennis elbow. Tennis elbow, lateral epicondylitis, comparing cortisone,
PRP and placebo. And the placebo and the PRP were the same and the cortisone was much more effective.
These were back to back studies, different institutions and it was informative for me
because I've read the literature. Our literature is replete with studies that say, oh well,
you know, PRP really helps. And I see patients all the time that have had PRP injections
based on my current knowledge of the literature for rotator cuff repairs,
for tendon ruptures, for lateral epicondylitis, certainly for Tommy Johns and medial epicondyl,
medial tendon ruptures. I have a PRP machine in my office in Manhattan and I use it twice a year.
For what?
For when someone begs me to do it.
Yeah. I mean, I guess, again, not to be skeptical, but I suppose a doctor can make more charging for
PRP than cortisone. I mean, cortisone is pretty cheap.
Cortisone, well, one, it's covered by insurance and two, yes, it's a couple hundred dollars for
a shot. Typically, in my office, that's one of the reasons I don't use it, is a thousand dollars
and it's not necessarily covered and people charge a lot more. Some people charge $2,500
for a PRP injection. So until, look, I'm not saying that it doesn't someday.
PRP, the concept is great. As you know, it has growth factors. It's, it's our own bodily,
you know, fluids. And so it's perfectly reasonable, but it hasn't yet borne out to be a game changer.
Now, if you take someone who's the highest level athlete and they have bursitis, sure,
inject some PRP in there, some stem cells, whatever, maybe it'll be better. Who knows?
There's not really good data on it, but there's no downside to doing it. The only downside sometimes
I see many more flare reactions from PRP injected into tennis elbow where people are really painful
for a couple of weeks and they end up coming to me for either surgery or cortisone. They'd say,
I don't want another one of those. I don't want another one of those. And that's just anecdotal
for me. I don't have a, I don't have a comparative study.
Yeah. I, I, I, and I probably need to spend more time in the literature, but I really,
the few times I've kind of looked with some interest usually on the request of a patient
who's kind of going through this. I just haven't found data that are convincing enough,
even though again, mechanistically there's a high plausibility and,
but I think the problem is we don't have that natural history. This is, this is the problem.
There's lots of anecdotes that say this injury was present. Stem cells were injected. The injury
is gone radiographically. Yes. The problem is we don't have the contra positive case.
We don't. The best natural history study we have on, and this has nothing to do with treatment. This
is asymptomatic rotator cuff tears is came out of WashU. One of my best friends in orthopedics,
Ken Yamaguchi was lead on that article. They looked at ultrasounds, which was great because
they're non-invasive, non costly, and very effective. If you have a good ultra stenographer,
and they looked at the natural history of these asymptomatic, asymptomatic tears, and they found
that they obviously documented the percentage of, of, of asymptomatic tears in the general population,
but they looked at them longitudinally and they never repaired on their own. They at very best,
a subset of them stayed the same. The larger the tear, the more likely it was to become even larger
with time. And become symptomatic? And become symptomatic. A subset of those became symptomatic.
Yes. So, and that's, it was really well done. It got a lot of press. So none got better
spontaneous. Correct. Okay. So that, so that would suggest that if people are saying, Hey,
here's my MRI pre and post stem cells, and it got better, that, that would at least suggest that in
that individual, it might've worked. If you had enough and they were done with the same, as you
know, MRIs very significantly from, from machine to machine. So they would have to be very well
controlled. Yeah. You showed, if you showed me even 20 patients done by someone that I know is
legitimate and they did that and showed comparative MRIs that even 10 out of 20 showed healing
reconstitution and I'd be in. Yeah. Well, I hope that study is being done. I suspect that there
were a number of obstacles to it. If it's not being done again, it's always possible it's being done.
I'm just unaware of it. But one of them would be, you'd have to standardize the process of generating
the stem cell. Absolutely. One of the challenges of doing a clinical trial is everybody has to get
the same drug. Yes. And if the drug differs, it becomes problematic. Do you know how standardized
the procedure is for capturing and processing stem cells? Yes. Non. It is. Non-stand-on.
Yeah. So that's part of the challenge. It differs between the different companies
that bring the machines in. It differs between the individual clinicians and so forth. So yes,
that's one of the things that my colleagues and I discuss quite a lot is they, it's not,
it can be apples and oranges. A couple other injuries I want to talk about in the shoulder
before we move to the elbow. So the AC separation, when does it require a repair? When does it just
get left alone and you're stuck looking with a little bit of deformation? Yeah, that's great.
That's a great question because they're so common, the injuries. So let me draw a picture.
Okay. So we have here a just, we've removed the glenohumeral joint and we just have the
AC joint. This is the clavicle coming across. These are the two stabilizers of the clavicle.
One is that's the coracoid process and these are the coracoclavicular ligaments.
And we're just looking at that and done, which is why it looks like a little nub and circle,
but of course it runs. Yeah. It's a thumb that sticks out from that yet another weird part of
that scapula. It's got to be the weirdest looking bone in the body, right? Yeah. And so, and then
secondarily we have the acromiocavicular joint that we were talking about and those are the
ligaments that are circumferential around the chromiocavicular joint. So if you fall hard off
your bike and you sprain your AC joint, we call that a type one. You sprain your AC joint,
you stretch a little bit and injure these ligaments and maybe even stretch those a tiny bit.
It's not displaced. But it doesn't look any different on x-ray. And that is a great one.
Those can hurt and those can damage the cartilage a little bit and you can get a
great one that persists and being painful, but generally they don't, they go away.
I did this recently on some slime out in Dripping Springs riding a bike out there. I just,
low water crossing, just went out like, like it was on ice and, and it, that's exactly what I had.
And it hurt for six weeks and then it was gone. It's completely normal.
But it wasn't. Sorry, that diagnosis by the way,
was just pressing right on it. That's how you know it.
Well, I know it because by pressing right on it, it hurt like heck, but it didn't
blot. It didn't move up and down and I could lift my shoulder and I wouldn't,
I could feel it not moving. So one of the things that we, that, that are biomechanically
interesting. We talked to the residents about when we're teaching is it's not that the
clavicle pulls up. It's that the shoulder falls away. These is the primary suspension.
One of the primary suspenders of the shoulder are these two ligamentous structures.
I see.
So if you tear them, the shoulder kind of falls away. So that's why we treat it by wearing a
sling and get that weight of that heavy weight of the arm off. Now down here we have, I have a
shadow drawn. Here's the ACE. Here's the clavicle. We have one acromion, which it's sitting up about
30% or so. That's where you've clearly torn the AC ligaments and you've partially torn,
maybe completely torn, but it just didn't distort it too much where you have, you know,
you have a complete tear, but it's only up about 30%. That's a grade two, grade two. And that,
almost all those can be treated non-operatively. Occasionally those will, again, like the ones
they can hurt, persist, you might have to do something later, but they're basically stable.
And when you treat it non-operatively, is the treatment that it will return to its position
with elevation?
Sometimes, but usually not. Usually it stays a little elevated, a little proud, but people
don't really care. It's very barely asymmetric. Okay. Then you get here where you have a complete,
it's completely up. And we measure that by the distance between the coracoid and the clavicle.
I've drawn it here to just express that, that difference there in the height. And that is that
coracocavicular distance. If it's here, if it's up to 30% widening increase in that space, then
that's the grade two. If it's a hundred percent or more, then that's a grade three. If it gets up to
a hundred percent, even those, there was a good study done a long time, probably 20 years ago for
NFL athletes who had sustained these. And the prevailing wisdom for the doctors who were
treating the NFL teams was that most of that type threes did not need treatment, surgical treatment,
but a subset of them did go on to needing it later. Now in reality, when they're up that high
and people want to get back sooner, we have met better reconstructive techniques now. And so you
can kind of get back on the bike. And if you're a professional cyclist, if you fix them and get back
on the bike in three or four weeks sort of thing. So there's a gray zone, but the type threes are
that transition. Now, if they are the other- The four is more than a hundred percent cap.
Yes. And then sometimes it can be trapped behind the scapula and all sorts of other things. But
the threes are the sweet spot. The vast majority of the operative ones are in the three category.
And I saw a guy the other day and I kind of presented both options to him. He's a, he's a
athlete. He's a weightlifter, but he's, but he's, he was late forties. And I just gave him the
options. I said, look, one of the things you might consider, and this applies to a lot of what I do
is I said, look, yeah, we can fix this. We can fix it tomorrow or next week. But you could also
wait and see how you feel in three or four weeks. I can do the same repair in three or four weeks.
Yeah, you don't lose anything. You don't lose anything by waiting in that, in that realm. Now,
you do if you wait three months or six months because you don't have the same biology going on.
And so, and he ended up not wanting it because he felt great. And so-
How far out was he from the insurance?
He was four weeks when he started.
And the pain was already gone.
Almost already gone. He saw the trajectory being so good that he decided that he wanted to wait.
And the only issue that he's going to struggle with now is the asymmetry aesthetically.
The asymmetry and yes.
It won't have a functional impairment.
Generally not. Except if you're doing certain types, like if you're heavy flies, heavy bench,
even people who rest, you know, do the, I don't do squats, squatted, but you know, heavy-
Yeah, yeah, yeah. But a high neck, high back squat.
Yeah, high back squat. And those could, I presume that could irritate them and be
problematic. So, and so there are some-
And so the repair here is done how?
Yeah. So this is where I differ from some. A lot of people just get in and get out quickly and they
will- Let me draw it here. So if you have it fairly fresh and you have good ligamentous tissue in here,
then we do what's called a dog bone, which is basically two titanium grommets. And this is
heavy polyester suture. We drill through everything, drill through the clavicle,
drill through the coracoid, and then pass, it's just kind of using some little tricks,
pass the suture up through, pull everything down, have your assistant pull it down,
that you tie that over and it is rock solid. Rock solid. And they really do well.
Interesting. So in other words, you sort of, you don't do it by going back to the acromion process.
Right. Yeah. Right. You go, you get the anatomy, you get the-
You line up the anatomy. You get the two one ligaments to be in continuity again,
and then they can heal. And is that a biodegradable polymer? No.
No. So that'll stay forever. Yeah. And so yeah, and it's super strong. And so you can really,
I mean, you don't, you don't, this might go in a week, but you can, depending on what their sport
is, you can let them get back at maybe three or four weeks, certainly six weeks. Six weeks,
this thing is pretty strong where you can do most things. Before we leave the clavicle,
I only asked about this because I just had a patient that went through it. When the clavicle
and the mediastinum separate, I assume that's not as common. No, it is not. It's way less common,
but it's, it can be very problematic. I'm going to draw a great picture. I think so that. Please,
because you know, while you're drawing that, I'll explain the situation. This was a patient who,
um, I'm trying to remember what the, what caused the injury. I,
I wonder if it was a fall, a high fall. Um, it might've even been off a horse or something
as possible. Um, but what surprised me was the patient who was in New York
basically called that morning to say, look, I just saw two surgeons at HSS and they said,
I need to have surgery right away. Um, and you know, I guess it's interesting, right? There are
some things in orthopedic surgery that are, um, are, are a need for an emergent case. Uh, and this
very few, but it's possible. Yes. Yeah.
This is a, a, um, Lord Dottic view, uh, basically of the manubrium sternum, which is our breast
plate there and our, where we can follow our clavicle across to that and we can feel the little
nubs right there at the base. We can feel those sternoclebicular joints. Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
So you can see it's even worse than the shoulder. It's a very shallow joint. So if you take a
hard blow laterally, hockey players get slammed up against the glass. It's a common,
more common injury in that the football players, the quarterbacks that get tackled by these
300 pounders and their shoulders are wedged together like that. And just so happens that,
that's what the injury, not to this extent, but the injury that Quinn Ewers, the quarterback for UT
suffer was knocked out in the Alabama game. He's now back. So he obviously didn't have this full
dislocation, but that's what can happen in weird circumstances. And that's what you were talking
about. The mechanics can be that, and it happens a little more commonly in kids, but it can, if the,
the fall is just right and the cancer is just right, it will open this up, tear everything,
and then displace it behind the manubrium. And that's where the, the major, you know,
carotid artery, the drug, vein, lives. And that can be a huge, huge life threatening, not, not life.
Well, it could be life threatening for sure. Yeah. So we have to be careful with those. But this one,
where it's subluxes out the front, those are also problem. You can see that they, they, there's
nothing, there's no way it's going to fall back into place there. So either they stay out, they
stabilize and people just don't do that much to irritate them or they have to be reconstructed.
And I've had to go in and reconstruct these where I take a tendon from the forearm and make a figure
of eight across the front and basically rebuild those ligaments to hold it back in place. And
why do you do that as opposed to doing an anchor or something like that? Yeah, it's just stronger.
You need some extra collagen there. So what is it about the insult laterally that will
determine a separation here versus here. These are two weak points at each end of the clavicle.
Much more frequently, you're right. Much more frequently here. Well, much more frequently
there, but that's usually a top down. That's usually pitching forward and landing and having
it be that way. But what happens more commonly than the SC joint, the sternoclebicular joint,
is just a clavicle fracture, which are ubiquitous. And that just fractures somewhere, you know,
over there. And then we fix them some and we don't fix others. But in those heel. But the joint,
that weird little joint is very important. It's not common, but it's not rare. So let's talk
briefly about a total shoulder replacement. I think a lot of people are pretty familiar with
a total knee replacement and total hip replacement. To me, the hip replacement has been one of the
modern marvels of orthopedic surgery in the last 30 years. When I think back to when I was in
medical school, that was a brutal procedure. And today, these patients getting total hip
replacements, I mean, they're laughing at everybody else. They do outpatient. Yeah. I mean,
they walk out of the door. It is an outpatient procedure. I still don't, I have to save that
for another discussion. I don't understand how that procedure is so easy today. First off,
what is the indication for the total shoulder replacement? And then secondly, let's talk
briefly about what is actually being replaced and what that recovery is like and what limitations
exist after the fact. That's great. It is also an outpatient procedure unless you have
comorbidities. I do most of these. Okay. And I can even use a smaller picture now because
the types of implants we're using now have evolved significantly.
Yeah. All right. So when you've worn down the cartilage completely, either on one or both of
the surfaces, then that's incompatible with good function, usually because of pain. And you ask,
what is the primary indication? It's pain. I don't care. I see patients all the time who come in,
who have the ugliest x-rays you've ever seen to your point about the cervical spine,
which is so important. They have no pain and they can do whatever they want to do. As you know,
that the scapula, the scapula thoracic motion can give us a lot of functions. So they're fine.
And I just occasionally they'll say, Hey, you know, I'm going on a trip where I want to be able to
play golf for three weeks or two weeks with my, you know, family. Maybe could you give me an
injection? Sure. Give them a cortisone shot and they rock on that. They get three months,
four months of relief, and then they keep going. So it's only the very active people who need to
be able to do separate certain things. And age is not a factor. My oldest patient who I did shoulder
replacements on quite a long time ago was the, um, she was 97 and she was spry and healthy,
walked the streets of Manhattan up and down. She actually still worked at 97. I won't say
where cause it might give it away. She was the oldest and longest standing employee of a, of a,
of a famous place. And she, um, and after I did that, I did them back to back and I'd see her on
the street walking down 57th street and she'd say, Hey doc, I'm doing great. And she was 97, 98, 99.
I lost track of that point. So it totally changed her life cause she couldn't use her arms because
they were hurting so much. So age is not a factor to your, and just to be clear, was her arthritis
the result of likely a labral repair that never, like what caused so much degeneration in her?
Some people just get it. It's no different than you. Oh, so it's not constant subluxations
necessarily that are necessary. These, you know, some people just have, I, one of my attendings
when I was in either med school residency said, yeah, it's like a paint job. You can have a paint
job. That's a Mercedes. You can have a paint job. That's a Ford Pinto. And I'm not saying anything
derogatory to Pinto's, uh, but you know, the, the, the quality of the paint job can, uh, what you're
born with. And, um, so that's the main thing. And that's the main source of garden variety,
osteoarthritis of the shoulder. And then there are the athletes who are separate categories based on
what you're wearing. So, um, the youngest you've ever done this on the youngest I've ever done a
replacement, a full replacement, almost 55. Yeah. I don't, I, I'm usually we'll do a work around.
I saw a guy, um, about 15 years ago who came to me, he had, he had pretty, you can see it visually,
but it wasn't terrible. And he said he was been booked for a replacement. I said, look,
you're a little young and he was, he was about 48. And I said, you're too young for me. I wouldn't,
I think we should at least give something else a shot. I said, what I would probably do,
even though the data is not great. It's one of the few things I do that I know,
but I tell him at the outset that you have about a 50% chance of getting better.
And that's just a scope clean out. We know they have arthritis. They don't have instability and
just try to clean them out and buy them some more time, kick this can as far down the road as
possible. About 15 years later, he came back to me showing me shoulder motion was fine. He had,
his x-rays had an advanced and he came for something else. So that was an example of what
I, you know, try to do, but he can't always effect that, but that was just an anecdotal
and it's worth doing. It's such a minimal operation, right? No recovery. So, um,
and oftentimes if people have bilateral osteoarthritis, they, um, they don't,
they don't need both sides done. They're happy with one side to, they have a good one that they
reach over dominant arm or something like that. But an example of sort of a very active to our
point about physiology and biologic age and so forth. A really wonderful athletic woman who was
an avid sailing. She sailed in regattas, raced, uh, still at the age of about 75. She was still
going racing all the time, pulling lanyards, et cetera. And she said, I can't do this anymore.
I just can't do it. And I want to keep doing it. Can I keep doing that? And I said, sure. So I
replaced both of her shoulders and she, how much do you separate those two operations by? She was
about four months apart. Yeah. It was kind of more. She said, I'm going to give up a year
of the sailing. Yeah. I want to get back to it. So, um, you could do them a little closer together
if you want. Um, and she, uh, she's still sailing. You still, so, so let's go over the anatomy here
or the replacement. Obviously there's two pieces to it, right? There's the, the humeral side and
the glenoid side. Yeah. So, um, well, you know what? Let me, I'm going to draw another picture
real fast that will show what a arthritic shoulder looks like. And then that'll help. Yeah. I'll do
it small. So in the little picture, uh, to the left, I've drawn an arthritic shoulder, not well,
but I've drawn it to make a point. So it kind of, the head kind of flattens out. You have no space
in there at all. You get a bone spur down here. You get some spurring around the perimeter of the
glenoid and all of that conspires to greatly diminish the motion of the shoulder and,
and cause pain. So they get two, there's two reasons they come dysfunction because they can't
do what they desperately want to do, whether it's recreational or work sometimes. And number two,
pain, uh, either one of those is a solid indication for it when the radiographic findings are there.
And if we do that, then what we do is, is go in and now we do these through incision that big,
you know, uh, it's just a very small interior incision and take down part or all or part or
most of the subscapularis, the tendon in the front, we have to have a window in. Now we can work
through the interval, the space between the super space and the subscapularis, but only if it's a
more limited replacement. And, but anyway, you take some of that off, you have a window there,
you have retractors in and you use an oscillating saw and just take that arthritic head off of there
like that. And all the bone spurs. Then, um, with that space that that creates, you use another
retractor, push the head, the, the shaft and what's left of the shaft, what's left of the shaft away.
And then you get in and work on the glenoid and you ream that down to where it's all smooth,
get the bone spurs out of the perimeter and then put in this little, um, high density polyethylene
solid ultra high molecular weight polyethylene. Exactly. Very durable. I mean, you wear out.
It's the same thing. That's the tibial plateau. Exactly. Exactly. Same. It's great. And then
these have little pegs, you drill holes, you maybe, uh, usually cement those in just a little bit,
uh, some are press fit, but usually cemented in a little bit, just that part. And it just,
it's a perfect, nice new Teflon surface for them, this cobalt chromium or whatever,
alloy it is, uh, for the head and you, the, you know, the bone has a central core and you clean
that out, get it fixed. And this is press fit. We don't cement these anymore unless people have
really bad bone or supervision, just press fit it into that can sell us bone. And, uh, and it's super
solid. The rotator cuff is kept intact. The rotator cuff is still intact on top. You're working
around that reattach the subscapularis. And so if you're going to transect the subscapularis,
what is the least traumatic place to do it completely within the muscle I'm assuming?
Yeah. No, no, actually on the tendon where it inserts. Oh, you have to because you're reattaching.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That makes sense. And, uh, we leave a sleeve so we can suture tendon to tendon,
but then we also put this heavy suture into bone. So you get bone reinforcement and you've got tendon
to tendon healing. You also, by doing that, you maintain the normal length. So you get. So the
only thing, I mean, this is oversimplification, but the biggest thing this person is missing is a
labrum. Yes. Yeah. And they don't really need it. So what stabilizes this joint? The fact that it's
arthritic, it's already stabilized itself, unless it's a weird dislocating joint, you know, which is
a different entity and you have to address that differently for the garden variety one, they've
already kind of stiffened up all the tissues, even though. So what does their capsule look like when
you go in typically? It's thick, super thick, super thick. We resect some of it even. It's so thick.
Okay. It's kind of space occupying almost. And what is this person's in a good case? Yeah. What
is the limitation on this person a year out from surgery? Yeah. Really nothing except heavy weights.
Like I don't want people doing bench press. I don't want them doing the, you know, iron cross
type things. And they're using not, I had one patient. Can they throw a ball? Yeah. Yeah. I think
throw a ball. They can play catch. I'm saying they can play catch with their grandkids and play catch
with their grandkids for sure. They can play tennis. They can play tennis and play tennis and play
golf. They shoot a basketball. Yeah. Can they swim? Yes. Oh yeah. Oh yeah. That's one of the big,
the big ones. People love swimming. You know, later in life, it's such good. Yeah. Fantastic.
And they can swim until they're a hundred and, and you can absolutely, oh yeah, you can swim
until the cows come home here. Yeah. So this is just another one of those game changing operations.
Right. Yeah. But it's a, it's different than the hips and the knees. The hips and the knees allow
people to live in the world again. These are game changer quality of life things. Yeah. And I won't
do them if I know I can manage them and kick the can down the road and just inject them once
a year with cortisone. I want them, I want them to be dragging that arm in. I want them to be
saying, you got to do it now. I'm not getting enough relief from the cortisone and do it.
Yeah. All right. Well, let's, let's pivot now to talk about another piece of anatomy down the arm,
which is the elbow. So let's take a moment and just go back to the anatomy. Do you want to draw a
little sketch of how the humorous lines up with the ulnar and the radius? Very much so. All right.
So the big diagram is looking straight at the antecubital fossa. And then obviously the side
diagram is, is showing the arm flexed. So walk people through what these, these three bones are
and then the sort of overlaying muscles. So this is, as you said, the, the, the front of the elbows
here, the humorous bone, which is the arm bone is coming down. And you see, it's a super weird
undulating structure there, which makes it intrinsically quite stable. So much different
because there's more to dig into. Exactly. There's all these fun little, you know,
almost jigsaw puzzle pieces that stick together. We have the radial head, which is the rotating
bone of the forearm. And then we have the ulna, which is the fixed straight bone of the forearm.
And then we have, what's, what's cool about the elbow is the tendons that go down to the forearm
into the hand originate above the joint, more or less, right. Close juxto, articulate close to
joint, but above it. And then the ones that go from, from the shoulder and arm down, uh, attach
below the joint. And this is the biceps tendon here, the big biceps muscle here, the biceps
and attaching to the radius. And we'll talk about that. This is the lateral side, the outside of
your elbow. And the, the blue is the muscle tendon units that are attached there, anchored to this
little circle or oval. And then the red part is where tearing typically occurs in tennis elbow
on the inside of the elbow, where our funny bone nerve is the funny bone nerve is the ulnar nerve.
And that's, that's the green structure in cross section. And then overlying that as the muscles,
the flexor pronator muscles that, that help bend the elbow and, and pronate the forearm.
And those can tear around in this region. And that's actually where we get golfer's elbow and
what it's known as golfer's elbow, which is medial epicondylitis, medial. And then the lateral side,
which is the tennis elbow is lateral epicondylitis. And those are the most, these three, the biceps
tendon. And these two are the most common tendon injuries by far. The fourth, which is less common,
is shown in the lateral, which is the triceps coming down and attaching to the tip of our elbow.
We talked about the bursa before, and there is a bursa right here that lives over the tip of our
elbow and we can get the big golf ball size or filling of fluid. And that's the olecranon bursa.
And so, um, I think it's beyond what we're talking about today to go into the fractures,
but any parts of these can be broken. And, uh, the elbow is a very finicky joint. You can see because
it's stable because of those undulating surfaces, but because they're undulating,
there's less wiggle room, there's less. And they, if you don't get those things perfect,
when you fix them, they can quickly lead to arthritis. And some of the, even the subtle
fracture patterns that happen and aren't seen or appreciated can lead to rapid destruction of the
joint. So it's a finicky joint. It is also, oh, I've drawn this blue structure here,
which is a very thick ligament on the inside of the elbow. That is the Tommy John ligament. It's
not really Tommy John and even, uh, well, I'll clarify that in a minute, but that's the medial
collateral ligament or the owner collateral ligament. And that's the one that's torn and
throwing athletes. Um, and that's can be a career ending except now because of the reconstructive
surgery, it's generally not. Um, so let's talk just briefly about why the, um, lateral epicondyle,
if there's inflammation in that tendon, we sort of think of that as the, the injury a tennis player
gets, whereas inflammation in the medial tendon is more attributed to what a golfer gets. Of course,
people who have never played tennis or golf often get these things, but it could be illustrative
just to explain the movement patterns. Great. So those are not dissimilar from the super
splenatus tendon where they have a little ringing out and they, they kind of can become degenerative
and partially tear. Just like we talked about rotator cuffs, there are tons of people walking
down the streets with partial tears and those tendons and they're asymptomatic use patterns are
significant for that. The reason the lateral was historically associated and called tennis elbow
is because of one handed back hands. It's a much less mechanically sound and it's, we have less
strength with our external rotators than we have with our pectoralis and our subscapularis for
forehand shots. So it's under more stress and, and you can get them at any age, but the sweet spot of
seeing treating this is 40 to 60, 40 to 60. Now that, that is creeping up to the 70s and so
forth because again, people are so active. So that's why it's been associated with tennis elbow.
Ironically now I'm seeing justice in tennis players and competitive tennis players. I'm seeing
justice much medial epicondylitis, which is traditionally golfer's elbow. And the reason
is because everybody is trying to hit massive topspin and they are hit using their pronator
so much more than they used to when we were, when I was a kid and playing, I try to hit topspin now.
And, and so that's a reason why it's stimulated more. Why does the golfer get it? I don't play
golf. So I don't appreciate it enough. So historically, historically,
even though golfers were getting it, I don't know why, because you're not supposed to be,
it's overheating with your, your trailing arm. Most people play right-handed and they were getting
it on their right medial epicondylitis because they were overheating, hitting stomps, hitting rocks,
you know, duffing. And it was that Joel, again, the eccentric load on these tenants, which our
on these tenants, which our tenants don't like, but I'm seeing now because people are hitting so
much harder, they're hitting bigger clubs, especially drivers and such, they're getting
more left leading arm lateral epicondylitis in golfers. On the leading arm. On the leading arms.
Because that, and that, that's more logical actually. Yeah. But they're just trying to hit
harder and farther. And you know, once these big hitters are on there, they're trying to mimic them
and so forth. So is the first line treatment for that rest followed by, you know, rest and NSAIDs
presumably followed by cortisone and things of that nature. Right. So the first line of treatment
is always is rest, good stretching, just like you stretch your hamstrings to keep from tearing
them as frequently or injuring them as frequently. And, and usually just NSAIDs by mouth. If they're
on, rarely do I use physical therapy for these formally because it's just not much to do.
But if the, if they're just too painful to even, some people wake up in the morning, they can't
even straighten their elbow out. They're so painful. They're so spongy and really inflamed.
So those, I still don't splint them, but I have them stretch. But more often because they can't
use their arm, I will go ahead and give them kind of a half dose of cortisone just to cool everything
down. Yeah. You injected me probably four or five years ago when I was sort of in the transition of
really learning how to control my scapula and had sort of overcooked too many pullups. Yeah. And
all this pull up pain was translating into tennis elbow. Yeah. I was surprised at, and it was stubborn.
I mean, I, this thing, I, I came to you after six months of pain, but that one injection cooled it
off. That never hurt again. Yeah. Because basically I had already fixed the underlying
movement pattern. I just needed to cool the fire off. Is that a common scenario? It really is. It
really is. I, and again, I don't operate on, I mean, because it's so common, I ended up doing a
lot of these procedures, but I don't operate on, I'd say one out of five at the most, 20% at the
most. Most people get better. And so operating on the lateral versus the medial side, what are the
indications? Yeah. The indications are the same, failing conservative treatment, a lot of stretching,
a lot of strengthening. A lot of people get these, in your case, it was mechanics overdoing,
but a lot of people get these because they're, they're getting back into something that they
haven't been doing in a long time and they overdo it. And it can be just weights and weightlifting,
but honestly, it's something as mundane. I'll see these after people have gone traveling for two
weeks, just lifting their luggage, dragging their luggage around. So it's all comers, but
the theme is that conditioning, if they've had it chronically, not in your case, of course, but
a lot of people come in and they're already kind of weak. They don't have strong grip strength. They
don't have good tone. And so strengthening is a critical component. If I can get, if they can
squeeze my, I have one of my devices, if they can squeeze that without just a little pain, then I
just have them do that first, stretching and strengthening. And, and, and sometimes that'll
cure it and often it'll cure it. Then, but if they can't squeeze it without undue pain, I give them
a little dose of cortisone. If it's chronic like yours was, then there's not that much to do. Your
fit, your, your gut great tone and you've got full motion. So it's only, yeah, give it a little
booster dose just to knock it out. We think sometimes we haven't ever done the study to prove
it, but we think sometimes just sticking the needle in a few times kind of stimulates a healing.
Yeah. I've certainly seen a lot of anecdotal stuff around dry needling, just getting the dry needle
in there. I believe in that. Yeah. And just, uh, increasing the influx of inflammatory, uh,
uh, cells and cleaning up getting macrophages to come and clean it up. Yeah. So outside of fractures,
how often are you seeing acute injuries to the elbow that ultimately are surgical cases?
So one of the common ones is the, um, middle age, but very active fit person who
maybe had a little antecedent elbow pain or forearm pain. They didn't quite know what it was,
but they did workarounds and then they ruptured their distal biceps. And so they get a Popeye
muscle. It's all weird and even quivering and they come in and they go, Oh my God, you've got to do
something. And, um, the cool thing about the bicep, we think of the biceps as, as being, you know,
we do biceps, but it's an elbow flexor and it is a secondary elbow flexor, but it's the primary
supinator of the form. So people come in and they lose when they, when they tear their biceps,
they don't lose that much flexion strength, but they lose most of their supination strength. So
if they are used to turning screwdrivers, wrenches, um, even surgical instruments, maybe
depending on what they do, um, then it can be really disabling. So that factors into the physical
exam then, doesn't it? Oh yeah. And it's funny, they'll come in, they won't be painful to say,
I think it's better. And yeah, I've got this, but I can live with the deformity,
which I don't care about the formity either. Um, and then I will pronate them to wrap that tendon
kind of around the radius. And then I have them pull up like they're doing a pronated curl
and they scream. And it's just, you get it just isolated. And that's a very good point about that.
And then you test their supination. They didn't know that they didn't have any supination strength
and you test their other side and they can lift you off the table. And then this side,
they can't even do it. So, um, so when you surgically repair that, are you reattaching
the tendon? Yeah. Same place. So it's like a tendinesis. Yeah. Yeah. It's, it's, it's great.
It's great operation. So that's a good outcome operation. Oh yeah. Uh, I had a guy on the other
day, it just looks just like you, you know, good, good, strong arms and everything. And he's doing
this all the time and he ruptured his and, um, he came back in for, uh, actually with his son.
And he said, he said, man, if you need anybody to, he said, my arm is stronger than it's been
in a long time. And that's, I'll speak to that. But he said, he said, yeah, if you need somebody
to, to, to call anybody to talk to him about how great this operation is, just let me know.
But he was, he said he was, a lot of them say, you know, I feel almost like I'm stronger than
I was before. Well, you're only putting it back where it came from, but they probably had a
partial tear for a long time. They're working around, they were little deconditioned in their
biceps. They were compensating for the, with their brachialis, the big muscle underneath that.
And, um, so that, and then they get even stronger because they have a good tendon again.
Wow. We talked, you want to just briefly talk about the Tommy John, which again has kind of
revolutionized major league baseball. So when this tears, um, and this tears, the, uh,
on the medial side, you all of, and in fact, it's super physiologic torques that ligament is subjected
to super physiologic in throwers and high level throwers who are throwing 90 plus miles per hour.
It is subjected to such, such forces, traction forces that it will rupture.
And the way they keep from rupturing in general is by fitness, by steady long-term fitness.
And that's flexor pronator fitness, that shoulder, streakness, uh, shoulder strengthening and, uh,
biceps, triceps, and so forth. By strengthening everything around it, you can protect that ligament.
And if you don't, then it can rupture because it's being subjected repetitively over and over
over again, year after year to super physiologic loads. And, um, so when it ruptures, it's easy
instantaneously. They lose it, they can throw, but they lose 10 miles per hour on their fast ball.
They just, it just immediately downgrades their ability to throw.
That's so interesting because most of us wouldn't, I mean, like, I don't think I could throw a ball
50 miles an hour. So to think like, does that mean I would go from 50 to 40? No. Or it just
means I could never get, I wouldn't notice it. Is that the difference? Yeah. And so we don't,
that's the, that's the common fallacy of people coming in all the time and they, all of us playing
tennis, uh, playing, uh, certainly golf, throwing balls, playing catch. We don't need it. We don't
need the ligament. So that is literally an operation that is only designed for the most elite
throwers. Yes. Period. Awesome. And that's a common misconception. Of course, one of the,
are there some shady people, sorry to interrupt you, are there some shady people out there that
are doing that operation on non-athletes? Sure. Sure. But more importantly, and I say this,
I'm sure they have love in their heart, but there's some shady parents too, who will bring their kids
in who say, you know, we know our kid has this great potential. Can you do, because the stories
about Tommy John surgery, which this is not Tommy John surgery anymore. What was done on Tommy John
was not the same operation. It was the same ligament, but it's totally different now.
But it's good to refer to it as that. I, it's nothing, the guy who invented it was brilliant.
But parents will come in and say, you know, my, my kid needs five miles per hour on the fast ball.
And because so many people like the biceps have had partial tears, they've finally torn, had a
reconstruction and they gain six or seven miles faster than they've thrown as an adult. It's,
it's because they had a partial tear and never could get that final extra velocity. And then once
they have a reconstruction, they can. And so that travels through the chat rooms and lore. And then
parents come in and say, Hey, can, and their kid has no problem. And they say, can, can we do it,
Tommy John so that we can get more velocity. And you have to explain to them that there's
nothing wrong with their kid's elbow. There's just something that the kid is not destined to be,
you know, Nolan Ryan. Yeah. Interesting. So, and it's, it's with best of intentions,
but you know, things get distorted. What about the tricep tendon? Does that ever,
what, what type of injury will, will injure that tendon to the point where it's coming off the
electron on? You already know. It's what you, you talk about all the time. It's the eccentric loading.
So it's the, they almost always tear falling, skiing where they're trying to stop themselves
from smashing their face. Yeah. Oh wow. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. They rip off like that. I see them
every winter and how clean a break is it? It varies. Some people, if they've had chronic
condition, we'll have a little bone spurs in there and it'll pull off kind of part of the bone spur
and everything. Usually it pulls off the bone or leaves a little stub there. And it's pretty clean
usually, but man, it is the triceps is a huge muscle. Bigger than biceps. Yeah. Yeah. Huge muscle.
And so it's really disabling. People can't even push up out of chairs. You have to fix those.
Yeah. I mean, you have to, I mean, there's, they're not ruptured in sedentary, non low functioning
people. They rupture in active people. You've got to fix them. Okay. So maybe now we could just kind
of have you examine my elbow and go through all of these planes of motion. Cause obviously you want
to know how I'm flexing, how I'm extending supinating and pronating and my strength,
eccentrically and concentrically, I guess. Yeah, that's right. And in the elbow, it's,
it's very distinct. There are very specific stresses you can put on the elbow that will
guide you, guide us directly to what is hurting. And again, it goes back to a lot of middle-aged
athletic people have some changes in the lateral epicondylate, condon muscles, the medial epicondyl
muscles, some even in the triceps and the distal biceps. You have to isolate those and make sure
they're symptomatic. Okay. So as we were discussing, the elbow is a super weird, complicated joint
and there's a lot of things going on there. So let's cover that a little bit and see what's,
what's going on. So one of the cool things about, as we talked about is that carrying angle. And I'm
going to look and see, do you have symmetry? Do you have any swelling? Do you have any things that
look atypical? Well, I can tell you one that's super easy to just to see. If you rupture your
distal biceps, as many people who are doing CrossFit, being pushed by people that are half their age in
the gym and being pushed too much, they rupture the distal biceps here and then your biceps
contour shifts up. So if we come right here and we look, you have a nice distal, distal muscle
belly that's way, way down, which is what you want that level. You're about two finger breasts
will go up for finger breasts and it just, it's disconnected. And what's weird about that is
it's not. So if I test you in supination like that, whether you have a good biceps or not,
you're going to be super strong and it's not going to hurt because that's mostly brachialis,
that underlying broad, strong muscle that gives us our basic curling capability. The biceps
is cool because, and we can watch your biceps because it's well defined, is we go from pronation
supination with a little resistance. I'll just resist a little bit. You go there, you can see it
ball up a little bit. So it's contracting and pulling up. That biceps is the primary supinator.
So I'm testing that now. If I have you supinate and it hurts or it's weak, then we know something's
going on right there. Secondarily, if I have you do a pronated curl in that position, that will hurt
like crazy if you have even a partial tear of the distal biceps. In that pain, people say,
well, it's not my biceps, it's down in here, but that's where it attaches. It's way down in here.
It attaches to the radius and rotates the radius. So that's a super cool, super great, easy way to
chest. Now, if we look at the lateral epicondyle, we talked about tennis elbow, lateral epicondylitis,
that's down here. Very pinpoint. People say, how did you know where it was? Well, it's not hard
because that's where everything happens. And it's right there. The ECRB tendon lies deep right next
to the bone and it will often be swollen, spongy, very tender. So we palpate that. We can see it,
we sponge it. And sometimes I can feel if it's a medium sized partial thickness tear, I can feel
the defect in there just with my thumb. And people don't like that. You don't keep torturing it. Then
with the elbow straight, I have you pull up against me and like that. And that will hurt badly.
Now, for some reason, when we flex this way and pull up again, it hurts a little less. I don't
even know why that is. I've never been able to figure that out. But both of those will hurt with
tennis elbow. And that's a pretty simple, straightforward diagnosis. Now on the inside,
I'll use this elbow. The medial epicondyle, which is golfer's elbow, is it tends to be even more
tender. And I think that's because the ulnar nerve lies so close to it. And it's very spongy,
very swollen, very tender right there. It's a little bit different anatomically in terms of
the way the tendon inserts. So these need surgery much less. But man, when they're on fire, they
really hurt. People can't even press, you know, it's this movement here. That's what really
causes that to hurt there. Now in your case, and we're going to talk about the nerves, I think
later. But you have, I want to feel your nerve and I can, you can see that I can roll your ulnar nerve,
the funny bone nerve up over that medial epicondyle bone. So you have a very mobile
ulnar nerve. And we'll talk about that a little more. But that's a normal variant. And that's
just what it is. And that's fine. Okay, let's see now, very importantly in the elbow, we want to
look at range of motion. It's very common for athletes, long time weight lifters, football
players, you know, all sorts of people to have a contracture of the elbow. So you have nice,
full, mild hyperextension, not dramatic. If you have genetic laxity, sometimes that'll go back
45 degrees. You don't, it's just nice, full, easy motion, minus, I would call it minus 10 degrees
at the most. And then I look at your flexion, which is normally up around 150 degrees and so forth,
again, from that zero position. Very important to look at that. We need, we know a functional arc
is about a hundred degree arc, we can function well, but we have to get up to about 130 to be
able to get to our hair and face and mouth. And so that's a common result of minor fractures in
the elbow, inflammation in the elbow, and so forth. Professional pitchers, almost all of them have
about a 15 to 20 degree elbow contracture from all the loads that have been put on the elbow,
and they're functional, they're fine. We're going to talk about the nerves later. So that's really
the, oh, the triceps. So the triceps attaches here on the olecranon and you've got a big,
well-developed triceps here and we've got, we've got your triceps inserting there. Now we can
watch that and people who are doing a lot of weight lifting, especially been out of it for
a long time or they're doing a lot of pushups things, that's where they'll get the triceps
tendonitis or a partial rupture. You talked about the eccentric loading. If you land hard and you
have that eccentric load, you can tear off part or all the triceps. That's a miserable, always
surgical diagnosis because you just can't do anything. You can't even push up out of a chair.
You need that big triceps. So we look at that. Now, if you just have tendonitis, what I'll do is
hyperflex and then have you push against me like this, push hard. That hurts like crazy if you have
any inflammation there because there's such a biomechanical disadvantage when it's trying to
extend from a very flexed position. You know better than me. And so what do you think is the ideal,
since you do a lot of this and talked to a lot of your patients about it, what do you think is the,
I don't know the answer to this, the ideal position for doing triceps workouts?
I mean, I think the literature actually suggests that you want to be in an extended position of
the humerus or flexed positions. You want a humeral flexed so that to stretch the
stretch the triceps, you want the tricep to be under a stretch. So it's better than doing them
down here. Correct. Interesting. So basically if you're on your back doing like a skull pressure,
or if you're using a pulley, you're doing it kind of overhead. That's informative for me.
It just assumes your shoulders can tolerate it. So for example, when I was recovering from my
surgery, the only thing I could do, I'm having a towel between my arms. I'm doing this way,
and I'm doing this way. So it's really just a functioning area. Okay, that's great. I did not
know that. And I hadn't really thought about that before. That's good enough. Okay. So that's
pretty much all of the muscle tendon units that are commonly injured around the elbow.
All right. So we've got the shoulder and the elbow behind us. That leaves us with the hand
and the wrist, which is effectively how we mediate contact with the outside world and our extremities.
I would say this to me is like a black box. I didn't actually do a rotation in orthopedics or
plastics, so no exposure to that. Now in general surgery, you cross cover plastics sometimes, so
new enough to know what not to do when someone came in with hand trauma. But it's obviously
a highly specialized field. You've done a fellowship just in hand. It basically seems
anybody who wants to operate on the hand has to not only complete the orthopedics program or
plastics program, but then go completely do that dedicated program. That's right. Yeah. I mean,
I suppose you could pick it up, but to be able to do that in certainly a big city or a dense
metropolitan area, you would need to have fellowship training. And it's just there's so
much as we talked about before, just like in the shoulder, just like in biologics, just like in
everything you do, there's such an explosion of information. It's hard to keep track of everything.
Before we get into the hand, what do we know today about the hand in terms of repair or injury
that you didn't know when you finished residency? And I don't mean you personally, but I just mean
wasn't known then that is known today. You know, that's a fascinating topic because well before
I started starting in the 50s and 60s, they had developed microvascular techniques. And that's
really the, that was the holy grail of so much in the hand. You could have a laceration or a war
injury or something. And there really wasn't much to do for many of those injuries, especially nerve
and blood vessel related. So you would do a lot of amputations. You do it just were not reconstructable.
And so the war experience actually did develop that. And one of my forebears,
Jay William Littler, who was one of the most famous, if not the most famous living hand surgeon for
for a few decades in the world, was exposed to that at Valley Forge and elsewhere during the war.
And that's how they, that he and other really luminaries in the field developed these techniques
that brought us where we are today. I'd say the most significant advancement since I
graduated and went into private practice has been the hand transplantation, the complete
hand transplantation, which is a very, very, as you know, it involves general surgeons, it involves
hand surgeons, it involves so many, a huge team to be able to do that and to achieve that. And,
and the results are mixed. But how many have been done? I don't even know now. But it was as recently
as five years ago, only a few had been done. So it's all been in these last several years that,
that these teams have been built up at the larger institutions to be able to handle that. But even
there, it's fraught with peril in that you have to have a perfect patient, physiologically speaking,
and you know, co-morbidities greatly decrease the likelihood of success there. And, and it requires
a huge investment for the patients themselves. And so even a single hand amputation is not nearly
as reasonable of an indication as a bilateral hand amputee. Those are the ones that generally
can qualify and they have to meet all the physiologic parameters and so forth. So it's,
it's, it's, you know, I don't even know that much about it. One of my partners has been on one of
those teams and he knows much more about it, Luke Catalano. And where is the, where is the,
are they joined at the mid point of the wrist? Right. Is that the distal, distal forearm?
I'm sorry, the distal forearm, right. Where you can get that, you're beyond that transition zone
and you can link up tendon to tendon usually. And then of course the nerves can be linked as well.
And so it's, yeah, it's fascinating. So that's the biggest. And it's the same immunologic process.
You have to HLA match these things because they're all cadaveric, of course. Exactly. Exactly. And
that's, as you well know, and you know way more about that than I do because of the general
surgical background, but obviously the immuno immunologic suppression to allow these things to
not be a graft versus host disease. And it's, it's, it's a wild, wild time really. And we will get
better. I think the other thing, the only other thing that's changed a lot is that relates so
much to the hand. As you mentioned, it's how we interact with the world is the, you know,
spinal implants and the various types of full muscle transfers that can, that can restore
function in the hand for someone who previously had no ability to control even a prosthesis,
these electro electrical prostheses now that are linked to the brain. And so it's, it's, it's cool.
So what type of injuries does someone have in the forearm that are there injuries where they will
take a muscle from the leg or something like a sartorius and attach it there? Absolutely. Yeah.
Yeah. And it's really intended to just give some primitive function back to be able to flex the
elbow, for instance, or extend the elbow or flex the wrist. And so it's really more the elbow more
than anything because most of these injuries that people, patients can still control the shoulder
can position the arm somewhere. But as you know, I mean, if you just even forget about a very
devastating injury, but if you just have an elbow extension contracture where you cannot flex better
than 90 degrees, you can't get your hand to your mouth, to your hair, to your face. You can't do
a lot. There's many, many limitations to that. So, and that's just to get through an average day,
not anything specialized such as playing an instrument or throwing a football or something.
So when we talked about the shoulder and the elbow, do you have a sense of what fraction of
those injuries that require surgical intervention are the result of an acute trauma versus a chronic
injury where, now obviously a lot of the chronic stuff is on top of an acute event, like a
subluxation that happened, you know, that over and over and over again leads to, for example,
my injury. But do you have a sense of like what that division is?
Yes. And the division I do, but it also varies depending on where you are. In my practice now,
I took trauma call for a couple of decades, but I no longer take. So I see cold trauma that still
needs plenty of surgery, but it's not that it's not acute, it's subacute and then needs to be
fixed in a delayed fashion. So if you are in a practice such as a county hospital where there's
trauma coming in from the hot, the, the, whether it's hunters, whether it's highways and et cetera,
then you're doing a lot, you're a much higher percentage of your day and your week is spent
repairing acute traumatic, often poly trauma injuries. And I've been there and done that, but
the, and someone who has a mature metropolitan type practice, that's, it's more in the area of 50-50.
There's plenty of, of arthritic conditions of wear and tear conditions of, of whether it's from,
you know, any sort of gym work or, you know, getting back into various forms of exercise or
the weekend warrior phenomenon. And those are sometimes injuries, but they're not dramatic,
traumatic injuries. And then there are the people that are falling off the scooters and the, and
water skiing, dislocating their shoulders, all, all that spectrum. But the actual, the, the actual
acute, any, and something as mundane as, as cutting avocados. I see tons of nerve injuries and
tendon injuries in the palm. The Sunday morning bagel injury. And so, so, but, but it's usually
spread pretty evenly between arthritic and sort of sports related ruptures and injuries. And then
fractures and dislocations and ruptures due to traumatic events. Well, if there's a,
well, if the bony anatomy of the shoulder is a little more straightforward, it starts to get a
little more complicated in the elbow and it gets a little more rigid. I mean, the hand is really
complex. So how do you, how do you even go about beginning to explain the anatomy of the hand,
which has, I don't know, how many bones does the hand have? Well, you know, that, that even varies.
But if you think about it, you have, you have five fingers and you have in those each finger has
three bones except for the thumb, which has two. So you there, you've got the 12 plus two is 14.
And then you have the, the next layer, which are the metacarpals. And that's of course,
five of those. And then the carpal bones, which are all these small bones. We, we had a resident
that used to make fun of hand surgeons who would say, never operate on a bone you can swallow.
And so he was just in a fun way, pillaring the, the fine sort of smaller caliber things that
we're dealing with in the hand and wrist region. And the wrist has the bones that are held tightly
together. And there are, there are multiple bones there. Some of, there are often what are called
coalitions where they're fused together. So that's why I mean that it varies. But the, the wrist owns
the one bone that is the hardest to heal in the body. And that's the scapoid bone, because it's,
it's like a carob coated cashew. It's almost all encompassed by cartilage. So there's only a couple
of little areas where tiny blood vessels can get into that bone. And unlike almost all the other,
if not all the other bones in our body, the, we don't have what we call anti-grade flow into that
bone. It leaving the heart going down through the arteries and the capillaries and going into
the bone from point A distally to point B, it goes in retrograde. So if you, if you crack that
bone in the middle at baseline, it has very little blood supply. Then you crack it and you probably
disrupt the blood. Exactly. And so there's a high risk of non-union. It takes the average bone in
the body in an adult takes six weeks to heal. And these generally take 10 to 12 weeks to heal the
scapoid bones. And what's the common injury that breaks the scapoid? Yeah, there's, there, it's
mainly a hard fall with the, just the right position of the wrist where it's leveraging on that. And
it's the scapoid spans the two rows of bones in the wrist that we call the, the distal row and the
proximal row of these arcs of bones. And, um, and it spans that. So it gets leveraged on in a certain
way with certain positions and then a directed force. Usually it's a wrist extension force.
And does that patient typically present with a lot of pain or? That's a great question. So no,
often they know they injured their wrist and they'll get some swelling there, but it's not that bad.
And there's nothing, there's no great distortion of the wrist. So that's not, when you, when you
fracture your distal radius and it's like a ball, it's up and it looks like a dinner fork and you
know, something's wrong and you, you know, you, sometimes people get a lightheaded and pass out
and they just look at their wrist. This doesn't happen with the scapoid. And, and it's often
young athletes, right? So they don't, they shake it off. They shake it off. They're used to pain
and then they come in often they'll come in at six weeks. They can't lift weights. They can't
do a clean and jerk. They can't shuck somebody, you know, on the offensive line. And then that,
then they get evaluated and we find the scapoid fracture and we've already lost six weeks there.
And if, am I remembering correctly, is the scapoid fracture, the one that's really easy to miss on an
X-ray, you kind of need the MRI to see it. Yeah. Yeah. Or is it a CT? Which one is the
modality? MRI is where we detect occult hidden fractures of the, of the scapoid. And, and why
is that by the way? Because normally CT is the imaging of choice for bone. Great question. It's
just that you don't have enough. The bone's not big enough. Yeah. And so we can see. So you're
looking for the signal. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You're looking for the fat signal. Yeah. Yeah. That,
that's, and I, and I've, I've seen a number of people who have had that issue missed and a lot
of times they don't even necessarily tie it back to the fall. Right. Right. But it's been long enough.
So, so what is the treatment plan for that patient? So it's evolved a little. Historically,
we treated all of these nonoperatively. And then there was a period when, actually an Australian
fellow named Herbert came up with a really ingenious screw that was, had two sets of threads on it.
And they were different pitch. So when you'd screw it down the middle of the bone and turn it,
and when it engaged both bones, it would actually compress them together because they were different
pitch. And that was called the Herbert screw. And that was a game changer for us to be able to treat,
especially athletes. And show folks where this bone is and where you access it operative. Right.
So the, there are different schools of thought on that. When I was coming out of training,
everybody made an incision down here to fix these in a full incision to expose everything.
You had jigs that you can put those screws down. I do almost all of mine percutaneously
through it. I mean, literally an incision this big, and I'll go either retrograde often
or anti-grade. And it's just a, it's, it's really a 3d effort to just get it in the right position,
get a central core guide wire down. And then, and then you use a little, um, a little drill
hand drilled to drill out that and then put the screw down over the wire. And it's really great
because patients already hardly feel that they've had any surgery. They heal very quickly, faster,
and you can even start movement earlier so that when it is healed, you already have your movement
back. So you're not stiff and then having to do a lot of physical therapy on top of that.
So what are other scenarios when you would not operate on a scaphoid fracture?
There are many, if they're non displaced, then we can expect them to heal.
Would you put a cast on or would you put a, at least a splint? We know that you can just basically,
as long as you mobilize the wrist, even if you leave the thumb, thumb and fingers free,
that these will heal. Um, then you look at comorbidities and you look at life, um, life,
needs. So the athletes often get a screw because they just can get back faster,
even with protection. The, um, surgeons often want to have them fixed, uh,
fixed a number because they just want to get back to be able to operate, which they can do.
And what would be the time course to recovery? If you, let's just say you're in that lucky camp where
the day it falls, you're smart enough to, to, you know, know that it's the scaphoid and you go and
get the MRI, confirm it, you have surgery the next day. How long until you're, um, catching a ball
again? Yeah, catching a ball generally about six weeks for that. Operating if you're a surgeon.
A week. Oh wow. Yeah, it's really fast. So as long as it's not contact, you're doing it within a week.
Right. And that's the nice, that's the, that's the game changer really that we have now.
Um, you, a moment ago alluded to something that is one of the few things I do remember from residency,
which was the position to make this splint. What is it about having the wrist in this position
that, you know, for us general surgeons would be basically, let's just let the hand guys look at
this tomorrow morning. We don't have to call them at two o'clock in the morning if this is a
non-operative or non-urgent issue, but let's at least put them in this safe position. What is it
about that position that's safe? So the, the essentially neutral position, which looks like
actually, have you shown some wrist extension, but it's really neutral in terms of the carpoise.
What that does is that, um, one of the important things it does is when we are in too much flexion
and we see this occasionally where people just aren't thinking about it. They just slap a splint
on and don't really know that what you're talking about is, uh, too much flexion or too much
extension. Then that increases the pressure on the median nerve and the carpal tunnel. So people
can get, especially with some extra swelling from the injury, they can get actually acute carpal
tunnel syndrome that can be quite substantial in those more extreme positions. So a neutral
position is great for that. It's also best for function in terms of just if you're in a splint,
but at least trying to get some finger movement, maybe typing at a keyboard or something, then
that's a good neutral position. I will, on occasion, if I have to mobilize, um, uh, someone, I will,
and they have a unique, uh, a musician, for example, I will immobilize them in the position
they need, for instance, to be able to at least play their electric bass. I just had a patient
the other day who plays both upright bass and electric bass. And so he asked me, I said, well,
how are you? We're just playing electric bass. He said, fine. I said, then show me the position
your hand. I'll put you in that splint in that position. So he's able to keep playing and even
doing gigs that way. So, um, you know, it's, everybody's different. Um, but it's, it's an
important consideration. All right. So what do we need to understand about the anatomy of the radial
bone, ulnar bone, and these two big nerves? I'm guessing the median nerve, if I recall, runs there
and the ulnar nerve runs on the pinky side, correct? That's right. And we'll, we'll go,
we'll see that in our exam shortly. But yes. And then the third nerve, which is completes the hand
is the radial nerve and that's purely sensory along here, but it is important and provides
sensory on the backside of the hand and the thumb and most of the backside of the hand,
but the ulnar nerve, um, you're right. And both of those are at risk for lacerations, um, far, um,
and they're at risk even when you distort the anatomy with through a fracture. And so those
are the two big ways. I kind of remember the median nerve being bigger than I expected. What's
the approximate size of the median nerve? Yeah. So it's, it's a, it's an oval shape and cross section.
And it, it varies obviously on the side. It's about three or four millimeters wide,
by two millimeters deep, right? Even, even bigger. That would be, you know, a smaller
petite person would have about that size. And I've seen them as large as almost a centimeter wide
and four or five millimeters thick in a large hand. Oh yeah. I mean, just insane, which I guess
speaks to the innovation of this unbelievable part of our body that occupies so much of our
homunculus, right? Yes. Yeah. So I've always said this because, uh, you know, I've talked about this
that I've in terms of using meaningful hand use is so important for cognitive development and
wellbeing and sick, over 60% of our higher cortical neurons are devoted just to our hand
through the homunculus. And you know, you've seen that homunculus on the UNI seen it many times,
but it's big ears, um, and you know, big eyes, but huge hands and then a tiny torso, you know,
little shriveled up tiny torso. And so that's what's super cool. So yes, I mean, we need to
keep using our hands to keep our minds vital in whatever form we're doing. And actually some great
studies have been done on that to show what's the effect of just typing at a keyboard. And it doesn't
stimulate our, our, our cortex very much at all, uh, typing, nor does texting, uh, handwriting,
which is an art form, even though it's, doesn't feel like it for, for many of us. Um, but, uh,
handwriting still does stimulate our brain. Uh, they did a study a long time ago at university of,
I believe it's in Virginia, I think, or maybe Indiana. And they looked at kids who were
asked to handwrite versus type, uh, the answers to, uh, essay questions and the kids who were
handwriting used longer sentences, bigger words, more ideas, and, and produce it faster than the
kids who were typing. And they're, and they were measuring their cortical activity and their
core activity was way more with the handwriting. That's digression, but it's important to your
point that, that there's so many nerve endings concentrated in our hands that we really need to,
to keep them functioning and get them back to function as quickly as possible.
So you mentioned already the carpal tunnel. Let's talk about what this carpal tunnel syndrome is.
It's come up a couple of times and, and obviously there's, there's technically what's carpal tunnel
syndrome and then there's the symptoms of it, which can be produced by compression or injury
elsewhere. But, um, what creates the tunnel per se? Yeah. So it's great. It's super cool. When you
look in cross section, if you, if you took a cross section through the hand right here,
the carpal tunnel is created by a Roman arch of bones, just like the Roman arches where that
central core, I can't remember the name of the bone keystone, maybe, uh, it wedges in and keeps
that arch intact. And that's exactly what we have in the reverse. Then we have a tie bar across the
top, which is a very thick transverse carpal ligament, and it holds that together and that creates a,
a just a, a U-shaped, uh, parabolic inverted parabola tunnel through which the nine flexor
tendons and the median nerve pass and occasionally a medium sized artery. Now explain why there are
nine flexor tendons. Right. So there's two to each finger, lesser finger, and then there's only one
to the thumb. And, uh, and those are, it's, it's fascinating to, to look into that and see it just
so happens that, uh, um, position wise, if we look at our palm up, the median nerve is running
down almost the center of the wrist and it is the most superficial so that if we then flex our
wrist down, those flexor tendons are trying to bow string down, they will press that median nerve
up against that rigid transverse carpal ligament. If we have swelling edema, inflammatory tissues,
such as in rheumatoid arthritis, where that builds up, that becomes a space occupying lesion
in a fixed, confined cross-sectional area. And then it compresses that nerve, the nerve,
the tendons aren't really vulnerable in that way. Uh, but the nerve is very vulnerable to compression.
That's why it's such a ubiquitous problem. And so from a motor standpoint, the median nerve controls
which function versus the ulnar nerve. That's great. So important of a question. And, and by the
way, there is some confusion. People, people very often come to me and say, I think I have
median nerve. I mean, I think I have a carpal tunnel syndrome and, and the thing they don't,
you know, just because it's such a ubiquitous bandied about term, but you must have numbness
and tingling in the median nerve distribution, which is the palm side of the thumb index middle
and usually half of the ring finger. If you don't have numbness and tingling there, you,
you're very unlikely to have carpal tunnel syndrome. However, if you have an arthritic process,
you can, without having as much numbness and tingling, you can have isolated atrophy of the
muscles, the thenar, the thumb muscles here that give us our opposable thumb. You can have atrophy
that looks like an indentation right there. And some people can have that quietly. It can
be just a very gradual, just from the encroachment on that nerve of the bone spurs that grow through
the arthritic process. So that's the exception where sometimes you can have isolated motor.
And very rarely in a younger person, I will see where they have an odd motor branch, which is the
nerve that comes off the median nerve that goes to those muscles. They'll have a weird compression
of just that. So a younger person who doesn't have any numbness and tingling, and then has isolated
atrophy. So that needs to be addressed surgically as well. But the, the thing that fits with the
carpal tunnel is that if you're pregnant, there's a lot often in third trimester when women are
dealing this is just because of swelling, just because of swelling, the fluid imbalances that
are going on there, that's a possibility. People who use jackhammers or people who are cyclists,
and they're always pressing down and putting extra pressure on that area can get carpal tunnel
syndrome only when they're cycling. So it's a dynamic situation. Weightlifters can get it
depending on what the style of what they're doing. But the stereotype is people who are typing a lot,
isn't it? Yeah, that is. Is that a true carpal tunnel syndrome? So generally speaking,
most people don't get carpal tunnel just from typing. There was a massive class action lawsuit
against IBM 100 years ago. I don't know how long and they lost because they couldn't prove, I mean,
IBM didn't lose the, they lost the case because they couldn't prove that it was
caused. There was no data suggests that it was caused by just using a keyboard. However,
if you already have it, absolutely that activity will exacerbate it. And, and that's why ergonomics
are so important, you know, sitting there, how you're sitting. I mean, during COVID, everybody
went back home and worked from home and worked at a sometimes random, the kitchen table or their
bed with their laptop and their, so there's a lot more of these both wrist tendonitis and carpal
tunnel syndrome after that, which you don't, that doesn't affect the ulnar nerve, which is the other
nerve that we're talking about. The ulnar nerve is so important because while our opposable thumb is
critically important, that's governed mostly by the, by the, um, median nerve. The ulnar nerve
supplies almost all the rest of the muscles, small muscles of the hand. And those we call
the intrinsic muscles of the hand, which are basically what allow us to spread our fingers
apart, pull our fingers together, do these weird funky positions that we do, like the intrinsic
plus position there, that, that position, being able to do that with your hand is almost all ulnar
nerve. And if you cut the ulnar nerve right here at the wrist, your hand will do just that. And you
will not be able to do anything but, but a little bit of that you can't. So the, so the flexors of
each finger are all ulnar. Well, the, the intrinsic flexors are ulnar. The extrinsics are split between
the median more approximately in the form are split between the median and the ulnar. But lifting a
finger this way is intrinsic. Yeah. Lifting them. Yes. This way at the sort of the, this knuckle
level is in all intrinsic, all intrinsic. And we don't have extenders, extensors we, or we do.
We do, but not intrinsically. We have, well, not for the, these level, the MP joints, that's
extrinsic extension. But what I mean, the, the, I'd love to draw a picture of the finger mechanism.
It's made, so it just, I just find it so cool. It's so much more complicated than biomechanically
than the flexors. The flexors are pretty simple. And what's fascinating about the hand is despite,
you know, being able to play Rachmaninoff or a violin concerto or be able to do so many,
build a watch, the hand is actually more primitive of a structure. It's, it's still,
it's pretty much unchanged except for the opposable thumb. It's a pretty primitive structure
in the sense of evolutionarily speaking. Our foot is a, is a fantastically adapted and modified
over evolution to walk. We were talking about that before when we started walking on all fours,
our, I mean, when we stood up and became bipeds, our foot completely changed.
So the, is, I mean, I know we joke about it, but is the opposable thumb the primary difference
between us and a primate? Yes. Well, it depends on, we're, we're part of the higher prime. Yeah.
Between the lower primate. The lower primates, exactly. That's really, and that's why, you know,
we're not, once we were no longer arboreal where our thumb was in the plane of the palm and we
would hang from, you know, tree limbs, then when we came around, we could start making tools and
developing our, I mean, and that's, that's the thing. Our brains grew and we started using our
hands and making tools. That's when our brains, our heads enlarged. I mean, it's just so cool.
Yeah. So I mean, I consider and talk about the hand all day, especially given how little I
understand it. So what are some of the other injuries that are pretty common? Either, again,
the injury you'll see more commonly in the 60, 70 year old versus in the athlete, the kind of the
wear and tear injuries, what are the most common fractures? Yeah. So yeah, I think we would break
it up into the acute traumatic events, which are most often fractures, but can be also
dislocations. And then we, then we would say the wear and tear type injuries, which are usually
start in middle age and go on into older age. And then the, and then the actual, what was the third
we were talking about? We said that for, oh, oh, and then, and then the, the absolute degenerative
arthritic types of problems that are inevitable for many of us. And they vary among individuals
based on genetics and lifestyle and so forth. And so the fractures, the most common by far
is the distal radius fracture. That's just the big bone of the radius. Now the radius, the form is
super cool because we already talked about the elbow. We looked at that really complex, weird,
undulating structure there. The ulna that we talked about is the elbow bone that we feel the
prominence of our elbow. And that's a straight bone. And that goes down and forms the, the bump
here that we've seen on the back of our wrist. And that's the ulna. The radius is, is, is a curved
arching bone that is curved so it can get around the radius as we pronate and supinate. So the
radius is flared and provides the biggest structure at the wrist level. And, but it's
much smaller at the elbow level. And so it rotates around through a fixed ulna. The ulna never moves.
It, I mean, it moves this way, but it doesn't move or it's relatively, and, and the radius just
rotates back and forth. So any disruption of that can dramatically alter our ability to hold a, a,
a bowl of soup or to, to pronate and type and write. And so, and that can be disrupted in many ways.
The fractures, the radius is, is super common to fall and have a bending moment on that. And it,
and it fractures and displaces. And, but then you can often, you know, something falls hard on you.
You fall. I mean, we see them commonly in kids who are falling off the jungle gems. They'll have
a both bone form fracture in the mid forearm. And that's just another bending moment. Those
bones break in half or sometimes they bend. One of them breaks, one of them bends if they're,
the kids are young enough. And so that very, can very much disrupt the function there. And so at
any different point along the form, depending on the mechanism, these bones can break. And when
they do, if they're displaced, we have to often fix them except in very young kids.
That reminds me by the way, I don't know what it is. I vaguely remember this from,
from medical school and I never saw them in residency, although I told it was very common,
but I guess I just didn't do enough to, to see it where a parent grabs a kid by the arm to yank
him across the road. And what, what is that injury that's supposed to be pretty common?
That's nursemaid's elbow. And that is a subluxation of that. Yeah. That round radial head at the elbow.
And I had the, I guess, interesting and informative experience to create one in my own daughter.
She liked to be my first, first daughter. I would spin her around, you know, like you see people.
Yeah. And I remember spinning around, she was giggling and so forth. And then I felt just the
tiniest little weird movement in her elbow. It kind of threw her hand and I saw her face start to
scrunch up. I set her down her face. And then I just had this vision. I knew what it was. I
quickly did the reduction maneuver so fast that she hadn't even started crying. And then
it just immediately stopped hurting. And she wanted, I could tell she was getting ready to
start crying, but then she had no reason to because it didn't hurt. So it was kind of,
we were in that. And remind me what that reduction is again. So what's happening? So the radius,
which is on this side, the outer side. Exactly. When you pronate and you pull and kind of give a
various moment, it will cause that radial head just to slip out this way a little bit. So the
easy maneuver because the stable position is just you supinate and you put a little pressure on that,
you supinate and then flex the elbow up. So this is the most stable position of that bone. And it
will pop back in every time. Now, if you, if there's stay out and then you go sit in an
emergency room for eight hours or six hours, harder and harder to get back in, you often have
to do an under anesthesia to this day. I am still paranoid. Anytime I have to grab one of my boys,
but I'm going to do it. And I'm always like trying to figure out how to reduce it. If I ever
screw it up. So yeah, I've seen, I've seen a lot of radial fractures in, in friends and kids. And
it doesn't, it really seems like one of those awful luck things sometimes. Like if you fall
out of a tree, you fall out of a tree. And if you're, if you slip on ice that you don't see
and you're totally not ready for that fall, it can happen to the best person. There's, there's,
yeah. And then the older we get, of course, if we have a little osteoporosis,
osteopenia on x-ray and osteoporosis, then it takes less and less force to fracture those bones.
And yeah, what breaks the ulnar bone? Does it ever break on its own?
So there's the most common one is a direct blow via, it can be in football. It can be a weight
falling. It can be a door smashing into you is a, what's called a nightstick fracture. And it's
named for that because especially the, the Billy clubs in, in the UK where, you know, that, that
would strike you when your hand was up and it cracks the ulnar along there. That's the most common.
And, but it can often be fractured also in association with the distal radius. The
styloid part can come off, it's attached to a ligament or the just the, they can just both
snap at the same time. And that complicates the treatment, but it's, so those are the most common
ones. And then the other one, which is really more of an elbow fracture, but it's the ulna is the
olecranon. And that's a common, common fracture. And that's really simple. I see those in very,
when you're falling your elbow, the only other way you can kind of pull that bone off is if you
fall really hard, say snow skiing, you're falling hard. And as you talk about the eccentric load,
that triceps pulls it right off. And yeah, I mean, you're the expert on eccentric loading. And I love
the fact that you educate so many people about that because it's way more, um, injurious in a way.
What about the chronic sort of injuries of the hand and wrist that ultimately require
surgical care? Yeah. So there's, there's, you can break them down into sort of overuse patterns,
which are more tendonitis. And if you have a long enough standing tendonitis, you can start to it.
The tendonitis is an tino sinovitis. So those are subtle differences. A tendonitis is just inflammation
in the tendon. And if it's beginning to wear and tear and degenerate, you'll get some longitudinal
fissuring in those, those collagen fibers. And then it fills in with some inflammatory tissue,
and then that can envelop the tendon. And so you're getting kind of a constant rubbing and
further degeneration of that. You get chronic pain, you can inject it with cortisone, but then
ultimately they can rupture. And, and depending on how much and how much force they're being
subjected to and for how long it's been there. So that's one. Then the tino sinovitis is a subset
of that where we have these effectively watertight tubes, specifically in our flexor tendons. And
those tendons are gliding beautifully in there. There's a little bit of fluid our body produces
to keep them gliding smoothly and a little bit of what we call tino synovium, which is just a
filmy structure that gives them some lubricating Teflani feel. If that gets inflamed from overuse,
whether you're a violinist or a heavy weight lifter doing all sorts of things over and over
again, you can develop inflammation there. And then that becomes trapped in there and it really
hurts. It can eliminate mobility and it can even cause them sometimes to lock down. And those are
super common. And we can often cure them with just cortisone shots or rest or both, but then
ultimately a subset of them, because they're so ubiquitous, require surgery, which is very minor,
but it's important because the hand function, if you have one finger that's really stiff,
whether you dislocated it or even just sprained it, the other fingers, they're all linked so
indelibly together that actually it will make your whole hand feel stiff.
Yeah. So it's funny you say that. So as you know, I'm really obsessed with grip strength and all
sorts of crazy shenanigans. And maybe about a year ago, I started experimenting kind of like
training sort of the way that rock climbers do where you're using only finger strength. And
what blew me away was how much weaker I felt all the way through my lats when I would restrict
the amount of fingers I could use to pull up. So if you just said do pull ups, you can use your
whole hand, do pull ups, no problem. You just barely noticed that. I feel like I'm perfectly
connected from the bar to my lats. And now you say, okay, Peter, you're not going to get to use
your whole hand or your thumb, just use your four fingers. Actually that gets a little harder.
Way harder.
It took me a while to work up to 10 four finger pull ups.
Well, that's impressive that you can do that because yeah, I know exactly what you're talking about.
It took a long time. I mean, it took a couple months. Then I moved to three finger pull ups.
I mean, it's an order of magnitude harder.
It's crazy, right?
And I don't think I've been able to, I don't know, I don't know that I even got to try two finger
because I was still really nowhere near getting to 10 three finger pull ups. And so why is that?
Because I'm no less strong in my lats, in my biceps, in all these other muscles. Why is it
that simply take, and by the way, it was the pinky that I was removing of all fingers. You'd think
it does nothing. Why when I can only have these three fingers, does all of my strength fade away?
I've never been asked that directly, but I have a couple of theories on that. One is,
and it applies to sort of the weakness I feel and detect asymmetrically in,
let's say a rotator cuff. If you have a small partial thickness rotator cuff tear, well,
that's tiny. It's mechanically not relevant. And yet you can be quite weak.
Your brain is the smart, so smart, it knows it doesn't want to overstress that area. So I,
my instinct is that the first reaction, especially when you've never done that before,
is for your brain to say, whoa, that's putting way too much tension on the other one. So I'm going
to relax everything. I'm not going to give you what you need because they may rupture. Interesting.
Right. I think that's probably the biggest explanation for that. But specifically,
when you're talking about grip strength, what's ironic is that the, the ulnar nerve,
which is only these two fingers, is much more important for grip strength than these.
Interesting. So if you have these, if you have, let's say you have an ulnar nerve that's completely
in and a median nerve that's out, you're going to be pretty strong still. Whereas if you have an
ulnar nerve out and a median nerve that's still in, you're going to be much weaker.
Wow. So just for people listening to us, which hopefully nobody's just listening to this podcast
because it's hard to, but you're saying pinky and ring finger matter more to grip than middle finger,
four finger thumb, which is under the median distribution. I don't, I agree with that. I mean,
that even just feel, I feel like I can engage my forearms much more with my pinky and ring finger.
Oh yeah, for sure. Absolutely. Why is that? I mean, it's evolution, I guess.
That's insane. You know what? It makes me wonder if I should be doing these three fingers.
That's what I think. That's what I think. Yeah, because I was doing, yeah, yeah. Oh, that's,
I'm going to try that today. Good. Report back to me. I'll let you just learn that rather than me
having to learn it. That is amazing. I just, you know, I'm endlessly fascinated by what our hands
are capable of. And I think of it as such a, well, such a force multiplier for our species.
Right. It's an unbelievable asset and our ability to carry things is, you know, Michael Easter has
written about this at length in his book, The Comfort Crisis, which of course is what has
introduced us all to rucking. But, you know, other animals can carry a lot if they're domesticated
and you put it on their back. But in terms of like, you know, we can carry our body weight and
our hands. Crazy. And that is mind boggling and it speaks to kind of remarkable engineering and
to think that a lot of that is made possible by this opposable thumb as well is pretty cool.
And even going back to the elbow anatomically, when you look at the Vitruvian man and when you
look at the standard anatomic position of, in medicine, the elbow has a carrying angle built
into it to get whatever we carry away from our body. So we can carry more. So we have a 12 to 15
degree natural built in what's called valgus or away from our bodies to give us more area to carry
heavy things with. It's super cool. So let's talk about the final category of these, which are the
arthritics. And here you have really two, you have this rheumatoid or autoimmune form of arthritis,
which, you know, I think anybody who's seen patients with that recognize it is just looks
like an awful affliction. Yes. Where it's not only functionally impeding, but also physically
deforming of the fingers and the joints. Yes. Versus the much more common osteoarthritic,
which I assume is more aware and tear than just a, you know, it doesn't have that autoimmune
component. So first of all, what's the distribution and breakdown of those and which one of those
ultimately can require surgical intervention? Right. So historically, just in my orthopedic
lifetime, I see very few now rheumatoid, arthritic, and what we would call the, the, um,
RA negative, uh, where the testing, we know they have the, the visible, yeah, the phenotype,
but they don't necessarily have all the lab stories to lab abnormalities to back them up. But I see
way more now less than I ever saw before because of the medical therapies, just so much biologics
are so amazing. They've been absolute game changers and keep people normal for such a long
time. So that's one thing, but in general, I mean, when I started practice, I would see,
I would have to operate as often in a patient with rheumatoid arthritis and those deformities
that happen and you're trying to beat them, beat the body to addressing the deformities so they
don't get bad enough to where they really require joint replacements and much more complicated
recoveries and so forth. So it's always, it was always a battle and kind of like you racing a car,
you know, you're just trying to get, get just a little bit ahead and just do whatever you can do
to, to win that. And now, I mean, I would say I probably see maybe one a month that needs surgery
and that's pretty rare. So, and the surgery is because of such a significant functional
limitation. Yes. Yeah. It's always in the case, I mean, it can be in the elbow, it can be in the
shoulder, but usually in the hand and it's a tendon subluxation joint deviation that then
weakens their hand and decreases their ability to remain independent. The goal obviously,
and to the point of what our hands do for us, if we maintain reasonably good hand function,
we can remain independent. As soon as we lose our hand function, we become dependent on others,
period. And so that's what our whole goal is to maintain that, that fierce independence. So yeah,
that's that. But then on the other hand, then we have the wear and tear osteoarthritis concept and
and that varies among individuals. Some people have really good hands till the, till the very end.
And they have, I liken it to a paint job, you know, on a car, a cheap one. We talked about that before
and versus a very nice thick paint job that that holds up, but there is a big genetic component.
I see patients come in that'll maybe be, you know, only 50, very young. They'll come in and they'll
already have a lot of the visible alterations, not terrible functionally, but they're getting
the nobbiness. They're getting a little bit of inflammation in the joints out here, maybe down
at the thumb base. And they'll say, hey, so what can you do? My hands look exactly like my mom's
did or my dad's did. And there's, there's, there's real evidence to support that. Some people are
more predisposed than others. Now, the one exception is the ubiquitous about 50% of all
of us will develop arthritis at the base of our thumb. And that's that opposable thumb. And that's
the problem with that is it's all about biomechanics. It has to do too much. There's six degrees of
freedom. It's just this biconcave saddle joint that in order to come back and forth this way,
radial and ulnar deviation, then straight up, palmar abduction that way, and then rotating around
and pronating in order to oppose the thumb tip to the fingertips. It's doing three different
directional movements. And this joint is doing this and this and this, and it just wears out.
And so it's just subjected to so many odd stresses and it's unstable like the shoulder by definition.
We couldn't have it. It gives it that amazing mobility. And so, so what do we, so 50% of people
in their lifetime, if I'm hearing correctly, will experience osteoarthritis of that joint. Yes.
In what fraction of those people will it pose a functional limitation that is, you know, not
something that's just treatable with some of leaves here and there. So we, we know that obviously we
don't know what percentage of the population that all of us as a group are treating, but we do know,
what we do know is that we don't know the exact subset. We know that there's many people walking
around with basal arthritis that never have pain. They have some stiffness, some deformity, and they
don't hurt. We know that we don't know that exact number. However, what we do know that, and we've
published papers on this, is that of the people that present with some pain, about 25% of those,
which would be, I guess, 12 and a half percent of the overall population potentially are, are going
to need surgery on that at some point. So one fourth, one fourth of the people that present with
pain in the thumb are going to need surgery. And what is the surgical procedure? It varies,
depending on what stage they present at. And we've done staging systems and so forth, but it's some
form of reconstruction. Unlike the hips and knees that are so ubiquitous and so wonderful, they've
kept people back to their fully active lives by, by doing them, we don't have those kind of great
implants for this. That just doesn't, they don't work. There's very high failure rates. If, if a,
if a hip replacement or a knee replacement has a 5% failure rate at five or 10 years,
the thumbs are 70% failure rate of all the previous. So what we do and was invented by my
forebearers and we've modified them over time, but it's basically doing a reconstruction using your
own tissue. And that's what's super cool, which we didn't mention is because of the way our limbs
evolved, we have so much protective redundancy. We have so many tendons, like all of the flexor
tendons that flex the fingers also flex the wrist and give a strength just like you were talking
about with the pull ups. Well, you have wrist flexors that only attach right here that also
give you that flexion and we, and those all are housed in the forearm. And then you have the
extensors that do that. And then you have some that are just, we have multiple tendons that pull
the thumb out. They do subtle differences, but we can use those and we do use those to transfer
and to use them as tendon grafts. Now, a cool thing that goes back to the evolution
is if you look at your hand, hold your hands out and pull and flex your wrist a little bit.
I can't tell from yours. You can see here, you can look on yourself. You can see here,
I had this big tendon that comes up when I, yeah. So on this side, I don't have one.
It's just missing. Oh, I have huge ones. Yeah.
I have huge ones on both sides. Okay. So evolutionarily, that's the, that's the
palmaris longus. Those are hugely developed in quadrupeds and horses and so forth. The
big important muscle. Well, don't do anything in us. They don't do anything. So we use that as a
tendon graft all the time. We just take it. I mean, it's just, it's attached to a little whipped
small muscle. I'm closer to the horses. I knew that about me. And so mine, we're evolving away.
15% of people don't have any. So does that mean you're not actually addressing the surface of
the saddle joint, which is arthritic in this procedure? Good point. You're not recreating
some artificial joint. What we're creating is a pseudoarthrosis. We stabilize it, get it
stabilized back on top. In my case, I take a little bit of the bone off to create a space and
then I roll up the rest of that tendon and put it in there. And that relieves the pain and restores
function. Yes. So this is a high success operation. Very high success. Yeah. Very high.
I don't know how I didn't realize you could make a case that roughly five to 10% of the population
will require this at some point in their life. Yeah. If their activity, obviously a subset are
very sedentary and don't do much and they're not going to need it and they'll wear a splint for
the rest of their days. But if they're presenting with the pain, that's the point. We don't know
what the end is, but other than being the general population as a whole, but people who present with
pain are active enough. So would you say this is the single most common non-traumatic surgical
repair of the hand? Non-traumatic, other than a, well, and even a trigger finger you could
attribute to, so of the major surgery done in the hand, yes, by far. Okay. By far. So you mentioned
trigger finger. What's that? Well, trigger finger is what we were talking about before,
where the inflammation of the sheath. And then right in the middle here, there's a series of
pulleys and these are super cool. I'm going to draw a picture if I may. Yeah. Okay. So we're
looking at the side of the hand. Yes. So we're looking and let's just say this is the middle
finger. It's the longest and this is the metacarpal. This is the first of the three bones of the finger
proper. And what I've drawn here, this black line coming underneath is the flexor tendon.
And that's the one that does curls. All our curl allows you to do all your pull-ups. So there's
four bones there, just so people can see. I don't want them to miss the one. This one is kind of
hidden within the hand because that's through here. Yeah. And so then there's the three
successive. And so if you just, if you had a muscle attached to this and you pulled on it and
didn't have those blue structures, then this would bowstring just like a fishing pole. If you don't
put the fishing line through the islets, then it just stays way away. And it's actually stronger
that way, but you lose all the mobility. So you lose the capacity to really curl your fingers
tightly. So that's what they're gliding through. And those are fibroosseous tunnels and just fibrous
tissue, very strong, which you mentioned rock climbing, they can rupture because you're putting
so much force on those in such funky positions and isolating two fingers, one finger and so forth.
So I see that a lot in rock climbers, but the point here is that as you're rubbing constantly
going back and forth, whether you're playing a concerto or you're rock climbing, you can get
inflamed along that sheath. This particular pulley here is down in the palm. And that's the
most common site to have inflammation to where you can even get some nodular swelling in the tendon
and that thickening up of that pulley. And then it just actually catches and we call it a trigger
finger because it's like pulling a trigger on a gun. It has that feeling. And we frequently have
to inject those with cortisone and frequently have to operate on their ubiquitous. And about half of
them recover with just a cortisone injection. Yeah. I always say actually more in the order,
depending on how, if we get to them, if you take someone who presents within say six weeks of onset,
there's about a 75% cure rate with one or two injections. So the longer you wait, the more
likely potential damage you cause and the more chronic inflammation that ensues. Correct. But
we don't, and this applies kind of a general consensus. I think we talked about this before
when we were talking about cortisone shots is in these types of soft tissue procedures, we don't
keep injecting cortisone, cortisone, cortisone, because it can lead to soft tissue degradation
and ultimately even tendon ruptures. I've never seen one in my practice, but we know they can
exist. And what do you use as a rule of thumb for how many times you'll put three, three,
at three in the lifetime of the joint, three in the lifetime of that tendon sheath, unless it's
very, very broad. Usually you don't see someone back 10 years later who needs another injection.
But if I did, I'd be willing to do that again because everything has normalized physiologically
at that point. Now, the other cool thing that I was talking about before when we were talking about
you asked about the extensors versus flexors. So if we look at the red, this is the extrinsic
extensor tendon that will straighten up the knuckles. But then we look further out and we
see, well, that only stops, that tendon stops at the middle knuckle, but what allows, what pulls
the whole finger straight? And it's actually this intrinsic muscle here that's tapering down
and has a very thin tendon. It turns into a lateral band and it travels from the palm side
up above the middle knuckle, above that axis of rotation. And then it goes all the way on
attaches to the tip. And so it's a super cool mechanism that through a series of mechanical
placements, it's able to extend the finger even though contracting by contracting. It's
very counterintuitive. I mean, most people wouldn't immediately get that. You have great
biomechanical sense because yes, by contracting, it's straightening up the finger. It's super cool.
But it doesn't take much. Like if you take a direct blow to that knuckle right there and that tendon
just slips because you've disrupted some soft tissue, it can slip below the axis of rotation.
Then it becomes a flexor and you get a near deformity, which looks like that. You cannot
straighten your finger up because those lateral bands that are used to extending the finger have
slipped down. Now they become a flexor just like you said. So it's super cool and just so intricate.
And I vaguely remember one sort of surgical emergency in the hand where that sheath would
become infected. Yes, very good. Yes. It's one of the few really orthopedic emergencies in the hand,
which is, yes, tenosynovitis and then it becomes supporative or infected and pus in there.
And those people, I mean, there's so many nerves in our hand anyway. When you get even a few drops
of purulent pus in the finger sheath, it hurts like crazy. And your posture is down like this.
You can't straighten your finger up at all and it's exquisitely tender and it looks swollen just
along that sheath. And yeah, it's an operative urgency or emergency. And how does a person get
that infection? It's usually an open injury or? Yeah, sometimes just a little, it can even be a
pinprick. It's sometimes an insect bite, you know, with a stinger and often just a tiny little, you
know, you can be like a graph if you're using sports equipment, you can get a little graphite,
tiny stiff graphite puncture. How often, how many times a year do you see one of those?
I don't see them as much. I'm not in the ER, but they're ubiquitous. I mean,
they're coming all the time, year round. Okay. Should we do an exam of the hand and wrist now?
Yes, let's do. Let's do. Great.
Okay. So now, you know, we've, we've been talking a lot about the kind of a forearm
wrist and hand. And so we can go through some of the common diagnoses of those.
Again, inspection is so important. We look for swelling. If you have what's called dequeurvains,
tenicinovitis, you'll see swelling here. If you have basal joint arthritis, you'll see bulging
here. If you have a torn radial collateral ligament, then you'll see a resting deviation of
the thumb and it's very prominent. If you have some arthritis or tenicinovitis of the big extensor
tendon through here on the owner side, that'll be prominent. A ganglion cyst, of course, sticks out
like a big, you know, well, goose egg there on top, usually most commonly right here.
We look for atrophy. Very important. We were talking about that before. So if I look at your
hand, there's three places that I look for atrophy. I look over here and I see that that's
plump and not flattened out. What it'll do is it'll look like a gaunt, you know, face. And then over
here, I look here, this also can develop an atrophy there. I had a young woman a long time ago,
had never been reported, who had traumatically, very active athletic person, had traumatically
torn off that first dorsal neurosius muscle. So she didn't have a nerve problem. She tore the
insertion right off of there, which is what gives you that strength there. And so she had just
already atrophied. This was at four weeks, it was already atrophied. So I reattached it and it came
back. It's fine. Then, and very importantly, looking at the thin arm muscles, we want to see
a nice plump, convex surface. If it starts to flatten or even just be soft when you palpate it,
then we worry about the nerve, not enough nerve signal going to that and developing the early
atrophy. So we look at that, we look at the rotation. So again, we've inspected. I'm not
going to test strength yet. I'm going to look at rotation, I mean, wrist and finger motion. So
we look at the full pronation, full supination, very subtly between individuals, but more or less,
we're looking for 90, 90 of pronation, supination. And then we look at the wrist, and we want to see
that you have roughly, that can vary a lot, but somewhere between 70 and 90 of extension and 70
and 90 of flexion, we want to know if that hurts or if we feel crepitus, that crunchy feeling that
can indicate inflammation in the joint. Similarly, when we're pronating supinating, we're feeling for
inflammation there. If you walk in and you have a very prominent distal ulna, especially asymmetrically,
that's important to me because, and especially if you had a traumatic accident, these are commonly
missed. There's some thick ligaments here, the DRUJ ligaments, and those can allow the ulna to
rise and the radius to fall away from that. And it's very disabling, especially for athletes. And
so I see it in hockey players who take the slam. And so I'm checking that and looking for that
stability there as I rotate and watch it. Then, so we've looked at range of motion. Now, for the thumb,
this joint right here, the MCP joint, where you have a skier's thumb for the ulnar-clouded ligament
and a radial-clouded ligament tear, though that's the most variable joint in the body in terms of
varying among individuals. So you have minus 30 passively, and you flex nicely down to about 70.
We look at my thumb. I hyper-extend a lot more, but I only flex down to about 40. And that's just,
everybody's different. So we want to compare the two and see. And especially on laxity, even side
to side, if I'm testing this and you have a tear, it'll go way over sometimes to 60 degrees, 70
degrees, either direction. We know that's asymmetric and that's not going to withstand
and need to be repaired. Fingers, you know, we want to just simply see if you make a tight fist,
which you can, you can really nicely curl those fingers down. If you've had various injuries,
that's going to be altered. When you straighten them back up, if one of them stays stuck down,
then you probably have a locked trigger finger. And I have to pry that open. And then I feel
in palpate, I feel a nodule, I feel the swelling in the tendon, the tenderness. And then we know
that's what you have. It's very easy. Now, next, we need to remember that for a lot of overuse
strain, whether you're a professional musician or working out in a gym regularly or irregularly,
more commonly, there's two sites where you can get the most common injury. And you know this
in spades is the musculotendinous junction. You talked about the eccentric loading. And there's
two spots for that. There's one right here and there's one right here. There's these short
tendons that attach to the bones up here and you can get the muscle tendon junction injured there.
And you can get where the tendons become the long tendons and the muscle, that, that, that
transition zone. And those are the two places. So we're going to test those. A lot of patients
come in and say, I'm having pain here. Every time I try to work out or play tennis or whatever,
or here. And so that's what we're feeling for. Now, I can test this. You pull up against me hard,
rock solid, pull down against me, down this way, hard. And that's great. We have your thumb pull
up this way, super strong, have you spread your fingers out real stiff. That's very strong. Now,
that is overlaying into the nerve exam that we look for. And that those are the intrinsic muscles.
That's the ulnar nerve. If you have a bad ulnar nerve from here to here, it's going to give away
and just fall away and they'll be weak. Similarly, I want to look at your thenar strength and have
you come bring your thumb right up out of the palm, like you're a good higher primate, and then push
against me. And that's rock solid. And that's, we see this bulge up there. And so that tells us that
your thenar muscle and your median nerve are working fine. Let's see what other common things.
You know, something is simple. We didn't talk about this too much, but so common and ubiquitous
are just sprained fingers. People jam their fingers, baseball, softball, working out, whatever.
And what's crazy is you sprain these joints and we can palpate those. And we can test them. Some
people tear them, but we test them. They feel fine. They're strong, but they're swollen. They're
bulbous. They tender. And that can take months and months to go away. So you just have to counsel
people, your patients, my patients, to just be patient with it. Keep using them. There's no harm
in using them. The cool thing about ligaments is they heal with motion. So we don't want to mobilize
them too long. That's a common misconception. I see patients who have had bad sprains, even
dislocations, and they they're put into a splint. They come see me three weeks later, they're already
stiff. I would move those immediately, maybe one to two days to rest them a little bit and then get
them moving. Okay. So we've done, we've done and remember that, and well, you know this and not
remember, but we were talking about the fact that we have the extrinsic tendons, both the extensors
and the flexors. And those are muscles through here and then tendons through here all the way
out to the fingertips. So we, we can isolate and find, let's say you have a little, you're cutting
an avocado and you poke right in there. You have maybe numbness along here. We know you cut the
digital nerve there. And this finger, when you make a fist, this one just stays up like that.
And that, that tells me that there's something wrong with the tendon. Then I try to isolate
that, say, well, can you bend the tip? And you say, oh yeah, I can bend the tip. But then I say,
and that isolates the long flexor, but then I do this and you, and you can't bend it. Then that
says, okay, you cut the superficial one of the two tendons there. So it's really easy anatomically
to figure these things out. And I think that's about it. If you have it, we talked about the
dinner fork deformity. If you have a distal radius fracture across here, it comes up here and goes
this way. I mean, there's a true notable deformity. And so we're, you know, the, the population with
your help is becoming younger and younger. And so we are more and more aggressive because there are
70, 80, 90 year olds who are working out, who are playing sports, and we want to keep them
going as long as possible because I'm getting close to that. And so, you know, so we fix those,
we get them back. My mom was 80, 82, and she broke her wrist, put a titanium plate on there.
And she was, she, right. You didn't even know that she had it and she was using it the, you know,
two weeks later. So, okay. So the final thing you wanted to talk about was kind of all of the
nerve pains that can presumably not just wreak havoc down here from a pain and, you know,
suffering standpoint, but also from a diagnostic standpoint. Yes. Yes. So, so many people present
with numbness, tingling, weakness, or pain in the upper limb. And it can be, it can start from the
neck where the nerve roots exit and travel under our collarbone through the brachial plexus in
between the scalene muscles, and then travels through our armpit and then comes down in through
the arm and into the hand. And the, and they, it can be confounding. A perfect example of how
confounding it can be is a, is a now more commonly known, although it's, I wouldn't call it rare,
but it's uncommon, is Parsonage-Turner syndrome. It's a fascinating study in that whole process
from the neck down. And the other term for it is a brachial neuritis, as in brachial plexus neuritis.
And it's an inflammation of those nerves. We think it's probably viral related because there's
usually a viral prodrome associated, but doesn't have to be, but it's an acute dramatic onset
of pain all through here. And then some, what we call mixed plexopathy, some mixed bag of
palsy, weakness, numbness, and it can be in multiple different nerves. It can even lead to,
and one of the most common presenting ways is long thoracic nerve, which is part of the brachial
plexus, and you get scapular winging. So you, you lift your arm up and it just falls down because
your scapula cannot support the shoulder and arm weight because the muscle of the, the, the,
of the shoulder girdle cannot support that. And it's super cool. And, and it, and it presents as
a mix. So it affects multiple nerves because those nerves are more common up here and then they
diverge into the different nerves, which I still, you know, you remember in med school trying to
learn the brachial plexus and it was, it was brutal because it's really complicated. Okay. So,
so these are people who show up and they, you, you certainly couldn't attribute what they're
experiencing to any one thing. That's the point. Like it's not like they have one or two discs
that could be bulging and causing that symptom. It's not like they could have even transacted
their long thoracic nerve. Like a woman who has a mastectomy, you're always looking out for that
post-mastectomy. It's like they would have to have six lesions simultaneously. Exactly. And it
just doesn't happen except with that. So that's a, that's a great lead into what the majority.
By the way, is that just a self-limited thing or do you give these people steroids?
Steroids. Yeah. And the neurologist now, they make the diagnosis if you send them to them
and we give steroids and most of them recover completely. A few have some residual deficits
forever, at least long-term. Okay. So then that takes us to people presenting. I have a ton of
patients who present with shoulder pain and they may have a little something on their MRI that they
may have brought in with them, but that shoulder pain is actually coming from their neck from,
and so then I'll have someone who will present with carpal tunnel syndrome, but it's, there's
a little extra stuff going on. Maybe some ulnar nerve and the little finger,
maybe some shoulder pain, maybe some arm pain. And the cool thing about, diagnostically speaking,
is an intrinsic shoulder problem such as a rotator cuff tear or inflammation, bursitis, etc.,
usually travels down underneath the pain, underneath the delt, the big deltoid muscle,
but almost never goes below the elbow. So if I see pain that's in the shoulder going below the
elbow, I'm thinking maybe neck or maybe something else. Then, secondarily, if someone complains of,
let's say they come in and they say, yeah, I've got numbness here, but I've also got some numbness
on the back of the hand. The radial nerve is rarely involved in association with carpal tunnel
or cubital tunnel. And, oh yeah, my neck's been really stiff. Just subtle little cues that you can
get by speaking with them. Well, they could have something that I know you know about and that can
be called double crush. And that is where you get pinching of the nerve in the neck, maybe through a
disc, maybe through a foraminal osteophyte that narrows that little canal that passes through.
And then, because the axoplasmic flow or the nerve tube, the communication of it is disrupted
or compressed, it renders them more susceptible to milder compression down at the carpal tunnel
or the cubital tunnel at the elbow. So they're getting a double crush. Now, for those, I don't
treat necks other than treating them initially with some PT and maybe steroids or something.
And I refer those out. But many patients will then see a neck surgeon who will say, well,
you don't really need surgery. Yes, I think you do have double crush, but you can go ahead and treat.
I can go ahead and treat, let's say they have moderate carpal tunnel. I can do a carpal tunnel
release and they'll still get better. They may not get all the way better, though most of their
carpal tunnel will go away, but they'll still have some of the upper nerve pain.
So the double crush phenomena is real and true. And that's another category of patient.
Then there's the weird lower cervical that I just learned not that long ago from a really smart
neck surgeon is it's pretty consistent that the lower level, the C7 nerve root level,
if they have compression down there, then that that goes deep under the scapula and gives them
that deep scapular plane. And in the problem there, and what's been so great for me to learn
this later in my career is I often would see patients will develop scapulothoracic bursitis,
and you can clearly get that from lifting weights, especially if you've been out of the weight room
for a long time, you go back into it, you can get a lot of upper trapezius periscapular rhomboid
type pain from overuse and those overlap. So you really have to do the diagnostic work
and talk to the patients and listen to the patients to differentiate that. And then of course,
in our exam, we can we can see that too. And I think that's more or less what I would want to say
the one patient that I would I think illustrates this how complicated it can be with someone who
had a bad shoulder fracture is treated in the emergency department, put into a sling, but then
also may be told to do pendulum exercises. Well, it was an unstable fracture, very unstable. And so
the weight of our arm, I mean, I'm sure you've did that in general surgery way more than me,
the weight of the arm is enormous if you have to amputate an arm for a tumor or something. And all
that weight pulling on an unstable fracture, well, that put tremendous traction on the nerves ended
up killing his ulnar and median nerve. Ulnar and median nerve are out. He came in his hand was like
that. He couldn't he couldn't oppose his thumb. He couldn't do anything. And I all I had left to work
with was the radial nerve innervated, which are the wrist extensors and the supinators. And I was
able to transfer some things and give him back some pretty good function. And but it was all just
due to track. What was the what was that length of time it took for that for those nerves to under
traction die? Yeah, it was fast, super fast. Oh, probably within I saw him eight weeks post-op. So
he was fully there. But he started saying he started losing hand function at about three weeks
within three weeks of the fracture. And no one picked up on this? No. Yeah, it was it was pretty
tragic. Yeah. Well, do you want to do an exam and kind of go over some of those things as well?
Yeah, we wrap up. Okay, great. Let's do that. Okay.
Okay, so we talked about kind of the nerve compressive neuropathies, nerve injuries that
can happen. And so this is very brief, but just to kind of go through the route of the nerves for
your viewers. And so if we look at your neck, we want to say maybe you have some neck stiffness,
maybe not, but we look and see and we say this side it goes, I'm going to take it less. Let's say
it only goes to 30 degrees horizontal rotation, whereas this side goes farther than we say, oh,
maybe there's some asymmetry there. Any tightness and asymmetry in the neck can actually cause
pinching of those nerves come out of your neck and give a lot of neck pain, but also pain down
there. You can go ahead and extend your neck that way. That's great. And then chin to your chest. So
I want to just basically look at that. The last one of that is just horizontal rotation that way
in that way. And that gives me a sense of maybe there's a component of that. Then, you know, we
send patients to neurologists to look at the nerves, the function. They do two kinds of
testings and the electromyography, and then they do nerve conduction, but we can do a poor man's
test quite well. Poor man's neurologic exam, just like this. So we know the nerves come out of the
neck. They go through between the anterior and middle scaling muscles. These secondary respiratory
muscles that are up here and they pass us through there. And if I roll through there and you have a
disc, you will say, oh, that's sending, that's going down to my left arm, my right arm, both
arms. So it's a real easy palpation of those irritated nerves. Then we look at that. They're
coming under the collarbone. They're coming down through deep to your pectoralis here and then
coming in through the axilla. The next place I can get access to those nerves is here medially.
We know the ulnar and median nerve and well, the radial nerve comes over here, but the owner and
median nerves right here. So I'll palpate right up against your bone and see, and that too. Oh,
yeah, that's definitely giving me stuff here. If you tell me that is giving you numbness and
tingling to there or to your thumb, then when I get down here, I know that it's not just carpal
tunnel or cubital tunnel. I know it's got to be some component coming from your neck. It's a very
simple, easy way. Anything above the elbow is irritated from up here. Anything below it could
be both. And we almost never from your neck, we almost never just see a pure ulnar neuropathy just
coming from your neck. Usually there's something else, like a little radial nerve, a little medial
nerve, something else. So then we come down to your ulnar nerve. Let's use this elbow because
it's better. So I've already checked your motion and then I feel your nerve and the groove there,
the funny bone nerve. And yours is, as we said, pretty mobile. I can kind of pull it up over the
edge, but it's not bad. Now I would tap on that lightly and see, does that cause electrical shocks?
And does that give you, oh, oh, I don't like that. Now a lot of us can have a little irritation,
so we want to compare and see what you have. Secondly, I want to flex up and see what that
nerve does. Now you have a very well developed triceps. I have seen people who are super avid
and that have these huge triceps and throwing athletes as well, where they are pressing their
triceps is overdeveloped here and it's pressing up against the nerve. So it's a different form
of cubital tunnel syndrome. It's not really in the cubital tunnel, but I've seen that a lot in athletes.
This ulnar nerve, I want to test and see what it's doing. If you're a throwing athlete and your nerve
slips back and forth, you can get snapping nerve and it's really irritable. You can no longer feel
the seams on your slider or your fastball. And so that is often needs surgery and even the weakness
of grip. Now we come down here and then I can press on that. I can flex it up and hold it.
And if that starts to cause numbness and tingling in your hand, then that's a secondary. You will
have already probably told me, yeah, you know, I get this. I wake up with my hand on an nerve
quite numb and that's, we all tend to start out this way and end up this way. And the only problem
there is that that can happen to any of us, but if it's regular and frequent and lingering,
or if we get it when we're typing or playing a piccolo or a cello, then that's a different
issue. And when you look further, lastly, coming down the form, there's two more nerves that we
can look at. The ulnar nerve rarely is involved down here. It's almost always 98% of the time at
the elbow. The radial nerve comes out from under here. It's just the sensory terminal branch of
the radial nerve that does so much good work for extending our wrist and our triceps and everything.
And it goes down to here and provides sensation in this part of the hand. And we can tap on that
and come down and then it will give electrical shocks down here. It can be very nerve wracking.
I've seen a lot of musicians with that. You have a loose wristband on now. Some people wear heavy
watches, heavy bracelets, and you can get that. Or if you've been arrested and they put their
handcuffs too tight, you haven't been arrested recently. Not recently. Not recently, okay.
And so that will cause a lot of numbness. They're really aggravating. So we look for that.
And then the last one is the median nerve, which is here. This is the carpal tunnel. Now,
the most sensitive and specific test for carpal tunnel syndrome is just to put thumb pressure
directly over that transverse carpal ligament. I'm effectively doing what you're doing when you're
driving or maybe riding a cycling. I'm putting extra pressure. And you're going to tell me
if that causes numbness, tingling, pain sometimes, but mainly numbness and tingling
in the median nerve distribution, that thumb, index, middle, and half the ring finger. And if
it does, then that's golden. We know you have carpal tunnel syndrome. And then the others that
we look for are these tenile signs. I'll go along here and tap. And the nerve, if you have bad carpal
tunnel, that median nerve can be irritable as it's lying in between these muscle bellies. And so we
can tap along there and you get a tenile sign and it sends electrical shocks. That's the second
way we can test it. The third way is just to have you mimic what you would do and the
phalines test where you hold them down like that and that reproduces as well. The most one is the
most sensitive and specific as the one I already did, but those are other. And that's pretty much
it for the, oh, there's one other component is we always want to look, if you have winging of the
scapula, you can do a push up against the wall. We can see if one side sticks out and that's that
upper cervical nerve rate, the long thoracic nerve. And that's really about it.
So, Walton, the last thing I want to talk about, and we've been talking for quite a while, so I
really appreciate you making the time, is I want to talk about the Musician Treatment Foundation,
which you founded almost six years ago. In fact, I feel like it's indirectly how we met
because one of the doctors who introduced me to you in New York City got to know you,
I think indirectly through your involvement with taking care of some of the best musicians in the
world. And that led to us meeting and such and such. And obviously I've been to some of the
concerts you've held. So, I mean, just tell folks a little bit about what is it about music that has
been such a passion. It seems to be as much a passion for you as orthopedic surgery.
Yeah, it is. And thank you for bringing it up. Thank you for wanting to talk a little bit about
it. I'm always happy to talk about it. I was lucky enough, we historically as orthopedic surgeons
treat a lot of athletes, but I was fortunate enough to start my practice in New York City.
And I was lucky enough to sort of inherit the caring of the New York Philharmonic and the
Metropolitan Opera orchestras, which are mainstays of that classical music echelon really. And then
that spilled over into Broadway, the musicians who are all manner of genres because there's so many
diverse shows there, and then the jazz musicians in rock and roll and so forth. So, yes, I've always
had a passion for music and love it. And to be able to take care of these is both very stressful
initially and also incredibly rewarding, right? And they are, they're like musicians and, I mean,
they're like athletes and that they're doing this day in and day out. It's their livelihood. And if
it's disrupted their way of being and then their, both their mental health and their financial health
is greatly jeopardized. And like athletes who give us so much entertainment in the world,
musicians speak the universal language of medicine, which obviously bypasses some of the
horrible political infighting that goes on. And it's just beautiful. Of music. And they give it
back to us. And so, but if you're not in the Philharmonic or not in the Metropolitan Opera orchestra
or in a long running show on Broadway, you're a freelance. And you're a freelance who doesn't
know when your next gig is going to happen and you can't afford insurance. And it's,
so I've, for my whole career, I've been taking care of freelance musicians and some of them
maybe have spouses or significant others who have insurance or some of them have, but many of them
don't, most of them don't frankly. And so I was always discounting my, my cost sometimes down to
nothing depending on who it was. And, or I'd take a chicken or a signed CD or something that they
would bring to me, some, some home baked cookies. And, but the costs are absolutely exorbitant for
healthcare. Right. Cause you can't waving your costs is one thing. You can't wave the anesthesia's
cost. You can't wave the Surgeon Center cost. Thank you. That's exactly right. And the average
cost for a rotator cuff repair is about currently just to, if you pay out of pocket, about the best
you can do through a surgery center, which is less cost on a hospital is about $25,000. Well,
the average income for a fully professional but freelance musician in Austin pre-COVID was
$16,000 a year. One six, one six. So they can't even think about it. So this was what was going
on for years. And it was always in my mind, always upsetting me. And that we, that as a culture,
we don't support the arts more. And I don't need to get political about that. It's not political.
It's just cultural. And so then I had my cousin Thor, who's a mainstay of the Austin music scene,
cut his digital nerve of his finger. He's a percussionist of course, cause his name is Thor.
And, and he couldn't play because it was so, he had such a neuroma that it formed and he didn't
have insurance. And he called me weeks after he had just had a simple closure. And he said,
I can't feel my finger and I can't play. And I said, well, you have, you have miles? And he said,
yeah, I've got plenty of miles cause I tour. And I said, we'll fly up to New York and we'll fix it.
So I, since I, um, know the surgery center and know the anesthesiologist, I said, look,
this is my cousin Thor. I need to, you know, I need you to throw him a bone. So they didn't
charge him. And of course I didn't either. And so fixed it. He was fine. He was my patient zero,
if you will. That was kind of your aha moment. That was the aha moment. And then I'm lucky enough,
as you said, to treat a lot of other musicians and know a lot of other musicians. So one day,
Elvis Costello and Diana Kral were in and, and I just kind of said, Hey, look, I'm thinking about
doing this officially. Uh, would you guys help me in some way? Anyway, I didn't care. Just put your
name on a website or something. They said, sure. What do you have in mind? I said, well, you could
just be an advisor or if I could just use your name, you're so well-loved and beloved. And they
said, well, let us be full, you know, full board members. And he said, my only stipulation is I
have to do all the boating because Diana's the busiest woman in show business. So, um, uh, so
I said, yes. And in 2017, we got, uh, IRS, uh, nonprofit status. And then Elvis said, I'm going
to do the first concert. I'll, I love the Paramount theater in Austin. Let's do it in Austin. I'll do
a two hour solo show. And we raised about a quarter of a million dollars with that. And that was our
seed money. And people came pouring in here in Austin. Ham is a big organization that does so
much as for so long, but it's the, you know, it's the health Alliance for Austin musicians,
but they don't provide the actual care. And they were struggling to get specialists to actually
discount their care or provide the care. And orthopedically speaking, having not having your
upper limb, your shoulder, elbow, or hand, you can't make music. Yeah. So just give us a brief
sense. Cause I know you and I have talked about this so much cause I'm so fascinated by this topic,
help people understand the physical demand of, you know, playing a violin or playing the drums.
I know you see my daughter plays the drums and get some sense of that, but, um,
a it's a very asymmetric activity, but what are the types of injuries that you're seeing
the high level musicians coming with that are a threat to their livelihood? Well,
one of the things I say, uh, I've lectured on this quite a bit as I say, you know,
musicians are people too. And so they do all the stupid things that we all do to injure ourselves.
That's a separate category. And those are injuries and they need to be treated though.
The unique aspect of that is that they can't necessarily take the same rest when they know.
And they have to be a hundred percent because if, if you're a violinist in the Philharmonic
and you are, there are 15 other highest level musicians waiting in the ranks,
waiting for you to screw up once a little shot and Freud there. They don't think ill of you,
but they would love to have the opportunity to sit in your seat, your chair on the, on the stage.
So there's all that tension, all that stress of having worked so hard and then having it.
And you have to be a hundred percent. You can't be, you can't, like I can do surgery with probably
three fingers, but you know, if you can't flex down your index finger or whatever, uh, on the,
on the, on the fret, then you can't make the music. So, uh, that's one aspect of it. And the other
aspect is that by comparison, they're not trying to jump higher, hit the ball farther, drive the
car faster. All the different ways that athletes like you are trying to maximize your output.
They are submaximal athletes, but they, but they have to be there.
So repetitious. Yeah. I mean, you think about how many, I think what there's in a, in a standard
NFL game, they're about 30 passes, 35 passes. Well in a typical one Mozart violin concerto.
It's 20,000 bow strokes in one playing of a, of a, of a huh. Concerto. And they do that repeatedly
over and over and over again. And to your point, yeah, it's a lot of these are very unnatural.
And we think about violinists, we think, oh, they're in their hands. Well, their shoulders,
they are adducted. They are externally rotated. Their other one is up in the impingement zone,
which we'll see from our exam. They're living eight hours a day doing this. That is terrible
for the shoulders. And then you think of the drummers, high hats, and every, which way they're
going and every, and going massively for three hours straight. It's just uncanny that they even
survive in my opinion. And so, so it's very, very different. I mean, I don't even know how many
passes Tom Brady has thrown in his career, but it's not that huge of a number. Right.
Relative to this. Right. And so, so anyway, so it, it, we, we were flooded with patients initially.
There was this backlog of patients who hadn't played for six months, nine months, and they were
just fallow. They were trying to get odd jobs. They weren't getting any gigs. They couldn't take
gigs. I had one patient, the very first patient who we've talked about. So I can mention her name,
Jennifer Jackson. She's a great singer songwriter in Austin and tours around. Did she play last year
at the concert? She did. Oh no, no, I'm sorry. She did not. She was on our, our, kind of our,
our movie about it. Okay. Got it. She had bilateral full thickness rotator cuff tears.
Bilateral. And she came in, she had already gone to try to see somebody. It was going to cost her
$10,000 or more. She had some very minimal insurance. And I said, look, you need, we need
to fix these. Let's do it. Get you back. And she goes, well, how much is it going to cost me? I said,
it's not going to cost you anything. And she just start crying. So now it's not going to cost you
anything. So we've in, in the five years, almost now coming up, well, yeah, uh, five plus years,
we've provided over $2 million in free care to under an uninsured professional. And how many,
how many musicians have had surgery? Oh, we've had probably I've done, um, four dozen, probably four
dozen, uh, around, around 50, um, musicians. And that doesn't include the ones that I've been
discounting that these are the ones that we've actually funneled through the, through. Yeah.
But we've got hundreds of non-operative because a non-operative is just as bad. I mean, right. So
if you can get a cortisone shot in there and get them totally better. Yeah. So we have hundreds
more of that. And, um, you know, it's, it's, it's been mind boggling. And the cool thing,
we have an upcoming concert in December with Elvis, with Roseanne Cash, John Levin,
fall Jason Isbell, a bunch of great people. Um, the, um, the cool thing about our, our,
our situation is that I've now been able to recruit over 60 colleagues who I know I trust.
They have the same ethic. They want to give back who are shoulder, elbow, and hand surgeons at the
best places around the country. We're going to have, we're launching that in December. It's called
the P4M, the Physicians for Musicians Network. They're going to do be doing so far. I've provided
all the care and now they're going to be helping provide care. So now really, we just need more
dollars coming in to help cover the other costs. Cause so basically you're always getting the
physicians to waive their fee. You now need to be able to basically use the nonprofit resources to
fund the surge of centers and anesthesia fees. And actually, I'm sure you're getting some
anesthesiologists who are musicians as well. We've been unsuccessful in that. It's ironic and
a little embittering for me, but I know we will be able to, once I'm hoping that people listening to
this who are anesthesiologists, someone's going to be like, wait a minute. I need to find fellow
anesthesiologists and we can start to pair those services.
And, and nice thing is that most surgeons, including myself, have some either participation
or partial ownership of a surgery center. So I happened to have built one here in Austin
and we provide that at one, I think it's one 10th of Medicare. So it's basically nothing.
It's our biggest cost by far as the anesthesia. Yeah. What's your vision for how big this can
get and what has to get there? I mean, so you have the big fundraiser every year, which is a
huge concert, gala, amazing. Each year it seems to be getting more and more incredible. What type
of fundraising goes on outside of that per year? It's actually been, I'm kind of a one man
fundraising machine because of all my generous patients, especially in New York and in Austin
too. And I tell everybody, I can't scream it from the mountaintops, but we're starting to get some
some grants, some grants were applying for grants, which is great. But anybody who knows
any organizations that provide community, you know, grants and so forth, we are right in the
thick of communities because it keeps, holds communities together. It develops relationships
that weren't there before and it's all ages, right? It's just. So this is a huge deal this year,
Alton is that you've now recruited other doctors because the scalability of this was limited when
you were the only surgeon. Exactly. But now that you've got how many more surgeons? We have over 60
signed on now. Amazing. Yeah. Yeah. So that's going to be a game changer. That's an amazing success.
And my idea, and they all have their own pods of, I mean, I treat more musicians and maybe anybody,
but in what I do, but they all treat some and they can access those. They can access donors in the
different towns. We have Seattle, we have LA, we have Nashville, we have New York, of course,
Chicago, New Orleans, the list goes on and on. And so yeah, when we can access that,
it will build the support, I think, significantly. Well, Alton, I could sit here and talk for about
another two hours, but I know you have a flight to catch to New York. It's probably apparent to
people listening to this, but you practice bicostally. Yes. So you, you, or not bicostally
rather, but you practice in two cities. So you're, you're Monday, Friday, you see clinic and you see
patients in clinic and operate in Austin. And then Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, you're in
New York city and you do this over and over and over again. I've had the privilege of seeing you
in both cities. I've had the privilege of sending patients to you in both cities. I don't know how
you do it. I used to do that and I can't do it anymore, but I'm so grateful for this discussion.
I think a lot of people are going to help from it. And obviously I'm so grateful for you personally
for the help in my life and obviously that of my patients. So thank you. Yeah. The gratitude is
likewise. Actually, I just want to give you a shout out. You at some point in one of our many
meetings, you said, you know, you mentioned rucking and I, you know, I didn't really know
that much about it, but you gave me the link. I bought it. I'm only carrying 35 pounds. That's
awesome. But I've been actually run rucking because I love running. I've always run. It has
changed my body in, in I've, I've only been doing it about three months and I only get to do it two
or three times a week. It's changed my body. I feel so much lighter, so much stronger and better.
And although I'm pretty old, I feel great and it, I commend you and I thank you because it's been a
game changer for me. Yeah. I'm the rucking evangelist. Well, thank you very much all. And this was
fantastic. Great. Thanks.