Hey everyone, welcome to the Drive podcast. I'm your host, Peter Attia.
So good to sit down with you, brother. You too. Thanks for having me.
So much to talk about, but I feel like I just want to start with kind of getting a sense
of the first time you heard about this. Was it a call from Darren? Like how did you even
get involved in this project?
Yeah, I had a call from Darren. It'd be going back on three years now. And he said, I want
to do this series, docu-series called Limitless on longevity. And he said, I know you're a
fit, healthy guy, but we want to dive into the science and put you in some pretty extreme,
intense, physical, emotional situations and see how you fare. And you can be the guinea
pig as far as the longevity science goes. And I said, why not? And initially, it was
supposed to be about a three week shoot. And I know you and I have talked about this a
lot. The once COVID hit, the show got spread out over two and a half years. And really,
it transformed in the best way possible. I think due to having a hell of a lot more time
than I think we'd first anticipated, we were able to flesh out each episode, explore the
science in greater detail. I was able to grow throughout the experience and have different
opinions on myself, different opinions on how I approached health and wellness. So yeah,
I'm really proud of how it turned out. And I think it was a lot due to the time span we're
able to shoot it on. So kind of going back to this, first of all, I can't believe they
bait and switched you on three weeks of shooting because like, even before COVID, I was involved
in four weeks of shooting. So I don't know where, where anybody thought it was.
Initially, it was two and I was like, I can't fit that in my schedule. That was three and
two and a half years. And we joke about it, right? What do we call it? Relentless.
We're going to do a title change. Limited. I was going to call it.
So where were you in? Had you, you were done Avengers by that point?
Yeah, what did I, I done Avengers. I think I was doing the press tour about the time this came up
and you hadn't done Love and Thunder. So I remember three years ago, almost to the day
I was sitting in my apartment here in New York with Darren, Ruth, Arie, I mean, every, you know,
sort of like the core group from Newtopia and from Protozoa. And at that point, so call it November
of 2019, they had the idea for six episodes, it was still a bit foggy. And it's kind of amazing how
quickly they morphed that into that first shoot when we started in January. Was there anything
about it that you had apprehension about doing? I mean, besides the time, obviously time is an
issue based on your schedule, but, you know, were you nervous, worried, anxious about doing this?
Because this is not acting. Yeah, I was, to be honest. So I had never hosted anything before.
And it's one thing to, you know, hide behind the character and behind the mask of whatever
individual you're playing in a film setting. But then to be yourself, you know, I've done
obviously plenty of interviews and so on. But to be in a situation like this, where it was
not only looking into the science, but dissecting kind of my abilities and seeing what my limits
were in one regard. And, you know, there was a vulnerability that's required there. I had to be
authentic. So I, you know, didn't want to hold back. But it's, yeah, it was a little more of a
hesitation or a lot more sort of thinking about it as how I was going to come across and was it
going to be genuine? Was it going to be appreciated or not? Or, you know, all sorts of silly kind of
doubts and any questions start to creep in that I wasn't normally sort of thinking about.
And then the thing transformed anyway, as far as my initial, was there any hesitation around taking
on the show? I don't think any of us knew what it was going to be. You know, the three or four weeks
that we'd talk about even when you're involved. And I spoke to Darren the last couple of days
about this. He said, yeah, it was a very different beast at the beginning. And due to the time, but
also, I think due to what I was willing to do and the commitment I had for it, it was allowed to
evolve and become something bigger. And as did the challenges, you know, there were discussions about
cold water immersion and we're going to do ice baths and so on. And then it was like, well,
let's go to Norway and let's, you know, swim in the Arctic Ocean. And it sort of
became more and more epic as it went on. It feels like you and I don't want to project this, but
so correct me if I'm wrong. But as I watched you, because, you know, one of the things about this
that was kind of a joy is how close we became as a group like you, your team, me, like the whole
group kind of coalesced. It's like you seem to trust the team even more and more as time went on
and gave more and more of yourself because again, you know, everybody sort of got involved in this
with the expectation this was going to be, you know, bracketed in terms of time and COVID in
part. But also I just think the, you know, the breadth of expectation of what this could be
expanded the scope so much. Do you get the sense that you were willing to give way more of yourself
as this thing went on that maybe you had committed to up front? Absolutely. And I think
due to what you're saying about there's a trust there with the people I was working with.
I knew on paper that these were the experts in their field and all of you were going to take care
of me and advise me in the right way. But it's like you're working with a director and each of
the experts in each of these series were kind of leading the way and they're at the helm. And I was
following and if I have a good relationship with my director and I trust them and that only comes
through experience and time spent, then I'm going to give more of myself and take more risks and
not feel like it's going to be exploited in any way. So the first episode that we filmed was the
fasting one. Look, I'm going to do it with you. Yeah. Yeah. It makes it a lot easier to go through
this with somebody else. So okay, good. We'll suffer together. We will. I've definitely gone
a day without food before. I think I get pretty cranky when I've missed a meal. Certainly
detrimental to my happiness. It's a pretty long time. Why four days? Why not? Why not longer?
I mean, what is the benefit with four days? Why that number? Three to four days is probably that
window at which we do enough to change how your body is interacting with the absence of nutrients
to basically do kind of a reboot on your system. Oh really? Do you think I'm going to be able to
hold them together? Do you reckon in your experience you see a lot of people the first time they do it
succeed? In the next four days there is no doubt in my mind there will be a period of time in which
you feel sluggish or tears. Yeah. Kind of grumpy, grouchy, whatever. But if you really stop to think
about it, this idea that we kind of live today where we're sort of surrounded by unlimited access
to food and we can eat three meals and snack in between them, that's a relatively recent addition
to our species. Right. And our ancestors would have gone days without food all the time and not
only did they have to do that, they had the ability to in a period of starvation actually go out and hunt.
I feel that I think that shows up third or fourth in the sequence. Yeah, it does. What did you know
going into that and what was your expectation? Just that I had never fasted before and I knew
that this was going to be a challenge. And I don't think you knew how long it was going to be or
anything like that. I mean, we sort of sprung that on you in real time over that dinner. We did. I
think the initial discussions were around like intermittent fasting and restricted sort of
feeding windows. And then it was like, oh, maybe we'll do a day or a couple of days. And you're
like, no, we're doing four days. And by the way, I suggested three. Did you? I did. And they said,
no, no, we're going to go one more because I said I wouldn't normally have a patient go more than
three days on the first one. And they pushed it to four. It was, yeah, I don't know. I mean,
as we talked about many times, my expectation or kind of thoughts around would I be able to do it
or not? I think we're in line with yours. I thought, look, we're going to commit. We're going to do it.
But we kept discussing, you know, you'll kick into ketosis on day two, you know, and maybe day
three and then come to like day four. And I'm like, no, I'm not feeling any of the sharpness or
alertness. And then right in the afternoon when we went spearfishing, probably at the right time,
it kept in and things started to sort of percolate. I remember saying to Tanya,
I think it was to Tanya, it might have been somebody else, but I think it was to Tanya as we
were getting ready to head out on the boat. That was the moment when I kind of realized how
sort of strong you were, because I felt like you didn't have that much time to prepare for that
exercise. And it wasn't under ideal circumstances. It's one thing to say, you're going to do your
first fast. It's going to be for four days. And it was hard enough. I mean, we worked out every day.
We had a bunch of other things that we had to do, but then learning an entirely new skill around
breath holding and spearfishing. I mean, I think we'll be challenging under any circumstance.
How much of that do you remember? You know, it's been almost three years since we filmed that,
but how much of that do you remember? And was there ever a moment when you thought,
I'm not worried that something's going to happen to me, but I'm worried that I'm not going to be
successful. Yeah, I think that was most of the episodes. As I'd get to, you know, doing the Arctic
swim or doing the four day fast or climbing the rope, I kept thinking, if I don't complete this
exercise, it's not really an episode or it's pretty anticlimactic. And so there was definitely
a healthy amount of fear there kind of motivating me. But I don't know, it also coming back to
the why of it and why we're doing it and understanding the specific purpose of
each challenge was, you know, on one hand, looked like they were trying to kill me. But
on the other hand, was like, there was an incredible amount of information and knowledge
and support and science there that says you do this, you do this consistently, you work this
into your daily routine, then the benefits are exponential. So let's think about Norway,
because that was we filmed that in I think February, right? We went right from Australia,
maybe had two weeks off, and then we're all in Norway. My recollection of that was a beauty like
I couldn't imagine. So we were there to do this thing, but it was in this place that you would
normally never go to, I feel like we took like three flights to get there or something crazy.
So, again, Ross spoke about this a little bit last night, which was, it was another example of
you were being asked to do something much quicker than you would normally do. So,
right, I think you didn't how many was the first day you jumped in that water? Because it's different
than an ice bath. Like you can send an ice bath all you want. It's totally different experience
to jump in the ocean when it's 36 degrees Fahrenheit. Yes. Some of the episodes I was
able to train for specifically probably the strength episode that was on and off
of the course of six, seven months, and then I had injuries and so on. But the cold water immersion,
I mean, I did a couple of ice baths back in. We were doing some in Australia.
Back in Australia. And that was new to me. And then I was talking to Ross about it. And
the sort of overarching idea was that, you know, they were talking about developing brown fat,
you know, and we're going to monitor that. Ross is like, no, not in four days. This is going to
happen. And so it became as much adaptation around cold water immersion as much as it was
sort of a resilience test or just a grit head down go for it. Because the first time we jumped in the
water in Norway, and we were in there for four and a half minutes. And that was longer than any ice
bath I've had. But it was snowing. I'm breathing in, you know, freezing cold air. And windy. And
I'm also moving, you know, you sit in an ice bath and there's a couple of mill of water that starts
to heat up. You stay still, you're trading water, then none of that's happening. So a lot of it was
trusting Ross and listening to Ross's voice and just kind of, again, back to what you said about
the trust. If I didn't have Ross there coaching me through it, having also done it and even to even
more extremes, I would have questioned it to no end. And in particular, on that actual, on the
actual swim itself, halfway through, I was like, every part of me was like, you're dying, get out
of the water. Yeah, explain to me and to folks watching and listening what it feels like, because
I have never been in water that cold. I've done long swims at about 49 degrees. And even at that
temperature, which seems balmy compared to 36, I mean, that's a big difference, right? It feels
like you're on fire. Oh, yeah. It actually feels like you're in boiling oil, which I think most
people wouldn't understand. How is that possible that you can get in something so cold and the
sensation is that of being lit on fire? And then the other thing that I think is, I'm curious to
whether you felt it as well is the breathlessness. Like it starts to take your breath away. Yeah,
it definitely, I mean, I'm not going to sound overly dramatic, but it was one of the most painful
things I've ever done. And again, the comparison to the ice bar is very different. The big thing
was putting my head underwater. Again, an ice bar. Remind me, did you have earplugs? I don't think I
did. No. And the big difference, by the way. Oh, yeah. But I was standing on the shore,
and all the training we'd done was treading water head above water. And Ross is like, let's go for
a proper swim tomorrow. And I was like, I don't, I just don't want to do it, mate. I'm just saving
it for the day. Or, you know, the afternoon when we actually shoot it, I'm just going to go for it.
Because if I experience, and I think in hindsight, if I had have experienced how painful it was,
I would have been even more doubtful. So I was standing on the edge and he said, we want to warm
up as much as possible before you get on and strip off and dive in. And he said, and then when you get
in, just take a second to try and adjust before you put your head under. And we did the warm up,
I walked down to the edge, and I didn't even know if they were rolling. And I was like, I'm out of
here. I'm in the water and I'm off. And Ross didn't even have time to jump onto the boat that
was chasing us along. I jumped in, just started going. And the first like, I don't know, maybe
25, 30, 40 meters, I was like, got this. You know what, I'm going all the way. I'm going,
I'm coming back. I'm doing two laps. And out of nowhere, once the initial sort of adrenaline
went, I felt the most extreme headache, pain, right? To all through and to the back of my eyes,
the front of my head everywhere. And I started, I was looking at the bottom as I was swimming,
and I started getting really dizzy. And then I all of a sudden stopped and I was like, I'm going to
throw up like it was that painful. And I look and I've actually swum off course a bit. And I've
started swimming toward where the couple of the camera guys are. And they're like, the buoys that
way go that way. So I head down again. And the whole time I'm just like, nah, get out, get out,
get out. And then I have another voice in my head, I have Ross's voice there saying,
come on, fight, fight, dig in. And I just started going for it. But what starts to happen is your
arms and legs are just like lead balloons. Nothing works. And I didn't even, you know,
I felt like I was swimming like this, a little chicken. And you can't keep your fingers together.
So your fingers start to splay. You can't hold the water. And it's just like, it was gnarly.
And then I got to the buoy and they're all cheering and stuff. And, you know, Darren said,
I was waiting for a big celebration. I was like, I couldn't move. I was supposed to die. And then
the jet ski pulls up and he's like, well done, mate. And I'm like, I can't help me on, mate.
I can't lift my arms. And they drag me up onto it. And then the same thing would have
gone on the boat. Everyone's like cheering and Ross is like, get out of the way. And he came
in with a blanket and a little beanie and sort of started warming me up and so on.
Yeah, it was wild. But the, I've never felt the endorphin kick and the sort of elation
that I felt afterward. It was incredible. And I just remember this, the most serene, peaceful
state in awe of everything. And we are there in Norway. It's the most stunning backdrop. But
it's just this wonderful sense of calm and overwhelming sort of joy. And I think
it then it comes with anytime you achieve something that you think is impossible or
overcome some great challenge or, you know, in the face of diversity or whatever you have
overcome it. There is such a beautiful feeling. It made me think about people who, you know,
climb Everest and do extreme feats all the time. And the rest of us are wondering why the hell
would you do that? I believe it's for that moment. That post feeling was pretty special.
I remember it for a long time. Well, I think there's actually something within that. It's
not just the accomplishing the feet. It's the temporal juxtaposition of being so low and so high.
Right. Right. Like I don't think, you know how we don't feel speed? Like if you're on an airplane,
you don't feel it. You feel acceleration. In other words, we're only wired, I think,
to feel a rate of change. Right. And I think that's true of emotion. Like if you're constantly
in a state of bliss, everything is going well all the time. I don't think you feel profound joy.
So I think the reason in part, I mean, I think there's a physiologic expectation for what you
experience. We'll talk about that in a sec. But I think what you're also experiencing is
four minutes earlier, I thought I was going to die. And even if the upper part of your brain
knew you weren't, the reptilian part of your brain absolutely believed it. You were dead.
And then four or five minutes later, you have this unbelievable surge of positive emotion.
I don't think you can find a period of time. And when just four minutes, you can go from your
absolute lowest to your absolute highest. I think that's the thing. That's the juice.
Yeah, absolutely. And with no negative, lasting injury, et cetera. Yeah, for sure.
I mean, of all the things in limitless, right, the strength stuff, the endurance stuff,
the mental challenges, all those things. The hardest one to make the case for,
this will make you live longer, is go and jump in the Arctic Ocean and swim. However,
I think about the benefits of cold water. I think that is something everybody should get used to
exposing. I mean, just this morning, right? Like, you and I had breakfast, had to really quickly go
up, shower, come get over here. I still made time to spend 30 seconds to a minute in the ice water
of the shower in the hotel. And I love that feeling of the first time you get into the ice water,
you feel that little thing. And I mean, there is really compelling evidence at what this does to
brain chemistry. And so that's the other thing that I think you're also experiencing, although
in your swim, it was to a much higher degree than just taking a cold shower and ice bath. But you
were, I think, probably being flooded with endorphins and neurotransmitters that are very
positive. Absolutely. And you still do this. I mean, this is still kind of a part of your routine.
You're constantly taking an ice bath. Yeah. And it's probably about exactly what you're saying,
like the endorphin kick, but also, every time we get in the ice bath, whether I'm somewhat used to
it, it's still brutal. But the moment you get out, it's like you say, you've gone from one extreme
to another. So it's an instant sort of kick of happiness. But I find even like, you know,
just from inflammation, repair, the general mood, my if I had, you know, wake up in the morning,
and I'm feeling off and I'm achy and I'm not in the space, I can have a hot shower and like,
I'm still a bit doughy, but I jump in the cold and completely different. It's a game changer.
So does Elsa join you? Do your kids join you? One of my kids often tries to jump in for
not that long, but gives it a go. Yeah. Elsa does it too. We have a sauna and an ice bath set up at
home. And it's the best. It's the best rehab. I couldn't agree more. Single best investment
I've ever made was the sauna cold plunge at home. Yeah, definitely. So let's talk about strength.
So Chris, you obviously spend a lot of time working on your strength training. What type of
program do you do? I mean, I've over the years, training for different roles and for Thor,
in particular, it was about getting big and mass. I do shoulders one day, arms and other, back,
chest, legs. Got it. Okay. You're okay? Uh-huh.
Obviously, he's in amazing shape. Most of us would look at Chris and give anything to look like that.
But there's always room for improvement. There are more than 600 muscles in the human body.
And for longevity, you've got to make good use of as many as possible.
So when I assessed Chris's muscular power and efficiency, his flexibility and agility,
I found he could be working a wider range of those muscles.
And he could improve his stamina.
I think that was, I think, an awesome episode because I think, and this is a great example of
where COVID really benefited the series. Because the initial challenge for strength was
kind of an interesting challenge, but I think the one you ultimately ended up doing was better.
Yeah. And my only view on this was from a scientific perspective, what can we say about
strength and longevity or fitness and longevity and really like kind of grip strength,
cardiorespiratory fitness would be top of the list. And that's why I think that that challenge
was a perfect challenge because it's grip strength, it's top end cardiorespiratory fitness.
Yeah. Initially, yeah, initially it was I was going to be in a harness and pulling a car across
a section of land. And Ross Edgley had done that, I think for 20 hours or something crazy. So he was
like, I'll try and get it to that. And we were doing it and I did like, I did a good month, like
pulling the sled in the backyard. I had a little Polaris doing buggy thing that I was pulling for
a bit. And it just started to like, aggravate my back and joints and everything. And then so we
transitioned then to the rope climb. And as you say, it was probably more on point as far as the
science around strength and longevity. And then I started training for the rope climb, I'd never
climbed the rope before. And Ross had also done a feat like that. And so it was, was training me.
He said to me, look, you want to be strong, but you don't want to be heavy. The heavier you are,
the harder it is to get up that rope. So I had a three meter rope in my house.
And that's 10 feet for the Americans. Yeah, 10 feet my house. And I was going kind of three
quarters the way up and just jumping off and back up and down and doing loops like that.
And one day I jumped down, blew my ankle out and I ruptured all the ligaments and tore ligaments.
What happened by the way? Like, was there anything different that day?
I literally just landed on the... The UFC was on, right? My mates were in the next room and I was
in the gym where my house set up. And they got quit starting. I'm like, I'm just getting in 15
minutes and I'm up and down. And it must have been like, you know, last one. And I just jumped off
and I had a mat there and it just, I just rolled my ankle. And it just blew out. And straight away
looked at it was ballooned and utopia and all the team from Nat Geo were in Australia ready to shoot.
I think it was next week. So, I called them up and said, this ain't going to happen. And I had a
doctor have a look and I said, yeah, this is not good. And that was the rope. That was the foot.
I was going to anchor off as I was pulling myself up. And for folks that have seen Thor,
you've got kind of different bodies in there. Obviously, I assume the biggest you were in
Thor was that scene when you were in front of Russell Crowe. Yeah. By the way, I was that size
for that afternoon and kind of fluctuate through the film. Obviously, you pick your windows and
doors of kind of, you know, where to be your biggest. And this was like, I had been training
with Ross prior to that, and quite intensely and learned some pretty unique special things and how
to just kind of blast the body and do the most effective, intense workouts and when and what to
eat and so on. So, I was schooled in that more so than I'd ever been before. So, I had an opportunity
to get stronger, bigger than I ever was. But the timing of it didn't line up with this event. And so
Ross turns up and I tried to, hadn't been using the rope at all because I'd been working and we
started doing it and I was just heavy. And I was getting like three, four pulls up and I was just
like, everything was tightening up and so on. So, we had about two weeks where I just stopped lifting
weights completely. And it's funny, I don't know, you know, every time if you've ever put on a big
amount of muscle that it doesn't take long for your body to go. Okay, this is, we can switch gears
now. And so, I started doing a lot more rope pulls and sled pulls and got down to the Blue Mountains
where we shot and there was a... And what was your weight doing during that period of time? How much
weight were you dropping? I mean, it was only a few weeks, a little bit. But I was still... Did you
make an effort to reduce your intake as well? Yeah. Because you were eating like crazy. Two and a half
weeks. I stopped lifting weights. I reduced my calories pretty dramatically and maybe lost a
couple of kilo. I don't know. It might have been like two or nine or something. But still heavier
than I should have been for it. Yeah. And we get to the Blue Mountains and it's the most beautiful
setting. And there's the cable cart across two mountains. There's a thousand foot off the ground.
And we go out onto this cart and they throw the rope out and it's 100 feet the rope, which is
three, four times longer than anything I've climbed in my training or anything.
So again, this became less about what you've trained for this and more about just, again,
grit and will and just get up there. And I just remember Ross kind of at the top of the cart going,
make it a fist fight. Make it a fight. Come on, big man.
Stand by for the doors opening.
Got the rope going out.
Oh, don't even look out there.
Why? That's all hits me.
And all the little voices of doubt that I've been pushing aside in my mind
start to get louder and louder.
I'm looking down and I'm thinking that is not something I fancy doing.
But I cannot let Chris see any moment of doubt in my mind at all.
Oh.
Switch on. Switch on. Switch on. Yeah.
Ready?
So I'm getting winched down and it feels a lot longer than 100 feet.
I don't want to look back up because I'm like, this is so much further than I've ever climbed.
How long did it actually take start to finish?
Probably, I don't know, probably a couple of minutes. It's a long time to be, there's no,
there's a harness that will catch me if I fall, but none of it is helping me up the road.
And I was surprised the quad burn was one of the most gnarly things.
More than your hands, more than your forearms.
Both, biceps and forearms. I mean, when I got off, I had like claws. I couldn't extend my fingers.
They were locked. But my quads and especially my right leg kind of doing the push and the anchor.
So how do you feel physically now from a strength perspective in terms of like
how this has kind of morphed your training a little bit?
I feel it's more specific, my training now. I used to just sort of go in,
and I still do to an extent, like, and just start throwing weights around and go,
I get biceps, I go back and I get chest and shoulders and just as heavy as I could,
as much as I could. And when I was a bit younger, I could get away with doing that.
And then now it's like, oh, geez, I'm just not warming that up properly.
Or, you know, you're kind of hitting everything too many times. And so
just being smart about the training. And that came from working with Ross and
my trainer Luke Zocki as well. And we did, he just targeted much more targeted approach.
He has really interesting, intense ways to work out though. It's everything is about sort of
explosive energy, like light up your, was it your parasympathetic nervous system and just
switch on sympathetic. Yeah. So what are you guys? Simultaneous? Sorry. Yeah.
And fire up and just explosive up and then slow negatives. That made dramatic differences. I got
far more gains than I had previously training like that. Now you actually, I don't think I've
told you this by the way, but you know, in the process of kind of going through a lot of your
genetic stuff, which we're doing now, right? Like, so kind of, we'll talk about this in a second,
but kind of doing this, you know, we actually found that you have a very favorable gene around
muscle fibers. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, so I think that, you know, we were going to talk a second
about kind of like a gene you have that, that we wish we could erase, but on the flip side,
you got it. You've got a pretty favorable gene around a fast twitch muscle fibers. Yeah. So I
think, you know, you sort of have a genetic predisposition to be muscular and to be strong
and to be explosive. It's, I've always, even I was lean when I was younger, but as soon as I started
even when I was playing footy, you know, I was 17 doing more pushups, whatever I would, I would
grow. And it's, you know, I've always had to work my ass off in that space, but it, yeah, I do feel
I've had some, some benefits there. It's a, it's a great variant of a gene to have as you age,
because one of the hallmarks of aging is actually atrophy shrinkage of these fast twitch muscle
fibers. So shrinkage in Norway, definitely. Different type. Different type, but yes, yes,
yes. So as we get older, these slow twitch muscle fibers are shrinking in everybody. And that's why
people are losing strength and power and explosiveness most rapidly as they age,
much more than they're losing endurance, slow fiber, right? So, you know, one of the things
we always talk about with our patients is, Hey, we need you lifting weights all the time. Yeah.
You start early and you never stop lifting weights. And the heaviest you can lift is the
better because it's only through lifting heavy weights that you can really get those fast twitch
type two muscle fibers firing. So the fact that you kind of have a genetic predisposition to have
more of them is a good thing, which then brings us to kind of like some of the other stuff we talked
about. So, you know, one of my earliest memories of this whole experience was in December of 2019,
we took advantage of the fact that you were in LA to get some blood work done. And, you know,
Darren said, look, here's the deal. You and Chris are going to sit down in January in Australia to
kick off the first bit of shooting. And I want you to walk Chris through his blood work, just as you
would do with a patient the very first time. And I said, okay, great. So we get the, I get the blood
test back about two weeks before I'm supposed to go out to Australia. And I see something in it that
you know, I say, Darren, I can't walk him through this for the first time on camera.
It's not, that's not fair to him. And I know you guys would like, I mean, I know that that's what
sort of the drama is, but this is a bit too much. But I can't tell you, Darren, what it is. So
without telling you, you need to trust me that this can't be done on camera for the first time.
This one thing, you can do the whole lab, but this one thing. So I asked him to sort of trust me and
he did. And then that, and then we connected. So he called me first. Yeah. He caught him in a
panic and was like, you've got to call Peter Attia, something's come up. And, but I don't know what
it is. And I was like, how long have I got left? And, and so I was kind of rattled before we even
got on the phone. We did sort of the million dollar work up on you. We've got every blood test one can
get. And I've looked at every gene in your body six ways to Sunday. And overall, your labs look
fantastic. And I think looking at you from the outside, it's clear how much you take care of
yourself. But we did find a couple of things that are a cause for concern. Some of the genetic
testing that we did looked at a gene for a protein called ApoE. You have a very rare combination,
which is you have two copies of ApoE4, a set from your mom and a set from your dad.
And what does that mean exactly? That means you have an increased risk of Alzheimer's disease.
How much higher? Probably somewhere between eight and 10 times higher than that of someone in the
general population. You're right. Okay. You know, you're, I don't know, you're constantly thinking
you're going to live forever, especially as a young individual. And then to all of a sudden be
told all this may be the thing that might take you out was like, whoa, kind of floored me for a minute.
You know, it's hard to imagine, but it's my belief that if we take every step possible,
we can reduce your risk to that of anyone else. Sure. In fact, I don't think you'll believe me
when I say this, but I think you will in time. You having this gene is probably a blessing.
Because of the motivation that will get me to. Yeah. Yeah. This is going to motivate you to take
steps today that most people your age would never think about until there's their fifties or sixties.
Sure. I hadn't had too many patients that had this combination of ApoE4, four. It's not a very
common genotype. It's only about 1% of the population. So I've probably only at that time
had maybe three patients that had it. And truthfully, two of the three of them
kind of suspected it before the blood test based on their family history. In one case,
about a 40 year old woman, total shocker. And so I remember just sort of trying to say, look,
this is a gene that really increases risk of Alzheimer's disease, but it's not a deterministic
gene. And that's, I think just something someone like me can take for granted because I'm sort of
in this space. I understand that, but I think that's a hard concept to explain to somebody
who doesn't eat, sleep and breathe genetics, which is you have this gene and it doesn't guarantee
this thing is going to happen. And there are some genes that do, by the way, there were certain
genes that if you have the gene, if the gene for Huntington's disease, you're going to get
Huntington's disease. This isn't that kind of gene, but it's increasing your odds. And that's the bad
news. And then the good news is the earlier you know this, the more you can do to mitigate risk.
So that's sort of, that was my message, but what did you hear? I mean, how much do you think back
to that day? Again, I knew nothing about the science or the sort of the markers and so on
outside of that one conversation. And so I hung up and I was trying to explain it to my wife and
I was like, yeah, I'm not really sure what he just said, but I think I, you know, I'm more
vulnerable to Alzheimer's. And then we had another conversation. And I wish we'd had more
conversations immediately after because I did spend sort of a week going, what does this mean?
And I'm trying to talk to my parents about it. And they didn't know much about it either.
My grandfather has Alzheimer's and it's been very tragic to watch. And so they were aware of it,
but didn't know in any great detail about the gene combination we're talking about.
But as you say, it was just a good sort of kick in the ass and a reminder to, you know, do what I
can, whatever's within my control and within my power to give myself the best fighting chance.
And, you know, whatever work I'm doing for brain health benefits the rest of my body and the rest
of my life anyway. So, yeah, we turned it into a positive. You know, one of the things that was
sort of interesting about filming this is we obviously came out, we filmed it and we did
everything in duplicate for those episodes, right? We did it where we did everything. We talked about
all this and we went through all this stuff. And then of course, it was also done, which is, hey,
there's a really good chance that we're not going to want to talk about this particular aspect of
Chris's health publicly. So let's redo that whole thing, but without that. And I think for about
two years, it was, we didn't know which version of this was going to happen. Obviously, the decision
was a hundred percent yours. Why, when and why did you decide that you wanted to be public with
something so personal? Once I understood more about it, but also the same reason it's motivated me to
make positive changes, I thought, well, that's a great opportunity for anyone else out there
who may be in the same situation to either go and get checked or to understand more about brain
health and see what they have within their power to make that change. So I thought, oh, it's a,
I don't know, it's a missed opportunity to motivate others to do the same if I don't talk about it.
And then they cut together two versions of the episode. And the other one was just kind of fell
flat. So this had, there was no, it didn't over dramatize or exploit or anything. I think what
they did a great job at was it just became relatable. It became, and this is what most
of the series was like, look, he's a human being, like you or I, and you know, the sort of superhero
costume aside, this is an individual who has many of the same challenges and is up against the same
things that all of us. So even though you have two copies of the APO-E4 gene, which is a very
rare combination, you know, 20 to 25% of the population has at least one copy of the E4 gene.
And even though that doesn't increase their risk as much as the increase that you experience,
it still does. In fact, even though it's only 20 to 25% of the population that has that gene,
that group of people makes up about two thirds of cases of Alzheimer's disease. So I do think,
you know, I applaud you for doing it. And I'm really glad you did decide to do this because I,
I've always said I really wish every single person would know their APO-E genotype early in life.
And there, and there's a lot of resistance in the medical community to this truthfully. There are a
lot of physicians who would say, look, no one should know that. There's nothing that can be
done about it. Why would you burden somebody with that knowledge? And people like me and Richard
Isaacson, Kellyanne Neotis, you know, people I work with, I mean, we fundamentally disagree
with that, Chris. We think that is complete nonsense. And we think that this is absolutely
a condition through which you have an enormous lever arm to mitigate risk. And if that's true,
which I wholeheartedly believe it is, then not knowing that information early is criminal.
Yeah. Well, and also as we're saying that whatever I do in regards to, you know,
protection and arming myself with, you know, the sort of tools to have the best chance,
it benefits everything else anyway. You know, we talked about, you know, reducing stress levels,
more mindfulness practices, the certain training I do, nutrition, my sleep habits,
all those things about a dramatic difference in every other part of my life too. So,
you know, one of the things I'll talk about is sauna, right?
But Peter's convinced that regular saunas can boost my long-term health.
You know, now that we just got in here, Chris, let's take your pulse.
Yeah. You're about 64 beats per minute, but we've got this temperature cranked up to about 195
degree Fahrenheit. So let's see where you are in a couple of minutes.
I guess I got to get used to this hate. Yeah. We're uncomfortable right now because we're hot.
And in response to that, our body is trying to cool us off. And so it's pumping harder so that
your heart can quickly get the blood to the outside of your body. And just as exercise is known to help
with cardiovascular disease, I think sauna has a number of those benefits as well.
How much of a fan were you of sauna before we shot that series in Norway and then really kind
of got into the science of why it's likely, it hasn't been proven yet to the same extent that
some things have because so much of the data is observational, but it's so overwhelmingly
positive in the same direction with every single study. And I think we're quite confident it is.
You know, I know you've always enjoyed it, but has that taken on kind of a more urgent role?
Yeah, definitely. I mean, definitely during having shot the show, it's made it,
or it's become a bigger part of my daily routine, often after a workout. And again,
I don't know what the science says, but I know I feel great after doing it. Same with an ice bath.
And so if sort of mood elevation was the only thing, then I'm all about it.
Well, I would say even if, you know, the emphasis and the benefit of the heat shock proteins is less
than what we think, I agree with you. I think just the psychological benefit and the sleep benefit.
I mean, the difference in my sleep between when I sauna and when I don't is so noticeable that,
and we, you know, then again, are we going to question the benefits of sleep? I don't think so.
I mean, there is no doubt, even with if I've been training a lot and I wake up achy in particular,
you know, like I've had issues with my back over the years, if I wake up and I get in the sauna in
the morning and I do an ice bath or either or like, I feel 50, 60 percent better. And the sort of,
you know, that's the thing you lie in bed all night and you're in that position and
everything starts to kind of, I don't know, lies dormant and becomes, I don't know, there's no
fluidity there, you know what I mean? You wake up and you're stiff and sore and then you get into
one of those spaces, the hot, the cold or the hot. And instantly I feel like everything's just kind of
lit up and awakened. So when we think about kind of the last episode, which is the one that we saw
in the premiere, we were talking about this over breakfast today, but that episode maybe more than
any other really reaped the benefit of COVID because it had so much more time to flesh out.
You know, when I think about what the first version of the final episode was supposed to look
like, if this was kind of blasted through in 2020, I won't restate what that episode was supposed to
be, but it was kind of gimmicky. It didn't work. I didn't think it would work. And then what it became
is unbelievable. What was, in your mind, how was the evolution of that episode? Because I,
did you have much of a hand in the creative side of that or were you kind of just a passenger?
I was a passenger and I was kept in the dark intentionally. Darren didn't want me to know
much about it. It was an immersive theater experience and I'm glad I didn't know it because
I feel like I would have had preconceived sort of ideas and then expectations and I wouldn't,
you know, couldn't have helped acting a certain way or reacting a certain way based on that. So
to go into it blind and just open and ready for whatever they were going to throw at me or throw
me into was exciting and different to the other episodes. Everything else was about being prepped
in some way and learning and understanding some of the science prior to shooting, whereas this,
it was about all I knew was it was about the acceptance of death.
All I've been told is that I'm about to jump forward 50 years into the future
and spend the next three days living the life of an octogenarian.
The architect of this strange challenge is Dr. PJ Miller, a world-renowned pallet
of care physician. His work centers on unlocking the transformative power of accepting aging
and death. Dying offers us something but we can change how we see it, what we do with it,
how we play with it. Chris is about to take part in a truly unique experiment.
Ready my old man? Uh, don't know. I mean ask me in three days time, baby.
What did that suit feel like? Uh, just uncomfortable and incredibly restrictive.
And I talk about this in the episode, the way people then spoke to me because I knew I couldn't
hear properly and you know there was all this condescending sort of patronizing tone of,
you know, how you hear people and some of the time talk to the elderly, you know.
And it may be immediately going, oh my god, I hope I don't do that. But incredibly isolating too,
visions diminished and as I said you can't hear restricted so everything is, has been,
has been pulled away. All the sort of your abilities that were there the hour before I put
it on. And also not having 50 years to transition into that. Yeah, overnight. One extreme to the
other in the opposite direction to what we've told them before. There are so many things about
that episode that are beyond beautiful. One of them to me, it's just a very subtle thing is that
all of the residents of that place were not actors. Yeah. And what was it like kind of
interacting with them? Because you know you watch the episode, it's like a, you know,
slightly over an hour long episode, but I assume shooting it was days, at minimum three days.
Yeah. So you have a lot of time on that set. I reckon some of those folks didn't necessarily
know who you were prior to that episode. I don't think I'm down to be honest. Which must have been
a great relief, wasn't it? It was, it was really nice. It was, it was unique and different on so
many levels that that episode. But to be in a retirement village with elderly folks who,
you know, were there for the fun of the episode, but were just genuine and truthful and honest and
didn't hold back with anything that we're thinking. And there was sort of the no filter
approach to things was, it was great. It was refreshing, you know, I think being in a sort of
industry where a lot of people do know who you are. And a lot of the time you're sort of
supporting what you're doing and everything's kind of tried to, you know, be made or be
accommodating as possible. That was like, no, you're one of us now. And it was fantastic. It
brought me straight back to Earth, if I'd drifted previously. Well, having known you for many years
now, you're pretty down to Earth. But I still think that that must have been even another level
because you're so far out of your comfort zone. This wasn't the, there's no superhero component
to this. No. I was a lot more nervous about that episode than anything else. Because it wasn't
something I could fight or muscle through or just put my head down, you know, grip my teeth and go
for it. I had to be completely open and vulnerable and accessible and confront things that I had
never really thought about that much and interact with people who were at the end of their days,
or who had dealt with death in very extreme ways or come close to death. And so to go from sort of
one environment of physical sort of challenges and feats and then go into this emotional state
was a real shock and an adjustment. And I'm so proud of what the episode is and became because
it's unlike anything I've certainly ever done, but unlike anything I think that I've seen before in
the doc space. Several moments that really stood out to me. I'm guessing you didn't know
B.J. Miller's story before that episode. No, I didn't. Because it came across as
really genuine when you're hearing it for the first time on camera. It looked to me as though
that was the first time you were hearing. It was. Do you recall what that felt like? Because it
seemed like you got quite emotional. And I'm curious as to what was more emotional. Was it
the tragedy of his story or was it more how moved you were by his resilience and how he overcame it
to do what he's doing? A combination of things. He's one of the most unique individuals I've ever
met. This is something saintly and otherworldly about him. He is such a beautiful individual.
Certainly his story shook me. And also the strength now that in which he reflects upon it
and his attitude toward what happened to him was so inspiring. It made me, you know, I was in a,
I was really exhausted coming into that episode. I was at the end of a, you know,
felt like a five year run of different films and work and we're shooting this series throughout.
And I was, I think I was more vulnerable than I'd been in a long time, just out of exhaustion,
but also out of the questions that were starting to circulate through my head. And a lot of them
were to do with, you know, this point in my life and, and, um, am I proud of what I've done? Am I,
you know, what's next? Um, and all I kept thinking was I have been sprinting through life and the
moments and opportunities and I'm grateful for them, but I've been very quickly going to the
next one, the next one, next one. And I was in a, in a bit of a state of, um, what's next and,
and what's the point and who am I and all of these kind of, uh, questions that I hadn't sort of
been able to analyze, but were there in the back of my head. And my mum had said something to me
a few days before that she'd, she'd had this experience where she came pretty close to what
she thought was going to be her death in a very instant sort of moment. Um, and she's fine now,
but said, Oh, you know, I wasn't at all afraid to go because I realized I'm so thankful for my life
and I'm so happy that everything I've had and all the experiences I have. And I thought, well,
what a beautiful feeling. And then in that moment, I think I was talking to BJ about it and I got
really emotional because I realized that I just, well, I'm not ready yet. You know, I, I have all
these beautiful things around me and family and friends, but I can't go yet. This is not,
this is not my time. And, and, and it was strange because we're manipulating
everything in that space to make me feel like I'm going to die. And I'm asked to think about my
death, what, how I would want it to be. And so on. But I had this, this sort of sense of urgency
just, I'm not ready. And it made me think about my kids and how they're growing up and things are
changing so dramatically. And like, oh, I just want, I want to sit, I want to, I want to soak it
in. I don't want to be in a sprint anymore. I want to be more present. I want to be right here and
appreciate everything that's in front of me. And, and again, I, it, I tried to articulate that a few
times and, and I, I feel, I don't know if I've hit the nail on the head is exactly why it's something
in me sort of felt so fragile at that point. But yeah, it, that whole experience sort of
shook me to my core and made me want to slow down and just race home to my family and my kids and
not jump on another plane and travel and work and do anything else. You know, it was, it was, we in
in the best way. I think the time when you were sitting on the bench next to Natalie was sort of
equally profound. At least it appeared that way as an observer. I assume it's the same. You weren't
aware of Natalie's story and you're probably sitting there thinking, why are they having me
sit and talk to a 27 year old, very normal, healthy appearing woman? Yeah. Yeah, definitely.
Okay. Again, just such a, again, that what she said particularly was there's an urgency from her
to shake people and say, wake up. It doesn't last forever. You know, it could, you're, the end could
come at any moment. So make the most of it and love and laugh and live with a sense of gratitude and
joy and incredibly inspiring and heartbreaking hearing what she's been facing at such a young
age too. And I'm really thankful that I had those conversations and I was forced to think this way
and had this realization now, not when I'm 80, you know, I'm glad I'm not sitting on my deathbed
going, ah, damn, I should have done this. I could have done this. I found out I've done that. So,
I don't know. I feel like there's just sort of an awakening or sort of shake up or whatever you
want to call it, um, came at the perfect time for me. You and I talked about this at like last month,
I think, but you haven't had more than two months off in about 10 years, right? Yeah, pretty much.
So we've had, you know, during COVID, but even then I was still working or prepping things.
So how, how do you reconcile the fact that you work so hard and you've been so successful
and with that success has come so many wonderful things, right? It's,
you've got wealth, you've got fame, you've got a platform, right? We're sitting here talking about
more people are going to know what the Apo E4 gene is and why they need to be tested and what
they can do about it because of this episode, because of this series than anything else that
would have ever come out of the scientific literature ever. And all of that is attributed
to the fact that you have a platform to do this. So there's all of these amazing things,
both to you personally and to society at large that come from this, but at the same time,
that's not sustainable. Um, you once told me a story about something your daughter said
when you kind of half jokingly suggested to her, you might retire. Do you remember what that was?
Yeah. Um, yeah, I was talking to her and as I've done, feel like I've been doing for a long time,
my kids and like, you know, every time I've left to go on another trip, I'm going to work. I'm like,
it's not long, you know, and soon I'm going to take some downtime. And I think, you know,
my daughter sort of rolls her eyes at times these days and says, yeah, sure. And I, um, I said,
and then this time I said, look, you know, when I've done this tour, I'm, I'm having a big chunk
of time at home and she goes, oh, great. Awesome. Be fun. And, and I said, yeah. And maybe, maybe I'll
just, maybe I'll just retire. Maybe, maybe this is it. Maybe I'll stay home with you forever now.
And she's like, no, dad, you can't. And I was like, why aren't you guys kids love seeing you play
Thor. And it was just beautiful kind of moment of like, oh yeah, maybe it does. There is a purpose
to it. You know, I think for me, it's, I've been chasing my career and, and I've been doing it
for a number of reasons, but you know, it's been my journey and there's a sense of sort of guilt
that comes with that of sort of chasing down my dreams all the time. And when you have kids, it's
not about your dreams anymore. It's about theirs and I have a family to take care of. And, um,
I was really sort of questioning kind of what I've contributed or done. And hearing her say that was
like a, you know, beautiful little moment. And so I don't want to retire and, and, you know,
for a number of reasons, but, um, I certainly want to replenish and, you know, fill up my cup again.
I feel like it's, uh, it's just been sort of flat stick for so long now. Um, and I've loved it.
And I'm very thankful for it, but I need to have, you know, a chunk of time at home now and sort of,
yeah, I get re-inspired, I guess.
Yes. How was your sleep now compared to three years ago? Because I remember when you struggled,
you had a, you had a very restless mind. You would, you would wake up a lot in the middle of the night
and you'd have a thought and you'd fixate on it. And sometimes it was a very rational thought. Like,
you know, I'm worried about the success of this film. I'm worried about my relationship with my
wife. I'm worried about like, these were all very normal things to be, uh, concerned with, but, but
they would wake you up, right? And you wouldn't be able to go back to sleep. And then sometimes
they were things that maybe seemed less rational. Um, which by the way, I'm not being critical of
you because every one of us has those very irrational thoughts. Mostly irrational.
It's a dress. It definitely affects my sleep. And this is just going back a few years, you know,
this is not such a big issue these days, but, um, actually it's not true. It is.
Yeah. Like I'll go to sleep fine. And then at two 30, there's a shot of adrenaline and my brain will
just start going through a checklist of things. We'll like, does that bother me? Does that bother
all that one? Yeah, good. Let's think about that. Let's tear that apart.
Are you getting nervous a bit now? A little wave of nausea.
Sometimes I don't even know why. And I wish I could deal with that stress better.
Just got a whole lot really different. Not just because it sucks.
But also it could be killing me.
How, how has that changed? And has this, has this series given you a different perspective
on anything that has, has given you more peace? Yeah, definitely. Um, I think generally I'm
sleeping better than, than I was back then. Uh, I think just running in a state of fight or flight
constantly. And you know what, but that was required for me to become an actor, you know,
to, to, for me to leave Australia with, you know, not a whole lot of money in the bank and
live on people's couches and audition and audition and, you know,
do it, go, go through that sort of grind and be told no a million times and still, you know,
obsessively be pushing forward requires a huge amount of compulsive, obsessive sort of, you know,
self-motivated drive. And then the problem is you then start to achieve those things.
And I'm no longer in the same sort of fight that I was, but I'm still acting like I am. My internal
sort of environment is still thinking it's, you know, running away from the dinosaurs or whatever,
you know, goes back to, sort of, to our sort of ancestral, you know, makeup. And so,
you know, my, the more comfortable I get, the more I sort of rationally talk myself through,
hey, it's all okay now, you know, like you're, you know, we can afford to do this and this and
this and you don't have to worry so much about it not working out. Some of that dissipates, but
it's there all the time, you know, and I'd be lying if I said that I had a complete handle on it.
But again, I don't want to kind of dismiss it too much because it's what got me here. And it's a
tool that I will still need to use at certain times. It's just monitoring that. And I don't know,
I hear a lot of people talk about that, though, you know, people in the sort of friends of mine,
sports players and so on with that, what's required to get them to that place. It's a blessing and a
curse, you know, and it's a hard thing to switch on, switch off, sorry, once you've opened the gates.
Yeah, I think that's a very common thread for people who have achieved great success. And
when you think about your motivation, right, when you think about
the love you have for your craft, is there a way to use excitement more than fear? Like how,
you know, because I think back to, you know, your beginning, right, as you talked about,
you know, you've spoken a lot about, and I think you even did in some of the episodes, you spoke
about how, you know, one day you found out your father, you know, like wasn't going to be paying
off the mortgage anytime soon. Like you sort of had this realization of the fact that your parents
have done so much for you and your brothers with the means that they had. But you wanted more for
them. And so part of your fuel for success was like, I want to take care of my family as well,
not just the kids that I'm going to have, which you didn't yet have, but like, these people who
you love so much. And there's a bit of fear in that, right? There's a bit of like, do or die.
But at the same time, there's also a real passion you have for what you do.
You're, in other words, you're an artist, right? And so artists enjoy making art.
Is it about shifting the balance of what's the fire? Like, where's the fire coming from? Is the
fire coming from a place of fear? Is the fire coming from a place of love? I mean, do those do
those go back and forth for you from time to time in different seasons? Yeah, I used to get, I had,
excuse me, very intense, like, performance anxiety when I was first acting. And I would, it was
debilitating, I would go to auditions, and I'd want to throw up, but it'd be shaking. And then
even when I got jobs, and I don't know how I was getting jobs based on how nervous I was in those
auditions, but I was then be on a set. And it was like, I couldn't think or see, you know, I felt
I was gonna pass out like, and I had, I was fighting that for years. And you talk about fear
or excitement. And I remember reading something that took a series of tests with athletes,
performers, musicians, actors, whatever, anyone in a sort of adrenaline fueled sort of space.
And they said, Okay, before the event, are you nervous or excited? And some of them said they
were scared out of their mind. Some of them said they were pumped. The interesting thing was they
all had the same physical response, yeah, elevated heart, pulse, etc. Clammy hands, shorter breath,
all the only difference was how they labeled that feeling. And so for me, that was a real light bulb
moment. And I thought, Oh, okay, so when this feeling comes out, I've been about to walk onto a
set. And what and you know, I programmed myself to say, Oh, this is bad fear, this is fear, this is
a negative. Yeah. I then went, Nope, this is this is a positive. I'm getting my spidey senses right
now. I'm going to be able to think faster, react quicker, I'm going to see clearer, I'm going to,
you know, my vision will be sharp. And it was and that was all it was was a decision then to see it
differently. Then sort of, you know, as time goes on, I think the fear does have its place though,
you know, I think you sort of would have heard people talking that the fear pushes you, your
purpose pulls you. And both of them need to have equal sort of relevance in the conversation. And
it's a bloody good motivator to, you know, the half of these challenges, my fear of looking ridiculous
if I didn't complete this task, or the fact that the episode wouldn't have worked, you know,
they kept me going. But also the sort of purpose and why I was doing it kept me going. So I think
that both deserve conversation, just it's about balance. And if and if either of them get too much
attention, then you know, you have too much of my purpose and my thing, it can be like a humility
there, you know, the fear I fear I fear has I feel has allowed me to have more of a self deprecating
sort of sense of humor about myself, and the world and the work and hopefully kept me humble to.
What was the first role you had where you allowed yourself to think, I'm gonna make it?
Well, it's interesting, the first Thor film, I thought, great, this is, I mean, the game, certainly.
But what you would hear was the first Thor film.
Oh, God, was it 2010? Yeah, yeah. I thought this is good. I'm kind of in the mix. But I didn't know
if the film was going to work. I didn't know if we're going to do an Avengers film. And you weren't
the first choice? Or were you? Wasn't there something funny in the audition there? Yeah,
there was I auditioned initially, that didn't get a callback. It got some pretty bad feedback.
And what was the feedback? Just no good. Just really direct feedback, really like minimal feedback,
which is like, you're not even we're not even gonna give you any sort of, you know, constructive
criticism or anything. It was just kind of minimal and nothing. And, and I was shooting a film in
Vancouver. And my little brother calls me up and said, Oh, they're gonna fly me out from Australia
to LA for this film Thor. And I was like, What? And he was like, Yeah, I don't know, I sent an
audition on a tape and going over and like, Oh, that's awesome, man. Congrats. Wow. What do you
know? And then the trades, I think variety or deadline come out and had like the six final
guys for Thor and Liam was one of those people. And it was with Josh Whedon and Drew Goddard on
his cabin in the woods. And they both said, What the hell's going on here? Is this your brother?
And I go, Yeah, and he goes, Why are you in the mix? You should be Thor. And I was like,
I didn't get a call back. So none of them ended up getting it. They reopened the casting. And I got
a chance to do an audition and I sent in a tape. And I was called back in to meet with Ken Branner
and do the audition. And I just had a very different attitude about it. I didn't put anyone
at pedal store like I did the first time I had like, there was a little little shift off. Yeah,
my brother had gotten there and I hadn't and it was a good motivation. And and it was about
perspective, you know, and then I was able to walk in that room and give the best version of
whatever I had to offer, as opposed to people pleasing and going and going, Is this what you
want? Or is it this this way? And then, you know, there's nothing. There's a lack of strength there,
I think that needed the character to be assertive. And so I had a lot more sort of
presence in that space. And I did the first time around. And then, then got the part.
How long does an audition take? Well, I mean, usually you have a few days to learn it. Sometimes
you have a call you at lunchtime and they say, come in this afternoon and read. And but when
you're actually there in front of them, it can be, again, depending on how well or bad it goes,
it could be five minutes, it could be two minutes, it could be an hour. And I've had I've had both.
I've had like people answer the phone midway through my audition when I first got the town
and just be like, Yeah, yeah, cool. Yeah, yeah. And I'm like, I'm supposed to be still going. And
just like, Yep, that's great. Thank you very much. We'll call you. And you're like, Oh, my God,
it's good. Brutal. You get enough of them and it's you either become numb to it or it destroys you.
How'd you hear about Rush?
So Ron Howard was making the film. I didn't know anything about Formula One.
Because you didn't know me.
I didn't know you. I didn't know you. And, and I said, my agent had called me and said, Oh,
you should do an audition. And Ron said, Oh, look, I've seen Floyd. He's great, but he's not right
for the character. You know, he won't fit in the Formula One car. And I said, I said, Well,
I'm not that size. And he said, Yeah, it's okay. And I said, I'm doing it and doing an audition.
And I watched an interview with James Hunt. And my hair was kind of long enough that I could kind
of style it exactly how his was. And I had, you know, been practicing the accent and didn't
audition and he saw it and went, Okay, cool. He already picked Daniel for Nicky. I think he had.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, you know, my feelings on that film. Yeah. Like, if you were able,
if you were getting a dollar for every time that film got watched by me, I would, you'd be even
more wealthy. Yeah, mate. I'm, I'm, I'm so thankful. It's such a good movie. You would know it better
than I do at this point. I haven't seen it since, since the premiere. Are you kidding me? It's hard
to watch yourself, you know, it's, um, so you don't take your kids to Thor and they don't watch it
around the house. I know you take them to the premiere, but like, yeah, um, no, I'll take them
to a cave. Well, that was the first premiere I took them to, but, um, I'll watch it once or twice,
or if I'm producing it, then I'm, I have to, you know, stick through it a bit more, but, um,
it's, you know, and it should be uncomfortable, I think. Yeah. This is something Gnostos says,
think about enjoying it too much. So if we're sitting here in five years and your life is better
than it is today, especially in accordance with the final episode of Limitless, right? Meaning
you're running less. Um, the balance between purpose and fear is more in favor of purpose than
fear. You feel more connected to your kids, your family. What has to be true? What are you doing?
Look, I don't think it's, um, this is another thing that came up in the episode. I just want
to sort of clarify. I don't feel like I've been doing anything wrong as much as I've just been
in the storm of it. Yeah. And I have a beautiful relationship with my kids and my wife and my
family. It's, and I'll be there with them, but my brain is pulled in and in other places. And so
for things to be even better, um, would just be about, like, is it just about a state of mind or
does it mean it's both? Because in the episode I was talking about this and I said, I was being
asked to imagine what my death would look like. And if this was my final moment, who would I have
around me? Where would I be? And I realized it's in the living room with my family and friends. And
that's every other weekend. Yeah, I have it. So it was as much a moment of it's already right here in
front of you, change your attitude. And also in addition to that was, okay, I want to do this even
more now. And I have an opportunity to do that because I'm not in the fight or the sprint anymore.
And so it would be to be more curated with my choices and have more time pre and post the film
to prepare and decompress as opposed to just piling one after the other. Does that mean more
directing, you know, shifting the balance a little bit? I think it's who the directors are, you know,
I think working with people that are at the top of their game and I've been so lucky to work with
some wonderful people. But to continue just work with George Miller, and to continue to work with
individuals like that, where I'm learning from them, it's a collaboration, but they're at the helm,
they're steering the ship, I don't have to feel like I got to police anyone else there, you know,
is the dream. And then you're inspired by those people. And you're doing it for the right reasons.
It's from an artistic space and an expression as opposed to, you know, a financial one. Oh,
that's a good payday. Script sucks, but I get paid well, you know, so I've done a few times,
you know. And so, yeah, to be more curated in my choices and, you know, have more stillness and
more calm either side of it. Chris, I think, you know, I think about the last three years and I
think about the when we started this thing in January, for me, one of the most unexpected
joys of this because I, you know, I really only did this because of Darren, you know, Darren and I
were and remain such good friends and the chance to do something fun like this with him was the
motivation. But I think, you know, a very pleasant surprise for me has been meeting you and meeting
all the people around you. And it gives me great comfort as now someone who's become a close friend
of yours to know that you are surrounded by these amazing people, you know, like Ben and Aaron and
Zock and your family and your parents and your brothers. I mean, you are rich, Chris, you are
rich in people. And I suspect that's actually probably your greatest asset. So it's been a real
privilege to be a part of that. Well, it's been wonderful getting to know you too, mate. It's
been the biggest joys that people have met through this experience and the knowledge, one thing with
the friendships that are most important. So thank you, buddy. Thanks for sitting down with me.
Bye.