Hey everyone, welcome to the drive podcast. I'm your host Peter Attia.
Well, Lane, we're back for another round of this, but this time we finally get to do it in person.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to this. This will be a, I said it'd be a little bit different.
So let's talk about your training because right now you are training for the worlds in powerlifting.
We had a great chance to kind of catch up on some of your training yesterday. I probably won't get
into as much detail as you and I got into last night because that might be more detailed than
the average non-nerd is interested in. But maybe just briefly kind of explain the sport of power
lifting. You know, there are three lifts, how it works. And then I want to talk about kind of how
you're training for that and some of the challenges of that. Yeah. So power lifting is a very basic
sport. Like you mentioned, there's three lifts, the squat, the bench press, the deadlift, and they go
in that order. You get three attempts on each and they're progressive. So for example, once you put
in an attempt, like let's say you put in a squat attempt of 550 pounds for your opener, if you miss
it, you can't go down. So usually the way people do it is, you know, first attempt is a pretty
conservative weight, kind of like a last warm up. Second attempt is getting close to something that's,
you know, pretty reasonable, like, you know, RPE 9, 9.5. And then your last one, you're hoping to
get kind of your true maximum. And it's basically highest total wins. Between the three different
lifts. Correct. So at Worlds, they will give medals for individual lifts. So there'll be a
gold, silver, and bronze for squat, gold, silver, bronze for bench press, and gold, silver, bronze
for deadlift. And then there'll be those medals also for the overall. And the overall is just the
summation of the total of the number of lifts you hit. So when you do your three squat, three bench,
three dead, are you doing them in that order or are you going? Yeah. Yeah. So it's you do all three
squats go, then all three bench press, then all three deadlift. Typically how much time in between
each attempt? Yeah. So it just, it can really depend. The last time I did Worlds in 2015,
that was a very, very fast meet. So in our flight, there was only 11 people. So meaning, you know,
you have the person who has the lightest squat will go first up to the heaviest squat. And then
those will continue to cycle through. Same thing for bench press thing for deadlift. And the whole
meet took over just, just over two hours. But I've been in meets that have taken as long as three
and a half. So it really just depends on your flight, how quickly the spotters. But if I'm doing
the math, I mean, that means you might only have 15 minutes between lifts. Usually you'll get about
at least 30 because the way they run it is there's, there's no real breaks for people who are
spectating. So they'll have two flights going at the same time. So what'll happen is they'll have
an A flight and a B flight typically. Sometimes they'll have C flights as well if they're, if it's
a really, really packed meet like Nationals. But at Worlds, it's usually just an A and a B flight.
And they just separate those based on opening squats. And usually the B flight will have the
top lifters in it. So you have some time. So you're, while the other folks are lifting,
you're typically warming up, getting ready. And then once, for example, the squats are finished,
A flight will start for bench. And then if you're in B flight, you can have time to warm up.
So what are you doing between? So let's just say between lift one and two,
lift one shouldn't have been that stressful if you did it correctly.
Is, does your, does what you eat matter much? Does how you, are you getting any tissue work? Like what,
what do you need to do? Let's just say you have 30 minutes between those attempts. What do you need
to do to maximize your odds? So usually between the lifts themselves, like between squat and bench
press, we'll have 30 to 60 minutes, depending on how quickly things are going. But what about between
the squat attempts? Like between the actual attempts themselves? I mean, I'll take a drink
of water. I might like throw some candy in or something like that really quickly if I feel like
I need it. But for the most part, I'm just mentally trying to get myself in the right zone.
And it is a little bit tricky because you can't keep yourself at that really high level of arousal
the entire time because you'll just wear out really quickly. So for me, the trick is bringing
that arousal down for about, you know, five minutes or so, so that I can just relax just enough,
and then start to focus back up. And it's almost like, it's like a wave, you're kind of letting
yourself come down. And then when the time is right, and really timing is a big thing in this,
because once the bar is loaded, they call bar is loaded, you'll have one minute to get the down
command for squat or bench press or whatever it is. So really, and there can be mistakes where
like maybe you come out and you forgot your belt or you something happens. So I really try to make
it to where when they say bar is loaded, I get out there very quickly so that if there is anything
wrong, I can address it and have time. So really timing it and saying, okay, how many people were
in front of me? How long do I need to amp up? Usually for me, I like to have about two or three
minutes to really get like very aroused and very amped up. And so just trying to time that correctly
is kind of tough. But like I said, for the first five minutes afterwards, I kind of let myself
come down, but I never like truly relax. I'm still like got my music on. I'm still thinking
about what I've got to do, but I'm not like really hyper focusing. And then as it starts to come into
the last five minutes for the lift, you know, I'm putting whatever I need on to focus myself,
you know, mental imagery, visualization. And then by the end, I'm even doing like breath work. Like
I really I want my heart rate to be about 160 170. By the time I go out to hit my left, like I want
to be very amped. Yeah, I was gonna ask you what your heart rate got to. I would imagine your blood
glucose is probably about 160 as well. Probably. I've never. Your liver is just, you know, hepatic
glucose output at the max. Yeah. I mean, you know, your stress hormones are going to be high. You know,
it's really interesting. I was a little bit off topic, but I was listening to a sports psychologist
talk about how the differences between excitement and anxiety are and anxiousness are almost you
can't almost pick them out. It's just your perception. And I remembered when I played
baseball in high school, I would come up to the plate with the thought process of don't strike out.
You don't want to look stupid. Just put the ball in play. It wasn't the process of I'm going to
drive these runs in. I'm going to, you know, do X, Y, Z. And I was watching an episode of the ultimate
fighter probably 13, 14 years ago is where Matt Sarah versus Matt Hughes. And one of the fighters
was getting like really like like vomiting before a match because he was so nervous and he was over
the bucket going, I can't do this anymore. I hate the way this feels. I can't do this. And Matt
Sarah just looked at him and said, what are you talking about, man? That's the feeling of being
alive. You care about something so much that your body is reacting this way. And ever since then,
it completely flipped the way I looked at competition. And so now before when I would
get nervous playing baseball, I would try to like calm myself down. Like, why can't I feel normal?
Why don't I feel relaxed? And now when I feel those nerves start to kick in, I just tell myself,
this is a good thing. This is a good thing. This is your body getting you ready. This is you being
ready to go. And really like that reframing of things and just accepting and being okay with
the anxiety has helped me so much. Yeah. Well, I think, you know, something like that in power
lifting where the stakes are really high and it's really short. It's not like, you know, in tennis,
you can have one bad match, right? Or one bad serve and it doesn't end the entire thing. In power
lifting, it can. And I guess the other thing I guess is the stakes are kind of high from an injury
standpoint as well because you are pushing at your limit. Have you ever injured yourself in a meet?
So not to the point where I couldn't continue or, you know, had really bad pain during, but at the
Arnold in 2015, at the Arnold Pro meet, I had aggravated my back a week out pretty badly.
And then the day of the meet when I hit my last squat, which was 661 pounds,
I kind of rotated a little bit coming up. And the next day I could definitely feel it like in my,
it was actually closer to my upper lumbar or lower thoracic. I definitely had quite a bit of
pain there. So what's interesting is you don't, you typically don't see people get injured at
meets. It does happen, but I would say that it's less frequent than during training. That's, I don't
have any data on that. I'm just guessing. But I think part of it is you are so focused and you are
so excited. You're very tight. Like you're, you're very, you know, conscious of what you're doing.
At the end of the day, it is just one rep where I've tended.
Yeah. Where's the volume when you're training and you're also probably more broken down and
more fatigued. Yeah. So when you get ready for a meet, if you've done your due diligence,
hopefully you've kind of dissipated a lot of that fatigue to, you know, rest and tapering.
Whereas when you're in the throws of training and you just kind of high levels of fatigue,
maybe you're just not able to execute the lifts as well because of that fatigue.
Um, that's where things tend to happen, especially like if you're doing, you know,
multiple repetitions as you get closer to failure, just the opportunity to get out of position or
make mistakes, those sorts of things. So it is definitely, uh, one of the things that, you know,
is part of the game. Um, like you're just going to deal with pain. Um, but I always tell people to
like, you know, I'm 40 now and most 40 year olds, 50 year olds, they have pain anyway. So I'd rather
be strong and have pain than be weak and have pain. How many times a year can you peak for a meet
or maybe not necessarily even you, but at the top level of powerlifting, how many really good meets
in a year does it, does it lift or have? So I, this is just completely my opinion. Uh,
and it's, it's based on my own experience, but for me, I've done it where I've only, I've done one,
I've done it where I've done like four level meets. Four was way too much. Um,
I think probably two is the sweet spot for me. Um, you know, it gives you time to really,
I don't think I've ever gone into a meet and just been like, Oh, I feel a hundred percent healthy
and nothing hurts or anything like that. It's, it's kind of, it's not the same thing as getting
ready for like a fight, but I mean, in order to be able to execute a heavy lift, you have to lift
heavy. And so part of that is you're going to accumulate some from dinks and some dunks.
And so really it's about getting to competition day with enough fitness level in terms of being
able to execute heavy lifts while dissipating fatigue and being in low enough levels of pain
that you can execute. Um, and so afterwards, really, it's always been the most dangerous when
I feel good after a meet. Cause then I just tend to like go in like on Monday and say, well, let's
get right back into training. And really the smart thing to do is just to take some time, you know,
train for fun, you know, keep that core strength, but move more towards accessory movements and
things that don't beat me up so much for several months, then kind of reenter like a more of a,
like building accumulation phase where volume is going up, but the weights still aren't super heavy.
And then those last three, four months, four week, now it's time to start putting in, you know,
more heavy weights and starting to ramp up towards where the end, I mean, like by the end of my
training, I'm mostly on my competition lifts, just hitting heavy singles. So that's where I want to
talk about is, um, what can the rest of us who aren't power lifters learn just about strength?
Because if I wanted to frame this for a listener, cause people have heard me talk about this, but
the two metrics that are most significantly associated with longevity. Uh, so if we were
to stack up every possible known risk factors, the smoking type two diabetes, high blood pressure,
coronary artery disease, end state kidney disease, whatever. And we were to talk about
how much of a hazard ratio do these bring to you in terms of all cause mortality.
They're, they're quite big, you know, hypertension is about a 20%. Uh, type two diabetes is about a
30% increase in mortality. Smoking is 50% increase being weak relative to being strong is about 250%.
Having a very low VO two max in the bottom 25% of the population versus being in the top
two and a half percent of the population is about 400%. So when you line everything up, the two things
that stand out the most are incredible cardio respiratory fitness as measured by VO two max
and strength. And then a third is muscle mass. But I think when you look at the data, you realize
muscle mass is so coupled to strength that that association is tight. The point being is if you're
listening to this podcast and thus far into this podcast, your eyes are sort of glazing over as
we're sitting here talking about powerlifting. It's probably worth pointing out that even if you
never once care to do a heavy squat or heavy bench press or a heavy deadlift, you have to be strong.
And in these studies where these associations continue to show up over and over and over,
again, they're using things like grip strength, bench press, leg extension, things that are a
little less technical. But the point remains, anybody who's going to a power meet and crushing
a deadlift has pretty strong grip strength. So I think it becomes important for people to
understand how to train for power. And so let's now talk a little bit about that. So if a person
comes to you and says, I want to get stronger, and that's my primary objective in the weight room,
it's more so than the aesthetic, because we're going to talk about that later. What are some of
the principles they need to keep in mind? So what's interesting is the principles are pretty much
the same. It's just the level to which they're applied. And I think it's important to point out
that there are diminishing returns with strength and turn. Well, I'm sure there are. The studies
are refined enough to pick this out at this point, because it's not like they're getting a population
of power lifters looking at their longevity. But my guess is that at a certain point, you pretty
much get all the benefits and just getting even stronger is probably not going to give you more.
Especially if it comes at the risk of injury that can later on in life.
Sure. And then I think like, you also see with like running, there's kind of like a J shaped curve.
Part of me thinks that just the people that take it so far, whether it be powerlifting, running,
whatever, that it's not that their sport makes them more prone to more to early mortality,
but more so that they probably have other behaviors of being an extremist that probably
contribute to that. Interesting. But I think that's something that I think
as far as strength goes, really what we're talking about is progressive overload.
I mean, that that is the most important core principle. And it actually really applies to
a lot of things in life, to be quite honest. But when it comes to lifting weights, a lot of people
hear progressive overload and they just think weight on the bar. And that is the most simple
way to explain it, right? So if you come in, you've never done some sort of squat movement before,
and you do 95 pounds for five reps. And then the next week you come in, you do a hundred.
And the next week coming into you to 105. At the same number of reps.
At the same number of reps, right? You know, that is a form of progressive overload. And most people,
when they enter the gym, that's kind of their experience. They don't need to increase that
number. They don't need to really, they can increase the reps. But for the most part,
when you first start going to the gym, you're just going to be able to put more weight on the bar
pretty much every week. And that is a perfectly reasonable way to progress. And I mean, even,
you know, I know we haven't gotten here yet, but people will say, well, you know, I'm post-mental
pause a woman or I'm a 75 year old male. Like it's too late for me. No, it's not. Now is the best
time. In fact, when I was at University of Illinois, where I was in a department of nutritional
sciences right across the street in the exercise physiology department, they were conducting a
study on frail elderly. So people who basically almost couldn't couldn't really walk like they
could, but it was very tough for them. And they just started progressive overloading them. And
that looked like basically squatting to a really high chair to start. Right. And what they saw was
incredible in like 12 weeks, they actually had people who could squat down to like a below
parallel chair and come back up, which may not sound like much for the average person. But when
you're talking about somebody who's, you know, frail elderly, the difference in functionality
and their lifestyle is going to be incredible in terms of what they can do. So what I'll tell people
is what you can learn from power lifters is that progressive overload one in terms of weight on the
bar, but nobody's able to increase weight on the bar forever. That that's just, it's not going to
happen. And the longer you get into it, the more nonlinear it's going to be. It's going to be,
you're going to go down and come up and go down and come back up. But there's also other ways to
progressively overload, one being more repetitions and the other being adding more hard sets. So
the latter adding more hard sets is really something you only need to get to as you get to
be more advanced. Because like I said, you're not going to be able to add strength forever and you're
not going to be able to add reps forever either. So by the way, this is one thing that from one of
our earlier discussions that really started to change my training, I started adding a little
bit more set at slightly lower RPE to net increase volume. So I was, I think doing a lot more RPE 8,
9 stuff, but you can only get a few sets at that level. Like you're really, really spent. And instead
I was saying, well, wait a minute, why don't we do a little more RPE 6 and 7 and add more sets,
more volume. One, I feel like it's lowering my risk of injury. And two, as you said, it's really
just another way to progressively overload. Yeah. And you're always weighing those two things,
kind of your stimulus versus fatigue ratio. And that's something, so I'm coached by a guy named
Zach Robinson, who's doing his PhD in Mike Zordos' lab at FAU, great lab. And he talks about stimulus
versus fatigue a lot. And they do a lot of training in that kind of RPE 5 to 6 area, which
some people call that easy. When it comes to compound lift, I wouldn't really call it easy.
But it's kind of like, how can we maximize our stimulus and minimize fatigue? And if you're
talking about an RPE 9, for example, how many sets at RPE 9 can you get?
I don't know about you. I have like one to two.
Right. Right. Before you really have to drop the weight down or whatnot.
Or before someone like me who's not at the level that a power lift is at,
my form starts to compromise. Right. And Mike Israel actually had a great kind of take on this
too, in terms of training to failure. He's like, if you take a squat, like a free barbell squat to
failure for 10 reps, and then you try to do another set with that same weight, how many reps will you
get? I mean, I know from doing sets to failure of 10 reps of free barbell squat, I might not even
be able to get like two or three reps on my next set because it's just so fatiguing.
So that is one thing that's important to point out when we talk about RPEs, which is kind of a
measure for proximity to failure. Yeah. I guess just we talked about it on a previous podcast.
Why don't you tell people how RPE works? Because I think it's really a fantastic system.
But you do need to push yourself in the gym to really understand what they feel like.
Yeah. So RPE is kind of a, it's been adapted from running to lifting and it's on a scale of one to
10 or I guess even zero, but RPE 10 being you had no more reps left. That was your absolute all out,
like a hundred percent effort. RPE 9 is you could have done one more rep, RPE 8, one more rep,
so on and so forth. And one of the issues is we know you don't have to train to failure to grow
muscle. In fact, it may actually be a little bit counterproductive just in terms of the fatigue
that it causes relative to the stimulus. We know that, you know, for most movements,
you get most of the hypertrophy and strength benefits going within a few reps of failure.
So RPE like seven, eight. And obviously if you can do more volume, it may be even more beneficial.
But the downside is if you've never actually taken something to failure, like true failure,
people are really bad at estimating it. And so it was beginners and intermediates. They find that
they tend to underestimate their RPE by about five, which is pretty incredible. And we've seen it in
the lab, like we'll take somebody in and they'll put a weight on, they'll do a rep and-
And you'll ask them what's your RPE right now?
What was that like? And they'll say their RPE and then the research will actually make them take it
to failure while they're like yelling at them and encouraging them. And on average, they'll get five
more reps than they estimated they would have. I can totally believe that.
Yeah. Whereas when they look at RPE validity and advanced lifters, it tends to be much more
accurate, much more accurate. So there was actually a study, I was in a powerlifting meet
where they had a Tindo unit on the bar and they were measuring our bar velocity and they were
asking us to rate our RPE after every attempt. And they found that RPE as validated by velocity data
was a pretty good measure in that population of power lifters because they've taken so many sets
near failure. So your point is well taken. You do need some experience of going really hard and
really close to failure. But once you have that experience and you understand what that feels like,
then you can estimate better. You're probably better off staying a few reps shy of failure
and accumulating volume that way just because going to failure is just so incredibly fatiguing.
So for a person who, again, is not planning to go to a power meet,
is there a need for them to go below four reps in training?
I would say-
That's an arbitrary number, but you know what I'm getting at.
I would say probably not. I mean, you can get plenty strong, even doing sets of 10,
those sorts of things.
Oh, that's interesting. I would have thought you needed to get at least into the fives and
sixes sometimes.
But-
So you can get really strong doing sets 10, 15, those sorts of things. Now, you will not be as
strong even per cross-sectional area as somebody who trains for strength because strength is a
specific skill. And even like myself, you know, my best squat ever is a 668. And when I was, you know,
six months out from that, it's not like I, you know, I added weight to the bar that I was able
to squat, but it's not like I added that much more lean body mass because I didn't.
I was practicing the skill of a one rep max, which allowed me to better do the one rep max.
And you were practicing at what percent of ultimately became 661?
Usually around 90, 95, but not very much at 95, mostly at 90 for like singles.
And what was your RPE when you did those singles?
So usually about eight and a half or nine.
Yeah.
Okay. So you would do multiple of that. Just doing the math. Let's just say that's 620 or
something like that.
Yes.
Yeah. So let's say it's called 600 pounds. So you would do a 600 pound signal
three times in a workout.
Something like that.
Okay.
And what you're, what you're kind of making gains on at that point is just your
one, it just teaches you how to grind through a lift because a lot of people have never had
the experience of really sticking with a lift. And interestingly, the more advanced somebody
gets in terms of strength, the slower their one rep max velocity will be.
And we see this in research studies all the time.
Somebody who's kind of new will come in, they will absolutely smoke a weight.
You put five pounds on and then they get stapled because it's just,
they don't have that grind capacity.
They don't, they don't know how to do it. And part of that may be psychological,
but part of that's probably physiological too.
So interesting.
In terms of you just haven't trained your body to recruit all the fibers that it can get.
So, you know, lean body mass and strength are very closely tied together.
But when it gets to those finer levels of strength, it's kind of just practicing
the actual one rep max.
So when it comes to getting strong, you can absolutely get strong doing sets 10, 15,
because you're increasing your lean body mass.
Do you need to do sets of three, four? No.
But what I would say is don't necessarily count them out because a lot of people actually just
do really well with variety.
So, you know, periodization was kind of a big thing for lifting back in the day.
And now we've kind of shown that at least in the research studies, it doesn't appear to
produce greater gains in lean body mass, maybe a little bit better strength gains,
but that's probably just because people peak better when you're periodizing things.
But what tends to actually be shown is that people just tend to like periodization better
because they're varying their repetitions.
They're not as bored, right?
So you never want to kind of poo-poo the psychological effects of those things.
I talk about this with diet as well.
Adherence is the most important thing, just getting people to come in and do it.
So especially for people who are coming into the gym, you know, if they're just trying to get
stronger and be healthy, well, for me, if I'm like talking to them or coaching them or whatever it is,
it's like, well, what do you enjoy?
What's going to get you to show up consistently, right?
Oh, you don't want a free squat? That's fine.
Let's leg press.
You know, there's many ways to skin a cat.
You don't want a barbell deadlift?
Okay, no problem.
Let's do some RDLs, you know, those sorts of things, you know, slightly less technical lifts.
They're still going to produce really great gains in terms of strength, lean body mass,
those sorts of things.
So if you're not going to specifically compete in a strength sport, there's so many paths to roam
in terms of getting stronger and increasing lean body mass.
So do you think there were some principles, for example, like let's say a person isn't
confident that they have the technical ability to execute a squat or a deadlift.
Let's look at a hip thruster.
Again, you can screw that up too, and you could hurt yourself, but it's a lot harder to hurt
yourself doing that.
Do you think there is still an essential need for some sort of compound movement,
like a hip thruster, at least as a compliment or a leg press, as you point out?
You know, it's pretty funny.
I went through a phase where everything I learned from the magazines, the bro science,
I was like, well, this all has to be junk, you know?
And now we're actually having studies come out that are validating some of this bro science
from like 20, 30 years ago.
So there does appear to be like different areas of the leg muscles, the quadriceps,
for example, that are better activated by say a leg extension compared to a leg press
compared to a squat.
So I do think it is good to have variety.
I think it is good to have compound lifts as well.
And in fact, there's some interesting data that suggests that you don't have to get as
close to failure on compound lifts to still get the same stimulation compared to isolation
exercises where you do seem to have to get much closer to failure to get those benefits.
But also just thinking about like, again, if we're kind of like looking at the longevity
or the quality of life piece, what is most analogous to what these people are going to
be doing or where they're going to be needing it?
Well, if it's bending over and picking something up, that's some kind of hinge,
right?
Some kind of hinge.
If it's sitting down and standing back up, some kind of squat.
Now, you can use variations, right?
And I would never, I don't want to say never because it's a superlative.
But I very rarely would take somebody who's like fresh off the street and just put a barbell on
their back and say, okay, learn how to squat because I mean, it's going to be like Bambi
trying to stand up, right?
Ideally, you're probably going to maybe even start them off with no weight and just teach them
how to hinge, how to use their hips, how to use their knees, how to track their legs with their
feet and those sorts of things and just balance.
Because if you've never put a barbell on your back, I mean, it's not a comfortable position.
And honestly, to do it well, you shouldn't feel comfortable.
You should feel very tight most places.
And then once they're established with that, then moving to where they're holding a kettlebell in
front of them, and then you can progress with weight with that.
And then maybe you progress to something like a safety bar where they're not having to worry
so much about hands and whatnot to a box and then eventually take the box away.
And then maybe then you can progress to a barbell squat.
But I would say that, you know, the Puritan and me would be like, yes, everybody should barbell
squat. But I know that that's not true.
I think the biggest thing is just getting something close and analogous to the things
that are going to be important in your day to day life.
As you get older, especially if, you know, quality of life is important to you.
And I mean, when we talk about, you know, people who fall as elderly, I think I read something
insane, like half the people over age 65 who go in the hospital for a fall never come out.
Or I think it's something of that nature.
Yeah, I mean, I've seen many studies on this.
The one that sticks out in my mind was 30 to 40 percent of people over the age of 65
who break their hip will not live will be dead within a year of that insult.
Yeah, because you got infection and then you have that you're also like,
they're going to have to be immobilized.
Right. And then they get pneumonia or adelectasis pneumonia or something like that.
So, yeah, it's it's awful.
I mean, I think, you know, there's a study and I think I even mentioned this on a previous
podcast, but we should link to it.
It was an Australian study that took a group of older women.
I don't remember exactly how old they were, but they certainly looked like they were in
their 60s or above who all had osteo, at least osteopenia, if not osteoporosis.
And it put them on a relatively unsophisticated lifting program, unsophisticated in that there
wasn't a lot of instruction other than just pick up weights.
It was mostly just pick up weights.
And as I saw the video on YouTube of the P.I. discussing this, isn't it fantastic?
Because they're in this totally old school gym and you've got these old ladies picking up weights,
walking around some of them getting really I remember one lady was picking up her body
weight. Yeah.
I mean, she was basically deadlifting her body weight.
Yeah.
These are women who had never lifted a weight before and their symptoms just got so much better.
Absolutely. And I mean, the best thing you can do for like bone density is lift weight.
So this isn't like a mutually exclusive thing.
In fact, people get really focused on the bone density portion of this when we talk about falls
and whatnot. So they get very focused on how do we keep them from breaking their
hip? What if they didn't fall in the first place?
Yeah.
Right. What if they had the strength to catch themselves?
Exactly. Yeah.
The balance to catch themselves. And then like, again, even if they did fall, if you have more
muscle mass, you're probably going to have more bone density as well. These are all things that
are going to help. And, you know, resistance training is great because you can have these
other sort of interventions that can improve lean body mass and whatnot.
But they all work way better with resistance training because you're creating the need
for the tissue. And that's something I think that has been missed a little bit is the
teleological perspective of this, which is you have to give your body a reason to lay down tissue.
Muscle tissue is pretty energetically expensive, relatively speaking. So again,
I'm kind of speaking philosophically, but the body is not just going to go, oh, yeah,
we got some extra calories. Let's just lay down some lean tissue. It doesn't make sense because
from the body's perspective, the number one thing it's trying to do is keep you alive long enough
to reproduce. And then once you've done that, just trying to prevent you from starving,
like the risk of dying from starvation over the course of human history is way is magnitudes
greater than like diseases from too much nutrition. I mean, that's basically a 20th,
21st century problem. So the idea that, oh, well, like if I eat some higher protein, I can lay down
some more lean body mass. Yeah, you can, but it's going to be really, really minimal compared to
what you can build through resistance training. And then when you couple resistance training with
high enough protein or, you know, any of these other modalities, now you're creating the turnover
in the tissue that the body has the requirement to lay down that tissue. So what do we know about
the peak capacity for strength as a person ages? Does this differ between men and women? And I'm
sure there's variability for people, but I mean, on a per pound basis, are you stronger today than
you were at 20? Yeah, I am stronger today than I was at 20. Are you stronger than you were at 35?
No, no, that's come off my peak a little bit. But that's, I don't think that's like a
sarcopenia thing. I just think that that's accumulation of injuries and not being able
to train the way I used to be able to train. Okay. So I used to be able to train much harder
than I can train now. Like my, my governor is not the work ethic. It's the, it's the, okay,
how hard can I train before the pain level gets too high? So it's not that you're losing type
two fibers, that you're losing some of the 2A or 2B fibers, and that that's why you're not quite
as strong. Would you, do you believe that on a muscle biopsy basis, you're, you could be as
strong now as you were at 30? I think I probably could. Yeah. It's, it's, if you look at the
research literature, you do see differences between young and old, but most of those get
ameliorated when you start adding in resistance training. And more to your point, you know,
the idea of how much strength could I gain? How much lean mass could I gain?
Based on what I've seen, so let's take men and women, for example,
women have been shown to gain just as much lean mass as a percentage of their starting lean mass.
It is the relative increase. So for example, if people add 10% lean mass, something like that.
Well, if you're a male and you have, you know, 70 kilos of lean mass, now you're 77. If you're a
female, you had 50 kilos of lean mass, now you're 55, right? So the male added seven kilos, the female
added five kilos, but relative to their start, they added the same. And that's what the research
literature says is they pretty much can add the same amount as a percentage of their starting lean
mass and the same thing for strength. And actually, there's some evidence that women
may be able to tolerate higher training volumes than men too. Now, I'm not sure if that's-
Is that across all ages, you think? Or is that within a certain age?
They've only really looked at it in kind of young adults, like 20s and 30s. So it's hard to say.
But I wonder if that's just more of a function of they're just smaller bodies handling less weight.
I do- My wife would tell you that no one can handle a cold less than me. And I think it's true.
I have an insanely high pain tolerance, except for when my sinuses are congested and I have a
miserable cough and I turn into a little baby. So there might be something about women just being
tougher too. Yeah, I think. So I've thought about this quite a bit. So if you look at,
let's look at super heavyweight power lifters, just an extremely simple, right?
And these are guys that weigh over what? What's the-
Oh, like Ray Williams, for example. So he's one of the greatest drug tested power lifters in history.
First man to raw squat over a thousand pounds. He was a college football player. They dexed him.
He had 308 pounds of lean mass and he's probably over 400 pounds of total body weight.
How much? Lean mass?
Over 300 pounds. Incredible. Now, his, like, let's say we're talking about working with 80%
of a one rat max. His 80% is 800 pounds. A female is 80% if she's doing a one rat max of 300 pounds
is 240 pounds. They're the same percentage. I'm not sure that you can say that the same thing in
terms of what happens with the body. I know- Because at the end of the day,
connective tissue is connective tissue. Right. I know very, very few super heavyweight power lifters
who train the main lifts like three, four times a week, like some of the lighter weight classes do.
So I do think there's something about like the absolute load. So part of me thinks the idea
that women can recover a little bit better might be that they're just using absolute lower loads,
but we'd have to have some more intricate research.
Now, there's an interesting point about that study because I know the one that you were talking about
and I've heard people use that study to suggest that testosterone is not important
in muscle gain. The idea being if women can add 10% to their base and men are adding 10% to their
base, clearly men and women have a log full difference in testosterone. Therefore,
testosterone doesn't matter. But of course, you only need to look at tested versus untested
power lifters and bodybuilders to know testosterone is doing something. So how do you reconcile these?
I think part of it is, so if we look at like, let's take the men and women example.
One of the main benefits of testosterone is the increase in satellite cell number that you get,
which is going to increase your potential for increasing muscle mass. So I don't want to talk
about this like it's hard and stone proven, but there's a theory out there I tend to agree with
called the myonuclear domain theory. So for those people who aren't familiar with satellite cells,
satellite cells are quescent cells that sit on kind of the outside of a muscle fiber.
And through various ways, resistance training, testosterone, whatever, you can get those
satellite cells to be donated to the muscle fiber and muscle fiber is the only cells that are
multi nucleated. And we think the reason is, is that each myonuclei can only control protein
synthesis for a certain area. So you can only get the muscle fiber can only grow as big as it has
myonuclei. So the more myonuclei you can donate, the greater your potential is. And so one of the
things that we think is a reason that men have more lean mass than women, you know, is during
puberty, because up till puberty, males and females tend to have similar amounts of lean mass.
But during puberty, that's when we start to see these hormonal differences emerge. And that
exposure to testosterone increases that myonuclei number and just gives them a greater overall
potential for lean mass, which again, makes sense if you think about it as a relative percentage.
So now when you talk about taking exogenous levels of testosterone,
now you're donating even more myonuclei. And so you can reach a higher ceiling. So I think,
honestly, I mean, this, this might give me a little bit of trouble, but I think that's actually the
strongest argument against kind of the crossover of transgender sports of, you know, people who
previously were male now identify as female is you can't really get rid of those extra nuclei of the
of the long term benefit that's conveyed by the fusion of those myonuclei. So for example,
and we see this with like muscle memory, for example. So we know that when you stop,
if you've trained before, but you stop training, you can gain back muscle much faster than it takes
to build it. And they've even shown this in people who have stopped training for years,
that they gain it back faster than it originally took to build it. The other interesting thing is
they did a study where they looked at giving testosterone to it was either rats or mice. I
can't remember which one. So they, they were able to resistance train them. And it's funny to see
these like rat resistance training setups. I'm sure you've seen them. So one group, they did not
give testosterone. The other group, they gave testosterone. Now, of course, both gain strength,
both gain lean body mass, but the group getting testosterone obviously gain more. Then they had
a complete washout period. And basically for as long as it took for them both to get back to kind
of their original lean mass number, then they both had them retrain again, but no drugs in either
group. And the group that originally had testosterone just that once gained muscle significantly faster
than the other group. And our best understanding is it's probably these myonuclei that got fused
through that extra testosterone that confers that long-term benefit. So that's kind of how we think
about that. Do we think that that's kind of like only during a critical window of development,
or does that happen if you're 40 years old and you're taking exogenous testosterone?
See, that's where it gets more tricky. We don't, we don't really know. I think part of it may be,
you know, if you're, if you have a certain testosterone, and I'm, there's no data on this,
so I'm, I'm speculating 100%. But if you have a certain level of testosterone, you've had that,
you know, through puberty and now you're an adult, and you kind of maintain that, that's just kind
of your native natural, let's say you don't get too obese or too underweight, whatever.
You've probably fused the amount of myonuclei that you're going to fuse, at least from testosterone,
right? But now if you start taking exogenously, you've now ramped that up another notch. Now you
can fuse more myonuclei, which again, anecdotally would make sense because if we look at the drug
use and bodybuilding, it's continued to go up, up, up, up, up. And now we're getting to the point where,
you know, these guys really aren't getting much bigger, because there's just only so many drugs
they can take before. I mean, and we're seeing it now, many of them are, I think last year,
there was something like a half dozen professional bodybuilders who died. So it's getting to the point
where they really can't go any higher in drugs. And you're seeing that lean mass start to cap out.
And this is why because you compete in tested or drug free powerlifting,
as good as it is, they make you guys take a polygraph that says, have you used drugs in five
years? And that's an interesting window of time, right? Because you'd think like, why would they
care if you used performance enhancing drugs five years ago, but in theory, they do care,
because you may still confer a benefit five years later, even if you've actually been drug free.
So that's what we did natural bodybuilding when I competed in natural bodybuilding.
And powerlifting, they don't do the polygraph. They don't. So you just, you cannot test positive
so we are completely underwater. So basically the way the water drug testing works is once you
enter the water drug testing pool, so you've qualified for some kind of international competition,
you could be drug tested at any time. So you have to provide, you have to use a whereabouts form,
you have to provide your whereabouts, all that kind of thing. And if they, if it's during your
window and they say, Hey, you need to be drug tested and you don't do it, you can get a strike
against you and be out of competition for a certain period of time.
So there's pluses and minuses to both methods, right? Like polygraph obviously
is not something that's crazy accurate, right? I don't think they allow it in a court of law.
But just the idea that you are going to be asked that and it could be something that you fail,
probably keeps quite a few people from doing it. And the other thing I tell people is
there's just not really any money in this stuff. So it's, you know, are there cheaters,
absolutely. Is it rampant? I would kind of be surprised because there's just not that much
money. Now, when you talk about sports where you can make millions of dollars,
yeah, I would not be surprised if there's rampant cheating because you're talking about millions of
dollars. I think the most money that's ever been on the line for me competing was like two or
three thousand dollars. So it's, you know, I love to do it. Not being done for the money.
No, no, for sure. Yeah. So with the, with the polygraph, at least it allows you to kind of go
back, like you said. Now, interestingly, the data that we just talked about kind of suggests that,
well, if it was five years ago, it doesn't matter. You still got an advantage. But they're also
trying to balance that with, you know, at some point you got to let people come clean if they've
used in the past. Yeah. And I actually agree with that point of view in terms of like I spoke with
a guy who competed in bodybuilding. He's like, you know, I was 17 years old. Some guy to Jim gave me
something. I was an idiot. I didn't like ask what it was. And, you know, I got like a bunch of side
effects and like, you know, I got bigger and stronger. But he's like, you know, looking back,
it was like I really regret doing that at that age. Well, should that be punished for like his
entire life and not able to compete in drug free bodybuilding? I mean, you can make the argument. I
understand the argument. But, you know, I'm in favor of being a little bit more inclusive in terms of
that. So, you know, you've you mentioned that, you know, you're as you're getting ready to train
for worlds. Just I think it was a couple of days yesterday. You've said to me, you know, your back
kind of hurt. You really backed off. Also, this is your first major international meet in about seven
years. And a lot of that was due to injuries, of which back was the most prevalent. But I think
you also mentioned a little bit of knee pain as well. Right. Yep. Yep. So how do you think about
this personally? How much longer do you want to be loading yourself at the, you know, basically
putting cars on your back and lifting cars off the ground? Right. Which is effectively what you're
doing. Yeah. I mean, candidly, if I went out my one master's worlds, I'd probably give a real hard
thought about like, OK, I think I'm done at least competing in this. But the other part of me
is kind of like I think that part of my problem is I love to train so much. I never really gave
myself the time to get pain free. As soon as I started feeling better, I would just start pushing
again. And I do think I've slowly gotten more intelligent because I used to think I was basically
Superman. So I think I've just matured a little bit. And even like yesterday, like getting to a
certain point, warming up on squats and saying, all right, it's not happening today. There's no
reason to try and force this. I think previously I would kind of create a narrative in my mind of
I'm going to power through this because it's what it takes. And yeah, at some points like you have
to I think one of the most important things is knowing when to press the gas pedal and knowing
when to back off a little bit. And sometimes discretion is the better part of valor. And for me,
I'm probably a little bit weird in that like I would train three or four hours a day because
I just love to train. I love the way it makes me feel. I love feeling strong. Part of me,
the egocentric part of me probably loves to feel like a badass loading up, you know, five,
six hundred pounds in a gym and whatnot. But I've kind of gotten to the point now where I'm like,
all right, if it's there today, we take it. If it's not there, we take what's there. And then
we live to fight another day because I've just had so many experiences where I've tried to
press on this. And with the way pain works, the more pain you have, the more pain you're going to
have because you just end up getting fixated and ruminating on it. And the research actually shows
that the more you ruminate on it, the more you think about it and the more times you trigger it,
the worse it's going to get. And so it's like this delicate balance between, you know, I kind
of know how far I can press something before I'm making it worse because the research also shows
that you don't want to completely just stop lifting because you detrain. And then when you come back,
even if you're pain free, you're more likely to retrigger it because you've lost that adaptation.
So it's kind of like when you have those pain triggers, trying to find either a weight amount
or a movement pattern or something similar to what you're trying to do, but it's low enough pain
that you can start to build back from that. So like, for example, yesterday,
ideally I would have done some squats and deadlifts. Couldn't do them. Okay. I'm going to go
and do some leg press. I'm still going to get some stimulation from my quads, the primary movers of
the squat. I'm going to go do single leg dumbbell RDLs. I was able to do those with no pain. Is it
loading it as much as I would like? No, but I'm still using my hamstrings. I'm using my lower back.
I'm getting in some of that movement pattern and I'm still getting a training effect, some adaptation
without further triggering that pain. So. And then so what did you do today? So today I just kind of
was like pretty much just cleaning up stuff I missed throughout the week. So I just had some
dumbbell pressing. I did some more single leg RDLs and I did some mobility work. So not a whole
lot of intensive stuff, but you know, really when you consider like what I do, ideally all I would
do would be squat bench press and deadlift. Right. It's completely specific to what I'm going to
express on competition day. But those are also very fatiguing movements. I think, and I think
part of that too is just when you know how much you can do and you know how much you've done,
you kind of have like this anxiety about those movements because it's like you're almost being
tested and comparing them to what you previously done. So sometimes just creating, you know, a
little bit of a variation of that movement where you're not, you can kind of just let the weight
happen and pick your RPE. And if it's not, you know, a previous set weight, it doesn't bother you.
So I've started using a lot more variations to build that baseline level of strength. And then
again, when it comes to the actual competition lifts, I'm mostly just focusing on doing like
heavy singles and building my volume through other areas. And how many times a week will you do those
heavy single workouts? Once or twice. Once or twice, just depending on how I feel.
I've often thought there would be a really interesting experiment I'd like to do.
I wouldn't do it, but I'd like to oversee it. I'd like to see it being done, I guess,
which is you take a power lifter and their entire training cycle, like six months building up to a
competition, they have no idea what's on the bar. So they're basically, they have a really good coach
and the coach is telling them for every set, how many reps to do or what RPE to go until.
So it's completely being programmed, but you get out, you eliminate the problem you just talked
about, which is you take the psychology away and you don't let the athletes suffer from knowing,
oh my God, I should be able to do this many reps. They don't know. So one day they might get down on
a bar and the bar is going to be really light and they're going to be told, you're going to, you know,
I think you're going to get 10 reps here. Let's see it. And they have no idea what percentage of
their max it ever is. So it's interesting. One of the top lifters in the world, somebody I competed
against multiple times, a guy named Bryce Lewis. So he actually trained an entire training cycle
that way. So he would have his girlfriend put trash bags over the weights. I don't know if
he still does that, but he- So she would load up every set. So she, but she had to be the one to
know what every set needed to be in advance. So she was, um, she's a competitive power lifter as
well. I think a world champion as well. And so yeah, she would kind of like look at what his
RPs were supposed to be at, load the weight up, put the trash bags over it, and then he would go do
it, you know, and probably just for what she meant. Super interesting. Now for me, that might work,
but I, for whatever reason- You like to control things a little bit. Yeah. There's some people on
meet day, they'll tell their coach, don't tell me what you're putting on the bar. Just tell me
what it is. Just put it on. Just make me do it. I'll go do it. I want to know. Uh, I don't know.
Maybe it's just part of how my brain's wired, whatever, because I also have a trust with my
coach and all the coaches I've had have been great. Honestly, I've worked with a couple of different
people and they've all been great. Um, I just had such a good, um, trust in my coach that I just
knew if they put something on the bar, they're not going to put something on the bar that they
don't think I can do. They know I can do it. It's my job to go and execute. And I think that that's a,
a really, when you have a good like meet day coach, that is so valuable because like I know
they're not going to put something on I can't do. So it's just up to me to go out and do it.
So what about nutrition? How does nutrition faction into factor into powerlifting? You're,
you're at 208 pounds or so right now. It's about the weight you're going to compete at.
You once told me that the difference between powerlifting and bodybuilding is in powerlifting,
all of your pain is compressed into the gym and bodybuilding. Most of your pain is actually out
of the gym. Uh, and having not done either, I mean, I did some powerlifting growing up,
but, but basically having never really done either of those at a serious level,
I can appreciate it just based on the concept. So, you know, you've been here now a few days,
we've had a bunch of meals together. You're just eating like a normal guy. Like, you know, we're,
we're eating whatever the hell we want. Um, is there anything you will do as you get closer to
the meat with your nutrition specifically? Because I know that you'd like to come in two
pounds or so below your target, but that's something you can modify in days outside of
just calories. Is there something you're going to manipulate with macros or anything that you're
going to be thinking about, you know, with respect to more creatine that you're going to be loading
or anything that you're, you're needling that way? Not really. I mean, at least for me, because I'm
sitting, you know, very close to the weight class that I'm going to compete in. Um, I don't really
have to make a bunch of changes. Now, if it was, you know, if I was sitting at say 215 pounds,
217 pounds, then it gets to the point where a weight cuts to a five becomes a little bit
untenable because, uh, where I compete, it's a two hour weigh in. So if you're cutting, you know,
10, 15 pounds, you're not going to be able to rehydrate and refuel quickly enough.
Two hours, meaning two hours between weigh in and competition.
And lifting, correct. Yep. So.
Yeah. Unlike the day before where you'd have a full day to catch up.
Right. So there are organizations where you can weigh in a day before. And I think actually one
organization had 48 hour weigh in. So there were guys, which actually in a way makes it more
dangerous because people will cut really, really cut. Oh yeah. I think Dan Green, who's, uh, really
well known, untested power lifter. Uh, I think he weighed in at 220 and then like the next day was
walking around like 255 or something like that. So just incredible like amounts of weight these guys
are cutting. Um, and so yeah, you'll see them with IVs and all that kind of stuff. So for us,
I mean, it's really like you can cut two, three, maybe 4% of your body weight, but you really don't
want to go much more than that because with two hours, you just don't have time.
So are you sticking with the same, are you doing one or you doing five grams of creatine daily right
now? Yep. I, so I, I keep my creatine in because I can modify, which is like sodium and modifying
fiber a little bit, uh, to get some water weight out those, those last few days. Uh, and like you
mentioned, I'll usually try to be a little bit under the day before the meat so I can eat enough
calories the day before where I don't feel like I'm having to shovel down food because, you know,
if you had to go pretty, if I have to go pretty aggressive, like for a Saturday meet Thursday,
Friday. Now on Saturday with that weigh in, I've got two hours to get food down. There's also a
lot of stuff I got to do. I got to get, um, you know, I got to warm up. I got a, I want my brain
free to think about the stuff I've got to do not be like, okay, well I've got to get down this.
I've got to get down that like I'll take some PD lighter or some kind of electrolytes, those
sorts of things. But for the most part, I've never really had issues with cramping. Uh, I've never
had issues with energy on meat day. Um, and I think a lot of that is just, I keep myself
pretty close to within striking distance. And then the other benefit is, you know,
your leverages can change it, you know, based on your weight thickness, you know, your, the tightness
of your belt can change. All that stuff can make a difference in terms of the style of squat you do
or how you feel. So just, you know, being able to train in a manner that's going to be very
similar to how I compete, I feel like is a little bit of an advantage for me compared to people who
have to cut quite a bit of weight. And if you had to guess by Dexa, what would your body fat be
at weigh in? Uh, I caliper at around 8%. So I would say Dexa is probably like 11 or 12,
something like that. Cause in my experience, Dexa is usually three, four percent higher than calipers.
So by most people standards still incredibly lean, but not necessarily by bodybuilding standards,
of course. Yeah, absolutely. So, okay. Well, let's actually, let's talk a little bit more about
creatine. Um, we talked about it really briefly on one of our podcasts, but we, we were kind of
at the end. So I want to kind of go back and make sure people understand that it's one of the
supplements we get the most questions about. It's also one of the supplements that we feel the most
confident telling patients, like if, you know, this is a supplement worth taking, it's clearly
passed test number one, which is it's safe. Uh, and it passes test number two, which is it's probably
got efficacy. Um, Washington said it's got efficacy. The real question is, you know, are you okay with
a little bit of weight gain? Cause that's, you know, you're going to pull more water in. So, um,
explain to people a little bit about why creatine is so important. And presumably this is something
that's really important in powerlifting. I'm guessing going into a bodybuilding meat,
you probably don't want creatine for that extra weight or do you? So I think it's actually great
for bodybuilding. Okay, great. I want to hear about it. Cause I would assumed it would, you'd
have a little more water, but maybe the water is all in the muscle and that's where you want it.
Yeah. So, uh, so creatine is a high energy phosphate donor. So in, in muscle,
it exists as phosphocreatin. And when you take supplemental creatine, uh, you'll,
it'll come into the muscle, it'll get a phosphate attached to it, phosphocreatin. And originally
the only mechanism we thought of, well, it's a high energy phosphate donor. So people will perform
better. But then we saw people increase their lean body mass, increase their strength. Uh,
and there's even like benefits in terms of cognitive benefits appear to be pretty clear
that there's some cognitive benefits as well. Uh, so as you mentioned, like in terms of safety
and efficacy data, I mean, to me, there's no strikes really, I tell people, I'm like, I don't
even know where we're having this conversation anymore. And it's also, you know, it's gone up
in price a little bit recently because of the supply chain stuff, but it's still relatively
inexpensive, incredibly inexpensive for, for what you're getting here. So, you know, when I see
people talk about like some of these other supplements and they're not even taking creatine
monohydrate, and I'm like, well, you're, you're stepping over pennies or sorry, you're stepping
over dollars to pick up pennies because this is just the lowest hanging fruit.
But are you still at, even at your size and even at your demand, is there any benefit to taking
more than about five grams a day? Some people have postulated there might be, I haven't seen
really clear evidence for it yet. You could argue that there's really no downside to taking the
extra. The downside might be some GI irritation for some people. Creatin can be a GI irritant,
which I think we'll circle back to. But we know it can act as a high energy phosphate donor. So,
when you are exercising or just doing anything, you, your energy currency of yourselves ATP,
and in order to drive muscular contraction, your ATP donates a phosphate and that liberation of
that phosphate to form ADP and a free phosphate is energetically favorable and helps drive these
muscular contractions. So creatine can act or phosphocreatin can act as a high energy phosphate
donor to reform ATP and allow you to perform better. But it's also a really powerful osmolite.
And so it pulls water into muscle tissue, which in and of itself may actually be anabolic. So
like just a muscle cell being more hydrated, there's some evidence that that can actually
improve the, that it's more anabolic environment. But regardless of the mechanism, we do know that
when you take creatine, you see improvements in lean mass. And some people will say, well,
that's just water. Well, that's what muscle mostly is. That muscle is 70% water. So whether it's,
and there's actually research to show that even non-contractile, just water improves,
may improve strength and contractability. So we're not sure exactly how, but it could just be like
the volumization of the cell is just a benefit. There's also sort of a, you could also kind of
make up at least conceptually a framework that says a more hydrated cell is more able to calculate,
more able to carry out its function, right? So the function of a myofibril is contractile release,
contract release, and it has more water. It sort of seems logical to me that it's going to be better
at clearing metabolic waste and recruiting fuel, which at least be two things that would factor
into its ability to do that. Yeah. I mean, the other thing about it is if you look at like
anything that improves hypertrophy, a big portion of it is water. It's not just all myofibrillar.
So I think regardless of the mechanisms, I mean, it's pretty clear that this stuff works. It's
pretty clear it's safe. I mean, they've done numerous randomized control trials, some of them
being well over a year long. Yes, you get an increase in creatinine, which can be a marker
of renal function. Although the data, on this lane, there was a paper that just came out a
couple of weeks ago that we were really happy to see. We've abandoned looking at looking at serum
creatinine for renal function because it's just too easy to get fooled by people with varying
muscle mass and training volume. So we've completely abandoned it. So every time you order labs on
somebody and you see their creatinine, it'll tell you what their estimated glomerular filtration
rate is. We just ignore it completely. We only look at cystatin C. So everything we do is based
off that. And there was a paper in JAMA a couple of weeks ago that basically said as much, which
is maybe we should look more at cystatin C instead of creatinine. So I would even say that hopefully
this is a PSA for other docs out there listening and other patients to say, please look at my
cystatin C as a way to estimate kidney function. Yeah. I tell people, there's some other things
that can get a little bit wonky, like from lifting weights like liver enzymes and whatnot.
And I tell people you have to keep in mind these are markers. Okay. So if you have liver failure
or you have kidney failure, it's very, very likely you will have elevated liver enzymes and elevated
creatinine. But just because you have elevated liver enzymes or elevated creatinine does not
mean that you necessarily have damage to those tissues. So you have to disconnect those two.
And I don't think that, you know, I feel like correlation versus causation is just not something
that's taught very well in school. Because I even see not really good doctors, but some physicians
get so hung up on just, well, this is on the page and this is supposed to be in normal range and it's
not. It's like, but just look at the person sitting in front of you who obviously works out, is in good
shape. If you're concerned about their kidneys, then do a 24 hour urine collection or an ultrasound
or whatever you have to do to verify that they're safe. But I mean, I just, I don't worry about that
kind of stuff. There's also been some people who have said, well, creatinine can cause hair loss and
you've got to be careful about that. I'm not, I don't think the data on that's very compelling at
all. So there was a single study that showed an increase in DHT from supplementing with creatinine.
One study, 2009, I've never seen it replicated, never seen any follow up.
How much did DHT increase by?
I'd have to go back and look. I can't remember the exact amount. It was significant.
But the interesting thing is we know creatinine doesn't affect androgen levels. So it's kind of
like, where is this increase in DHT coming from? Right? Like it has to come from somewhere.
And we, like I said, there's no randomized control trials showing that creatinine actually causes
changes to hair follicles or actual hair loss. So maybe it does. But I would think that if that
data existed, we probably would have seen it already. Do we think that there are significant
benefits from supplementation even on nonlifting days? So for example, on hard cardio days,
assuming we're not talking about sprints. So clearly there would be a benefit in sprinting
because the creatinine phosphate system is really lending to that ATP generation during that
incredibly high intensity stuff. But like if you're out there doing a VO2 max day, which is,
that's a really hard day. Those are kind of three to eight minute all out intervals,
which is aerobic. It's peak aerobic. Do you still get a benefit, do you think, from creatinine?
I would guess yes. There was a recent meta-analysis that came out and looked at like different ways
of taking creatinine. And it was useful data, but in some ways it was kind of frustrating because
they basically showed, well, you take five grams a day, you get increases in lean mass and strength
and performance. You take more than five grams a day, you also get increases in lean mass and
performance. But it's hard to kind of compare them directly based on the way they did the meta-analysis.
And then they also looked at, okay, if we just take them on lifting days, okay, you get benefits.
If you take them on non-lifting days, you also get benefits. What I would say is that
you probably can get away with just taking it on lifting days, but keep in mind that the benefits
of creatinine are an accumulation. So you've really got to saturate the muscle cell. That's
the key. Because when we were kids, you would load it. You would do like, I feel like you did
30 grams a day for a week or something crazy. Yeah. And then five grams thereafter. And of course,
this was reading bro science magazines. You would then do that for a couple of months,
and then you would come off it for a month, and then you would repeat the cycle. Am I making that
up or is that about- No, no, that was definitely a thing. So I will say that the research does show
if you load it, you will saturate the muscle cell faster. Now, I always try to tell people,
there's no solutions, there's only trade-offs, right? So the trade-off with this is a lot of
people will get pretty bad GI irritation with loading creatinine in terms of like GI bloating,
nausea, those sorts of things. So if you just take- Because you're playing the long game,
it doesn't really matter. Right. I mean, you're talking about getting the results you want in
one week as opposed to three weeks. It's really not a big difference. So if you just want to take
five grams a day, within a few weeks, you'll be saturated and you'll be getting the same benefits.
So it's really, I guess if you were somebody who'd never taken it before and you've got a big
athletic event coming up and you really want to be on it for it, that could make sense. But for
most people, I would say just take five grams a day. And when people say, well, what if I just
take it on lifting days? Yeah, probably could, but it's also like, it's pretty darn cheap.
Yeah. I actually think it's just easier to not forget. It's easier to forget something when you
only do it on certain days. Sometimes it's just easier to make it a part of the routine.
Yeah. And what I would say too, is people ask you about timing of creatine, those sorts of things.
There's some really small, really tenuous, I really want to emphasize that evidence that perhaps
after a workout might be better than before workout, but I tell people, just take it whenever
you'll take it regularly. So for me, I just get up in the morning and I take it. And that's what
I worry about. Now, as far as like the cycling on and off. So there's evidence that you do reduce
your endogenous production of creatine when you're on it. There's also evidence that the
creatine receptor on the muscle cell does down regulate a little bit. Now, the important thing
to keep in mind is that doesn't mean that your intracellular levels of creatine are falling.
So they've actually never shown that even like far out that those phosphocreatin levels in your
muscle drop. So what I would say is I don't really think there's a reason to come off because
they have shown that if you do come off within a month or so, kind of everything goes back to
normal, but you lose the benefit of the supplemental creatine. So I would say as long as
intracellular levels of creatine are not falling, there's really no benefit to coming off. I mean,
it used to be like, I think people kind of just equated supplements with steroids. And so like,
well, you're supposed to cycle steroids, so we should cycle supplements. And you know,
creatine is not hormonal. It's not the same biofeedback loop. So I would say there's probably
no reason to cycle it. So something else that kind of bridges the world between bodybuilding
and powerlifting is this question I wanted to ask you about, which is basically one of
Newton's laws, right? So force equals mass times acceleration. Okay. So let's just say I'm on the
ground. I've got my dumbbells or I'm on a bench and I've got my dumbbells and I'm going to press
them. One school of thought is press them as quickly as possible because force equals mass
times acceleration. The mass of this thing is fixed. So any speed with which I lift it is
accelerating because I'm moving against gravity, but the faster I can do it, the greater the force.
But of course, at some point, the weight becomes so heavy that you increase the effort more on the
mass variable than on the acceleration variable. So in other words, we can manipulate mass and
acceleration to reach maximum force. Now, an extreme example of that is you doing a one rep max.
But as you pointed out, the more elite a powerlifter becomes, the slower that is. In other words,
the lower the acceleration is, and therefore the more they're emphasizing the mass, which is of
course what you get scored on. No one's scoring you on the acceleration. Right. How does, how do
we think about that in terms of mixing and matching the mass versus the acceleration variable
in an effort to optimize force? Because of course we also don't want to go to maximum force every
time because if I did maximum force with a lightweight, I'd probably move it too quickly.
I could injure myself as well. So did you think about the variation of mass and acceleration
when you're moving weight? So yeah. So if you think about what the expression of strength is,
it's basically force. So as you mentioned, if it's a very heavy weight, it'll just move slower.
If it's a lightweight, you can still apply the same force and it will just move more quickly.
So this is actually a concept that I heard my coach Zach talk about on a podcast
was they do quite a bit of, we'll do a heavy single or double or whatever it is. And then
our back offsets are relatively light, like talking RPE four or five, but trying to move
them as quickly as possible. On both. Let's just talk about the concentric now. And then I want to
actually come and have the discussion about the eccentric. Yeah. On the concentric. Yeah. Exactly.
And because that is in terms of strength, that is the closest expression of that.
So in other words, if I'm understanding correctly, you're saying your coach is saying, look,
on the heavy weights, they're going to move slow because they have to.
But to keep training strength, I want you to move as quickly as possible as we come down on weight.
Bingo. Bingo. And that, so the idea is, but we're still applying the same force, it's going to move
more quickly, but it's going to be less fatiguing because it's lighter weight. So that's kind of the
concept behind it. Now in terms of. Is that happening with you? So for example, when you did,
let's just say your back wasn't hurting yesterday. If you were out there doing,
today was an RPE six day. Do you think that your speed would have increased sufficiently that you
would have almost matched 90% of the force you'd put out on a one rep max best? It's hard to tell
because I've never actually done a calculation of the force. I imagine there's probably a sweet spot
somewhere in there where like too heavy probably has less force than, you know, but yeah, I'm not,
I'm not sure where that is. As far as like, um, hypertrophy, I think that force is probably less
important. I think it's more about just having enough sufficiently hard sets, however you slice
that. So, uh, for example, like the whole idea of time under tension training was very popular. Um,
and if you look at some of the initial research, um, I think there was a study where they had people
doing curls and I may butcher the study, so I apologize, but it was kind of like a six second
eccentric six second concentric. And they had them go to failure and they had another group that just
did normal kind of cadence and they had to match the number of reps and found that the group that
was, uh, doing the slow eccentrics and slow concentrics gained more muscle. And so people said,
well, see, there you go. Well, the problem is they were using like 30% of their one rep max for like
10 reps going really slow. Well, if you're going at a normal pace, how many times could you do 30%
of one rep max? I mean, you could do 30, 40, 50 reps, right? So it wasn't, I don't want to say the
study was bad. It's not bad. It answered the question it wanted to answer, but if you're going
to compare them straight up, really what it needs to be is if you take both of these things to failure,
so the same level of intensity or sufficient difficulty, what does the outcome look like then?
And so when they do that, they really see very little difference between, uh, slow lifting and
fast lifting. Um, there was a study that just came out that looked at fast eccentrics versus slow
eccentrics and found that there was actually a little bit better, uh, outcomes with fast eccentrics
compared to slow eccentrics. And that actually relates back to, with respect to muscle mass.
Yeah. Which you mentioned this to me earlier. The only time I've ever done a fast eccentric
is on my extra fly machine, that machine that I, in the gym, because you're forced to, like it's,
it's pulling you down so quickly that you're screaming down and you're coming to a stop.
Outside of that, it never occurred to me to do an eccentric quickly. Like if I'm doing
eccentric deadlifts, I'm actually almost trying to come down as slowly as I can in my head,
thinking this is more beneficial because I was thinking it's more time under tension.
It's probably partly with the lift too as well. Um, and, um, there's probably
it's cut, it's kind of like you don't want to take it too extreme, right? Like if you're
actual, like if you're doing a squat and you just dive bomb and there's no tension on the bar,
right? One, that's going to look really bad when you're trying to come out of it. Uh, and two,
it's probably not the, what they're actually seeing in the research. I think the idea of a,
let's use a bicep curl cause that's a, it's a safer exercise. So this research suggests that
you've take two people that are doing the exact same weight and they're the same people basically.
And they're doing the same speed of their concentric. And one of them is doing, let's say
it's a two second concentric and he's doing a two second eccentric. And the other guy's going
two up six down. They're saying the two, two will technically produce more hypertrophy.
Might be better. So I say might because it's just so interesting. Yeah.
Now, if you think about like mechanotransduction and you know, the force, the mechanical tension
being applied to a muscle, when you're kind of getting to that point where the muscle is stopping
and then having to come the other way, if it's fast, I mean, that's probably more tension at
that specific point. Yeah. Yeah. So we just don't know enough about this stuff right now to really
be able to say for sure. But I think, you know, and I also don't want to make it sound like there's
no benefit to like slow movements, especially for people who like have pain or they don't want to go
heavy, you know, those sorts of things. Then, you know, slowing down a movement to either one,
because a lot of times pain can be tied to velocity. If you just slow down a movement,
it will be as painful. So I've used tempo training, like pretty liberally in some of my training
cycles just to make it so I had to use less weight, but still make it pretty difficult.
Now, was it as good as, you know, me doing my regular movement? Maybe not, but it's still
better than doing nothing. Right. So it's always important to keep those, like those things in mind
in terms of like, don't let, you know, perfection be the enemy of progress. So I do think that like
slow movements still have application for people, like I said, who have pain or if they don't feel
comfortable with heavy weight, you can make it much more difficult just by slowing down the movement.
At the end of the day, the biggest determinant is just doing enough number of hard sets. However,
that kind of looks now, there are a couple of patients that I've had over the years whose
disdain for exercise is so great that the most I can negotiate them doing
is one 20 to 30 minute workout per week doing the super slow protocol where they go to, you know,
they have these specific gyms that have very specific types of equipment. Yep. And they're
going to do, I don't know, maybe eight to 10 different machines, and they're only going to
do one set and it's going to be to failure. And the sets are typically titrated to be somewhere
between 90 and 105 seconds. So about a minute 30 to a minute 45 is the sweet spot, right? So if you're
going more than that, the weight's too heavy. If you're, the weight's too light, if you're less than
that, the weight's too heavy. And they might do like four simple upper body, four upper lower. So
there might be a press, a pull, a bicep, a tricep, a leg press, you know, all that kind of stuff.
Now, the reason I sort of negotiate that is my alternative is they'll do nothing. And I'm thinking,
I probably can't get any better benefit in 30 minutes once a week than I can there.
If it's done right. Now, the challenge that I've realized with that type of exercise,
because I've done this many times myself, it's actually really hard to go to failure.
At the end of the day, it can be done, but it can't be done often. And I actually think it's
really hard to do it eight consecutive times, which is basically what you're asking a person to do
in 30 minutes to truly go to failure. So what is your take on the super slow protocols,
which clearly guys like Mike Menser have, you know, like there are really famous body builders
who have taken these protocols to the limits. But what's your take both on the physiology of it and
then the psychology of it? Yeah, so I think that just kind of shows that there's, you know,
there's many ways to skin a cat, right? And when it comes to hypertrophy, you really have a lot of
options and certainly no one will argue that you can grow, can't grow muscle that way because you
can. It is kind of remarkable, isn't it? To think that like, yeah, these people could do 30 minutes
once a week and grow muscle. Yeah. In fact, there was, there was actually, so a friend of mine,
Jeremy Linneke is professor at Ole Miss. I had Jeremy's been on the podcast. Yeah. BFR. Yeah.
Yeah. He's great. My claim to fame is I actually introduced him to BFR. So, but they actually
published a paper where they looked at just flexing like isometric contraction. And we're
actually able to show like with long isometric contractions, like some hypertrophy, which before
that we always thought, oh, isometric doesn't actually grow muscle, right? Like there's,
there's a little benefit to it. So yeah, I think that we just, I hate to be the typical tools in
a toolkit, but things are tools in the toolkit. And we were talking about people who are, you know,
they don't want to be bodybuilders. They just want to get some of these benefits from resistance
training. It really is what can we do to get them in the gym consistently? And is it as good as like,
you know, compound movements with free bar and, you know, training at a normal pace? Maybe not,
but it's a heck of a lot better than them sitting at home and doing nothing. So I think, I think
that's really important to understand. And when it comes to like the super slow, the physiology of
the hypertrophy response, what's wild is we still don't fully understand how the process of muscle
hypertrophy occurs. Like we know that you need to progressively overload to continue causing the
hypertrophy response. We know what things are associated with hypertrophy, but every time they
try to get really granular with it, we still have a lot of gaps in our understanding. Now,
one of the things we do think matters is metabolic stress. So this idea that you're accumulating
these metabolic byproducts inside the muscle as you work it out. So that kind of like the pump,
right? That does appear to have some decent mechanistic data to support it, like in terms
of, you know, hydrogen ion accumulation, how that may affect some, you know, signaling,
those sorts of things, even right down to like calcium release into the sarcoplasm.
So I think when you're dealing with like that super slow protocol, you're kind of pushing a
little bit more on that metabolic stress as opposed to like the, the mechanical tension portion of it.
But there still is mechanical tension. I think a lot of people think about mechanical tension just
literally as weight on the bar. And I think what people don't realize is mechanical tension is
kind of cumulative. Because otherwise, why wouldn't we just load up a heavy single and just do that
every time, right? Because that's the most amount of mechanical tension you can get in terms of like
a set point in time. So to me, it seems pretty obvious that mechanical tension has to be like a
little bit cumulative throughout a set. And so if you're doing super slow, okay, you might have a
pretty lightweight, but you've also got a really long time that's under that really lightweight,
and you're accumulating the metabolic stress and some mechanical tension. So to me, it makes sense
that you would have some of those benefits. What I would say is, I think the bigger downside is
you're probably not going to get as strong doing that methodology as you are actually like doing a
little bit more normal pace. And it may have a little bit less functionality than somebody who's
done kind of more traditional strength training. That's my bigger issue with it truthfully is,
it's the one, I don't think people really can go to failure. Because I mean, you'll get a couple
of sets here and there, but it's really difficult. So I think it's easier to do an exercise where
you don't have to go to failure, but you make up for it on volume. But then your other point here
is, I think you're really missing out on the reason why we exercise. We generally don't, I mean,
sometimes we exercise to be a better at lifting. Powerlifting is the only example of that. But
outside of that, we lift for life. And I do worry that when we rob people of movements that require
more than one plane, movements that require balance and some coordination,
we're not giving them the full benefit of the exercise, of the reason to exercise that is.
Yeah. And I would agree with that. And again, that has to be one of those things where...
It's better than the couch, as you said. It's much better than the couch. Yeah. And so,
I mean, we, I think a lot of people when they get into things, especially now we have paralysis
by analysis. And I'll tell people like, you know, at a certain point, your paralysis by analysis is
actually just your excuse to do nothing. So just go do, go do something, right? Like go throw
something against a wall and see what sticks, right? But when it comes to people who may have
been sedentary, I mean, sometimes the conversation I'll have is, hey, what do you like doing? Like,
is there something you like doing? Right. And let's press on that a little bit. Because if the,
if the only outcome that we're going for is perfection, well, not a lot of people are going
to be able to hit that. So, yeah, I really do think a lot of it boils down to a conversation of,
okay, yeah, this isn't as good as this, but it's still better than that. And I think
that conversation is a lot of the stuff that gets lost, that nuance gets lost in a lot of
these conversations, especially because, and, you know, you're an optimizer. I love to talk
about optimal because it's like, as scientists, that's kind of where we live and what we think
about. But it's like, do people really need optimal to get out of like the state we're in,
where so many people have type two diabetes and have, you know, obesity and these are dying from
heart disease and cancer? No, we just, like, honestly, if we get them to get 50% of the way
there, probably see a huge benefit. Well, and that's really the flip side to this, the stats
I gave earlier in this discussion, which were how high VO two max and high strength were the two
biggest predictors of longevity. And that's true by a country mile. But the part that I didn't
mention that is now worth mentioning is that when you break people down into quartiles or
quintiles of fitness and strength, the biggest jump in the benefit, right? So the biggest
improvement in mortality always comes from being in the bottom quintile or quartile to the next one.
This is a really important point that shouldn't be lost. So people are sitting here listening to us
thinking, look at these two idiots who train all day and love this stuff. Like, that's nice for
you to say, no, actually, you're going to achieve the most benefit when you go from being in the
lowest 20% of the population to the second 20th percentile of population. And that can't be
overstated. I mean, that's so in other words, the curve looks like this. And I think one of the
biggest failures of the fitness industry, quite honestly, is convincing people that they need to
have a shredded six pack and be really muscular to be fit. Like, no, you don't have to. In fact,
I would argue that most people that are that lean probably don't feel that fit. I know that when I
was very lean for bodybuilding, I had no energy, no sex drive, thought about food all the time,
and, you know, was a miserable human. So like, the real sweet spot is probably where you got a little
bit of fluff. You're still relatively lean. But, you know, even not getting to that point, just
moving. I mean, look at the step data. The step data is very, very clear too. Like, there is a
huge inflection at about 8,000 steps per day. Where, yeah, you still get benefits by going even up to
like 20,000 steps a day. But the vast majority of the benefits just go from like, I mean, the
dip off in mortality. I'm sure you've seen it. It's like going from 2,000 to 8,000. It's like
precipitous. It's like free falling off a cliff. How drastically that decreases mortality. And I
don't think there's anything magic about steps. I just think you're just literally looking at people
getting more active. So I think one of the biggest failures in the fitness industry is the messaging
that you need to look like this in order for you to be healthy. When the messaging should be,
hey, for you to be healthy, it's really like a very low barrier to entry. Like, even if you just
get out and walk, you know, for 30 minutes a day. So much benefit from that just compared to just
sitting down. You know, just doing anything in the gym, even if it's people say, oh, machines are
worthless. They're not worthless. Machines are great tools. You're still applying tension to
the muscle. Would I argue that maybe, you know, a free barbell movement might be more functional?
Maybe. But if it's the difference between the 70 year old female who's never resistance trained
before getting into the gym and doing something or not, I'm going to be like, yeah, knock yourself
out of machines. So I think that is a huge failure of the fitness industry in the messaging, which is
you need to look like this in order for you to have achieved health. So on that front,
because I do want to talk a little bit about bodybuilding, both in your own personal experience
and just again, the insights that we can gain. I don't think most people listening to this myself
included ever want to be 4% or 5% body fat, which is you don't. Yeah. So, but look, I'm sure somebody
who's 25% body fat would like to be 20% body fat. And can they learn something from bodybuilder? But
just picking up where you went, where do you see, you know, kind of the general role of fitness
experts in social media? How can a person sort of make sense of the never ending sea of experts out
there? Man. So a couple years ago, we had a guy in our podcast named Alan Livenovitz. He's been on Joe
Rogan's podcast too, and he's a religious studies expert, but he wrote a book on kind of like the
naturalism fallacy. And we were talking about like how hard it is for people to identify experts.
And he said something that I thought was really insightful. He said, what you should look for
an expert is the exact opposite of what you probably think you should look for. If somebody
sounds really confident, they're probably not an expert. What you really want to look for is people
who sound kind of doubtful. And they say things like probably, maybe, possibly, you know, if you,
when you speak to true experts, usually if you ask them a question, the first thing they'll do is ask
you a question back, unless the question is very contextual, right? So I'll get people who say,
hey, what are your thoughts on X, right? And usually I'll say, okay, well, as it pertains to
what, like hypertrophy or strength or fitness or, you know, like I need context in order to be able
to answer the question correctly. And so I think looking for people, like people ask me like, what
do you think about like credentials? I'm like, credentials help. Like if I see somebody has a
PhD in a certain subject, I'm probably going to give them a lot more leeway in terms of, okay,
if they say something I disagree with, let me see why they said that, you know, let's,
let's dig a little bit deeper. But I've seen some PhDs say some really dumb stuff. I've seen people
from Harvard say really dumb stuff. I've probably said really dumb stuff, right? Like it doesn't
stop you. Credentials aren't a, they're a nice thing, but they're not foolproof. So really,
I try to listen to how people speak. But given that you have such a knowledge background,
it's, it's a lot easier for you to kind of look at, you know, someone's Instagram account and
pretty quickly realize this person knows nothing. They might look good. They might be a great
marketer, but they don't really know anything. Yeah. But, you know, the average person doesn't
have your knowledge base. Correct. And so what, what else can they rely on? So clearly that's one
great criteria or two, right? Is, you know, some sense of credentialing can be helpful. Some sense
of speaking with nuance and being comfortable with uncertainty. I think that's also helpful.
Are there any other tools that a person can use to disentangle this world?
People who say the magic words, I don't know, you know, like that again sounds counterintuitive,
but I remember when, so when I was part of getting my PhD, I had to do what was called a qualifying
exam. And so that is a four hour oral examination in front of four professors. And when I was
prepping for this, Dr. Lehman, who you've had on the podcast, he, he said, they're going to push
you in whatever subject they start out on until you don't know. And you need to be able to say,
I don't know. And so they did exactly that. Like I'll still never forget the way they started off
the qualifying exam was let's talk about vitamins. What's your favorite? So vitamin D. Okay. Where
is it synthesized? And they kept pushing until I just didn't know. And I'll still never forget.
They asked me like an acid base balance question in the long and I started to get up on the wipe
off board and like try to draw. And I just turned around and said, I don't know this one. So, okay,
move on. And when I got done, they said, you were actually one of the best students we've had the
last few years because you knew what you knew and you knew what you didn't know. And they, that
division puts such an emphasis on not going outside your lane, not speaking about something,
not speculating, not speculating about something that you didn't know and trying to pass it off
like you did. So I think that just got hammered into me. So when it comes to looking at other
folks, one, if they're willing to like know their scope and not feel the need to comment on every
single thing, that's a good, that's a good metric. Also, you know, I'm going to paint with a broad
brush and there's always exceptions to this. But people who use like tips, tricks, hacks,
five things to never do, five things to always do the best worst people who use a lot of superlatives.
That's not typically the way that experts talk. You know, I say a lot, there's no solutions,
there's only trade offs, right? There's certain tools that make a lot more sense,
depending on somebody's goals and where they're at than compared to somebody else and vice versa.
But that almost suggests that social media is negatively selecting, because a lot of those
things that you said, certainty, you know, a flare for showmanship, tips, tricks and listicles,
that's against attention. I think the algorithm likes those things because they get a lot of
attention, even if some of that attention isn't warranted. So that adds another layer of confusion
to this, which is it is difficult. And it's, you know, even when I scroll through Instagram,
I'm amazed at how much it's trying to push to me. You know, I miss the day when all I saw on
Instagram were the 40 people I followed. Yep. Like those, I feel like that was the good old day.
And in the sequence of the way things were posted too.
It was like, oh, here's what this friend of mine did. Here's what this friend of mine did. Here's
what this person who I don't know, but who I respect, the way that I did it, I was like,
and now it's insane, the barrage of stuff that Instagram thinks I want to see. And admittedly,
sometimes it's right. Yeah. But so many times it's just wrong. And it makes me think, well,
if that's my experience, that's got to be everybody's experience. And it is. I think
Alan talked about this as information silos. And this is a broader problem, but it is a problem
in nutrition and fitness specifically. You know, people don't really, if you just follow the people
you follow and the accounts that get suggested to you, you're actually not broadening anything.
Right. So you're, you're sitting in an information, information silo. And what happens is,
or at least what I think is happening is, you know, previously nineties, two thousands,
eighties, whatever, you know, you'd come across people with differences of opinion to you and
you could have a conversation with them. And it usually was, you know, sometimes it could be
contentious. But for the most part, I would say like, when you can sit down and look a human being
in the eyes and talk about your differences, it's usually not as confrontational. Right.
Now we have whole generations of people who are not used to seeing opinions different than their
own or thoughts or beliefs that are different from their own because they're in those information
silos. And when they get exposed to something different, they just don't know how to handle it.
And so, I mean, like you see some really like extreme responses, even to stuff like nutrition,
you know, like I can't name how many times I've been called a shill for, you know, XYZ, you know,
big meat, big dairy, artificial sweeteners, big sugar, you know, because it's almost like, well,
it can't possibly be somebody just has a different opinion based on this data. They have to be a bad
person. So I do think it's a real problem. And what you said is very well taken that is, you know,
you almost have to be willing to do clickbait to really get your stuff out there. And so I, as a
business owner who does a lot of the business through Instagram, I really have to try to screw
it a fine line of I am trying to get people's attention and not lose the nuance and the context
and all those things are important. And, you know, trust me, there's days where I'm like, man,
I can make so much money if I just, you know, but that isn't how I want to live my life or leave my
legacy or anything. And so you're an interesting person because your personality on Twitter and
your personality on Instagram are quite different. And your personality in real life is totally
different. Yeah. So people who know you, like I know you, you almost don't recognize. Now, tell
me a little bit about that. Has that been an evolution? Because I have to be honest with you,
I quite envy your personality on Twitter. I've just made a decision that I've almost always been
able to uphold, which is I'm not going to get drawn into it. Yeah. Right. In fact, I don't
really even look at comments on Twitter anymore. Posting ghosts. Posting ghosts as Rogan has
adequately reminded me many times. So, but I'll be honest with you, I see enough negative ones
where I just want to spank the living shit out of the person on the other. I mean, I want to,
with words, eviscerate them. Yeah. And 99.9% of the time I refrain from doing it.
But I really get a kick out of the fact that a lot of times you just spank people into the next
century. So tell me about that. How, you know, so is it a conscious decision? Because it never comes
across as unhinged. It never comes across as terribly reactionary. It usually comes across
as kind of calculated. Yeah. But yeah. So just walk me through your thinking. So I think it
probably was a little bit unhinged when I first started, you know, like the internet was just in
general, like I'm bodybuilding forums. It's like, well, you disagree with me. You call me a name.
Well, you know, but I think, you know, my style isn't going to be for everybody.
And I think part of it, honestly, if I had to like psychoanalyze myself, probably goes back to like
me being bullied as a kid. And I almost view like misinformation and people who, especially
like you've probably noticed, I save my most, the biggest amount of vitriol for people who
is very clearly have a pattern of behavior that's also being monetized. Right. So that's like,
when you're like preying on the desperation and ignorance of people, I'm going to have very little
sympathy for you. And I think part of that evolved to out of my coaching and seeing how many people
came to me, like quite frankly, feeling broken, because they tried so many of these things that
were the solution and the cure. And when it didn't work for them, they're just like, oh, I'm,
you know, something wrong with me. It's like, nothing's wrong with you. You just like, you
haven't been executing on these principles that work. Right. And so I really have tried to kind
of like dial it back a little bit because I think I took it too far at a certain point.
But now I just try to like use it to be funny, right? Like to get to get some attention. Like,
I think one of my, one of my most popular. So what's funny is like my best Instagram posts are
all just screenshots of my Twitter. Like if you look at my, you can go to your insights, right?
And you look at my top performing posts. It's like 95% Twitter screenshots, right? So,
um, yeah, I think my, one of my top rated posts of all time was, um, Mark Hyman had said something
and my, my response was just stop making shit up. Just, just, you know, very like, you know, uh,
cavalier and, you know, funny. And, you know, I think there are some people who would absolutely
would turn them off and I get that. But then I also speak to the person, people who are like,
yeah, I'm tired of like stuff being overly sanitized. And I just wish somebody would tell
me how they really feel. Right? So, and it's funny cause I've had so many academics reach out to me
behind closed doors and say, I love your Twitter. I love just watching you like, you know,
break this stuff down. And the thing is I'll say to people is it's like, you know,
it's never just me attacking the person. I'm also providing like citations and I'm, or logic and
data and whatnot. Uh, but I'm just trying to make it funny and engaging, you know, um, you know,
but I'll always have a conversation with some, with somebody like, for example, um,
Thomas DeLauer is a great example. So, uh, I've done several videos, kind of debunking some of
the claims he made. And actually one day he just reached out to me and said, Hey man, I want you to
know that, um, I actually really respect you and you've actually made me change the way I think
about some of this stuff. Would you want to come on my podcast? Yeah, man, let's do it. Because I
really respect anybody who can be self-reflective enough to go, you know what? I might've been
wrong or just even like wanting to get a different perspective on things. So just another great
example of that. I'm actually going and speaking at a low carb conference next year. Um, the joke
was like, are you, are you going to need a, do I need to bring bodyguards? You know? Um,
it, that's so interesting to me. I, um, I don't know. And I'm not close enough to any of the
dietary communities to know. Uh, obviously I still get very strongly associated with a low carb
ideology, which is funny given that you see how many carbohydrates I eat. Um, but what is the
view about you and low carbohydrate diets? Because you know, I, I, I've never heard you
say anything that is uniquely, uh, anti low carb other than, you know, the stuff we've already
talked about on the previous podcasts. Yeah. So I always tell people, so I'm like,
how could I be anti low carb? If you go to my, our, our nutrition coaching app, carbon diet coach,
two of the, two of the six settings are low carbohydrate. There's low carbohydrate and
there's ketogenic. So how could I possibly be low carb or anti low carb? And I think that this is
just an example of, uh, I call this the Tim Tebow effect. So, uh, but it's just like polarization. So
do you remember when, uh, Tim Tebow was playing NFL football? My hypothesis was there is very few
people, there are very few people in the middle about Tim Tebow. You either love them or you hate
them. And the way this kind of comes up is like, if you watch this guy and you're like, yeah, you
know, he's not really that good. He's got weird mechanics. He's more of a running back than he is
a quarterback and he's kind of preachy, but you know, he's all right. But then you see all these
people saying he's the Heisman. He, you know, he's going to playoffs like, well, you know, he's
better than your quarterback. Like, you know, this, that you go, what are you talking about?
Like his completion person, it just like 45%. How can you say he's good? Then you have the other side,
which people like, like me, I actually was kind of a Tim Tebow fan. Cause I'm like, you know,
he seems like a nice guy who works hard. Um, maybe not the best genetics to be a quarterback,
but like, you know, he's been successful. Like that's, that's admirable. And then you look over
here and you see all these people going, he sucks. He's terrible. And it's like, well, he did win a
playoff game, you know? So I think this happens in, with many different subjects and even right. Like
we were talking about this the other day, you know, you're a car guy. I'm not a car guy, right? So I've
posted many times. In fact, when we bought our, our new house, I'm going to take a picture of me
with the car outside the house. It's going to be the greatest picture that ever goes to my social
media. Cause I've still got my grad school car, which is a 2003 Alero. And I've just never,
I just never felt the need to get rid of it. Right. So you got this really dinky old car with
me on the hood sitting outside this, you know, wonderful, you know, big house and sure enough,
we got like 1500 comments, but some of the comments were, and I was talking about how
basically saying, you know, my ability to delay gratification is what got me here. And
you can do it too. Like delaying gratification and anything is so essential for success in almost
any goal. Cause it's so crazy how in almost anything, whatever provides you like short term
relief for happiness almost always makes it worse in the longterm and vice versa. But people
would say, why do you, why do you hate people who buy nice cars? I'm like, where did I say I hate
people buy nice cars. I never said that, you know, same thing with low carb that my messaging has
consistently been usually there'll be some kind of insane claim, you know, like calories don't
matter or, you know, you can eat as much on low carb as you want, not gained fat. And then I'm
like, well, here's citation, citation, citation, low carb does not appear to be better for fat loss
than, you know, calorie protein, equated diets that are not low carb, but that means choose what
you prefer because it's not worse. So by all means, like if you like low carb, go right ahead.
I don't enjoy low carb, but I know many people that do. And so I think one of the reasons people
get so troubled about this is they find something that worked for them and they then retroactively
try to find the evidence to show that it's the best thing that there is. And which, which of the
two landscapes, nutrition and exercise, do you think is more culty? My impression is nutrition.
Definitely nutrition. Definitely nutrition. And do you think that that's because of the
ubiquity of food in our lives and the fact that we all have almost equally a personal relationship
with food, whereas not everybody exercises the same amount. And do you think that that's.
So there's two things, especially here in America, we come from a Puritan background. And I think
that this this kind of thinking that anything that is pleasurable at all must be bad for you
and you cannot have it. You should feel bad about it. Right. So I think that causes people to get
a little bit tribal in terms of like, I mean, I've had people like say horrible, like moral judgments,
because like I'll post me eating a bag of Skittles or something like that. You know,
never mind the fact I just went and trained for three hours, you know.
I think somebody like called me a disgusting sugar addict one time.
So that's one part of it. I think it's the smaller part. I think the bigger part is what you just said.
If it's funny, whenever I meet new people, I'm always kind of hesitant to, you know,
if they don't know anything about me to tell them that I have a background in nutrition,
PhD nutrition, because usually one of a couple of things happens. They either clam up real quick,
like brought to dinner and they get very self-conscious about what they're eating, which
bro, I just ordered the fries like, you know, you're good.
Or I get like blitzkrieged with questions, but mostly people wanting me to validate what they
already believe to be true. But if I was, if I sat down, I said, you know, I'm a theoretical
astrophysicist. We might talk about space a little bit, but they're probably not going to question my
beliefs or my opinions on string theory. Right. But I think because everyone eats and everyone
knows something about their body, right or wrong, they have drawn certain conclusions about what
they put in their body and what happens to their body. And so I think because of that, because
everybody has an opinion about nutrition, it makes it really tough because people are already like,
just natively have certain beliefs. And we know how hard it is to change people's beliefs. There
was a classic study. It was in politics. It was a classic study where they showed hard data,
and this was for both parties. They would either refute a preconceived belief or support it.
I think one of them was with I can't remember what they used for Republicans, but for Democrats,
the belief was that I think George W. Bush stopped or outlawed funding for stem cell research or
something like that. The reality was he just stopped federal funding. He didn't outlaw it.
So they showed people this, these facts. By the way, again, if I butchered that, I apologize
to anyone watching, but I think that was it. They showed people these facts and it didn't matter.
If they believed that he had outlawed it, even if they showed them the facts that he didn't,
they still, it still reinforced their pre-existing belief. It actually made their belief stronger.
And the same thing was true for Republicans, by the way. And I don't think it's a Republican or
Democrat problem. I think it's a people problem, to be honest. And I think one of the benefits I had
very early on in grad school was Dr. Lehman just absolutely dismantling so many beliefs I had.
But then, but doing it in a way that wasn't judgmental or made me feel bad. And what I
tell people now, it's like being wrong about something is a beautiful thing. Because if I'm
already right about everything, then I'm already doing everything the best I can and I can't get
better. But if I'm doing something, if I'm wrong about something, that's actually awesome because
now I have something I can improve on. So now I tell people I like being right, right? Like I'll
do cartwheels in my living room if I'm right. But if I'm wrong, I don't really take that much
offense to it because it's just data. It's not, there's no ethical judgment. And I've changed my
mind about a myriad of things. I was going to ask you, what are three of the most impactful things
that you have changed your opinion on in nutrition specifically? And let's make it recent, because I
know for any of us, if we go back a decade, it's an eternity in terms of our understanding of
nutrition science or something like that. But let's pick a narrow window of maybe like three or four
years. What would be sort of three areas where your opinion has really changed in a manner that
actually leads to either a different behavior in you or a different coaching input to your clients?
I think of three things right away. So first thing being LDL cholesterol. So when I got to grad school,
the kind of the narrative and even out of the lab I was in was, it's really, we don't think it's LDL.
It's more the HDL to LDL ratio and the particle size and those sorts of things.
And I kept that probably until about five years ago, four years ago. And I just saw enough of these
Mendelian randomizations come out. It's like, wow, that's pretty powerful. When you look at the
mortality rate and it is like linear with the exposure, the lifetime exposure to LDL, I'm like,
can't really hold this belief anymore because it's just not supported by the data.
And it actually changed my opinion on like, you know, now I'm a little bit more conscious about
the saturated fat I consume. We talked about like I actually started taking a low dose of a statin.
And that's helped. So I've never had super high LDL, but I've always been around 150 to 125,
even if I reduce my saturated fat, increase my fiber. I eat probably 60, 70 grams of fiber a day.
So, you know, I think people get that one twisted a little bit because they'll hear things like,
well, it doesn't consider HDL. It doesn't consider this. No, you have to understand what an
independent risk factor means. It means that all things being equal, are you better off having
higher HDL? Yeah. But HDL is more of a marker of metabolic health because we have some drug trials
and Mendelian randomizations now where they modulate HDL and it doesn't really seem to make
a difference. Whereas if you modulate LDL, so even at high HDL or low HDL in both stratifications,
lower LDL is almost always better for cardiovascular disease and mortality.
I feel like I need to do a podcast on Mendelian randomization. I write about it in my book.
And I actually- It's very powerful.
Yeah. And I understand why it doesn't get more attention because you do have to really get into
the weeds of genetic sorting and the statistical methods that are involved. But I actually in the
book write about it as one of the five pillars of evidence that we should be relying on as we
formulate insights with respect to anything that we do. So that's an interesting one. And obviously,
it has a parallel piece, which is around your relationship to saturated fat.
Yeah. And I think one of the things to keep in mind is when you're looking at mortality,
cardiovascular disease, this is where nutrition science can become so limited. And the power with
Mendelian randomization is you're kind of looking at a lifetime randomized control trial.
That's right. Right. So people will point out things like the Minnesota coronary study,
and I think there was another Australian study and they said, well, look at this randomized control
trial where they looked at high saturated fat versus low saturated fat, and there wasn't a
difference or that sort of thing. And one of the biggest problems with those studies is,
you know, they're two years, which is a really long time for a randomized control trial.
But when you're talking about a disease that is a lifetime exposure, two years in people that are
in their forties, I mean, you're just not going to have that many incidences to pick up on.
So when you're looking at Mendelian randomization, you can get around that because you're looking at
people across their lifetimes. And the way I kind of explain, and I don't consider myself a lipid
expert, but the way I try to explain like lifetime exposure risk is imagine if you and I start
investing, right? And you get in at 8%. We both invest $10,000. You get an 8%, I get a 6%.
If we look after a year or two, I mean, you'll have more, but it won't be like statistically
different, right? But if you look at four years, you're going to have a lot more. And I don't know
how much exactly, but my guess is it's going to be magnitudes of times greater because you're, again,
lifetime exposure. Actually, I've done this exercise and it was initially in my book. I
actually use this exact analysis was $1,000 invested at, I think I chose 6% versus 4%,
or maybe it was even 6 versus 5. It was something that was small enough that at 5 and 10 years
wasn't enormous, but at 40, 50 and 60 years was staggering. And that was the exact point,
which is the cumulative effect of compounding over a lifetime is so nonlinear that I don't think
we are capable of understanding it. Like I don't think we can ever cognitively realize it until we
literally just do the calculations and they're staring us in the face. Yeah. And I think, you
know, that, that again, that's one thing I changed my mind on that. I was pretty, I was pretty strong
belief about it. And, you know, it's kind of like, well, how much evidence do you need? Like,
you know, we, we still have kind of LDL denialists out there. And I think it's one of the, I think
it's one of the most dangerous things I see actually. Yeah. I mean, like you have the mechanism,
the penetration of the endothelium, it's very clear that that happens. We have the animal models
that show linear dose independent effects. You have the Mendelian randomization and you have
the clinical trials in humans. And you have the prospective cohort studies. And then you have the,
you have the genetic studies. So, right. You have the PCSK9 over and under expressors. So, so,
I want to come back to the Minnesota heart study in a moment, but let's go on and hear the other two.
Yeah. So supplemental branched amino acids. That's another one. I used to be a big advocate for that.
In fact, the first supplement company I had five years ago, we sold a product with branched
amino acids in it. And then my, my current supplement company, Outwork Nutrition,
we do not have a branched amino acid product because. And that was basically taking the three
branched amino acids as an in workout supplement. As a post-workout recovery supplement. I still
do think there may be a small benefit for delayed onset muscle soreness with branched chains that
may be outside of just regular protein, but based on the cost and honestly, like the,
the negative impact on taste too, because that's the, the Lucene is horrible, right? Oh, yeah.
You know, I used to, I think I told you, I used to spike five grams of Lucene into my water
during a workout. I mean, it's the most awful tasting. Is there any other, is there any other
amino acid that tastes as bad as Lucene? Probably some of the sulfur based ones, you know, cysteine
or methionine. Yeah. No, it's pretty bad. And the fact it's also non-polar, so it doesn't dissolve.
Yeah, it doesn't dissolve. Well, you're shaking it constantly.
Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, I was a big advocate for that. I was sponsored by a company called
Salvation for years that had a branch amino acid product.
Has the rest of the world caught up to that or BCAA is still a big product.
They still are a big product. They still are a big product, but most evidence-based folks,
you know, will say, Hey, we just, there's, it's not really, it's not better than protein.
Yeah. Right. In fact, the actual,
the research tends to suggest whey protein is actually better than branched chains.
Even when you equate for the dose of branched chains in the protein.
So yeah, I just kind of got to the point where I'm like, if I, if I put this in the products,
I'm just doing it because my, you know, I'm tied to branch chains, right? Like people are expecting
this from me because like my PhD was in Lucene in the branch, amino acid and the metabolism and
other effects on muscle protein synthesis. But I just, I couldn't hold that position anymore based
on the evidence because it was just too strong. And then the other one that I have now lost in my
brain. Oh, so the idea that I used to really kind of discourage people from intermittent fasting.
So the other thing I changed my opinion on was intermittent fasting,
at least in terms of like your traditional 16, eight, because I used to say, well, I'm worried
about the, the catabolic effects of it, you know, that sort of thing, at least when combined with
resistance training and sufficient total protein and that the caveat should be that they also,
the, in these studies, they trained within their feeding window. There's some really good studies
by Grant Tinsley on this. There doesn't appear to be at least not statistically significant
differences in lean mass between people who do 16, eight intermittent fasting versus people who
just eat continuously. So I used to be like somebody like, well, you know, really like every
four hours should be getting a protein dose, that sort of thing. Maybe if you plot it out over 30
years, it'll make a difference on how much lean mass you gain. So I would still say if you're
somebody who is a bodybuilder and you want to absolutely squeeze out every last ounce of muscle
that you can get, I still would say like any form of intermittent fasting probably isn't optimal,
but for the average person, can you get plenty strong, plenty big and still do intermittent
fasting? At least the 16, eight, I would say absolutely. Which is really interesting because
I've kind of gone the other way from you. Yeah, you were saying. I used to be a big proponent
and then what I was seeing clinically, so this was really just anecdotal, but when you see it
over and over and over and over again on so many patients on whom you have DEXA data and
was, we were seeing a real deterioration of body composition. Now were they still definitely
getting enough total protein? No, and that's my point. So what I know was happening was
they were falling behind on protein. And so the question then becomes one of efficacy versus
effectiveness. In other words, the data which are done under controlled settings say if I control
for total protein, it can be identical, but the effectiveness version of that is in practice,
do people make that happen? And I guess what I would say is we weren't seeing it. So we still use
intermittent fasting in patients as one of the three big levers of energy restriction, but we
have a big red caution button all over it that says if you choose this instead of caloric
restriction or dietary restriction, if you want to choose time restriction as your lever,
you're going to have to go out of your way to make sure you are not compromising protein.
Yeah. And I think one of the things I'll tell people is, and I can do dogmatism over all these
different disciplines, including what I like, which is flexible dieting, but people get too hung up on
the actual fasting part of intermittent fasting. You're reducing your energy intake. It's a tool
and a lot of people, it works great. They say I'm not hungry. It didn't feel like I was dieting.
Awesome. But so people will say, well, is it going to break a fast if I have coffee?
Will it break a fast if I chew gum? Will it break a fast if I have a protein shake? And what I'll
say is like, well, why are you fasting? And usually if they're like... And by the way,
I'm only laughing because I'm guilty of this. Right. I used to really think about the details
of that and that I just don't think... Look, I think autophagy is an incredibly important
part of our ability to regenerate. I just don't think there's a chance you're getting any meaningful
amount of it in 16 hours. And therefore, to your point, we would even tell patients now to have a
protein shake outside of that feeding window. In fact, I think you and I even spoke about that idea,
which was if it's really all about energy restriction, what's an extra 200 calories
outside of your feeding window? Exactly. Actually, if you look at some of the effects of high protein
diets, they actually are not dissimilar from some of the effects you get from fasting, at least like
liver metabolism and whatnot. So I would say to somebody, well, don't worry about breaking your
fast in terms of you're eating something. If you're worried about it, intermittently fast your
carbohydrate and fat intake and just have an extra dose of protein in the morning, or essential
amino acids or whatever you want. Because now you're getting that anabolic stimulus,
spreading it out a little bit more. You're making sure you get enough total protein in during the
day. And quite honestly, I mean, this is a theory that Dr. Lehman and I had, which was breakfast
probably is the most important protein dosing of the day because you are coming off a significant
period of fasting. And then if you're extending that out, like how much longer are you extending
that out? What does that mean? You know, it's long term. I think I told you, I've officially
taken to bribing my 14 year old daughter. Yeah. Yeah. So there's now real stakes on the line for
her to get that minimum 30 grams of protein. No pun intended mistake, right? That's right.
Minimum 30 grams before she goes to school in the morning. Yeah. I'm like an awful father.
So it's interesting how that that that kind of dogmatism plays out. Like you have the same thing
with low carb, right? Like people so worried about getting any carbs. Meanwhile, they're like dumping
oil on their salad and, you know, putting butter in their coffee and, you know, eating like loads
of bacon or they're, they're eating keto ice cream because it's not spiking their blood sugar. But
it's like, if you looked at the keto ice cream, it's actually more calories than like, like we're,
we're missing the entire point here, right? Yeah. And the same thing goes for like flexible dieting.
Like I had people who were like, it's like they were trying to hack the system of how can I eat
as much junk food as I would. I'm allowed 3000 calories a day. What if it's all Skittles? Right.
So like, what if I do just protein shake, you know, Skittles and peanut butter. And my point is like,
listen, like if you take anything too far, it's probably a really bad idea. Right. And one of the
things I said about flexible dieting too is like, we know fiber is really important. Like, you know,
there are some folks who are kind of anti fiber now. Oh, really? Oh, yeah. I've missed this. I've
missed this move. Well, the carnivore, the carnivore folks. Ah, okay. Okay. It's funny. Like, um,
I was in a debate one time with a carnivore advocate and you know, my research was sponsored
by the Egg Nutrition Center, the National Dairy Council and the National Cattlemen's Beef
Association. And I, if anybody should be pro carnivore. Yeah. And I said, the fact that I'm
sitting here defending plants is actually kind of mind blowing to me. And if anything, it should
actually increase your trust in what I'm saying, because I mean, I am a fan of high quality animal
protein. I think it's, what is the argument? Let's talk for a moment about the carnivore diet.
Obviously for people listening, it's pretty straightforward explanation. It's a diet where
you only eat meat. Right. And I've heard some versions now where people eat honey and fruits
and whatnot, which I'm not sure how that's carnivore anymore. But in any case, I would say
that's a little better. But so the argument against, what's the argument in favor of that?
What do they propose is the reason to do it? So the reason to do it is, I mean, it's basically
anecdotal. People have done this and they've seen this, right? And of course, like you could
absolutely lose weight doing something like that. Some people. It was pretty easy to see how you
would lose weight only through the lens of dietary, the strict enough dietary restriction
is going to ultimately reduce. I mean, how much meat can you eat? Even if it's fatty meat, right?
Like so. And the justification is why I still go to the bathroom just fine. It's like, well,
that's not why you should eat fiber. I mean, yeah, it helps, but that's, that's the last reason to
eat fiber, in my opinion. So that the, they also, some people have said, well, it helped clear up
some autoimmune issues. That's hard to quantify. And some people say, well, like it lowered my
inflammation and, and, and my GI problems. So this is one thing a lot of people get mixed up.
They'll get like bloated or have GI discomfort and they equate that with inflammation.
Yeah. You may have like some, you might have some, like some localized inflammation,
although it's probably based on what we know about like IBS and whatnot. It's probably just like,
like Barrow sensitivity, but that's not the same thing as like, well, usually say, well,
did you get your CRP measured? Like, did you get your IL-6 measured? You know, that's inflammation.
When we talk about inflammation, that's what we're talking about. Now.
But how do you make, let's assume that they, that all those things are true. Let's assume that I
went on a carnivore diet and my actual biomarkers of inflammation improved and my symptoms improved.
I don't know what the number is, but if you think of the average number of foods a person will eat
in a given week, different foods, let's posit that it's in the tens, maybe a hundred. If you
eliminate all but one of them, it's not a good experiment to, you haven't really learned a lot.
You've learned that something in those 99 might have been the problem. That's a hard way to learn
that. So one of the things I've said, I think a lot of people are getting benefits is they're
basically doing an elimination diet. So for the most part, most people don't have sensitivities
to meat, but like I think many people just not being in tune with their body probably have IBS,
FODMAP sensitivities where they're fermenting a lot of fructans, oligosaccharides, those sorts of
things. And that fermentation for people with IBS is even though it's a healthy thing because
bacteria getting fuel from fiber is a healthy thing. If it's causing pain, they're equating
that with being something negative, which obviously we don't want anybody to be in pain.
I still believe that there are a lot of people who have wheat sensitivities that are not
full on gluten sensitivities that don't rise to the level of celiac disease.
Yeah, it's possible. So it's one of those things where they eliminate all plants and they go,
well, I feel better. Okay. Well, now the next step should be adding things back in one by one
and let's figure out what's actually causing those problems. So what I would submit to people is like
still try to include fruits and vegetables and just slowly add them back in and see what works
for you because I think, and this gets into kind of like dietary protein longevity. I think a lot of
this negative perception of animal protein with longevity and health is people who eat high
amounts of animal protein. These aren't people for the most part. They're not eating like lean cuts
of sirloin and chicken breasts and whatnot. People eating high meat are typically eating
high amounts of processed meat and they eat less amounts of fruits and vegetables. In fact,
there's a really classic study, in my opinion, from Maximoff in 2020 and they looked, I think it was
quintals, so four different like serving amounts of fruits and vegetables and four serving amounts
of meat, so lowest to highest, right? And when you look at like low vegetable intake, there is like
a linear effect of, or sorry, if you look at like going from high to low vegetable intake, linear
effect on the incidence of cancer and meat, as you go up in meat, not correcting for fruits and
vegetable intake, you have a linear effect of meat on cancer. But guess what happens when you couple
the highest quintile of meat intake with also the highest quintile of fruits and vegetable intake?
There's no effect. Like you have the same risk for cancer with high meat and high fruit and
vegetable intake as you do with low meat and high fruit and vegetable intake. So to me, that suggests
it's less about the meat you're eating and more about what you're eating instead of, right? So
one of the things to keep in mind with nutrition is when we tell people to eat more or eat less of
something, usually there's a replacement that happens, right? It doesn't happen in a vacuum.
So to me, if we're talking about carnivore, sure, okay, I like high quality protein, great.
I would argue probably lean cuts are a little bit better option. But for God's sakes, have some fruits
and vegetables with it because it's what's going to mitigate your risk. Now you said you're getting
about 40 grams of fiber a day. I'm around 60. 60. And that's total soluble and insoluble.
Yeah, it's total. And so what are your sources? Where do you get the, like, what's the main foods
that are contributing to that? So I'll do like a lot of rice to cauliflower. I'll do quite a, you
know, broccoli, some beans. I'll also do, I love apples. So that's kind of my go to fruit source.
How many grams of fiber in an apple?
Oh, I want to say it's like three or four grams, maybe a little bit less than that.
Okay.
It's not a huge amount, but like, if you want something a little bit more packed, you know,
like berries, berries tend to be really fiber dense compared to something like apples.
You know, like something like a banana is a fruit, but relatively low fiber, all things considered.
But even like the higher sugar, lower fiber fruits are still like relatively well associated
with good health outcomes. So, and then honestly, like people are going to laugh and be judgmental.
I love popcorn. So popcorn actually is pretty darn high fiber.
More than corn on the kernel per kernel basis.
I don't know about that.
Because I feel like you could eat more corn than popcorn.
Oh yeah. Yeah, yeah. So popcorn is actually very filling.
That's one reason I got into eating it during bodybuilding competitions.
Like obviously like I would just like air pop popcorn and I'll usually like put a little bit
of cinnamon and Splenda over that and then like a little bit of like the butter spray.
I mean, it takes you, you know, for 50 grams of carbohydrate from popcorn,
it'll take you like 20, 30 minutes to eat it, you know.
So I just found that that like helped me control my hunger.
And in 50 grams of popcorn, you're getting around like
6 to 10 grams of fiber depending on the specific brand you're using.
So that's actually like, I love that as a snack because it's like, it's, you know,
is it as healthy as if I had some fruits and vegetables? Probably not.
But you know, as far as a snack goes, it's, you know, pretty good and very filling.
So I do that. And then like just miscellaneous sources throughout the day.
But I think one of the things to really look at is, you know, people,
I was in a debate with Paul Saldino one time and we were talking about fiber.
And one of the things he said- And he's a big carnivore advocate.
Big carnivore advocate. One of the things he said was,
well, you know, this stuff with fiber, it's just healthy user bias.
People eat more fiber.
You know, they just have other health promoting behaviors.
Now that's a real thing in terms of like cohort studies and cross-sectional data.
Observational data. It is a real thing.
But when you're dealing with something that's kind of a healthy user bias,
typically you'll see like the data is not consistent, right?
Like some one study will say one thing, one study might have no effect.
One study might say a different thing.
And that's what like you see that with meat.
That's right.
Like you see that with meat longevity.
I was just looking at some meta-analysis earlier that one meta-analysis
even showed that after controlling for confounding variables,
that actually animal protein was not associated with increased mortality.
But- You don't see it with exercise.
You don't see it with exercise.
You don't see it with the smoking studies in the opposite direction.
You don't see it with fiber.
The effect in fiber, at least in terms of like cardiovascular disease, cancer,
it is a very consistent effect.
And it's very consistent even across all the meta-analyses I've seen.
So do we have a 10 year randomized control trial of giving people enough fiber versus
not enough fiber and seeing how that comes?
No, and we'll never have that.
But do I feel very comfortable saying that I think fiber helps reduce the risk of
cardiovascular disease and cancer based on the data we have?
Oh yeah.
I feel very comfortable saying that.
And what's the RDA on fiber?
Is it 30 grams?
Not that the RDA matters.
I'm just kind of curious.
I think it's 20 to 30 grams.
I'll be honest.
I haven't looked at it a while.
I know they change the guidelines a while back too.
What I tell people a good target to shoot for is like 15 grams per thousand calories.
I mean, I would love to go more, but at some point it just becomes intractable
to get that much fiber at that low calories.
Now all the things that you mentioned for fiber, you're eating real food to get it.
So how do we think about it in terms of,
bars and things that seem, I've heard different things about this where,
you know, if you look at the incretin effect, for example, you know, it would
suggest that the fiber that's in a processed bar is not really contributing
the way a fiber is in the way you just described it.
If you're actually eating cauliflower or beans or things like that.
Yeah.
So I try not to fall into the naturalistic fallacy, right?
And I get, I get a little bit cringed when I hear processed fiber.
A little bit cringed when I hear processed, unprocessed,
because what we do to food now and everything's processed.
Yeah.
Processing in and of itself.
Processing doesn't mean bad.
I just mean, and I'm really talking about this purely through the lens of the
disruption of the actual kernel.
For sure.
And what that actually does at the GLP one level.
Yeah.
So getting back to that, yeah, I would say that mother nature's kitchen is probably,
you know, better than, you know, a fiber bar that's like some indigestible form of glucose or,
you know, some less digestible form of, of a starchy carbohydrate.
But is it better than nothing?
Again, it's kind of like, you know, it's probably better than nothing.
But if somebody says, well, I'm getting 40 grams of fiber a day and it's because they're eating
like three protein bars, that 14 grams of fiber, I would argue that, well, it's probably not
equivalent to getting six to eight servings of fruits and vegetables.
So let's, let's talk about one other sort of macronutrient or subset of macronutrient,
which is polyunsaturated fatty acids, right?
So this is one of those things I always tell people, there's nothing in nutrition that I'm
more confused about than the role of omega six PUFAs.
So let's go back to that Minnesota coronary experiment that you mentioned.
It's, it's a very unique experiment, probably never to be replicated.
No, no, IRB would ever approve it again.
And I'm still trying to track down Chris Ramston who wrote the, like, paper that looked at all of
the data that were never published in Franza's first study, but I'll, I'll retell the study to
the best of my recollection, which is super foggy at this point.
So this was a study carried out in Minnesota.
Please correct me if I'm missing any details.
It was carried out in an assisted living or mental facility and it might've been two arms.
I can't remember.
What makes this special then is that the subjects in this study were fed every meal.
So what makes this a really unique study is that it was not a free living study,
though it had free living duration.
I want to say the average duration was three years.
Just over two, I think.
Was it?
Okay.
Just over two.
So the study was five years.
Yes.
Yeah.
But the feeding intervention was only two.
Two, I think because people were kind of going in and out of facility,
the average subject duration was about two, two and a half years.
So for this period of time, every meal is being fed and there's, patients are randomized
into two groups, isocaloric, isomacro, but at the fat level, one group was high saturated fat,
one group was low saturated fat.
If I recall the reduction in saturated fat was not trivial.
It was 30%.
What was it?
18.5 is a number that sticks out in my mind and I can't remember, but do you remember the exact?
I don't remember the exact number, but it was.
It was a really big reduction in saturated fat.
It was not something that I would say, well, there just wasn't a big enough difference.
That's right.
Yeah.
So I think we can all look at it and say, wow, these guys were getting a lot of saturated fat.
These guys were getting a lot of omega six polyunsaturated.
Was it canola?
What was the dominant form of the oil?
I don't remember that actually.
It might've been corn oil.
I don't remember which one it was, which of the big four safflower.
But I think it was canola, but I could be wrong on that.
We'll obviously post a link to the original study.
The study goes on and it completes, they get all the data.
Oh, what was the hypothesis that was being tested?
The hypothesis was being tested was in this really well designed, elegant study,
the group on the lower saturated fat arm should have had fewer cardiovascular events.
Because this was right at the time when the theory initially proposed by Ansel Keys in about 1961
was that saturated fat specifically was the driver of blood lipids.
And this was really the connection to the lipid heart hypothesis.
This was supposed to be kind of like the nail in the coffin for that hypothesis,
in terms of like cementing it as legit.
That's correct.
Because so the idea was this group on the higher saturated fat, they would have more heart attacks.
And you couldn't argue these data.
This was really clear.
You've also had a high power to this study because it was very large.
It was like 500 something people.
Oh, I think it was more.
Was it more?
Yeah, I think it was a stag.
I was amazed at how big the number was.
And they were old, which meant you were going to see events.
You couldn't do a two year study in 40 year olds.
You see no events in anybody.
So it had all these things going for it.
1973, the results come out.
There's no difference.
The study goes unpublished.
It's not published until 1989.
16 years later, Frans publishes it.
When asked why, he said quite plainly, we didn't like the way it turned out.
Now a guy named Chris Ramsden, who I believe is still at the NIH though,
if you're listening to this and anybody knows him, please tell him I've been trying to reach
him for the past two years unsuccessfully.
Won't return any emails.
He comes along maybe five years ago and finds a whole bunch of unpublished data and republishes.
I think one, if not two studies in the BMJ.
Before we get to what Ramsden's findings are, my interpretation of the study that I just
described, my initial representation or my initial interpretation of that 10 years ago
was saturated fats not causing heart disease.
10 years later, my representation was or my interpretation was
that study wasn't long enough to see a difference.
Cholesterol, at the time they did measure total cholesterol levels, they didn't fractionate
cholesterol at the time.
They couldn't measure LDL or HDL or anything like that.
There was about a 30 milligram per deciliter reduction in total cholesterol on the low
saturated fat group, which again, now you have a biomarker that tells you, this intervention
worked and the majority of that 30 milligrams per deciliter was probably LDL cholesterol,
could they have measured it?
Then my interpretation turned into two years of an intervention wasn't long enough.
If you took a bunch of people and put them on a statin for two years, you probably wouldn't
see a difference.
You could miss a difference.
Now, the PCSK9 trials suggested otherwise.
It was really interesting, the Odyssey and Fourier trials in 2015, which were testing
the most potent lipid lowering drugs available, actually did show a benefit in about two and a
half to three years.
They were crushing LDL.
Again, it's an area under the curve problem.
This one was reducing it, but not crushing it.
That's where I left it.
I think it's important to point out too, that the modifications you can make to cholesterol
from diet in some cases can be quite small compared to what you can get from pharmaceutical
interventions.
That's right.
Outside of the most extreme, I'm sure if somebody went on to a zero saturated fat, 12% total fat
calorie restricted diet, they could probably cut their cholesterol in half, but they'd be
doing a whole bunch of harm, I would argue, along the way.
In the other direction, you do have some people like in the low carb community who are bragging
about LDL cholesterol levels in the 500s.
Well, that's what I was going to say.
You can do the opposite much more.
It's an unbounded problem above.
It's obviously a bounded problem below.
Ramston's data suggests that actually the people in the PUFA group had worse outcomes.
Now, that really kind of throws me for a loop and that's frankly why I kind of want to have him on
the podcast because his data suggests that at least this particular PUFA had a negative
cardiovascular effect.
Now, to me, that study is probably, if the details of that study are consistent, that would be
the most damning evidence against N6 PUFAs in terms of lowering lipids, but raising events.
By the way, there is a precedent for that.
There was a drug that was approved in the 1960s that actually lowered cholesterol, but
increased cardiovascular events.
That drug was withdrawn.
This was back in the day.
Do you know what the mechanism was for that?
I can speculate, yeah.
I actually recently discussed this on a podcast.
The mechanism that it's believed that this drug worked is it prevented the conversion of
desmostral to cholesterol.
That's the final step of cholesterol synthesis in one of the two pathways.
When you gave people this drug, and the name always escapes me,
triametral or something like that, when you gave people this drug, their cholesterol went down
significantly.
The drug was approved on the basis of cholesterol lowering, not on the basis of outcomes.
Today, cholesterol drugs are only approved on the basis of outcomes as well.
But then it had to be pulled from the market because you saw the events.
I don't think they ever investigated it, but I think today we look back and we think that
desmostral acted perhaps as bad, if not worse, than cholesterol in terms of the oxidative process.
You basically lowered cholesterol, but the precursor went through the roof and the precursor
was at least as bad, if not more damaging.
Ah, interesting.
Yeah.
So that's the suspicion.
The point only being there is there was a precedent for you can lower cholesterol and worsen events.
Yeah.
And so Ramstein proposes a series of mechanisms by which that might be the case with at least this
polyunsaturated fat.
Conversely, there is a lot of epidemiology that says the opposite, that polyunsaturated fats,
whenever you substitute saturated for polyunsaturated, things get better.
Nobody's disputing MUFA over here.
Like the data seem unambiguously clear that MUFA is the best of the three fats,
both epidemiologically and experimentally.
So how do you think about the breakdown, not the breakdown, but what I mean is the
distribution of how one should think about distributing their fats?
So I've actually have seen some epidemiology that showed that
PUFAs were actually lowering events more.
No, that's what I'm saying.
Yeah.
That's what I'm saying.
The PUFA data look like it's more favorable than the SFA.
Well, even then model-unsaturated too.
Ah, okay.
Yeah, I got it.
But I mean, again, you're dealing with cohort data and whatnot.
We all know the limitations there.
As far as the Minnesota coronary study, I think I get really,
it's probably going to sound like a cop out, but I've really gotten to the point after seeing
just so many random events and studies where I go, I don't know what one study means, no matter
how well done it is.
Now, I have seen studies that were so compelling that I swayed my opinion a little bit, but it was
usually because there was also other contextual data that made sense.
The way this one came about, it's like, like I said, we don't really know how to reconcile this
because even if you look at some of these Omega 6 fats, and I think one of the big mechanisms
has been proposed is, well, they're going to increase inflammation because those double
bonds can be oxidized, that oxidation cause inflammation.
But if we look at the hard outcome data and randomized control trials where they give
like linoleic acid or alpha linoleic acid or whatever, I mean, you just don't see inflammation
go up if they're not increasing total calories, right?
In fact, you usually, especially if you're replacing it for saturated fat, sometimes
you see inflammation go down.
So I just don't, honestly, this is one of those things where I go, I don't really know what it
means.
And I think-
So I don't feel bad now saying, I literally don't know what the answer is.
Yeah.
I mean, I just have no clue.
I think it's one of those things where it's, you kind of have to look at the weight of the
evidence and then couple that with some of the mechanistic evidence and look at the human
outcome mechanisms we can see, which is, okay, maybe we can't do a two year randomized control
trial, but 12 weeks is enough time to see differences in inflammation if something's
going to cause a difference in inflammation.
So we can look at that.
I don't know if that was his main mechanism that he proposed for how it was occurring.
It was absolutely one of them.
Yeah.
God, it's been so long since I looked at his bigger BMJ paper.
So I don't want to, we'll attach to the paper in the show notes so people can kind of go
through it.
He actually, if I recall, I can almost picture it.
There's a figure that kind of actually kind of nicely walks through what the proposed
mechanisms are.
So I think the other thing to consider is like we just talked about how when you suggest
cutting something out, you place it with other things.
And I think in the last 20 or 30 years, the biggest contribution to added calories in
the diet is actually added oils.
So on a per calorie basis, I don't think that there's like, you know, the big demon right
now is seed oils.
Like that is like, I haven't even done a post about it yet because the anti seed oil crowd
is just so vitriolic and so nuts that I'm like, all right, how, how, when do I want to
wade into this conversation?
But I think that.
And tell me about this crowd.
This, this, this, this particular sect is of which religion?
Are they?
They're definitely more towards like the low carb carnivore.
I think a lot of this is there's a lot of people in the low carb community who've kind of like
tried to abdicate saturated fat, like make it.
Oh, it's it's not bad or it's not.
It's innocuous, you know, that sort of or it's even it's it's healthy because look at,
you know, if you look at elderly people, people who have higher LDL cholesterol live longer.
And it's like, well, that's because they're probably actually getting in enough food.
And when you're elderly, it becomes a wasting problem and not a not an obesity problem.
But that's a that's a separate conversation.
But I think a lot of it stemmed from, OK, we want to make saturated fat a good guy.
So somebody has to be the bad guy.
And so and so it's been it's been seed oils.
And yeah, it's very, very like very powerful belief that some people hold on this.
So I think.
And again, if you just look at top level stuff, it fits.
It fits a pretty good story, right?
Which is we never ate these seed oils 120 years ago, right?
They represented this much of our total fat calories today.
They're this much of our fat calories.
And look at all the things that are wrong with the world today.
So it's got that kind of top level story, which I think a lot of things do.
Right. Sugar has the same thing.
Like we ate this much sugar in 1900.
We ate this much sugar in the year 2000.
Look what got worse.
So it's it's it's important to understand, I guess, how.
I mean, I've certainly fallen for that, right?
Like there's I've looked at that and gone, yeah, that that's got to be the seed oils.
It's got to be the sugar.
It's got to be that it's got to be it's really easy to make a bogeyman.
Yeah.
And I think when you look through the data and try to be unbiased about it,
what you see is like the continuous.
The continuous bogeyman is really it's just energy toxicity.
I mean, what you're dealing with is just extra energy because regardless,
because people will say, well, you know, we did the the food guide pyramid and people
did it and everybody got sicker.
People kind of did it.
They didn't really do it because the food guide pyramid also said exercise and reduce your
calorie consumption.
So, yeah, they they add in more carbohydrates, but they really didn't decrease their fat intake
either. And so, yeah, as we added more calories, we had more of these problems.
And so that's interesting.
I'd really love to know because unfortunately we only have food availability and waste data.
So we have to use food availability and waste to take a delta to estimate what's happening.
And I've personally always found that to be difficult.
The other thing I find impossible is to estimate what I eat.
I want to actually ask you about how you do it because I think you're much more dialed into this.
If I could tell you at the end of a day within a thousand calories, what I've not a thousand,
I could probably do it within a thousand.
There's no way I could tell you within a day, 500 calories within what I've done.
It's just not possible.
I can't personally do it.
I don't have that that infrastructure.
So I really believe that we've probably underestimated in the low fat craze how much
fat didn't go down and how much low fat stuff did go up.
Well, think about going to a restaurant.
Right. And if you've ever been to a restaurant where they go to the cheesecake factory,
you look at the calories and the dishes.
Like, how do you get that much in there?
Well, you carbs contribute to that.
But the way you densify food is with fat.
Like fat is what will take something from a 500 calorie dish to a 1500 calorie dish.
So I think when it comes to estimations.
Yeah. Last night we were out and you were eating ad lib.
But I know in your head the wheels were kind of telling you like at some point,
I think I even asked you and you made some comment like, yeah, I got about 600 more to go.
Is that literally just repetitions like you've done enough food logging in your life that you
you can look at a brownie and you can look at a sandwich and you just sort of know what you're
getting. So I'll tell people for some people like that's not a sustainable way to live to
just keep a running track in their head or whatnot.
Because you let me back up just a little bit higher level view.
If you want to lose fat or control body weight, you have to practice some form of restriction.
Now you can pick the form of restriction you want. For me, the easiest thing for me is to be able to
eat what I want within reason. Right. What you want, when you want, but just control the amount.
Bingo. Right. So if you do that, you're going to have to track calories or macros or whatever it is.
Or you can restrict time. Right. Or you can restrict a certain macronutrient group or,
you know, you say, I'm just going to eat mentally processed food. So there's some form of restriction
you have to do. Now, what's interesting is none of these forms of restriction seem to be emerged as
being better than another in terms of adherence across a population level. So it really does boil
down to the individual. So I always say you have to practice some form of restriction, but choose
the form of restriction that feels the least restrictive for you. So for me, that's just been
tracking macros. Did you play much with the others? A little bit. Yeah. Like, you know,
kind of clean eating back in the early 2000s, which was, you know, mentally processed foods and,
you know, high fiber and whatnot. And I actually found that I just ended up kind of, I wouldn't
say I developed binge eating disorder, but I did start kind of binge eating because it was like,
so if you look at the psychology of binge eating, it's really interesting. We had Professor Jake
Leonard on our podcast a while back and his expertise is in eating disorders. And he said,
really, there's two things that are kind of essential for an eating disorder to emerge.
The first is, you know, some sort of poor body image perception, right? That's kind of a prerequisite.
The second is hard food rules. So when you create hard food rules,
it just does a weird thing in your mind. So for example, I'm sorry, are both of those
necessary or sufficient or the necessary and sufficient? Both of those seem to predict.
So when you look at the vast majority of people, I want to say every single person.
Sure. When we look at the vast majority of people who develop eating disorders, those are two things.
Those two things show up more often. So what I found was that I would kind of take it.
And sorry for my ignorance. Is binge eating defined as, because that obviously doesn't involve
purging necessarily. Right. Binging just means overeating. Like how do we technically define
binging? Yeah, it's I actually don't know the criteria, but from what Dr. Leonard said,
it's kind of like periods of really intense food consumption, followed by a lot of guilt,
like feeling guilty and with or without compensatory mechanisms. Because sometimes
people will exercise in response to people. Okay. And or deprivation would be another
compensatory. Correct. Correct. Okay. And usually you're talking about like, you're not talking
about, Oh, yeah, I had an extra cookie. You're talking about like, you ate the whole box of
Oreos or whatever it is. So usually, I mean, I'm guessing, but it would probably be on the
magnitude of like, you know, over a thousand calories that, you know, a sitting unintended.
And the other thing is it tends to be kind of a it can be tied to stress as well. That's another
part of it. But for me, I found that I would just kind of go in the bodily magazine said I couldn't
have sugar, you know, can't have, you know, this can have that. And the rules for what was clean
seemed to be very arbitrary. But I was young, I didn't know any better. So I'm like, Okay, well,
I'll I won't have these quote unquote, bad foods. And the weirdest thing started happening,
I actually started eating more of them. Because when I would get more of the things you weren't
supposed to write because when I get exposed to it, I wasn't able to moderate it. Because it was like,
you know, I'm in college, buddies bring home a pizza, the apartment, hey, Lane, you want some?
Sure. Or I would like try to avoid and it feels so bad that I'm trying to avoid. But the outcome
was the same, which was I would just end up eating way more than I had intended to or even felt hungry
for. But it was like this mindset of, well, this is bad. This I'm not going to eat this again.
It's my last time eating this because I'm going to be really serious after this. So since I've
already broken the seal, as well just go all the way by as well just go all the way. Right.
And so I just kept going through this. And finally, I was kind of like,
this seems to be really ineffective towards my goals. I wonder if it's the fact that I'm just,
you know, I have pizza or the fact that I'm eating like an entire large pizza to myself.
That's the problem. So at that point, I was kind of like, well, let's just try this whole portion
control thing and see if this works. And funny enough, I was able to modulate my body composition
by eating foods I still enjoyed, but controlling portion size. And it was really interesting. I was
supposed to debate this is like seven, eight years ago, I was going to debate a bodybuilding coach
at a seminar about clean eating versus flexible dieting, which is kind of what I practice,
which is, you know, tracking my macros and kind of treating it like a budget.
And my opening argument, he ended up bowing out of the debate. But my opening argument was I had
gone to his Facebook and looked at his cheat meals and had estimated the calories in his
cheat meals in terms of a per week basis and then put up what my calories were from, you know,
junk food on a per week basis was going to show that his was actually higher because in the
concentrated amount he was taking in, he was actually taking in more calories from those foods.
And so my point was going to be. So you're telling me it's really bad to have a cookie,
but if I binge on it, it's OK as long as I don't have it the rest of the week,
because that seems like a really odd metric. I mean, my guess is that everyone, if we exposed
everyone to all three different forms of restriction, you would have a rank order for any person of
what's most effective, both biochemically and also psychologically. It's a min max. You'd have
to find an optimization. What fraction of the population do you think will do best, meaning
they'll have the best physical response and also just psychologically will have the best response
to caloric restriction as a tool or flexible dieting? And I say this knowing there's no data,
but thinking asking you to think about clients and what percentage of people.
Yeah, I think, you know, part of it is some people will be resistant at first and then
actually really enjoy it later, which I'm sure you've seen that with fasting as well or, you know,
low carb, those sorts of things. But it really just boils down to how willing is somebody to
make this part of their lifestyle. Right. So all of them have downsides. Right. Like if you're on a
ketogenic diet and you go out and I mean, there's a lot you can't eat, but you can usually make do
most places like get some funny looks from your friends and family, but, you know, whatever.
Time restricted feeding. You know, hey, you want to go out and join us for breakfast?
Oh, I can't. I'll sit and I'll drink some water. You know, so there's downsides with flexible
dieting. The downside is I've got to account for it. Right. And actually, so we know the data on
reporting for food is like people under report by like 50 percent and it's pretty consistent in the
studies and people really take that as like an affront. So I'm not a liar. Yeah. Well, I don't
think that people are lying. I think people are just really horrible estimators of what they eat.
You know, like if you ever want to be depressed, go way out of serving of cereal or way out of
serving of ice cream or serving a peanut butter. You know, people when they do these these food
recalls, I mean, a serving of ice cream is not a bowl of ice cream. Like a bowl of ice cream is
probably three times more than a serving in terms of what people are actually taking in.
So it makes total sense as to why people underestimate their energy intake.
And one of the things I'll say is even if you don't land on flexible dieting as the tool that
you want to use, tracking and weighing every single thing you put in your mouth for a week
is an incredibly valuable tool because it will teach you about portion control. And actually,
you'll learn more about nutrition in that week than probably doing anything else, to be honest.
Now, a lot of people don't want to do it because it's a lot the same reason a lot of people don't
want to keep a budget for for their money because they don't want to know where it's going because
then it's kind of like here's the mirror and you have to look at yourself and say,
oh, where have I been spending my money? Right. Oh, I spent, you know, five hundred dollars on
Uber Eats last month or, you know, whatever it is. But then with, you know, macro tracking again,
it's very much, oh, man, I want and I've I've I have had this so many times people say I'm
eating fifteen hundred calories a day and can't lose weight. And it's hard to believe you can't
lose weight on fifteen hundred calories. There was a I will say there was a metabolic award study
where they put people on fifteen hundred calories and there was actually one person who gained just
a tiny amount of weight over like a camera with a time period. But the vast majority lost weight.
I wonder what was going on with that one person. Right. So maybe endocrine issue or something like
that. Yeah. Yeah. So I think the point that I would make is that I do think it's useful for people
to try tracking for a while. I mean, again, we have people like, you know, our app is different than a
calorie tracking app because it actually gives you, you know, macros to eat based on your dietary
preference and your goals, and then it will it will adjust them based on how you're progressing.
So it's not just a one and done calculation. And a lot of people love that. But they also
people who have never tracked before go, oh, my God, I didn't know what I was eating.
Like and, you know, it has a barcode scanner and all that kind of stuff. So it's much easier.
Like when I first started doing this, it was me going to the grocery store with the complete
book of food counts and going, OK, where is it? OK, there it is. But now, after having done this
sort of stuff for, you know, 20 years. Like last night, picking up that brownie, I'm picking it up.
And I know what's the calculation. How did you do the count? So all I do is I just like, I don't
know what particular brownie that is. I don't know how they made or anything like that. But it's
likely that the calorie density is going to be similar to other brownies. Right. The carb fat
ratio might be a little bit different, but the calorie density is probably going to be pretty
similar. So I really just try to think about what do I think this weighs? Right. And so last
time I was kind of like, it's a little bit denser than normal brownie. I put it about 40 grams.
Right. And so I put that in. Now, did I? You didn't put it into an app, did you? Didn't.
Yeah. Oh, you did. I just put it in my app. Oh, OK. OK. But I just pulled up like some random brownie
from Sara Lee or whatever. Got it. Got it. So I'll kind of do that now. OK. I feel a bit better now.
I literally thought you were doing this in your head the whole time. Oh, no, no, no, no. I was like,
God, how is he doing that? So I, yeah, the apps now make it much easier. But then the night before
when we were out at dinner or two nights ago, I didn't see you putting anything in the app. And
I did it after. But how? How did you remember what we ate and how would you like the bone marrow and
all that crazy stuff we were eating? So like how are you estimating all that stuff? Yeah. So there
was an entry for bone marrow that I found. Now, again, the point that I think I'll make is it's
very likely that some of these are inaccurate, right? But it's better. It's going to be more
accurate than just kind of going, oh, I have no idea. So I'm not going to worry about it.
Right. Do you think that the act of tracking it is what's putting a governor on it? In other words,
do you think the fact that you had to enter 40 grams of brownie is what prevented you from having
three? At this point, no. But for some people, absolutely. Right. And we, I mean, this is the
one of the most basic laws of science. When you monitor something, it changes. Right. So I've done
this so many times with people who have said the following, you know, like I'm eating for
ten or calories, can't lose fat. And I've said, listen, I don't expect you to do this forever,
but for one week, just one week, everything you put in your mouth, weigh it on a scale and track it.
Okay. And then come back to me and let's talk. One of two things happen. They go, oh, my God.
Oh, I was actually eating 2800 calories. I go, well, welcome to freedom because now you know
that you're not broken. Right. Like you're you're actually like you can modify. Right.
Or the other thing happens. They actually eat the amount of calories they said they were eating.
And they're starving. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. So, yeah, it's it's what monitored
is what gets changed. And we know that like right down on a particle basis, if you monitor it,
it changes its behavior. So when you get people to monitor things, they change their behavior.
It's like if I if somebody is like, oh, we're going to do we're going to do Lane's budget
for the month and, you know, we're going to put it on YouTube as a video or something. Right.
Okay. Well, like all of a sudden we're like, well, let's spend money on this. It's not going to look
good. You know, like when we monitor things, it changes. But but we know that about behavior.
We can use that to our advantage. So I think the like if I was getting ready for a bodybuilding
show, for example, I would have to change how I do things. I couldn't just go out and just kind of
guesstimate like that. I would have to get much more granular. And now the sacrifice might be,
okay, maybe I'll still go out to eat, but I'm going to have to take all the ingredients,
put them on my scale and, you know, and then and then track. Oh, so which sucks. But no, I mean,
look, that's if that's what you're doing, that's what you're doing. Like that's that's the price
you have to pay to to get it good. And then the other the other the other the sacrifice that if
I want to do a bodybuilding shows, OK, I'm just I can't go out my friends anymore. Right. Yeah.
Or at least in the final. Yeah. And I would say like in the last four weeks, I don't I pretty much
a hermit. You know what I mean? But yeah, it's all all these different forms of restriction are just
tools. Right. But I do think having that accounting, looking through what you're actually
having is really educational for a lot of folks. And I would say to people who are listening or
who are watching and have never done it, like try to do it without judgment towards yourself.
You know, like really without judgment, just be curious, you know, and see, hmm, I wonder what
this is. And I think what you'll find is if you just enter it with that genuine curiosity,
you'll find some things out that will be really helpful towards you for you.
And you'll also learn so much about portion sizes that you'll go, whoa. Yeah. I didn't realize that
restaurants serve such massive portion sizes. Right. Like it's going to sound bad, but I can't
tell you how many times I'm going to eat something and go, yeah, I'm good. I don't I don't I don't
need any more. And are you still hungry when you push it away? It's, you know, being in tune with
your hunger signals, plus like some bit of monitoring is helpful. The one other thing I'll
say is like, you know, being in tune with hunger signals is great, but that's also hard when you're
eating processed food, like energy dense, hyper palatable food. You know, previously,
based on our hunger signals, we could, you know, auto regulate what we ate. Yeah. Because we're in
a situation where food wasn't energy dense enough, like you would have to become uncomfortable,
you know, to just based on the volume, just based on the volume of food you were eating.
And even like up until the 1950s, we had hyper processed, you know, food, whatever. But you had
to walk down to the bakery to get it. Right. You didn't have it in like really nice available. And
I still think the serving sizes were a lot smaller. Oh, yeah. If you look at dinner plates,
like the early 1900s, they're like this, and then they're like this. And then now you got
dinner plates. I think anybody listening to this who's been to Europe will will will recognize
this, but it never ceases to amaze me no matter how many times I go to Italy or something like
that. I can't get over how small the portions are. And it's really wonderful because I'm just a
glutton. Like I will I don't know. I think it's part of it is like you grow up as an immigrant
kid. You eat what's on your plate. Like we do not throw out food in this house. And how many times
do I get that lecture about those kids in Africa that don't have anything? And it's like you're
going to sit here until you eat that thing on your plate. And it wasn't like I was being forced to
eat bad food. It was like, right, you know, liver and spinach and stuff I hated. But like the clean
plate was just a part of your mind. Same. Grew up in a lower middle class family. And so it was very
much like we don't waste food in this house. So I think there's still a little bit of the, you know,
I was joking about it yesterday. Like I eat off my kids plates now. It's like what you're not
throwing that out. Give me that. Do you think you'll do another bodybuilding show or you do you
plan to do that anymore? Right now I consider myself in a long off season. I'm not sure. I think,
you know, it's if right now there's just so many things going on business wise.
And, you know, I'm kind of in a place where I'm very grateful for that and I want to get it while
I can get it. And hopefully we can get to the point where we're working because we want to work,
not because we feel like we have to work. I mean, that's kind of the dream. I love what I do. I don't
see myself ever like retiring, retiring. But it would be nice to be able to have like a little
more freedom to go and do the things that I really am super passionate about doing and not having to
worry about doing some of the more granular stuff. So, you know, bodybuilding, getting ready for a
show would would take a significant amount of energy and time. So in powerlifting already does
that. It's just that, you know, I can do that without the brain fog and the mood swings and
all that kind of stuff. I mean, it is it's really funny if you look at case studies of bodybuilders
like by the time they're at show. So literally every single case study on natural bodybuilders
shows that they're hypogonadal by the time they hit stage. Of course. Yeah. I mean, and I'm somebody
like my testosterone. I've had it measured probably a half dozen times in the last five years.
The lowest it's ever been is 900. And the highest it's been, I think I hit like almost 1100.
And that's, you know, people will say, well, see, he's not drug free or whatever. But
I would tell you my LHS normal and my FSH is normal and all that kind of stuff. So
but when I was competing in bodybuilding, it was under 300. Like when I was that close to a show,
because it's just it just I mean, think about the hungriest you've ever been in your life.
And now imagine that feeling doesn't leave you for weeks. That's all and the lowest energy like
I can how many what's the absolute nadir of calories you're consuming at the lowest. So the
lowest I've ever been like at kind of this level of lean mass was nineteen hundred. And how many
grams of protein are in that nineteen hundred. So that was like 260 grams of protein. So I was like
around one hundred or under one hundred grams of carbohydrate a day and like 30 40 grams of fat,
if I recall correctly. What does that look like? Practically. Like what are the what's the actual
foods you're eating? I mean, egg whites, chicken breast, some Greek yogurt, you know, fat free
Greek yogurt. I mean, you're really you have to be very careful with your fats when you're that low
calorie. Meaning you have to be careful you don't go too low on the fats. Well, and that you get.
But at a certain point, you know, the idea is well, keep your fats high enough and you're
going well at a certain point, you're like, all right, yeah, I'd like to have my hormones there,
but I also need to get lean enough. You know, so. So meaning be careful that too much fat isn't
sneaking in. Oh, yeah. Yeah. I mean, like just eating something that's, you know, like seven
grams of fat, which all, you know, accounts is a low fat item. I had to be careful about that
because it could just sneak up very quickly. Yeah. You can't have nuts or something like that.
Oh, no, no, no, no. So, you know, the low energy to like I can literally remember
being on my couch. I was probably three weeks out from a show.
I had just gotten done training sitting on my couch and the remote control was probably I just
like sat down like literally like plopped down. Remote control was probably, you know, five feet
away. And the Real Housewives of some county was playing. I abhor that show. And I sat and watched
the entire show because I was not willing to get up to go get that remote because I was that
exhausted. And it's like now you see like. And how many weeks in to that degree of
color restriction? Do you think you were at that point? That was like 20 weeks in. Well,
not not at 19. So my calories have progressively come down. Really, it's it's mostly a body fat
issue. Like I've I've had clients who were able to eat higher calories and get really lean at a
certain point of body fat level. It just doesn't matter if you're that lean and your leptin is that
low and your testosterone is that low. I mean, yeah, it's it's just Eric Helms describes contest
prep is like you're circling a drain and you're just trying to delay going down the drain as long
as possible. But eventually you go down the drain. So how do you get the energy to get on stage? Is
that basically one big push of carbs shortly enough before you go on stage that it's not going
to show up in your physique? So I will say like there are spurts where you feel OK when you're
when you're in those, you know, the dregs of contest prep. I'll also say that like for me to
get from like say 15 percent on calipers to seven percent on calipers. It's not difficult at all. In
fact, I I had gone up a weight class in piloting a few years ago and then came back down. It was
about a 30 pound weight drop. But so 15 to seven easy from seven to and I think the lowest I ever
caliper it was two percent and terribly watching. No, I don't think I was two percent. It's probably
more like five or six. But to go from seven to three or two, which is an absolute lower amount
of fat loss, was infinitely more difficult. It's like the best way to describe it is like kind of
like you get a fresh roll toothpaste to get out some toothpaste. Very easy. Then as that toothpaste
tube gets, you know, emptier and emptier. How much effort do you have to put in to just squeeze out
that last little bit of toothpaste? I mean, it's it's magnitudes higher than at the beginning.
And contest prep is very much like that. So like you. But you do have times where you have energy
because you start to train two or three hours. Right. And trust me like that.
That is actually the part I despise the most of contest prep is at a certain point, I just don't
like training anymore. I'm just doing it for energy expenditure and retaining muscle. I'm not doing it
because I'm passionate about training and I'm somebody who I love to train. It's like my favorite
thing in the world. And but there will be times where it's like you go and you have a little bit
better workouts. I did periodize my nutrition, so I would have some higher calorie days on days that
were more demanding for training, usually like lower body training days as far as like getting
on stage. Well, one thing is I never cut water for bodybuilding shows. A lot of people do that.
I think it's silly because think about a muscle is 70 percent water. And in your native state,
you you keep more water inside your muscle cell than you do outside your muscle cell.
And, you know, this is just basically shot the A's principle. If you begin removing more fluid,
like via dueritic or fluid restriction or sodium restriction. Well, what happens? Well, sure,
you remove it from the subcutaneous layer, but you're also going to remove it in the same
proportion from the from the intracellular layer. All you're going to do is just become flatter.
In the intravascular layer, you get hypotensive. Exactly. So
one thing that helped me is that I didn't cut water, so I felt I never was like dehydrated or
anything like that. Didn't cut sodium and I could go into the physiology behind why I think it's
silly to cut sodium as well. I didn't take it to erratic. But yes, like during peak week,
food went back up because the idea is diuretics even legal in tested take OTC diuretics. So you
could take like dandelion root and those sorts of things. But yeah, it's it's very funny like the
logic behind why people cut water and sodium. And I think it's like somebody just saw a figure of
the sodium potassium pump in a book. And they're like, oh, see, the cell wants to get sodium out
and potassium in. So let's cut sodium and load potassium. And it's like, if you actually look at
the physiology, if you get the sodium to potassium ratio too low, it'll actually cause you to retain
water as well like the you'll actually start reabsorbing water in the distal tubule of the kidney.
So yeah, I think that that helped with my energy and whatnot. But definitely food in the days before
the competition comes up, because at that point, like if you're still trying to lose body fat that
close, it's probably not going to go well for you. And so I'll like usually in peak week, I'll start
feeling better as opposed to worse. And then on the day of the show, you know, I'm usually having,
you know, three to 400 grams of carbohydrates, something like that.
So it's, you know, it's very interesting because a lot of the dogmas in bodybuilding originated
like wrestling and endurance running. You know, if you look at the correlation was kind of like,
well, wrestlers cut water and they look really lean. So we should cut water. Right. And I'll always
use the example of if you've ever seen George St. Pierre when he weighed in, he looked like
gaunt, you know, not very, I mean, just didn't look healthy, not very muscular. And then the day
of the fight, 24 hours later, I mean, he looks like a bodybuilder. You know what I mean? Like he
looks pretty jacked. Well, that will just show you what, like drinking water, eating enough sodium
and carbohydrate will do for your muscle fullness because muscles are 70% water. So yeah, I think
that that all that stuff kind of helped me have a little bit more longevity in that sport. And so
far as like I wasn't beating my body up with, you know, fluid restriction. So you're 40 now when
you sort of think about yourself being 60 or 70. How do you think about aging in terms of the
reductions in strength, which is obviously an important part of your identity? And I think
part of your identity and the change in physique, you know, do you think that it's going to be a
difficult transition? And I'm not suggesting that the alternative to what you're doing now is sitting
on a couch all day drinking beer, of course. But, you know, invariably, whether you're Arnold
Schwarzenegger or, you know, anyone who's really fit, like you're not going to look the same when
you're 60. I think about this a lot, you know, I bugged my wife or not bugger. I just, I say all
the time, I'm like, God, I can't stand my face like it's so wrinkled and beaten up from all the sun.
And she's like, well, you don't do anything about it. She's like, you could go and see a dermatologist.
And I'm like, yeah, I'm just too lazy. I think it's easier to sit here and sort of gripe about it
and think about like, just have these vain thoughts of, well, the older I get, the older I look,
you know. Yeah. I mean, I consider and say, oh, no, I'll be fine. No, of course I'm going to struggle
with it. Like, you know, look at any like athlete, you know, that is your identity for such a long
period of your life. Now, I think I'm fortunate in that I've kind of had multiple identities.
So I've had, you know, academic, you know, influencer, entrepreneur, you know, power lifter,
bodybuilder, scientist. So I think it'll be a little bit easier for me because I already have
other things that I care about, you know, and then being a dad, I already have other things I
care about. But of course, it'll be hard. Like, you know, like, don't. Nobody who's successful
doesn't have any ego whatsoever, you know. And so I'm not going to lie, like when I load up a bar
with 500 pounds in a commercial gym and, you know, I'm squatting that like part of me feels like a
badass, you know what I mean? And so, yeah, there's going to be part of me that absolutely
missed that. You know, that's why you have the guy who's like, well, you know, when I was in high
school, you know, I benched four or five or whatever it is, or, you know, I squatted 600 until
my knees hurt. So my goal is to not be that guy, you know, other than just like if somebody asked
me about what I've done to do it. But I think really what's going to be most important for me
is just trying to not judge it and just, you know, find other things that I can, you know,
be interested in. And I still always left. I'll always train. I love it too much to not do it.
It makes me feel too good. And quite frankly, like, if you look at some of the people who've
been doing it for a really long time, I mean, you know, it was I got a great compliment the other
day because I was in the gym and I just kind of casually brought up that I was I turned 40 this
year and lady was like, what? I was like, yeah, you know, and she said, oh, I would have guessed
that you were like, you know, mid 30s. Oh, thank you. You know, but I think like resistance training,
I mean, as far as like keeping you young, that's one of the things I agree. I feel like I feel like
for both men and women, it's it's it is it is a fountain of youth, both cosmetically and also
internally. Oh, even looking at some of the the bodybuilders out there, notwithstanding like some
of the drug stuff. Yeah. But some of them still look really good into their fifties. You know,
if they if they continue to do it. Now, there's a lot of guys who get out of it and kind of once
that identity is gone, they just go, what's the point of putting energy into lifting? But, you
know, like Jay Cutler is in his 40s. And yeah, I was about to say Jay Cutler is my favorite of the
kind of recent bodybuilders. He's the only bodybuilder like of that group that I follow on
Instagram. I enjoy looking at him. Yeah, I know. I mean, he still looks to be in insane shape.
Yeah. And if you look at him, he goes trains every day. He still eats really well. You know,
he just kind of got he likes that lifestyle and got used to it. And, you know, it shows.
But yeah, it would definitely be a hard transition. But I'm I'm sure I'll find something to,
you know, bury myself in. And, you know, who knows? We'll see.
Well, we went a little longer than we expected to.
We've cut ourselves out of a few extracurricular activities. I had planned this afternoon, but
maybe we'll have time tomorrow. So anyway, Lane, awesome to sit down with you.
Thanks again for making the time. Yeah. Thanks for having me. It was fun.